foreign
welcome everyone I'm Tanya Weiser really nice to have you all here and
don't worry if you weren't here last week you can also go to YouTube and
watch the video from last class because there's you know we won't be able to
review it all but we Don will give us a little bit of an overview or a reminder of what we covered
but it's all good so yeah warm warm welcome to each of you
in addition to YouTube I want to especially encourage you to go to audiodarma.org
because there you can either listen to an audio recording you can watch the video there and you can also download or
view any of the handouts so if you missed a class or just want a refresher that's a great resource
um and I just want to start before we really get into it by
asking if everyone's okay the practice here usually is that the teachers remove
their mask while teaching and that everybody else stays masked we've got HEPA filtration in the big system and
these little blue air filters all around so just make eye contact with me and let
me know whether or not that's all right with you okay all right great
okay now that I'm not wearing a mask is the volume still okay or am I blowing
you away so welcome to part two of a five-part
introduction to meditation series my name is Dawn Neil Tanya Weiser
already introduced herself and um just want to offer a really brief
overview of the highlights from last week the first week
this is a mindfulness course mindfulness meditation course and as many of you
probably know mindfulness meditation or mindfulness in general can be engaged in without being Buddhist
there's absolutely no requirement that you change your beliefs in any way
this is a cultivation of learning a certain kind of intimacy with life
of what's Happening while it's happening rather than thinking about it imagining
it projecting it remembering it and so that intimacy that checking in
with what's happening while it's happening is a more kind of direct experience than
living in the world of ideas what this tends to cultivate is the
capacity for choice but capacity for a distance between what is happening in
our world or in our minds and our response to it and um
that choice in um sort of the Buddhist ethics that we draw
on allows the possibility for non-harming a
life of non-harming and I like to think of it as non-harming
begins at home and our bodies our home our hearts our minds our home
so this body this heart this mind is where
we're going to be exploring and the home base for most of us here
is the breath and we use some kind of terms of art or special language that
I'll explain briefly um the breath is the home base
of where to bring the attention back to for most meditators that's also
sometimes called the anchor the anchor of your meditation or the object of attention so if we talk
about an object of attention we're just talking about what we're paying attention to on purpose
so you'll hear each of us use those words interchangeably
so meditating or many many forms of meditation but
mindfulness meditation is observing with awareness seeing knowing what's
happening here now while it's happening it's like a naturalist observing nature
and it's helpful in that process to
take an external posture that's comfortable but alert so you can just check in with how you're sitting now
and an internal posture or stance that is also balanced
open receptive kind forgiving
maybe even a little bit playful or experimental
so we covered two sitting two postures meditation postures last week sitting
and standing there's not time to go through the different sitting postures tonight later in the night I'll touch on
lying down as an option as well and and later on in the course we'll
talk about walking meditation so
that's a very brief overview does um if
you if there's anything else you want to say I think you could take a couple more minutes if there's just just saying if
you feel like there's okay um I think I'd like to see what
questions are in the room and then maybe I'll say a word or two after that so
does anybody have questions either based on what I've heard so far or based on what I've said so far what you've heard
so far or um from last week
we got a lot of people here who've done the class before or have never done the class at all so yeah so I think what I'd
like to do if you're all right with it is for us to start with names [Music]
maybe we can just go around and with Tanya
my name is Chelan
thank you Michael and Grace I'm Scott I'm Kevin
I'm Loki hi everyone Andrew
and Tanya great great
so um just tapping into what might be helpful
for those of you who have is there anyone here who's never meditated never
looked at an instruction nothing no okay
um I think maybe the only other thing that
is really important to say is that um
it's always always okay to begin again and again and again
and if thoughts are popping into your head or distractions are popping into your head and your mind is going all
over the place to just be easy with it it's pretty rare in meditation that
thinking stops and it's not necessarily what we're trying to cultivate especially when beginning
it's much more about a hopeful healthy relationship to what's
happening in our hearts and minds and bodies that the incredible skill that this
practice confers and if I were to distill
all of Buddhist practice mindfulness practice down to one sentence I would
say the core of it is about relationship how we relate to reality
so that's what I have Tanya would you like to add anything before moving into the
instructions
I think I'll um since I'm talking next I think I'll go ahead and whenever you're done with this
section I'll just sort of maybe add my pieces and okay great
so we teach the class progressively we first week we focus on breath so that's
what we talked about last week was mindfulness of breathing and sort of the experience of where you
can feel the breath at the nose and the back of the throat the chest the belly
helping ourselves sort of invite ourselves to let the belly relax
so maybe put your hands over your belly buttons with me for a moment
see if you can breathe in and press your hands out with your breath letting your
belly really poke out
so it's shifting or breathing from a lot of us do chest breathing
and so the idea here is try and breathe into the hands expand the belly it's going to feel artificial and weird to
get started and then with exhale press you know the belly in with the
hands and help bring the belly button toward the spine breathe out more air than you brought in
and then you'll feel yourself wanting to take a breath go ahead and let it come in deep and
you'll feel it's starting to right come in a little deeper easier just repeat that a few times right so breathing in
pressing the belly out with the hands our hands out with the belly
really full and then the exhale pushing and using your hands to support the belly button
going toward the spine and pressing out more air than you breathed in
and then waiting to feel that wanting to breathe and really allow to come down in
and deep could I see some bellies moving
Can you feel it in your belly you feel like you got the diaphragm oh yawning that's a good indicator
nice anybody feeling like they can't quite get it
oh okay good so just now allowing your breath to return to however it wants to
breathe this is just a nice practice when we get started to help us find that full breath
another thing is to lift those shoulders up and roll them back
kind of a counter stretch to how we go through most of the day in our lives
and you can press the elbows down towards your hips
kind of keeping the shoulders back but then allowing the hands to rest in your
lap or on your legs
so becoming connected to our breath can be very helpful for meditation it's
often kind of the core anchor object of attention sort of the
tether the things that kind of helps us stay connected to the present moment
you might just take a three breath Journey right now just see if you can't stay intimately connected with
your breath like kind of like writing a wave sort of the really letting it come in
and lift you up rising up and then the wave recedes just staying
really close to that whole expansion and contraction
seeing if there's a pause at the end of the exhale at the top of the inhale
just staying right with it just three breaths just three breaths
and then notice how you feel just notice what how it
felt to take a three breath Journey do you feel any different
you feel any more present a little bit yeah
sometimes um when we're having a meditation period it
can be helpful to come back to this idea of just three breaths just try and be with three breaths in a
row especially if we're struggling to stay present with our thinking or emotions
you know too much try this three breath Journey any point in your meditation
it's a goal that feels pretty doable and just and just enough to help us kind
of reset sometimes
so the amazing thing about breathing is um it is we can be aware of just the breath
but we also can feel the breath in the whole body
and just just see for a moment or two just see what happens if you just kind of open your
awareness up to fill your whole body here and experience your body breathing
what can you notice
you might want to once again take a longer deeper breath just because that gives you a little bit of an extra oxygen
boost that sometimes is very tangible in the body
it looks like you are all fairly comfortable with being with your breath is that correct is anybody
uncomfortable with the breath
no everybody's okay all right great
so let's imagine let's just pretend you were at class last week
you had these instructions you started to feel this intimacy with
the breathing and that you spent time cultivating your
relationship with breathing this last week he meditated or maybe you were aware of
your breathing as you walked around imagine sort of just doing that in and
out of the flow of your life now you might be feeling a little bit
more connected to the experience of breathing this this week after a week of
practicing
maybe you would have experienced some moments of like oh that was helpful
like remembering to take some breaths you know
and so this week we'll expand and this week the practice will be to start to
tune into the body the whole body and the experiences through the body
and that doesn't mean you won't notice breathing okay right so you're going to still
notice breathing but we're going to kind of expand like it's like growing the circles of
awareness so last week we were working more on the breath and now we'll grow it a little bit and include all the
experiences that can happen through the body seeing touching smelling tasting
hearing Sensations in the whole body
but before we start you know I start giving instructions on how to do mindfulness of the body
you're going to hear this a lot I think from Donna and I we both emphasize this a lot which is this idea of
how are we relating to our body
and you know what what is your relationship with your body like
you know some people really feel at home and comfortable in their body and some people really feel
very uncomfortable in their body there's a James Joyce novel that starts
with uh describing the main character who lives just a little bit outside of his body
so when you think about yourself how much of you do you think lives and
grounds in your body and how much of you stays a little bit removed ahead of or
away from that felt sense of the body
so the you know if we if we're someone who tends to not be that comfortable not
that at home in our body it could either feel really great
to come home to the body or it also can sometimes mean that we feel feelings
that we haven't been wanting to feel so just
as much as you can be very compassionate with yourself and try and stay with what arises
I was trying to stay close to that feeling of the body sometimes we trust our body bodies a lot
we have a real like to me there's this awe you know like
we don't have to tell our body how to eat how to digest the food that we eat
just does it or to clean it out or to pump the blood
or like the body knows how to do this it's remarkable it has so much
intelligence in it can you imagine if we had to try and tell the body what to do with all these
processes that are going on and sometimes things happen in our lives
that trigger a sense of mistrust in our body because we get sick or something happens
so just check in right now and notice where's my trust level with my body
right now it's important to honor what is
comfortable for you but what can you trust about your body
the hair grows my eyes blink I breathe
there's another part of our experience that can impact our relationship with our body which is kind of the commentary
The Narrative that we might have like I should be skinnier I should be more fit
I should be taller I should be shorter you know I should have
brown eyes or green eyes or blue eyes you know I should have curly hair no I
should have straight hair no I should have long hair short hair you know I shouldn't be balding I should be you
know like I should shave it all up there's so many messages that we get and can carry around
that have that affect our ability to settle in and be comfortable in the body
that we have
and this matters because we need to kind of understand are we coming to our body
with a sense of trust and comfort contentment as best we can
or are we hesitating or feeling critical
because that that energy of being critical or distancing or not wanting to
be in our bodies will affect our experience in meditation and so it's you
may not be able to change that but it's good to know it that inner posture the inner
relationship to ourselves and as much as possible be soft and kind
around it whatever's there
the thing about the body is it itself is not ruminating
Isn't that cool we our minds are but our bodies are not ruminating right the body is just
feeling and being present it's aware and vibrant
in in other words it's already mindful
so the body is this incredible Gateway incredible way for us to find the
present moment because you know if you just sit here
for a second and feel the sensations they're they're happening right here
they're changing you know can you feel into the sensations in your body
it's um the sensations are like the language of the body
it's how the body communicates it tells us a lot you know those feelings of butterfly when you're nervous well it's
actually connected to the brain and communicating you know what we're sensing
so there's a lot of wisdom for us to tune into in the body
the way that we let the body know it's heard is that we feel
it's like the listening is to feel to receive the sensations to receive the signals
Body Sensations can be pleasant and unpleasant and neither
kind of more neutral so sometimes it can be helpful just to have a very simple noting of oh this is
a pleasant sensation or this is unpleasant or I don't know this is neutral this is
neither plus a nor unpleasant and then just if we're having in
particular when we're having unpleasant Sensations just trying to keep it really simple and Don will talk about pain
working with pain in the body later you know
so you know are you any of you sports fans watch sports Nancy back there
how do you feel about the commentators in in sports
uh-huh yeah so you know I'm sure even if you aren't sports fans you've watched sports
right and you've heard the commentators right and they really pump up the energy
and some of them are too much maybe like Nancy's saying and others may be more
subtle right depending on the sport or the commentator and
um but if you can imagine whatever sport you might be thinking of in the moment imagine the volume off
you're watching the sport and there's no commentator
just seeing if you're watching tennis the flow maybe hear the you know ball or football
or you know whatever it is baseball soccer just seeing seeing the moment in
your mind's eye watching the sport without any comments
just the natural flow seeing things moving can you feel how different that might be
to watch the sports without the commentator I see grace saying yes anybody else can
you imagine how different that would be so in the same way actually when we're
meditating it's possible to turn off the commentator
to turn the volume way down anywhere to stop tuning in to the inner commentator
so just by tuning in just to the sensations to the flow of the breath to
the experience of hearing if you're having a hard time as you
meditate because the commentator is really going maybe open your eyes it's okay to open your eyes
what we want is to be present and we we need to trust
what helps us be present so even though we might invite you to close your eyes
if you're having a hard time orienting and it helps you to open your eyes please open your eyes
one little thing that after sometimes when we open our eyes we need to orient like we need to actually look around for
a minute help us it's sort of like helping us oh yeah okay this is where I am
okay everybody else is meditating too okay I'm all right you know sometimes
that's kind of what we need to do after we do that then it can be
it can help settle if we just gaze like a 45 degree Slant with our eyes down on
the soft carpet just a soft dropping of the eyes
and and then let it sort of just be you know a little blurry
we take in a lot when we look around there's a lot of stimulation in the visual world
and so we need to learn how to direct our
awareness right and be with what we're directing so let's do a little experiment in this
regard to learning how to move our awareness around to choose what we focus
on so let's start by feeling our feet
so just what do you first notice just being aware
and then see if you can kind of let your feet be flat and really feel maybe even
pressed down a little bit and see if you can feel even pressure
on the inside outside edges the front and the back of the feet where they're making contact with the
carpet or the cushion maybe you can even tune in to where the
arch is that isn't pressing into the surface
that's feeling the sensations of the bottom of the feet and then maybe wrapping the awareness up to the top of
the feet and feeling you know sort of the tops of the toes maybe even
can you feel into where the toenails are and if you can't feel just imagine this
whole Space nothing wrong if you don't feel any of
these details you can just hold your awareness around the area of your feet
and then just hold the foot the both feet as a whole
seeing what you can open to and sense into heat cool
tingling pressure skin touching skin like the toes
pressing into each other all these different things that we can feel and just our feet
and with the next inhale and exhale letting go of the feet
and then bringing your awareness up into like the head and the neck
is sort of exploring this area feeling maybe the jaw
cheeks nose
temples eyebrows maybe the forehead and with that
forehead just seeing if you can't take a deep breath in and invite not
forcing anything but just inviting a little bit of a relaxation in the face
we tend to hold a lot of tension in our eyebrow area eyes and face and jaw
[Applause]
I hear a yawn that's always good and then notice the top of the head
see if you can feel the hairs on your head
and then again expanding to feel the the whole of the head the front the sides
the back just feeling the sensations
how it feels different in the face than it does in the neck than it does on the head and the ears
and then taking a breath in and out letting go of the head and neck
and then let's place our hands if they're not already touching put your hands together
and fill your hands
just notice what you can feel build where they're warm when they're touching or maybe they're cold
Can You Feel the space in the middle of the Palms that aren't touching can you
feel what isn't tuck being touched
noticing the difference between the palms and the backs of the hands and how they feel different
how the air might be very gently very lightly cool when it where it
touches your hands
and then with the next inhale and exhale letting go of the hands
and then let me ask you what happened to your feet when you were paying attention
to your hands laughs or your head when you are paying
attention to your feet did you know you had a head when you were paying attention to your feet
you just did an amazing practice of moving your awareness of choosing what
you were paying attention to and it was all about Sensations and
experience you were having in your body in this moment
so it's not that we lose our hands our feet or head when we're paying attention
to something else they're always there
but we prioritized being aware of these body parts in this exercise
and so as we move into more of this meditation practice on the body
the invitation is to prioritize being aware of Sensations in the body
doesn't mean you won't have thoughts or feelings emotions
you're just going to kind of prioritize what you're taking in what you're giving your awareness
which is what your most precious commodity in my view what you're giving your awareness to
what you're tuning it into
so it's very helpful to do this kind of as we did here with this light sense of curiosity and investigation
we were sort of exploring together would you say so bringing this this kind of inner
relationship like this inner relationship of being curious attentive
right we were very attentive here
and we're sort of exploring what's happening how are things unfolding
did anyone try to make their feet feel a particular way
right we just came to see what was there and so this is the idea this is we just
had this perfect experience to help you right this reference of oh how did I do it oh yeah yeah
right so you don't need to make anything happen in your meditation
no two meditations will be the same it's really about opening up and being
with our experience tuning into what's happening in the present moment without a lot of the
extra commentary just the simple like noting maybe cool or warmer hands or sensation right
neutral unpleasant feelings whatever just just that little bit that's all we need
all right so you're all already meditating it feels
to me so we'll just kind of continue here for a little bit longer
and we'll start I'll start you with some guidance that's going to be focusing on the breath
just as kind of to give you that experience of tuning into the breath
and then we'll you know open it up a little bit to the body
so you might take a moment to adjust your posture maybe a rock back and forth
or front and back and just stretch a little bit maybe move the shoulders or you know
stand up if you want to do standing practice
and when we when we're sitting formally it's very helpful to be very conscious
about it sort of like okay we need to kind of tune tell our brains and our bodies okay
it's time we're gonna pay attention to our experience we're going to meditate
you know so all right so in this posture and taking a posture that's upright
so just a little bit of an uplift feeling like the head reaching toward
the ceiling and we're not if we slouch forward we're
going to cut off our capacity to breathe and we'll get kind of sleepy so we want to kind of pull it up and roll those
shoulders back feel the feet firmly planted and find the hands in a comfortable
posture and take a few deep breaths yeah
and notice if you're you know breathing with a diaphragm right now on
automatically and if you're not you might want to take
those conscious deeper belly breaths
it's kind of helpful pretty much every time I sit down I start with a few longer slower deeper breaths really
consciously breathing and helping reset my system
and so okay mind and body here we are
we are ready to pay attention to our experience of breathing
may I tune in to my experience of breathing and be curious and interested
and stay connected
you might just start by noticing the feeling of the breath it comes and
goes from the nostril area
can you feel the way that it feels different to inhale the air past your
nose versus exhale it
and you can also notice the feeling of the breath and the throat the back of the throat and
sort of massaging the chest and the belly
and just getting a feel for where is it easiest for me
to stay connected to breathing what part of the breath sit down in the belly
sit at the nose where is it easiest for me tonight
right now to feel the breathing and wherever that is just spend a few
breaths tuning in and being curious about that
area that experience
and you might notice at some point that your mind wants to think about something
it's what Minds do you think
so it's not a problem right just allowing the mind to have its thoughts
and if you happen to get caught up in thinking
some point you'll remember oh oh yeah
I was trying to pay attention to my breathing
which means you're already mindful
which means we can just be like great
that's right I want to notice my breath
that's all that's all
how does this breath feel
thinking's nature it's not a problem
we're working not on trying to make it not happen but just to change oh maybe how an enum how unraptured we
are by it to maybe be able to choose when we want
to think and pay attention to the Watson when we want to direct our awareness
to a different part of our experience
so if thinking is strong or emotions are strong you could just note oh thoughting
thinking's happening or emotion
just taking a few more of three breath Journeys here
and then allow your awareness to just open up to the whole body
wherever there's prominent Sensations or feelings
in the body just allowing those to be known be received
member Sensations is the language of the body and feeling them is how they're heard
just tuning in again to the sensations
maybe a gentle label of pulsing
cool warm keeping your awareness more on this
experience than on the name
maybe noticing hearing
[Music]
so there are two microphones on the floor which you both pick those up and
turn them on there's a little button to push just kind of push it in and hold it pressed and you get your little green
light that's right and um you know this class is being
recorded so it's very helpful to use the microphone to speak into
and we're going to take a few minutes Don and I both to we would like to hear from you about what did you notice how
was it for you what was easy what was hard
do you have a question it's really a benefit to all of us if
you could share a few words about your experience and so Grace are you willing
to share something
batteries out a technical note if you hold it kind of
like this close close and sort of like pointing at your mouth
it picks up
um maybe it's the energy of being together I was able to concentrate on
breeding better than doing it myself and this became easier to just
concentrate on breathing so that was my experience tonight and your boys very calming that really
helps stay with it beautiful yeah usually my thought just goes everywhere
and I can continue yeah so I'll just keep up but
today was very um I was able to sustain that peace just
culture and breathing um I like that great thank you Grace
thank you sharing and I'll start on this side I'm Scott and I had a rough day at the office I
thought I would cheat and have a drink before I came decided not to this is actually so relaxing as my first
meditation I almost find myself almost falling asleep twice which I normally don't do at this hour so it was really
interesting just seeing how calm and relaxing it took the stress of
the day away
hello dawn hello Tony hello everyone yes I I too as Scott was saying I was very
relaxed which is why I was trying to keep my eyes open rather than clothes for this meditation because
um I did try the from last week's class the whole focusing on one area and then
just kind of zoning it out like keeping it within like my periphery kind of worked but then I
I found myself closing my eyes and then I'm like no I'm falling asleep so let me open them again and
but it was okay not trying to resist anything and just being mindful of the
breath and what else just knowing when I wasn't focusing on that just
going back to that and it's just it's like Ping Pong back and forth yeah I'm
like okay but um I was it was nice to know as Don had mentioned that in
meditation thinking is always present I mean but the awareness practice with the feed
in the hands it was very simple but then I realized oh my my presence isn't so
much in my body but up here and right and I I'm like oh I sometimes I bring
whatever's up here into my meditation and then it's I'm aware of something that I would rather not be aware of
rather than just on the breath and just sitting and being
I was thank you great great chair thank you
thank you great
hi my name is Chelan um what I've found is that it really it
really um is a real add-in to my life because I
find that if I really practice this breathing um when I go when I gone go to bed and
I'm thinking about all the things from the day and so I just focus on the breath and my body and you know just
relaxing and wow I'm out so it really is helpful that
way I mean I'm doing it on purpose so I now if I sit here and I yeah then
I'm not doing that on purpose but it really helps helps me at night to just calm down and be able to doze off
great Nathan did you no
foreign am I allowed to fall asleep like maybe
not in the beginning but like I've heard of like monks kind of falling asleep and it's like that's okay
yeah there are different schools I've thought about this as a beginner or relative
beginner it's helpful to try to stay awake um and unless you're using it
intentionally I do the same thing at night I breathe myself to sleep and depending on the style of meditation
it can be possible to watch your mind descending into sleep
so I don't recommend trying it at first necessarily but you could play with that at night and see
like what what's the last thought I noticed what's the last breath I notice
that's interesting thank you
anyone have any questions about the instructions anything that didn't feel very clear
or you want repeated or said differently
yeah thank you hi um when you when I'm concentrating on
the breath and the commentator the Mind start you know disrupting or talking too
loud um I find it difficult to concentrate on the breath again so what I do is I I
don't know if it does okay but I just get one word and I just repeat it and
repeat it and repeat it until the comments go away and then go back into
the breath is that a no no a good thing
so there are so many different kinds of meditation and sometimes repeating one
word can be like a mantra meditation if you're trying to practice mindfulness
meditation you may try one word that's linked to your physical experience
like breathing or sitting or thinking
okay for me I find it super helpful to name whatever process is happening in a
simple way just naming that thinking is thinking okay
pops the awareness out of getting sucked into the thinking
and that cultivates that muscle that Tanya's talking about that strength
so I don't know is that helpful at all yeah thank you and it's totally valid there are entirely valid traditions of
meditation that do use a word in fact in
some beginning meditation courses people will count from one to ten and Back
Again so if my mind is going absolutely Bonkers sometimes I still do that like
count the breaths exactly counting the breaths one on the in-breath one on the out breath two on the in-breath two on
the out breath so and that keeps it again linked to your physical Sensations
okay yeah it was really skillful what you did I mean it worked right I just
said one one one one great yeah uh so the commentator went away
beautiful so you know that's that's an example of um
choosing what you put your awareness on you were choosing to put it on the word
one right now like Don's saying try and Link it with what's hap something that's
happening right because that's the that's the kind of Pinnacle of mindfulness pain you know the present
moment practice of mindfulness but very skillful thank you yeah it doesn't work to try
and fight with the thinking if you haven't noticed if you try and get in there and argue with it you're
just still thinking so you did a nice job of Shifting your awareness you were choosing
that's beautiful thank you
all right okay so that's also a beautiful example of
creativity and meditation right and we want to encourage you to experiment and
find ways that work for you it's okay to bring your intelligence your creativity
even a little bit of your imagination to your present moment experience the key
is to your present moment's experience imagination can easily go spinning off into
the virtual reality engines we all carry around inside of us
so um I'm gonna do a little bit of a talk
about working with discomfort and pain but before I start I'm going to model a
lying down posture right here on the floor and just to name
that for me I started I came in through what we call the ducadorway the
discomfort or pain suffering doorway into meditation so the lying down posture was my only
option for the first year or so so you don't need to do it in some ways it
is the most challenging posture because as many of you have noticed when the mind starts getting relaxed what are we
conditioned to do it's right fall asleep so but if you find you know you've got
awful back pain or hip pain or neck pain or something I just want to provide this
as an alternative and it's a completely valid form there's
many descriptions of the Buddha meditating lying down so he had a bad back towards the end of
his life so we're going to try this with the icon
offer a couple of quick options you're welcome to use a little pillow
behind your head or under your neck if that's helpful or one under your knees
I find it helpful to use if the intent is to stay awake and meditate a different spot or a different posture
than I sleep in so
one option is to leave your knees up like this and
you tint them so that they support each other and the pressure is very light as if
it's just enough to maybe hold a piece of paper between your knees
or and or you can lift one hand up or
some people do both hands up 90 degrees
it is pretty much impossible to fall asleep during this because as soon as you start
we'll do that and that wakes you up usually before your hand even hits the ground
and then another option is to take some kind of intentional posture with the
hands like this or this
so that's a way of relaxing your nervous system very quickly physically
and a really safe place to play with this is in bed at night before you're
ready to go to sleep because if you fall asleep it's all good you win either way
so working with pain
one of the most maybe the most helpful thing is
again Tanya and I keep talking about noticing your relationship to what's happening
noticing the relationship to any discomfort in the body I'm talking here
tonight about physical pain we'll talk about more emotional kinds of stuff later in the course
so um pain is composed of layers there's the
raw Sensation that the nerves are sending to the brain and then there is the layer of the
mental response to it and pain is often
hard to ignore it is designed to be hard to ignore this is not a coincidence right
so any layers of extra reactivity resistance
disliking anger that is directed towards the pain
clinical Studies have shown it does make the subjective experience of the pain worse sometimes much worse
now it's far easier for me to say that from than for any of us to change our relationship to it
however knowing it might be helpful right just knowing that
so um to give one of the most helpful attitudes to bring relationships to
bring is to consider this body your lifelong companion your lifelong
companion and to offer compassion towards that part of the body or just
your whole body as it hurts that mental attitude will often help
soften things some for me when I first started experiencing major pain I blamed myself
and guess what that did right
okay so on a practical level that's noticing the inner commentary
am I bludgeoning the pain am I budgeting myself because of the pain can I be kind can I notice the tone of
my internal voice so that to one way of approaching it
noting labeling as Tanya was talking about is also really helpful
and you can label using hurts or pain it's actually more helpful to drop it
down a level to kind of the raw sensation
so is it burning is it hot
is it contracted intense just noticing all the little Sensations
around it okay so that's another way of working
with it micro Sensations within the pain and each of these techniques work for
different people at different times okay okay I'm naming each of them and you can
use them in concert with each other if the pain is really intense sometimes
it's helpful to be around the edges of it right not dive straight in the middle
although if your mindfulness is strong really focusing on it without aversion
without them or attitude can actually help it decompose to its
the sensations that make it up and it can dissolve or shift or change and to
notice all of the little Sensations that are dissolving shifting changing
when we're having an negative relationship to a
pain it's really easy for it to become really solid and feel kind of like a block
and if we get curious almost nothing in our bodies is actually the same for very long
and so to just notice the shifting notice that and they're even usually
little gaps moments of not pain or places technique number three places
in the body where there are not pain there is not pain when I first started practicing I got
this instruction on the only place I could find was my earlobe
so I focused on my earlobe both earlobes actually so it can be like almost like finding a
safe space in your body tip of the nose works for a lot of people
elbow sometimes toe so um
it's like Tanya was talking about that practice of intentionally Shifting the attention
it's the opposite of the allowing it of the attention to rest in it if that's
too intense shift it somewhere else it can be the whole body maybe the
container your whole body feels better than just that one spot
um so the classic kind of instruction is to turn attention towards the predominant
sensation for as long as it lasts and when it shifts and changes to return your attention
to whatever was your major focus of the whole body the breath
another way of approaching it is um
in that sort of safe space if it's too much is to
practice with another anchor object of attention entirely
and that for many people is sound sound tends to bring us out the
attention outward and I don't know if any of you could just hear the distant sound of the train
I that's a really good example you can almost feel your attention expanding out
to where the sound is that's often the perception and allowing the attention to rest there
can provide a perception of more space
for the sensation to be in so
just to invite all of us to take a few minutes to let that rest
do you have any specific questions about what I just said before I start us in a meditation anything that I said that
didn't make sense okay we'll play with it and there'll be more
opportunity for questions later so finding a comfortable posture
balances relaxation and alertness however makes most sense for you right
now sitting standing lying down
and taking a moment to notice your whole body
just how it is right now in a really General sense
noticing sensations of warmth or cool
contact of your feet on cushion or floor
all of the little emotions and Sensations that let you know this body
is alive
and now allowing the sensation of breathing for just a
moment or two maybe in your belly your diaphragm
to be your anchor
one two three breaths three breath Journey
and then to notice expand the attention through your body
and notice if there are any predominant Sensations other than breathing
it could be discomfort or pain or it could just be something else and
the purpose of experimenting
allowing that that sensation
be the main focus object of attention for a moment
noticing the area around the sensation
noticing any tiny shifts
micro changes within the area maybe a bunch of little Sensations
noticing any way it changes
maybe applying a soft label a mental note
bribing it
and now if it is faded
Shifting the attention again back to the breathing
and when the next sensation comes along besides breathing
allowing that to be in the foreground
noticing the area around it within it
noting simply the difference is there
and now inviting the attention to move to hearing
sound
perhaps the sound of my voice
the soft sounds in the room in the building
distant sounds of movement
outside of the building
noticing the coming and going of sound
noticing the relationship of your mind and your
heart with the sounds
[Music]
so thank you for your practice and now we have another brief period of
questions sharings answers with both Tanya and myself
thank you for the meditation Don you're welcome
what'd you guys notice
hi oh sorry
um for me this standing meditation here really works I the commentator goes away
and I was concentrating it is more focused on my
on my body and the sensations and and so
it was I really like it really on breathing and balance it was that
beautiful me beautiful so let me make sure I understood you you said that
particular meditation session you felt like the commentator really
died back yes uh the previous session I did the
standing too but it was more towards not falling asleep it was to be when I was
sitting down I was so relaxed I was falling asleep yeah but this time the
standard meditation was I barely had a commentator it was just
breathing and and balancing my body to be standing relaxing and and at the same
time aware wonderful thank you
hello um I have a question regarding like when you're
meditating and you're your attention is on the pain whether it
be like a sensation I know for this talk it was about like
body sensation but what if you are thinking about something that's bothering you that's painful but it's
emotional and I suppose like when I do resist I don't
know if that's should I wait next week for the next come back next week it's perfect it's great it's all that's
you're right on track that's right hold that Curiosity yeah yeah
it's a great question [Music] and you can if you have stuff come up
you can use some of these tips just to apply them kindness always helps
what like I found myself in the meditation like oh I I ate too much
before going to the meditation so I'm feeling uncomfortable but I'm like I just noted that and and so that was okay
but like what what else can I say regarding that like oh may I be happy
safe peaceful and and free that that thing I mean beyond that
or just like what else do I say or do I have to say something in particular
so it's a bigger question um you don't need to say anything
necessarily but just like the the shortest version
is it's okay it's okay but you hear the tone of my voice
it's more about the tone than whatever the words are
and just like Tanya has been saying notice it it's great noticing that
you're noticing it that's good mindfulness and so
to feel good about that
any other questions or comments I'm really curious how that meditation
was for some of the other people in the room
did you ever come it looked like you were I was kind of rubbing my knee but I do have a question
oh my God thank you Mike I'm a bad I have a bad knee and it's been bothering me but um earlier you had said something
along the lines that a researcher study showed something about exacerbating the pain if you thought I was wondering if
you could repeat that I didn't catch that part yeah yeah so um clinical pain psychologists research
psychologists have discovered that um
catastrophizing pain or having a really negative attitude about it or like oh
this is going to last forever and it's horrible and it's going to get worse all of those things actually increase our
subjective experience of the pain like it actually feels worse
um even this is a little Jedi mind trick that I didn't think to put in the talk but
um calling it my pain can make it stronger and allow and just noticing pain is
arising or discomfort is arising can disidentify with it a little bit so that
it is not quite as strong so it's so much about what you were
talking about like that that voice that commentary is um
a lot of what can help lock it in or increase it or start to
ease it a little bit it's it's both psychology and sensation is in pain
I hope was that helpful yeah yeah that's very helpful I just kind of missed that part it might be a question for next
week though but I wonder how that is also related to like the um psychological pain or the emotional pain
well I'll say one real quick thing which is that actually physical pain and
emotional pain share the same circuits in the brain so they are very connected and and in
fact there's studies now that are being done on painkillers and how they can
affect your emotional states so yep Tylenol I saw one in particular
in Tylenol that um so there you go
a quick bit um so I've been coming here for a few months now and then today traffic was hectic and I thought I
should just turn around I'm not going to have good meditation session or whatnot but I was able to drop into the mindfulness and and have a good
meditation session but I've noticed I used to have a judgey part of myself when I first started coming here my mind
is wandering I'm thinking about something embarrassing that happened and I'd really Snappy judgy and now I notice
myself being a lot more compassionate but I'm starting to mourn at the old uh
um sort of uh judge EB but yeah that's just something I noticed today that's beautiful great example of noticing how
you're relating the inner relationship it's this this practice is
you can't do this practice without paying attention to how you're relating to yourself yeah
it's so critical it makes all the difference it will
completely impact your experience of meditating
me too
so let me shift and just give you um just a reminder as you hopefully you all got a handout
on the second side it has your your homework
so the invitation is to practice for 20 minutes every day
I always like to say you know it's more important that you practice every day than for 20 minutes so if you
can't do 20 to 15 if you can't do 15 do 10 if you can't do 10 do five if you
can't do 10 do two right or five you could do two but and
you can also break it up so the goal is to try and get 20 minutes of practice every day
yeah so this week mindfulness of the body
that the what we were doing in in this sculpt room together that's what we want
you to practice this week and the handout will have some beautiful instructions for you to help you
remember so um
another invitation is that you know during a two-hour period of the week
being mindful of your body while you're doing something right periodically noticing what's
happening your shoulders your stomach your face your breathing right just
noticing tension and just ease and try and relax when you
find yourself tensing up the third thing invitation is to do one
meal mindfully eating this really practice mindfulness of
eating it's the body and wow there's some great things to start to notice
you might start salivating before you get your food in your mouth you know if you take your time you'll you can notice
these things and then the fourth is to kind of be curious about when when it
is your attention gets distracted or fragmented or you know
pulled into something that you don't you didn't really Choose Or wouldn't want to choose to pay attention to so start to
notice what your patterns are where do you get caught where does your attention get snagged in something
um and then if you have if you have anybody you're talking to about meditation take
time to share what you're noticing with them
we're over a minute so let me move quickly then into just the dedication of Merit which is
um you know we have in this in this lineage it's very important to understand that
we practice for ourselves others and both right we that we benefit ourselves but
as we benefit ourselves we benefit others and it benefits both and that we it's very helpful to
acknowledge this and so may we dedicate the benefits of
this practice to all beings everywhere without
exception may all beings benefit from being able to direct their awareness
and tune into how they're being aware of their experience
[Music]
[Music] thank you so much thank you for your
kind attention and engagement lovely to be here with you and Donna and I will be
back next week so we'll be talking about emotions expanding the circle after a wider
all right take care you guys