yeah good morning good day everybody
I'll begin our third day of Stillness and the movement Adventure
so today I will be continuing um this theme of
Stillness and movement will be incorporating Stillness in the movement with emotions
as well as well as the body
okay let's begin
take a few moments to settle into the space you're in
allow this arriving and entering into this body and mind and heart
to be a gradual process not rushing pushing
and being gentle kind
arriving Here and Now
entering into the Temple of this body mind and heart
making our seat
maybe just this words already evokes a sense of
grounded and uplifted
what's the felt sense of a settling into this body mind and heart
feeling and sensing
your own experience
maybe the global sense of the body posture
sitting lying down
maybe the contact of the body with the floor Earth
earthy body resting on Earth
giving this body to The Wonder of a gravity
nothing to do naturally settling down
the earthy part of the body is naturally grounding
stabilizing
solid steady
somewhat still
resting in the Stillness in the body
maybe just a hint of it or relatively still
doesn't have to be some kind of a grand levels of a
Stillness it's a relatively unmoving
study quiet
sitting like a mountain
there's a fears resonant
you can simply rest here maybe that's enough
otherwise you can follow the words
open to receive the felt sense of the movements of the
breath
and Stillness highlights the movements
becomes obvious
leaving and sensing
the sensations of the movements in the body
however they may show up for you
maybe it's the flow of the breath
coursing through the Torso
maybe it's the expansion and contraction
that's everything moves through the body
nothing to do or simply becoming available
for the natural movements and the Stillness in the body
and other Sensations in the body may become
felt invisible
energetic field
pulsations vibrations
tingling
sway
whatever may be available
to the motion of the sensations
feel and sense
and Stillness never left us
in a sense of a lightness may be here
and deepening sense of grounding maybe here
not just the quieting and Stillness in the knowing
in the feeling and sensing
this is the perfect perfect place to rest in
if you like
do you feel wailing open to receive
the movements of the Mind may be waves of emotions
conceiving the Waves by resting
in the vast of Stillness in the knowing
as if you're settling in the bottom of the quiet Lake
and feel and sense the waves on the surface
maybe big waves or small waves
and nothing is felt emotionally
maybe just a tenderness
quiet kindness
version infusion
may have an embodied resonance
a beat or the coolness
related to the emotions
lasting in the bottom of the lake
to feel no sense
sensations of the body May coming
thoughts may come in
all of it can be received without
in the vast quietness
this is a safe place to feel
even if it's unpleasant
letting go of the storytelling of the emotions
lasting in the feeling and sensing
the emotions move
and emotions in your hearts and Minds
and in the body
like the clouds storms
and move through the tall mountain
all Mountain remains I'm moving
at a pleasant unpleasant
abide in the field of peace
and into Stillness
abide independent not claiming to anything in this world
foreign [Music]
today um I brought another
great woman disciple of the Buddha with us
her name is Sona and Sona is very different from the two
women I spoke about in the last two days
and Sona was a known Buddhist times to be a mother or a housewife were the many
children in fact she had
10 children this is kind of a little harder for us to relate to in our modern day life
um but it's not uncommon in the ancient times
maybe ancient India and even maybe it's it's still so in
some part of the world nowadays I know for myself
my grandmother had five children and many in her generation had six seven
eight children and um women Mary very young and so they often
have a lot of kids what is not common for Sona is that all
her kids were doing really well all 10 children were doing really well
that's kind of special and they had their own families their businesses were doing well and
they probably had it you know she probably had to grandchildren and so it was all good
and that's probably not very uh very common
um her husband was a devotee to the disciple of the Buddha
and at some point her husband decided to
join the monastic Sangha with the Buddha and so that left the sauna along with
all her children all her ten children um initially this wasn't quite an issue
and those days often the elderlies were
cared for by the children and all 10 of her children were doing really well so
she decided I'm just going to give away all my possessions and split it over
um across all 10 families 10 children's families and she asked if she could just
stay one with the one child at a time and kind of just rotate this
she didn't have a lot of needs so bear um necessity would do and that was working
well for a while and back then that weren't to really senior centers so that was how
elderlies often being cared for
um but that didn't last very long after some time
and there were began to be disputes
bitterness complaints acquisitions and we probably all know you know
they're probably a bunch of family dramas when in-laws are living
with the with the family and so the challenges with the living with the in-laws have restored to the
test of time from thousands of years ago till now and so that was the case for Sona
that was a saddening okay imagine you know she had given away everything to
all her children and her husband is no longer there to go
back to and so she thought well and there was really no other
option but for her to also join the Buddhism monastic Sangha
and there was no refuge in the children's homes or you know she also had no home of her
own and so she joined the monastic Sangha
that was the only way for her but
um this also turns out to be not easy for Sona joining
um the monastic Sangha of the Buddha uh
she her path a monastic path wasn't like
badass that I saw I described yesterday
or patacharas um when she joined the monastic Sangha she
realized all the way up till that point at that point of her life she had always
lived as a most of her life were kind of like wife
mother grandmother and she had a really hard time to adapt
into a monastic Sangha life and maybe a lot different to live in a
monastic Sangha and he made were the people who you don't really know whether you like them
or not like and don't like them and there are a lot a lot of different
kind of things to do you know maybe the cooties or the cabins
need to be fixed and and they needed to learn to fix the cabins and all of this
kind of things um and she had no clue about those
and by the time she joined a monastic Sangha she was already kind of old and
weak you know wasn't very young and so she
did the things her ways and other nouns did things their ways and she often get
criticized by other nuts maybe they were younger maybe a lot of
them were younger and they would criticize her even on small matters
so that was really tough for her and so
um but Sona one of the prominent qualities of this woman Sona was that
she's courageous strong determined
she wasn't discouraged by any of these challenges that she's facing
so her sincerity dedication and the steadfastness let her one step at a time
on the Dharma path so she just kept at it
you know there is this term that one of my teachers is Philip Moffett sometimes would say
I've got practice the practice not practicing the results and so she
just gave herself over to practice as much as she could
and she probably didn't have a very good memory but she said the Buddha's
teachings in her memory she memorized it by heart and she practiced whenever she
remembered to do so that was kind of a wholeheartedness that
she went forth with this monastic life
and so definitely not like um bada who was very quick to add a
grasp at the teachings um this was not easy and she's like this
Turtle you know going one step at a time but she kept going
and one day this was what happened as she recounted this uh in the Legends of
the teres apadana and so she said
and then nanas left me alone in the retreat for a Buddhist announce
going off with the instruction he kept the water while we're gone
you can see you know this nouns were a little kind of mean when I read this you
know they were all going for retreat and and but they they asked a Sona to go
heat up the water while they're gone but um this is what happened
she said then bring water I poured it into a
small pot after placing it on the hearse
seated I then came toward my heart
just in the Simplicity of those activities pouring water into the small pot and
putting it on the Hearth she sat down and her mind became collected
settled you can say entered into a state of a
samadhi and mindfulness
just so she says seeing the bodies this easedness
essencelessness impermanence throwing off all the defilements
I achieved our hardship
so right in this process she saw the impermanence
not self and she let go of all the defilements
and became one of the awakened women then coming back those nuns asked me
about the hot water through concentration on the fire I quickly made the flame ignite
yes maybe she had a little psychic power or something uh kind of fun
and then astonished the nouns made to that fact available to the Buddha
hearing it Buddha Overjoyed spoke this
verse right now a life lived only for one day undertaken
with a strong effort is better than a century lived inert lacking energy
so she was known to be one of the foremost of the nouns who had courageous
energy courageous effort in this whole process never giving up
I was determined her old age her household holder
conditioning didn't hinder her capacity to practice at all
she practiced the practice patiently and wholeheartedly
one moment at a time I was reflecting that in the age and the
culture well one is constantly pushed for efficiency
speed patience and a wholeheartedness can be
hard to come by and yet this can be one of those most
important qualities and capacity to cultivate
and through this story it may also realize that the meeting
difficulties and challenges are inevitable on our Dharma path
the Buddha experienced immense challenges too before his Awakening
including fear and dread living in the forest and he faced it
and so did this disciple sauna and so will wait
if we were to continue on our own Dharma path
and Jack cornfield said this in his book The Path with the heart
as we follow a genuine path of a practice our sufferings may seem to increase
because we no longer hide from them and from ourselves
when we don't follow the old habits of a fantasy and Escape
we're left facing the actual problems and the contradictions of our life
a genuine spiritual path does not avoid difficulties
or mistakes but leads us to the art of making mistakes wakefully
bring them to the transformative power of our hearts
and so as we rest abide
in the Stillness openness of our heart
we allow the difficulties the storms
to pass through or not to push them away
to run away from them but we're cultivating this capacity
to allow to be with the challenges and difficulties of
our own life and the lives of all beings
so may this be the trans transformative power of our heart
for the well-being of all beings everywhere
thank you everyone for being here
may you all be well