so welcome I'm Nikki in Mountain View California on seated oloney land
and delighted to join you for a happy hour in this moment in time whatever your time zone is and and we are Live on
YouTube um so so I see a small strip of of your faces on top and I'm spot lit in order
to to have privacy so so who wants to say hi who would like to share their
voice their Goodwill their friendliness take it away hey this is uh don from DC hi Don
this is Barbara from Alameda hi Barbara and did I hear
Jesse Jesse here hi Jesse welcome to you both Sarah from New York hi Claire
red and Oakland hi Fred yeah I knew here I'm sure hi everyone
hi Neil hi this is rain from San Francisco hi rain welcome
and bill says hello from Dallas hi Bill Murray Christine huru from Sydney
Australia good afternoon tea I think it's afternoon Sydney good morning from Sunny Japan
says hi here from San Diego Hi Megan from
Palo Alto and Sarah from Toronto we're definitely International we covered the northern
um Southern Hemisphere and high Jamie from Novato who else wants to say hi
Steve from Houston hi Steve welcome and hi Peter from Virginia hi ah sweet I
love uh I love the community gathering in High Berry who sends Metta from DC ah sweet
sweet very sweet oh anyone else any last minute hellos
before we transition hi Vicky from Oakland hi Vicky welcome
great I feel my heart has been warmed up with all the hellos and chat and all the
voices and ah and oh yes we have hello hello
um on YouTube from uh rugosa who says
sends warm greetings from New England sweet so all right let's transition
and I ask you to mute yourselves on Zoom if you are unmuted
and I think Neil for posting information about happy
hour Google groups in chat if you're new to happy hour um you are warmly invited to join the
mailing list it's low in traffic but high in heart where resources are shared and at this
time I change the settings so that the chat will only come to me but I ask you to keep that channel quiet and
um also I start recording for the sake of Audio Dharma
here we go great so hello and welcome everyone
lovely to see you beautiful to be with you
um so today I'd like to
um invite us to consider oh it's called a um a masquerader of
meta or In classical language in the teachings of meta it's considered a near
enemy of meta and that is love with attachment love with attachment with
clinging with expectation Etc and a lot of times uh for us
um it could actually be a bit of a puzzle what what is meant
how can you love how can you love someone without this attachment because of course we're
attached to people that we love and our friends and family how so how does this
thing work anyway what's um can you just willy-nilly like not like them kind of be aloof from them
I'm going to say a couple of words and then transition into meditation so that we explore it together
so the idea here is um loving without conditions so hear the
word attachment is set a sense of expectation of either reciprocity or or
or um wanting them expecting them to do something for your love you back it's in
a way if you think of generosity of heart think of love as generosity love
and care is something that we give really so if you were generous if you were generous to someone with this
expectation with an attachment that oh I'm going to be generous to them so that
they're generous back to me um so that I give him a gift oh they give me a gift as well a bigger gift
and not to say there is anything wrong with it it's not a sin it's just it
causes um suffering it causes more pain it causes expectations it gets entangled it
gets complicated whereas if you look into your heart and remember a time that
you truly truly gave something maybe a gift maybe something of your resources
you gave money you gave your time you gave your affection your attention
with absolutely no expectation um of this being or organization giving
something back to you it was just truly a gift from your heart without a
quote-unquote attachment without expectation can see you can feel
to your own experience that that was a much Freer much easier much
hmm just more Joyful Way To Give
So Meta is the same way this idea of metal without attachment or love without
attachment whether it's for friends family people we know we don't know Etc it's a sense
of care it's a sense of um Good Will friendliness again there's so many nuances
with meta that um you're giving your friendliness without expectation of being paid back
or or being loved back or cared for in return and it's a much
um Freer freedom nibana you know these these words are
synonyms of one another it's much Freer way to care so that's what I like to
invite us to explore and and relate to today in our practice so
so with that let's uh let's explore let's sit
get into our meditation posture maybe you need to move left and right a bit
forward and backwards ah find the center of gravity for your
body maybe roll your shoulders back
and arriving in this body
Landing with an open heart
without attachments to outcome
as if we give ourselves this gift of this practice
generously with no expectations
happens if you release this tightness of expectation
we don't let go of aspiration which is our values our intentions
what uplifts our heart but we let go of expectation
She's Tight demanding limiting
see what happens if you sit if you arrive in this moment
generosity of heart towards yourself towards this moment
bringing your good will your kindness letting go of expecting how it needs to
be letting go of control [Music]
relaxing the body softening the mind softening the heart
relaxing the Mind relaxing softening see if there is tightening there's
expectation if there's a narrative that the mind is clinging to I expect this I
expect that I want this
notice notice
can there be a softening
can there at least be a seeing that there's attachment to particular outcome
and nothing else would be good enough
relax relax soften Dear Heart oh dear heart there are so many ways to the temple so
many ways to the temple
connecting with the sensations of the body of the breath
and then move through let them be nourishing calming
can there be a sense of kindness good well towards this moment
towards this being who is me can I appreciate
be friendly to myself to my mind
to my body my heart no matter what's happening
even if they're not quote unquote behaving the way I want them to behave right now
can I still be kind friendly care love without attachment to outcome
I've met her for myself
not needing to earn it or do anything to deserve it but just because I exist
I'm a human being and it's hard enough to be a human on this Earth
this body this mind this heart can I love it
her flow feels too strong can I care can I be friendly
just because
and I love myself just as I am
without attachment to outcome
really generously
putting down the shoulds the musts the half turns
can I accept at least myself just as I am the Suzuki roshi sang
you are perfect Just As You Are Perfect Just As You Are
and there is room for improvement can I care for myself with this
spirit
I'm doing the best I can I'm doing the best I can
this being who is me given all the causes and conditions of their birth their upbringing genetics
experiences exposures doing the best they can
I shower this being who is me with friendliness warmth kindness as if
giving them a big warm teddy bear hug
our government
if it's challenging in any way to
meta for yourself without expectation or attachment
perhaps you can see a loving being a compassionate being or
maybe the Buddha or the Quan Yin the paragons of compassion and kindness
holding you with kind eyes without expectation of any outcome
any way you need to be
or anything you have to do it was just showering
sharing with meta with kindness
friendliness warm-heartedness love
foreign
[Music] of Loving Care be nourishing healing relaxing
steadying your heart filling your heart
and now can we turn and offer this kindness this generosity
of spirit of heart to someone we know
a dear friend family member someone we care about could be a pet
and offer them kindness generosity of heart love
meta with no strings attached
without any expectation of reciprocation
any particular way we want them to behave see if it's possible for even a single
second and if it becomes challenging then come
back to yourself and receive it from your compassionate person
foreign
[Music] wishing them well
with no expectations there might be areas of their behavior or the way they
are that you may not approve of or like but not condoning them but can you
wish them well unconditionally
they too are doing the best they can even the causes and conditions
that has brought them to this point in their life
they could do differently they would
for the last minute of this practice can you see both yourself in this this dear being
held and Care unconditional care and love
by this compassionate being and you conjured up maybe a person who's
been loving in your life non-judgmentally or the Buddha
being of light the Sun
shining indiscriminately at everything and everyone
as we bring this practice to foreclose
letting go of any expectations for what should have happened didn't happen during this
practice period letting go with meta with care
no expectations or planted seeds this is an expression of meta
In This Moment appreciation care friendliness towards
yourself you're planting seeds May the seeds we plant together towards
goodness kindness friendliness may they be of benefit
for the Awakening of all beings everywhere may all things be happy may all beings
be free unconditionally including ourselves
thanks everyone everybody's back welcome back
and uh would love to hear from you what was the exploration like what they
should discover either as you're exploring or or um
as as you're meditating any aha moments or any challenges or
um Peter uh your guidance uh allowed me to be
able to more um uh when the second time came around I
I my mind was blank I didn't think I had anything to say but I guess between past
history and your um your guidance about guidelines uh I
said let me start talking and see what comes and wow it was useful to voice it and and just
be vulnerable and and find where where I was at that I didn't know
that's nice beautiful oh that makes me happy to know
and Peter thanks so much for sharing this this is when small groups are
so powerful really powerful in the way of allowing one just as you explore as
you explained to explore for your own sake you're not speaking for the sake of
others but you become surprised wow you go deeper in your understanding and your
Insight exactly as you shared I'm so delighted that you you decided to give
it a try okay let me give it a try let me explore for my own sake and that you
felt safe enough also with in your group to do that
thanks to them as well to offer that to you beautiful yay thanks for that that's
lovely makes me so happy yeah um no please
thanks Nikki um in our group tonight I think there was a great piece of advice that or not
advice but I think a teaching arose um from from one of the the people that
shared which uh which I found really really beneficial so when when I was thinking about
conditional love it has all these layers all this complication all of these conditions and uh the teaching that was
shared was this practice of waking up in the morning and saying how are you doing buddy and just that lightness and that
ease and that uncomplicated relationship I think it just kind of clicked and it made so much sense that you know things
don't have to be so complicated you know we make them complicated so why not just be kind
eat thank you for sharing that thank you for sharing that wisdom from your group this this lightness right because these
layers of conditionality make it kind of heavy like like a lead balloon it's just
it's heavy whereas you take the lead out you just let it be light as a balloon with something like oh yeah how are you
doing buddy just oh this expression of care I love it I love it how beautiful thanks love very sweet
oh oh open for for any other Reflections
also in chat if you like to type them to me directly I will read the
reflections without your name and I'm glad that uh you found the
comments about crosstalk helpful this is great makes me happy Jesse
yeah thanks thank you for this guidance and this teaching today I appreciate you mentioning like the images of the Buddha
or like just kind of more neutral images that are much easier for me to work with images of a Buddhist statue and I also
used like a single blade of grass just growing from the ground just like
plants kind of blossoming and flowering and like seeking towards the light and
somehow to me that's that's like a a visual of unconditional love even though
I'm not sure maybe not other people would see it that way but somehow it just resonates as it's just like a
growth towards the Sun oh beautiful thanks for bringing this in
Jesse what oh that that uplifts my heart and as you were saying that also something else came to my mind as I was
looking actually in the image behind me the sunflowers because they're so happy right they're just unconditionally
smiling at you no matter who or what you are they're just loving you right that's
what I love about sunflowers they make me happy so that's the same scent so I I guess I could have suggested
um blade of grass as well as sunflowers
yeah thanks for bringing that in that's great beautiful
ah well thank you all thank you for engaging with this practice my heart
feels lighter and happier for having spent this time with you thank you for
bringing your yourself your whole self your whole heart to this beautiful
practice our community our world is a better place because we we engage in
this way together so thank you everyone may you be well may you be happy may you
be free and may your practice benefit not just yourself but all things
everywhere may all beings be well may all beings be free
thanks everyone