hello everyone and
happy to be here with you happy to welcome you and um
and there's something that begins to happen maybe for many of us
if we pay attention if we allow it to be the case something begins to happen as soon as we
put ourselves into our meditation posture especially if we've been doing it for a
long time it's a familiar posture and the
associations are there the orientation the
the Body Mind hearts
inclination to become meditative
is um you know can kind of kick in and and one of the consequences of sitting
down to meditate or one of the aspects of it
is that it it is a stopping if you're sitting
in meditation seated meditation you've stopped activity other activities
moving about in your mind hopefully you've stopped
searching the web or with your eyes your ears trying to
figure something out trying to search and study and
perhaps it's a stopping of the rumination
Fantasy spinning out there's a kind of a stopping that goes on here
and it's a stopping that is not meant to be a breaking bracing
it's a stopping that's meant to help us
become clear to see more clearly to recognize it's like being on a making
it to a Promontory if this the point
and once we kind of come up to that Vista point we can see the land around us we see it more clearly
and so this stopping in meditation and we stopped you know if it's whatever
is easy to stop we stop and except for mindfulness we stop
moving as much as we can stop a lot of discursive thinking
having conversations and talking about things to ourselves
we might stop tensing sometimes we don't even know how much
we're tensing until we stop and sit down and begin feeling the body
and the body itself will kind of begin releasing the tension which is a kind of a stopping of it
and that this stopping is meant to kind of clear the clouds the fog help us to
see clearly so it's not stopping for its own sake
but stopping so we can see so here we are
some people call it a sacred pause a sacred stopping
in Chinese Buddhism the Chinese pictogram character for
samadhi or samatha is the Chinese character for stop
so somehow the samadhi is a kind of a deep stopping as opposed to a deep attainment
just pause sacred pause so
assuming a meditation posture that
supports you to let the body be still
and gently as the body is still
can you let there be any inner stilling of the body
by relaxing maybe relaxing from the core or outwards
maybe relaxing from outside from the edges into the core
if you're able to feel someplace deep inside that still
peaceful has some quality of not moving and
agitation soft Stillness
Within as you exhale
relax everything around it and settle into that inner Stillness
gently letting the Mind become still
quieting and stopping discursive thoughts you might still have other kinds of
thoughts simple thoughts of meditation but the large conversations in the mind
them become quiet
if they are the fog let that fog clear
the son of awareness has come up
clearing the fog
and with whatever Stillness stopping you can easily do
May that allow you to have a bit more clarity of Mind
Clarity of awareness as you accompany your breathing
there is a kind of stopping that is resignation
giving up and shutting down
and there's the kind of stopping
that is opening up
to gaze upon the view to gaze upon what is here
without interfering
just Clarity letting things come in as clear as they can
interview into perception
if you find yourself thinking a lot consider stopping
consider becoming Stiller and in distilling of the Mind
becoming clearer
and then let that clearing accompany your breathing
or let your breathing accompany the clearness
what can you stop
and in stopping opening to Greater clarity
Here and Now
and as we come to the end of the sitting
for a few moments here assume
that your heart your heart's wish
is to be able to smile and it's on the verge of smiling
if only something else would stop
what needs to stop to make room
for the heart to smile
What Fear what desires disappointments
would need to pause so you can gaze upon the world with a
smiling heart
not because you're making it smile because it's what this what the heart
wants to do it's asking to be able to smile
to be uncovered from the coverings of
fear and desires despair disappointment grief
fantasy the rumination
to allow there to be a pause to all those things
so there can be an uncovering of The Smiling heart
and from that heart to gaze upon the world kindly
kind smile that wishes well for everyone
may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to this third talk on strategies for working with challenges
we have and um
one of the skills one of the ways of developing skills for being with life's challenges
is to um train on the small challenges
life gives many of us huge challenges from time to time
some of them are so big that the legacy of them still live in Us in difficult ways fear and anger and
grief and different things and sometimes it's too much to be able to
sit with it be with it uh to open to it and without having trained without
having prepared the ground would be able to do that some challenges possible you know
especially personal inner challenges that our Legacy of other things that's happened to us
sometimes it's better to do our best to kind of manage with them wisely put them on on
the side until we spend that time preparing ourselves for really
addressing them in a useful way and then training with the small
challenges and the training for this week is to start becoming start asking yourself the
question oh uh what's the what strategy are you using
in relationship to this challenge you're feeling what are you trying to do with it
and simply asking that question and stopping to investigate that is a powerful thing to do because it
begins to pull you out from being entangled or lost in that challenge
it's like stepping back and trying to get the overview What's Happening Here and given what's happening how am I
responding what is my mind my heart trying to do here and there are two general ways that
things to notice whether what's go what the direction you're going makes it harder to be aware
shuts down awareness kind of you get wrapped up or entangled in what's going on
or trapped by it or hindered by it or it's a way or there's a strategy that
has more the effect of helping you to open more help you see more clearly help the wisdom in you to come forth the
wisdom that can only come forth if you're not entangled if you're not lost in it or caught up in it you have to be
able to step back pause and make room for some for wisdom clarity
compassion to kind of show itself in a way it can't show itself if we're entangled or caught in what's happening
and this is also why it's so powerful jamilia asked the question what's happening here and what am I trying to
do and so in terms of trying to this week using the hindrances as a reference for
the five hundreds for what this dysfunctional ways of being with challenges today it's the third hindrance which is
usually translated into English as sloth and torpor and um I don't think that that is quite
right translation of the Pali the the first word that's translated as sloth
more literally means to become stiff or rigid and maybe it's akin to the modern
psychological idea of freeze like when people some people freeze in the in the
face of challenge freeze fight or flight
and so it's a shutting down of something shuts down something closes
down and uh we freeze uh maybe go numb
and um and this can often be a product of fear fear gets the upper hand and
kind of shuts us down it's too much what's happening there can be other strong emotions that has that effect on
us and it can have it can have the byproduct of turning away from what's
Happening part of the reason to shut down or to freeze or to become rigid is
so that we don't have to deal with something and so sometimes it's like the ostrich
that puts his head supposedly head in the sand to not see the danger so that
um sometimes the freezing is kind of a shutting down and just and um and
sometimes when it's real real extreme happened to me when I was young I remember something that made me really
afraid afraid and I had a clear feeling that I just disappeared I wasn't there I
couldn't understand why people were looking in my direction because I disappeared and and it wasn't
imminently dangerous situation but um so there's no immediate threat to me
but I remember that later I found myself walking down the street and no idea how
I got there something inside of me had turned off and and I guess I left the place and and
I don't know how I left what I said so this is something shut down
and um and uh and so we can feel that and we
can feel kind of shutting down closing down closing up
um resisting kind of I'm not going to deal with this something gets rigid something gets tight something gets
closed locked and now we can feel it physically sometimes we can feel it over the heart
remember when I was I think I was 16 15 or 16 Maybe 15.
a friend of mine said something to me and I literally felt like the doors of
my heart just closed they locked up and I remember having this thought kind of like I'm never going to open that again
and um it wasn't until I started meditating some four or five years later that something that had closed that day
began opening so shutting down closing up
and um the um so that's kind of the
dysfunctional way of responding the more functional way the healthier way the wise way also involves a
stopping stilling both of these are kind of a stopping
and the but the other side of it the functional side of doing the same kind of thing
is to stop to pay attention to stop to be present more for what's going on
to take a step back either metaphorically in the mind or sometimes physically to get the overview what's
happening here if there's an argument and you're caught in the In the Heat of the argument
sometimes it's a really healthy thing to stop to pause ask for a pause and maybe
even you know step away a few feet you know pause I need to spend time thinking I need to kind of feel what's going on
and maybe kind of make it a little physical distance he also maybe
explaining why so you can catch your breath so you can get your bearings and really understand better what's going on
and so to the degree to which there can be an inter stilling
to stop being in the form of an interstelling not a numbing the interstelling is um again allows us
to feel make room for what's there there's a feeling not of closing down or locking up but there's a stilling which
has more feeling of opening up of becoming more full or or kind of a
sacred pause What's Happening Here what am I feeling what am I thinking
what am I trying to do what's happening with the person that
I'm with or the situation I'm with um can I take it take a second look what's happening and the day of pausing
and looking pausing and reflecting I find invaluable because even to this day
my mind will produce interpretations or bias or jump to conclusions about a
situation and if I'm kind of moving along kind of fast I don't see my mind
has done it that's there's something in my mind that predisposes it sometimes to a certain
confidence in my ideas and so I have a erroneous idea but the confidence I have
rides along with it thinking that it's right but I know myself well enough that if I
can pause stop become little but still then I can see oh that's an
interpretation I'm overlaying a guess onto the situation and then I've learned to put a question
mark after my assumptions my guesses my conclusions that I make even when I'm
confident sometimes that I'm right I'll learn to put a question mark after it what is this
is this really so and um and the more consequential my
view is my decision is my ideas are about what's out there the more important I feel it is to stop
and pause and live for a while that conclusion reflect on it see if it comes up
repeatedly you know if it comes up two or three more times like oh yeah this is right
this is right then then maybe I gave it a little more
Credence then maybe I give it more attention and explore a little bit more what's going on
but this stopping so we can see stopping so we can question
stopping so that we can catch our breath and really kind of look at things in a fresh way
so there are two forms of stopping just like in in relationship to
hindrances there's two forms of each kind of movement of the Mind One is the hindrance and one is opening to wisdom
and um so with the first hindrance desire that
their sensual desire there's desires which are causes problems and there's this desire
to open up a desire to see and to be free there's healthy desires
and when we're with challenges can we see the difference which desire are we operating on
in challenges there's averting and there's healthy averting turning
away or saying no and so can we see a difference between the healthy and the unhealthy
and today there's a healthy the unhealthy kind of hindrance of sloth and
torpor um freezing getting still getting numb
getting shutting down go ahead and going to sleep in a certain way and there is
um stopping pausing that it opens us up that makes us more
clear makes room for wisdom um
so um um so this is a
my words for today and what I'd like to suggest is that you
take a look at this the movement of shutting down turning off getting bored
going numb losing interest all that is a symptom of this third hindrance
waking up being interested clear investigating
even a situation that the first might seem boring certainly there's something about it
that you can study and look at and kind of see what what's the interesting thing what's going on here
to do the little bit of work pausing stopping not to be lazy
but pause and stopping so you can figure out what is the mind's work here
that is beneficial and healthy and creates maybe a better connection
and empathy for the person with the situation I'm with with myself
so you might look today for opportunities for this see what goes on with your mind your awareness
is it in some way or they're shutting down or is it opening up in the situation
you're in and if you see the difference choose
opening up so thank you very much and um
look forward to being together tomorrow