this so my friends the here we are again
end of the week and I'm aware that the theme of the week
is practicing with challenges and
uh one of the really important
components of a healthy approach to challenges is confidence
to have confidence in oneself to have confidence in the practice so it's not
just oneself and um
and part of what makes challenges difficult is a lack of confidence like a kind of a helplessness hopelessness
feeling can't be done feeling that we're going to be overwhelmed by a situation
and certainly there are ways in which we cannot stop tidal waves coming sometimes
but uh but there it makes a difference if we can meet them with Dharma confidence the
confidence in the practice and there's many components of this kind of confidence and many aspects of how it
would play out in the real world but for now I want to offer one
and that is to an attitude of being
available to be changed in a healthy way
to be available for what's happening always ready
so that there's not a shield up we're not closed up we're not lost in our
thoughts and our fears and our doubts but a kind of openness
a kind of uh
counterphobic where we what's the challenge comes rather than stepping away we in internally at least not maybe
physically but internally we step towards okay I'm available for this
and I'm available to be changed what is this what is what is needed
from me what is what useful ways can I now
let go show up invoke positive qualities
How can I enter this as a practice opportunity what's the practice here
and even if the and how not to meet the challenge and already have lost before it has
arrived or before it's over so
to be available to have confidence to bring the practice of attention
the practice of available awareness that's there for
what's coming is the proposal for this morning's meditation
so to gently
take some time to enter into your posture
if it's comfortable close your eyes
and already from the start in inner stance and inner attitude
of being available to what is
by discovering it knowing it recognizing what is this experience I'm having Here
and Now through my body
to be available to feel the tensions of the body
without preconceived ideas or attitudes about what it means to have tensions
just to feel it to be available
for a discovery here now
availability that also makes room for the tensions to relax
partly on their own when they are known
and then being available to how the body experiences breathing
putting aside attitudes beliefs about breathing and mindfulness of
breathing in favor of recognizing how it is the body is experiencing
breathing now
and to have confidence in mindfulness confidence and awareness
is to appreciate that it's quite significant value and valuable
to meet whatever is happening with a clear recognition clear awareness
and clear knowing
without needing to fix anything or change anything
just be present for breathing
the attitude of availability is closely connected to being receptive
to experience receptive to the body breathing
relaxing any way in which you're asserting yourself
With Attitudes beliefs trying to do things make things be different
foreign
thank you foreign
all right
to meditate calling upon your confidence
in the practice confidence of an honest
clear awareness
of the present moment
without getting into thoughts and Analysis
commentary just aware
and with whatever confidence you have in the practice
to relax in such a way that you're available
to be changed to be freed
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
turn towards whatever confidence you have in the practice
confidence of being present to whatever might come
and turning towards an availability
to be a refuge for others
your availability to be a safe person for others
where for certain times right now you don't have to be protecting yourself
and making yourself safe but you're available
to be a refuge her friend
for others
and then to turn your attention outward
maybe in preparation for beginning to re-engage in the world of
people and animals and
this Earth and to consider how to enter back in
to the world with a confidence and availability
in openness a receptivity
and a wish to be safe from caring for others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone and Welcome to our fifth talk on the Dharma
of challenges and this talk and last week talk and
and if I think about it maybe the last four weeks of topics
have a kind of uh background for or laying the foundation for what's
going to come which is talking about the challenges that we have and how we
can address it with the Dharma with practice with mindfulness
and um and hopefully the things we've done in December there was a lot of talk about
the positive states of practice that those acts actually part of this Foundation of now looking at challenges
more and um and Following last week
what is the Dharma last Friday I talked about the Dharma
being Dharma as transformation that Dharma and is not just a it's not
just a set of teachings it's not just a practice but it's also the
transformation that's the beneficial change that comes about through the
practice and through finding in the practice the
healthy appropriate attitude with which to meet life to be with life
so um in the uh about three weeks ago or so I gave a
talk on these five beneficial States for listening to the Dharma hearing it be
people when people were in these states the Buddha would recognize it then he would teach them the Dharma that was
transformative that would change them and this is to have a mind that's bright
inspired to have a mind that is receptive or ready
to have to be free of hindrances to be malleable pliable workable to have a
malleable soft mind and
so the city of being soft and receptive and available to be changed is such an
important attitude for our life and it's easy to have a simplistic and
obvious and sometimes important attitude that would know that I can't do that I
have to protect myself I have to defend myself I have to take care of myself I can't just be available I'll be taking
advantage of and to some degree that's true and we have to be do this wisely
but uh as the our wisdom and confidence grows about how to be in the world
that without harming ourselves through our clinging through our anger through
our ill will hostility through our greed
Envy all kinds of things that we do that we learn how to be in the midst of
challenges while being available for change and
to be changed so one of the really I think clear for
me representations of this is the idea of dialogue with others how to be in
dialogue how to be in a productive not just discussion about something but dialogue for me means you're addressing
some theme some ideas some concern exploring something whether it's exploring a conflict you
have or exploring some Dharma idea that in a dialogue that it's not if
we're only about convincing other people that we're right then we're not available to be changed
and you still might be right and maybe you'll stay right but that doesn't mean you can't be
available to be transformed to be changed by the other person to hear new ideas to hear
them in a different way to understand to expand your horizons so you understand well I am right but this person also has
something they're adding something they're not taking it away it's not either or and available to be changed available to
learn something new and without a dialogue without that good availability I don't think it's really
dialogue it might be just a spouting opinions and it might be mostly trying to it's
mostly a debate um but to be available to be in dialogue
with its attitude how can I how can I learn something here and is there something more I can learn or
you know what can I do so so this availability to be changed to be
transformed in a beneficial way and it was relevant for me just before
we started this uh meditation that the technology wasn't
working here when I sat down and so I had to call for help from someone and
we're trying to figure it out then and normally in the minutes before uh we're sitting networks I start here I'm
getting ready and a little bit getting my thoughts in in organized and what
we're going to talk about but today I really couldn't do it much because of the dealing with the technology and
getting things set up properly and um and but I was kind of happy uh
because I said oh this is a challenge I'm not being able to do it how I usually want to do it but um
but let's see what happens here now let's see what arises this is happening
and I'm available for what comes next I'm available to see how this unfolds or
what arises out of this and um and so rather than being kind of
concerned about you know or distressed around you know maybe we're not going to get the sound system working in time for
the 7 A.M and all these people will be sitting there and um you know waiting and I have you know
we're supposed to start on time um I certainly wanted to try to be on time and be available be here but it was
I also had this kind of curiosity or this availability okay this is how it is
now and um I don't need to stress I don't need to
get you know any to have any kind of fear
let's just see and so this essence of availability uh uh made the whole thing you know
easier than it could have been how much more pleasant than it could have been it was it was nice it was a you know and it
was wonderful to receive my friends support uh and to feel generosity of helping making it out as problem solved
so um the um to be available to be transformed
it's essential for doing Dharma practice and and so because it's so important
uh we want to understand what gets in the way of being
transformed what why we're kind of stuck why we're protected why we're resisting
or shut down or closed up or why we're
insisting that we're right or insisting has to be at my way and you know the um
what's going on for us and so the reference point this the standard
um that I want to be available to be transformed to be changed by the situation
to be freed by it I can't do that I'm not doing that
that's interesting and so keep that in mind you know am I available to be changed am I available to be transformed
by this am I available to be freed by it and then we start discovering maybe we
don't have a lot of confidence maybe we don't have a lot of um sense of safety we don't have a we're
you know we're afraid we're assertive we want something and uh and then to not just take that
for granted not to accept it as a given but to put a question mark next to it do
I really need this to be this way is there another way uh is there another way of being safe is
there another way of caring for this situation is there another way of of protecting myself that's not shutting
down is there a way of you know what can I what do I have to let go of to be
available this is such an important question because so many times what we have to do
is to let go of something we're attached to let go of some excessive
and I'm just underlined excessive self-preoccupation in such a way that we let go of it
it feels like a relief in the moment in and of itself something that was closed or tight or stressed
softens let's go we might feel more vulnerable because of that
and so then we have to figure out how to be with our vulnerability maybe we have to have effective ways of
protecting ourselves or but I have to do some cautious things maybe not be in
certain situations or not talk about certain things
um but we're not closing down we're not shutting down or resisting we're just taking care of ourselves
while we're available and it open caring way for ourselves
so um the Dharma as transformation it is here to transform us in a
beneficial way it is here to free us from the stresses the distresses the
fears the the way that we often live under
there is this is a path of Liberation and Liberation is a transformation
and if you want to follow this path to develop the confidence and the love for
being available to be transformed and to hear Dharma teachings and read
books on Dharma and not read it to for it to reinforce our own opinions
but maybe it's nice it's it you know supports how we understand things but
not to like lob onto that actually be willing to be challenged by what we read
and what we hear question it the more unless we agree with it the more
valuable it is for us to engage in a deeper reflection and what's happening
here what's going on and rather than quickly coming to a judgment oh this is right this is wrong
so in Dharma life to have the confidence to always be
looking always be seeing where is the opening where is the possibility where's the doorway here
to be Freer where is it to be available to be transformed to let go of something
to bring forth available to bring forth some of the beauty Beauty that's in our
hearts available to let our friendliness our kindness our love to be present
and how to be available for challenges not only so that would be changed by
them but also can we can be changed by what's best the best qualities of our
own hearts to be available here to see what goodness can come out
in the context of our confidence are a kind of a strength
and um without allowing the good in us to come forth
then maybe challenges can't transform Us in other ways
so um the Dharma of challenges and the willingness to be changed the
willingness to be transformed and this is part of the art of Dharma practice because the Dharma is partly
what it is partly is a transformation process a liberate liberating process
all in its own time trusting the process so uh thank you
for this and um you might see in the course of this next time until Monday
um this notion of being available to be changed both by the external world but also by
your internal world What comes forth how often are you available and how
often are you going about your day in a way actually you're not gonna you're not you're not really available
you're like just insisting on everything being this way or busy in such a way that
it's only one way to do it what would be like to go through your day
noticing when you're available to be changed and when you're not
and what do you learn through that so thank you
very very much and I appreciate this chance to explore this with you and I hope that I haven't anything I've said
hasn't disrespected how difficult some of your challenges are that make it seem like it's too you know
easy or simple to do to be with them but uh maybe as we learn to work with a
this the smaller challenges of a life we're preparing ourselves to be
available and and uh and know how to address the large ones
so thank you and I look forward to continuing Monday
thank you