well good morning everyone my name is May Elliott and this is day four of our
five day series on the five hindrances okay so the hindrances are known for
clouding over or obscuring the clarity of the mind so if we want to be able to
stay with the breath or stay present for our life getting to know what obscures
that present is really important like what is it that keeps us from being here
and now so today we'll zoom in on the fourth the fourth hindrance of
restlessness and the antidote to restlessness is calm so in the
meditation today we'll we'll invite in some calming factors
um then if you're ever having a hard time being present with restlessness or it's too overwhelming inviting in calm
can be really helpful so let's begin I go ahead and find your meditation posture
and that could be sitting standing lying down whatever posture works for you
and rather than go straight to our meditation anchor this morning sometimes
it can be nice to just take stock of what's happening in the mind uh the heart and in the body so that's how
we'll begin today so to start let's just take a an
inventory of what's the body feel like maybe starting with a global sense of
the body and its posture right now
I'm just seeing what you notice
you might notice that certain areas are tighter than others others more relaxed
or spacious you might notice different temperatures or movement in the body
just meeting what you find with a non-judgmental curious attitude
and having acknowledged what it's like in the body in this moment let's shift our attention to the heart
so what's happening in the heart this motion this morning is there a particular emotion present
maybe just a background mood
and it's okay if you don't have a perfect name to describe what you're feeling right now
just sensing what it's like is enough
sometimes people say oh there's nothing happening right now there's no emotion
there's no mood and if that's the case for you you might check a little closer
um because sometimes that means that there's just a little light sense of calm that's present
so you might see if that's true for you
and then shifting to notice what's happening in the mind what sorts of
thoughts might be present are there a lot of thoughts flurrying
around are they few and far between are they loud and captivating or maybe
soft and wispy I'll just take a moment to see what's happening in the thinking muscle we're
not actually going looking for any thoughts we're going to practice staying here in the body being still and maybe
no thoughts will Arise at all but if one moves through then we'll notice it as a
phenomenon in the present moment not getting captured by its story but seeing
that it's occurring and then we can let it go
so as we explore the present moment uh we're just meeting things as they are
without being in conflict with them
and now that we've taken some time to recognize things as they are
we can invite in some settledness so bring attention to your anchor
maybe the breath feeling the breath where you sense it most predominantly
maybe in the nose the chest or the belly or your anchor might be the soundscape
or a global sense of the body
so we're allowing the attention to connect with the anchor and then to sustain attention with that anchor we're
creating continuous attention and engaging in a samata practice like
this where we tune into our anchor this is one of the traditional ways of
bringing forth calm sometimes translates as calm abiding
this is a calm abiding practice to allow the mind to rest on an anchor and return
to it again and again and the breath particularly while all
anchors will do the breath is particularly helpful as
as a tool for relaxation
so if the breath is your anchor you might try relaxing a little bit every
time you exhale just inviting the mind and heart and body to relax on each
exhale so we'll sit in silence together now for some time just doing this practice
allowing the mind and heart to learn to rest
um
and when the mind wanders we gently and kindly bring the Mind back
to our anchor sliding back to our anchor no need to
wince or judge ourselves for thinking
it's a natural outcome of the mind to produce thoughts instead when we notice it's happen we
slide right back to the Anchor back to the breath back to the soundscape
back to the body
as we begin to settle we'll now turn the attention towards any calmness that
might be present and this doesn't need to be an all-pervading Tranquility there might be
parts of the experience that aren't tranquil that aren't calm um then that's okay
um but as we bring awareness to our experience we might see whether there's any Tranquility or calm that's present
so the Mind might not be calm but the body might be
or the mind and body might not be calm but the space around you the room you're
sitting in might have a sort of Tranquility to it so we can lean on whatever Tranquility
is present whatever is not tranquil whatever is not
calm can slide into the background can shift into the background then we can allow our attention to
recognize any Tranquility that's that's present um
and whatever Tranquility we find we can allow ourselves to be nourished by that
so go ahead and take some time to sense now how is it for you
often the mind is anxious and racing and we don't really realize oh the body's
actually tranquil right now okay let's find some peace resting in
the body
or if you're in a quiet room allowing the mind to attune to the space
around you well there's there's something that feels settled in the space I'm in
so attuning to the Tranquility that's around you sometimes we feel this if we're ever sitting meditation in nature
so we can lean on that tranquility
so go ahead and take some time discovering now um where you might sense into calm
um where you might find calm in your experience right now and allowing yourself to really be present for that
the Buddha's guidance is to be present for wholesome states to really take them
in to be mindful of them so allow that to register if you come in contact with calm really
let that in be present for it
foreign
and at any time if it's supportive for you can return to your anchor
allowing the mind to settle there
and remembering that that practice is a calm abiding practice
inviting in relaxation foreign
softening
allowing yourself to be soothed by the breath
if you're having a hard time connecting with the practices that I'm offering
this morning you might check to see what else is going on
it might be that one of the other hindrances is present so you might check to see if sense
desire is present or ill will aversion or sloth and torpor
sleepiness and if so you can do one of the
practices that I shared on the other days maybe recognizing and feeling what's going on
may be beneficial energy of our practice together today benefit all beings so
they may be happy healthy safe
and completely free from suffering
all right welcome back everyone here we are again
resuming our study of the five hindrances uh these habits of mind that
inhibit clarity I'd like to start by emphasizing that
the hindrances are no small matter the the Buddha compared the experience of
having hindrances um to a variety of very severe circumstances
um he said that the experiences or the experience of the hindrances is comparable to being imprisoned
he said they're comparable to being enslaved he compared them to being on a
dangerous Journey to having a severe illness or to be saddled by having a great debt
and perhaps more striking he says that when the the hindrance is abate when we're free from hindrance
um this is as good as being cured from illness or being freed from prison or being released from slavery or having
finally paid off a great debt or making it to safety on a dangerous Journey
so you can imagine like there's a tremendous amount of relief when any of
these things would happen connecting with the relief of making it to safety after a dangerous Journey or the sense
of freedom of being released from prison or slavery or the joy of recovering from
illness like these are really dramatic most if not all of us are afflicted by
the hindrances with frequency so hearing these descriptions for what is possible
when we're free from hindrance is pretty incentivizing so
um this practice can really allow for a tremendous amount of Freedom if we can really study the
hindrances if we can really get to know them and learn how they operate in us we
can learn to see the veil of the hindrances um so much Freedom can be possible
so today we'll talk about restlessness yesterday we discussed the third
hindrance sloth and torpor so the third and fourth hindrance have a strong energetic quality with Sloth and torpor
being low energy and restlessness often high energy it often kind of an over abundance of
energy sometimes this hindrance of restlessness is referred to as worry and flurry where
the mental representation of the hindrance is worry and the physical representation is flurry and so it does
manifest in these two different ways physically or mentally so the physical manifestation
might manifest as we can't sit still in meditation or we keep fidgeting or
shifting or itching of physical restlessness can arise also
it's the desire to bolt rush out of the meditation hall or off of our cushion
um for in daily life that physical restlessness might come forth as needing
to keep doing things getting home from work and racing around the house because we just can't drop the momentum of our
work day and all of these you may be sensing there can be a compulsive quality to
them the mental manifestation for restlessness is a mind that's agitated a
mind that's scattered lots of scattered thinking where the mind just won't won't settle
um where thinking is really persistent and while restlessness isn't always
based in fear often restlessness can involve anxiety or worrying and we might see this
anxious form of restlessness when we're rehearsing what we're going to say in a
conversation you may have noticed that happening in meditation or when we're engaging in excessive planning or
Imagining the worst um it might be ruminating over a concern
about one's self-image so all of these can have a Restless quality to them
and while restlessness can be fueled by fear it can also come forth as a product of a kind of stuck or frustrated desire
or constrained aversion um and so when we meet restlessness we can
do our typical one-size-fits-all approach to the hindrances where we recognize the
restlessness the restlessness is present so we know oh this is restlessness and
Scattered thinking agitation anxious thinking um and then we feel what that
restlessness is is like in the body we feel the compulsion to move the
agitation high energy so this this is a classic way to work
with restlessness additionally one of the traditional approaches to
restlessness is to notice what caused it what triggered the restlessness
um so often when we're lost in thought in meditation there can be some form of
restlessness present if we discover that we're restlessness we so we recognize oh this is
restlessness we can then ask what's underneath this what am I feeling
right now as in uh what emotion is present right now and this can be part
of our two-part practice you know where uh we recognize then we feel the hindrance
um so first we recognize the restlessness and then we might ask okay what's what's going on here what am I
feeling um to recognize what's below the restlessness
um so um if we are able to identify what's causing it what's triggering the
restlessness then we can practice mindfulness of the underlying emotion then whatever we discover below the
restlessness say anxiety then we can really take care of that anxiety we can we can feel it
fully and sometimes practicing mindfulness of the underlying emotion can actually be even more skillful than
just staying with the restlessness itself so I happen to sit a two-month
Meditation Retreat just prior to my my wedding many years ago and
um just before the set just before the retreat I came across a meme with a caption uh the happiest moment of my
wedding was realizing the planning is over so uh if you've ever planned a wedding
you might be able to relate to that I certainly could um so understandably one of my top 10
hits during the retreat involved wedding planning thoughts so I would be rethinking details uh the expense the
invitation list what type of cake which dress you know all of the logistics so
I found myself caught in these kind of extended bouts of thinking many times
during the meditation on this Retreat before doing that first step of recognizing that restlessness was at
play where I was like you know eventually oh this is just restlessness
and even once I saw that it took a while before I learned to ask
what's beneath all this thinking like okay this is restlessness but what am I
feeling right now what's beneath all of this thinking um and asking this allowed for an even
deeper recognition so often these these repetitive story lines are fueled by an underlying
emotion or physical experience as Gil would say it's as though there's a
factory deep in the body then it's the factory that's the source of anxiety and
it's the anxiety that's pumping out the thoughts it's the factory that's the source of the underlying emotion and
it's that emotion that's pumping out the thoughts so the thoughts are just the off-gassing from the deeper source so we
could keep sweeping the thoughts away from now until eternity but the underlying emotion is going to keep
turning them out until we give it the attention it's asking for so to give it the attention
it's asking for to actually address the thinking we actually need to go to the
source we need to go down into the factory and to go down into the factory that
means actually feeling what's happening in the body so we release the thoughts we go down to
the factory we feel the constriction in the body the way that worry or anxiety
tightens the heart maybe sensing the raised shoulders or whatever other Sensations might be present
so when we return to this practice recognize and feel when we go down to
the factory you know this is when we engage the step of feeling our experience going down
into the factory um we sense what's happening through somatic sense
now this this allows us to address the felt experience at the source rather
than just sweeping away the thoughts over and over again which you know they're just like the thoughts are like
smoke coming out of the Smoke Stacks so we go to the source we recognize and then we go to the source go down to the
factory and we feel what's happening and as I mentioned earlier restlessness
can come from a variety of sources um which is one of the reasons it's helpful
to ask those questions of what am I feeling right now what's underneath this um
and with that said it is it is really common that the source is worry and
anxiety anxiety fueling the factory so knowing this it can be helpful to
remember that fear is such a natural part of Being Human we've been deeply conditioned to feel fear and we don't
need to be hard on ourselves about being fearful the Dharma teacher and author
Mark lesser reminds us that we're the descendants of the nervous Apes all the
chilled out Apes got eaten so it's the nervous Apes that survived and made baby Apes
anxiety is deeply conditioned in us um you know we've inherited
um a survival strategy um this capacity do you feel to feel fear which keeps us safe
so if we're experiencing a fear-based restlessness it can help to do this with an attitude
of gentleness um so just to help bring forth that
attitude of gentleness we might take a moment just to imagine what it's like to
see a scared dog it might be shaking um it gets little ears are drooped way
back the Tails tucked the posture might be cowering now if this was your dog and
you knew that you could comfort it how would you be with that animal how would you greet it how would you take
care of it so you might be gentle or loving you
might hold it and keep it warm ensuring it feels safe so if you notice restlessness and
discover that below the restlessness there's some fear in the heart there's some anxiety
can you bring that same gentle loving attention to the anxiety um bringing that same care that same
compassion you'd bring to a little animal that's having a hard time ultimately can you help the fear feel
safe
okay so now I want to talk about a slightly different and more subtle
manifestation of restlessness we've already talked about how restlessness can manifest physically and how it can
appear as mental emotional activity and agitation
I want to talk about how restlessness also points to a much deeper habit of mind the simple habit of um where the
mind is just moving out of the present at all so ajan Amaro and ajan pasino explain it
like this and this quote is from the island it's a book Island which is an
excellent book I highly recommend it
and it goes like this of the ten obstacles or Fetters that
stand in the way of Enlightenment the penultimate is restlessness
the restlessness to which this refers is not the fidgeting of the uncomfortable meditator
it is the subtlest of feelings that there might be something better over there or just in the future
a feeling that that which is Out Of Reach might have more value in some way than this
it is the ever so Insidious addiction to time and its promises
so as one nears full Enlightenment restlessness is one of the last Fetters
to be uprooted it's so deeply conditioned in us to lean towards some
better moment ever so slightly even just that forward lean and I love that line
the ever so Insidious addiction to time and its promises
so we can think of restlessness as manifesting at different levels of subtlety on a coarser level there's a
physical restlessness and then maybe a little more subtle than that mental
emotional restlessness and agitation and on an even more subtle subtle level than
that there's this ongoing sense that there might be something just a little better just Out Of Reach
Okay so if retinosis arises or go-to practice is
the mindfulness practice of recognizing and feeling but as I said in the meditation this morning and you can
apply an antidote and that antidote is um uh Plumbing or Tranquility so if you
feel restlessness you can return to your meditation anchor and do samata that calm abiding practice
um and what we're doing here is we're just allowing in in that practice
um the comma biting practice we're allowing the mind to gravitate around something that's simple and that simple
object can be a refuge for the mind that's racing it around and it's Tangled Up In all sorts of complex anxiety
producing storylines um if however focusing on the anchor of
meditation actually tightens the mind or increases the energy you can give the
mind a wider pasture to open up the attention um for example opening the attention to
sounds in a really nice wide way and that can bring in some calm so you
can make the the field of attention all wide so the Restless energy can just
kind of pinball around in the mind or body but we're not being jerked around by it because we're in this large field
um and as I mentioned in the meditation another way to connect with calm is just
to notice where where there's already calm that's present so for me it's not uncommon that I'll be mentally Restless
um but there might be an area of the body that's relaxed so I'll rest in that part of the body I'll allow that part of
the body to be soothing to the mind um and in the meditation in a meditation
hall or in nature or in a quiet room these spaces can bring forth calm as
well to tune into the calm that's around us so today
um see if you can identify a moment of restlessness um maybe it's physical or maybe it's a
mental feeling um and rather than acting out on the restlessness externally
um see if you can just recognize the restlessness as restlessness I'm like oh
this is worry and flurry and then get to know it let them feel it bringing that
same kindness and care that you'd bring to an anxious animal a little puppy or
whatever it is that brings forth some sense of gentleness and compassion
so I hope you have a lovely day today and that you're able to stay connected to your practice thank you for being
here thanks