welcome
everyone Friday and our discussion of compassion
continues um a little hiccup with the stream I'm not sure what happened this
morning many of you have made it over to uh this new URL but
I I hope there's not too much
confusion spending five days uh practicing thinking talking living
compassion so sweet so sweet um thank you for thank you for doing this thank
you for your practice let's um let's settle right
into some meditation and then we will bring our fifth
session to its
conclusion so the meditation for today will
be um maybe a simple one we will we'll start as we have been
with settling in this um this body this mind this
heart then uh gently call up
compassion and then um once we've once we've really spent some
time cultivating compassion we'll take a look at just what is the quality of the
mind when it is uh arousing compassion sustaining
compassion when it's suffused or filled with compassion what are the qualities that are
there let's start with the
settling
May our posture be balanced and
grounded connected to the
Earth of the
Earth
man with each breath coming into coming into
balance alignment and
presence
a few minutes to
settle to be with the
senses
and when we're
ready inclining the Mind toward
compassion arousing compassion in the
body taking that
attitude perhaps with the help of an image or a
reflection may we be free from suffering and harm
from
may we be free from the
suffering
Red Line On Our intention the wish that others be free
that we be free from
suffering
rousing the wish that beings be free from
suffering sensitive to the effect this has on our body and
mind inviting compassion throughout the
body this kind
care may all being be free from
suffering
arousing compassion sustaining
compassion this body and mind becoming
compassion now to bring in the question just how is this compassionate
mind bring in just a little bit of
Investigation not to interfere with our practice of
compassion but to come to know it
is this compassionate mind clearly
mindful how is it
energy
is there Joy even
Joy or is there a calm
balance
settledness just how is this compassionate
mind
just how is this compassionate mind what qualities are
here
now as we come to the end of this
sitting inviting ease and relaxation into this
body with a wish for the welfare of all
beings as we hear the sound of the
Bell May our in I of compassion go along with the
sound spreading in all directions may all beings be
happy and may they be free from
suffering
hello again welcome good moment good morning good
day it's our fifth day on the topic of
compassion and I'd like to talk a a little bit about compassion and
Awakening gosh my curiosity is so strong I wonder how it's been for you to um see
and practice bringing com compassion
into into your worlds each of our worlds how has that
been I wonder if there have been any moments in your in your week that stand
out to you when you're when you're bringing this attitude of kindness into
your words and your thoughts and your Deeds anyway my curiosity is strong as
we get started we we've talked a lot about how the the
Practical scope of compassion is this meta loving kindness
that can be expressed in all of our actions and this is inspiring in part
because it means it means that our compassion can be
expressed uh through our conduct and that we can bring our wisdom
our wisdom to recognize what we need to
recognize what others need and to in one way of speaking uh live
beautifully so to say something about compassion and Awakening will move the scope just a little
bit from the expression in daily life to
meditation so
one of the things that makes compassion and the other Brahma viharas loving kindness sympathetic joy and
equinity such powerful meditation practices is they have this they have
this natural uh natural way that they can undermine some of the challenges that
come uh with some other focuses of meditation practice um I know for for some people it's
possible when say we're focusing on the breath or um there can be a way that we
grab after the focus of meditation the object of meditation and the mind can sort of
get contracted and tight to maybe get a headache but there's something folded
right in with the gentleness the gentleness of compassion and the focus
that is the whole body and then actually all all space all
beings it takes a very very wide hug to hold all
beings so this um you can see right there in the posture this the difference
between sort of a crunching or pushing Contracting head that's uh trying to
follow after the breath for example versus the natural posture of
this br God hug of course breath meditation does not have to be contracted it's just one of
the one of the things that can happen there's also a way that the um
taking compassion as a meditation subject it perfumes the mind the object
itself or focusing on compassion and it it creates an atmosphere almost in in
our body and in our our mind that's um that's conditioned by
compassion this is pretty powerful because it it undermines directly those
roots of what we call UNH wholesome conduct those roots of um
greed grasping um the roots of ill will and
aversion and hatred uh and cruelty and the roots of delusion
ignorance and all of these with this gentle mist of compassion they're all
undermined they're all undermined so that instead instead of our our thoughts words and deeds feeding these roots
instead we feed the roots of meta and we bring real care and love into the
world and then a third a third um Fe
feature of all of the Brahma viharas but speaking specifically about compassion
is they have they have the power to bring both calm and insight right
together and this is a this is a powerful combination in the early tradition of course we've seen over the
week the way that compassion uh can bring can can BR soothing settling
calming just here just here and of course as Gil says many many
times um we the meditation brings calm not
just to be calm we bring calm in order to see and
that's where the Insight comes in it's like uh calming in order to see
is a bit like uh setting up our telescope on a on a tripod nice and
steady nice and still so that we can see the stars
or another metaphor is like letting the letting the uh
water say a deep say a deep pool become very very still and very
very clear so that we can see all the way to the bottom there's a beautiful there's a
beautiful image in a Zen poem of seeing all the way to the bottom of the the bottom of the water the large silent
fish that are swimming there these things we wouldn't be able to see without
Tranquility but these both coming together tranquility and
insight so something we did this morning in the meditation and one of the ways that we can invite the Insight aspect
into into um compassion practice is by by opening this
investigation a little bit of of a little bit of curiosity posing the
question just how is this compassionate mind and with that question we lean in
the direction of insight bringing Insight together with tranquility and especially
powerful in in terms of the movement toward Awakening with a practice like
compassion we take a few steps in the direction of Awakening um but by looking after the
seven awaking Awakening factors so is there uh is there
mindfulness in a compassionate mind Compassionate Heart Is there the second
factor which is investigation uh this is the this is the
the quality that asks oh what what exactly is here if mindfulness
mindfulness is the quality that knows what's here investigation is the one
that says oh what exactly is here this this um investigation Builds
on with the next Awakening Factor it takes some energy to look into the mind and the heart and do the medit
meditation practice so energy can be aroused and then these first three
together mindfulness investigation and energy they
seed um they seed the arising of joy
like a bright full body beautiful Joy it can be or it can be quite
subtle but is there joy in a compassionate
mind and then the fifth of the seven Awakening factors is there
Tranquility is there Tranquility then is there
concentration collectedness settledness here is the Mind
settling and then the seventh is their mental balance
equinity that can look upon all things all beings all phenomena with a measure
of balance so are the are these here what
exactly is here in this compassionate mind and doing this sort of
Investigation as we're saying it brings together tranquility and insight which
can set the stage for a very deep letting go or another deep letting
go just as uh just as I quoted Gil is saying we don't we don't practice calm
just for calm and actually we don't even practice Insight just for
insight but uh but we condition a sort of Letting Go that allows us to be free
allows us to be free in some way in all
circumstances so I wanted to take a moment to to say a couple of things about why why
compassion and Awakening why this um why this is so
inspiring there's something there's something to me I wonder how it is for
you there's something for me that's that is quite inspiring about
um the power of compassion as a meditation practice to bring
about um these degrees of freedom just very very
quickly uh it's not only about the speed um but it's it's that we can taste the
flavor of Freedom uh it with compassion it's right there it's right nearby and that this
can be such a powerful uh Touchstone for us or a guide or a
guideline we taste taste the flavor of freedom and we know to move in this
direction something that's inspiring about compassion practice and that also on the on the the
um let's say the path of the path of compass compassion is onward leading and it goes so far in the direction of
freedom and then the third reason is that the the freedom that we taste and
the inspiration that we take from the possibility of Freedom it's
the um the influence of compassion is evident throughout the path and it's evident in every action
when we practice it this there's this one teaching that
says a mind well cultivated and loving kindness is supreme in
Beauty a mind well cultivated in loving kindness is supreme in
Beauty so over the last several days we've covered a covered a bit of territory from compassion as it relates
to deep rest and how to love sustainably how to release the hindrances and practice seclusion the
importance of meta as a root for compassion and then discuss to not self
and then how this path can lead onward in the direction of
Awakening I'd like to close the series with a an image and I mentioned before
about uh the circle of compassion the circle of compassion and
the notion here is that um self-cultivation the work that we do on
with ourselves it benefits others and then benefiting others
enhances our self-cultivation we we enact and develop
cultivate compassion right here right right here with this one and that benefits
beings real concrete actual beings and then the benefits to those
other beings that that circles back and nourishes a practice the circle of
compassion thank you very much for your your um kind attention and your practice
this week May our May our time together um be of great benefit to us and to all
beings may all beings be happy may they be safe and may they be
free take good
care