good day everyone and welcome to the morning
sitting as we continue our week um with these wholesome qualities of Mind known
as the Divine abodes or Brahma vihara we are building on a foundation of meta or
Goodwill loving kindness yesterday we were focused on
how Goodwill that meets suffering responds with compassion with
caring and today we'll focus on how good will that meets happiness responds with
appreciative Joy also called sympathetic joy in other words we're happy for the
Good Fortune of others and we want to see their happiness
continue the mind that can be happy uh at others happiness and not caught
caught up in jealousy or competition is a mind that can come to
freedom from dissatisfaction stress and
suffering this is a mental state by the way that's really different from
complacency it's not just that we're okay we're actually uh feeling happy and
there's an availability of peace with respect to the way life works you know sometimes people are happy sometimes
they're unhappy sometimes we have UPS sometimes we have downs and appreciative Joy does not mean
that we give up any motivation to help those who are not so
fortunate it means we see how life has this disparity a human
culture uh creates disparities and we have compassion for the way that affects
people we see how privilege operates and we're able to use whatever
gifts that come our way not just for our own pleasure but to support wholesome
action in the world whether that action is very local where you live or has a
bigger reach um so sympathetic Joy is this beautiful quality
and skill that has strength and it's also able to offer strength to
others so with that we'll begin our formal
meditation taking time to find the posture that supports
you perhaps to take some longer deeper
breaths and release any obvious tension or anything
extra
as you take these deliberate breaths bringing energy into the body with the
in breath and
releasing with the out
breath notice what's arising in Awareness right
now in the
mind the
heart what's arising in the
body and taking some time to bring any ease or
softening that's available to any area of
preoccupation any area of
difficulty
and perhaps allowing yourself to feel the presence of
aliveness Vitality energy in the
body you might feel it in Brea in the
breathing in and
out or in the warmth and coolness of different areas of the
body
you might feel pulsing or vibration in the
noticing any good feelings in any area of the body the Heart
Center even if some areas are uncomfortable there may be other areas
that feel good that feel some ease
perhaps sending yourself the silent wish may the Vitality of this body
continue
allowing yourself to feel any positive physical
emotional mental feelings that are
present
and noticing states of heart and mind that accompany various Sensations in the
body appreciating in any supportive emotions or
thoughts the presence of any happiness or Joy or
contentment appreciating all that arises whether difficult or
joyful it's all in information that awareness is allowing
us to see as it arises as it stays for a
while as it
passes this morning for those who would like I'll offer a guided practice of
appreciative Joy you can feel free to part participate or if this does not fit
where your practice is this morning letting the sound of my voice Fade Into
the background and continuing with what it what you need in your
practice today we can experiment with feeling appreciative joy for a good
friend or someone for whom some aspect of life is going going
well right
now when you're ready bringing this person to
mind and imagining their face glowing with
happiness and seeing them on the receiving end of Good
Fortune perhaps silently receiving or repeating phrases of appreciative joy in
the mind I'll offer some and you may have some that spontaneous ly occur to you as
well I'm happy that you're
happy I take joy in your good
fortune may your happiness continue and
grow may you grow in happiness peace and
freedom
continuing on your own with the phrases that speak to you or simply feeling the
heart filling with appreciative joy and perhaps metaphorically sending
that to the person whose happiness you are
appreciating may your happiness continue and
grow may you grow in happiness peace and
freedom
for
so mudita is the poly word for appreciative joy and it's sometimes
translated as empathetic Joy or sympathetic joy and it's what Goodwill or meta feel
feels when it encounters happiness it wants the happiness of
others and and oneself to continue um perhaps it's easiest to feel
for yourself or the people that you love or like um if we interestingly if we fear
deprivation or we've unconsciously harbored some idea that there's a
limited supply of happiness um in such a way that if it goes to
someone else or people we don't like there will be less for us so sometimes people feel competitive
about good fortune or even feel Envy um when someone else receives something
that they want for themselves but of course we can always contemplate does
another person's happiness diminish yours what ideas or attitudes might
underly that what experiences might be behind that um at another time when you you are
happy how would it be for you to know that others resented you or begrudged
your happiness it' be pretty uncomfortable yeah so there's no need to judge
ourselves or others in this practice we can take into account that um we
ourselves and people who have some wisdom have had sometime or other behaved
unskillfully and that people uh have been harmed by
that also that people who have harmed others including any time we may have done some harm at other times have been
good to someone else so a lot of this is about
separating unskillful behavior from the person themselves and realizing how big
big a role conditioning plays in unskillful behavior and that can help us realize
that appreciative joy for someone else's happiness really gets to the root
of their potential as a human being um we can think about them as an innocent
baby to whom events then happened so sending wishes for continued
happiness to their inner potential in a way to grow into a skillful kind person
and sending that to ourselves as well that person or or this person with
this potential sending that person the appreciative Joy just as we would want
to receive sympathetic Joy when things go well for ourselves despite the fact
that we're imperfect perhaps including the wish
that someday we and others will be freed from
suffering towards genuine sustainable happiness in the
Dharma we may struggle with the realization that some have been born into privilege or currently enjoy
some good fortune While others are deprived of resources for even the most
basic B needs water food shelter love in light of this it's really helpful to
remember equinity you know like a balanced mind and a wise
View and that wise view includes the recognition that actions have
consequences all human actions have
consequences so there are consequences from inequity
and the correction of it is probably not happening anywhere near as quickly as we
want but equinity together with sympathetic Joy
compassion and Goodwill or loving kindness can help us remain
constructive while we're aware of the imbalance uh between those who have happy circumstances and those who
don't appreciative Joy has this wonderful quality as do all the brah viharas of
helping us see that happiness creates more happiness each of these Brahma viharas
Foster an increase in themselves in the world so if we offer kindness kindness
is more likely to be offered in return if we offer compassion that's likely to
grow around us and happiness becomes more more abundant when we celebrate
Good Fortune when it comes along and you know when any uh of these
Brahma viharas including appreciative Joy when it feels difficult to
access it's always useful and skillful to wish that we could send wishes of one
of these qualities so for example may I open to the happiness I see in others
that's a wish to have access to appreciative joy and we can balance any reactivity
with our capacity to think wise thoughts for example I know that uh things that
people get through crime or uh malfeasance don't
last I see that human life is short I see that sooner or later
suffering and sorrow come to everyone and and most importantly may I
not begrudge a few passing moments of happiness in this life
it's not as abundant as we wish it were sometimes so this practice of
appreciative Joy uh by the way is of course supported by these other Brahma viharas maybe you
felt that you know when there's kindness and Goodwill happiness grows when there's compassion
and care for others happiness is then a possibility
again each one strengthens and supports others and I want to read you an excerpt
from an essay by a monastic nanica Tera
and he was someone who lived in the last century a german-born terava Buddhist
monk and Scholar um after he ordained in Sri Lanka he
later became the co-founder of the Buddhist publication Society authored a
ton of books and articles and he mentored and taught a whole generation of Western Buddhist
leaders for example Bodi and many of us who have read you know many of the sutas
translated by bod will appreciate how important that is since he's done so
many translations s on which those of us who speak English now depend for our
information about the original Buddhist sutas or as close to them as we can get
so nanaka wrote compassion
prevents love and sympathetic Joy from forgetting that while we are enjoying or
giving temporary and limited happiness there still exist at that time the most
Dreadful states of suffering in the world it reminds them that our happiness
coexists with measureless misery perhaps at the next
doorstep it's a reminder to love and sympathetic joy that there's more suffering in the world than we are able
to help mitigate and that after the effect of such mitigation has vanished sorrow and
pain are sure to arise a new until suffering is uprooted entirely at the
attainment of nibana so this is one of the roles of compassion compassion does not allow
that love and sympathetic Joy shut themselves off against the wide world by
confining themselves to just one narrow sector compassion prevents love and
sympathetic Joy from turning into States of selfsat satisfied complacency within some jealously
guarded Petty kind of Happiness compassion stir and urges love
and he's referring to meta here to widen its sphere it stirs and urges sympathetic
joy to search for fresh nourishment nourishment not not be complacent and
stuck in one moment it helps both of them to grow
into truly boundless States like The Meta that I read to you earlier this
week was encouraging boundless loving kindness sympathetic Joy holds
compassion back from being overwhelmed at the side of the world suffering from
being absorbed by it to the exclusion of everything else it keeps us from falling
into grief constant grief sympathetic Joy relieves tension of Mind sues the
painful burning of the Compassionate Heart it keeps compassion away from
melancholic brooding without purpose from a feudal sentimentality that merely
weakens and consumes the strength of mind and heart sympathetic Joy develops
compassion into active
sympathy sympathetic Joy gives to equinity the mild Serenity that softens
its Stern appearance it is the Divine smile on the face of the Buddha a smile
that persists in spite of his deep knowledge of the world's suffering a
smile that gives Solace and hope fearlessness and
confidence wide open are the doors to Deliverance it it says so that's what
anapon Tera reminded us of and that is how these qualities balance one
another as you practice appreciative Joy you'll
probably notice maybe you just noticed that it has an energizing capacity it
can lighten our hearts and that's skillful to keep in mind when you find your heart sinking into sadness at the
suffering in the world G grief sympathetic Joy
benefits tremendously from continual grounding in
mindfulness and that's the way that it won't kind of Veer into giddiness or
kind of overe excitation uh which isn't really the aim of this
practice it can be a calm kind of appreciation or joy and it doesn't need
excitement to flourish so I hope for those of you who are
enjoying these practices uh that you perhaps use today to touch
into appreciative Joy noticing happiness around you noticing happiness inside you
and being able to take a few moments to feel that and enjoy
that um it's been wonderful sharing this with you this morning and I wish you a
very joyful day see you tomorrow
morning