so happy to be here and in uh preparing
for the meditation today um at the
um I want to kind of create an image for
you or an um imagine that
you you in in the you have two Neighbors in the home you live in one on each side
two sets of neighbors and they both have uh children about the same age and you've grown up with these
children you've known when they you known they were babies you've been a babysitter for them and you known them
when they were younger kids and and sometimes they came over to your house when the parents couldn't take care of
them and um and the parents didn't take care of
them very well there was no love in the home and a lot of conflict and a lot of yelling and and
um and maybe neglect of the
children but they would come over to your house and play and feel safe with you and the only place they really felt
safe and comfortable and and uh the only place they had someone who believed in them and uh who showed them that they
were lovable and and you loved having them come over and because you were between these two their two homes the
kids felt like they were free to come over to you whenever they wanted to you had invited them and they'd often come
and play and go there as a refuge but as they became
teenagers and um at some point uh there was a huge conflict between them they
both felt hurt and and offended or um violated by the other and uh they were
arguing and bordering on fighting and the T the tension and the hostility
between them uh was intense partly because they were both uh responding to
each other in the way that they had learned to be in Conflict growing up in their homes and uh it was escalating and it
didn't seem like it was going to go anywhere good but coincidentally because of
their trust in you they both came over to your home at the same
time and they uh so you invited them in and sat down and you could feel the
tension the hostility the that between them and kind of they wouldn't look at each other and but you loved them both
you cared for them both and certainly you were not going to take sides in the dispute you were going to help them
settle their quarrel in some way or reconcile in such a way that if they had disagreements and had different points
of you or something that they would um settle down and see each other in the
with the love and friendship that they had for so many years and um and sure enough just
because they're sitting with you and you were able to be calm and impartial uh listening to both accepting
them both they both calm down and you saw as they calmed down they relaxed
that they started looking at each other and you could feel that there was the the old love they had between them was
kind of there but the tension was somewhat still there but as that did ipated you
realized that now it became even your your involvement became even more
important that now even sometimes they would talk about other things and get distracted from their conflict and you
felt that now now it's even more important that you're present for them that you're present and they can feel
that you believe in them you trust them you think that uh you have confidence in
their ability to be honest to talk honestly what's going on and to find a way
way so in the same way when we sit to meditate uh we are the person in the
home in between in between all the different aspects of ourselves and uh and we need to be
impartial we need to trust and have confidence in ourselves and our
capacities that we can find a way and have this kind of confidence and trust
and love and in ourselves so something in ourselves can relax deeply and as we
get calmer in meditation the Mind might easily drift off into thoughts of all
kinds maybe no longer any kind of sense of conflict with ourselves or challenge
in the world and it turns out that this is even more important time for us to
stay present more important time to receive our breath receive our Body
Sensations to just be with ourselves and so with that as an image
for our meditation let's begin so to
[Music] um assume a meditation
posture maybe with a
presence with whatever posture you're doing you have a
presence that you would offer the neighboring teens
that they felt that you were there for them that you were going to listen and
hear and feel and and view them with the
kindness the care the believing in
them and so to sit here with that posture and maybe gently close your
eyes and to prepare yourself to Center yourself
to be able to offer this caring presence to take a few long slow deep
breaths just big enough that is comfortable for you remains
comfortable relax and settle on the
exhale
and if it's easy enough extend the exhale a bit so there's more time in
which to release in the body settle in the
body
and letting your breathing return to normal but continue on the
exhale to settle
into being centered here in your
body so there's stability the kind of stability where
you don't lean forward or pull back stability that allows you to
maintain an open impartial
presence not taking sides in anything
relaxing the thinking mind or maybe as you exhale
allow the thinking mind to relax and maybe it could relax because
of your kind way generous caring way in
which you are present for your mind for your thinking
mind that you believe in yourself that you can in
fact return to
a to becoming
whole that you can in fact settle the mind to touch
into some of the best qualities of
yourself peace and calm
settle into a way of being that you're not operating with a
view that anything is wrong about yourself or anything is wrong about your
inner
life maybe if there's tension it's just something that can relax
under the warmth of your caring
attention and then if it's comfortable for you to imagine that the breathing your
breathing is at the center of all of who you
are and that if you can touch that center with care acceptance
impartiality as if that Center can do no wrong
that you just can love and care and make room for listen
deeply to yourself through this essential feature
of your life that kind of Nexus meeting point of
your life in your
breathing
for
and if you find yourself somewhat calm and relaxed but your mind mind is easily
drifting off in thought think of this
time as a time that it's most important for your heart for your breath your
inner life to have you stay present impartially
kindly staying present because you believe in yourself that
yes all things can be
healed all all things of the heart can be
healed the path of deep Peace and Freedom can be your
path stay present offer
yourself the love the
care that you might want to
offer to neighboring
gids
for
so then as we come to the end of his sitting
to turn your attention your thoughts your
imagination to the people around you in your
world in your household or in your neighborhood your
community the wider provinces and counties States Nation Nations the
world as if your your accepting heart your impartial
heart cannot doesn't take sides with anything because you know that more
valuable than taking sides is to be a refuge for all
people to be someone who's safe for all people
so that the deepest places of tension holding attachment and
hurt for others can be in the presence of
someone who supports its relaxation who supports its
release not taking sides when we offer our care and love
has a good chance of allowing something deeper than the conflict to heal to
relax the Buddha said make yourself safe for all
beings may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free
thank
you
so hello and welcome to this fifth talk on the Buddha's teachings on
quarrels and I today I broadcasting this giving this talk from Spirit Rock
meditation center and um here here together with uh Quan Yin the great
embodiment of U bodhisatwa of compassion which seems appropriate for
the topic we're talking about this week and
um once when I I met shinen young talking with him he was one of the Great
Elder vasna teachers in the United States brilliant man very
creative and as a as a Buddhist teacher and
um he once created a program to teach mindfulness to teenagers I believe some
of them were troubled teenagers and um and uh I was really
struck by the the principle by which he
taught these teenagers mindfulness first what he would do is they were going to come to him for
the I guess training and mindfulness and he asked them to bring uh whatever was their favorite
music and they would come with their favorite music and and they would listen to it a big part of the the session with
him was listening to that music and he would not teach them any mindfulness what he would do and he
wouldn't teach it directly what he would do he would at ask them questions about
listening to their music and um questions about the
experience of being with their music uh what their mind does when their music there listening to music so I don't know
exactly what his questions were but I can imagine that he might ask for example when you most enjoyed your music
how did how did you feel and what was a quality what was how do you characterize
your attention when you were most enjoying your music and there were time were there
were there times when you kind of lost track of your music that you got drifted off in thought what was that like for
you and what was what was that the quality of your being at that point and
and being distracted from the music and and as he asked those questions it directed the teens
attention to ways of to pay attention inside of themselves which they maybe
had never occurred to pay attention to before and as they appreciated that maybe he was teaching them uh to
recognize the kind of attention they brought to all that and um and the principle that I
wanted to share with you that as he taught teens this way and asked them these questions he said the most uh
fundamental um principle that the facilitator had to operate with
was no matter what answer the teens provided for the questions they were all
accepted no question was questioned or not not good enough or wrong every
question was right every question was held as if right every answer that he
was practicing kind of an unconditional acceptance of each teen and their own
experience and how they reported on it and part of what they're learning in my fulness was the example of shinzen Yang
or people he trained to do this um and the kind of attention they brought they
created space and allowed each teen to be themselves and perhaps for some of these teens maybe the troubled ones
there had not been many adults in their life who just had that kind of unconditional acceptance or willingness
just to receive them as if nothing is wrong and so they
um they um that's how they learn m fulness so this is also a principle for
us that we can practice this mindfulness this way and for ourselves and maybe in
learning to do this for ourselves that we can do no wrong it's just something else to bring a certain kind of
attention to and really see and make space for and uh I think shinzen brought a
sense of safety to the teens so the Buddha said make yourself safe for all
beings make yourself safe for yourself so that in the field of your awareness
your attention there's no criticism no blame that in a certain way you you can
do no wrong conventionally you might do something which is not healthy and
helpful and wholesome but there's something more much more valuable than
seeing it as wrong and that is this caring attention that holds it that allows something to settle to resolve to
uh process itself to let go because we believe I believe in you all
of you that you have the ability to heal to settle to drop into this deeper place
of wholeness that is inhibited or blocked whenever we're involved in
seeing ourselves as wrong and of course we do things which are harmful we do
things which we regret we do things that uh treat ourselves in ways that are not so healthy uh this is part of the human
life that we do this and not to accept it naively please
go ahead and keep doing that but there's a way of offering a kind of safety and attention attentive safety that allows
something to relax and we have access to something deeper within us deeper Wellsprings of well-being and
wholeness so when we come applying this to quarrels and disputes that if we're
engaged in quarrels and disputes um there is some deeper agenda or deeper
possibility that uh we might want to offer that we learn as we learn it
through this Buddhist practice as we learn to do this for ourselves we learn to enter into disagreements conflicts uh
in a in an approach that we're not looking to be right or to blame other people we're not looking to cond known
what's happened we're not looking to allow whatever is uh harmful to continue
but we are bringing a kind of an attitude a kind of a tension that uh
we're making ourselves safe for others so that people We're In conflict with do not feel our hostility do not feel that
we have blamed them or boxed them into a certain perspect uh perception of who
they are and and that uh they feel like they're now have to you know verbal box
it out with us to protect themselves at the same time offering
safety to others that way does not mean we have to give into them it's actually a to for us to give ourselves safety
means that we have the ability to hold our ground to be centered on ourselves and be able to say no no I can't go
along with that but we can do that without hostility without yelling without
arguments and to feel the Inner Strength that no one's going to push us over we're not going to agree to anything
that we don't want to do other people might do things that in the world that maybe we don't agree with but um we
don't have to agree then we can maybe stay as a person who is safe for all
beings and this goes along with the Buddha teachings that uh uh one of the
core ethical teachings that comes from a ethical set of precepts called the 10
skillful actions these are more important than the five precepts because the 10 skillful actions which are the
first four are the same um but these 10 skillful actions are the very actions
that people who are on the path to practice uh uh could use as a reference
point for how to live their lives the five precepts are just basic precepts of
living a good life we can do uh for practitioners we want to up the standard
we want to be more careful and these 10 skillful actions provide that and one of
them is uh we are to abandon malicious speech hostile speech
and I want to read to you the full explanation of the how how to practice
with abandoning malicious speech one abstains from malicious
speech one does not repeat elsewhere what one has heard here in order to
divide those people from these nor does one repeat these PE uh to
these people what was heard elsewhere in order to divide divide these people from
those So to avoid dividing people to not speak in a way that there ends up being
hostility between people or or suspicion between people or hostility in any kind
of way thus one is one who reunites those
who are divided a promoter of friendships he who enjoys Concord
rejoices in Concord Delights in Concord a speaker of words that promote
Concord so um so this the different this this
very important distinction between speaking words that divides people and
even if the person that you're talking about is not present if you speak in kind of malicious gossipy way about
someone about how they made a mistake and how terrible they are uh you are now
promoting a division between the the person you're talking about and the person that
you're talking to and that spreads and uh but to be a person who
doesn't have uh divide but maybe you need to talk about some of the difficulties and behavior of others
which is harmful or challenging you have to figure out the solution for but the
idea is to do so in a way that doesn't create divisions uh it might be with the
attitude I'm really troubled by this person's doing I think it needs to stop I can't go along with it but I want to I
have to figure out a way to talk to this person or find a way to deal with this that doesn't perpetuate the hostility
doesn't accentuate the Divide if anything can I address this issue in a
way that uh that shows my care or shows kind of an attempt to try to be friends
again and um the um um and so the
um um um so this is this is a kind of a
fundamental teaching the Buddha has for people who are on the path of
Liberation and uh because to to divide to be hostile to be malicious goes in
the opposite direction for people who are wanting to go the path to freedom to
compassion to care and um so um but that does not mean that
avoiding malicious talk the talk that divides to talk with in Friendly ways or
talk in ways that unite people doesn't mean that we're avoiding difficult conversations
um so the another quote from the Buddha this has to do with the monastic
community and this is a community that's has everyone has AG agreed to uh
Come Together live together by certain agreements that they're accountable for
so it's in that context that he uh has this rule for monastics or is this
guideline sometimes monastics have to reprove each other sometimes they have to talk to
each other and say you know what you did wasn't right or that's not how it should be or you may did something that was
harmful here and um and you know there's there's all these rules monastics have
hundreds of rules that they have to live by and um and so and they're accountable
to them and some are quite serious there's a set of five that if they break these rules uh that they're
automatically no longer a man Mantic and can never be a monastic again like if they kill
someone and um so here what the Buddha said how does a monastic reprove
another by speaking at the right time speaking what is
factual speaking with gentleness and speaking about what is
connected to Liberation and speaking with Good Will
so this is a high stand standard So speaking with friendliness with Good Will so if you don't have good will
don't reprove anyone don't confront someone about what they've been doing if
you can't have Goodwill for them don't do it at the wrong time when they're not ready when it's not going to
have any benefits uh be careful to speak what is factual don't interpret
don't you know lead with with your feelings your attitudes as if that's the
truth speak with gentleness and then I love that speak with what with what is connected to
Liberation speak in a way that's connected to your own Liberation not in the opposite way speak in a way that
supports liberation of others and um and
uh uh and in the liberation of others you can um
the first step to that is to help people feel safe with you even if they're
attacking you hopefully just verbally there's something very powerful about
being a safe person for them so uh we will be in quarrels and
disputes conflict disagreements in this world of ours and uh there is another way than
violence there is another way than um uh hostility
and and uh divisiveness and I'll end with uh
another that I mentioned on my Sunday talk uh this week about the different uh
groups uh that are offering a nonviolent approach uh that trying to unite people
not divide people in the conflict in the Middle East and there's a an organization called Family
Circle and there about 700 members and these are people in Israel and Palestine
whose children have been killed in the Israeli over the years decades over the
Israeli um Palestinian violence and um and uh they get them to
come together because of their shared grief shared pain of having lost their sometimes very young children um one
person I read about uh his children was standing a Palestinian child was standing in front of the school imagine
school and was shot by um Israeli bullets the context of it uh you know I
don't know but still it was the killing of a child and very difficult but they
these parents come together to tr to um and become friends with each other across the Israeli Palestinian divide to
to find another way to find a way of Peace because they believe that there's
no solution in violence it just perpetuates the Cycles so let's not perpetuate the
cycles of any kind of violence including those that come out of ordinary disputes
and quarrels and let's find a way to bring safety peace and nonviolence so
that the best in each person's heart can grow can we have confidence that in at
the base of the of the heart the base of everyone's heart there is a a potential
for wholeness for love for nonviolence for care that uh can heal this
world so thank you for this week thank you for allowing me to talk about these
topics the last two weeks that have been so important for me and um I'll be uh
teaching Retreats for the next two weeks and uh Kota conin will come here next
week to speak with you and Diana Clark will be back the following
um following week and in and in three weeks I'll be back and which I do always
look forward to coming and uh sitting and speaking with you thank you so much
for the
opportunity