Welcome to our meditation together
and I'd like this uh meditation to be about something that I've in the past
have called Integrity but not necessarily the modern
understanding of that of uh of maybe ethical Integrity but doesn't exclude it
but Integrity kind of like uh being whole everything coming together into a
one and we have the uh possibility of each of us of sitting
quietly and relaxing all the ways that we live
divided fragmented and having an experience of ourselves as being
whole and uh and and being whole comes with maybe a feeling of being at home of
a deep belonging here belonging here in this universe there's nothing that
undermines our sense of place and sense of of
um you know um nothing undermines
Us and how this wholeness can be found is not by convincing our elves
that we're whole or that argue the point it's uh it's easy enough to use logic to
come to all kinds of different conclusions in this regard but rather uh to discover what
happens when we are no longer seeing our
life seeing ourselves through the lens of our Concepts and
ideas when the thinking mind quiets when the thinking mind is no
longer the dominant filter through which we know experience
ourselves the thinking mind is uh often
fragmented uh if we're caught up in preoccupations then that itself is a
fragmentation because it leaves so much of ourselves out if we're hyperfocused
on one particular thing and if what the the preoccupation has to do is about
ourselves that there's something wrong with us or with our problems not to diminish the fact that
we have challenges in our life but to be preoccupied with it um limits the full
scope of what we take in the full scope of all that we
are and so there we're fragmented we're divided and so as we meditate uh to
begin quieting relaxing
settling so that we can appreciate how we
are when we don't have words ideas
images that in any kind of way limits us any kind of way undermines
Us in any kind of way uh puts us uh in conflict with part of who we
are there's the good part and the bad part and
um and so conceit self- preoccupation are all ways of being
fragmented of being divided so with that as an introduction
we'll meditate and assuming a relaxed alert
posture that's the right posture for you and so the idea is to enter
into your body and feel it from the inside out and make the
adjustments that allow your body to relax the
most but it also allows the body to have a certain degree of
Vitality
alertness if we have a posture that only expresses
relaxation we might be missing out on the deeper kind of relaxation that
can only only happen if we also have a degree of
alertness alert clear
present lowering your gaze and perhaps closing your
eyes many of the tensions We Carry in our body are a
byproduct of the ways that we
think the force that's behind how we
think and to gently relax the
body without
ambition without any ill
will gently
lovingly feel your body and as you exhale
relax relaxing into
the pull of the pull of
gravity and is there any way that your force of your
thinking is impacting your physical experience in your
body
maybe there's pressure or tension in the head in the forehead or the
eyes in the area of the brain as you exhale
exhale let that soften
relax perhaps a g gentling of whatever force is behind
thinking
and if it's easy enough to do as you
exhale let go of your thinking let whatever
topic theme that you're thinking about it let it Drift Away fade
away so that the end of the exhale there's a moment or so of where
you can tune in to the absence of
thinking and in that absence of thinking
take in the whole of your experience Here and
Now
for
beyond the edges of your thinking
is an experience of wholeness an experience where there's no
divisions no
fragmentation a wholeness that includes thinking
but doesn't believe that thinking this is the whole story it's just
thoughts in the
vastness of the wholeness we experience by opening
up all our
senses
for
for you might try
feeling the pull into the world of
thinking the glue or the
gravitational pull into it the stickiness of
thinking and then feel your way beyond that edges of that pull
a wider sense of how awareness doesn't have to be collapsed into
thoughts but the awareness that is beyond the edges of thoughts
ideas impulses that
includes it all within its sphere
for
e
any thought you have any idea
that sees you in any way less than whole any way less than
beautiful finish that thought thought and end it with not
so not
so
e
for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to relax as you exhale to settle into your body more
fully and feel any of the ways that you might be a
little bit more settled or calm in your
body and if not in your body may be in your heart if you're not in your heart
perhaps the in the
mind and when we are relaxed in the mind the heart the
body then we belong to
ourselves we're here in a way that
is inclusive and allowing and
friendly when we're at ease it's easier to
avoid believing the thoughts that undermine
us that limit
us and as we come to the end of the sitting we could also consider
how we might be with others in a relaxed way as
well so that our thoughts about them do not limit
them
do not diminish them or undermine them in any
way let us meet other people so we can see their
wholeness even if they can't if we can see
them as part of the whole of this life is if they too belong
here and are respected as
such May our relaxed gaze look upon
everyone as whole human beings and as such we offer them our
Good Will May all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may all beings experience their wholeness no parts left
[Music]
out thank
you
so hello to the second talk about my Dharma
life and how I came into it and
began so my interest in Buddhism began in college but it was more I would say
an intellectual interest at least the extent of which I engaged in it but a few things happened then at the
end of college I did take got interested in meditation not the end of college end
of my second year and I took a class on um a class I took I was initiated into TM
Transcendental Meditation and received received the Mantra and began meditating 20 minutes a
day and um I did that for 2 or 3 months and I felt quite calm with it it was
really nice um and then um come the end of
the the school year I decided to drop out of college I was happy enough being
there but I didn't find after two years of being there a passion for any particular subject to to study and I
thought well this is too important uh to get a college degree to go to study in college should I should only do it if I
had a passion for something and since I didn't I dropped out of college and um
and that was relatively common back then dropping out was a kind of expression dropping out of society
and and uh so I dropped out of college and um that summer I had the opportunity to
crew on a sale boat across the Atlantic and I spent probably six weeks or seven
weeks on the boat and um it was uh amazing experience to be away from um
Society away from the business and doings of school and college and all
everything and to spend long hours on uh at the Helm of the boat the um um my my
favorite was doing it in the middle of the night to be in the middle of the Atlantic um with all the amazing stars
and um kind of a certain peacefulness and being far away from everything and
feeling kind of the danger of just a few feet away if I fell in the water no one
would ever find me and the boat would just kind of sail
along and um and I uh something settled in me in the course of that sail trip
and I I felt kind of uh I decided at the beginning of that trip that um there was
nothing wrong with having a fantasy life and uh I was disinclined to censor
myself in any way and the fascinating thing that happened was that uh at the
helm we we didn't have um Auto ster back then so we had to kind of be at the
wheel of the boat um uh all the time and
and um and so every few seconds you know constantly you're checking it's like driving a car in the freeway but a
little bit more D dramatic uh you're constantly kind of checking the sails checking the waves checking the compass
to see if the boat's off course a little bit and then uh adjusting and constantly
adjusting and and you can't take your attention off very long and um there
were big waves coming from behind on the sailboat so if you weren't paying attention those w waves could would uh
cause major problems for the boat and um and uh but at the same time I let my
thoughts be free my fantasy Go Go free and the combination of giving my mind
freedom to do whatever at once and coming back every second every couple of seconds to the present moment proved to
be a wonderful recipe for getting settled and peaceful and by the end of
this trip across the Atlantic I was actually quite exca and uh but this combination of this
inner freedom and staying present became a guide when I eventually started doing Zen practice for how to
practice um so I did I was quite ecstatic and I even had the thought I'll never de never be depressed again and
then uh I dropped out of college I moved to Berkeley and try to find my way in life and figure out what to do and find
work and uh things proved difficult during that time I couldn't find work I had no skills and um I didn't know how
and and um and I got more depressed and that ever been in my life before but
what happened there in that uh there's a book a bookstore called Cody book store
Telegraph Avenue and I found a magazine or kind of a magazine like
booklet about a very large Comm excuse me
about a very about a very large commune hippie commune in Tennessee it
was the largest hippie commun in the United States at the time this was 1974 uh it had 700 people living there
and um it had its Genesis in hat Ashbury and LSD and psychedelics and the teacher
of it his main um one of his teachers was Alti and the other was the Zen
master Suzuki rushi and um so I saw this place and I thought well that's interesting I'd
interested maybe stopping by and coincidentally what happened for that uh in the January of that year I
had the occasion to take a Greyhound bus across the country and I stopped in I
think it was Memphis and took a local bus down to the this called the farm and um and what I encountered there
and some changed my life two things I encountered one was um
you know this community had been based on you know LSD that was that was a spiritual practice was taking LSD and um
and they had a lot of Integrity in doing it and but they had gotten arrested in
Tennessee because that Tennessee you couldn't do that uh and so the founder and a few of the leaders of the
community were in jail when I got there and they had looked for another practice
uh what could they do that was legal in Tennessee that as as valuable as LSD for
the spiritual connection is a profound way of being and what they had found was
honesty and I'd never been in a community of people who were so honest and who had the capacity to stop
whenever there was any social tension any kind of tension at all their practice was to stop and have a
conversation about that tension and what was going on until there was real honesty and someone really understood
deeply about themselves and what they were doing and I could watch these conversations and the honesty in which
people practiced and it was so inspired and um and was inspired by how
they got really good at it and they got skilled at having these conversations so after a while some people could do them
very quickly uh initially it would take a long time to have these conversations but they always stopped that was our
practice this inspired me to no end uh this idea that people can be practice
this kind of honesty and the second thing that happened there was um the kind of the
Bible of this large commune was the book Zen my beginners mind that had only come
out a couple years before it was the Zen teachings of this Zen Masters shrio
Suzuki rushi the founder of San Francisco Zen Center and that blew me away because as I read this book I had
this distinct feeling that um he was saying things that I knew but didn't
really know consciously like was this recognition oh yes oh yes oh yes as I
read this book and it seemed to me the book talked a lot about zazen meditation Zen
meditation and um so I was but we didn't do much meditation at on the farm we did
a lot of work had a lot of truth telling and um and the other thing it
was a a large community of kind of overall uh middle class uh White
American hippies and um I was one of them more or less and so in some ways I felt very
comfortable there but because I grew up quite a bit in Europe I had a
Cosmopolitan upbringing I changed schools 12 times in the first 12 years of
growing up sometimes going back to the same school but um uh you know Europe I
lived in Italy and Switzerland and Norway and United States um uh I think
because of that experience I felt very cautious about homogeneity and I felt that uh being
around a whole bunch of people who are just like me was not a safe thing to do that I would kind of be we all be caught
up in the same delusions the same kind of way of thinking so because of that I
left and um and uh the
um I left and went to um and when I left uh soon thereafter I went to check out
to San Francisco Zen Center and I showed up there and was kind of impressed and
wanted to come back and then I came back to be there for two weeks as a guest student and uh something in me kind of
felt that home this is the practice I want to do and um and uh and there was a kind of
clarity around it but you know I was I think I was 20 maybe
21 21 and I felt it's too early for me to
um make this kind of decision and I have to go up back to Norway where I was
still a Norwegian citizen that was my home country and I had to go back to Norway to uh figure out my relationship
to my this home country and what I was going to do in relationship to it and and so I felt like I had some things to
take care of first before I can decide to kind of really give myself over to
Zen and um so that's what I did as I um
I I think I caught a ride some kind of ride service the ride bulletin board
back then in colleges they had bulletin boards people looking for Riders and I I
got a ride to the east coast and then I worked my way across the Atlantic on a freighter and um and
then took me to Spain and then I hitchhiked from Spain to U no I think I
took a bus uh to to uh Holland and in Holland I uh got passage again in
another small kind of cargo boat back to my home country and now I was interested in
Zen and uh I also had an interest in Sufism mostly from reading about it and
I went to back to my home country with this question you know do I want to go and study Zen or do I want to kind of
somehow study uh Sufism and um and there to kind of
explore my roots and uh figure out what to do and um
and uh by now I had this uh these two strong influences on me that uh the Zen
the Zen meditation the focus on honesty that I learned at the farm and um and so
now I was going to find my way um back there in in Norway so that's running out
of time and I'll continue um um tomorrow and thank you for
listening and
uh