hello and welcome everyone lovely to be with you lovely to see you that's one
delightful aspect of happy hour because I actually get to see you or 7am I feel
people's presence through YouTube it's just on YouTube not on Zoom but anyway
lovely to be with you it Delights me to see your faces feel your presence
so um
so the theme I'd like to invite us to explore and happy hour today
um is is the theme of meta
in combined with sense of playfulness sense of playfulness actually this whole
week with for the 7 A.M I'm bringing some playfulness and some improv improvising our life is the theme so so
hope so bringing in the theme the scent the sense of practicing meta for
ourselves for others the sense of lightness well this clayfulness with
this sense of ah light touch it's fun having fun with the practice
not as a grim duty of okay I need to be kind it's important to be kind no no oh
wow let's try this on for a size kind of fun it's like a game like a play like what happens in this heart when we it's
like a instrument it's like a musical instrument oh what happens when you play the strings like this oh wow that's kind
of fun what if I do do it like that what what happens what sounds come come come
out of of these heart strings if I play meta songs or just a sense of creativity
playfulness with their practice so that's all I need to say to set up
the stage and I'll uh offer invitations
during the guided meditation so so with that let's begin let's arrive
let's land in our seat
In This Moment In Time
Let There Be lightness sense of ease playfulness as you
as you arrive as you release relax your body
as if this period of practice is a treat
it's a sweet treat this fun unactivity called meditation practice
how fun we get to explore our minds we get to
explore our heart
we get to play in the sandbox
it's not just the same old same old every moment is no fresh this breath
and this body in this moment fresh like the spring
and imagining it you were opening a window
big window the fresh air outside
opening this window to allow fresh air to come in
fresh Breeze spring breathe
meeting this moment this breath
as if it's the fresh Breeze in a fully opened window
fully open window of scent store
Sensations opened with freshness
saving the breaths in the body
with delight how fun Spidey knows how to breathe I
don't have to do anything
there's no doing that needs to be done it's just receiving relax receive no
no this sense of curiosity childlike interest curiosity sense of
wonder what will happen to our heart to our state of mind
if we wish well for ourselves and others let's try it on for science what happens
let's play
through the lenses of chili curiosity read to mind a childhood friend
and maybe in your mind's eye you're the same age as they are right now
friend you remember talking with playing with
going to school with
whatever age is fine speak up a friend where there is a sense of Goodwill kindness
sweetness oh childhood friend sweet
bring them to your mind's eye this Simplicity childlike simplicity
from the world you inhabited once together with them
perhaps even see both of you as children
and playing with good wishes for both of you
playing around with Goodwill light touch
seeing your friend through your young eyes
wishing them happiness you want them to be happy to be well
you want from this perspective for the two of you to happily play together
happily laugh together Eagle together
ride your bike or play with dolls or whatever it might be
let yourself inhabit the simple childlike world
Simplicity of kindness
liking our friend wanting them to be happy wanting both of us to be happy very
simple light touch
play around with this see what's support supportive for you
and this exploration lay in the sandbox of mitta
see where your heart leads maybe your attention turns to a younger
version of yourself wishing them well
seeing their sweetness sweetness of this young person who's you
let your heart be filled with the goodness of yourself as a young
as a young and young one and your friend
bringing to mind your beautiful qualities maybe you were kind
or or curious or adventurous
maybe you were playful
your heart have lightness lightness the spirit of play
as you explore the sandbox of kindness for yourself for your friend
you can be creative
it's okay to be creative maybe at the time you and your friend
and play with Legos for example but it's okay to imagine
you and your friend playing with Legos having fun you wish these two kids well
in their joy in your imagination
now for the fun of it imagine yourself the age you are
with your childhood friend at your current age imagine yourself
playing or talking or doing homework or
riding your bikes playing with your dolls just having fun
a little silly but why not why not
drawing playing with Legos imagine yourself as an adult playing
with your friend
laughing being silly
maybe the adult versions of you have have water guns
squirting each other with delight
or whatever else you like to imagine joyous ridiculous and fun
Let There Be meta lighter
lightness Goodwill laughter
Good Will Good Will kindness in your play
jumping row playing hopscotch singing songs
you see yourself as an adult
playing with your friends with good will lightness
silliness
images might be ludicrous that's exactly the point
that there be lightness levity kindness
kindness for everyone yourself your friend or friends
Michelle wish well for every single person
with lightness levity
wherever your friends are may they be well
wishing well for them for yourself
May their hearts be light full of joy levity play
may your heart be filled with laughter and joy levity and play
bringing each of your friends and yourself to mind to Heart
with lightness with a smile wishing them well
may be their younger version
their older version
one by one
and as we bring this guided meditation sit to a close together
appreciating appreciating yourself or having showed up
having showed up as best as you're able to planting wholesome seeds
of lightness kindness levity
Delight laughter
they may flower into ease more kindness freedom for yourself
and for the benefit of all beings holy beings yours
your life touches directly indirectly and Beyond
may all beings be happy may all beings be well
may all beings everywhere including this being who is me
no joy of goodness and be free
[Music]
thanks everyone
thank you for your practice
so so what we did
what I invited you to try to try on our size
is this sense of for many of us maybe not for everyone but but maybe for
for many the childhood there is a sense of curiosity and and likeness and play
so which which we lose when we become adults we become so serious everything
is so so important that there's such such a sense of gravity and I can also
um impact the way that we see everyone and see ourselves in the world can impact
our practice as the Grim duty this heaviness of it so this was an
invitation to try and and in whatever way that it worked for you to try on the
sense of lightness so the invitation was to see yourself playing just really
feeling to touch into the sense of levity play that that we knew as
children and then to have these Preposterous images of us playing as adults doing the same games and and
um and really just as an invitation to feel into the lightness and also meta
can flow so easily out of that that lightness this good will for ourselves for our friends so as so likeness play
as as a bridge to kindness you know you want your friends to be happy you want
to be happy you want to play happily together so that as a bridge and
um it was an invitation to try it on for size I mean I worked for some of you not for some of you it's okay it's perfectly
fine it's not the only way it's just one exploration
so as we turn into uh to practice into small group practice
the invitation is to feel into um to feel into the sense of lightness
levity play and maybe if you wanted to share one aspect of how the practice
worked for you or didn't it's perfectly fine or you can offer a
your silence and just say pass and maybe something I'll offer as an
example so for me as I was guiding in many different things but one thing was that as I was inviting you to imagine
as an adult I had this memory that my cousins used to visit and were roughly
the same age there were like maybe five or six of us we would have this fake marching band we would just make a lot
of noise going from room to room to room like one after another and I just
imagined us you know banging on pots and pans as adults and just walking from how
how ludicrous there's a sense of play oh yeah we don't play but but I can imagine ourselves laughing as adults how silly
that would be we actually did that why not so I also wanted to
um invite you to to respect each other's privacy whatever is said in the Sacred
Space of the small groups stays in the Sacred Space of the small groups it's not repeated elsewhere
and the invitation is to take care of yourselves take care of others no questions no questioning no leading you
just offer one reflection one short reflection then the next person can share a reflection or say pass and then
the next person and then your turn comes so we'll just make the reflections really short maybe just 30 seconds or a
minute so that other people will have a chance and will come back to us and maybe we'll share something is another
story or something else or another way that our hearts may be found its way into lightness into a meta into yeah
there's more lightness about my body and my mind my heart um I can have this child like this
lightness about me as I go about my my adults practice and adult ways of being
so and let's go uh all in alphabetical
order um and again you can always just say pass and maybe the next time your turn
comes you can you'll offer something or not it's perfectly fine so I'm creating
the rooms and take care of yourselves take care of each other and have fun
this is a Sandbox see it as a Sandbox for play for the levity don't don't all
of a sudden get so serious with with uh with your
your practice mates here we go
welcome back everyone welcome back we have some time for
Reflections for reports how was the practice for you how were the groups you
can either raise your hand and and bring your voice in or you can type in chat
the chat is now open to everyone if you want to talk to everyone you're welcome to if you just want to send it to me
privately you're welcome to do that as well it'll be a uh
um Anonymous reflection so what uh what came up what did you notice
in this practice either for yourself individually or in
the group
person who is an iPhone I don't see your name hi sujan
um so when we talk about you know want me to try food and I
thought of one um friends um I visit their family and had a fun
together but the thing is that I in my life I'm very
playful now I'm like yes I was like and then I realized when I grow up in Korea
um our family was like more of a lot of like strict and I was not allowed to
have really fun as a kids um you know like you know when I wanted
to have a really fun my mom doesn't like it and it's just all those things reminds me of how I have not have fallen
so long and then I finally when I grew up now since 20 years ago I came here
from I mean from Korea and I learned so much of so much of fun in life so yeah
yeah thank you for sharing that so so what I'm hearing is that for you actually the bringing back the memories
of childhood and friendship and and and fun actually that doesn't work so well and and I bet there are others for whom
I know for others actually another person uh chat or send me a chat uh but
it doesn't quite work because childhood wasn't a happy time or a playful time and and and
absolutely so that's not a very helpful way in these are just invitations and
yet what I'm hearing for you sujang as you've become an an adult you've re-parented yourself in in in
playfulness in the ways of having fun actually having a light-heartedness so
so basically the point of these invitations was for us to find a way to bring light-heartedness a little bit of
Light art and it's unusual it's in it's in childhood for many not for everyone and it's okay but there are other kids
you know where do you find light-heartedness where do you find lightness can you bring that and it
sounds like you found that in your adult life and so bringing a sense of that
into your life and into your practice otherwise it can become so heavy as I said this morning of course you guys may
not have been there really this is an invitation to see them
the fullness in emptiness because it every it The Emptiness is the mark of
existence nothing exists independent of other things and so so there is a sense
of freedom of emptiness lightness of emptiness and yet there is this fullness
there is this Joy there's the joy of possibility so so that's what I'm trying
to invite us to not be fixed into it's only this way and it's only this and
it's very heavy and it's very tight and but open up so that and each of you
might have your own way it may not be in the childhood but it might be in other ways so thank you for bringing that in
really appreciate it thank you
any other realizations aha moments
[Music]
you still wait let me try again bear good work the first time oh I did
okay so right I mean this was like a lot of fun I thought I mean I that was sort of
you know it was playful I guess um by the way I did imagine myself as an adult playing with a little kid on a
seesaw it was it was hysterical something right at Looney Tunes um you know one of the things I noticed
was you know when you think about little kids you know it's hard not to like wish
them well you know right and you know right even the ones who like were really
difficult for me right it really made my life miserable right it was obvious they were having a freaking hard time back
then you know and you know they grow up into adults who maybe are still having a
hard time you know and and it was like you know it really felt just warm and compassionate
to you know you know people I probably would have been up here not knowing because you
know and it was nice beautiful thank you Neil I just you yeah
beautiful I couldn't say it better
how can you not feel you know good will wish wish well for these for these kids
and and you just yeah you put it so well that that was the intention that was the hope of the practice so thank you for
your practice report yay I'm glad it worked yay your practice report makes me happy
that's lovely thanks Neil I'm glad you're happy I'm happy
I'm happier [Music]
um it was really fun um I got to um
um play with um my childhood friend and then it kind of transformed into my
five-year-old and my ten-year-old parts of myself and the five-year-old is the
parts that I see in myself today the jovial the playful the brat you know um and it was really nice it lifted my
heart I love that word you used was levity oh I could feel the levity in my heart
connecting to those parts of myself and the 10 year old was kind of like there was some sadness
there and it was like comforting that part of myself it was just amazing this it I don't it was transformational for
me it was wonderful to get in touch and have so much fun it was really really fun it was like I've been like in this
place where like serious decisions and it's like I got to get out and just play it was so fun thank you Nikki oh thank
you Irma that's just lovely and I'm so also moved to hear this this this
movement of your heart to you know towards compassion and kindness for the 10 year old five-year-old these
different versions um of yourself that's that and and also to get out of this this fixation of
seriousness that we get into as adults habit patterns so beautiful thanks so
much for that report um I'll go to chat a couple of chats here uh one person said my group and I agree
we need to find a deck of cards or board games at home and use them an accessible form of play as long as we don't fall
into feeling competitive yes and kitty says publicly likeness is okay but the
permission to be happy without expecting the other shoe to drop not so that meditation made me realize my automatic
thinking in that way thank you so much for sharing that that inside guitar yeah
so interesting to to um to see that yeah beautiful Ali
hi Nikki thank you thank you for this and also it dovetails uh the beautiful
talk in the morning I was there it's wonderful and then what we did I mean what I did and then we we all did four
of us in in the in the room is that just brought into the present moment and started laughing uh you know in the 10
10 minutes that we were together and just having it creating a Sandbox and just playing and you know within the
limitations of the zoom and it was wonderful and I it was interesting for me how ready I was to jump into that
play mode like back in uh you know back like back in the childhood being in a sandbox and playing
and all that kind of stuff it was just bursting for it to come up and thank you thank you it just makes me happy to know
and to to get a whiff of how actually in the small group in your group also you
jumped in to play together in real time there's a laughter and levity and and oh
we lose that we lose that and it's so important not in our lives and in our
practice practices life life is practice to bring that light-heartedness when
we're so hard on ourselves okay concentrate all right oh you missed a breath oh sweetheart it's okay it's all
right you know just being a little light-hearted a little silly with ourselves
um so it's it's it's really an an empowered way to practice thank you
Ellie thanks for bringing that in and thanks to all of you for your practice for for hanging in there exploring this
this interesting and um perhaps unusual uh invitation so
we've come to um through David I do see your hand but we've come to uh 6 59
unless it's really quick okay so your hand disappear um so I like to thank you all thank you
for your practice may you be well may you be happy may you be safe may you may
you have levity may we all be of service with little likeness of heart
[Music] thanks everyone take good care be well