good evening uh good evening to those of you watching on
YouTube my name is Jim Podolski I'm filling in
for Diana this week and next as she's away
so I'm kind of like your substitute teacher don't expect to hear the same kind of
things that you'd hear from Diana she didn't give me a topic to talk about
tonight so I thought I would talk about Labor Day
and how that relates to Buddhism uh
if any of you are not from the U.S labor day is a national holiday
here in the United States it started in the late 19th century
because of Labor unrest and it was in an official holiday in 1894 by President
Grover Cleveland so I think management and labor still is
at odds maybe not quite as strongly as they were back then but
um I think it's still relevant um
one of the things that I think has changed over time and has certainly changed in my
understanding of Labor Day and what it is that I'm celebrating is that
it's not just for trade and labor unions anymore
as important as they are and a big part of the U.S economy
I look at Labor as as this Day celebrating all sorts of
Labor not just done in factories and in mines but in railroads but in offices
in hospitals in schools
Outdoors at construction sites and agricultural fields
um and in the home
there's a lot of Labor that goes on in domestic environments
some of its paid labor some of its unpaid labor
some of it's volunteer but I think
recognizing that labor is being valuable to what keeps our society running what
keeps us Keeps Us fed which keeps us closed which
keeps us housed which attends to our
um our health and our education
so I hope you've all had some chance to reflect on on
labor and its role today
and then the question is well how does that where's the overlap between Labor Day
and Buddhism or what the Buddha taught
well at the core of what the Buddha taught were practices things that we could do
to cultivate um living in a way that would lead to
Greater freedom and greater um
release from suffering from greed delusion and hatred
and hence at least in the tarabadan tradition of Buddhism what's Central to
the teachings are the Eightfold Path and just yesterday we we started a nine
month series on the Eightfold Path um
which is going to start the the first uh Alum the first Factor will be covered
next month broadly speaking the Eightfold Path has
three groupings there's one grouping of factors related to
um cultivating ethics leading A Life That's
at the very least harmless that causes no harm and also may be beneficial
to oneself and others the second grouping is about the
cultivation of mind that is through doing mindfulness meditation concentration developing
the ability to have a stable and clear awareness of
what's going on and the third grouping is the wisdom
factors of wise View and wise intention
So within that first grouping of leading an ethical life
or cultivating an ethical life there's one element that's about
um right action or wise action
so following the precepts in a way that leads to not harming yourself or not
harming others through the things that you do
the second factor in that grouping is wise speech
that is speaking in a way that doesn't at the
very least doesn't cause harm but also in the best way
um is beneficial to oneself and others
and the third factor in that grouping is right livelihood
or wise like livelihood and maybe that's where
the overlap between Buddhism and Labor Day um
is the most obvious right livelihood is about
um in some ways is about earning a living or
sustaining oneself in the world in a way that's non-harming
and is of benefit to oneself and to others
so that said there's a lot that's been written about
the Eightfold Path there's books and there's talks
there's at least four books that come to mind for me right now there's one by bikubody
won by um Ponte gunaratna Gil frondsdale who's written a book on
the Eightfold Path Gregory Kramer and many many others
so as a result I'm not going to talk about the Eightfold Path or I'm not even going to talk about right livelihood
I would encourage you if if that phrase right livelihood
Sparks your interest that there's many talks on Audio Dharma and Dharma seed
and books to read so
and that points to how to how do you how do you work or
um how do you just live your life some people have said well I'm I'm retired now so I don't have to worry
about right livelihood but unless you lay in bed all day you
probably go out and do things and so how do you how do you spend your time
in a way that's um
beneficial and meaningful
what I want to talk about tonight instead are some practices that I've learned
over the years on retreat and
if you'll bear with me they they do relate to to labor
um oftentimes unreach if you've been on retreat one of the things that the the teachers
will sometimes say is that meal time is sort of the entertainment
portion of the show you know there's there's there's a lot of times when you're doing sitting and
walking and sitting and walking and then when you sit down to eat
um it's almost always Pleasant
and it's an experience that really wakes up all six senses right when you're
eating there's there's taste there's smell there's sight
there's if it's crunchy sound and also the uh the Mind door you have
opinions about what you're eating and so forth so eating can be a very
um Rich time to practice mindfulness
in a way that generally isn't very challenging
I mean unless they're serving something that you absolutely can't stand you know it's mostly a pleasant
experience to cultivate mindfulness
and earlier this year I gave a talk that included a component of how one might cultivate mindfulness through eating
the other practice that isn't taught so much
and I I think is well it's not taught outside of retreat
practice but I think is is useful for everyone is what you do before you start to eat
and the practice that was taught to me is one that requires a certain degree of
imagination a certain amount of creativity which is when you look at the food
try to imagine the people that
all the people that were involved in the cultivation of that
food so on Retreat it's it's vegetarian so
you know Imagining the people that have tilled the soil who have planted the
seeds who have watered it who've weeded it
and then who have harvested it um after its Harvest it's transported
some of the food then goes to a place to be processed so there's all sorts of processing that involves people
human labor Packaging [Music]
and going out through a distribution network of trucks and trains and other vehicles to
get it um closer to you
and then the people in the kitchen like on Retreat the
people in the kitchen oftentimes are other yogis volunteers that have
prepared the food cleaned it um
served it and then there's another whole group of
people who ensure that the food that you're going to eat is safe
you know from from the moment it's it's hard from the
moment that it's planted until it gets to you there's there's uh regulations
and organizations that labor to make sure that
that it's highly unlikely that you'll get sick it's it's it's maybe
99.99 it's it's not a hundred percent but
um I think in my life I've only had food poisoning twice that I know of
which probably was not the case in my grandparents day or their parents day
um you know you couldn't be assured that what you were getting to eat was
um wasn't going to make you ill so those are all so just imagining all
of those people that have been involved in
um in producing your food every morning I have oatmeal steel cut oats so I think
of the people that grew the oats that harvested them the their processed
they go to the store there's people there that handle them
I provide the labor to cook them
the blueberries and blueberries come from Canada The Raspberries come from Mexico
the pomegranates come from South America the walnuts I think are from California
the bananas are from Central America so people in all of these places
have labored to produce this food and bring it to me
and so one of the practices that I do not not every single meal but many
is to just at least briefly think about how
this food has been produced and
arrived at my table on my plate
and then to add another layer to that think of all of the people that supported those people
who fed them who clothed them who house them who educated them who took care of their
health their family their Community their friends
co-workers it's really quite amazing to think about
how many people are involved in just a simple bowl of oatmeal in the
morning
you might ask why am I talking about this like well it's an interesting practice right you
know to exercise the imagination to think about
um how how this food came to be here
but you want to ask so what who cares
well I I can think of three levels or three
um ways that that reflection that reflection of how how
your food is produced and and arrives you
that can be beneficial the first one is that it brings about a
recognition and acknowledgment that
there were that you're dependent on many many people for something just as basic as as a meal
um I imagine that the people in this room and the people
on YouTube probably have at least one meal a day but there's many people in the world
that don't so you know kind of recognizing that those of us that do get to eat at least
once a day are doing it with the help of many many other people
so recognizing that dependence on others
the fact that as much as we might like to think of ourselves as
um self-sufficient and autonomous
that really at least once a day we're relying on many other people
that were connected to those other people and they're relying on us
you know to um to to feed the economic system
so that just that recognition and acknowledgment of dependence I think can
have a benefit recognizing seeing more clearly that
who are not as maybe independent or autonomous as we think
the second level that comes to my mind is
that it's a chance to cultivate gratitude
um
I have to admit growing up gratitude was sort of forced on me by my
parents like I had to thank my aunt for getting clothes rather than toys for
Christmas and I looked at it as kind of a um [Music]
just the social requirement not so much something that was
valuable but as I got older I found that you know actually
cultivating gratitude led to Greater happiness and a greater sense of contentment
so in this meal reflection you might imagine feeling gratitude to all of
these people that are supporting you nutritionally
I know one of the practices that I took up oh maybe 10 or more years ago was
every time I went into a coffee shop to get a hot chocolate or something
that I'd always leave some tip but I'd also personally thank the person that made my hot chocolate I'd always
make sure that they heard me say thank you and at first it was kind of mechanical
and then after a while I found it really started to become much more automatic that that
um that it made me feel happier and at
least some of the time the Barista would um
you know light up a little bit by being thanked you know that this wasn't just
another customer demand making some demand but that they were actually
grateful for their efforts
so this meal reflection practice can be a time to help cultivate gratitude
I know I've read that there are people that keep gratitude journals
that have a journal Maybe before they maybe when they first wake
up or maybe before they go to sleep at night writing one or two things that
they're grateful for and over time it's been reported to me I
don't do that myself but it's been reported to me that they just feel happier they you know it kind of
kind of works against a certain innate
um tendency of the brain to remember what didn't go right you know the the sort of
the negativity bias that they talk about that by recognizing that there were things that
happened that you're grateful for that that can actually help counteract that bias and actually make
you feel a little bit more satisfied a little bit more content
so if you
if you do this meal reflection whenever it occurs to you to do it
There's an opportunity there for cultivating gratitude
that mostly is going to benefit you because you're the one that's seeing it
you might get a chance to stick your head in the kitchen if you're ornery well it's hard on Retreat you're usually
silent but maybe after the retreat thanking the cooks expressing your gratitude for
what they've offered you certainly at restaurants or
um cafes that's an option or if you go to somebody's house for a meal
thanking them not not just out of a sense of social commitment but out of a
sense of um it being beneficial
so and then the third level is there's a a practice that's
um taught here at IMC like every evening they have something called or every
weekday evening something called the happy hour which is
um cultivating one of four practices called Brahma biharas and
maybe the main one is loving kindness so in the loving kindness practice
that's all taught all over the world you often offer phrases of well-wishing
to categories of people to usually start with people that are easy
to wish well for like mentors teachers people that
you don't really have any um
that mostly you feel very good about might be yourself as well
and offering phrases of wishing them to be safe to be happy to be healthy and to
be peaceful um so there's usually the the easy
people the benefactors friends are usually a second category that are usually fairly easy to be wish
well for but you might you know have a few uh little sticking points with them
from time to time and then neutral people people that you don't really know just wishing well to
people that you might see in the airport or in the supermarket
and then difficult people so that's the way loving kindness is
often taught with this meal reflection you have
people that mostly are going to probably fall in one of the first three categories
you could see them as benefactors people that are supporting your life in some
way they might be friends they might be people that you know
um and a lot of them might be neutral people people that you don't really have any direct
um connection with but that you can wish them well you know that their lives be safe
and happy and healthy and peaceful
and you might wonder well what good does it do for me to wish them well if they
never see me they don't they have no idea who I am but it does it changes you
it changes it that this loving-kindness practice can
um soften aversion
so you know so the to repeat the three
levels there's um the recognition and acknowledgment of
being dependent on other people cultivation of gratitude
and then also cultivation of love and kindness so those are three
three um benefits
of doing this meal reflection
I had dinner on Saturday night with a friend of mine who I've known from a food group
that we formed 20 years ago and I told this person that I was going to give a
talk about meal reflection and they had actually lived at San Francisco Zen Center for
about eight years and so they sent me
chant that they do at send center before every meal so here it's not just
a single person doing it in silence but it's actually the whole group of people sitting in the dining room read
this chant I won't chant it but I'll read it
um we reflect on the effort that brought us this food and consider how it comes to
us we reflect on our virtue and practice and whether we are worthy of this
offering we regard it as essential to keep the Mind free from excesses such as greed
we regard this food as good medicine to sustain our life for the sake of Enlightenment we receive
this food first this for the three Treasures
next for the four benefactors finally for the beings in the six realms
may all be equally nourished
so I'll read this one again you can find this on the San Francisco
Zen Center website we reflect on the effort that brought us
this food and consider how it comes to us we reflect on our virtue and practice
and whether we are worthy of this offering we regard it as essential to keep the
Mind free from excesses such as greed we regard this food as good medicine to
sustain our life for the sake of Enlightenment we now receive this food
first this is for the three Treasures next for the four benefactors
finally for the beings in the six realms may all be equally nourished
and this person also gave me another version of this that from tiknot Han
who's a was a renowned
Vietnamese zen teacher
and it has a somewhat different ring to it
this food is the gift of the whole universe the Earth the sky and the work of many
beings may we be mindful and so be worthy of
receiving it may we transform our unskillful states of mind and learn to eat in moderation
may we take only foods that nourish us and prevent illness
may we practice so that all people in the world will have enough to eat
we accept this food that we we may realize the path of understanding and love
and I'll I'll read it again I'm not exactly sure where this is on the web but probably if you
look at tiknot Han and food blessing you can find it
this food is the gift of the whole universe the Earth the sky and the work of many
beings may we be mindful and so be worthy of receiving it
may we transform our unskillful states of mind and learn to eat in moderation
may we take our take only foods that nourish us and prevent illness
may we practice so that all people in the world will have enough to eat
we accept this food that we may realize the path of understanding and love
so I felt very happy that this person sent me these these two chants and um they also sent me their version
they [Music] um you don't necessarily have to use the exact wordings here but you might
put together one that that works for you what struck me when I read these
um Not only was it acknowledging that it
that it comes from many beings
but it points to uh howied how much we eat you know that
it's like learning to eat in moderation so oftentimes I know for myself oftentimes
if I'm really hungry I just will overeat because it's just it's good food it's
really wonderful it's nothing really wrong with that but there is some value in learning to just
just eat what sustains the body
um and helps keep the Mind clearer than it can be if we
over indulge um there's a pardon here about food that
nourishes us and prevents illness so eating healthy food eating food that um
is nutritious and doesn't um
doesn't negatively impact our immune system
and then finally there's in particularly in the second one there's um we accept this food that we may realize
the path of understanding and love so seeing that
we can have higher intentions than just having one more meal that the intention
behind eating is so that we can
develop we can develop understanding and love understand greater uh
cultivate greater wisdom
so that's that's it for me uh
I really appreciate all of the
um I not only appreciate appreciate everyone who's makes the food that I eat
each day but I appreciate all of the teachers that I've had that
have taught me the values of
yeah of living wisely earning a living wisely eating wisely
and cultivating gratitude and loving kindness so
thank you all
so do you have any questions or comments or something everyone just take this
microphone I know it seems crazy but there actually
are a couple of people on the on the YouTube channel okay
um thank you for the talk I was just thinking of when you're um talking about uh the mindfulness and the appreciation for the food how I was thinking across
uh other religions or cultures it seems like food is kind of a um a thing that takes importance and
whatnot and I was thinking of like maybe Native American culture and and sort of using all the food that you have and I
know like in Catholicism and there are certain days where you don't eat uh certain types of food or whatnot but
it's just interesting how that kind of um uh is found kind of a commonality
yeah yeah thank you yeah yeah that those are are great observations I mean that
it isn't just it isn't just Buddhists that are into this that I mean food is
you know fundamental to life and and uh in
in some ways very fundamental to community and connection and one of the
one of the things that I enjoyed when my parents were alive were um
no matter what was going on in the family when we sat down together to eat a meal like for Thanksgiving or
Christmas or something that there was just a sense of happiness
and connection that came from that
okay well um unfortunately I'm not close to the
computer so I can't tell whether there's any questions in the in the chat
so I think I'll just uh end there thank you and uh
may you enjoy the rest of Labor Day