welcome welcome everybody you're welcome to move around if you'd like sit in a chair or move
chairs or come up front or something like this we put chairs not really knowing how many people will be here so
just want to let you know move to where you'll be
[Applause] comfortable so I don't know if you guys
were like me but uh somehow when I first started meditating I had this idea like
oh just be relaxing and all those like pesky emotions would just go away and an
opportunity to uh just be quiet it turns out right that didn't
happen and maybe that's been true for you too especially if we have a regular meditation practice if we have a
commitment that we're going to sit every morning for example some mornings we
wake up and we're cranky so we meditate with crankiness or maybe we feel sad or
maybe we still feel tired or hungry you like all these types of things or maybe there's some times in
which you go to sit to meditate and you feel really easeful and relaxed and
steady and then maybe a memory comes up and then there's emotion fear or anger
or sadness or maybe you're thinking about something in the future and fear and anger comes
up so meditation and emotions right they definitely go
together and we have we might even have this idea like oh to be an awakened means to not have
emotions it's not how it works it's not that we like get rid of emotions it's
instead that the suffering that we are adding to emotions
just doesn't exist anymore sadness it still arise but it's not a
problem there's no suffering associated with it anger might arise it's not a
problem there's just no suffering associated with it and it arises and passes away it's like short duration
might be intense but it's like oh wow oh this is what anger is
like so in order to find like Freedom some ease some peacefulness
with whatever is arising in our meditation in our daily life that of course would include with emotions with
our emotional life whichever emotions of course most often we want to
talk about the difficult ones anger sadness
fear we want to keep all the love and the joy and the happiness of course we
do and it is true that we tend to talk more about the
difficult emotions because they're difficult but also because there's a way
in which there's a collapsing there's a shutting down there's a like getting stuck with
difficult emotions and then there's a this strong sense of self that gets created I'll talk a little bit more
about this but that's in contrast when there's love and joy and happiness we
tend to be open and then when there's open there's can be more shedding and to be letting go
and this open and shedding is the direction towards more freedom as opposed to this collapsed and tight and
I got to figure it out I got to make it go away or something like this so that's
often why we talk more about the difficult emotions the happiness and the joy that's an inherent part of practice
it's definitely a part of practice to himself just talks about this how they
are factors of Awakening joy and happiness so they're definitely part of it and they arise naturally so I don't
want to like say emotions and only focus on the difficult ones and not
acknowledge that's why there's so much beautiful the most beautiful experiences
of my life have definitely been associated with
meditation so but how can we how can we find Freedom with our emotions
recognizing that they're not going to disappear they're a part of our life our meditation life our daily life our work
life our personal life they're just a part of our life how can we find Freedom how can we
feel like we don't feel overwhelmed by them or to feel like we don't have to try to avoid them but instead to have
confidence okay I'm going to do this and then it's I'm probably I'm going to feel fear or I do feel fear but to find a way
to do it anyways have those difficult
conversations to be able to support somebody who's I often give this example
because it's uh it's really touching to be able I've had this experience a number of times to just hold the space
when somebody relates terrible diagnosis or a terrible breakup or you know
something that family member that's really just heartbreaking has happened to be able to just be with the
difficulty of that and not collapse and blame or somehow lash
out but to be some steadiness that then supports everybody else we shouldn't
underestimate how powerful that is like how different this world would be if
more and more of us could do this hold the difficulties
so in order to find Freedom with our emotions we don't get to say okay I'm
not going to have any instead the freedom is with our relationship to the
emotions how we respond how we react how we feel about
them the emotions will come and go because life brings us things we don't
get to choose that so practice is really about our
relationship and so often we don't even notice what our relationship is to an
emotion because we're overwhelmed with it and we're trying to push it away most
likely or manipulate it and change it or make it be different so there's two kind of like
categories this might be a gross simplification but some sometimes I like to do this just because it can be
helpful like little hooks or that we can hook some of our thoughts or ideas on so
might be like way we can understand like two categories of relationship to
emotions that we can work with maybe like two levers that uh we can pull or
dials we can twist one is to look at any
resistance we have and I'll talk about this more some of
this pushing away or turning away or I don't want to go
away right there's so many ways this shows up in our lives or two being
identified with it I'm angry I'm mad this means I'm an
angry person I shouldn't be an angry person I'm an angry person and maybe we beat up
on ourselves a little bit or maybe we have the sense because I'm angry then you know people are just going to
respond to me in this certain way or I can't go there because I'll lash out and they'll be angry or they're expecting me
to be mad or there's a way in which we can like take on these emotions as part
of our self-de the way that we view ourselves the way that we just think it's part of
who we are it's true its experiences we're
having we experiencing anger there's no denying that but it's sometimes what the meaning
we attach to it is where some of these there's this word levers or dials that
uh we can turn levers we can push with our relationship to
emotions our resistance and what the meaning we're making very often that
meaning is about what it means about us as a person the identification that we
have with us so this
shift from a away from identifying or making it mean something to just
recognizing instead of I'm
sad and then when we say that oh just I think naturally that comes along with a
statement like that is all the other times we've been sad and this fear that how long am I
going to be sad I don't want to be sad again and because I'm sad that means
that I can't do this or that or the other
thing especially these days right if you look on social media there's this False
Image that everybody's uh portraying writing putting online and we start to feel like oh I'm
isolated because my life doesn't look like that I have difficulties but you
you know of course nobody's putting that online so they're they have these false lives that are getting broadcast but
nevertheless so this shift away from thinking I'm
sad to sadness has arisen sadness is here
sadness feels like this and I know this is clunky language this isn't a way that we would normally
speak to ourselves or to others but I have found this is so
helpful just this little if we can remember right to make this little shift in the way that we just verbalize it to
ourselves to others sadness is here sadness is being experienced
sadness has arisen sadness feels heavy on my shoulders and I feel this pressure
behind my eyes like I'm going to cry then that kind of like undermines
all the story making and the meaning making and instead it just allows us to
honor the sadness to honor our
experience and to know it's like this sadness is like
this there's also a big shift that can happen when we think when we notice the
resistance resistance shows up in so many ways that can be subtle and we
don't even really notice it it can be this way if we find ourselves really
tangled up with a particular emotional experience
anger and we feel like we just can't get rid of the anger part of it is maybe there's some of this identification this
meaning remember this one time I was really angry this is years ago but I was
really angry but I had had have been that angry
I don't know for a long long long time and I was surprised by this all the energy that came with it and I kind of
liked it all of a sudden I felt really powerful and like wow but it turned out
to be so corrosive and really just
awful this was a good learning but there's a way in which maybe we have this me
that we're assigning like oh it makes me I'm powerful because I'm angry or
because makes me I can push people or things away but resistance also shows up in
subtle ways I'm sorry so part of what uh keeps
anger around can also be resistance it's like why am I angry I don't want to be angry I shouldn't be
angry especially often women get this message that we shouldn't be angry angry and then if we are like oh no I
hope I didn't they didn't see that or I may have to do some apologizing and I don't know how to apologize or I don't
want to apologize or all these things all this stuff that gets
uh Tangled Up I kind of like this word Tangled Up with the anchor I'm just
using angor as an example this could be sadness it could be fear any of these difficult
emotions but if we don't have resistance there can be a way like there could be this anger
arrives uh heat in the face maybe a sense of energy maybe a sense of like
kind of like this you know sense of power like oh or it could also be a
collapsing like oh I'm so mad but I don't want to be mad
but it just arises experience it acknowledge it and it passes away it's the nature of these
difficult emotions to do that so as a want to kind of like
support working with these difficult motions either with the meaning we're assigning to them or the resistance we
have to them and borrowing something that Gil did a couple of years ago
and of making some modifications I kind of liked what what
he offered and I'm altering it to for my purposes
here and he offered something to as a help work with
fear and I'm using fear as an example for any difficult emotion it's a way to work with fear and
the acronym f e a r
fear what is the first f is friend we I mean technically probably
would say bef friend but I guess now you can like click something that's like a friend or so to friend the
experience is there this way that we can stop pushing it
away right this is the opposite of being res having
resistance I'm sorry I'm remembering now that I lost my train of thought earlier I want to say a little bit more about
resistance I was saying that it can show up in subtle ways it shows up in one is like it's the prolongation of the
emotion but also is just some general avoidance a lot of avoidance and
avoidance shows up with just wanting to distract ourselves always picking up our phone or
always doing something other than what needs to be done is we're trying to
avoid something and often what it is is is an uncomfortable experience
erience or maybe some ways of the way that we're resisting is just telling
ourselves like okay I just have to get awakened or something like this and I
have to have some more spiritual something and then all these emotions will go away we might have this
story it's true that the troubless or the difficulties of emotions go away but
Emotions Don't Go Away we don't stop becoming humans
so to friend this difficult emotion to friend fear is different
than being aversive different than being ashamed it's different than trying to
fix it it's a different than attacking the fear trying to make it go away it's
different than analyzing it trying to figure it out like when a child is afraid we don't
do all these things we don't yell at them more instead maybe we take them into our lap and hold
them Comfort them we pay attention to
them maybe caress them be a friend be a parent be a aunt uncle whatever
grandparent whatever our relationship is whatever is appropriate for them but to be
present for a child or that part of ourself that is having fear or is
sad is there a way that we can acknowledge it and respect
it so much about this practice is kind like becoming whole stopping the trying
the ways that we try to excise cut off parts of
ourselves is there a way kind of like the fear feels s
safe to just be fear this isn't necessarily
easy but is there a way that we can acknowledge it's already
there and there is truth in this cute little saying that what we resist
persists so just this recognition that okay there's fear here here sadness here
and there's there there's this way in which mindfulness practice we could say is all about this too is kind of like
meeting whatever is arising in our experience with some attention and some
care Jack cornfield now kind of talks about mindfulness as a loving awareness and so is there a way that we can bring
this loving awareness to this experience of this difficult emotion so f is
friend be friend e
explore there's lots of different ways we can explore one is additive feel in
the body this is a way to kind of like get into the present moment and to disrupt the momentum of the thinking
mind resisting mind it's also a way to create a little space between us and the
fear or or sadness or anger or anything that's difficult because if often if we
are like are collapsed into it and we're completely identified with it and we're just overwhelmed by let's say
fear then that's often happening in the um in the mind and in the body but
there's something that's happening in the mind that's kind of like a promoting it or supporting it so to explore how
does this feel in the body and even to ask that question is to
create a little space between what's been look at and the looker and that
little bit of space is where we can find some Freedom kind of like disrupts the
momentum also so to explore where how does this feel in the
body and this kind of maybe just this stance of exploration instead of trying
to push it away but instead of like curiosity what is this what's what's
going on not that we have to figure it
out the point is not to find answers the point is to
question and so this is so different than how we are usually in our daily life it's you know we're trying to find
answers and figure things out of course we are it's fun to do that it's rewarding to do
that but is there a way to have the sense of
exploration so not only when we feel it in the body it also can help us to
clarify what is the fear versus what is the resistance to
the fear that might not always be clear maybe the fear is for example a lump in
the throat but not in the belly maybe there resistance is this
activation this sense of restlessness or energy want to jump up and run
away but maybe we it just starts to feel like a big jumble of
uncomfortableness but maybe we can explore what does Fear feel like what
does resistance feel like and maybe it's not immediately clear what the differences but again
it's the asking the question and to create this space around
the experience of fear disrupt the momentum because I'm talking about disrupting the momentum a lot of what
the momentum is doing is creating meaning because I'm afraid means that
I'm weak and I've always been weak and I was
hoping that this meditation practice would be better but now it's bringing up my fear and it's just making me feel
worse or you know there's all these things that we could do all the thoughts that could happen in our
minds so this exploration how does it feel in the body the fear and the
resistance it's also to turn towards the object of the fear what is it that we're
afraid of part of that this question of what is
it that we're afraid of is to recognize that some fear is appropriate there's of course if we're
in imminent danger or we expect that it's
dangerous some of it is maybe it's uh maybe I'll stick with appropriate it's
appropriate to fear that we may harm ourselves we may harm others or we may
harm our integrity do something that uh makes us not feel so good about
ourselves that we regret but there's also this kind of
like fear or that's unhealthy that like uh diminishes the quality of our life or
keeps us from living a full life or causes us to lash out and harm
others and then of course there's some fear that we can't I've tried probably
all of you have tried too to talk myself out of a fear ears that aren't quite logical but I just have them
anyways there's something about I have this fear I don't really like to do this I
I'm getting better I can do this but I don't really like to cross the street not in a
crosswalk I kind of have like this memory of been yelled at I think this you know when I was I don't know you
know five years old like don't cross the street and so now I always feel like oh
my gosh I have to be a crosswalk or something even though I'm I'm an adult and I can look both ways you know all
this stuff but but even though I try to just uh talk myself like d you shouldn't
be afraid I can do it but there's still that little uncomfortableness it's just
we all have these things some of my friends tease me about
it and some of my friends are just like we just it doesn't matter Dana we are
crossing here they just force me to do it it's okay right I haven't been run over
yet but there's this way in which we so we might re when we look towards the object of the
fear we might know some is healthy and appropriate I don't want to like demonize all fear and but also some of
it is some anxiety and we can't talk ourselves out of
it sometimes we can sometimes we might notice if we really look at the object
we kind of explore the object we see oh this maybe isn't helpful and there's a way in which we
can it can release not always not always but this exploration
is about our experience and the
object but here's something that's maybe I'll add this there's
a way in which I me to ask what we're
afraid of is also a way that we're kind of respecting the fear or respecting the
anger instead of being just dismissive of it or chastising ourselves to kind of like say okay what
is the object it's to acknowledge oh yeah the fear the anger the sadness is
here let's explore it let's not ignore it
but here's something that can be really helpful and it's not necessarily easy to
do but to explore look for what is it
that feels threatened what inside of me feels
threatened what is it
because sometimes it doesn't have a real
basis for example we might have these underlying beliefs that we don't really owledge and
these beliefs are what's underneath the fear for
example we might have this belief everybody has to like
me all the time
everybody and then where there's fear is like oh I don't want to do that because
they won't like it and they may not like me I don't want to say no even though it's crossing a boundary or I actually
can't even do that I would have to stay up late and not get enough sleep or you
know something like this if they somebody asks us to do something extra that we feel like we just can't really
put on our plate but we do it anyways so what is it that feels
threatened maybe this view we have about ourselves I always have to be the wise funny one and then oh I'm afraid that
they won't think that I'm wise if I say that or if I go or don't go or all these views we have about ourselves these
often they're hidden so in fear and anger and
sadness there's this way in which this exploration the E of exploration is to
kind of like turn around and look what is it that's feels
threatened sometimes anger is this what feels threatened too sometimes sadness is also what something feels threatened
so to explore is like the physical experience explore the object what is it
that we're afraid of and then to explore like what is the what is it that feels
threatened what's fearing
because we might discover that these are just bits of our imagination Concepts
ideas constructs ideas that we have about ourself but you know they're ephemeral
they're not real they're just ideas thoughts
Notions we may have gotten them you know by a sincere method you know through our
culture our family but they're not tangible things
that can't that will always be there that can't change morph go
away and in some ways that which feels threatened is just another
identity sometimes we get identified with the fear but if we're not identified with
the fear there might be another identity that um is fearing feeling
fearful so what are what are I maybe an easier
way to think about it's like the meaning making that's happening here is there's this way that we
can explore like what's our what's underneath this what kind of beliefs or
Notions or ideas we have friend explore A is for
allow allow we could says to notice the resistance and as best we can to soften
it allow also means to notice the identification the way that we think it
means something about us can we soften that and just recognize
nope this is just an experience the fear is here but I am not I am not the
fear so this idea of allow if the fear is very strong it can be wise not to just jump
right into it instead maybe just do it very short bouts to feel it and then to
back away so not to explore it or to allow it for a long bouts because
there's a way if there's lot of any strong emotion it'll just tip us into overwhelm and that's not the direction
we want to go because we don't have access to our wisdom and tools and
wherewith all when we're in overwhelm so especially with really strong things just to touch into them
allow them friend them explore them maybe just for a short bit and then back
away pull away come back another day another
time slowly approach and back off if you're in meditation and like
you're something like a strong emotion comes up one thing you can do is just open your
eyes and maybe still stay in the meditation posture but Open the eyes and
like look straight ahead and then like kind of Orient yes okay I'm here in this
room and I'm sitting I can feel the pressure against my body I'm here and that can be a way in which can
help interrupt that and help us to feel more stabilized if you can continue
meditating maybe keep your eyes open as a way to
kind of like is it one way to like back
off but there's a way this uh movement of allowing like inherent in this is
this sense of trusting trusting that our inner life knows how to take care of
itself we don't have to make it be different we don't have to fix
it it's impressive what can happen if we make room for things to unfold on their
own it's not always easy to do this right because there's this way in which
we it's we're in the unknown territory perhaps and it feels
uncomfortable but as best we can to allow it is to allow this unfolding which
often is the often not what we're expecting and is maybe the most beautiful thing
that can happen there's a metabolism that can happen in a different
way friend explore
allow maybe I'll say something about allow also is that you know not all
fears are going to go away we have existential fears as part
of The Human Experience maybe that goes away I don't know but I
think it's you know it's a big deal to have this kind of fear of death for many of us it's not front of
mind but it's there right when we're afraid when we're in a situation which
we might die soon or or fear that we have when a loved one
is doing something dangerous so this allowing
is part of learning to be with what
is not making it go away cuz maybe it's not going to go away but can it not get
in our way and we can practice with this with
small things with small discomforts for me I started I didn't
know this was practice for allowing discomfort but turn out to be great practice
I used to do um some yoga Yin Yoga some of you might know about this where you
take a posture and you hold it for a long time in the beginning the posture is perfectly fine but then you know
after 2 minutes 3 minutes four minutes it starts to become uncomfortable and
you do this a way in which you're not hurting or damaging yourself in any way but just to like just to stay stay even
though it was physically uncomfortable just really gave me a lot of confidence that kind of bled out into other areas
of my life to be with difficult emotions difficult uh Sensations and other
ways so maybe that's something kind of like this
allowing and then the r released and I'm saying this kind of
as a past tense released as the as opposed
to an imperative release let go of if you could do that you wouldn't
need all these other steps right you would have just let go of it and you would have gone on your Merry
way but what happens here actually I'm saying released as maybe as
a past participle I guess or something like this so I don't want to give the
impression that you have to do something but what happens is if we
shift our relationship with the identific ation the meaning making or our
resistance the fear just gets released on its own as its
nature so as the resistance abates the fear abates or the difficulty abates or
as the identification with it the getting all tangled up with it as that starts to soften or abates then the
emotion intensity softens and abates so R is for released when or maybe when
we look around and we see that excuse me that which is uh feels threatened like
oh yeah maybe that was just an underlying belief that was just a belief and doesn't have any
substance maybe when we realize that then the fear is
released so there's these ways in which if we work with the Rel relationship
with the fear maybe I should make that that or be about relationship to
fear released relationship but the the key to release is to working with the
relationship because if we're trying to get rid of the emotion itself there's a way in
which it's like the Torah baby right we push it with our hands and we get stuck
so then we try to push away with our feet and now our hands and our feet are stuck then we try to push it with our
head and then our hands feet and head are stuck but if we work with our
relationship to it I used f a AR friend explore allow
released as an acronym maybe doesn't happen in that
order maybe it's not just fear anger or sadness just is a way for us to work
with our relationship to difficult emotions so that we can find Freedom with them so that when emotions arise
they don't have to be a problem it's just what's happening at that
moment and I'll stop there and I'll open it up to see if there are some questions
or comments thank
you
I I went to school in San Francisco and I was always afraid of jaywalk in San Francisco too because it's so loud and the hills you can't see if cars are
coming over but in San Jose it's no problem where I'm from I'm talking about the the fear and so I think like
emotions are are normal and I I sometimes think of like my friends I have you know friends who might have the
whole Gambit of emotions but for me myself I I think um when I notice it
coming up like oh no I've been here before this is not good or I don't like this fing or that feeling that's
probably the part that might throw me off and then I'll try and Monday night quarterback after I'm like I didn't do
well or I could have done better in this area or whatnot but so I don't know if it's maybe a more practice thing or what
would you probably can you tell me a little bit more about what does the Monday night quarterbacking feel like or
like what are what's the nature of that is it a what's the tone what's the attitude is it like so so like afterward
when I'm debriefing with myself or with somebody who I might call an expert like you know I'll go to Buddy and what would
you have done in this situation like oh my goodness I I totally messed that one up or foot and mouth syndrome or
something like that but I'm more hard on myself kind of afterwards or something
so it's not so on the the the afterwards it's not about saying like oh
okay I see that that was kind of triggered but I couldn't figure it out okay well maybe next time or is it a t
like oh dang it I'm never G to get this I'm always doing this probably the more extreme one that that points out yeah so
common right this kind like the inner critic gets activated when we're trying to make some changes in our behaviors or
the way that we show up there a few things we can do one is when you find your so you have a difficult emotion and
maybe you get all tangled up and then later you kind of like do a postmortem
right or Monday Morning Quarterback or whatever it is this kind of thing um to look at it one and then after that
to recognize oh I'm trying to make changes and it takes time I'm trying to
do something different it takes time because that is to help with the inner
critic because the inner critic just that's just another way of resistance or
it's just another form of getting all tingled up but there's a way that we can
soften the inner critic say yeah of course I had difficulties and then the inner critic
arose oh yeah of course it takes time it and we have to see these things over and
over again but unless we can get to this softer place where we where the inner
critic is soft then we'll just keep on doing this over and over because the inner critic
is the form that resistance is showing up to soften the resistance to say is to
be like oh okay yeah that's yeah I see how this is a pattern I have H well I know it takes time to undo
patterns let's see what I do next time you know to really have a different shift a different attitude maybe is that
is that helpful makes sense yes thank
you anybody anybody else have a comment or
question okay well may you not have any fear when
you're like walking out to your car even if you have to cross the street and I'm wishing you all a lovely
evening thank you