hello and welcome and welcome to
meditation session welcome to yourself may you welcome yourself
here in the meditation we're doing
and perhaps this expression of welcoming
yourself is relatively novel in the context of
meditation so it represents a reframing a kind of like little switch in the mind oh
something a little different than business as usual activity of the Mind as usual very different perspective
and in doing meditation it's often useful to to put a question mark
after any kind of common way in perspective in which we see our lives and
to see things in a new way and one of the interesting
analogies for this is some of you might have had the experience
of driving a car maybe driving long distance and
so focused on the road that you don't notice that the windshield is steadily getting dirtier
and dirtier and then so finally something happens maybe a passenger points it out to you
and you shift your gaze from the road out there to Little Bits to the
windshield itself and say sure enough it's quite Dusty quite dirty and
and then you clean you start the car and you clean it and lo and behold it's amazingly clear
so the same way in meditation we can be so concerned with our concerns
that we don't see how we're concerned we don't see the windshield through
which we are looking the filter through which we're looking
add our concerns our challenges what's happening for us in our lives
and that can be internally with ourselves we could be sick or have pain
some kind of inner distress emotional difficulty
and it could be things externally and in no way to diminish the value and
importance of these challenges maybe because they're important
uh it's it's valuable to really be clear understand the nature of the filter
through which we're seeing the windshield driving safely is phenomenally important
and if the windshield is really all fogged up and dirty maybe driving becomes dangerous
so there's a simple but maybe not easy a way of looking at
this how we are it has to do with is the way in which we are
concerned about anything Are we more
are we harder or softer Are we more contracted or more open
Are we more assertive involved entangled or a more
receptive available soft ready
so this is something that we can feel
and sense in the mind in the mind's eye or the mind's way of
perceiving we can see that the person we're perceiving through a kind of hardness
through a kind of the seeing the perception is soft we're asserting we're receptive we are
closed down we're open we are there's there's an ouch in how we're aware or
there's an ah so uh so today's meditation I'll
guide you into uh a little bit of this attention to
how we're aware not just what we're aware of
and um and it begins kind of immediately it's
kind of like all of meditation in a sense can be understood as a settling opening of the how we are
so assuming a
meditation posture
that the posture itself manifests a certain degree of
embodied alertness
even if you're laying down and there's a way of adjusting the shoulder blades in
the upper back maybe letting shoulder blades kind of somehow let them come down the back and the chest to come out
a little bit if the feet are laid straight to
pull the feet up so they're your knees are up closer to the ceiling bent
and then gently closing the eyes
and spending some good time at the beginning relaxing the body
the more relaxed we can become the clearer we can see
how we are aware how we're concerned
how we attend
so taking a few long slow deep breaths and relaxing on the exhale
relaxing the whole body
relaxing the mind as you exhale
and then taking a few that in your breathing return to normal
and relaxing the muscles of your face
almost as if the muscles gently fall away from the skull
softening around the shoulders
releasing the shoulders
and maybe a small adjustment in the hands where they are
their position can support softening of the shoulders
softening the belly
and then in the most matter of fact simple way as if nothing is wrong
notice that if if your body is bracing itself
or pulled in tight anywhere
or activate it in a kind of upward Direction
and if it is on the exhale soften all that
and then taking a look at your mind the mental activity your thinking mind
is that activating
is it energetic and busy past thinking
is it tight or narrow
and riding on the exhale can you let the thinking mind soften
expand
relaxing The Source from which thinking arises
and now calmly become more fully aware of the body
breathing
and notice how you're aware is how you're aware simple and relaxed
or is there any strain or
tightness resistance
any way in which you're aware attitude with which you're aware
which has some form of ouch in it something unpleasant
or is there anything in how you're aware that has an ah
that is Pleasant or feel has a good feeling maybe awareness feels receptive or open
soft maybe there's a gentleness
how you're aware is like the windshield
any way that your the way you're aware that has any ouch in it any stress or
strain in it that's the dust on the windshield
relax soften how you're aware
see if you can feel the ah
in being aware that's not dependent
on being able to stay present continuously
but is dependent and whenever you come back to being aware
that you do so an easy relaxed way
as often as you can
okay
how would you characterize the way that you're aware
is it more on the outside or in the ah side
are you aware in a way that you enjoy
if not how can you shift how you're aware
to be more enjoyable
and one way to do that is to shift your attention away from
your concerns away from your attitudes
to the simplicity relax soft
receptive awareness
and then as we come to the end of this meditation to check in with yourself again
to how you're aware
are you aware through any filters of tension or strain or resistance
any fear or desires
and if that has to be for now can you relax around those ways
it's okay it's okay to be how you are
and maybe that's okayness is its own perspective its own way of
gazing upon yourself
and then in the same way to gaze upon the world
it's okay whatever attitude you have or reaction
you have to the world it's okay
put in that okayness is there a softer more receptive way
being present for the world and others
what can you what can you learn from meditation
about a way of perceiving the world being present for the world
that is beneficial that's generous
that allows you to see things more clearly as they are
and perhaps we're that way of seeing that way of seeing can be a channel for
your good will for your kindness your care Your Love
and maybe these words can carry your Good Will and love out
into the world may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe be may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone and
kind of nice to begin speaking after having meditated a
little bit with you all of you thank you
and the topic today is called this week is called The Challenge check-in
and the suggestion is that to take the time maybe a time to pause
to take time to have this checklist to go through
to find out how you are what's going on
not only is it useful to really understand and feel discover how we are [Music]
but it's also a reframing it's a changing of perspective from the usual way of checking in with
ourselves or knowing ourselves to something that is dharmic something
that the Buddha recommended it's really productive and useful for becoming
disentangled from our life from ourselves
and um and they often I mean oftentimes it's easy that that the common way of
being in the world of knowing ourselves is through the filter of our desires our
fears our aversions our confusions our strains our resistances
and and so we can take the whole package of Who We Are and uh and subjected to
General ized opinions generalist idea
about you know about who I am what's going on and maybe uh one of the most
General that the kind of judgment we can have about ourselves so
we can live under it can be a real real challenge is all the things that goes under the
category I am bad I am wrong
and not so obvious but all the ways in which we live under the category I am
right I am good can be also limiting for who we are and
one way it limits us it keeps us from seeing more deeply what's going on within us underneath those
generalizations and um and to see more directly and
deeply and so the Buddha's check what I'm calling the Buddha's uh checklist
is a way of dropping below the generalizations below the kind of belief and judgments
we have and this is a phenomenally generous thing to do to ourselves
to free ourselves from the generalizations from the
judgments from the ideas we kind of struggled under
where that represents being entangled that represent being kind of being
caught up and excessively concerned about something or
um and when we take the time to stop to do this checklist check-in
then we um we're actually stepping out of
the strong winds that are pushing us along we're stepping out of we're
stepping off the the you know the conveyor belt sidewalk
that's walking along in some building and we're not being carried along anymore we're stopping to take a step
back and see what's happening here and in a way that we can't see if we're
carried along if we're caught up in what's happening in these generalizations or the feelings we have
and um so to check in you know how am I on my body What's Happening Here
if there's 10 if you're tense and you didn't know it maybe it's useful to relax
check in with the feeling tones is this experience really unpleasant
or is it really Pleasant and if you're caught up in the unpleasant
is that the full story is there pleasure here as well or is there some shift of
orientation is the unpleasantness more product of my own mind
my own mind's reactivity than it is in the activity that I'm in
checking in with the state of the Mind is it contracted or is it expansive
and then today the fourth foundation of the Buddha is that mental processes in
the mind in some ways are not too different uh they're kind of overlapping with the third Foundation
um and um and so the activities the process of the operating principles that
are driving the mind or supporting the mind what are they
and so is there um so the Buddha list gave a list of the five hindrances
and he also gave a list for the seven factors of Awakening and the five hindrances are ways of
being there are sticky entangled knotted up
with experience and the Buddha uses the word nodded up in terms of how we can get caught up and
stuff and then the um the seven factors of Awakening how we loosen how we untie
how we become clear the five hindrances are considered
things that hinder our ability to see clearly the seven factor is Awakening and what
supports us to see clearly so um so certainly if you know these
things you can kind of check in with yourself what oh how what should these are operating someone who does a lot of vipassana
practice should really be kind of second nature to notice what are the hindrances when they're operating
and also uh even in subtle ways in which the seven factors of Awakening operate for us
but for day-to-day and what I would like to say is um is noticing if how we're
oh involved in anything at all involved in thoughts involved in activities in the world
involved in conversations do we feel um entangled in it do we feel caught in
it and in such a way that there's an ouch or do we feel expansive in it open in it
are we agitated is the energy kind of activated and or or is the or is the energy the for
the the feeling energy feeling of it one of being suffused
and this has something to do with the source they see there's seven factors of these um the fourth foundations The
Source from which so much of our Behavior arises out of
the hindrances are behavior that rises out of a source which is very limited
and very tight and narrow and constricted or entangled Maybe
this what arises out of the seven factor of Awakening is also energetic but it's
an energy which is not entangled or agitated or activated but rather an
energy or a Vitality in the body that feels like it suffuses us it
spreads more widely it's and it's the difference between being
um in a tornado versus being in a really relaxing pool
of water so both of them can be energetic in a way these two states but the quality of
the energy the quality of the activation or the quality of the how we're engaged
how we are with our experience how we're attentive is radically different
so to um so what are the mental processes involved are they the hindrances or are
they more the seven factors of Awakening and are they more
something that feels unpleasant to be how we're involved uh more like a fight or flight the
hindrances could be analyzed from the point of view of a fight flight or freeze
not completely but good but it's a little bit and um and the the seven factors of
Awakening can be more more like relax nurture soothe
um you know uh approach
so the operating principles of the mind that are the source from how we see the
world how we are in the world so this change of perspective this check-in that we're doing
comes to the point where the check-in itself is contributing to a positive way of
being present a positive kind of more something it cleans in the direction of seven factors of Awakening
so part of the value of this mindfulness check-in is that in and of its on one hand we're
learning how we are we're learning to see ourselves from a different point of view and on the other hand we are bringing
into the ecosystem a healthy way of being present and
seeing and checking in that is not entangled not caught up
so both of these work together and both of them are important changing the perspective of how we see
ourselves when we're challenged according using the perspective of these four different areas of what's happening
for us and bringing it's kind of like bringing
an adult into the room of a lot of teenagers kind of having a fight or something it's kind of like bringing a wise Elder
into the into the mix using the check-in
is bringing into the ecosystem a new way of being
and the whole ecosystem can change by that introduction
just simply stopping and checking in and maybe going through these four how am I physically
how am I you know feeling tone how am I my mind
stayed High Am I by the underlying processes of how I'm involved I'm
concerned so for today I would like to suggest for
you is that uh through the day periodically to be if you like schedules you can
schedule it once an hour or some way or other
um do some quality take quality time it doesn't have to be law maybe it can be
two minutes to stop maybe even close your eyes
check in with yourself using these four different check-ins
but but notice as you do it or when you have done it if the if the check-in itself the
attention that we bring that is looking at ourselves in this way has that in fact introduced something
nice into the system is a check in itself
more like a wise Elder has entered the room and everyone relax and feels oh good
there's someone here who's wise someone here who helps me to be present
see what the effect is on you of introducing their mindfulness check-in that we're
talking about this week so thank you very much and uh look
forward to tomorrow