hello again so my name is Maria
strotman and um I have been around IMC for something
over 25 years as a student and a teacher of the
Dharma and I use those two words interchangeably
teacher and student because the one thing I'm sure
of is that I don't know I don't
know there are many things I don't know and the things that I'm sure of I'm
unsure of in the last few
weeks we have been talking about nonh
hatred how do we deal with conflict how are we in the midst of the
unacceptable and floating around in the back of my mind is well we really have to talk about forgiveness and because
I've been talking about forgiveness to a number of students over the last few
months and have to deal with the fact that basically they are rejecting what I
say I've had to think about why is that why is it that what I say about
forgiveness comes across as something that's just not possible how do we
forgive what is unacceptable you know on the face of it
they just don't go together if it's unacceptable how can I forgive
it I can't say it's okay I'll just forget
it so the good news is that's what not what I mean by
forgiveness it's not what I mean by
forgiveness so I'm going to spend a little bit of time talking about what we
mean when we say forgiveness and what I mean when I say forgiveness and why we
get tank l in this I can't let go of this harm that you have done
me so so one of the things that's true is when we think about forgiveness we
are used to thinking of it almost as a transaction you have harmed me you now
owe me there is a debt to be paid there is a need for Retribution there's rep
reparations you must apologize you must pay me back there there's a need to even things
up you know we we kind of think of it as a balance somehow somehow the word
forgiveness has taken on a connotation of something bought and
sold something that where there there is this transaction between one activity
and and another but
forgiveness is actually a state of mind and it's a state of mind that has
to do with what one holds in one's heart what do you hold in your heart
what do I hold in my
heart so what do we do how do we live with hatred and
conflict and ill will and the uncertain certainties that
come with them how do we keep from falling into
anger and ill will when someone harms us when someone is doing something that we
find abhorent how do we keep from falling into that feeling of you must not only
you must be stopped but you must pay back that payback feature somehow has gotten embedded in
our idea of forgiveness if I forgive you then I'm telling you it's
okay really huh I don't intend to say it's
okay I don't intend to say that it's all
right the dictionary says that uh forgiveness is to cease to feel
resentment against on account of a wrong
committed that's the dictionary differ to cease to feel
resistance resentment ah now now we're getting
closer resentment how could you how could you
have done that to me how could they do that to
them and the buildup of that resentment you know I've lived long
enough that a lot of bad things have happened in my life things that I've been resentful
about things that have been harmful to me things I thought were
wrong some of those things I carried around with me for a very very very long
time and in letting go of those things I didn't pardon them I didn't absolve
people it's not as if forgiveness is necessarily tied to
confession I was raised Catholic so you know I got used to going in saying
confession and the priest would tell me how many Hail Marys I had to say so that I could wipe those sins
away you know this tendency to say if I do something bad that I have to pay for
it yeah I can see some I can see some reason for
Retribution but the person who's holding the other end of that string and saying
I'm not going to let go of that string I'm going to tie myself to you the question is why why are you tying
yourself to that bad event why am I tying myself to my
ex-husband's foibles what's that
about why am I carrying around resistance resentment for someone
stealing my work and Publishing it why why why why hold on to it what
difference does it make it makes a difference real difference it's a
harming but holding on to the resentment is not harming anybody but me
that's the part that part of the suffering I don't want to hold on to that anymore that's the part that we get rid
of in in forgiveness so there are lots of definitions for for uh synonyms for for
forgiveness things like pardon remission Indulgence understanding tolerance
somehow all of those seem to give somebody a pass right right I don't want to give anybody a pass I don't want to
say it's okay I don't want to say it doesn't
matter I might want to provide people with Mercy with
clemency that kind of forgiveness where I say okay okay but
suppose suppose I decide I'm going to forgive you because now you're going to owe
me H now we're back into the transaction phase and it's not Mercy at
all it's something entirely different now it's much more
vengeful or
greedy I've known people who have totally destroyed relationships because
they're waiting for an apology if if you can't apologize to me
that's it it's over really over an
apology because there's so much weight on that apology it has something to do with who I am and what I mean and who
you are and what you mean and we really load up these things that are
harmful and we build them into something we create we we create a harm story and
then when it starts to fade we build it up again we retell the story so that we can be angry
again and Wars full of savagery and cruelty have Arisen from murderous
attacks not everything is
Trivial when harm is done we tend to establish blame we measure the amount of
harm we vow we're not going to forget them we're not going to forget this
source of harm we don't condem condone this
behavior and therefore you need to be
punished and we measure it out you know so much punishment for so much
offense
somehow we need to step away from this tendency to take those who harm us as
somehow directing against me and mine and who I am and what I am the
self-interest of the harm the
self-interest
when we look at it from the Buddhist point of view there there is what we call a forgiveness practice and it's
usually best based on a couple of different ideas one of which is don't hold hatred in one's heart non-h hatred
the practice of non-h hatred which is kind of where I'm going to go with this the importance of forgiving oneself
so that we don't turn harm against us and turn it into self-criticism and uh a
belief that this wouldn't have happened if I'd been a better person and and the third one is non- clinging
non- clinging don't hold on to that
string but how do we refer to the process of letting go of the past
without saying something about pretending there wasn't any hurt or granting somebody a free pass or making
an excuse for someone so at one point in my practice I decided that I was
carrying a lot of resentment toward my father and I spent a lot of time doing
forgiveness practice around my father and eventually I came to the
point where I said okay you know what he did the best he could do and I got to
let go of that and about the 150th time I heard myself say he did the best he
could do I realized I was making an excuse for him and what if it wasn't the
best he could do and I had to start the whole thing over again because I hadn't let go of it I
just made an excuse for it so one of the things about
forgiveness is you have to be brutally honest you have to really look at what you're
what you're deciding and why you're deciding it what am I saying about
it but to me forgiveness means renouncing the suffering of anger and
resentment renouncing the suffering that comes with anger and
resentment that's what forgiveness is it almost doesn't matter who the person is
myself EX's in my life governments doing things I don't
believe in the anger and the hatred I have to
own the resentment I have to own they didn't create that I am
that's that's kind of tough really you know somebody harms you and then you have to take you have to take
responsibility for your response yep that's how it
works that's how it
works we have to stay in a place where we don't hold grudges or hold on to Old
hurts or arrive at a place where we don't hold
grudges or hold on to Old hurts because you know face it we all have
them but letting go of them is also
possible and then one day you wake up and you say what was the big
deal why was that so hard I still don't agree with what that
person did and I'm not going to go to them and say it was okay but I can go to them and
say you know what I'm free of you now I'm actually free of
that because I am not holding ill will toward
you because of that that's what freedom
is and that's what forgiveness is it's residing in the place where I am
not tied to that you know some people think that the
way to get through forgiveness towards someone that has offended you is to do
meta practice and it's it's useful to do meta practice you know wishing people well because it softens your heart or
tends to soften Your Heart Makes Your Heart more resilient more willing to
open but there's a tendency to think that if
you've harmed me I'm just going to wish you well and you know then everything will be great but what if you don't wish
them well what if you just want to
break the connection that keeps you tied to them in any
way what if you just wish you could wish them well that's pretty
good I wish I could wish you will because I don't want to be tied to
thinking ill of you anymore and that's what I'm giving
up that's what I'm letting go of I'm letting go of the desire to harm
you in return I'm saying no to
that I'm living in the now and not in the memory of what
happened this is possible this is
possible it's possible to forgive ourselves now how how often if you said
to yourself why did I do that why did I stay there why did I do this
and ring our hands
regretting there's nothing wrong with regret and
remorse but then we let go of
it guilt is not useful it just builds up the story about
what a crummy person I am
rather I want to live in a world where happiness is possible I regret that and I'm not going
to do that again I regret that and now I'm I'm
severing that relationship so I don't have to do that
anymore you know in the when I was talking about non-h
hatred I read from the the beginning of the dapada
right that that talked about the importance of keeping up a free and open
heart all experience is preceded by mind led by mind made by mind speak or act
with a corrupted mind and suffering follows like the wheels of a cart behind
the hose of the ox all experiences preceded by mind led by
mind made by mind speak or act with a peaceful mind and happiness follows like
a never departing Shadow I find that just gloriously
hopeful yes that's where I want to live right there and what comes
immediately after that is
he abused me attacked me defeated me robbed me for those carrying on like
this hatred does not end she abused me attacked me defeated
me robbed me for those not carrying on like this hatred
ends this sounds like the way I look at forgiveness letting go of resentment
removing myself from harm but letting go of the need for
Retribution to write old wrongs stepping away from the connection that is tying
me down to a constant retelling of the
story constant retelling of the story
the Buddhist says speak not harshly to anyone for those spoken to might retort
indeed angry speech hurts and retaliation May overtake
you you know as we as we hit back the next thing that happens is they hit back
at us and then we hit back at them and then they hit back with us does this sound like any conversations you've
[Music] had and on and on and on it
goes he who checks Rising anger as a
charioteer checks a rolling Chariot Chariot him I call a true
charioteer others only hold the reins another quote from the
Buddha he's saying that controlling one's anger controlling one's need to
strike back puts you in control
it really puts you in the place where the suffering only occurs if you allow it
to it's not as if it happens overnight you know you just decide okay I'm not going to let it bother me anymore really
I'm talking about years of practicing this to see any
change but it's the small things that make a difference I was looking here I'm
going to read you something here from uh Jane
hfield see this this
poem is called changing everything changing everything I was walking again in the
woods a yellow light was sifting all I saw willfully with a cold heart I took a
stick lifted it to the opposite side of the path there I said to myself that's done
now brushing one hand against the other to clean them of the tiny fragments of bark
a tiny thing lifting a stick and moving it to the other side of the
path taking one action and saying I'm not going to do
that I'm going to drop that I'm not going to pick up
that
insult and then you go oh you know that wasn't so bad that that actually
oh it changes everything it changes
everything now the Buddha did actually talk about forgiveness and he had a word
there's a word in poly called comma k h m a it means the Earth
what does that have to do with forgiveness and it it is the patient
forgiving tolerant enduring bearing harded hardened
to it's the sense of uh continuation
steadiness kind of steadiness of mind and he referred to it when he talked
about the difference of when he talked about conflict between his monks and he
said okay conflict will arise and so
what he did not want to have happen was for people to endure continuing conflict so there was
he set out a number of rules for how they should resolve conflict among the groups and it involved people getting
together and the the wrongdoer the wrongdoer should admit his
transgression and the person the other person should accept that
apology and then they should agree to go forward under certain rules but but you
have to agree that you on what's right and what's wrong at the outset and if you can't then you cannot
reconcile so there's a difference between forgiveness and Reconciliation
so there is someone that I've been talking to for quite a long time who who really wants to
reconcile with a family member and can't seem to make it
happen but sometimes you have to learn to accept that it's a two-way street and
you have to give up expecting what is not offered what is not on offer
and not continue your own suffering by trying to write a wrong that requires something of someone
who is unwilling to go there reconciliation is not the same
thing as finding forgiveness and letting go of ill will they're different functions
entirely different features
so I have this this quote from uh TANF when you forgive me for harming you you
decide not to retaliate to seek no Revenge you don't have to like me you
simply unburden yourself of the weight of resentment and cut the cycle of
Retribution that would otherwise keep us in snarled in an ugly samsaric wrestling
match this is a gift you give us both totally on your own without my having to
know or understand what you've done you see forgiveness doesn't require
the other person to know that you've forgiven
them you're totally free of the other person all you have to do is let go of
it you don't have to tell them you don't have to explain it to
them you don't have to justify
it you just
stop what we want to do is live more in the world of response rather than
reactivity you can respond to what is harmful reactivity is more of a an
automatic response where you you not paying any attention to what's going on and you tend to get things that are not
very skillful as a consequence of that but with a steady mind we can see
what's happening we can see an offense happening and we can say this is very
familiar I think I'll pause here I don't have to go into
this I think I said a couple of weeks ago
that I was very happy when I watched uh a recent TV show and found found myself
not reacting to something that's a a typical trigger for me and I oh my
goodness look at that I didn't react it was very
exciting there's a a famous Tibetan story about a couple of monks that had been uh imprisoned and afterward one's
saying to the other well you know do you think you can ever forgive him and he said never never I'll never forgive them
and he said oh too bad you're still imprisoned and that's the way it is if
you can never forgive someone you are the person who is imprisoned by
that and that's what you need to let go of that's what we need to let go
of first free ourselves free
ourselves we have to see what we're holding in our hearts and that's where we want to put our
energy what am I holding in my heart how can I how can I see that in a
way so that's going to give me another opportunity to read a poem to
you this is about not having any
practice so this is by uh wava sorka who's a a Polish poet uh Nobel
laurate life while you wait performance without
rehearsal body without alterations head without premeditation I know nothing of the role
I play I only know it's mine I can't exchange it I have to guess on the spot
just what this play is all about ill prepared for the privilege of living I can barely keep up with the
pace that the action demands I improvise although I hate improvisation I trip at
every step over my own ignorance I can't conceal my hasted
manners my instincts are for hamy histrionics stage fright makes excuses
for me which humiliates me more extenuating circumstances strike me as
cruel words and impulses you can't take back Stars you'll never get counted your
character like a raincoat you button on the run the pitiful results of all this
unexpectedness if I could just rehearse one Wednesday in advance or repeat a single Thursday that
has passed but here comes Friday with a script I haven't seen is it fair I ask
my voice a little horse since I couldn't even Clear My Throat off stage you'd be wrong to think it's just a slap Dash
quiz taken in makeshift accommodations oh no I'm standing on the set and I see
how strong it is the props are surprisingly precise the machine rotating the stage
has been around even longer longer the farthest Galaxies have been turned on oh
no there's no question this must be the premiere and whatever I do will become
forever what I've done whatever I do will become forever
what I've done so hold in your
heart who you want to be how you want to be
don't give anyone else the power to decide that it's hard enough to decide for
yourself the practices that we typically use for forgiveness fat practice are
very simple for any harm that I may have caused myself knowing or unknowingly
through my thoughts words or actions I offer myself forgiveness as best I
can everything else is a variation of
that for any harm you may have caused me knowingly or unknowingly through
thoughts words or actions I offer my forgiveness as best I
can for any harm I have done you through thoughts words or
actions knowingly or unknowingly I ask your
forgiveness as best you can that's
it those phrases you repeat
them and see what arises in your heart see what comes
up it doesn't say shame on you shame on me it says may I let go of any
resentment I have toward myself for any actions I may have taken knowingly or
unknowingly through thought word or deed as best I can I mean there are all
kinds of little slippery places there it's not harsh it's not intended
to be harsh it's intended to be free and open so that you can be free and open so
that I can be free and
open the word forgiveness is not an eraser it's really a letting
go
it's it's taking the tension between you and some previous event and saying I
don't have to hold on to this it says absolutely nothing about
whether you continue to fight against a cause stand up for a cause reject
Behavior form opin opinions about behaviors it only says I'm letting go of
the
resentment I had a I had I was uh active in a particular
environmental issue at one time and there was a person who was sort of the
head of the other side and every time I would head to town
that guy's name would come in my mind and I would just become agitated as I
was driving to town this is when I lived out in the country and I could feel that agitation and my stomach would get tense
and and then I thought about that and I thought you know this person does not
even know I exist this person that I'm giving this
power to create this turmoil in my stomach doesn't
know my resentment this is all mine all mine
whatever else is true whether I continue to fight against what he is trying to do to the
environment and he continues to do whatever he's doing to the environment has nothing to do with my getting all
roiled up and upset on the way to town and when you see that
clearly it becomes very easy to let go of
it wait a minute what's what am I getting upset about this
is it's right here all I have to do is stop doing that all I have to do is say
okay this isn't useful i' got to go do something useful now to to get rid of
the extra stuff that we imbue the extra
importance taking the weight of resentment off our
plates that's forgiveness so those are my thoughts I
hope that's helpful thank
you so any comments questions I do accept
criticism
would you please use the the microphone because we're recording this okay just hold it uh I just write things down I
just have on my phone we all have notes right and I just write down the thought
and often I don't go back and read it again and it seems to relieve if you know what I'm saying
uhhuh uhuh
the practice of not letting something
Fester not having to retell the
story that poem you read about the stage who wrote that and what was it name that
was awesome it's a woman wava sorka oh lovely I won't remember that
one uh polish she's um It's s z ym b o r
s k a i think I'll come up afterwards in I w't remember that but that was just
like oh yeah that's that's my life yeah I love that one
yeah
I guess for me um uh a thought of
forgiveness brings with it sort of a fear that if the person that I'm
forgiving um has done something wrong and and I forgive them then maybe
they're going to do it again um
and yeah I don't know how to deal with that yeah yeah that that's that's a a
um that's a very valid concern and um
and it is not Inc included in caring resentment so if I fear someone's going
to do it again whatever it is then I feel feel that I have a responsibility
to uh either not put myself in the way of that happening again
or somehow trying to prevent it to happen from happening to others so an example
of that might be uh uh any kind of racial
discrimination or uh uh uh being in an abusive
household it it's not okay I might let go of my resentment but that has to stop
whatever that that behavior is abuse of other people harming of other people
this that has to that has to be stopped and so uh the forgiveness is not saying
that's okay now if it's a if if the forgiveness
is within an ongoing relationship then there is a need for the the process of
reconciliation where where there is an agreement on what is right or wrong or there has to be some some
break so uh I don't want to imply that it should it should be allowed to happen
again also kind of tied in with that is uh when
one remains in a relationship where it is repeated
then uh there's a possibility for self criticism from that as well and so
coming to terms with why one is choosing to stay in that relationship is very
important thank you I'm I don't know if I addressed your particular issue but
that's um I I think it's extremely important
that forgiveness does not include it's okay okay that this happens again it can't happen you can't if if
it's harmful it should not happen there's uh there's a wonderful quote
unfortunately I cannot remember the Korean Zen master's name but he had this
this wonderful phrase he said there is no right and no wrong but
right is right and wrong is wrong and when when you think about that it's you
know you may think this is right and I may think that is right and they won't
agree but killing someone is wrong so so in that regard you know you
can if if you hear that in your head and you listen to that I may not agree with
you but this Behavior I will not
tolerate but I don't have to tie myself to the bird burden of resentment as a
consequence that space I have to navigate that's that's on me the the burden of ill will and and
resentment
okay okay be safe everyone
thank you I've enjoyed being here the last three weeks it's been
fun good
night