so I have been away and Retreats the last two weeks and uh I still
feel somehow the presence of those Retreats and so I'm going to offer something uh this morning for meditation
that does come um that does uh come to
um uh from from the retreat
and we'll see if it works for you all this way outside of Retreats and
um so now some people are saying they have no sound but I think that
uh uh let's see let's wait a moment and see if uh what other people say sound is
good okay so I think that uh it might be a local
issue so okay so we'll start and um I'll take you maybe on a
little journey uh for
uh um the general theme for this week is
attitude the attitudes that we live our lives by and some of these attitudes are
quite deep some of these attitudes are uh we're not often conscious of them but
they can be pervasive uh setting the mood or setting the orientation
perspective by which we live our lives and how we understand ourselves and part of the possibility of
meditation is that it's a um quieting movement of the mind so
that we begin quieting some of of the voices some of the attitudes some of the beliefs some of the uh ways of thinking
ways of believing about ourselves our life that have a chance to quiet down because they're no longer active every
belief every way of thinking is an activity of the mind it's not inherent
in the universe and so to quiet the thinking mind so that we see ourselves and see
the world without the usual f filters of how we uh approach the world the usual
filters for understanding ourselves the internalized messages we
have from our society about who we are or all kinds of conclusions we have and these are getting
quieter and so when we start meditation with the process of relaxation um this is not
uh beginning Buddhism it's really the the uh uh part and parcel of this very
deep movement to settling
deactivating some of the unnecessary activations of the mind that do not give us a
accurate perspective on this life of ours so to assume a meditation
posture and to gently close your eyes
and take a few moments to feel your body as if it's okay to be just the way
you are whatever way you are almost as if you appreciate that
whatever is happening for you whatever way you are is part of a wholeness of the
moment and you are going to to sit in the middle of that
wholeness feeling and knowing the discomforts of the body the emotions of
the body the tensions as if it's part of the
wholeness discovering what's
here
and then gently taking some deeper breaths and on the exhale relaxing the
body not breathing in too deeply but just enough so that's there's a pleasure
aliveness that comes from breathing in deeply and then relaxing the muscles of
the
face maybe you can imagine the muscles of the face falling away from the bone the
skull relaxing around the
eyes and then to breathe gently and
deeply as you exhale relax the shoulders soften in the
shoulders there's a way in which relaxing the body the tensions of the
body helps the mind to
relax the tensions in the body begin in the
mind breathing in and relaxing the
belly
on the exhale now the feel the feel the area of your heart
heart center and relax soften in the
heart
as you continue relaxing the thinking
muscle whatever Sensations there are in the head or in thighs shoulder
belly connected to
thinking ancient Buddhists imagine there was a puppeteer in the
head with strings that tugged on all the
muscles and letting that Puppeteer relax
settle
down and then relaxing on the exhale down into
your torso maybe even all the way down to the belly
and feeling the movements of the body as you
breathe maybe almost as if you're gently being rocked by by small waves as you float on
water
for if there's a lot of
thinking with each
exhale quiet the thinking
mind if you think in [Music] words let your thinking become like a
library voice quiet soft maybe even
loving if you think in images perhaps there's a way of slowing them
down or letting them recede a little bit into the
distance so they're not so
pressing
for
allowing the Torso the belly the chest
to experience the movements of
breathing maybe as gentle waves while you're sitting on a little
boat rowboat comforting small
movements
for
if you find yourself thinking
trusting that it's something there's something deeper here for you to rest
in if the thinking mind can become quieter so
softer more relaxed letting go of thoughts and
letting go into the body's experience of
breathing
for
and then to imagine a very peaceful Clear
Lake the water is so clear you can see down to the bottom clearly see the
bottom of the lake it's peaceful
clear clean
a beautiful Stillness in the water and you have a round Flat
Rock of some very light
material and you take the Rock and you release it into the
water and as you watch it settle to the bottom of the
lake let your thinking become quiet quieter as everything
settles let your awareness settle let you settle into the bottom of
your inner Lake to come to a rest in the deepest
place within and for from
there become attuned to the body
breathing and from the deepest place you [Music]
know gently say no thank
you to any thoughts that
arise especially any
thoughts that have any criticism
or judgment negative judgments about yourself
you don't need to think these right now let go let
go relax into the depths of your
being
here there can be a place within when we're relaxed and
settled where there's no need for any thoughts that there's
something wrong with us those are
extra without those thoughts
we can experience ourselves as being
whole no part pushed out no part
judged as thinking gets quiet it can heal the inner divisions we
have
and everything we are could be included in the
whole
for
e
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to imagine that you're sitting within a
large sphere of goodness of
warmth of safety and that all of who you
are makes up that sphere
you have nothing to prove nothing to
assert you're allowed to be yourself in whatever way you
are but not choosing any particular
aspect letting it all exist within a larger
hole parts of yourself yourself that you know and you don't
know and from whatever place inside that's calm or
relaxed even if it's just ever so slightly
so imagine you're gazing upon other
people looking upon them from a place of safety and maybe
contentment and from there maybe there's Goodwill
warmth [Music]
care and see if you can from that place have desires for their will well
beinging a
well-wishing May the people of my life be
happy May the people of my life be
safe may the people of my
life be healthy
May the people of my life be
peaceful may they be free a freedom where there can be their
wholeness where they can settle and be contented and happy as they are in their
wholeness the wholeness which does not act
from The Limited perspectives of anger ill will or
greed may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may the way that we look upon
people help them see themselves as whole
respected and loved people in this
world
[Music]
thank
you
so good morning everyone and welcome to this morning or this uh Monday here in
California morning in California and um I feel like in this
day in November just before Thanksgiving that here in the United
States we kind of turned a corner to a new season and um and with Thanksgiving
coming up I thought it might be nice to uh spend the week on
a in beginning of this winter season focusing on the topic of
attitude there was a time when I taught the introduction to mindfulness
meditation which normally is a 5we program there was a a period of time few
years where I did six weeks where one of the weeks was um the fifth week became a
focus on uh mindfulness of attitude and attitude is very important
because it's the uh it's the background or the manner or the lens
by which we see the world understand the world behave in the world and um and it's often invisible
because it's kind of like um if you're looking you're focusing on what you're
seeing it's you might not be paying any attention to the fact that you're straining or that you're afraid and
you're you're looking for the dangers or the safety or that you are thinking that you
you know in order to be have a good time and be safe or be comfortable in
yourself you have there has to be pleasure and so looking for where is it Pleasant where is the nice things to do
and so there's an attitude behind or a belief behind how we
see how we talk how we live and those attitudes can be quite deep and
subconscious and that we don't are not often conscious of them one that I had
uh in when I I started my meditation practice in the monasteries at some point I realized
that no matter what I was experiencing the belief the attitude I
have towards all of it was it it's not the real thing um so in any any meditation
experience any way I was like if I was calm it wasn't the real calm if I was
present it wasn't the real way of being present if I um if I was breathing it wasn't their true way that you're
supposed to breathe when you meditate and I didn't know that I had this belief it was very very quiet in the back of
the mind but it it it uh it brought a kind of a discontent and a
dissatisfaction and kind of little bit feeling of an adequacy or that I carried with me and everything I was doing and
uh I was so grateful to see it because once I saw it I saw well this is a little bit
ridiculous and then um I tried tried for a while just to switch the belief to um
if it's happening to me it's the real thing and um and that kind of loosened
things up and broke up the the um the strength of this uh this this attitude
that I carried with me for so long and so uh to become aware of
attitude and as we do this week I would like to um say that um
um um um there are kind of like two categories of attitudes that we have
depending on the source within which it comes from one is an attitude that is from
reactivity and maybe from a certain kind of conceit and the other arises out of it
is maybe a kind of activity but arises out of a non-activity arises out of a deep
ability to not always be busy not be racing around not do doing not feel like
we have to accomplish something or fix something or understand something but let
something a deep rest happen so uh for today I'd like to
suggest that some one attitude that can be pervasive in some people's lives is
um desire uh that there's always wanting something and uh and so sometimes there
are some people who um Can want without even having something in mind of what
they want it's just the habit of wanting the desire to have something and so they're kind of uh wherever they go
they're looking for what is it I might want in this situation what do I want to get what do I want
to what I want to do or have or receive or and there's always this wanting like
and some of it can come from a feeling of uh lack feeling of inadequacy feeling of of um scarcity even
and um uh I spent uh uh a period of time
in my very early 20s being very poor and not having enough
food and for a while after that period um I became uh kind of a little bit
neurotic eater I just like just always looking for food and wanting food and eating a lot to make up for it and this
wanting was just so powerful until um until I really started uh meditating and
settle something deep deep inside of me and um and so uh and so that wanting that
desire sometimes that greed um uh is expressed in how we use our eyes where
the eyes are searching and scanning and maybe a little bit coming out of their sockets kind of like the are straining
to kind of figure out what is it that I want or how do I get it or something and
um I've had that uh when when I went to bookstores and when I was younger I loved to the idea of when I was poor I
couldn't buy books much but I wanted books and um and uh I used just look at
all these titles look at books and you know I was in in the bookstore looking for the books that I wanted to buy buy
buy buy but you know I wasn't going to buy any but you know and left bookstores with kind of headache and exhausted from
it so sometimes in the eyes sometimes in uh our posture leaning
forward or tensing up in a kind of way from the desire and um so to begin becoming
sensitive to a pervasive attitude manner a mood of desire which maybe
underlies a lot of the behavior we have a lot of ways we're thinking um if you
track your what you're thinking about through the day how much of the thoughts are motivated by desire and wanting
something wanting something different and um and as I said some of
that can be born from a discontent from an attitude from a belief that there's not enough that there's we're afraid we
want to prove ourselves we want to be you know approved of by other people all
kinds of things can go behind uh that desire but they're all activities of the
mind and um kind of of the surface mind and as we meditate as we have some some
some way to quiet that surface mind and there's an absence of always doing
always going and um and then there can be uh the alternative i' like to propose to this
mind that's always Desiring is to uh
contentment to be content to content with what you have to be contented with
um your basic requisites cared for and um and uh roof over your house
you know clothes on your body um you know just you you know just uh content
with the basics you're safe you're cared for and um and uh but it's not a
contentment that is a belief or something you have to do or now talk yourself into it's a contentment that
comes from the mind being quiet enough that it's not operating from this desire
and feeling of lack which are activated States reactive States and this
quietness this contentment that is almost a non-doing or arises out of of
this deep subtleness that um you have to stay settled to feel this deep contentment or
return to it it's not something if you lose your contentment you have to do more to become content it's more like an
undoing and um and realizing that uh there is a contentment that's possible a
certain kind of contentment not necessarily content with everything but
uh the ongoing attitude the mood that we're in that's what we're talking about this week so that they even though that
you might be discontented with something politics or something um that um the the
ongoing attitude by which you see the world understand the world understand yourself uh is seen through a a uh lens
of contentment there's a mood of contentment that's pervasive it's the background for how you think and speak
and go about the day and um and I'd like to propose that
that sense of contentment um uh arises when we're not
activated with other attitudes other beliefs other ways of thinking that
somehow are critical somehow are divisive somehow fracturing something
that takes away our overall sense of hope wholeness when we're operating from the
those the thoughts the belief that something's wrong with us the acting
from a place that we're a problem and there's problems with us we all have
so-called problems we all have things ways in which we you know are not
perfect but to be operating with that as an attitude it's just pervasive carrying
with us retelling ourselves the same story the same idea so we walk travel
around with that attitude all the time is completely unnecessary and to find some way to
settle that to step away from it to uh enough so that we don't believe it
enough so that a different attitude is the one that is supporting us that's uh
feeding us that's um um benefiting us and we're not walking around with an
attitude that's undermining ourselves so even if some of the things you about you are true that maybe you
have some kind of Quirk that's difficult um do not make not use that as
as the basis for a pervasive attitude that you carry with you all the time
that's unnecessary there's ways of being honest and clear and practical about the quirks
we have without it becoming a pervasive view that something wrong
with me something I have that I'm a problem for the world or something like that and
so contentment so today I'd like to suggest that if you're interested that uh you
kind of ride through the day with an investigation and looking at these two
how does desire work for you how pervasive is it how much are you caught in the world of Desire you're wanting
things and uh is there kind of not just a doing of contentment which is not so
interesting but rather a settling into contentment a kind of uh opening up and
relaxing into a place where more where there's a sense of wholeness of who we are rather than a sense of divisiveness
or fractured sense of self and in that wholeness there's less to do less to
prove and from out of that can come a contentment out of that contentment can come a very
different way to operate in the world and speak and do things and you know be
a full fully engaged citizen but uh but from an attitude that's
beneficial so um so to spend some time
uh appreciating uh what might be the pervasive attitudes that you carry with
you and consider whether attitudes the attitude that you're carrying does it
need to be uh 247 does it need to be always operating and always the view
through which you see things and if it's a reactive attitude or or undermining
attitude um is there an alternative and for today it's I suggest you look at
desires and contentment and um is there a way to be
content and still take care of what you need take care of what needs to happen
but from that contentment rather than from an attitude of Desire or even
greed so thank you so um May
uh this support your deep well-being to see the difference between
these two kinds of attitudes