so good morning good
day and um Buddhism Buddhist Meditation is often
associated with relaxation with becoming
calm and maybe for good reason because many people in the modern world uh are
stressed and um I would propose that in the ancient
world in the time of the Buddha that the association with calm and
relaxation was less prominent than the association with being
courageous that the people who really set out to do uh this Buddhist practice in
a in a dedicated way we're often seen as going against
the stream of against the against the current of popular
culture and uh against the expectations of what was family and Society wanted of
them and also against the current of their own attachments and clinging and
that around and uh uh to go against the current to do
what was maybe unpopular to really stand up and uh and not give in to attachments
of all kinds to fears of all kinds this took courage and uh and so they way that the
word for effort in practice could be translated as courageous
effort some people and I think when in when it was translated to Tibetan it be
became a heroic effort and um and this calls it calls a
lot on us relaxation it's almost like doesn't call much on us it's more like
giving up or relaxing or or not needing to do anything in a life where people are so
busy and have to do do do it's a medicine to be able to relax and feel
comfortable with oneself at ease with oneself and at home with oneself without having to prove oneself or apologize for
oneself so there's good reason to emphasize this letting go and relaxing
and just being but at the most it's half of what uh this practice is about the other half
is to actually act courageously um to act on the path of
Liberation with courage with confidence with conviction with
Assurance um to make choices of what to let go of and what to engage
in uh so that we can engage in the path of practice so we can engage in this
world uh in a caring way for others and um so the he of of Courage so I'd like
to suggest for this sitting that um that we we
sit uh and we haven't done I don't think we've really done this uh these years
now of doing YouTube so at least for today I'd like to call upon you to sit
with uh courage or sit with a strength as if you're sitting upright and you're
engaging actively um rather than simply s settling back and letting go and letting
go and uh there's a way of
engaging sitting upright or laying down in such a way that there's a a real kind
of Engagement uh strength yes I'm here yes I'm showing
up and um and uh and then with that strength
with the metaphor of of standing upright or sitting upright um letting the uh all
kinds of things that are unneeded fall away like raindrops are
said to just wash right off the edges of the lotus blossom the lotus lotus
leaves and um and you might end up parts of you as relaxed as other ways but with
a certain kind of alertness and Clarity and definitiveness yes here I am clearly purposefully
intently almost as if the mind can then relax deeply maybe even deeper the mind
can maybe become quieter than ever because something inside of your
knows that you're showing up and being present courageously for something which is important and that is to be alive now
and now without fear without attachments
without clinging without resistance but really showing up for this
moment so to assume a meditation posture
that for you is the right posture but give some care to the
posture so that it's a posture that certainly allows you to be at ease in
your body at ease in your posture but also a posture
that gives expression or taps into your
capacity for being being here and now in a strong
way in a confident way for people sitting in a chair in a
cushion maybe sitting up a little straighter or a lot
straighter maybe allowing that chest or be a little bit open and
expanded and then lowering your your eyes your
gaze or if it's comfortable for you
to close your
eyes
and see in this sitting here quietly with your eyes closed your gaze
down see inside of you is there a
place for where confidence
resides courage and if it's not
available now where in your body do you associate
what part of your body do you associate with being confident strong
and courageous in showing up and really being
here and maybe offering some energy intentionality into this place of
strength
perhaps a courageous strength a
courageous willingness to show up and be here that can be that can
Infuse the Deep inhale with
strength and a reassuring confident relaxing as you
exhale
for and letting your breathing return to
normal and is there a way of breathing in gently but firmly
clearly through the places of holding and
tension you might have that doesn't relax them you're not
trying to relax anything but as you breathe in through everything
confidently it's almost as if [Music] you're breaking through the
tension
almost like you're walking
through snow which has a crisp Frozen top and each time you
step the the ice breaks and you settle into the soft
snow
with every inhale the inhale begins and
arises and expresses confidence
courage with the inhale where you can face anything be with
anything as if the inhale and
moves through breaks through
whatever tension there might be resistance there might
be and the exhale is landing back into the softness
Within
for
e
e if you find yourself thinking a lot or
preoccupied rather than letting go of that become
bigger than that stand up metaphorically stand up
for yourself and be stronger more
courageous let your awareness Ness and your dedication be more
powerful than the
distractions show up in a strong way here I am to be
present present with the breathing with the
body to be here and aware
awake
e
for
if you are calmer now more settled than you were at the beginning of the
sitting in the midst of that
calmness can you
arouse a quiet
confidence a courage a way of being courageously
here present for whatever is here with you
with strength with a kind
of standing up showing up for yourself for the
situation courageously present with a calm Quiet
Mind
for
e
that
for
and as we come to the end of this
sitting do once again touch into where inside of you
is a place of confidence and courage maybe not present now but where
would it be present when that's true for
you and maybe settle into that place open
yourself to that place appreciate whatever capacity
however small you have of courage
courageous effort and imagine
yourself standing maybe on a small
Hilltop overlooking a vast multitude of
people and standing there confidently
courageously clearly unapologetically
wishing everyone
well may all people be
happy may all people be free of strife and
War may all people be
safe far away from
violence may all people be
peaceful untroubled with animosity
hostility the hatred is of other people
and may all people be
free free of
Oppression free of discrimination and free of hostility
and free of beings
suppressed held back confidently let's wish everyone
well confidently let our well-wishing our
care for the world be stronger than our
fear our hate our delusion our greed and
conceit let this practice
awaken a confident courageous way of being in this
world
[Music]
thank
you
so we come to the fifth talk on
nonviolence and I think most of you clearly know that this is a maybe
understated way of responding to the TR horrible horrific
violence that's happening in the Middle East and um but also in my heart the
horrific violence in Ukraine and Syria Sudan Burma all over the
world and um and then this last meditation I led
it might not have been maybe the most popular meditation that I've got of meditation I've
given if maybe because many people associate Buddhist Meditation with
acceptance with relaxation with allowing with just settling back and being no one
going nowhere nothing to do and um i' would like to propose that
that's only half the picture and in fact to make that the full picture of what Buddhist practice is is to uh short
Change oneself is to to uh uh not really step
up to really live in this world in a completely free way the Buddha did not
avoid the world after he was enlightened he engaged in the world uh he intentionally went into
places where people were back to his home one of the first things he did was go back to his
hometown and uh visit his people and and and uh and so half of the
practice may be considered relaxation the other half of practice is to awaken
awaken a an energy a capacity to act and
to uh to not be in held in check by
fear uh not be held in check with resistance not being held in check by
diminishing ourselves or making ourselves some artificial little there's a way of letting go of
self-conceit letting go of fear that allows us to show up more
fully uh in fact when to practice mindfulness to really be present in such
a way that we're no longer limited by our fear um there's nothing that limits us
from acting wisely well compassionately
in this world and uh and Buddhist practice is about
going forth is about connecting is about living for the welfare and happiness of
everyone I quoted it earlier in the week but one of the very important quotes for
me in the Buddhist discourses it the one that says that a wise person does not
intend harm to self to other to self and
and others and to the whole world rather a wise person intends welfare for self
intends welfare for others intends welfare for self and others intends
welfare for the whole world and it's not just intending but it's also showing up
and um so uh I would like to give a couple of quotes and then make a what
for me is a very important uh
statement so this idea of showing up courageously uh the Buddha uses
metaphors that it's not so popular to use in the modern Western Buddhist
circles um there's a very strong ethos against anything that is
excessively um assertive or masculine or Macho or Warrior
like um and so there's been a strong movement of backing down from these
kinds of metaphors at the Buddha uses a lot Warrior kind of metaphors and um I've been avoiding them
mostly because if I use them people would be critical and uh surprised when uh women
teachers are allowed to use it and in hearing it was really inspiring to come from women but here is one that
uh um um compared to a person who conquers a
thousand times a thousand people is the person who conquers
oneself the person who conquers oneself is supreme in
battle so the greatest battle we fight is the one with ourselves we fight all
the ways that we limit ourselves hold oursel in check get attached live in fear
that is the battle that's where we show up and that's what we have courage to do
in this practice and certainly relaxing takes courage to really relax
deeply uh to settle back and allow our experience to go through us it takes
courage but these two uh elements letting go and courageous acern they go
hand in hand one done sometime some situations one predom dominates other
the others but it's not all about letting go it's also about action and courageous action and this battle with
oneself um that doesn't mean that we're hostile towards ourselves or aggressive
to ourselves or hating ourselves it means that we actually love ourselves because we want to stop the ways in
which we limit ourselves and then the person who day
and night Delights in harmony lessness and has loving kindness towards all
beings is the one who has no hate for anyone so here we get again the Buddha's
idea of harmlessness but here Delights in living a harmless life comes with loving kindness free of
hatred towards hostility towards anyone these are some of the key and most important teachings the Buddha
gives and uh over and over again we see this emphasis on living a harmless life
but living with meta with loving kindness with no hate for anyone but
this does not mean that we're passive and
um there's uh that Buddha's example of his life is not one of a passive passive
person he was engaged with people and the situations of his time but here's a
small um quote that I kind of like that
um it is possible Ananda the Buddha speaking to his main
attendant it is possible that you can look on with
indifference at an elder monastic a senior monastic
being being offended truly
Ananda care does not grow from being still
unreactive when a senior monastic is being offended so if there's if someone's
being offended uh stand up get involved don't just do nothing is
the teaching here and um and the Buddha even said to his monastics even if your teacher does
something which is an ethical uh speak up talk to the person
speak up don't let them get away with it and
um and then um so the reason I want to emphasize today
action and end this week with us stepping up and doing
something is that the more we're troubled more we're
distressed but by events in the world the more important it is for us to
act to do something to live differently and to Simply sit back and
be angry and upset and Afraid and expect someone else to do everything to have
opinions about what should have happened and who's wrong is not helpful for this
world the world needs people who step up who courageously act in the world
and there's many ways of doing this and uh and and uh each person has
to find what's appropriate for them their life their situation and what the doors that are opening for them for what
they can do if uh you know I if I think if if the San Andrea's fault U uh
ruptures here in the peninsula where I live and there's a massive earthquake like there was in San Francisco in 1906
you know their fault is only a mile or two away um I bet we would see
heroic efforts by the survivors uh tireless efforts to really
help and step forward and help and do something uh that people are not going to say well I'm going to go meditate now
we step up and do otherwise we're actually harming ourselves so in my
situation uh the um when 9/11 happened
I had this strong understanding that I had to do something different the first
thing I did different was that small thing was that two weeks later I was supposed to give a dayong workshop on
the Buddhist teachings of unmindfulness and I decided I can't do that uh not right after 911 so I changed
the workshop to be a workshop on the Buddhist teachings on peace and uh but that was a small thing
it wasn't enough and the last thing I was I wanted to do was to go back to business as usual and that happens over
and over again in ways we so many times in our life we read something horrible thing in the in the news uh and then
we're changed for a while but then things go back to usual the the murdering of George Floyd
was horrendous and had a big impact on so many people and highlighted the racism in the United States in a way
that had really been highlighted before I believe and many people were alarmed
and there was movements to change but now some years later how much has changed how many people have stopped
their focus on this issue and concern and so many things kind of
passed much more quickly but with 911 I said I have we I have to be changed by
this if I'm not changed by this I haven't really taken it in and so uh and
also one of the institutions I'm involved with the Sati Center which was a is a Buddhist study center so we have
to I said we have to do more than just study the sutas study of the Buddhist teachings we have to do something for
our society so uh from that we decided to do the Buddhist chaplaincy program and now
for 20 over 20 years now we've been teaching a yearlong introduction to Buddhist chaplaincy that's trained now
many many people in the skills and the orientation to Buddhist chaping has opened doors for people into this very
significant way of offering spiritual care people have become um hospital
chaplains prison chaplains um people have been involved in uh politics and in in in chaplaincy
kind of ways and all kinds of places people have stepped up and offered care
and um and that his chaplaincy program has started because of 911 has now
spawned two other similar programs uh in chaplaincy and um so you know a big part
of my life the last 20 years has been oriented around what impact how it was
changed by 9/11 with the with the situation now for a couple of years in Ukraine which is
huge the amount of violence we're seeing and what's happening now in
Gaza uh and Israel it's huge and you know it's impacted many of us for many
decades the endless cycles of violence there but there's something different qualitatively different now more
powerful what's happening now they have so many children being killed teens
being shot down um innocent people being
you know murdered and uh and people kind of living uh a life that's worse than I I
go often to St Quinton is the state prison here in California and the pictures and the reports I get of people
how they live in Gaza sounds like it's worse than what it's like in prison here in United
States and now it's a lot of opinions a lot of ideas about all kinds of things
but free of opinions are we willing to be changed by
by this and so what I would like to suggest is the more deeply we are
impacted that we do ourselves harm if we don't allow ourselves to change and do
something different and it might not be that we do something for the people in
Gaza and Israel how much can we do there from our distance but maybe we do we we now
motivated to do something else better uh many times when I read in the newspaper horrific things that impact me
it motivates me to be a better Buddhist teacher to give myself more to this teaching and this work because I believe
this work is peacemaking this this work is helping so many people become free of
suffering but sometimes that's doesn't feel like enough so now with for me I've been impacted a lot by these last couple
of weeks uh with Israel and Gaza and uh the question is at my age at my point in
my life what do I do what how do I do things that are different and um so I
don't know yet what's possible what I can do and what doors will open up that are appropriate to step through true but
um you know like I created the chaplaincy program many years ago I've
wondered about training in Sati Center this study group Center we have um may
be creating a program or facilitating a program in um nonviolence not training
in non-violence and the strategies of it and the wisdom of it the uh the
philosophy of it the the um and the inner work that that has to happen in
order to be able to be a nonviolent warrior in a sense for
peace or I may also have been interested in for many years of Buddhist peace studies a little bit
more kind uh social justice and politics and having to do with
peace but you know it's uh I've devoted my life to other things these years and as a Buddhist teacher and my my time is
limited and what can I create at this point in my life so I'm wondering so I'm
I'm I'm reflect I'm not just giving this an example I'm reflecting on this thinking about how do how do I be different because of this it's not
enough just to sit in back and have opinions so um so I offer that to you as something
for you to think about that the more deeply you've been impacted
by tragedies of this world that we live in and your own personal ones or the ones
around you or near you or the ones in other places in the world that um maybe
you'll do yourself a disservice if you just kind of Hope just to relax chill
out get it back get back to life as usual that uh maybe you do yourself a
tremendous service of evoking a degree of courage and strength that yes uh you
will step forward and be different and act differently and contribute to this world in a different way and to do it in
your way in the way that's appropriate for you so it's not a source of stress
it's not a source of exhaustion it's a source of inspiration and enlightening
and meaningful for you the Buddhist dedication to non-harming includes not Haring oneself
benefiting oneself and so this courageous way of in the world for the
welfare of everyone includes for yourself and so that it's not stressful
it's not causing more harm to yourself it's not putting yourself in Greater danger to feel even more distressed it's
the opposite that you step forward into the world to meet the suffering of the world in such a way that you are a
better person because of it nourish by it freed by it even this is
possible courageous action in the world can be
transformative so thank you very much and um I hope this week has given you
things to think about and consider in in a serious way and uh certainly this
teaching for all its way of it shortcomings in terms of really actively
addressing kind of things more specifically for me is very important teachings and I share with you something
that's been at the center of my life for many years and I'm glad to be able to speak speak about it so thank you very
much