sitting down here for the first time in three weeks I'm uh feel
very delighted
happy and I wish you a warm greeting here from the Insight
Meditation Center and warm greeting from
the from the momentum of the 3-we retreat that I was just teaching at our
Insight retreat center and uh it's nice that they ended
on Saturday it's nice now to come Monday morning and and sit here when just first
arrived here it was still dark and just like uh going for the morning meditation at the retreat center
it was still dark so um thank you for being
here one of the challenges around meditation is to avoid over prioritizing
thinking certainly to avoid being stuck in thinking and it might be useful to
consider that uh the role of thinking ordinary
thinking discursive thinking the useful role that it has is it's a
bridge between an inner Source
within and our action how we live and if we understand that to be a
bridge then we see that action is more important than thinking we learn more about ourselves
in our actions than we do in our thoughts even though many people are trying to understand themselves trying
to understand something through thinking we understand more of ourselves
through action than thinking if our thinking is a bridge to understand to be in touch with
this some a source within exactly what the sources is is
maybe each person needs to discover for themselves but it's The Source from
where generosity flows where love flows
kindness benevolence where respect for others and
for oneself the source for an inner peace and
well-being the source for an inner intuition
for for wisdom for acting on love acting on kindness acting
on generosity these wonderful positive
motivations and impulses have a source within us they
don't just kind of appear out of thin blue Air and it's possible to be disconnected
from them partly by being overly preoccupied with thinking
and partly because uh more surface reactivities dominate for us our our
aversions our desires our [Music]
greedspeed itation is a place where we more discover this Source
Within than action but in discovering that Source
within for these this whole nurturing
tender kind strength that we capable of having
inside uh we discover it there so that uh when we act we can act from that
place mediated by our thinking so to assume a meditation
posture and perhaps you find a
posture that provides you with some sense or some approximation or some
intimation of an inner strength that is also intimately
connected to a kind a tenderness or a Simplicity
of being that
gentleness tenderness and gentleness are trying to point to a way
of being where we're not asserting
ourselves demanding things of the world and of ourselves not fending things off
involved in conflicts and fights it's simp Simplicity of being at
least in our inner
life finding a place within that will provide
wisdom for how we act in the world
later and then gently closing the eyes
and taking a few moments to
feel in your body whatever place you
think might be the source for your goodness
for benevolence for
kindness and from that place as if the breathing begins there
taking a few long slow deep
breaths maybe an expansion of the body as you breathe
in that spreads out words from that
source and returns to it on the
exhale
letting your breathing return to
normal and as you exhale continue to relax parts of your body your face your
shoulders your belly but doing so is a settling
in through some sort Source
within that you might Inuit it or or use your best
guess where such a source might
be
feeling whatever tension or pressure or weariness there might be in the thinking
mind and gently Relax The Thinking mind as you
exhale
for
and then if it is comfortable for
you to settle into your body
breathing where the beginning of your breathing of the inhale
is connected to some place inside deep inside in your torso
perhaps where there's a feeling of inner intimacy
or Stillness or
calm
as you exhale letting go of thoughts and letting go into that
Stillness that intimate quiet maybe tender
place
for
e
e if thinking is the bridge between some
inner source of benevolence
goodness and our actions and the action of
meditation involves having thinking gently
quietly point us back to
Inner source of tenderness goodness a place of safety
and good
will gently simple
thoughts bring you back to that
inner that inner source that inner
quiet
for
e
and as we come to the end of this sitting to see now feel
now for any place within that feels tender or
gentle a place where self preoccupation self
assertion anxiety around self is lessened is
quiet maybe a place of softness or
warmth a place that from where love kindness can
arise a place where that can receive love or
kindness can recognize
it and consider if you're in touch with such a
place within that this is something that is worth protecting
safeguarding because it safeguards us it protects
us to stay close to
this and may we at the end of this sitting wish this for
others that they feel an inner safety and
well-being that connects them to the source of
benevolence in their own hearts and their own
body may all
beings receive and offer the
full pallet of benevolence that humans are capable
of may all beings have the safety that allows for them to
be generous and kind and
friendly may all beings have the trust that allows them
to rest in inner safety and
well-being may all beings have the
freedom to be able to act from the benevolent Source
within may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may we find ways to support this in the
world
[Music] thank
you
so hello and welcome to this Monday where we begin a
new theme for 7 a.m. teachings our 7 a.m.
Explorations and um I'll be here for the next two weeks and then I go back on to teach
another weeklong Retreat so in these two weeks it's 10 of
these weekday morning City things and uh so I'm inspired to teach
uh to use the basis for these 10 days uh what's called the 10 protectors the 10
supports and uh this uh word uh Nati can
mean someone who really is a protector someone who safeguards others and um also someone who helps
someone who supports and the idea is that um there
are these 10 protectors that we have and how we live
how we act in the world how we um the attitudes we have the
motivations we have and that uh these 10 protectors that we have are something we
can call upon something we can um have as a protection and this assumes that
there is something worth protecting um and it's not you know
ourselves in the kind of General way we might be concerned about ourselves uh because we have all kinds
of complicated relationships with ourselves all kinds of complicated uh maybe some not so helpful attitudes
About Me Myself and mine and even selfishness that comes along and um and
we're not trying to protect our selfishness but to protect uh a deep Source within
and I use the word Source um maybe it should be the idea the word should be
that concept should be held a little bit lightly but um uh we have anxiety for
example that's the source for um fretting and worrying about our life and
the future uh and that that anxiety could be felt physically somewhere in our body that's activated in tense
maybe uh we could have uh a feeling of a different kind of tension inside
different kind of maybe um um hurt or
anger that can be the source for ill will and even hostility and we have a sources within
or a place or a location or something that some conditions that need to kind
of be in place for us to come with into the world with generosity with benevolence with
kindness with friendliness uh with um a sense of care
and for the for the world and ourselves and that that that Source if
we may on inside tends to be overridden or covered over or uh obscured by
overlay active mind that's driven by anxiety or hostility or conceit or
desires of what we want lust and greed and when those kinds of uh things
settle quiet um then these deeper U motivations
deeper way way of being can show themselves and uh it can appear through
as we get calmer more subtle and it can be quite wonderful to feel a kind of deep sense of inner Intimacy in the here
and now in the present moment with our lived experience that's below the
discursive level of thought where we might often be caught up in and discursive thinking that's driven by um
these more unhealthy or obscuring uh attitudes
motivations so we C and settle and come into the present moment through our body
and some point there might be a feeling of I'm home there's an intimacy there's a a place of where there's more wisdom
more sensitivity and um and so that sense or feeling for that inside which it's not
meant to be a spec I call it a source it's not meant to be uh you know
identifiable as okay right there is where it is um but sometimes there more
effusive place within U maybe somewhere in the Torso in the belly some people
might associate with the heart some people with the belly uh some people in some other kind of effusive way that
spreads through the body a kind of sense of goodness or Wellness that is
there and um and this uh uh and so this
is worth protecting this needs a protector for us because the way life is the way that um uh we are sometimes
caught up in the world um not only can obscure it but can also kind of limit it
or or or even damage it in some ways and so to know how to to call upon those
things that will protect it and um and the first thing that uh in
this list of 10 is um virtuous conduct the actions that we do in the
world that we do actions which are ethical or are wholesome uh that have that uh uh that
are beneficial in the world that do not cause harm so um
nonharming actions in the world and these uh virtuous actions and it's
thinking about this it's useful I think to consider that um sometimes we learn more
about ourselves through our actions than through our thinking I think some people in the modern world have become
excessively preoccupied with their thoughts trying to think their way out
of everything or to to figure out everything or understand everything as if thinking is a vehicle for making
sense of the world making sense of oneself protecting oneself planning better for the future remembering all
about the past to make it better or something and certainly thoughts have a very important role in our lives but uh
uh it's not necessarily where we come to the best understanding of ourselves that um many ways we
understand ourselves better through actions but what we do in our lives and how what we say in our lives and if we and if we
see and hear and understand that the actions then become a window into
understanding something deeper about ourselves and the role the thinking has
is to be a bridge between our actions our speech and some uh the source within
and if the source within is anxiety and anger and hostility greed and lust then
the actions have a particular shape and form but if um The Source
uh of is this place of benevolence non- assertiveness non-c conceit nonhostility
non greed non lust uh uh very then
thinking is the medium is the me is a bridge for that that place to come into
the world and uh in our actions and it goes in both directions so our actions
protect this inner place of goodness and it's really worth
protecting and so the more people meditate for example there are other ways of tapping into this the more we
understand this is Health this is a kind of Inner Health inner uh um Beauty
inner um uh um Freedom that's worth
protecting it's a place that um where that
recognizes the value of being truthful recognizes it truth in
ourselves recognize it in others it's a place that um that uh resonates with
kindness It's a place that uh uh acknowledges or conf affirms the value
of friendliness or generosity and um it can see it in the
others see it in the world and and uh and respond to it it can offer it to the
world and so one of the ways to protect this place is to live a life of virtuous
conduct to live a life that uh abstains from doing the things that we know are
going to harm harm other people or we maybe uh maybe suspect
might harm other people and the tradition certainly lists five things
that uh are harmful it's harmful to be
killing or uh physically harming others with violence
with it's harmful to others uh to steal to steal from them to take what is not
given it harmful to others to to be involved in sexual misconduct sexuality
which take advantage of people we're we assert ourselves over people there's an
aggression in the in the sexuality there is a deceit in it there's lying there is
um uh a lack of respect for for the other person that lack of respect for
other partners that we have and and um and then uh there's uh
we harm by lying and we harm uh not directly but
indirectly ourselves and others with uh the consumption of alcohol and
recreational drugs and a lot of harm gets done in our society for this and
there might be other ways in which we harm but uh at least for these five areas to really uh a if you want to
protect our inner goodness want to help Discover it and let it kind of flourish
then um these things are are really important so in the list of these 10
protect protectors our actions can protect they there's a and there's a
bridge there's a channel between uh these actions to living a life of uh
ethical integrity and this inner inner life and that bridge that channel is our
thinking if we know that we're living ethically know that we're not causing other people harm intentionally and
overt ways uh that's to be celebrated that's to be appreciated and so to have
thoughts that uh uh that have inner confidence that we're not causing harm
thoughts that uh recognize it appreciate that um uh and letting those thoughts
kind of point us back to that place The Source within that resonates that
recognizes the inner wholesomeness of uh of of living
without motivations to harm anyone at at all without any hostility or any greed
that that can cause harm and there is this kind of sensibility sensitivity
that exists within us that uh that um that
that that's what feels the best the intuition of our goodness intuition of
our ethical Integrity intuition of a deeper Wellspring of um benevolence that we can
live our life by so the first protector we have is our
actions and specifically uh being careful to live a wholesome life a wholesome uh based on the five precepts
not to kill or physically harm people not to steal not to engage in sexual
misconduct not to lie and not to abuse intoxicants so
um I hope that uh on this day as we go through these 10
protectors that we can have that um you the the kind of the most obvious because
they can be seen um and maybe you could take a look at your actions and your speech and
consider um where your actions where your speech comes from and is there a
way of speaking a way of acting that you feel Safeguard something precious uh
within so thank you very much and uh I look forward to
it tomorrow