so hello again hello and welcome to happy hour everyone so in the
us tonight is the eve before Thanksgiving this um the holiday of
giving thanks and uh I know that our Canadian friends have had their uh
Thanksgiving about a month ago already but you know it's always good to give thanks um so so in honor of of coming
together and giving thanks we'll we'll practice uh um gratitude the Gratitude
practice which is a beautiful practice an uplifting practice it's it's one of
the beautiful heart practices so let us engage together in this way and just one
thing that I say uh before we get started is um gratitude
practice uh it's best done not as a an
obligation that you should be grateful you know because you have this or that or
because you're not suffering grossly or there people are suffering more in the world so this this this shoting of
gratitude doesn't work it's it feels contractive um it works most beautifully
it opens the heart best when um it's just genuine that that that the heart
really has a deep appreciation for for something for anything and I usually
like to start the practice not thinking about what you have in your life that
you want to be grateful for that's that's a great practice too but what I like to do actually usually starting
this practice from right here and now so the way I like to lead it tonight is for
us to just come to our bodies and breath and just settle just settle in the silence um without any thoughts of what
to be grateful for and just be just settle just settle in the silence and
then from this place of stability see what bubbles up see what bubbles up in
this moment maybe appreciating the silence oh appreciation gratitude for
that maybe appreciating the softness of the cushion we're sitting on just so let it be more um arising from the moments
experience right here right now instead of a thinking practice and again there value to that thinking practice to and
will lead the two towards the end but it's nice to start really grounded in the here and now so so that's the method
to Madness today or gratitude Madness so let's begin let's begin practicing
together so so I like to invite you to arrive and
settle in your body
feeling your feet on the
earth body on the
cushion feel your breath moving through your belly your whole
body
just coming to the breath the sensations of the body the Simplicity of this
moment calming and settling and soothing for a few
minutes on our own
and the thoughts are rising about the past and future like helium balloons letting them
go releasing them and coming back to the Body Sensations of the body the breath
just this breath just this one it's never been
will never be connecting with this
breath hence yourself right
here
there be an appreciation for the silence in this moment right
appreciating gift of being able to sit in silence
together
we be appreciative of this breath this INB breath this out
breath however it
is
and we appreciate be appreciative of this mind
that cognizes that perceives that
knows right now whatever is
happening this faculty of knowing mysterious this faculty of
Consciousness alive within each of us
and wee appreciative of this sense of awareness whatever it's aware of if if
it's aware of thoughts that are going past and
present can we be grateful for this
mind that things that problem solv problem
solves can we be grateful for our heart our capacity to
care our capacity to be impacted feel care love and to even feel
pain to to
resonate to be
sensitive not a rock but a sensitive sensitiveness that we
have to love to be love to appreciate it to be touched
moved and to also even
hurt heartful emotional capacity we have
can we be grateful for all of
it
and then letting go of all that coming back to silence and sensations of the
body the breath the Simplicity of
it grateful for
Simplicity
grateful for resting in Simplicity In This
Moment
maybe as we feel our body sitting on the chair or a
cushion and there be gratitude for this chair cushion everything that has come
to make it be here right now all the workers fabric filling worksman ship
planning roads
Transportation all the infrastructure that has made this chair
possible
maybe if we're [Music] feeling the clothes in our skin having
gratitude for being covered with perhaps warm or cool
clothing wherever you are can every everything that has come
together make this possible
here the food that we have eaten that's giving us energy right now
to be present and to
function
I believe it's Carl Sean who said that if you want to make an apple pie
first you need to create the whole universe all the causes and conditions
atoms all the Stardust and million years of billions of years of evolution to
make all of this
possible it's just the amazing magnificence of being a part of this
gratitude for being a part of this conscious it's a part of this mystery of
existing
usually get stuck in the minutia of Our Lives Opening Our perspective to the
Wonder and gratitude of it
all
and as we bring this meditation to a close appreciating this being who's me
who's brought me to this moment to practice practice to cultivate my
heart in community appreciating the
community appreciating it all even even the challenges even the challenges it's
like this and it won't always
be may all beings everywhere
be happy and free including
[Music]
ourselves thanks everyone thank you for your your
practice so like to invite us to do a very uplifting practice just makes the
heart happy and this practice is in small groups where we each person will
share one nugget and the question is what what are you grateful for what are
you grateful for and it's it's really a beautiful way to share and bring joy mudita vicarious joy joy for the joy of
others we've done this a few times before and every time we do it I see you
come back from the groups with a bigger smile and you went in so just happy
happiness arises naturally we don't have to push it just what are you grateful for so one person will offer one thing
they're grateful for I'm grateful for um being practicing with you for the for
happy hour and maybe the next person will say something the next person will just go around and round and round and
holding each other with care with appreciation with gratitude yeah it's
it's precious to be able to have this uh opportunity this community to uh yeah to
to be able to share in this way so let's do reverse alphabetical order for the um
speaking and you can always say pass not a problem and uh let's see what else
[Music] um um yeah take care of yourselves take
care of each other no questioning no directing advising yeah let it be simple
all right I'm going to create the rooms have fun take
care okay welcome back everyone um we have a few minutes for
Reflections any Reflections you like to share especially if you haven't shared in the large group for a while you can
also put your Reflections in chat uh if you type them to me individually I won't
privately I won't read your name otherwise I read your name so any Reflections you like to share any
questions anything from this practice T and you are smiling one of you says I feel much
better from sharing gratitude a Amy says my group was magic meta
that's sweet that's very sweet I did definitely see the smiles
when you came
back I see your hand [Music]
knil two thoughts first we should do this every night this was
great okay so second you know I've been
thinking the universe is something like 14 billion years old my life is a blank
in the lifespan of the Universe I can't make my life fun every
second or pleasurable or whatever but whatever it is it's better than the rest
of those 14 billion years for my
viewpoint so now it's not hard it's not so easy to remember that all the time
but but I'm
trying wooo keep on keep on love it love
it love it Neil exactly that's absolutely right I love it yeah it's
even the the the pain the whatever you know the complexities or that we make
our small self and it's even that is amazing right it's compared to the rest
of it as you were saying exactly yeah thanks Neil thanks for sharing that was
lovely to hear your Reflections [Music]
Amy yeah this was great thank you so much um I'm really grateful for like the
awareness of like we talked about this the transient nature of things and um
how much my practice has helped with move through the moments meet the moments and move through them I the last
two weeks have been like some of the hardest moments in my life where my mom's been in the hospital straight from
Retreat I didn't get to end Retreat without and then her it was Tia that
made her dementia worse and so now it's like I only have her for seconds and
it's it's heartbreaking but I also remember what we talked about the Beautiful Moments of it and I had a beautiful conversation of love with her
and and I even if I'm like at my lowest I wake up the next morning sometimes
grounded with Gill or looking forward to this and and I'm like like I'm in love
I'm in The Meta I I trust in the unfolding and I'll me it and I'm just
like it feels like a superpower that I can move through moments and be okay and
see love in darkness you know ah thank you Amy I couldn't have
said it any better thank you to see love and light in the
darkness yeah gratitude for it all thank you that's such a beautiful beautiful
note to end on thank you Amy thank you so much for offering
this my heart is warmed by all of you thank you so much
for your beauty your goodness your practice being exactly as you are with
all the complexities of Being Human as we love and we ache and hurt and Bumble
our way along and grow and grow in goodness and Divinity grows through us
growing so thank you all may all beings be well may all beings be free and may
all beings truly know their own magnificence including us
[Music]
thanks everyone be well Happy Thanksgiving to you and yours bye-bye