greetings friends greetings from Mountain View California and seated oloni land where I am in this moment in
time lovely to be with you lovely to feel your presence
and um happy Friday if if it is Friday in your
time zone still happy This Moment In Time
so so we've been exploring we've been exploring the theme of Dharma of improv
The Improv of Dharma for the past week and
um and today and and as I was planning on
uh for today there are a few more themes dharmic improv themes uh
so I I had a hard time I have to admit choosing one to conclude our our week so
so here we go this is this is the winner but just so you know that there are of
course there's always more it's always good to know there is more to to
and more to grow and and learn so so this theme
is the theme of um we are a character in our story we
are a character in the story we're a protagonist in this story given all the
causes and conditions we have become this protagonist this character in the story and in uh this particular way
these thoughts emotions Etc and it's not as fixed as we take it to be it's really
not as fixed as we take it to be it it changes all the time have you noticed
impermanence I've heard that somewhere Anita um so this this not not taking ourselves
to be a fixed entity and and also it relates to this another
Mark of existence not just in permanence but also anata in personality that
there's so much flexibility you wake up feeling one way having particular thoughts body feeling a particular way
two hours later different thoughts with a relationship to someone else as if
it's a different person relationally so so there's it's we all co-create we are
being co-created by the environment and we keep co-creating ourselves in the
environment so so now to take ourselves at this fixed fixed person in a playful
way in a playful way not in a judgmental way but in a very playful way
acknowledging that yeah this person knows me there's a lot of range there's a lot of flexibility not feeling stuck
um as we sometimes do when our vision gets tight in our lives like this is the
only way I'm in pain this is difficult um there's so many possibilities even in
the midst of pain and challenges always so many possibilities so
so with that in mind I will invite us for some um
with some invitations during our meditation and um and then more on this when we
practice when uh when I offer uh reflection so
so with that let's let's arrive let's arrive in this
body and The Way We Know It In This Moment In
Time arriving with the body
greeting the body
greeting the moment
and if you might remember from yesterday let us feel embody let us feel
sense our feet on the Earth our legs
our sit bones connected to the cushion
the chair our abdomen
receiving the breath or chest neck and shoulders
face and head
feel this body sitting relaxing letting go of tightness
releasing feeling itself from the inside
receiving the breath this breath
in this moment in time keeps changing shifting in breath out breath
greeting it with light with lightness
of the lightness of changing nature of this moment
impermanence has a sense of lightness to it
can be delightful
this fleeting nature of phenomena
this breath
and now we're going to
try some dharmic experiments
if you wish
as you feel your limbs yourself
however you're showing up in this moment in time meditating
imagine always imagine
that do you have an invitation from from a meditation teacher
living or in the past to enter into their mind enter their heart their body
and rest meditate like them
so perhaps accepting this invitation
like your body and take the shape of the sitting like their
body sense of Integrity a brightness
how about your heart
let it feel into the
resolve intention
as well as the gentleness
the openness
and their mind perhaps you imagine it being undistracted
steady calm peaceful
delighted enjoying the practice
it's like a transmission inner transmission
you are practicing yes them In This Moment try it on for size
have fun with it have fun with this inspired invitation
in any way that it might support you
not too much thinking
being simply being
now letting go I think all of this available to you later
keeping any lessons that might have come up any insights
and I will shift it around and now imagine
[Music] the Buddha you might have chosen the Buddha in the past
invitation but now inviting the Buddha your inner Buddha
is a historic figure
who knocks on your door and says let me help you let me support you
and you feel your inner Buddha
yilda Buddha infused in your heart and your mind in your body
practicing as you heart of compassion
wisdom
such unfathomable beautiful qualities you don't have to think about them
your inner Buddha is shining
it's completely infusing your body and mind
when you're practicing now
as this inner Buddha no thinking just let it be
let the Buddha guide the way
you don't have to think and figure this out or doubt it Trust
that there is an inner Buddha in you
in your wisdom and compassion
Trust let them lead the way
let them practice
and at any moment you can begin again
you can begin begin again as the inner Buddha meditating becoming
the inner Buddha in this moment reconnect with it begin again no need for self-judgment
chastisement the connection gets lost not a problem
connect again
practicing as your inner Buddha coming
the inner Buddha in this moment
what would the inner would I do how would they feel
how how are they be be them
be them
as we turn to close this sit together
at the last minutes feeling into the qualities of the Buddha
in your heart body and mind peace
happiness
impediment Joy Joy wisdom love
service let them shine
in your inner but a shine within you infusing you
with a taste of whatever is needed
and trusting trusting that goodness is always available
be faint but be called upon
your inner Buddha inner source of wisdom love peace
it's always here sometimes subtle always here
waiting to be uncovered listen to connected to
trusting that we're planting seeds of reconnecting uncovering
becoming or inner put on more and more
and offering our goodness suffering our co-created Collective
goodness inner Buddhists to all beings everywhere
may all beings be well may all beings know their own inner
goodness wake up may all beings wake up
to their inner Buddha to their Buddha nature including ourselves may all beings be free
thank you thanks for your practice friends
so it's weird take a moment to transition the recordings if you like to put a word or
two in the um chat about what's arising for you in
this moment to bring it into the field you are welcome to
Hello friends and greetings greetings to you
so We are continuing the theme of improv of
the Dharma the Dharma of improv this week and in our practice I just asked you if you
would like to put some words as to what came up after the guided meditation and I'll bring some of them
into the space beautiful lightness inspired gratitude
and Grace deeply peaceful lightness compassion native wisdom
radiating radiant shining sense of humor love it
shake it till you make it that's great actually I would say fake it till you become it I think that's the way I like
to rephrase that thank you for that aliveness joyous gratitude infused with Buddha
nature beautiful always a beginner thank you so much so many beautiful
reflections blissful creative
yes yeah we can have a lot of creativity in our
in our practice there are so many doorways to the temple so many doorways
and sense of humor is one of them and sometimes we when we enter the
the path of practice we think okay it's got to be serious actually humor can be a great
support great support this lightness of heart
Awakening is just too serious is yeah too serious for for us to have no humor
about it ah beautiful thank you so much
so so as I mentioned briefly many themes but the one for today is
is this idea of of um again from the dharmic sense from the
dharmic perspective as I mentioned there is [Music] um a sense of likeness of impermanence the
shifting changing nature of ourselves our thoughts our bodies our
personalities our reaction reactions the co-creation in a particular environment
with particular people we show up differently and and that impermanence leads to one
perspective one way to experience anata in personality it's it's co-created there's this such lightness about it can
be co-created in a different way this this person we are the sense of self is
is created is Created from so many cause and conditions so many cause and
conditions which is actually one way to to understand emptiness everything is
codependently arising our personality how we are reacting
um if I say personality feels a little fixed but but um the way we are showing up in the
particular moment are reactions are such co-creations of the environment and
previous experience and and so many different factors and our thoughts are our perspective of
course our review this is fixed this is who I am this is the way I am this is how I relate
and and the Buddha has invited us to really see
these characteristics of existence these marks of existence that yes it is it is
co-created nothing is our personality our self is co-created is codependently
arising in each and every moment so why don't we support a a more kind a
more wise co-creation we can support it of course we can we're part of one of these causes and conditions
so so from the perspective improv actually the perspective of improv you
are taking on these characters when you're playing a scene when you're
playing uh with with other players you're taking on a character
um and the character keeps shifting and changing and moving and and you'd take a character in one one scene and one game
and another character another and this and what I've discovered and actually
many people have discovered this as you take on a different character different
aspects of your personality different aspects of your perception different aspects of your behavior
um all of these become Unleashed you're not as fixed as you realize there's so much more degrees of freedom
and in fact simply taking the physicality of another being another
person can shift your um State of Mind I hide a um I
practitioner Yogi some years ago on a retreat on a silent Retreat and
[Music] um and what they shared with me was uh so
interesting and insightful they said that at first for maybe for some time they had felt annoyed by people they had
felt annoyed by oh this person who's walking so slowly or that person who's
like this and that person just kind of their mind this judgmental mind was was
just uh frustrated with people and then what they decided they made a decision
okay what what if actually they had an observation what if what if um they
there's something about their physicality that's actually making them be in a world in a particular way so
what they did the decision they made was to take on the physicality of different people that at first they were annoyed
by so perhaps there was an older person this was a younger person um
um the um the uh
um you know the older person maybe the fact that they're actually you know they're
um they're they're maybe hunched over a little bit you know walking slowly and this younger person
tried that they tried walking more slowly with perhaps less certainty in
their steps or um and and what they shared was that
every diff every body posture that they took every character they entered there
are different ways that they saw the world they're different ways that they became and their heart opened to to
compassion for the the beings at whom they were annoyed at first because they
they entered their character their world through their their their body through
their the uh the physicality and in fact as an improv performer as an improv
player one of the exercises that you take on different physicalities to enter
um different characters through their physicality but of course you can enter them in so many different ways
um both to open our hearts to compassion to kindness to to Insight
as well as what we tried for example what we tried with the guided meditation
was was a different version of a practice that's called Buddha nusrati Buddha nusati is reflection on the
beautiful qualities of the Buddha reflection on the Buddha recollecting the Buddha nusrati recollecting
remembering Buddha remembering the Buddha so so there are ways that this practice can traditionally be practiced
when you think about you conjure up the beautiful qualities of the Buddha
ah wise gosh yes Wise Wise or or or
generous generous generous generous peaceful yes yes all-knowing knowing of
all worlds so sorry collecting your minds and then it and and then when you
practice it actually I've practiced the Recollections of the Buddha a lot and I love this practice so if you're feeling
upset or unhappy or or depressed oh my goodness do Recollections of the Buddha
it just Inspire it just infuses your heart with light and Bliss and your
inner Buddha uh becomes alive and that's what I was inviting you to to basically doing this practice of of Recollections
Recollections of the qualities of the Buddha in in this creative way in this
creative way of the Buddha entering and actually all infusing this quality oh yes
oh yes how would they be right now how they said how would they pay attention
oh yes the Buddha so um and as I and I was practicing along with you and there
was just such a sense of really uh shining shining this this this this
light this This brilliant light of of goodness of the Buddha that oh yes it's
here too it's here too trust that it's here too we all have it of course we have it of course
sometimes it might feel more more covered or or we have to listen more
closely to uncover it but it's always here it's always here
foreign so so there are a lot of different ideas
and concepts are brought in but but basically it the um
as the theme for today our personality the way we are the way
we take ourselves to be is so flexible it's co-created it's it is impersonal it
is co-created it's an aspect of emptiness um codependently erosion and we can play
around with skillful means skillful means of recollecting the qualities of
the Buddha beautiful qualities of the Buddha letting it nourish us Infuse us so
basically we're playing the Buddha character right in improv terms we would be we're playing the Buddha as as
someone said we're um faking it until we become it of course please let's all fake it until we
become it because it that's how it happens um what would they put that to you know
if you have decisions today the rest of them what would they put to do what would this person do what would you know
this favorite uh teacher I saw someone mention Brahm in in the chat who actually losing
there's a lot of humor in his teachings very very funny uh funny person funny
guy um so yeah what would I jump prop do in this case it's so so bringing this this
creativity that we have it's we have so many tools and skills on the path to Awakening so many tools and and another
one as I mentioned you can enter other people's worlds other physics reality see the world from their perspective
it's really empathy it's empathy and compassion so so this improv this
playfulness of taking on different characters maybe you decide after this this Sid you go around maybe your day or
part of your day as some character some you know as the Buddha is one of your favorite teachers
whoever you or or so be creative be creative today play
around with or maybe I'm going to go around as a happy person as the Happy Buddha I'm just going to go around and
make my breakfast or or make my lunch or interact with my friends or
that's the Happy Buddha or as the wise but as the compassionate but as the generous Buddha
so so thank you all thank you for your practice this whole week this has been
fun exploring this and um yeah it's it's
been a delight to share all of this with you thank you for your enthusiasm for your practice your heart your your
um yeah your Buddha natures coming to the fore playing in this way
so so be well see you on the path come to
happy hour if you want more um more of this well maybe I'll do
something similar to this tonight at happy hour but come to happy hour I'll see you on the path in different in
different ways yeah see you on the path take good care be well dear friends much
love all blessings it's been a delight take
good care bye