hello hi June welcome you can also say hello in here if you
have different uh mother tongues you're welcome to say hello in those languages if you like
where in New York hi Claire hello I'm Tanya normally from California
hi Claudia from a different time zone welcome
and bill says hello from Dallas Josefina from Oakland Barbara and Santa Cruz and
I just heard Hugh who's saying hello hi you hi hello from San Diego hello and
Natalie says hello on YouTube hi Natalie welcome our YouTube friends for joining
us at the same time sweet very sweet okay let's get started iPad from
Sausalito nice nice thank you for joining and thanks Neil for posting information
information about happy hour Google Groups at this point if you are um
unmuted I suggest that you mute yourselves and we're going to transition now
um to our meditation together and I change a few settings add in another
setting that I change is uh sending
chats now will only be sent to host but I ask you to keep that channel quiet
and and let's see what else
um yeah so I'm going to turn down recording for the sake of Audio Dharma
here we go there so hello and welcome everyone to
this rendition of happier happy happy Monday or whatever day it is in your
time zone okay and um
yeah um tempted not to share any Reflections as
I've been experimenting with in just getting into the meditation let's do that and maybe I'll say a few words to
to uh to support to guide but yeah I have a theme in mind tonight so let's uh
um I always have a name in mind but anyway Let's uh let's practice together let's let's uh meditate together so
ah arriving arriving in this body
ah arriving in this moment
arriving arriving together the sense of collecting Gathering
sometimes we feel perhaps that we've been scattered with
the demands or thoughts our priorities
our hearts scattered now we collect we collect we collect ourselves We
Gather ourselves as we gather together we also gather ourselves
which is another way to consider the practice of concentration or somebody
samadi or samata practice Gathering we collect ourselves We Gather ourselves
lovingly come sweetie come become whole become
aligned all the pieces of the puzzle
scattered bring him together ah
I'm bringing our attention
this breath to this body sense of Integrity wholeness
there might be demands on our attention and our emotions we say yes we know we
know and it's okay we're not going to abandon you we're
just going to nourish ourselves for a moment for a few moments with
Silence with the breath with presence so that we have more stability to
include it all so with that attitude of openness
spaciousness
coming to ourselves coming holy to ourselves
connecting with the breath sensations of the breath in the body not
the idea of it perceiving the breath in the abdomen
feeling the sensations quite amazing
feel like a lullaby these Sensations
and if thoughts arise not bad there's anything wrong with thinking but for now we say no thank you
please come back later hearing Primacy to what's important
right now what is important right now
In This Moment
rest your heart rest
no need to flutter here and there there
sweet butterfly of the Mind the heart rest rest dear rest
nope
just this breath
just this can we give Primacy
and we make this the most important priority right now just this
Justice really grocking
this is the most important Act
this dedication in this moment of her heart to this practice our attention
Gathering our attention is the most important thing can we really get it
can we really align with this of thinking about this or that or planning or
chest let go just this
just letting yourself be breathed
just be awake in this moment
it's passing moment
can we nourish our hearts ourselves can we be kind to ourselves
by just attending to one thing the Simplicity of being not doing
Thomas Merton celebrated Trappist Monk
share his words let them wash over you while you're in a meditative state
the rush and pressure of Modern Life are a form
perhaps the most common form
of of its innate violence
the pervasive form of contemporary violence
to allow oneself to be carried away by a multitude of conflicting concerns
to surrender too many demands
amid oneself to too many projects
we want to help everyone and everything is to succumb to violence
and we in this moment not succumb to this inner form of
what he calls violence pulled this way in that all the demands be just
getting a sense of what is the most important what is
and sitting sitting Landing
wholeheartedly in the most important thing
and a descend in Buddhism the most important thing is to know what is the most important
thing saying from Zen to rest
rest to rest and the most important thing right now not running this way or that
as a sense of Meta Care service to yourself and others
what is the most important thing in this moment just drop it into
your body to your heart not into your head
maybe nothing will come up it's okay sit and breathe with this question
let it gather you calm you settle you
can you imagine for a moment conjure up connect with what is the most
important priority in your life right now what value
what act what service and connect with that sit with that rest
with that so if you're sitting in a warm bath
at this aspiration support you and golf you no distraction
just one thing just one thing just this breathe with it
as an aspect of as an expression of meta to yourself
what do you need to release say no say no to so that you can
be aligned with what is the most important thing
in this moment in your life and not to think about it but drop it in
as a reflection
let yourself just breathe with this question but do I need to let go
say no to
don't think about it just be breathed
the answers will find you you don't have to go find them
and you need to let go of In This Moment it's thinking just let yourself be breathed
simple
and as we turn towards the end of this sitting let go of many self-judgment if it's
arising or has arisen not needed not needed
let go it's one thing you need to let go of right now any self-criticism you've done your best
you've showed up that's beautiful that is so beautiful
thank you me for showing up doing my best yes
ah recognizing your own goodness having done your best
without attachment to outcome and offering your goodness
of intention your wholeheartedness your desire for
cultivation [Music] for your own sake and others offer this
goodness to all beings everywhere sharing yes I share my goodness I share my life
I share my engagements
fruit of my engagement wholesome engagement offered to all beings everywhere may my
life be of benefit may my practice be of benefit may all beings everywhere including
myself be free
thanks everyone thanks for your practice thickness of your practice so
the aim I wanted to think in and I brought in for us to contemplate to consider is
is as I read the quote um by Thomas Merton which I'm sure Neil
will find later about the violence of our times and and send it to the mailing list later
um it's really about being distracted and pulled in this and that did and the
other and what do we need to let go out of care out of love out of mitta for
ourselves and others not to be pulled in so many ways and what do we need to let
go of in our lives and not and what about this moment and what is the most
important thing what is the most important can we just sit in that can we sit in our highest value our highest
intention and just let it sink and open our hearts we can just become beautiful
and and accomplished a Divine Compass yes this is what I intend to
to engage with I'm intended to be engaging with in this in this life so
that's the invitation that was the invitation as much as it showed up or didn't it's fine let go of any
self-judgment the audio is available for listening later as well
so now engaging in small groups can be quite inspiring what and the inquiries
what are you what I would do what should you let go of why should you let go of
what do you what what is appropriate for you to let go of uh in this moment what
is appropriate for you to let go of in your life and so what is appropriate and again your responses as you as you uh
come together and share and hold each other can be inspiring can be supportive
you're not the only one who needs to let go I need to let go of business I'm
saying yes to too many things um so all of us it's it's right it's a
good um reflection for all of us
and um so that's the invitation what is and and what what what is appropriate to let
go of right now and the question the answer might be I don't know I'm just sitting with that I don't know what's appropriate to let go of maybe I engage
too much with other I try to take care of others too much or whatever it might be just
exploring and then the the other inquiry question that you can reflect on
together might be what is the most important thing what is the most important thing do I know what that is
and maybe you do maybe you don't you don't have to share it if you don't want to just if you wanted to that could be
another exploration so two questions what to let go of and what is the most important thing again
you can choose to engage with one uh or both uh in in any way so
so I'm going to create the the groups as
always please take care of yourselves take care of each other and each person
can just share from their own experience um
and um and just sharing from your own Express not asking others questions not
directing the group to show up share something and we'll go uh the first in
the order of uh your birth date being close is to January 1st so that first
you'll have a little bit of conversation figure out the order first person will just say maybe
a minute of Reflections make space for other people don't go on and on please
just a minute of Reflections or just one nugget 30 seconds 30 seconds of
reflection and then the next person and then next person I will come back to you so go around and round so
so I'm going to create the groups please take care of yourselves take care of
each other again no directing and and um just and if you want to say pass if
you don't want to say anything that's perfectly fine you can say pass um so here we go enjoy enjoy connecting
with others here we go
okay the groups would close in about eight seconds and it does happen that we accidentally
get out when we don't want to [Laughter] I know that happens often it's okay
all right okay the rooms are closed everybody's back welcome back everyone
and um we have uh opportunity chance for uh
for Reflections questions and also I have the quote I put the quote actually
in I'll put it in I I read part of it I didn't read the whole thing but I'll put
it in um in chat you can read the whole thing later but right now please pay attention
to whoever is going to be sharing their reflection so especially if you haven't
spoken yet or for a while any Reflections from the meditation from the
small groups what to uh what to release what to cultivate really sit in
for the benefit of all beings any Reflections you can also put your Reflections in chat you can type them if
they're sent to me privately um let me change the settings oh wait here we go you can send them to everyone
in which case you will be public or you can just send them to me
privately and I will just read your reflection not not your name just one reflection
[Music] Inspirations from yourself or here fellow practitioners
one of you says we shared having anxiety about social interactions yeah
thanks for sharing that one says cultivating kindness letting go of worry and concern for the future
requires courage yes absolutely yeah
and bill says I thought this meditation was
very inspiring apparently Diana's waving her hand but I don't see you guys because I only see a small strip so it
will be Adelia and then Diane if you can find a way to raise your Zoom hand that way I can actually see you Adelia please
hello um as I practice more I am beginning to
question or maybe even some of them are slipping away some of the motivations
in my life and what I'm pursuing um and at the moment it's disorienting
you know I'm not quite sure it's very uncertain and I'm not quite sure how to structure my life or what to
pursue anymore but so that question of what to let go resonates and it feels like some of it
will just go naturally yeah yeah thanks for sharing that and
and speaking really from a an honest truthful place of this is what it feels
like when I'm letting go of what doesn't really resonate anymore there is um an unsettledness of what now what
what is um important what next what what and and
beautiful stay stay there because that place of unsettledness that place of the
don't know mind that place of okay I'm letting go of it doesn't quite serve me anymore but I'm not quite Landing
elsewhere yet it's perfectly fine it's the it's the Bardo it's like you know you've you've you know this image of
Runners when they've leapt right they've taken a leap they're not on land anymore
like they're in mid-air and mid-air actually if you open up like wait we
have where am I but but trust the momentum trust the momentum and and that
is a rich place to be one can see it as unsettling but one can
actually see it as a place of possibility you've left safe land that didn't serve you anymore
so yes you're opening up the possibility celebrating that thank you for sharing
that Delia beautiful okay it will take uh Anna
last reflection well I just want to thank you this may
be repetitive but I I love the Simplicity of this meditation and the uh
um the questions and especially not knowing I don't know and um
and it's okay to not know and and um not needing an answer the answers
will come this is something that's so pretty that I can really work with on a
daily basis so yeah um especially if you're feeling unsettled I
just recently like today something's left me and I've been thinking what's going on here where'd that go what what
happened to it so we can be right in the middle of all kinds of processes yeah out thank you beautiful thank you so
much Diana yeah thank you it's just working with all of that so I'll share a couple of things that have come to me in
chat to um one person has said reminding myself I'm only human and doing my best
self-compassion beautiful yay um one more person says my group reminded
me we must let go of the past and what's most important is to know
that everything is temporary this made me feel grateful to be sharing in conversation with my group since that
too is temporary and the last and uh let's see one more
I see all that when will the recording be available it
probably in uh I don't know in 15 20 minutes as soon as I can Audio Dharma
processes it uh let's see anything else I can quickly say before wrapping up
um yeah I think that's it and how to let go
of The Cloud of Unknowing well you don't want to let go of The Cloud of Unknowing you want to embrace
The Cloud of Unknowing that's where it's really yeah you want to be in the cloud about knowing that's actually where it's
juicy that's where the certainties were like oh you just we we we're the know it
all but The Cloud of Unknowing that don't know why and actually maybe I'll do a session on the donut mind
all right yes and the video is already available thank you Neil for pointing that out for
having my back all right thank you all thank you so much for your practice thank you so much for your cultivation
You Beautiful People let us all let go of what's not needed embrace
what is most important what is our heart is called to cultivating goodness and
Beauty for the benefit of ourselves and the world may all beings be well may all
beings be happy [Music]
thanks everyone take good care