hello everyone Welcome to our meditation together
and uh I very much appreciate that the
gatherness of this practice that we never really walk this path Dharma path
path alone even if we're meditating alone it's not really alone
we're accompanied by generations of
practitioners before us and many practitioners who are
practicing to this day and and then for all of us here
sharing this time together to meditate thank you
and as we begin I want to
and
as we begin I want to evoke a description of the school of Zen that
I practiced in the sotozen school many years ago
and the way that they describe themselves first they said they
were they were claimed to be more the Zen of farmers other forms of Zen were
more of the sin of the Samurais and I like this idea of farmers who are
tilling the soil and the kind of certain kind of humbleness of
being with a um the you know the soil and that life Outdoors
but also they describe that kind that form of Zen as being the description of
it was attention to detail and there's something powerful about
attending to the details of our life as if they matter
and so one of the things that matter it's a small detail
but is the posture you assume when you meditate
and some people air in the side of being as comfortable as they can
and that could be fine it can be appropriate but in doing that maybe you miss an
opportunity because one of the details of a healthy life a strong life A Life That's not
swept this way in that way by The Winds of Life by the tragedies of life
is a life that has some degree of confidence in it
confidence is the ballast confidence is the way in which something is rooted so it doesn't move so easily
and in terms of attention to detail even if you don't feel much confidence
to assume a posture that expresses confidence
let your put your body in a position that if someone saw you or if you
saw someone this way you oh that person's confident
and there's nothing insincere about placing the body in this posture
even if you feel a lack of confidence
but sometimes if you lead with the body the Mind follows
if you lead with a body there's a marvelous reference point
to understand ourselves better and maybe one of the reference points of
a confident posture is that it's easier to see the lack of
confidence that maybe we don't have to believe in him
maybe we can kind of sit strong firm
rooted here and not be pushed around so much by The
Winds of the Mind so assuming a meditation posture
that maybe if you're up for it you feel expressive some confidence
maybe a posture that allows the chest to be open a little bit
coming forward into the world not puffed up certainly
confidence is not arrogance
and maybe one where the back is a little bit straighter more self-supporting
a little bit more upright
and then take some time to feel a solid
contact with whatever is holding up your body if you're sitting in a chair it can
begin with the feet maybe both soles of the feet firmly
on the floor and some block you have to hold up the feet
if you're sitting cross-legged take some time to feel the triangle of
the knees and the butt and maybe even Rock back and forth and
feel the stability of the contact your weight resting
against the mat your cushion your floor
and there's an art to relaxing parts of the body
not so that you sink but so that your spine
is gently lifted up up straightened
sometimes relaxing in the waist
relaxing the small on the back
relaxing the top of the thighs
it's a way of doing that again allows that kind of lifting
up out of that it'd be spine to be a little straighter
and if your eyes are not closed to close them now so you can better feel
the solidity of your body the weight the substantiality of it
the three-dimensionality of your body sitting here
and is there some place in your body that you associate with confidence
or if not confident someplace where some kind of inner strength resides
however weak however small
and put your attention in that place breathe with it
and if it's there to feel the confidence the strength appreciate it
confidence and the physicality where the body knows it is here
the body knows feels its Vitality its livingness
the body has no doubts
of the time and place where it resides Here and Now
and then taking a few long slow deep breaths
and as you exhale relaxing the mind
as you exhale letting go of doubt
of any thought that diminishes your own value
as you exhale letting go into
foreign body
a body that supports breathing
makes room for breathing
a body that yields to the movements of breathing
no resistance just yielding
and as we continue meditating perhaps some of the body's confidence
can gently lovingly support you to be present here and now
with your breathing with your body
confidently letting go of any thoughts that you have
by having a posture which is confident
the confidence can be silent no thoughts no ideas that have to go
with it in fact it's a confidence that allows
the thinking mind to rest
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
in the subtle ways in subtle ways
can you sit up a little bit with more confidence
or revoke more confident way of being
here in this meditation
even if you just imagine yourself confident
a certain Inner Strength foreign
faith in one's own capacity to be present
to be able to face the challenges of life
kind of confident that is Pleasant
that you appreciate having it
then with this confidence gaze out upon the world
looking upon all things kindly
with kind eyes friendly eyes
where the confidence supports your ability to remain
with a kind regard for all things
that kind of confidence that supports
Good Will supports kindness
may all beings be happy
male beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and in directing this Good Will to all beings
we are directing it also to our fellow meditators
each of them is part of this category of all beings
so I end this meditation with a wish that each of you be well and
happy may all of you be happy
may all of you be safe may all of you be peaceful
and may all of you be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone and coming to the
fifth of these five talks for those of you who looked for them in
the recordings that there this week the talks are called hindrances and
assistances and the things that hinder us the things that assist us in this life
and I'm looking at these things that um categories of ways of being which can
either go in a hindering way or a assisting way a positive way so desires
can hinder and desires can help free us and move us
in good directions averting can take the form of hostility
and aversion but averting can also be turning away in a healthy way an appropriate way stepping away
that um being
freezing and sloth torpor and going numb
is a version of being still but the hindering one is also the the
Stillness which is clarifying creates Clarity and presence
there is uh being animated the energies of our life
that can lead to restlessness then preoccupation and thoughts and regrets
and there's also a way of being animated that comes from a deeper place that suffuses us with a sense of wonderful
vitality and today the hindrance
well maybe the kind of category is not knowing and not knowing can take the form of
confusion doubt indecisiveness and uncertainty
and people get caught up in these and make all kinds of bad decisions
because of their doubt or they make no decision at all because of the indecisiveness and they're kind of
caught but the positive side of this is
um is a certain confidence
decisiveness that doesn't have to know anything
it can be a I like to sometimes we don't know and they're not knowing leads to doubt
or the not knowing can be held in confidence one could know clearly I don't know
but we say that not collapsing and not getting agitated not feeling ashamed
but rather we take a posture of confidence if you're standing to stand with both feet firmly on the ground
Standing Tall and and just kind of as if it's
completely fine not to know and just announce even to the whole world I don't know
and uh almost as if uh people will be inspired that it's
possible to be alive and confident in breathing and not to know
so a person is has no doubts that
they're con that they don't know they know they don't know not confused about it
they're not uncertain about it and they're not there's no lack of confidence in not
knowing there's a confidence in not knowing def definitively I don't know
and there's some real value in that kind of clarity because then we don't give up our
confidence we can stay in our place of strength in a sense We Stand Tall
and then we can look around from that place and see much better
we can understand and start understanding what is happening in small degrees but if we succumb to doubt and confusion
and decisiveness and and um and kind of adapt so some kind of
doubt is cynicism and skepticism that keeps us swirling in thoughts keeps us
from showing up in a confident way
and I'd like to suggest that confidence doesn't require us to understand
or to make a decision we can stand and confident and relaxed
in whatever way we are in life there's no reason not to
and so there's a kind of healthy not knowing
the not knowing that maybe opens the possibilities where we're more available to the World to See Clearly
and there's a kind of not knowing that leads to doubt and uncertainty and confusion and kind of spiraling out and
feeling we have to know and certainly there are times we have to
make decisions in life and um so there's being caught in indecisiveness is not so healthy
but to confidently assert confidently recognize that
I I don't know what to do now I'm being indecisive I'm not making a decision
just that confidence in making that statement Standing Tall and confident
my to just might give you access to something some other way of knowing some other way
of of deciding than if we get caught in the Trap Of Us
of hindering doubt the doubt that we kind of just
agitatedly uncertain agitatively feeling lost and confused and and uncertain what
to do the body being confident the heart being confident even if the mind doesn't know
what to do can be a guide and a support for finding someplace inside that knows wisely what
to do so um
so look for opportunities when you don't know or you're not sure
and to study yourself and see and you're not sureness you're not knowing do you somehow are
get influenced that in a certain way by that that is depleting lowers your energy lowers your confidence it's a
little bit of a downer or can you step into not knowing
as if it's almost like a I don't know like a room that you're stepping into
and yes I'm in this room of not knowing but to stand they are confident
and this has a lot to do with where we identify ourselves
if we identify ourselves as the one who's confused who doesn't know who is uncertain
then we might not be able to find a way out to use a lame but if we don't know and if we're not
certain but we think of it just a room we're in or a situation we're in
and we identify if we're going to identify with anything and to identify the one that who can who can do this
postural confidence who can stand clearly definitively I am here
I am present no doubt about it and do that with strength and confidence
then the uh then then the not knowing that maybe even the confusion of what to
do is not going to debilitate us the same way as if we identify with it
if we see it as a personal uh kind of fault or failure that we're that way
so what are the great possibilities of meditation is that to sit with some modicum of
relaxed confidence in the midst of whatever storm is going on
and whatever confusion is going on so I offered this week
as the kind of the background for this week or assumption
is that when we feel challenges in our life
it's very easy to be swept up in the drama and their concerns and they're trying to figure out and
and the difficulty of it and sometimes whether it's conscious or
semi-conscious unconscious or semi-conscious or scheming conscious we can have strategies of trying to cope
with it which are not helpful and those are the five hindrances
and sometimes the five hindrances are used to try to escape so we don't have to face the challenge
even restlessness and agitation and doubt sometimes is a running away and
sometimes it's safer to be caught in those than to feel like you're addressing it directly what's going on
but to to but to take the time to pause to step back and ask the question
what is my strategy with this challenge how am I responding to it
what's my relationship to it what am I trying to do
in relationship to it what desires are part of it when motivations are
coming up simply to ask that question
begins to create some space begins to create some Independence creates it's got a little different ecology
than if we're caught up in the challenge and if we've learned something about
being confident in some simple way then that stepping away to ask this
question what is going on here for me what am I doing how am I responding
to ask that question from that place of confidence makes also it changes the ecology in
which we're working with it's not easy to remember to be confident because the habit of
succumbing the habit of criticism or feeling kind of somehow
identifying ourselves with all this is hard but to switch this
where we get caught by just simply asking questions pausing stepping back what's going on here
and then if they are the hindrances that are operating remember that they if you don't don't
necessarily throw away the baby with the bathwater maybe the hindrances
are connected have a relationship to the other side to a positive side
and see if you can swing the pendulum to the other side or evoke the other
so if there's a lot of sensual desire for Addictive Behavior for
for getting lost in comfort food or whatever can you swing over and and evoke your
capacity for aspiration your capacity for inspired desire for
the good if you're caught up in hostility and aversion
can you swing the other side and say you know this is a difficult situation is
there some way that I could step away now pause either from the situation or from my own
aversion maybe that's what I should step away from avert myself so I can see more
clearly so so and these positive aspiration
stepping away being still for the sake of clarity
finding a place to be animated that from within that has a pleasure to it that
feels Pleasant and not harmful and the way that agitation and
restlessness can be harmful and to find a conflict in a place of not
knowing if that's what's going on all these positive ways assist us they
work together they support us and to have these is almost as checklists
that we go through can support this ability to step away
from being mired in the challenge
to do this in the small challenges of life
so they become kind of easier and easier more familiar practices to do
then at some point you come to a big practice Big Challenge and you might have some healthy
beneficial capacity to go through this and in a more a clearer way
so now I have some announcements so the two of them one is that um
for the next few weeks we have guests coming for the Monday this YouTube
teachings in the morning here I'm going to be away I'm going to teach a retreat and have a vacation with my
wife and then um I come when I come back from that I go immediately to do another
retreat at our Retreat Center so I think it's about a month before I come back to be here
and with you all and I've invited the wonderful teachers to teach in my place
and um and some of them you know I think they've all they've all been here before
and um and I'm delighted that they can come and if and in this way Mutual wonderful way
of mutual support if you want to support them and their efforts they get up in
the morning while they're here that would be kind of inspiring for everyone
and um and so I'll continue when I come back with a series on challenges I hope you
find it useful and and um and uh
and then the last uh announcement is that uh the way that we post
uh you know broadcast these these on YouTube is that um
when I'm not here it's it's people usually do it from their homes and to do
that they have to uh we have to create a zoom a room and then through Zoom there's a way of of uh transferring this
the the broadcast over to YouTube so you can see it here but we don't not all the some teachers
know how to do it for themselves but some don't and so we have some dedicated volunteers
here who've been helping with this uh setting up the room with the zoom room for the teachers and supporting them too
so they can teach this way but we need more and so if any of you would be interested in volunteering
learning what it would take to um to do this task I mean it's a lot of these
technology tasks are difficult until you learn them and then they're easy so to get a hang of it and if you're
interested in helping with that to be from anywhere in the world you can email contact at Insight
meditationcenter.org or you used to go on the Gen on the website and find the general kind of information
email and that'll be forwarded to Kevin and Kevin will contact you and and
probably train you or something so thank you very much and um
I appreciate this time with you all this week and and that I do look forward to and
happily to the chance to come back here in a month and then we'll do our we'll
make some words at some point when I come back it's close to the time of um or finishing our third year of doing
this on YouTube and and for me that's quite a wonderful anniversary and
as we start our fourth year thank you