good morning everyone and welcome can you hear me okay here
and uh welcome to those of you online and uh it feels very
I don't know it feels very encouraging to know their people participating in
from all over and online and
so the Buddha
used a lot of ordinary Concepts ordinary activities as
metaphors for to for the spiritual practice and teachings that he had
and so for example the word that's often translated into English as craving
literally means thirst so thirst was the kind of the metaphor for human craving
the word for grasping is the word for fuel like the fuel of
Fire and somehow or clinging is the few and somehow like a flame somehow clings to
the wood that it's burning and so the fuel for so uh and so there happens to be
that both the clinging and the word fuel are synonymous and so it's a wonderful
idea that clinging is the fuel for more clinging
so another very common idea that the Buddha borrowed to make is a metaphor
for the psychological life event mental life is the idea of food
and that we have food that we can feed our mental life
but we have to be careful what food we feed it some food is detrimental
gives you indigestion and some food helps you to thrive
so to be able to know what kind of food that we're taking in psychologically mentally is actually quite helpful
so to that's what the topic is today is the Buddha's teachings on food
and um but this is a kind of metaphoric use of the word
and so to start I want to tell a somewhat famous
Japanese Buddhist story that uh
kind of apply in a particular way so there's a story of a
some kind of erudite academic scholar who comes
who's maybe a great scholar on the philosophy of Buddhism and he goes to see a Zen master to have
a Dharma discussion about things and so there's a message well come and have tea
and so they're sitting together and the Zen master ends this academic hands
the academic an empty cup of tea and then he grabs a teapot to pour the tea
into the cup and when the cup is full of tea
the the Zen master does not stop pouring the tea
and so it's a tea starts pouring out and the academic said stop stop the cup
is full can't take anymore in the Zen master then stops and he says well in the same way you're so full of
your knowledge that you're coming here you can't there's no room for more
so whether that's fair for the the academic or not I don't know
but uh certainly it's possible and I actually came to a not a zen
master but many years ago I came to my Burmese teacher upandita and I had all
these questions I wanted to get down to the bottom of something and I probably had a little bit of opinion so I was trying to move the move the conversation
in a particular way and at some point he stopped and looked at me and said Gil
are you here for your own opinions or to learn something
so um so um
so the food we eat can fill us but how it fills us is very
significant there are some mental food that we take in that fills us so there's
no more room for anything else and then there's other kinds of food that we take in psychological food
that actually has the opposite effect it actually creates more space for more
a feeling of abundance happens when we take in this food and then that abundance there's room for all kinds of
things so for example if a person is filled with desire
for a particular person maybe it's sexual desire of a particular person
and they say you know I really love that person you know but really the love is wanting the person more than I don't
know genuine kind of Goodwill or appreciation
and it's possible that that sexual desire is so strong that there's not there's no room for
anything else that's what the person's thinking about they're wanting and and if anybody stands in the way they're
hardly noticed and you know and someone asked them a question and they
hardly hear the question because they're consumed by this desire
on the other hand if a person is um has just a tremendous appreciation
for someone and and Goodwill that has space for the person to be who
they are then there's also space for other people the mind is not narrowed and caught up
in particular desire but rather is taking in a broad
appreciation that has an opening feeling it opens the heart expands the mind
and so but both of those are kinds of food the sexual desire thing
can feed more sexual desire one way that sometimes works is that
sometimes desire like that maybe comes from a feeling of discontent and maybe
loneliness and paradoxically being pouring yourself into sexual desire at the expense of
everything else is a kind of alienation from oneself and so it kind of adds to the alienation
adds to the dissatisfaction that kind of the desire is supposed to kind of this wage
so the same thing with alcohol there are all kinds of desires that people are addicted to that they kind of feel
something temporarily but they don't really you know they feel something that doesn't let other things in but it
leaves something empty there's other things that fills us
nicely and but rather than filling us so that we're
there's no space for anything else it actually makes us more expensive more more wonderfully available and empty
so in the teachings of the Buddha he gave he talked about these two forces
the food that leads to indigestion or food that leads to kind
of to our detriment and the food that leads to our betterment the food that can actually be
beneficial to have in this practice and these two different processes he
summarized in a teaching called the five hindrances
and the positive is the five the seven factors of Awakening and he would often hold the two together
you know teach the two together almost like one is the antidote for the other or the opposite the other
so he said that uh the food for sensual desire
is obsessing about what's attractive so somehow looking at what's attractive
all the time that's what we focus on and so some you know with our media that
we have if you're spending a lot of time looking at media looking at advertisements for I don't know what
you know you know beautiful cars
then I can imagine that then after a while that there's more and more desire for beautiful cars and they don't notice
anything else I was a little bit kind of surprised at myself kind of it was very I thought
indicative of how this food thing can happen unconsciously so when I first moved to the peninsula
here in over 33 years ago I had been given an old Toyota Celica
some of you know what that was it was happily read and um but it was you know it was 14
years old by the time I got it and so it was kind of old and and uh and I was very happy and content with it was given
to me and so I was driving around and I would drive around I used to teach in Palo
Alto this group and so I'd go there for dinner before I taught Monday nights and stuff
and that was happily going along with my old soap metal car and then but in Palo Alto back then even
then there weren't many old cars there were a lot of new cars
and after doing some years of driving around I think it took some years maybe the food came in kind of slow
but maybe after about five or six years of doing this
um I start maybe even more but I started noticing
so that by time my car my car was 20 years old and um I noticed that um
I started having new car thoughts you know it'd be nice to have a new car
and and before that I was always I would have gone any any car would do or you know I would have been happy to get a
used car why buy a new car and but I think I was slowly being influenced by what I saw every day
it was coming in oh this is what you do or to fit in and fit into the crowd or something you should have a new car
something like that and I was like I was like wow look at that Gail where did that come from
and that was happening unconsciously what if I got home and spend you know every waking hours you know searching
for magazine back then or you know the web and like to look at cars and look at that car and
and um you know it would probably would if it could affect someone especially that desire is kind of feeding and
feeding and feeding something so they would also said ill will
hostility is fed by looking at what you're
repulsed by if you're repulsed by something and really feel kind of like off by
something if you then go on the web to really you know search for all the
instances of things you're repulsed by you know what is that going to do to you that's going to feed something feed
something feed something and so I think that in some ways that happens with politics
people are repulsed by the opposition about how terrible they are how awful it is but there's a drive to keep renewing
that and studying it and seeing it and so the hostility then builds and builds and builds and some of that you know
it's a kind of unconsciously building it just becomes kind of like isn't this ordinary it's normal to be this way
sloth and torpor which is not a uh just being tired or fatigued is a kind of
deep weariness of the mind that psychological in its root resistance
kind of giving up the sloth and torpora has food
and sometimes it can be posture to give in to sloth and torper
posteriorly then maybe the you know and you stay home and you just kind of hang out and
just watch more and more TV and uh you know if something begins to sink
and and you know the Energy starts to drain and there's more of the sloth and torpor
uh restlessness agitation is the feeding for that is being
unsettled according to the Buddha the word is unsettled are agitated and um and how you know
I've seen this in myself is that if I'm Restless or agitated I'm activated in a
certain way and for me I get activated kind of upward Direction it kind of goes up into my upper torso into my head I'm
kind of like you know like activated and so I'm unsettled
and so if I keep focusing on that feeling of agitation the feeling of you know with restlessness it kind of feeds
itself like something's wrong and then oh yes something is definitely wrong because I feel it's wrong
and then it gets even more wrong there's something you know off so so if I focus on that feeling of
agitation it tends to feed more of its aim
doubt is the same way that that doubt and focusing on what we don't understand
focusing on how we don't understand uh can be a little bit of addiction for people because
there's a assumption that only by understanding can be we be safe or get ahead in life
and so we keep focused noticing how much we don't understand so we can't be safe and then doubt kind of spirals
on the other hand and this is where I think it gets the most interesting is we can be fed by healthy things
spiritually healthy dharmically healthy phenomenon and that's what the seven factors of
Awakening are and they don't close us down they don't fill us in a way so we have no space for
something else but rather they open us so there's much
more space and it's part of the Delight of these seven factors is it gives a kind of Independence to the inner life
where there's room and to not be caught there's a space to not be caught by things that are usually caught by
and so the Buddha said that the food for mindfulness
are the are the objects of mindfulness
and that could be any object of mindfulness but when we see something as an object to be mindful of then we're
establishing a different kind of relationship to it than if we're not mindful
so an example might be that I really want a new car like that's like that's
going to be the key to a happy successful life and that's what it takes
and so I'm really you know zeroed in on this new car thing
um so what's the proper object for mindfulness it's not
the cars rather it's the desire I have for the cars
and as soon as I bring clear mindfulness to the desire then now there's space
there's a kind of the mindfulness the clear mindfulness has a quality of of of spaciousness a little bit of healthy
distance and independence from what we're focusing on so to have a clear sense of how to and
what to have as the object of mindfulness and what mindfulness is that's different than being absorbed in
what I want it's oh it's the desire look at that desire and then specifically for the Buddha
there's four general areas where mindfulness can be focused on that's
really supportive this Independence is freedom is uh the body mindfulness of the body
that's the object so if I have desire for car and I'm really agitated around I have to
have it then how does that you know let's be mindful of how that feels in the body
so it's turning the attention away from the desire of the car 180 degrees to feel what it's like in a
physically to have that desire or to have that hate or to have that
restlessness whatever it might be and it's I feel it physically I feel the agitation I feel the contraction the
tension that I carry and to have that wonderful connection of knowing and seeing agitation tension in
the body but in a mindfulness which is a little bit independent as spacious allows it to
be there that gives room for the body to begin to relax because the mind is no longer caught up
in the desire it's now involved with the mindfulness of the desire that part of the physical
and that allows something to relax to feel the pleasant and unpleasantness
of the experience there's another object for mindfulness so I have this desire for the car
and someone says is that Pleasant oh yeah that's so pleasant those cars are so great
but if I do 180 degree turn to really feel the direct living experience here
the cars are still Pleasant but my desire is not the tension around wanting and searching
and deciding between the cars it's um there's a lot of unpleasantness here
then wow I had no idea how unpleasant this so anger hostility can have a certain
pleasure to it but if we really turn deeply and feel to what it's like we see
how harmful it is to the person who is hostile so you've oh wait a minute this is
terrible I'm doing this to myself and then there's the Mind state
to be aware of what is a state of mind that's operating and again this is to be aware of the I
like to call it the quality of your inner life rather than mind State what's the quality of your inner life
when you're Desiring a new car and caught up in it and you feel like the new the inner desire the quality in your
life is not so pristine it's not so beautiful it's not so spacious it's not
expensive it's not the feeling of abundance it's the opposite I feel like I lack
feel that you know that um you know tight constricted of wanting there's no
room for things in that space and then the fourth Foundation is to
start understanding some of the mental processes at work understanding the hindrances that are
there understanding the some factors of Awakening which is kind of makes this whole thing then repetitive and repeats
itself so the first of the seven factors of Awakening is mindfulness
and that's when the object of mindfulness support more mindfulness
because it's satisfying to have this kind of wonderful attention that's not locked in it's not
caught as that attention is there is what's called usually called
investigation and but what it literally means is distinct the process of the mind making
healthy distinctions and so if you um
if you're able to see all this carefully then you can make the distinction oh
this activity wanting to have a new card such an addicted way
that's very different than being mindful of the desire
seeing that distinction is really helpful because then there's a chance for you to
choose the one that feels better for you if you don't see that distinction don't you might as well continue thinking
about the car so being able to distinguish options in the present moment oh this opens me up
this closes me down this has an ouch in it this has an ah in it this feels good
be able to make these very simple distinctions and then to choose which distinction
encourages more of making these distinctions mindfulness perceives it more and more we become experts we
become skilled at seeing what is harmful and what is not what is wholesome and what is not and this in Buddhism is
considered to be an invaluable skill to develop to really tune into the moment
and have the agency to see and have the agency over what is a wholesome and
unwholesome what is gives indigestion and what kind of creates some help for you
and it isn't like a lot of analysis that's involved it's a product of having it just clear
mindfulness of the moment the mindfulness reveals kind of oh
that's tense this is not tense this feels
kind of supportive this doesn't feel supportive with that agency with that seeing then
there's the third found factor of Awakening which is engagement energy
this is where agency comes into a play and this is where we see I think I'm
going to choose the mindfulness over preoccupation with a car
there is a choice involved I'm going to engage over here
and having that choice um
supports more choices supporting a choice that brings energy
that brings engagement that brings a kind of this is this feels good
if we keep making choices to make us feel bad then we're going to kind of kind of
spiral down and become lethargic and become discouraged and all kinds of things
so there is something very important in psychologically for us that we feed ourselves with good choices
and that can be you know macro level but it's also this micro level of the Mind
and it can be as simple as choosing to be mindful feels much better to be mindful of this
than the alternative that it leads to the fourth factor of
Awakening which is joy and that as we learn to make choices to
go towards the wholesome Moment by moment this is good this feels good be mindful here be mindful here this feels
good it's kind of like this yes begins appearing yes yes it feels good yes here
here yes yes we see the difference between a Horseman
and wholesome that's oh yes that's so great to see this difference yes
choose the whole small yeah that feels nice and so the joys is kind of the quality of yes
and that and that yes that that recognizing what's joyful is a food for
more joy the next factor of Awakening is
tranquility with enough Joy something inside of us can begin to settle
and here the Buddha said the food for tranquility is more tranquility
and how I understand that I've come to appreciate this is that if you feel like Tranquility is useful
it's a nice thing notice the Tranquility that's always already here
can you find inside of yourself some reference point for tranquility
I could be inflamed if inflamed around what kind of
car to buy the new car that I'm supposed to get and then then a friend of mine says Gil
you don't have much tranquility you know yeah Tranquility might be nice for you and I I don't I don't know
anything about tranquility and then first my friend says I just look out the window
it's a beautiful spring day out there it's uh it's it's a look out you see
look at the street it's so calm and peaceful and I look oh look at that yeah it is tranquil
in fact my butt on the couch feels tranquility
and then slowly you know my friend turns on tranquil music
and then something inside of me Settles Tranquility is the food for more tranquility
if we stay in Restless agitated mode that's the food for more restlessness
and agitation so this shift and that's also where this this second
factor of Awakening of this ability to distinguish oh that this is the path towards being
Restless this is a path to being a little more tranquil is so useful yes to that
the next factor of Awakening is samadhi concentration
and here the food for this deeper concentration unification of Mind deeper
meditative meditative States and all that is something the Buddha calls the
evidence the sign the evidence for concentration the evidence for being
concentrated or settled or Unified
as people develop concentration in meditation there are symptoms of those concentrated
states that appear if some of those are physical something begins shifting and changing in the body
the body feels more unified there might be a kind of nice feeling of of Tranquility a glow a warmth the
breathing can start for some people can start feeling quite beautiful they're like oh this breathing is so
great it doesn't feel like a beautiful feeling but sometimes there's a tingling that
begins happening in the body some people see white light they might see these are
all symptoms of the mind getting calm and subtle then concentrated
as we take in the symptoms of concentration they become the food for more concentration
to recognize the very things that are happening as we get concentrated is the support for letting you know the mind
getting interested or focused or gathered together around this good things that are happening so it gets
more and more settled more and more focused and then the seventh factor of working
is equanimity and here like with Tranquility Equanimity is a food for Equanimity the
so if you're not if you have no Equanimity then good luck
but if you have some Equanimity and remember this is seven factors of Awakening so it comes on the uh it
follows these first seven so they kind of build on each other starting with mindfulness so you might not have
Equanimity at first but as you keep practicing it starts to come and but when it comes
pay attention to it take it in let it register because the Equanimity is the food for
equanimity so one of the things that I think is
quite marvelous about this kind of teaching is you don't have to understand the
cause of your suffering you don't have to analyze yourself to no end
you don't necessarily have to fix the other people in your household or in the world around you
that they have become better so you can be good it's all about turning in and being fed
and supportive by something that's available in making these simple distinctions here for
yourself in your own psychology and your own mental engagement with the world
and it begins by making the distinction between being Mindful and not mindful
and as we learn to be more and more mindful we start seeing that distinction and it makes a world of difference to
really recognize it to know when you're Mindful and when you're kind of like just absorbed and lost in the experience
it can make a huge difference the other day I was at kind of I was
every once in a while have something I think of a little bit like a headache a migraine and it wasn't so bad last time but uh I
started feeling kind of I feel strange in my stomach and I get really hungry but I'm full and I
get this headache and it's kind of a drag but you know I've learned to be mindful on it and there's a way of being mindful
as I feel like I'm not identified with it it's like it's almost like it's not me but it is me I'm not like pretending
it's not but there's a in when a mindfulness like this independent through space it's almost as if who I am
is the mindfulness not these difficult feelings if I'm not mindful I could feel I could
feel a few days ago I could feel it sometimes almost like my identity sunk into those feelings like that's who I
was and there was a world of difference between that's who I am versus this is what I'm mindful of
and just felt you know so much easier to go through life this way through just this I'm mindful of this okay this is
what's happening and and I'm not identified I'm not lost or absorbed in it
but there's this place of freedom or Independence that's there at the same time that's not denying it
I don't feel like I'm aloof I don't feel like I'm distant I don't think I'm denying anything it's just like this is
real this is this is more real than what this identification thing
so to be able to make this distinction between being Mindful and not mindful
that's the food for the other six vectors of Awakening they grow and develop and as they receive them then
appreciate them and then there's so much more room so much more space so much more freedom in
the mind and it turns out that just a few you have to decide how many
of the problems you have in your life somehow in a funny kind of way
gets solved if you change your state of your mind
into a mind that's mindful sees clearly is engaged nicely
has Joy has tranquility is deeply settled and has a degree of
equanimity these are states of abundance these are states of of there are Treasures
and so the reference point for what needs to happen changes for us and it turns out now it's hard to
believe that Gill's happiness is not dependent on the car
it just turns out that's you know who who would have imagined
yeah so so food what do you so what do you feed
yourself with what do you do all the time all the time
the food for the hindrances is very much tied to what we're thinking
about all the time and um and she almost might want to think that the food for these hindrances
for what gives you indigestion has to do with thinking about cars all the time
thinking about hate thinking about the doubt about how terrible things are there's something about
watching the mind ruminate and and
spin out you can feel how it's not good food for the heart not
good food for the mind you can spill how it's and a lot of it's a tremendous amount of psychological distress in our
society comes from how people are constantly thinking constantly thinking and
thinking the same thing negative thing over and over again it's just debilitating it's a kind of food
and it is possible to change the diet and that's what Buddhist practice is
about changing the diet so it's a healthy diet of the input that we take into the heart
the mind is something much more beneficial and for the Buddha I think it begins by
being mindful such such a powerful thing to learn and it's not something to you learn just
overnight like oh that's mindfulness is something you keep learning and growing in the years and
decades you do it it's a fantastic thing that just kind of discovering oh that's what it is oh okay wonderful
so I hope that this week you make a resolution to eat better yeah
and uh and that you find this teaching uh applicable that you might want to
experiment and take a deeper look at yourself and chances are
that if you don't do that if you don't stop use this kind of this kind of teaching to take a deeper look at what
you're doing chances are pretty high that you'll be on a diet That's not
healthy for you the more of a preoccupied and lost in our thoughts lost in our it's usually
not healthy to be unpreoccupied chances are then you have space for
these beautiful qualities of heart that Buddhism cherishes
so may you eat well so we have a few minutes and if some of you would like to ask any questions
about this you're welcome to ask or comments or
if you have any experiences having a good diet maybe we have some testimonials
can people hear me with a mask on um
trying to frame the question and completely resonates everything you've said my difficulty uh I will be fully
transparent I have two children and both of them are suffering because of a family situation that has unfolded
post-covered through no Faults of their own and so I see my oldest in particular who's 17 and
Awakening to the world suffering quite greatly because of factors that are Beyond her own control and I understand
that my suffering is because of her suffering and I don't know how to help her to see how she spends and spends on
the doubt and the things that she cannot control that are causing genuine suffering through no fault of her own
and so that causes me great suffering and I'm I'm unable to skillfully understand how
to support navigate how to how to feel Equanimity how to reach a state of
equanimity when someone I love so much is suffering
that's a very important question and it's probably has so many different
factors that then he's answer I'll give you a response I'll give you is maybe kind of too narrow or you know might
miss you even but here are some ideas is that some of your suffering some of
your pain let's say use the word pain rather than suffering some of your pain is completely appropriate for a parent
to have for a distressed child of course what parent wouldn't be
some of the pain is more to do with you than with your your child
and so this idea of turning your attention 180 degrees back to yourself so you can ban distinguish
distinguishing between the pain the parental pain that's of course is going to be there
and and the parental pain which is debilitating for you the first I'd like to suggest can actually be energizing in
a good way the second undermines you it gets in the way
and uh and uh and so one of the interesting kind of things to think about maybe as a reference point is a as
a not a not not a judgment or a conclusion about yourself but as a way of seeing yourself better
is uh try the assumption that the extra suffering that you have
is from a lack of confidence
just that might kind of like well what what why am I lacking Comfort what's
that about could it be and and so I don't have an answer but that
said you'd like to explore that and uh exactly but the um
one of the principles that I kind of live by especially with children they really need to feel
the the care the love and the acceptance of a parent who's present not
necessarily a parent who can fix their problems but a parent who really is there and understands but and
accompanies them with it in a healthy way and if a parent's trying too much to fix
sometimes that's appropriate for a parent to do that to get the Band-Aid out and put it on the cuts but uh but
sometimes uh the very movement of fixing um if we're so reactive ourselves and
have all this extra suffering we're actually modeling a way of being in the world that teaches
kids to be distressed but if we can model being calm
being caring but being untroubled by how they are
I think that then they start getting sense of something that was another possibility in the world and so certainly your daughter needs you
so anyway so those are those are kind of my preliminary thoughts I don't know if they
give you enough to reflect on it it does thank you thank
you
thank you I really empathize with what she said I suffer from the same thing
you know over and over again uh in my case a lot of it has to do with the fact
that overly over synthesized to the uh to the suffering of my
offspring she's a very very hard charging hard driving individual and she's pregnant
and she's also getting a degree at the same time she's raising an infant
she's got all these plates in the air and my wife and I have distinctly
different approach to how we observe her mind causes a lot of suffering here's for by all appearances doesn't seem to
and that has to be the fact that I'm constantly tuned into everything she does and if I can just learn to step away
from it and just calm down the very first step is to be less sensitive or
synthesized to what's going on I'm hoping that then the second step is all
these things that you wonderful things that you describe come to play but I won't allow it to happen because I'm so
constantly tuned into everything that's going on so I've got to detune myself first before I can more or less get into
that state of calm and Equanimity or whatever you want to call it so if hopefully you'll allow me to give you a
carrot if you could stop being so overly
concerned with your daughter and thinking about her staying in touch with her finding out what's going on all
the time and just constantly kind of being with her challenges if you could stop doing that and calm
down in a deep way and really take a vacation from that you know whether it's a few hours or a few
days or just long enough then when you're with her when you're in contact
with her you're probably being bring much more benefit to that relationship
so when you're not with her you're preparing yourself to be with her and her suffering
if you're not with her don't bother suffering so much let it be
in the background because you have something much more important to do so you can be a good father a helpful
father that's the carrot
so maybe one more
hi um so can people hear me yeah I really enjoyed your talk guilt um I have
something a little less meaningful and deep than the other two questions
I was just protesting some parts of your
speech because sometimes the compulsion or the attachment isn't really rational so for instance if I see a plate of
french fries and I have this deep craving for it or something I really want to buy then I could think well just
uh investigate the desire let go of the attachment but I really really want it
to so there's some kind of compulsiveness there um I'll probably just reach out and have
the rest of the phrase so I just was wondering about the irrational parts of it or the compulsion the kind of
holding on really tight yeah well that's the way people are sometimes
[Laughter] and um and so
uh classically in Buddhism one of the most important practices that are the
entry-level practice to really get started so you can really do everything else and and I don't entry entry level
doesn't mean that it's like remedial it just means it's it's so important it's like that's what I'm emphasizing how
important it is classically with we don't teach much in the West and that is restraint
so look for opportunities where this compulsion operates and practice some
kind of wise restraint I don't know about French fries because they're going to get stale if you don't eat them right away
but uh but uh the shopping thing make a commitment to yourself maybe
that whenever you feel compulsion to buy something you always wait a day
and that's the restraint part and then the next day maybe you're you
know it all it all changes in your view of it changes but to practice restraint
and don't order french fries and uh and so with your compulsions that
are irrational um you know you can't go back and look
at the cause or why it's working it's just so hard but by practicing restraint you
cultivate something strong in you and that becomes stronger and stronger that hopefully you find the light and joy in
having that kind of autonomy look there's a compulsion and I'm not going to do anything isn't that
great how does that sound yeah that sounds good thank you
great so um thank you all very much for being here and participating and
um I don't know if it's if it's if it's not raining it's just cloudy I'm happy to meet is it is
it yeah yeah but in here but is how's is it raining outside
and
because some of you like it's nice to meet with some of you some of you like doing that and I like it in the parking lot so if it's not raining
um you know I think there was supposed to be a little Gap today
it's sprinkling okay let's not do it then so and then we have here in a I don't know in 15 minutes or so we have
uh Dharma rocks for the Children's Program here so
um if you want to talk hopefully you can do it out in the deck or something and not linger here too much they want to
set up and um yes oh so we had it we had a first kind of
I don't know call it social event kind of special event or celebrate celebratory event here for someone on
Friday and there was a lot of food and um
it was kind of it was catered so um it'd be great if some of you are hungry or or
would like to take it home or something I think maybe it's out in the kitchen on the counter there so please help
yourself no friend no french fries thank you