well good morning at the
moment I feel a little reluctant to speak I think
uh sometimes sitting sitting down in this meditation posture I already start
feeling settled and I also seeing the chats and
reflecting on this community on YouTube and our time
together I just feels happy and happy and
contented and so words don't seem so I don't know
present so sitting here this way the
Highlight or the orientation that becomes clearer than
when maybe I'm a little bit quicker to speak or have something
on my mind to speak is that what's also close by is a
feeling of Freedom a freedom of
it's more like I'm aware of the the pauses and silence in the music
more than the notes being played or aware of the space in a large
room more than the people and things in the room and I'm more aware of a sense of
freedom from pressure and tension and clinging
then I am the kind of things that I would be thinking about speaking
about what I'm doing in the
moment so to sit with an orientation to meditate
with an orientation of what's not here the of one wonderful
absence not because we're remembering what's not here but because we
feel the peace that's right here the space that's right
here to see a door that's wide open and to freely walk through it is to
appreciate the empty space of the doorway
so to begin our
meditation assuming
a meditation post posture which is appropriate for
you and every time we go to
meditate what an appropriate posture is changes even ever so
slightly and the longer we meditate the more we're attuned to the
subtleties of the choices the way of sitting the adjustments to be
made the longer we sitting the more it's a homecoming to go into this
posture and gently closing your
eyes and regardless of if there's tension or pressure or
preoccupation can you also find in your body or heart or
mind an appreciation
allowing your yourself to become
quieter
Stiller the absence of busy
activity maybe an absence
of a busy mind
the mind that begins to quiet and
settle and then I C easy way in a way that feels just right for
your breathing take some deeper breaths deeper inhales longer
exhales just deep enough that you
enjoy and if you enjoy the deeper
breathing enter into that pleasure as you
breathe stay close to
it as you exhale see if you can find some pleasure
enjoyment in relaxing the
body letting the breathing return to normal and is there any enjoyment or
pleasure however
subtle in a simple ordinary
breathing
and then as you breathe as you exhale to go through different points of
your body face shoulder belly
elsewhere and soften relax your body and see if there can be
some small pleasure in the
relaxing even if otherwise you're challenged with some emotion or
state there on the edges of how you are feel the enjoyment of
relaxing
e
and then centering yourself on the body's
experience of breathing
and in the most immediate here and
now as if there's no future things to do or past to
remember here and now is there any feeling or sense of
contentment appreciation of just this
here any pleasure of just being present
here enter into that
enjoyment however small it is as a
doorway to not prioritizing other things that you tend
to be caught up
in
for
e
if
meditation is a practice of
contentment a contentment that's
found in the Silence of the the
mind like the silence between notes in
music or the spaciousness of a large open space
where there's lots of breathing room just to
be we a Stillness of an early morning
before there's any feeling of needing to do
anything a full contentment is a Stillness of the body and
mind in here and
now and whatever way you can feel content with just this moment being
alive enter that contentment and
breathe
for
during meditation there doesn't have to be a
reason to be peaceful to be
content to be
happy these States can be allowed to arise and
be for no
reason except that you're alive and
breathing
for
e
and then as we come to the end of this
meditation to once again relax on the
exhale relax the whole
body
release relax particular places in your body
soften soften the thinking
mind releasing tension associated with
thinking releasing any a contraction
around your
emotions and perhaps quietly sitting here for a
minute or so attuned
to a freedom of heart a freedom of mind that allows all things to be as
they are just for
now in the context of Freedom
contentment
and then preparing yourself for the end of the meditation turn the Mind's Eye
outward to gaze up on the world that you'll return to from your
meditation in your home or neighborhood or places of
work your
communities and gaze upon it all
kindly wishing those people you'll encounter
well well
wishing may all beings be
happy may all beings be PE be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free and thank
you
warm greetings for the last Fifth and last Talk of the series on
attitudes and today the topic is going from stress to
freedom and I want to propose that stress might be seen as a kind
of uh attitude in that it can be pervasive it can be chronic that we
carry stress in our bodies and hearts and minds and it also um it's kind of like a
mood in that it has an influence on us uh we're not stress if we're uh stressed
there's no there's a cost to being stressed it's not without an impact that
it has on us and one of the impacts a stress can have especially ongoing
stress is that it self- reinforces that uh ongoing stress is
stressful ongoing stress is uncomfortable and then how we react to
discomfort is sometimes with more stress so uh if we are afraid that's stressful
to live with chronic anxiety and but that discomfort of that anxiety uh makes
us want to somehow respond react do something um that reinforces it because
if we feel stress around being anxious or anxiety produces stress that creates
discomfort and then we have more reason to be or more fuel for being anxious
same thing with being angry and resentful or envious same thing with having full of um craving and
ambition uh same thing with being confused used there's a many things
which feel very uncomfortable and uh and in that discomfort there's a birth of stress
which makes us more uncomfortable which gives birth to more stress so for this reason I think of
stress as being like an attitude we have an attitude of stress almost as if we go
into any situation at all and the attitude is this is going to be challenged for me and this is going to
be uncomfortable and so I tense up I contract I feel internal pressure uh
pushing leaning forward holding back um making myself small making
myself big in an assertive way uh to get what I think I need to do to protect
myself or get what I think I need to have so all these things this kind of forcefulness
stressfulness um uh becomes chronic and becomes kind of continually reinforcing
a discomfort which drives more of the same the alternative is uh to search for
the freedom in any circumstance we're in the freedom from stress the freedom from
reactivity the freedom from pressure or tension the freedom from straining and
um or or pulling back or making ourselves all or or asserting
ourselves that um there's a freedom that comes from not asserting
ourselves in some aggressive way and not um diminishing ourselves in any kind of
way a uh freedom of just being able to breathe as if you have complete
permission to be alive to be present to breathe to to be valuable and important
that no one can take away from you no one can take away your
basic capacity to find that middle way between
assertion and collapse pushing forward pressure and pulling back and giving up
and having maybe apathy even apathy is also kind of
stressful its own way but that middle way of just like here I
am here I am and I'm allowed to breathe I'm allowed to have my eyes be relaxed and not
straining or trying to figure something out I'm allowed just to be relaxed and present
in my body and a a milestone or turning point
in the practice of Buddhism and meditation is to have a visceral feeling
of freedom of an absence of stress of an
absence of the Mind straining or pushing or collapsing or pulling
back uh a sense of ease and just Simplicity that is almost as if there's
an absence of any demands on us absence of any demands we put on
ourselves we can still take care of of things we can still do things and accomplish things but we do it without
stress we do it without any sense of demand a sense of should a sense of Duty
that is burdensome to carry with us that we do it in with
freedom some people that idea of fre doing things with freedom means that we
do it without expectations or measuring ourselves by the results we do it because we do it
complete completely fully freely and we deal with the results when
the results occur whether they occur or not uh it's in the doing in a free way
that we find our joy or happiness so at some point in meditation
there starts to be an inkling a small it's kind of like the you know the just
the beginning of light of the Dawn as the dawn begins to show a little inkling
a little hint of what it's like to be free what it's like to be unattached or
non straining what it's like to be without stress maybe there's still
stress in our system but there's some place where some chronic stress is beginning to relax ah look at that
that's possible and as that sense of nonstress non strain non non-
contraction non pressure begins to get stronger a point comes where this
becomes compelling this becomes a reference point for how we live our lives this
becomes a kind of an attitude of Freedom an attitude that is an
orientation towards the freedom that's always here always available here and
now and maybe that you have most most of us will have more freedom in the moment
than we Avail ourselves of or more freedom that we're living in than we
notice because the mind has a selective uh attention where it's focuses on what
it's afraid of What It Wants What It doesn't like and tends to be absorbed and then spin out and be caught up in
its own little world but at some point there's an attitude that we live in a mood that we
live in in or a orientation or a view that
um of freedom of uh absence of strain of and
there's many uh things that come with this sense of
Freedom today I'm thinking of contentment kind of just a Content just
to be alive just to be here just to do what we're doing when we're doing it and um
sometimes it's comes along with a sense of love or care for the world around
us not having stress does not mean we don't care in fact care that's done
through stress is probably not done with love but more maybe a sense of Duty
maybe and um or something else but the the love that comes out of
Freedom that Joy the contentment so to go from
stress to Freedom not just assume that the
alternative to stress is being D being without stress
de-stressed but that the alternative to stress is a certain kind of Freedom that
gives us lots of breathing room Freedom that gives us a sense of fresh air for
the heart or the Mind an openness a brightness a
peacefulness that's the what's available when there's when we figure out how to
release our stress as we become more relaxed as we
living less stressful look for the freedom become let this let's Freedom be
recognized so that it starts becoming the attitude with which we live an attitude of
staying free staying not caught
up and in so be in so doing being wonderfully available to the world as an
emissary of Freedom as a model of Freedom as a
in it's in a certain kind of way a giving the gift of
freedom because we're not imposing our stress on anyone else we're doing the
opposite we're imp we're offering others space to be who they
are so thank you thank you for this week and I hope that those of you in the
United States appreciate this uh holiday that we have of giving thanks and I
offer my thanks to all of you and the chance to be together this way and to
meditate this way with you and to be able to teach and um I look forward to
beginning again with a new series on Monday thank
you