so good good morning everyone can you hear me okay is it loud enough
and um thank you for being here to speak personally for myself I find
that really wonderful to meditate together in a group it's a different kind of uh
there's a different I don't know exactly the right word to use but a different kind of grounding a different kind of
kind of settleness that when the group of people sit together and of course that can be quite
wonderful for sometimes and it could also be difficult because it also highlights maybe how
Restless the mind is or how much you know impatience there might be and you know
ordinarily we wouldn't see that so clearly because
we might um just get up and
turn the TV on or do something to distract us go eat or something
and but here kind of like maybe because you're with other people there's a little bit more care to keep the
container to keep the stay within it and then it could clear out I'm really impatient or why does my
mind and mind is out of control they can't wait until this is over you know surely they they must have
slept through the Bell and so we get to see what the Mind does
you know and that that's a really one of the gifts of meditation is to see ourselves clearly both at what is
wonderful but also what is challenging for us so we can take really see it honestly and clearly
and find a way to work through it and um the topic I want to talk today
about today is the imagination and uh in our
the way I was kind of brought up in Buddhism first in Zen and also in vipassana
we were kind of like the anti-imagination people because imagination we're like the just
seeing things as they are people like just see things as they are directly the direct experience of what is
and Imagination is a way of losing touch with how things are directly it's like
superimposing some ideas a projection of some fantasy or something on a situation
that distorts it in some way and at least that's that's the way that I was kind of I came into this tradition
and uh and I'm grateful for that I'm grateful for how much it pulled the rug
from underneath or clarified how much fantasy I lived in
which was plenty and how much I projected artificially you know constructs on top of the others the
world and also on top of myself there's so many ways in which I imagined who I
was or imagined who I shouldn't be or measured myself against some imaginary
idea of what a person's going to be and so the imagination played a big role in having this this kind of practice that
constantly pointed that out that don't go there don't go there was actually very helpful for me
but it also limits our full Humanity that imagination is important and part
of human life it's so important that it's probably unimaginable without it
I think we're always imagining somehow even if you're um you know you go out for a walk on a
cloudy day and you imagine what it would be like if it rained you know it might rain that's kind of imagination
and so you take an umbrella if you hadn't kind of that kind of idea
of imagination maybe you you wouldn't have gotten the umbrella or something
I don't know if that was a good example but uh my attempt so it turns out that in the teachings of
the Buddha there's a lot of different teachings about imagination however the English translators often
don't translate it that way they one of the words for that I'd like
to translate is Imagination they might translate as conceives and conceives I
don't know what imagination that evokes for you but conceives it feels to me a little
more conceptual like you have a concept you create what's delightful about conceives is it
has a connotation that you're inventing something you're CR brings something into birth you're conceiving something
maybe it is a fantasy doesn't really exist but um and then there's also a words
that uh sometimes translated as one regards you know regards what does that mean
um and but the the the Pali word is uh
has the word uh see or visualize in it some nepasity
and um and so but the way it's used if you see it kind of a kind of just like
to visualize or imagine so here's a Buddha's use of imagination
I'll give you an example and it's supposed to evoke your imagination
in a way that makes a point that maybe inspires you maybe gets you to think
about a different something in a different way and maybe points to Something in
yourself or in human nature that that um is better better kind of conveyed
through an act of imagination than it is to tell you this in prose
just like matter-of-fact way so this is this is this has come from the Buddha that's uh I'll paraphrase it for but um
so at least in the time of the Buddha at least there was a great
God in the Heavenly Realms named Brahma and Brahma was kind of like the ruler of
all the gods of his realm and he had a great palace Majestic in
the sky somewhere and he had a majestic you know
a gust throne only person who's supposed to sit on
that Throne is Brahma himself well one day Brahma was off some other
parts of the Heavenly realms doing what Brahma does and there was a little
ugly little runt of a troll and not that they had trolls in Ancient
India but the the Indian word is probably those of
you know Sanskrit yaksha so he came into the palace and came into
the Royal Court or the Divine court and jumped up on that throne
and this you don't do and so the other gods in the court started telling that you know you
shouldn't be up there you know that's only for Brahma please get down and he wouldn't get down
so a common thing to do and something so important is not being adhered to is to
get angry and so the voices went up and the other God said you have to get down you must
get down and and the more angry they were and the more Stern they were and offensive they were
the more that ugly little yaksha got bigger
and bigger and more beautiful and More Beautiful until he was sitting there huge and big
and radiant and Beautiful on the throne well this confused the court Gods to no
end so they went looking for Brahma and explained what was going on
and Brahma said I know what's happening so in a snap of his finger because he's a God he returned to his Palace
and he stood in front of this his own throne and he bowed deeply
to the yaksha and said nice to see you
we haven't seen each other for a long time and you're quite beautiful big and I
hope you're comfortable up there and anything I can do for you and as he kind of treated in that way
kindly generously with kind of hospitality at his own
place this Yorkshire started to shrink and shrink and get smaller and smaller and
smaller until finally poof he managed
so then the great God Brahma sat up back on his throne and explained to everyone
in the court this ugly little brunt of a troll
is an anger eating troll so if you come with
anger he'll eat it it nourishes him and he
grows and becomes bigger and bigger and bigger but if you don't offer anger then you're
not nourishing this challenging thing and it gets smaller and smaller and
smaller so that's the story so it's you know may it's a fable maybe
it happened back then but uh it's the to tell that story is uh evokes the act of imagination for
the audience and I think for some of us it's kind of evocative like what does this mean like
you can imagine it and all that and imagine these people angry and this person getting bigger and
and it's kind of a fable for careful what you do with your anger
because some of the some of who you are some of the challenging parts of you
if you are angry something grows in you
and probably none of you have an angry little runt of a troll inside of you but but you know you have something in
there and sometimes anger is self-fulfilling you would get angry and we get angry at
ourselves and we feel awful and bad and then we kind of get more angry and more
blame and upset and so uh this idea that there's
something that thrives in anger but that
diminishes and vanishes in kindness is I think you know it's a wonderful
little story and it's a story that I've used I've taught to children I've been invited to um
elementary schools to teach kids like just introduce kids say something Buddhist or something and I've told that
story and um
so um so yeah that's a kind of a use of
imagination you know harnessing it for the purposes of making some point and the Buddha is full of things like
that and uh and he uses them also for the purposes of supporting people's
meditation practice he wanted he he encouraged people to use their imagination their memory
to recollect things that were inspired them
so there was an inspiration of gladness of joy of delight
that's associated with meditation practice and you know you don't want to overdo it
if you know sometimes you're kind of supposed to be miserable in meditation
um but not you're supposed to make yourself that way but but it just we're supposed to kind
of really meet ourselves as we are and some people are experts at running away and trying to avoid and fix and not
face what's going on but can we Face really the difficulties in our challenges and unresolved issues
can we Face them with a way that's inspired that we're glad to look at our
impatience even though I'm restless and want to bolt from meditation
wow is it some way that you can feel okay this is difficult but I'm inspired
I want to do this and so the Buddha uh encouraged people to call on their imagination for that
purpose so for example to imagine your own virtue
and if you have enough virtue that makes you inspired oh yeah you know I'm basically a good person
I haven't killed anyone lately and I haven't robbed any banks lately you know it's pretty good
unfortunately for this world it's pretty good because you know so much bad stuff happens
and um and so um or think about somebody else's virtue
that you know that you really inspires you that's think about something that makes you
happy um I know that I've sometimes been in meditation and struggled and then
there's been someone else on the retreat who sat so well
they just felt they're kind of simple almost selfless dedication just to be
there and practice all the time in a nice way and wow okay well if that person can do it I think I'll stay here
and so now my eyes I remember that person sit there okay keep going that's
an act of imagination of sorts and then for oh so there's a challenge
is called the five hindrances the five obstacles for meditation
of preoccupation with or addiction to things like sensual desire
ill will um freezing or becoming really stiff or
closed down inertia restlessness
and doubt and so the meditators have to work with this
the Buddha gave one set of of similes to describe what it's like
to you know to have these another set of similes for what it's like to not have
them and here he's using the imagination to give people and maybe in a a palpable
visceral sense feeling for what it's like when these aren't here
so we can recognize their absence so we can kind of look at the little opening
in our hearts that kind of show us well this is the way you know not to be caught by these
things so I'll uh so
um so freedom from addiction preoccupation
of essential desire is visualized and he used as the word visual visualize here
a person who has paid off a business loan when the business business has prospered
and you can now support their family isn't that nice
so I don't know if any of you have really been struggling under death I don't know what central desire
addiction to it is like how it's a death exactly but the freedom from that thing oh now I don't have this heaviness this
uh preoccupation this concern this constant nagging that I have to kind of
pay the debt back and freedom and again the word freedom
is an opera in a word that evokes something in the imagination uh freedom from ill will is visualized
as a person who is ill suffering terribly sick with no appetite and
weakened body who recovers and regains their appetite and bodily strength
some of you have probably been really sick and finally when you're well and the first time you can leave your house wow
I'm still weak but boy is it good to be in fresh air and kind of as delightful
finally we've relieved of ill will we carried the resentment for years and years people carry resentment
for a lifetime but then to find it finally lifts oh wow it's like that illness is gone
I hope I have nothing immunity
freedom from this kind of inertia stiffness usually called sloth and
torpor but uh kind of um resistance
is as a person is freed from prison and bondage
without any lost to Lost to their wealth kind of you know so when we're stuck in
some kind of heavy burden weighing down kind of mental state
it's kind of like being in prison so the freedom from prison
freedom from restlessness or agitation
a person who had been a slave dependent on others and unable to go wherever they
wish becomes a free person who is independent of others and is able to go
anywhere so agitation something that's not your
choice is kind of forcing you to be do things and be engaged and be busy and
involved and so agitations you know he feels like you're a slave of something and finally this other thing in you
you're independent of you're not caught by it freedom from doubt is visualized as a
person with many possessions and much wealth who manages to travel
through a desert to safety with no loss in property
so doubt somehow is like being in the desert it's dangerous place if you're
caught in doubt you don't act you don't protect things you don't take care of things you just don't know what to do I
guess and um so to finally be free from this being lost in the desert
so I don't know if those you know these are ancient similes so I don't know if these work for you but the principle I'm
trying to pass on here was the Buddha used the act of imagination and to try
to evoke that for people and there's kind of two general types of imagination the Buddha used or pointed
to the acts of imagination that he used different words to describe words to describe
uh one are the ones that are I I like to call uh recollective just to recollect
something that is from your world that you somehow have a connection to so
it's evoking something you're already familiar with hopefully none of you have been a slave
or been in prison but uh it's part of unfortunately part of our wider world
and we've had examples we've read about such things we know about such things exist so it's recollecting something
we've learned about in some ways the other form of imagination is
inventive and that is it has not doesn't really have much to do with the real world
except in terms of fantasy and um and one imagines things
so the recollective one that's used beneficial
has many purposes and I'll offer you one purpose for a Dharma practice
through another Act of imagination the recollective imagination is to help
the heart sing does your heart sing I haven't heard me here
um you know it's a it's a metaphor for something that I think for some of us
kind of just feels like there's a delight The Joy a lightness a kind of freedom of expression from our hearts
what a great thing for the heart to be this way and so this opening this kind of delight
so it makes the hearts or make the heart smile it's also you know again an act of imagination
um versus the ones that uh feel that uh feel like burdens
that feel like having heavy weight on your shoulders it feels like the world is closing in on you
and the and the the inventive ones the ones where we kind of
construct some kind of fantasy that is not really part of the real world
is where we often get in trouble so delusions of grandeur
you know that I'm better than everyone else or better than those people and that I think many people are one way
or others are just you know easy enough to fall into and that's that would be inventive you
know because it's creating something which doesn't really exist in the real world in a in the real non-human world
uh the non-inventive world and that is it's a comparison with other
people delusionary Grandeur is in contrast to other people I'm going to save everyone in the world
and um and um that's just an event invention of the Mind
that is usually a burden for other people too
the um so you know so what are the what are the
stories the imagination that we project on ourselves that diminishes us
so we imagine ourselves as being worse than others we imagine ourselves to be inadequate
we imagine ourselves to be somehow um you know
something or other it was so bad for me when I was quite Young when I was a member of like in or like in college
first year to a college that the only relief I could get sometimes
was uh to imagine that I was invisible to everybody
and so I'd go through campus kind of imagining no one could see me and so that was act imagination that gave me
some relief because the alternative was so worse you know that I was constantly comparing
myself as being less than worse than terrible or something I was somehow wrong
and um I didn't have to I didn't have to have a reason to be a wrong person I was just inherently wrong
so you know it was very relatively simple fantasy to have because it didn't
have didn't require any proof and um so
it turns out that this famous teaching that Buddhism has about there is the the
the fantasy way in which it's presented as I say that carefully is a fantasy it's a
misunderstanding is that Buddha teaches there is no self have you heard that idea
he actually didn't teach it that way but what he did teach repeatedly
is the use of the word imagine ATI
that if you um to imagine
what's me what's myself and who I really am that is a problem
don't imagine yourself as a certain kind of self don't imagine
yourself as possessing certain qualities and activities don't imagine that you
are that you you know building yourself up in a particular way
so the the one of the main thrusts of this teachings is not to deny the self
it's also not in any kind of way to build itself up to invent the self
with the imagination don't imagine it and we have plenty of help in imagining
yourself there's people you know in the advertisement industry who are paid a
tremendous amount of money to trick us into imagining ourselves in
one way or the other imagining we're inadequate in some ways and would become adequate if we you know have a different
color lipstick and um and so we're being fed this kind of into the imagination constantly
I think politicians do it sometimes the imagination is used to demonize the enemy or demonize people
who are the opposition and they're using our capacity for imagination to construct to invent the
other in a way that's deleterious and so this thing about imagining a self
Imagining the self of others is such a dangerous thing the internalized imagination that other
people project racism that sometimes is is an imagination that's projected on
people and then some people that internalize it
some people adopt it they believe it and also both sides of the racism divide
and it's it's an act of imagination it's an invention of some kind of concept idea that then unfortunately has a
tremendous reality in how people treat each other and so the teachings of around self and
non-self has a lot to do with don't imagine a self
and as we learn to notice this inventive way in which the mind
has these ideas fantasies condemnations
ideas of who I am when I'm supposed to be what I am in relationship with other people who I am that otherwise other
people see me um
as we kind of have fantasies sometimes says compensation for a lot of suffering
we have that I mean some of the delusion of grandeur is a compensation or delusion you know maybe not delusions
of grandeur but delusions of fantasies of you know
um you know wonderful things
you know how often are sexual fantasies about sex and how much is it about some kind of compensation for just feeling an
adequate and trying to fantasize some wonderful situation where it's kind of like a Utopia or a connection and with
someone else so part of what we do in mindfulness
is in fact to start becoming sensitive and aware of how this constructive imaginary use
of the Mind operates and it might help to appreciate that
there are useful ways of using the imagination and they're really harmful ways of using it
and because if it's all if it's just imagination that's kind of pushed away like the way it was when I was a new
student then your part of you is kind of a healthy part of our human functioning is
not included in the practice but maybe there's an appropriate way to
use the imagination to bring us to a time and place
where we are free of it to use imagination to inspire us to
practice to use the imagination to feel or sense where the opening is to Greater
peace and greater subtleness and greater freedom and we use it only to the extent that
it's helpful we don't try to use it as a sledgehammer to break through the door
to the other side you know you know not desperately trying to do something we use it to say I'm
desperate now let me imagine that my awaren my my
breathing is like a soft massage and I'm going to massage my desperation
I've used um I love water
I've been out you know I grew up in a culture where we're close to the water on the water a lot
and so the idea of the Waves brushing up against the sand beach is
such a welcome homecoming for me so to sit in meditation imagine the
breathing is like waves coming and going up on the sand and then if I feel
you know something's really hard for me to be with than to imagine that's with those waves washing over allows me to
stay present for the difficulty and keep it really simple it's just a nice way of using
imagination helps me to be with difficulty rather than just kind of restless and
agitated about it I also partly I think because of how
much time I spent on water um
there's something about water it's going off into the Horizon and then the sky
and the space that goes up forever that one of the I feel very sometimes in
meditation I would imagine with my eyes closed that I'm looking out
into the deep universe the dark deep Universe kind of
spaciously going out to know and for me because of my background that's a really
comforting image I don't think for some people it wouldn't be that way but for me it's
just like oh it actually helped me feel at home in this universe and um
when I was like even when I was a little kid like you know eight nine years old and laying in bed I would have kind of
just spontaneously I would have this sense that I was looking out into the universe and I was home
and um and so to this day occasionally if I find myself kind of
you know my mind is a little bit kind of
not cooperating and it just doesn't seem like it's a big deal it's not like I have to go do some
deep looking at my mind just okay it's enough let me just kind of look into the
universe now with my eyes closed and then things get peaceful and quiet for me it's an act of imagination
so how do you use your imagination I think that probably most of you do
and if you don't realize that it there's a danger that often your
imagination is using you in ways that don't support you
that gives you uh projects into the future of fantasies and ideas of the
future that uh you know it's all going to be catastrophes
catastrophe thinking or we use our imagination to reconstruct
the past and I've certainly done that held some
kind of resentment or annoyance towards someone because you know I had imagined
what really happened only to find out later when I talked to the person
it was nothing like I'd imagined nothing and I had this is you know
annoyance irritation or something or towards someone that had no basis in reality
isn't that embarrassing and I said wow this mind of mine that
has this capacity to you know to imagine a past that never was there but and I
live as if it did luckily nowadays I know to always check I've learned very well what my mind is
able to construct and I can see it happening now and this is one of the gifts of meditation is to
really to be able to be present enough to watch thoughts images ideas arise in
the mind and track it and see it well enough to understand what it is and not
be fooled by it to put a question mark next to it and say well maybe let's go check it out
let me ask the person and um
you know and you said the other day we were together you said you know you're pretty lousy
is that what you said or maybe I'd say it better you know when we were together last last time as I
left you said something I couldn't quite hear you have a little bit of hard of hearing which is true
and uh you know what did you say so that's a nice way of saying it right oh I said you're lovely
yeah and so you know I was living in a fantasy and that meant and story about
what you know how they were treating me and all their different wrongs that's happened to me
so I hope that this talk I mean nice if it inspired you
but I hope this talk um uh evokes a curiosity and interest
through you in how you live in the world of imagination
and how can it be done in a way that supports you in in your life and helps
you in a healthy appropriate way and how is it that the imagination is
not helpful how does it a burden how does it kind of put you in prison how does it limit your life
how does how does it really weigh you down and for the Buddha
a lot of one of the kind of um Gathering points
for a lot of Burden a lot of suffering is all the ways that we all the
imagination that's used to construct to invent a sense of self and idea of self
and you don't have to be too concerned about this idea that there's not supposed to be any self
but then when you do Dharma practice you are supposed to be concerned about how we are inventing a self imagining
yourself and become more and more wise about how this works
and then the wonderful spiritual question
is who are you when you're not imagining Who You Are
then who are you or to say it even more powerful I think
who are you when you don't answer that question with a thought
then who and even better probably from a Buddhist
point of view is not who are you
but what is here what is left here
when you're not imagining what is here is left
when you don't use thoughts to tell you because even even this innocent use of
and who are you might actually limit something powerful and when you don't
let that limit you then what what is here what is what manifests itself What flows
what comes so use your imagination well
thank you so we have a couple of minutes and
um if somebody anyone wants to ask a question or a comment and then when I finish here those you want to come with
me out to the parking lot afterwards we can have a conversation out there with our masks off
and just continue this or something else but yes anybody any anyone now wants to say anything
foreign
talking about this imagination especially for the future I tend to
think of it as planning right and I think as long as I don't get
attached to the one way of possible future right then I think
there's not I don't see anything wrong with it right like I also can imagine several
possible Futures and probable Futures and unprobable futures and me and if I'm
not attached to say what I thought was probable future like in your case you thought this person going to say this
but they said that I'm not seeing it as a way of kind of like something wrong I
did and I should stop doing that and instead I say I just shouldn't be attaching myself to this what I thought
was probable future but there's nothing wrong with it I don't see like why like that's why I think seeing things clearly
right I'm not imagining it we have limited set of words here like English is a kind of funny language to be to be
present here and now wisely includes being aware of the future and
what might happen and includes what happened in the past the present moment here and now it doesn't have to exclude
a concern for the past and the present and um and that's a wise part of life to
plan ahead to think ahead and imagine what might happen and prepare for contingency plans bring the umbrella
you know or something and uh you know my life I I have a very full life
and so um I need to take time to think in the future this is what's going to happen
this is happening and okay if I'm going to do them I better do some things now first and get ready and let's organize
things and set up and and you know let people like in my career you know Dharma
teachers like me we often have to plan two years in advance
uh so everything can be done you know everything works no it coordinated with everybody else so I can show up and tell
people to be in the present
that's great to bind you
so um I have a question regarding uh contemplative practice in general
um because in other religions um their prayers it's a form of content
contemplative practice but um in Buddhism we have meditation we have
different lineage right different traditions but what do to you is the key difference
between this contemplative practice and others and there's some framework like
taking in some sort of faith-based practice in other religions it could
keep it close to your mouth um is the key difference is whether you you talk about emergence basically
be there and see things emerge right don't limit yourself to one possibility but there are other
um um religious people who
follow the you know who sorry um the the key difference to some some
people say the key difference is whether you allow that emergence or that contemplative practice lead you to
open-mindedness or you are enforcing your own belief right which could be
problematic for the world so I think the broader question is what's unique about this practice and this contemplative
practice versus others and why is it better or or maybe it's not better or
yeah yeah thank you it's a it's a it's a I think it's a reasonable and a good question but I'm not really qualified to
to talk about other people's practices uh you know and and uh and I certainly
not interested in talking about it in a way that makes one better than the other you know that I think uh different
religions have a whole world system a whole philosophy or view of view of life and logic that things make sense in
their world view and their kind of whole thing and so you ask what is the purpose and are you are you that purpose that
they want to that they're offering and that world view that that purpose is within does that work for me
so in Buddhism we have a kind of a world view we have a purpose within that world view
and um it I don't think necessarily has to work for everybody else but uh you
know it you know so you have to and then and so if you're interested in this important question you're asking I think
it's for you to answer really but you have to go and study each one well enough to be able to compare and see is
it apples and oranges or is it different kinds of apples sorry and the reason I ask this question
is I'm trying to deal with because my my family my husband I'm more leaning
towards my hearing is hard and the best thing to do if you hold it uh horizontally so it's like that and
really importantly so the reason I asked that question is that it's a um it's in
my own personal life I am leaning toward this tradition and this practice but for
my family they're more CR they're Christian they have their Christian belief and how do I reconcile that and
how do I convince my husband to come do my practice because kind of sound it
has to be split into two anyway yeah after we can tell however there's
imagine there's two things is how do you reconcile the two practices but also how
do you have harmony with your family and and your kids yes yeah how do you
how do you how are you in harmony so this is an important question and and so there's different ways of answering your
question one is at the terms in with the terms
that you offered another way which you didn't ask but which is the orientation of this
practice is um what's happening in you
emotionally deep down that's the source of this question and you don't have to
answer now but uh what happens if you practice with that fear or that distress
and if the fear goes away how do you answer the question then
and so but if the fear Remains the answer the the the rational answer to
the question might not really be addressing what's deep down inside
and so the interest here with our practice is always to go deep and what's the what's the depths here and can we
clarify that before we clarify some of the things that are that are you know not quite as deep
um so I don't know if that's a satisfying answer for you but that would be the approach here and
and then and then you're in a better position to ask to answer the question yourself
okay so thank you so uh in one announcement and that is
that um it's been you know for at IMC here the
pandemic in a sense began as in something that affected us on a Saturday
when we were going to uh one day Meditation Retreat here people showed up
and we'd already that evening not before just decided that we can't beat you know we're quarantined now where we can't
meet so people showed up and we sat out outside the here and talked for a while and and um and then we closed we are
closed and that was the that was it and I don't think we've had a really a day long here for IMC since then
anyway we're having one of the first ones uh Saturday
so it's you know three years and uh so don Neal is teaching a
day-long Meditation Retreat I think it's on the seven factors of Awakening there's always that right there's a
flyer there's Flyers out there on the counter yeah looking beautiful flyer and now what's the time for it
9 30 9 30 to 4 30 and uh again people are wearing masks but you're welcome to
come and if you would like to come here and and um and Don's a great teacher and
so it I think it should be you know things were starting to open up and people are more comfortable all this and
I mean I suspect that a good number of you are comfortable to be here without masks
some of you would never come here without masks but so for those of you who are comfortable
not wearing masks I want to thank you for wearing masks and doing it carefully I think it's a gift and I just I think
it helps this kind of environment that we're in to uh to be able to meditate in a way that makes people's
be able to let go more deep more deeply and so in a few minutes you can take a
chair folding chair out there in the parking lot if you want to meet and because some of us are going to meet out there maybe partly if you're at all
inclined it'd be great if you turn to somewhere next to you and just said hello to them and welcome them even if this is your first time you can welcome
them thank you