welcome and welcome to your meditation during this guided meditation
time one of the strong associations I believe with mindfulness
meditation and often how I teach is that mindfulness is a
non-reactive awareness that doesn't add anything to the experience just is
present for our experience as it is and that when we practice that way
then we're not allowed to um change anything we're not allowed
to think about anything um something like
that but in in fact this mindfulness
practice as a Buddhist practice uh sometimes it's useful to
think of it as a strategy and we're using the best
strategy we have we we know of to become free to become
liberated and sometimes we practice non-reactive awareness and that's really you know a
really value Val invaluable sometimes we practice not
adding anything or projecting anything onto experience no
stories but sometimes we do sometimes it's strategic it's useful to change our experience
sometimes it's useful to have stories that we tell ourselves sometimes it's useful to
interpret our experience in ways that support the the strategy of being able
to be here present alive and be
free so this week we're doing I'm talking about wise
thinking and often I believe for many human
beings uh thinking goes unexamined unconsidered we just think
what we think and we might be troubled by it we might uh be in involved in it
it just kind of goes along on its own merry way and we're kind of the participants of it and you know but if
we're living a mindful life in a deliberate life uh we don't just let our
thinking go on overdrive go on automatic pilot we can actually engage it in a
useful way in a strategic way they Buddha said that a watched mind
brings happiness if we don't don't watch your mind and the mind goes an automatic
pilot that can often be a recipe for suffering so here we are to wake up to
be present to see be wise watch the mind but also to engage the mind in a useful
way so in relationship to thinking we can think in ways that support this path
we can think in ways that helps us to get helps the Mind get quieter Stiller more focused more non-reactive to our
experience thinking can be part of our support system for all
this and one way that happens is in preparation for really settling into the
heart of meditation when we first sit down we could notice how we're thinking
we could take some we could think in wiser ways we can
tell stories in wiser ways we can imagine in ways that support
us use the imagination so that's what we'll do today and uh and uh in this day this
week of uh the wise use of thinking in meditation so to assume a meditation
posture and without much other preparation
now gently close your
eyes and to whatever ability you have to
imagine or to tell yourself a story
imagine that you are sitting in the room or the place where
you're sitting to meditate begin a story that
says in this story I'm sitting in this room in my meditation
posture and then imagine that they tell the story of here you are and you're
checking in with yourself imagine that you're a person who's
thinking and notice are you thinking thoughts that
you're happy to
have
and gently tell yourself the
story of yourself sitting here meditating and the way to do that one
way to do it is gently tell yourself give yourself
instructions in meditation rather than relying on me to do it guided
meditation gently calmly instruct yourself use your
thoughts to think thoughts of instruction and we'll do that for a few
minutes
silently
and if you have a story unconscious sub conscious automatic
story of what it's like for you to be practicing what it's like to give yourself
instructions what your current circumstances are like and if that story distracts
you tell yourself a different story tell yourself the story that of
now here meditating
tell yourself the story the experience of what it's like
to be in your body breathing maybe narrating it as if
someone's listening to this
count
for
as you're sitting here tell the story give the explanation
to yourself of how sitting
meditating can be helpful for you
supportive perhaps explaining it to yourself
with a voice that's calm supportive kind here let me tell
you this is what this meditation is about now this is what I'm trying to
do because I care I care about myself I care about you speaking to
yourself gently quietly as an alternative to other
stories and habitual ways of
thinking
e
gently give yourself relaxing
instruction at the end of the inhale
relax at the end of a thought
relax
let there be a ongoing relaxed clear intentional
instruction maybe just with the sing even the single word
relax
e if your mind is easily
distracted tell yourself the story of about being
distracted tell it to yourself in a quiet calm peace peaceful
voice and it as you tell yourself the story of being distracted or starting to
be collected the story of whatever your
experience is at the end of each
sentence Point yourself to the quiet and Stillness that's
here the silence at the end of a
thought
and when the mind gets distracted
again deliberately bring in different thoughts the thoughts about
meditating and what you're doing and the goodness of
it and let the each of those thoughts point back to the Stillness the
silence
if any thoughts come up that undermine
you that somehow are critical or fear producing
or any ones that are unpleasant to
have substitute them substitute them with
deliberate real itic thoughts supportive
thoughts about doing the
meditation in a way that points to a quiet
intimacy of breathing
mindfully that does so with a positive
regard for yourself for the practice and for whatever your
experience
is kind regard for all
things
for
e
if you find yourself distracted don't simply let go of your
distractions offer a reframing of whatever you're thinking
about it can be as simple as adding not now this is not the time to
have these thoughts or it's not
so or if your distractions are fantasy
imagination reframe your
interest to being intimate with reality as it is in the
present
if the thoughts are
negative reframe those
thoughts in such a way that they don't undermine you
maybe the simple statement I see
you I know you distracted
thought it's okay for you to rest and relax because right now I'm
meditating
for
and consciously you can use a thought that points Beyond
thinking the gentle calm thought
listen and then listen to The Silence where there is no
thinking the thought feel that points you to
feeling not
thinking the thought Stillness that point points to
whatever non-discursive Stillness there is here in this body
or in the space around
you
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting in some way that seems realistic to
you tell yourself a
positive a story of positive regard for
yourself ideas of how how you'd like to support
yourself how meditation is helpful how taking this time to
meditate even if it was not a good meditation how it was good to do
this maybe even having a a small smile on your lips appreciating
yourself and then turning your gaze outward into the world and if it's nice for you you can
tell brief story of how our lives are so
interdependent on the lives and work work and efforts of so many people we benefit immensely from The
Unseen labor of people in our neighborhood in
our wider communities other countries of the whole
world reminding yourself of this story of the amazing supportive Network that
brings us our food our clothes our all that we need for our
life and then think thoughts of goodwi for all those people who lives support
[Music] yours wouldn't it be nice wouldn't it it
be wonderful if they could be happy and peaceful and
safe wouldn't it be wonderful if you were happy peaceful and
safe and so all the networks of interconnection we have all the ways that
we share this planet is filled with mutual kind
regard and may we contribute
ours may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings everywhere be
free
[Music]
thank [Music]
you
so continuing on the theme of wise
thinking you know in a Buddhist practice all our life is a subject for
practice everything that we are about is a worthy object for our mindfulness and
attention and that includes the world of thinking and certainly we there's a lot to learn about thinking by being being
mindful of it but also it's uh the thinking is such
an important activity that uh a necessary activity
for our lives that uh we don't have to leave it to chance what we think about
we don't have to let the the automatic pilot let us think whatever we think uh we don't have
to be the victim of our thoughts
and we could think deliberately things such are supportive and helpful we can change the currents that were uh the
river of thinking that we're involved in we can introduce new things to have filling our mind and all
that this has to be done wisely so it's not just simply uh covering how we are covering
it over and kind of creating a happy scenario so that we don't feel our
sadness or our grief or or anger and pretend that we're kind everything is good and nice that doesn't
work but uh we don't have to just kind of go along with whatever our mind gives us in terms of our thinking our
distracted thoughts uh we can uh you know we can kind of in in a certain
sense be in charge of our thoughts rather than the thoughts be in charge of
us and um so one form of thinking that's quite
common is the story- making mind we're constructing stories we're constructing
scenarios images scenes predictions um if you're planning the
future that's a partly a story about what we think is going to happen and how we're going to uh what we're going to
say and how we're going to behave in the story if we're remembering the past it's usually a story about something that
happened then and there's a narrative behind it some times there's a narrative a
framework around which we tell story about our present moment oh this is not going to work out I can't do this uh
this is hard this is too hard um or this is uh great I'm wonderful and I want
everyone to appreciate me more and more because how wonderful I am there's kind of all this kind of more things going on
and those stories can be elaborate in terms of fantasies and creating huge
scenarios and if those stories are
are of unfortunate kind of if they're uh
hor fear stories if they're angry stories if they're despair stories if
they're conceit stories it kind of creates a mood and affects us in
profound ways it's kind of like there's mood music that comes along with the stories we tell us and that mood music
can depress us or enliven US us can benefit us or close us
down and so to uh uh to learn how in
just the right way not too much it's almost better to do a little bit too little is to engage in deliberate
thought while we meditate to think wisely to recognize what we're thinking
about and reframe it so for example a lot of the story making mind one of the
characters main characters in the story is ourselves and it uh and sometimes we
repeat the same story over and over again the same memory the same repeated kind of telling us the story telling
ourselves the conclusion of the story the implications of the story over and over again you know and it and if it's
debilitating if it's uh draining us of our kind of energy our life
Vitality then it's probably probably not useful to keep telling us ourselves that story repeatedly over and over
again and so to to take in a certain way
take responsibility or take control of our own mind our own Thinking by
figuring out how to think in a way that's not debilitating think in a
different way maybe there's ways of thinking about your distracted thoughts
where you tell yourself a different story where you tell yourself it's not like that there's another P
perspective sometimes you can tell yourself a a reframing of what you're doing so it could be for example you had
something difficult that happened to you and you feel really bad about yourself then to reframe
it what could I learn from this how can I be a better person in the future
rather than being weighed down by the past let me learn from that what can I learn from that experience
so that's being truthful honest you know and direct and real about what happened but it's reframing it in a way so that
it does something positive for us we learn something we learn how to be better because of it so that's kind of
stepping in and and and whenever something's
debilitating try not to participate in the thoughts that we churn out that are
debilitating be honest about why we're doing it what we're feeling but is there another way of
understanding it another story you can tell ourselves like if you're doing Buddhist practice you can say well
instead of kind of ruminating about this story over and over again the the story I have is that now I
can bring it into I can bring I can fold this into my practice I have a practice
that helps liberate this I have a practice that helps U bring kind kindness or gentleness or Stillness to
this I have a practice that Shields me from the impact of these because the
stronger the mindfulness is the less the mood music of those stories are going to
penetrate into my heart so telling yourself that story
because those can be true stories they can actually call upon positive ways of
being and the new story a new framework can be something that brings us a little bit of Joy or happiness or relief or
confidence oh it can be a different way so I'm not suggesting we do this all
the time but I am suggesting maybe doing doing it when it's the better
alternative if we notice that what we're doing is spinning out in our thoughts or pulled into the distractive thoughts or
we've had the same thought the same story you know a thousand times then you probably have something
better to do you don't need to do it again and so to step forward with some
sense of agency some sense of of uh ability to
change the currents of your life some ability to of controlling yourself being
a kind of a u monitoring yourself and and um and
um and taking control over yourself to some degree by
engaging in a reframing a new story that uh is a better one than the
one that's debilitating you again not to make up something not to invent something not to project kind
of fake kind of pos positive regard onto ourselves to
really recognize what's happening and and then reframe it for some way that
realistically is a much better story much more interesting if there's a lot a lot of
challenges for example I've known people who when it was refrained for them that
they're learning to practice with this so they can help others who have the same problem the same
challenge suddenly they they they get boyed up they get inspired oh yes when I
just focusing on myself the main subject to my story I feel I feel more depressed
I feel like one more time it's so hard but when I think oh there's a a
higher purpose for going through with this to learn and recognize and practice with this I'm going to be able to
support other people going through it they'll understand them better the more I understand myself with my difficulty
the more I understand other people with this difficulty the more I learn to be be patient the more I learn to have
Insight the more I learn to practice with it I can maybe support other people to do the
same and um so the main point I'm trying to make today
is don't be a victim to your of your stories don't operate on automatic pilot
of how what you think about through the day uh as if it's that's you have to or
that just kind of who you you are your thoughts and these or you have no say
over what you think you have to just go along with it or you believe that every thought you have is
true and so it has to be there it's not the case we could have some
role in how we think and what we think about and we can think in in ways that
are supportive and helpful and for those of us who are doing Buddhist practice we
have a whole repertoire to our whole set of understandings about what we're doing
that's actually quite profound so to call upon how we understand the practice
and how it's beneficial and how the bringing the practice to our difficulties is a reframing of the
difficulty it's it's inserting or bringing into it a new
story the story of practice the story of the Buddha story about how we're going
to practice with this and find our Liberation from it or we're going to sit patiently and
not give into it maybe we tell ourselves the story of Mara and uh and Mara's story is uh that
the mara comes to the Buddha this uh Temptation devilish kind of person who's
trying to stop the person the Buddha from being enlightened and uh he comes to the
Buddha and uh the story the Buddha tells is not that he has to fight and battle
Mara but he just looks at him straight in the eye and he says Mara I see
you and that's enough he doesn't he's not for or against Mara he's not
criticizing Mara he says Mara I see you and to be clearly seen Mara can't stand
that and just disappears goes away can't manage Mara loses his power if he seeing
that clearly so there's Mara story you have your challenges your strong drives and
desires and Ill Wills that come up so powerfully tell yourself the story of
Mara you might say the words Mara I see you and use that to really see what's
going on in such Clarity that you're not being pulled into the world of your
desires and aversions you're standing out and really seeing Oh this is what it is
and that uh so this is a skill to learn deliberate thinking
reframing uh your experience um and certainly can seem
like you're being busy in meditation when you do this um but the idea is to develop this
skill this orientation so you know when to bring it in because it's
supportive you know when this is the better alternative to do rather than
verily going along in distracted thought so may you today as you go
through the day may you find ways to reframe your
experience or to place whatever is happening to you into a different story
than the one that you're habitually engaged in or unconsciously engaged in may your
life occur within stories that bring you and others tremendous
benefit and freedom thank
you