so good day we'll go ahead and get started nice to see everyone
those of you who are commenting so please
um settle in for our meditation together finding a posture for your sitting
we're standing or lying down and just allow yourself to
I'm into the internal awareness
how the body feels from the inside
perhaps closing your eyes in order to bring the attention more inward
and maybe taking a long slow deep breath
really feeling the lungs and on the exhale settling a little bit further just into
how you are this morning or day
softening the face
the eyes and the eye sockets allowing the jaw to release
softening down through the throat shoulder area
the arms and the hands
softening down into the Torso letting the feeling into the rib cage the front the
back the sides letting that feel relaxed
letting the belly be round
expansive
and down into the legs softening any bracing in the legs or the feet
so that we have this invitation of some flexibility in the body
sensing the contact points where you're sitting where your hands and maybe touching your
body if your lips are touching just simple
contact points and making sure those places aren't pressing
against each other rather just
resting Softly surface is touching Softly
I'm feeling the groundedness when you're sitting in this way
there's a connection to what you're sitting on stability
this week's meditations are exploring these qualities of the elements
as noted in Buddhist teachings and today we'll focus on the water
element the water element has two main qualities
wetness and cohesion so we can feel Water Element directly in
the mouth in the eyes if we're sweating there's moisture associated with the
body
touching into those places now
bring to mind now how the solidity of
Earth is softened by water
Earth with no water and easily becomes a powder like sand or dry soil
but when a little water is added then it binds together there's a coherence or a cohesion along
with the wetness of water
letting the soft moist feelings in the body
also bring a softness to the mind
maybe a unification the way water dissolves disparate things and unites
them in a solution
feeling a connection throughout the whole body
and feeling how the mind can naturally be aligned with the body
the attitude of softening and dissolving barriers
could relate to an emotional tone of
lightness given if humor or amusement
gentle gentle humor so in this meditation you're encouraged
to see the mind with lightness
perhaps simply smiling at the wandering mind
if it's wandering so connecting in with the breath the
body mindfulness
presence with how things are
setting the intention to simply stay with
things as they are stay connected
so there's a coherence and a cohesion between mind and body and heart
flow of experience
you may notice that there are various thoughts and
forces in the mind pulling away not wanting to flow along gently
or be Unified I'm reminded of Jack cornfield saying
that he named the various voices of his thoughts
he had names for the characters that appeared in his mind sometimes if one of them piped up
he would just bow internally and say thanks for your opinion
and move on
and as we settle in a bit of more we can let go of any remaining imagery
or words that we might be retaining and just
notice how experience as a flow a flow to it
and letting it flow along like a river swirling around you and passing on
passing through not getting stuck not solidifying
and also not wandering away
stream of experience just keeps flowing on if we let it
it's a bit like sitting on the riverbank stable where we are and letting it all
Flow by all through
just resting with that for a while now and so and
thank you
sometimes the river of experience as Eddies in it
and we can find ourselves swirling around and around in a little place that is not flowing on
and at that time we can smile at the mind
for its caughtness and that may gently
allow it to pass out into the current that flows again
oh
foreign
[Music] experience of
Body Sensations and impressions in the mind
when we open to that it creates a certain lightness
that's felt literally in the body
almost as if the body becomes transparent
or just simpler mind becomes
wider simpler
and there's a way that we can carry that sense forward into the day
experience flows along and changes off the cushion just as much as on
each moment different
and interaction a task that we're doing
the thought or emotion passing through as we sit with a cup of tea
always changing and flowing on and if we're open to
being with that movement letting it change letting it unfold
and bringing a certain acceptance and lightness to that
then we can offer that as a gift to the world
our willingness to just keep staying present even as things change
helps others to be less stuck less caught in fixity
tension gripping feelings that we know also in ourselves
but the degree to which we can let those go can loosen a situation
can help a challenge or difficulty can pass more
easily or simply to be with the difficulty that
isn't passing and it can add
happiness and joy that's available in a situation
where is being stuck dampens those kinds of things
so through our practice we become a
gift in the form of openness and flow and ease
passing through like water poem
May that guide us today
[Music]
so we have a different emotional flavor or tone each day of this week
based on the classical Indian rasa or savers
the Insight teacher Sylvia Borstein says that we need three things in our
practice gentleness precision and humor
so true so as we look at these flavors or
emotional tones um we can look back that Monday was love
and care which might relate to gentleness Tuesday was heroism and persistent
effort maybe the connection there to Clarity is Less Direct but it is true that we can't
see clearly if we don't make some effort to remain undistracted and to look carefully
so we have gentleness precision and humor so we've made it today today's flavor is humor
very helpful to have a sense of humor in our Dharma practice
it's even you know it's probably necessary for healing
in Dharma practice and you know especially mindfulness practice helps us to see through things if we
stick with it teasing things apart or breaking them open or differentiating
experience so that we can see different parts of it and not be fooled by the kind of solid
seeming picture that we saw at the beginning I think nearly everyone has this
experience even quite soon after starting practice and just more and more over the years where we start
with something that seems so solid so
bound up in certain ways and if we just look at it and keep turning it over
encountering it again and again it kind of breaks apart we see different pieces oh
it's not all one thing it's got these little parts so this is this process of seeing
through also called disenchantment in Buddhism nebida
that word doesn't always sound appealing but what it means is this way that we're
no longer Enchanted or Charmed into just seeing something a little bit illusory and
often solid but instead we see pieces of it we see that it's empty we see
different aspects of it the spell is no longer cast on us
so disenchantment is a positive term in Buddhist practice
and once we have some experience with seeing through something
then we gain the ability to gently poke fun at some of the mind's tricks and
also some of the wider cultures traits you know we aren't so attached to things
being a certain way we know that they're differentiated we know also that they're
often created or constructed to be a certain way because we've seen
the process in the mind of constructing them how my mind just
produced that anger or that something else
so it's very freeing to see that to see that things are not so solid they
shift and change a lot of it we're making up and so then we can smile at the antics
of the mind at least sometimes this poor silly mind
do you feel that sometimes so you know just as a simple example we
don't control what thought will arrive next who knows what the mind's going to
toss up next Gill tells a story of walking one time he was walking to IMC
from his house and he just happened to walk by a pickup truck that had a big tarp over the back
of it not such an uncommon sight but um his mind produced the thought I
wonder if there's a body under that tarp and he thought what where did that come
from who knows you know who knows why the Mind said that
so we have I think numerous instances of this during the day where the Mind
produces some thought based on sensory input and we don't know where that came
from but it's kind of amusing if we're we're open to the amusing side of him
and this can even extend you know into areas that we would consider more
serious the spiritual realm or religious culture I'm thinking now about the uh
the Dalai Lama who of course has a very uh honored
position and so the result is that when he goes to teach somewhere there's a lot of Pomp and beautiful things and you
know high up seats and all of this and sometimes you can see him laughing at
that right um he he takes it lightly but in a
skillful way you know um he he very much takes seriously his
role as the bodhisattva of compassion for our world
um but he's not caught up in that in a sense and there's a certain way that the lightness contributes to his
um his gentleness his healing his love I remember him watching him Ascend up to
a high teaching seat on some something he was going to teach and of course it was very well padded right and so he got
up there and he realized oh this is soft what they put up here for me and he
kind of bounced on it for a moment like a child might bounce on a bed and um you
could see he was just amused and delighted um right there in the middle of giving you
know setting up for a serious teaching so you know that's that kind of um
skillful likeness comes from seeing the emptiness of the world seeing through
the constructions of what we're making and creating so there's a way that you know we can
develop that skill also and I think it's actually important for our practice to have that side
there's a prayer in the Adriana practice where one asks give me energy to see
through life's illusions it's a nice wish
and there's humor in the sutras also there's a wonderful story in a text called the udana about a monk named
Nanda and it seems that Nanda was discontent
with the monastic life and he told his comrades that he was planning to disrobe
and so they went and told the Buddha who summoned Nanda and the Buddha asked him
why he was discontent and he talked about a woman
he said on departing from home a sucking woman the loveliest in the land with her
hair half combed looked up at me and said may you return soon master and he
was so smitten with her that he he just couldn't be satisfied with the monastic life
so the Buddha doesn't try to reply to this directly instead he grabs Nanda by
the arm and he transports him up to one of the heaven Realms and there Nanda
sees Saka the ruler of the Davis being attended upon by the text says 500
pink-footed nymphs um apparently this is a reference by the
way to a practice a beautification practice in Ancient India where women
would Rouge their feet we think Rouge is just for the face but they put it on their feet
so 500 pink footed nymphs and the the Buddha asks Nanda which is Lovelier
these nymphs or the socking woman that he couldn't get over and he says oh the
nymphs and so the Buddha um promises Nanda 500 pink-footed nymphs
if he will stay as a monk living the holy life and he agrees so
um of course the other monks hear about this and they tease him incessantly and
they say the venerable Nanda is living the holy life for the sake of nymphs
and he becomes very embarrassed and ashamed by this and that is exactly what
prompts him to go practice rigorously the result of which is that he gains are
a hardship you know enlightenment so at that point he has a different view
of the world he has seen through all the constructions and all the antics of his
mind and he as an aura hunt he goes back to the Buddha and he says
um about those 500 nymphs never mind
so it's a great story I think it's clear it's clear to me at least that the
compilers of the poly Canon had some sense of humor so
um you know there are more subtle indications of humor also there's a asuta where the Buddha kind of jokes
with the monks um he says to them a little bit you can almost hear the kind of the tone he says
you may well acquire that possession that is permanent Everlasting
Eternal not subject to change and that might endure as long as eternity
but do you see any such possession and amongst all say no venerable sir and so
he Praises them saying that's true I don't see any such possession either and then he goes on and says you may
well cling to that doctrine of self that would not arrive arouse sorrow lamentation pain grief and despair and
one who clings to it but do you see any such doctrine of self
no venerable sir he agrees so he you
know he seems to be gently teasing them and I think as we get more familiar with
the suit as we start to see places where there is subtle humor or irony or poking fun more of them than we might think
so you know how can we use this flavor of humor lightness Amusement in our
practice and we've already noted some but I'd like to add one more angle
so if there's something that we can't laugh about
most likely there is some identification there some kind of clinging some kind of
identity usually so we can use this negative approach what we don't laugh about to highlight
where we're clinging and then maybe we can try to bring some lightness to it
you know what we don't find funny reveals where our identity is invested it's not that everything should be
humorous but if we can't find any lightness in some area it's worth
investigating to see if there's some sticking point there
and just as we heard in the super quote a moment ago the Buddha points out that the identification is a form of
suffering you know you might find that self you can cling to that won't bring sorrow but do you see such a self
no I don't know was a boxer before he
became a monk and even when he was a well-known teacher he retained some of that kind of
a belligerent air sometimes that could come across as Gruff or blunt to people
and sometimes people took offense at him because they thought that a spiritual
teacher should be kind and gentle in a certain in a particular way
and if anyone challenged his demeanor Bajan Buddha Dasa would Roar with
laughter and he would say oh that's just my personality so
you know there's a way that humor has an important place in our practice
in the right way in a skillful way it can be done unskillfully also but it's a
key component of Dharma practice and especially when we start seeing clearly
into all the strange habits that our mind is accumulated lightness really
helps so that is our flavor for today and I hope you might find some ways in your
day today to look with lightness or smile at something
that um that you could have gotten caught up in give it a try
be well