so I would like to talk about compassion today
and it is one of the great ideals of Buddhism some people associate Buddhism
with compassion and wisdom and um and I could
I can confidently say that I I would not be sitting here
today if it wasn't for people who had compassion for me or I experienced
their compassion and if compassion experience of it struggles with it we're
not at the center of my own life it's been a very important part of shaping me as an adult as a practitioner
as even a teacher but having said that
I also would like to say because it's kind of an ideal ideals are
dangerous and um and people will often come to Buddhism for answers
and like answers to Life's big questions or answers to the personal challenges and whatever
and you know it depends on the perspective you know maybe you could say yes Buddhism has all kinds of answers
but for today I'd like to say that Buddhism doesn't provide answers
what Buddhism provides is a very clear mirror in which we can see
ourselves so we can find the answers here within ourselves
not because you thought it out you know the reason they're all out to the answers but there's something deeper
some deep seeing of ourselves that we do through Buddhist practice and so that's a very significant
statement that the answers are not in Buddhism but they're in ourselves because that's an encouragement to turn
the attention out of trying to get a PhD in Buddha studies or
the equivalent and which some people do and uh and
instead to turn the attention deeply in and and uh and and see what we discover
there so in relationship to compassion then uh compassion is not a singular thing a
singular state and uh and so but many people will think it's the singular state it just is what
they think it is it is how they've experienced it for themselves and and then when they're being compassionate
they just have one option of how to be compassionate
and but that one option might not be the best option it might not be the range of
options of what compassion can be many years ago here in this room uh when
Monday night I asked the people that um how do you know you're aware
and I it wasn't a leading it wasn't a rhetorical question I was just curious what people would say
but I was surprised by the answers and what surprised me was how wide-ranging
the answers were and I realized that I had been naive as a teacher which is or
you know somehow I also it was operating idea that I you know whatever I thought awareness was and I teach about
awareness that I assumed everyone else had the same idea and when I heard when I heard all the
different answers I was so in awe and so appreciative and so wow there's a lot of
things when I say awareness people are receiving it in different ways and maybe
each of the different ways is a good maybe because their idea is good also it works fine okay but um but so the same
thing with compassion I think there's many many ways in which people hear the word compassion have what they have in
mind uh Sharon Salzburg tells the story of um
of going to Russia and teaching in English uh with a translator
and she would use the word compassion in a talk the kind of talk maybe she would give in the United States a talk that
usually had people kind of inspired when they heard the word compassion you could you could tell by the audience
expression and when the translator translated into Russian everyone got sunk and depressed
looking [Music] and and so finally she asked you know
you know what what's this word you're translating as compassion and it I don't know what it was exactly her book that
she wrote about it and it says it but it was like maybe misery
and so the reference point for what compassion is is different and in fact the same thing is true in Buddhist
languages the word karuna or the way the words these words are translated or
understood are very different than some of these other Asian languages in the
English word compassion and if it was translated more like how people understand it I think some of us would
maybe not be so you know it wouldn't quite click for us in English speakers
so um that's a way of saying that maybe many
things are compassion but the emphasis of the talk today is uh you're welcome
to have compassion as you think it is Maybe
but uh but rather with them there's what I want to stress today is not what
compassion is but what compassion is accompanied with
so maybe the maybe there's an Ecology of our hearts our minds
and that ecology comes along with all kinds of different species or you know you know and so and maybe
compassion just one of those species and how that species operates in a particular ecology depends on the other
species are there there might be a lot of invasive species invasive species which are causing a problem
and or there might be other species that gone extinct and that causes a problem
so there's all kinds of things that might accompany compassion so what accompanies your compassion
what accompanies your care your love for for other people or for yourself and
that I think part of the kind of the opening up what is this and the other thing is um
what are some of the uh intermental activities qualities
States that contribute that's at this that are the foundation for you to be
compassionate and as I've talked I've taught recently on YouTube in 7 A.M there are different
kinds of awareness that people have just like I pointed out to the beginning that different people say different things
there's awareness but we actually have many things that could be awareness many ways in which we attend many ways in
which we have attention for different things and so if we only have one idea of what
com what awareness is then as we are aware of suffering in the
world or in ourselves that's one way of being aware might not be the best one
for the circumstance it uh maybe if you're a feeling person
only feeling compassion and identifying with compassion of
someone else might actually be harmful for you might not be actually a good thing
but if you have this idea I'm supposed to be compassionate and and this is what I think compassion is and then you get
completely disparited by it or exhausted by it the problem might not be with compassion the
problem might not be about with other people suffering is too much it might be the way in which you receive it the way
how you're aware of it so rather than emphasizing the feeling
of it you emphasize the knowing of it a little bit more cognitive that might actually create a more
balance and healthy kind of connection to suffering so the how we're compassionate what
accompanies it is part of it but before I kind of go into that more I
want to uh a wonderful I think it's a wonderful kind of etymology etymology game the root of
words
Indian word for compassion is usually uh in our scene is karuna
and that comes from the root Cur which means to make or to do
and um and so some people will see that karuna is sacred action
it's a very special kind of form of acting in the world and what I like about this is that it
involves an activity it's a creative aspect of what we do it's not it doesn't it's not about being
a victim is not what the world does to us but rather what arises emerges from us
as we meet the world so it's a kind of action of sorts of
mental action action of the heart and to see it as something that emerges
rather than something that reacts to something that we contribute rather than
something that as I said before maybe the victim of we're passively experiencing uh you know we've passively
experiencing suffering in some way and we have compassion just so it might it might arrived intuitively
it might arrive without something we make happen but still it's something that emerges in
response which might change the kind of orientation we have
about what compassion is that often too often people I think who
are troubled by Compassion or get exhausted they're allowing themselves a little bit to be the victim of it
it's happening to them rather than being centered in the place where we kind of
are the the Agents of our life or the the source of our life I like remember the agent
maybe the source of our life and as we sit in meditation
there also we're not supposed to end up becoming passive people who just kind of passively aware
it's a whole process of discovery the mirror feeling here
to let go of to shed all the unhealthy ways in which we're attached clinging
hateful unhealthy ways of being afraid and let let all that fall away
to discover that we have a capacity a wonderful Source Within
that animates us a wonderful Source within that is a source of the Sacred
action sacred kind of place of where life can our inner life how we live in the world can come from
and that the more free we are in Buddhism the more that inner source that emerges
replaces the controlling mind the figuring out mind the reactive mind and
there's something beautiful here for us to come from so compassion is this this interaction
that emerges as a response but not as a reaction
so one of the meanings of compassion is uh is to be in the presence of suffering
and I say it that way carefully so I'm not saying uh feeling suffering
empathy as wonderful as it might be also has many meanings
and sometimes empathy people interpret it I have to feel what other people are feeling
and if we're straight out equally feeling their suffering in the same way their suffering we're feeling they're
suffering the same way they're feeling it we're in trouble you know it just you know if if it's you
know it's so you know are we supposed to feel as bad as they are um no that's not the point
so for some people to feel someone else is suffering how do we ex how do we be present for it
to be attuned to it not to ignore it not to be a distance not not to kind of hold
it at Bay but to be attuned to be in harmony with it to be present for it is a very different
kind of language and experience than to feel other people
suffering now some of you might find this troubling I'm saying this and maybe your
way of feeling it just works really wonderful because I meant again there's many ways in which people feel the word
right you have to feel sorry for Dharma teachers I hope
because we have to use words and that's why you should feel sorry for
us because you know when words have definitions and definitions are
different people have different definitions for words and so we might miss you or we might be partial we can't
say it all or something so so um so you might have a wonderful way of
feeling that works fine and keeps you in Balance but it but in terms of this mirror that Buddhism is what I'm
teaching here about maybe this is a mirror for you to look the way that I feel other people suffering is that
really the best way is that being attuned to myself and others that being in
harmony with it what is it what does Gill mean by harmony with suffering so that's a good mirror to consider like
a harm I guess they're rather than just feeling what would it mean to be in harmony with it or attuned to it
and one of the things I'd like it to mean is you're not a victim of the suffering
that you're not taking on it as a burden you're not caught up in taking responsibility for
it which was has been maybe still is a little bit my Achilles heel to feel responsible I have to do
something here and it's up to me and and um and if that's what comes along
with the feeling of suffering you know feeling it at that time is not really
in the law in the big picture so healthy so to be sorry to be so part of the
definition I'd like to offer for compassion is to be in the presence of suffering
ourselves and the suffering of others and to have the aspiration
for it to end the aspiration for it to come to an end and
kind of limited that simply what's lacking in that definition of
compassion is doing anything about it the action part
so I would like to bracket that for now and and first the word compassion and
its simplest forms I would propose is to be present for suffering in some
way and have within us the aspiration for that suffering to come to an end
or to be a weekend or a lesson in some way and I use the word aspiration very
carefully as well because I'm inspired by the word aspiration more that I'm
inspired by the word the desire or even the wish rather than desire that
suffering not be there or the wish that not be there aspiration for me is part of this emergent deeper quality
I think because it's related to the word breathing and so to Aspire like respire to Aspire
comes from some place deep inside that is not reactive doesn't come from Fear
doesn't come from this kind of heady idea of responsibility doesn't come from shoulds that we've
learned from society it comes from something deep inside that
can only come when our breathing is easy and ease full breath a relaxed breath
and the um the Buddha has a there's a word in Pali that's translated as uh
Assurance to feel like to feel assured and the literal meaning of the word is
to breathe easily and meditation practice and Buddhist
practice one of the goals is to live a life where you can breathe easily
someone asks you what is meditation breathing with ease doesn't that wouldn't be that nice nice
definition so so the aspiration what comes we breathe with ease
so when you're in the presence of suffering what happens to your breathing
that's part of the ecology that's part of what accompanies compassion how you're breathing
as you breathing as you're breathing tightened up as you're breathing getting short and shallow
are you hyperventilating what what's happening with your breathing and
somehow have you lost touch with an easeful breath and you might then argue well I'm not
supposed to have an easeful breath now this is a serious thing this person's having a I'm supposed to be tense
that be careful with that assumption the reason why is be careful with the safety that you have to be tense
uh one of the reasons is so the other people think is because then other person can see that I care
one of the most significant early experiences of compassion I had was uh when someone was very close to
was almost looked like the person was going to die and there was a zen teacher who I was
standing in a courtyard a little bit and so I was explaining my situation
and this person was so relaxed and at ease hearing all this and the way I wasn't
and had the most level of compassion and understanding of what I was going
through of anybody else that I've ever ever you know talked to about it and that combination of clearly he's
understood clearly care deeply and clearly there was a kind of love present
and the person was at ease was it calm that was I'd never seen that
combination and that was one of those things that changed my life to be in the presence of that
so to um to breathe easily so aspiration where does the wish for someone not suffer
come from in you it can come from Fear it can come more for your from your own
discomfort than the discomfort of the other person this is I can't stand this you know this
is too much for me let's get you know the aspirin let's get whatever let's get
this to stop you know so I have to do something here we have to fix it you know so and that's my compassion
I can guarantee that if you're too overtly acting that way you're probably
not helping the person you're helping trying to do if you're it's mostly about yourself
so this breathing easily is the aspiration
and then then what else does it come with this being present for others what else
is there in that presence that attention the aspiration what else is there
it's not uncommon that it can come with a lot of conceit
maybe not the kind of conceit that we talk about that person's conceited but a lot of self-concern how we look to other
people you know how we appear to them and how they judge us and what they'll think of us and what I'm supposed to do
and what kind of person I'm supposed to be and you know I'm supposed to be compassionate like I don't know someone
and uh and you know so there's all this selfing all the self-identity all the
self kind of Concepts that are coming into play that are making the whole that's kind of
muddying the water agitating it all it makes it hard for the easy breathing
making it hard for it to kind of just flow into some natural way
so I think for many people this idea of self and me experiencing it me doing
something is complicated because of it's a magnet for ideas we have about what is supposed
to be a good person what it's supposed what it's like to be a bad person I'm not supposed to be
and all those things can they be shed can they be let go of
maybe not easily but if you keep doing a regular practice a meditation you'll
learn how to drop some of the all this extra baggage that we carry around so much often extra baggage around self
and so if you really want to be compassionate in this world meditate be mindful so you'll learn how
to shed concepts of self that complicate your
capacity to breathe easily in the presence of suffering
it is is does aversion arise some people are so so chronically or so
consistently have aversion in their life they don't even know they have it and so their idea of compassion is
inseparable from having some aversion it might be aversion to the suffering not the person but it's still it's there
some people's operate where it's uh with a kind of chronic or Perpetual forms of
wanting something needing something and so when there's compassion that
sense of neediness is also kind of entangled with the compassion but it's not even we don't see it because we have
no experience it's invisible to us how much we're always operating with desires all the time
and this again is why mindfulness of meditation is so helpful as we see get quieter and Stiller and and more stable
meditation what we start seeing better and better um the inner drives of aversion of
hostility of anger the inner drives of desire and neediness that might be there
and when and we see it better it's uh that's good news
most people think it's bad news it's good news because if you see it
clearly then you start becoming free of it might still be there but is that DACA
doesn't have to influence what goes on so so even just what I've said so far
is is uh explaining that a different way of being
with compassion than maybe you've ever thought about it's practicing with it is taking a
second look it's stopping with it it's something not just to assume is one thing and you have to do that one thing
and be that way but it's actually something to uh to stop and take a good look on
have him have the mirror of mindfulness really what is this what's going on when I'm compassionate
what definitions of self are complicating it what's happening with my breathing
what are the desires and aversions that are operating what are the fears that are operating with it and how do they
influence the compassion what is my confusion and doubts are there confusion and doubts in it
and um and so you know to look at this and then
on the more kind of healthy side of it which is what I talked about this last
week and at 7 A.M is um uh you know is there some
is there wisdom operating together with the compassion and the wisdom is to really look at how
we're aware look and how we're engaging to can we to recognize
oh what what are we what direction are we moving
not what's happening to me but what direction am I going here
I think there's a lot of people who over emphasize what's happening to them
as if that they have to understand it and be with it and struggle with it but in Buddhism we're often looking
where is this going in the next Second and the next minute
so if I if I really hate how if I really feel
like a aversion to my confusion around the suffering I'm experiencing
if I kind of get caught up in that aversion I have to fix things there I have to change things I better you know
whatever I can immediately with with wisdom you can immediately sense oh this is going
in a bad Direction this is going to make me more tense this is feeding aversion
If instead you see that yes I'm full of confusion but if I bring mindfulness to the
confusion yeah that's going in a better direction for the next few seconds
look at that so to bring wisdom to bear
on our compassion and the shorthand of what I thought for the last five days
is is is to have these questions where is this going right now what momentum
what how is this leaning and then by seeing clearly that we
always have one of two options we have the options to make it worse the
situation or make the situation better in some way or the other
at the minimum mindfulness makes all situations better just to be mindful of it
um distractedness not being distracted and not mindful generally makes things worse
being self-critical makes it worse being self-accepting self-loving makes it a
little bit better so that path so
is there Joy with a Compassion or is a compassion Suite I like the word sweet
again what I mean by sweet and you mean by sweet might be very different
what I mean by joy and you meet me by Joy will be different but is there something that feels really
right something that you value how you feel when you have the compassion
if you don't something is probably needs to be
fine-tuned the Attunement is not quite right the harmony is not found
it's not easy to find the sweetness of compassion
that it is possible and so if you start kind of looking at
there's more to compassion than just a singular idea compassion has these things accompanying it
and those accompaniments make a big difference so is there sweetness
is there some degree of Tranquility is there some calm with your if your
tense probably affects your breathing if you're tense probably that compassion
can't be so attuned and in harmony with the situation you're in
is there some equanimity in Equanimity here I Define as non-reactivity
doesn't mean non-responsiveness but reactivity is this kind of you know is the um is is in Buddhism reactivity
is not healthy this emergent responsiveness is a whole different animal
that we're looking for that can only really happen well when the breathing is
easy imagine that breathing in an easy way is like one of
the great keys to a good life it's a key to wisdom it's a key to
finding our way in this life but you know it's it's you know it's to
say it is so simple but to do it breathing is one of those great mirrors
we're always looking for mirrors in Buddhism to really understand because the answers are here in ourselves
and breathing is one of those mirrors so um
so all this that I'm saying today is before you act
so that was a big list of things to do Gill someone might say
that's you know you're telling me to go spend the next you know two hours going through a
checklist before I help my neighbor who's you know you know needs groceries
um I think is too but to start doing the
practices looking at using this The Compassion mirror to understand yourself better and over the days weeks months
and years you do it this will become second nature some months you'll be focusing more on
your breathing some once more in the sweetness so you know you begin finding your way with it and this is a practice
that will develop and mature your compassion over the years that you do it
and it'll become second nature and um if the person needs to go to the
emergency room don't go through the checklist of all these things don't worry about if your compassion is
off just take them to the ER and then deal with it later yourself
but um but the idea is to become wise really wise about what compassion is
so when the when the aspiration for the suffering to end
is in a time and place where you connect
you can act from a really good foundation and so maybe you become for someone else
what that zen teacher was for me turns out that what you do for the
person will change their life less than the fact that you're able to be
there in a caring loving way really present understanding
and have a deep sense of ease palpable sense of ease and that those all came together in such
a way that wow is this possible in this life and maybe you'll turn change someone
else's life maybe you managed to get them their
groceries or to the ER but how you did it
was what changed their life not that the fact that they went they had more food to eat or
the doctors you know help them out in something
so I think it's a sacred work this work of looking deeply and
practicing with our response to and our presence to suffering in the world
and our compassion our care our kindness our friendliness it's sacred work
because it's the kind of it's sacred because it has a lot to do with our
connectivity with other people how we live in the presence of others and that that bridge that those
relationships that we have you know if if that's not sacred
I'd like to know what you think is and maybe we're both right
but uh it's um it's a sacred work to uh to
find an Attunement and harmony and
aspiration in the world of compassion and suffering
may you find it for yours towards yourself may you find it towards others
and may all of us be nourished
by the sweetness of compassion thank you
so we have about five minutes before we you know scheduled ending and then I'm going to go up to pretty
quickly after that to set up for this community meeting we have but if any of you would like to have a
comment or a question about any of this especially if you feel like you'd feel unsettled without asking it
oh you have a testimonial about compassion
hey um could you provide the poly word for Assurance and breathing easy again
it's the poly word you know it's it's I don't think I have it accurately anymore but I think
it's asada I think
foreign actually reminded me of something that
just happened in the last year my father-in-law had a heart attack and my
husband of course was distraught over it and
he lives in India so of course you can't do anything right away like you can't
hop in a car and go see your father-in-law to make sure things are taken care of
but that's of course what my husband wanted to do was like find the flight and like let's go as quickly as possible
and I said wait just take a deep breath even if we get a flight right now it
won't leave till tomorrow so just take a deep breath let's assess the situation let's just take a moment
to you know figure out one do we need to go right now maybe we can if he's stable
we can leave in a week and we'll go see him and it'll be okay you know
um anyway a lot of things ended up happening we didn't end up going to India but uh the point was just being
able to just take a moment to calm before rushing to do this that and the other
thing really helped ensure that we didn't just react out of
you know compassion instead we and you had and you had enough come to offer him
a different perspective so he could kind of relax yes yes I wish you'd been around me sometimes in my life
I mean I've had times in my life you know I remember it's been a good I think good number of years ago now but where I
reacted you know and acted quickly and the Recently I was reminded that um
of this I I once called the fire department and they came
because I didn't take a second look I just that paused long enough to take a
second and look but I would have realized it was when nothing was needed
so um so last one and if you can take the mic
pushing this lady raise is a very important one to me uh I wonder if the
kind of situation they were facing was it Compassion or was it programmed response that you were supposed to do a
certain thing you certain way because we all face that it was a little bit slower so the programmed response yeah as
opposed to compassion a program a program response I suppose is acting on
habit or on on policy that we have that we see from our
society this is what you're supposed to do exactly yeah yeah so I think that uh you know if we keep
using this mirror of mindfulness to look at ourselves hopefully we'll recognize what's driving our
and if it's a program if it's a should um then I I put I would put that in the
category of reactivity because it's a kind of a surface response that comes from the the concepts ideas of what we
have and um and I would take the time then and really delve settled more deeply in
and see if there's a deeper source for for the compassion what could be either
or it could be combination of it too yeah thank you thank you okay so so
again so one of the things that I did in this talk I think is to
I distinguished or separated out um the aspiration
that someone to wish that someone suffering ends from our acting on it
it doesn't have to be so separate but by distinguishing them and separating them it's an encouragement to pause and
settle back and wait and see where the where the action might come from
and and in that looking more deeply it's a whole Ecology of what what is
accompanying what you call compassion and you might discover there's a lot there that's worth taking into account
and practicing with and before you act so thank you very much
and um