hello hello everyone my name is Maria stratman I've been here this week for Gill
it's been a delightful week for me thank you all for being here
what we've been talking about this this week is began from a place of how do we deal
with self-criticism silk blame
and so we've been spending the week thinking about what what gives rise to self-blame and
self-criticism and how can we cultivate the state of blamelessness
the state where we are not turning against ourselves and constantly criticizing what we do at the same time
as we are doing our practice and living our lives with all of the fullness that
is inherent in that so we talked about the effective impermanent impermanence the
unsatisfactoriness of things because they arise and pass away cannot be dependent upon
we talked about judgment the effect of judgment and how judgment and comparison
drives us to think something less of one thing over another less of ourselves
over another less of ourselves over an ideal we talked about doubt the effect of
doubt that doubt undermines everything it clouds everything it is it's like
walking in fog and then we talked about forgiveness
which is really the act of not placing blame not placing blame
that condoning or excusing but not placing blame
not denying the effect of impermanence and today what I'd like to talk about it
turns out I have 15 minutes to talk about three different topics which is clearly not going to happen so I'm going
to try to limit to to something that makes sense when I was in my late 20s I
went to work for an engineering firm I was a chemist I was also the only woman
uh so I was the only chemist I was the only woman in a
outside of the the accounting office and the and the uh the secretaries in the
front office and I I was very confused about who I
was and how I fit into this very heavily Machinist
environment that I existed in and one day a painter came up to me and he said
I am totally confused by you so this was someone had just come in to paint he said some days you are you're like this
you're wearing a tie-dye you look like a you look like a hippie you have a T-shirt and jeans and and then some days
you have a suit on who are you
and that has stuck with me you know who are you who are you is it accumulation of all
kinds of things all kinds of aspects of yourself all kinds of conditions that you find
yourself in whoa am I is changing all the time
all the time so I don't wear tight eyes as often as I used to though do I remain
very attached to them for enlivened by them
the colors and the brightness but I also have days when what seems appropriate is
the closed in quietness of just black and that these colors reflect attitudes
changing pieces of myself things that I need to see
and I've given up the habit of it needing to be a certain way
because here's the thing our suffering depends not on
having things the way we want them but seeing things just as they are
just as they are and not expecting them to be a certain way
even though it's very human to expect things to be a certain way but to see when that's what's operating
seeing things clearly seeing things clearly leads to non-blame
leads to blamelessness to see that
suffering co-arises with wanting things to be other than they are
I want more of this I want less of this I want you to be this way I want this
conditions to be that way all of this wanting
and not being happy unless what we want is realized
this this is what leads to suffering so how do we get to the point where we
can really see things clearly where we're not confused by our the views that
we bring into the moment or the attitude that we have when we get up in the morning or whether we're wearing a
tie-dye shirt or or a suit not to be confused by this
but to just see this is what's happening this is what's happening
this is what's happening
because our suffering depends on seeing things clearly checking in with our intentions
and then taking the next step that's all we have control over is just the next step
what operates from Our intention so if we have in our hearts ill will
irritation anything that that creates tension and
ugliness in in our lives if that's what we're feeding that's what's going to feed into this moment
that's the condition of this moment that's what I can see I can see
my being angry with that person or being upset with that person and really
wanting not to be I really don't want to carry that into the future I heard Gill say one time something that
was just absolutely wonderful he said if you can't let go of the ill will at least notice that you're a person who
wants to let go of the oh well this is a softening of the heart
I want to let go of that I want to let go of it just that very Act is shifting
the small shift is what makes a difference that's what changes everything
that's what changes everything I want to but only if you want to
and that's the part about seeing clearly that's the part about seeing clearly
being in touch with our intentions means noticing what our intentions are we have Global intentions
I have the intention to be open-hearted I'm not always open-hearted but it is my
overwhelming attention and sometimes I will find myself
that person cut me off on the freeway and I'll feel myself
feel the anger if they go into my body I feel my my belly tightened I feel the adrenaline rising in my body and then I
notice that all of that's happening and I say yes but yes but
and then I see it isn't that this is a bad person that's not what's happening what's
happening is I was startled I was frightened by someone pulling in front of me in the freeway
oh that's what was happening now I go to oh
I want to be safe I want everyone to be safe and suddenly I've gone from the ill will
to May everybody on the freeway be safe
including this driver who may not have had evil intentions when he cut me off
maybe it was the last chance he had to get off the freeway and he didn't know where he was
but I don't have to make those conditional statements about this person I can just change what's happening in me
I can notice I don't want to go there and see that there's something else that
act of noticing I don't want to go there I don't like this feeling this is uncomfortable allows us to see something
else because we're not spending our time justifying that ill will when we don't
spend the time that way we don't use the precious time that way we have time in
that moment to see something else to see something else is happening
to give space for uh I just wanted to be safe
we live in a world where bad stuff happens
now we can say that if everybody was good bad stuff wouldn't happen but somehow I don't think so good and bad
being comparative terms what's good for me may not be good for you and what's bad for me may not be bad for you
and there are gradations all along the Spectrum
so what do we do when we discover a family member is hurting themselves
they're lost in alcoholism or drugs and we care about them and we see very
clearly if they just did this it would be so simple
or receive for ourselves why can't I do this why can't I stick to this plan why can't I always have in
mind kind speech why is this happening because it happens
it doesn't have to have the meaning that someone is at fault that someone is
blameworthy
nor does it mean that we excuse deliberate actions of ill will that's not necessary
but it turns out that taking responsibility for everything in life being wonderful
is a large part of suffering and what can we do about that what we
can do is try to arrive at the place where we say okay I my intention is to see
clearly so my route to this at one time I felt
uh totally destroyed by how alienated I had
become from my family over something that had happened something that I did in response to something
and it was roundly not everybody in my family condemned it their their life I
have eight siblings so there are lots of people with lots of voices
but I did something that I felt was essential that was important for me and to not support bad behavior
and uh I was not well liked in my family as a
consequence of doing this and I I was plagued by that I went off on a month-long retreat at
the forest refuge and I told Joseph Goldstein oh I have this really problem this great problem you know my family's
so disappointed in me and and I know I'm right and and he said ah I know what you can do he
seemed so excited he knew just what to do and he told me to do Equanimity practice
so which I never really practiced before so what I did was take a few phrases a few
standard phrases and I will try to give you those phrases let me see I'll put
them here I'll put them in chat and if maybe Kevin
can you put them or or in
in on YouTube okay there are the phrases
all right so they are I am heir to my own Karma
my suffering or lack of suffering depends on my own intentions and actions
not what others may wish or what I may wish
despite what I may wish things are as they are
may I see things just as they are
may I meet the arising and passing away of all things with Equanimity and
balance so for this month on Retreat every time
I did walking meditation I repeated these phrases in my head
that's thousands of times I just repeated these phrases over and
over again I would occasionally insert that opening through the dhamapata which is easier for me to see the route of
karma than to just refer to Karma so I don't want to get off on what does karma mean
but just that I am heir to my own attitudes and conditions that I create
not what others may wish or what I may wish and you can say this for others as well
despite what I may wish things are as they are
their happiness depends on their own intentions and actions not what I may
wish for them and over time after after about two
weeks I came to the place where I realized
my suffering is the result of my actions and my intentions
that's it it comes home right there
right there my happiness is caused by my not accepting my mind
being unwilling to see things just as they are
so I offer these phrases to you they've been life-saving for me they've allowed me to continue
reevaluating my entry point to the moment
for evaluating where am I now despite what I may wish things are as
they are let me see them clearly let me see them bright as they are
what's happening for me now what's the energetic state in my body how am I feeling where in my body am I feeling
that rest in the here and now and don't get pulled off into the story
don't get pulled off into the story just here and now
just this
is another Jane hirschfield poem from the same book that I seem to be hooked on this
week the book is ledger the name of the poem is you go to sleep in one room and wake
in another you go to sleep in one room and wake in another
you go to sleep in one time and wake in another men land on the Moon
viewed and blurred black and white and static on a big screen in Central Park
standing in darkness with others your grandfather did not see this
your grandchildren will not see this soon no 50 years back
unemphatic the wheelbarrowed Stars hung above
many days like a nephew resemble the one beforehand but they are not the one beforehand
each was singular spendable eaten with pepper and salt you go deep in one
person's bed and wake in another go sleep in one person's bed and wake in another your face after toweling changed
from the face that was washed you go to sleep in one world and wake in another
you who were not your life nor were stranger to it you who were not your
name your ribs your skin will go as a suitcase that takes inside it the room
only after you know this can you know this and a knock glass that loses what has
been spilled you will know this only after you know this will you know
this my saying it you're hearing it doesn't do it once you know
then you know and it's always with you
may we all see clearly may we all see what is before us and what we are part
of to see it not as meaningful but in the being of it
may you be in this moment and be free thank you for your time thank you thank
you so I'm open to questions comments
hey thank you Maria we've got uh Layla from YouTube she asked
um I guess you had an earlier comment this week uh related to around judgment lies all
Buddhism so that sounds Gloria she said she she
uh was hoping that you'd elaborate on that I don't quite remember saying that but
but I might have because I don't plan everything I say
so uh um apparently I was thinking about
Buddhism as being uh [Music] it's one of the four noble truths of
Buddhism being that suffering exists suffering arises we can see this is the
cause of suffering this is what leads to suffering this is what leads to the end
of suffering and in that process that that realizing that things arise and pass
away and that we have some effect on whether we choose the rising of
suffering or the ending of suffering and that judgment is the place that very often we go astray and instead of saying
uh this is what gives rise to suffering and then stopping
vowing not to do that again we get lost in
establishing blame for for what has happened by ourselves or others and we
get lost in the story and we forget to just look at ah this gives Rises to suffering this end suffering when when
the Buddha was instructing his son who had done some horrible thing he turned over a monk's Bull and um so the monk
didn't get to eat that day and instead of castigating his son and telling him how wrong it was he said you know rahua
this is it this is all of it before during and after any action
think does is this causing suffering for me for you for either of us if it's
causing suffering stop if it's not causing suffering
cultivated this is Buddhism
and requires seeing really clearly so I'm not sure exactly what I was
thinking at the time Layla but I hope that answers your question that's how I relate to it now
thank you Maria also if people want to raise their hand in Zoom um
please go feel free to do so or you can post your question in chat uh kind of like a follow-on question that happened
in uh YouTube was how does one see clearly when I was from Marlene
yeah yeah so the seeing clearly has to do with not taking the first piece of
information you get like that person hurt me by running over in
front of me in their car by tearing in front of me but to say
if I let go of that string of that story what else is true now and so it's a
process of just saying well I'm a little scared and noticing that shakiness
noticing that shakiness and not causing that calling that shakiness more about
anger well yes I'm shaking in Anger no I'm shaking I'm just shaking what does
that does that have to signify what the Mind
automatically goes to so it's a process of over time learning one's mind habits
what does my mind do when I get shook last night I was sitting uh having
dinner with our family and the the dog was under the table and I didn't realize
she'd crawled over close to my chair and and suddenly she stretched and her claw
hit the side of my foot that with my sandaled foot and I leapt up and everybody said what's wrong and I said I
didn't leap up but I jerked up and people said what's wrong I said oh it's nothing I was just startled
okay never underestimate if you're startled you're startled it doesn't have to mean
oh that crummy dog shouldn't be under the table just notice oh I'm startled that's how
you get to don't be in a hurry to name something naming something is very useful in
meditation but not so much if you're just trying to see what else is here
because whatever you name something creates a story
so it just leave space thank you
thank you and you can go ahead and unmute yourself I am
hello Maria hello everybody I'm going to be a cheerleader for Maria but because I
just thought this week was terrific and secondly that the lines that did you say
they were from Mr Goldstein um so you told me those lines about 10
years ago and I have to say it was an amazing turning point for me and it has
opened up a whole world of looking at myris you know conditioning as part of
my responsibility as opposed to selfing myself um and I just hi And I memorized them at
the time you said them to me and I use them almost every day to just ground me
so I recommend them really highly to everybody it's it's it's just it just
brings you right back to the essence of this moment and it does really help with
that tendency to blame that because you're seeing conditioning as part of it
and anyway blah blah so thank you Maria for everything and I just I'm a cheerleader for that those lines that
you passed on thank you
it came from YouTube asked Maria are there any suggestions for working with
tight areas in one's body EG tightness around the heart area which
occurs with me often [Music]
though um
so the natural thing is to want that typist to go away I would want it to go
away and when I noticed that tightness rather than trying to think of ways to
ease it I focus on
the tightness as the the core of
the rawness in me this is the place where that
that I feel the physical pla pain of whatever my emotional state is
and in seeing that I empathize with myself
I see it oh you're trying so hard
and in that in that shift to oh I see you're trying so hard
there is a a shift to compassion for oneself
and that being able to empathize and see clearly oh that's painful not not
pitying but oh I see that I see that in you softens the heart
it isn't in that moment going to just change everything but it is a gradual seeing
oh there's there's tightness here it is
does it feel like a crushing tightness does it feel like a stretched tightness
does it can I see something else about this tightness other than it's tight does it
feel protective does it feel over extended does it feel
camouflaged does it feel like it's hidden from B I was very aware at one time I I had the
the reason I talked so much about an open heart is that when I first began meditating I became very aware of how
protected my heart was and I literally imagined it with a brick
wall and iron gates in front of it it was it was a formidable formidable
structure and first the gates kind of opened a
little bit but the wall was still there that brick wall was still there
and then one day it wasn't there anymore but it's a gradual crumbling so so I
don't know the nature of the of the the tightness in your heart
but never underestimate that some of the tightness can come from over efforting and trying to break it loose
and sometimes what's required is to just say May the tightness in my heart relax and
then you'll notice sometime yeah so one of the breakthroughs for me was suddenly recalling that when my dog
had cancer and had they they just sewed you back up and they tried to give her some
some drug to ease her pain and it was she had a uh the obvious opposite
reaction to which became very agitated and I went and I climbed into the cage with her and I thought anybody that will
climb into a dog cage to comfort the dog is not heartless
so I couldn't see it for myself but I could see it in another way
so so don't give up on yourself the way to work on it is to befriend yourself
befriend yourself be your own grandma
thank you Catherine you can go ahead and unmute
hi Maria thank you it's been so helpful this week I'm really really grateful
um I want to just name what I find to be the
particular challenge of like chronic conditions that
feel like they lead to a lot of suffering like for myself I'm on day eight of a migraine and they and I live
with chronic pain all the time but then sometimes it it flares and on you know
day two I'm like okay Equanimity okay let me observe but there is something
that happens as for me um as the as the these conditions that are
very painful continue that's something it gets harder it gets tiring these
intentions get harder to hold the perspective clear perspective gets
harder to hold and at the same time it gets easier to start to blame myself for
the conditions am I air what have I been doing that has caused this Karma which
is awful um and I'm speaking this because I think many of us live with
um causes and condition or conditions or experiences that don't just change and
it's very easy I think for the mind to be like okay do I believe in
impermanence when it's been 30 years of intense pain
um so and then starting to be like well then it must be my fault that I can't
just keep continually coming to the present moment and seeing it afresh when
it seems so repetitive so I I know that compassion I know the like basic
approaches here it's just hard and um any any sort of support and boosting
um for those of us in similar situations I would be grateful for thank you
oh I'm sorry I'm sorry for all your suffering really they the um
Buddhism is not a bolster against pain only the additional thing
ourselves for that pain so um so so
once again I think the the the the Refuge the the place of Refuge is to
befriend oneself and to realize that this this is painful
and unlike other instructions around mainefulness it is not useful to
concentrate on that pain is that useful it is just there it's rather like ate in a restaurant the
other night and well walked in and the noise was so loud all those surfaces were hard and it was so loud it just
hurt my ears and after about 10 minutes I was no longer noticing it was still loud but I just wasn't my awareness had
kind of moved on whereas if I had focused on that loudness it never would have improved it would always have been
very very very very loud now that's not the same thing as the pain from a migraine which I understand is
overwhelming or can be overwhelming and so when one is faced with overwhelming
business this is what's true In This Moment the condition is overwhelming to
to admit to oneself this is overwhelming and despite everything I am still here
there's a sort of reinforcement of the confidence that comes from saying I am
still here here I am with all the things that are true
it may feel like this is killing me but it hasn't I'm here
I'm here wounded weary
and undaunted by that woundedness and that weariness
we do this in the presence of grief we do this in the presence of of
catastrophe all sorts of catastrophes that happen in life
and when we feel like there's nobody else to blame it must be my fault that I can't overcome this
existence is not about overcoming anything but to just be here and say ah
damn that hurts and then to let that go not to stay with
that story not to stay with one's awareness in that place it's not I'm not
saying to divert one's attention but merely then to notice something else
to light a candle to look outside and see something that pleases you
and know that that's here too not instead of two
there are some recordings on Audio Dharma on how to deal with chronic pain
and those teachers are maybe more useful to you than I am but
so you know you you could go you can go to our click on Audio Dharma and you can
get you can search by topic or you can search by teacher
you know so if you went there you could go to the menu for teachers and you'd
get you know all of the things if you put in my name you get all of the things that I've recorded over the last 15 plus years
so there's lots of resources there that you might find useful and uh and as
Friedman has done a lot of uh really lovely things on the subject of pain
thank you so much okay Theresa you can unmute
my Teresa hi Maria um I have a quick question yesterday you said that there were some openings on
the group um sessions and I went there after
um yesterday and um there was nothing left and
I I'm having trouble getting to that site the genus genius sign up site
through IMC I can do the individual ones but I I'm
having trouble finding the group one but yesterday I found it except there wasn't any more slots left no they went very
quickly okay um so I used to do more sessions but uh
it was oh I've I've cut back a little bit on
the number of sessions so okay well don't they open up each month oh
and the other thing they do they open up uh they're on a rotating basis and they right now I've set them to three weeks
in advance because and I used to do three a week and now I'm doing just one extra every other week so oh and on the
number that are available so I might change that in the future but that's how it is right now because I'm quite busy
app is fine um okay all right so so and yeah and and
the way to get to those though is through IMC there is there must be a
link in IMC to those sign ups yes there is yeah okay
and um the other thing I would say is check back because people often when I
mentioned that there were slots the the this Saturday's group was full and then two two people canceled and you know
shortly before sometimes those those positions open up okay thank you
so Roni thank you Maria um I think I want to clarify something
in my mind which I'm a little confused by when I am struggling with judgment or
inability to forgive to find that Equanimity It's mighty hard
and I think usually I would end up going to some form of compassion practice to
offer myself that um I I maybe in my mind right now I'm
not sure where to look at that going to look for Equanimity when I'm so stuck in my pattern can you offer some advice
on that so um so
on the on the practice of on say do loving-kindness practice meta
practice uh it it can be useful to use it to soften your heart not not to sort of
repair what's going on but as a as when you when you find rigidity being established I can't let go of that
I just can't let go of that then sometimes a meta practice will just for
yourself not for others just for yourself wishing yourself well wishing
yourself well will will do that little shift I mentioned before where you can shift
from from the all that heavy effort to just
I'm not really trying and there's a there's a kind of letting go and a
little relaxation of breath the the thing is when in the Dharma Pata
where the phrases I read yesterday about a hatred only Ends by non-hatred that
that's usually often has been translated or uh hatred Never Ends by hatred but by
Love Alone does hatred end but we don't have to go so far as to
love what's causing us pain and suffering we just have to stop hating
and so it's the letting go of the story so every time I hear myself justifying
well yeah I'm mad because or I hear myself say oh you always do or any of
those triggering things that are the messages in my brain I I say I I relax
that story I'm not going to keep telling that story sometimes I stop in the
middle of a sentence it's so it's so familiar to me and and it's repeating in
my head I'll stop in the middle of the sentence and just say I don't have to say that I know the source of that pain I don't
have to tell myself about it so that it it steps down from
both having to defend how I feel the rigidity
I feel to saying this is this is where it is and to and to rest and even I wish
I could let go of it to this there's there's a place where one finds refuge
in resting in one's good intentions it's not giving up it's not saying it's
okay it's not excusing but it's it's seeing very clearly
how how much one wishes to be free
of the the curse of not being able to lay it down now yesterday Susie reacted to my saying
refusing to let go of because she'd never heard me say that before
it's recognizing that sometimes that harm that we have received has become a
familiar partner and feels somehow right it's that making it part of me
and the refusal is not overt or conscious it's just oh yeah just what I
was expecting the the familiarity of a chronic issue
the feeling how familiar it is not your friend
you have to notice oh I'm becoming I'm becoming used to this has this
become a habit as opposed to how I'm reacting to what's
happening right now so the closer you can get to just what's happening now the
closer you can get to seeing things clearly and to realize that that what you think about it the opinion you have
about what's happening is not What's Happening Now what's happening now is the pain of that opinion
does that help kind of consider it just see if that opens anything for you
hey Maria well thank you for your teaching this week I think that's pretty much everything all the questions and
raised hands so thank you very much thank you everyone