so
um so today I want to talk about a topic which may or may not be
popular and uh that that topic is Faith and uh some people love this topic
some people just the word of it raises a raises alarm for them
and I do hope that in the course of the talk uh the talk will be inspiring
something in you and and there's a number of steps that we're going to go
through the first is going to be um something that maybe isn't so popular
but uh is linguistic what word are we talking about what do we mean when we use the
word faith and um but the important aspect of this is that part of Buddhism the
engagement for for people who don't speak poly didn't grw up with this ancient Buddhist
language part of the as we try to understand this tradition there's a part
of it that we get to make for ourselves we get to understand and construct the
part of Buddhism that's really personal personalize the religion some very deep and important way and there's a part of
it if you want to be engaged in Buddhism it's not something you you it's your personal opinion your personal whe you
know whatever you'd like it to be that's what you make it up there is something which has some Integrity to it which is
Buddhism but what is that so what is it that you get to make up personalize in
some very important way and what is it that you can't quite personalize and still call it Buddhism so that's part of
the Journey of this talk uh as we go into this word
faith so begin with a story that uh before when the Buddha
before he was Buddha when he was gotama in the seek out and is seeking for
awakening for the end of suffering he practiced with different teachers and uh he perfected what they
had to teach and they actually wanted him to be a teacher in their system and he said no this is not it
yet and but he made this very interesting statement he said um my
these teachers I have they have a certain Faith they have faith and I have
faith so I think I can go off and do it in myself by myself but he wasn't enlightened yet
there was no Buddha in the world yet to have faith in there was no Buddhist teachings to have faith in there was he
he used the word faith that's something he had and um and so it wasn't a belief in
something but it was a confidence in in something is it was it in himself was it
in something that wasn't quite himself what was it that he meant by the word
faith the the word he's using in P is Sada and srit some of you who Indian
background maybe know it more as Shada and um and so what is it that this
how is it how do we translate this word into English some translators do not use the
word faith often for good good reason and uh and the most common one
they use is confidence sometimes people use the word trust those are the three kind of
primary words but the word faith in English has a wide Rich uh range of meanings some of
them which have wonderfully evocative emotional qualities to it heartfelt qu qualities that the word confidence
doesn't have confidence as a as important as it is um I it from I think
for most people doesn't necessarily evoke some deep feeling of heartfelt trust or something really kind kind of
inspiring in the heart confidence is good but um and um so so the the other word
that's often associated with faith in English is belief now what's fascinating about the
word belief is that in its history it comes from it comes from the word to
love Leaf in Old English and in German me meant to love and Scholars of ancient
of middle age middle medieval religion say that there was no questioning
whether you believed or didn't believe in God in 10th Century 12th century Germany or
France or some place like that it was just taken for granted but when you said you believed in God
what you were saying you love God and you know there a different feeling there's here this is what this
is where I put my love and uh so to believe not as a Act
of just Credence like okay they I have to believe these in English you know I have to kind of now accept these
teachings as being true that's not the that's not maybe what the original idea of belief is but
this is where I put my love so if faith and belief are related
is there something about faith that this is what I this is where I put my love my this is where I put my heartfelt
feeling of value and appreciation and Delight is in
something we use the word faith in many fascinating ways I think in
English uh uh keep the faith asso partly means that keep the
commitment keep your appreciation of something keep going with it being
faithful to something means don't betray it being faithful in marriage don't don't betray it be stay to the
commitment it's more than having confidence you you lose something if you
keep translating Sada as confidence you lose a sense of Love or commitment a
certain loyalty Fidelity uh is uh is a
related to the same Roots Latin roots as faith is related but it means that means
kind of a loyalty the faith that we keep Loyals they committed I uh the way that I all these
words have different meanings for every individual different associations there's an expression in
English uh a person of faith and for me that just makes me happy when I hear
that phrase for other of you probably it frightens you so so all depends on the
associations we have right and so for me the person of faith is someone who holds
certain fundamental values of goodness it is not about what they believe but
rather that they're ethical a person of faith I expect a certain high level of
of of moral goodness that the how they go through the world I think of them as someone who's more gentle not assertive
not domineering uh kind of a gentle kind of willingness to be of service from their
love so what does the what do these words mean for you and that's where you
get to make it up you get to take the word ancient word Sada very important word in Buddhism and
decide for yourself what is the word that you would like what English word
works for you that inspires you that's meaningful for you that is useful for you to have if if you translating as
faith is not useful for you don't translate it that way if these you know
well-meaning Buddhist teachers use the word faith just code
switch and just okay you know that person said Faith so I'm going to use
confidence the teachers who like to use confidence for Sada want to really want to emphasize
practicing you want to have confidence that this is something you can do and so
just like learning any kind of skill you it helps to have confidence in learning that skill so Buddhist practice involves
developing skills and so emphasizing the confidence side means okay I can do it
I'm going to engage some people like trust there are
plenty of times in my Buddhist career where I prefer to translate sada's trust
there was something profound that I really really felt like I could rest in or rely on that really would support me
and one of the primary things that I trust fundamentally uh that's come from doing
this practice is mindfulness itself it's not a belief but it's a capacity that I
have it's a practice or a capacity a way of being that I just trust more than
anything else because it's it's proved reliable over and over again and then there's word belief and
now that you know that belief at least originally meant to love maybe you want to translate Faith as something to do
with love uh faith is where we put our heart
in so it's heartfelt or what we weren't willing to put our heart in and let our
heart rely on so in the ancient tradition in Buddha
Faith was more a quality of personality of character more than a faculty that we
have more than an action that we do so again it's pointing to something deeper
than many of the ways we think about and we think about you know having faith in something but rather a fa a faculty that
we have that we can awaken and what is that what would it be for you so this is
a part of Buddhism you get to make up for yourself personalize and the meaning of these
words words and how we play with them and so some of you have been around my teachings long enough and probably more
than I should someone will ask a question and I'll say well that depends on what you mean by the
word and uh because then we want that's a way of being careful and respectful for people because otherwise we might
miss each other because we might have different definitions of the word and if we specify what we mean I think it's
much more we can find our way together so this word
Sada so um um so when the Buddha before he
awakened Saidi have S and that that g gave him the trust the
faith the confidence the love to go off and practice also another story that Buddha
tells before he was awakened was um uh how he dealt with
fear he had fear isn't that nice to know some some of you probably have occasional
fear anxiety and stuff and so the Buddha did it as well and he had to practice with his fear uh that's was something he
had to contend with and um and the
um many of the Buddhist practitioners in his time went off into the forest to
practice alone and some fell came along to the Buddha and said well it's frightening to go into the forest and
practice isn't it isn't too frightening to be able to practice you can't get concentrated in the forest and the
Buddha said well actually before I was awakened I went into the forest too and
practiced but before I did I checked check checked myself out to make sure
that I was prepared for that and he said do I have any sensual desire that's
going to make it difficult to be in the forest alone like if you're lusting after a person in the forest all the
time that's it's not you're not going to get concentrated so do I have any sensual desire no do I have any ill will any
resentments left over no do I have any resistance do I
have any uh uh ways in which I'm caught in my fear Frozen in my fear
no do I have any agitation or regrets
no do I have any doubt no anybody who anybody who has these
things would probably be afraid when they go into the forest then he makes interesting
statement um do I have any the word is uh in English um alarm or
Terror uh maybe you know he's not he's not an alarmist so you know some people
get alarmed by all kinds of things and um but he said no I don't I'm
not an alarmist and I don't get terrorized by things so what he means by that I don't
know it's kind of interesting so what he's doing is checking himself out and
maybe if he had those things he realized these have I have to work through these first so he'd go to a
therapist you know if he was in modern America who can be very helpful for some
of these things when they're really really difficult but you know work through it
or come and start basic meditation practice because that's a lot of what we're working through at some point he was ready to go
into the forest and in fact he was afraid it just
kind of a delightful little I think description of his
fear on on especially auspicious nights
I dwelt in awe inspiring horrifying abodes as Orchard shrines Woodland
shrines and tree shrines and while and while I dwelt
there a wild animal would come upon me or a peacock would knock off a
branch or a wind would rustle the leaves I remember sometimes backpacking
in this was here as by myself no one no one around for Miles dark in my little tent and there
were monsters walking crunching the leaves around what are
these monsters doing around here crunch crunch CL snap and um you know if I was
awake and it was daytime I I you know I would rustling of the leaves would not
do anything for me but when in the dark in the s there were times where I
couldn't sleep so uh but what he does list the
footnote in the talk so what he does how he deals with his fear in practicing alone in the dark in these frightening
places was whatever posture he was in he stayed in that posture and was mindful
present for that and somehow staying present for it not giving into it not running away not
collapsing around it staying with it and in a dignified way somehow he worked
through it he doesn't go into the details here but it's kind of that he was prepared he was ready at this point
in his life to sit or be really present for fear when it
arose but you saw he was prepared right so are we prepared for
it so uh so the that the that this was
important is not a coincidence that they checked himself out you saw what was uh
what he had worked through and what he didn't have is not a coincidence for what Buddhism is about the part of
Buddhism that you're not supposed to change the part of Buddhism if you want into Buddhism you have to kind of accept
as being very important and now we come to the topic of of Faith Sada again that
um the the uh uh emotional qualities the Buddha
Associates with faith you get a sense of what it's about is
calmness Clarity and
um and confidence confidence Clarity and
confidence so those are kind of the associated terms it's it's not it's not to be
Zealot it's to be peaceful some it helps you be profoundly
peaceful so what is it that that does that and so to to to reach this level
and there's different levels of Faith but this level of Faith that's really
confident and now there's going to be a Fidelity to it there's a loyalty there's a commitment to something which is more
than a belief something in a sense that maybe even in a sense more than the usual me
that you identify with not transpersonal exactly but not
necessarily personal either something that maybe is in you but which is not who you think
you are what what could that be to have faith in that to have confidence in
that so um and this is the core confidence that uh you know the core
kind of confidence that the Buddha really is pointing that it's possible for us to experience and grow in this
practice so this is going to be a little bit
boring so you know you're forewarned but it's also going to be
phenomenally important and I hope by the time I
finish this talk this is going to inspire you to no end so be patient with
the boredom but listen to this listen to it as if it's a guided
meditation where the key words are pointing something deep inside of you a
possibility something that if you really could do this in a thorough way would be
transformative you don't have to believe anything there's no Creeds to have faith
in and some of you are going to think this has nothing to do with religion and I came to Buddhism it's a
religion and this is like what you you fill in the
blank and some of this language you're not going to like some of you so you're forward you know this is
like you know caution this is the caution
statement there are these imperfections that defile the
mind some of you don't like the word defile and uh but I remember you get to
make up parts of your Buddhism and what you can make up to some within certain
range is how you how you translate these words into
English and I wouldn't translate it as defile that's what this book this this
um but anyway there are these imperfections that defile the
mind ctiv and unrighteousness unrighteous
greed is an imperfection that soils the Mind ill will soils the Mind anger soils
the Mind resentment contempt insolence Envy avarice deceit fraud obstinacy
rivalry conceit uh arrogance vanity and negligence are
imperfections that defile the mind what a glist did you get
bored no no it's exciting edge of your
seats okay so there's a it's 17 things that he says soil the
mind so now imagine a world where humans didn't have
this imagine really knowing and trusting someone you know who has none of
this imagine that would that be like imagine if this was actually the
common denominator of all religions of all political
parties of all isms was let's not have let's not be
Covetous let's not have greed let's work through our ill will and our anger let's
not have resentment and contempt let's find a way not to be insolent Envy envious acious deceitful
fraud full obstinate uh
rivalry conceit arrogance vanity negligence wow what if that was the
common denominator we all shared wouldn't it be a different world I propose that there would be a
revolutionary change in our societies if we all agreed yes
we're not going to argue what you believe we're not going to be opposed to what your political stance you have all
those things provided we all agree on this
WOW wouldn't that be good so these are the things that soil
the mind the Buddha said but then and this is the exciting
part of the boredom um
knowing that Covetous covetousness and greed is an imperfection that soils the
mind a person abandons it knowing ill will one abandons it
knowing each of these Seven Things One abandons it so that's pretty
good but then comes even the better part once once it's been
abandoned then you have a mind you have a heart in which those things are not
present when a practitioner has known that
covetousness and greed has been abandoned when the practitioner knows
ill will has been abandoned anger knows the absence of these things
knows the absence of resentment and envy and hostility and rivalry and really
knows that absence but knowing is not an abstract cognitive idea that's gone what's the
heart experience what's the embodied experience what's the Mind experience of
not having that agitation the contraction the pressure of these kinds
of forces when they're operating in us what's that absent
like wow that is peaceful that's settled that's a relief
wow I've known people who've had resentments for years and years I've
known people who've Decades of their policy of how to live is to be angry They Carried with them the whole
time I've known people who for decades have had desire greed be the driving
force of their life what a relief to finally have these kinds of powerful
forces not operating to know this possibility for
oneself to have experienced that kind of Peace
this is what provides an unshakable think this trans this translator calls
it this translator was con unwavering confidence some people did unshakable
confidence in that possibility the literal meaning in ply
again because remember you you get to have some there's some Choice here you how you translate it uh the uh the
English um the py uh literally means um
confidence based on knowing so it's uh you you know something now
for yourself it's not based on trusting this book or trusting me but it's
trusting what you've all what you've really experienced is for yourself if you have
that then the Buddha says you can have real confidence in the
Buddha in the Dharma in the s in Buddhism
because what is Buddhism what is the essence and what the purpose of
Buddhism at the foundation it's not about a
belief but rather about doing this becoming free of these things that
soil the mind and whereas like before I said it' be great if this could be the common
denominator of all religions all isms not only is the common denominator
of Buddhism Buddhist teachings it's the purpose of Buddhist
teachings this is what's ultimate in Buddhism it's not a glorious
ultimate it's not like you know you you go to a block party and your neighbors say what is your this
Buddhism you're doing what is the purpose of it and you pull out your list of 17 things oh the
purpose is to be free of covetous greed anger envy and by the time you finish
the 17 you know they've already gone off to someplace else or they're feeling sorry
for you because their their ultimate is Cosmic Consciousness their ultimate is
you know some Grand glorious sexy kind of kind of thing you know and um and you
know or even just something beautiful like their ultimate is love like they listen to all we hear all this like well
well okay I I guess it's okay for you but what about love what about
compassion what about beauty what about you know great spiritual
States these are great spiritual States these are beautiful States these are the
uh the doors that open so that we can have love and compassion and care for
each other these are profound things so we might not be we might not
make impression on our neighbors but that's actually a good
thing because I think we don't want to hold Buddhism up as being too
special because that's one of the ways of soiling the mind it's really special but let's not
be too caught up in it because this is this is what it's about so so to have faith in this
possibility possibility of this kind of Freedom this kind of absence of these
these difficult states of Mind these painful states of mind and then to live in the world based
on them is this something we have faith in is it something we have confidence in is
something that we TR is it something you want to trust is this something that you want to have Fidelity
to it you want to have loyalty to this is this something that has so such great
value that you're going to be committed to it and not get not give it up too
lightly too easily you're not going to come along and and finally decide well
yes this non- anger thing is good but now I'm now I'm it's I'm Justified to be
angry greed is good you know non- greed is pretty good but yeah but this thing is so good it's okay okay for me to have
Greed for this you know or
uh Fidelity commitment to something that we know
we've known we've discovered for ourselves a feeling of being clean
inside a feeling of being uh uh cleansed
of these this these dirty these things that soil us that pressure us that hurt
us that you feel the beauty of it and the relief of it the goodness of it the
wonderfulness of it to feel the value of this this I'm not going to give this up
easily there are forces inside of me that want to give those up they're still the forces of anger and greed and envy
and all these things can be there but I've experienced the absence of it and
I'm committed to it I'm not going to give in easily to these other things not going to give myself give myself up for
them I'm not going to lose myself in these things and how am I going to how am I
going to do that not give myself up not lose myself to them I'm going to
practice I I have faith in this prati I Fai of practicing I I might not be a good
practitioner but at least I have a practice at least that's what I'm faithful to is to practice and try to
stay close to this this is what's important and how do we make it so
important that it becomes the most important thing in your life this this thing
here more important than your family for
example one way is to appreciate that with this as a foundation this kind of
Freedom your love and care for your family would be so much greater all
these things get in the way so you can safely tell your family I
have something that's more important than you because hopefully you tell it tell
it to them the right way um you they they've
understood because of it you actually have so much more
love available you could ever could have had if these states had stayed in
you isn't that nice what a nice trade-off no no I want you to be angry
and greedy because I want to be the most important person for
you no no so in Buddhism faith is important or
confidence or trust Fidelity is important commitment is important but you're asked to make to
know what that is for yourself it's some possibility and potential that you
have and um and I hope that you're inspired by that potential that you have
I hope that it gives you something that you really a basis upon which to
live a a a a foundation a common denominator of how we want to live in
this world and if we do it I propose that it's a revolutionary act to do it if we want a
world where we can that's going to be peaceful nowadays when there's so much war and horror horrific war going
on if we want peace to begin with us if peace is going
to start with you if you don't don't are only only
expecting other people to create World Peace but if it's going to start with you this kind of teaching is pointing
the way may each of
us be Fe be free of covetousness
greed ill will anger
resentment contempt insolence Envy aition
ious deceit fraud obsy
rivalry conceit arrogance vanity and here it says
negligence I like to translate that word as
carelessness so you get to make up part of Buddhism for yourself but if it's
Buddhist there's part you can't make up and that's your heart's
Freedom may you be free so thank you very much