beautiful hi everyone lovely to see you be with you
so what I'd like to do uh this evening offer this evening for our practice
Reflections is um is to start practicing together and
I'll introduce the theme in the guided meditation and I'll say a couple words about it afterwards so
let's just begin sitting together meditating together so
so invite you to settle to arrive in your body
and if you're sitting let yourself feel a set of a sense of
Integrity in your posture if you're sitting in a chair
feel the bottom of your feet both feet planted
on the Earth the softening
into your feet the softening into your sit bones
into their abdomen softening of your
neck and shoulders your eyes in their socket
your forehead let the skin be soft not wrinkled
your jaw let it be loosened
let your breath be free
that's controlled constricted but moving freely
however it wants to be long or short
Let each out of breath settle you
releasing tightness holding
settling letting go more deeply with each out breath
nothing needs to happen
just here simply here
being breathed releasing letting go
with every exhale
here so delicious
to be present with whatever is
here
not thinking not analyzing what is here but just being with it breathing with
whatever is present in the body
I'd like to invite you to bring to
your heart invite the presence of someone for whom
Good Will kindness comes with his you don't have a complicated
relationship with them ideally and ideally they're alive
could be a pet could be a child someone easy
opening them into your heart's face
feeling their presence
noticing how you feel when you invite them
into your sphere of awareness does the smile show up
is your sense of gladness sense of safety Delight
a sense of care appreciation love
notice the shift
from this felt sense however subtle it might be
sharing your goodness your good well your appreciation
before them could be without words
without phrases it could be with the simple phrases of meta I wish you well I
appreciate you I wish you well or with the four more traditional
phrases may you be safe dear one
keeping their image or felt sense whatever keeps
the connection with this being a lie for you keeping it up may you be safe from inner
and outer arm I wish you safety
although I know absolute safety is not guaranteed in the world I
offer this wish to you as a gift of Good Will I wish you well I wish you safety
I wish you happiness may you be may you be happy
may you be healthy as much as possible
and may you have ease in your life take care of yourself happily
May there be ease for you
keep it really easy whatever works phrases or not
simple phrases four phrases
may you be saved
happy
healthy May IVs
connecting with their image their felt sense to keep it
right keep the practice bright through the connection
now as you give as you share your good will cultivate meta for this
their being or all of them now
consider an aspect of this being
that um you really appreciate a particular aspect of them maybe they're really kind
or generous or easy going or
or they're a great cook and cook for you with so much love or
anything else one aspect
bring that to the Forefront as you appreciate them as you
share Metta share your meta your loving kindness with them for them
foreign
is just how they make you feel accepted safe
regard to the Forefront and chairman
foreign
I'd like to invite you
bring yourself in
the receiving matters if you are giving meta sharing it both
to the steer being this easy being and next to them it was yourself
an image of you felt sense of yourself
and maybe you're easy being dear being in you in this image they're interacting
[Music] the way they usually do taking a walk sitting having tea or
whatever it might be
share Mentor for both of them may both of you one is your dear being the other is
yourself an image of you with an interaction
interacting with your friend hey both of you both of you
be safe from harm
no AIDS stepping outside of yourself and seeing yourself within interacting with
your dear being is an aspect of impersonality
cultivating the universality meta may you may you both
being dear beings may be safe maybe happy
may you be healthy as much as possible
having a felt sends an image of both of you these dear beings interacting
may you both have ease
it's safe
happy
healthy is
appreciating that both of these beings are doing their best
foreign
show up as well as they possibly can see yourself in a
in a kind light
just as you see your dear being in a kind light foreign
person with Good Will and kindness
ascribing goodness and Goodwill
foreign
and you appreciate you appreciate all of your
ear being your friend and all of yourself
seeing the good making space for what's challenging with kindness
with Compassion maybe even fears compassion but still making room for all
parts
with Goodwill
no part left out
and as we bring as we bring this
sitting to a close together appreciating your own goodness for
having shown up practiced as well as you're able to In This Moment In Time
seeing your own goodness
and making room for what's challenging
inside and outside
and all of us together having co-created the space to
practice together to cultivate meta kindness Goodwill
generosity of spirit sharing this goodness
in our hearts with all beings everywhere trusting knowing that
our practice isn't just good for us it doesn't just impact us
impacts others our loved ones our friends
strangers reverberates in ways we cannot even imagine
through the world may all beings everywhere including
ourselves be happy may all beings
including ourselves be free
[Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so what we did this evening just a few words
um I'll review what we did was we uh
began with settling in the body with the breath
relaxing softening in the areas that were tight
need to be released and then
invited the breath to be releasing with every out breath to
settle us more deeply into our heart into our posture into the present
moment and then we invited someone we cared about we did
meta for them any way that it was easy then brought to our minds and aspect of
them that we really appreciate we really love so that we really our hearts gather around that
around the goodness the brightness and then we invited ourselves as a beloved other in
interaction interacting with our dear being something we haven't explored here in
happy hour so many ways and then wishing well for both of these beings or doing their best interacting
which is just a different way to get to mitta for ourselves because sometimes
meta for ourselves can be so challenging so these are so many different ways we we uh
try to get to it so and um
yeah metaphor dear being meta for ourselves through
that seeing ourselves as a as a beloved other and also this way of stepping out
of ourselves and seeing us ourselves in interaction with someone we care about is is also ties into as I was mentioning
there's a sense of universality that impersonality not self like oh yes just good will Goodwill it is us here that's
considering all of this and yet there is something tapping into the universality of Goodwill that's just available
so so I'd like to invite us
to um do not transition doing things a little differently just trying things
out for science I'm going to invite us to transition now to small groups and
then we'll have time for Reflections after that when we come out and
um with the recap uh groups of size roughly three
hopefully um the invitation always is as we
connect with other people in the Dharma with other practitioners and this contemplation the invitation tonight
with this question with this practice we did is um for each person to perhaps if you if you
would like to share a little bit of what was it like for you there's no right or wrong and say I fell asleep my mind was
distracted it's okay it's fine um or maybe something new came up when
you saw yourself in interaction with someone else just offering that again as as a gift as a gift to the Sangha then
notice also your intention why are you speaking is it to to be of service of to
to also to of service to yourself and others but not in a way of self-aggrandizing but just humbly with
humility sharing um your your insights with others and
you can also say pass or when you return comes and say thank you pass and then maybe later when it comes your way you
can say something or not it's all good um and
and each person maybe will just say something for a minute or two and then make sure you leave space for the next
person and then the next person and then it'll come back to you so you can go around a couple times
um and not no asking questions no directing other people's experience just
sharing from your own experience very simple and then ask and then letting
others share from theirs be kind this is really breakout groups
are perfect place to stay embodied and speak from your body to practice
mindfulness of speaking mindfulness of listening it's such such a beautiful
practice instead of like okay it's recess blah blah blah blah blah blah blah blah please don't do that
say in your bodies this is it's really important practice so many things can light up okay
so I'm going to open the breakout rooms and I'll give it a little extra minute
actually can I do that right now let's see can I uh
I'm gonna create but I'm going to give you a few extra minutes at the end when the timer ends just so that you have a
heads up okay here we go I'm going to open them up take care of yourselves take care of each other be kind be kind
their rooms are closed everybody is back and we have a few minutes for uh
flexions questions comments observations either from the guided meditation the
referral your group from your breakout connection with
the Sangha you can either type them in chat if you like um and if you type them privately to me I
will just read your comment or question not your name or you can also raise your
Zoom hand so
many Reflections you like to share questions
what was it like yeah true please
okay yeah thanks thank you Nikki uh good evening everyone so that was very
lovely meditation and uh very very lovely very interesting for me was
seeing myself in third person something I haven't experimented with
but he was very powerful so thank you so much for that and one I think that we discussed a little bit in
our small group was uh how it's not always easy to find uncomplicated
people to drag my tattoo so if you've got family usually there's a lot of love
but really uncomplicated is that I was as easy and and I was just lucky that for me it
happened that talked about neutral person today did something really nice to me so I was able to bring that person
in which I didn't I don't know very well at all and so but he did something nice so there was that
it was so easy to open the heart there was nothing between us really a negative so it was
it felt really uh great choice it took a little bit but at
the end was really really a great choice and it really opened my heart a lot
just wanted to share that beautiful thanks so much for sharing the bad Pietra and I appreciate the wisdom
that you had to to bring in a neutral person for you today this person that
had done something nice to you your heart was open and many times it is skillful to bring a neutral person if if
as you said some of the dear people we love yeah their relationships are complicated and so yes very skillful
beautiful how you you brought in a neutral person who had become a dear
person in a way with their through their kindness and just let the heart be open and explore oh wow me as a third person
being kind being interacting with someone so the back that can be very onward leading also
glad that that Lit something up for you thank you thank you thank you so much
for your practice thank you yeah Serena
thank you so much for your teachings
um I'm going to ask a question about um
how to skillfully deal with um
oh God I can't even think of the word right now um
okay maybe Pedro can help me what was the word I used in our group
you can type it in chat Pietra if you you can
are sending to Serena also
well it's a type of ill will you know it's like not not really
um resentment no no resentment is no it's
it's a lot less it's it's less savvier than resentment oil will irritation
irritation irritation that's it that's what it was thanks Peter so I felt a lot
of irritation during the meditation and I really did not
I didn't feel like I had the um the capacity at that point in time to
[Music] um to handle the irritation so I basically decided to do something else so let me
ask you so what um so I have an idea what the irritation uh I already have
some thoughts but I wanted to ask you so if you can go back in time and get a sense of what was the irritation what
was the source of it that as you as well as you can tell maybe it's hard to tell it was just a feeling of irritation that
you came in with and an irritable mind
yeah well I I wasn't aware that I was I'm I'm um actually quarantined from code phone
covered right now and I it's the first time that I'm aware that
I've had covered in the past three years and actually I wound up at the hospital for it so I was back since yesterday but
what I have noticed is even at the hospital I was irritated with this lady
who could not get it right something right so um
so I guess the for me it's really important
it feels so strong when their rotation comes on yeah that I feel like I I'm not able to
really um get a handle it on the top of the
time that it it's on so unless I could just totally turn it off to something
totally different it doesn't feel like I can handle just
being with the irritation so for the benefit of time I'm going to I got it
just what's happening and thank you for sharing and I'm so sorry to hear that you've been so sick with coffee Serena
and had to go to the hospital glad you're back at home feeling better hopefully you're recovering so so
regarding your question about irritation in the limited time left
um a couple of things one is you know if if the body is feeling ill
or or out of balance if you're sick with a virus fighting then there's less
there's less um uh room really so it's like a tire you
know there's less air in the tire so it's easier for that for for one to get irritated so so turn turn towards the
irritation turns because when you're irritated you're the person who was like you're the you know you're both hurting
yourself and you're harming others so so bring compassion especially when you're sick
especially when you're sick bring compassion which is like a soothing sound like it's okay as well as patience
patience and compassion those are the two antidotes for irritation especially
patients it's not going to get any better or easier if you're irritated and you're it it just you know that that
that's a wisdom practice bringing the patience in so bring patience in as well as compassion for yourself was really
hurting right now with the irritation um and distraction is not this is not a
very good strategy because uh I mean sometimes it can feel skillful but overall it's better to actually work
with it head on with with wisdom bringing in
a dose of patience and compassion for yourself who's
suffering at that moment so thank you for bringing that in Serena thank you
so it is seven o'clock and our time has
come to an end our time together thank you all so much for your practice for
your cultivation cultivation of your heart for the sake of all beings
may all beings including ourselves be well may all beings be free
foreign