so today I would like to focus a talk around a particular
poem that the Buddha taught it was a poem that he seemed to have been eager to have his students people
memorize because there's accounts in the ancient texts of um of you know him
helping people memorize the text he had recited so they'd learn it and um
it was an oral tradition back then in the ancient world so there was no Library you could go to so if you wanted
to have access to teachings in the texts you had to have memorized them
and so all the suit does all these this discourses were eventually memorized but
many of them were put to memory after he died but during his lifetime there's only a
particular ones that we have record of that he was actively teaching people to
memorize so I take that to being that it was really important for the Buddha
and he gave then he explained or gave an analysis of the poem as well
and whether the Capone is a poem or whether it's a song is a little bit of a
you know interpretive exercise there was a time when some of the
early Western Scholars especially from Sri Lanka who spoke English would call
these kinds of poems ballads and sometimes the way they're chanted
can sound very much like a something that we may be Associated more with a
song or or ballet or something and that helps the memorization of it
the and so this one is called
um it has an interesting title I I call it an auspicious day
and the word for auspicious bada means something like something that is
so uh fortunate something that's wondrous a blessing auspicious
and but the word rata r-a-t-t-a can mean night
and but it seems in the ancient world uh it also meant the day just like in
English um uh data the word Day means both daytime and the whole 24 hours
but uh in uh uh week so they would count the days by
how many nights it's been and so if you said that if you said you know an auspicious night people
understood in the context it would be a day so I translated as an auspicious day
but it's interesting because the word rata is uh is a particular grammatical
formulation of the word Raga which can mean a kind
of a passionate attachment and uh and so so one translation that
bikubody had in his early translation was inauspicious attachment
and so it's a kind of word play going on here so is it okay to be attached well
if you're attached to this maybe it isn't too bad maybe it helps you to be if you're attached to healthy
things then as long as it's helping you it's okay to be attached but when you realize it's not it's hindering you
that's when we let go of it and this is a very nice way of understanding attachments there's a tendency in
Buddhism to kind of like it's all or nothing like if you're attached let go you're not supposed to be that way
but rather that recognize well there's often a reason to be attached it's the
reason why people are attached to strategy for something and maybe sometimes it's not a bad
strategy and so for example being attached to your health
might be good until the point especially if you're sick but then if you're really
healthy if you're excessively attached to the health at some point you might find that it's actually making you unhealthy because you're kind of so much
preoccupied and worried and stressing about it so so the uh so an auspicious attachment
if you're going to have an attachment nadarma the one I'm going to read uh this would be good
oh as long as it's good and then you let go so this is I also I call this uh poem
um the vipassana anthem so uh for the inside movement for us all
kind of like a this is you know has such a wonderful special place for us
and um so um
there's four verses four four stanzas
an auspicious day don't chase the past
or long for the future the past is Left Behind
the future not yet reached clearly see phenomena
anywhere they appear not faltering and not agitated knowing
this develop the mind ardently do what should be done today
who knows death may come tomorrow
there is no bargaining with mortality and death's great Army
whoever lives thus ardent active day and night is says that peaceful Sage one who has
an auspicious day so I think part of the power of this
poem is the third stanza verse uh ardently do what should be done today
who knows death may come tomorrow there is no bargaining with mortality
and death's great Army the um
so um and here the lesson of this death contemplation taking it into a seriously
is not morbid it's not kind of to be you know and uh and it's not then to live in
such a way that you have a better rebirth or something but rather to take this
moment seriously as the place for practice as a place to be mindful and
attentive and more than that this is the place to have insight
and um and that if you can have inside here if you're able to live really centered here as life is being lived in
a lived moment and lived life and have insight as you go along then
this is an auspicious day says the peaceful Sage peaceful Sage is a word
for the title for the Buddha but the word peaceful is important because this is the purpose of this path
this is the purpose of this auspicious practice is so we can discover for ourselves a deep abiding sense of peace
one of the great gifts that we can give the world is to die peacefully
if it's possible that we do the truth it helps people not be afraid of life
it's been lots of studies done that have pointed out that um something like
there's a tendency for uh for the people who are afraid of death
to be afraid to live their life fully and the people who are not afraid of death tend to live Fuller more engaged
life exactly how that how to explain that I don't know and but but it's an
interesting correlation and so so it starts with this kind of
instructions that don't chase the past or along for the future the past is Left
Behind in the future not yet reached uh one of the lessons that I learned
slowly over the years was when I thought about the future imagine the future and planned around
the future had wishes and fears about the future
um I had plenty of it for all kinds of situations and it turned out I had an amazingly
poor prediction rate that I would predict you know based on
some idea of what was going to happen in the future and so many times it didn't work out that way it did happen
differently than I was planned or how I thought or was afraid and so it's slowly dawned on me that I
had very bad record and even then it took a long time for
that to sink in deeply and eventually I realized oh
I don't know the future and so I'm not going to be so attached to it or so caught in my prediction
I might take it into account and you know do some modicum at least bring an umbrella or something
but in case but uh the uh it kind of loosened up
my my way I was attached to the Future cut up in the future concerned about the
future and I discovered as I learned to let go of that pre-concern the preoccupation
with my future and I would show up and I discovered that generally once I'm
there in the moment I generally know how to find my way with it and that helped me relax even more
and the result of that relaxation was a greater appreciation and willingness
just to be with here with what's going on be present
so the future is not yet reached the past is Left Behind and um
you know I've held on to the Past not want to let go and nothing you know when I hold on to the memories hold on to the
people hold on to whatever who I was back then and sometimes it's held me back
sometimes my self-image of myself was based on who I was in the past and I'm
still trying to prove that or be that and it's going to interfere with my ability to be present here in a full way
don't chase the past or long for the future so when the Buddha uh after he gave this
poem in one of the sutos where it appears and he then gives an explanation of what it means
and I want to explain that to you if I can but I would like to do it first with
a an analogy many years ago I read of a study
where some psychologists took um a
an actor and to give a talk at some significant
conference and um and after that actor gave this
talk they would interview the people coming out into the lobby how was that how was that what did you think of that
talk and um and uh people would say that was really great it was wonderful the best
things happening at the conference the thing was that the script that the
actor had been given to read or to present to the conference was nonsense
it it didn't make any sense and so there was something about the
actor's delivery something about the actor that led people to believe that there was
something significant here being told the article I read about it didn't say
too much about the actor but one of the things I I imagined it wouldn't be surprised the actor was probably a tall
white middle-aged man a kind of a certain kind of person that tends to be given a lot of authority
automatically when they show up unfortunately people like me maybe sometimes
and and so uh and perhaps the person had a
great melodious voice it was really enjoyable to listen to them and could speak with great confidence as an actor
right like they really knew what they were talking about and I imagine maybe that I could imagine for example that maybe they dropped
certain words got repeated maybe the word peace got repeated
and but the sentence didn't make any sense but people hear the word peace and so they were in my whole piece oh yeah
peace oh yeah peace and they'd be reminded and then when they left they thought that's what they were left with this guy talked about peace I'm so glad
people did it there's so much conflict and um and uh so in this scenario
the audience some of the audience are making certain things up first uh they're making things up based
on appearance appearance of who the person is based on their voice their sound and that's just
what's being approached and they're making something up it maybe the
researchers wanted people to make it up I don't know you know but still the audience was actively involved by their
own background and predispositions making up some idea of who this person was this is an authoritative person
speaking authoritatively uh they were also making up that it was pleasant
enjoyable maybe because of this style of delivery maybe the person was animated
in a wonderful way maybe the voice was really Pleasant to listen to and so they
were making up this idea this is a really Pleasant event to be here I really enjoy being here
was the enjoyment really there or how much were we responsible for the creation of it
they had Concepts the made-up Concepts so this person knows what he's talking
about this is a great talk and they were making up these Concepts that they were then living in
they also were making up all kinds of reactions and inner things in their mind they were constructing universes of
um you know you know I'm so wonderful I came out on time to the conference I paid my my lots of money for it this is
a great thing I can't wait until I go you know I don't know what you know we're making up a whole story a little
Universe of what it means to be there and and how wonderful it is and
and then probably the knowing of it the knowing all this also felt really good wow I'm in the know now
my first zen teacher had this way of talking about uh where's zen zen fit
into current event world of current events and he was you know friends with the
governor and different people in Washington and and famous people and so we were given this feeling as he spoke
that our practicing Zen was on the Forefront of our culture
and it was so good to know this to be part of this so that was kind of you know it was rather unfortunate it was actually not
so helpful for um for our sen students to be caught in the
grip of this kind of thing that being created so these people the audience was
creating something so I hope you appreciate that and um so we our minds are creative our
minds have an amazing capacity to make things up and in fact it needs to it's doing it
all the time and generally it's predictive ability to create images and ideas and
is relatively good otherwise you wouldn't have made it here today you do just enough to find here
but but sometimes how we create things gets in the way and causes US problems
so then this is how the Buddha ex it didn't no did what I didn't know the study but what he said in explaining
this that the chase that um chasing the past
what that means is some translators translators Reviving The Past
what it means is that the idea of of making up ideas
of who we were in the past making up the appearances that we had
making up um you know I've seen the lives I've reviewed my life in my old age now I now
will make up new ideas of what I was like in the past you know it I mean sometimes I tell
myself well now I know better now I recognize who I was a long time ago but do I really you know it's kind of still
kind of an appearance and making up an appearance somehow and um and then making up Sensations
you know things in the past that were unpleasant at the time now I'm go back look back I'm grateful for and there and
I see them as a pleasant event or opposite happens something that was a
pleasant now is seen as unpleasant so this idea of you know we were constructing the past the concepts we
have about the past changes and we make up new ideas new concepts of it the fish
gets bigger by the telling right the new concepts of the fish they say and then our reactions and the story
making mind that we live in changes over time of the past and then our sense of knowing and now
with the quality of knowing that happens as we know the past so the Buddha specified these five different areas
that people make things up and so not chasing the past is in is
means don't make things up about yourself in the past this way
and longing for the future it's the same thing about the future don't make things
up about yourself about the future because you'll get in trouble for it that's how you get we have a lot of
suffering can come from some fixed idea this is who I am
I'm this way I'm supposed to be its way I should be this way this is happening to me I'm a victim to
all this you know or I'm asserting myself I'm supposed to have I deserve things or there's a complicated world of
self that we create part of the function of mindfulness is to take a good look at and see to
discover to really understand how it's working and then here in the text it goes on and
says clearly see phenomena anywhere they appear so what this means is there's a stay in
the present moment enough that you see what's happening as it's occurring
the constant flow and change oftentimes we live retrospectively
or you know in the present moment like something happens and then we spend a little while thinking about it
uh there's not a few times that I've noticed that someone is talking and um
and uh I'm beginning to thinking about something and I realized I don't I didn't hear what they were saying for a
while because and it happens the most for me occasionally I hope
um when I'm on um on Zoom especially with the group of people you
know somehow I think about something I've gotten distracted or something's happened and I'm in my world of thinking
and um and so I'm not there as it's occurring maybe someone said something and I found myself reflecting on it and
I'm in the now I'm lingering in the past but this ability to really stay here in
the present moment is um is where we see Insight that's the
kind of the key thing about this to be pasna practice we do is to not just see what's happening not to see what's here
but to see it as it's happening and you can't see it as it's happening
if we're living in the constructs the Mind makes the concepts it lives in
if you see a river going by and you just think that's a river
and you live in the concept of the river you might not notice what the river is is constantly flowing
you can kind of get into your head oh that's a river maybe I should go swimming in it I didn't bring a bathing suit I don't have a bathing suit where
am I going to get a bathing suit it'd be great to go in the river yeah I bet it's nice and comfortable I love swimming I'm
such a great swimmer and and we're living in a world of that we're making up in a sense and of thought and we've
lose touch with the actual experience of the river we're relating to it but now it's relating through the conceptual
mind the story making mind and so but to really be in the experience of the river what you'll see
is the river is constantly flowing and that's a very different way of experiencing a river than all the
stories we're making up around it and we're doing vipassana that's where we kind of want to try to rest in uh
especially meditation is in the as thing occur as things are happening this is
where we have insight so then the Buddha goes on and he says in the poem
um not faltering and not agitated knowing this developed the mind
so this is not just simply to be in the present moment for the presence moment's sake but that we're actually learning to
develop ourselves to become a stronger mind clear mind uh more centered mind more receptive
mind there's all kinds of ways the mind gets developed and as it does so the qualitative way in
which we can live our life now be attentive and be present changes
so that as the quality of the Mind increases then we're able to move closer
and closer to a time when we know what to let go of so we can be at peace in
this world in the moment as it's current occurring even if it's our last day and last
minutes of life we know how to be peaceful we know this is what's possible
and to the Buddha in its explanation of this text then he explains what he means by not faltering
and um and to not falter and is is as things
are occurring in the present moment uh we don't
um make a self in relationship to it so as for example things appear
or our appearances are there it's a sense to say Sensations are there our thoughts are there
um I saw that in my mind whereas I was meditating today where you know I sat down to meditate and um and I could see
for a while the first I don't know a few minutes I could see that I was teetering
back and forth between being my thoughts and knowing that I was thinking
and I could easily slip back into just being my thoughts so in a sense I am my
thinking because that that's where kind of was a living and then as I was settling I could see you know you know I
could know that my mind was thinking I was thinking I was like kind of like I was like kind of like the image I had
was I was kind of looking up into my mind saying the mind is thinking a lot and that was a much better place to be
that was kind of interesting oh I might just look at that it's like this you know the radio is on
as opposed to getting swept into the the radio and kind of believing I'm the I
don't know what I'm the I'm the thoughts and so uh so you can believe uh you're
forgive your thinking you know I am my thoughts you can believe the thoughts are part of
me thoughts are in me uh the uh
um the thought you know there's all these ideas senses of self we create in relationship to our thoughts to our
feelings to our perceptions to our thought ideas to our con being conscious
and again it's a made-up mind it's the constructive creative mind and for the
Buddha this idea that we create a self an identity around it is different than having an identity
so you know some of us have identities which are obvious to some of us these to
ourselves and that we kind of need to have it uh you know we could find certain parts of the world we need to
kind of behave accordingly according to our identity some some are role identities
some are gender identities it used to be they had male and female bathrooms
and um and Once Upon a Time by mistake I went into the women's bathroom
this was not a good thing and no one saw me but I realized when I
walked out that uh oh I could have gotten big trouble for this
so you're supposed to kind of behave you know know certain things about the identity but so so some of them were
born with in all kinds of ways but some of it is made up
um so if my I'm you know an identity it kind of have especially sitting here giving a Dharma talk is um I'm a
Buddhist teacher so it's okay I think you're you're kind of going along with it so it's okay for
now it has a it has a purpose but when I go home
and my wife and my kids guess what identity is no longer
relevant Once Upon A May 25 years ago when I
started teach I came home to my wife we were talking and she stopped me and said Gil
you're using that voice I was using the teacher voice for her
you know that's not the place to be a teacher right so so sometimes you get in trouble we have these identities but we use them
inappropriately we hold on to them we get attached to them some identities are are value judgments I'm a lousy person
I'm a bad person I'm a right good person I'm the best person I'm this kind of
person you know and so we live in these values of ourselves and some people it's tremendously heavy the weight they carry
the negative identities they're holding for themselves you know I'm
uh I mean for me you know some of you heard this before when I was in my 20s I
thought that the Gill was short for guilt and because uh I I I I didn't have to do
anything to be guilty I just was and if I did something then I was guilty but I didn't you know like I
remember seeing it really clearly this is where I it was by doing meditation practice that I saw it so clearly
uh because I was walking across a meditation hall floor when people are meditating and just walking across the
floor I was guilty I mean what am I guilty for I'm not just walking you know but it was
such a strong tendency of mine so the identity of being the guilty one was strong for me so I had taken on that
burden that kind of identity so for the Buddha not faltering
is not to take on make up and live in these made-up identities and be attached to them
the attachment itself is a problem the attachment to seeing how this works
to being in the present moment the moment moment seeing things that they occur seeing how attachments occur to
see the arising of a story The arising of a made-up idea
oh I hear it's occurring and this is one of the values of really being present as
things are occurring is you have a better chance to notice when we start making up stories making up identities
making up these things that we're living in and then we can put a question mark next to it is this really useful is this
true maybe I don't need to do this so you're just trading one attachment
for another a painful one that's painful for you and sometimes for others for an
attachment which is the opposite is one's beneficial develops the mind not faltering not getting hung up not
agitated identity that we make up trips people up
it makes people agitated and you can see it a little bit some of
us some of you may be um if uh
if people either praise you or condemn you
I bet you either falter or get agitated if you get praise the agitation is kind of a good agitation feels good wow
I mean if they criticize you it's like a bad agitation or you're faltering you know
now that I have this now that I'm so great I have to keep it up and then we're tripped after each we
tripped up or something so uh so this power of this mindfulness
practice is that of cutting through the ways we get caught
in identity and Concepts in this made-up world that's actually much bigger part
of our life than most people realize and so it is to develop the mind is to
have this clear capacity for insight that's clear ability to name and see and
see through it and and for what purpose so we can relax
deeply deep enough to experience a deep abiding sense of peace
ardently do what should be done today who knows death may come tomorrow
there's no bargaining with mortality and death's great Army since there's no bargaining no escaping
death for the Buddhist point of view this is what's worth doing
this moment this minute this time this day is when we have our lived life
live it fully but not greedily like live it fully to have you know
by going to Disneyland or something live it fully by waking up being a
really present for the lived moment the live moment is more exciting than
Disneyland whoever lives thus ardent
active day and night is says the peaceful Sage
one who has an auspicious day
so this is the ipasna anthem
if we know that the Buddha encourage people to memorize it maybe you'll
memorize it and um and um
so those are my my thoughts for today
so do you have any comments you'd like to make or any questions about this
or anything else
good morning um so this is a somewhat minor piece of what you were
talking about but you mentioned sometimes especially on Zoom
you're somebody's talking and then you're thinking about some reflecting on something else that
they said or whatever it is getting distracted by some thoughts
and I just wonder in those situations
like sometimes is it skillful to just try to slow the conversation down to
because I noticed sometimes for me it's hard because maybe that reflection needed some time
to maybe it was an important reflection and then the conversation is just moving on and
yeah does that make sense it makes a lot of sense and if you and uh for you to be tracking yourself well
enough to know what you need in order to participate in that conversation is a really important skill to have and
whether it's appropriate to ask for things to slow down or not for you depends whether it's one-on-one and
you're talking about something really important interpersonally that's completely good or I've been involved in
conversations where someone is moving on very quickly and I said we have to make
an important decision or something and I've explicitly asked sometimes can we slow down I need to track this much
better and can we go over this again or something can you can you repeat this what you said
so I think that's a a really useful skill when to do it and when to not do
it you know if it's a you know if it's uh you know that big
conference with a thousand people there um and uh and to ask the persons
presenting say it's not nonsense it's really good to ask them to slow down for your sake and you're one out of a
thousand people might be a disservice to everyone else makes the whole thing more difficult for everyone else so you have
to kind of you know understand the context situation but I love it that you're asking this and that's there are
times when that's really healthy okay good
good and then hopefully the people you're with appreciate that because you know that's part of the context you say
you know can you can we slow down and that person doesn't have the ability for that or it doesn't somehow or
takes it too personally like they've done something wrong and it just makes the whole situation more difficult than it had to be so it's understanding
context is such an important part of living a wise life yeah I mean I think maybe one more piece
that I'm reflecting on is maybe sometimes I need to
take care of it in some way like write down a quick note or something about an Insight that I had so that I
can not keep churning on it and then be able to return to what's happening now
because it's not the appropriate time yeah yeah I've been some things I've done a
few things to help me be present sometimes I have taken notes as I listen if there's a long presentation because I
take notes I don't need I don't really need to take notes but by taking notes I stay present and more actively and I'm not less likely to wander off
and the other thing I do is I make sure I sit straight on Zoom if because if I kind of relax
and sit back I'm more likely to my mind's more likely not to be present fully for the
experience to track it
hi thank you for the talk somehow I find it though um a little bit remote from
the realities if we're living in this paradise where everybody is peaceful and
you know there's no problems no protest no nothing like this so it feels a
little bit um theoretical perhaps and makes me wonder like have you ever
participated in any sort of protest in what protest like protesting against
something yeah and how would that go and I guess I would like to hear some side
of some some sort of like example of how to do more of a peaceful protest perhaps
like you know the world is full of problems and we do not live in the like you know Paradise so to speak do you
understand what I'm saying yeah very much so but um I think that uh what it's inspired to do is to kind of put it back
on you that um you're not if if you think we live in Paradise here in Silicon Valley uh
you're not looking uh that's not what I'm saying I'm saying the opposite actually listening to this
poem yeah it's great I mean it feels to me that it would be great to follow this
poem If we were living in Paradise but unfortunately we're not living in paradise and thus this prioritizing this
peaceful being and stuff like that that just seems to be like like some sort of some sort of fairy tale I guess do you
see what I'm saying I understand what you're saying but I don't I don't see the logic of it because in my logic that if you can do
this if you can try if you could really be present enough to watch how you construct your reality your life
then you can be peaceful in the middle of conflict you can then you can you're much better
positioned to be able to do things wisely when things are really difficult and challenging it's the people who
don't know themselves well and don't can't track their reactions their responses internally who when there's
conflict and difficulty even if they go through a protest they're peaceful for a while but then that someone kind of
yells you know you're crazy protesting and they're before they know it they're punching the person out they've they're
certainly reactive so I think that this here is a recipe for responsible engagement in the world
and the challenges and I'm you know I'm staking my life not on the making people kind of uh you know
in some kind of retired Enlightenment that they just sit and stay home and do
Wordle [Laughter]
but I want you know I want this practice to be one that makes people change agents for for a peaceful world
okay and right here in Silicon Valley I mean there's a there's like a fifth of the people here in Silicon Valley are
hungry that's a big that's a very high percentage go visit Second Harvest
they're they're one of the premiere organizations here that are non-profit that's uh trying to bring food to the
hungry and there's a huge population of people who they're feeding so it's right here
close by thank you do you have time for one more thought
yeah um I I get what you were saying I thought that was an astute observation
um about the practicality of this this very um wise uh poem and it just dawned on me
there's a real world example um that's been unfolding globally right for the past I don't know
nine months it's and I appreciate what you were saying Gil about us being creative beings we
are talking a recession into existence why right maybe we should be talking
something else into existence but it's becoming well I don't believe it but
others believe it's a self-fulfilling prophecy a recession is coming a recession is coming why don't we all
collectively try to think of the opposite or maybe think of nothing and then see what happens
so I just found this to be very timely yeah yeah poem that you've shared yeah there's so many things that we actually
think into existence that much more than people realize that you know we live some things are uh are
a self-fulfilling prophecies and so if we believe certain things then we everything organizes around that and
so it becomes true and um and I've known people who I've seen who
are aversive people and very angry and so and they have this idea that everyone
else is out to get them everyone else is mean but so they could but they're more angry but then when they go someplace they
have this this atmosphere of anger around them and then people are treating
them unkindly and so it's fulfilling the very things that they're afraid of or they want so so the power of this
creative mind is quite something so this practice of you know clearly see
phenomena anywhere they appear it's really the present phenomena means as your experiences are happening as your
inner life gets born to really see it clearly is such a relief it's so needed
for our society um you know it's a you know I've put a tremendous amount of Hope in having
people become healthy in this way
great so may you have an auspicious day laughs
thank you very much and if you want to stay around a little
bit and say hello to each other maybe you can say hello to the person next to you and then say goodbye or
but it's nice to have a little bit of community