foreign
and welcome and
so
maybe I
maybe I already feel kind of quiet
so this topic of
the beach today's topic is truth
and meditation is
the mindfulness meditation is the practice of being truthful to oneself
that we often say we talk we talk about a simple recognition of what's happening
in the present moment and some people use Mental noting
noting what's happening in the moment with little mental note breathing in breathing out hearing
itching and um
the um but those are all small little statements of Truth saying
what is true in the moment in our experience in our sensory experience
but also we can say truth about other things
like now I'm quiet I feel quiet internally or I'm agitated or I'm happy or sad
and it's the accumulation of these simple freely given
moments of Truth that build in meditation
that help things help us to grow in the Dharma help us to become quiet
help us to become clear unconflicted
so you might think of meditation as the continuous Act
of being truthful being true
to this moment becoming aware of what's Happening truthfully
and this of course means much more than just recognizing that we're breathing in and breathing out
it's really recognizing how we actually are quality of the heart the quality of the
inner being how we're showing up in the world at this moment
recognizing what we're avoiding and hiding from or
recognizing the emotions the beliefs the feelings
that are driving the distracted mind preoccupied mind the concerned mind
and the continuous Act of being truthful
creates a change something different happens with us
under the influence of just being true eventually we would discover what a
relief it is even there's a freedom to be found
in the capacity the ability to be truthful say the truth to
ourselves and it might not be actually using words
or it might be a deeper knowing that this is what's happening this is what it is
so as we meditate today you might want to keep in mind that what we're practicing is not
concentration not calm not
being present for the present moment all those things help and support
what is the heart of meditation which is being truthful being true
to this moment how it actually is so assuming a meditation posture
sometimes it's the emphasis this is the word dignified posture
there's a dignity in showing up to be truthful
to be the truth to be true
there's a dignity a nobility
to be a true person
to Stand Tall to sit still and sit tall to lay down tall
here
and
gently lowering the Gaze if the eyes are open
and then perhaps closing the eyes
and gently breathing a little deeper
just deep enough that you feel a fuller connection to your torso your
body your belly and chest
and a longer exhale than usual long enough to let something
relax in your body giving away
easing up
breathing out a little longer and
so that the thinking mind could quiet down
thinking mind can relax
letting breathing return to normal
and if you're quiet for a few moments to feel and sense and know yourself
what is true for you right now
in what way can truth telling recognizing the truth
be quieting be freeing
be opening
so something inside something in the mind or the heart
response positively
to the recognition of what is true for you right now
sometimes breathing
to how we breathe is influenced by how we are
and there's a way of being grounded or being settled in what's true
whether it's comfortable or not by recognizing how it is that it's
in the breathing itself
and gently
Let The Rhythm of breathing be like a massage or a
kind physical contact touching
what is true Within
when you notice that you're distracted don't worry about that
don't be concerned or rush back to the breath instead
just be truthful truthfully recognize that you're
distracted Let It Be A Moment of Truth telling or
truth recognition that is satisfying in and of itself
that's freeing
that is healing and growing
recognizing how things are without any conflict
just the truth
however you are recognizing it honestly truthfully
maybe taking the time to feel into yourself what's below the surface
and in the truth-telling
might there be some relief some opening
some making space for how you are
and then as we come to the end of this meditation
to take a few moments to appreciate
the value benefits goodness of telling the truth to ourselves
growth healing freedom
even love and compassion
grow better when we are truthful to ourselves to what's
happening with ourselves and our response to the world
and may it be that our capacity to be truthful serves for the benefit and Welfare of
all people including ourselves
may it be on this day that our meditation practice our
truth-telling is dedicated to
the benefit of everyone may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
good morning good day
and um so this is the second talk on the five criteria that Buddha used
for why speech and um these five criteria can be taken as
questions that we ask ourselves before we speak and yesterday I talked about
when the question is is it timely is it the right time to say what we want to
say to ask what we want to ask today the topic is or the question is is
it truthful are we speaking the truth and um
I kind of like it that this the second that we ask is a timely first that's
kind of like the high end like even the truth might not be timely might not be the
right time to speak the truth if we start with truth then maybe we are
um we speak inappropriately at times when it doesn't help maybe even Harms
makes things more difficult so is it timely then today is it
truthful and of course the topic of what is true and how do we recognize the truth is can
be philosophically or linguistically complex but uh a simple way of understanding it
is that um it's uh that the minimum that the
truth is involves an absence of Deceit there's no intention no effort to
deceive anybody um with what we're saying what we're doing
and um because if with deception we're clearly not speaking the truth
other times we might be attempting to say what's true or we think we say what's true but it might not be true but
there's not we're not intentionally trying to be deceitful
we're trying to be truthful and one of the ways to
strengthen our capacity or heighten our capacity to be true is when we say something to follow up
immediately with the basis upon which we think it's true why do we think
something is true so for example I if you you know rather
than saying that um you know you know today is a great day
it's not gonna you can say today um it's my interpretation that it's a
great day so we're saying that on what basis we're making the claim it's an interpretation
or it's a great day for me rather than just making a blanket
statement for everyone so be a little more specific and say what's the basis is for something
that would have emphasized this they said if especially with religious statements that you say on the basis of
what do you make a claim a religious spiritual claim is it you based on your faith is it
based on your reasoning is it based on the tradition you're in or a teacher where the teacher has said
um is it based on something you've experienced and because even experience is
interpreted and it's personal so as soon as you make these caveats or
these these explanations then people will uh then it's not a declarative
statement and declarative statements are questionable how truthful they are
but if you specify or contextualize how you come to this conclusion then
then it's easier to participate in a conversation with the others and it's also easier to stay closer to what's
true so to be truthful is this truthful what I'm going to say how can I say it so
it's truthful and so this is my interpretation to be truthful today to you all of you I can
say that I value this idea of Truth and the Buddha emphasized it and I would
like to try to explain my interpretation of why this is important
so you know that's you know that now I'm speaking the truth
and I'm contextualizing what I'm going to say so you don't have to automatically assume that I'm making
declarative statements that's of what's absolutely true in the universe but rather it's my interpretation and
you'll have to hear it and see what's true for you as you hear it and what works for you
foreign speaking the truth is a way to heal it's
the way to grow it's a way to mend relationships it's a way of finding
a way to connect more deeply to others we connect more deeply when we're truthful
when we're deceitful we're actually creating a barriers between connectivity
between people and the kind of alienation a separation and um
the uh it's probably true to say that spiritually
there's no spiritual growth there's no growth in the Dharma without a
dedication to being truthful to the truth the truth is that important
and and ultimately maybe what we're looking for is to become not just
truthful but becoming a true person a person is true in how they live their
lives how they express their lives how they speak and so asking everyone's else a question
before speaking is this true or how can I speak this that I want to say in a way that feels truthful to me
the um and then it's also a very powerful practice to to this I think of
true speaking the truth as being mindfulness out loud that uh mindfulness meditation or
mindfulness practice for oneself is really a continual Act of saying the truth to ourselves saying the truth of
what's happening in our experience and not deceiving ourselves and um and then so so doing that out
loud isn't my you know being truthful honest is true is mindfulness out loud
and uh but in that it's mindful then if we feel that we want to lie
feel we want to kind of bend the truth in some way this is a really useful time
for deepening our own introspection to really take a good look at what's
happening here with me now because what motivates the desire to be to lie
what motivates being deceitful and uh is it fear is it greed is it
anger is it conceit of some type and you know avoiding embarrassment or
you know hiding from people not so they don't know who we are what's what we do
is it to try to get our way in the world or to what what's motivating it
and and uh the advantage of asking that question what's motivating my desire to
to lie is to because that the deeper
motivations for that that's an important place of practice that's important place of really looking deeply
because the opportunity there is to discover what we're attached to discover what we're clinging to and so ever what
kind of conceit there's self-making what you're involved in so that we can begin dissolving it so we can become Freer
from these kinds of attachments there's a kind of delight that exists in
Dharma practice of recognizing where we're caught recognize our attachments
and that the light is there because we realize oh this is where the practice is now I get to practice
this is good rather than assuming that Buddhist practice is all about joy and delight and kind of skipping in
the clouds and a Happy Lucky way uh Buddhist practices a lot about this deeper deeper truth-telling
and a deep appreciation for the value of doing so seeing our attachments and clinging so
that we can find we can be on the path of freedom from it all
so rather than seeing you know our attachments as bad news to identify there's a way in which in a certain way
if we're committed to being truthful it's good news so uh I think that the dedication to be
truthful begins highlighting all the little ways we exaggerate a little ways we bend the
truth maybe sometimes we do it for the city what we think is the sake of the other person
and um you know so it's not to hurt them or or upset them or something
and um and so that seems good some Compassion
or care involved in that but is it necessary to be deceitful to lie
and so part of the art of speaking the truth in our relationships with others is to avoid causing harm and avoid lying
and sometimes that takes some cleverness or take some consideration or reframing
the conversation or sometimes even responding with a non-sequitur
and uh and um the um
or finding some way to you know to say something that may be satisfies the
person's question but doesn't really address it because to address it honestly it just would be complicated
That's a classic example someone gives is someone's dressed for their wedding
about to go into the ceremony and they ask you you know what do you think of my
my dress or my suit or my clothes and uh and you think it's you know maybe
pretty gaudy or the wrong you know the color combination
the colors clash or something but you don't want to say that just before someone goes into their their wedding
the truthful statement about what you think is uh you know what you really think and so what can you say that's
truthful and you might say you know that um something like
you you know wow it it was a really is it tailor-made it really fits your body
really well or you say something different you say recognize say something it's truthful
that is not your first impression but something that you have to think about and tell yeah I can say I can speak
about that and that maybe settles the person or allows people to kind of go along
so uh um to be truthful and speaking the truth
when there's conflict and challenges can be very hard and so this is why it's
important to remember the first criteria is it the right time to be have a an
honest conversation with someone are they ready for it are you ready for it but then the other three criteria which
we'll do over the next days also come into play It's Not only is it truthful
and therefore I should say it it's a truthful and
can I say it in a useful way can I say it in a supportive way
g'day how can I say the truth so that it's beneficial
and so we'll talk more about this as we go along here so um
is it true and what happens to you when you ask
that question and today as you go about your day you might have occasion to
speak and if there's enough self-reflection as you're about to speak
maybe you could ask yourself the question is it what I'm going to say about to say
is it truthful and uh
and is it truthful and a simple and clear way or is it truthful in an exaggerated way or an understated way or
leading something out you know why why am I kind of adjusting myself and
speaking the truth what's the motivation for that I'm not saying your motivation is wrong
because of that but start looking more deeply so is it truthful can you be truthful
what motivates any kind of
moving away from the really clear simple truthful statement
so um it's a great practice
and you might after do after maybe before you go to sleep or at some point
at the end of the day near the end of the day just review
what you've talked about through the day and review it little bit for this
question of truth how truthful was I today and where might I have been where
could I have been more truthful where could I have been wiser about how I spoke the truth where was I
kind of twisting the truth a little bit and why sometimes it's hard to do this exercise
in the you know live in the present moment as we're speaking but sometimes reviewing it can really help us to see
what's going on and I offer you this not as a not so
that the you know highlights something bad about
yourself but really to highlight your capacity to grow and develop and learn
and heal some deep way Within it's a powerful thing to speak the truth
and um I've I've found it amazing what opens up and what opens up in
relationships when we learn the art of truth-telling but it is an art and it
takes a while to to learn that skill and it's a skill well well worth learning
so thank you very much