good morning everyone and it's very nice to be back here with you
all and and uh it's also very nice to be here just in
this posture my meditation posture because I feel like I'm
it's a continuity of being together with a group of people on Retreat this last
two weeks and it's a continuity with all the people who
I've Had The Good Fortune to meditate with and share this life and share these
teachings and explore the Dharma so and now here we are to do the same
and I'm very grateful and very appreciative of all of you being here
so that we can share this together
and um so
um a valuable question
for people doing mindfulness practice is what would I be experiencing right
now if I was not distracted
sometimes we miss a lot in our lives by being distracted we miss a deeper connection to our life
to in the immediacy of it as it's unfolding a deeper we make and miss a deeper
connection to ourselves and all the complexity of what it means to be a human being but to really be
present for it all and not be distracted and we if we're distracted we miss a
deeper connection to other people and that can simply be or not so simple
but be a deeper perception of others to take them in understand
them really be attuned to what's going on for them
and then we also miss the richness
the the something I would say the Prof found aspects of what happens between us as
human beings and between us and the world around us in that relationship and that
relatedness in the way that there's a give and take or there's a
ways in which how we are meets how the world is and how other
people are and in that mix there's a richness there's a profundity
there is so much of value so to not be distracted him
not be distracted by our judgments of what's Happening that keeps us removed
from a deeper perception seeing understanding
to not be uh just distracted by our
emotions especially fears and diversions and desires which Cloud the water
make it more difficult to really be present for ourselves underneath the desires aversions fears
and to perceive the world uh
more deeply than only what's seen through the lens of fear or desire or
aversion okay so what to happen what is your
experience of life when you're not distracted and that question can be behind any time
and place we find ourselves but it can be right now as we sit here in this meditation
and maybe you'll discover some answers to this question and at the end of The Meditation I will
offer a specific Focus for this question
but to live with this question for the first good part of this meditation
um and so I would encourage you not to answer the question
with the distracted mind meaning don't spend a lot of time thinking about the
answer which if it's commentating on the answer
thinking about the question or commentating about the question or or
reacting to the question just sit down and drop that question
into your meditation periodically as we go through this these
minutes together and see not what you answer intellectually
but what appears as an answer in your direct experience
of Here and Now so what is your experience
if you are not distracted
so to assume a meditation posture
and gently close your eyes
and the realm of what answers this question
is our direct experience and so they begin with a establishing a
connection to our direct embodied experience to take a few long slow deep breaths
a ritual of connecting to now and here
a feeling of your body from the inside out does the rib cages expand
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and for the next three or four breaths to continue relaxing your body
your shoulders your face your belly
and then settling into your breathing
perhaps with every exhale
letting go of the thoughts that have arisen
maybe Letting Go twice once at the beginning of the exhale
and if there's enough time perhaps uh letting go in a relaxing
at the end of your exhale
maybe so the exhale continues
for a few moments more
relaxing into the silence
and what is your experience when you are not distracted by thoughts
okay
thank you
foreign
and then to add to the question
how might you appreciate others when you're not not distracted
when you're not distracted I'll make you better appreciate other
people
and it's customary or a deep practice
to dedicate the benefits of Buddhist practice do the welfare and
happiness of others
and that might begin by appreciating the value and the
importance of others
and simply that appreciating other people is the beginning of bringing them
benefit happiness well-being
and may it be that our ability to be undestructed
enables a greater appreciation of others
so that we're motivated
to be in the world to benefit others
may all beings be happy
may all beings
live into their potential to be happy
may all beings be safe
May there have capacity to feel safe inwardly and outwardly
come to a great fruition
may all beings be peaceful
May their capacity to experience profound peace
be easily accessible for them
and may all beings be free
May the inherit inherent possibility
of being free from oppression
inwardly and outwardly
may they be free of that may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you [Music]
seems like I have to go and push another button to make all this work here hang on a minute
this okay it worked great so um
hello everyone and I'm quite happy to be here with you all
and what I'd like to do uh this week is to continue this intermittent series
that I've been doing when I'm here related to compassion
and the premise around this is that
the desire to live with compassion to be
more compassionate is supported by understanding the many things that come together to really let
allow compassion to be strong or full complete
and that a quick headlong movement into compassion
might be okay but it might leave out too much of ourselves it might leave too
much of our potential or the fullness the full embodiment the full
quality of compassion that is nourishing
that is beneficial certainly for the people we have compassion for
and also for ourselves that we don't leave ourselves out in
being compassionate and one of the reasons for that is that compassion we have the way we care for others
is so much better and cleaner if we have cared for ourselves properly if we
include ourselves as a foundation for a healthy form of compassion
so to understand the different elements and Dynamics within ourselves that
contribute to a healthy compassion is a is really important
and so many weeks ago I said there were five different elements that come
together for this kind of healthy compassion and um so there were five A's so
awareness Attunement appreciation
aspiration and then the action and um and so to take time to understand
these different aspects of compassion and things that contribute the foundations for them and then to uh bring them along with us
when we're going to be compassionate and that can be second nature after a while as we understand it so it doesn't take
that long and or the each of these different foundations can be cultivated so that
they are there more often for ourselves
and so the um
so I've I've spent now a week on these different on some of these elements
there was a week on awareness and a week on Attunement and today I want to spend
this week on the week of appreciation and I mean the depreciation is a
wonderful quality I hope that each of you understand that when you feel
appreciation for anything at all that it's a nice feeling it's an inspired feeling it's a it's a kind of a happy
feeling to appreciate something appreciate oneself appreciate others appreciate our experience our Good
Fortune what's happening and the ability to
um appreciate is a enriching experience for anybody's life
to spend more time appreciating in a realistic way the goodness the
benefits the well-being The Good Fortune we have is an antidote to spending too much time
ruminating about our Misfortune what is not going right
and um there's a kind of sometimes a certain bias that many human beings have
for being a to of tuning in to their Misfortune and overlooking their Good
Fortune what it is to appreciate and um and some people who live lives that are
a dream for many people around the world who are poor and oppressed and
challenged in so many different ways um there's a dream that they could live that way
people who live that live in a you know and sometimes in a
modern Western Society where there's so much
so much available for us we don't appreciate how much is available how much support how much
goodness there is how much benefit we get because we focus more on the areas
of our misfortune not to dismiss Misfortune but to put it
in the context of something larger and put it in a more maybe a realistic context
and one of that those ways is to appreciate more and then take in the benefits of
appreciation and for compassion it's invaluable to
appreciate the people we have compassion for and to appreciate them in deep ways not
some surface way or not some policy of appreciation but really to take people
in and one way to really appreciate well is not to be distracted by our thoughts our
concerns our worries about people about what we feel we need to do not be
distracted by our sense of responsibility which sometimes can be activating and oddly enough
distance us from others if we kind of inhabit the uh the strong ideas and
feelings I should do something I'm responsible I have to do something it's up to me all of which kind of maybe puts
the focus back on oneself but to take time to be in our direct
experience to appreciate others in in deeper and deeper ways
so appreciation is a number of things one is to value
whatever we appreciate I think we value give give it value give it importance
so to appreciate other people is to see them through with if it's valuable see
if there's important to see them with uh um yeah see that they're they're
precious human beings they're valuable human beings that they're important human beings
and if we want to be compassionate to people we also need to consider what it
is that supports people what what they benefit from and how they we they their situation can be improved
and not a few people their situation has improved if they experience others
appreciating them that others treat them as important as valuable
and just to stop and do that is invaluable
and and if we get caught up immediately we need to do something we miss the
opportunity there have been times when people homeless people have asked me for
something and maybe it's my circumstance that I'm not in a situation to provide them with
what they want and um and certainly been times in my life where I just kept walking and ignored them
but this idea that this that it's a gift to appreciate people
I've turned towards them and said hello or said I'm sorry or not right now or
but I wish you well or thank you it really stop and take them in and look at
them at least and and not to to you know to ignore them as if they're important people and so
this can be done in all kinds of circumstances in family and friends and work and that we take the time to
recognize them and they're important um and everyone is important to not see
everyone as a valuable human being in some way or other um
by looking past what they do to see their potential to see something deeper
in them than their their actions is one of the great things even people sometimes who
are doing things which are harming others sometimes they do it because they have never been valued themselves and they're
hurt and they're spreading the hurt around the others to others and the ability to stop and see them in
a deeper way than their actions sometimes transforms them that might be
beginning of what stops them from their maladaptive Behavior
so to see that everyone's important and part of appreciation also many
people feel or sometimes explained is gratitude that there's also a feeling of gratitude
that we're receiving something from others we're receiving their goodness we're receiving benefit from them we're
we're receiving you know that we benefit also from other presence of others
and what does it take to be grateful for a stranger grateful that they're alive grateful
that they connected us to life more fully grateful that here too is where we
bring our practice and our love our care here thank you
and um the um um and so the value to see the
importance of people to be grateful for people that they exist no matter their circumstance
that uh whatever their age is we appreciate them
whatever their nationality is we appreciate them whatever their race is
we appreciate them whatever their gender is and now we understand there are many
variations of gender many and to really allow people to kind of inhabit who they
are and and um and appreciate them for deeply
it would be as a gift to appreciate their sexuality through who they are sexually whatever Partnerships they have
without others whatever their orientation is and again there to appreciate the variety the richness
of uh sexual expression and and you know it's kind of pointless
to diminish people for their gender or their sexuality their nationality their race
but to step forward and say yes hi you are important and valuable and
dignified and equal member of the human race and
people whatever ability people have and I appreciate so much now that we
understand that there's such a wide range of ways that brains operate ways
that uh abilities that people have and that each
one is if a pool the human being regardless of
or as they are and abilities and mental abilities emotional abilities physical
abilities and um and to really kind of no matter who comes in front of us
to have the first instinct the first kind of approach approach to take the time
to perceive them without distractions to perceive them without judgments to perceive them without commentary
to perceive them with a willingness and an openness and a wisdom to see this too
is a full maybe uh perfect maybe or something this too is a
human being that can be appreciated as a human being as they are
and uh there's a lack of this in our world
probably all over we go we find a lack of people being appreciated deeply
and I know people who just simply going to the supermarket and shopping
they can feel that there's people don't appreciate them for whatever reason all
there's so many reasons we do this people who are short or feel like
they're overlooked people who are old experienced feel that they're overlooked people ever who are of some minority
race feel that they're ignored people who display characteristics that or features
or of whatever way that people are ignored or dismissed or worse that goes
on it's a form of care and love and and
benefit for oneself and for others to appreciate them to be
grateful for them to open and allow ourselves to see them as dignified and
valuable human beings and wouldn't this be a good foundation for compassion
I said maybe less compassion is needed in this world
if we treat each other this way so appreciation will be the topic for
this week and um and I'm looking forward to I appreciate
the opportunity to spend this week on this topic and appreciate all of you for not only
being present here today for this but also so many of you have been present and for so long on these 7 A.M sittings
as YouTube sittings and I really feel uh it's been invaluable for me and
to be able to come in in and offer these teachings and have these kinds of
considerations so I want to thank all of you and um
may we continue thank you