Hello friends hello and greetings from Mountain View California I'm seated
alone hope you are well In This Moment In Time and uh delighted to continue our
exploration together this week and the important practice of
why speech that we engage with every day externally and internally
and um a day will um explore
two of the invitations or or directions that the Buddha gives us about why
speech given that there are six I want to explore and we have five days so today we're gonna do two and the two
today are is it is it beneficial is it connected to the goal of the path or is it idle chatter
so we're going to actually bring all of those together in one and the other one is it kind is it kind so
is it beneficial is it kind so we will uh begin with exploring that
um exploring these in our inner speech in our inner practice
and uh um then we'll explore them with uh dharmet so
let's begin Let's uh let's land in our bodies
let's arrive in this moment in time
together
letting there be a sense of uprightness in the body
now Pride but not uptight a sense of uprightness of integrity
enacting with your values why am I here
why am I sitting practicing In This Moment In Time
answer that for yourself
and after connecting with your intention spending your intention
toward this period of practice with kindness
directing turning your awareness inward the body
sensations of the feet and the Earth stabilizing grounding
sensations of your sit bones your bottom on the
cushion the chair your hands on your lap
these touch points
help them ground you
connecting with the breath and the abdomen the lower part of the
body so that there's a sense of grounding settling
connecting becoming aware
aware of the sensations of the breath
in the body calm and settle
and then when thoughts arise the inner speech arises
let us know not to be entangled with or absorbed
with but just to know
is this inner speech beneficial is it connected with the goal of the path
it's connected with my intention In This Moment is it beneficial to me beneficially find in that way
is beneficial connected to the goal of the path in this moment
or is it idle chatter
simply getting to know and if you decide it's idle chatter can you be kind and
maybe smilingly smilingly let go
and also noticing the tone of this inner speech is it kind
is it spoken with a mind of loving kindness
towards yourself towards others shining the light of awareness
of mindfulness on our inner speech
and then when you've seen when the heart has known as seen
with mindfulness and release let go
let the breath the sensations of the breath and the body be primary settling
calming centering
foreign
Let the Body be relaxed the Mind relaxed and no seeing
the landscape of the Mind the heart
seeing it with kindness not deluding ourselves
and Gathering collecting with the breath
of the sensations of the breath
foreign
and we just utter and listen to Silence with it
which is what's most beneficial In This Moment
internally
listening to the silence kind silence Within
foreign
and as we turn to the end of this sitting together
Let There Be kindness a heart the mind of loving kindness towards yourself
or having showed up or having practiced as best as you were able to without an
attachment to outcome in a particular way you've done
your best letting go of any self-judgment Let
There Be appreciation for yourself and and others this wonderful Sangha other
practitioners who support you by they're showing up
for their practice collectively let us all
recognize the goodness co-created here and offer a share
this goodness this Merit to all pigs everywhere
May our turning towards goodness this goodness serve
not just myself all beings everywhere in ways I cannot imagine may all beings
be safe from harm inner and outer harm
be happy and joyous be healthy as much as
possible and have ease in their lives especially those in challenging
circumstances around the world right now natural disasters Wars
mailing especially those be free from suffering
may all beings be well may all beings be free including ourselves
uh greetings everyone I'm delighted to be
continuing to share these important teachings
on why speech part of the Eightfold Path
the third path Factor so
why speech appropriate speech not only important in the way that we impact the
world not just with our speech but with our writing our text our tweets
with their phenomenal speed and and reach but also how it shapes and forms
who we are so taking it on not just as a set of moral rules that I should not lie
I should not um speak what's not beneficial but really as an internal scaffold of who we
are to form our own Karma the person we are the person we are becoming is is
Sublime training and
um one way that
um an author James clear the author of the book Atomic habits a great book
puts it in a secular way but really it's about how we build our Karma uh is about
our actions and note that in Buddhism actions aren't just physical actions
they are um mental actions when you think that's considered a mental action uh Speech
action of of speaking and of course physical actions so actions really takes
everything um into consideration so with with this quote
um consider action in in all these ways including speech so
so from James Clear every action you take is a vote for the type of person
you wish to become no single instance will transform your beliefs but as the
votes build up so does the evidence of your new identity
so if if you so I love the way they think about every action as a vote for
the type of person you wish to become so I want to be more ethical I want to
to not speak idly and just blah blah blah blah blah
so with this now um we uh this being the fourth day we've
been covering we've been discussing this I want to remind us of what we've discussed so far so the first was is it
true what what I'm about to say is it true and factual
um there's some nuances of factual it's not just our perception our our imagine our our perceptions or our emotions but
also is it factual supported by facts so is it true and factual was the first one I discussed on Monday
and uh and then the second day we discussed is it
divisive is it divisive or does it create Harmony
then we added some Nuance to both of those and then yesterday we discussed is it harsh and abusive or is it gentle is
my speech uttered in anger or both internally and externally of course or
is it gentle soothing to the ear agreeable as the Buddha directs us to
speak thank you So today we're going to add two more and
tomorrow the last one um so is it idle chatter or is it
beneficial so these are from two different teachings as I mentioned the first day but just to remind you the
Buddha gives uh in one list there are four um definitions of um of what is why
speech and in another uh uh uh teaching he gives another five and they kind of
map but not quite and if you put them together you end up getting six so so
um in fact let me be more specific so the um
uh so the um so maybe I'll share that that on the
last day I'll just given their remaining time I'll talk about these two okay I'm just gonna move on
um so so is it is it idle chatter so
idle chatter um is considered unwise speech or wrong speech inappropriate speech and idle
chatter um any talk that's not associated with
with Liberation and freedom and and the Dharma for monks is considered Idol
chatter and the word actually idle chatter in Pali is an onomatopoeia
um is a word that sounds like what it is it's some papalapa some Papa Palapa and
the first P has an h i after it so some papalapa is like some papalapa you know just the sense of some papalapas
right it's you get the sense so so any speech that's not associated with The
Liberation for monks so so they have a higher standard it's considered some
Papa we're lay people we have a different standard we do engage with with others
in a social way with our co-workers with our friends family speech has a way to
Bond as a way to to make relationships and not every
um conversation will be about Liberation and yet to consider is it is it idle
chatter are we just opening our mouths to just fill the space blah blah blah
blah are we feeling uncomfortable with with silence and just rushing to fill it
in um how are we feeling how how are we
feeding our mind with what we say and also what we consume are we consuming
some Papa lapa just blah blah blah blah blah blah just like idle chatter social
media Island Shadow yeah Somebody went on vacation okay great I'm happy for them but some people is it all some
Popple up um what are we consuming what are we um what are we putting and how are we
engaging are we indulging uh because we are
trying to get the self our self-sense or are we getting riled up so so all of
these all of these questions about why am I speaking in fact there is the great
acronym from the teacher Jonathan uh Faust and the acronym is weight w-a-i-t
and it stands for why am I talking I love that why am I talking so
internally why am I talking why am I talking in this moment why am I talking
and having a little bit of humor with that can be helpful why am I talking
um is it um yeah why am I talking what is my intention right now why is what is my
intention and again it goes back to the intention why am I talking am I just feeling space or is it beneficial is it
beneficial for my own benefit for others benefit and benefit not you know greed
hate or delusion but is it connected benefit is defined as the goal of the
path so whatever is connected to the goal of the path is is considered
beneficial for for my benefit other people's well-being benefit in this way why am I talking why am I talking
so the Buddha instructs us to abandon
abandoning Idol chatter one abstains from Idol chatter one speaks in season
speaks what is factual what is in accordance with the goal the dhamma and
the vinaya vinaya is the rules for the monks so this part it was for the monks and then one speaks I love this one speaks
words worth treasuring one speaks words worth treasuring
seasonable reasonable circumscribed connected with the goal words worth
treasuring so that is one question to ask ourselves
is it idle chatter what I'm engaging with or is it beneficial so bringing
those together and then the other question the other um uh directive but Buddha gives us I want
to cover that in the time remaining is um am I speaking with a mind of loving
kindness am I speaking with a mind of love and kindness and in shorthand
um this guideline is often expressed as is it kind what am I what I'm saying is it kind and
I like the the shorthand um is it kind because it's short and yet
I don't love the shorthand and I'll tell you why because is it kind is is kind of
is cutting um is cutting ourselves short of the goal of how actually Buddha
speaks it you know the directive in the suit is given Ally speaking with a mind
of loving kindness yes it's a mouthful it's long but it's different from just being kind you can say something that's
kind but may not be completely spoken with it mind of love and kindness right you can just be try to be kind yeah
great it's a great start please say things that are kind wonderful it's a great start but imbuing speaking with a
mind of the heart of love and kindness is is the more wholesome the more complete uh aspiration for training
ourselves am I speaking with a mind of loving kindness and yes of course
whatever comes from that mind of loving kindness spoken with that then it is
spoken with with kindness it is going to be kind but um that is the invitation and um
imbuing our hearts with a mind of good will for ourselves for others 360 degrees so not just speaking for their
benefit and to our own detriment or other way around with really kindness 360 degrees and in fact another teaching
uh Buddha says that one doesn't say something that's to one's own detriment
so this mind of loving kindness covers covers it all
it's not just other focused it's it's really internal and externally focused because you are part of the all beings
this being is part of the all-being so for benefit of all beings no one left out
and and um imbuing our hearts our minds with loving kindness before we speak can
support us uh to minimize the agitation of remorse and regret later
so a lot of uh
you know beautiful teachings just grateful to the Buddha all these beautiful teachings and tomorrow we will
turn to the last one um which is is it timely is it the right time and as all these things that we
have discussed so far um if if they are satisfied yes yes yes but
it's not the right time it's it's not it's still not it's not wise speech and the Buddha gives some beautiful
teachings about is at the right time um and there's a that I'd love to share
with you tomorrow so so thank you so much everyone for your practice today for your showing up
and um for for today's practice day I'd like to invite you to
to become sensitive to your speech in regards to these two things one is is it
idle chatter what I'm consuming and what I'm speaking is it idle chatter or is it
beneficial and bring in This Acronym weight why am I talking why am I talking
in this moment is it better to be silent um and then also am I speaking with a
mind with a heart of loving kindness what what am I bringing in here am I speaking with the heart of loving
kindness uh and if you feel like it's it's juggling too many balls just pause pause come back to your body it's okay
to have silence it's okay to be silent for a moment get your bearings get your get
reconnected with with your body heart and mind and and uh engage again
so thank you all delighted to be practicing together thank you for your
practice um may you be well may you be free see you tomorrow