uh welcome everyone my name is May Elliott and this week we'll be focusing
on the five hindrances with each day focusing on one of the five and uh
during the Dharma talk I'll offer a practice uh that that works for all five
hindrances kind of a one-size-fits-all practice however each hindrance has its own
specific antidote and uh and during the guided meditations each day we'll explore the antidote for
each of the hindrances so today I'll be speaking about sense desire and one of the antidotes for
sense desire is observation of impermanence so the emphasis of the
meditation today will be noticing the passing away of experience and particularly if there's anything
Pleasant in one's experience watching the passing away of that
um as for the the structure of the meditation we'll stay with a primary
anchor and then if something becomes predominant will allow ourselves to connect with that new object then coming
back to the main anchor again so let's go ahead and get started
go ahead and find yourself in a stable upright posture
something that allows you to be alert and also relaxed at the same time
and connecting with a landing point for your meditation primary anchor
a place where your attention can rest that might be the breath I might be
focusing on sounds or it might be tuning into a global
sense of the body I'm just going to the bodily posture sitting and any of these
are fine as a as a primary anchor I'll provide instructions for working
with the breath but please stay connected to whatever anchor works for you
so coming into um a meditative space
all right taking a few deep breaths
and seeing if it's available to let go of anything extra
softening the muscles of the face the jaw
relaxing the shoulders
softening the belly
um and setting the intention to be here for
this time together
allowing your attention to make contact with the breath
the soundscape or the bodily posture and then sustaining that contact really
intending to be with it for the full length of the inhale the full length of the exhale
staying with whatever experience you're with
and if you notice that there's a lot of thinking this morning
you might just bow to the thoughts releasing them and then just slide right
back to the breath no need to be hard on ourselves for
thinking judge ourselves just the function of the mind to do this
in the same way that the mouth produces saliva uh the brain produces thoughts
this is just the function of that organ
so it's okay if there's thoughts now we just kindly direct the attention
back to the breath back to our primary anchor
so we'll take some time now to land together in silence sensing our experience
with a felt sense of the present moment
foreign
try bringing your attention to the end of the exhale
noticing the ending of the breath
noticing the way that the exhale slowly Fades out and dissipates
so we're allowing the mind to register the ending of things
foreign
knowing that the source of suffering is craving
clinging if we're able to see the endings of
things the passing away of all phenomena it's much less likely that we will
crave and cling to pleasant experience if we know that even that will pass away
so we're training the mind in seeing the endings of things so that the cheetah the heart mind can
be trained in letting go can be trained in seeing that all things pass
no need to Crave or cling anything
even if we get it we get what we want it too will pass
so to have insight into this quality of impermanence
allows us to hold things with an open hand
with a heart of non-clinging
developing Equanimity for the arising and passing of all experience
foreign
and as you breathe you might notice if there's any other Body Sensations that
are predominant in experience
maybe a sensation in the knee takes your attention
so then you allow the attention to feel the sensations in the knee
let me zoom in on those Sensations to really get a feel for them
you might notice the arising and passing of those Sensations
noticing if foreign
sensation in the knee is no longer predominant anymore seeing that passing
away and then returning to the breath
or if there is an itch noticing
the passing away of the sensation maybe the escalation of the sensation
changing from mild to intense and then the sustaining and the passing away of
that sensation so we're just taking some time now to
notice Body Sensations watching Body Sensations arise and pass
with a particular emphasis on the passing
foreign
foreign particularly if you're noticing any
Pleasant Sensations in the body
may be the sensation of ease maybe there's some relaxation or spaciousness
or there's some gladness in the heart
foreign you can allow yourself to attend to
those Sensations
allow yourself to be nourished by them to really take them in
and then be present for their passing away
and sometimes they might sustain for a long time or a short time without much
change just really being there for when there is a change
and if there's nothing Pleasant In This Moment maybe only a neutral experiences neither
Pleasant or unpleasant or maybe there's Pleasant or there maybe there's unpleasant Sensations
that's fine too you can attend to those and see see the passing away of them as well
foreign
of experience where you can attend to the passing away of things
where you can observe impermanence is at the ear door noticing the passing
away of sounds so you might try that now
sensing into the soundscape maybe there's bird calls or there's
traffic sounds
I'm taking a moment to rest in the soundscape sensing the passing away of the sounds
foreign as we do this practice we might notice that some
some Sensations some sounds they actually sustain for quite a long time
one area that we can notice the passing away of these things is just when the
attention shifts to a different object so there might be the sound of the refrigerator hum sustaining in the
background but when the the attention shifts from the soundscape to the breath
that refrigerator hum momentarily passes away when we shift the focus of our
attention
so that's another way that we can attend to the passing away of experience for
objects that seem to sustain
foreign as we near the end of our meditation
together see if you can notice the moment the
meditation the formal meditation comes to a close noticing the passing away of this
experience the way that it goes into the vanishing
and may our insight into impermanence our understanding of this change be a
catalyst for our own Awakening and The Awakening of others
may all beings be happy healthy safe and
completely free
foreign
welcome back I hope you enjoyed the meditation again my name is May Elliott
and I'm really happy to be here with you this week so for for the first several years of my
meditation practice my Central Central task of meditation was coming back to
the breath the mind would deviate from the breath and I would bring it back and then I
would do it again and I would bring it back and I'd bring it back and I'd bring it back and I'd bring it back this might
sound familiar to you and while this is skillful in many ways it really took a
long time for me before I realized it would actually be worthwhile to see why the mind was leaving to begin with like
what was happening that was causing the mind to deviate from the breath in the first place like what was hijacking the
mind and taking it for a ride so it wasn't until I started learning
about the five hindrances that I really started seeing what was fueling my discursive thinking and why it was
happening and then how to become free of it so I really see a study as the
hindrances of the hindrances as being essential for anyone training in
meditation which is exactly why I want to spend some time covering the basic
teachings on the hindrances this week so this is such a helpful training for for
anyone interested in the art of meditation and it completely applies to
daily life practices as well so this is really a Cornerstone for learning how to
be free in one's life and in one's practice so the five hindrances are start with a
sense desire the second is ill will often referred to as a version
um the third is sleepiness also known as sloth and torpor the fourth is restlessness and the last is doubt
so these are five specific states of mind that the the Buddha named as being
known for obscuring clarity the hindrances inhibit our ability to see
clearly they they cover over and Veil the mind but we usually don't even notice that
they're happening there's a way that
um they're they're almost sneaky in the way that we get hijacked by them but we
don't even know that they're present so by studying the hindrances we're actually taking a look at the veil and
we're taking a look at what inhibits the clarity of mind or we might say we are unveiling the
veil we're studying that which obscures so in this talk I'll share
a general singular practice that can we that can be used for working with all five of the hindrances can vote one size
fits all practice and then each day I'll go through through each hindrance one by
one to share some of the specific information about that hindrance and some particular ways of practicing with
each so today we'll be talking about sense desire in Pali that's Kama Chanda
and ways we might think of this hindrance include as we might think of
it as craving wanting to acquire things longing grasping
and this hindrance is at work when We crave food and drink when We crave
entertainment sexuality it can be mild or it can be
the force behind staggering addictions so since desire might be at work if
we're hankering for another Netflix episode or if we're decorating our
living space or if we're seeking pleasurable music or the perfect cup of coffee then it can even be active when
we're we're trying to recreate a blissful meditation experience so these
can all be expressions of sense desire so as you know we have five senses
seeing hearing smelling tasting touching in Buddhism we talk about six senses the
sixth being the mind the mind is considered a sense gate and thinking is the activity
um so sense desire is craving for Pleasant experiences at any of the sense
Gates um because the and because the mind can really conjure anything that lends
itself to fabricating things that we want it lends itself to fabricating the
idea of pleasant experiences Pleasant sense experiences so generally what's at the heart of our
sense desire is a feeling that something could make this moment better that this moment is insufficient and that
happiness resides in the next sense pleasure experience and in Western
culture there's this this kind of unspoken story of how to create a happy life like a happy life is when we can
string together enough back to back Pleasant moments almost like stringing beads onto a necklace
and avoiding all of the unpleasant moments and then that's that's what we call a happy life
um but of course we don't have much control over what's Pleasant and unpleasant and um as I touched on in the
meditation anything that's Pleasant passes away anyways
so now I do want to note that not all desires are a problem
you're wanting to be free from suffering uh to be compassionate wanting to be patient like these are actually
wholesome Desires in Pali Kusa La Chanda or dhamachanda and these can these can
refer to Wholesome Desires in contrast with tanha the word that's used to
describe describe craving that leads to suffering
and yet while not all desires should be let go of you know we don't want to get
rid of our desire for awakening or to be kind it's good to have the ability to
let go of them because we can still suffer even if we're we're grasping a wholesome desire
okay so now that I've shared just a a bit like the the lay of the land around
sense desire I want to share uh the the one size fits-all practice that you can apply to all the hindrances
um and if this is the only thing you take away this week um it will serve you well um so it has just two steps to it it's
really simple um and it's uh the first is to recognize and the second is to feel
um so that's what we're doing when a hindrance arises we're recognizing it and we're feeling it so the first
recognize we're recognizing what's present often when we're entranced by hindrance there's typically an object
we're fixated on and this is particularly true with desire and ill will the second hindrance you know we're
fixated on wanting a better apartment or feeling annoyed by a grumpy co-worker so
in these situations we're preoccupied with the object with the apartment or
with the co-worker then there tends to be a lot of mental proliferation about getting what's wanted or getting away
what from what's not wanted and and this is where the practice can be extremely beneficial in meditation
instead of just being lost in thoughts and then bringing the Mind back to the
breath if you notice the same theme coming up in the mind multiple times like oh that
restaurant thought again or um shopping thought or a sexual fantasy or whatever it is
um this is a great moment to practice this first step of recognition um and you might just ask you know is
there a hindrance present if you notice that track replaying or another way to
put this is um what's fueling this thought what's fueling this thought what's behind this
and then sometimes that can help us recognize the hindrance that that's operating below the mental proliferation
so we might realize oh this is sense desire or oh this is doubt and it's
really helpful to know a hindrance as a hindrance like to be aware that it's
present we're we're so often transfixed by the storyline of what we want or don't want
that we don't even know that the desire or the aversion are fueling the whole show
so sometimes just the act of naming something in this act of recognition
um makes it so something loses its power so sometimes if there's something within
us that's asking for attention to recognize it to identify it gives it the
attention it's been seeking and it can release the author and psychiatrist Dan Siegel
coined the phrasement and so sometimes there's a way that this
act of naming it can allow for release so so
um I have a chronic health issue and that and that health issue can make it so that for me digesting food can be
painful so if I eat one bite too much I'll often experience physical pain for
a number of hours so I have to have a really precise relationship with sense desire for food
and it's not uncommon that a food thought will arise in the mind maybe
maybe an image of an ice cream cone floats across the screen and if it's not
a time that I can eat that food the mind will pretty quickly recognize ah craving
and it will drop the um the thought and it will drop the associated craving so there's a way that
that recognition allows for a release and of course this Letting Go isn't
always available so in these cases simple recognition won't cause the hindrance to dispel so
then we have the opportunity to practice the Second Step so recognize and then secondly feel so we're feeling the
hindrance and specifically um in the body we get to know the
hindrance get curious about it and investigate what's going on
um so in this way of working with the hindrance with the hindrances we let go
of obsessing about the object and instead turn our attention 180
degrees to look inward at the desire at the aversion the restlessness the doubt
turning to look at those at um themselves so so this can begin to
pull us out of our trance out of our daydream rather than trying to get rid of the
hindrance we turn and look at it with an attitude of acceptance and openness we we recognize and we feel it
but I want to say just a little bit more about what I mean by feeling it um like how do we get curious about it
and get to know it um we feel feel the experience in the body like is there tightness is there
pressure is there tingling or heat so that's how what I mean by feeling it
and for sense desire there's often a contraction or tension in the body so
you might just see if that's present for you other ways we might feel the experiences
we might sense what sort of energy is in the body is it high or low energy maybe
a high frequency racing or on the other end of the spectrum maybe a heaviness or
drooping or lethargy and for sense desire for some people it
has a heightened energy to it because there's a motivation to get something there can be a forward lean
um so we might also feel the interested in the hindrance in the mind heart what's
the emotional tone um how does it color the mind oh what
does it make you want to do are there repeating thought patterns um so we're just we're exploring it when
we feel the hindrance so that's it two steps recognize and feel really easy
in in applying these to sense desire it can be really interesting because
sometimes sense desire at first glance can can present itself as being quite
enjoyable like we can get really excited about a home improvement project or
um or maybe there's a new purchase and the thought can have kind of a pleasant
Sparkle to it and under the surface as we begin to
investigate this further often what we find as the Mind becomes more settled is
that even that that state of craving itself um is a state that reflects a a sense of
insufficiency there's an underlying sense of not enough or of lack
so if you're having a hard time staying mindful of sense desire of doing this
practice of recognizing and feeling then you might try an antidote so an antidote is traditionally a
medicine taken to counteract a particular poison and this isn't any different so when do we apply an antidote to a
hindrance so when a person has become overwhelmed or has the sense of like I can't deal with this then it's time to
try something different so if you've practiced mindfulness of the hindrance for a while and it's not
softening then you might apply an antidote to just to help restore the Natural Balance of the Mind
so as we went over in our meditation today one of the antidotes for sense
desire is impermanence or inconstancy um you know whatever it is that we want
will pass away in time and in deeper meditation uh watching the passing away
of things to actually observe impermanence at work this can more more deeply mature our wisdom and and when we
understand at a deeper level how everything is falling away and changing it's really hard to be fooled by sense
desire because we know the pleasure will pass so so lastly and with all the hindrances
don't miss recognizing when they're absent um you know allow yourself to feel the
goodness of a mind that's free of sense desire and I mean allow yourself to register the felt sense the felt
experience of satisfaction and contentment because the more satisfaction you're present for in your
life the less likely it is that the mechanism of sense desire will need to
kick in to begin with so um so just maybe a moment of for a
moment I'll just mention Just a Touch about the attitude we're meeting the hindrances without judgment it's just a
neutral seeing with a wise Calm Mind of a grandmother like oh just desire just
craving it's okay so um during your day today I hope you're
able to recognize and feel any expressions of sense desire that might
arise for you and I hope you can do this with a sense of playfulness curiosity
and patience thank you so much for your attention this morning and I hope you have a lovely day take care