hello everyone and
welcome and today I want to introduce
meditation as generosity that the act of meditation is
a continual Act of generosity and
uh and in that regard I'm inspired that
that in the classic teachings of the Buddha the upper reaching upper reaches
of spiritual growth of meditation practice is a very
profound letting go and it turns out that some of the
words that the Buddha uses for letting go he has a number of words maybe it's
such a central part of his teachings that um the more you're involved in something
the more variation and names you can have some of us will just call a wave a wave but
oceanographer might have many different names for different kinds of waves or
clouds are just clouds for me but someone who knows about clouds can identify all the different
types so uh the variations of letting go
but some of the words the Buddha uses for letting go have a double meaning and they also mean
generosity one of those is the word chaga c a g which uh means to relinquish or let go
and it also is used in the Buddhist teachings as a as an expression of
generosity there's a word translated as um as uh relinquishment into English
which also has the meaning of giving or generosity
and one the way we can understand this is that uh if you hold something tight
in your hand in order to give it away you have to also let go you have to also
relinquish it and you can you Poss relinquish under
Force against your will uh it's possible to do it reluctantly but it's also sometimes we
do it with our generosity our sense of delight and appreciation the of Freedom
here like there's no almost maybe even no self-consciousness in the ACT no it's
not about me it's just about the Delight of hear please and this it's an expression of our
freedom so it's in that that regard that we talk about meditation is
generosity to let go into the present
moment an act of generosity where the giver and the the
receiver are the same we give fully let go
fully not hold on to anything fully and we
benefit we give so we can be free we are free so that we can
give and meditation is the opportunity where really the giver and the receiver
are the same we do it so deeply and fully that the notion of giving and
giver and receiver Falls away the Oneness of giving and letting
go the Oneness of generosity and
relinquishment so to assume a posture for meditation but to do so as an act of
generosity to yourself that this meditation posture
gives you you're giving yourself a chance to sit with
dignity to sit in a way that or or whatever posture you have to have a
sense that there's dignity and nobility there is respect for this body
for ourselves for our hearts and that's an act of
generosity and to let go of the ways in which we collapse
or the ways in which we're under the weight
of challenging emotions certainly we can have them but to but to succumb under
the weight of them is not a generous thing to do it's also not generous to the
difficult emotions but to take a posture of
dignity respect as if your difficult
emotions are being respected as if you're rising to the
occasion to meet them as if you have value and
dignity and then to gently close your
eyes even closing your eyes can be
generosity the generosity of offering your full inner attention
now to yourself without being distracted by
sights around you like you're sitting with a friend on
a park bench to really listen to the friend and close your eyes to sit with
yourself to really listen feel be
here and then taking a few long slow deep breaths it's a gift to your body to take
in a deep breath of oxygen and it's a gift to your body to
relax as you exhale
a kind act to the body here relax
soften and then to let your breathing return to normal
allowing breathing to be a gift that supports your
life and that as you exhale do not only let go
of the old Air that's being released the carbon dioxide but let the exhale also be a
release of tension in your body
scanning your body for where there's holding that you can let go of and in the Letting
Go offer something good for your body the absence of
tension
and if you also relax your thinking mind think of that relaxation as a
gift do doing something good for the
mind and appreciating it as an act of generosity no matter how small the
Letting Go the releasing relaxing is appreciate offering the gift of
relaxation to the thinking
mind
for and if you're caught up in
thoughts let go of the thoughts but let
go as a form of generosity as a way to offer something
beneficial here it's okay to relax let
go moving the thinking mind
to a healthier functioning one that's not caught in the
grip of
attachments
for
for centering yourself on your
breathing and with a very openhearted open-minded
way giving attention to your breathing as an act of
generosity it's it's a way of giving space allowing breathing more
room it's a way of valuing and
appreciating this life here and
now giving ourselves over to breathing is an
alternative to the mind being free to be involved in thoughts which are
tense or stressful
disconnecting to appreciate the giving of attention to
our lived experience breathing in and breathing
out
for
to keep you in the rhythm of the breathing to keep you in the flow of
attention think of attention let attention be an act of
generosity a relinquishment of
distractions a giving of oneself to the
breathing
giving oneself to to give all of
oneself to the present moment of our own
experience and in this way giving ourselves
over to ourselves to the lived experience of
ourselves
now
for
e
rather than giving yourself over to thinking give yourself over to the
immediacy of your lived experience through your
body your heart through the inner
experience of being here and
now
for
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting part of the tremendous benefit of giving ourselves to
ourselves to give ourselves over to the fullness the
three-dimensionality of ourselves here and now to be in our body sensing and
feeling part of the benefit of that there's much more of ourselves here
now with which to be present for other
people we're less likely to be distracted less likely to be caught in
tension less likely to be fragmented or
divided different divided their divided attention divided
intention we're much more we have much more to offer in the gift of listening the gift
of seeing the gift of attending to this life to
others and may it be that this practice of ours gives us the capacity to be present
for this world that we contribute to people's
happiness their safety their
peace and their freedom from suffering may that be our
Legacy may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be
free and may our ability to be
mindful be a gift that contributes to this
possibility [Music]
thank
you
e
so I come to this last talk
on kind of a little bit of my story my story in the
Dharma and yesterday I came more or less to
the the beginning of IMC here in Redwood red Redwood City and being able to
purchase this building that I'm sitting in and we're able to do it out of the generosity of the sellers the two
ministers Christian ministers who wanted us to buy the church because they also
provided us with the necessary loan to buy it and it would have been hard for us to have had the money also it took a
year and a half from the time that they told us that we're interesting selling it to us before they even showed us the
building and that worked really well for our mindfulness approach just doing things mindfully
slowly uh uh caringly we kind of got ready and prepared for this process and
that was exceptional because in in this area back then uh you had to have made a
bid for buying a property probably the day before it went on the market it was
that fast you it had to be really quick and so we didn't really have that ability and and um and uh and also
wasn't the kind of our way of doing things and and it's important that we do things buy things move ahead build our
program on our in our community all in a way that feels harmonious with u the practice we're
doing that's harmonious with being hopefully being relaxed at ease not
pushing not trying to make something happen for which there is no um kind of momentum and delight and
enthusiasm for doing so after that the long period of
uh we bought the building and and that was phenomenally beneficial for our
community to have now this kind of blank canvas to grow our programs and grow all kinds of things and with that our
community grew and um both in numbers but but also in uh kind of the the the
maturity of people's practice and the different expressions of people's practice having a place like this
allowed people to develop and grow in leadership grow in generosity grow in um
goodwi and and and friendships Dharma friendships and Dharma conversations and
they became a very rich kind of network of Dharma life that people not to participate in that uh was really
beneficial for everyone including myself and uh and as it developed one of
the really key aspects of this was uh people's generosity and um generosity as
volunteers and we had a huge number we have a large large number of volunteers and um and also people's
generosity financially and uh we did buy the building with debt mortgage and I
think within two or three years we raised the money to uh retire the morgage and own the building
outright the same thing happened with IRC that um we you know it's there was a
Wellspring of generosity Wellspring of support and and uh in 199 19 2005 was
about the time we started to be serious about looking for a retreat center and
um and so we started the search and and um and a lot as we went along uh uh uh
it took a long time it took about five six years of searching and looking but that also was beneficial for us it
prepared us for it and eventually we were able to uh raise enough
money and uh and then and we were able to buy the building and we had a mortgage at first and uh and a variety
of things happened that I think probably within um I would say um six years that morgage
was put to rest including the tremendous generosity of some of our some of our uh
big donors and um but also for thousands of
people from all over the country that uh really want really inspired by our model of
generosity and uh and for these last you know 24 years now or so uh that I or 20
plus years of live of practicing here in IRC uh I've been inspired over and over
and over again by the generosity of the community and how much support there is
and it's been part of my uh certainly vision of having a community a Dharma Community where that's the case because
I feel I believe that Dharma practice unfolds best where it's all voluntary and it's all given freely to
the people who come and so this ability to give freely by everyone uh is
beneficial it's it's a gift to ourselves to do that and so it's a gift to others
and this mutuality of giving and receiving and how they're all kind of folded together is such an inspiring
thing and this to see it operating in this community is is uh one of the great
experiences of my life and um so we were here and we were able
to start developing programs the community was maturing and as they mature we developed more programs and
for to match the maturity of where people are at and um and EV visioned
grew of being able to uh support people in the Dharma in this practice uh in all
areas of their life kind of expand outwards and keep developing and certainly The Retreat Center was one way
of doing that at some point it became clear that uh to mature further people are really ready to have easy access to
Retreats and to sit with us and and uh and to mature
there and um it's became very successful the retreat center and some ways that
does the the idea of easy availability of of offering Retreats freely was
fulfilled because to rent facilities which we did before that was so much more expensive and it would have been
more and more out of the reach to do a as many Retreats as we do every year and um so it's phenomenal that we have this
beautiful Retreat Center we developed a study center not IMC particularly but this community and
we have the Sati Center for Buddhist studies which is thriving and kind of grew slowly and now it's thriving over
the last few years uh one of the great things that rose out of here was uh
because we had this place partly and was possible to enion more for new things uh
with the study center Sati Center Buddhist studies after uh 2001 uh September 11th
2001 um that had a huge impact on me and I some point I felt I was walking on the
beach someplace thinking about this and um and I think you know this had such a big
impact on me that uh it's it's going to do it's going to actually be a kind of continuation of the
violence if I'm not changed by this event changed for the the better and uh
somehow something has to change and be different after that horrendous
event and um and I said what well how how do I want to be different how do how do this the scene the Arma communities
that I'm involved and how can we be different after something like this and after in that walk on the beach I
decided oh let's start a Buddhist chaplaincy
program Let's uh I learned just enough about chaplaincy that what a deep
spiritual caregiving it is to people who are not just Buddhists but all walks of white life in the times of the greatest
crisis in their lives um that they go through in in uh hospitals and in
prisons and in hospices and many different places chaplain kind of meet
uh they're like firefighters they run towards the fire chaplain go towards some of the greatest suffering that
humans have that other people may sometimes pull away from and I so we started a chaplaincy program an
introduction to Buddhist chaplaincy and it's not a full-fledged professional chaplaincy program but it opened the
door it has been for not for 20 more than 20 years it's continued and it's one of the bright lights of my life the
fact that we open this door to the world of spiritual caregiving to so many people who come and do the training and
that that program has developed now into not only in-person program but a second online person uh program
and then to I did it partly to support the continued maturity of this community uh the IMC Community because I felt that
we had to learn we had to develop people who grew in spiritual care in compassion
expressions of their compassion and we had a community of people to caretake for people were dying and getting old
and going through their own crisises and I felt it we important to develop we grew to develop a a community that also
could care for each other with all the different things and
um and so um it's been a a
phenomenal pleasure joy for me and a growth for me to become see my own
practice my own generosity my own Letting Go My Own clarification of my
intentions clarification of my mind um of my heart to watch it in this kind of
rich rich world of Dharma growth that we have and I feel so grateful to be able
to be so much opportunities now to develop teachings and develop programs
and to allow people to grow and develop and expand outwards and fill in the gaps
of what it means to be a fully developed you know Buddhist practitioner
fully developed human being in this world and how we've supported different people to individuate in different
ways uh because we offer so many different things that kind of support for Direction people to go in different
directions and and I think one of the really uh
impactful things of this growth of this community over these years is my phenomenal
appreciation of the individuals who I encounter the phenomenal uh appreciation
of the uniqueness of each person um as they follow this path of awareness of
mindfulness of care and compassion um the um there's one thing
to offer teachings and another thing to take those teachings and personalize them in each person for their own kind
of path through life to find how to support that and and coming to really appreciate the beauty of everyone and
the sincerity of people and and how each person has this beautiful unfolding that
is their own and uh it's not a cookie cutter kind of approach though sometimes
the teachings might sound that way just do this follow the breath or something but it's not the it's not cookie cutter
it's it's really it's it's opening a breathing room and space for everyone to find out kind of who they are and who
they are in this complicated world and how we participate in this world in a
rich way and uh you know I set myself up many
years ago to set my I dedicated my life to try to make this world a better place
to come to the end of suffering in this world and uh in the scale of suffering in this
in this world you know perhaps I've just done a drop maybe not even a drop of
difference but I feel that it's phenomenal what has grown and developed
uh over these years with so many people stepping up to support and to practice and to
Dedicated that uh uh I never would would have when I set myself my dedication to
kind of to alleviate suffering the world and make that the central focus of My Life um the um I I could never have
imagined that how much we've been able to do here and now uh as we continue uh with
our community and now the expanded community of so many people like you all
um spread out across the globe spread far and wide uh it's very exciting for
me to see how it grows and how now there's new potential um during the pandemic we
expanded our potential with this with technology being able to do this now uh online and reaches more people and we
have now a whole kind of uh uh online onine Retreat Center we call it Insight
Retreat online that is offering Retreats for people online that have been very
very impactful and so to watch this growth and this development and now I
find myself still quite inspired what we're doing here and quite inspired by
this my role as a Visionary and quite inspired by the potential that's still here and how
we're still growing and developing in this field of generosity and um it's very important for us to do
it in a dharmic way in a way that's relaxed and doesn't Force anything but
uh I take Delight in the dayto day of what we do here and the momentum of and
I'm curious very curious and interested in discovering where we go next and how
we continue growing and developing in this phenomenal Community now of growing number of teachers growing number of of
practitioners growing a number of mature people and um and uh I look forward to
the chance to continue benefiting this world and alleviating suffering wherever
we can so thank you uh very much for
allowing me to speak this for last two weeks and I do wish that I had uh taken
time to take questions from you and I'm going to look for an opport Unity for that sometime over the next period and
um where I can find some freedom and we'll do one of these some freedom of time to be able to uh maybe take some
time at the end of this to have one of the community meetings we've had and next opportunity we'll do it um I'm
going to be away on Retreat next week so Matthew Bren silver will be here next week and then I'll be back for one week
and then uh not here be last week of uh of the year
so thank you very much and um then I look forward to our
continuation