oh yes reminded that Martin Luther King day it's one of my favorite holidays and
Martin Luther King is one of my heroes and I appreciate him so much and
part of it is um all kinds of reasons too celebrate him
for myself I I I've put tremendous value in the
in the people who have advocated for non-violent
a change they're dedicated to non-violent civil disabedience and
and the courage to do that against tremendous odds and violence
then how what a powerful lesson it is for us that there's an alternative to violence
takes a lot of Courage and um
that I think that uh I'd rather
not live in a world where the first choice to settle disputes is violence
so
hello everyone and welcome to this Monday and it's a holiday here in the United States
celebrating Martin Luther King Jr and um
I think it's one of my favorite holidays for what though all the tremendous good that represents in the values that
Martin Luther King stood for and I wish we could have more celebrations of such values
so so these weeks
the focus on these 7 A.M is is how to practice with challenges
and we're still laying down the foundation for doing so
and today for the meditation I'd like to suggest that one of the very important
foundations for living with challenges dealing with challenges is our physical
body and well I shouldn't say physical body I should maybe say the body that we
experience the experience body if I say that because the way we
experience the body is a is a Cooperative Enterprise of the mind and
the body they participate in our sense or the way we experience our bodies not
separate from how the mind processes it and registers it
and this experienced body that we can feel and sense and know
uh is not static it's not it's a lump of Flesh it's something that's dynamic
and wise and it's not just the recipient of
challenges like a victim of challenges uh it's a
it's Instinct it's kind of nature is to is to respond and process and work with
whatever is coming and there's a tremendous uh
movement in this body to homeostasis to Healing to wholeness
if we allow it and so when there's challenges it's it's quite powerful to especially like in
meditation um to keep coming back and how is a body
experiencing this and not only experiencing it but how's the body processing it
I like the expression composting it how I feel what the chat what the
challenge feels like in the body uh but trust the body
don't uh don't um kind of just be the recipient and just
kind of the person who's the burdener burdened by whatever's happening allow the body
to trust the body trust how the body make room for the body feel it in the body
and there's a number of things that can happen one is that they can be very grounding
it's very easy they get ungrounded now uncentered disoriented
by being in our thoughts and stories and ideas and spinning around and being in
the body is an alternative for being repetitively glossed and caught up in the spinning mind so being in the body
is grounding being in the body gives us a more
sensitivity to what's really happening there if the if that sensitivity what's
happening there is too much for our degree of sensitivity then it's useful to uh move the body
let the body's movements allow things to be easier to be with and for people
doing mindfulness practice the two meditation practices that are embodied
embodied practices is sitting meditation we really feel it's all here but if it's
too much then to stand up and do a walking meditation and let the walking be the movement that holds it all
perhaps there's more to be said like this but this is the basic ones
and um but keep referring back to the body refer back to the body
Let the Body be the center and don't ignore everything else but see
if the body if you trust the body of the body can somehow make space
make room for the challenges you're feeling Within
so the trainings are huge training and mindfulness so training and mindfulness of the body
awareness embodied awareness so that's what we'll do today
so taking a meditation posture
and this posture we take is such an important resource support
for how we can be what challenges to take a posture
that expresses confidence Express is a kind of
I can do this dignity
value confidence in the posture
even if you don't feel confident it's possible to assume a confident
posture and that makes a difference
and then to gently close your eyes
and to begin inhabiting the body discovering the body
to take long slow deep breaths
feeling the rib cage stretch and expand as you breathe in deeply
maybe expanding of the belly
maybe a lifting an expansion of the back rib cage
and as you as you inhale all as you inhale
then as you exhale let it all relax
letting your breathing return to normal
and continue to relax the body and the exhale and as you relax it
let that be an occasion for sensing and feeling more fully the area that relaxes
feeling it and sensing it with a silent mind
on the exhale relaxing muscles of the face
relaxing the shoulders
relaxing the belly
relaxing your legs thighs calves
so that you're not Fighting Gravity
you're going along with gravity so your legs feet
feel more grounded on the surface that supports them
and then gently become aware of the body breathing
imagine the sensations of breathing in the body
is the center of all things and you stay close to that Center
staying close to breathing
around the edges of that Center through your body
how are you feel your way into how you are right now
while being centered breathing in and breathing out
and whatever Way You Are feel it how it is
in your body to be this way
with breathing being a gentle massage or a gentle stroking
touching how you are in the body
but staying primarily with the breathing
so you don't get lost in concerns about how you are
foreign
and if anything takes you away from your breathing
that concern or preoccupation is there any correlation any way that
has shifted how you feel in your body
know the distracted mind physically
know your emotions as they appear physically
trust the body feel how it is in the body whatever is happening
Sound Outside what's happened in the body
feeling the body while continuing to breathe in the room
mindfully
trust that the most important thing now
is to experience your life as felt by your body
and perhaps that's a protection
from spinning out in thoughts
even a protection from Fear
becoming too strong
and if there is fear or distress in the body
feel it as long as it's comfortable to do so
or feel elsewhere in your body places of stability
spaciousness calm
that can support you with a challenge
okay
imagine for the last five minutes of the meditation
that your body has a tremendous confidence
to be present for itself
to feel it's embodied existence
and all the sensations and emotions and activities
the body can sit still and quiet process it all allow it all to be
allow it all to move sit with this embodied confidence
with the mind starting to become more quiet and still
and as we come to the end of this meditation
to bring your attention in your body
to where there might be a tenderness or a gentleness
maybe where there is a love or care
good will
and how does that live in you how do you feel this in your body
is there some way that you can for a minute or two here make a room
for kindness and Good Will towards others
an embodied sense of kindness gentleness attentiveness
and to wish to well have well wishes for others
no matter who they are or where they are do we be nice if they could be safe and
happy even our enemies might be nicer to
everyone if they were safe and happy and peaceful
may we share this human life together
offering our good will sharing it with everyone
perhaps we never know we might be planting seeds of Good Will and kindness
all over wherever we go who knows how they will sprout
after we're gone
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
male beings be peaceful
may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you
so good morning or good day and we'll continue this ongoing series
on practicing with challenges in any challenge at all from the minor
to the extreme though the extreme might need Extra Care and attentiveness and and uh
any kind of a specialty to it but maybe we'll get to that later in this ongoing
series but we're laying down the foundation now and um
the elements that are really helpful for being able to address whatever challenges we have
so today this week I want to focus on What's called the four foundations of mindfulness I think most of you know
what they are and I've taught about it here before the body feelings mind States and mental
processes and and how they can be a tremendous
support Foundation kind of a grounding for working with challenges
and to introduce this idea I want to tell you a Buddhist Fable kind of an
Tale that of it's kind of like that Chicken
Little and the sky is falling there was a rabbit in the ancient world
who would who was um sleeping taking a nap under and mango
tree and at some point a mango
a big big mango from high up in the tree fell on the ground right next to the
head of the rabbit was sleeping and with a big bang and a shake and a
woke the rabbit up and the rabbit immediately assumed that
the sky was falling so the rabbit jumped up and started running away yelling the sky is falling
the sky is falling came across a a school the whole herd of rabbits
and uh and when they heard that the sky is falling they started screaming and running along too a sky is falling the
sky is falling in they went further and they came across a us a whole bunch of
deer and the deer heard about this and they started running too the sky is falling and they went further along and
they saw the water buffaloes and the water buffaloes and elephants started
and the Elephant started and everybody started running all of them thinking they about to run fast because the sky
was falling and um and uh high up on the mountain on a
cliff overlooking all this that was a Lion and the lion could see that this
huge mass of animals was running right for a cliff and would kind of jumped right a fall right off if they kept
running at the speed so the lion kind of quickly got in front of them jumped in front of them and
roared and said stop and then he asked you know what you know the elephants why are you running oh
because the water buffalo said the sky is falling as this as the water buffalo
and they said oh it's because of the deer and the deer said oh it's because of the rabbits and then why did why were
you running the line asked the rabbits and all the rabbits looked at the first rabbit and said well we heard him say
that sky is falling and um and the uh
and that so then the lion said well let's go investigate where were you sleeping
so they went to investigate went back to the tree and there right next to where
the rabbit was sleeping was the Big Mango and everyone realized that there was no
sky falling it was just a mango that had fallen so uh in this jatica tale this birth
story the story of course the Buddha was the lion in a previous lifetime
but the important thing was this idea of knowing to investigate
and if we if we don't have them the Mind capability to investigate what's
happening then with challenges we're kind of sometimes caught up in the swirl and the agitation of it all and the
preoccupation and and more importantly the assumptions we have around what's
happening the concepts the abstractions the future the plannings the predictions
the the kind of all kinds of fixed ideas
about who we are and what's happening to us and so the ability to stop before we go
over the cliff and investigate to take a good look what's Happening Here
requires knowing where to look where is the grounding where is the useful places to bring attention
and and so the Buddha offered these four areas what's called four foundations for
establishments for mindfulness and so when we're in challenges
we can check in with ourselves uh how are how are these particular
areas being experienced how is it being felt in the body
is this Pleasant or unpleasant what kind of mind state is operating when I'm caught up in this involved in
this challenge and what are the mental processes that are reacting and and and uh
to the challenge and what are the mental states that are supportive of being with the this Challenge in a better way
so those four areas is an alternative to the abstractions we
live in the big stories and predictions and ideas that are generated by fear and
by anger and by confusion it's a particular subset of the total
whole Gestalt of it all a Gestalt which is often
infused with imagination with assumptions with
predictions with thoughts and beliefs and ideas about self
and some of the ways that we enter into challenges actually limit our ability to it wisely actually part of what makes it
the challenge so much more difficult is the ways in which our inner life
responds to it and lives with it and is confused by it or caught up in it and all that
and because that's so much of the challenges the challenge is not the challenge challenge out there or the
challenge but rather what we can call the challenge but rather how we are in
relationship to it it's so powerful to do the mindfulness
check-in check in with ourselves go through the checklist if you like such things
okay this is challenging now how does this how is this being felt in the body
what is activating the body where am I tense in the body where am I contracted in the body
am I even connected to my body or am I disconnected to my body with all this what's happening here with the body
uh what's happening with the feeling tone is this really unpleasant is it really Pleasant more than a physical
experience the predominant experience is the unpleasantness of it all
what's happening with the Mind States that you know is it confined contracted
is the Mind filled with desires and greed and wanting something so desperately needing something so
desperately or is the Mind angry and blaming and upset and guilty all the
kind of kind of forms of aversion is the Mind confused perplexed lost
is the Mind narrow and tight is it expansive and open how's the Mind state
and then or then the mental processes is there are we operating with the hindrances
is there ill will is there consensual desire or covetousness is there sloth
and torpers their agitation restlessness remorse is there doubt
it or is there calm can there be calm here is their mindfulness can there be mindfulness
here is there a curiosity and investigation
is there Joy is there Tranquility is there some ability to stay focused here
and centered concentrated what about equanimity so as we do this check-in
we can discover which of these predominates and sometimes what predominates or what
or where which of these four needs the most attention we're Gathering the information together
about how we are so that we can know how wisely to respond to the situation
this presupposes we do this check-in not in the middle of a traffic accident in
the middle of having the accident when we have to take care of things but we're doing it when we can like in
meditation or when we're not right in the middle of the fire of a challenge that we have to put out the fire
other times do the mindfulness check-in and notice which of these four
predominate know how they operate then you're in a better position to
respond and know what to do after the check-in and the check-in can
go quite quickly and it might be the responses to go for a walk or call a friend or do
something really nice or it might be to go to bed and put the sheets over your head it might be all kinds of things
that you do it might be to go meditate but you're Gathering the information to
see how it's happening here and you're breaking the trance of the minds kind of
overall picture and fear and concern of what it is you're beginning to break that caught upness in the assumptions
and the sky is falling kind of attitude it's very respectful to do this kind of
check-in to really get underneath the surface of the assumptions the beliefs that are operating with it all
did you find out what's Happening Here and then based on that deciding what to
do but if what you're doing is mindfulness like mindfulness meditation
then as we see which is most predominant or which is most in need of being really
present for and one of the the defaults that is many
times is useful not always is to stay close to how it is in your body
feel the embodied nature of it uh what's happening in your body trust
the body don't treat the body as a static victim or res just a receiver of
experiences it's a participant in experiences it has its own wisdom it has
its own goodness its own its own um what what it brings to the ex to
what's happening if we allow it if we make room for it if we're willing to kind of drop into the
body get centered grounded in the body and then let the body process what's
happening and some of this is because when we're challenged there's can be a lot of
reactivity a lot of tension and tightness and contraction
in the body and so by feeling the body the body wants to relax and as we allow ourselves
to feel it's kind of like we get out of the way we're not continuing to direct
attention from the mind to the body the mind is lighting up so the body has a
chance to relax so um
so the mindfulness check-in it's a way of uh changing the
perspective of what's happening for us that's useful to do
at the right time as I said earlier when we're not right in the middle of having to deal with
something but you know when it we take it home with us or you know when we're more in this quiet situation
and um and maybe there's a time and place to do the mindfulness check-in the
four foundations and see what you learned from that and so for this week we'll go through
this checklist we'll go through and see how to use these four foundations
as a way of bringing it a useful perspective
to our lives when we're challenged um it's an alternative perspective
then maybe the perspective that we usually bring and by doing the checklist approach this
other perspective it might highlight for you the perspective that you were bringing
you might you might then see it more clearly and maybe see that some of the
perspectives some of the assumptions and beliefs that go into how we respond and see a challenge maybe our
optional provisional not needed that actually interfere with their ability to
be wise and how to care and take care of challenges
so mindfulness checklist and um and uh
so for the next days we'll go through these four and emphasize its value of each one and tomorrow we'll do
a very important topic the four challenges which has to do with
mindfulness of of the pleasant and the unpleasant
where the pleasant actually has a very important role
so thank you and may you
go through the checklist today periodically and see what it does for you in different circumstances
thank you