so hello everyone and aware that in one way
many of you are spread out throughout the globe
participating in another way you are here in
IMC at Redwood City California here in our meditation Hall
and um I'm happy to have you along and to share this practice and this teaching
and this community together with all of us so um
one of the things that classically the classic Buddhism and I think we do
plenty enough in the modern world is we associate we sometimes treat the
mind as almost like another person sometimes we
certainly we identify with our mind as being this is who I am but sometimes we kind of relate to the mind as if it's
another person almost it's not that not us any more than Maybe
I don't know if this is a good analogy but after you cut off your fingernail clippings those clippings are not quite
you anymore so there's kind of a freedom kind of a independence from the mind
um which we can upon with which we can look upon the mind we can see it we can
relate to it we can be wiser than certainly parts of the mind that get us into trouble
and um so in that regard sometimes it might be helpful to think of the Mind
as a child and sometimes children in order to feel safe I need to have
clear boundaries set you know you know and usually with some kind of hopefully
compassionate but very clear statement of no so a certain one of our our sons
he was I think much more aware and understanding of the world than we ever imagined when he was young
before he was verbal or when he was just a toddler and um
and now he was somewhat afraid quite a bit I think because he was so smart he
kind of understood much more of what was going on or much more of maybe the dangers or something
but sometimes he would push against the limits of what was appropriate behavior
and and it was necessary to say no and now you have to stop or that we
don't do that here or something and sometimes they have to be said very clearly definitively
and uh sometimes when we uh we it wasn't exactly my character to do that
so I had to kind of learn to be able to say say that and the remarkable thing that I saw
was that for a moment he would look very frustrated and angry
but oh just a moment immediately afterwards he became much
more subtle than happy it's like now he knew the how far he
could go he could he could know where what he was supposed to do or it was understandable now something about the
world he didn't understand and maybe he was pushing the limits of things to see to understand better how
does this world work and then it says no would tell them and and then he would just relax
so in the same way our mind is that the way sometimes
sometimes practicing acceptance of it or being
compassionate to it and in ways that just allow it to continue the way it's doing
sometimes sometimes that's exactly the right thing to do and sometimes it's not
the right thing and sometimes what's appropriate is to say no
not that stop we're not going there we're not doing that
we've had those thoughts those feelings those fantasies
thousands of times and having and thinking about ruminating about it
doesn't help doesn't lead anywhere maybe it's so it's kind of a waste of
time to do it now A Thousand and One Time or this train of thought this train of
ideas and desires or versions doesn't help anyone it's not supportive
maybe even makes things worse and so the Mind needs to hear
a very clear line no we don't do that
and how we tell the mind this how we establish a strong no in practice
that's uh not harsh not punitive not judgmental not diversive no hostility
involved just a Clarity a Clarity and a definitiveness no we don't stand behind
this this is not what we do sometimes it's phenomenally helpful in
meditation especially if you know what you're thinking about
is nonsense or is just simply not just an old Habit to continue ruminating
about something so the wise use of no
and the wise use of saying no and then averting the gays attention from what is
not wise to what is wise and for the purpose of meditation here is to focus
on breathing
present moment so maybe for this meditation if you'd like you can experiment
as I guide you with um finding a way to
appropriately in a healthy way
to say no to things which are not appropriate
not healthy so assuming your meditation posture
and
if it's comfortable closing your eyes
and begin with saying yes yes to being here in this body at this
time maybe taking a few long slow deep
breaths and the exhale can be a long yes
here I am this is the place a clear reminder
here now
letting your breathing return to normal and scanning through your body to see
where you can relax face the shoulders the belly
and you might gently softly say yes to each little movement of
relaxation a yes were you allowed to appreciate and enjoy
the benefit of relaxing
and then also maybe relaxing a thinking mind
stepping away from thinking and ruminating first with a gentle yes to relaxing
softening quieting the thinking mind
maybe with each exhale
and then settling down on your breathing gently ever so softly
maybe a gentle yes or a gentle
almost like a silent acknowledgment
it's a yes to the inhale yes to the exhale
and if you find yourself wondering often thought frequently
experiment with saying no
or enough stop
or if it feels nicer to do so you could say more politely
this is not helpful let's stop
enough now we have something else to do
something very brief and you might try experimenting as you
say the no to the thinking mind
to do so at the top of the inhale before you exhale
it might take me in holding your breath slightly so the shorter the statement is
the better and after you've made your statement of
no
then relax let go with the exhale
saying no to thinking at the top of the inhale
and maybe enjoying quiet surfing on the exhale
foreign
is there anything at this moment that it would be useful even
compassionate to say no to
no to your involvement with
and then as we come to the end of the sitting to turn your attention outward
to this suffering world to the people that you care for
to the world you care for
and consider your love your care your kindness
Your Capacity to serve this world better
is there anything that you have within you
that you could compassionately say no to
that reduces obstacles to your love
to your care to your kindness for this world
and in saying no to it it makes more room
for Goodwill for well-wishing for kindness for
friendliness and may it be that this meditation we do
supports us to be a friend of others the friend of
the world may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
and may each of us contribute to this possibility
as friends of the world
[Music]
[Music] thank you
foreign
so then continuing today with the strategies for dealing with challenges
and we have healthy strategies and unhealthy strategies
and all too often the unhealthy strategies the which are often our best efforts to
cope with great difficulty sometimes makes situation worse or we
spiral out we get caught up in the reactivity to
the challenges we have and and sometimes that reactivity or the
caught upness or what gets triggered in us can be so strong that it's uh can be
overwhelming and challenging so it's helpful if we develop a habit of
looking at how we are in challenges with the question what's that my strategy here what am I trying to do
how am I reacting or responding to this challenge that I have
and so there are five hindrances are often unhealthy strategies
and we're trying our best to cope with it but we're often choosing a way which
maybe can seem beneficial but actually is not
and this is particularly true with the second of the hindrances which is often translated into English
as a version and so in Buddhist English we have to understand that when the word aversion
is used it it doesn't mean just simply the state of averting ourselves from
something but it's also the state of having certain kind of hostility or ill
will towards something and sometimes uh the the instinct to
fight the instinct to attack the challenge we have um it can seem uh very productive or
very important or appropriate or justified in the moment and but uh and maybe it even
accomplishes what we want but it does so at a tremendous cost
and the example that I've used often I apologize for repeating myself is again
back to my son when he was young um there were some times when my no to
him uh was I used what I called my strong voice
and um and I'm afraid that I was you know pretty angry by that time that I used it but I I felt like this has to
stop and so I had a strong voice and then he would stop and
um times when I said no to him and it was appropriate there were times it was helpful for him to hear that and he
would be happy afterwards he knew the limits of what he could do and he understood the world a little bit better but when I used to a strong voice I
would accomplish what I wanted to do and I said oh that worked you know and and that was good but then sometime
later I heard him using the same voice for his younger brother
and I thought oh my what have I done here what kind of conditioning what example have I given of what's
appropriate how to be with people and so the long-term consequences of of
the strong voice kind of strong no aversion sometimes it accomplishes what we want in the moment
is not so healthy it creates unhealthy relationships perhaps
so um so but you know it is attempt to take care of ourselves at times
as other sometimes uh a version or no is uh doesn't really take care of ourselves
what does it take what's it what it's taken care of is our desires taking care of our our conceit
and um and we don't want that threatened in any way we want to be able to do whatever we want
so there's a whole world of strategy that comes into play with the second hindrance with a version and we have to
understand this is a strategy we're trying to accomplish something in the world through it
then the question is is there a more healthy way of accomplishing this you know some of the same things
a more healthy thing that we would want so the the the uh the healthy side of
aversion is averting there is a healthy appropriate turning away from things
stepping away from things I'm not going to say that I'm not going to go into that I'm not going to participate in
this and um but it isn't with hostility it isn't with uh anger
it isn't with um shutting down but it's saying this is not working and until
somehow this can work better I'm going to step back I'm going to turn away and um and so there's all kinds of
healthy turning away that we can do in our in our life and our strategy
so turning away so we can recover turning away so we can settle ourselves or discover ourselves
understand what how we've been impacted so that later we might be able to if it's appropriate to come back and have a
conversation or deal with some issue but to go ahead long you know
rushing into trying to take care of our problem that doesn't have to be taken care of in
the moment maybe there can be even a few minutes wait so we could catch our breath get some
clear sense of what's happening so we can find other strategies besides hostility
besides blaming someone and sometimes that hostility is directed
to oneself and um and that's just as important when the hostility is directed to the blame
is directed to oneself the guilt the shame the you know here I did it I made
a big mistake again I um that kind of aversion or hostility or or criticism of ourselves
also is a strategy that trying to make things better but it
doesn't and so is there another way is there a way of recognizing wow that
didn't work maybe I did say something I shouldn't have said and I'm going to turn away from that I'm
not going to do that again but I'm not going to attack myself I'm not going to live
under the weight of guilt or shame I'm going to do something better
I'm going to say no to it and in the future I'm going to dedicate myself to doing better in the future
I'm going to find a better way and so in Buddhism we learn from the past just enough
to be inspired even be encouraged there's a better way I'm going to find
it I'm going to do that I'm going to say no to behavior which is not healthy
and try to find healthy ways of doing that there are definitely times where we want
to learn to avert times when we want to say no there's a way of saying no to someone
that is not um attacking them or exactly saying
you know you're wrong that can't be done but we say no I can't participate in
that no this doesn't work for me no
um I think that if that's the way this conversation is going I think that I
need to step away a little bit and I need to regroup because this is this kind of conversation
um and causes me to not come from my best place or to be clear I
don't want to I feel my anger coming up now and I find that I don't want to be able I don't want to talk from my hostility
and my anger can we take a break I'd like to go around the block and chill and then you come back and you still are
very definitive and say no this doesn't work this is not right for me or can we find we have to find a different
way so we're definitive we're clear but we don't come from a place of
hostility the strategy we have is how can we find a way to be connected how can we find a
way to cooperate in this endeavor how can we find a way that um that like take care of myself in a
definitive and clear way I stand up for myself but no one's attacked that no one there's no hostility
and um and so there's I've noticed I've seen sometimes
in Buddhism where we have the strong value of not acting with aversion not having a
version that people misunderstand it to think they're never allowed to say no
they're never allowed to turn away step away from something
because oh that's a version or something so that's not true so
the strategy there's a strategy of averting and that strategy can in One Direction
it contains hostility ill will in the other direction it contains
wisdom it contains non-ill will not hostility
and and in the non-hostile way of saying no or averting
so it's possible to have that be very definitive and being definitive and establishing
clear limits of what's you're going to participate in or what you're going to do can be done with love can be done
with kindness it might not be reciprocated people might misunderstand
but on one hand that's their problem psychologically for themselves that's
what they have to come to terms with but many people are not going to do that so then you have to decide
if you explain to them more the impact of their actions how they are or maybe
you see more clearly what they're capable of and what their Tendencies are and it gives you more information about
how much you should step away saying oh this doesn't work at all I don't think we can find a way here now
that I understand this person is kind of stuck in that particular thing
so um so one of the most important things I
would like to suggest is that around this is that when we're challenged
take a little bit of time to consider what do you what in relationship to the
challenge are you trying to do what do you what are you trying to do
what are you trying to accomplish and how are you and is the way you're trying to do that does it work is it
healthy because many times and challenges people are operating from gut reactions
sometimes with um you know quick decisions or
things are not considered or not thought out and um and so a Dharma life is one where
we don't act impulsively um sometimes you might act spontaneously
but we never act impulsively where we're acting from our reactivity we take time
to ask the question what am I trying to do here what am I trying to accomplish and is the way that I'm doing it is it
for the welfare and well-being of everyone concerned
and that I think is the real key of a Dharma process is how is this how can we find a
way that's the best for everyone involved in the conflict even the people who are causing so much trouble
it does not mean we have to put up with it it does not mean that we have to we can't avert and step away or be clear
but the notion that it's not me versus you
um but rather yeah what's best for all of us you don't have to say that you're
doing that but that leads to long-term well-being
hostility only leads to very short-term well-being at the best
so asking yourself what are you trying to do and is the way you're doing it is
it really healthy for you and for others and for this world
so thank you and um we'll continue going through these
strategies for challenges tomorrow