foreign bye bye
and hello everybody else welcome is there anybody here for their first
time oh welcome glad to have you here
um are you comfortable with my mask off great
so my name is Tanya Tanya Weiser nice to see some of you again I've seen
recently yep nice to see some I haven't
so I've been um of thinking about the asuta majma Nakaya
128. a lot and um
the things that I've really been struck by
as I've been kind of studying the suta is how much the suta is about generosity
ethical action and meditation and meditation in the broadest sense
from mindfulness practice meditation and daily life to concentration practice
and how supportive each of those things are
for supporting a clear mind
the it's said in the in the teachings that
the true nature of the mind is radiance
and as our mind is radiant our hearts is free to express
generosity kindness caring ethical action
so this particular suta and come back to the kind of
um well
it's named that suta is called Corruptions and it's um
in the translation by bikus Jato that I used so I don't read Paulie so I'm
reading the English and as it's interpreted
but you know and so the the um the Corruptions are really the things
that cloud that luminescent mind heart
and I'll talk about them more later but I kind of want to go through the suta a little bit and
really look at because these the qualities of generosity and ethical
action and meditation [Music]
are demonstrated more than they're really spoken about
so the suta starts with the Buddha in a monastery
and at that time there was a group of mendicants who were arguing quarreling and disputing continually wounding each
other with barbed words and when the Buddha was in this
Monastery a mendicant came up to the Buddha about stood to one side
and told them what was happening with these mendicants who were arguing
disputing and he said please Gert please sir go to
these mendicants out of compassion and the Buddha consented in silence
so when I just look at this um I see
generosity on the part of the Buddha right to consent to leave a monastery
who is meditating and you know
it's very ethical to take our time to care for our minds
to take care of our body hearts and mind and meditation and practice
foreign
Buddha goes to um these you know mendicants who are
quarreling arguing hurting each other with words so all of those things are the opposite
of generosity ethical action and meditation there's no
none of those qualities present and so he the Buddha arrives and he says
enough men again stop arguing quarreling and disputing
he said it three times and each time the mendicant I'm assuming the one that went
to go get him said wait sir let the Buddha the lord of
the dhamma remain passive dwelling in Blissful meditation in the
present life so three times essentially the Buddha tried to get these arguing mendicans to
stop the talk to practice and they didn't listen so three times
the mendicant says to him take care of yourself Buddha they're not
listening
so the Buddha robed up in the morning and went out for alms
and came back God is lodging in order and took his bowl and robe and
um and then he recited a poem before he left sort of right there
and he said when many voices shout at once no one thinks that they're a fool
so right away when people are shouting at once there's right no generosity
everybody's trying to grab the space there's no right speech right they're
all shouting so there's not ethical action and they're certainly not paying attention to their mindfulness
so he said while the Sangha is being split none thought another to be better adults
pretending to be astute they talk their Words Right Out of Bounds
again out of ethical action they blab at will so no restraint right
their mouths a gape and no one knows what leads them on so they're just sort of
the energies of the hindrances right these Corruptions are what are driving
their behaviors
they abuse me they hit me they beat me they robbed me is what he's saying they say
and he says for those who bear such a grudge hatred never ends
for those who bear no grudge no such Grudge hatred does have an end for never
is hatred settled by hate it's only settled by love this is an
eternal truth and to settle a conflict we need generosity right
we need ethical action we need to speak with wisdom we need to act and behave
with wisdom and to be mindful
the Buddha goes on to say others don't understand that here we need to be restrained so these
these um these hindrances these things that
obstruct the clear mind their energies
they they're they're it's part of nature we all have them they've had we've had you know they've been in our culture for
eons in the world's cultures
and if you know if we don't restrain them they they just keep going and they
grow their habits that becomes much more than a habit
our conditioning our personalities
and he says but those who understand this this need to be restrained
being clever they settle their conflicts right
Breakers of Bones and takers of lives thieves of cattle horses and wealth
those who plunder the nation even they can come together so why on
Earth can't you and he says if you find an alert
companion a wise and virtuous friend then overcoming all adversities wander
with them joyful and mindful if you find no alert companion
no wise and virtuous friend than like a king who flees his conquered realm wander alone like a tusker in the Wilds
a tusker is a male elephant with the tusks right large confident
he said it's better to wander alone there's no fellowship with fools
wander alone and do no wrong at ease like a tusker in the wild
so the Buddha says this and then he moves on and he goes to visit
um amendakin in another Village
and the mendicant was bagu and the bagu saw the Buddha coming off in a distance
so very much unlike the other group
when bagu saw the Buddha coming he spread out a seed
placed water for washing his feet and when the Buddha came the Buddha sat
on the seat and washed his feet and bagu bowed to the Buddha and sat down to one side
so we see the complete opposite expression of when someone's meeting the
Buddha here there's generosity ethical action and mindfulness
and the Buddha says to him I hope you're keeping well mendicant I hope you're all
right and I hope you're having no trouble getting alms food
and bagu says I'm keeping well sir I'm all right and I'm having no trouble getting alms food
and then as a you know response the Buddha educated encouraged fired up and
inspired bagu with the Dharma talk which is another you know set of
generosity right ethical action and mindfulness or meditation
so there's no mention of the that in the suta there's no mention of the generosity the
kindness that they're showing the care and regard it's just telling you simply describing this right so if you're if
you're you know there's this way I think in which the Buddha taught so much by what he showed us
we often will read a suta and if you just read the sutta based on the content
it's the content is much more focused on you know
ill will and hatred and you know sort of
um conflict and
and then the Buddha again sort of to me it's like okay he's at a monastery he's practicing he's invited he's asked to
come and help and so he just gets up and goes you know just responds and then he
goes to the combosos and they're arguing and he's no use so he leaves there and
goes and helps bagu and then he gets up and goes again
and he goes this time to see three venerables who were staying in the
Eastern bamboo Park and as he approached the park the park keeper saw the Buddha
coming along and said to the Buddha he clearly doesn't know who the Buddha
is right and he says don't come into this park aesthetic
there are three gentlemen who love themselves staying here
what a way to describe the mendicant staying in that Park three
gentlemen who love themselves staying here do not disturb them
and anruda who's one of the mendicants there sees the Buddha and sees the park keeper and so you know says no no it's
okay you know and calls to his other Companions and says come forth venerables come forth
our teacher the blessed one has arrived
so we see in this progress progression now in the second progression bagu was
you know stood and prepared for the Buddha and but there was not not this
come forth come forth our teacher the blessed one has arrived so we're seeing another kind of layer of welcoming
another layer of generosity and you know kind speech in this
and then the three venerables came out to greet the Buddha and all three of them engaged in this greeting so one
received his bowl and his robe one spread out a seed and one set water
out for washing his feet and the Buddha sat on the seat spread
out and washed his feet and and then the venerables bowed and sat down to one side
and the Buddha starts the conversation in the same way he says I hope you're keeping well
I hope you're all right I hope you're having no trouble getting alms food and anruda says we're keeping well sir
we're all right and we're having no trouble getting alms food so just taking a moment with this
keeping well you know that's a no it's important for us to keep well
right it's really meaningful to say I hope you're keeping well
and getting alms food is incredibly important because that's the you know what we need to survive and a body right
we need food and um
and then the Buddha you know goes on and he says because he's found out yes you're getting your nourishment you're
keeping well and and he goes on to say I hope you're living in harmony
appreciating each other without quarreling blending like milk
and water and regarding each other with kindly eyes wow that's quite a description right
like quite quite a lot for the Buddha to be saying living in harmony
appreciating each other without quarreling blending like milk and water and regarding each other with kindly
eyes you can see if they're behaving this way why the park keeper would say there are
three people who are loving themselves right and on Ruda says indeed sir we're living
in harmony as you say
and then the Buddha asked something incredibly important
but how do you live this way
so I think this is incredibly important to ask this question
I think it's a question we don't ask enough of ourselves
says if you don't question and discover the factors that contribute to a
positive State of Mind the mind takes those States good States for granted
so when things are good and going well ask yourself questions like what is
happening now why are things going well what attitude is present
in this way you start to recognize to really see
what we're doing to support the arising of well-being
both in our own minds and in our interactions with others how do you live this way
not just you know I hope you're you know you're in harmony but do you know how
you're doing this is so important for our practice
on Ruda answers and he has an answer he can say and what he says is
in this case sir I think so he's saying I think to myself I'm
fortunate so very fortunate so he's expressing gratitude right appreciation
and that's a very powerful and supportive factor for helping us value
what we're doing really important for us to kind of take the time to appreciate
what we're doing that's supporting our well-being
and he thinks he's fortunate to live together with spiritual companions such as these
I feel fortunate to have this Sangha here this place to come to have people
here to practice with and he says I consistently treat these
venerables with kindness by way of body speech and mind in both public and
private so in public and private it's sort of like internally and externally so it's not just an external expression
that he's doing he's actually relating to them in those same ways inside of
himself yeah sometimes we act kindly on the outside but we don't feel so kindly on
the inside and he thinks to himself you know well
I'm assuming like he has his own ideas come up right his own wishes his own things and so he says well why don't I
set aside my own ideas and just go along with these venerables ideas
and that's what I do though we're different in body sir we're one in mind it seems to me
and then the venerables his other companions they said likewise and they added that is how we live in harmony
appreciating each other without quarreling blending like milk and water and regarding each other with kindly
eyes so one of the things that um
the Buddha had said earlier was living in harmony right so you know this is
when we're interacting in a way that has a a pleasing effect
if it's music it's melodious but you know when you see people interacting together working together
if you've been on a retreat have any of you been on a retreat
yeah oh yeah well it's a beautiful place to see especially at the Insight Retreat
Center you know people are all in silence and then there's like
in particular I love the morning Sangha service at Insight Retreat Center
after the first meditation everybody clean spends 20 minutes
cleaning and they're just sort of dancing and weaving and working around each other
and everybody has their jobs and and doing them with such care and it's very
melodious it's really beautiful the other thing that I want to emphasize
here is the Buddha said Mutual are you being is this Mutual and I think this is really important
because it's like the song of service everyone is engaged right everyone is
engaged shared reciprocated
so you know they say yes we're blending while we're regarding each other well
and the Buddha says good good you know sadhu sadhu I hope you're living diligently keen and
Resolute so now you know are you also kind of living in a way that shows
diligence keenness and resolution so you know this diligence is showing care and
Consciousness in one's work or duties right
Keen sort of like having some ardencies some energy
you know and Resolute sort of admirably and purposefully determined unwavering
so are you living this way and he said and Ruda says yes indeed sir we live diligently and again this good question
is but how how do you live this way and on Ruda says in this case sir
whoever returns from alms round prepares the seats and puts out the drinking water and the rubbish bin if there's
anything left over whoever returns last eats if they like otherwise they throw it out where there
is and I love this little that grows so they're paying attention to where they're disposing of the food not just
to destroy plants that are growing or animals or they drop it into water that has no
living creatures again attending to the life that's there
and then they put away their seats drinking water and rubbish bin and sweep the refractory and if someone sees that
a pot of water for washing drinking or the toilet is empty so if you notice this they set it up
they're taking care of each other if someone sees that the um oh let's see
and if he can't do it he summons another with a wave of the hand and they set it up by lifting it with their hands
together but they don't break into speech for that reason
every five days we sit together for the whole night and discuss the teachings that's when they speak
and they talk about the Dharma and that is how they live diligently keen and resolute
and the Buddha says good good good
and then he says so he's going to move into a whole
nother realm with these mendicants that he didn't ever have a chance to even
begin with the first and wasn't kind of discussed or shared with the second
so now he asks but as you live diligently like this have you achieved any superhuman
distinction and knowledge and vision worthy of the noble ones a meditation at
ease so this is referencing deep concentration and insight
in general it's said that when people don't live in harmony with each other
they obstruct their access to the dhamma when we live in harmony access to the
dhamma appears this is probably why the Buddha is going further with these mendicants and his
teaching they're accessible and they're living in harmony so their access to the
dhamma should be available it should it should appear
on Ruda says well sir
and this is this is actually a really great example of how to talk about your practice
well sir while editing meditating and he describes how diligent keen and alert
and resolute we perceive both light and vision of forms
but before long the light and vision of forms vanish and we haven't worked out the reason for
that so
you know when we go and we're sort of sharing our practice it's really helpful to sort of name how we're practicing
what arises what we're seeing and that's when they're referencing this light and in the forms so what do we notice and
then what happens from there and so essentially they're describing
that they begin to get concentrated and then the concentration dissipates
and then he says and we haven't figured out why they don't they don't yet know why
that's happening
so the Buddha responds again with tremendous
generosity and um and he decides to tell them about his
own what he learned and his own practice and actually he shares about it from a
first person perspective and says this is what happened for me when that was going on
and we'll go through this but this is where the Buddha starts to talk about these hindrances
and how they arise in meditation practice and so he said before my Awakening
when I was still unawakened but intent on awakening
I too perceived both light and vision of forms but before long my light and vision of
forms vanished and so it occurred to me and this is so
important what is the cause what is the reason why my light and vision of forms
vanish and naruta was saying he hadn't figured that out but remember this is a
worthy question when you are meditating and things come up
and you notice them it's very worthwhile to reflect on what was going on what
changed what qualities were present and so the first thing that the Buddhist
shares that occurred to him was that doubt arose in me
and because of that my immersion fell away immersion is the concentration
when immersion Falls away the light and vision of forms vanish and then he says I'll make sure that
doubt will not arise in me again so doubt
I love in the suit that doubt is the first hindrance to be named
it is so common for us to have doubt
so common for us to question how we should practice right what is my
practice good enough am I good enough right what teacher should I listen to you know there's so much that we can
doubt and when we feel that doubt we we lack
conviction right we become indecisive or hesitant dubious suspicious confused
and those things really affect our ability to you know kind of be Ardent
right to be committed to be you know focused and energetic and committed to
our practice and there are many causes so the Buddha
actually doesn't explain what doubt is in the sutta I'm explaining it to you a little
bit and he doesn't say to them this is what
you'll feel when you notice doubt and you know he doesn't tell them what
the cause of Doubt is which in a way is also incredibly beautiful and generous because all of us
have our own experience of what doubt is and we all need to Discover it for
ourselves and know how it manifests in our practice and so he's saying look for doubt but
you've got to figure it out because we really all do we learn from
each other you know we we can read and but it's starting it's it's when we recognize it as it's arising in our own
mental space and our own hearts that's when we have the moments that wow
those are precious moments so these hindrances that arise are actually also the guides toward freedom
if we can recognize them and see them and meet them skillfully they're Treasures
they are part of practice they obscure the mind but they also when we work with them
dissolve at least temporarily
one one you know thing to think about um
in our modern society often a main source of Doubt is giving inappropriate
attention to thinking to speculating and analyzing to doing a
lot of thinking most of us have kind of a value of cleverness and thinking and
wielding these answers and you know but the Buddha's teaching
says thinking is the cause of many many problems
so I'll just you know I'm just gonna point to one little thing there's so many kinds of Doubt so I'm just gonna
point to one little thing and you know
the other thing is that um
yeah well let's see so then they'll just go on so then the
Buddha says while meditating and so he brings back up diligent keen and
Resolute this is how he was meditating I perceived both light and vision of forms
but before long my light and vision of forms vanished it occurred to me what is the cause what's the reason why
my light and vision and form vanished so he's not
feeling sorry for himself he's not trying to make himself have a
different experience he simply recognizing something you know
was getting clear the mind was getting concentrated and then it vanished
okay what happened and we have to be pretty close to that
event to be able to say what happened often right so it's really when we have
an event in our meditation and we get caught in a hindrance right wow just like gold is right there
if we can really say oh I want to notice not damn I'm angry again
but rather oh oh this is nature this is a rising let me open up to this can I
reflect what happened here what generated the appearance of this
doubt or what generated the appearance and in this time the Buddha says it
occurred to me loss of focus arose in me and it was because of that that my
immersion fell away and so loss of focus is could be part of
sloth and torpor which is another one of the hindrances sort of the torpor is
um the Mind sags the mind is diffuse and not focused
kind of a little bit out of it
and so the the focus lack of focus right is going to affect a staying present
and the for me when I think about the a loss
of focus what I associate a lot of causes of that are actually a lack of
Interest are we are we interested in what's happening
like really seeing what's going on are we inspired
are we inspired by our practice by our teacher by the Sangha by the people around us
and do we have faith do we have faith in this practice in the Buddha the Dharma and the Sangha and
those things support Focus right and energy and interest
so next the Buddha goes on and he says while meditating dullness and drowsiness arose in me
and every time he says I'm going to make sure that neither nicked out nor loss of focus nor dullness and drowsiness and
all the other things He's listed before I'm going to make sure they will not you know arise in me again
so dullness and drowsiness might be the part of sloth and torpor which is the
sloth part which is the in the body usually energetically
so it's kind of a lack of energy and it can be due to a variety of causes we
need to kind of figure out what that is for ourselves sometimes it's very simple we ate too
much for dinner we didn't get enough sleep we didn't exercise
like not exercising can make us feel slothful we watch too much TV right but
again sort of if we find ourselves really drowsy in our meditation pay attention
right pay attention to like okay what why might I be feeling drowsy here
the Buddha goes on to name a few other things um
but I kind of want to pause here because we're getting near the end and just see if anyone has any thoughts Reflections
questions I can go in any direction
um that you all are interested in if there is an interest
great
thanks Tonya uh I'm interested in this phrase light and vision of forms and I
wonder if you could say a bit about your interpretation of what that means yeah
um I mean I think that there's
one one interpretation of that could be that it's like the the nimita or the
beginning of going into a genre a concentrated state the light right so that's one
possibility um and it's also you know fairly common for
people again just as they start to concentration start to get concentrated their mind can be quite bright
um it also could just mean potentially that
there's something about the clarity of how one is seeing you know that they get the dark and
light sort of kind of implies there's something quite clear that's being seen
you're really aware of what's Happening so those are possible what do you think
of that yeah that sounds good thank you yeah yeah thanks for the question
I think you know I really want to emphasize how important it is to connect
our behavior in the world and how we live with what happens in meditation
and that when when we're in the world and we're enacting you know the hindrances of doubt
right classically they're listed desire sensual desires a wanting
pleasantness aversion or ill will
restlessness and worry which is oh well sloth and torpor and
doubt and so you can think about desire and aversion as
both energies moving in opposite directions desire is the one thing of something the
energy is a pulling and aversion is wanting to get rid of something but they're both focused on
a wanting more or not sloth and torpor and restlessness system
worry are kind of the opposite right sloth and torpor is a lack of energy a lack of you know a Clarity in the mind
and and um restlessness and worry is too much energy in the body
a mind that's too worried too frenetic and then doubt which we've talked about
right so these you can if you just think about them as energies
um you can see how they're you know like the Buddha will say that um both
both desire and ill will are there from the birth right there's just they're
they're like life energies we need to go for food and we need to get away from being hurt in the simplest form
and that so they're very innately you know there and
um the others kind of come along later right as we become more aware of
ourselves and you know sort of various other things but if we allow these energies to
continue to manifest in our lives without without discipline
they become habits and then they become
you know characteristics personality structures
so next month Diana Clyde Clark and I are going to teach a hindrances class
using The Wizard of Oz as a reference
it's such a great I'm so it's going to be really fun and such a great sort of example of
personalities that kind of created personalities out of the different hindrances with the characters in that
show and you know you might ask yourself of these hindrances which one what do I
have this personality type often you'll hear in Buddhism there's
three personality types agreed aversion and deluded but I actually I like this
idea of like the five personality types of the hindrances all five of them because that certainly seems relevant
um to me and if you come uh watch The Wizard of Oz with us we'll
show little clips so if you're interested I encourage you to watch the movie before you come but
um starting of the first Thursday in March
it's a 6 30 is the start time will end at eight
and so it'll be for five Thursdays in March yeah and uh so come ready to
have fun yeah so
it's really it's really really um I guess one final thing I'll say
is um
oh I like this I'll share this it's not what I was going to say but I looked up data corruption in Wikipedia as a
reference because they use this word Corruptions and I liked it so much better than many and so in Wikipedia it
says data corruption refers to errors and computer data that occur right right
occurred during writing reading storage transmission or processing right and it they introduce unintended
changes to the original data and that's a way to think about the hindrances they come in at some point and they make
unintended changes to what we're doing feeling saying and then it goes on in
general when data corruption occurs a file containing that data will produce unexpected results
yes well that certainly can happen when we get you know driven by the energies
of the hindrances and um you know the results can be very minor
too very major a system crash and then I love this too there are two types of data corruption associated with
computer systems undetected and detected that's so great that's so simple the
hindrances we either see them or they don't and what happens if we don't see them
right they just run rampant and so in the computer World undetected
data corruption also known as um silent data corruption results in the
most dangerous errors right detected data corruption
may be permanent with the loss of data or may be temporary when some part of the system is able to detect and correct
the error so May our systems detect data errors
thank you for your kind attention
[Applause]