YouTube [Laughter]
yeah so welcome this is class four of five on the five hindrances and we're using
the story The Wizard of Oz as a reference point and I'm kind of
thinking about how these hindrances show up in that movie hi welcome
um so last week we talked about um restlessness and worry
and I just want to say again just this invitation to kind of hold the
hindrances in a few ways one is as about energy
energies that directed like of what you want energies are directed at getting away or pushing away from something so
that's the greed or the desire and the aversion so it's you can feel it in the
body right thanks Gus
and so you know this is energy you can it's a momentum
right and then uh restlessness is worry is too much energy
too much energy in the body or too much energy in the mind
and a way to think about for me the container
how the mind is holding something impacts also the energy so if you think
about a bouncing ball in a small space
it if it keeps bound it has something to bounce against it's going to keep going right longer and longer if it's really
small tight space it goes if the Space is really big
it's not going to keep going for as long because it doesn't keep having this resistance or this pressure to keep it
going so if we can broaden the space in our
minds our hearts to be with whatever's going on it can
help lessen that intensity of energy in the body and the in the mind
I'll just say this about sloth and torpor which is what we're going to talk about tonight
and another way you can think about what happens when you have too much space
like if you imagine you have all day two weeks one month of nothing
you have to do sometimes it's it we just kind of get
immobilized because there's too much space there's not enough kind of
something to push against or move us toward right so in an opposite way sloth
and topper might be too much space in the mind or in the structure of our life we're in the space where give permission
we're giving ourselves even so energy right so if we have too much
space Maybe we lose our energy it flattens
to little space it can create a tighter environment for reactivity and the buildup of excessive energy
so this idea of the energy helps kind of
us see I think kind of fine-tune our relationship with these hindrances not as something horrible that's haunting us
or you know that we're bad it's more about like again to me seeing it as
feedback like it's a reflection of what's happening within in some way or another
and if we can recognize it we can go oh maybe I need to put a little more
attention here or maybe I need to take off a little bit of attention here or if I'm leaning too much into
something like uh yeah remembering where that leads us and the same with the
aversion another way to think about the hindrances is is that they're veils they
cover something and you know the teachings in the in the
time from the time of the Buddha and the sutas occasionally you'll see these references that the Mind itself is pure
and bright just that's the natural nature of the Mind and so
what if there's something covering that what if we all have this
and there's things that cover it that prevent us from kind of seeing clearly
to it or through it and the Buddha gave similes having to do
with water for each of the the hindrances and so a mind clear of hindrances is
described as a very clear pool of water
so you can look in you can see and penetrate see the rocks and the fish and
the algae and you know it's clear to you what it is and what's happening in there
you could see a reflection without Distortion right
if you have desire in the mind the veil is kind of equated to die
you know like a color crimson red or something put in the
water and so it tints right just like sunglasses
I had somebody who came to this class when we were talking about this and I was talking about you know tinting
wearing sunglasses affects the colors that you see right and so he had this
huge aha moment because he ran through a red light
because of or a green light he must have stopped at a green light because the
tinting in his glasses turned the green to like what looked like red
so this the color you know the way we're seeing can impact how we perceive what
we're looking at so if we're looking into the pond and it's all Rosy it might make us think oh
it's so beautiful look at how the fish is this color and it's you know purple and instead it's just you know gray or
something and the impact or the veil of ill will
in the water is like boiling water so you can't see into it because the
water is not still and it's also hot and dangerous right so you can't even really
get close to it to the veil you know prevents us from seeing
with restlessness and worry it's like wind wind on a lake right really kicks
up the waves and you again it's choppy and the water is Disturbed so you you
can't see clearly and with Sloth and torpor it's equated with like algae
right sludge that makes it hard to move hard to see it's like have you ever had algae water
you know it's not easy to clear out you know this is not easy I had I've had
fish tanks right and you know even if you wipe off the glass you're just the water is fill me there's
a lot of work to trying to get it clean and usually you just have to get rid of most of the water clean out
the Rocks clean the glass and leave some in for the pH balance but you know it's
this long process it can take a while you might have to change the water a few times
so the Veil I like this idea of like you know the
nature of the Mind the nature of the heart is radiant and free of these things
and conditions just like weather happen in our lives and they're going to disturb
that capacity to see through see with see into with that kind of clarity and
brightness and we're using The Wizard of Oz as a
reference and I say we Diana's not here tonight because she's sick so hopefully she'll be back next week for the last
class but um we wanted to you know we Diana and I when we've taught this before we
have this idea just let's demystify these hindrances let's not make them into bad things they're if you actually
see I've said this before but think about it if you see clearly
what's happening you can pull the veil back the curtain back and who does this
in The Wizard of Oz who reveals Toto
right I mean here's this wizard hiding have you seen the movie
oh yeah so the wizard right just this little guy
making up lots of stories intimidating people pretending to have power hides behind
this curtain and then has this projected had with this flame coming out of it
speaking in this deep demanding voice and Toto's like to me the little symbol
of mindfulness right sort of this clear ability to see and he just runs over there and pulls
the curve back and reveals the wizard and that revealing
that's a c it's a pathway to Freedom if we can see it we can relate to it we can
know and we can be free from it we're you know remember how frightened they were
when they were visiting the wizard as he was you know booming voice and they're all shivering
and quivering and you know you pull back that curtain and
you realize wow this is make believe and how often do we make ourselves
shiver and quiver because of our mental mind imagining creating
these intensities these stories and if we can recognize what we're doing
we can pull our own corn back and free ourselves from the Wizards of the world and our own mind
so does anyone want to say anything about working with restlessness and worry this past week or
any Reflections from the class from last week before we kind of move into
slop and torpor in the context of Wizard of Oz and then in the context of the Dharma
great that's okay
I was just gonna ask because you were just talking about like revealing the curtain and like similarly revealing
things in our life that were like covered before and as you were saying that I was just
thinking like like the example you gave in The Wizard of Oz it's like a very clear
uh thing that gets revealed but like often I feel like things are way more
complicated especially when you look like different perspectives and how like someone sees
something versus another person and it's usually not as straightforward as like oh this person did this to me it might
be like oh they were feeling this way and they reacted this way which made me feel this it's like I don't know I feel
like it gets very muddy and I don't know if you have any thoughts
around I don't I think I struggle a little bit in general with like meditation and like doing raft and
things like that because I just feel like there's usually not this very clear path
towards like walking through my feelings or emotions or like processing events
um and revealing things when I don't know like yeah I just feel like I don't know how
to do it well yeah well um
I have a lot of things to say so um what can I say right now a couple of
you know um
remember that when we're doing mindfulness
we can only do mindfulness of our own experience
right we can only really be mindful of what we're sensing in our bodies
what we're thinking what we're feeling and know that we're seeing things but
from our own perspective we can't know exactly what anyone else
is seeing thinking feeling we can be sensitive and empathic and pick up on stuff but truly it's only the
other person that can and we don't have to agree we can be in
the same room in the same time same things happening and have two very different experiences
and there's there's stories I don't remember who the monks are but there are stories from some monks right who are
practitioners in Europe I don't remember they were traveling together and they were talking later about these events
that they shared and they all had a really different stories really different perceptions of the
experience and that's just the reality of life so if we're trying to
make everything match up with other people and their experience
somebody's always trying to then distort their own experience
all of our experiences colored and influenced by our history our personality the way we see and
relate our mind thinks some people think you know an image as some people think in words
some people don't really think an either you know our minds are unique and our
histories are unique in the way we even Define something is impacted by everything behind us
so maybe if you try and simplify
and really get clear that all you need to know is what's going on for you what your truth is
it doesn't mean it's that capital T truth but it means that you can settle with
something because you know what's true for you does that make sense
yeah the other thing I'll say is that um
in May the last three weeks of may not all
because I'm doing an intro series after this one but in May I'm doing raft just for three
weeks just draft and I'm hoping to do some practices where people are willing
to have me guide them through it and share out loud what's happening so I can guide you through more
so come back in May laughs
all right so let's talk about sloth and torpor and The Wizard of Oz for a moment
so sloth right is very the physical aspect of this hindrance
it's the heaviness the the frozenness the not being able to move or get up you
know and so who in The Wizard of Oz is stuck
slow the Tin Man right he's rested shut
he can't move oh okay I'm afraid he's just talking out of
the corner of his mouth and you know um so he needs to be oiled and
greased and and then if you watch him right he
he kind of has a sadness to him there's a little bit of a
you know a little bit of a sadness to his face and you know there's a way in
which I think depression is a little bit like the torpor right and and the energy in the body and the
energy in the mind kind of affect the way he speaks so he's kind of like slowly his head's kind of sideways and
you know just sort of his affect his opposite of the straw man the straw man
who has all kinds of restlessness and worry right all kinds of extra energy his mood will swing from this to that
rapidly the Tin Man no no no you don't see that right so this is a kind of an example of
how more sloth and torper manifest and look just this sort of flatter slower
kind of uh you knowness
sad subdued Maybe and
tarper and sloth actually you know they don't mean you don't have energy
they mean you're not accessing your energy
one you know you've seen how people can go from no energy to tons of energy snap
of a finger because something interesting comes along or something that excites them happens right so that
energy was there it just wasn't accessed because their mind wasn't turned on or
their ideas and beliefs weren't that you know positive and energetic and what is
it that this Tin Man Is Telling himself what does he tell Dorothy the straw man
he just says he doesn't have a heart he he tells himself he has no heart and
he tells them he really believes he has no heart but yet he's sad and he's romantic and he's longing a partner
right you know you don't feel those things if you have no heart but he's
telling himself he has no heart and he believes his story and when we believe the stories are we
tell ourselves like this it affects our energy affects our mood
and our bodies and our minds and think about
what is it like to imagine not having a heart not having an emotional connection what
what does life look like
great really you know lacking vibrancy
right and that's kind of how he presents lacking vibrancy it's so pithy I think
it's so pithy what they've done in this story with these characters actually and it's quite extreme you know and the
story stories kind of wild but the more I think about it the more I'm like wow
this is such a great such a great way to tell us about the way we are you know
so there's another person in the story who tells himself that he can't do
things and things are too hard they're too dangerous and it affects him and his energy in some ways it's a
little different but I wonder about the lion and I wonder if there's some way you
know he certainly has you know worry but does he also have some sloth and torpor
in there that kind of are impacting him we can have multiple hindrances
and then there's one other really poignant example of sloth and torpor and that's the field of poppies
right drugs right poppy opiates it's like
we you know opiates make us feel like it's a warm hug and we fall asleep and
we lounge around and you know they essentially go into this field and they all fall asleep right so they're lacking
awareness in the mind and body such a another example of how you know
whether it's drugs or what we're doing that can induce states of coma like
consciousness yeah so now I kind of shift in less weight
who has other ideas anybody else have other ideas from the story that might might reflect sloth and torpor nope
if you do if anything pops up feel free to share um
So within the Dharma I talked about you know the the pond the algae filled Pond right it's a simile taught by the the
Buddha and you know been sort of talking about you know the sloth and torpor comes from
you know really a lot of it can come from our mind the way we're thinking about things
the perspective we have on things how tight we are around things or how
slack we are how much permission giving we are giving ourselves
you know um and so the sloth is the physical the torpor is the mind the dull cloudy weary
easily drifting into thought there's something that
um Gill calls the sinking mind
which is related to a torpor in the mind and it actually you know in deeper
meditation it can be in a little bit seductive and pleasant it's like this feeling of just I don't
know yeah like sinking right just this sinking sinking feeling and just not
even knowing you're not aware because you're so I don't know lost
yeah and so when it's really strong there can be you know insufficient mindfulness to
even know we're in it
so um well you know emotional energies or
attitudes also affects our energy like a feeling of discouragement frustration boredom
or even indifference right boredom to me is a lack of um
Connection in the present moment it's it's not not being present an indifference to me is a form of
hostility really I feel um there's a feeling giving up can
induce sloth and torp or hopelessness right and the other thing is resistance
when we're resisting something we can find ourselves in a attention a space of
tension that immobilizes us in a way right so if we're something needs to
happen and we think it needs to happen but we can't do it we won't do it we can get stuck
immobilized
it can also come up when we have a sense of not feeling satisfied gratified
um it can come up when we feel like there's no benefit to us and whatever's happening
some people your all of us probably to some extent are really motivated when
we feel like we're being seen in a favorable way
um and when we don't feel that way when we don't feel like you know we're being
acknowledged or important it can be very easy to shut down
and kind of shift into a sloth and torper space
so there's a few more things to say but um I think I'll move to practice tips and I
kind of want it because I'm going to have you guys talk right in your small group and I want to give you room to
name some of this stuff right it's fun um
so just some simple practice tips always for me it's always the first
thing is to name it to be aware of it we have to recognize it right
so the raft are recognize mindfulness bring awareness to it
and then the second part is the AE which is to allow it to be there so if we're struggling with it we're not going to
see it clearly we're it's like adding waves to the water we've got to find a way to allow it to be seen as it exists
already to give it space birth
um and maybe I'll save the other tips for
after you guys do a little small group discussion then we can kind of talk about that so
I think you know with five there's five of you so why don't you just be one group
you know and um you can just sort of make a little circle back there and go ahead and do
that you know just turn your chairs whatever I don't mean like you have to go but like just it's probably easier on that side of the
room
and just invite you first to go around the circle and say your names and a little bit about your relationship to
IMC or to practice where you live maybe
and then I'll give you the first question this is just sort of get to know your Dharma friends
all right and um so let me just see how does this question
land for you guys right I'm open to we can fine tune so the first question would be kind of
how do you experience sloth and torp or just in general exploring and sharing a little bit and
um like you know think about it how it shows up in your mind how it shows up in your body and
where it shows up just sort of reflect a little bit let yourself connect with how
it comes into your life and and so just take turn turns one at a time I think
one at a time or do let me let me ask would you rather say one way and then go
to the next person and hear what they say like to help generate ideas or would you rather be able to talk by yourself just
for a couple of minutes and let yourself free flow what would you prefer
you
um I've never done this exact moment in
time before so I have no experience with this moment foreign
okay how about we start with two rounds lightning rounds where you just drop in
one or two things that you're aware of just like a short little thing just to help you get the juices go and then the
third round each person take a little longer to say a little bit more how does that sound
great no I hey the hindrances show up
everywhere
uh
no pressure foreign
I have just become much more aware recently of listening to my body and feeling things in my body and uh
certainly when I'm meditating I'm far more aware of nowadays of uh sloth and
thorpor showing up sloth showing up as kind of very imperceptible slouch
and also a fairly imperceptible change of the attitude of my my head
um it's only with lightning round you're next yeah here we go
um I want to know do they have to go together um no I mean that's a rhetorical
question but they don't always go together and for me it turns up a lot when things
are too hard if I'm thinking about something and it's too hard and I don't want to deal with it so I
don't
yeah this one is difficult for me to identify but I think I'm gonna go with
the stuckness in a lot of my emotions where I get exhausted and then just lay
out basically familiar shows up with uh
ruminations it's a sort of like a byproduct of those
um I was going to say I guess this is a case where it doesn't go together but for I guess this is sloth like just
procrastination like I'll have something running through my mind of like I gotta do this and then I just never
physically get to doing it
you could also kind of watch how far you're into the ice cream container
you're trying to avoid things um I think also with respect to torpor kind
of to your a couple of you guys have made this point again listening to my body sometimes if I'm not doing
something that I feel like I should be doing I'll start the sense uh tension in my body and it's weird because uh
tension and torp don't seem to go together but to the extent that I'm not being present with something
that I feel that I should be present with I'll actually start to feel it in my body I'll start to feel it as attention
foreign
because eight or nine o'clock comes at night and I don't want to deal and I lay
down on the couch and I watch watch Netflix and I don't want to talk to anybody
I don't I don't want to deal with anything and
I kind of like it it you know I don't do it during the day
and and then it's sort of helpful to end the day that way
so it's not all bad or a hindrance sometimes
to piggyback off of that I'm like going going all day that I experience the same
thing but also the long to-do list is waiting you're like okay well I don't have enough energy right now I'm gonna
listen and rest but am I being lazy should I do the five things that I need to get done by tomorrow
so that's how I experience it as well yeah for me it's uh
usually follows an after afternoon nap and I'll lay there and just allow my
body to feel this deep sense of relaxation I
don't know if that's sloth interpret me but that it's a very nice state of like
you Susan it's a very nice state to be in and then all of a sudden the mindfulness kicks in and there's all
these things to do and uh and just step out of that and go on with
the rest of the day yeah I think similar to what everyone said I feel like I consume media a lot
to like stop thinking uh which I don't know if that's a form of torpor but then I don't
feel like it has the benefits maybe that you you said you feel like I feel like it kind of makes things worse or makes
me feel worse instead
sorry I'm still on the body think but I think sloth and torpart kind of go
together they they kind of happen together um
I have a I can potentially sit down and be on
YouTube for hours you know um
but what I've learned recently and you know I'll be splayed out in my couch watching nice big screen watching
YouTube you're familiar with us and uh I think everybody's from Netflix
YouTube uh what I realized recently is
if I just get up if I just stand up it changes everything and you know I'll go turn off YouTube
and I'll get on with my life I don't even know where I'm going but just the getting up
because I tell myself this is not what I want and then without any real way to kind of
think about it you know I can't think my way through it I'm in the state I'm kind of like the Tin man I'm stuck and
what I realized is I just randomly just pop up and then popping up all of a sudden the
Mind State changes and I think they happen kind of together and uh so then
both the sloth and the torpor kind of liver seed
I don't know but what what happens now
foreign
and it sounds like you know that nobody needs to wax on about it right so
um so then let's move to question two and question two is what I'd like to
invite you to do is to talk about activities and topics
um Etc that bring a sense of Vitality to you and your life
and and then also to talk about maybe you should start with a for I don't know
where you want to go let's end with this Vitality I think but the other is and
what topics or activities leave you feeling dull drained or lifeless
um so what's that YouTube right that's me for sure
um so just and you can so like you know it doesn't have to be lightning but you can do it similarly and you can talk a
little more if you want to reflect and share more than one thing at once and just allow yourselves to connect but
um you could do maybe we do first round of what brings energy vitality and then a
second round of what brings a lack of it the opposite and then let's go back to Vitality does that sound good okay
okay so I have a dog and we walk
sometimes she looks at me like I don't want to walk but I love being outside and even if it's the same
root I'm happy to be outside and it's mostly
three times a day and sometimes it's early in the morning or later at night and during the day and it's fine with me
I too have been not trying to watch so much sports or TV or even have this TV on as background noise so I find myself
cooking or walking sitting at a park and on the bench
um reading a book or catching up with a close friend that
I haven't that I that's all my to-do list I find uh swimming is one of my favorite
activities I've swim first in the first thing in the morning not only twice a week but it's enough to
carry me through the entire week and when I start bogging down I go off
to the gym and work out I find it a real excessive workout a good workout
it just you know it really puts a lot of energy in the body yeah
yeah I think similar to everyone like movement definitely helps in whatever form and sometimes if I'm really like because
I'm trying to like wean myself off of like Tick Tock and the really like addictive apps so I'm like okay a
podcast is like a step down so I'll like listen to a podcast while I do some movement so at least I'm not like stuck
in one place um helps a little bit how many of the tick tocks have you
gone by where they remind you not to stay on [Applause]
so I take it off my phone and and then if I want to do it I'll put it on and then I take it off my phone so uh I mean
you guys have heard me say this before but um what really energizes me nowadays is
the Arts just pursuing the Arts museums I'm now in a choir I like going
to Symphonies I like going anything that is that is performing arts I find very energizing I'm planning a trip to the
Getty museum this summer too which will be a hoot
so what does not energize me I have this Habit in the morning that after I walk
the dog while I drink my coffee I go through my emails
and then I look at Facebook and it's always so unsatisfying and I think why do I do this every day
but it's such a habit and I have to start
yeah and there's nothing exciting I do a lot of deletes
Facebook social media Tick Tock Instagram YouTube and
um TV
well uh I think with I still work quite a bit you know I should be retired but I
I enjoy what I do but there are some things that I don't enjoy that I do it
really uh it's like it's work that I don't want to
get my hands dirty with and I with my enthusiasm dries up when I when I have
and yet I still manage to get through it
I was going to say like during the covid pandemic like work from home period I think I had like the most sloth
interpreter that I've ever had and I have like a more physical I mean a more physical kind of field where I need to
like go into the office so during those like three months that I was at home I just
laid around all day and yeah I'm somewhat retired and there's certain
tasks also of the work that I do which is like oh God it's like you're having all my teeth
pulled at the same time and it still has to get done
um I I'm a people person and although I can
be home I live alone and not talk to anybody for four days then I think and I'm not bored I think
I'm boring but I'm not bored and then I think I like the world I'm
gonna get out in the world and the other thing I do a lot is travel and that for me is um it's so everything it's
educational it's experience it's fabulous and I'm very lucky that I can do it so I'm going to Turkey
cool
we're back to question one question yeah
um I have found myself like getting rid of stuff that just sits there that you don't use so decluttering and also
Shifting the energy with the furniture that I have um it brings me a lot of joy
and I have nothing more to offer thanks I know I'm trying to think of things
um yeah I think definitely like talking to people if that's available
[Music] um another thing I've been doing recently is like instead of social media
from my phone I'll go on like Google Maps and find like interesting restaurants or like things I'll just be
like oh cool I didn't even know this stuff existed around me I don't know if that starts to fall into like the desire
category but thank you it helps with the slot and torpor I
guess
I don't know if I have another one uh I mean I like doing projects around
the house and uh I don't do them all the time but when I get started with one it's always very
energizing I just like doing projects on them when they're done I like going back and looking at them 10
times and just saying wow it wasn't that a nice job
nice and what happened to your energy just
during this time during your time sharing here
Pleasant yes soft soft comfortable comfortable
uh-huh all right so you noticed in your body
and it was so funny because I was watching your body language from the back when I was asking about start with
positive go to the black and you're like go back to the positive
more yeah and so and just thinking about these things affects what you feel in your body right
um yeah just just remarkable to notice that I think
so um is there anything else you guys want to share with each other or any key
takeaways maybe just do another round with a mic just what's your take away from your
sharing your experience your own Reflections or what you heard you know how might this support you in
your practice whether it's daily life or on the cushion
um I'm not alone and that's a very important part of
compassion self-compassion I think none of us is uh
weirdly separate and doing shut the uh you wish other people didn't see all the
time we're all in this together we're all dealing with it I think that is good for both
compassion for others and more importantly self-compassion
always passing it to you do you have to pass it somewhere else
um I think I was just going to say like coming into this session I was like oh I don't really know if I'm going to relate
that much to sloth and torper like I related a lot to like worry and anxiety from the last session because I just
feel like that's my Baseline But like after hearing more about it and like talking about I'm like yeah I do have a
lot of that like sometimes stemming from the worry and anxiety that leads me into it which is interesting and then also
trying to avoid it it makes me go into like other hindrances which is interesting oh yeah
the one takeaway for me is just what I'm feeling at this moment is just
be more in the present moment I think that's a one of the best
um thank you enhancements for
getting out of that place of sloth and torp or just being the present moment as
soon as I noticed it then I take evasive action on it
um this is the most challenging hindrance for me to recognize
I'm recognizing that um
identifying it I mean naming it I have identified it but naming it
the couch with Netflix you know that kind of thing it it's yeah and
um so that's always helpful to actually look at it and not just live it every
day nice just thank each other and maybe we can
come back to the semi-large Circle
all right foreign
so let me ask you would you like to do the guided practice now or would you like me to talk a little bit about some
of the antidotes I would
antidotes okay great because it's all fresh in your mind okay
um so before I go into that I just want to say a couple more things so one of the things that can happen is that if we
have something going on that we're not really ready to face or it feels like too much
it's often you know soft and tarpal will arise and there can be some wisdom to
that so you know I think we have to at certain times when we know there's a lot
going on there can still be things being processed right so it's really keeping
asking the question is it hindering me in some way or is it is what needed is a
little bit more Stillness right and one of the key ways to figure that out is notice after you rest do you
feel any lighter or better and if you don't and you feel heavier you probably need to be moving more if that makes
sense does that make sense Susan so this idea that again I'll repeat this
there can be times in our lives where there's something that's going on that we don't want to deal with it could be a
task you brought up Joe like something that you don't want to do at work and so it brings up this like uh right
but you and and Gus both talked about just doing it right and you get through it and you feel better and that's a good
indicator that that's the right thing to do there can also be big things going on in our life like breakups or you know
people dying or something like that that feel overwhelming that feel like they're it's
almost too hard to be with it and so sometimes a result can be this sloth and torpor come up
and sometimes I think there's some wisdom in that so but we still need to discern because
we can also go down in the sinking hole right and get really
heavy weighted and not move and not do things that we need to be doing to take care of ourselves right so
I just wanted to bring some ideas some balance and to the idea of like it's not always bad to be in sloth and torper
right sometimes there's a needed rebalancing right or a need to kind of shut down a
little bit and part of that is due to an imbalance Susan I think what you were talking
about you know you like to get to the end of the night and watch Netflix because you described a busy busy busy
busy maybe there's an imbalance between effort and relaxation as we're going
about life so if we're putting in Cassandra I think you said this too right if we're put doing too much too much too much too
much we can kind of collapse into sloth and tarper and so what happens if we try and build
more balance more rest more breaks in our daily routine so we're not driving
so hard so hard and then just sort of collapse right so finding that balance between effort
and relaxation is part of the the
antidote right and you already named many of the things
I'm going to say one was just you know Gus you talked about just standing up
I have that experience you know where I'll just be like I'm just done I don't even have words for it I'm just like I
can't do this anymore you know and I just stand up or I you know turn off the TV or I shut my computer because I'm
just done right and it could be anything and and shifting
just changes can help change and get me out of it and like you said I don't even consent of you said it's hardest to
recognize and that's because it is that kind of a there's a there's a real heaviness of that
inhibits our capacity to really recognize with Clarity what's going on
so some things to do are arouse energy particularly before you're going to
meditate okay so this is for an example or before you need to do something that's hard for you to do
go for a brisk walk right sit more upright
open your eyes wash your face with cold water open a window cool down heat you know
right so and if you're you know
can make yourself a little bit uncomfortable whatever you're doing so you're not just sinking into the couch
or sinking into your meditation cushions you know don't get too comfortable it
sort of invites that's falling asleep state another thing to do is to investigate
drop in some questions like if I had energy now I would dot dot dot what
would you do if you had energy right now and then what is it I really want right
now like trying to sometimes we're you know we're not getting what we
really want and we're not really acknowledging that so we're tuning out so what is it I really want or what is
it I really don't want right now like to help us name it right
another practice is to reflect on death and dying all right
to think about you know life is short what does it mean what's the purpose and meaning in our
life and our practice so to you know reflect on the Buddha the Dharma the
Sangha things that bring a sense of purpose inspiration and connect you with the preciousness of life
and no matter what just keep practicing don't get up and walk away just because you're having a bout of sloth and torpor
you know don't walk away from your practice I mean I mean walk away from your TV not your
practice any thoughts any additions anything else
you want to add Gus great just get the mic would ya
thank you
from what you said it sounds like there's a space for
mindful sloth say more
it's what you were saying about you may not be in the right space to be
active but you can be mindful that what you need right now looks like a hindrance but it's not
what you need yeah that's right and yeah and um yeah and so it's you know you know how
when there are times your energy can arise right away you know
but there might be other states and times where it's more because you end up finding out you were sick you didn't
realize you were getting sick you know so there there sometimes if your energy won't shift and you try
these things maybe you're just tired or maybe there's just too much then you need rest
yeah so it's discernment I guess it's hard to say mindful sloth and
torpora it's hard to but but mindful of it and then exploring investigating
what's needed and how do I respond if I do this how do I respond if I do that
that makes sense thank you anything else
I don't know if it's my age or what but when you said you
know rest during the day and there's a balance so growing up it was like
I'll go the other way as I'm older as I'm old I have given myself permission
to nap during the day if I want I've retired a couple of years ago but I
never would have done that ever you know the day was filled with doing
things and never would I do that and when I first started giving myself
permission to do that I thought this is great I love this yeah so it it you know
it depends on also where you are in your life if you and now I know that people you know
you have to be happy in your workplace and you should and there should be a balance but when I no I work you know
you just worked so it's a whole different thing I think yeah and you know different Generations
have different attitudes about it because some of the you know younger people I work with are I'm not doing
that they're like I'm not doing that I know I watch you do that no way thank you and that's what I mean it like I
never would have said that yeah yeah but you know I mean we're all we all
have to look at our own patterns you know what is our what's the conditioning because there's also other
things actually there are other messages people get
um that make it more okay or less okay for them to rest that you know in some parts of our you
know culture there are you know people who experience tremendous pressure
to kind of always having to be on and to look good and be to present smart
because they're pushing against a lot of stereotypes or other barriers in their
life so there are a lot of reasons that cause people to have various
attitudes about it whether it's okay to nap or not okay to nap and
there's a there's been some books and writings about
um what's it the you know sort of rest as
Revolution you know rest as you know kind of a way to take back one's power
you know so especially in the black community but
yeah any any other wonderful Reflections thoughts yeah Gus
great little
I have a hard time with the death and dying part of it sometimes I'll think to myself you know hey
you're 67 years old it's not like you know you have an internet amount of time left here what are you gonna do
absolutely does not work for me it just doesn't good well it's good to know right what
what does work for you so what does inspire you guys
that something that is not what that does to me what that does to me is it makes me
feel kind of guilty that I should be doing certain things it has a negative
connotation right thou should I should do this right
it doesn't work for me so yeah it has to be positive it has to be onward leading I have a hard time with
that one yeah I just wanted to comment thank you yeah and you know none of these are um
you know the answers for everybody right and this is the beauty of the Buddhist teaching
it's about trying and then reflecting
you know I love the teaching that the Buddha gave to rahula right this is his son his son was pretty young
and maybe had lied to somebody and so the Buddha gave him a talking and said you know rahula before you speak reflect
and think about whether this might cause harm to yourself others or both
and then during your speaking rahula reflect is is what I'm saying causing harm to
myself to others or both and then after I'm done speaking reflect
again because you know we our awareness can change over that period of time
and so this practice is really about like it's not just about intentions it's
not just about doing what you're told to do but reflect learn as you go along notice and there's never it's like the
effort and the things we need to do are always changing because our conditions are changing
what we need one day we might need a different something another day and we have to keep not going into automatic
pilot that takes us away from the vibrancy of our life but keep checking in keep
reflecting listening noticing the impact
yeah okay let's do raft at this point it'll
be fairly short so so the raft is the recognize allow
feel tease apart and then trust my extra T is
trusting and you don't have to go through the whole
thing again it might be that it's enough just to recognize something so don't try and
make something happen in your practice right allow yourself to notice what's
happening as we practice
so taking a moment to fill your body feel your feet
kind of be the snow globe that got set down let the snow flakes come to settle
coming home connecting with the present moment
so this is uh going to be an interesting thing right to try and practice with Sloth and torpor which
can be hard to be aware of so let's see if we can
do it from a perspective of kind of more of the observing mind
so just drop in the question and see if your mind can offer you a memory
of a time where you really didn't have energy you didn't have
mental Clarity you didn't have the mindfulness where you were kind of in that sinking
space and remember you're here now as you see this memory
and if you could just wiggle your fingers to let me know when you've got something in mind so I know
one it's okay to shift
okay I think I think I got all fingers wiggled so just seeing this moment in your
history your experience whether it was recent or not just kind of seeing it as
clearly as possible recognizing the lighting the time of day
the location notice what's happening notice of you yawn or start to feel sleepy just even
being aware of that as you start to check in notice how your body's feeling as you're
bringing it to mind
and can you practice the recognition
like I see you and you know can is it feel right to say
I see you sloth and torpor I see you lack of energy I see you boredom
disinterest whatever it is that feels like naming looking in the
eyes of this energy seeing it
in such a way that it feels seen
and then there's a movement here when when the time is right to this ability
to allow that experience to be there
so it's not endorsing it it's not like jumping in that pool
saying this is great and it's not saying it's bad
it's just saying allowing yourself to sense and be with this experience with
as much mindfulness as possible right now and if there's resistance to it ask
yourself if it's needed maybe it's helping a little bit not fall into the sinking hole of it
if it's not needed maybe invite the resistance to relax
and as there's willingness in the system moving to feeling it in the body
moving away from the stories or the imagery and noticing maybe a body scan
of How It's impacting the energy in your body starting at the top of the head and
noticing the forehead the eyes
the jaw the neck
shoulders feeling if there's a heaviness about
wanting to lean forward or back or
just continuing to move down the body your own time
trying to be as aware of possible in the present moment
connecting with the experience not the story as much as possible
and when you're ready
when they're you know when there's Clarity or if you need to bring a little more energy into the practice the next
part would be to allow this space maybe a big table
of chairs and a room and allow the different parts
that are coming together to make and create this experience of
sloth and torpor to have their own seat at the table
I'm just first naming whatever seems obvious we don't need to pull on the
strings more we allow space for things to unfold to reveal themselves
and just pulling back if you can in your mind's eye a little bit just to have that bird's eye view of that moment in
time bird's eye view of the ability to see what led up to what contributed
thoughts feelings beliefs people situations lack of sleep
just allowing those things to be seen and invited to sit at the table
there's nothing that can't be here right this this practice is about
allowing ourselves to be with not consumed by not collapsing into
but allowing things to have their own space
and as you look around the table
let's drop in the question to the room is there anything you need me to know
about you do any of these visitors
is there anything I need to know about you
and as much as possible having a the grace and the capacity to appreciate
each part and whatever it has to share
at some point here maybe reflect on what shifted and changed that allowed this
experience to change
that shifted and changed that helped the energy and the life force kind of come
back in
and what in this practice was useful for you
can you trust the practice let me trust the Insight or that these
things come and go their states
and lots of times with the trusting part of raft it's like I suggest you kind of
imagine that laying back and this practice with soft and torper
I'm going to invite you to imagine standing up
reaching your arms to the sky taking a deep breath
looking around being in nature
and then to look back in at the table and just see how these eyes see
the situation
and if there's a sense of appreciation for your effort for your practice
maybe about to yourself to your heart your mind for
relieving really revealing revealing whatever was revealed
laughs [Music]
so recognize allow which is not the same as endorsing
it's acknowledging and allowing something that already exists to be seen and felt it's already there
it's to then maybe if there's too much resistance to what's there to recognize
the resistance and then allow the resistance to be felt
I kind of see it like there's this thing and if I'm resisting it the resistance
gets between knee my awareness and the thing so instead of trying to do this
with the thing I work with the resistance just turning toward whatever resistance
is there and and kind of then you could just practice with that or it dissipates and
you're able to connect more with the thing from there we move to feeling it in the
body right allowing ourselves to get in touch with how this experience this thought is
impacting our physical self and then to allow whatever's unfolding
in this process to kind of have its own room and space at this table with this imaginary room and
the idea of the room being big enough for whatever needs to be there
and the trust to me is a reminder that things are impermanent this is an experience it's not me it's
not who I am and that suffering actually is a guide
and if we can turn toward the suffering we we have a capacity to be free like
pulling the curtain back we have the capacity to learn
to move toward freedom so that was the practice
how was it working with Sloth and torpor in this practice
what would you say a word or more than about it Susan there's the mic right at
your
it was really interesting I felt myself resisting
that I was sitting up straighter instead of folding into myself which I felt that
day and I thought I'm sitting up I'm not there I'm not
giving in and how did that change what happened
it did I mean how did it change what happened yeah
sitting up and not giving in oh it felt powerful it felt powerful
great thank you
I was really moved by this raft image immediately popped in my head of
something that has been really traumatic for me in the last three months and but the beauty of it like at the end I was
out in nature with a picnic blanket with all of the things that wanted to be
there it was very moving and touching
did he'd be interested to hear how it was for you
um I think uh if I remember right you said to like remember a previous kind of
memory which I feel like was easier for me than doing something current yeah
um for sure and I feel like um even like yeah looking at something that
maybe I kind of dismissed or like I was like okay that's over so I'm not going to think about it anymore and kind of
like definitely like like when we did the table thing I was like oh there's like six different things I could name that
were like contributing to like me shutting down in that moment beautiful um so that was really helpful beautiful
so you know how I I didn't say it tonight because I was kind of tailoring
for this particular hindrance but to when we do this practice to make sure it's not going to overwhelm whatever
we're practicing with practice with what we can be with and it's never too late to practice with
anything because even as we're having a memory we're having an experience in the
present moment and there's a way to process that experience in the present moment even
though we can't go back and change time you know so choosing something that's
historical that's not as intense if that's what works it works so I'm
really glad you had that experience
yeah gus please
um these five probably don't happen on their own right there
yeah absolutely they're mixed right absolutely um I was thinking that
there seems to be some relationship between aversion and sloth and torpor and
clinging and restlessness right and doubt also probably is associated
with Sloth and torpor so maybe I mean does this make sense that if you're
feeling yourself in a state of sloth and torpart do you could you reasonably ask yourself
what are you being aversive to right now what are you doubting right now yes but
I would say it's not just those things right because actually excessive
Desiring can lead to a shutting down and soft and Harper right and doubt can lead to restlessness
and worry so there's there's not it's not one
directional or but it's Dynamic and so always it it's good to ask those kinds
of questions but don't make assumptions exactly about oh you know that one-to-one correlation
yeah and it might be a pairing that's very consistent for you but even then don't lock in that it's
okay right oh that's good yeah
so we're almost at the end and
um you know I just want to invite you to continue to play and experiment with
your effort what you bring to your practice all right um and that idea of more space or less
space right so in terms of the restlessness and worries they're too
much tightness construction do I need more space if there's a lot of lack and I bring a little bit more tension or
uprightness to to what's happening right now to my attention
and you might even like actually deliberately practice with like way too
much energy and then not enough energy just playfully exploring what happens
you know just seeing in real life what happens in you
um so thank you for your practice your
participation your sharing so Delight I look forward to our final week next week
talking about doubt and the kind of big ta-da with the Wizard of Oz so thank you
so much with