so hello
welcome it's Wednesday morning here in now San
Francisco see we have people actually from around the
world wonderful to be with you our theme for the week is
compassion and um I don't think you can hear what I
hear right now but just above me there is
um there's a whole group of Zen practitioners who are doing their
morning practice together and it's uh they're very
familiar sounds to me I I lived in this place for a very long time or what feels to me like a very long
time um and I'm I'm back overnight night in uh Zen Center just for the day so
looks a little different around me sounds a little different around me but being here I feel
the I feel the the power of the connection of uh a group of so many folks so many
people who are dedicated to the well-being of everyone but that's the driving force of
the practice so I for you that as we're getting
started so today our Focus will be Meta Meta practice and we'll talk we'll talk
a little bit more about about that but uh first let's meditate
together and what I have in mind for the the meditation this morning is um as we
always do first let's settle and then um we'll turn turn our
attention to arousing loving kindness arousing
benevolence friendliness and letting that
um in so many words sort of fill us as best we can almost like a light
and then once the once we've practiced loving kindness for a bit we'll make a transition to to
compassion and we'll we will do some meditative cultivation of compassion
that's a
trajectory let's find our way into meditation
posture
in the silence settling the attention resting
the attention on the
body on the whole
body each breath calling us
back right
here and now is a fine time if you notice any
physical
tensions maybe with an exhale
release and just so if you notice
preoccupations mental tensions mental
contractions maybe with an exhale
release
as we settle what is right here in our sensate
world
immediate
with just these few minutes of mindfulness accompanying the
body clearly
knowing let's turn our attention to arousing
meta loving kindness [Music]
benevolence in whatever way works for you inviting the disposition
friendliness that kind mental
attitude the disposition of the
heart for some a reflection
helps tuning into the intention the simple
wish may you be happy
may we be
happy may all beings experience happiness and the
causes of
Happiness feeling this as a gentle wish for the possibility of
happiness
arousing this attitude of [Music]
Goodwill for some an image is
helpful calling to mind someone naturally
invites your inclination to benevolence wishing them
well and offering this
intention may you be
happy
may we be
may all beings have happiness and the causes of
[Music]
happiness
cheing in from time to [Music]
time how is the body responding to this reflection
and the
mind is the wish for well-being having an
effect
may you be
happy may we be
happy
may all beings be [Music] happy and have the causes of
happiness
warming and nourishing the heart in this [Music] way by arousing this attitude of
benevolence now a subtle shift in the
practice
in much the same way making a
wish may you be free from
suffering may we be free from
suffering may all beings be free from
suffering
this slight turning of the heart from meta to
compassion arousing the wish for beings to be
free
and for the last few minutes of this [Music]
sitting pulling ourselves back back into
relaxation and settling on a wish for ease for just this one
being this one body and
mind may I be at use may I be
at
so welcome
again on this week focusing on
compassion and today turning our attention to meta loving kindness
yesterday I was joining you from the Redwood forest in Santa Cruz where I now
live and today I'm in San Francisco in the downstairs of San
Francisco's in Center so the the scenery is different the sounds are
different that the the practice continues wherever we
are so uh I thought it would start with a um
a simple story having just just recently moved to inside Retreat Center uh I'm I'm
discovering the Flora and the fauna and was sitting on my
porch um doing some work on the computer and I noticed a little a little
bird a little bird I think I jum junko had a little black head and then landed
on the railing next to me I thought huh that's interesting and
then uh it took me a minute to realize this uh they were standing on an empty
bird bath and the bird was I'm now
anthropomorphizing but I was imagining as the head was turning it was saying to me uh Where is my water
Where Is My Water please give me some water and it was so natural it was just
so it was like so easily putting one in one together uh this this uh arising of
oh yes clearly I I can help this being right now I can I can offer my support
in this simple way um and I felt this meta wish come up oh oh little one may
you be safe may you take care of yourself with ease may you be protected and so
I build up the bird bath and learned how to drink and then flew
off in that context it simply made sense to put down what I was doing my my uh
laptop was much less important than offering some care to this
bird so an instance of friendliness um thinking about meta
uh meta we talk about is an attitude of benevolence or an intention of
benevolence it has these um connotations or um layers also of
protection uh and this basic disposition of
friendliness all of that is there turns out in the in the atmology of the word benevolence this a disposition to do
good um it apparently comes from the Latin for uh Good Feeling Good willll kindness
which breaks down into the Latin for well and wish it's so
perfect H the perfect word for meta benevolence So Meta practice though I I
deliberately offer a simple example of how meta can show up in one's life
um metha can can can actually operate along a spectrum it can be quite simple
and specific offering offering um offering water to this bird or it can be
quite powerful and directed to all beings So Meta fills this whole
range and U and has quite a a transformative power and the vudi Maga
one of the stages of method development in that path is um what they call breaking down the
barriers where the the wish for well-being becomes so pervasive that it equally equally um
Shines on all
beings one of the one of the very practical
um uh teachings regarding meta is that we don't have to do it only on the
meditation cushion uh in some ways um I borrow this from bin Alo he says meta loving
kindness benevolence provides the Practical scope for expressing one's compassionate
intent to me I hear this as when I have the wish for others to be free from suffering I can enact that through
through meta and this is possible because we can practice meta through our body through
our speech and then with our thinking I love this aspect of method
and it's actually made manifest through our concrete actions they can be big they can be
small I want to illustrate this uh this way that me this meta can be so
practical and manifest in in our in our everyday actions U there's a suta that I
I point to a lot maaya 31 Chula go Singa sua in which um venerable anuda and two
other monks are living together venerable nandia venerable uh
kimila the Buddha comes to visit them and I love this after after the
three monks pay respects to the Buddha they all sit down and um the Buddha asks
them a kind question he he simply says I hope you're
all keeping up well I hope you're comfortable and I hope you're not having
any trouble getting uh supporting yourselves getting alms food and
um anuda responds we're keeping well we're able to feed ourselves well uh
then the Buddha the Buddha says oh I hope you are living in Concord with mutual appreciation without
disputing blending like milk and water viewing each other with kindness
eyes anuda affirms that they are and then the Buddha asks oh how are you doing this and this is where meta
becomes concrete anuda says that he regularly he
regularly reflects on what a gain it is to be practicing in s to be practicing
in community with with these other two monks um that he says it's a gain for me
a great great gain that I'm living with these companions this is part of the joy when
I sign on in the mornings for the 7 amm sa and I see all the greetings and I I hear anuda oh this is
a gain for us this is a gain for us practicing with our
Companions and then anuda says as to how he how they're living in
Concord he says I do bodily acts of loving kindness
toward these others that is to say he he does actions for for them or for the
whole with an intention of benevolence may you be happy may this
being be happy oh I'll take care of this I'll take care of this may you be
happy there's an added to mention that uh these monks they're not only doing bodily actions of loving kindness and
benevolence um but they're they're doing them both in ways that can be seen and
ways that can't be seen and both of those are effective they're not U they're not doing metap for the uh to
look good to each other they're doing it to nourish this wish may we be
happy but not only do they do bodily acts but also verbal acts of loving
kindness they say both openly and privately and then mental acts of loving
kindness maybe the uh appreciation practice that anuda mentioned could be
could be an example of that and then the last part of this
section is that anuda says they put aside their
preferences this way they say it why should I not set aside what I wish to do
and do what these venerable ones wish to do then I set aside what I wish to do and do what these venerable ones wish to
do we are different in body venerable sir but one in mind he says to the
Buddha venerable analo has an important comment about this last this last bit
about um setting aside what we wish to do he makes the observation that that
[Music] um all three of these monks are engaging in that part of the practice
so um it's not an instance of one powerful personality dominating the
group and the others sort of go along but all three of them instead have
maybe this perspective of what's best for the whole what's best for all of these beings and they act in accord with
that rather than their personal
preference so I love this that meta can be manifest
in body speech and mind and there are two important ways that this uh connects
to our compassion practice and both of these are illustrated by an image from later Buddhist tradition of compassion
as like a tree compassion like a tree and then
meta benevolence is like the root of the tree
and just in the way that the root of a plant provides two functions it serves
as a a foundation and it it provides nourishment and it's just the same with
meta So Meta provides the the foundation by being the foundational Brahma vihara
was uh first of the heart practices in the four of meta compassion sympathetic
joy and equin meta provides the foundation and then it also provides the
nourishment I think we get a sense of that when we we look at the way that anuda nandia uh Kimo were living
together that uh practicing mea even just on the level of intention
but then also making making it manifest in our body speech and mind how it
nourishes the heart you have a feeling for this maybe in contrast we can
consider the way that that um ill will comes with a cost whereas an attitude of benevolence
can actually feed
nourish there's a there's a way in which the all four of the brah beara practices work together and balance each other
karuna karuna uh compassion can have this way that um if we're if we're not
particularly careful or if we if we don't watch out for this it is possible
because we're reflecting on someone who is having difficulty may you be free from suffering there's a possibility of uh
elevating on self and then then we get into what the visi Maga calls the near enemy of compassion which is
pity meta protects against this or it it works as a counterbalance because meta
Shines on everything and everyone equally I'll close with the image of the
way analo talks about the four bahad viharas he talks about
U all four of them is like the sun shining meta is like the Sun at noon
shining brightly and equally on everyone compassion is like sunlight at
Sunset darkness is Right nearby uh but the sunlight is shining all the way more
beautifully sympathetic Joy is like Sunrise all this Joy like bird
singing and then equinity the last of the the four Brahma viharas is like at
midnight the cool shining of the light of the
Moon I leave you with this this morning this complete set of
practices May our meta May our Goodwill n compassion and may it benefit both our
own practice and everyone all beings everyone we encounter everyone they
encounter and on and on May all beings be happy may they be free good morning