welcome everyone and thank you for being here
as we train our minds by practicing meditation
we are not looking for some special experience
but rather we're putting in place wholesome Tendencies of the Mind
awesome conditions so that we can open up
and greet our experience in a way that is liberating
rather than stuck and reactive
so as you know this is a gradual path And We Begin by accepting and getting to
know who we are
and our theme for this week opening the Dharma heart
to me that means learning to trust what the present moment is offering us
without needing to change how things are in order to be okay
and for those of us who have been conditioned by trauma
it can be that trusting anything uh can be quite a tall order
so let's begin our meditation by formulating Our intention
the idea that motivates us to practice
on Monday I shared with you my personal intention which is
may I be Safe Haven of kindness
and emptiness for all beings everywhere
so take a moment now to formulate your deepest wish what brings you to practice meditation
and assuming your meditation posture whether you're sitting or lying down or
maybe even standing
and feeling the support of the Earth resting
the Earth to support you
feeling that contact of the buttocks or the back or the feet
with the Earth and sending your roots down deep
and then gently aligning the spine
so that the energy flows nicely from Heaven to Earth and back right through
your spinal column
see if you can land in a posture that
gives you a sense of quiet confidence and you feel alert and balanced
and now we'll give ourselves the gift of letting go
to the extent we can relaxing first of all the body
the head the neck and shoulders
relaxing the arms the elbows wrists
hands
relaxing the heart area in the belly
on the hips
and legs and the feet and letting go of any obvious tensions
that we can't let go of and
just bringing a sense of softness to those tensions that
are difficult to let go of
and now we'll begin with a short practice of
metamedication just to warm up our mindfulness a little
bit so if you like you can bring a
benefactor to come and see it in front of you someone who invariably brings you Joy
when you're with them
or if you're comfortable offering meta to yourself then you can
just do it that way
may I may you may all beings
be safe and protected
may we be happy
may we be peaceful and may we know moments of freedom
so lighting a little candle of well-wishing in our hearts
for ourselves and for everyone for this community the whole world
and we bring in the wisdom Factor
of asking where do we place our trust
do we trust the mind that is spinning with preoccupations
or is the invitation to choose stepping into the present moment
leaving all our preoccupations outside the door for this brief half
hour
as you may know the Holly word for mindfulness or awareness is
Sati and I often think of Sati as my
best friend in this endeavor and I invite her to come and sit with me
consciously choosing resting in
relaxing into open awareness
it's like putting my head inside his lap perhaps
okay let's let the Mind settle down now
and staying with our ever-changing experience of the breath
as our meditation object gently taking in a long slow deep breath
appreciating the whole cycle of the breath
as the inhale progressively flows into the exhale
and the exhale flows into the inhale
and letting our full awareness inhabit the process of breathing
trusting it is possible to let the Mind settle
down
and enjoying the beautiful connection of just settling into the world of the
breath breathing in
and settling
breathing out openness
trusting the company of being with the breath
and letting the eyes close as you settle into the breath
being here with his Heaven flow
of the experience of breathing is all we need
softening the muscles of the face forehead
the eye eyes around the eyes and behind the eyes
sinuses and the cheeks the lips and mouth and the jaw
and joining the breath on this
quiet Journey through the inhale
and the exhale breathing in
feeling settled and breathing out
the clarity that comes from open awareness
as we settle the body and the mind breathing in
this makes the space for the clarity of open awareness
and we can offer that clarity to the world
to each other and to ourselves
and with the warm heart kindness breathing in
settling breathing out
open and clear
foreign
thank you
and if the Mind should wander as Minds tend to do
coming back with a smile settling into the breath
and the clarity of awareness
thank you
and as we come to the end of the city
with a mind that has benefited from appreciating
some of the goodness in ourselves and in our world
and through the goodness of our practice
may we from our Center of settledness and clarity
now radiate our heartfelt wish that all beings everywhere
be safe may all beings be happy
may we all be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
foreign
friends I'm glad to be here with you
um some of you have been asking about when this series of guided meditations and talks will be up on the Audio Dharma
and many of you know this but the beautiful entity that is IMC has a
remarkable business model which is one of generosity and there's not a single uh paid
employee so everything works because a dedicated Army of volunteers
uh offer their time freely and in this case the person responsible
for putting these talks up on the Audio Dharma is a way so everything will be up at some point
but I can't exactly tell you when
also uh someone asked where I'm teaching from and uh I live in a very remote and
beautiful spot in the south of France near a huge Nature Reserve
beautiful stars lots of biodiversity and lots of quiet
but if you're into entertaining and shopping you wouldn't like it here at all
um so today we come to the last talk in this
series of wholesome qualities that we can cultivate
to prepare the mind and the heart for awakening
uh on Monday I talked about Paulie as being a language that is highly
polysemic and that's not a pun um polysemic is is a Greek origin and it
it means that quite often a single word will have a number of quite different
meanings so in the early text the word for the quality we'll explore today is Asana
and it's not related to vipassana which has two s's in a one n this word
has one s and two ends uh Gil translates Asana as uh clear
happy and trusting but literally uh it means something like
settling forward so in probably the previous means
forward or onward or to the four
and it brings the idea of this quality of Mind as one that is on relieving
and then um sud is the root of the word Sana
and it means sit or settle so
um uh literally means settled but as an
adjective it's translated as bright clear pure
transparent and it can also mean
being full of Faith having confidence and trusting
and in addition to that it includes a sense of being pleased and happy
so I think that the the root um of the word is has a lot to do with
what it means for us as meditators um of being settled
as the big part of how this all comes about in my uh professional life I used to
work as a limnologist and that's somebody who studies the Ecology of
lakes and rivers and coastal areas and I like to think of taking a sample
of a column of Lake water from near the bottom to near the surface
and then letting it sit long enough so that all the drags and the particles
can settle to the bottom and what's left at the top is water that is transparent
and clear so if we sit long enough
and let the Mind settle down we can enjoy a mind that is transparent
and clear and able to let in the light of the
Dharma so drama practice is often thought of
as a process of purification and it does take a while and it does
require letting the magic happen but in the
transformation habit and the opening up that makes that possible
So eventually if we sit long enough and let the Mind settle down
we do have moments when our preoccupations are no longer running the
show so instead of letting the Mind keep
stirring up the dregs of thoughts and preoccupations we can perhaps dare to let things settle
if only for a short time so don't be discouraged if you can't yet
remain settled for a long time you might think of your self as a parent
and your mind as a little toddler and if you've had kids you'll remember
how wonderful it was when your little toddler first stood up
and then finally took a couple of steps and of course plop down right away
but those baby steps were just glorious and a cause of great happiness for you
so um celebrate your baby steps of letting the Mind settle down
and then trusting the emptiness of a mind with awareness that is wide
open receptive soft
unobstructed by preoccupations [Music] glad and confident
I think the idea of trust is key to being able to walk this path
I had the Good Fortune to receive lay ordination from my zinc teacher
shouldn't use Suzuki roshi and he gave me the Buddhist name kancho
doshin which means something like feel illuminate
path of faith so for the feel illuminate part I I
remember my first two years in the monastery where
I cried silently in nearly every period of meditation and often throughout the
day and the tears just kept coming and this did
feel like a process of purification
and I think perhaps with the first part of my name feel illuminate
Suzuki roshu was encouraging me to trust the process of letting my feelings
arise and eventually like the way
and then as for being a path of Faith well I don't think this was my strong
point um of course my faith in my teacher and my
faith in the Buddhist teachings was Rock Solid but Faith confidence in myself
was really sorely lacking
so for me learning to trust has been a big part of learning to walk this path
but the Buddha never wanted his disciples to trust blindly on the
contrary the Dharma does a splendid job of pointing away
but even with that each of us has to learn how to realize it for ourselves
because we're all different we all have our own causes and conditions
our own knots to untie and unwind
we need to learn where we get stuck where we cling how we become reactive
so right now [Music]
where am I putting my trust am I trusting my fear
am I trusting anger am I filling up the radiant emptiness of
the present moment with needing to prove myself With Me Myself and mine
wanting to be someone
or might it be possible to trust this radiant emptiness
it is available to each of us when we stop filling it up with our
agendas and preoccupations
do I trust noise or clitorous silence
what kind of trust is needed so that I can let the dredge dregs of
selfing settle out allowing for the clarity
that is needed for insight
though the qualities that the Buddha sought to inspire in his followers
to prepare them for his deepest teachings who are being receptive
having a mind that's soft without the Fetters of fixed views and
conceit free of the preoccupations of the
hindrances glad and inspired to practice
and with today's quality a mind that is settled clear
bright and confident
and then when these qualities are in place and we have opened the Dharma heart
then we can finally understand the deepest teachings of the Buddha
so do you know what these deepest teachings are
um they may sound rather pedestrian at first not so mind-blowing
and in the discourse I'm referring to this week Imagine
91 in the middle length discourses when the Brahman uh brahmayu had these
wholesome qualities of mind and the Dharma eye arose in him
then the Buddha said all of it is subject to arising
is subject to cessation and with this where my you saw the
Dharma and became enlightened so that's all there is to it
to really know that oh it is subject to arising is subject to cessation
but you know of course it's not enough to just know it with the mind we have to
know it with our whole being and be transformed by it
so my suggestion to you with the teachings of this week is that for the Dharma eye to open in
you you may need to do some preliminary work of opening the Dharma
heart we need to
get to the bottom of our suffering and see the uselessness of clinging to anything
bringing all of you of Who You Are to walking this path
and then letting go of trusting the small self of Me Myself and mine
and opening up for and making space for trusting
the Dharma to take you in the direction of freedom
when we can let the Mind settle and get out of their way the Dharma
knows where to take us and that's something we can trust
thank you and a small announcement is that next
week you will be in good hands with my friend
Don Neal Dawn and I were thesis buddies six years
ago when we did our master's degree with Gill franzal as our major professor
so I'm sure you'll enjoy next week as well thank you for being here