so welcome folks um yeah nice to be with
you okay let's uh let's
it
either easing your way
in or uh starting on a dime and
dropping
everything
sometimes we have to kind of tunnel our way into the present
moment sometimes it's uh right there waiting for us with one
breath
sometimes skillful to uh kind of palpate the psychospiritual
body you know where does it hurt what
needs are uh blessing love
awareness the Loops of thought that uh won't
unwind the heartaches
anxieties
we just do uh what we can
to give
um give our blessing to
uh the surges of of energy in body and
mind in this way our uh
heart becomes more and more
uh available to this
breath
we're practicing being uh
softened by all
phenomena by words and images what we call
Thinking by emotion and other
sensation
by the
breath it's all
phenomena treated like uh the the Buddha's
whisperings
and when the heart loses its suppleness as it does as it
will loses its suppleness when we become
identified when
imperfection feels like a problem to be
solved when it feels like uh we must Retreat to the headquarters of uh self
and rearrange
samsara
when we lose our softness we soften
again
we can actually uh feel something like this uh
softening this way that we trust our heart to uh meet the intensity of The
Human Condition
in the transition from uh the the uh clench to fist of
clinging to the release of letting go that
uh that movement is a kind of
softening doesn't mean we're free of discomfort then or that the
softening itself is totally
Pleasant but something about it
is the kind of anxiety
agitation of attempting to control this
moment that melts
away and just that is a deep relief to something in our
heart and so maybe we're breathing feeling our body or hearing
sound practicing in whatever way we
practice then there's some
noticing of
brittleness we breathe and
soften
all phenomena mean the same
thing let
go
it's a a path to freedom but it's also
practicing freedom the way an
athlete practices a basketball shot free throw or
something we're
practicing
freedom doesn't mean
we make the
shot but we
practice doesn't mean we
pretend to like what we don't like or be okay with what doesn't feel
okay but we
practice we rehearse our own
freedom
okay folks that's good to sit with you
um so yesterday was um
effort and effortlessness and uh the effort the
effort that we make and and the the kind of momentum of
goodness I don't know whether it's momentum or inertia somebody once harass me about that I'm
not sure which kind of stand metaphorical
here uh but
today today uh disenchantment disenchantment with uh samsara and uh
the abiding care for the World
engagement and so the um the Buddhist path uh
really it begins with a recognition of the vulnerability of The Human Condition
aging sickness death they kind of like the dimension of human life that is sort
of defenseless and that's generally
construed as a problem to be solved a kind of condition to be
exited and it's probably underemphasized in a lot of modern articulations of
Dharma but a lot of the sutas the sense of of um something
like get me out of here is too much and it was and it is and
it's very understandable that uh one
might be dissatisfied with uh the intensity of of even a fortunate very
fortunate life um
so the the kind of instruction curiously is to stay very
deeply with sensory experience as I was instructing in the
The Meditation to stay deeply with sensory experience but that when we stay
that deeply it actually takes us out of the ordinary sensory
world famous from right
B uh when when uh in the scene is merely
the seen and and it goes on and the cognized Really the co is merely the cognized then you will not be with
that when you're not with that you will not be in that when Bia you are not in
that then bahah you will be NE Nei here nor Beyond nor in between the two just
this is the end of
suffering um a lot to say about that um but this
this way in which our immersion into sensory experience uh gives us a kind of
foothold uh outside it that's one way of dealing with the
intensity the vulnerability of The Human Condition uh modern interpretations of
insight practice uh often celebrate
vulnerability and it's Associated duty to
care uh the way that just perceiving vulnerability opens our heart right it's
um uh yeah it's um takes a very Harden heart to see
vulnerability and exercise cruelty or something like
this so we're in the kind of like early phases really of extrapolating a lay
path from a monastic tradition so are we are we renouncing
samsara are we redeeming samsara are we doing
both can can uh a kind of
disenchantment and love of The Human Condition fit
together so on the disenchantment side we do have
this um this deep conditioning that there's something we could acquire something we could
acquire that might resolve all of our
longings the Buddha says
no no there's a way that um until we some
some part of us gives up on the world we're always um expecting more than the
the world can give us Oh's expecting the things of the world to
give us more than they can and we don't grow much on the path
unless there's some measure of renouncing the
world s Vega that kind of I spoke about this uh the the dayong at IRC couple
weeks ago um there are just too many kind of toys
and bells and promises and distractions for our spiritual practice
to take root unless there's some sense of just like my longings will not be
satiated by this world by sensory
experience so from Tanis biku uh s Vega was what the
Young Prince at artha felt on his first exposure to aging illness and death it's
a hard word to translate because it covers such a complex range at least three clusters of
feeling at once the oppressive sense of shock dismay and alienation that come
from realizing the futility and meaninglessness of life as it's normally lived
a chastening sense of our own complacency and foolishness in having let ourselves live so
unconsciously and an anxious sense of urgency in trying to find a way out of the meaningless
cycle Buddhism not only is not only confident that it can handle feelings of
svea but it's also one of the few religions that actually cultivates them to a radical
extent its solution to the problems of Life demands so so much dedicated effort
that only strong s Vega will keep the practicing Buddhist from slipping back
into their old
ways we can be
um completely mesmerized by Sam Sara's shell
game from Cradle to grave
just looking looking
looking where is it where's my
life we can be um perpetually enticed into just the fixing and achieving and
becoming acquiring owning and then it's time to
die and everything broken it cannot be fixed and nothing is
owned aan suito said the hardest thing for a human being is what's
enough because you can always want
more and so there is this movement in spiritual practice this kind of Turning
Away the Dharma is not something for nothing it's
not and this is this is a measure of
disenchantment and yet the pivot here the yet
yet we only want to escape some
sorrow because we care so much about suffering uing our own that of
others we care so much about it
and maybe the kind of movement of becoming disenchanted we turn away from
the world because well at least I can uh free my own heart that's maybe what I
can manage and that's true that's true 600
BC that's true now but times are different now it's not 600
BC and uh in a way
technology science has scaled our defilements but also our
parames it's made us obviously like profound existential threat to our own
existence but it's also developed you know um our goodness in
amazing ways we have tremendous power to engage and help others we
understand uh our bodies in like incredibly nuanced ways right I was I
was at a um lecture conversation on on uh just a
couple days ago Monday night and uh like learning about kind of glob Health
conversation and um I I diarrhea is still like the cause
of death for several hundred, kids less than five you know and um oral oral
rehydration solution kits with with with zinc cost about $3 to deliver and you do
some math you do some kind of medical statistics and analysis and um if you
treat several hundred kids with severe diarrheal disease you'll save a life
yeah cost about $2,000 is the estimate yeah and
um so what am I supposed to do with that you
know renounce some Sara go back to
meditating fiddle with the OA cesas you
know the middle path uh the middle path between everything means everything and
nothing means anything
and as we actually loosen the grip on the world this actually dramatizes the
plight of humanity as we get Space through a measure of
disenchantment and letting go that space comes to be filled with
care and our gestures of love will not turn Sam Sora into a Utopia the first
Noble Truth will never be eradicated but yeah this little patch of
suffering I want to care for
that again uh this from Ria Kong uh when I think about the sadness of the world
their sadness becomes mine oh that my priest's robe were wide
enough to gather up all the suffering people in this floating
world and we know the robe will uh
never be wide enough but
uh that it were
so and so one foot out of this world and
one foot uh really really in
it
I offer this for your uh consideration and
uh we'll be back tomorrow
probably sorry for any confusion about the stream it keeps defaulting to to a
private stream so apologize if there's any confusion and uh May uh may we all
have uh um a good day of uh practice in the
broadest sense of that word okay