so hello and welcome to our meditation
session and one of the things that I think meditation and
is associated with often is calming becoming calmer and to only think of it
for that purpose is pretty reductionistic but becoming calm is
certainly extremely valuable one of the purposes of becoming calm and
one of the means of becoming calm and one of the consequences of
becoming calm is uh the relaxing of clinging the
relaxing of attachment of gripping of
uh strong ways in which we hold on or resist in a way that's stressful for our
minds our hearts our body and to emphasize letting go to
emphasize non-attachment non- clinging in the abstract sometimes it's hard to
understand why or but in um or the value of that but
one of the things we're doing through mindfulness practice is uh developing a
heightened sensitivity uh a greater uh
awareness of what it's like physically
emotionally mentally when we're clinging to feel the unpleasantness of clinging
to feel the tightness of it the the pain of it
even to feel to really kind of be present such a way we feel of course we
want to relax that kind of tension it's like holding if someone's really angry and they hold their hand in a fist
that they might even know that they're holding their hands in a fist and then a friend comes along and sees how tense we
are and just picks up our Fist and holds it gently lovingly and then oh now we
realize and now we can we realize how painful it is to hold the hand that way and we
relax so part of this practice then is to
be in the present moment so we can feel and sense what
this living life is like for us so we can see where we are hung
up and to loosen up Let
Up release because we know we
feel and if we don't feel well if we haven't really taken in the
experience of clinging of attachment and see in the
moment the unsatisfactory of of it unsatisfactoriness of it then I suggest
you don't let go you don't relax but you bring a greater attention
to it until you feel how unsatisfactory it is to do it to be that
way so assuming a meditation
posture and now think of this posture as a posture that your body is going to
be an instrument a fine well calibrated
instrument for sensing and
feeling your lived experience giving some care that it's a posture
that supports a heightened
sensitivity and gently closing the
eyes and this instrument of the body to be more connected to
it take a few long slow deep breaths just deep
enough that you feel more connected but not
winded then a long slow exhale little longer than usually
would as a way of relaxing the body sensitive to the body as you
breathe in relaxing as you
exhale
for
and letting the breathing return to normal and with normal breath
continue just allow yourself to feel your body more fully as you
inhale maybe the Torso shoulders the
chest wherever the body
is activated by breathing in and on the
exhale relaxing
breathing in and feeling more fully the mind
the thinking mind and as you exhale soften Relax The
Thinking
mind
and if you're relaxed and it's easy to just ride the breathing easy to settle into the
present moment continue practicing this way
but if there's any way that you're hung up you have concerns
preoccupations resistance or contractions anything that can be
called an attachment or a clinging holding
on
resisting it's okay that you're this way the task is as you breathe in feel
it more fully allow yourself to feel
it till you feel how unsatisfactory it is how there's
something deep inside of that attachment that
clinging that wants to let go
and on the exhale let go
soften loosen but only after you've
known felt what it's like to be
attached never let go without knowing first
what attachment feels
like
for
e
remembering to take your time to sense and
feel the physicality of clinging of being
preoccupied holding on
fixating whatever way whatever version of clinging you
have the task is to know it well feel it
well until you feel almost as if it comes out of the
clinging itself the desire to
relax the wisdom that letting go is
wise
that's
for
e
[Music]
for
e
and then as we come to the end of a sitting to take a brief few moments
here to feel yourself more
deeply is there something about how you might be more subtle or calmer or a
little bit more clear and
aware that makes you more sensitive to clinging and grasping
contraction holding on
resisting and even if those things are not present
present is there a reference point
now for deeper feeling of them when they
occur not a judgment of them not ideas about clinging but to
actually feel and sense what it's like
how can you become
wiser when you have a deeper sensitivity to clinging and
grasping to desire and
aversion
and the more we can become aware of the remaining ways that we still
cling or hold on or attached maybe the greater
patience and generosity and Care compassion with we can have for
others who are clinging and grasping and holding
on that we see in others ourselves we see in ourselves
others we feel and know the challenges that are deep
inside and now our own perhaps allows us to
be to gaze upon others more generously more
kindly as we all go through this difficult World difficult
life may all beings be
happy may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be
safe and may all beings be free of
[Music]
suffering thank
you
so so then I continue with uh the story of my Dharma life and for this week it's
more my life as a teacher and uh I ended yesterday by talking
about how we decided to become incorporated as a religious
nonprofit and that happened in 1997 and the purpose of that was to uh
be able to purchase our own property to have our own Center and um so that process began
of seeing how we could do that and uh early on we had this idea
that um actually we had the the first and maybe the only fundraising committee
meeting group of people who were interested in trying to fundraise for this purpose and we met in someone's
living room and um Terry lesser who's our yoga teacher here for many years at
IMC she said uh Money Follows the practice and as soon as she said that we
stopped talking about how to raise money and rather talked about how we could offer more practice
opportunities and we did a survey of the community see what kind of practice opportunities they wanted and one of the
things that was desired was to have a Sunday morning program other was to have a yoga program and um and other things and so
we started a Sunday morning program uh in ptoa valy and by now we were using many
different facilities around during through the week through all the different programs we have been
developing we had two programs a week at the Friends Meeting House we had at the
community center in Porta Valley we had the Sunday morning program we had a
dayong retreats in um uh in a couple of other
churches a Presbyterian church and a Unitarian Church that we did on often on Saturdays we started started doing
Retreats kind of weekend Retreats at a Zen Center up in the mountains here
called jakoi wonderful little Z Zen Center and uh and then a SAA kind of
connection uh offered me a uh a room in her house that had its
own door to the outdoors that I could use as an office where I could meet
people because before that if I had to was going to meet oneon-one for practice discussions with people when the weather
was good on meet in Parks as City city parks and when the weather wasn't good I would meet at coffee shops and and that
was kind of you know interesting to be having very deep difficult conversations in a coffee shop and sometimes people
were crying telling me about their life or something and and but that was the only we didn't have any space because we
had no place of our own and so then we had this so then I
had this office in uh this person's home and so we had all these different places and it became clear and clearer that we
were we had enough programs through the week that we can consolidate them all just move them all into our own Center
it kind of like Justified having our own place but we just developed our practice
as um and then we also in having deciding to have first uh we had first Monday evening then Thursday evening and
then Sunday evening one of the clear decisions that I made was that I didn't
want to be a teacher uh teaching too many people at one time and and uh so when we had about
a 100 people coming Monday nights we started the second program on Thursday nights to take the pressure off Monday
and then we started Sunday morning and um it would have been a lot easier for me to just give one Dharma talk a week
to a big group of people and maybe it would have been more efficient in some ways but I felt that
the Dynamics of being a teacher in the front of a very large group of people there was a lot there's a lot of
projection even if it's unconscious it just that fact that so many people are focused on one individual and the way we
do it in the inside World giving Dhat talks I think it creates kind of a skewed relationship and uh or
projections or associations to all that and I wanted to uh I wasn't interested
in that I wanted to keep you know things kind of simple and more basic and I didn't I didn't want to become like a
big teacher somehow and and one of the aspects of that was that when we meeting
at the Friends Meeting House um everywhere we met I just sat on the floor on a zapaton on a meditation mat
but uh then slowly people said well we can't see you at the big room you have to be up elevate a little bit and I
resisted that a lot to even to go up I think eight or 10 inches on a little platform was I didn't want that because
I felt associated with kind of becoming a little bit too special or something and then at IMC we brought that platform
with us here and then they wanted it higher and I resisted that and and um and would only
use it sometimes but now and that's what I'm sitting on now it's probably 15 Ines or so and uh and now it just seems like
what we do but I had this concern about you know the the uh elevation of uh projection
the elevation of authority power all kinds of things that goes in being this
role as a teacher so we were started to looked for a place and uh we I think we were pretty
naive but how we were going to finance it and how you know we didn't but we were surprised that before we even
started asking for money when people learned that we were wanted to buy a place people walked up to us with checks
and said here it wasn't like big checks necessarily but people just started offering US money and and um and then we
started raising money with the fundraising letter once a year and then at some point uh we heard about um uh a
minister couple in Redwood City who were the Ministers of this building here and
it had been a um it would built by a small uh Christian denomination called
First Christian Assembly and um they were a little bit mystical Christians they sat in silence
a lot and the uh elderly couple were ready to sell it but they wanted to sell
it to someone who um also sat inside silence and we had a middle a person
between us a bridge to us between the them who knew us and knew them and introduced
us and um and so uh I called them up and they were
certainly interested but the message we got back is don't call us we'll call you so we drove by the place and saw it but
and it was the kind of the furthest limit of how the geographical area we
thought we would maybe could move to and um and so we didn't call them for
I think I called them one more time this was in January I think and or something like that April and then uh the
following January we still hadn't been shown the church and so I called them up
and a little bit honestly a little bit as a kind of a way to see if we can get some contact going I said
um um you know we were looking for a place to be able to hold some kind of event we want to do could we use your
church and uh and uh the one Minister I talked to on the phone uh basically said
no I think but we had an hourlong conversation and that was really nice and then I was next day I talked to the
the spouse in other hourong conversation and by that time we were like best friends and we talked a few more times
on the phone it just felt so much love so much warmth going on and they just assumed that they were going to sell it
to us they hadn't even shown it to us and uh they even said that they would uh carry the loan which we didn't have
really the money to do that with you know to buy it ourselves and um it was very strange to
have all this going without actually having seen it and um and so finally in September of
2021 uh the um uh they showed it to us
and and uh it was just kind of a wonderful connection with them and they were so happy with our community and us
with them and we bought it and then in 20 January 2022
20 2002 so September 2001 we we saw it bought it and then moved in January of
uh 2002 in looking for it we had uh we
visioned for it and the we did I had we had I had a bigger Vision at just having a center uh the dream I had was since I
was going to be rooted here in this area now that it would be nice to be able to provide uh a Buddhist practice
opportunities or support for people uh throughout their lifetimes from uh
childhood to from Cradle to grave kind of thing and so they one of the Visions
we originally had was to find a property that was big enough to have a community Meditation Center a place for people to
do long-term self- Retreats and a hospice and uh those three would be kind
of synergy of a certain kind of depth of spirituality and connection we had thoughts about
children's programs and when we finally moved here uh we were kind of a little
bit of pioneers for the mindfulness in schools movement and um the few of us
here met rically and organized the first conference uh in the country on mindfulness in the school systems and
people came from all over to uh you know because it was the first one and to have this conference so there was a bigger
vision of what was possible that started with a looking at a center like
this as I continued teaching uh before we bought the place I
had my first CH my my wife and I we had our first child and uh that was a real
turning point for me because um it uh we had a high-spirited child
and uh parenting for me was quite demanding monastic life was easier for
me than parenting and I often was very tired and and um my wife and I were
often very tired from the constant care of this child and we had no support we
didn't have grandparents nearby we didn't have we didn't have any Nanny and
things like that and one one point we we brought our child to a uh the first kind
of kind of a preschool kind of thing and and um and it was
a he kind of was expelled from preschool uh within a few weeks flun throughout
out of preschool so that was a glorious beginning to his uh educational career I
think because he he woke up other woke other kids up during the nap and that was a no now for that
place and um but what happened for me as a teacher was I no longer had time to
prepare for my talks and I um and I was
tired so I would show up to teach and I thought that my the quality of my talks
I thought was really dropping dramatically but the odd thing that happened people seemed to appreciate my
talks more and more and I think what was happening was that I was becoming less intellectual about the Dharma and more
talking from from some you know from the state that I was in talking about how
things were for me personally and and uh and people resonated more than with the
talks and and that also then was a beginning of uh I felt really the
beginning of be of starting to be ATT tuned to how being a teacher is uh its own practice and uh an
example of this would be I'd be sitting like I'm here now in my meditation posture to give these talks and as I
taught uh I would be paying careful attention to where if I was leaning forward or
being pulled back or the tone of my voice and there were so many little feedback loops inside of me of where I
got caught I was concerned about what people were thinking about me or you know if one person in the in the
hall walked out I could feel like like I got oh no I'm failing or something and
and I could feel you know sometimes it was subtle but I could feel the shifts of attachment or
uh uh I have fear sometimes if one person was sitting looking down shaking their head like this I noticed that my
eyes went to that person all the time as if that person was the arbitrator of how successful I was in teaching and so I
got to see a lot of the conceit a lot of the attachment a lot of the fears there
was a in this posture I could see the subtlest shifts and movements represented how I got caught and so as I
was teaching um um I was kind of using this as a practice thing and uh and that
was uh really important for me I learned so much about myself uh practicing
paying attention as a teacher in this role and um and that was a good thing
because as we got the center here then I started teaching even more and and um
and that just stly grown over time so I think we'll do one more day on
this Gil story and um and then we'll see what's next after that so thank you and
um and um I appreciate all of you and this chance to
tell these stories and I hope that uh it's somehow instructive or helpful for
you thank
you