good morning Sangha good morning warm greetings IMC Global YouTube Sangha it's a delight
to be with you again see all of the um greetings in the chat good morning good
morning warm greeting excuse the momentary reverberation
zoom and YouTube do not always um interact well
so happy to be with you and um
just before we settle in taking a few moments to take in
where you are physically and where you are in terms of this
global network of practitioners
feeling into your heart for whatever mood attitude
State of Mind is present this morning feeling into your body
or whatever is there and feeling into the goodness of being
here together
[Music]
perhaps taking a last look real close to asteroid at the greetings
from around the world and then moving the attention inwards
finding a posture that is warm balanced
receptive the balance of uprightness and alertness
allowing a smile to come to your lips if that feels
nice congruent for you
and settling in settling in perhaps with one or two deep
breaths
the tuning connecting to your body our mind
wrapping yourself in find attention
allowing your body to relax and biting the eyes to relax
good job
the temples and the cheeks the neck the occipital muscles
perhaps raising and lowering the shoulders to allow them to relax
inviting the arms and hands
the soften
noticing the natural Flex of the ribs diaphragm belly
happens with breathing and allowing the breathing
be natural nothing special needs to happen
failing into perhaps
the pleasure of the breath massaging the inside of the ribs
the inside of the back muscles rest at the core and viscera
in allowing awareness to fill the whole top part of your body torso
belly neck shoulders and the head
and the way water fills a sponge allowing the awareness to seep down into the hips the hip points
the buttocks as they contact whatever surface you're sitting or reclining on
rooted feeling supported by your surface
and by the vast strength of the Earth
underneath
allowing awareness to fill the legs the thighs hamstrings knees shins calves
knowing from the inside out
awareness and relaxation flowing through the legs down into the ankles
filling the feet
noticing the contact of the feet and the floor
depression mat
and then noticing your whole body
nothing left out present immersed here in this moment
and turning into the vibrancy the aliveness
of the sensory details of this moment this breath
this body
can be helpful to tune into the details breathing
or the field of sensations of the whole body very intentionally
distinctly
you're focusing on the breath doesn't work for you
please use the following instructions with the sensations of your whole body
or even with the act of hearing
to zoom in tune in to the wavelength
of the details of now
choosing a location to attune to the breath
could be the subtle transfusion [Music]
transpiration of Life Energy through all of your
body's cells or perhaps
the sense of the breath at the tip of the nose or the top of the lip
where the whole body of the breath from beginning to end
remember it's easiest to connect sustain draw a little Comfort or
pleasure
dedicating the attention to the details
a lived experience of breathing
allowing other phenomenon thoughts Sensations
sound to come and go in the periphery
and Gathering the attention
around this breath
sustaining contact
that barely noticeable moment the in-breath begins
through all the tiny Sensations
the breath moves into this body
look at that tiny pause and the body is filled with air
and releases into the Opera
noticing the play of Sensations perhaps at the left of the nose
or anywhere else that makes no sense
sometimes the in-breath has a bit more coolness
vibration
the out breath maybe smoother moisture warmer
relaxing into the flow the natural rhythm
of these unfolding Sensations
you know having the mind and heart to unify with the embodied sensations of
breathing resting releasing into
the flow of now this moment
foreign
[Music] the body heart and mind
to soften release
open into let go
allowing any rhythm relaxation
Comfort or pleasure being present with breathing
no matter how small
to be noticed appreciated
foreign
in the last moments of this formal meditation
the invitation is to gather together
recollect the collects
any moments of goodness moments of awareness mindfulness
softening or relaxation pleasure or patience
and Savor them appreciate them in your heart
and then turning your internal gaze outwards throughout your life
sharing offering some of that goodness
what words to the others you encounter
who your life touches directly or indirectly
writing the determination the aditana
that this practice May benefit the self and all of those around us
the goodness overflowing like water overflowing a vessel
we all beings everywhere be happy
see you peaceful
be all beings everywhere be free of suffering
you know the joy and Bliss of Awakening
[Laughter]
foreign
[Music] trash collection day
good morning
special good morning to those of you who arrived a touch late
we are in day four of a five day series on factors of mind
that supports devotee wisdom concentration
in meditation practice and that support us in daily life
we started with the fundamentals of mindfulness and practice Intelligence on
Monday and then moved into a series of mental factors known as
the five yonic factors there are five factors that support this
greater stability and refinement deepening of meditation
so we covered vitaka and vichara connecting and sustaining
then the emergent factors of joy
and happiness or contentment and today we cover the fifth of those five factors
quality known as a kagata
eka g-g-a-t-a-a-t-a
and that translates as single pointed concentration
unification and those are some of the translations I'll go into a few more of them in a few
minutes first I want to start with a story
near the end of his life the Buddha was visited by an emissary of a very bad
King it was just not a nice person committed patricide to take the throne
and this king king had seen the Buddha before but it was
maybe a little shy to be in the presence of the Buddha again given all of his misdeeds so he sent an emissary a
minister along to ask the Buddha a question and his um his question was predicated
based on the notion the truism that Buddhas Never Lie
so the king thought to take advantage of this and sends this Minister along to ask about the king's chances of
conquering and neighboring people the vajis and he's asked this question directly
and the Buddha doesn't actually address this emissary head-on that instead turns to his dear
cousin in attendant Ananda and asks him a series of questions that make
it known that as long as the vatis these neighboring people Gather in peace disperse in peace and
conduct themselves with Harmony and respect they will stay Unified
and unconquered so this is timeless societal advice that
happens to be timely for many of us right now also a really good analogy for our minds
If We Gather the constituents of our minds in Harmony and respect
stability emerges our hearts and Minds can unify
the polybird for Unity is used to refer to both group deliberation
and unification around a topic and to unifying in meditation then it's
called a kagata in meditation this process of
unification is unifying streams of thought impulses and attention in a
congruent Direction just like little rivulets gather and flow into streams
and those streams gather and flow into rivers and then those River Rivers eventually gather together and flow into
Great Mighty Rivers like that
another example is if you picture a pile of iron filings just kind of all in many
directions and you pass a magnet over them they all unify and move in the same
direction it's like that
congruent alignment so
invite you to feel in your body feel into some of the range of translations
unification being collected
calm one pointedness
Tranquility or Serenity of mind
so that's one range I'll talk about that for a little while and then bring in another
when this quality is present all of the other factors of Mind we've
talked about over this past week are in synchrony congruent aligned and
moving in the same direction there's momentum but it's a quiet
still momentum not Gathering
magnetism if you will as that synchrony tranquility
Serenity grows the experience of our hearts Minds bodies becomes more quiet
subtler there are several stages to this each a
marked shift into a deep and stable State of Consciousness known as Janna
and Janna 's are usually almost always only available in deep
Retreat long retreat for most people
that's okay the rest of the time the Mind naturally produces thought most of
the time thinking is its natural function that's not an enemy much wisdom can be gathered
from this broad receptive mindful awareness and practice
intelligence and then sometimes these stages take hold
and while we're not going to experience them in a half hour sit or a single YouTube
video I'm going to speak them as similes that
the Buddha offered that can evoke a sense or a taste of how each stage of
unification in this progression unfolds and there are four that I'll talk about
as I speak these similes the invitation is to feel them in your body
and perhaps visualize them and if you can't visualize or feel into your body imagining that you can visualize
or feel into it's just fine that works too
so settle back for a moment maybe take a breath or a sip of tea
and then open your receptive awareness your intuition
so in connecting sustaining
Joy and easeful contentment happiness are all present
and unified it can feel like needing moisture into
dough so that the moisture pervades evenly
all throughout
feeling that often it can feel like ripples are weird
the breath massaging every part of the body the attention
massaging every part
the Buddha described this process as being like water added to Bath powder
kneaded together skillfully to create a single soft ball of soap
moisture is pleasurable awareness throughout the whole body and mind
testing three energetic experience
none in the second similarly the mental movements of connecting
sustaining attention become unnecessary and drop away
only joy happy contentment remain Unified
the body and mind an experience like a clear Mountain Lake
no rain or streams feeding it replenished only by a cool internal
spring an internal Wellspring of well-being
and even that in the next stage that energetic quality softens
and quiet and each individual person's body and
mind are submerged and unified with calm
content happiness a calm content pleasure
is like water touching lotuses of many many different colors that are completely submerged
in the cool clear water from tip to root
immersed no part left out
then everything except for calms I mean unified Equanimity drops away
like after emerging from a cool soothing bath and being wrapped from head to toe
in a soft bright white cloth or fluffy towel
enveloped like stepping out of that cool Shady Spring
so imagining feeling in your body for any sense of resonance or any intuitive
glimpse these similes provided the process of serenity
unification is a progressive Letting Go a letting go of what's more obvious or
coarse into what's calmer and more peaceful
stage has its own value and each must be released in order to
make space for a more calm and peaceful place
and perhaps this is why in kagata usually translated as unification
or collected calm it also has the meaning of a capacity to make
distinctions discernment is developed in this process
of learning to make distinctions between the different mental factors which we've been learning all week and also in the
process of letting go of the more energetic and exciting in favor of the Tranquil and the
peaceful this helps to mature a practice
and happily that maturity these lessons
don't require deep Retreat and uncommon stance of mind to start to learn them and embody them
tastes of each of these factors including unification begin to train our capacity
for letting go and experiencing how these different mental factors can
deepen broaden and add beautiful qualities to our meditation
so thank you thank you for your attention today tomorrow the topic is how wisdom can
support the development of these factors and how the development of these factors
supports the growth and wisdom I love that the similes and comments
coming in and encourage you to share whatever observations or
glimpses you had with each other and with me and if you have any questions based on
the four talks I've given so far please drop them in the chat I can't promise I'll get to all of them
but I will certainly try to read them in so thank you Sangha for your kind
attention and your homework assignment if you wish to
take it until tomorrow is to notice what brings more peace
and unification to your heart and mind thank you