oh hello and welcome to happy hour
so for today's practice um I think what I like to do is to invite
us to start with a a settling with a quiet meditation
and the inspiration for today's practice is um
is uh is happiness is happiness and the path of practice
the Buddha was known as the happy one as the happy one man there is no
no shame no problem in in Wishing happiness in fact it's part of the meta
wish wishing for ourselves to be happy wishing for others to be happy
um and and offering it so the inspiration today is offering this wish for happiness as a
wish as a blessing not attached to it oh I'm not happy I want to be happy why I'm not
happy in this area of so if you become really contracted around happiness or
lack of Happiness that's a sure way to become unhappy it's the perfect recipe
for unhappiness just but but if wishes for happiness are are
shared as an intention as a blessing as a good will as a gift without attachment
as a gift without strings attached you don't give gifts with strings attached
so why would you give yourself gifts with strings attached I wish
myself well I really do tight no no no no may I be well may there be happiness
May there be Joy blessing and and seeing the effect of
that playing around with that so that's the the little inspiration for today's
practice and we'll play around with it
so with that invite I invite us to settle
into our bodies In This Moment In Time whatever is
arising and then connecting with the body
with the Earth the contact points
on with the breath in the body
and letting each breath be easeful calming soothing
pilling the soil
for ease
nowhere to go nothing to do the happiness of just being here with this breath so much
happiness happiness of undistractibility
not wanting just here with the breath
let's explore this happiness first as much as it's available
and after thoughts distractions the happiness of releasing letting go
non-judgment
and as if you're returning your radio tuning your radio your perception your
awareness tune into the subtle radio station
a quiet contentment quiet happiness in this moment
it's very subtle very soft
but it's definitely here for every single one of us
no matter the conditions the body and the heart and mind it's very subtle
you can just be perceived perhaps as quiet
settlement settling peace
it's the moment's respite or it could be a little louder my
contentment this simple nourishing happiness
it's here already
peace and quiet he's and quiet is already here we just keep staring it up
can we tune into it foreign
consider the breath your tuning instrument the breath in the body
embodied breath so you're tuning lever
there are so many radio stations on the style
thoughts worries challenges pain there's plenty there's plenty there's also
contentment nascent happiness and joy
sorry to hear in the moment's respite
you can all tune into it
and let it reverberate through the body even if there is pain
for example in my body there's a lot of pain right now and yet there is this they sent him to have his Joy quiet Joy
I'm tuning into and inviting you to dare to dare to tune
in as well it's possible for all of us
the practice
practice with it
as you find your way to tune turn the dial
the happiness of awareness this breath this moment just being
even if you tune for a moment and you feel it oh yeah
there is happiness here 's contentment
along with everything else but this is what I choose to tune into
and you can say if you wish I am happy
there is contentment there is joy or I am joyous whatever resonates
or may I tune into joy into happiness may I be happy
whatever version that works for you
I am happy
or may I be may I tune to it see what works play around
offer it as a wish as a blessing as an invocation aspiration to lift your
heart
turn towards the good
and be very subtle it's okay
or maybe it's just simply I'm okay I'm okay
and if this practice of tuning into this goodness the wellness contentment
happiness is working a subtle way bringing Happiness joy
as an act of matter you can continue stay with this
and if you like to switch to the more familiar may I be happy you can do that as well
as I met a wish for yourself either way
foreign
and as we turn to bring this sit to a close
feeling into any nuances of contentment peace joy
happiness might have been touched into tuned into
with appreciation letting them reverberate through your body one more time
there would be gratitude appreciation even for the slightest bit which again could be co-existent with
challenges pain difficulty
and the attuning into what's good what's here already
and appreciating with with wholeheartedness
interesting that we are planting seeds of kindness Goodwill
a meta wishing ourselves well seeing ourselves while tuning into happiness is an act of
matter it's not taking ourselves for granted but taking care of our heart to tune
into contentment joy happiness self-love
the way of loving ourselves ending to our hearts
and trusting that we're planting seeds kindness care
love for ourselves and for others
to be more available or patient with others when we're happy
content and of service may we be of service
may we wake up may all beings awaken
may all beings be truly truly happy
[Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so so what we did the night Lord this morning or whatever your time zone might
be in this moment in time it's an invitation to tune into quiet contentment quiet
contentment peace ease Happiness joy just a whole
range of possibilities and and again there's so many different
channels in the mind and the heart and as I shared with you with my body there's a lot of pain right now and
possible to tune into tune into happiness tune into yeah there was
contentment of just being here being with the breath there's a goodness there's a contentment there's a delight
happiness in that and and that it's it's as we blow on it it it grows so yes you
can be I can be in pain and I can be happy at the same time yes I'm happy not
in pain of course you know as human beings we often get so narrow our Focus
gets so narrow especially when we have difficulty that becomes the only thing that's happening in our field of
experience completely pushing out everything else but there's so much
presence so many things that we can tune into so this was a an invitation to tune
into contentment goodness peace happiness right here and now
um and and listen to it more and more Let It reverberate and see what happens
and and as I shared for me there was a sense of oh yeah I am happy as I as I stayed tuned into this Channel and the
contentment The Joy the the uh the Gratitude yeah there's so
much goodness right now yes yes happiness is here along with everything
else well that was the invitation and if it worked for you this this way
of tuning into meta and self-care great if it didn't work no problem no worries
there's so many ways so many doors into the temple
so the invitation now as we turn to small groups together
is to uh to if you wish you are welcome to share
um one one nugget about how this practice was for you oh this part oh there was an
aha moment here or this was challenging just one nugget but you practice if you
wish or you can also share um silence just kind-hearted silencing just
being present and you can say pass when your turn comes and next person will share we'll say
pass and next person will share or say pass and your turn comes again so so you'll go around and around hopefully a
couple of times not having a long monologue but but uh but just brief and
also be inspired because as odd as you listen to others you can be inspired by what they found what how they practiced
how they turned to this practice and just sharing from your own
experience not asking questions from others not directing anyone else's
experience showing as you are with kindness with humility
um and with aspiration to support others and be supported
um offering again as a way of being held witness not to impress not to
we're really speaking for our own benefit not for anybody else's benefit
be kind be kind and everything you say here of course stays here in small
groups so and let's Go reverse alphabetical order according to first name first name
yes the first character that shows up I'm going to create the rooms
have fun take care take care of yourselves take care of
each other and here we go
okay welcome back everyone welcome back so we have a few minutes
for Reflections aha moments challenges questions and I'd like to invite you if
you haven't spoken actually in in the large group to pull forward and if you
have spoken pullback really make space for those who perhaps have not shared
before or tend to hold back so um I'd like to hear from
from you here are willing to share what came up for you how was it what happened
she while waiting for your hands I'll share one of the reflection that was shared with me in chat privately that
was a beautiful meditation they have to go back to work now hopefully now with more contentment
yay may you all have more contentment so any reflections
done I haven't heard from you in a long time yeah I've been lost
in the wilderness the um I I re the we are talking in our group uh I think we
all really enjoyed the the metaphor of um tuning in and um
I uh I'm the or actually not recently but for a long
time this endless thinking and uh and for me the the tuning in it was really
subtle as you mentioned and uh and for me that it wasn't so much
happiness happiness but this sort of every once in a while I would it was just quiet and it was her for me it was
like this relief of like oh god wow this is nice and um anyway thank you so much
beautiful thanks so much for sharing that Don I love it yes yes that's exactly it it's subtle they take some
tuning and there are different nuances that arise right which is this oh this sense of relief just as you you
beautifully shared oh how nice how nice it is subtle happiness so if you have
actually time to to tune into it more of that that sense of relief is is a subtle
form of Happiness yes yeah I see your nodding yeah yeah sweet beautiful that's
exactly it love it yay yay and know that this practice is always
available to you especially when there's yeah thoughts and worries and concerns and concentration yeah I'm going to tune
to something different which is already here trust that it's here for every single one of us
I know that it's here for all of us
I trust it nowhere else please
maybe you'll take one more reflection red
hi hi I was saying to my group that sometimes uh with a meditation like this
with a with a suggestion involved where the fine-tuning I'll experience something in
the midst of it and then maybe a few hours later it will
will come back with greater force and I I'll feel something that
um I'll be surprised by I mean I will associate it with the meditation but it
will seem to have come around a corner and it's you know it's a happy surprise and one of the people in our group uh
use the um likened it to ripening which I thought was a really a really apt way of
putting it that it it needs to sit it incubates it uh
I don't know why but it just seems to need a little extra time sometimes
thank you thank you Fred thanks so much for bringing that into the space how how
powerful how important to to share that for everyone's benefit yes pay attention
and yes it does need time to ripen we are planting seeds we completely are
planting seeds even if we feel during the meditation you know something happened or not much happened or mine
was all distracting or later oh yeah well look at that and yeah so powerful
thanks so much for bringing that in Fred really appreciate it yeah beautiful beautiful
so dear ones as I don't see any other hands and didn't don't see any other Reflections
in chat maybe this is a good time on those two beautiful shares to to bring
our practice to a close and may may we continue to tune in to tune subtly into
this this die a tune or dial to contentment peace
release happiness and and help it grow listen to it more and more so that
starting from crackly it becomes loud and clear may you all be well may we all be well
may we all be happy in all things everywhere
[Music]
thanks for your practice everyone take good care be