hello everyone and welcome
and as we begin get ready for meditation I would like to
um mention yesterday we I talked about openness being open
to whatever is happening in such a way that there's like lots of room for experience you can just
experiences thoughts feelings sounds occurrences around us when we meditate
don't have to stick anywhere we don't have to pick them up we don't start thinking about them we don't have to react there can be kind
of an openness like an open window just allow things to pass through
and um and this related to other kinds of teachings from meditation of meditation
being a radical acceptance of the present moment being kind of Thoroughly receptive to
experience and in that class that category or kind
of side of meditation as important as it is um it's good to have it balanced with
another side and that is um then the two can go together they
don't have to be separate but as a way of talking and that is
um the side of being upright the side of not collapsing
we don't uh metaphorically we're sitting upright and
we're sitting uncollapsed on we're not finding difficult things
that we're experiencing thinking about remembering feeling and just kind of
kind of bending over and putting our hand on her forehead and feeling sorry for ourselves or
we're not giving up on ourselves or giving up our ability to you know be be
grounded firm stable by the moment
so on one hand we're quite open to our experience
which might seem a little bit like we're just available to be victims of challenges
but the other side of it is we are not we're being undefeated
we are not cowering we're not giving up we're not collapsing
we're not um giving up giving in to the inner forces
that might be pushing us driving us to run away or give up or collapse or feel
sorry for ourselves or get involved in angry thoughts of
Revenge or um no we're not giving up our our
presence and stability here because of some fantastically wonderful pleasurable
fantasy that we get pulled into so this ability to be grounded and
upright grounded and just hear in a strong way goes together with this
openness and the uprightness gives a kind of strength and grounding and
and um kind of a freedom that adds to the freedom of just being
open and unaffected by what happens everything just passes right through in a certain way
and that combination then is certainly a preparation
for what might come the healthy things that might come and one of those healthy things is our
capacity for compassion and for love so this is not an aloofness or pulling
away the uprightness means we're right here for it for experience
there's no question that we're no we we're really here we're not avoiding anything
so to assume a meditation posture
and
closing the eyes and if you were going to call
on your inner strength to assume a posture that's upright
literally or metaphorically that feels like a strong
stance of being really here a strength that gives
emphasis on yes here I am
so it might be some way that the chest is not collapsed pulled in
might be some way that the head the position of the head and the neck where the
the back of the top back of the head gets pulled up towards the ceiling
or there's a little bit space form between the last vertebrae of the spine and the and the
skull
and then you might sway back and forth a bit partly to feel
the shifting pressure or weight of your legs your feet your bottom
and whatever is holding you up and then
bring that sway to Stillness and feel definitively
the way that the weight of your body is supported received
by the chair your cushion the floor the bed
in finding Within some place where personal strength
resides maybe it's a small little marble-sized place
somewhere in the Torso or in the hands or the feet
anywhere where some and with reference
to that strength the place of strength
taking some gently deeper breaths
almost as an expression of Your Inner Strength
exhaling relaxing as a definitive way of settling into
here taking your place this is your place to be
letting your breathing return to normal
and scanning through your body both to relax where there might be
tension
and release any place where we're contracted
breathing in and breathing out as you breathe in
as your lungs fill and your diaphragms pushes down
let that be a clear establishment
of stability uprightness strength
each inhale as a expression of
taking your place here
each exhale it's a relaxing and softening opening
non-resistance in the exhale
and gently as you breathe
without resisting anything and without collapsing or giving up or
giving in really here now in the present
breathing
finding in the breath in each breath
strength definitive Clarity of being here
just now
staying open to your present moment experience
with the support of inner steadiness
stability a strength
of upright
embodiment of attention
foreign
so then as we come to the end of this sitting
to gently maybe even lovingly
feel yourself rooted Here and Now
in your body in your body
rising out of whatever supports the weight of your body
feeling some inner stabilities
Inner Strength and maybe for a couple of minutes here
embodying that by sitting a little bit straighter
a little bit more a posture of definitively being here
and when you are here in a strong full way
upright imagine that your love your kindness
your compassion is supported by that strength supported
by that uprightness maybe like an antenna which is well
positioned to send out a signal far and wide
where you send out your care for the world your care of others
whatever a good will wishing
love that you have
for the circles of people around you those who are close in that you know the
best friends Neighbors
outward encircles into your community and communities out into the world
May are Inner Strength May our ability to be
upright and not collapse not give up not give in
but to really be here fully present May It Be
a means through which our care and love for the
world can flow
may we be a antenna that broadcasts well and far
kindness and friendliness
respect for others care for others appreciation of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free of suffering
and may we with our inner strength and stability
be a caring companion for others
moving through this life may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
hello and welcome to our third talk on Attunement
and the topic of Attunement is the practice of Attunement
is considered here one of the building blocks for compassion
to have a rush to be compassionate before we've put in place the building blocks for it
can easily lead to compassion being misguided and compassionate to be even detrimental
for those who are being compassionate in these days has been for a while now
to talk about um compassion fatigue compassion overwhelm
and it seems strange that anyone would ever be exhausted or overwhelmed by compassion
compassion is to be overwhelmed or fatigued by compassion would be like
saying that um that uh
I don't know the ocean is tired of being wet
they um the
you know the warm day is exhausted from being warm
that compassion by itself is not tiring
is not exhausting it's not it does compassion by itself does not make us
victims does not hurt us even what what's difficult is when compassion
is mixed in with all kinds of other attitudes and tensions and attachments
and things and but it's often it's considered to be part of compassion so people don't see
the difference but if we have these building blocks in place to be compassionate then
compassion can flow through us in a way that's even nourishing for us much more beneficial for others without
the exhaustion so one of these qualities is Attunement
which this week I'm offering five different aspects of Attunement
and today with the letter U in this in the acronym touch
is upright that when we encounter suffering
it's an occasion to make sure that we establish an uprightness
and what that means is we find our place of strength
and maybe it's an unfortunate term in the United States these days for how it's been used but um but if we can kind
of do away with some of the most recent kind of ways discussed in the news
kind of like stand our ground stand in our place not to attack anyone not to run away
from anyone but just really you know own our place where we are stands upright
firm strong not to be domineering not to be aloof or
distant but in order to so the openness we have can be supported by strength
and um into this uprightness for me implies a non-collapse not giving up not
giving in sometimes when they're suffering people want us to kind of participate in
their suffering on their terms and do the things that they want or they think is important to do
and it's not really clear that that's always the case should be necessary and the best thing to do
and so to um to it's kind of like taking a sacred pause
to take time to be open present see the situation more fully and establish
ourselves in in the presence of this in a stable
relaxed open way and it's a way that our strength Inner
Strength can kind of we can be embodied with our strength and the proposal I like to make uh is
the that when we are strong our love is is more valuable
when we are really standing upright metaphorically you know
you know really kind of embodied and present in a clear way
that when we love someone when we care for them when we're kind when we're
friendly it has more resonance it has more it's more is communicated through
it when we're open and uh you know I have the kind of
openness with that stand our ground we're not asserting ourselves uh we're not dominating over people
we're not rushing to kind of take care of them but we are
expressing care ing for and caring can be two different
things caring for is what we do caring is a attitude
and that attitude has more space it can be bigger when when we're really open
and there's a kind of inner largeness in space and awareness and when there's a
stability and uprightness of strength they a uh a
a embodiment that's really here for the situation
then it people notice more feel it more there more
if we are kind of uh you know sitting quietly to not disturb anyone in
the corner of the room kind of making ourselves a little bit small and we're sitting there kind of saying may you be
happy may you be peaceful that might be nice to do that but it
doesn't have the same level of of of impact I think that sitting up in the
same chair or pulling the chair out away from the corner so we're there clearly in the room together with people and
then we have an attitude of kindness then it's noticed that it's felt that has more it has more texture it has more
aliveness it has more there and um so uprightness
so the first of these five qualities with the acronym touch is to talk with
people find out what's going on no no think about it that's tomorrow
think about it have some thinking have some reflection what's going on here how
am I and what how am I receiving this how am I present for this what's the
circumference of what the context for the suffering that I'm in touch with or that I have myself
what's a useful way to be with it what does it mean to be attuned how do I come into harmony with it or balance with it
so asking questions is a big part of thinking about it having a you know
um and it's not necessarily asking why something's happening but thinking about how is it I can be present and attuned
to be open to experience is to increase our capacity to hold it
and rather than fixing things a lot of Dharma practices about expanding our
capacity to be present for our discomfort for things that are difficult for challenging things
without resisting without collapsing and when we don't collapse then we can
be upright and so uh to to think
to be open to be upright and and then tomorrow you'll see that
that's when we're there's the C is to communicate to actually talk to people
talk talk about what's going on it's before acting before acting out of the
compassion and so this uprightness where
there's non-collapse a powerful concept that comes from the Buddha in the kind
of CIS kinds of situations is to be undefeated do not be defeated by circumstance
do not sink down into being a victim but rather a rise to the occasion to be
strong a rise to the occasion to be free arise to the occasion to be someone who
takes a stance in mindfulness who's the way mindfulness is the home
from which we live in this world attentive strong presence
and um so to
practice now uprightness not giving in and not giving up
not belittling ourselves diminishing ourselves but also not aggrandizing
ourselves as simple relaxed really here I am definitively
not needing anything from other people not uh asserting myself to other people not
giving in to what other people want automatically but here I am be present
so as you practice these things uh thinking being open being stable and
strong it's often useful to start in areas where it's relatively easy
because it's like building a muscle if we just go immediately into some of the biggest sufferings that humans can
experience we might not be ready for it it's kind of like you have to work out a little bit and become familiar with the
territory and how to be and build a strength and build confidence in these different steps
so I'd encourage you to see if there's ways peaceful ways non-assertive ways
that you can be upright today just to so you really can be present and
take in the experience see yourself see the situation more fully without giving in to anything
giving up on anything without feeling guilt or feeling
unimportant and there's a wonderful place in uprightness
of neither feeling the conceit of being important nor feeling the conceit of being
unimportant and if you are upright and present
being neither important nor unimportant
what are you what is that like so thank you and um
then we'll continue tomorrow