so hello and welcome everyone lovely to be with
[Music] you and feel you even though we are not
in the same location there is a goodness there's an um yeah there's a beauty
especially at the beginning when we come together and say hello from different places on this Earth it always warms my
heart so for today's practice I'd like to invite you to um
consider um this this invitation and the
invitation is living this moment living this
moment of Our Lives as if it really
matters because it does what if we treat this moment not as
a throwaway moment as like oh yeah this moment and then there will be another moment but living this precious moment
of our precious human birth as if it really mattered because
it does and and that's not a way for us to
get really tight and stressed and like ah this moment matters no it's not an
invitation to get us all tight that's not the intention but it's an
invitation to expand our heart and sense of inhabiting this moment this moment
yes this a beautiful moment no matter what is going on in the body in the mind
and the heart that this yeah this moment matters I I am here I'm conscious I'm
alive I'm living this mystery this amazing mystery called called life I'm a
part of it yeah the cause and condition things are you know they pain and
difficulty and my life and in the world it's messy and yet wow this moment
matters this moment of of this being's life how can I live this
moment how can I live this moment treat this moment and really inhabit this
moment with a sense of spaciousness ease
and and appreciation for its fullness fullness in the ways that I usually
don't appreciate I'm always trying to prepare for the next moment or get rid of something or planning or thinking or
remembering or busy but this moment right here can I honor it can I can I
honor this life in this very moment um so this is the invitation for our
practice tonight and may not happen in every moment of the guided meditation it's perfectly fine but if it happens in
just a moment or two of yeah I can live
this moment cultivate my heart my mind inhabit this moment
um feeling that it it it this is this really matters I matter this matters I
matter ah can I give myself this sense of care and love and
appreciation as if it really matters because it does in ways we cannot fathom
we cannot understand but trusting that it matters what we do matters what we do
matters the way we show up in this moment matters not just to the being
this being who is me but in in an interconnected way in a interconnected
way matters to all beings so all right enough of a
preamble let's um let's begin our uh meditation
together so let us arrive let us [Music]
arrive in this body in this moment
relaxing the Mind relaxing the body the
heart letting go of preoccupations what has come
before planning for the future moment just releasing into this moment this
precious passing moment right
here
feeling the sensations of our feet on the earth the bottom of the [Music]
feet well rooted grounded feeling the sensations of her sit Bones on the chair
and the cushion our hands on our lap touching
one another and feeling receiving the
sensations of breathing in the
abdom
we have an attitude of releasing the past and the future in
this moment and inhabiting this moment [Music] fully showing up fully in this moment
with kindness towards ourselves embracing ourselves embracing
this moment unconditionally embracing this
moment unconditional
is it possible to embrace this moment with a full heart
[Music]
unconditionally living it inhabiting it as if it really matters notice how that
might shift your stance stance of your heart your body
your mind subtle shift that actually can be
huge fully embracing unconditionally embracing as if you're embracing your
friend family member
really it matters matters to inhabit this moment
fully UND
distractedly
if you find that the mind is resting on a thought past future may distracted not a problem not
a problem notice notice what's happening in this moment and celebrate that you're
awake now and can you inhabit this moment fully this
moment with intentionality bringing your whole heart
to it your whole body your whole heart all of
you the whole power Beauty Grace of you this being who
is you filling
out filling out the space of this
moment as if you a
balloon that was not quite inflated or
it pop up do you are not quite inhabiting your
life this moment of your life and you fully inhabit it however it is with its
challenges with its beauty Grace opportunities difficulties fully open
into it expand into it let your heart expand
not contract but expand shining its way growing its way
into this
moment
May wonder what does this even mean to inhabit this moment fully as if this
moment of Life matters really matters as if my whole life
matters you don't have to know in your head explore with your heart what does
it mean to you in this moment live the question discover for
yourself
How can there be kindness gentleness
wisdom it's a wave fully
embracing friendly Embrace of yourself This Moment whatever is
happening fully inhabiting with
presence it helps let the breath in breath out breath be the
anchor keeping you connected to your intention
way I show up in this moment or myself really
matters
the way I show up in this moment really matters not just to me but
others in ways I can't fathom so how do I want to show up in this
moment
one last invitation for the last few minutes if you
like what if this were the last moment of my life how would I want to show up and
feel In This Moment have gratitude appreciation for everything that is or
has been and has been with fullness of intention fullness of
heart how do I want to show up if this was a
period This Moment was a period to my
life the sentence of my
life
may we live the moments of Our Lives
well may we love
well maybe live may we live wisely fully
with presence and intention and may we serve
well may all beings everywhere be happy and be free including
[Music]
ourselves everyone
[Music] so you for your practice and uh before
we transition to small groups I want to ask you invite you if you like to share a word or phrase in
chat what uh how do you feel what's the impact
um maybe I'll share my word or phrase ra for me I feel more full I feel my heart is
Fuller full of intention as if I'm sitting taller I'm inhabiting my mind my
body are inhabiting more space more full this fullness of
intention and you can send your reflection to everyone in which case
I'll say your name otherwise if it's just to me I'll read um just you the word you offered love is one of the
offerings Heron says collected and [Music]
content Jerry says
concentrated Mishu allowing accepting Petra open SAR
motivated aara calm the
connected private chat peaceful heart a bill says couldn't concentrate
frustrated it's okay can you accept that fully can you be with that fully it's
okay it's okay interested curious clar says gratitude Erica
hoping ah another private one surprised by my presence
beautiful yeah Aran revealed much of complicated thinking that is present not
a problem good to have Clarity whatever is arising complicated thinking
frustration distraction can we be with it all just as it is can we be with it
all just as it is inhabit this moment fully
so so i' like to invite you all to engage with one another what if we live
this moment of Our Lives how might that shift even if whether it was present in this guided meditation or if it was not
present in this guided meditation what would it be like what do you imagine how might shift your attitude towards
yourself towards others towards your life this this gift that is your life
your impermanent life or limited amount of time and we're always so uh concerned
with things that are not going well and and that that we miss we miss the grace of it as techan has said
um walking on water is not the miracle walking on
Earth is the miracle we're all engaging in Miracles every moment of being alive
so so the invitation for the small groups
is to again explore for your your own benefit as you speak You're exploring
the other two people are just holding you witness they're not going to ask you questions even if they didn't understand
a word of what you said they're just going to hold kind compassionate presence no questions asked you're just
exploring for your own benefit what would it be like I don't know um and
then you offer a nugget the next person offers a nugget or reflection reflecting for their own benefit the next person
then comes back to you so go around a few times doesn't have to be a long
monologue just one nugget of exploration uh offered for the benefit
of yourself and um yeah as a gift so so I'm going to
create the small groups and and yes let's go alphabetical order reverse
alphabetical order in terms uh with last name
and here we go I'm going to create the breakout rooms and take care of yourselves take
care of each other be kind um yeah and explore what with this
reflection what if I lived this moment of Molly life as if it really mattered or my whole life as if it really
mattered because it does so creating the rooms take care of yourselves take care
of each other here we go okay the rooms are closed everybody's
back we have some time for Reflections questions um comments what did you
discover you can raise your hand especially if you haven't spoken recently in the small groups in the
large group um or you can also share it in chat either privately to me in which
case I won't read your name or you can share it with the whole group so what uh
what did you discover from this practice something shift and open up for
you I'd love to
hear and be quite a juicy practice and also can be confusing so everything is
welcome
there I'm GNA jump in because I love your topic um it's been sort of the
standard actually the standard of my life for a number of years because there was a movie done maybe as long as 10
years ago maybe longer called a bugs life and the songwriter for that movie
his name has unfortunately to gone out of my head in the middle of thinking about this tonight but he won an Oscar
for the first time he'd written scores of songs for movies never one anything
um and you would know all his songs he's very good anyway so he wrote a song for this movie called it's the rest of your
life so live it well this has been my Anthem ever since
I heard it because it is it's what we all it it would behoove us well to do
this let's put it that way um and I've always been one to look I I've had a
tough life and I've always looked at all the horrible things that have happened to me instead of looking at any of the
good things that came into my life uh and there were a lot of those too so I try to stay focused on the good things
coming in so that's why I gratitude on beautiful thank you Claire I have to go
find this this song now it's so sweet you love I'm going to go find it and I'm
sure by the time we finish the sentence you know who would have found it and put
the link in chat or something you know who but no pressure no
pressure great thanks Claire she lovely thank thank you for bringing this in
beautiful Petro please well thank you so much for this
practice was um yeah lovely and Powerful at the same time I was something I was sharing in the small group is um how
many moments in my life I live like they don't matter they're just a transition
to something else that will really matter and then when I get there it's just well that also doesn't matter as
much and there is the next thing coming up so lot of delusional moments uh but
this practice was very grounding to go back to yeah every moment matters so I
was so I really thank you for that lot of gratitude for that and I was also wondering is there any advice to bring
that more into maybe everyday life when we really get caught up in this Transitions and really forget about this
uh the preciousness of the moment of each moment yeah yeah thank you thanks
both for the reflection of how it it it really resonated for you and also the
question about how to live it remember to live it more um so so similar to
quote unquote mindfulness or or being aware it's it's easy to be mindful it's
and it's easy to forget right it's it's hard to remember it's easy to do it it's hard to forget so I mean h it's hard to
remember that's what I meant it's hard to so so that's why we practice that's why we practice on the cushion to bring
this reflection in so that it becomes more of an inclination of the mind and and also it would be helpful to have
some um um uh it's like habit stacking so you you
stack this reflection with especially those times that you tend to take them
for granted so maybe there are times that you're like oh I'm just going to go on I don't know social some social media
and it's just a wait time between whatever this and that it's like this doesn't matter like oh make a connection
to the times you go on a particular I don't know Facebook or whatever it is or this is the time like this matters this
moment of my life matters how can I really take care and again maybe it is appropriate to go on social media maybe
it is that is the appropriate thing to do in that moment if you connect but but be conscious of it so maybe connected
with with those moments that usually kind of um it it's as if it doesn't matter does
that make sense what I'm suggesting yeah yes yes connected yeah thank you thank you much thank you thank you and Peggy
um I it was kind of challenging for me I kept going back to um some part of my
past which um something today reminded me of I guess and kept trying to come
back to my breath and um and what does this mean and I finally came to well
these thoughts are here and um what if what if this mattered and I was here
with them which helped me bring more kindness to them which was much more helpful and the small group was really
nice just I heard some um commonalities that it was just so nice for me to feel
less alone with um some thought pattern that I have that's tremendous piggy I thank you
for your practice report I love how your heart and mind found a way to be with
what seemed to be challenging you know this pattern of you know something that has um been up for you they entanglement
you know thinking about something and then instead of beating yourself up okay how can I this matters what is going to
what does it teach me in this moment can I be with this with kindness what does this teach me right here this matters
this moment matters even this this rumination matters it's not like I need to push it away but how can I be with
this in a way that I learned so that's beautiful thanks Peggy thank you
Lely yeah Maran also says what Peggy just
report is pretty much exactly what my practice was like too yay that's sweet yeah that's great TK thank you Peggy
says here Fred hi uh for whatever reasons this
this didn't feel very difficult to do tonight and I'm aware that if I were to do it right now or tomorrow it might be
much harder so whatever the series of uh forces that brought it
to be a you know a kind of agreeable practice you know I'm thankful for them
but I recognized that it wasn't actually a big deal you know I I felt present of the moment it wasn't dramatic wasn't any
Revelation it was just being there and and that was fine that was and being
there is always so much better than not being there or you know struggling to be
there um and I just really appreciated the
lowkey what the low the lowkey pleasure is almost too strong a word but just the
um a little slow vibration of presence that that I got to enjoy beautiful thank
you thank you FR thanks for bringing that in and in and and um adding uh what
you've added to to this beautiful painting that all of you are painting
together with your Reflections in the way that the practice showed up for you that can and it can show up in so many
different ways as we find our way and and I appreciate what you shared in the way that yeah it was a low key um my
word not yours kind of ordinary extraordinary presence and that's beautiful and delicious right this sense
of ordinariness oh yeah this is beautiful delicious and and yes sometimes I can also if you do it again
maybe later at a different time cause a condition it'll feel extraordinary like wow the power of this move like or or
some other thing anyway beautiful thanks for the the range of
experiences and [Music]
lastly uh so for me it would be um to live the moment fully would be um living
from my deepest intentions perhaps to be kind or um
not to harm self for others and others and also to be fully present I
guess for people in the moment beautiful yeah thank you and and
I love the fully present for people and um and also the kindness and um I
appreciate the the the people also includes you Leslie right the kindness
to yourself and present for yourself for others and for yourself loveely thanks
for sharing that the the um the connection of wholehearted intention
with what it means to to be fully present in this moment to to live according to your intentions yes
wholeheartedness it's um thank you thanks lesie another reflection that comes up for me and I was coming up
while I was giving the guided meditation is is um is um this this phrase that I
think I brought in this wholehearted this this fullness of intention fullness of intention to bring
to this moment this sense of fullness of Our intention which is fullness of our
filling this moment F filling this moment up with our presence that is
imbued with our full the fullness of Our intention lots of words but but I think
you see what I'm um referring to and it showed up in so many beautiful different
ways for for so many of you so yay my heart feels full my heart definitely
feels full tonight from this practice from from sitting together from your
Reflections just very very happy so so let's bring let's bring uh oh yes wait
couple of Reflections from YouTube um uh Penny J says along the same lines Claire
it takes too long to get love right and then we die so long so long life is good
pain is good and broken hearts get broken open yeah yeah oh those were my
thoughts just before I heard you speak CLA so you're getting Reflections this I I love how the the zoom World also comes
together with the YouTube World from other folks of commenting and andh holding each other very sweet so thank
you all thank you for your practice thank you for your fullness of intention
showing up for yourself showing up for one another in this moment of Our Lives
um it matters you matter this matters may all beings including ourselves be
well may they live according to intentions may they all wake up including
[Music] ourselves
thanks everyone take good care be well I'm going to ask you all to unmute
yourself for our cofin is goodbye here we go