oh good morning everyone can you hear me all right is it loud enough for everyone
it is of course a strange question because if you don't hear I think
he won't answer it it's so I trust that it's loud enough
I'm happy to be here with you and I just come back from having
a Tata Retreat that's Spirit Rock which was still feels like it's part of me
and um before that had gone on a
kind of a three-day Retreat that we'll talk about in a few minutes
you turbo it's a little bit louder I think I think needs to be louder so let's see is it uh loud enough now is
it coming along there is our hearing system devices that some people use on just on the counter
and there's another room but it seems like is it allowed sorry should we do a little bit louder
though a little bit maybe just a little bit
foreign
Rock they did something which was unusual for me was they had the speaker systems on
really loud and um and it was kind of surprising
but um that's my my hearing is you know getting weaker and I've kind of discovered that
um I didn't realize how hard I was trying to listen whenever I hear he was going I thought
it was just normal or something and uh and now with hearing system devices and these loudspeakers at Spirit Rock I said
oh look at that gill you know this is more relaxed now even though it seems too loud
so anyway we're still it's always a work in progress figuring this out
so a story
there was a claim to Buddhist Monastery where many hundreds people came to be
monastics amongst the nuns and uh they're always you know
a group of new monastics that came every year and first year the monastery is often
challenging just getting used to the lifestyle getting used to the schedule getting up very early in the morning
a lot of a lot of meditation a lot of work a lot of being in community a lot
of Silence it's all the stuff that uh and if you're a new monastic you're kind
of like at the bottom of the totem pole of certain kind of seniority so sometimes some of the more challenging
jobs are given to you and so at some point during the year the
for the abyss invited all the new monastics to go into pilgrimage
and they were like so relieved what fantastic a pilgrimage and we were told we're going on the pilgrimage to the
sacred Buddhist sites wow yeah the Buddha talked about the value of going and visiting where the
Buddha was born where he was enlightened where he first taught and where he died they're
considered to be the four most sacred sites for at least our kind of Buddhism and so they oh that's baby we'll go on a
plane it will go off and it'll be great to go to pilgrimage to the holy sites
so uh they all got ready we're ready and they
and uh there was a big a couple of like fancy
tour buses that can't even pick them up but the monastery Gates and they didn't know where they were going
and they first went to a hospital and the Abbas led him through the halls
and the rooms of the hospital and through the emergency room and all the different places and they saw people at
all kinds of levels and kinds of sicknesses and illnesses and injuries and
and um so that was kind of some of them I never really been the hospital that much
and so um then they finished and they got back on their tour buses
and they went on to the next step of the pilgrimage and they went to um
a hospice and there they saw people
who were all kinds of stages of dying
from there they went to an old age home and they saw all the different stages of
getting old and what that means to the mind to the of
the heart sometimes to the body all kinds of wow there's a lot of ways of
being old and then they got back on their tour buses and the buses took them back to
the monastery and there they went to the hospice in
the monastery where there was an old Monk one of the oldest in the monastery
who was there in the hospice in his last days
and they went to see him and he didn't have much to say or anything to say but there was this wonderful Sparkle in
his eyes the light didn't seem like it depended on seeing
them his Sparkle just like he just had to Sparkle and he was very peaceful very
calm feeling of deep kind of Tranquility just
to be with him and then the abbess took them to
a meeting room in the monastery and she said now you've seen the four holy
sites of Buddhism sickness old age death
and a practitioner who's found deep abiding peace
so rather than being a place to go this holy sites were human conditions
and there's something about the encounter with human conditions in an honest direct way which does something
to Buddhists their holy sites how could that be How could a hospital be a holy site
hospice an old age home how could this be
and I think a little bit the answer is in that fourth fourth holy site
a practitioner who's found their piece a practitioner who's able to die with a
Sparkle with the Delight with joy and peace and all the conditions of Life have been
settled and um and to honestly and fully
encounter this human condition of ours not pretend it's differently not to run
away not kind of touch into some of these existential conditions that will visit all of us if we're lucky enough
that and kind of skirt around them and avoid them Buddha says stop
and take a good look stop and really be present practice with that
let that be a mirror to see yourself to see your reactions your fears your
activities your distractions your preoccupations
because this because this Buddhist practice is here to meet
help us support us through the biggest deepest most challenging experiences any
person could have in their human life this is not a hobby what we do in
Buddhism it's not you know an Excursion on a tour bus to Disneyland
just to kind of having you know Wonderful Disneyland like spiritual
experiences the holy sites of Buddhism
a pilgrimage is a journey to a sacred place that's like if you go
to the dictionary that's one of the first meanings you have for it
the word pilgrim and pilgrimage turns out that it's closely related
etymologically from the same Source Latin source as the word Peregrine the
bird the peregrine falcon isn't that pretty cool
a peregrine falcon I just kind of you know when they're soaring
the high up in the sky traveling long distances there's this kind of Freedom there
in the Buddhism there's this idea that Birds when they fly through the sky leave no traces there's no
there are tracks left behind and that's held up as kind of an ideal that when you go through life like in
your backpacking this is the ideal leave no traces in Buddhism there's this ideal that go
through life and don't leave any traces and they don't mean like don't you know
don't don't go through your life so no one ever remembers you when you die or anything but don't leave anything
sticky don't leave anything undone or unresolved don't leave any
Karma behind don't leave any any disturbances behind don't leave the
world in their worst place than you found it leave it in a better place leave the
only traces that way so um
the um from the Latin root pilgrimage means to
go through the field apparently in Latin it kind of meant the field was abroad like somebody comes
from away or to going abroad or coming from abroad so it doesn't mean that much to
etymology but journeying to a holy place and I've known people who've gone on
pilgrimages long pilgrimages I've met people on pilgrimage
and uh classically people do it for many reasons and sometimes they do it because their
life is falling apart I've known people who
um they've lost something very important about their life and they felt lost they
didn't know what to do and so it wasn't like they were going to a pilgrimage to a place a sacred place
to get to the place they were going because then it's needed to kind of
regroup or ReDiscover who they are question their life and reflect on what
their life is about and and then also to be open to new
experiences some of the great pilgrimage routes in the world there's a lot of pilgrims and
so you never know who you're going to meet on the route and what you're going to counter what are you going to
struggle with what you're dealing with classically a pilgrim travels with very
little is kind of a lives kind of a life that's close to poverty
um you know staying and hostels perhaps there's Pilgrim hospitals and some hostels in some places and
I stayed one and I've stayed in some and one of them I would suspect there were probably 200
people in the room men women and everything else
and um while sleeping under the same roof and you know the same kind of room there
were some dividing walk kind of partial walls so it wasn't like you saw everyone at the same time but you heard everyone
at the same time and it was phenomenal to hear the snoring at night
because I used to live near the ocean and it was wonderful to hear the waves
crashing at night you tend to hear them more at night than during the day and you hear the crashing waves and so it's
kind of comforting well when you have 200 people I don't know how many of them are snorers but
it was remarkable I don't know if this is a common phenomena that they were synchronized
at least in the hostel I was in and they were they'd come in waves like
you'd start they'd start up and they'd all kind of come to a crescendo together
and then they'd go down and get quiet get quiet for next hour or something and
then up again and it became like um like a phenomena
of nature it came like the waves at the beach I wasn't disturbed by it how could you be disturbed by waves at
the beach you mean like wow so it was like a natural phenomenon I said so if you ever have to have a
roommate in some place who snores going to pilgrimage first
and maybe it won't be disturbed by the snoring it's not just
anyway so you have to deal with all this stuff you know and what do you mean what about privacy and
whatever room with all these people and so um
and sometimes people go on meditation Retreats because it's kind of like a pilgrimage for them they don't know
they're going through some big crisis some big issue in their life that they don't know what else to do they're lost
they're suffering in some way and some people come they're not lost but this is what they want to do they want to go and
Retreat and develop their practice deepen their meditation but some people come because it's the only thing they
know what to do in a time of great crisis then this is what comes to mind as I
sitting here many years ago there was a woman who came to a retreat I was teaching it was in the Redwoods here
deep in the Redwoods so it took a while dirt road to get there and
and she came to the retreat and so I asked her why are you here
my husband made me and why did your husband make you come
to the retreat because that's kind of to require someone to come to retrieve this kind of like unusual right it's probably
it's counter-indicated I had an affair
does that put the whole that put a different context on it so I don't know what the husband was thinking but that's
a different spousal response response to an affair than many other many of the responses you
read about novels maybe you wouldn't make a good novel if
you know just the marital crisis ended up in a retreat
but anyway that was kind of you know there goes some place where you kind of working through something and discovering something and confronting
something in your life in an important way and uh and pilgrimage is often done on
foot and I I've known people who also who don't go in a pilgrimage per se but do
these long through hikes they go for weeks and weeks sometimes for a hike and some of them do it because nothing else
makes sense anymore some people do it because they have to find some other thing to Value to do
some people do it to kind of reflect on their life I did it I didn't do a long hike but the
gift that my family gave me when I turned 50 was the gift to go up in this year is to do a solo hike
to spend a week up in the wilderness by myself up there and so I did and I used that occasion
walking up in the Sierras by myself it was early in the early in the spring was like beginning of May there was still
snow on the ground and as far as I could tell I was the first one in the backcountry and so it was pretty much alone I think
I saw one person in the far in the distance across the valley at one point and um and I reflected on now that I was
50. what do I want to do with the rest of my life what's important for me and that was an important reflection in
time I came back kind of not exactly renewed but I came back with real
clarity about what I wanted to do and they and it was a really I think was helpful to know that
to know it and in my case it was just keep doing what I was doing so because I but to have that kind of
time to really look at that so um
so I think about three of us in this room today
went on a pilgrimage two weeks ago the four of us who are here right now
amazing there were 12 of us and a third of them are here in this room
and um and uh there have been Buddhist pilgrimages uh
here in California in the past I don't know if it was a pilgrimage but one of
the phenomenal uh Buddhist events kind of pilgrimage kind of events
was uh done by a I think he was American from Tennessee
or Kentucky I think he used to be like a folk singer in the 60s
but he went off to be ordained in a Chinese Buddhist Monastery here in California
and learned Chinese fluent in Chinese and been a monk phenomenal practitioner
his name is Reverend hingsher and um he came to the family Retreat I taught
at Spirit Rock once and he brought his guitar and he sang a song to the kids called put on your samadi shoes
it was so much fun and I bet the various temples in California wonderful men
well his pilgrimage was I think they had a temple in Los Angeles Maybe
and they had have one in Ukiah and so he walked up Highway one maybe or
you know I don't know if it's just Highway 1 but it walked certainly along Highway One from Southern California all the way up
to yokaya but that that's phenomenal kind of but um uh what's more phenomenal
was that I think he took three steps
he would stop and he would do a full prostration on the ground I think
frustration where you kind of completely flat on the ground every third step
that takes a while that makes an impact
I don't know what he was doing in his mind I wouldn't be surprised as if he was chanting his chance or something
and he had a a late person who went along with a a van
and so there was some equipment with him probably and maybe that's how we had food and so all he had to go with him is
his robes and his shoes and his uh I don't know if he had gloves for his hands but every time he went down
and so he wrote a book about it I never read it but um and um
so that was one that was one of the earliest kind of pilgrimages things I knew and then from Spirit Rock out of Spirit Rock Community there was a as it
has been for many years now a bicycle pilgrimage and one a few years ago they started from IMC
the pilgrimage and they've gone from here to various interesting places often they go to Buddhist monasteries in
Northern California so that's nice and um so two weeks ago
starting today I was part of a group of about 12 people
who went on a pilgrimage from Spirit Rock walking to the green Gulf Sun
Center the distance is not you know you know as long as pilgrimages often are but it was
meant to be a a trial to kind of begin if maybe a pilgrimage route a Buddhist
pilgrimage route here in California for walking and that would go through Buddhist
centers and so there's these two there's Spirit Rock Meditation Center in Marin County
uh kind of if more or less on the north side of Mount Tamalpais
and then there's on the south side of Mount Tamalpais there is green Gulf Shen
Center also in Marin County and the distance that we walked was about 26 miles I believe
and we did it over three days and uh it was a quite a wonderful event
to be able to do this kind of thing and I was actually surprised by how wonderful it was at least for me
and um so some of the details of it was that
we asked Spirit Rock if we could so we could leave early in the morning on
Monday we asked Spirit Rock if we come and sleep in their meditation Hall they have two big meditation Halls so
with the lower one and um and they said sure not only that but you're welcome to have
dinner then I sudden when you arrive on Sunday and you're welcome to have breakfast but just keep the just clean
up after yourself and so we showed up and not only that we
were welcomed so warmly and ready to help set us up and they had to kind of
meditation mats like this and and a few futons set up for us
and um so um
and so we kind of spread out meditation all some people outside the meditation Hall but two different places slept
and uh and that was kind of nice but what was nice about it was the generosity that Spirit Rock would offer
us this opportunity and at pilgrimages where there's generosity that supports it from the
community makes it kind of richer and something more heartfelt or more kind of like meaningful oh not only are we doing
this kind of little bit active renunciation you know this going on a sacred place but there's support for it
and so uh then we set off the next morning oh then that evening we were so
lucky there was a there's a wonderful Spirit Rock teacher named Ann Cushman who came and gave us a little Dharma
talk and what I didn't know is uh she'd been on Buddhist pilgrimages in India and she
actually had gone to India to research it to write a book about it so she knew more about Buddhist pilgrimages than
most people so she kind of launched us and like was a wonderful celebratory way
and one of her uh the Mantra she gave us was
um there's plenty of time how often do you go through your life
with that is there Mantra oh there's plenty of time no
I think that uh this funny time thing all right many people maybe not all of
you but many people
are time poor we live in time poverty
everyone in the world has the same amount of time kind of every day if you live through the day everyone has the
same amount of time but so it's an equal opportunity event time
but sometimes people live it in poverty and some people live in abundance
and I think around here a good percentage of people are pretty poor I wonder if there's a direct correlation
to wealth the more wealthy you are the more you live in time poverty
I suspect there might be something like that but any case that was kind of the mantra
there's plenty of time and we got up in the morning and we and then there was someone uh supporters of
the pilgrimage who showed up with their cars and trucks to take all our sleeping
gear tents and sleeping bags and drive it to where we're going to sleep that next night
and so we wouldn't all we had to carry was like day packs and just lunch and fruit water and so that was nice
and then we showed up at the place where eventually where we're going to Camp that night to enter our surprise at least to my
surprise all our tents were set up not only they drive everything there so
we got there it would be all there they set it up and uh I think we also some of us had
camping chairs and they were set up it was quite touching
so then we walked and um and uh after a short walk not too far we came
to this wonderful Redwood Bay Tree that'll kind of Grove next to a creek
and we stopped there to have some ritual and the rituals seemed very meaningful
they were all the rituals were kind of connected to the four natural elements
in Buddhism of Earth water Fire and Air so just that being in
the natural setting and being connected to these elements kind of made the natural world come alive more and in a
nice way but one of the very meaningful things for me in that opening was there was
someone there who did this wonderful with it with rulers
that were that kind of were represented chronology over time different kind of ways of using that to see something kind
of brought to life the kind of the kind of the
human and geological vegetative history of where we were
and and how you know
how long our lives were at that up to that point got a sense of that and then put that in
the context of how long non-indigenous life a lot in digit of humans had been in
this bipartis part of California 200 about 200 350 years or something
and then um and then how long indigenous people had
been in this part of California and and the the the age that was given was 35
000 years so compare your lifetime to 35 000 years
compare non-indigenous immigrants to this area and 35 000 years it creates quite a different context
for this place and who was here and so the more recent decade asked Millennia
was the Miwok native indigenous people
and then we did it for Bay trees Bay trees had been in that part of this of the country for 20 million years
wow as we were under them right on these Bay trees wow and then we did it for redwood trees and
we looked up at the redwood trees and they'd been there for we were told 200 million
years and then later in the hike we saw a sign that said that um that the river
trees are some of the oldest and largest living creatures in the world
so 200 million years that's a long time
and uh in fact probably Redwood City this land that we're on
maybe they didn't even exist right there because we're probably we're under water
and we're still waiting for the mud to build up to create this and not only that but
probably we were in a different location I wouldn't be surprised if if this land that we're sitting on was
where Mexico City is now because these Continental shifts and changes of
everything at all I mean we've had all these different continents we don't I don't even know the names of all the continents that have been
appeared and disappeared on this planet the shifting changing so anyways we
started this wonderful presentation about time and who was here and all this
stuff and and they kind of made enriched the kind of walking we did and
then as I walked there was a kind of like there's plenty of time kind of Mantra came up for me
and what came up for me that I repeated to myself because it just felt so delicious I felt so nice well I was
surprised how nice I felt walking I do a lot of Walking In The Hills in
the mountains my wife and I one of our favorite things to do and I have no regrets of how I walk but
there was different walking on a pit as a pilgrim and the difference was that um in the
pilgrim as a pilgrim I wasn't really trying to get anywhere even welcome to my wife out in the Hills
we kind of tried to get to the end kind of but here was really clearly there was
nowhere to go so my Mantra was myself was um while going nowhere
going somewhere so the emphasis was not going anywhere but we were walking and we're going to
this green Gulch Sun Center and uh and it kind of it was kind of like being on a retreat where time Falls
away and there's nothing to have to do or accomplish just peaceful settled to
relax just just this moment it's enough just to be alive
how often in your life would you say wow
just to be alive is enough
without it but but I have my to-do list I have my responsibilities I have to do
this to make them safe I have to I have to just to be alive just to breathe
and so in this pilgrimage we took the approach was that we were not going
to a sacred site every step was the arriving at a sacred
site and so we called this the pilgrimage was in the in poly is upasamapada
steps of peace we were just doing steps of peace
this step we've arrived this is it what a great thing
wow this step this step so it kind of felt that way as we went along
and then there were people who supported us there were sometimes we had to drive from
where we ended up the day the first day to where the campground was so their people came and picked us up kind of
phenomenal and then they drove us back the next day because we could pick up where we left off because pilgrims can't skip
you know and uh and then we went through a beautiful countryside
you know it was some of the really spectacular hikes in the Bay Area
that we went through and were in but the most wonderful wonderful most wonderful one but one of them was really special
we were got up and left at 6 30 the last morning
and we we hike down Mount Tam into Muir Woods
early in the morning before most people had gotten there Muir Woods has considered almost a sacred place
and um and in fact some of the Groves in muirwoods are named as religiously
there's like Cathedral Grove for example and and to be able to meet millions of
people go there and so but to go early in the morning I guess it's kind of closed if you drive
in but if you hike in you can get in and it's spectacularly beautiful and quiet
and peaceful and we sat there and meditated in the Grove and in the woods and it was so nice to to be there
and what enriched it also for me was this whole trip was also some of the
challenges there weren't a lot of challenges I would say we were pretty fortunate the whole thing
but there was this cold wind but you know that especially the first
night and then we had rain and then not being able to sleep because
their pain was pounding on the tent for a while in the middle of the night midnight so that that's you know
it's a little bit you know you you wouldn't want that for yourself but if you step back it's kind of
desired that a pilgrimage has its challenges it makes it more real so that
was kind of you know small scale challenges but it was kind of nice that it wasn't just all kind of a nice simple
thing to do and then it was nice also when we came into for me came into Muir Woods they
had these visitors signed these information signs on there and one that one that was most powerful
for me was a sign that talked about the history of this piece of land and how it
became a park and the people who preserved it and
saved it and John Muir and different people to the theater
Roosevelt was a player in this the president so it had what uh all the kind of things
you expect you know about all the historical things that made be it here but now there's a different sensitivity
to what it means what all this means so they had added
notes I kind of like by the way and they talked about all the people who
had saved this natural parts of California for parks and to save it for the prostate prosperity in the way they
did um we're really into eugenics and white supremacy and that whites were
white people really their Superior race including the president Theodore Roosevelt and
and your wood I'm your John Muir had some of these qualities in himself as well
and it just felt so I was so kind of relieved to see this being named
this too is part of it is part of it I wouldn't I want to say it's sacred but this too is part of the profundity of
this life we have to deal with and see honestly and clearly and some of the ways in which we
preserve the natural world in the United States has been a form of environmental and
economic and racial Injustice to do it and denying the existence of people who
were in the land beforehand and as if they had no role that they weren't part of it
and so to just be able to walk through the natural world here the Wilderness that's preserved and saved and and
somehow ooh and ah and feel that it's sacred without recognizing the bigger
context and who would say which is in maybe as a kind of
partial sacredness not the full thing so I was kind of glad that came to the
end kind of come to the end of her pilgrimage that also was included and I thought that was also important to this
too this too and then we came down to Muir Beach
where the bottom of your the valley there that goes up into the green Gulch Zen Center
which is was originally a farm and um and I lived there 40 years ago
more 40 almost 45 years ago now and work the fields and it was kind of
special for me to go back there and see the field see where I'd worked and imagine Gill as a 45 year old 45 you
know 45 years ago is a long-haired hippie you know working the farm
and um and then we came and then we came to gringold and the woman Fu Schrader
who had been the abbess there for the last nine years just a month ago stepped out
she received us and um and she in the zendo in their
meditation Hall and we were able to kind of end the meditate there and
and then she gave us a beautiful Dharma talk so we had a Dharma talk at the beginning at the end from these
wonderful teachers and then green Gulch invited us for lunch what and that this too you know this
generosity and support for the pilgrims
so so we had there was more but um but it felt uh precious
to have a pilgrimage in California every Buddhist country that every
country that Buddhism goes to in Asia eventually there's been pilgrimage sites
created and they're certainly in India and China and the ones I know about and
in Japan there's a really rich background of pilgrimages routes that go on and the pilgrimage routes themselves
are seen as almost sacred people have been walking them for over a thousand years in some places
and 2000 years and um so this is sacralizing is that a
word sacralizing um the geography by the associations it
has and to make part of California at least for Buddhists have a kind of sacredness
to it because people have found profundity in stepping on this land and
being there and attuning to the environment their practice to the environment who they are
to um find peace with every step
s of peace and um and we did it for three days
people can do it for months the long trips long hikes where get where you're
going is not the point it's how you step that's a point
so that's nice but the lesson of this
is maybe you're on a pilgrimage every day when you wake up
maybe every time you go to the market and you walk down the aisles it's a
pilgrimage can they be steps of peace what would it mean
you don't have time for that that's a silly
you have important products to get into your shopping cart [Laughter]
and you have to look and make sure you get the right one and the right price and and also study what other people are
getting and judge them and for what they're doing there's all these important things to do in life and get
finished with so you can go do other important things so sorry about that and you know so this
pilgrimage thing is kind of a headache now it challenges you like it makes you
question you what are you doing with his life of yours what are you doing
and um why not make every day a pilgrimage why not have plenty of time why not just
make every step the step of peace
just that question you might have really good answers to say why you shouldn't be that way
but maybe that's your going and you know like I did Into the Wilderness that questioned my life when I was 50 and
come back with more clarity of what I was doing maybe you'll come back with Clarity and wisdom about why it's really necessary
for you to 95 of the time to be in a rush
to get someplace to do something go to the next thing maybe there's good reasons
or maybe there's sometimes good reasons
but maybe there's not good reasons to do it as often as you do it
maybe there's something very profound that you offer the world
not just for yourself the possibility that just this moment is
enough here in this moment you're going to find your peace you can find your well-being you can
find your contentment and maybe not even for its own sake
but maybe because that's the way you can be attuned
to others that's a way to be attuned to others so that some of the most deepest ways that
we can connect to others with compassion with love with kindness with friendliness has the best chance to come
through and that was one of the nice things about this pilgrimage some of the people
I went on I never met before but it was marvelous to do these 12 people together
and share this thing together and and have this common Bond of humanity and
engagement and warmth and friendship and and this kind of shared shared
pilgrimage there was a kind of a depth that happened in the community I felt that was really special
can that be a lesson for all of us who went on the pilgrimage that actually this is possible even in
the supermarket engine only those other people were paying
attention but you're standing in the line waiting for your turn and you're there to say
hello you're there to kind of appreciate people if only they get their met their you
know face out of the National Enquirer but then just to live there ready ready
it's every moment as sacred pilgrimage
so thank you thank you for being here today and thank you for just sitting and meditating here
and perhaps this was a pilgrimage just being here this morning and and I hope that um
some of the qualities of what I was talking about just exist from coming here for these this time we had together
thank you