so the last few talks I've been talking about this idea of the role of thoughts and
beliefs and views and what an impact they have in our
practice and how the Buddha really emphasized direct experience rather than views but of
course we also have Right View as the right wise view I'll talk a little bit
about that as a first step in the 0.8fold path
but today I want to talk a little bit uh different idea about views
and that sometimes we use spiritual just use that generic word
kind of spiritual views or ideas or beliefs
as a way to sidestep or avoid
what's going on in our lives in terms where maybe holding on to views
as a way to not be with what our experiences and help us so that we don't
have to face some uncomfortable things whether it's emotional issues or things
that are inside us that's maybe you're not even clear what it is we just have this feeling like we don't want to look
at it Whatever It Is so maybe I'd say that the key words here
are the side step and avoid so of course like views of course we
need to have them there an integral part of what it means to be human it's an integral part of
our practice or even if you don't have a practice but it's when we use them as a way to
not look at things that may be helpful and not only that
we use the views to kind of legitimize our avoidance
from how we're using them as a way to like oh yeah I don't need to look at that because of X Y or Z
I'll explore that a little bit tonight so we might say that um
this is a process in which we are using the practice that is supposed to
help us work with a problem as a way to avoid a problem so we
started thinking it's going to help us
sorry about that so it's when we we have this practice
that we initiated to help us work or find some ease with a problem but
the way that we unknowingly kind of are using it is to just help us avoid it
or not look at it or sidestep it in some kind of way or white
wash it or this thing that we want to try to find a better relationship with or have
more ease with instead we end up kind of avoiding so for example we might have this
Buddhist teaching on Equanimity it's really held you know really high esteem in Buddhist practice
being able to have this sense of balance and evenness with whatever is arising
but we might hear this in fact I think it's probably all of us
do this or have done it this teaching about Equanimity this evenness and balance balance and we
might kind of like slide into indifference and recalling it Equanimity oh this is a
wise mature way to be with it but in fact what has happened is we've actually disconnected
from our experience disconnected from what we're feeling or we're disconnected to what's happening
in our environment and that's why we're able to have some balance and evenness
is because we're not engaged with what's happening instead we have this aloofness
maybe even some coldness and we're thinking like oh this is equanimity
but in fact you know Equanimity has a quality of warmth and connection and openness and spaciousness
and that's what gives the room for the balance and evenness is because there's this big space in which we're allowing
things to be whatever they are but we're still connected with what's happening that's maybe one way maybe another way
is if we might have this
thought in our mind we might actually hear ourselves saying that something like well
if that makes you uncomfortable well that's just part of your practice
kind of like saying well it's your problem if what I said makes you feel
uncomfortable or it's uh your problem you just have to work with it if somehow
What's Happening Here in the community in the group or something like this isn't your preference
and to be sure sometimes that is an appropriate response but if we always find ourselves kind of
thinking that that people are getting annoyed with us or irritated with us and we're thinking well you just need to
practice with that clearly you're not as awake and as I am and you have preferences or you know
something like that maybe I'm exaggerating this to make a point but there's a way in which we
might think that um well you just practice everybody just has to practice with whatever arises in
their mind and we don't somehow have to take responsibility for how we're affecting others
maybe to some of the insensitivities we have or some ignorance we have and
biases we have that come out in our language or our behavior and that
we might not intend to but it might be hurtful to others
so instead of saying oh that's just your practice can we recognize oh I I harmed somebody with my
words or my actions even though we didn't mean to instead of kind of trying to whitewash
it away or so there's an expression that was coined
by John Wellwood of Buddhist practitioner I think it was in the 90s
I think it was he was a psychologist and a Buddhist practitioner is a few books
that right now the titles Escape my mind but I think he coined this
expression and it's called spiritual bypassing if you've heard of this
and and I would say it's it's probably everybody does this if
course we do because this is part of how we find our way with practice or new
ideas or new ways of showing up new ways maybe of speaking interacting with others is sometimes we get it right and
sometimes we don't of course it does it's not like we're going to learn some hear something and then just do it perfectly every time
and sometimes we just we're not uh feeling we don't feel well either we
have some emotional turmoil or if we're not sleeping or whatever it might be physical pain
and so maybe we don't have access to our greatest wisdom and wisdom and instead we're slipping into something that we
just feel like okay I need to avoid or bypass because I don't really have the capacity
right now and maybe it's not a conscious thought it just happens
it can be helpful to recognize though that this is something that's not uncommon
psychologists they like to look at this and they say well yeah some people get become really spiritual and do this
spiritual bypass and they'll use the language kind of like a as a defense mechanism as a way to disconnect us from
our feelings as a way to disengage with what's happening or to Shield us
from something that's uncomfortable
maybe it's some truth that we've seen about ourselves some truth that we've
seen about our life it's not unfolding the way we expected
and and rather than acknowledging that then I remember doing this spiritual
bypassing and so spiritual bypassing is this
related to the our relationship to the practice or
um you know how we're like holding on to it or interpreting it so it's not so
much our practice itself I would say I guess maybe one could argue that okay
it is the practice but it's like the manner in which we practice but I don't want it to sound
like okay well you shouldn't do any spiritual things Buddhist things any
spiritual tradition because you're just using it to avoid the difficulties I
don't want to say that I don't want to say that I just want to highlight that this is a
natural part of what happens is that sometimes we use it as a way to just make ourselves feel
better without actually using practices in a way to help us find more freedom
sometimes we might think that just avoiding everything that's unpleasant is freedom
but there's a sense of freedom is like has a sense of possibility
even though it's uncomfortable even though it's not what we want even
though it's uh maybe even exactly what we don't want
but this sense of like oh yeah this this this has potential here I can feel that
this is the way forward and often it is kind of like a feeling like our intuition kind of acknowledges okay yeah
this is the way forward
so I'll say that for me uh I would unknowingly would do a certain
amount of this of this what we might call spiritual bypassing is just because
this mind for whatever reason can get settled
I have stories about why that is maybe I'll just say just my professional training and stuff was just a lot of having to
focus a lot of focus you know just the years and years and years of having to focus
and just kind of bled into my meditation practice so I kind of like use concentration as a
way to like numb myself from you know difficulties some
of the emotional turmoil or confusion especially in my early Retreat practice
I would go on all these Retreats and get concentrated
there was some relief there but and it wasn't all bad of course there were some
useful things too but I didn't notice how I was often not being mindful
but just being concentrated getting concentrated instead so kind of maybe
not as sensitive to what else was happening like my environment or my inner life but instead I was kind of
like concentrated you know I found my way through that
but uh it took me some time because I just to recognize oh yeah
it was a habit that had fallen into that maybe it wasn't I could have there could
have been worse habits of course right but this idea I thought I was being Mindful and I thought I was following
the instructions and turns out I wasn't in the way that maybe would have been
more helpful I also know there's a
somebody was reporting to me they were describing their practice and we were
talking about loving kindness practice and this individual was saying yeah I'd love to do loving kindness and I do it
all the time and I thought oh that's fantastic that's great and we were talking about it a little bit more and I
said well maybe you could describe to me you know what your love and kindness practice is
and essentially boiled down to whenever she was angry or annoyed with somebody
she would just no I said the gender I meant not to but this person would say
may you be happy may you be healthy but you know it was kind of this contrived thing just to
help her not feel the annoyance and frustration and anger and she was doing
it a lot all day long so she was feeling like oh yeah I'm really spiritual and doing love and kindness practice
I don't blame her of course because loving kindness sometimes does
open our hearts and make us feel this connection and warmth towards people
and we practice it with difficult people so of course it makes sense to be doing it in this setting but in this way it
was kind of like a sledgehammer or something like to maybe just make the situation go away
or make what she was feeling trying to go away
so spiritual bypassing also can be related to attachment to views
it's like holding on to views beliefs practices
thoughts we might think that they serve like spiritual thoughts or spiritual views or
spiritual ideas and therefore we should hold on to them but there's a way in which
you like maybe I'll say this that integral to like Buddhist practice is the even the idea that you practice
but with meditation practice with with speech livelihood
with our actions following the precepts ethical Behavior right there's all these
things that we do as opposed to just have beliefs or
thoughts that we're just holding on to and so and seven factors of Awakening
one of the key elements here is investigation to like be engaged with what's happening and to be open to
learning about it being open to learning something new it's really integral to practice these
ideas of investigation and practicing
but there can be some way of between spiritual practice in which kind of the
investigation and the practice is kind of like gone to the side
and instead we have these you know dogmatism or fundamentalism or like no
it's this way and somehow there can be this feeling
like it's like maybe it's comforting to like okay I know the truth
and I'm right and everybody else is wrong and I don't have to bother with all that pesky meditation practice it's
hard I don't like it I get to feel like I'm the right and everybody else is wrong
but of course of course the kind of it I mean I want
to say of course we do this to different extremes about different ideas
a friend of mine was telling me about a small little suit to study group that got created and people were really
dedicated to practice loved studying the suit does and they would get together and read them and talk about them and
you know have and said some of them one person like read Paulie so could like
look at the language and talk about it and talk about how meaningful and fun and to be with like-minded people and to
engage with them and until
it came to a particular suit that really emphasized this one particular
teaching and one person said yeah I I don't know I'm not so sure about that I'm not
really going to emphasize that and one other person said no you have to
you how can you be a Buddhist practitioner you have to believe all of this and you're not a real Buddhist
practitioner if this person happened to be the person who said this isn't important for me right now was a teacher
right who had dedicated their life to being to the Dharma but you could see where you know this
one individual had this one idea and then that group kind of ended up falling apart and there was like a lot
of kind of lament like it was so rich and fun and
engaging and kind of opening up some new ideas but because one person had this idea these are these particular things
that are in the suit does and you Orient your life around them and if you
don't
so instead of this kind of like engaging with or investigating kind of like
sliding into some fundamentalism and I know Gil and I in our majama class
that we teach the suit to study class that we teach we talk about this a lot how the last thing we want is for some
fundamentalism or dogmatism so we often are looking at okay what are the poly words here and they can be understood
this way and they could be understood this other way it's kind of translators choice of how they interpret this or
emphasize it and really want to recognize that there's some ambiguity
there last thing we want is to just cling and say this is the absolute truth
that's not freedom that's not freedom
if you feel like you have it and nobody else does then you have to
prop it up like no no that's true because x y z and then you have to like
not be as open to other people
so there's a sway in which holding on to views as a way of maybe spiritual bypassing
and views maybe I'll say that or underlying beliefs or Concepts or
thoughts Notions that we have and often they're hidden
like we don't even really know that we have these views until
we bump up against something that's really against our views or makes us feel uncomfortable
and then it becomes highlighted oh yeah
that we may not be come clear about our views until they are threatened Maybe
by a crisis we may think that we
understand in permanence until the left one gets a terrible
diagnosis and then we realize oh yeah I did kind
of have this Hidden View that lots of things are impermanent but
somehow there's a sway that we kind of thought there were some exceptions when we say it out loud it
doesn't make any sense but we didn't realize that we kind of thought maybe relationships go sour
okay I thought oh no I thought that this was something that stable it was going to be a lasting
source of happiness or maybe we may not even know about some
of these deeper views that we have until they're reflected back to us by teachers or friends or maybe even sometimes the
most difficult people in our life they're difficult because they're highlighting for us something that we
don't like about ourselves some idea that
maybe we have this view that um we must be productive
like that's what it means to be a good quote unquote person is to be productive
and then we spend all of our time you know trying to just do things
and then maybe something happens we're not able to be productive we get sick
or maybe we lose our employment or maybe we have to stop doing what we
usually do to take care of somebody or maybe we retire
and then we start to realize oh wow now that I'm not productive in the
way that I was I didn't realize how I had this view that my value somehow was
associated with this and not recognizing that we have value
of course we do it's not dependent on how much we're
doing I know this is a little bit of heresy
especially here kind of like in Silicon Valley where we really pride ourselves and working working working and I
certainly went through phases in my life I did that too and you know I still have some vestiges
of that now but what are some of these like
underlying views that we have
maybe I'll also say that something about views is that they're
resistant to change often even if we have some information
that says that they're oh maybe this doesn't make sense they often have this kind of
embeddedness or this inertia to them so that we can't
just change them and of course we know this right in the
past couple of years this has really been highlighted that there might be this Persistence of a view or a belief
because we're getting all our information from just a very highly select sources that just
can reaffirm our views we don't have we're not exposed to any
alternative or ideas or even this idea of confirmation bias
right where we might see some clear information that is
not the same as our views we might have this maybe this underlying view that
the world is not safe and then we have to like feel like we're
always being vigilant might be perfectly legitimate reason why
a person doesn't think that the world is safe I don't want to diminish that
but sometimes they are overlooking the times when they are feeling safe
when they're maybe at home with their loved ones under a blanket watching TV
or when they're petting their dog or you know something like this
so even though there might be some data that's coming in that there is times that are that were safe
I don't want to diminish that we have these views it's just human nature that
we hold on to them and that we're impacted by earlier experiences in our
life so we don't want to have this idea of like oh I shouldn't hold on to views
okay now that I know that I'm going to just drop all of them I have to honor and respect our
experience and just to recognize oh
okay this is a view I have it feels integral to how I navigate the world it feels integral to
how I conceive of myself and it makes sense
right now it's how I navigate right now it's how
I'm making sense of what it means to be the person that I experienced myself to be right now
and have this little openness to that instead of this feeling like nope this is how it is
but there's also a way in which sometimes we might be holding on to views
just because we don't like the ambiguity we feel a little bit uncomfortable we
want there is something reassuring it's just about finding something to land on
and stand on like nope this is it this
trying to think of like one that I wanted to say the Earth is flat
really right there was a long time when people still believe that even though you know all the scientists are and I
guess the the people going on the ships were coming back around you know years later saying actually it's not flat
but there's a way in which I don't want we just want to have something decided
so we might hold on to it and we don't want to address it again like nope I just decided this once and I'm not going
to come back around or maybe there's just this idea of
stubbornness to I don't want to change views because
they don't want to acknowledge that maybe they're influenced by others or
maybe that's somebody else had a better idea or that's maybe it's what implies that
maybe their idea wasn't the best idea something like this
so clinging to views is a part of I'll say
maybe maybe a part of spiritual bypassing
but I would say so it's not like we have to abandon all our views we don't go to the opposite extreme we might think of
views and our relationship to them happening along a spectrum
so in one way is which we're holding on to ideas that
I believe this and everybody else who believes anything different is wrong and
I'm not going to change my mind and then there's something in the middle
about like views are helpful and supportive and I'm holding them a little bit lightly
a good example of this is uh Right View wise view as I mentioned earlier
or that Buddha he recognized the importance of use because it influences our actions and influence our
aspirations it influences just other the way our thoughts are
priorities has such an integral way in which we navigate the world
and so he offered Right View at the beginning of the Eightfold Path
one way we might understand or work with Right View is just using it as
a framework to say okay there's suffering
and there's a way to the ending of suffering we could simplify right view
in this way as a as a framework in which to view our
experience does this lead to suffering or away from suffering and that could be
really helpful to be sensitive to that
but we can also hold on to the Buddhist teachings
as a way that to recognize that cling interviews is still clinging
and clinging does not lead to Greater Freedom it's just
thinking that leads to suffering so that doesn't mean that we should like
get rid of like right view or something like this but instead
we can maybe building on the simile of the raft is that the teachings
are a raft that brings us from this Shore in which there's suffering and difficulties and
over this expanse of water to the other Shore where there's the ending of suffering
so we use the teachings right to help as a raft that brings us to the other side
and for those of you who are familiar with this assembly of the raft you'll know that
Buddha gives the teaching when you get to the other side you don't think like wow that was so
helpful I don't think I could have got across without that raft now I'm going to carry this raft wherever I go on my head and shoulders
has this little detail in the suit does on my head and shoulders just in case I might need it
no that's like clinging to views it's like we hold it when it's helpful and let it
go when it's not helpful so this opposite is kind of clinging
and then so that's maybe I'm talking about this spectrum so we have this really clinging
like using views and as a way to bring more freedom and ease Peace Love
goodness into our lives and then we might say there's this other
side which maybe in some ways we would even say is not on the Spectrum but just
on the opposite to end and this is this um
freedom from the attachment of views and awakened completely awakened people who
has overcome all attachments it's part of what Liberation is
is just recognizing that things are arising and passing they arise due to conditions
and some way there's no reification of anything
say like I like this I don't like that it doesn't happen because there isn't
the self in the center that is
different or distinct from whatever's arising different than what's all the
conditions it's just part of the conditions that are arising and there's
no need to hold on and grasp to a view have a view when it's helpful and put it
down when it's not helpful and then part of so that's maybe I'll
say the end of this end of the spectrum and so the Buddhist position is not that all
of you should be discarded it's just that we're flexible in how we
use them and the movement towards freedom is all
clinging or holding on to them less and less and less until there's just maybe more like a
flowing of experience or conditions coming and going
so this idea of spiritual bypassing is a way in which we might use spiritual
teachings or practices as a way to help us avoid what's uncomfortable
so what was supposed to maybe we started the Buddhist practice for meditation practice because we wanted to find more
ease in our life and then we discover that it doesn't necessarily help us but in the way that
can is onward leading but just helps us avoid
and then one of the ways this spiritual bypassing is happening is by clinging to
views it's like I know the truth or or not being willing to have this
beginner's mind or this an open mind to some other ideas
so maybe I'll end there and open it up to see if there's some questions or
comments about a big spiritual bypassing or clinging to
views
yeah thank you oh what I was thinking about as you
spoke which is kind of it kind of overlaps with what you were
talking about is um the comfort of delusion
which is kind of what I've been reflecting on lately like there's some delusion that's really uncomfortable we want to get out of it quickly
but there's also a lot of comfort in delusion and then the motivation to resolve it is
is tricky and so as you were speaking I was thinking like
overlaps with what you're talking about you know because when I know what my opinion is then I
know who I am and there's comfort in knowing who I am
and um it's more uncomfortable
to abide in that uncertainty of not having a set identity sometimes you know
not being so fixated not so clearly formed right
sometimes it's more uncomfortable that uh
uh a knowing and less definite
um place
so I would like to ask you said when we have this like I know and
but I have that that's the truth and I'm it's the self-righteousness that uh comes up sometimes right we all do this
we all love this word but is it maybe in that moment it feels good right because there's this up surge
of energy and but there's this sense of disconnection too right so yeah sure
ultimately it's it's uncomfortable and even the yeah absolutely and it's divisive and it's um there's so there's
a lack of connection because I'm opposing um absolutely
um but also the the comfort of
delusion is even just like
falling asleep in the chair watching the
TV show on a Saturday afternoon kind of just falling into
um you know it's very comfortable yeah yeah
um and sometimes we need this though I want to say sometimes humans need to kind of like disengage and recharge is
that yeah absolutely I mean well we need it until we don't need it but
we convince ourselves we need it this is part of practice is to figure
out right yeah I mean again
why would we you know
the comfort of delusion is all these different nuanced levels sometimes it's it's clinging to a strong view sometimes
it's having no opinion sometimes it's [Music] um
just spacing out sometimes it's you know but there's this stickiness which is
um the on I mean you know the language gets
nuanced because we it's it's we can say it's the unwillingness to see
clear but it's not the unwillingness you know it's just there's delusion right
um so um anyway it's been my reflection lately that
um yeah the comfort of delusion and how to overcome that sometimes it's clearer
than others and and then you know there's just delusion yeah I guess I wouldn't use the word delusion
though there's a delusion right it has a little bit pejorative flavor to it
um at least in my ears it does but sometimes swears we like are unknowingly
disengaging because we don't feel like we have the energy or the capacity or
the wherewithal to meet with what's happening and I feel so much about practice it's about just increasing our
capacity to be with whatever is arising so we don't have maybe the capacity
right now but maybe we have more capacity than we used to and maybe we'll be able to hold those uncomfortable
experiences or thoughts or something like that yes absolutely the word
delusion is just the word that's used so it's not I'm not using it in a critical sense in
the moment but it's ignorance or whatever it's the word that's used to
in the classical sense right so just where we aren't enlightened we aren't clear we
are with it right until we become awakened we all have that right but uh
and we're not quite motivated to overcome it
well you probably wouldn't be here if there wasn't a part of you that was smart
um yeah thank you anybody else have a comment or
a question
okay okay so thank you thank you for your practice and for being here and wishing you a
good rest of the evening