so hello everyone and welcome
and I feel at the moment quite fortunate that we get to sit here in meditation I
get to somehow talk about meditation a little bit and this guidance I'll
offer it's as I give this uh morning guidances I'm also guiding
myself uh kind of to in doing the guidance these
guided meditations is kind of opportunity for me to drop in within to
my connection to meditation my inner life an in inner life that has become
much richer uh uh through meditation
practice so the topic I want to introduce today is um well with first
the introduction and then the topic um it's uh sometimes known that
ethics in Buddhism is not meant to be a set of rules that we are obligated to
adhere to they are uh trainings they are trainings that we engage in they are
trainings we engage in for our own benefit and they are gifts that we give to the World gift of safety and
trainings in for ourselves to tap into and support and discover something
really valuable within so that our ethical behavior is not a commandment but is
something that is inspired by the our inner state of heart our inner State of
Mind our quality of our inner being and uh and so there's a word in
poly that means U both beautiful some one dictionary also provides the
word Charming or auspicious but it also has a meaning of
uh virtue or uh having uh uh yes having
an uh has an ethical quality and someone who has this kalana this beauty is also
someone who has ethical um an ethical virtue or ethical
position on the inside and to connect Beauty and ethics is I think quite uh
profound um that uh it's our inner beauty that we discover that we cultivate that we
evoke that is the source of living an ethical
life so inner beauty what is
it so to begin with the assuming a
posture and meditation posture is a posture that
allows or begins a process of connecting
to our inner life to assume a posture that allows
there to be some degree small degree maybe of confidence
manifested through the
body that provides a posture that provides some
stability where our weight [Music]
our is against the uh firmly against but whatever body firmly against
some something that supports it the floor chair
bed and a posture that maybe begins to provide us with some inner
stability a place that's stable maybe that's deeper or lower in our
torso than where there might be anxiety
or
agitation and lowering the
Gaze
gently closing the
eyes and then in a way that is in harmony
with something gentle or beautiful
Within take some little deeper
breaths smooth
slow not so deep that it's a
challenge but deep enough to feel your torso more
fully and a little longer exhale so the longer period of
exhaling gives it bigger chance longer chance to let go settle
in let the weight of your body settle into whatever supports
it
for
letting your breathing return to normal and with a normal
breath moving through your body and on the exhale seeing if there's places of
softening relaxing the muscles around the eyes
the face the shoulders or the
belly
for
and then as you exhale maybe you can
also relax your thinking
mind soften
it let there be a quieting of your thinking
and as a thinking mind
relaxes allow yourself to settle into your body
breathing
for
and then see if you can find a place within that you
associate with an inner goodness an
inner sense of ethical Integrity or
beauty maybe underneath any place of agitation
or
recrimination deep inside where do you associate where do
you feel or sense the source of goodness might
be and if there is such a
place breathe with
that as if your breathing moves through it like a gentle
wind or your breathing begins and
ends in that place
for
e
and then coming to the end of this sitting to take a few moments to
see where inside do you associate with inner goodness maybe a place of
Love kindness a place
of where there's a desire Not to cause harm in this
world maybe a place of care for this
world
and if there is such a place maybe without feeling those things now but associated with
those to let their inner eye gaze upon the world the whole
world leaving no one out considering all all of
humanity our family may all
people have opportunities for great
happiness may all people have safety and how they live their lives and
go about their every day May all
people know peace wake up to a peaceful world
without conflict and
War may all people be free free of Oppression and poverty
and and free of inner turmoil
and attachments and
challenges may all beings be
happy and may we consider the small and the big ways that we can contribute to
that
thank
you
e
so so we come to the third talk on that 10 protectors the 10 supports or the 10
helpers depending on how we translate the word Nati the poly word and this is
a teaching coming from the Buddha that appears in the numerical discourses it's on the in the
10th chapter it's the discourse number 17 and um what's provided is a list
without much discussion or any discussion about them
and um but it's a wonderful list and in other places these are discussed these
these qualities are discussed in different ways and uh and today the protect
is uh having good spiritual friends the so the first was our own
virtue the second yesterday was what was it yesterday um yeah sometimes my mind
doesn't work so fast sitting here and already kind of my mind going with the
next thing um but anyway today it's um loving kind it's uh kalana Mita
and uh the word kalayana can mean um beautiful that's usually the first
dictionary definition and but it also uh refers to
the kind of inner beauty from which uh virtue arises ethical Integrity arises
from which the disposition to be honest and truthful appears and so someone
who's a good spiritual friend Kalita is someone who is honest someone
who has a kind of a virtuous behavior and
life it's also meant to be it also refers to someone who is a spiritual
teacher uh the Buddha was considered to be the great Kalita someone who opens the door for a
spiritual life a life of on the path to Liberation someone who knows it and
supports to others in uh doing this and um and so the idea here is this they're
a kalana um they're also uh uh they possess a certain kind of inner beauty
and ethical beauty that uh is part of what they're pointing to as a possibility for for you for everyone
else and to have a few kalas to have a few of these good spiritual friends
these uh beautiful spiritual friend friendships is a great support for
ourselves it is and it's also a protection um the uh to have good
spiritual friends who you're a little bit accountable to uh means that when
you're about to do something that you don't quite feel good about you remember your good spiritual friends and would
you want to tell them about what you're doing um would you like would you like them to know about it and if the answer
is no then you probably be careful not to do it uh not that these good
spiritual friends are policing you and saying you know watching you and judging
you if you do something that is not quite coming from this beautiful ethical place within um but uh the teachings of
the Buddha there's he assumes that people have a natural desire uh to not do something that would
be disapproved of dis dis that there these good spiritual friends would
disapprove of uh that there would be a certain degree of of
um of kind of awkwardness or regret or
or um kind of self uh
self not feeling good about oneself uh if we're doing something that our good spiritual friends would disapprove
of um so some of this then is um finding
having good spiritual friends and having those that not only can be someone that we trust and someone we
think is wise but also someone maybe who could encourage um the practice and
bringing out the best qualities we have in the Buddhist teachings a good spiritual friend is someone who supports
us to develop the seven factors of Awakening these are some of the most beautiful qualities of heart that come
out of um you know deep Dharma practice uh the cultivation or the development of
of present moment awareness mindfulness uh investigation uh kind of a delightful
and wholesome effort and engagement in the practice uh Joy
Tranquility um somi and
equinity um the Buddha said that the that the um it's a beautiful teaching I
think of just as the sun just as the dawn is the
precursor uh to the Rising Sun so uh
externally the precursor or the what's uh the heralding forth are own
Awakening is uh a good spiritual friend so externally it's good spiritual
friends and internally is our capacity to to to have a deep profound form of
con contemplation attention to our inner life and this profound contemplation
this profound kind of uh speaks to that we can have this inner beauty and this
is one of the uh word plays around the word kalamita that usually it probably means
you know good spiritual friends we have externally but uh it also can mean uh
friendship with our own Beauty our own ethical integrity
and so that um uh our own inner beauty can be a protection for for us our own
inner beauty our own sense of ethical sens sensibility if we stay close to
that and that supports us that protects us from doing things that we later regret it protects us from uh being mean
to people for example or hostile it pre prevents us from uh actions that harm
other people that we you know that we some how would later regret there is a
kind of guidance that we can receive internally if we're settled on ourselves and settled and relaxed and connected to
this this soft or this quiet place inside that um offers uh a clear kind of
guidance and Living Well living out of out of a sense of goodness and compassion and
care so uh whether we find a good spiritual friend externally that we stay
in touch with enough uh that um um for me when I was uh a new student in
Buddhism um I was fortunate to have good spiritual teachers who I didn't talk to
regularly but um I saw them regularly and they reminded me and just the fact
that they were around or that I went to their talks and different things I felt
oh this is um support for me this is reminds me uh to uh to practice and really live
from the best places from inside and um so to have good spiritual
friends externally and then to offer in yourself uh discover a friendship with
what is beautiful within and to protect that to support that because it will it
will protect you it will guide you it will uh keep you close to what's really valuable and
important and probably that makes life a lot simpler living unethically lying for
example and and stealing and kind of doing things which are ethically
questionable uh tends to create a more complicated life um the little uh saying
is that um uh it's better to be honest because then there's less you have to
remember if we start lying then you have important to remember Iz to keep them going and um but when you're being
honest you know you don't necessarily have to be remember what you said because there you know there's no you
know there's no need to keep the the LIE going so a simpler
life so um an inner Simplicity of being an inner Joy of being and inner beauty
of being this Kalita externally and internally
uh is one of the great supports and when we don't have it internally then uh it
can be really useful to have it externally and uh to have s members
other practitioners other people who you feel are virtuous and have this inner beauty and um to spend time with them to
be around them to be reminded by them uh that it is possible
uh to be that way ourselves to be around them enough to be inspired by them so
that yes I this is this is who I feel like I'm when I'm most myself this is
where I want to come from so um May you consider both the
topic of your inner beauty and also who are the people in your life that uh live
uh in such a way that you're inspired inspires your beauty inside who is uh
truthful who is ethically um virtuous who is has some quality of
goodness that uh inspires you it doesn't have to be a Buddhist but uh
um stay close to them let that let your familiarity your contact with them uh
protect what is maybe most valuable in yourself so thank you very much and
um continue tomorrow oh yes so this the second quality we talked about yesterday
was learning much learning learning about the Dharma learning about goodness
um through study so um virtue
learning applying what we learn and then today as good spiritual friends thank
you