so I wanted to start with this uh story a little bit about uh comes from the
Buddha's life that the tradition holds that shortly after his Awakening
the Buddha said wow I want to you know share this well his initial spot is like
I don't think I want to talk about this nobody's going to get this but then he was convinced like okay if I'm going to
teach somebody I want to teach some of my former teachers but his former
teachers were no longer alive so he said well I'm going to go teach some of people that I practiced with earlier so
he finds them and teaches them what uh what he
had awakened to and one out of the five becomes awakened his name is
kondan and after hearing these uh from the Buddha K has an
experience and then he says wow what wow I'm adding the wow
part it's a little uh lip there but uh K says whatever is subject to arising is
subject to Sensation that is like whatever comes to be will at some point
no longer to be whatever has the nature to be born has the nature to die of
course of course often we don't think about it this way but this was Kon after
he was awaken something that uh he said this was like his big Insight that
allowed him to become awakened so that's the first person that
becomes awakened that the Buddha teaches we don't hear very much the details of the other four because these uh were
these five uh people practiced together and they practiced with the Buddha and then the Buddha went his own way and these
five stay together so we hear about the first one he says whatever has the nature to arise has the nature to pass
away we don't know what happens to there before they become awakened but we don't know any details number six somebody who
is the opposite of these um Aesthetics
these people that the Buddha was uh practicing with a very wealthy
person this person has lots of pal is and has their life you know this opulent
lifestyle and uh for one night or maybe it's like early
morning he just feels like you know this isn't all it's cracked up to
be and he decides to go out for a walk his name is yasa and yasa happens
to see the Buddha the Buddha sees yasa and the and uh
and Y alsoa goes up to the Buddha and kind of the Buddha invites him to like sit down and Y saying you
know this Diana's interpretation it's not all like it's cracked up to be to
have all this wealth and this opulent lifestyle so the Buddha says well I'll
show you some real peace gives him some teachings y also has a breakthrough and
says whatever is subject to arising is subject to
sensation whatever has the nature to be born is the nature to die things arise
and pass away they begin and they cease so that's number
six number seven is y's father who comes out to find what happened to yasa he
wakes up in the morning yasa isn't there and his father comes out to see him the Buddha gives his father a
teaching and we don't know the details exactly oh yeah yes we do know a little bit of the details about that one but he
doesn't say what is rising what is whatever has the nature to rise has the nature to pass away it's number seven is
y's father number eight and number nine are two women you know often we don't
hear about this in the story of the Buddha but the eighth and nth person to become awakened eighth and nth student
of the Buddha are two women who also become awakened and they also say
whatever has the nature to arve has the nature to pass away so there's something about seeing
that things have their the nature to arise and pass away that is associated with some really deep insight into some
really deep uh shift or change in the way that somebody thinks or considers
the world or moves in the world and that's a little bit what I'd like to talk about tonight is this Rec
recognition that things come and go I can't help but do this with my hand
because it's kind of like this like they show up and then they are not showing up
anymore they arise and they pass away maybe I'll say that uh some of you
might know be familiar with the satian this is the kind of like the text the
premiere text that talks about mindfulness practice talks about these uh the these foundations for mindfulness
and it has a number of different practices in there to help establish uh
mindfulness 13 different practices one of them is often what we teach is you
should be aware of the sensations of breathing but in this uh foundational
text after each uh instruction about mindfulness is then the instruction
to abide cont cont lating the nature of arising the nature of passing away and
that the N that the phenomena have the nature to both arise and pass away so one of our key texts and
practices is pointing to this Insight seeing things arise and pass
away so what does this mean well maybe one thing that I'll say
is that um these instructions or this pointing
doesn't require that we actually see the moment the precise moment something
arises or the precise moment that something passes away ends we don't have
to see every single beginning and we don't have to like see and be present for every single
ending but it's just this deep recognition like oh yeah everything's
beginning and ending wherever I look there's a sense of beginning or or
ending and we might say well mountains of course are a they're not
ending but right every time a animal walks on the mountain and dislodges just
a tiny bit of soil the soil is only going in One Direction right it's always only going
down the wind does something with the soil it's only going One Direction
too it'll be a really long time but mountains also are changing right that's
why we have a Grand Canyon and you know all these types of things so even lot of
the things that we think are stable are actually changing also so I talked about this uh seeing
this arising and passing away is associated with uh Awakening but I want to share some
other benefits of noticing the changing nature of
everything really things I keep on using this expression arise and pass away how
there's coming and going there's this way this recognition
that things will not always be the same can bring actually some depth and
meaning to our lives but we tend to take for granted things that we like oh yeah okay it's going to be there
tomorrow but there's this way of like just recognizing like yeah I don't actually know that things are going to
be the same way tomorrow this is a valid assumption for many things
but you know we don't exactly know what the future is going to hold we live in earthquake
country maybe there'll be an earthquake we don't know all kinds of things can happen we
don't know it's just awful right maybe you guys have this feeling too like to see
accidents on the freeway like oh right these people whoever was in the accident
they weren't planning that this came out as surprise and know KN on wood right it's uh not us
going home tonight but there's no guarantees so there's this way this
recognizing that things can change They do change maybe it helps us appreciate
the moments that we have and there's a book written by Steven
Levine I don't know how to pronounce his last name I can't remember if it's LaVine or LaVine but
nevertheless um a year to live how to live this year as if it were
your last and there's been courses on this book that are taught at spit Rock and elsewhere I haven't read the book I
haven't taken the course but I know people have had and they've uh have shared with me how just this idea like
okay what would you do if you knew you only had one year to live well your priorities might shift
fact chances are your priorities will shift and they something that I really appreciate is they talk about like
having more courage like okay I'm going to do those things that I want to do even though I'm
afraid to do them often we don't do things because we think oh I'll do it
later when it's easier when I have more courage but if you realize no I just may
not even have these opportunities this recognition that things change maybe maybe that supports
having a sense of Courage even though there are fear and uncomfortable things
and and also people have reported this with they realize they have one year to live that they take the time to repair
some relationships that might need some repairing making amends or doing
whatever needs to be done in that kind of Realm like taking care of those things
so that uh you can leave without the people I don't know
having unfinished business it's terrible right if you have unfinished unfinished business with
somebody and they die then you don't really have a chance to
finish it in maybe the conventional way you still have opportunity with your mind to get to a different place with it
but it's not the same exactly so this one benefit of
impermanence is this recognizing we don't have forever and maybe we'll start to get our
what is that expression that the doctors say you better get your Affairs in order
right maybe we'll get our Affairs in order not wait until we have some terrible
diagnosis but another advantage or a benefit of impermanence maybe is so
obvious that it goes uh without saying is that if things couldn't change then
there would be no growth there would be no maturation
there'd be no learning there'd be no like this sense of movement towards
greater and greater freedom I mean that's implicit in this whole idea that we can mature and change
so impermanence means that we'll be it's possible to let go of those things that
are not so helpful for us and to develop different ways of
being in the world different habits different patterns more loving kindness more
care more presence more mindfulness careful with our speech our actions all
these things so that's a second benefit of mindfulness a third one is also
something that often we don't think about too much but if things weren't
changing it would be just awful it'd be like sto to find
boring I'm reminded of maybe you guys uh remember this movie uh Groundhog Day I
just love this movie I've watched it many many times and this character right who has
this experience happens to be Crown hog day but he has the exact same day over and over and over again and uh early in
the um movie after it's he realizes it's always going to be the same are all the
different ways he tries to kill himself dropping a toaster in the um bathtub or
driving off a cliff with the groundhog at the steering wheel you know all these things just this
recognition like oh there's like no sense of going forward if it's always going to be the
same so there's these ways in which you know impermanence or changing nature
really add some can add some depth and meaning to our
life but I also want to kind of like Circle back around to how I started this with these stories of these individuals
who are getting awakened and there's this some wisdom that comes with this
letting go and maybe I'll start with this that um or I'm sorry this wisdom that comes
with seeing impermanence because if we sit with our experience like if we're really present
for our experience we'll see that it's changing it's always changing there's either
flickering or it's um getting louder then softer or it's moving location or
you know intensity it's always changing a little
bit but what isn't changing are Notions we have in the head
abstract ideas Concepts those those like you know we
just uh have some steadiness but our actual experience what's actually
happening is always changing and to make this distinction
between an experience and a concept that is a label
that we assign to the experience are two different things the map is not the
territory the menu reading the menu is not the same as eating the food completely different but they're both
pointing to cheeseburger with fries for
example so part of impermanence is or noticing or practicing with impermanence
is to notice this is to notice that it's not um that the con the
concepts are staying the same and when we are relating to the concepts it feels like everything's the same oh yeah here
I am I'm bored again doing this meditation and I'm just
bored and if you just think okay I'm bored it's like every other time or I'm
Restless just like I have been every other time or I'm having a hard time staying awake just like every other time
if you have a relationship with those words and it feels like every other
time but if you sink into the
experience oh yeah there's a sense of like I just want to get up and run away
or I want to get up and write that note on my phone or I need to send that email I forgot or add that thing to my
shopping list or whatever it is or maybe sometimes a sense of boredom comes with
oh my gosh this reminds me of high school English it was so boring and I
don't know we all have different associations so the experience is always
different even though we might be using the same word
and there's this way that um recognizing that the not
the how we use the concepts to describe
experiences but also if we really are with the experiences we can also notice they have
the quality of changing
being impermanent beginning ending changing in intensity or something but
if we are with our experience there's a way in which we can also start to like get underneath maybe the experience
instead of it being something the sadness this experience of the
excitement in the chest maybe of excitement or maybe some concern the
shoulders going up and feeling some tightness we can get underneath and notice the
qualities of these experiences so there's three maybe
elements there's the concept about the experience there's the experience itself which is mostly bodily experiences and
then there's the qualities of experiences and these qualities are that they're
changing and so as we start to see this deepening
this starting to see the qualities rather than just the experiences
themselves is a type of deepening maybe like Concepts experience
qualities and it's this recognition of the qualities that can have a real
transformative power but how can we do this how can we make this transition
from Concepts to experiences to the qualities and part of that is to have a
sense of stability with our practice this sense of gathered this sense of
collectedness and how that might work is we start where we are of course we do it's not possible to
start anywhere else but just to acknowledge you know what I feel really
agitated and I feel like anything except stable and collected and gathered that
might just be what the experience is or maybe it's just a subtle amount of
agitation but there are many ways in which we can be like fragmented or jumping around or have a little bit of
restlessness and there's layers and layers and layers of this as we'll discover as the mind gets more and more
quiet we'll discover there's more and more subtle layers of this agitation
but we shouldn't underestimate like how power powerful it is just to name it
this is a concept but it's a way in which we are no longer turning away like
agitation is here and it feels like
this so is there a way that we can not be agitated about the
agitation not to be restless with the restlessness not have aversion to the
aversion but in some way just to turn towards it acknowledge this is the
experience right now it's Restless I feel Restless there's restlessness right
now I'm using these words restless and agitation just to cover a whole range of everything that isn't just this sense of
collectedness or gathered and this part of like learning
how to recognize what's happening in a way that allows what's
happening to be happening very powerful not easy something that
definitely a practice but is there a way to just be with okay it's like this
right now and maybe the mind can only like it's like this and then off it goes you know into something else and then it
comes around like oh yeah okay I'm agitated oh then off it goes and then it comes back around but is there a way to
not be agitated about agitated but instead maybe you could ask
yourself how can I be with this agitation in a way that's not in
conflict with it without pushing it away without
demanding that it be different without wishing that it were different
but instead to kind of like honor and respect our experience and there's something about the allowing
not being in conflict with respecting and honoring our
experience that allows some disentanglement from what's
Happening so there might still be restlessness there might still be
agitation might still be sloth and torp or longing or aversion doubt whatever it
might be and it might still be there but the problem of it drains
out there's still the same experience but it's not something that we're trying
to make different instead it's like oh yeah this is what restlessness feels
like it's uncomfortable it's not my
preference and it's like this wow is
powerful right because then we can bring that into so many areas of Our Lives we
can show up for our life and show up for other people in so many different ways so to ask this question well how
can I be aware of this agitation in a way that's not in conflict with it in
the sense that we don't have to get rid of anything we don't have to make it different but instead just to show up
for what's happening because if we are going down this path
of mindfulness and this collectedness we will all
discover sooner or later as we're searching for security
and safety in a place where we can finally get everything perfect so we can rest and relax of course we are we're
looking for this this place where we can just abide happy
this is to be found in this in an attitude an attitude of trust an
attitude of allowing there isn't some perfect place
where we're going to land and it's going to be perfect
forever it's instead of this recognition of the feeling of not feeling safety or
uh security or settledness is so much related to our trying to shove things to
be different manipulate engineer manufacturer push them to be a little bit
different maybe I'll say that again that so much of
our feeling r or feeling like we want a sense of security or a place to
land is because is things we often are not Landing we're trying to make them be
different we're trying to somehow not be with what's happening
so the real security and happiness is comes with this sense of allowing with
allowing things to be as they are even if it's not what we want and to be sure I am not talking
about just passivity for the rest of our life I'm not talking about becoming dormant I'm talking about when we when
it just the trying to make things be different gets put down then something
else can arise and some of this something else is this great
wisdom that leads to Awakening and as part of Awakening is that when we see
that things oh yeah things are arising and passing and I can't make them be
exactly how I want there's this deep letting go that
just naturally happens we don't make this Letting Go
happen there's just this recognition that it's meaningless to hold on cling
to changing phenomena and trying to change things is
one form of clinging even though it doesn't feel like it it's the way that we're getting
tangled up with it but it's meaningless to try to control and quarrel with a
changing phenomena and there's something deep within us that realize oh yeah things
are changing I don't have to hold on I don't have to try to control
it and then there's just this letting go and this letting go is
transformative and it's part of the characteris of the first stages of Awakening is
about this letting go and it can all start just with this Insight that things
change and there's can be this way that maybe as the mindfulness or the
concentration or practice uh deepens or matures or whatever word we want to use
there may be a time in which we just noticing the beginnings of things the most
common cuz things that are new like catch our attention but then maybe with practice
we'll start to see oh yeah things are ending too maybe we don't see the exact ending
but we start to notice absences as well as presences oh yeah that pain in the knee
it's not the same as it was in fact actually like had forgotten about
it or there's this um way in which we might just notice that
things are flickering like really fast and so they don't have this sense
of solidity that we thought that they did often we can't see this until the mind is really quiet often this is not
until we're on a retreat setting but we start to see that yeah
things aren't like as solid as uh as they uh often
appear so this idea that things have the nature
to arise and pass away this is not meant to just necessarily just be a teaching
and something you have to adopt and believe and we can bring in science to support it but there's a way in which
that's just a uh deep recognition that happens oh yeah everything's changing
and there's just this natural letting that happens and with
that deep kind of letting go happens is a really deep Freedom as
well this there's no longer a sense of desperately trying to control
everything often that's where we lose Freedom right just when we're trying to control or we're feeling like we're
getting pushed around but but maybe all end there this idea of impermanence and
how it's related to to many benefits of course but importantly it's related to
some deep insights that lead to Greater freedom and maybe with that I'll open it
up and see if there's some questions or
comments I he'll bring you a microphone so
hi I'm glad I came today because exactly where I am nice trying
to to let go and
just it's uh changing try to change it so hard it's like I don't accept What's
happen happening or what's not happening it's I'm so happy that I you
you said it all is it's I'm going to think about it I'm going to practice it
and I meditate all the time so maybe with the Mind
mindfulness I could stop
this keep changing keep as you said I it's like what I have is enough it's
more than enough but still I I'm looking for something else to be complete to be
more secure and when I look at it I say I am secure I am
okay but still deep down or in my mind I
want to change it this is not good enough so
I'm glad I hear you I think makes sense it really makes sense in in the realm of
mindfulness yeah yeah in the realm of um what Buddha did or and nothing permanent
and I love it that it's just arise and passes that's so true M thank you so
much you're welcome you're welcome and there's a way that we can practice with this just in our everyday life just
noticing you know the beginnings of things just say okay I'm just going to notice the beginnings of things or I'm
going to notice the endings of things just you know going around our everyday life and just setting that intention
usually at the beginning we won't remember but then if we just keep on setting that intention eventually we'll
remember when know it's like oh yeah this is ending and then there's a way in
which there can be a little more freedom we can just discover yeah it's that everything things changing and it
becomes a little bit easier exactly exactly thank Youk and did you did you
raise your hand back there so can you bring that give the microphone to her and then we'll move it over here thank
you thank you so much it's a wonderful topic and it seems very simple
impermanence but um I think the hardest thing
is when I'm trying to let go my attack attachment to what is especially if
things are longstanding if things have been certain way a long for a long
time it's really hard to let go it's really hard to accept that something has
changed and that clinging and that fighting to fix the fighting to go back
to things were despite knowing
that this two shall pass and Things Are permanent and I know all of those things but it's just really hard to put it into
practice so yeah maybe one thing I would say is like we like all of us understand
this thing about impermanence so it's not so much an intellectual
understanding as it's a way in which we just deeply know it and part of the way that we deeply know it is just to see it
again and again and again and again so there's something that's can be really powerful just in your everyday
experience uh I I'll just make this up like just
noticing how the sensations within your hands are changing throughout the day
sometimes you are feeling things that are cool and uh hard sometimes you're
feeling something that are neutral or they don't not too heavy sometimes you feel something that's heavier I don't
know just choose something and you just notice like oh yeah this is changing so so to get into the physical
experiences and to change them is what's uh often needed because we can think
about these things and that's often not enough there's a way in which to to know
it in a different way in an additional way does that make sense I'll try thank you I think in even in the fear
conference somebody talked about body scans and how they had underestimated body scans and then they realize they're
actually so I I appreciate that yeah thank you yeah body scans is a good thing too yeah
yeah and then do I do anything to it I'm just
speaking to it oh okay well this is probably going to sound kind of mundane but mundane is
good mundane is good uh I I'm terribly resistant to
change it's absolutely incredible I get an A+ in being resistant to
change but today was really strange I I decided I wanted to go to East West books you probably know East West books
in Mountain View on Castro and uh first first of all oh my God where am I supposed to park they closed off the
street I'm in a state of panic right because I couldn't remember which the cross street was uh but finally I was
sent in the right direction and just out of the blue this really nice man was was
walking down to Books Inc and we started chatting for a few minutes it was brief but it was very pleasant very nice you
know we were talking about how there used book sink used to be upstairs and there was a coffee house upstairs and
that was so cool because I love that place and then uh what was the order I went into East West and there were two
women who were extremely helpful I said I need something I need uh something for anxiety what do you have well they the
whole book whole book stor has changed completely those little books with affirmations used to be at the front
last time I went there which was probably years ago as but she was leading me all around the store and just
just incredibly helpful I I was amazed and then after I left
uh uh I went into went into um what is that place called a little oh geez Paris
Paris Baguette or whatever it's called um and behold a French woman I mean I didn't even know she was French I said
was that France Fran was that Fran she how did you know I don't know I'm just
it might have been the way she was dressed and then we start talking exchanging I didn't expect this to
happen you know really connected really connected and then after I left going
towards my car there was this Chinese woman I think she was Chinese Asian out front of one of the
places and uh we started talking and she just she said well you know don't worry
about this you know I I guess I started talking about wishing I had a boyfriend you know she says you you'll meet one
you're going to meet one tomorrow you know she I mean I couldn't believe
because I was open-minded that's really what it was I was open to
change I need to more to be more open to change so oh well I want to force it
just let it happen naturally right well there's is this way that says I need to
it's like kind of like embedded in said that yeah right like I should or something but why not do the same thing
just start noticing change like simple tangible change and there's a way that it just makes it
more like oh yeah of course everything's changing like once we kind of like turn our attention to it then it'll just
start showing up everywhere and then once we start to see oh it's already inherent in so much of my existence then
it just becomes a little bit more familiar and less uh a problem yeah I
like just noticing what's already happening yeah thank you volunteers
I guess not I think maybe Scott here will take
it just before I was here this evening um I arrived early was lying in my car
little snap take a little nap and I did suffer a loss about a year ago coming up on the
anniversary and when I was laying in the car I was kind of thinking
well it is the nature of things to die and to pass on and I take some comfort in that and
then I start wondering is that sort of a is that an Adaptive stance
um seems sort of like a sort of rationalizing you know I've suffered
this thing and okay that's kind of like saying well it's not so bad
I really know where I'm going with this but uh it feels like uh there might be an element of clinging and even asking
that question arising like is this is this a useful thought to have
just to look at that and say
well we all we all die all things
die but I would say that grief though was
something to really honor and respect and that of course there's grief
with loss and something for us to recognize that we all have our own
timelines our own ways that we express it and and to say like oh all things die
there is a way that maybe isn't honoring the grief if there's still grief there and that's part of our process is to
recognize is that this is what's happening yes we understand that things die but that doesn't mean we
don't feel acutely that loss
yeah thank you Scott because maybe I didn't say that explicitly I'm talking about impermanence and things and but I
do want to say right there of course there's loss of course heartbreaking loss it's just part
of it Human Condition too nobody nobody's
immune so I was going to make a comment uh like you I I really like uh Groundhog
Day I I listen to it almost every single ground did oh you
do watch it yeah I mean I have a copy of it at
home and one thing that came to me was what shifted for him was it when he went
from seeing his existence as a burden to seeing something that was valuable that
he loved and it was that love and respect and valuing
that really made a change to
um how he held everything yeah yeah I I agree when he stopped being so
self-concerned instead was helping others and I love this scene do you guys know this movie like where the there's
all these older ladies their their car gets a flat tire and he's already there
and he's helping to them change the tire he's jacking up the car I don't know there's something so sweet about this I
just love it so yeah thank you Jim thank you for
that okay well I guess even this class tonight is
impermanent I'm just wishing you all a lovely evening thank
you and a safe travels home and I'll see you next week