so hello everyone very happy to be back here with
you all to sit here and at IMC and
welcome you into the IMC
orbit the IMC Community for this Monday morning and um it's pretty special that
I have this opportunity to be with you in this way and and it's pretty special that there's
such a wonderful Rich sense of community that's forming just from the chats and for those of you
not reading or writing in the chats I just know that uh this is a very that
those chats kind of um exhibit they're very
warm um Community kind of
warm-hearted supportive community that gathers for these
meditations so probably for some of you maybe for
many of you one of the challenges of meditation is having a wise relationship
with thinking and some of you maybe think a
lot in meditation and and it
becomes more time for thinking than it is time for
meditation some of you might struggle with your thinking and maybe even think have think
that you're thinking is an enemy and something you have to fight
against for this meditation I would like you to be
allowed to think and I'll offer some
guidance through the sitting around
thinking certainly you can be centered in your
breathing while you're aware that you're thinking you don't have to let go of
your thoughts but to be curious about
them to see them clearly for what they
are to in a sense stand away from them and look back at them oh this is
thinking yes this is what my thinking is about get to know your
thinking but may be a little bit like getting to know someone who's speaking a foreign language you don't understand
and what are some of the things you can pick up to this person who's
thinking all along breathing in breathing
out almost like breathing is the beat to the
music and the music is your thinking so to begin by assuming a a
apprpriate posture for you that supports your ability to be
both relaxed and alert alert and
relaxed and no matter what posture you normally take is there some way
of straightening out the spine adjusting so that your shoulders a
little bit shoulder blades are a little bit going down your back so that your chest comes out a
little bit in a way that might even look like a posture of
confidence gently lower your
gaze and feel the effect low that lowering your gaze
has and then seeing what effect closing the eyes has close the
eyes and then seeing what effect effect it has on you to slowly take some deeper breaths
comfortably deep with comfortably long
exhales continue taking some deeper
breaths and now on the exhale relax your
body relax particular Parts the whole or the whole
body and see what the effect is on you in that part of your body that relaxes
on your whole body on your heart on your
mind and then noticing what shifts and what happens to you let your breathing
return to normal be with your normal
breathing and see what's happening now as a consequence of normal
breathing
and then with normal breathing continue the process of relaxing your
body but maybe almost imagining that relaxing as a a door that opens or a slide you slide
down and as the doors fully open or they come to the bottom of the
slide how are you what's shifted and
changed being open and receptive to what effect the relaxing has
had so as you exhale relaxing the
belly
as you exhale relaxing the
chest
relaxing the
shoulders relaxing the muscles of your
face
and again seeing what effect it has on you on the exhale Relax The Thinking
mind calming the thinking
mind support for calming the Mind thinking mind is to be reassuring for
it be in reassuring attention a
reassuring attendant to how the thinking mind might
be anxious or
upset
and then settle centering yourself on the body
breathing maybe the movements of the belly or the
chest
and even following W one full cycle of breathing in and breathing
out resting with it being receptive to
it what effect does it have on
you
feeling their rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out
and with Brea breathing is the rhythm is the
beat also be aware of your mind
thinking you're allowed to think but know you're
thinking as if
thinking is happening between your breathing around
it
just as you can hear the drum beat together with the other
music know the beat of the
breathing together with the music of
thinking
and as you're aware of thinking what effect does the thinking have on
you does IT project the mood or a tone does it contribute tension or
relaxation are your thoughts harmless
Whispers or are they intense demands for attention
and whatever way you're thinking it's fine breathe with it breathe through
them keep the beat going a steady
beat
e
for
if you find yourself thinking it's fine breathe with it allow your thinking
to be there as if breathing is a gentle wind
blowing through the thoughts and
notice what influence impact mood does thinking cast upon
you and how might that change if you see See
Clearly thinking and the influence it
has
e
e and then the last couple of minutes here
before starting to
end how have these minutes of meditation affected your
thinking as the nature of your thinking
changed as the mood behind your thinking
changed as the strength of thinking
changed as this space or the Stillness or the silence around
thoughts become
bigger
e
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to think now about the people in your life the people that you care
for the people for whom you have friendly
regard friends family Neighbors
co-workers people you know about from books or talks that you've
listened
to in whatever friendly regard you have for
them think about them and how the how what elicits
friendliness what you appreciate
apprciate and feel the influence of those thoughts on
you and then letting your kind regard open now as wide and expansive as
possible wishing that any benefit from this meditation can be for the welfare and
happiness of Others May others be
happy May others be
safe may others be
peaceful May others be free
may all beings be safe and may we
contribute to that
[Music]
possibility
thank [Music]
you
so hello and welcome on this Monday when I begin we
begin a new series of to of new topic for the
week and um maybe because I just came from meditating for a week or teaching
for a week on a retreat somehow what's surfaced for me is to want to talk about
is thinking and um a very important part of a wise life is becoming wise about our
thinking often enough I think for many people thinking happens Auto on
automatic pilot and we just take our thinking for
granted that this is how it should be and thinking just churs out whatever thoughts it does and we just go along
for the ride and the thoughts that we have can have a huge influence on us and uh and
if we just an automatic pilot just allowing those thoughts to be there and have that influence on us they can it
can be quite detrimental as I like to say that some psychologists believe that one of the
leading causes for depression is rumination if we are thinking thoughts
which are not Pleasant that having one of those thoughts might be just you know a small
little drop of unpleasantness or unpleasant effect on us but if we have
the same kind of thought over and over and over again throughout the day it begins wearing us down it begins filling
us with with the unpleasantness of that
comes along with them so if th those thoughts are self-criticism of any kind if we're
constantly having thoughts about our shame or our guilt or our inadequacy or
our whatever it might be um the frequency of those thoughts are
never questioned maybe may maybe to some degree all those might be
true so that they warrant a few thoughts and reflection and
consideration but there's no need to have thoughts like that repeatedly over
and over and over again it's uh if anybody talked as repeatedly as we might be talking to
ourselves we would wonder about uh their mental health or they they seem like
they're quite foolish but we don't question the foolishness of ourselves having the same
thought it's you thinking can be automatic it can be uh we take it for granted this is what how thing should
be so to uh start becoming mindful of
thinking is hugely important some people have no clue how
to do this and some of this might be because we have variet variety of
different cognitive abilities ways in which the Mind cognizes understands uh our
life and uh and some of those are almost can be kind of um um
um preverbal they're kind of preverbal or nonverbal ways of understanding and
processing there's uh however there's also verbal ways there's the inner voice
that the inner speech that we have some people don't have an inner speech they
have uh inner images that they produce but whether it's images
or inner speech uh it tends to follow uh the rules of
our language it tends to follow the story The Narrative that uh that's that
U uh inner speech can make and so to become aware of how this works for us
and one one interesting Discovery is do you think mostly in images or mostly in
words when you're actively thinking and and then as you think
what influence does that thinking have on you is it uplifting is it energizing in a nice way is it
agitating uh is it make you sad does it make you feel shame or embarrassment or
or deflated what's the influence that the thoughts have thoughts do not need to influence
us they do not need to come along with a mood that sets sets the mood up for how
we have to feel um and they but it's hard to tease those
apart uh I've had um I've sat you know quietly and and then I've thought about
when my kids were young you know my thought would come up about some danger they're in you know there's they might
something might happen and uh and sometimes it would come up this image or idea would come up Suddenly and I could
feel the influence would have had was fear throughout my body and um but there was no they
weren't any imminent danger they were um but those thoughts
those images that I had had cast this incredible spell on her my
body and um it doesn't have to be that way it's possible to have uh clear
enough attention recognition that in a certain way is
stronger than the influence of the thoughts it's um you know it's uh like
going to a horror movie and we feel afraid there's fear but if you you know
look around the maybe if you look around the the theater and see there's people eating popcorn and and U falling asleep
or doing what they do in theaters then um you know you not absorbed in the
images on the screen and maybe the images don't affect you as much or if
you start looking at the cinem cinemat graphic techniques used with uh with the
movie then you're not so caught in the story and you're not lost in it and it doesn't have such a big effect so to
step back and kind of look where does what influence does thinking have so the the kind of inner voice the
images the way of thinking might be discursive and um the word
discursive the which way I use it I might not be quite what the dictionary
says that one is just rambling thoughts kind of going this way and that way and
uh running around and do this and that thought and just kind of Maybe Maybe
random but I also think of it as carrying on a discourse carrying on a conversation in our
mind and it could be a conversation that we're um uh judging ourselves and
thinking about all that's bad it could be a conversation about planning what's going to have Imagining the future it
could be a conversation about what happened in the past repeating it over and over again it could literally be a
conversation that you're imagining with another person and you're even filling in their part of the
conversation and um so it's a relatively active and energetic way of having a
conversation in the mind or disc jumping around from one topic to another U but
still kind of carrying on a conversation so the inner voice is speaking or the inner projector is projecting images of
all this kind of stuff and um and if these are taken for granted this is the way it has to be
then we're really limiting uh our the the capacity limiting the full richness
of what our inner inner life mental life can be about so to recognize oh I'm having a
conversation I'm having a movie of what's going to come and this is the
influence it has wow look at that influence and what difference does it
make to you when you recognize you're having a conversation recognize your
inner voice is kind of going along and it has an effect on you the mood on your
mood your your energ energy your even how you understand
yourself and is that influence necessary do we need to believe every
thought do we need to be affected by every thought like we do we need to you
know go to horror movies all the time do we need to go you know to be not not
that all thoughts are scary but they can be angry and they can be critical or what influence do they
have and um and what difference does it make when you know and recognize that
influence so this can be subtle it could be um very very strong the subtle as I
said um to do it for a long period of time for hours repeatedly coming back to
it can have a huge impact on our life and how we understand ourselves and
affect ourselves and we don't have to believe every thought
we have we don't have to be under its influence emotionally mood-wise we don't
have to or what we think does not have to um agitate us
or depress us we can just breathe with it breathe through it breathing is a bit
of a protection not the way to stop thinking it's a bit of prot protection so that we
have a more balanced perspective of thinking and our involvement with them and how they
influence us and so to learn the art of breathing with through the thinking mind
to breathe alongside of breathing that way the mental energy
doesn't go all into the thoughts there's something else another perspective another balancing Force while we're
thinking I think this is one reason why some people like to go for a walk when
they're really troubled uh it's kind of like you go for a walk with yourself it's like almost
like having a friend it's kind of like something else is going on rather than being caught in your in your mind so uh
to gives it a fresh perspective it breaks up the Hony of of thinking that
it has on us so the same thing with breathing breathing can be like kind of like going going for a walk with oneself
accompanying it breathing through through and then uh maybe a little
Shield gentle Shield or a gentle uh wind that blows away that
influence that the thoughts might have on us otherwise and does that help us to see
our thinking in a wiser way does that help us to reconsider to question are
these thoughts true are they useful and is there a better way to
think are there better thoughts to have and what might those
be and if there are better thoughts to have consciously
deliberately begin having those thoughts you're allowed
to have a sense of deliberateness with what you think as opposed to just being
the the victim of whatever the mind wants to spew out or run you can actually
choose maybe not for a long time but you can break the chain and think about things which are
reasonable and true and things which are uplifting and supportive things that are
wise and uh take your mind for a walk so that the thinking mind the discursive
mind doesn't have the upper hand and then the next few days I'll talk
about different kinds of thinking different ways of thinking because if we
only know if we never thought about it never really understood all the
different aspects of thinking then we might be very limited in how we think
and therefore more likely to be the victim of how we think so as we learn
new ways of thinking uh that can set us free in many
ways so thank you for this and uh I look forward to continuing
tomorrow