hello everyone and
welcome when I think about mindfulness practice I often think about something I
consider a synonym to mindfulness and um or an very important
element of it and that is honesty that honesty is mindfulness out
loud and of course we don't necessarily say everything that's going on in us out
loud but uh this idea that mindfulness involves an honesty to
oneself it's sometimes said that um you know it's not always so clear how much honesty we should provide
the world if it things can it can be hurtful for people to say things that
what we really think the the bride at the wedding asks
you what you think of her address and it's better not to say exactly what you
think and um so the
um um but the in Buddhism it said it's never okay to lie to oneself never what
one should always be honest to oneself so the Mind mindfulness is a self honesty we sit down to and to be honest
about what's happening for ourselves here and now and
uh some people will practice what's called mental noting as part of
mindfulness practice and that's kind of saying to oneself what it is that's
happening in the moment but that's an opportunity for that Honesty oh I'm feel
feeling agitated that's what's happening or I'm troubled that's what's happening or you know that I'm spinning
out and whatever it might be
and and with that uh honesty with a moment of
mindfulness it isn't that that's the end of the story just note what's happening
and then go on to not the next thing there's the art of mindfulness or this kind of awareness practice
is to stay present after we clearly know
something we note something or we it doesn't have to be verbal or in thoughts
it could be a silent knowing but we clearly know something oh this is what's happening as if it's a a statement of
Truth it could be as simple as I'm I'm exhaling oh this is an
exhale and then after that clarity this is an
exhale then stay and like almost like the the that Clarity opens the door for
you to feel the breeze coming in from outside
or if the breeze arising out of the practice stay present and what happens
in the wake of that Clarity it's like you you're opening yourself up to feel
okay what's here now don't be a hurry so one way to do this in fact is with the
breathing is to recognize for example the exhale oh this is an
exhale and then be available to feel what arises in the wake of that and that
might be the inhale or it might be the inhale is little bit uh constricted so you
recognize oh constricted in breath now what happened in the wake of recognizing
that like Rec the recognition is a clearing of the space now to feel what
follows it might be the exhale but it might also be something
happens with the constriction it opens it softens it somehow is held in a
different way just by the honesty so to think of mindfulness practice as a practice of
honesty where we're being being with what is and in that recognition of what is
being a little bit more open to feel it more fully or be with the present more
in the wake of that Clarity and then we do it again and
again so again with the breathing it could be kind of oh this is an exhale
this is how the exhale is and then open and you might feel the inh ale but
maybe it doesn't have the same qualitative knowing or recognition or
about the inhale it's just felt intimately in a different way in the
wake of that Clarity and then again with the exhale no oh this is an exhale this is how it
is it's smooth it's long it's it's a settling in and now what's next and the
next moment doesn't have to be known in the same way it can be
felt what happens in the wake of it and then a moment of knowing and feeling
knowing and feeling honesty and deeper
recognition so assuming a meditation
posture lowering your gaze and if it's comfortable closing
your
eyes and just as you are recognizing how you are now in the
most obvious way it doesn't matter so much for the
purpose of practice how you are now what matters is the honesty of recognizing
it recognizing and then being open to sense
and feel what follows for just a few moments and then
do it
again the clear recognition and then to feel or sense
what follows means that we're not caught up in the stories the
ideas of what's happening but we're
here for a deeper intimacy with
oneself taking a few breaths to
relax settle
in
for
and then settling into your breathing feeling the inhale and
exhales
taking a moment to recognize how you are a truth
telling and letting that recognition being an opening to feel the body more fully in how you
are maybe feeling how breathing
is as you may have as you have just made a truth statement about
yourself
for
e
practicing honesty of how you are right
now and then following that honest
recognition feel and sense what follows
how it is in your body as you return to
breathing
for
for and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to [Music] consider how it's possible to Center
oneself in the middle of self
honesty if we clearly recognize how we are what's happening for
US settle into that or stand in the middle of it
and with that as a foundation being available to feel sense
know the world around us to have a
deeper sensitivity to the
world because honesty puts us in deeper touch with with
ourselves the more we're in touch with ourselves the more we can be in touch
with the
world staying centered in an honest connection to
oneself and then gazing out upon the people in
our lives people will encounter
today the world around us and gazing upon them
kindly with generosity with [Music]
care with good will
may all people realize the
potential for being at peace with
themselves may all beings realize their
potential for abiding in a peaceful
heart May all beings realize their
capacity to be safe to themselves for
themselves may all beings be [Music] free of the attachments the
and in doing so may they genuinely be
happy maybe may they have experience of safety that's inner and
outer may they experience peace in themselves and a peace around
them and may they be free
within and may they experience freedom in the world in which they
walk may all beings be touched by our well-wishing and our
friendship [Music]
thank [Music]
you
so hello and I continue now the third part of
my story with Buddhist practice and I had been introduced to
Zen practice and was very attracted to it and then I went uh back to Norway in
order to kind of kind of come to terms with what my
relationship was to my my home country I hadn't lived there for many years growing up but had gone back
frequently so I made it back and I had various Adventures I worked uh that fall
in um I think it was a fall of 74 uh on the docks in the town of city
of Bergen a dock worker mostly loading and unloading small cargo
boats and um and uh
I had a wonderful disc discover you know there were very little Buddhists that I in Norway but there was one famous I
don't know how famous he was my girlfriend at the time knew about him because he lived near where she grew up
uh a Buddhist hermit high up in the mountains in the snow in the coldest part of
Norway and um it was I went to visited him for two weeks in the middle of January and and kind of climbed the
mountain it's he would lived in a small cabin but it was uh probably the closest thing in my life of following
the the kind of U cartoon idea of going into the EMAs to find a high up in the
cave to find a wise person and um so I've SP two weeks with him and and that
was kind of fascinating um spent the morning skiing in the High Country by myself in the afternoons having long
conversations with him and then um but the important thing that
happened there in Norway was that I stayed for a year and um uh the
following six months I lived on a small farm in southern Norway with a wonderful
couple who um took me in and included me and their family like their family life
their their uh farming life and uh I love the life there I loved getting up
in the morning caring for the cows and the farm and it was just a lovely lifestyle for me and um so much so that
I kind of decided I wanted to be a farmer in Norway and but in the course of that
time my friends left for a week and U on vacation with me taking care of the farm
and the cows and it was the first time in my life that I had been alone uh for
that length of time I didn't the only person I saw for that week was the mail carrier who came walking up the road
kind of at a at a distance and I could see him down the road our the farm was
at the end of a kind of dirt road and and
um and otherwise I didn't see anyone and what happened in the course of that week
uh I wasn't meditating I don't think I was just kind of living the life alone but the daily life became kind of a
heightened meditation it kind of heightened awareness and without the social contact and just being alone I
became acutely aware of my surroundings everything started to Sparkle everything
seemed to be bright brighter than usual and I just kind of delight in how beautiful everything was and also I
became more acutely aware of even my thoughts that I ever have before and they had kind of a sparkle I don't know
if they were particularly good thoughts but it just everything had a Clarity the sense of awareness became very
present moment very clear and it felt so satisfying to be alive and to be
there it was kind of like I later I felt that was kind of like on a Meditation Retreat without
meditating and um and when my friends came back that sense of uh Clarity and
peace went away and and I felt the loss of that and
I didn't decide to become a Hermit myself but rather I then now had a quest
and the quest was uh I worded how can I be alone uh with others how can I have
this intimacy this peace this Clarity this kind of sense of being awake um
with other people um and so that became kind of the spiritual Quest the question
that I had that I started to explore and think about the other thing that happened on that farm was I did start at some point
meditating every day every morning before going to breakfast but it very quickly became clear that going to
breakfast kind of feeling very peaceful and calm not feeling needing to say anything and and just being present in a
relaxed Silent Way didn't work for the friendship with a couple the farmers um
that somehow it was awkward to be there this new way that I knew how to be uh
with um where they expected kind of the old Gil to be there to interact in a usual normal way at
breakfast and I decided that I either had to um stop meditating or I had to
lose my friends so I start decided to stop meditating until the duration of that
time living there I also decided that I wanted to become a small farmer in Norway but to do that in Norway you had
to um go to vacational school to be trained to be a farmer only then could you buy a
farm and I decided that um that uh I
only had two more years to get a a degree from the University of California
and if I went to the University of California at Davis which is one of the Premier agricultural schools in the
world I would fulfill the requirement for buying a farm in Norway and I would
also uh have such a good training wouldn't just be vocational school that if at some point in the future of my
life I wanted to do something else with that uh degree that I could do that also
I wanted to be back close to San Francisco zent Center and Davis was about I don't know an hour an hour and a
half Drive from San Francisco so I came back uh to go to uh
school at UC Davis to finish up there and uh to get a degree in
Agronomy and which is what I did but when I got there I began immediately to
get uh start meditating twice a day in the same schedule kind of that they did at the San Francisco Zen Center which
was two periods I think it was uh I think it was the same I did two periods of 40 minute Zen meditation one in the
morning one before going to bed but never on Sunday because at the San Francisco Zen Center they never
meditated on Sunday it was like their day off so I figured that was the way to do it and there was a small Cien group
in Davis and I went to them twice a week Tuesday and Thursday evenings and sat with
them and it was really clear that I started meditating that fall when I started col returned to college because
um I was uh uh um I was suffering part of it I was very lonely part of it were
other issues that I was dealing with and it uh the primary reason to start meditating regularly was I thought that
the meditation would help me deal with my suffering my anxiety my loneliness my
all kinds of things that I felt and um so I started meditating every day and um and then this very
strange thing happened after some months and for me and that was that uh the kind
of uh surface suffering that I was trying to address it kind of faded away maybe through the meditation maybe
because I got busy with school and I had some friends there but also um kind of faded away but I noticed that uh so the
reason for why I was meditating disappeared but I still meditated and I
found that really strange that I would do met continue this twice a day meditation without the reason I had
before and I had no other reasons to do it I could I could kind of come up with that I'm kind of a rational person and
so I wanted to have reasons for why I do things and I found it really strange
that I kept meditating with no reason like this is what I did and and so I
kept doing it and wondering why am I doing this and um and so then I came to
um at some point I came to a realization understanding that I was meditating for
the same reason reason that maybe a dancer dances or an artist paints or
musician plays the musical instrument for me uh the meditation was a way of
was a form of self-expression almost like an artistic expression and that um and that it was a
very deep way of expressing something that was I didn't even know was there something deep inside that I could
characterize by peace or calm or kind of a sense of aliveness that felt such such
goodness in it like I was more alive in meditation than in any other time in my life it just felt so
right and the the the word the key word that I used to characterize how I felt
was integrity and it I didn't have a sense that the word integrity was connected to
ethics so it wasn't ethical Integrity um maybe it was closer to a sense of wholeness so Integrity being
one being full like all of me was there and that integrity was real was then the
the the became then the purpose for meditation to experience that Integrity
so it wasn't some big goal for enlightenment in the future but it was really to sit down and be in that
integrity and that wholeness and that expressivity of of the meditation
itself and um and I didn't luckily I didn't have any sense to idea I didn't know much about meditation so I wasn't
burdened by the idea that I was supposed to stop thinking so my thinking Minds kind of continued but there was this
deeper Wellspring of something happening there and then um uh and then at some
point during those two years at Davis um I had this uh uh
idea uh why do I feel this Integrity only in my
meditation uh it's the same mind in meditation as outside of medit meditation why can't I have the same
Integrity outside and now my quest became um uh how can I extend this
Integrity or live with this Integrity in my daily life and outside of meditation I continued meditating but
now the meditation had a second purpose and that is it's set the stage it give
me the familiarity to some way of being I want to discover how do you be this way in daily life as
well so when I graduated from um Davis then um I didn't go back to Norway
to become a a farmer um by this time I'd been going to Zen Center throughout
those two years in Davis and going down there to practice there and do dayong Retreats and other
things and uh so then um when I finished I decided I would move closer to Zen Center to practice
there and um and uh but part of the reason I went there was that when I went
visiting to a Zen Center uh this remarkable thing happened was that um
when I would talk to this especially the more seniors and practitioners um they were mirrors for
myself I saw myself better I saw that I was playing social games like I was
trying to impress people I was trying to show them what a great person I was or I had had an image of myself I wanted to
replicate so they would see me through that idea I have who I should be all kinds of things kind of social games
that I I was kind of got got away with my my friends my friends actually did
the same we kind of expected it of each other maybe and we just kind of merrily went along but uh there at Zen Center
there was no response to that those games and and because there was no
response to the senior practitioners there and their uh I didn't feel like they were cold I just felt like of
course they're not going to respond to something like that and so I saw myself much better and I said this is really
good this idea of trying to bring that Integrity into my daily life to live with people who are going to mirror me
this way will really be a big help so when I moved to Zen Center I moved first I lived in in the rental department near
the San Francisco Zen Center I um that was the motivation was not to meditate
more but to uh find it a better way to integrate what I was experiencing ing
meditation into my daily life as a consequence of that I meditated even
more because Zen Center you know go there and meditate more with them and um and so that was the
beginning of uh kind of being a a deeper end student I'll just mention one last thing
that I um I lived in the neighborhood of Zen
Center for about six s s eight months and uh and then I uh went and did
a week-long retreat at their Farm the green g uh Z Center which I hadn't visited before I don't think and it
hadn't really been in my mind and I discovered a farm and I said wow this would allows me to bring
together the things I love my farming and Zen practice so I think in April of
uh 1989 1979 I moved to greul to live live
there and practice there and that was my beginning of the residential kind of monastic
life so um and they'll continue with that tomorrow thank
you