hello everyone welcome and for this morning I'd like to begin
with a parts of a poem by Walt Whitman wonderful poem for that has a lot of uh
speaks I think in many ways parts of it to our practice
This song is called song of the open road and the part that I'll read to introduce
are sitting is uh he writes
I inhale droughts of space
the East and the West are mine the North and the South are mine
I am larger better than I thought
I did not know I held so much goodness
all seems beautiful to me
so to inhale space
all around us is in a sense Infinite Space
and to bring that into ourselves as we sit
and as we exhale let it all expand outwards to fill all
of space awareness spacious spacious awareness inside
spacious awareness outside
he writes elsewhere just before in the long poem about loosening up all that holds him
all the ways that were held are cling or grave let it loosen and then he talks about
space and we'll see later that this uh this
the context of also talking about listening listening to others listening
well letting go
so there's no holding on to
definitions and constructions and
ways in which we put boundaries in lines around ourselves
and our life and then to discover that we're better than we thought
behold so much goodness and everything is beautiful
so to assume a meditation posture
and maybe you can adjust your posture
so it's a posture that gives you some access
or might approximate giving you access
to your own goodness into your beauty
to the beauty all around
and in caring for your posture your body
to gently close your eyes and feel this body as if you've never
felt it before as if it's the very first time that you
are sensing
sensing more fully
sensing and caring for the body and one expression of caring is to relax
to soften the body the tensions of the body
softening around any tension that doesn't want to relax it's okay
to be tense if it's difficult to Let It Go
being okay sitting here with it feeling your body
maybe feeling the global body
in whatever way that's easy
breathing in space as you inhale
in a sense as we inhale the toward the chest ribcage lungs expand
and in a sense there's more space within that's created
and as we inhale in the chest expands belly expands
we expand into the space around us
and that has your exhale perhaps relaxing into the space that
surrounds you
a releasing of fixed ideas of yourself of your body
loosening up the line between you and the space around you
the line between your thoughts and the space around your thoughts
as you exhale softening the thinking mind
relaxing
we often don't know how much goodness is within us
because we're telling ourselves stories and ideas of the opposite
to relax those stories those ideas sitting here gently breathing in space
relaxing into space
trusting for these few minutes that you are better than you ever could
have imagined
that there's more goodness within than you ever could have known
and as you breathe out Here and Now
maybe all things can be beautiful
not least because we stopped the stories and ideas that they are otherwise
letting go letting go of the chatter of thinking
judging wanting
perhaps so you can listen deeply Within
when we let go of trying to be good
but listen with a quiet mind
you might discover there's more goodness within than you ever could have imagined
let go and listen deeply
tenderly
foreign
to listen well
is to know how to quiet
the voices inside the ideas the desires
that interfere with an open listening
maybe a listening from the heart
a listening that's not trying to control things
fix things
listening that where we listen to our own heart
to our own depths quietly and non-judgmentally
and then to listen to others not through the filter of our desires or
our fears our resentments and annoyances
but to listen from the quiet heart
and if we listen from the heart we might be able to listen
to the hearts of others
to listen to what's deeper within them than their
words they say the behaviors they do
to listen in such a way that we are connected
with each other's hearts
and from there
to offer to the world our our good will
our well-wishing May It Be
that what we learn through meditation
serves us to live a life that promotes the welfare
and happiness of everyone our self-included
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
foreign
[Music]
thank you
so good morning hello on this Wednesday morning and
the third talk on wise listening
I could just as well maybe call it a um
caring listening with care but why is listening
and there's a story in the ramayana one of the great Classics of Indian
literature and religion of Rama uh going for a walk Walking in the
forest and Rama Hears A Very faint voice
and he can't quite hear what it is but he's listening and getting very quiet
very still maybe if he stands still so he can listen to that what's this voice
he hears in the forest and he still can't quite hear what it's
saying but after a while he gets some sense of from where it's the voice is coming
and it guides him to to walk in that direction it kind of follows the voice listens and as he gets closer to the
source he begins hearing what the voice is saying
and it's saying his name Rama Rama
and so he listens and he goes closer and closer finally it comes to this very
large Boulder and uh and it seems like the voice is coming from inside the boulder
and uh and so then he puts he gently puts his hand and touches the boulder
at which point the boulder kind of dissolves and there's a
a woman emerges out of that Boulder
and uh and they agreed and they somehow I don't know how the story goes beyond
that but in a sense he meets himself
that part of himself which is petrified that's locked in that's frozen that's
hidden and lost to him even himself and so this idea that there is some if
you listen care if we know how to listen or the equivalent is to send sort of
feel where the listening is not through the filter of our desires filters of our
uh ideas of self and the conceits we have about how terrible we are or how
wonderful we are or how you know that Define and limit ourselves
that there's no hindrances in the listening there's no aversion no
agitation and no spinning of stories and and bringing along the luggage of the
past the memories but just to learn how to listen the peaceful quiet Deep Way
not even listening with the ears but listening with the whole body or listening with a heart
and there is within us something that is calling us maybe not
with our name but uh for the language of the Buddha it's the Dharma
that's coming here come here come here I think
invites us to come invites us to investigate and so come and see come and see
so if you listen to this kind of sometimes very subtle voice that's within this message from within
and then follow it to get closer to it sense it until we can do the equivalent of
putting our hands gently on it the image that I like is the idea of cupping our hands together and coming
underneath and just holding what's there with support sometimes what's deep inside is fear
sometimes it's sorrow sometimes it's hurt just to hold it
gently um and uh and um and then whatever is petrified
whatever is Frozen whatever um is locked within has a chance to
dissolve and um and so here we have a story of listening deeply
listening and hearing and listen going along with what we're hearing and um
and so uh the role of listening some people will say that uh listening
requires some degree of letting go of control you know if we don't like what we're
seeing we can close our eyes and we can look away to you know in a sense maybe we can't do
the same thing with the ears um we can't you know you can put I guess you guys guess you can put uh
earplugs in cover your ears but uh the um
the ears are just more kind of open to what's there and uh so to uh you'll control what you
hear there's a loss letting go of control of a certain type when we and that's a part of the
challenge of really good listening is the the balance between the control to
listen and the letting go of control of what we're hearing
and if we're listening to ourselves in a deep way the same kind of balance of
having enough control of ourselves to be able to really listen but in such a way that we're letting go
of control of what we're listening to that we allow what's listening what
we're listening sensing feeling to show itself and so
um this is where this wonderful poem by Walt Whitman
uh much of it is wonderful I think and called a song of the open road
and um so um
uh so here in the kind of the middle of the long poem
I'll start from this sentence from this hour
Freedom with an exclamation mark so from this hour
freedom from this hour I ordain myself loosened
of limits and imaginary lines listening to others
and considering well what they say pausing
searching receiving contemplating
gently but with undeniable will
divesting myself of the holes that would hold me
I inhale droughts of space the East and the West are mined and the
north and south are mine I am larger better
than I thought I did not know I held so much goodness
all seems beautiful to me
so there here we have this wonderful combination of letting go of
here he's called it holds attachments letting go of control even at the same
time a very clear sense of being in charge of oneself first he makes this very strong
statement that it's kind of like a promise or a state assertion that from
now on I'm going to be free and how we can say that with confidence
and because you can't just make yourself free of course but I think that he's seen something
inside of himself some capacity not to hold himself
uh not to not to uh
hold himself in bondage not to keep himself from his only inner freedom
and I ordained myself loosened of limits and imaginary lines this is a great out
of Buddhism that we limit ourselves with our thoughts our constructs the the
imaginary lines definitions that we use to understand ourselves the world around us and people
and um and then he's going to listen to others so he's not saying the result of his
freedom he's thinking he could do whatever he wants overriding people and not caring for them the first thing he
says he's going to do with his freedom is to listen to others
and considering well what they say I hear this to be wishing to God to be
giving them the benefit of the doubt and listen well what listening well means for me is you want to listen below their
words you want to listen even below the surface emotions that's driving their
words listen to either their goodness that's deep inside
listen to the pain which is deep inside listen to that potential for goodness
and Freedom From Pain that's deep inside everyone everyone listen to that so that
in the listening you may be beginning to awaken that possibility of freedom in them
so first thing with this Freedom he says is that he's going to listen to others pausing searching receiving
contemplating and divesting himself of what holds that
would hold me and for then after the you know after
listening then he talks about just Infinite Space becoming everything becoming large and spacious
when he's let go of what holds him his attachments then there's a feeling of expansiveness
and I am larger and better than I thought I did not know I held so much goodness
imagine listening to others
you know where you know that they are better than they've ever thought so the third guideline for speaking that
Buddha gave is speak in a way that goes right to the heart
touches other people's hearts touches your own heart
so with listening listen from the heart lifts it in a way that touches the
hearts of others listen in a way that you have let go of your attachments so you can be attuned
to the possibility potential for freedom and peace and happiness that others have
because if we're only reacting to the surface to their anger to their bitterness to
their complaints to their fears their anxieties we don't want to deny those and not see
it and not understand that but if we only listen to that we kind of
stay at that level it might even reinforce that that's all that's all that counts that's
all there is but if you can listen to what's deeper listen in a way that touches their
hearts listen from a way that you're listening from your heart from your capacity for a
deeper tenderness a deeper love a deeper care and maybe then you can begin
doing the work that Walt Whitman says pausing searching receiving
contemplating that maybe allows you to be attuned to how
they are larger better than you think but also they're better
than they thought ever thought that maybe you discover
that they hold a lot of goodness but maybe your gift is you see that they
hold more goodness than they ever realized and you appreciate that you appreciate them
that's what allows this affirming of the goodness of others is recognizing it's
amazing what that makes room for and allows to happen and come forth that
will not come forth if we remain in our reactivity to them or in our trying to
control them or fix them so to listen well
to listen to what calls you in the forest
deep inside and to listen to what's deep inside in
the forest of others may we all listen to each other well
and in that listening bring forth the best in all of us thank you