hello good morning those who are here and good any time of
the day for those who are joining through the live stream
I just moved it closer I think that's better now yeah thanks great oh and then recording yes of course
so so let's settle in and begin by uh
arriving and meditating together so I'll give some light guidance
to help us arrive settle really arrive
and yeah we'll take it from there together how does that sound
let's begin let's begin
begin again and again each moment ah it's wrong with the new beginning
each moment in new arrival
arriving arriving here in this body
In This Moment In Time
fresh new full of possibilities
of this moment
in the same way that if we have a cup with stale cold tea in
it we have to throw it out to make room for fresh
new warranty if there's stale thoughts regurgitations
let's release them just for this period release them now
making room for fresh
ability goodness
feeling this body our sit bones and the cushion or the chair
if you're sitting on a chair your feet on the floor if you're in a cushion your legs touching the Earth
hands on your lap all these touch points
which we can always come back to these touch points
resting resting in this body resting in the space that surrounds the body
resting
and including everything including the sounds they're not
distractions they're just sounds they're just sounds
let your heart relax release in the midst of all this the body breathing pulsating
alive
sounds the energy in the room and the quiet the silence
between all the busyness outside and inside
tune the frequency of your radio as if you had a radio internally
tune into the calm the channel of the calm there is this calm in between
everything else all the noise all the chatter in the mind follow the chatter inside
outside yes those are there too
holler all the news and this and that but tune
in right now ah tune into the silence between the noise
and holds all the noise holds it all
I let the breath the sensations of the breath in the body guide you
connecting to the breath in the body
relaxing relax relax the body
receive the breath not tightly but spaciously
oh dear breath
enjoying the breath enjoying the breath
and if the tuning of the attention drifts if it drifts
like an old radio that drifts to other frequencies of
thought and plans and worries a return re
re-engage
again and again this moment with the breath with the silence that holds it all
permeates everything internally it's there you know it's there
us that it's here it's already here
enjoy this breath
can I enjoy this breath
how can I find a way to rest
collect myself gather gather myself
collect and gather myself the entirety of the length of the
in-breath cozy
sweet spacious
and then the out breath
this practice is not about forcing it's about learning
finding ways for Joy contentment
enjoyment and there is plenty
right here relax and receive
what a miracle this body is alive and breathing
foreign
when the mind the heart is content where it is it doesn't want to drift anywhere
see how you can bring in ease to the body relax the body
the body is tight
tune into the joy the Delight just quietly sitting
and breathing it's not a forcing
finding the Delight the contentment that keeps us here
it's not about forcing
foreign
Letting Go letting go of thoughts not now not now thank you
back another time not
not just this breath
just here
foreign
can I slow down enough
can I slow down and fall in love with the breath
for just a moment
may not even know what it means but curious
what does it mean to fall in love with the breath
foreign
with Valentine's Day coming up next week make the breath your Valentine right now
appreciating
honoring loving delighting in
the breath
can you make yourself this body your Valentine
not another
being who is you
whose care is entrusted to you
this being worked so hard
you know their challenges through and through
appreciating honoring loving with every breath
this dear being who's doing their best
just this breath in this body
with kindness with menta being your own beloved other
not another
and as we bring this sitting to a close
appreciating but you showed up but you did your best
without any self-judgment or what arose or did not arise you showed up you did
your best trust that you
have planted seeds for goodness
calm wholesomeness kindness and let go of the rest
trusting in this goodness together we all share this co-created
goodness we offer it we offer it to the world
may my goodness May uh my attempts
may I may my engagement serve my own Awakening my own ease and
freedom from suffering my own happiness as well as everybody
else's in the world
male beings everywhere be happy
may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you for your practice foreign
all right
hello again good morning
how are you feeling I see nods give me a few words how are
you feeling happy thank you content
peaceful connected and joyful
settled what else and everything is welcome if
you feel feeling stirred up that's fine too bring it on
I'm feeling calmer than I entered to more settled yeah anything else
anything else in the room you want to bring in
ah connected yeah yeah also sense of connection it's
so nice to sit with people I love Zoom don't get me wrong I
love the little squares I've been I've fallen in love with the zoom over the past three years teaching a lot on Zoom
and yet the goodness also too to the embodied presence to the embodied
presence yeah so I bring that in just not sharing my Reflections but also
for us to feel that there's something especially for those who are in the room and if you are joining us from YouTube
there is a Sangha there's a YouTube song I to really feel into energetically and
yet here feeling into yeah it is nice Sangha Community yay how wonderful other
human beings were on this path source of joy
so today I'd like to share some Reflections on
Gathering collecting the mind the heart just this
sense of settledness that many of you gave a gave a shout out for the sense of
settledness calmness happiness contentment all of these are in each
other's neighborhood and
formally formally in um the the title or the topic of this
this uh talk is um the poly word is samadhi samadhi
or often translated as concentration but concentration brings up the sense of
concentration whereas this word samadhis actually
um it means to put together to place
together to collect to gather in the Chon tradition actually it's
often translated as calm abiding oh I like that right it's a different translations of concentration calm
abiding feel that on your body right concentration is like okay I gotta concentrate remember math class again
for some people that worse if it works for you go with it but the idea again with that translation of concentration
is to gathers when the orange juice is concentrated it's gathered it's Collective it's it's Essence right it's
whereas we have it's like a word map we have so many different
associations with the word concentration that sometimes it's not helpful but calm abiding
collectedness Gathering and in fact the word itself in in Pali
samadhi comes is from the prefix sum which means together and the Ruda which
means to put or place so to place together to put together
to bring together so unifying the mind in a steady
undistracted awareness in the words of Richard shenkman in his book samadhi
so this idea of collectedness collecting ourselves because that feels delicious
doesn't it oh yeah collecting myself instead of being scattered the opposite is being scattered being everywhere
collected scattered and especially in our Modern Life
I think as the speed of of technology and communication and just the Deluge of
information in so many ways um
has increased has increased social media and news outlets
etc etc even entertainment Outlets just just the number of
um entertainment options available just so many ways we can get scattered
so raise your hand if you felt scattered at least one moment the past week
two moments yeah it's
all the hands go up of course it's her common Humanity now this and in fact I
should have asked you to look around it's a common name of course we get scattered
this is the condition of um our lives right now
in the west actually everywhere in the world it turns out but especially in in here in Silicon Valley and then the West
in general so so to help to support ourselves we
want to collect ourselves and calm ourselves collect ourselves
and so so the question might arise well okay why do I want to collect myself let's do
the why let's do the how how do I collect myself is it by force is it like okay now I'm
gonna collect myself okay and and push away all distractions like to have a a
um a a an aversive fighting attitude with
everything like every distraction every noise like stop I'm collecting myself is it that that I'm making fun of it
clearly not right that's not the way to collect ourselves but but collecting ourselves really is through enjoyment
and falling in love with peace with contentment that's the way it's
done it's there's no other way it's it's not by the force of will and when the
whip like okay constant right now um You can try that it doesn't it's I'll
say more about in a moment but in Praise of collectedness and
praise of collectiveness I wanted to also share this quote which I love by
Thomas Merton the celebrated famous Trappist monk who
was also a good friend of uh his Holiness the Dalai Lama they were
buddies so Thomas Merton many of you might already know his name
um I love this quote by him there is a and and he said this
gosh how many years ago now uh decades ago I don't have the date of of the
quote but decades and he's been dead for a while so decades ago there is a pervasive form of
contemporary violence to which the idealist most easily succumbs activism
and overwork the rush and pressure of Modern Life are
a form perhaps the most common form of its innate violence
to allow oneself to be carried away by a multitude of conflicting concerns
surrender to too many demands to commit oneself to too many projects
to want to help everyone in everything is to succumb to violence
the frenzy of our activism neutralizes our work for peace
it destroys our own inner capacity for peace it destroys the fruitfulness of our own
work because it kills the root of inner wisdom which makes work fruitful
powerful words from a Wise Wise being
too many demands too many projects
want to help everyone and everything do you identify with too many projects
raise your hand too many yeah
so this this um what he talks about which we recognize this inner capacity for peace
this to cultivate this inner capacity for peace to maintain that so that our outer
work in the world is inspired it comes out of that inner capacity that inner
holding of of Peace of stability of stability
so now motivating I'm trying to motivate a little bit probably doesn't I don't need to motivate why
practicing calm abiding settling Gathering is important but I
will just spell it out it is the way that we create this this fort this
stability this sense of um this this it's like a foundation it's
like a rock solid foundation on which our work in the world is based and also
our inner work of insight is based on calm
so the practice of calm abiding Gathering collecting
concentrating the Mind settling the mind we all just use the word settling the
mind the practice of cultivating samadhi to add to any extent
possible and they're quite a range in levels of of of depth of settle settling
that our minds can cultivate but at any level cultivating somebody is
the precursor is the precursor to Insight is the precursor to Insight
internally and externally if we don't have a settled and calm mind we cannot
clearly see it's not possible
so imagine your mind you have binoculars right you're and you're trying to look
at your life you're trying to look at your habit patterns you're trying to look at the world right the the lens of
inside the the binoculars of insight but if you don't have a stable
base if you don't put it on a tripod if it's just moving moving moving you can't
really look the image keeps shifting and changing there needs to be
stability so that you can take your breath oh that's what's happening okay
so that building that that that tripod that we set
the binoculars on for the sake of insight and inside by the way is also another word for vipassana those who
have been practicing for a while if we pass a nut inside practice seeing things as they are arising passing all of that
um and the precursor to that is somebody's
is calming settling the mind and also if we take Insight because insights really
are personal we always have in this practice you know many times
um maybe beginners think okay all these insights I hear about all I hear about
impermanence and I hear about not self I especially want that not self thing that how do I get to that that Insight like
that sounds or or emptiness that's what I want that sounds so cool give me some emptiness okay slow down
slow down it's from it starts from the personal
and when you have the insights that are in personal nature then it extends to
then you can see the universal but you can jump into the universal it becomes
spiritual bypass if you start if you want to just see the universal and poo poo the in the person I don't even exist
I don't yeah the Buddha says there's no self not so yeah no no no no come back get quiet down calm down slow down
cultivate some somebody some stability of the mind and get to see the insights
your own insights from the personal level oh wow I'm suffering
I'm really attached to this relationship that did not work I am really suffering
there's a lot of suffering here okay how do I work with this there's personal
suffering here there's attachment there's wanting there's anger there's resentment there is self-blame wow okay
okay I'm gonna start there it's not like okay that's all personal forget it I just want to go and
like chill out and do the not self thing because no no no start you have to start
right because what can happen whoa many different ways different
people have different but I'll just give one example you know you stay with you stay with say
um with the the um the pain the suffering okay so the
teachings all right mindfulness of the body is the first Sati patana the First Foundation
of mindfulness okay so you start to feel the sensations in the body yes really hurts
ouch this really hurts and then by actually acknowledging the
pain that oh yeah this really really hurts I'm really hurting right oh
sweetheart that arises compassion compassion oh
that which may not have been there because you were just kicking yourself I shouldn't have said that I should have done that I was I'm really hurting right
now I'm really hurting right now right now so there can be a sense of compassion that arises this really hurts
I'm really hurting oh if I have actually compassion kindness
ah things are easier and also the heart is not just easier but also you get a
sense the mind the heart can get a sense that wow other people are going through that
too then the heart can open up to compassion for others this is hard or
that other friend of mine who a few months ago was going through something similar and I just like yeah yeah I was
checking you know for Facebook while we were wonderful now oh that ouch ouch and your heart opens up
oh that was really so in that way through your personal suffering you open
up to compassion not just for yourself but universally so it's through the personal becomes the
universal for example with compassion similarly with all the other insights with
impermanence things arise and pass away you just keep having you have to keep
noticing seeing in detail yeah it rises and passes away I woke up this morning
oh yeah I was really really upset oh that mind state that heart state has
gone away and then it starts to become Universal everything is impermanent everything is impermanent then the next
time something happens and you're in the midst of fear like ah what if this never ends of everything is simple
I know that I deeply know everything is impermanent so
and impersonal so let's talk about anatas not self in personality you get
to see when you really slow down and you get to see the Mind States you get to
see the sensations in the body they all arise and pass and you have no control when you get to see you have no control
over say aging over
how this body recovers or doesn't recover from say a cut like wow
you can't do this the body is doing this or all the other ways that there is no
governability there is you can start with the body but there's so many different ways to have all of these
insights a gazillion ways to have these insects but they the point I want to
make is it starts with the personal that's the point I want to make I don't want to give a a 24 hour or 48 hour
discourse and all the ways to have these insights because there's so many different ways
but but the point is it starts with the personal insights and
further back pull back a little more starts with having a calm settled mind
that is able to have the insights if if it's the binoculars of all over the
place you cannot have you're just kind of you're in the Whirlwind of a thought
an entangle it won't Sun Tangled laughs stabilize
put your foot down sit down rest calm the body calm the
mind
so so many so many wives so many why wise to do
to practice calming settling the mind
okay so I could continue but you might say okay I'm all right yes
I'm signing up so how do I do this how do I settle
well as I've been intimating and also also as I've been leading in the excuse
me guided meditation it is through enjoying through loving
through finding contentment because when the mind is content
when the heart loves what's happening it doesn't want to go anywhere
think of a hobby you have something you really enjoy doing
you just get absorbed and ours can go by you may not even eat
because you're so absorbed you're loving what you're doing so that's the kind of relationship
cultivate with practice it's not a Grim
Duty I have to sit you know science says 30 minutes a day is good for my health no fall in love with it fall in love
with it that's the only way to do this so
there are different methods so so there are different techniques lots of
different objects for developing concentration for developing collection of the mind and
and different techniques and ways and do this and do that and yet
the ethos the way to approach it all of them is similar so
so I'll talk a little bit about both so
so there are many different concentration objects many different ways to collect the mind
so in the West we tend to
practice with mindfulness of the breath that's our primary object yes familiar
with that one yeah that's that's usually the anchor right we go to the breath
we see thoughts entanglements mother go back to the breath or tune back to the breath yes you're with me yeah
everybody's had instructions on mindfulness of the breath yes okay so that's primarily the the
object however there are 40 different objects
in the visudi Maga which is the path of purification this thousand page manual
two thousand year old manual practice manual which is wonderful then
wonderfully obtuse and great um there are 30 different objects
and um one of them is the breath
and then there are the Brahma vihars the the practice of the heart for example
meta loving kindness and compassion and you know all the four Brahma vihar as
the practice of our muddita vicarious joy and Equanimity those four are some
of the 40 different ways to read the common collect the mind when you sit and
wish yourself well or wish somebody else well and engage really engage Stay Stay
you stay with that practice the Mind collects and settles and becomes happy
then then there are a bunch of other objects that's 10 of them they're called
the casinos and there are basically visualization objects for this practice
and some people actually um they pre they their minds take better
to the visualization object and my favorite visualization object is what is
called the white Casino in fact I taught a an online retreat at IRC at the end of
last year and I'm teaching another one online it's on my website
in beginning of March so so the white casino is a just a basically the color
white and the mind can be can just settle and be absorbed and and find
peace just collecting with a white disc white circle and it becomes expansive
and some people report that it's actually easier for them to connect with that a sense of Purity and calm and
subtleness compared to the breath um so so there are many many different
objects many many different ways for for the settling to happen one thing to to
keep in mind with calming collecting the mind around an object is
the difference between samata practice practice samadhi samata
is the name of the practice samadhi is the state so the practice of collecting the Mind
versus Insight practice also translated as vipassana
these two are a little different so let me decode it for you so with
collecting the mind you keep coming back to the same object
keep coming back when other things happen thoughts Etc you say not now you let them go you let them go you let you
keep coming back to the same object over and over and over again
okay compared to that inside practice
is the mind rests on say
the sensations of the Body for a while sees the three characteristics these
they're rising and passing and and then moves to another object moves to thought sees they're arising and passing Etc
says so so it keeps moving from object to object to object so in the words of
Steve Armstrong concentration practice is like absolute
monogamy you are dedicated to one object alone it's just breath or it's just a white
Casino that's it everything else like it's distractions you're just coming back
in inside practice maybe you start here here's where it
gets so so actually let me share his word so he he calls um
inside practice To Be A Serial monogamy
so your monogamous you give all your attention to one object you know the sensations of the body and then oh maybe
Vaden are feeling tone Oh this is how it's changing and shifting and then maybe thought so they're rising and
passing so you're giving your heart to one object you're really dedicated to it but then another object and another
object another object okay so what tends to get confusing for
Western practitioners hearing this is wait wait a minute that's not how I practice I I start with the breath I'm
just staying with the breath and then I've been taught as a western
practitioner okay then thoughts arise okay maybe I I notice thoughts are rising I pay attention to them a little
bit and then I let them go and I come back to the breath right because that's self familiar for many of you okay so
that that is um called dry vipassana that's
essentially the style that there are many many different styles so it's going a one level deeper
so so let's so there are two let's just for Simplicity say there are two
different ways to practice vipassana and inside practice one way is to spend days weeks months
years practicing samata collecting the mind and when you really really have a
collected mind settled mind then you you practice vipassana right
it's always a precursor right it's always a precursor so always has to happen first okay right that's one way
not taught in the west that's so there are some teachers who teach this way my
teacher peroxide or venerable peroxide a whom I studied with you know you practice the concentration samata until
janas and absorptions you might have happened so really deep states of concentration arise and then only then
you switch to vipassana okay that's one way however in the west the mahasi
method that's mostly taught is kind of interleaved so the past the summer
targets interleaved with the vipassana gets interleaved that's why it's called drive apasana so you start with a little
bit of samadhi you calm and collect the mind right
and then oh thought arises okay now it becomes a fast enough now you actually
go to the thought and you see like oh yes distraction maybe you label it even
yes labeling noting anyone yeah you're like oh yeah that's the kind of thought I'm having planning is self-judgment you
get to see it then so we were still doing vipassana with me now we let go of it and we come
back so we're now doing what we're doing some of the practice right calming the Mind stabilizing it a little bit so that
we have enough stability the next time oh backache oh tight moving tension
right you get to investigate investigate in the body a little bit now you're
doing what then after a while ah the body doesn't
attract your attention this much right the instructions are you let it go you come back to the breath now you're doing
what yes so you see how it's interleaved
yeah whereas in this other style you're just doing like Summit a day and night
and day and night and like after months like okay now we're gonna do vipassana it's just like okay now you're ready now
you're just gonna investigate all all phenomena so
so and having said that it is helpful it is
helpful if your mind is is or heart is is
um drawn to it to take some time in your practice to
settle the mind a little more to just create more settledness through these various practices
so I want to come back to Joy I also want to say because this is so important
so important so this is from ajan suchito
respected monk in in this tradition so about practice of samadhi this is
what he says I think of enjoyment as receiving joy
and samadhi as the art of refined enjoyment
it is the careful collecting of oneself to the joy in the present moment
joyfulness means there is no fear no tension no out to there isn't anything
we have to do about it so there is stillness it's just this
right so so cultivating
samadhi collecting the mind of course there's engagement right you have to
engage but it's not effortful it's enjoyment it's tuning into the joy of
the moment so I have the breath remember I was inviting you to fall in love with the breath you know what is content how
can you enjoy this moment can you relax so relaxing the body is very important
if their body is tight getting it to settle is really hard
here's another quote about the use of pleasure in in calming
collecting the mind this one is from tanisara biku another celebrated monk in this
transition transition and tradition how do you use pleasure
focus on the breath right now of course he's talking about mindfulness of the breath as the object so
focus on the breath right now and see how it feels then experiment with the breath to see
how the way you breathe can produce either pleasure or pain
it may be subtle the difference between the two but it's there we've learned to
desensitize ourselves to this aspect of our awareness so it's going to take a
while to re-sensitize ourselves to begin seeing the patterns this is why we
practice keep coming back to the breath keep coming back to the breath
try to get more sensitive to this area of your awareness more skilled at
learning how to maximize the potential for pleasure Right Here and Now
simply by the way you breathe not only producing pleasure but also maintaining it
after all feelings of pleasure and Rapture are part of the path they are
tucked in the noble hateful path right under right concentration right under
right concentration and as part of the path they may have to be developed and
maintained as the Buddha said this pleasure is blameless
so there's a lot of pleasure and enjoyment to the practice to cultivating
samadhi samata this calm collected mind that for some people starts to get
addicted like oh I want that pleasure like okay let that go that's also impermanent by the kids so much pleasure
and so much calm collectedness which again the point is not to check out in
it but to use it as a basis for our life for our insight for our service for the
way we show up in the world anyway there's a lot more I can say and
and and I think I'm going to end now and and um maybe if you're interested you can
you'll come and I'll teach you about the white Casino online in a few weeks but I think I'll end there there's this this
is endless this is just so so joyous this topic and this cultivation and
sharing it and also just igniting perhaps igniting the the delight and
interest in others it's it's a practice that's been so meaningful to me in my
practice uh both driver passana this interleaving I've done that for many
years before practicing with with my teacher Parkside so
I hope the the reflections today were of service of of
to your practice to your Awakening and let's dedicate the goodness of our practice to all beings everywhere
ah May the goodness of our practice our our Attention our inspiration
our co-created goodness may they serve all beings everywhere
in their goodness and their Awakening may all beings everywhere
be free be awake including ourselves
[Music]
thanks for your attention everyone