welcome welcome nice to see you all seems like the volume is just a little
bit loud it's a little bit echoey can we turn it down just a little bit and then
I have to talk non-stop while you adjust them yeah that sounds good thank you
so happy MLK Day it's a day of service
not just a day off but a day of service and I was thinking like wow what would it be
like if everybody actually did a day of service today something to support their
communities and whatever way they wanted like what a
what how many things might shift if we had a day of Americans
thinking how they might support others and of course part of this practice is
about creating the conditions in which we can import and serve others
and support and serve ourselves without making a distinction necessarily
I do also want to mention about the weather this kind of
sincere wish that I hope all of you are safe and things are going well it's a quite something that here in the Bay
Area right there's some neighborhoods that are like Wahoo all this rain and then there's other neighborhoods you
know just the mudslides some trees falling there's like you know different places having really different
experiences I saw in the news that just not very far from here in the hills in Belmont
there's a big slide wasn't clear to me I think a house maybe slid I don't know but uh
you know those people are having a very different experience than me that lives on the third floor
and I never worry about flooding
so I'm teaching this course on some factors of Awakening
and I was teaching yesterday and the factor is joy that we've been
talking about and you know the students they have some readings to do and like a little talk
and all these kinds of things and one thing that um
I hear my notes about Joy is something that Matthew brand silver said years ago
some of you may know he Matthew Prince or he's a teacher he teaches here on occasion and at The Retreat Center
and he talked about something that uh I just remembered it all these years later
something that you know is a support for the arising of joy and he talked about the joy of being wrong
and you might like wait what did I hear that right but just this recognition that this idea
or this notion that we have to be right or we need to be right
really constricts our lives really constricts our relationships
that's somebody quite some time ago tell me Well Diana
would you I don't remember exactly what it was but it this person said to me would you
rather be right or would you rather have healthy relationships
and I realized that I had this habit of like correcting people like no it's not actually like that it's you know this or
that and quite annoying I'm sure
so method runs over this idea of joy of being wrong
another way to think about it is the joy of learning something new you thought you might have a clear idea
of how something works or how it is and maybe it's not where you want or
whatever it is but then to realize oh actually it's a little bit different
than what I was thinking or maybe it's a lot different
because the truth is this practice is a little bit about the joy of being wrong
I have this idea or this teaching that there's these underlying
[Music] qualities that are the kind of the root of all of
our suffering greed hatred and delusion we could say that delusion right is just
not seen clearly or being completely ignorant of it
and so we're delusional until we're not until we see things more clearly and so in some ways we might say that we
were wrong and then we become right it's another way to say it so the joy of being wrong
but that's Joy is not the topic for tonight maybe it should be
but I want to also talk about this other way in which Joy arises joy and
happiness and this is um from a suit term and I talked about this
maybe last year I don't remember exactly when but just briefly here's a excerpt from this who does
where the Buddha says suppose a person were to take a loan and undertake business and their business
was successful so that they could repay all the money of the old loan and there would remain
enough extra money to maintain a spouse that I'm considering this they would be
glad and full of joy and then it continues suppose a person
were Afflicted suffering and Gravely ill and their food would not agree with them
and their body had no strength but later they would recover from the
Affliction and their food would agree with them and their body would regain strength
that I'm considering this they would be glad and full of joy
so this recognition that being in debt is kind of like burdensome and when you
get out of Dutch there's this this feeling of relief when you're sick and you recover from
that sickness there's this feeling of gladness and happiness or even when you might remember it bring it to mind is
this sense of joy and happiness and I like to read another little
excerpt of a suit again this is um
the Buddha attributed to the Buddha one who removes the anger that has
arisen as one removes with herbs the snakes spreading Venom
that person sloughs off the here and Beyond as a snake says its old worn out
skin this expression sloughs off the here and Beyond here and Beyond is like this one
way we can interpret is this real concern about this and that and this other thing is this a sense of this
papancha like oh all these things that we're worrying about
but to Slough that off as a snake sheds its old worn out skin
one who was cut off greed as if plucking a Lotus growing in a lake
that person sloughs off the here and Beyond as a snake sheds its old worn out
skin so these little vignettes that I've been
pointing to or the joy of being wrong and kind of the happiness and the way that happens
after being the let's see this was um having a loan or being ill some of you
may recognize these are assemblies for the hindrances things that kind of get in the way of our practice
shedding the skin the SE are all pointing to kind of like a letting go
sloughing off shedding what's no longer helpful what's no longer useful
and that not only that that there's a sense of relief afterwards
and I I watched it in order to understand this a little better I watched a video about how snakes shed
their skin it's quite some it's quite a process but
the I watched a video with some snake Handler describing it and he says you know the snakes feel very vulnerable as
they're shedding their skin and but then when they do and it takes some time but when they do they just feel
great they I don't know if we would use the word frisky but uh they feel
better so this idea of letting go
letting go of what's not helpful letting go of what's constricting us
letting go of what doesn't feel like it's supporting us
this is a natural process what I just describe these are natural things
it's a just a falling away of what it's
not needed anymore what isn't helpful it's often this falling away the
shedding happens due to we have like a new understanding
a new way of seeing things or we have this um see them in a way that we didn't
before like oh yeah this doesn't make sense to hold on to anymore
and maybe there's not even that thought maybe there's just this natural letting go
so letting go this integral to this practice of this Buddhist practice and in some way we
might say that all these practices come down to this idea of just letting go letting go
to be sure this idea of nabana Awakening Enlightenment greater Freedom
peace all of these are related to letting go
shedding what's not needed anymore what's not helpful sloughing off what's
not helpful so this idea of naban is to let go thoroughly
completely in a way that's such nothing is left in
fact that there isn't even anybody to let go of anything
but it to have the the confidence or the trust to do this when we so often with
our lives and certainly our society promotes this it's so much about like
kind of acquiring and getting having more and more
so this practice is encouraging us to look the to have this opposite movement
and I'd like to highlight here that this is a natural process it's
not something that is uh gets wrenched out of our hands while we're screaming
holding on to it something like that because one of the things it's not so
much about what we lose when we're letting go it's more about what we gain
and I've been pointing to some of the joy and the happiness but there's also
the sense of relief or unburdening lightening up or something that just
feels better this is a silly example but this is kind
of the way that I was thinking about that the other day I was in my kitchen and I needed to get something out of a
drawer and you know there's something like stuck in the drawer just because it was had too much stuff in it
like oh I don't need two of these okay I can donate this I can donate this and then you know just getting rid of things
that aren't needed and now the drawer just opens readily
it's kind of like that like things that are just oh this gets in the way
this can maybe support somebody else or may have some other
use but it doesn't need to be in this drawer right now
that's kind of the feeling I have this idea of letting go but we might feel uncomfortable with
this idea of letting go certainly because in some ways that might sound a lot like
uh renunciation which generally we're not so keen on or maybe it's this idea of
surrender which generally we're not so keen on I think of Americans that we don't
really like these ideas necessarily maybe because there's a sense of
deprivation or maybe a lack of safety if we were to let go maybe we would feel
vulnerable maybe we feel like all these things that we're holding on to literal
objects as well as views about ourselves about the world
maybe we have this sense that they make us safe they help us keep the world orderly and
predictable and in a way that makes us feel more comfortable
but something that I um I think I heard this from Gail franstal first I'm not sure
some years ago I heard this and it this also really stayed with me what if we kind of said of this idea of letting go
sometimes we might see this word giving up but that doesn't sound so and so uh inviting either like
to give up so I was like that definitely feels like surrender but what if we think about like give
up as in higher Like to Move It Up
that's the I think the origin of this expression is to like put up on the
altar so to give it up is in this way to maybe as an offering to
and the service of having a better life and the service of
what opening up to whatever might be available and for no longer holding so tightly to things
maybe it's an act of generosity to give up give up some of our
strongly held ideas or views about what it means to be successful or
what it means to be a good person or what it means to be a good practitioner
whatever it might be
but this we're not just letting go of I talked about nabana as letting go of
everything but this is a process it's a it's a path that we practice
and then we walk along and the path of so much of it is about kind of letting
go shedding what's not needed but it's always in the service of what's wholesome what's
helpful what's skillful not
what causes more suffering it's more to move in to help support
these wholesome states of Mind beneficial states of Mind spacious states of mind
maybe we could say like in the service of creating this uh inner treasure or
this inner wealth maybe we're exchanging some of these
things objects or views that we thought were going to make us
wealthy some kind of way but maybe we might still feel this inner
whole or incompleteness or something so there's some of this giving away giving
up letting go that really supports this inner wealth
these inner Treasures certainly joy and happiness are part of those
and we need joy and happiness all of us do
not only do we need it it's an integral part of the path absolutely integral
path of practice is not always easy first Noble Truth we're pointing to duka
this path cannot be just about duka duka duka right there needs to be joy and
happiness too otherwise we can't really open to the dukkha The Suffering The
difficulties it has to be a balance has to be wholesome otherwise we can't do it humans can't
just be with duka all the time
so the Buddha never says that we have to give away or renounce our wealth our
personal possessions instead we're letting go of that which is not useful
for letting go of things that don't serve us the obvious ones are
manifestations of greed hatred and delusion but those show up in so many ways that
sometimes we don't even quite recognize them
so this is this letting go is maybe it's part of the practice
and it's a gradual process it's a gradual process to unlearn a a
lifetime of clinging and craving I feel holding on
to and one way that this might have been
Gill so that I saw him give this example maybe some of you have seen him do this
too the way that we're talking about letting go we could give this example is um
with the striker here one way to let go is to drop it
so you're just let it go let go make a large sound that's a bonus
but there's another way and just to undo our fist we still have it that our relationship
to it has changed we're no longer really holding on to it so if we're doing this where we're
letting it go maybe that's helpful and skillful but
sometimes that feels like a shoving away whereas this ways we're just letting go of the clinging
might still have a striker for just not clinging
so really this is the movement this opening the fist
anything and everything we could say that this whole practice is
to help us do that to learn how to do that
and so there's this poem from rosemary traumer she's a wonderful poet I just appreciate
her so much she's also a practitioner and she talks about this a little about
this short little poem and it's called a little pep talk
and it goes like this the swirling Ash doesn't try to become
log again the flying leaves don't attempt to return to the tree
The Girl Can't untwist her genome back into separate strands
the flower and the bread can't return to the sack and can't undo the kneading of
hands in all things lives in memory of letting
go and the chance to transform into what it can't know
what do you say to that heart good self what do you say to that
so this I think Rosemary trauma is trying to give herself a little talk recognizing that she knows that things
are better with letting go this recognition that everything that's
possible or exists now is the result of a certain amount of letting go
bread coming from flower Falling Leaves coming from trees Etc but letting go is also
the process of going forward to
so along these lines um agara it's a another Dharma teacher I just saw
this title of his Dharma talk if I didn't listen to the talk I just looked
at the title and I thought this title was great he said the title is from let go to
let's go so instead of this emphatic you know let
go something that you have to do is this movement of let's go it's part
of like this movement forward like let's let's go to a place where there's less clinging
more freedom so
maybe I'll just say that this letting go of this maybe the
we might call it a compulsion to really cling onto things
so it's not so much the objects themselves that we're worried about
but it's a clinging in the holding
and this includes letting go of a sense of self
so as we as our life unfolds we have these
outdated Notions of ideas of Who We Are
to let go of those they're no longer accurate
as we age and mature and grow and learn we might have learned things when we
were young When We Were Young that aren't so helpful for us anymore so can we let go of some of those ideas of how
we should be or how we shouldn't be or how we are or how we aren't
but then this practice is pointing to something even deeper just to even
let go of the idea of any self
whatsoever this sense of a self that's at the
center of everything feels like the whole world you know our
world feels it can feel like there's this permanent stable steady entity at
the center around which everything is circulating
if you really look it turns out it's not there
it's these momentary ideas oh it feels like there's a center there but then when you go to look at it
it's not there oh it's over here and then you go to look at it over there and oh it's not
there either this is often makes more sense
if often it's like some meditative experiences when the mind is really
quiet you can see this more clearly but it's maybe similar to this idea of
um when we're doing something that we really love hobby that we really love
whatever it might be knitting gardening gaming whatever it is
notice how there isn't a strong sense of self there there's just whatever it is you live to be doing drawing sketching
playing the guitar whatever it is it's just that activity
it's really an enjoyable experience because there isn't this sent this sense
of self in the center so we all have these experiences and
what this practice is pointing to is the freedom that we experience like in those
flow States but to have that all the time
and to feel the the freedom of that
and to be sure some things are worth holding on to
and some things are worth having in our life and are appropriate to have
relationships and values all kinds of things
but it it's this movement of just holding them like this with an open hand instead of like this
so again the emphasis is more on this movement as opposed to having to get rid
of any particular object or even our views I'm sure we have views
but what is it like to to have a view of this is this is what makes sense to me
right now this is my current understanding the way that I understand it seems like this
that's very different then I'm right and you're wrong to say like you know my understanding is
this is what makes the most sense or this is my provisional thinking can't see any other way but this is this
is the way that I'm holding it right now or what I'm thinking right now
so I'm talking about letting go in terms of like this Buddhist practice but to be sure letting go
is essential for just whether you're a practitioner or not just for a happy life
and we let go all the time we let go of plans when the weather changes the
person we were going to meet no longer can do it you know we let go of that we change our opinions on things
our preferences I used to really dislike ketchup now I
think ketchup is okay [Laughter] it just happens right
but of course this is uh in daily life we are letting go of
things but often we don't notice and we do this right just effortlessly
that's when we have new information or new understandings and so this is
pointing to the same thing and so
one thing that we could do in our daily life to support kind of
this movement towards letting go is to just let go of the clinging
for short moments oh
I think that um there's that ice cream in the freezer
or have this idea of like okay I really want this we have this desire and then clinging to this idea of
think that will definitely be a source of lasting happiness if I have more ice cream
but just say well what if I just let go of that idea right now
I have the desire but it's okay it can be there but I don't have to do anything with it so we're not holding on to it
tightly it's a little bit uncomfortable at the
beginning maybe but then notice that the Mind state it feels
kind of like strong and wholesome after doing that
maybe ice cream is too big of a
too big of a place to start because ice cream is often Associated when we don't
feel well we want to or have emotionally don't feel well we want to eat ice cream so maybe maybe we don't start there but
start where something that's easy I'm just like okay I'm gonna I want this
and maybe just to say maybe I don't need it right now something simple
maybe a cup of tea here at that moment like I'll wait a snack something like
this and so it's just one moment at a time
we're not saying that you forever you can't have a cup of tea or ice cream or a snack again but just to notice how
does it feel to have maybe like this desire and want
to hold on and instead to kind of lean back and say I don't think that I will
this moment I can next moment but this moment I'm not going to
and it's just like this it's just small moments
one after the other or maybe it's a moment of not clinging and then there's
a moment of clinging the next but just to notice how the mind feels
when we've been able to soften or let go some of that clinging and this can be a tremendous support
I'm talking about how the joy and happiness after letting go of these
things the joy of being wrong or when you're no longer sick
getting better or like a snake shedding its skin
but see for yourself what does it feel like when you do a
little bit of letting go and notice how it feels in the mind in
the body and the Heart and let that knowledge be a support for you
this is a gradual practice we've been cultivating the habit of getting
chances are most of our lives so this is definitely a gradual practice it takes time
it's not a straight linear
process requires us to let go of some of our allegiances to things that aren't so
helpful that might be pleasurable that's a process
but maybe we can choose to be a little bit
more skeptical about these things that we're holding on to do they will it really make me happy
in a way that's supportive and fulfilling
helps build the life that I want to build the direction I want to go
so this idea of letting go
maybe not just letting go but recognizing the the relief the joy that
happiness that's on the other side of that associated with it
so maybe I'll stop there and open it up to see if there are any questions or
comments
it's perfectly fine oh there we go behind you Jim foreign
my while we while you were speaking um I was thinking about
the relationships as something that is difficult to
you know shed but there's sometimes that urge to want
to shed certain relationships and things like that but
um I don't know how to navigate
the not letting go versus pushing away
um as well as thinking about
how that impacts other people as well so you know if I'm not clinging
is that something that affects other people in a negative way
does that cause suffering or
I guess I just I just think so much of
the way that we Express care and love is
by this clinging or at least in our culture right right you're you're here I have you
and trying to trying to navigate that better to hold it this way
um rather than than
saying it's hard to even put into words
um
even just holding sometimes doesn't seem like enough for relationships I will say that and when
you feel like I either need to hold on or push away and
I don't understand how you're supposed to determine that kind of Direction um so is your course so is your question
so to just be like this open-handed way yeah as opposed to
anything else right Holding On which either is bringing clothes or pushing away both of them are kind of like a
little bit of a yes but it's so much harder when it's in a
relationship because there's another person involved with it yeah and so if you're not you know it's
kind of like a tug rope that both of us are holding on to when we're supporting each other but if you let go then that
person falls yeah yeah it's quite something to just love
it's love Yeah and right and in relationships if one person right
exactly as you said starts to shift then of course it affects the other person and there might need to be some
renegotiating right maybe it doesn't even happen with words but uh this because often what happens when I need
to tell you this so I think we all know this that when where there's a little bit of holding then there's also there's
this little bit of well I want you to behave in this particular way and my preferences are that you do
it this way and not stop doing that thing that I think don't like and but um
part of this of to do this is to let go of that as well so they feel the freedom
but can they feel the warmth also so this is not easy right to re
defined renegotiate something in relationships but there's something really beautiful that happens when
people feel like you love them you care about them you see them you're with them
and you support them without insisting demanding that things be a certain way
people really Blossom under that right we all do does this I don't know if I'm answering
your question or not but but I feel like he did so okay
thank you does anybody else have a question
I think maybe more of a comment than a question um when you first started talking about letting go I thought of like subtracting
or getting what oh giving you know getting having less excess but then I started to think of it as a positive
maybe you let go of negative thoughts or or self-perceptions and it's actually you're gaining more more abundance of
things that you know make life a little bit more worthwhile and whatnot fantastic I love it thank you thank you
yep I could have said that too I could have kind of pointed to that letting go of negative thoughts but there's so many
things that we're holding on to that we're pretty convinced are gonna are really important that later turned out
not to be so important so maybe um not just the things that are negative thoughts but all kinds of things
but thank you for saying that I appreciate that
I don't know if our friends on the okay
okay thank you for your talk uh Diana I heard a talk Yesterday by a Tibetan
teacher about joy and uh he talked about
looking at the blockages to Joy I was wondering if so that's sort of
been resonating with me because sometimes on here talks about Joy
there can be a little bit like oh I should be I should be having an experience of joy and I'm not
and you know what's wrong with me
so do you have any things that you'd like to say about what blocks Joy
do you have an idea Jim of what blocks Joy well on a tube tin does and I think it
resonated which was um aversion
um yeah I'd say a version I would say the idea that you're supposed to have joy
that that's oppressive to feel like oh I'm supposed to be happy that doesn't make us feel happy right something like
this these ideas that we should be a particular way but you have more in the list
well um
so maybe you could talk a little bit about how does one
support the values that they have in a way that isn't clinging
you know I mean because sometimes we're going to hear about well just let go you know it's it's it's that but
um there do seem to be things that I value
that I'm willing to I don't know if I'd say fight for but
put effort into uh upholding
so how does how does that fit into letting go
and yet still having uh values particularly about
qualities that we cultivate in the practice Yeah Yeah
thank you for asking us because that is kind of a danger in this talk that I'm going like letting go letting go and you can feel like oh it's just this passive
just let go of everything and then you're a lump of something
yeah so it's in the service of what is wholesome and helpful and skillful
so I think the values that you have like we can use as a North star and the
letting go is to help what helps move towards that North Star so and some of the values of course are
maybe we might think of some of the parames or you know generosity or
loving kindness mindfulness the settleness of Mind honesty these types
of things so as opposed to grabbing on to the experience of them
using them as a direction and have our actions
go in that direction support that is that helpful at all using this kind of a different language as a North star as
opposed to something that you stop holding on to
yeah I think so so yeah thank you I I kind of appreciate how um maybe that that's maybe the
danger of a talk of that like this is this feeling of
like there's nothing to hold on to which turns out to be true but that's not
it's not uh what I um
but that's so that some like it can be a meditative experience where you can see like oh things things aren't as solid as
I thought that they were and that's kind of odd to talk about and it can be off-putting and and and comfortable to
talk about but this does sometimes arise as meditative experience and that's perfectly fine
part of the way part of the practice but thank you for your question I
appreciate that
okay oh okay so maybe one do you do you can do if you can uh I'll give you a
quick answer yeah I think letting go you know for all
this it's you know easier said than done I think the part of it is you know there may be times I feel like if I let go it
will be an empty hand the results and I think you know when you can go
for Time After Time with an empty hand and you know you I get caught in the the train of thought
where I'm just like okay so what what are the possibilities with this empty hand now
I don't see any possibilities this is why this is why I'm clinging to this thing so you know I guess maybe I can probably
answer my own question but it's like you know it's like what in this path we're on you know do we cultivate that
almost like this courage I'm sitting with the word courage now to kind of open the hand open or even the thing
might fly away that I'm clinging to and you know and that everything will be okay you know that's kind of the big question
I'm sitting with right now so I don't know if you have any thoughts I do I have a few thoughts one is
General letting goes that are just happening already when you're letting go of plans that you made or are you
letting go of a view that you had and you get some more information like oh wait oh that turns out not to be quite
right just notice those and you'll just start to see oh yeah this is a natural thing that you're doing already
we're just cultivating it and maybe broadening it so that's one thing a
second thing it's so much easier to let go if you have a feeling of abundance
as opposed to lack what supports a feeling of abundance turns out to be generosity in whatever
way if it's with your resources time money your generosity giving people a
benefit of the doubt whatever way Jen this is part of the reason why generosity is a kind of a fundamental
teaching is because it does gives a sense of abundance this feeling of like
oh yeah but I don't know to share it really touches us and affects us so
that also will support a sense of letting go and then I had a third one that just
slipped my mind let's see if it'll come back but some of them or you know it doesn't
have to be these grand gestures and as I said this is a long process it's a practice it definitely is
but just notice when unburdening happens
we tend to be dismissive of these things because we're busy trying to get something else and we're not even
noticing all the shedding that we're naturally doing but once you notice that and notice kind
of like how some of these um these suited quotes like the snake shedding its skin how it just feels like
oh what a relief but maybe sometimes this relief is really subtle
so it requires a little more pain attention to and I keep on talking wishing that that third thing would come
back into my mind but I'm afraid it hasn't so well I do with these two
okay so we're a few minutes after the hour so thank you
and if you'd like you're welcome to come back you to come up here and talk with me but otherwise I wish you all a
wonderful evening thank you