anyone welcome back my name is May Elliott and this is day three of our
five day series on the 5 hindrances so for those who struggle being present
during meditation I found that studying the five hindrances it's really an essential practice for understanding why
it is that we're losing presence you know what is it exactly that's clouding the mind and inhibiting our ability to
show up and what's often the case is that one of
the five hindrances is present um the mind gets stirred up in thought you got the root desire ill will
restlessness or doubt might be fueling the thinking mind or maybe you were just so sleepy and
foggy that we just can't be present and then maybe sloth and torpora are clouding the mind
so today we'll be focusing on sloth and torper also known as sleepiness so in
the meditation we'll play around with the classic antidote to sleepiness which is cultivating energy
so to begin please find your meditation posture
and to uh to bring forth energy in the practice it
can be really helpful to have an upright posture sometimes if we're really cozy and
comfortable and maybe leaning back on the back of a chair and a couch it's
really easy to get sleepier um that's a prime recipe for falling
asleep so um see if you can find an upright posture that's both alert and relaxed
stupid
I'm starting with a few deep breaths
and this signal for the body to land and show up
so we'll take a little time to [Music] um to connect with
with the present moment uh by making contact with our primary anchor so maybe
that's the breath maybe it's a global sense of the body posture sitting maybe
it's the soundscape this takes some time to land in your body with your sense Gates
seeing what it's like to be here
having connected to a felt sense of the present moment
let's take stock of the energy in the body kind of doing an energy inventory
so you might just check to see whether the energy is high or whether it's low or somewhere in between
on one end of the end of the spectrum we have a very energetic maybe excited
high energy on on the other end low heavy tired energy falling asleep
energy
so what's the energy like in your body and mind right now
foreign
we might find that the body is alert but the mind is sluggish
or sometimes the other way around where the mind is sluggish or dull but the
body is somewhat awake there's energy in the body so we're just exploring to see what we
find
so during the meditation I'll offer some antidotes to sleepiness to sloth and
torpor but even if your energy is high or well regulated even if you're not tired
during this meditation you might still just play around with some of the energy
practices that I'm offering um just so that you get a body memory of
how to do this
so to begin one of our classic antidotes to sleepiness is uh just to sit up
straighter like I mentioned at the beginning of the meditation if you find the mind getting too sluggish
just bring a little bit more energy into the posture a little bit more space between the
bones of the spine a little more lift in the back of the neck
and that can bring in a little more energy
another way to do this is by opening the eyes rather than meditating with the eyes closed let some light in
and it's fine if you want to change your posture or close your eyes again we're just trying these on a little bit here
you don't need to do each thing for the entire meditation
and we won't do these next ones now but it can also be helpful to stand up if
you're really falling asleep you can stand up and that's actually fine to do during the meditation now if you'd like
um others that we won't do include splashing cold water on the face
or going for a brisk walk these are energizers for our Bluetooths
you also might try Wheeling down the body if you're feeling sleepy
taking off the sweatshirt or opening a window
so if you'd like to try that you can see how that impacts energy in the body
and you don't need to you don't want to create too much movement
so these are all physical ways that we can change the energy in our practice
going forward I'll offer some some options to keep you still and seated in
your meditation things you can do with your eyes closed and your typical meditation posture
and for this you might bring to mind something that inspires you about
practice this is a reflection
often that which inspires us brings forth energy
so what brings forth energy for you maybe it's the final goal of Liberation
freedom from suffering the Deep wish to be free
or maybe there's a wish to be in service in the world living by The bodhisattva Vow
to save all beings from suffering
or maybe to be kinder to your family or to be less anxious at work
all of these are valid reasons for practice
so taking a moment to connect with what inspires you to practice what's
your motivation
so can you feel the way that this reflection brings a little bit more oomph to the breathness
a little more effort oh yeah there's a reason that I'm sitting here doing this
now a reason to bring the effort in
another way to bring forth energy in our practice is to increase the Curiosity
and bringing bringing forth this factor of Investigation so if we can become curious that can
really increase increase the energy here increase the effort
so you might get curious about noticing the exact moment the breath turns from an inhale to an
exhale and from an exhale to an inhale
you could be curious about the shape the breath takes maybe at Billows at the beginning and
then it gets small at the end maybe it's a thin narrow short breath
maybe it's smooth and even for the entire inhale
or choppy and staccato what's the shape and texture of the
breath
is the inhale longer than the exhale or the other way around
so this practice of cultivating curiosity which brings forth energy can
be done at any of the scent stores you can do it with a felt sense of the
breath how we just did where we can feel any other part of the body that brings forth interest for us
we can do it with a soundscape
maybe sensing into the nearest sounds
maybe sounds from one's own body
the sound of the breath
maybe sounds from digestion in the belly
or sounds in the room
and what are the far away sounds
bird calls water City sounds
can you catch each one
so now for a little creativity and playfulness
we can use the imagination to increase curiosity
so you might imagine for a moment
that you are inhabiting a body that's not your own Maybe
maybe you're an alien that was sent from space and you are inhabiting a human
suit to wear for the day so this is not something you'll find in
this utas um so we can employ our imagination to um
to bring forth curiosity in our practice so maybe this is your first time on
Earth and you're responsible for really getting to know what it's like to be in
a human body so can you explore the present moment
from that place
your first time being human what's it like to have senses
what's it like to feel so you can take the last few minutes of the meditation exploring in this way or
doing whatever other practice is supportive for you for cultivating curiosity
May the beneficial energy of our time together
benefit all being so they may be happy healthy safe and free from suffering
all right welcome back folks for those just arriving I'm mate Elliott
and we're continuing our series on the five hindrances
so um when I was a teenager one of my favorite things to do was to go
backpacking um we would go deep into the back country
carrying everything we needed on our backs and we'd hike out to remote lakes and
mountains and this part of this experience we needed to hike from water source to water source to refill our
water bottles and sometimes this would be from a tiny spring or a creek or a large lake
then we carried these little these little hand pumps that filtered out bacteria
I remember many peaceful afternoon sitting by a creek deep in the forest pumping water into my bottle
and the filters were pretty good but if the water we found was too murky or
filled with silt or too too overgrown with moss then the filters wouldn't be
able to do their job and we couldn't drink the water um so we really needed our water to be
somewhat clear in order to sustain us and to continue on our journey
similarly you know the Buddha compared the five hindrances to a pond with
unclear water so in an unafflicted mind the water's clear but in a mind that's afflicted by
the hindrances the water is unclear so the doubtful mind was compared to murky water you can't see through it
it's not the Sleepy mind is like water overgrown with moss
the restful the Restless mind is like stirred up water the mind with ill will
is boiling water as though a lot with anger and the desirous mind is compared
to water filled with colorful dye or a shade that's uh so enchanting it can
entrance us you know we're drawn to it so our mind is a little like the water
we'd find on these backpacking trips when the mind is clear it can be life-giving more like fresh spring water
if the mind's too agitated if it's too murky too overgrown then it's not clear
and we can't be nourished by it so today we'll focus on the third
hindrance sloth interpreter yeah now lots of these terms
um were translated when Victoria was Queen of England so the term sounds a little archaic but all sloth and torpor
really refers to is sleepiness other ways it might appear in our practice are
um and these words might be more resonant for you drowsiness fatigue lethargy
illness Etc um and in our practice we might come across
just a run-of-the-mill sleepiness where the body just um physiologically needs more sleep and
this technically isn't sloth and torpor it's not necessarily a hindrance if we're just physically needing more sleep
or under slept so then torp as a hindrance occurs when there's a
psychological cause to it for example boredom or indifference disinterest
complacency hopelessness so these are all things that can lead to
a dull mind that can lead to a mind that wants to go to sleep and I should also note that sloth
typically refers to a mental sleepiness and torpora to a physical tiredness
um and sloth interpreza hindrance are products of an attitude we have
so for example during daily life we accrue stories about ourselves and we
often replay them like blockbuster hits in our meditation
during meditation as the Mind learns to let go of these movie reruns sometimes
the lack of entertainment makes the Mind get sleepy um so as we develop a taste for the the
peace and Stillness at first it can it can register as boring and sleepiness
can arise we're not used to um the screen with a movie projected on
it so this would be an example of sloth and torpor resulting from a psychological Source rather than a lack
of sleep um or sometimes the energy expended from replaying the blockbuster hits has
exhausted us physically and mentally so we experience sloth and torper as as a result of writing the intensity of the
highs and little off lows often there's a Kim's notion in the body when when
we're riding the highs and lows and that can actually make us tired also
or sometimes we experience sloth and torpor because the mind doesn't want to experience a certain State
such as grief disappointment or self-judgment so in the same way that the Buddha
compared sloth and torpert to a pond overgrown with moss sometimes we want to
pull the metaphorical covers over our head and go to sleep rather than feel a
certain difficult emotion so the sleepiness actually functions as a strategy of avoidance
so as we move into this third hindrance of sloth interpreter we can see that it's really an energetic State you know
that's what we explored in our meditation the fourth hindrance of restlessness is also energetic so we
could say these two um or kind of two sides of the spectrum sloth and torber presenting as low
energy and restlessness muffin presenting as high energy
when I was sitting early my early meditation Retreats I had a lot of
sleepiness it was a lot of like the routine
um and this was really unpleasant for me and I spent a lot of time fighting it
um but what I learned through that was that much much of the suffering with sleepiness was actually my resistance to
it my sense that the the sleepiness shouldn't be there so for me it was actually a version that
was making the experience a suffering State sleepiness itself is karmically neutral it's not bad
um so what was happening for me is I was having a multiple hindrance attack the combination of sleepiness followed by
aversion let's go on to take just a little detour to mention how a version crops up in relationship to the other
hindrances um because the hindrances themselves are
often unpleasant in addition to the primary hindrance like sleepiness it's
not uncommon to have a version arise so if you can have our version arise with any of the hindrances it can arise even
in relationship to aversion so a version to a version like we're trying to get rid of our anger
and this is one of the reasons I call a version the tag along hindrance because it often
tags along with the others so as you practice with all of the hindrances no
notice if there's an attitude like oh no this shouldn't be happening or this
sleepiness is ruining my meditation a lot of my mind is so Restless there's
too much thinking I should know better often we when we see the aversion clearly we can begin to reorient and
learn to relate to the initial hindrance with more patience and kindness
so all to say you don't need to resist sleepiness or get aversive to it instead
can you befriend your sleepiness you can just make you can make friends with the
peaceful State it's a tranquil State that's not a bad thing and you can just bring mindfulness to that tranquil state
we can continue to be with the breath from a tired place
and it's fine if there are times when the mind isn't crystal clear if a period of meditation is is sleepy
then just be sleepy Buddha we shouldn't abandon a meditation
session because of sleepiness and it's a great training to be sleepy
because we will always have sleepy moments in our life so how can we learn how to be with them in a skillful way
come on so again the basic instruction for
sleepiness is to recognize it and we've talked about this practice each day so
far and we'll continue to so first we recognize the Sleep sleepiness and then we practice feeling it the second step
of feel so recognize and feel that's our primary practice for all the hindrances
um now for um while sleepiness I find it's actually easier to recognize than the other
hindrances when we feel sleepiness and we actually sense it in the present
moment I really want to emphasize something that I pointed to a lot in the meditation which is curiosity so if we
can sense more experience with curiosity that really turns up the dial on energy
so curiosity raises energy so that's that's what I really suggest when you
recognize and feel and the second step of getting to know the sleepiness with
curiosity feeling it with Curiosity has actually been revolutionary in my
practice with this hindrance sleepiness has actually become very interesting to
me so just as an example of some of the things that I would get curious about in
my my sloth and torper practice um sometimes I explore where is the
sleepiest spot in my entire body you know I'd find the epicenter of the
sleepiness and sometimes it might be the epicenter might might be right behind my
left thigh and if I go to that spot oh I dip out and if I kind of move away from
that spot in the body sometimes I'd be able to maintain the energy a little longer
or I might see if I could find the exact moment the mind slips into a sleep
States so that that crossover from awake to asleep in that first moment of
um a shift in state or I might check to see if I can I
notice if I fall asleep on an in-breath or an out breath or if I'm counting my breath from one to
ten um where do I lose track am I falling asleep
on breath two or do is it you know maybe I'm there for breaths one through five
and then I lose track around six and seven so these
are just all different ways that I found to to explore the experience um and and what I found is sometimes the
mind is just way too heavy uh too dull to notice any of that and then sometimes
there's other flavors of sleepiness where um there's a tiredness in the mind and there is that falling asleep but
it's a lighter feeling and it's um I'm more able to explore what's happening
there so you can just play around with these and see what you discover those are always just to to bring some
curiosity towards what it is that you're feeling and what you're noticing
so as mentioned um many times today um the antidote for sloth interpreter is
energy during the meditation I mentioned a few but just so you can hear them again if you're sleepy try opening your
eyes sitting up straighter taking a few deep breaths um if you were on Retreat and intending
to be sitting for a long time you might get up and go for a Brisk wash walk or
Splash cold water on the face um and if you need to go take a nap
there's no crime in napping one thing that was really helpful for me was making the bot the body colder so rather
than bundling up in a cozy way in the meditation hall or in my room sitting in
a T-shirt If the room is cool or opening the window and that brings my energy
right back up but if you're someone where you think
that it might be defensive sleep or you're you're becoming sleepy so then you don't
have to feel something or if you maybe if you just notice the pattern of sleeping is happening a lot you might
ask yourself is there something underneath this you just drop in that question is there
something underneath this um and that can at times reveal whether you know is there is there something
else that I'm feeling here and that can reveal what's going on unveiling any
underlying emotion or feeling that the sleepiness is masking and then lastly as
with all the hindrances notice when the sleepiness passes you know notice when those those clouds
clear and The Sun Shines again when the Mind perks up from the sleepiness and
there's energy that returns notice when the mind is bright
so just a few more notes on the attitude in meditation uh with this with the
hindrances um the Buddha was visited by hindrances up
through the night that led to his Awakening so it's not something to be so hard on ourselves about no need to judge
yourself for having hindrances instead we can relate to them as valuable Messengers that have come to teach us
you know can we respect our hindrances as teachers our role is to meet them not
as a diversion From the Path but as the path itself we can think of the
hindrances as whatever it is that we're dealing with we can think of that hindrance as the next stepping stone on
the path so when we we can meet a hindrance with
um with recognition with curiosity with patience we're simultaneously
cultivating a wholesome state so this isn't something going wrong when you can be present with a hindrance
so many wholesome qualities are being cultivated seeing a hindrance can actually bring
joy and Delight so working with the hindrances is cultivating these
beautiful qualities so today if you find yourself getting
sleepy rather than immediately reaching for the cup of coffee maybe just postpone the
coffee for a few minutes to explore what sleepiness is like what can you recognize and feel it can you get
curious about it how do you cultivate energy um is there a mental state causing the
sleepiness such as boredom when I was in high school doing my math homework I was sitting in my desk chair
often before I knew it I'd find myself waking up with my head on the desk so
you can guess how I felt about math in high school so clearly my attitude during that activity put me right to
sleep um what does sleepiness show up for you is the sleepiness serving as a mask to
block an emotion so there's plenty ways of it to explore with this and I hope that you uh you
enjoy it now you've had just enough sloth interpret today today that you
have the opportunity to cultivate all sorts of wholesome states of Mind in response thank you so much everyone
have a lovely day