so good morning hello
good afternoon for those of you elsewhere and
good evening so
in preparation for this meditation practice
who I think a wonderful principle for engaging in meditation
is to have some confidence in the instruction what we're what
you're doing in meditation to have some confidence that what you're
doing in meditation is wholesome it's healthy it's a good thing to do
and then to do it wholeheartedly
and wholeheartedly does not mean you know to make superhuman effort to strain or any kind of way
it can mean to give yourself over to the activity so that that's all you're doing
almost as you give yourself over to the activity so fully that you become the
activity almost or you know your self-consciousness and self-conscious
concerns Fall Away concerns about other things in other places other times
Falls away and it's akin to doing a hobby or reading a book or
playing a musical instrument or involved in maybe sports or play of some kind
where you give yourself over fully to the activity and that's part of why it's so refreshing it's kind of like all the
stresses of Life are preoccupations of life fall away and you're just kind of doing
the activity you're fully becoming the activity almost because you're give yourself to it
and it's possible to do this with meditation to give yourself over to to being
mindful to being present for breathing present for your body Here and Now
to enter into almost like you're entering into a new world
for the period of the meditation and you enter into that world fully
you step into it with leaving nothing behind
and so there's a kind of self-forgetting that can happen in a wholehearted effort
or this healthy kind of absorption or engagement in what we're doing
and um and it's possible with meditation and the deeper one goes in meditation the
more that meditation has that flavor that characteristic that giving ourselves that we kind of
there's a self-forgetting um you know all the different ways
self-conscious ways we can be in favor of fully being here
so to begin this wholehearted effort
to assume care take it to care in your meditation
posture so that you're doing it in some wholehearted way
like this is the posture that in which you're going to be not only alert than
aware mindful but you're going to have a posture that
manifest that engagement that alertness people people sitting in a chair or
sitting the floor it might mean sitting with a straighter back
sitting in such a way that the whole torso feels alert present
at a relaxed attention
if you're laying on your back or laying down to it
there might be ways of aligning your body maybe so it's more aligned more centered
that also gives you a feeling of being more attentive
maybe pulling up the knees if the legs are straight out or maybe
with your elbows on the you know being supported by whatever you're in bed or couch or floor have
your forearm pointing to the ceiling or both forearms pointing to the ceiling
so that there's some effort and engagement it could be adjusting the upper back so
that the chest somehow feels more open
and maybe the shoulders a little bit kind of can
be turned down and back along the back
in whatever posture you have to close your eyes
and take a few moments to appreciate that the
the meditation Temple the temple the
Sanctuary for meditation is this body
and to enter into this body where else would you be
sometimes we're in our thoughts that take us away from any
direct connect connection to our body
taking a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing as you exhale
taking a deep inhale and maybe on the exhale saying the word here
as you settle into enter into here and now
and then letting your breathing return to normal
to further relax the body and mind
and as you relax the body and mind on the exhale
let it be a kind of slipping in to the body
relaxing and settling into this body
as the playground as the temple
as the instrument musical instrument you're going to play
and then entering into the world of breathing
they call it a world of breathing is that the body's experience of breathing it's
multifaceted many Sensations come into play parts of
the body different parts of the body move as you breathe
breathing is connected to our emotional life
to the ways that we're thinking and to enter into kind of a curiosity
and simplicity
to be with the breathing whatever way it is
whether being with is so complete there's no room for judging anything or
wanting anything things don't have to be different
just this breath
so fully with this inhale that there is no future and past
and how we think or imagine just the inhale by itself
without any comparison to what it should be like
wholeheartedly being mindful
of how it is
allowing it to be as it is and you just
aware
the exhale experience of exhaling with no future
and past no concern about
trying to do something or get anywhere getting concentrated
just the Simplicity of entering into the world of one exhale
allowing it to be as it is so fully in the breath and in the exhale
there's no room for judging it or wanting it be different
whether it's comfortable or uncomfortable
makes no difference for the attention that attends
to the body breathing
if you find yourself thinking notice how that takes you away from
breathing from the body and see if you can reverse the direction
of entering into the body and breathing
giving yourself fully over to the simple activity of breathing
to being mindful of what is Here and Now
foreign
and then the last couple of minutes of this setting can you in some way
surrender into the practice of presence attention Here
and Now as if this is the most important thing
to do a caring for oneself caring for the
world even through being fully present to your experience
not straining but giving yourself over to being attentive
so fully that self-concern falls away
perhaps more often than we realize
self-concern is a source of stress
tension suffering
to drop self-concern in front of instant
for instead to live fully present here in our experience
and experience a happiness and freedom from that self-concern
and maybe realizing some people all over the world
suffer because of their self-preoccupation
attachments and wants and diversions
and to wish for all beings
to be free from that form of self-concern self-preoccupation
which is stressful and unhelpful
may all beings be happy
may they be safe
from painful self-preoccupation
may they experience the peace
when stressful self-concern has fallen away
may they be free
from all the attachments related to self oneself
may all beings be happy
[Music]
so thank you thank you for spending this time together
foreign
talk on compassionate action and um
that kind of that the focus of the talk is compassionate action for its own sake
compassion that action is often considered to be focused on the welfare
of others sometimes there's self-compassion
and sometimes there's a caring for oneself as one has compassionate care
for others it's possible to have compassionate
action care for both self and others and have an open-hearted open vision of
how to be in this world that we wish that everyone benefit to
everyone be free not just the parties involved or something
and there's a fifth kind of way of compassionate action
that for some Buddhist Traditions is considered to be the highest Pinnacle of compassion
and that is where they were so involved so engaged in the
compassionate action that there's a self-forgetting
and not sacrificing our own well-being
but because we know how to care in a healthy way for the world and ourselves it's it's
appropriate it's a beautiful thing to then do in that healthy way of being to
give ourselves over to it completely so that uh it's that you have self being
the agent of the activity kind of Falls away in some Buddhist Traditions they talk
about the Oneness of the compassionate person the
recipient of compassion and the act itself of compassion
that there's a cycle there's a kind of a a unit of kind of
of it's Inseparable or has no division or somehow we are immersed in it so that we
don't have so much the thoughts of it's me being compassionate we're helping
another person and even the idea that this is a compassion action can fall away once we
once we have decided that this is the right thing to do we give ourselves over to it fully
and there's a Simplicity and a freedom in the action then
and this is true for anything we do um
if you wash dishes in the sink and certainly there can be a lot of
self-preoccupation like I don't like doing the dishes I wish I didn't have to do it I'm always doing it it's not fair
or you know I have important things to do let's get this over quickly because I have to get to to do something that I
really want to do so there's a lot of self-concerns of different types there it might be
concerns about being the best dishwasher in the neighborhood and trying to prove yourself that everyone knows that you're
a good dishwasher there's also just washing dishes for the sake of washing dishes
and there's a kind of giving oneself over fully to the dishwashing that there
is no resistance there's a full participation and there's no judgment and no
self-concern in washing my dishes maybe no one's in the house with you so you
know he's not trying to prove anything to anyone and so this kind of giving yourself over to an activity
is a healthy activity is one of the
qualities of Freedom or happiness or Delight that as I said before is akin to
um you know became being absorbed and reading a good book or absorbed involved doing a hobby
doing art playing music and involved in his Sports perhaps or
all kinds of things that were we really kind of almost forget ourselves in the activity
and there might still be a lot of attention and monitoring of what's Happening Here and adjusting ourselves
but it's not kind of through the ordinary filter of Me Myself and mine
and self-concerned self-preoccupation what's in it for me
so this is one one way of if we're talking about compassionate action
it's it's uh it's one of the beautiful ways to practice compassionate action is
to have learned how to give yourself to something fully to participate fully so certain kind of
wind drag of self self-concern is not there there's a kind of refreshment refreshing
way and refresh refreshing that comes from dropping the self-concerns this
it's a lot of stress that many people have around me myself and mine and what's in it for me and what's going to
happen to me and what do people think and well people still like me and and am I doing it right am I doing it wrong and
you know do I need to apologize I'm sorry oh that is wind drag all that is kind of
interfering with kind of in a simple could be simple relaxed way doesn't have to be vigorous or forceful but in a
simple relaxed way to give ourselves over to the activity at hand and in this case the topic for this week is
compassionate action and this is uh maybe often not
associated with compassion and action because the emphasis is in helping someone who's suffering
uh they actually the emphasis is doing something but but uh you know
and there can even come a sense of obligation and responsibility it's up to me I have to do it I'm the one who's
going to help and and all that is wind drag all that adds
stress and if you've decided this is healthy the way and this is why all the things
we've been teaching I've been teaching over these last weeks about compassion all the different component parts of it
all the things that can come together to inform compassion a well-developed capacity for awareness
a well-developed capacity for Attunement to others and to oneself to the situation
a well-developed capacity for appreciation and respect for others
a well-developed capacity for considering what we Aspire what's the wish we want that goes along with
compassion what's the healthy aspiration and all those things then come together
in the in the action that we do and then we also consider what's their
right action which is kind of is the principles I offered earlier in the week
but when all these come together in maybe kind of over time to develop a
second nature and they don't have a lot of consideration and thoughts about it but uh then we can at some point we give
ourselves over to the activity at hand driving someone to the emergency and
those you're just there for that activity bringing someone in or cooking someone dinner who's sick
spending time with someone who is somehow in crisis and going for a walk
with them or sitting with them and listening to them um putting a Band-Aid on a small child's
knee who scraped it there's all kinds of ways in which we can be compassionate the action but at some point to
give over or to do it fully a wholeheartedness of full participation
so that self-preoccupation falls away and the advantage of that for compassion
action is I believe that then the compassion action can be clean it can be
unclouded it can be on agitated by things which are not
compassion more often than not self-concerned self-preocupation is not
you know as a hindrance for the purposes of compassion
and also then uh the compassionate action becomes a vehicle for our own
Freedom their freedom from self we learn so much about letting go when
we give ourselves over wholeheartedly to participate in healthy activities
so um so it's kind of the you know the
culmination of this week of talking about compassionate action is to come to
a point where compassionate action is done for its own sake
of course preceding it is the idea we're doing it for the sake of others or for ourselves or all those other things but
at some point we just kind of as we're doing it we can just let go of all those
thoughts and concerns and just give ourselves over to the Simplicity of the act that we're doing
and in doing so we benefit ourselves in a fantastic way we benefit ourselves by
getting a taste of freedom freedom of freedom from self and and then I think the Joy or the
happiness that can come with compassion has a chance has the most chance to flower and develop
and that's one of the great things about compassion is the way that it can be a
source of Happiness source of joy a source of well-being source of being
on the path to Freedom so um
so that's uh
my thoughts about compassionate action for this week and so I've been now it depends how we
count but the last six seven maybe eight weeks that I've
been doing these these YouTube teachings it's all been kind of focused around
compassion and I'm hoping that it's it's enriched you in understanding it's different aspects different
streams of of attention that we are or reflection about compassion that we
can bring to it to really enrich this world so that we don't think of compassion as
a in simplistic ways that we just jump to act as you know compassionate way without giving any
thought to the the multifaceted and valuable kind of richness that the
compassionate world is part of and um and uh so it's possible this is the last
week on this topic I'll be gone for two weeks and we have wonderful guests
coming for the next two weeks and um and I don't know what I'll do when I come
back I mean maybe I'll consider us two weeks more about compassion the follow-up on compassion
maybe there's a post-compassionate topic to talk about
so I don't know so so or I'll start a new topic so we'll see
and uh thank you very very much and I appreciate so much that the chance to explore this topic with you all for
these weeks and and um I look forward to do more more of it thank you