okay so why don't we go ahead and start
folks can continue to join us as they do and to settle in for meditation finding
your posture finding your place kind of orienting toward
doing this together so gently closing the eyes
[Music] feeling into the body and the
sitting posture or whatever posture you're in
some of these preliminary things sound very simple and you know
like maybe we could skip them after we've done them a few times but I find it so helpful to just begin with
feeling the body sensing into the touch points where
you're sitting feeling the stability the groundedness
in the place where you're sitting
and finding some balance in the body so it takes very little effort
to be sitting upright or lying in the position you're in
we don't want to be using a lot of muscles to do that
see if the bones can just be aligned
so that they are supporting you
sensing the straightness of the spine not in a rigid way
naturally has a few curves but there's a sense of uprightness
alignment and then the rest of the body can relax
around that uprightness so the shoulders soften
drop head floats on the spine
in the arms and legs can just feel like they're floating
the way the fronds of a sea plant float
softening the eyes and the eye sockets
the jaw
and softening whatever it's possible to soften in the heart area in the belly
in the back
just inviting some ease
letting the arms and legs be natural
soft
and bringing up the quality of mindfulness
mindfulness as the sense of being right in the present
moment connected to what's here
in a simple way in a non-judgmental way
just knowing this so sensing how that feels in the mind
to have mindfulness
and connecting that mindfulness in particular to the sensations of the
bread and we can start with the physical
breath the actual sense of air coming in going out
maybe we can actually feel the air as it enters the nostrils
or touches the upper lip
and there's an expansion of the chest or the belly
maybe we only feel that through the shift of the clothing on the skin but there's some indication of expansion
it's a whole series of emotions throughout the Torso
we don't need to make it do anything we just feel how it actually is right
now
I can also sense the breath as more of an energetic phenomenon
a more subtle flow that can extend well outside of the lung
area you know maybe we can feel breath energy
blowing into the legs and the arms
throughout the whole of the back or even up into the head
as you breathe is this is there this more subtle verb
energy
so this is one aspect of the air element s the breath energy
and it's also the quality of motion in the body
movement and flow are part of our experience of the material world
the air element is this experiential quality it's not a literal substance
so resting with this breath
flowing for a few minutes energetic error element
there is the most subtle of the four main material elements
so we may find that tuning into it naturally draws the line
down to a more tranquil state
can actually be used to quiet the mind a bit
tuning into the subtle energetic experience of the body
as the morning gets a bit quieter even a little bit
we can also sense or tune into our
awareness of the breath so there's the breath and there's the knowing of the breath
it's just a little turn of awareness to see the other side
and you sense the aspect of the mind that knows
the simple knowing of an object such as the breath energy
is consciousness
to know that we know
it's quite wonderful this capacity to know
also a bit mysterious how is it that we can have an experience
if you look at how it's happening look carefully
you can see that the knowing of an object Co arises with the object
we can't know a sensation before it occurs
we can't know it after it is gone
but when it's there there's the knowing of it
and there could only be knowing if there were something to know
it's amazing there can be some wonder and amazement
that our mind is knowing all of these experiences
so see if you can rest in this knowing
just appreciating this aliveness of knowing
to find that the Mind needs a place to rest tuning into that subtle
breath energy coming in going out we're still connected to the physical
world the breathing and there's the knowing of experience
breathing in and breathing out
foreign
s of this meditation we may notice how
the elements are interconnected
the air element and the breath that we've been tuning into
occurs because we have a body because there is
Earth the substance of this body draws in the
air through the working of the muscles
beer has a temperature often it's cool on the way in warm on
the way out
and it has a quality of connecting together the the body has the cohesion quality that's
associated with the water element the elements are not really
separate they have different aspects of material life
and all of them are known by consciousness
which Rises with them
it's almost a tautology how could we know the Earth Elemental even what it is
without knowing and how could there be knowing if there weren't something to know
so these are completely integrated also when we tune into the Consciousness side
you may have a sense of Marvel Wonder where's that coming from
what would it be like to go through the world marveling at what's appearing
might be pleasant it might be painful or neither one
all the fullness of life it's quite marvelous that it all comes
into this mind into this life
how would it be to live with a sense of Wonder
being here of seeing all of this of experiencing this
and how would we have to be to stay in touch with that sense of
Marvel even if it's painful what qualities of mind would we have to
have to still welcome experience as wonderful even when it's painful
and what a gift for the world it is to see life
as a wondrous opportunity an amazing thing
even in all of its complexity and challenge
as well as its ease and peace
truly that would be to know the fullness of life people like that are gifts to
the world able to have a bigger perspective
they will always Define somewhere to be easy with what's
happening why does the air able to move
so we'll see how it is to consider the Wonder
in life today
so the flavors of the week continue we are going through some of the classical
Indian rasa or Savers or flavors that teachings
can have and I want to bring in one more Dimension today as we've gotten pretty
far into this week which is noticing if there are certain
flavors that we're talking about that you rarely experience
or that you have a sense like oh that's not that important or I don't
know about that one something like that um or what is that I I never even
thought about that one then maybe it would be interesting to um
open to some of these other flavors the way we might try a different food
spice up our practice with an unusual flavor
because all of these are present in mesutas if we look for them we may just not have noticed if we're not really
attuned to that flavor so today we are looking at wonder and
amazement we could also say ah it's interesting that these are
recognized in the classical Indian cultural understanding as being
important flavors to have in art and also in spiritual teachings
I think it's an ingredient that is sometimes missing here in the West
I know not everyone listening is from the West but at least I'm aware of much of that
culture and Buddhism and you know we tend to have kind of prefer rationality
um wondering amazement um but the Buddha was very clear that
the Dharma the Deep Dharma is beyond the thinking mind he said that Liberation is unattainable
by mere reasoning so let's draw out
some meaning of that from the discourses of the Buddha
there is a story of a time that the Buddha was living with an intendant
named magia and you may know that Ananda was often
the Buddha's attendant and that's true but he actually came a little bit later the Buddha had some other attendance
before Ananda and at this time he was just living with
his attendant Makia just the two of them and magia asks permission to go meditate
alone in a lovely mango Grove and the the Buddha tries to dissuade him
from doing that alone but magia is very insistent and he asks
three times which usually means that the Buddha has to comply and eventually the
Buddha gives in because you know McGee is so eager to practice how can he you object to that so he sends him off
but mcgear did not have an easy time his mind was taken over by sensual thoughts
and thoughts of ill will and thoughts of harming his mind kind of went crazy and what's of Interest here is that is
his response um the suta says that in his mind he said this is truly astounding and
amazing I have gone forth out of Faith from the household life into homelessness yet I am still stalked by
these three kinds of bad unwholesome thoughts sensual thoughts thoughts of ill will and thoughts of harming
so how about that response he says it is astounding and amazing that his mind is
doing all of this I don't hear that very often from meditators here usually it's more like
Oh I'm a terrible meditator my mind is out of control or even goes farther to
I'm a terrible person to have thoughts like this or to be so bad at my
meditation how awful so maybe we could try reading experience
more like magia um when the mind is wild you can be amazed
and truly this mind has a mind of its own doesn't it can reduce all kinds of stuff
we touched a little bit into this yesterday the unpredictable quality of the mind when we talked about humor you
know like kill thinking I wonder if there's a body under that tarp so amazement is kind of related can also
be a helpful response when our mind is doing whatever it's doing wow how
amazing um so that's one side of amazement and wonder one that I think is pretty
accessible but in the sutas of course there is there are also instances where Advanced
meditators display what are called supernormal Powers you know the ability
for the mind to manipulate the physical world in unusual ways you know there are
discussions of levitation walking through walls kinds of things or the ability to see
very deeply with the mind you know beyond the way we normally are able to experience things like being able to
see sometimes what other people are thinking or being able to see our past
lives these kinds of powers come about
are said to come about let's say from developing strong concentration
and we don't emphasize them here in the west and the Buddha absolutely forbade
casual use of them for his followers so you know they're not really
emphasized as AIMS in the Buddhist teachings
but if we read the sutas honestly again they are sometimes strategically used to
shock people into presence or to evoke inspiration
there's a case where the Buddha uses his power to prevent someone from being able
to catch up with him even though the person is running as fast as they can and the Buddha is just walking at normal
speed and um this causes the person to stop stop
short that they you know that obviously something different is going on there
and because of you know the Buddha showing his power that way the person
stops and actually listens to the Buddha and give him a teaching which turned out
to be crucial for him so you know the Buddha was strategic in in
using that ability there are also cases where the um quite a few where the Buddha is asked
or even sometimes spontaneously tells the rebirth destination of someone who
is just tied and he even explains why he's doing that you know he doesn't just
do it so that people will be amazed or so that people will you know whatever but he he's very clear about why he's
doing that he says there are people who are inspired by things that are lofty
and when he unpacks that it's a bit of it it's that you know if people know
that someone has attained a certain stage of Liberation with their death and is reborn in a good destination they
might be inspired to practice while they're still alive here or just
um you know we can even see simpler versions of this maybe in
everyday life here you know there are people who are inspired that people go
on Long retreats you know just knowing that somebody is going on a three-month retreat
I've known people who were really inspired to know that they weren't going to do it necessarily but yeah we I mean
we offer that in our tradition at IMs every year there's a three-month Retreat it's always full
um that can be really inspiring so you know talking about kind of the
elevated mind states that are possible has a place on the path
there's also a discussion a discourse that's called wonderful and marvelous
and in this discourse Ananda is
um recounting a number of the wonderful and marvelous things about the Buddha's
past life in the 2C to Heaven before he was born here and then also coming into
his mother's womb to be born here and the birth itself you know there's kind
of a mythology around all of this and but what's interesting in this suto
wonderful and marvelous is that the Ananda explains all of these things in
the Buddha's presence saying that he heard all of these things from the Blessed one's own lips and the Buddha
doesn't object so I think we're to take them as true you know he says things like
um you know when the Buddha was born there were flowers blooming out of season and uh streams of water rained
down from heaven things like that so you know we can maybe take this metaphorically or
um or who knows we weren't there um but an interesting thing so all of
this is kind of there in the Sutton and we're you know the Buddhists acid we at
least agreeing with it and then the Buddha listens to this long recitation of you know Miracles without
comment and then he says to Ananda that being so Ananda remember this too as a
wonderful and marvelous quality of the tatagata meaning the Buddha here for the
tatagata feelings are known as they arise as they are present and as they
disappear perceptions are known as they arise as they are present and as they disappear
and thoughts are known as they arise as they are present and as they disappear
so it seems that after all these Miracles which apparently are true
the Buddha also really values the simple knowing of one's mind that is the
genuine miracle if you will
and he meant it actually even for himself there's a there's a pseudo from just after the Buddha's Awakening where
the Buddha realizes that it's um in his words it's painful to dwell without
reverence and deference and he's just been awakened right so
you'd think he would need that kind of thing but he looks around for something to be awed by some some person and he
doesn't see any being who's Superior in knowing than himself
so he decides to Revere the Dharma how about that and so even the Buddha
wanted to Revere something so he decides to Revere the natural laws of how things work
it's amazing this is a simple a natural element of the universe
that could evoke wonder and awe for us how amazing that this is there's this
mind there's all these things we can know about the body and the mind and there's Consciousness knowing it
that we didn't create wow
I originally studied science in my earlier life and I was drawn to it largely because of the feelings of awe
and wonder that I had as a child Imagining the universe and my place in
it nature is quite wonderful and marvelous and I hope we don't lose that in our
practice and in the little minutia of trying to get our life right and figure out our past and our relationships
nature so wonderful the mind is amazing
so we need this in our practice we need to bring in Inspiration faith
juice of some kind Wonder can evoke Joy can enliven and lift the heart
can enable us to move forward when we have no idea how you know we can get into situations
where we don't know how to go forward life can be like that it can bring
something large and then we we might really need something bigger than us
our small self so worried about getting everything together open the mind to
the Wonder the larger picture the sense of
the wholeness not as a philosophy but as a labor as an
emotional tone that's useful for us we don't have to make it into a big thing
and then we're gripping onto it just be with it feel it use it so that
the mind can become unstuck so
this is my suggestion for today the flavor of the day I hope you're getting a sense as we go
through these flavors of the breath that's offered in the teachings
breath that's possible in our heart and mind so
be well see you tomorrow