warm greetings
in Cloudy kind of a little bit wet
California here we've had unseasonable amount of
light rain through the week and clouds and cool weather
and I like it quite a bit yeah maybe for my
left over from my native town in Norway where I was
born Bergen where it rains quite a bit cloudy quite a bit
so my friends there are many motivations
for meditating but the ones that Buddhism somehow holds
up as Central to the Buddhist Enterprise could all be subsumed under the
expression benefit we are meditating practicing Buddhism to
benefit and who are we benefiting everyone
the Buddha said that a wise person is concerned with benefiting oneself
benefiting others benefiting self and others and benefiting the whole world
and uh it's kind of comprehensive and there's not choosing one or the other to
just benefit yourself just benefit others but there's a integrated whole
that is the domain of wise reflection and wise and motivation
and uh and if your motivation is to serve
others to benefit others when we sit down to meditate
one of the important ways to prepare ourselves to bring benefits to
the world is in fact to benefit ourselves it's important to do this it's important
to shed layers of reactivity and stress that we carry
it's important to shed layers of clinging and attachments and anxieties
that we carry because the more these are shed the more that not only are we available to
benefit the world but our very way of being in the world is beneficial
when people experience someone who feel who is calm who is uh seems to have no fear
someone who has no obstacles to their kindness and their love
and we benefit ours we benefit ourselves and bring forth what's beautiful within us those qualities then are available
for the world as well so when we sit down to meditate
one of the options you have and completion will do today is to orient the meditation from the
very beginning with a question what is beneficial for me
here and now let's not just go ahead and just meditate in roads just meditate because I'm
supposed to and I have a technique to do I have a way of practicing and I'll just do it because that's what I do
but rather take some time at the beginning to reflect how am I right now what's happening for
me and given what's happening how I am what would be beneficial what would be a
beneficial way to meditate and that there's layers of answering
that question one is to ask the questions in the point of view of your body
what's a better beneficial way to establish a posture for meditation
Maybe there's a deep need for rest and relaxation
maybe there's a deep need for strength maybe there's a deep need for
um to kind of really feel embodied and feel connected here in this body so that with
the body we can feel connected to the world around us and different postures support these
different things so to be a little bit conscious about what posture is useful for you
in small ways it might change from day to day
then you might ask what is beneficial for your heart
maybe it's taking time to acknowledge what's happening emotionally and with you
not to overlook it or try to Barrel through it maybe there's a some
tender loving care of some kind that your inner life could benefit from
meta kindness compassion
maybe your heart needs some honesty
sometimes truth-telling is the greatest need that some sometimes we have
to really acknowledge how we are what's happening in a clear and Unapologetic way
just oh it's like this something in the heart can settle sometimes when our situation ourselves
are really acknowledged
even to acknowledge that I'm afraid or acknowledge I'm depressed or acknowledged that I'm angry
that's a truth-telling that's often that's needed if we want to kind of start being bringing benefit to
ourselves and to the world because when it's honest then we can kind of find our way with it
what's beneficial for this mind maybe how we meditate is important for
the mind and the Heart to not strive or not to measure or not compare ourselves
to maybe it's helpful to be Fearless when we meditate
or un interruptible
undiscourageable even if there's this discouragement or to not let it get in the way even though
there is anxiety not let it get in the way so sitting here and just asking yourself
oh what way would what way of meditating right now would be beneficial
given everything and then meditating that way
or starting that way sometimes starting for just a few
minutes and then settling into the basic meditation practice sometimes just doing it longer
but what happens to you when you begin your meditation with a question what would be beneficial right now
in how to meditate and then proceed from there
now be quiet now as we meditate for the next minutes
foreign
okay
and as we come to the end of the sitting
to take in the idea that if we want to benefit others
spiritually or dharmically
we can do more if we have benefited ourselves spiritually or dharmically
and if we don't want to benefit others but only ourselves
if we're benefiting ourselves in the Dharma spiritually
we will somehow or other benefit others anyway
our own spiritual benefit our own dharmic benefit
is integrally linked to the welfare of others
for one thing the more we dharmically benefit ourselves
spiritually benefit ourselves the more we know what
dharmic benefit can be the more we can be attuned
to that possibility for other people as well
maybe people more than material help or emotional help
what goes deepest Into the Heart Is dharm is dharmic help spiritual help
something that touches a home inside of us that's deeper
than our emotional life our cognitive life
it may it be that as we navigate and walk this path of the Dharma
may it be that we do so to benefit ourselves to benefit others
to benefit self and others and to benefit the whole world
they are deepening deepening connection
to the dharmic life to the spiritual life be a support
for the welfare and happiness of all beings may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings know freedom freedom from suffering
and find it in their hearts
[Music]
thank you
all right
so thank you so we come to the last of these five
talks on Attunement and so the with the acronym touch
there's thinking thinking well thinking carefully about
the suffering we encounter because the Attunement we're talking about is the Attunement that allows
a meaningful important effective compassion healthy compassion to come
forth into our care for the world so before we're ready for compassion we
want to be attuned to the suffering and that can take some reflection and thinking
we want to be open to it willing to experience it and this willingness is openness to it is a profound thing
because it's part of the movement towards freedom freedom from resistance freedom from
picking things up freedom from blocking or
becoming the cut so free we're like an open window and everything can pass through without touching the window without
affecting the window breaking the glass being upright
stable strong undefeated
uncollapsed just fully present not assertive not withdrawing but a strong
sense of presence for with suffering we're encountering
and then communicating with people to really to be in conversation with them
and find out better what's going on don't assume we know don't assume we know what's needed
but to find out be in communication get the information
and then today the age of touch is help important part of of compassion is to
help to do something to alleviate the suffering in oneself and others and in
the whole world and um but uh as a kind of building
block to become compassionate and two real compassionate action
um the help that I'm going to talk about today is a little bit more maybe more modest or a stepping stone towards more
more full uh compassionate action to uh to help you want to be able to ask
the question what is helpful here what is beneficial and um and in all directions what is
beneficial for oneself because if we leave ourselves too much out of the equation
then we will um we can actually cause harm to ourselves and to others if we don't
carefully bring careful attention to our motivations our emotions our feelings our reaction to situation and just feel
like we're obligated to help someone with uh and we're supposed to be altruistic and not care for ourselves at
all we actually can be so disconnected from ourselves that inadvertently
unhelpful things will come out of us we say things we express things we we feel
kind of we actually discover where maybe feel you know there's anger in trying to help someone because we don't really
want to but we feel like we should and so what is helpful for ourselves in
this situation um and and this you know really questioning ourselves is very important
also because with compassionate action some people will live under uh rules of
obligation and the duty and shoulds that uh are
kind of authoritarian and kind of override any careful attention and and can exhaust people part of the
compassion fatigue can sometimes come from the sense of obligation that I have to do this I have to do this
and so to really question that is what is beneficial here for me um and because when I'm in benefit
especially spiritually benefited dharmically benefited and become settled
and peaceful and calm and have a nice presence then not only can we act better
but the action that we do conveys something important
many times the medium is the message if we do things because we're helping
someone because we're anxious and we're trying to you know assuage our fear or motivated by fear that'll have a very
different message to people than if we are calm and settled and we don't act from fear but we act with great
energy great Passion or something but we're calm and settled and present and
clearly kind of connected to the person we're doing it and the way that we can't be if we're being motivated by fear
and my what what is help of her oneself is to check in with oneself
and and understand what motivates us to be helpful because if we're motivating uh motivated
to help others because we're not really caring for them but if we really look carefully we're just trying to
get comfortable for ourselves we want to create a nice identity for ourselves we
want to be able to show the world that we're a good person and and we're more driven
by that than we are by the helping the other people
and all those other kind of those kinds of motivations for ourselves are not spiritually beneficial not dharmically
beneficial and naturally can cause kind of long-term harm sometimes even
but so to really check in what is really helpful and the more we practice the more we can answer that question in some
ways it's really deep or really full or concerned for our long-term happiness
and Welfare not the short term just making ourselves comfortable and um
so with that there's a reference point then we can ask what is helpful for the other person
remember we're talking about being attuned to the people and um and what it and what is helpful
uh if the other person is an important thing to question and not bring the wrong kind of help some people want to
be left alone they want to figure things out themselves they just want a companion they some people just want to
be seen and known in their struggles but they don't necessarily want someone to
come to support them and Aid them and fix things the problems for them so what is supportive for others and
occasionally people who do want to get help from other people that's not actually spiritually helpful
for them maybe it represents some way of always being kind of helpless and looking to others to be the savior
and so at some point we want to stop being the savior because people need to grow up people need to learn how to
stand their own two feet and to always come into the rescue is not really beneficial for others
to be uncaring is not beneficial but to be caring and allow someone to grow up is is good
and this other on one hand we we want to ask what's beneficial for ourselves what's beneficial for others
and this in this category of help here is also to ask because we're trying to
be attuned what form of help is attuned to myself
and as attuned to the person there so someone is having some challenge
say that uh they are late for late to go
someplace and maybe they have a flat tire and they don't know how to fix a flat tire
so on the surface just seems like what's best is to help them you know replace
put in the spare for them because maybe you know how to do it and that's nice
but maybe you don't have a clue how to put on a spare tire so it's not helpful to go and help them
with a tire then what might be helpful is to call someone who does
find some other kind of help and um or maybe there's you know the
person may be configured out there's no place to call maybe there's no cell phone you're in the desert you can't
help uh with it so what's attuned with what you can do and what this need is
and maybe what you can do is bring them water you realize they've been struggling for some time it's hot in the
desert and so you bring them water maybe you bring them some food to eat and say here take a break and let's let's uh
maybe you'll it looks like you need to drink and be settled a little bit and you can go back to it then
so there's an example of kind of what can I do that's appropriate for me and sometimes
like someone who's a a you know completely devoted introvert
sometimes they're just sitting on the Park Bench or something and accompanying them someplace to where they're
challenged and it doesn't you know not to be involved so much in conversation and fixing but just accompanying you
have the ability to be calm and centered and present and um and I've gone just to
sit with people um you know and be quiet and let them do
what they needed to do but they felt that there was some support quietly in the room uh or if you're a devoted extrovert and
you love to sing it might be that singing a song for the person
um is the right thing and I don't think that anybody wants me to sing exactly but uh but there are people who are
saying I knew I knew a chaplain who was in the hospital with someone who was dying in the emergency room it was kind
of a tragic death and the person was quite upset discouraged angry and had turned into
the turned her face into the wall and uh was was unresponsive to anybody
coming and to the chaplain just started singing a song and uh in the course of the song the
person kind of softened and opened up and turned around and then started to engage the chaplain
and um so what is the right way what's what's attuned to oneself what what we
can bring how do we help this person how do we help the person for what they
can receive some people are not able to help to receive what seems like the logical
obvious help that should be done uh they feel uh it's too they feel they
feel put put upon they feel it's too assertive people have entered their space too much they feel like they know
because then they feel obligated some cultures it's a deep sense of obligation that comes with helping people receiving
help and so it's difficult to kind of step into their in their zone so to
that's where the communication is important what will this person what does this person want to receive what
can they receive what when their end and um so um
you know so what kind of communication what kind maybe some people you know as
I said they just they just want to be quiet together with someone else someone else wants to join in a song
if someone came to me in the emergency and wanted to care for me and chances are expecting me to sing a song with
them is not really going to be you know be so helpful for me so this question of being attuned
it means questioning and considering all the factors that should be that are going that are in place to know how to
help what would be helpful here given oneself given the other person
given the situation with the Assumption and this I think is a really good assumption to go by
is that there are any given time there are many ways to help
not just one and if we are rushing into that one way that we think is the right
way then I know there's a good chance we're going to miss what the situation is really about the total situation
that includes oneself so uh touch
think open openness uprightness
communication and help all places where we do it we do
the work of Attunement of great so um
so thank you and I will be
away next week I'm back at the IRC for a retreat
and um actually for the next two weeks and next next week Don Neal will come
and wonderful new teacher coming up here at IMC and um and then the following week it's
going to be um Dakota o'connellan who taught for us last fall
and also a wonderful upcoming teacher here at IMC and then I'll be back in in after those
two weeks for one more week before I get ready and go and my month-long Retreat
that I'm doing a self Retreat for the month of June so um thank you and you'll be in good
hands with the teachers that are coming and um please support them in their their
capacity to be a teacher and appreciate them and and I'll see you in a couple of
weeks thank you very much and that point I want to continue on
this theme so this idea of compassion and is an ongoing theme and it's also an
ongoing way of dealing with the theme so far this year of how to be with challenges and now we're kind of
covering the area of compassion in that field so we've been doing that for a few weeks
and we'll continue for a while thank you