good morning everyone and have a good day
welcome here to the start of our week start of a new theme and
and uh feels nice to be here with you all
sitting here at IMC so um
and also uh I kind of feel like it's a special Monday because I Mark today as the
kind of the end of three years of these YouTube
meetings and beginning of the fourth year it seems quite significant
so thank you for being here as an introduction to this meditation
I would like to make some distinctions so and the distinctions are progression
kind of deeper and deeper into the source of ourselves so if we begin
with what we're doing whatever it might be if we're doing something
a little bit deeper inside was a decision to do it
if we go a little bit deeper inside there's no wish to do it
the desire to do it so the decision there's a desire there's a decision
and there is the doing of it if we go a little bit deeper down
below the desire the wish to do something for that wish to really be something to
work you know to really arise well
there is a place deeper down where there's space for it to rise there's a room
for it to appear there is a source deeper in from which
that desire arises and that can be one of two sources
it can come from our reactivity or we can come from something deeper
something that is the the seat
of our kindness a very very simple tenderness or
gentleness or kind of feeling of nurturing or
nourishing or tending both exist within us there is the
reactive place and there's the nurturing tending place
and you know within minutes we can go from one to the other we could be
nurturing and tending a little kitten
and we could be yelling at the you know someone who has driven their
car over our lawn and it's a very different kind of response a very different Source within
us when we're sitting in meditation
it's possible to step back into these layers of where
things come from it's possible to and especially it's possible to do so
when we're doing loving kindness meditation Goodwill meditation
when we're bringing kindness or friendliness to the Forefront and we're kind of centering ourselves with a
friendly attitude as the kind of the organizing principle
all right excuse me the organizing principle of
of the mind of the heart while we're meditating so it's there's possible to do loving
kindness meditation and doing it might be awkward might be difficult it might be easy the doing is
can be complicated but before the doing there's a decision
to be kind to a decision to practice being friendly to practice Goodwill met
them before that there's a desire to do so the wish to do
so before her decisions okay let's get let's get to work here and I'd like to propose that the
decision to do so is independent of how well we can do it
sometimes doing loving-kindness practices people so difficult they say they can't do it
for whatever reason however the wish to do so is the
beginning of Love beginning of kindness simply the wish to do so
and independent of whether we can
and to step back into that beginning place just to wish to do so the desire
to do so and appreciate that maybe is the beginning of a kind of Goodwill or well wishing to
ourselves or caring for ourselves caring for others caring for the world
and then also it's possible to a step further back to the maybe to the place where there's
Space Room for that desire to arise
if we're claustrophobic and with our experience thinking a lot or
cut up or pushing or wanting or something too much there's no room
and stepping back before or even the desire to have loving kindness
to making a room for our experience that is precious
that's a place also of a kind of a love a kind of a care a kind of a valuing
respecting what's here and in that making that room
there's a better chance for the desire to be
kind to be part of the nurturing attending
caring loving apparatus that's within us rather than
the reactive so we'll do so let me kindness practice but with this as a background
so to sit upright in a meditation posture
that is a posture that you assume to care for yourself
as if the posture itself
is a healthy posture for a year to you to meditate in
and to gently close your eyes
and it takes some long slow deep breaths pausing at the end of the exhale
just for a moment or two to make room and space and silence
for the inner life
deep breath in Long release with the exhale
pausing at the end of the exhale
make room for things to get quiet and peaceful settled
and to feel the natural urge to breathe in
and allow for that
and then to let your breathing return to normal
and then to gently
see if you can find a place within you that has the wish
for kindness to yourself or kindness for others whichever is
easiest for you
that wish is not dependent on being able to do it
not depending on having active kindness
but it's just a wish simple ordinary wish what a good idea it would be nice
if only
and in your own way
see if you can give thought words to that desire
gently quietly almost meditatively
give a voice to that desire
or let there be an attitude
or maybe an emotion
to appear that maybe is part of that desire
deep down inside where the desire to be kind arises
it's very private no one needs to know
that kindness can be their independent
of justification irrational reason
whoever you have kindness want to have kindness for that desire can be independent of
whether you or anyone deserves it it's just a good place to be it's a good
very simple healthy Source Within
you sit there quietly breathing with it giving space for it
becoming quiet around the simple
manifestation of kindness
which is the desire to be kind the wish
and if you have no desire whatsoever For Love or kindness good will
go deeper into the source
to where there is space room lots of room
to feel the depth within us
the space and the room that doesn't judge or doesn't
pile on beliefs attitudes and reactions
simple spacious awareness that has room for everything just as it
is
and is there a place in that spaciousness or space
for a simple tender nurturing feeling
caring for yourself
simple now a simple desire for your own welfare
it doesn't require you to act or do anything or
decide anything it's just a nice
simple glow of Goodwill
kind regard
a wishing to be kind a wishing to be loving
that plays deep inside where there's a desire to be kind desire to be
loving before judgments before decisions
before action before right and wrong
good and bad capable or incapable
deep in the privacy of your own heart
the most basic kind of kindness who wish to be kind
gently say words they give expression to this
or half words or silent words
attitude to this simplest form of kindness
the wish to be kind
foreign
and then to turn your attention out into the people around you and
your home or your neighborhood or your Province Wherever You Are
and perhaps you can have the wish that from this day
that you have good will meta for them
and stay connected to the wish before actually
practicing meta for them just simply stay with a wish
a private wish
where it's good for you to have that wish it's a satisfying feeling
ordinary wish for other people's welfare
and in a way that feels nice for you
expressing some words in your mind
the wish for others welfare
who are more deeply still not their wish for the welfares of
others but the wish that you had that wish
wouldn't it be nice if you could wish for the welfare and happiness of everyone
and wishing for that wish May that come out of you from someplace deep inside that
satisfying simple
maybe cozy
may it be as we come out of this meditation
that we we have more often we wish well for others
may they wish for wishing be a fuel and a support
for wanting to act
for the welfare and happiness of others
May our wishes lead to decisions to act and may the decisions lead to action
may we in some way
give expression to this great idea
the idea that others might be happy may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to beginning of the week and also the beginning of our fourth year
of gathering together for these morning um
sittings and talks and I'm delighted that we've been going
on for three years and how much we've I think we've connected and supported each other
and been able to explore the Dharma this way and I'm very happy that we're able to
continue now the pandemic is over more or less somewhat enough
that um I won't be here as much as I was during
the pandemic when I was here every day so I'll be here still quite a bit but we'll have now for the next year I think
we'll have a fair fair number of guest teachers coming as well to teach and
these guest teachers at many of them you know are very happy to come and be part
of this and I think it's a wonderful large happy Sangha we have with uh with
you all with us teachers being here and I'm happy we're continuing
so for this week we still want to continue with the theme
of how to practice with the challenges that we have
and but this week the topic is meeting challenges with love
and the kind of the question that I'd like to offer today
is uh when four challenges is when we're in challenges to ask ourselves the
question where's the love or what's the loving thing to do or where's the kindness
what's the kind thing to do the the nature of a challenge I think
often is that we get preoccupied it we get narrow and our Focus gets concerned
with what the challenge is and sometimes there's not that too much room processing room or thinking room or
reflective room reflection room to reflect on things when we're kind of involved with a challenge
the more intense the involvement were the challenges the more our focus our
narrow are becomes narrow and our world becomes smaller and smaller to we're
just with that the concern that is up and some of these challenges of course
are huge and tragic and um but still they kind of will kind
of take all the kind of attention out of like air out of the air
out of the room attention out of the space so that we're really kind of navigating this small little world over
the challenge itself and to ask the question where's the love or what's the kind thing to do here
begins to open it up again why leave love out why why leave out the
question what's the kind thing to do what's kind here in this situation
sometimes of course the challenge doesn't give us time it's not appropriate to take the time for that
but when a challenge is not you know immediate like immediately has to be addressed
um it might be invaluable to take the time to ask where is the love what would
be the kind thing to do here and um and this kindness this
uh especially when there's a challenge there might be a lot of protests you
know that's not what's needed now that's not appropriate now or the situation doesn't call for it no one deserves it
if someone else is involved I certainly don't want to be kind to them I mean I'm
angry with them and I just want them to suffer but if we take the time to step back
back back into ourselves and appreciate there are layers that of
of responses that exist within us and begin appreciating that rather than
being at the surface response to go deep down reactivity is always on the surface I
mean it might have Deep Roots inside but the reactivity is always kind of surface response
and one of the reasons we are to meditate to be mindful is to drop below
the reactive mind to relax the tensions in the body relax the tensions in the
mind so we begin having access to something else besides reactivity
and the strong Authority that sometimes reactivity can have over us
and so to um to drop ask a question you know where's the love what's the kind
thing here um it creates a pause creates a kind of
a questioning an inquiry that helps us maybe get below the reactive state of
mind and beginning to look more deeply what's going on here it might not be possible to love
where's the love I don't know it's not not available you might think what's the kind thing to do here and
that might be too hard to really have an answer but simply asking the question if
it allows space to for other information to come in then we can have maybe a different
approach to the challenge where we're we're having to address
so as we ask this question take the pause the inquiry then we can go down the layers so uh if the kind of top
layer is what we do below that is a decision
for what we do if there's a decision and below the decision there's the wish for something
we can wish without deciding to pursue it and so with kindness with good will
um there we might not have good will to act on we might not have made the decision that
we want to have good will but maybe deep down inside we could find a place where yes
kind of it would be nice if there was good will be nice if there was friendliness here
it'd be nice if it was in this system and the approach what's going on here and
what would that look like who are we being kind for
so if you're having technology of problems with your computer then I don't know if it makes sense to
have kindness for your computer but how about kindness for yourself what is it there's overriding what's the
sense of urgency what's a sense of frustration that gets in the way of the value of
love of kindness of wishing that we have we have love for ourselves
wishing we can be kind just that begins changing the Ecology of
it all if it challenges with someone else the person than our people
do we have nowhere deep down inside any desire for their welfare and their
happiness could we imagine that a context where
you would have that for that for those people or their you know beyond the pale no way nothing is possible
um or is there is there is it really all the time
or is the challenge with them contextual is there a different context where you
might feel some basic ordinary human Goodwill for them and care for them
and maybe there's the desire to be able to do it
even if you can't do it the desire to do it is a form of
kindness is a form of love and to appreciate
the desire to do a desire to have love the desire to be kind appreciate that as
a form of kindness I know it's hard to be kind all the time
it's hard to have it it's hard to want to be to uh to you know want welfare for others sometimes
but can you at least want to be able to do it
this is valuable for yourself it's medicine for us to be able to come back and find that place of basic goodness
basic care because if we're not connected to that we're estranged from ourselves change
the chances are we're living a little bit too much in the reactive world and and um and the projected world and the
fantasy world of ideas and Concepts and hurts
and do we we don't want to sacrifice we don't want to lose touch with this deep
place that can't be hurt the Deep place that can't be does not
transactional that's not dependent on anyone being anything even you being
anything that but rather is something before all that
the simplest rudimentary wish
desire to want to love
to want to be kind to want to care
take the time to find that maybe if you find that it's easier to
breathe maybe you find that you find there's a little more space in the challenge
maybe if you find that the challenge is still the same challenge but it's a
little bit more space for you to address it to be with it to not be battered around by it as much
where's the love what's that kind thing to do
and then to back up back up inside as deep
as you can go where you find something a little some
inkling some little impulse words love
even if it's not love it's towards love that's not dependent
on any condition in the world being one way or the other
it's just what the heart does
so this week I'd like us to reflect on this topic of love and kindness and good
will in times of challenge and um
and learn to bring that into the picture
rather than have blinders on with that often happen with the challenge that we
see it from a very narrow perspective and how do we include the perspective of
love of kindness of Goodwill so thank you very much and I hope that
as you go about your day today that um you can have that find that space within
that pause that quiet that you can recognize
an impulse to want to be kind to want to be loving
and maybe you can't take it any further than that and there's no need to feel guilty or feel like you're not loving
just the impulse towards love the desire to love
is plenty beneficial appreciate that
and appreciate it in the privacy of your heart so it doesn't get complicated with
all the issues of Life of people who should you or shouldn't you or
of course you should when no one needs to know so thank you very much