readings dear fellow Travelers
on this beautiful wholesome path
it's good to see you good to practice with you
so I need to begin by making a correction
that the Chinese character combining look and see
is not the one given for translating niroda cessation
but rather samadhi deep concentration
bringing the mind and the body and all of us
individually all the parts of us together
so it's a it's a beautiful quality of samadhi that nothing needs to be left out
even the parts of us were still
somewhat unskillful from time to time
now we'll begin um by formulating our deepest intention
why we are here to meditate
and it's advantageous if your intention includes
a dimension of altruism it's not only for you but it's for
everyone all beings and how we might contribute
to the well-being of everyone on this planet
setting your intention sets the stage
or your effort
so now assume a meditation posture
from which you feel you could practice
letting go relinquishing
letting go of tensions in the body
but also letting go of unwholesome mind States
like being tempted to jump on thought trades
so for me what I need in my posture for that is to know that I'm
upright that my three centers of brevity are
well balanced belly the heart and the head
and then I like the image of sending Roots deep down into the Earth
from where I have the sensation of contact with whatever is supporting me
where there is the floor a chair a cushion a bed
that's where we send down our roots
and then another invitation for our meditation today
is to throughout the whole half hour of practice
to Endeavor to maintain flavor
of kindness it's of all being kind to ourselves
being kind to whatever arises in the mind
being kind to our foibles or imperfections
just recognizing them without any Judgment at all
oh this is how it is
that's wholesome recognition
so now we'll do a brief body scan
from the soles of the feet up to the crown of the head
and as we do wherever we place our awareness we see
if there might be something there to let go of
and if it's not possible to release attention
then we settle for just softening
around whatever feels contracted
gently coming up the legs
now facing our awareness in the belly
if we're sitting that's far center of gravity
and if we're on a cushion it might be like a tripod
with the knees and
the bottom of the spine
if we're sitting in a chair it might be
under the thighs
and studying ourselves
as a way of inviting the mind
and maybe slow down a little bit
maybe take a break from
the distraction of thinking
and then continuing our scan up through the heart center
and showering ourselves
with loving kindness
it's really okay to be just too weird
up through the shoulders down through the arms and the hands
and then placing our awareness in the head area
are there any parts of the face that you would like
to soften a little bit
and taking the ritual long slow deep breath
in and out
making contact with the experience of breathing
and now we'll do a practice of reflection
based on the Awakening factor of Investigation
so if this is okay with you you're invited
ask yourself what in you
would benefit from letting go
what would you enjoy letting go of in your mind
and if you could take a brief vacation from whatever
stands in your way of quieting the mind
please celebrate that
it's wonderful it doesn't have to last
just a taste of a quiet mind is beautiful
I imagine most of you have already closed your eyes but in case you haven't
that can be beneficial
so staying with the cycle of the breath
and in the background keeping the flavor of kindness and also
a factor of Investigation [Music]
of what would it take
you to let go of keeping the mind so busy
don't keep practicing like this
and if a door should open for you
or it's the beauty of Tranquility
feel free to step through it
perhaps you've gotten a glimpse of what the obstacles
are that you need to clear
in order to advance on your chosen path
in that case the invitation is to revoke
The Awakening factor of effort
wholesome effort what do you need to let go of
to purify your efforts as you meditate
if the problem seems to be the wandering mind
might it be helpful to make a vow to just keep coming back
article physics has demonstrated that most
of this human body is in fact emptiness
so now the invitation is to
visualize that emptiness inside
and radiate
your emptiness which is infused with kindness
in all directions above and below
in front and back to the right to the left
the spend a few hours from radiating
purifying yourself and all beings in the whole universe
with emptiness infused with kindness
and now we come to the end of this city
and we radiate our well-wishing to all beings everywhere including
ourselves may we
and all beings be held in kindness
and may we all be free
[Music]
[Music] thank you
foreign
happy to be here with you I need to begin however by a correction
um uh a couple of Corrections
um one is that the um
the event on Saturday which is a fundraiser for a new monastery near
Seattle I didn't get that right
uh it's I kind of jumped to conclusions but it
it seemed to me to be a reasonable jump um
because when I I saw the invitation to this event there were six monastics
um with monks interspersed with nuns
and they were all named and I made the assumption that wow there
are going to be nuns in this monastery and that's not the case
my beloved mentor Aya anandabodi
actually um since she was uh she was also tagged in that
um
had to come out of her in fact that Monastery will just be for male monastics
and the reason they put uh nuns in there was not because they were going to be
part of the monastery but because they were friends of this future monastery
and um I guess Dr impostero wanted to make a
fundraising pitch for them as well um anyway I do apologize for
um my uncalled for jubilation but I'm happy for the monks that they're doing a fund
Reserve or this new their Mountain monastery
um and So today we're going to talk about
um last uh Olson mine State for the week
which is called vasaga v-o-s-s-a-g
-a 50 degrees and you know long marks
um but before I go there
I need to make a correction for um my teaching yesterday when I was
wanting to explain um the Chinese character
um that was used in the in the agamas to translate a poly term and I
have remembered that it was naroda but actually it wasn't pneumonia it it is
some samadhi so um this wonderful
uh picture of look and see is the Chinese uh term for samadhi
but actually you know it wasn't too far-fetched in my part to make this mistake because
samadhi is really related to niroda cessation
somebody being deep concentration because samadhi can be seen as the
quintessential stopping of the wandering mind
and when we finally stop well enough then
we can see we're ready for insight
and at that point nothing is going to stop us from
becoming enlightened
so stopping is the big part of samadhi
so um how would we describe somebody for me
it's a mind that is open
it's soft and steady
and it has a quality I believe of emptiness
a kind of emptiness that allows for receptivity
and that's what allows us or allows The meditator Who
can go deep into samadhi to really see things
as they really are um
so the theme for today is which is usually translated
as relinquishment and like all the other factors I've been
introducing this week it also has a very wide spectrum of its meaning in Bali
and we see this from the context in which we find it in different parts of the polycanon
so um sort of initial um
translation of voice relinquishment is Letting Go
and letting go can then mature into giving up
are unwholesome tendencies and that in turn
so I was against also translator is giving up and then it can go farther that can
lead to release and when release
is mature that is complete
relinquishment that's nibon blowing up the candle is blown out
we've dropped everything with let go of everything
that's you know when we get ready to be at our hunt so
may not be for this lifetime but uh that's where we're headed
um and then very interestingly another uh meaning of
in addition to letting go and relinquishment today is simply a
donation it also means giving
and the Beautiful hurt quality of generosity
and you may know if you've read some of the early texts that the Buddha
uh when especially when teaching lay practitioners the very first instruction
he would give would be to cultivate generosity
and then the next one uh even more important
is that when we're comfortable with being
generous than to really take seriously the five precepts
and really Endeavor to live as ethically as we possibly can
and I I love my um monastic teachers because they
they incarnate that so beautifully this Exquisite uh
um ethics non-harming
by himself so
um it's also said uh in the early text that
when we have mastered um making use of the wholesome mind
qualities of the seven Awakening factors what this ripens in
is relinquishment the same quality
so um another thing I'd like to stress
is that we're in the thinking mind does quiet down for a moment
for most of us it really that really feels good and
yet there's nothing
but you feel the goodness of this mind state
of Quiet Mind
and recognizing that when it happens even if it's not for a long time that's really valuable and it's really
good to take a moment to enjoy that
um and that's uh also
shines a light on the importance of joy in our practice
uh sort of like the puppy that I talked about earlier this week uh training a
puppy with treats rather than with punishment
our mind is going to respond favorably to
experiences that we perceive as joyful or happy
and and in a healthy way you'll want more of that so that helps to keep us on the
path when we when we really taste how good it is to let go of all that
um that thinking
um but as as we all know quieting our mental Fabrications
or mental constructions the word in poly is sangara
uh it takes a long time because it's not uh instinctive for us
and you know that your awareness your
mindfulness your attention where you've placed your attention is profound
when it's no longer coming from the control tower
and also when your experience is no longer one of reactivity
so this feeling of well-being and happiness joy
its function in meditation is to help us Trust
being here in this body in this moment however it
is so
um in his recordings of his meditation teachings of venerable analio
Begins by asking us to formulate in a altruistic way if possible our deepest
intention why are we here to meditate
and I think I'll I'll share with you um
my deepest intention which I came to a few years ago and stayed with me for a
while is I make a I make a vowel
to be a safe haven of kindness and emptiness
for all beings and the kindness is
is obvious but for someone like me who gets
caught in the comparing mind comparing myself to others
emptiness is really a valuable quality
to cultivate and I know that if I'm not empty
if I you know if I have fixed ideas in there uh or I'm you know just obsessed with
myself I can't be safe for others
so I really do want to be safe for others and
I think cultivating Emptiness is a very wholesome thing to do
so um if you'd like some homework uh at the
end of this week I suggest that you sit down with a Dharma buddy that you
trust and the two of you have an in-depth conversation where you ask each other
over and over again what keeps you from letting go
and then giving the your body a chance to think about it and answer it and when
they do then repeating the question to invite them to go down to a a deeper
level so yeah the the process of of
investigating our own mind state and
getting getting a glimpse of what is holding us back
from completely letting go
so um I'll be teaching here again the week of July 10th
but next week you will be treated to the teachings of my longtime Dharma buddy
Kim Allen and I believe that the theme will be
on another very different exploration of the faculty of taste
Roslyn which we've worked on together this week
so um to end this week of practicing
together I bow to each of you
to thank you for your beautiful practice
and we'll keep streaming the chat for a while in case you'd like to make any
comments or suggestions for improvement
thank you so much
I'm going to disappear uh there won't be a q a because my
adorable little grandsons are visiting and I need to go out and play with them
so That's all folks all right thank you Meg and uh thank you
to uh also our uh YouTube editors and Audio Drama editors that I've also
joined this morning also uh so Dimitra job who's playing with his grandchildren
today uh Julie and uh Kevin H so thank you everybody and everyone have a good week
take care