hello good day everyone
hope this is audible I'm sure the chat will let me know one way or another
so nice to be back with you yeah it's been a bit seeing all the smiles and vows and
hearts a fabulous way to start a Monday
so the uh the topic I have in mind for the week is the Buddha's teachings on social and
communal Harmony which I'm relating to is a sort of
compliment to make dollars teachings last week on the training and emptiness
so let's start with a sitting let's find our way into
our familiar upright steady
meditation posture
let's start with a few deep breaths
connecting deliberately with this body
a few deep breaths feeling our way
healing our way into alignment
and feeling our way into relaxation
and with this connection with the breathing
as our basis
let's begin this process of steadying our attention with the body Here and Now
Breath by breath with a steady attention
sensing the particulars
warmth and coolness
Stillness trembling
steadily moment after moment
breath after breath
tuning in to those inner senses
those inner senses that are knowing Moment by moment
what's happening in this body
now if it's available
within this field of the body and mind
staying sensitive
I'd invite you to give a little bit of attention to the arising of any impulse at all
any impulse
the intention arises to scratch a niche
move the body and deliberately take up a thought
pattern could be anything
foreign
mentally sensitive to this body
and gently monitoring or any impulse that arises
right there at the end pulse
is there a sense or feeling
of its quality is it moving us toward
wholesome beneficial action
or is there a quality to the impulse live on wholesomeness
not a judge but just to see
what's the quality of this impulse as it comes and inevitably goes
extentally sensitive
for this body and mind
ful as impulses arise
mindful as impulses pass away
sensing their quality
this is one way in to wise View
[Music]
so hello again whenever we do this by Monday morning
I sense this wonderful kind of coalescing of the group
the Sangha coming together and also this feeling of embarking on something
quite a feeling for a Monday so the the theme for today is is
um the Buddhist teaching on social and communal Harmony it's something I'd like
to explore this week with you these five sessions and
there's a way that ajan sumato talks about the qualities of the Dharma that I think is so apparent when we
consider the teachings on social and communal Harmony that not only is the Dharma well spoken
but that it's apparent Here and Now Timeless encouraging investigation
that it leads onward and it's to be experienced by each of us using wisdom
the Source I'm using for for the teaching is this book this Anthology the big body
put together called the Buddhist teachings on social and communal Harmony it has 10 sections but I've sort of
reorganized things and distilled them to some key points so that we can we can talk about this in five sessions
and my hope is that our our practice and discussion together will
reveal refine kind of remind us
of how we can apply the Dharma in our everyday lives
so uh one of the I've been thinking why this topic was so
up for me interesting to me and what's what's arising this morning is
that um gosh
you know it's it feels like a time of transition both personally and in the world and maybe there's something about
being in the United States and us being more or less perpetually in the election cycle
or I thought oh yes this is where I want to focus my attention social and communal Harmony I wonder
what the Buddha said about this like what there's so much wisdom he shares with us about the the inner life
also um yeah how how does he how does he talk about Community how does he talk about
Society what's available to us there the first thing that I that I want to
propose is that um with an unclear view with a foggy view
despite all of our efforts and our best intentions that we end up not acting in accord with the world
not acting in accord with things as they are or with others or with ourselves
and in a very real way with wrong view unclear view Harmony is absent
so the point of this point of this morning the right view is the Forerunner of Harmony
an upright view the Buddha said that just as the dawn is the Forerunner of
the Sun rising so is Right View the Forerunner of the noble Eightfold Path
it's the it's the thing that precedes and leads into all of these wholesome qualities
and as we'll talk about this week right view is the Forerunner of Happiness Here and Now and of Social and communal Harmony so
what's right view what's the Buddha talking about here it can sound a little bit like
right opinion which is decidedly not what the Buddha
meant uh in fact the Buddha Mourns over and over against clinging to views
instead of right opinion and the sort of uh
oh fallible stability that can come from that I think of right view more as a
working hypothesis something we can test something we can try out
and in Magic
the Buddha talks about right view in a number of ways he says he says it can be
the knowing of wholesome and unwholesome it can be understanding
um the relationship with um
any of the factors of the 12-fold chain and how they arise and how they pass away
so bikubody with social and communal
Harmony in mind pulls out some particular aspects of Right View for our attention
and he points out something interesting that the Buddha formulated right view in
response to some uh prevailing ideas of the time about
conditionality about cause and effect three things in particular
he formulated Right View to say one our actions
now have an effect in the future our actions of the past
have an effect now and third and this is crucial that we can discern
The Beneficial from the unbeneficial so maybe maybe we can already hear some
of the connections to Social and communal Harmony and maybe even think think of how the
how opposites might interfere with our interactions with others harmonious
aligned interactions with others one way we can flesh this out a bit is
by by getting to know a little bit what the Buddha was talking about when he said wrong view what's wrong view meet
chaditi okay you might hear the word wrong and go wait what okay wrong
are we allowed in the Buddha Dharma to talk about Rights and Wrongs is that
okay but I think I think we can consider that when running a hypothesis if we're
running if we're thinking of right view as a working hypothesis and running an experiment we need to be able to Define
some terms and make some distinctions in fact in um majima 117 and the Buddha
defines Right View as this capacity to distinguish right view from wrong View
so what view was um body pointing at that the Buddha was responding to again
it's in three parts one that there are no fruits of our Deeds
either in this life or Beyond that what we do now actually doesn't have an effect
in using the classic metaphor of karmic karmic seed and karmic fruit
this would be like saying if we plant seeds right now nothing will grow
and the quality of the the seed that we plant yeah nothing's going to come out
so no fruits of our Deeds was the the first
the first aspect of wrong view that the Buddha was was um
pointing away from and the second is that there's no way to distinguish
a wholesome Deed from an unwholesome deed can you imagine
in the in the karmic seed and karmic fruit analogy this might be like saying
that a kale seed which brings up something wholesome that can nourish our bodies is the same as a
poisonous castor bean seed that is toxic to the touch
that there's no difference between these two things we can't actually know that this is wholesome and this is
unwholesome so that's the second aspect and then the
third is that um with regard to the path that beings in the in the language of
the text are defiled and purified without cause
now what this actually means is that we we have no say in the quality of our life
that we have no moral agency and in the analogy this means that we we
can't plant any seeds and even if we did they wouldn't produce anything
wrong View the important upshot for for communal Harmony is that if we act in accord with
these three views actually there's no possibility for either growth in the path
and there's no point in conducting ourselves ethically because ethical conduct has no effect
so because voting extends the idea this way and he says that Harmony in any
community whether a small group or a whole society depends on a shared commitment to
ethical conduct and we might say that right view is what makes shared ethical conduct possible
it's the observation that our our Deeds now actually do have results in the future
that how how we've acted in the past is conditioning the mind of now the group of now
the scenario of now and that it's possible for us to distinguish a wholesome Deed from an
unwholesome deed the syllogism that bikubody is putting together here is pretty simple sort of
Right View is a condition for virtuous Behavior which is a condition for a harmonious
community we might say that the harmonious
community that the Buddha envisioned had as its basis a shared understanding
in wholesome conduct and a commitment to live according to
our observations this scope of Right View about cause and
effect is called mundane right view in contrast to what we what bikubody calls
Transcendent Right View which has more to do with um
a matured Right View that supports the the path of Liberation
specifically and this mundane Right View is where we begin this is our working hypothesis
he puts it another way and calls it the the right view of one's personal responsibility for one's Deeds
it's worth repeating and reflecting on this this notion of karma of causality of karmic fruit karmic seed
and the effect of karmic seeds in fruiting it's worth reflecting on this and repeating it because it's so Central
to the path and as we'll see through the week is the basis for an understanding in Social and
communal Harmony now how we go about training in this is
something we'll unpack over the the next several sessions but I'll say right now and flesh this out a
bit more tomorrow that the basic beginning exercise similar to what we did in the meditation today is acting
reflectively observing for ourselves the effect of our actions
observing the quality the quality of our of our impulses
and making sure making sure that we are paying attention
are we are we doing things that are wholesome are we harming others
um are we working for their suffering are we working for welfare and happiness
this is the practice in Right View and it shows up in all sorts of ways in the teaching
but it's worth saying again Harmony in any community
the small group or a whole society depends on this commitment
so in close I'll quote because body once more he says through mundane Right View
one understands that unwholesome Karma Deeds Arisen from impure motives
these eventually rebound upon oneself and bring suffering
a bad rebirth and spiritual deterioration conversely
one understands that wholesome Karma wholesome action Deeds are risen from virtuous motives lead to happiness
fortunate rebirth and spiritual progress so for us perhaps the centrality of
Right View it can be a powerful motivator to pursue the path with Clear Vision
clear seeing inspiring to think that we have agency
that our actions matter our actions have an effect on ourselves and others and we can distinguish
harmful from unharmful and then we have this practice of
refining our conduct iteratively because we understand that our Deeds
only not only Ripple out but they also rebound upon us
we take great care with our motives and observe the effect our actions have
and then as uh Reverend Angel likes to say it's a practice not a perfect
so we keep refining our skills it's not only us who benefits but the
entire community So Right View is the Forerunner of
communal Harmony tomorrow we'll continue with this theme of the Buddha's teachings on social and
communal Harmony and will turn specifically to the topic of uh personal training particularly as it relates to
Selah virtuous conduct best wishes
I I wish for you a fruitful day of practice take care