thank you everybody good to be here with you all
yeah just a feeling the enthusiasm and happiness in practicing together in this
mornings and and these days and so
um I received a request that I didn't say anything about myself introduced myself
yesterday and some people don't know me at all so maybe I just say a few words
um today about myself and so I'm in Chan I'm a long time
IMC IRC practitioner a few decades here
in the community and also have been practicing primarily
with the guild Franco for the last close to two two decades
um I've been very fortunate to be able to practice English community and
receiving the teachings and so in this last a few years having
under the training to be able to teach Dharma in the community and so I'm in
the current IRC IMC teacher training cohort
um and having very fortunate to be able to share Dharma share the practice with
everyone and so today we'll continue
and so in our meditation yesterday
um the focus was relaxation or relaxing
today we'll be expanding to add another word that starts with letter r
and that is recognition and so when our body mind and heart are
at ease and relaxed it is conducive for Clear recognition
to come forth and so today we'll um
kind of progress around this relaxed field and to begin to see things clearly
and so with that as the intro will begin our meditation together
so take a few moments to allow yourself to settle into a meditative posture
whether it's a sitting standing lying down
give yourself a few moments to arrive
Here and Now
ing clearly that you're arriving
at this moment in this space
with this experience
maybe start by having a global sense of the body sitting
lying down standing
allow the sense of a presence to come for us
we'll begin by inviting relaxation and ease
in the body mind and heart
will do a gentle scan of the body
from the bottom of the feet all the way up to the top of the head
relaxing your feet
maybe toes bottom of the feet top of the feet
relaxing legs
in the fleshy part of the legs the muscles
relaxing the knees thighs
it's a very gentle invitation
not an imposed expectation or a demands
soft soft invitation relax
allow the pelvic area to settle down naturally
giving to the wonders of gravity
nothing we have to do just resting down
relaxing the belly
softening and easing up any holding heightening
that it can't be softened
you know for me there is a sense of just gentle opening of the belly
as I breathe in
the relaxed settling as I breathe out
using up at the lower back ever so slightly
not a big project
softening and opening up the chest
ever so slightly so the shoulders can draw
relaxing the muscles and the upper back
let's flip out sense of your whole torso right now
letting shoulders arms and hands naturally drop
softening relaxing the neck
relaxing the face muscles and the face
jaw inside of the mouth
relaxing the forehead skull
what's the global sense of your body right here and right now
maybe a sense of a little more grounding now
relaxing the heart and the mind
however you may be associated with them
as the body mind and heart Settles
being a little more relaxed
and they began to recognize
different experiences
maybe you're recognizing a little bit of a calm
or maybe a lot
or maybe it's easy to recognize the thinking mind
so recognition naturally happens
when the body mind and heart are at ease
and clear seeing naturally happens
in a relaxed field
let me recognize the sound
and my boys the ambience the sound
and they recognize certain emotions
in the heart
allow this recognition
to be carried through in a useful and relaxed away
in simple recognition
a very light touch
it's a relaxation and direct connection
can happen anytime in the course of the meditation
maybe you'll recognize certain tension
extra tension like Joe was built up
invite relaxation and ease
social relaxing and recognizing
and support each other
a relaxed attention and hold our experiences like a holding
the premature baby
from yesterday's story
nothing to do is kind gentle contact
with the movements of the breath
tingling Sensations and the feet
and
it's inflating movements in the mind emotions
thoughts
holding them like a holding a baby
and when they leave allow them
allow them to leave on their own terms
as I rang the bell to end to the sitting if you like
you can stay in the meditative mode to receive the dharmette
[Music]
so a transition to the short dharmette
so today I'll continue the theme of
multifaceted nature of our normal practice
and I read one story yesterday um from this book a monastery with Ing
and this is the book that I've been reading from and
um we spoke about how an engineer who um
this practice kind of ran into a wall and this wall was a
kind of a how he was practicing with all of this conceptual Frameworks that were stuck in
his head and what happened was when
um the app is offered a new instruction
which is a holding the baby in premature maternity award
and through this gentle contact with the baby something opened up after
and this transition and so today I'll read uh yet another
story in this book [Music] um and there's a story touched a yet
another dimension of our practice and that probably all of us would have
to face at some point of our practice Journey so you know without spoiling you even
further I'm gonna read to this story for you
the story is called finding the right teacher
many people arrived at the monastery hoping to be admitted to the monastic
order some were sent away since what they were
searching for was not to be found in the monastery
once there was a 30 year old man who arrived at the monastery feeling
exhausted discouraged and hopeless he had decided he was no longer capable
living in the worldly life perhaps he hoped the monastery would
provide him with a pass that would bring him freedom
it was the birth of his second child that had pushed the man over the edge
he could no longer manage to live with the frustration and the demands on his
time that her family life had become he was also worn down by his older
child's constant of pushing the limit of acceptable behavior
decide to comment makes how many of us would relate to that right
when he came to the monastery he asked that he be put under the care of the abbess
or another great teacher who could help him find peace
he felt encouraged when he was told that this could be arranged
however first he would have to prepare himself and approve himself to be worthy by
sitting alone in meditation for seven days in a small waiting room next to the main
to the main entrance of the monastery
the man cry to the first two days during the third day
he was washed with alternating waves of nausea and the fear
the fourth was a spander reviewing his life
for the fifth and the sixth days he seems to be questioned
every belief he had by the seventh day
he was beginning to feel calmer and certainly more rested than when he had
arrived the days earlier add to the end of the seventh day
he eagerly waited to be admitted into the monastery and to find out who would
be his teacher when the seventh day was over
Abbas and herself came for the man she congratulated him on completing the
solitary retreat come said the abbess and I will introduce you to your new
teachers it took a while but we have found the ideal people who
can help you find both your spiritual strength and the freedom
the abyss then led the man out to the front gate of the monastery
waiting for him there were his wife and the two children
happily to see them the man raised out to embrace them
then the abyss declared your wife and the two children are your
ideal ideal teachers in your case nowhere else but in your own family will
you find the freedom you're looking for with that
app is close to the monastery gate
hmm okay so how many of you can relate to
the story and I can certainly relate it to the story myself
I'm having a child who knows just exactly which button to push and what
time and I can say for certain and that
um at times he is my best teacher
and practicing with the family is humbling challenging
and enriching
and I like this um specific words that the appest said
um that is said to the man that is
and that's where um you will find your spiritual strength
and the freedom
that's where you can find a strength and the freedom
and so for myself I can say for sure and that this years of a practicing with
a family child um
both my son and myself are growing and maturing in various ways
and so this is story um pointed out to some aspects of the
practice that all of us may have to consider at some
point prominent aspect that I like to share
um you know baby based on my own interpretation of this story there may
be many different interpretations of the story but that this is just the one
aspect of it which is that the Dharma practice is not
to escape from the challenges that we face
but rather were cultivating skillful ways to meet our challenges
and so this 30 year old man went to the monastery and had this a sense of trying
to escape out of the challenges that he was facing
and so somehow stay in the monastery would be the solution for him
into the overwhelming demands from the family kind of overpowered
audacity and yet and this is seven days solitary
retreat maybe in some ways um
opened up a little bit something inside of him
maybe you know this is a my own interpretation maybe I had a little
sense that um and that the solution is not found out
there but rather into something within
and the app is certainly recognized as for him and the practice has to unfold for this
particular man unfold in his family life
but of course you know you can see this is a Story the app is instruction seems
to um abbas's instruction and the seven day solitary Retreat it seems to somehow did
a little magic here but it is a story it is a tale in real
life there may be many many ways that
can support us to skillfully navigate meeting with the challenging situations
in life and for each of us and we may over time
find ways to engage meet with the
difficulties and challenges and what I want to offer a few words and
just some pointers of you know how we might meet with the challenges just like
this person who went on to the monastery to look for a teacher and sometimes when
we are overwhelmed by our own challenges finding a teacher finding a trustworthy
friends or a therapist and to talk about the challenges can be helpful and that
can offer a certain kind of a resource for us and other times maybe we know something
for ourselves how not to be caught by the overwhelm
and for myself staying close to mindfulness of the body
practice has been game changing in so many ways
in meeting all kinds of the challenges by staying with the felt sense in the
body it allowed me to see through many kind of mentally constructed
stories and surprisingly many of this
stories can both feel like enormous challenges that we can't get through
but when we're really staying with the body we began to see
that this are mental constructs that are not so solid
and there may be other ways that we can meet what the challenge is
for example turning to something that might provide a resource that supports
us like a loving kindness practice compassion practice
or maybe we do simple things that may be
supportive and helpful like going to explore nature
becoming more physically engaged in certain activities
like a garden name or going out for a run or cook a meal for
the family I'm naming this um
because there are many many skillful names that may be possible available
in different situations and at different times under the art of the practice is to
learn what might be suitable for our own situation
and so curiosity patience openness and courage to kind of explore
at different aspects and go a long way and no matter what practices we choose
to do
and so I think that may be enough to be said for today
um maybe one last point I wanted to say is
also that it's helpful to recognize what might not be supportive in situations in
challenging situations like a resorting to unwholesome Indulgence might not be helpful
and kind of binge watching news may not be very helpful
or resorting to various toxic kind of addictions may not be helpful
and these are the things that over time will begin to be able to discern
and so my invitation today I is
to invite us to include the challenges in our lives
include practicing with the challenges when we are able to do this for
ourselves this will be beneficial both for
ourselves and for all beings all around and so may this practice with challenges
be a beneficial resource for all beings everywhere
thank you everyone for your attention and I'll see you tomorrow