greetings friends greetings to all of you from
Mountain View California unseated oloni land hope you are well wherever you are
in the world and I'm delighted to be joining you
together joining each other to uh to practice this morning or In This Moment
In Time So today we're going to continue our exploration of compassion cultivation as
it is done in expanding concentric circles start with ourselves
good next category we extend to is the benefactor dear friend
and then the neutral person very important category that we worked with
yesterday and now today we've come to a uh a pivotal category one we've been
I've been looking forward to actually which is the person we have challenges with the person we have challenges with
and um I like to use the long version instead
of saying a challenging person because they're not from their vantage point they're not challenging they're just
doing the best they can and maybe they they think we're challenging but the person we're having
challenges with so at this moment in time
so the neutral person we worked with
yesterday is really the stepping stone to to expanding our heart bringing ease
to our heart with respect to someone we're having challenges with
so let's just practice together and I'll give some invitations for us to explore
and again this is for the benefit of the piece of our heart
um it's not it's not necessarily for them it's really for us to have peace and ease and
expansion of our of our compassion so so let's practice together
now arriving arriving arriving in our seat arriving in our
bodies arriving in this moment in time
feeling our feet on the Earth our legs our sit bones our hands
feeling our entire body seated and receiving the breath
and connecting allowing awareness invading inviting
inviting awareness to connect with the entirety of the breath
in breath hauls out breath in the body in the body
receiving the breath in the body
and as we sit and feel grieved letting there be a
sense of good will for ourselves sense of appreciation
for showing up we're showing up in this moment as best as we're able to
instance of Goodwill for ourselves
the appreciation that we are doing the best we can especially with respect to our challenges our difficulties
and
and with the same gesture of a mother holding a
child a newborn lovingly
letting ourselves with our tenderness be held
with kindness
and now inviting the neutral person we were practicing
with yesterday if you're not practicing yesterday no problem invite someone you don't know so well
appreciating their common Humanity just like me
just like me you have Joys and sorrows
and sitting them sitting with them in your heart space with Goodwill
with friendliness
you might notice that they're no longer neutral you've developed a
sense of affection warmth kinship with them
Maybe notice
if that is present or not yet which is perfectly fine
these categories are so transient
now inviting someone you're having Tom challenge with maybe nothing
number one person on your list the most challenging
the person you're having the most challenges with uh
somewhere in somewhere lower
bring this person to your mind to your heart
and if you need to keep them a little further away that's okay too
Hunter them up seeing them as clearly as you can
while staying embodied staying in your seat of stability
if it's possible to see them as clearly as possible
and see that just like you just like you this this person suffers just like you they suffer they suffer a
lot
just like you they're the object of affection
of other people other beings
they are there they have been there they are very dear
they are loved
appreciate it they're a good friend to someone
they are a good friend to someone
maybe they're really kind generous loyal
airing
supportive to someone
else like me they have hopes and aspirations have values
just like me they don't want to suffer just want to be happy they don't want to suffer
no one to be free from sorrow and pain
you are not condoning it any harm they have caused you
but we're letting go of that story right now
and just feeling into the common Humanity not condoning the harm
tuning into the common Humanity
separating the behavior from the person our hearts our minds can do that
we are capable you see the humanity
and hold this person with good will just because they're a human being just
like me and they suffer just like me wishing them well
as much as available as much as possible
and again it defend your heart and your mind they need to be far away in distance
on another on an island for you to feel safe enough to wish them
well that's okay
or they might be able to be closer really seeing feeling the common Humanity
just like me they suffer just like me just as I wish to be
free from sorrow may may this person be free
from sorrow
just as I would have E's and peace as I meet my challenges difficulties in my
life and peace as they meet their challenges
find your own way with the phrases
with seeing common Humanity trust that it's possible trust that you can
whatever amount available In This Moment
we wish you well
and also it might be helpful
to see the two of you you and the person you're having challenges with
in this entanglement and the way you're entangled or have
been entangled through all these causes and conditions that brought you together and
you got entangled in this way and wishing both of you well
wishing both of you well in ease with this entanglement that happened
where is happening I wish both of us is peace
freedom from sorrow and suffering
as we have been entangled
challenged
I wish you well
I hold with good will with understanding with ease with
friendliness both of us in this entanglement
offering ease to my heart it's okay it's okay
May both of us be free May both of us have ease
the midst of challenge I wish both of us well
and maybe your heart feels ready to release
and wish well release maybe just a little bit
release this entanglement in usual
for both of you
coming back to our seats
the breaths to the body as we turn to close this period of sitting together
and appreciating that we've showed up and we've done our best as best as we're able to
In This Moment In Time this practice giving our heart as much as possible
cultivating Good Will compassion
knowing that there are seeds of goodness planted a little ripen in their own time
not our time their own time
and without attachment the outcome Right Here and Now
sharing this co-created goodness offering it to all beings everywhere
may my practice be of service not just to myself and those
whose lives I touch directly but all things everywhere may all beings be free
may all beings be happy including myself
foreign
[Music] the recordings and are session from the meditation to a
dharmette you are invited if you want to put one word as to what's coming up
after this meditation for you you're invited to put it in chat
greetings everyone and just as we ended our
meditation I ask you to put maybe one word as to what's coming up and
in your heart rate now and I'll just offer a few things that you have offered
so many so many things in the space beautiful offerings release gratitude
love perspective confusion generosity entanglement a lot of it
some sadness holding lightly gratitude for the teachings kindness
softness of heart Humanity being present transformation easing of difficulty
loosening rumbling art understanding grief so yeah
loosening up thank you all thank you for for offering for offering what's arising
and being bringing to the space so today we are continuing
with the theme of with expansion of the cultivation compassion cultivation as
I've mentioned I'll review it it happens it's done systematically in concentric
circles starting with ourselves and our benefactor expanding some more
dear friend expanding some more neutral person expanding some more and then the person we have challenges with
and this this part is so rich this part is so rich this this
um this expansion of the heart for those we have challenges with
um as I said before the meditation I like
to not use in fact in the midwest we don't use the the traditional label for
this category the traditional label for this category is is the um
um enemy but in the west we don't say enemy we say often teachers say the
challenging person or difficult person and I don't like to say challenging or difficult person because if we label
that person in our minds as challenging or that's my difficult person like oh they're difficult for oh ouch already
we're labeling them we're already our mind our perception our perspective is already deciding that yet they are
difficult I'm the one doing my best they're difficult and that there's no such a thing we are entangled with one
another in fact they might think that we're the difficult or challenging person from their perspective so so
calling them with this label of this mouthful of the person we are having challenges with
right now you can add right now because maybe in the past we didn't have challenges with it maybe in the future
we would not have challenges um but right now we happen to be entangled we happen to be entangled
um and they happen to be entangled with us so so
compassion for the person we're having challenges with even saying that oh that to me in my
heart there are some there's some release right there it doesn't make it fixed there's no fixedness that oh yeah
they're the challenging person they're never going to change I'm never going to change but oh for right now we're
entangled it's just it's it's a fluid thing it's impermanent it brings the
acknowledgment of the grace of impermanence it brings that acknowledgment in there and right now just something has happened or is
happening that this entanglement because of all the causes and conditions many of them beyond our control
this entanglement is happening so
so it's very important as we cultivate and um it is very important as we cultivate the
compassion and open our hearts little by little as much as available to release
entanglement and wish well for the person uh we're having challenges with is um
it doesn't mean that we let go of the the harm that has been
done it doesn't mean this kind of compassion some people
um don't don't dip their toes because they're afraid
that they're going to become um they become weak they become more uh
vulnerable to to Future abuse no it doesn't work that way so so so
hear me out one is that we don't condone the actions
we separate the actions the behavior from the humanity of the individual and
we might still hold them accountable of course for their actions and
um and and maybe even keep some distance between us and them
um as I think Sylvia Borstein says we we may throw people out of our lives but we
don't throw them out of our hearts so you may decide okay this person you know
it's just not appropriate for us to have contact and and it's just too hurtful and and it's more it's wiser not to have
not to be in my life but you don't throw them out of your heart you wish them well you wish them well so can so
separating the behavior from the humanity of the person and if if the circumstances are such
that you continue to be engaged with the person again you engage from a place of
common Humanity kindness good will they're doing their best maybe they're screwing up maybe you're screwing up
it's it's an entanglement together and kindness for both of you good will for both of you and not condoning the
actions again uh separating the actions from the coming Humanity
of the person and in fact it takes a lot of courage and strength to have this
kind of compassion and this kind of kindness for the people we have had entanglements with it is
um it takes great courage and strength and it also gives us a sense of uprightness
and compassion their nuances to compassion compassion isn't just
um soft and and and and tender compassion can also be fierce fierce
compassion is another way that it shows up again it shows up with a lot of care but with a lot of wisdom of what is
appropriate um and and
when we have compassion 360 degrees including ourselves and other people say
if this is someone with whom we've been in say abusive relationship when we have
complete compassion for ourselves and them there is this sense of fierceness
compassion that comes in in our hearts like okay I care for you I love you and
for the sake of myself and you I'm not going to allow you to hurt me again
anymore so there's a sense of fierceness out of its and it's not out of hatred
it's not out of hatred for the other person but it's out of love for ourselves and for them like this is not
appropriate so love and wisdom really come in to create the sense of
um appropriateness and I in in the west we tend to call it boundaries but I don't
like the word boundaries because boundaries is already creating separation like oh you over the you know
you you're separate but we see the common Humanity but wisdom creates this
this I don't know this sense of um
um yeah this this the strength the sense of uprightness this sense of fierce
compassion for ourselves and for them to allow the to allow kindness compassion
to flow uh and not enabling not enabling uh
say abuse Etc so this is a very very important distinction to make
so yesterday I I promised to say a little bit about the um those that were to say
more about the um the enemies of of the near enemy and the far enemy
of compassion so we've already discussed in the past few days that the two of the
near enemies or the masqueraders things that masquerade as compassion but they're not compassion one of them being
empathic distress or grief with sense of grief you're falling into the waves with
the person instead of having the stability to have kindness for them um and that's a really important one we
discussed that you can go back and listen to number two I do to day two and
um we also discussed pity yesterday which is another masquerader which is a less than oh it never happened to me uh
so compassion from this high place of oh yeah I'm up here and I'll pour you poor you and pity is not compassion
now today I wanted to bring in What's called the far enemy which is another
word for saying the opposite the opposite of compassion and the opposite of compassion is cruelty is cruelty
so cruelty is is easily recognizable it's not a masquerader but say it can
arise um and when for example you're trying to to cultivate say compassion for the
person you're having challenges with and and if you're in your your brain to mind you bring to hard to come in humanity
you bring to mind the way they suffer and instead of your heart extending in
kindness oh oh you too like me oh YouTube like me it's like oh you're
feeling happy for their suffering ouch that is cruelty that is the definition
of Cruelty taking joy and Delight in other person's suffering so if that
arises please recognize it and then turn and then instead of
turning towards yourself with with you know self-judgment like oh how can I have cruel this is terrible like okay
pause pause pause bring in kindness and wisdom to yourself okay sweetheart
what's going on here you must be really really hurt to be resorting to Cruelty
sweetheart this is yeah this oh this is not good for you it's not good for your own heart development your own Karma the
way you feel the way you think the way you show up in the world so so can't so
bring kindness understanding acceptance instead of pushing it away and trying to make it into an exile
accept and understand it and that's step number one step number two is consider
the um the the [Music] um
the the deterrence the the the the heavy weight the karmic weight the the the
negative aspects um of of of Cruelty it's it's it's
um in fact it's it's almost like the cruelty and you know the other negative
um uh emotions externally like anger for example it's it's it's in the there's a
simile that it's likened to to you wearing a um the skin of a dead
um uh that snake which is kind of repulsive and ugly right it's like ooh
it's not very inviting so so you can light you can use similar you can use
some similar um uh similes and and feelings like yeah actually
cruelty it's quite unattractive the unattractiveness in in the qualities of
the heart so these are some ways to perhaps if if the far enemy if the
opposite of compassion arises if you're doing this practice you can support yourself so
so a lot more on this topic a lot more in this topic but uh
um we have one more day to practice together and um I want to invite you if you will
for the rest of the day if it's helpful to consider you and the person you've
been entangled with if it comes up to wish both of you well wish both of you in this entanglement wish both of you
and see if there can be some release you can do some release some letting go
yes um and and um
yeah somebody also put in schadenfreude yeah schadenfreude is this this great
German word taking joy in this in the pain and the sadness of others very yeah
it's that's another far enemy here so it's a cruelty so so thank you all for
for your engagement and I see there's a question about boundaries yeah um maybe I'll just take a moment to
clarify that so for me it's a sense of boundaries that we use is is such a sense of separation of our Humanity but
there's a way that we can have this this uprightness but with with kindness for ourselves kindness for others
um maybe I'll say more about that tomorrow the time has run out so thank you all may you be
well may you practice well with kindness with compassion if there are any entanglements for the rest of the day
and looking forward to practicing with you tomorrow be well