good morning or this those of you on this part of the
continent it's morning if you're on another continent it might not be morning
I'm happy to be here the second day and we're exploring the story of Mara
and Mara's armies and as usually happens in these 7 a.m's
we'll start with a guided meditation
so taking a moment to settle in
breathing yourself sitting
I'm bringing attention to the posture let's begin there
if you're and a seated position just noticing if the spine has some
uprightness and some ease
noticing if the ears are over the shoulders sometimes it's helpful to push
the chin back just a tiny bit really small
may not even be noticed by somebody else observing you but
pushing the chin back not down but back
can open up the top of the spine the neck
in a way that really supports some uprightness
and ease
feeling into the sitting base
buttocks the legs the feet foreign
connected grounded
and then just bringing this aliveness of attention I like this expression aliveness of
attention into the body into the bodily experience
inhabiting the body alive to the way that it feels right now
including the posture but also more generally
and then noticing the experience of breathing
explore this experience or feel it on its own terms
is there a way that we can step towards
the experience of breathing
Getting to Know It without
The Experience needing to be different
we're just noticing how it is
can we bring some curiosity
to the experience of breathing as if you've never been with the
sensations of breathing before
Maybe in the same way that a naturalist
observes nature can we be a naturalist
to the experience of breathing we're not trying to figure it out or
understand it we're just noticing [Music]
what does that feel
foreign
setting the Direction of our practice together as one of
kindness warmth
can we bring this quality of kindness in the manner in which we'll be paying
attention the way we're paying attention
can we imbue our attention with care
and warmth
and then when the mind wanders just very simply gently
with this warmth and kindness Begin Again
with the sensations of breathing
foreign and now
having studied a little bit settled a little bit
by resting the attention on the sensations of breathing
can open it up a little bit to other experiences that are compelling
sounds you know the sounds of airplanes
overhead or dogs barking nearby
someone who shares your household moving about
whatever it might be
just noticing no sound
and then can return to the anchor the sensations of breathing
in a relaxed easy manner
you don't have to pounce on other experiences we don't have to
jerk the Mind back
being mindful with kindness and warmth but not complacency or
just being casual
but being here with intention
maybe noticing that that sound is no longer compelling
but now perhaps there's a bodily sensation that's compelling
the pressure of the chair or cushion against the body perhaps
just notice pressure
and then begin again with the sensations of breathing
in this way we're open to The Human Experience
In This Moment bringing some curiosity
what does it feel like to be a human at this time at this moment
precisely now
without thinking that things should be otherwise
instead having some curiosity
not trying to figure things out but just curious what is there to notice
so we stay with the sensations of breathing until
something else becomes compelling
can bring our attention to that
then when it's no longer compelling
we return the sensations of breathing
foreign
in these last few minutes
what would it be like to bring some curiosity to the experience what's really
happening again not to figure it out or understand
it but to notice
notice the texture of the moment notice they are rising and passing of
the experiences being present for what's happening
foreign
[Music]
again it's lovely to be practicing with you all
yeah so yesterday I introduced this idea of stories and some other role that they
play in our practice and certainly in our tradition and in our lives
and it turns out there are a few different stories about the Buddha's Awakening and one of those stories
includes that as the Buddha to be was sitting underneath the Bodhi Tree having
this commitment that he's not going to move until he becomes a weekend that
Mara shows up and bringing his armies with him
so Mara if we might understand as representing or symbolizing that which
is obstructing or trying to prevent our movement towards Awakening or our
progress on the path towards greater freedom and peace
and so Mara as I said yesterday and I like to emphasize in this tradition Mara
is not a satanic figure it's the story of Mara versus the Buddha
is not a story of good versus evil instead it's a story of complacency
versus effort or complacency versus commitment
to practice and we have to be a little bit careful here because when we talk about effort
or commitment to practice there might be a tendency to think like we have to work
really hard and strive in some kind of way
but actually we we there certainly needs to be effort but too much efforting is
itself can be an obstruction to practice so part of the art of practice is knowing this right amount
so the story of Mara versus the Buddha is are we just
floating along in our life or are we engaged with it and and with
the teachings in our life in such a way that leads to Greater freedom leads to Greater peace leads to Greater
well-being leads to Awakening so part of this uh story is in modern
times of the arrow River Forest Hermitage in
Northern Ontario and Canada he's from the ajanta has written these kind of whimsical
stories of Mara kind of like fleshing out Mara as a character in a way that I
think it's delightful is a lot of fun so in these talks I'm just I'm
excerpting portions of this and gonna bring It Forward for us to explore and
enhance our practice so the setting is that this Mara
character is in this you know Fantastical beautiful uh
Palace or Castle or something like this and he's dictating these letters to the
leaders of ten armies and these 10 armies are in the story
said two are the ones that assailed the Buddha and we might even understand that they
assail us today so here's the preamble to the letters
and again I'm excerpting this so here's my rice we might even say
maybe in modern times he's emailing he's sending out a group email to the leaders of these armies
greetings to all my hard-working minions as you are well aware our overall
strategy seems to be working as smoothly as usual the vast multitude of beings
you wander in our little playground the great samsara
or by and large oblivious oblivious to the true nature of their predicament but
we must continue our unceasing efforts to maintain them in our power
so again Mara it's not that he wants people to experience pain and go to hell
or anything like that Mario just wants people to feel complacent and unaware
that greater Freedom Is Possible so it just wants to make them feel like
oh yeah this is good enough so then so that's the preamble to the
letters I accepted it but what I want to talk about today is that letter or email
that Mara is sending to the second Army I'm skipping over the first Army which
is sense desire but instead for this series in the in
these mornings I want to talk about those armies quote unquote that we don't talk about as much and so the second one
is boredom boredom as an army is a experience that
gets in the way of Greater Freedom so here's more here's Mara sending an email
to my second Army the host of boredom I extend greetings and congratulations
Your Role is to act in coordination with sensual desire the first Army we must
keep beings in a state of dissatisfaction with the present reality
what a scam we keep them craving always something exciting
something new but the trick is to keep them from paying attention to the present moment
because once they're fully present here and now then they cannot be bored but
lately we've managed to foster a social climate that positively discourages calmness and
Clarity their whole modern culture is fast and frenzied and the last half half
century or so has seen many advances in our efforts to fracture the human
attention span television was a great help but I think
the single greatest advance in the Triumph of boredom was the invention of
the internet and all that and social media
we've succeeded so well in this department that being bored is now considered one of the greatest evils of
life but should they stray close to the true
escape which of course lies in the middle way then we must redouble our efforts
whisper in their ears tell them again and again these good old lies
this is really boring get out and enjoy life
so this is Mara right kind of telling uh these minions of his army to just make
sure that people are not satisfied and to whisper in their ears this is really
boring get out and enjoy life right we might have these ideas about
our meditation practice that it's somehow getting in the way of our
enjoying life or that the experience of meditating is boring
so I'll flush out just a little bit what is this experience to be bored
it's we might consider it as a state of aversion this way in which the input of the
senses whatever senses seeing or hearing or Sensations in the body or even
thoughts they're not providing this desired kick of pleasure
that we've grown to really crave that we've grown to think that this must
be what it means to be alive is to always be stimulated in some kind of way so we always are like seeking this new
and exciting stimuli and while we these days we carry these little smartphones
and in our pockets that make sure that we're never bored in fact we might even think that today's
society is built in such a way to ensure that we're never bored right we have these entire Industries
those that develop apps and not to mention like the advertising agencies that are been created just to make sure
that we're not bored and instead we're always seeking this new stimuli
and not only that we've like become so accustomed to this idea of constantly doing something quote unquote whatever
that is exactly doing something you know maybe even if it's Doom scrolling on our smartphones like that's
better it seems than just to sit quietly
so there's a way in which not doing might make us feel a little bit uh
vulnerable or this way that makes us feel guilty
because we've become so accustomed to this idea that we should be doing something that somehow our value or the
purpose of our existence is to be doing something
that's not true it's not true
is this just I kind of like this story of Mara right this creature that's like
oh yeah okay if we make beans uh really dislike being bored always seeking some
stimuli then they'll never find greater Freedom which is of course what Mara would like
so can we work with boredom or what do we do if we find ourselves to
connect this is boring well it turns out that of course
mindfulness is this great way to work with this experience of boredom
one how does boredom really feel
foreign what is the experience of boredom
is it this dullness well what does dullness feel
like not the ideas about it but what is the experience
because it come to find out the way to work with boredom is uh actually to
bring curiosity to the experience to bring investigation to the experience
whatever experience we're having that includes the experience of boredom
so can we just pay a little bit closer attention maybe like inhabit The Experience no
matter how subtle even if we feel like well nothing's
happening that's why I'm bored can we feel into the subtleness of maybe
that feeling of nothing's happening and maybe there's like this smart like little subtle contraction in the mind
I don't want to be doing this because one of the truths of life and
phenomena as all of us know is that everything is always changing
it's a rising and passing away it's inconstant it's imperf impermanent nothing stays the same
so mindfulness is paying attention to what's happening as it's happening
and just we haven't often trained ourselves to be accustomed to noticing this small and the subtle changes in our
experience because we're so used to like exciting stimuli
so that might take a little bit of patience to just recognize oh yeah can
we just be with exactly this moment
just this moment is it like how does it feel and the inside what is
the breath what are my feet teaching it's the quality of the Mind state
and it turns out that with mindfulness practice is I'm sure many of you know
means that you will never be bored because there's always an opportunity to
be with the present moment and this is such a great way to increase our mindfulness capacity is it
we ever feel ourselves wanting to go towards that next uh stimulating thing that we think is going to be inside our
smartphones or on the other side of the computer screen
just bring some awareness to the experience to that Human Experience
and just see if we can notice some of the subtle changes that are happening
and then of course many of you know in the the stories of the Buddha include
that Mara visiting the Buddha even after he was awakened and what does the Buddha
say to him he says I see you Mara
and then Mara disappears so in the same way
here's boredom I see you boredom and it feels like this
and that's the ending of boredom so thank you for your attention and I
look forward to exploring some of these other armies of Mara later this week thank you very much