hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour and if you can hear me okay
okay give me a thumbs up audio is good fantastic so hello and welcome I'm Nikki
in Mountain View California and cated Oland welcoming you to this edition of
happy hour and who is here who wants to say hi share their
friendliness in uh in the zoom room and on YouTube hey this is Don D hi
Don hi Bill from Dallas hi Nate who says hi
on YouTube Neil in New Hampshire hi Neil
good evening Neil in Houston hi Neil Steve in Houston hello Steve also
in Houston and lost hi AIA and hi also in
chat it's going faster than I can keep up bill says hi from Dallas hi NE who
says from cooling Japan hi hi Bal hi Mari Christine who says huru from
Sydney Australia uh our Southern Hemisphere and Sarah Sara from Toronto Aloha says Amy
from aahu hi says he from San Diego and fil hi from Chicago land uh rugosa says
hi from rainy New England and Kane also on um on YouTube says H hello peoples
good morning from Perth in Western Australia and hi Claire from New York City Su Jun from San Francisco wow lots
of hellos very sweet busy Saturday night uh Friday night Saturday morning oh yeah
sweet okay well let's uh let's formally begin let's formally begin so um if if
you yes thank you Neil for posting information about the happy hour Google Groups if you're new to happy hour you
are warmly welcome to join the mailing list it's pretty low traffic and also we
have a document to look at uh as invitations to offer yourself and others
care and safety when you engage in the small breakout groups later okay so I
Chang the settings uh one can't mute oneself and also chats will only come to me but I
ask you to keep that channel quiet as well otherwise it can be quite distracting for me to read chats while
I'm uh teaching okay and then I'm going to
record for the sake of Audio Dharma and before I start that oh Kane the
information is shared on um uh Zoom only so you h you're welcome to hop on zoom
and and get the info but not on YouTube uh decided not to do that for a variety
ofon so okay so I'm going to start recording here we
go okay so hi everyone hello and welcome lovely to be with you great to see you
what a joy what a joy so so so
this being kind of towards the end of the week um on where I am in this
location in this world in this time and space um what I like to invite us is to
practice together and the teachings will come during the practice I'll keep it
relatively light so that we can have a spacious um sit together with with
teachings but it seemed more appropriate to me to do it that way okay
so so so let us let us arrive let us survive in our
bodies let us arrive in this moment in
time letting go of thoughts plans
[Music] preoccupations whatever has come
before and releasing completely giving our heart to this
moment however it's showing up can we receive it receive this moment
this experience with
benevolence with kindness friendliness meeting this moment with
friendliness whether there is pain in this moment
distraction sleepiness
heartache can we meet this moment with
friendliness and steadiness of
heart steadiness and for steadiness it helps to connect with the breath the
sensations of the breath in the
body not as a yard stick not as it should but as a way to support
ourselves as a way to sooe [Music]
stabilize the same way that an anchor can stabilize a [Music]
boat from drifting here and there and
everywhere and then and yet don't let it be so heavy-handed this anchor of the
[Music]
breath let it be feather-like gentle
loving calming and collecting
meeting this breath this breath just as in breath as a friend this out breath as a
friend this sensation as a friend
friend how do you usually meet a friend you open your arms you embrace
them perhaps you smile at them you're glad to see them even if
they're
weary
meeting this breath in breath out breath as a
friend see what can shift in the way you are being in this moment if you take
that this perspective
on
if your mind starts to wonder about what does it mean to meet this moment meet
this breath whatever is happening in the body and mind as a friend just remind
yourself how do you behave around a friend how do you meet them welcome them
greet them you know this already you know this through and
through all your inner
wisdom
if you find your mind is wandering and you meet it with kindness benevolence friendliness see what
happens
we are practicing meeting this moment like a
friend as a friend we are
practicing being friendly with
experience for the sake of ourselves and all
beings
I be friendly towards this body breathing sitting maybe
aching pulsating may be
friendly
Can I Be steady can there be steadiness in my
intense attention attention and [Music] friendliness
together and if there's no steadiness it's okay can I be friendly through other
friendliness reinvite steadiness not through ill
well
I connect and sustain every moment
connecting breath with this experience and sustaining my
awareness my connection and rels connect and
sustain connect and
sustain
and if the mind is distracted In This [Music] Moment try to connect and sustain your
attention with sensations of your body maybe the feet your sit bones your
hands really connect with the breath become more
embodied with a friendly
attitude
radiating friendliness radiating
friendliness drop it in see what might show up radiating
friends to yourself to the moment to
others
and as we bring this sitting period to a close can we offer friendliness to
ourselves for whatever showed up or didn't show up without
judgment it's okay can we appreciate that we showed up
and did our best and planted seeds can we [Music]
meet this moment of ending of the practice with friendliness not with
frustration or regret or what not just simply with
appreciation with friendliness we showed up yay yay
yay [Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your
practice so
so yeah so let's
turn um so uh yeah let's try maybe I'll ask
before we um uh turn to small groups maybe I'll
ask you all to share uh a reflection what's what's coming up for you in this
moment how are you feeling after this practice um just one word or phrase and
mind is um happy yeah
a sense of Happiness a little more steady and a
little more settled steady grounded sleepy that's perfectly fine Kinder more
friendly content yeah and everything is fine
self-compassionate thank you for the reflections proud of myself yay
[Laughter] yay yeah it's great brought yourself to
this practice it's beautiful um nice I think whatever is showing up
whether sleepiness or not or whatever it is letting there be um Let There Be
kindness friendliness giving love what I deserve yeah
peaceful home's reflection on YouTube
beautiful yeah disappointed yeah that's fine too can can we be friendly can we
be friendly with whatever is arising this is really the cultivation
of friendliness and meta that's the what we try to cultivate here with
this practice could we be friendly with whatever Rises instead of having an antag istic
relationship at peace with my distractions says another one of you
nice so so as we turn and actually before we
go into small groups um uh if it is possible um to post information Neil
about the Google Groups the person who was on YouTube is now on Zoom so if you could share that
again you thank thank you for posting that thanks NE so so as we turn to small
groups at this time here's the invitation the invitation is
um to to explore for your own sake what
does it mean what does it feel like to be friendly with experience what does it feel like for you what's what are the
challenges what are the gifts what is your growing Edge um just exploring for
your own sake and then the two other people in the room are just holding you witness and they're not going to ask you
questions clarifications that's not the purpose it and if you're listening and you didn't understand what the person
said it's not for you to understand you're just holding friendly space for
them you're just holding friendly space you're you're beaming you're radiating friendliness as they explore out loud
with your with the benefit of your find presence so you offer one nugget and as
you're exploring then past the Baton the next person will go reverse alphabetical order according to first
name next person will do an exploration for me to be friendly it means maybe it
means um yeah not being so hard on myself and being being more friendly and
not so judgmental that's that's my growing Edge maybe that's what they offer or something like that and the
next person offers for something and then comes back to you so you go around a few times be kind to yourself be kind
to each other no questions no advice um no cross talk just let yourself explore
for your own benefit really give it a try see see it's it's it's precious so
so with that I will create the breakout rooms
and where are you breakout rooms here we and making them great so yeah
any questions any anything before we go into the
groups okay I'm going to open the rooms take care of yourselves take care of
each other be kind and it's just such a privilege to be interacting with with uh
fellow Travelers okay here we
go
the rooms will close and about yes they're closed everybody's
back okay welcome back [Music] every or we have a few minutes for
Reflections for questions um what did you
discover from this practice and I especially like to invite those of you who haven't spoken in person recently if
you have please pull back and you're welcome to put your Reflections in chat but if you haven't spoken recently
please pull forward what did you discover for the benefit of every
yourself to
oh is chat not open I thought it was it is
open I feel like a sense in the last I'd say week or two of some progress that
feels nice I um I wrote on my mirror um I love you and so every time I'm doing
the dishes I'm in like a tiny little Ohana unit so it's like my sink for the bathroom and the dishes and all the
things I look at it and I just smile at myself and I I just I'm
trying I I'm able to pause and notice the inner critic I'm able to pause and
just be like oh there you are and I love myself and I'm giving myself the benefit
out that I'm doing the best I can and even though there's too many things to do and never enough time to do them that
like I'll figure it out and I have the best of intentions and so I'm Gonna Love This
Love Story we've been talking that you've mentioned I've dedicated to it I'm dedicated I'm going to do a ceremony
for I'm going to love myself For Better or For Worse yay this is so beautiful Amy this
is so beautiful thank it's it's really what you're speaking about is the wisdom of the ages it's not
self-advertisement um and and you know it it can be up and it's not what you're
talking about so I I I know what you're talking about it is beautiful it is the
wisdom of the ages we need to deeply appreciate love the
um the you know the goodness the beauty the challenges the the The Faults of
this being who means doing their best because that's how they're going to grow that's how they're going to show up as
their best they're not going to grow and become the best they can in in a
container of self-judgment and self-hatred it just does not happen it is in the container of love and accept
that actually one takes responsibility for for one's faults and one's
challenges like yeah sweetheart you screwed up I still love you and we're going to do better next time so I am
just Overjoyed to hear that you're dedicated to it and and the message is
getting through this is so beautiful and so creative to write it on your mirror thanks for sharing that anything else
you want to add a yeah just that I think you know and I do think it's giving me the capacity to to show up for others
and the same you know like that's the purpose of it right it's a much bigger purpose than this individualized nature
of meeting the inner critic differently um it's for a bigger scale for like we
do you know may have benefit all right so exactly right yeah we need to start
with ourselves so that we can have the
loving caring stance to towards all you [Music]
thank you Amy thanks so much for bring the yay celebrating
Y and and um Amy Megan says I'm Finly
understand how important self love is thank you yes exactly just what may
[Music] said service to to all being everyone we
don't do this for ourselves we can do it for all things everyone [Music]
I yeah I um had an interesting experience with Mara on my sit um I was
feeling a lot of anxiety in my body and I and I told Mara I saw her but I told
her I would take care of her and that it was okay and that um I trust her to be
with me so that was yeah that was really nice yeah beautiful and what happened oh um
my anxiety um dissipated and um and I also told myself
well it's not going to kill me and uh but I just
liked the um embodiment of the trust um
that um it would be okay and then I could take care of
it nice nice it's it's beautiful expression of friendliness towards XYZ
towards the moment towards challenges instead of having adding more aversion
to what is challenging meeting them with kindness and seeing how they get transformed because of course we've
tried you know hating them and pushing them away and being angry with them how
well did that work let's try something different for a while this is great thank you Audrey I
love it yeah friendliness towards far and also again to contextualize for for
those who might be new again what what Audrey is speaking about is not giving into the distractions and the mara you
know whatever Mara represents and here as some people might wonder what is this Mara they're talking about so in
Buddhism the um in in Buddhism uh Mara is the representation of all the what
what's called hindrances or rather all the coverings the the ill will and and
and being distracted and sleepy and you know all the things that get in the way it's kind of a personification of that
and yet the way to work with Mara is and and in this case the sense of anxiety
and and and remorse and restlessness is another one of the Mara and what Audrey
was speaking about and and it's so unhelpful to try when they arise on our
path and of course they arise they arise when we're meditating they arise in our daily life it's not helpful to to have
ill will and push them away in that way but um so so the the middle way is the
wise way between suppression and Indulgence so one
doesn't want to indulge them but you don't want to to suppress them either so
the middle way is why wise relationship and what Audrey was describing is this
wise relationship can I accept that you're here can I be friendly can I
soften around you not give in to you and yet not hate you so that that that
middleway wise um relationship thanks Audrey that was
great yeah yeah any other reflection before we
close especially if you have not spoken recently and of course you can put them
in chat remember yeah maybe we'll leave it as
that yeah
yeah so thank you so much for your
practice thank you so much for coming here thank you for um yeah cultivating
your heart being a resource for yourself being a resource for one another really
appreciate that you taking the time to practice cultivate for the for service
to um to all beings everywhere not just ourselves but all beings everywhere may
all beings be well may all beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone take care be well