so tonight I'd like to talk about the roots of dharmic happiness
and as introduction just visualize if you're a visualizer
imagine that you're on a path winding through an Ancient
cathedral-like Forest canopy like a rainforest or something like that
it's very quiet very deep silence
maybe a few bird calls light filtering through the leaves
and there's a sense of presence growing things and reverence
as you walk the path turns a corner and you come
upon a clearing and in the middle of the queering there's this massive beautiful Bodhi
Tree and the path kind of goes around circumambulates around the tree
so that you can see these big sloping partitions of the tree going down deep
into the Earth The Roots
there's a feeling of silence and awe and deep Trust in the Majesty of this place
so tonight I'm going to talk about some important roots
sources of dharmic development and happiness on the path
these are attitudes that are onward leading in both personal and spiritual
maturation and joy and they are
kind of trust or confidence in the path itself
there are a sense of and then the other three are called the three wholesome
roots the three wholesome roots and Buddhism and those are a non-greed non-hatred and
non-delusion so first the trust the con confidence
in the unfolding of the path of practice there are two poly words commonly used
to um that are commonly used that are translated as trust or confidence and
they're both very closely related to the word for tranquility or calm
passati and those two words Sada and avicha Pasada
you can hear the similarity right sadha is to rest the heart upon it's a
certain kind of trust settling at the heart
now vecha Pasada is verified Faith it's called it's the taste of something good
that's already unfolded or come from the practice
some little taste of freedom maybe a big Taste of freedom
in either case I'm a little bit more talking about the first one that's settling the heart the trusting the path
here but in either case they involve trusting the process the
intrinsic journey of the joy itself
just being on a path can be satisfying right maybe some of you have reference points
for this for me when I was a kid I went hiking in the Appalachian Trail with my parents my sister for weeks
and the act of the hiking itself was really
part of what was enjoyable right being surrounded by trees and nature and
silence and rhythms water for all that time
and occasionally we would come upon these kinds of viewpoints and they weren't that different than the
sorts of places you could drive up to in the Appalachian mountain range but the view was so much more beautiful
because we had sunk into it we were in the process we were working with it
um the completely different experience and just kind of like driving up and parking and hopping out of the car and
taking picture and going on right so
there's this satisfaction that deepens as we commit
more to the path commit more to the process
trust also can come in a sense of trusting the benefits of training the
heart training the mind the conditions of our lives are rarely chosen in entirety right some of them we
choose a lot of them come to us genetics happens dance culture family
whatever but still our choices our choices matter
they create new conditions the Derma teacher Susie Harrington has
an analogy a simile I really like it's of a kayaker kayaking down white water rapids
so the kayaker she doesn't choose the way the River cuts through the land or even the amount of water in the river
she certainly doesn't choose how intense the Rapids are or the Eddies or the
trees that have fallen any of the challenges yet
Choice matters there's a skill in operating that kayak even though all the
momentum is going in One Direction in the Stream of life
she dances through it right there's a way through
so this sense of the trust can also be
trusting the unfolding process while making wise choices
committing to a virtue to goodness is a really powerful form of conditioning
there's kind of a power or a purpose and putting that boat in the water in
the Stream choosing the path
the next three sort of wholesome sources foundations roots of dharmic development
and happiness are actually called the three wholesome roots in the teachings
and they are as I mentioned earlier non-greed non-hatred and non-delusion
and this kind of clunky wording is classic ancient Buddhism it's often
framed in the negative and or in the absence of the negative
it's via negativa framed in the absence of the negative and
there's some wisdom in that right non-greed is a huge range of things it's
not just generosity or contentment it's all these different ways of being
so I'll talk about a bit of the range of each of them but as I'm talking just
notice what branches of each root might you recognize or see in your heart and
your mind and your life so non-greed there's sort of a range of
meanings there the first being contentment just simple contentment
contentment of being on a path contentment of showing up for
yourself for the moment can also arrange towards generosity
as I mentioned a moment ago chaga is the poly word for that and that is the
primary practice of most Asian lay Buddhists sometimes it's the only practice and it
is a powerful practice it develops a sense of
non-self-centeredness and it's a type of letting go right
the kind of letting go it's also really powerful for
relationship building there's a lot to quote it's actually on
one of my walls it's kindness and giving creates love
kindness and giving creates love and I'm not necessarily talking about
romantic love here of course but connection
connection between us there's this sense of the Open Hand the
gesture of offering the Open Heart the letting go that happened through this
there's another dimension of non-greed which is Simplicity itself
the Simplicity of wants needs the Simplicity of one's schedule
this leads to a certain kind of a word that's not very popular in English
which is renunciation renunciation
which is another level of non-greed the not needing to begin with less about the
giving away and more about the not needing to take not needing to grab more
very counter cultural right in our society where we get all these
messages more and more and more you need to buy this get that to be this way or whatnot
this is instead a sense of enoughness just enough
it's okay
this kind of commitment to simplicity opens up time
time it's a gift allowing extra space excess baggage doesn't have to be taken
with us it's traveling light on the journey so to speak
I learned this really in a powerful way it's now been many years ago maybe 15 years ago I was traveling on an extended
trip through South Asia and at the time I was quite injured so I
couldn't take very much stuff even though I was gone for almost a year I had a carry-on wheelie
and I had like this ergonomic very light backpack couldn't put a lot in it
that taught me so much because on that trip occasionally I would get things
right and I realized every time I got something I had to give something else up because I couldn't carry all of it
and as the trip went on gradually I was shedding more and more giving more and
more away because as many veteran Travelers know
it's kind of a pain in the butt to manage that stuff to track all that stuff to keep all that stuff safe
it actually does not lead to a better experience it's a little bit harder to see in our
daily lives but there's truth there too how much time do we spend
keeping track of all of our stuff managing it
this is true of thinking even the thought processes
or the information we take in like the endless grasping for news or
Internet information can be stressful right
so the enoughness okay that's this is enough I've seen enough headlines for today
I've seen enough social media for the year whatever it is right [Music]
so um psychologists talk about I can't remember when I first learned this but
maybe some of you have heard of it there's the um the circle of concern
and the circle of action or efficacy and it's two co-centric rings in a diagram
and a very valid predictor of human happiness is how close those circles are
to each other if my circle for of concern is massive
and my sense of efficacy or action is Tiny what does that lead to
overwhelm fatalism stress
it's not to say we shouldn't be aware of what's happening around us but to balance those two
take actions that link those two
and to have a wise diet about this stuff right
it's um it's a kind of Simplicity that I've
really come to value and it does quiet the inner mental chatter as well
it's hard to have a peaceful evening meditation if all I've done is listened to news for the
last two hours or you know pick your own flavor of what this is right
so the Simplicity of thinking also involves
a Simplicity of relationship to life to my interpretations of things I mean
our minds our interpretation meaning making organs right that's what Minds do
and yet there are ways of having a simpler relationship to what that is
and to maybe not taking it so seriously all the time right
like oh yeah I remember one of my teachers used to say yada yada blah blah blah blah when he was talking about the
mind because it just goes on and there's a way of just stepping back and being simple with that
and over hours and days and weeks and years of practice
the mind starts to do it less I was really struck by this at one point
I don't remember at what point it was in my practice that I realized the inner narrator just doesn't talk very often
anymore I was like no wonder there's so much more space
wow so that can start to happen and then
everything else opens up right and there are times it comes up again of course
for us humans that's what Minds do but even then there's the distance it's
like the difference between being this close to the flat screen television
or being on the other side of the room and having a lot more space about
context or maybe even being outside the house glancing at the TV from across the
street through the window we don't have to be glued to the content of our thoughts when there's simplicity
it's just thinking conditioning mental habit
whatever it is and then there's a Simplicity of
awareness itself and that's more of an attribute of mindfulness Lucid awareness and I'll talk a little bit more about
that later but all of those things the contentment the generosity
the Simplicity the renunciation all their kinds of branches in the root of
non-greed and then we get to non-hatred Avera is
the Pali of era and
non-hatred is has it's got a very esteemed place in the Buddhist teachings
it's a really big deal it's often a cognate for meta Goodwill
love kindness and that's a beautiful thing it's a beautiful quality
it's also a whole range of non-hostility
and John pasano on a meta Retreat early in my practice named you know you don't have to start
out by loving all living beings that's a really high bar then why don't you practice not being
averse to them quite so often right that itself is a high bar depending on
the being and depending on my mind and the day right so
non-aversion non-hatred this broad flavor includes respect
non-contempt equanimity appreciation
kind curiosity all the way up through Goodwill
benevolence altruism
compassion there's a whole range maybe you can
think of others even not particularly caring
just letting someone be that's not hatred allowing
there's a distinction that has kind of become clearer to me over the time
I've practiced this path which is um
even the smallest movement of the heart or mind can be considered an action
right sometimes in meditation you might actually feel that it's um
the about twoness of maybe like getting up or the weaning forward of wanting or
the leaning back of not wanting but those kinds of really subtle actions
and these actions also aggregate to more of an action life action
to quote Saint Thomas Aquinas to love is to will the good of the other
to love is to will the good of the other
so there's an active component to that
compassion anukampa is um sort of the natural
compassion that arises it's a quivering or movement of the heart caring
and it has an implicit the wish to respond may not be able to respond depending on
the context or the circumstances but that movement of the heart is there
this kind of love compassion kindness and it belongs to all Humanity not just
Buddhism not just any religious tradition it belongs to all of them runs through all of them underpins all of
them whether it's Love by enemy or meta for all beings
or simple generosity and charity for those who need it
those all kind of interweave and the ultimate aim in this tradition
of Metta of loving kindness is to hold everyone in that kindness
without wishing harm on any of them again Avera
non-harming ahimsa these are powerful powerful intentions
to cultivate and Powerful moments to experience
what is it like to hold that intention without even
harming or deprecating oneself when it's not there when it's not actionable
when I might want to be feeling love and kindness what I'm feeling as grumpiness irritation or even rage
can there be kindness to the mind or heart that's not there
right now is that possible
and the discernment the discernment not to buy into
the unwholesome movement the unwholesome tendency
by honestly turning towards it with awareness
this kind of stuff strengthens the muscle of emotional and spiritual maturity
requires discernment right it's like understanding there's little bitty differences about what's happening in
the mind or what causes what in our hearts there's a story I love this is from a
podcast invisibilia some Seasons back I honestly don't
remember how many but it's the story of this family who's having
it's like a barbecue or a cookout in their backyard and it's you know maybe a
Saturday afternoon or a Sunday afternoon and you know they've got something grilling and other stuff on
the table and everybody's hanging out having a good time there's a little bit of wine and it starts getting towards dusk
it's a semi-urban environment right right and out of the Dusk and the space
between the houses comes a man with a knife intending to Rob them
and he shows up brandishes this knife and demands money
and the hostess without missing a Beat stands up
Smiles at him and said welcome would you like some food here have a
glass of wine the man is dumbfounded completely
perplexed just and he was kind of young and the way the story goes his lips sort
of started quivering and he accepted the wine put away the knife ran off I didn't see
him again but the next morning when they were finishing their cleaning up
they found that wine glass empty very carefully laid against the side of the
house he didn't even take the glass he made sure not to break it
that that's the power of meta kindness in the face of
something quite different in Psychology this is called a non-complementary response
when someone comes at you with rage what's the most natural thing any of us would have
fear or anger right depending some maybe both
there might be a fight flight or freeze response on a nervous system model
it can be an extraordinary Jujitsu of the moment to have a
different response than what that calls out by instinct
I've discovered this in my work as a Chaplain too one of the hospitals that I trained at
I used to get called they they did it once by accident I think because the person who usually dealt with such
things didn't couldn't respond and then after they figured out that it worked
they kept doing it um I'm very very upset family member
was in one of the waiting rooms I mean they were yelling and they were spouting off sort of like Angry comments and
just making a real scene and so they asked me to go down and talk
to them and I was happy to go talk to him security was sort of in the background they weren't coming up but
they were nearby in case things went South it was absolutely amazing just going up
to this man and very kindly meeting him and listening and eliciting
all the concerns and empathizing with the feelings the emotion just went down
and by the end of that conversation he was praising the service
he needed to be heard that's what you know I mean there were issues we needed to help with too and we
did but as far as the emotion went it just needed to be heard to be met
with attention and kindness
so I want a name that's not always the correct response or the wisest response
to these situations right and so a counter story this is one that
Sharon salzberg loves to tell so you may have heard it she is traveling in India by Rickshaw in
New Delhi and those of you who haven't been to India New Delhi is huge
it is busy it's chaotic and it's notoriously crime ridden
so she's on a rickshaw it's the bicycle kind not the motor kind and they're headed off to see her teacher menendra G
and the Rickshaw turns down a side street off of this just like massive
packed flow of traffic and a man tries to jump on the Rickshaw
and pull Sharon especially her purse off it's terrifying I'm sure
and together she and the driver were able to fend this man off and they made it to her teacher and she's
understandably very shaken and she looks at him and she said what do I do as a
Buddhist in a case like that immunity looks at her
and with a lot of love in his eyes he says my dear with every ounce of loving
kindness in your heart you hit him over the head with your umbrella
right so sometimes a really strong no is the
wisest thing this is not advocating being a doormat
non-hatred is not meaning opening ourselves up to violence or
abuse or anything else but it's more the attitude with which we
hold the boundary and the discernment to know when the non-complementary response is
appropriate and when the really strong no it's the most helpful response
so that brings me to us to non-delusion
discernment falls into that category discernment wisdom Clarity are all in the
non-delusion category so non-delusion
from a Buddhist perspective I think one could say it starts with Sati with mindfulness awareness
and that eventually matures into clarity
and wisdom discernment and wisdom and clarity
so Satya is like kind of an information gathering process
mindfulness mindfulness is got many nuances one could give an
entire talk on just what mindfulness means but it's got
different aspects to it and one of them is to be present with what is right
to be actually present with what is and that seems like a really powerful
underpinning for any kind of wisdom or non-delusion
if I'm in the virtual reality machine that runs up here my chances of non-delusion are a lot
smaller than if I'm present with what's actually unfolding
with the eyes see the ears here the body consents
so starting with mindfulness wherever it's
at occasional intentional sometimes it can even feel labored and
guilt sometimes says there's parts of the practice that can feel like manual labor
all of that still starts to cultivate the conditions for non-dollution
little by little later it can become useful
can get momentum and even feel completely natural and for some people it ends up becoming a trait actually
shifts our minds over time that neuroplasticity shifts in really beautiful ways
so that moment to moment process also includes a Resonance of recollecting or
recollecting there's a part of mindfulness that um
kind of casts it to way back just a little bit enough to recognize the thread between
the immediate past and the present and that's where wisdom can start to come it's when we see cause and effect
or conditions affecting each other and it starts to gain momentum that way
too it's like the moments of mindfulness gradually widen like puddles widening together to create a pond or something
like that
there's also though the recollection aspect of recollecting
the virtues in the practice your own virtues
this is also a form of non-delusion for some reason in our culture it's so
easy for people to feel like it's important to be down on ourselves to have some kind of critical Inner
Voice or that we won't somehow get stuff done if we're not hard on ourselves
recollecting virtues is actually an ancient practice it's one of the fundamental practices
our own virtues and those of others the good things we've done that too is a form of cutting through
delusion particularly particularly delusion if there's a negative mental habit
about the self for those people who are more apt to
cast flame outwards a better practice is to recollect the virtues of others
right that annoying office mate or the family member who chews wrong or has
the wrong political views or whatever it is
so this gradually begins to mature into the
kind of discernment I alluded to before and when mindfulness starts to mature
into discernment it's likened to being the gatekeeper of
a village keep in mind most of the similes and the Buddha's teachings are from the Bronze
Age in India right so the gatekeeper of a village a gatekeeper just kind of monitors all
the traffic going in and out knows how to get to the king
it's judicious about who to tell that information to and is judicious about
who to pass along Lord you know you might want to keep an eye on this gang of people
and it's kind of the same in our minds right to monitor the in and out traffic
the Buddha talks about there being two kinds of thought there's beneficial and unbeneficial
wholesome and unwholesome and so it can be as simple as that noticing is the effect
opening me up settling me motivating me or is it making me feel
kind of small and hopeless and yucky
is it resulting in actions that are helpful for myself and others or actions that bring greater suffering
to me and or others not to actually kind of the definition
of a wise person versus a foolish person and you know any of us can be wise or
foolish in any given moment but a foolish person is engaged in actions or thoughts that bring more suffering to
themselves others in the world different day
that person might be engaged in thoughts or actions that bring benefit to themselves and others in the world
and that to wisdom
so all of this kind of discernment kind of evolves into a greater wisdom and
this includes this more of a settled strength to see the opposite of the three
wholesome roots greed hatred and delusion and all of their cronies all of their henchmen
without losing our seat without being thrown off
because with the exception of the very rare fully enlightened awakened beings
all of us have some of it in our hearts Hearts just
Being Human and understanding that
when it's held well it can actually increase compassion and empathy connection
wisdom Alexander Schultz Nixon writes
if only it were all so simple if only there were evil people somewhere
insidiously committing evil deeds and it were necessary only to separate them from the rest of us and Destroy them
but the line dividing Good and Evil cuts through the heart of every human
being he then goes on to say the line
separating good and evil passes not through States nor through classes nor through
political parties either but right through every human heart and
through all human hearts it's what we do with it
how we relate to it how we act on that that's what matters
some days it's more or some days it's less you do a ton of spiritual practice and work on yourself and it's going to
get really small and even then I just think of many of you have
probably seen or heard the Dalai Lama laugh and he has this just amazingly
infectious laugh it's kind of like a little kids right and at one point
I've read this but I've also heard him say it he he laughs at seeing the
selfish and sneaky parts of his own mind the man's been practicing since he was I
don't know four and when asked you know fully purified in there it's like no
tries to sneak up on me now and then not mind so it's that holding it lightly
the Tendencies start to attenuate when held lightly
so all of this all this starts to kind of
pull together in a way to noticing the impact in our hearts
and in our relationships on how we're relating
to the things we don't like in ourselves and noticing the things that we
appreciate in ourselves and others the non-greet the non-hatred the non-delusion
because that whether you believe in terms of energy or neurology
that has Ripple effects in our lives
there's a second gatekeeper story and this one
this is a more sort of friendly human human like he's he's rendered in more
human way in the ancient discourses and there's a story he's like you know
the friendly sort and talks to everybody and people ask him questions going into this Village they're coming in for the
first time or relocating and so one group passes by and the head
of the group says so um tell me what are the people like here
and he smiles and looks at them and he said tell me what the people were like where
you used to live mean cunning conniving you couldn't
trust him as far as you could throw them they were awful and rude
you just nods I think you'll find people like that here
a few more parties go by maybe an hour or two another group comes by and someone poses the exact same question
maybe worded a little different what are the people like here anyway
give me an idea how did you find them where you used to live
kind generous trustworthy
I really I didn't want to leave but you know my husband he got this new job and here we are
they were amazing really good neighbors gatekeeper nods and he says
I think you'll find people much like that here
right so all of this wraps back around
to trust and contentment in the path
noticing what we put out is a lot like what we receive not always
but sometimes but trusting the process of the meditation this internal development
commitment to cultivating virtue and how that can shift things
there's a hidden almost selfish Joy with being involved in a path like this
particularly if it involves orienting around service to something
bigger than we are service to others
and um that can feed this light healthy sense
of a bigger picture that undercuts the greed hatred and delusion and helps the
non-greed non-hate non-delusion those roots to really grow
so just to recap in closing
trust in the unfolding path explore Express the many branches of
these roots of non-greed non-hatred non-delusion like contentment
simplicity generosity respect
kindness and good will mindfulness discernment
and enjoy it when you can thank you for your kind attention
we have just a moment or two if anyone has questions comments
um I ran a little longer than I expected so sorry it's a moment or two
people of the internet say thank you
May our practice here together be a cause and condition
for greater peace happiness
patience Simplicity good will
discernment and wisdom in our lives and may the benefits of this practice
Ripple out to all of the lives We Touch and all of the lives they touch
outward and outward may all beings be happy
safe peaceful and free [Music]
thank you all for the sincerity of your practice