so warm welcome again everyone here in IMC as well as those who are online on
YouTube you know from all over the world
I just came out of a week-long online Retreat on Friday
and so I'm still feeling some Rippling effect of it
and so at the end of The Retreat and I got an opportunity to share a gem
that arose out of the retreat and what came to me very strongly
over the course of the retreat was this deep sense
of trust and rootedness in sincere practice
sincerity of the practice
and then the context of the retreat we had a retreat theme
and there was samadhi and some of you know this concentration
as translated as concentration and many words samadhi
just by naming samadhi so often our mind immediately get to I
want to get that okay I don't want to have that
and so that becomes a goal of the retreat you know we get concentrated
or in the Bliss of a samadhi
and the teachers knew this very well so on the very first day Philip Moffett
one of the teachers of the retreat said this
we need to be cautious that we don't turn this Retreat into a hunting party
for concentration we're learning to recognize that
concentration naturally arises as a felt sense
such wisdom such a wisdom
you know we have a theme of samadhi Awakening
we can so easily get caught that that is something that we're getting
so I must retreat and fill up with the lead and this
guided meditation each morning at 8 A.M and English guided meditations
he would offer a preliminary kind of process
or you can call it Preparatory process to prepare our body mind and heart
so that we're ready and open to the whole process of the meditation
and this preliminary process is called arriving sequence
and I won't be talking about the arriving sequence but I wanted to share something I
learned from this process and so
um usually this morning third is an hour or a little over an hour or something like
that and the Philippa would offer this
microscopic level great minute details of
what happens as a we arrive on the cushion
on our seat with tiny little shifts in our posture
some shifts in our mind and heart and great detail great details
is this arriving sequence you know could be 15 20 30 minutes 35
minutes sometimes it feels like a forever and
you know this is an experience the student Retreat to so many people have heard about this arriving sequence and
practice the weather differ many times you know and in a hundreds of
times so sitting there just being with the arriving sequence
was not easy wow that was not ex what we expected you
know our mind wants to get to somebody
um but such a teaching so one day
sitting in this Timeless arriving sequence
it just dawned on me wow what a sincere practitioner
what a sincere teacher and he wasn't going to rush over it
he wasn't actually going anywhere he was just there
was what was present right in front of him with him
while he was offering and sharing pointers to the rest of us who was
practicing with him there was no shortcuts
no Fast Track just arriving
I was so touched and moved by that and when I recognized that
all of a sudden my body relaxed my heart softened
I was humbling and inspiring
and I had this immediate sense in my being and I finally arrived
and I didn't have to go anywhere
and so that's what I thought I was going to um share today
um that is the sincerity of the practice
and it's easy for us to come to the Dharma practice
using the same attitude that we may be having
um in engaging in all kinds of aspects of Our Lives right we're here to get
something or to achieve something uh something we want
or we wanted to come here to get rid of something that
really bothered us the bad stuff bad habits or
you know the lousy neighbors and you know who knows
so we can come here with the attitude attitude of
getting or getting rid of
I don't want to diminish that because all of us probably come to on the Dharma
through that we had something that connects to us and and we needed
something and yet and as we began to have some
understanding of the Dharma teachings and began to engage with the practice
ourselves
my soul will find out maybe for ourselves
that usual patterns of attitudes don't work
they just don't work they actually hinder how we practice
and so what's asked of us is something quite drastically different
from our usual attitudes and I would say what is asked of us
is to learn to practice sincerely
I'm intentionally passing here just to practice sincerely
nothing else period practicing sincerely period
just take a moment to feel into your being your heart and mind and
what did that what does that feel to you
know I've had many moments when this was said you know my mind would go what
don't we have to sincerely practice in order to
get something get somewhere and have something happened to us you know
we have lots of plans
that are we okay to just practice sincerely
so I'm very fond of the Suzanne story that Uncle tells us sometimes and I
think many of you probably have heard this that someone asked um
about Enlightenment and uh and he responded if you practice it sincerely
it's just as good so how is that possible
unless I wanted to unpack this sincere practice
a bit maybe in a few different dimensions this is just something that kind of
arose from the reflections of of the retreat and that I just came off
and doesn't mean that those are the only Dimensions there may be many other
dimensions associated with this as well
and so the first one and the first one about practicing
sincerely I is to become aware
to become aware of what is happening here
how we are practicing and what is here right now that's the very first thing
so even right now as we're all sitting together I'm speaking and you're
listening what's here are we aware
what's in our mind in our body in our heart
and if we are preoccupied with some
plans projections interpretations
we are not aware what is actually happening and whatever arises
maybe habitual patterns out of the storytelling mind
our impulsive mind and so the first thing is to become
aware and make contact with our lived experience
and not something in the past or in the future and so that's the first aspect of
sincere practice is just to become aware come in contact with
the lived experience Here and Now when we're not aware we can't be sincere
I'm gonna say this again when we're not aware we can't be sincere
because we don't know what is truly here
we're only going to be kind of living in the surface level of or storytelling
stories and ideas imaginations
so that's the first one now once we're aware the second
dimension of a sincerity is that of truthfulness
honesty
so when we practice it sincerely we're aware come to contact with our present
to lived experience and what's called for immediately
following that is to meet those experience truthfully
not how you prefer how would you'd rather but this
whatever is happening right now here this is the truth
and so if you're sitting down and you find yourself having aches and things in
the body there's a truth to that can we be with that honestly
or if there's something in the mind and I'm irritated and
or I have certain fear coming in my mind
is it okay to be with that as they are
meet with this truthfully and we all know that our minds tend to
skip over you know things that we don't want unpleasant experiences and
and of course you know we don't like that and it's not comfortable and
you know my mind tends to have this habit of Turning Away
and then to just kind of um reflecting you know often in our Dharma
teachings we offer this lists and Maps you know when we offer a list of eight
you know our mind can't stay at one or two we jump to
number eight within an hour the first 10 minutes we're not getting
to number four something is totally wrong with us right and then
but uh sincere practice asks us to be true to where we are how we are just as
is we're not moving away
and so um do I dare to stay true
to this this is another phrase that a fella be used very often on this retreat
do I dare do we dare and sometimes the what's here
we're afraid of so we run away do we dare so it takes courage and
um trust and integrity to really be here
and I really liked the Chinese translation of a sincerity I don't know
if any of you would know this and um
and it's meaning something like you know our heart it's what it means is that
it's something that our heart and mind can trust
when were sincere there is a certain kind of trustworthiness
in our heart in our mind
and maybe it's because that we can stay true with what is here
and so in in this way our heart and mind can trust it
and then the third aspect that I like to speak about and after us being aware
with what is happening and stay true or honest with our experience
the third dimension of a sincerity comes in in the form of being open
to what is here and this is a kind of opening on
you know I had this sense of a gesture I don't know some of you may be doing yoga
and it's a mountain pose in a mountain pose you stand on your mat you know with your kind of
hands open a heart lifted and and that you're open
to what comes this is that kind of a gesture we're
open to this experience fully wholeheartedly
you know not half-hearted and you know partially checked out
but we're really here fully I'm also find a find a fond of this
one-liner that girls sometimes talk about you know in order to get it from A
to B you stay at a fully
and so the same sense of opening up to embrace
stay with the experience fully
and we all have probably lots of examples of how we might be experiencing
what's happening half a half-heartedly right not totally fully
you may have had experience where you are with someone and you know someone is keeping and Company with you
but they're really not there maybe they're on the phone
and they're kind of gesture is you know they're not looking
at you or they're not there with you and they are kind of there but they're really not
there with you we all have experienced this and we can
be experienced with that part of ourselves in our inner being
you know some aspect of us that we may prefer not to be here is here
maybe somebody said something about me that that the defensive part of me is here
I don't like it I really want to wiggle out of this hurt feeling but it's here
can I be with this can I allow this to be here
without shuffling it around and pushing it away
and I remember on one Retreat a recent Retreat that gill
had given a long extended posture instruction
I was struck by the details that he offered in this
posture instruction kind of again as my new details of
different parts of the body energetic field and you know the jaw the eyes and
the eye socket and you know just kind of everything
and I was struck with me was wow how attuned he was
with all of us just with all of this is sitting and
it's just sitting here and it wasn't just for one sitting but it's over time over
the decades and Decades of a practice he was paying attention to how
posture shifts and changes so as if you're meeting this
as an old friend at the same time as a brand new friend
and so that's kind of the attitude that we're bringing in through the sincere practice
and we Embrace this so wholeheartedly that as if we've never
well actually we have never met this this moment before we just give
ourselves over to it bowing down to it
and then the last Dimension comes in
which is to be content with this
now that you're aware present honest truthful
open receptive
and be content with Where We Are how we are just as it is
it is easy for our mind to feel that somewhere else would be a better place to be
just not this but the sincere practice asks us to to
check can we be okay with this experience
whether it's a bliss pleasant experience or unpleasant
very uncomfortable so whatever is happening is good enough
it's good enough
you know our mind are tricky we don't always have clarity
and so on an invitation for this sincere practice
is to also open to this as a learning process
as an ongoing learning process that's part of the sincerity
sincere practice bring humility and modesty to our
practice setting ourselves up against some high standards
reading only kind of bring to come to us
and I want to share this poem that I just
heard this morning
and this is from this little book and the first free woman
it's a poems from the early Buddhist announce
and this is a from this nun whose name is rahini
the title of the poem is wandering star
you don't cut sorry I'm gonna restart you don't become the cloth just because
you put on ropes you don't don't turn into empty space
just because you carry a bowl the sun doesn't Bow Down
trees don't throw flowers at your feet
birds don't start answering when you call the path will hold even the biggest
mistakes the path will make room for even your
deepest regrets but you don't become the cloth of the of
the robe overnight you can begin very quietly
something you barely even notice like the touch of water on your skin
like a knife in a drawer like the next five minutes
unless they are your last
the path isn't a line on a map it's a great shining world
enter wherever you like
you might get thrown back once or twice but if we push through the outer layers
oh my siblings then you will know the true welcome that is the very
essence of the path
so we can always begin to enter
wherever we like
may we all practice sincerely
hmm so we have a little time
for some reflections and or questions oh let's see ah okay
Nancy please
thank you hi Yang thank you for being here today
I was wondering since we have this auspicious occasion of you being here if
you can tell the greater Sangha a little bit about the Asian Dharma Sangha okay
oh okay thank you thank you Nancy for bringing that in
and yeah we do have um IMC have um many different Affinity groups and
for me I'm specifically part of an Asian Dharma Circle
and offered through IMC that happens on Sunday afternoons it's usually
twice a month and you can check on our calendar and this is for those who are
self-identified as folks who have Asian background and to
join it and we usually have a very simple format and we
meditate together and we have a short a
Dharma Reflections offered and then we engage as a community kind of discuss
the Dharma and so to welcome anyone who joined and
please just check on the IMC calendar and then a website thank you Nancy for
bringing that in okay any other announcement
not and we have some time for yeah just some Reflections and questions you may
have
thank you
hi I I'm just curious to know what the name of that book you read the poem from
is yeah I like that poem yeah the first free woman
and this this is the book feel free to come up and take a look if you need but
it's called The First the free woman thank you
I want to thank you for your talk and that poem was very moving also um I
think I like the difference between that we're content with something versus
something is okay so for me the okay is less judgmental or
it's not as warm and fuzzy as content and yes can we be okay with things just
as they are so yeah great thank you yeah great yeah we find our own words you
know words are tricky you know we have our own associations with them so I'll
find the words that work for you you know and for me sometimes it's just oh this is good enough
that's that's enough yeah great
while you are very quiet and if there is no other comments or sharing
I guess we can end so maybe we'll end with a dedication of
a merit and together
yes take a moment to gather ourselves
and allow a sense of a gratitude to arise being grateful to be able to practice
together sharing Dharma together
grateful for our own presence right here our courage to be here
and may whatever benefits and goodness that arose out of
our practice together and our sharing together may they be shared
all around in all directions with all beings
may all beings be well may all beings be happy
and may all beings be free to everyone