good evening and welcome welcome
as you know we'll have a silent sit now so Jim will ring the bell for us in 45
minutes and then I'll give a talk we'll see you in 45 minutes
foreign and welcome welcome
maybe I'll say that you're welcome to sit wherever you would like if you feel like oh the chairs are not in the right
place some you can move chairs around or move cushions around or something like this too we never know exactly who's
going to arrive so we just chairs around so
I mean if any of you have had this I'm sorry my ears
there we go I'm wondering if any of you have had an
experience like this that uh something to me like early in my practice coming to meditation centers or
to Retreats when there's these long uh silent sits there would be this you know
meditating and then like wow that person in front of me is so still
I can't be that still oh this is awful I can never do this how can they do that
they'd never move at all and then a little bit later there's
somebody who's ruffling in their purse looking for something making lots of noise and like then this thought I am
such a great meditator I never make those kinds of noises or something right how we like end up comparing ourselves
to others and sometimes we feel like oh we're just awful and then feel like we're fantastic
and going back and forth and of course it's not only in meditation right where
this happens happens every all areas of Our Lives
probably isn't an area in which there isn't a subtle way in which this is happening
or an obvious way in which this is happening because there is this um
this pattern that's really deep and really uh persistent in humans
to compare to compare themselves to others
about anything oh that's a nice haircut maybe I should get my hair cut like that or oh those
are great socks oh my socks are better than that person's socks it's like whatever it is right we're always
finding something something to compare ourselves with
so there's this way in which sent in the Buddhist teachings we talk about this idea of self and not self or even have
this expression like selfing and we could say the experience of
selfing and measuring are synonyms and the way
that is is that if we're going to compare ourselves maybe I should say
measuring comparing selfing these are like all the same if we're going to compare ourselves to
others then we're making a very distinct I'm like this and they are like that
and so and we might think that we're better or worse or the same but there's this really sense of a making a
distinction between me and everything else that's
not me and a part of you might be saying well of course of course we are that silly Diana why are you even mentioning
this well there's a way in which we don't need to have such always be holding
these clear distinctions there's times when it's really helpful when you go to put your shoes back on it's helpful to
recognize these are my shoes and not somebody else's shoes or when you go home get to the car whatever
it is right there's these things in which it occasion situations in which it's enormously helpful to have a very
clean clear distinction this is me and this is not me
but we don't have to do that all the time
in fact it turns out that there's a lot of difficulties and I'll use this word suffering Duca and I'm using this word
suffering to mean a really giant range of something that's
just yeah a little mildly troubling to some really awful
torment or suffering so I'm using this one word to represent this whole range
so there's this what
so this deeply embedded and this very tenacious
pattern of comparing ourselves to others is something that the Buddha recognized and
that he spoke about and talked about kind of the suffering that's inherent there and I'll talk a little bit about
this but I want to also say that some of you may be familiar with this there's this
list of Fetters this word Fetters is a list of 10 that are these underlying
tendencies that humans have and then as the progression to more and more freedom
more and more Awakening more and more Liberation these Fetters are released abandoned and
no longer arise and they're in a particular order and
they're let go of in a particular order and the last one before you become an arhot
a completely awakened person like a Buddha is this comparing mind that's the
very last so I just want to highlight that this is a universal thing that all humans do
but a part of the reason why I want to talk about it is because there's a way in which we can reduce some of the
difficulties or suffering that's associated with it and there's also even a way in which we could reduce the
amount of the way that we do this and that we're comparing ourselves to others
so there's this uh idea that like maybe I'll just say this again this idea when we're measuring
as a way and we're also kind of like me in we're making a me
so comparing is also the sense of there's a me and not me
so there might be a way in which we feel like we're smarter than others or we have more expertise than others or might
be a way in which we feel kind of clumsy or unworthy or maybe there's ways in which we feel like we're the same as
everybody else but in all three of those scenarios we're comparing ourselves to others so it doesn't matter whether you
think yourself you're better you think you're worse or you think you're the same it's the activity of comparing it's
the activity of measuring and you know what I'm wondering if we
can turn off the air conditioning here yeah I could I'm seeing everybody's body
language and everybody's like this thank you Tim
if there's a way we can turn a feed it comes from uh these uh
Vents and it's really really forcefully
just to note there are microclimates here so if you're someone who's really sensitive to the cold you can like sit
on the stage because that's on the other side of those vents it's a little bit warmer over there just a heads up
thank you Tim
okay so I want to talk a little bit about this uh superiority comparison when you compare
and you think I'm better somehow so and in the um Buddhist
language this comparing this making this me and measuring they this word Mana
gets translated as conceit it's not the best translation because in English we
think of conceit is always when you think that you're better but this is pointing to just comparing
in general whether you think you're better you think you're the worse or you think the same it's the same word is used for all three I want to talk a
little bit about these three but there so this superiority
conceit is I think most of us are familiar with what this is this idea you
think that you're better better than others or above others in some kind of way and somehow this feeling that we're
more competent or more worthy or more deserving or whatever it is we might
know people who have this we might see it in ourselves in some certain
situations but there's a way that it also can show up in a subtle way
and this way that we have this maybe subtle belief somehow that we're special
or that the way that we do things or the our views our opinions are the right
ones or maybe we have this sense of kind of like being invulnerable or like I can do
this I'm going to go out and do this no harm is going to happen to me I I can handle this or there's these subtle ways
in which this superiority conceit uh shows up kind of like in our inner life
like the views that we have about ourselves and then I think all of us
recognize this in the world we see of this people show up with arrogance or
bragging or you know proclaiming how great they are they know things and of
course we can see this in the way that they treat other people that are in the in
service the wheat stuff the Barista whomever we can see this showing upright
and how they treat them but there's also a way in which you have
the superiority conceit is that you expect others to treat you a certain way
right that matches the view that you have of yourself and have you ever tried to change the
whole world so that they behave exactly how you think they should it doesn't work right it doesn't work
I'll talk a little bit more about that so one of the
obvious some one of the disadvantages besides irritating everybody around you of uh having this superiority conceit is
that there's a way in which if we see somebody who's having some real difficulties
whether we know them or we don't know them whatever our relationship is with them somebody that's having some real
difficulties and a person might have some compassion for them and we wish that their
difficulties go away and wish that they could have some happiness and well-being
and so this wish is compassion it's when loving kindness meets
difficulties it turns into compassion this wish for beings to not suffer but
if you have this superiority conceit then instead of compassion it turns into pity like you have pity for other people
and nobody likes that right nobody wants to feel like they're being pitied and
also it's just not a pleasant experience it does it doesn't help anybody it only makes others feel
bad probably even the person who's having that experience to feel have pity for others it's supposed
to have compassion and having the superiority conceit also like it gets in the way of allowing
people to listen deeply I know some people who that they're kind
of like often sometimes like interrupting before a person has been finished finished speaking and they'll
say yeah that's right yeah right right yeah right but even they'll say that even if the other person speaking is
telling something about their own personal experience that the person that has the superiority can see would know
nothing about so why are they saying yeah right right yeah yeah yeah yeah kind of dismissive this way so there's
this way in which you don't really listen deeply to others
and often you aren't connecting with others in this kind of ways this superiority conceit and it also kind of
like gets in the way of being able to hear criticism in a way that allows us
to have our best life that allows us to recognize oh I'm causing harm here or oh
I have this big blind spot whatever the harm or the blind spot might be we have the superiority conceit we don't
get to hear that or see that okay so that's the superiority you can
see what about this idea that inferiority can see this idea that we
feel less than turns out not to be so uncommon in fact
I would even say it's common I would say in my role as a Dharma teacher I hear about this a lot so maybe it's just
people who come to meditation centers at meditation practice but I don't think so
so there's this way in which we feel less worthy less knowledgeable less
attractive less valuable less anything you could whatever right it's
un that seems like the list is Limitless all these ways in which we can feel less
than in some kind of way and it's very painful I'm sure all of us have had
this experience it's a really painful experience to be stuck in
this feeling of good enough maybe I shouldn't even be here
and I remember in my professional life back when I was in Corporate America
I um was part of this committee and I just felt like wow everybody else has so
much more experience and so much more senior than me well you know what am I doing on this committee and I just like
when is this going to leave I just wanna I hope nobody asks me a question and I dare to speak and I couldn't wait for it
to be over and then uh afterwards somebody who I don't really knew a
little but came up to me and said why were you frowning so much during that whole meeting
like oh yeah if I showed up just because I was feeling like you know I didn't
feel like I belonged on that committee or that meeting that group or something like this so it just it's such an
awkward feeling this terrible of like yeah not enough
inadequate in some kind of way and so this shows up as this way that
can be uh maybe even a little bit subtle maybe it's obvious can also be in some
subtle ways in which that we feel like we don't really have the right to vouch
for ourselves we don't really have the right to express our views or our
opinions or share our thoughts or maybe we don't uh
feel like oh what I have to say isn't that important or it doesn't really matter
nobody else you know we'll just let everybody else speak or something like this somehow kind of like devaluing what
we have to offer devoting maybe even our life experience our wisdom we all have
wisdom you can have not gotten to this age in your life without some wisdom right we're all adults here right
so there's a way in which we might be Adept at praising others or seeing their
strengths or seeing their accomplishments but somehow we can't
quite acknowledge in ourselves some of our own strengths our
accomplishments or some of the ways that we show up in the world that are hopeful for others
some of the way that we show up in the world that helps to
not solve problems or maybe just isn't negligent just takes care of your
responsibilities as opposed to making it that somebody else has to take care of your responsibilities and
and there's this way in which when there's this inferiority conceit it
often comes not always but it often comes with this sense of
well this is how I truly am and this is how I'm going to be for the rest of my life you know there's this kind of sense
of yeah I'm always going to be inadequate and I'm doing this with my body right it kind of feels like this
this burdensome like oh yeah this is how I am this way we kind of like are diminishing ourselves but not only
diminishing ourselves we've kind of like glued onto this idea and this is the way
that it will always be or this is just this is how I truly am the real me is
inadequate insufficient not worthy or something like this
this hurts this is an awful
experience to have this feeling and to have these ideas
I'll talk a little bit more about that this in a moment but I also want to talk about the
equality conceit this idea of oh we think that we're the same and you might say well clearly that's
like the middle way you know I'm betting that's what the Buddhists are saying to do this uh equality conceit
but not so because it's still the problem isn't that uh how we come up
with the comparison the issue is the fact that we're comparing it doesn't matter what the results are
it's the fact that we're comparing which is where this kind of integral
um it's this cell phone that doesn't allow for greater freedom but there's to be
sure there's uh there is suffering in whatever the outcome of the comparion is
the superiority inferiority or equality so we might say that you know equality
can see it is a great thing partly because you know democracy is based on this this idea that everybody
has an opportunity to participate that all citizens have the same rights you
know this is a integral belief for democracies across the world there's of
course there's absolutely nothing wrong with this of course not of course not right there's nothing
wrong with that but there's this way in which sometimes we use this equality conceit as a way to
Define ourselves I'm the one that's like them
I'm the one that's part of this group not that group over there
there's this way in which there's still this strong sense of there's a self here
and it's uh even so maybe I'm the same as all of these but all of these people
are different than those people over there and there's this way is that it can feel
like reassuring of course it does and and we do want to normalize people's
experience and recognize the common Humanity about there's so many things that are common to The Human Experience
but there's this so it can't feel reassuring to feel like we're the same as others
but there's this way in which we're also making others different and that we're
like limiting ourselves like I'm I'm just this and I have to defend this
because there's always this well do I really belong to this group that person
didn't greet me the way that I thought that they should because I'm part of this group too but maybe not or you know
there's this way in which to feel like we're belonging to the group requires
that other people behave in a particular way in the same way that the superiority
conceit we kind of have this expectation that people will you know treat us like
we deserve like we expect but with equality conceit we also are expecting
other people to treat us as equals or that we belong or that we're part of
the group or something like this so there might be a way in which we have
this equality conceit that shows up and that we say okay well we're all equal in
this group so therefore no one deserves any preferential treatment
which in theory sounds nice but in order for there to be
um I wrote down this word here so fairness
and maybe we'd even say like justice that we can say you know some people who
have disadvantages maybe need something that's a little bit different than what the other people who don't have some
disadvantages just so that we can maintain this equality we need to make sure that these individuals still get to
go to school and have a job or move around town or whatever it is there's just one example that we want to think
like everybody should be treated exactly the same but you know for some people have disadvantages then they would be
completely left behind and that's not right that's not what not what we want to do
or maybe there's another way in which this equality conceits can be problematic is if we decide oh all human
beings are selfish or you could say make up anything you
want or just you know looking out for number one or lazy or whatever it is
there's this way in which we can use these blanket statements to say oh yeah
all human beings are the same I'm one of them and everybody else is have these uh
inherent qualities that are bad or unwanted in some kind of way
and there was this um let's see I had a note about this but
it's not here so I guess I won't say it then
so there's this so what is some of this suffering that's
associated with these conceits I've been talking about this the suffering of
making ourselves really distinct but certainly early in my practice that just did not make any sense at all to me
and so it might be like some this is something that's maybe a little pointed to
um with practice when we notice like for example when the we're doing something that we love one of our favorite things
a hobby there's just a sense of ease and whatever's needs to be done is
being done dancing the next move needs to be done Sports the next move needs to
be done knitting the next knitting gardening you know whatever it is
there isn't a sense of me doing there's just doing
and so that doing right there's more ease and freedom and openness and
spaciousness and just that doing is happening as opposed to I am doing that
so this is a subtle difference and so this um there's so there's
suffering and doing this measuring this mean and comparing having this conceit
because we're creating a self that is separate from everything else but I want to highlight some of the
other ways and that this brings in some suffering and one is this cognitive
dissonance that arises alluded to this earlier when people aren't treating us
the way that we are viewing ourselves this is really painful
you know to be disrespected or to be somebody to be dismissive of us
when we were thinking there's why are they treating me that way I'll like I'm
just asking for a cup you know coffee and maybe the Baristas being dismissive or actually this happened to me just
recently at the grocery store I don't know why but this one person like wouldn't even
acknowledge my existence and didn't even ask if I wanted bags or you know like
this didn't and just like beep beep beep and then just stood there and when it
was done and I had to look and see how much it was and you know it was just kind of I felt like oh it was kind of a
weird thing I kind of expected to at least be acknowledged that I was there you know it's a little ritual that
we do right with the grocery clerks when we're there so there can be this cognitive
dissonance and sometimes we are just dismissive of them when people don't
treat us the way that we expect or but maybe they are also seeing something
that we don't want to see in ourselves and that of course is also really uncomfortable but
I'd like to uh here's a quote from Paul Fulton
who's a Dharma teacher also and this is part of I would say selfing
in general and superiority conceived in particular
Paul Fulton writes the pleasure of feeling Superior is always precarious subject to being
erased with one untoward interaction once this comparing mind arises it
threatens to negate any nourishment we may have gained from our accomplishments
self-esteem is in constant renegotiation never a truly finished product immune
from fluctuation So This Is Us trying to make sure that we're getting training everybody to treat us in a
particular way I think that's once easy to see but this
the suffering of equality conceit is this way that it also depends on others
and there's a way in which we are if we do think that we are equal to
others or then here's the note that I was looking for earlier there's this way that we can have this
disillusionment with this with human potential there's a way in which we can feel like there's this mediocrity like
well they can do it so I I probably can't either or there's a way in which
we have this resignation or cynicism like yeah everybody is just out for themselves
and there's a way that the suffering with the inferiority you can see that one's obvious but the
superiority can see trying to always keep it up and the equality conceit the
way that um it's there's a way in which it can have this cynicism
this these ways they undermine us they undermine our
help us like lose our ground lose our uprightness lose our alignment
because we're trying to in some ways kind of like manipulate the
environment or manipulate our thoughts to support these conceits to either get
away from the suffering of them or try to maybe that's it basically just trying
to get away from the suffering of them and then of course not to mention that
life experiences can shatter these conceits these ideas that we have about
ourselves long-term relationships end and all of a
sudden like wow are these ideas about ourselves that maybe we discover
maybe they're not true or maybe illnesses or accidents and our
capabilities are diminished or different and we feel like oh I always thought I
was capable but now I'm not capable in this realm and all the difficulties
associated with that so how do we practice with this how can
we practice with this so in some way as I said you know conceit is the last Fetter to go before
complete Awakening so this is something that won't we can't expect it to go away this measuring is
not going to completely go away until we're completely awakened but is there a way we can diminish the
suffering and this is something that yakan Nakamura she's another you can Nakamura
the third Dharma teacher she lives in Switzerland and teaches in Switzerland and in the UK and a little bit at IMs
she had this idea that what if we notice the differences in people
it's like different flowers and I don't know why I kind of my when I
heard this I felt like that's right like it's different flowers have different
qualities and we don't necessarily going around and you know saying this one's
better or worse like maybe some are better for they last in the vase longer but maybe they're also these
are more beautiful or the scent is good or there's different qualities we don't just say with uh particular flowers like
oh this flowers this flower is good and we just say
different people are like different flowers because of course we are still
going to distinguish people we're gonna have discernment about people of course
we are we're going to notice people who have skills that we don't have we're going to notice people have
knowledge that we don't have maybe we have the knowledge and they don't have or age right people have you know age
differences and therefore they have different life experiences so the objective here is not to like get
completely stop comparing because we need to compare it just makes sense it's how we move
through the world and it's how we can learn from others it's how we can teach others
how we can help each other and there's this uh
rule that the monastics have many of you know reg the um monastics in this tradition they all
their meals with alms around so they have alms bowls so they only are allowed
to eat what gets put into their bowl every day and so one of the rules is that you
can't look in somebody else's Bowl you only look at what's in your bowl
so we might think of that as a way of you know not being so worried about what's happening with others is there a
way that we can say that okay you know they have their own path they have their life maybe we don't even know you know
what brought them to this moment and what are we doing with our life
our path you know what are our priorities and
how can we have a life go the direction that we wanted to go
so this encouragement to focus on what's relevant for us
comparing will happen but maybe there's a way that we can hold it a little bit more lightly
this recognition this is what humans do and we don't have to say it means that
we are like inherently inferior or inherently Superior just just okay at
this moment this person seems to have a skill set to knowledge capabilities that I don't have at this moment I have these
particular skills knowledge capabilities that somebody else doesn't have
at this moment we're the same we're all doing whatever it is that we're doing
together so one is to notice people's different types of flowers the second is to
there's something about the common Humanity like we all do this
and we don't have to believe the conclusions that we come to when
these comparisons are made maybe just like that a little um
anecdote I gave at the beginning where you think like oh my gosh I'm a terrible meditator and then just a few moments
later like Oh I'm a great meditator right it depends like who we're comparing ourselves to so we don't have
to like hold on to say this is inherent about who I am
and then there's also a way in which we can use this conceit in a skillful way there's a way in which we can use it as
a support because it's not going to go away until we're completely awakened so there's a way we can harness this to
support us and one is to be inspired by other people
I've told this story a number of times but it's getting back to meditating to my very first Retreat I didn't even know
it was humanly possible to sit still like that I didn't even know like now I
can just because I've been doing it for all these years but the beginning it's like humans can do this they can sit
without an odd in a chair you know with a back street for that long I was and I
felt first I felt really bad like oh my gosh this is a disaster I'm a disaster
but I also felt inspired like okay this is possible people can do this
there are people who have you know been practicing for a long time and you can sense the ease and the peace the
spaciousness that they have and you can say okay this is possible
to have more and more freedom in our lives have more and more ease in our life so we can be inspired
and we can be inspiring for others
right there's a way in which we show or just showing up in certain ways
we influence each other whether people are saying walking up to us and saying
you're so inspiring I can't believe that you did X Y or Z there's a way in which we can help um
like be the change we want to see in the world and show up in a way that has openness
spaciousness kindness and we can Inspire others
and we can be inspired by others so this is a way in which conceit can be part of
our practice there's also some of you might know this
um part of that Brahma vihar is that these are heart practices or heart qualities
or both practices and qualities and earlier I talked about compassion is
When Love or warm-heartedness and care love meets suffering it turns into
compassion this wish for the suffering to end in the same way and the opposite happens
when love meets somebody who's just having a fantastic time
maybe they got the job they wanted or maybe somebody in their family married somebody who is such a great partner for
them and we're really happy maybe there's um we something we've got great news
from the doctors from the test or something like that it's like something really good has happened so when love
meets there's something really good happening in somebody else it turns into
appreciative Joy we're happy that they're happy so this way there's this conceit that oh
they have something that maybe I don't have but I can be happy for them
I can join in their well-wishing and wish for their happiness to continue
because just think how the world would be if people were happy
if some of their wishes were coming true with what they really wanted just think how this world would be so of course we
want others to be happy we appreciate it when they're happy so when we see that
we can just allow ourselves to feel the happiness too
so in some ways we could say all of Buddhist practice is to help us with this conceit and then I'll just say
briefly I'll just drop in a few words practicing with impermanence noticing how things change
Everything Changes there are not exceptions Everything Changes
the only things that don't change right are ideas but actual experiences and
objects and things those change but so the ideas
this you know the next moment is going to be the next moment it's going to be different
and so we might feel inferior we might feel Superior we might feel equal like if we pay attention to how we compare
all throughout the day we'll just see that it's all over the place better worse the same
and just remember this like it's it's not like uh inherent to how we are we're not one
way or the other so just to notice how it's always changing it's always changing
and there's this recognition that when we notice it's always changing as well as recognize that this is something that
humans do we don't have to hold on to it so tightly like yeah okay right now I feel worse I feel like I can't play the
flute as well as this other person okay that's how it is this moment
a few moments I will feel differently but that's how I feel right now
conceit superiority conceit inferiority conceit equality conceit all three of
these have some suffering in them because we're making a self that's separate than
everything else but there's a way that we can just recognize that okay this is what humans
do and not draw any conclusions that this means this about me
it doesn't it just means at that moment you're having that comparing the way that you're comparing
so I'll stop there and maybe I'll open it up to see if there's some questions or comments I have a few minutes
here
you don't have to
hi thanks for the talk um when you were talking about the author who spoke about self-esteem I
forget his name Fulton or something like that it reminds me of a talk I heard by psychologist Kristen Neff and she had
talked about how a self-esteem is very fickle and I guess the American school system had taught self-esteem to kids
for however long and so her her sort of feel the study is a self-compassion it's
kind of the antidote because you can have a great day and then something goes wrong self-esteem goes down the drain
but for her it was a self-compassion was kind of the new new thing and sort of antidote to that though but thanks for
the talk thank you thank you for bringing in that idea of self-compassion and Kristen enough yeah she you know
she's a Buddhist practitioner as well as a as a psychologist yeah thank you thank you for bringing that in
self-compassion to have compassion for ourselves we have a lot of suffering
anybody else have a comment
okay so oh here's a comment over here your homework
[Applause] can you use conceit in a skillful way be
inspired by other people and can you maybe when you feel like you
have something that uh to offer the world maybe you feel like oh I have a skill or knowledge or something that
others is there a way that you can share it but without feeling like you know you have to teach others there's a way of
sharing so maybe that's one the second is to notice how it changes notice how
this comparing changes it's all throughout the day because sometimes we might fall into a idea
about ourselves or even about ourselves in one particular regard about
meditation or knowledge or whatever it is whatever it is is is that helpful as
homework more
you said yeah well there's so much rights that about uh how to kind of let go or soften this idea of a self that's
distinct and separate and has to be bolstered and supported and protected you know this self of ours there's we
could say like almost all Buddhist teachings are pointing to how actually there's suffering involved with that and
it's extra we don't need to do it so lots of Dharma talks lots of Derma
books are pointing to this okay thank you
if you have more questions you're welcome to come up here and ask me
this isn't working when I'm pushing oh [Laughter]
I had a grade for stubborn