okay hello everyone hi
welcome to happier and if you can hear me give me a thumbs up audio's okay
fantastic great let's begin let's begin by uh
warming the space with meta and I say hello welcome I'm McCain Mountain View
California and seated at olonieland who wants to help warm up the space with their hellos
hi I'm Stephanie I'm in Los Angeles hi Stephanie hi I'm Susan in San Mateo hi
Susan Emily New Hampshire hi Neil uh bill in Dallas hi Bill
Wayne in Richmond hi Wayne
um Nadine in Richmond maybe maybe the same reason hi Nadine
Gary in Toronto hi hi Terry not a different Toronto there's only one
Toronto that I know of but multiple Richmonds
great okay Let's uh any other last minute hellos
I think we're formerly beginning thanks Neil for posting information about the happy hour Google Groups as well as the
survey which we are closing today so I'd like to ask you at this point as
we're transitioning to our meditation to to um to mute yourself if you're unmuted
and I'm going to change my name here uh there so um and also I change the
settings uh so that accidental muting won't be possible I change the
chat settings only will come to the host who's me and
and uh and yet I'll ask you to keep that channel quiet until the end and last but
not least we're going to turn on recording for the sake of Audio Dharma
here we go great
so hello and welcome everyone to this rendition of happy hour happy making to
to be with you to see you and and looking forward to practicing together so so I like to just uh transition into
the guided meditation together and uh whatever you need to know I'll share
during the guidance and I might say a couple words afterwards so just trying
slightly different forms instead of giving it the Dartmouth at the beginning so let's Let's uh practice
so inviting you to get into your meditation posture whatever that
might be sitting standing lying down
and giving some attention to the body maybe the body needs to be just a little
stretched ah maybe the shoulders need to be rolled a
little bit as mine do or or this or weight needs to be shifted
back and forth side to side to find your center of gravity to really come into
your body maybe your ankles need to be rolled a little bit to bring some life some attention some awareness into the
legs your feet your hands maybe need to be rolled a
little bit this can also help actually this movement can help with a bit of embodiment just
bringing attention to the body maybe opening the jar
riving the body actually moving the body a little bit
waking it up
here here
and Landing Landing in your sit bones connection
connection points your bottom of the chair your feet with
the floor your hands with your lap
connecting with this body seated
all the sensations so many Sensations
bring him to the foreground
and connecting you with the sensations of the breath and the belly
each breath grounding
just this breath as if it were our last right here right
now as if it were the first and last Justice
breath the sensations of this breath here
letting go of everything else
it is so sweet and nourishing just to be here
with the nourishment of this breath
many thoughts arise not a problem to think and and yet right
now we choose to give our hearts to this practice
so in a friendly way we smile at the thoughts the plans
the occupations reoccupations thank you
giving my whole heart to this right now in this moment please come back later
if you're important enough you'll come back I'm gonna give this priority
if my heart priority just be
nourishing presence
with each breath
let go let go here here
thank you
foreign foreign
relaxing the mind releasing releasing
and now taking Stark of what's happening what's arising in the
body
areas where there's ease the areas where there's tightness pain maybe there's
fatigue or agitation tightness
and the body and in the mind how's your heart
your mind your heart mind and notice there's
not one thing there are multiple things always or could be say agitation sadness
boredom gladness gratitude peace all of them together everything
present and whatever you
give your attention to that becomes a measure that becomes more predominant
in that moment which is okay just notice there are a lot of things
a mix of nourishing and challenging
States mind body heart
now as if you were
you're sitting on the lap you were you gave yourself sit on the lap of the buddhao or
konyenby Paragon of compassion
or some other archetype maybe the being of light represents
complete acceptance for you they see you they know you through and
through all the cause and conditions of your life
and in fact they invite you to take their perspective with them so you're taking their perspective
looking at yourself looking at your life looking at your body
sensing your body your thoughts your mind State heart state
from their perspective you're joining them making a third person perspective
of compassion and kindness wisdom and kindness towards yourself
so say if there's crankiness in the body and the heart mind
you appreciate that from the perspective of complete acceptance wisdom and
compassion so many causes conditions in your life
anyone else was was in your shoes with the same
background genetics Life Experiences
everything that has happened
this would be what would be rising so get cut yourself some slack
and see the goodness in you Through The Eyes of the Buddha kuanian
you're being all right
if the voice of judgment comes up see that too as part of the cause and
conditions habit pattern not personal
it's like a recording it's been recorded a long time ago in your history and just
playing out
see the goodness is being who is you
is doing their best
and in the words of Suzuki roshi you're perfect as you are
you can use a little bit of improvement
and you hold both through this perspective of kindness
from this perspective of the third person perspective
Through The Eyes of the buddhan from their perspective wish yourself well
maybe you may you be safe dear one
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you have ease
if the Buddha was generously wishing you well with
abundant generosity of Art may you be safe
seeing yourself
third person maybe kneeling by the love of the Buddha
may you be safe
may you be happy
you'd be healthy
may you have east
thank you
seeing yourself in the third person with kindness with good will pushing yourself well may you be safe
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you have ease may you be free from suffering
you have peace and goodness and joy
whatever wishes for you appropriate In This Moment signifying your good will
this being who is you
thank you
how can I be a good friend to you
asking yourself from this perspective how can I be a good friend to you
not exacerbate what's difficult
to support you be kind
how can I love you more fully
thank you
foreign
as we turn to bring this meditation to a close
let's consider all those we know
it was near and dear those we have challenges with and we've hurt people
also Through The Eyes of the Buddha being of light
with benevolence they're all doing their best
given the causes and conditions that each and every one of us has
how can you be a good friend can you see them
be a good friend
as best as you're able to with benevolence wisdom kindness
wishing all beings well pinks everywhere
be well be safe happy may they be healthy
may they have these they all beings everywhere including
myself be free
[Music]
thank you thank you for your practice everyone okay
so that third person perspective that we worked with tonight can be very powerful
when when we see it when we try to play with this perspective and see ourselves
with benevolence with kindness or the eyes of of the Buddha Kuan Yen
um some some being that represents kindness and compassion and seeing ourselves from that perspective can open
open something up can open the sense of oh oh what what does what does this
person knows me need and am I making it worse with the judgments how can I be a
kind friend to myself so it can open up a new perspective that's often when we
are in our own mind and around maybe judgments are coming up or our regular habit patterns may not be
accessible so and um with that I'd like to invite us
to turn to practice in small groups now and
um the invitation tonight with the small groups uh the small breakout groups is um
how have you tried the third person perspective in this way what about it
works what about might be challenging what can support you uh what about taking the perspective of the Buddha
Kuan Yen Etc so so just playing around with perspectives sharing your aha moments or
or challenges or or maybe you fell asleep which is perfectly fine or maybe the whole time you were distracted which
is perfectly fine just checking in just a brief check in with each other in order to support and the invitation is
just speak from your own experience just a short nugget there's no right or wrong and then the next person will go
alphabetical order we share nugget and then the next person there is no asking questions or directing it's just we show
up and also when near turn comes you can just say pass perfectly fine to pass
and such a rare and beautiful opportunity to be able to uh share to
practice with others it's it's remarkable so I'm creating the breakout
groups ask you to be kind to yourself be kind to each other and I'm about to open
them actually let me here we go
foreign will close in five seconds we'll wait for everyone to get back
okay everybody's back so uh we have time for maybe just a couple of Reflections
and you're welcome to type them in chat if you like if you typed them to me
alone um there um it'll be private if you type it to everyone it'll be public and you
can also raise your hand any Reflections any aha moments any challenges
Marianne thank you Nikki
um I just wanted to say that the third person perspective is very helpful for
me both in giving myself meta and in concentration
because it seemed like the the uh I had more freedom to just let myself
concentrate and stop thinking because somebody else really important the Buddha was saying it's okay
yeah thank you beautiful thanks for sharing that lovely both and giving
kindness and in concentration just the sense of he's letting go yes the Buddha
the invoking the external and yet the Eternal Buddha the inner Buddha whatever
then beautiful thanks for that Marianne Jerry says I was kinder to myself and
then more kind to others as I am very good at self-criticism yeah
thanks Jerry yeah this third person perspective can really be helpful with criticism especially for for everyone so
Misha loses helpful to sense when Ian's warmth loving but not caught by my
personality the relief to be beyond my personality yay and then what a relief
right to have the wisdom and kindness and and not be caught beautiful just I'm
loving the practice reports and and one of you also sent me an email earlier today because this is a similar theme
that we worked with on Wednesday and then and one of you emailed and said yes this is
working for me great and and just things are easier with the third person perspective and just yeah yeah so
beautiful delightful lovely um any other Reflections before we close
this feels complete to me and um
and uh one of you says a new person wanted to know about the third person
is is that a mill confused by this comment does that mean when you became a
third person the new person wanted to nobody a new person in happy hours I'm
not quite sure but the the context of that question um yes
there there was a new person who has never been to a happy hour ever ever ever ever
and she was very confused and she wanted to know what it meant to have the
perspective of the third person oh okay got it thanks so so thank you for that
Serena and and I did explain it in the guided meditation I wonder if this person a joint leader uh in in the
middle of the guided meditation or or maybe but but the idea of the third person perspective is is the way I
guided it tonight was first we sit on the body and then we have a sense of oh
yes the Buddha the Buddha the kuanian externally that is just giving us love
and kindness and acceptance and then we take the perspective We join them looking at our own lives that's kind of
we take the third person perspective together with with kuanian
[Music] um with Kuan Yin or the Buddha so that's how we take the third person perspective
onto our lives so we're still us but so we know our own history our own life but
with this from this perspective of complete kindness and and generosity that's what that means
another person uh says hi Nikki one of our members felt more grounded from the practice after dealing with the
difficult news from the police officers in Tennessee yeah difficult difficult news
difficult times and they continue in in our country in our world and I'm glad to
hear that this practice that police could offer some support and some grounding
yeah yeah so yes uh
recording is available and uh I'll post it tonight
and um yeah and what I'm also just to let you know since I've been I'm
experimenting tonight with with a different length of happy hour not the whole hour but to see if it's actually
it's a little shorter if the guided if the guided meditation is the 30 minutes would keep that but the the um uh darmet
that Dharma talk is shorter if the reflections are briefer so that maybe instead of a full hour it'll be 15
minutes or something how does that feel um overall and it's 15 minutes now so
let's give that a try so let's let's close let's close our happy hour tonight
and as always I thank you for your practice for for your cultivation
showing up as best as you're able to may all beings be well may all beings be
free including ourselves [Music]
thanks everyone be well take good care of yourselves from a third person
perspective with lots of meta and love take care
stop recording I'm gonna stop the YouTube and not