so hello everyone and welcome
I hope you're doing well and
your area is doing well enough that you can sit here and meditate
aware of the challenges of this world while at the same time
being able to put it aside wisely safely
knowing that sitting and meditating is a preparation
for being in the world in a wiser way carrying away
that sitting in meditation and putting aside The Wider world
the best we can is
has the idea of turning ourselves into a gift for the world it's not an escape from the world
it's a pause just as it would be to pause to go in the shower so that you
can be clean for the people you're going to be visiting
so meditation prepares us to be the better people if we're
entering into the world
so one of the important aspects of Buddhist practice a little
bit like what I just did is to reframe how we
think about our lives approach Our Lives how how we're aware of Our Lives
because often the framework the orientation which we use is part of the
source of the challenges that we have and if we take our existing orientation
for granted which is what is so easy to do we grew up with
it it's we've had it all our life it's almost as you know it almost seems like it's inherent to existence that
the way that I see the world see myself that's the way things are but as we begin to settle in meditation
and mind begins to quiet some we learn either on our own or because in
the extents and teachings we hear that there are other Frameworks other points of view or
other very foundational kind of uh understandings from which we can live
our life so I'll offer Buddhism offers many of these but
I'll offer a few too today one is that when when we have anything
happening for us especially things that are challenging but even things that are really good
is not to dismiss any of them but allow us to be present in a wiser
way it's helpful if we don't identify with
them but don't take them to Define Who We Are and rather to add a very simple
four-letter word and that is with
so if we're filled with fear rather than saying I'm really afraid
we say I'm here with fear I'm here with
desire craving I'm here with anger and resentment I'm here with
doubt I'm here with distracted mind
I'm here with joy I'm here with calm
and when we say with rather than I am then there's a Gap a space
between us and what we're experiencing the and that space is invaluable
it might just be a crack initially but with that space with the width
now we can engage in deciding how close or how far away to be
with the difficulties we have what I mean with aware when we're aware
of it is awareness going to come in close and get really in touch with the feelings with what's
happening for us or can we do we want to step back almost
like we're standing across the street or up in a hill looking back at what it is
that's a challenge oh fear if I step back if I stay close it
just seems too much for me but if I step back 10 feet in my mind imagine
well still difficult but if I stand back up on the hill 100 feet away well I can
kind of then it's okay to feel the fear to be with it and I don't become it I don't get
influenced so strongly with it or there's a there's an agency there's
ability to kind of reclaim our life from the way we get swept up in what we identify with
and engaging in certain amount of agency certain amount of capacity
to say that oh I'm with this I'm with this difficulty and in that
width decide how close or how distant
you want to be or how close in or how expansive and spacious
you want to kind of oh I want to hold it how big of a container
do you need to make of awareness so that you can be with what's happening
so to experiment with this so
sitting and meditating sitting and
meditation posture and closing your eyes
and to then just check in with yourself how are you
just in the most General way and how are you sitting here
in whatever way you answer can you
kind of gently step back and say oh I'm with this way of being
so you don't have to identify yourself with it that this is who I am
but I'm with tiredness I'm with preoccupation
I'm with calm or agitation I'm with being okay
and then in that space of width or can you find a space between you in a
sense and with to decide how to
hold how to be aware of how you are
that's most helpful do you want to get in close and really
feel it intimately or do you want to open up and be
expansive spacious spacious rather than intimate
and then as you're sitting here your body is breathing
in a certain way you can just let yourself know that you're here with the breathing
and being with breathing does it feel nicest to be
intimate with the breath with a body breathing
or open up and be spacious spaciously receive
as if breathing
is a bird gently flapping its wings in a vast Open
Sky
or intimate and close
is if you curl up with a comfortable blanket
you kind of curl up with breathing or breathing curls up with you
you are not your breathing but you are with your breathing it
accompanies you
now to identify with it
but to accompany it to be with it
and in that space between you and it how will you be aware
if you take a time out for meditation to step back and
check in with how you are what's happening
in what way are you identified or caught up in something
where you can switch to recognizing it
has just it's your Witness
with preoccupation
with sadness with confidence
whatever it might be what are you leaving out
and then begin meditating again staying close with a place where
awareness mindfulness allows you to be with things
instead of being what's happening just with
to clearly recognize you can be with whatever is happening
and in that width
there is a gap between you and the phenomena
and in that Gap you can decide whether to be intimate
or to be spacious
and if things are difficult sometimes it's easier
to be with it if you're very intimate with the direct experience of it
and sometimes it's easier much easier
to open up and be very spacious maybe even
being aware of it with the kind of a peripheral vision
so you're not being aware of it directly
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
the ability to accompany to be with
becomes kind of a power strength
when we can learn to accompany and be with others
rather than being preoccupied with ourselves
rather than being preoccupied with ideas or should and shouldn't
preoccupied with pleasing or protecting ourselves from
others the operating word is preoccupied
to shift the frame of reference from being preoccupied to learning to be with
with ourselves and with others
and may have a clear sense of being with
there is in that place of agency a place of choice
for how we will be with
and one way to be with others
his spaciously calmly
so that maybe we can be with others kindly
may we accompany others in their lives
with our Good Will and encouragement
our appreciation of others our love for others
may we live with kind regard
for those we are with may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you
hello and welcome to our five part five part series on them
kind of mindfulness check-in I guess I'm calling it The challenge check-in
checking in with ourselves when we having challenges in our lives difficulties
I think Troubles of some kind or other and um to kind of present this in a
slightly different way perhaps than I have first couple of days we are using the the Buddha's fun
foundational teachings on mindfulness as a way of reframing
our challenges our difficulties that
we are often enough some of us ing a framework or an orientation or a
belief that um or an attitude which is not supportive
not helpful when we're in middle of challenges
and so rather than you know avoiding the challenge or pretending it's not there
uh or fixing it uh what we do in mindfulness practice is
we can reframe the situation so we approach it we see it in a new way that
may be more productive more helpful for us for how to be in the middle of it all
and since a lot of what a challenge is is how we are challenged with our
emotions our beliefs our physicality our fears all kinds of things that go on inside of us
that unless there's a you know an immediate Danger
it's invaluable to check in with ourselves how am I what's going on here
for me and so for example just simply coming down a little bit
makes us in a much better space some usually to to really see wisely what's going on
and so just just to take a pause and really and check in and we check in in
these four different ways it's a reframing and the value of this is that we often
will be caught in a framework that is clearly not helpful well not clearly as
we don't we don't know that but sometimes is self-reinforcing
and if I'm allowed to use an analogy or an example maybe of
if you have a tendency to to Really distrust dogs and Earth and in that
distrust you're angry at them if a dog comes along and you angry and
you stare at it with his Angry Eyes the dog will take that as a threat and
is maybe more likely to growl or attack than if you just kind of are ignoring
the dog and just kind of relaxed and at ease and you know not staring at it
and um and so to go around with an attitude a framework that all dogs are
terrible and bad and shouldn't be there and the Very attitude the dog picks up
something and then dogs all become that way
if we're afraid of dogs the same thing dogs have a way of picking up sometimes fear maybe sometimes we're afraid we
also stare at them trying to protect ourselves and the fear is it opens self-reinforcing
so it's a framework we have a fear or anger which uh
we believe is true as this is how things are and it's accurate
but we don't realize how much we're we're you know kind of sometimes self-perpetuating the proof that that's
the case and this can be work with people as well so sometimes if we can then see
how we are oh I'm I'm really angry I'm really afraid
and say well that's the framework that's the attitude to which I'm seeing things
certainly there might be threats out there and difficult things out there don't want to deny that I have to be
careful but let me take a let me reframe this for myself let me look at this from
different points of view and that's kind of the wisdom of the Buddha is to take that different
framework and see if there's a different way that's wiser more beneficial for how to be
so we ask ourselves you know how is this physically for me I was in terms of
feeling tones and today the emphasis is how is it in terms of the Mind States
and what's a state of mind with which I'm kind of with this or state of heart
that with which I'm with this experience what's happening and for example so if you notice that
the state of mind is one of anger or fear or greed or doubt or agitation
whatever it might be or the state of mind is contracted or the state of mind is scattered
if you're able to see that the way the Buddha presents the mindfulness practice
is to know that the mind or we are with
fear he actually with them anger with Desire with
being scattered with being contracted and this word with
I think is so phenomenally uh simple humble easy to overlook but is so powerful
it creates a little space between what's happening with us
and and the mind or the awareness or in
simple lay terms between you know me and the experience
and in that Gap in that little pause or that kind of recognizing then the question is the reframing is now that I
know that I'm with this this is here and it's kind of filling me in many ways
but I'm not it or I'm not it's not the awareness how do I want to be with that how can I
be with it and and one of the reframings we're
doing for it's so important in times of challenges is to begin finding some degree of
agency and choice to do something that is wise
and in meditation at least and sometimes in daily life it's a it can simply be
reorienting how we're going to be present for something so
um so uh and this meditation is a fantastic laboratory to work with this because
ideally you're comfortable safe in your meditation time maybe you've locked your
door so whatever you know close the door and really kind of feel okay you're clear that right now things are safe
uh you've looked around checked all the corners and under your bed and in the
closet and it's clear like okay it's okay for now and then to
um to uh um now ask the question of yourself how
should I be with this simply asking that question is an expression of agency of your own kind of
beginning of your of your own strength how do I want to be with us I'm with it now how do I want to be with it and it
might be that you'll learn very quickly I shouldn't be with us this is not
useful I I don't know how to be without spinning out or getting overwhelmed by it I need to take a break I need to
break the way in which I get sucked into it the whirlpool of it all and so we go off and do something
different something that you know stops that kind of being swept up in it
or we find a different framework to hold it so that we don't get swept up because
the framework itself creates a nice container and a nice balance a foundation a grounding
that that we can be with it in a good way healthy way
and so in terms of just awareness practice uh being with something you can ask the
question should I be intimate with it really close should I be very spacious
and there are sometimes I have difficulties physical pain or emotional pain and I find that it's most helpful to be
with it right in the in so intimate with it that I feel like I'm sitting at the heart of it
and sometimes that's useful and sometimes I find this that's not useful at all and what's useful is to step back
and kind of create a spaciousness or really be really wide
with it within a kind of expansive awareness expansive mind and sometimes we can use our imagination
to support this we can imagine that we're in this very very large room
and the road and the awareness is as big as the cathedral-like room and we can hold the challenge
or we're on a we're standing on a Hilltop you know 100 yards away
and we're at that distance and we're not holding at all we're just it's just like
so far away that oh yeah I can allow myself to be aware of it now
or perhaps we have some ability to shift the focus of attention
so maybe we come back to the breathing that's the center that's where we stay grounded the rhythm of breathing but
then in the peripheral vision kind of on the side we're kind of aware oh yeah I'm afraid
I'm upset I'm sad I'm whatever I tend to get pulled into I'm distracted the mind
is really busy and it's but it's there but you're not looking at it directly just like with a
dog don't look at it directly but kind of look away but you want to stay aware
that it's there so use that peripheral vision to kind of you know know what's
going on so in this third Foundation of mindfulness there are two ways that I
think is helpful that's emphasized here one is this word with
and the poly word that's used is the word it's a prefix being with a saw
essay and uh so uh with greed uh with ill will with
delusion and then also it's possible do it with uh healthy States
you know so the opposite whatever the opposite is of greed ill will and delusioned you know I'm
with this I'm with generosity I'm with
love I'm with wisdom and there's a fascinating thing that
goes on when we make this with is that some things
get weaker the difficulties the things that we that we are most react most reactivity tends
to get weaker tens is an operating word when we're with something that's re coming out of
our inner reactivity and it's um and it if it's coming out of
our on our inner Wellspring of
of wisdom Wellspring of innate capacity to be in within the world in a nurturing
way then that is um it tends to grow
and as it grows it tends to let me settle we start recognizing more and
more that spacious mind the expansive mind and um and that's a reframing
and learning how to reframe to be with stuff in an expensive way spaciously
so it's a little bit complicated maybe what I said today but um uh it's well worth kind of beginning
to see how the four foundations of mindfulness all four of them are a
reframing how is my this Challenge from the point of view of my physical experience
and once I'm aware of it physically that maybe gives me a foundation to
learn to be with it in a helpful way be present mindful in a compassionate way
how am I with the feelings is a pleasant or unpleasant and this gives you the power or the
strength to choose is it useful to stay with the unpleasantness
or would be useful to be more more bring in more of the pleasantness which is
here that's overlooked foreign state
what's this how are you what's the state of your yours you how are you with this what's the state
and to switch to I'm with this to help you find a more supportive way
to be with things so you might try today as you go through your day
to have uh when there's difficulties maybe start with the smaller ones
uh to notice how you fall into it or lean into it or get preoccupied in it
and see if you can switch to accompanying it accompanying how you are
being with how you are so that how you are is not driving you
almost subconsciously but you're really present and you're with it so that the
reactivity doesn't have the upper hand but you and then
see if you can figure out how to be with it wisely
so thank you my friends and
I look forward to tomorrow