my friends welcome and happy to be here
with you and to greet you with my delight that we have this time
together and
um so there's a saying about
mindfulness that is mindfulness is easy remembering to do
it is difficult so the act of mindfulness in
of itself is meant to be phenomenally simple so simple it's sometimes hard to
trust it so simple that it's uh maybe hard to remember to do
it and um and uh a lot of the practice
is remembering and coming back and coming back and um at some point in the
history of Buddhism uh the word Sati translated as mindfulness um was understood to be
remembering it has a really to related to the word memory or remembering so part of it is to remember
to do it and uh because it's so difficult to remember the mind wanders off it gets
caught up and thinking a lot um then
um there's a second practice that we can do that um
uh helps us to keep us in the flow of mindfulness it's also a way of
protecting ourselves mindfulness is meant to be protective so that we're protected from
picking up uh thoughts and impulses and
motivations attitudes which are harmful for ourselves or harmful for others and
it protects others it protects ourselves and so this not picking
up uh sometimes uh so when whatever happens when when you notice you're
not being clearly mindful in the present moment uh but you're kind of leaning
into or getting involved in or picked up in anything else let go of
it or if you see it arising don't pick it up let it
be so for this meditation certainly be mindful but
maybe the emphasis can be don't pick it up if you've picked it
up let it go if you can't let it go let it be let it be so so you stay in the in
mindfulness to do this not picking up and letting go require some degree of
mindfulness of awareness of what's Happening not picking up letting go let
you kind of settle back just be aware now of the breathing of the body be aware of what's Happening rather than
leaning into it or caught in it or reacting to it and um and this doesn't have to be
how you live your life but uh it can be very effective as a relaxed approach to
meditation so you stay a little bit alert let go don't pick up let things be
and stay in the Contin continuity and let that help you remember to stay
present so to assume a meditation
posture and a a posture that given you
the conditions of your body mind and
life uh allow you or support you in being aware in the present moment here
and now that can
be any one of the four Great postures the
standing so walking standing sitting and lying
down and perhaps gently closing your
eyes and with [Music]
some sense of dedication
devotion spend a few moments arriving here and
now if you have some preoccupations or something that's
strong happening to you acknowledge it kindly acknowledge it
oh this is what's happening name
it recognize it maybe feel how it is to be this way
now and then take a few long slow deep
breaths for now letting go of the thoughts and
tensions and concerns that you have let go the best you can at least the
tensions in the body related to it on the exhale deep inhale and exhale
release relax
for
and then letting your breathing return to normal and continue with a few rounds of
breathing to relax in your body relax any tension in your body
related to whatever you might be concerned
with whatever way you might be feeling it's okay to be how you are but let go
relax
and then relaxing the thinking mind any tension
and pressure that might be there softening in the forehead in the
skull any place you feel tension and pressure activation around
thinking relax the activation
for
and then settling down to be with your breathing be in your body
to be the home base the home for your
mindfulness present moment
awareness and if breathing is not the right place for
you go to your home base your default way of staying in the
present and as you do so be alert
enough to not pick up whatever arises you don't need to be aversive to
anything just don't pick it up don't be
involved no need to react
judge and then if not picking it up it's not enough let go of it let go of your
involvement with it the tension connected to
it or let it be so it has no hold over
you you can stay in the flow of
mindfulness protect your present moment
awareness and you'll be
protected
for
e
to help you not pick up to help you to let go you might say
gently kindly no thank
you or not now
for
e
gentle no thank you so you can not pick up or you can
let go and return to being
aware awareness that's not compromised just aware breathing body
body feelings thoughts resting in
awareness
e
for
by not picking up by letting [Music]
go something profound within is protected
BR if mindfulness of awareness has us connected to a deep
root of presence of wisdom or
Freedom then not picking up and not put not not picking
up Keeps Us close to
that treasure
within we do have something within to protect valuable to
protect that we lose all too
easily
for
there is a place within that's underneath the reactive
mind underneath the discursive mind story
mind where wisdom and
patience kindness
resides when not picking up when letting go and letting be can keep us close to
this deep root
inside we're protecting something
deep and as we come to the end of the sitting May our capacity to be
aware support us to stay
close to our deep inner capacity for
wisdom for kind attention patience
for generosity and
love and from there to gaze upon the world with good
will a good will that is a
well-wishing wishing everything in all directions well may all be
beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free [Music]
thank
you
so welcome to this ninth talk on the 10
protectors and this idea of uh
there are practices we can do that protect protect us and protect others
implies that there's something valuable to protect and
um and one of the discoveries through things like
meditation practice and spiritual practices of different kinds and other ways of being in the
world we discover that there is uh uh a place within of
well-being a place of happiness or peace a place of
wisdom a place that uh where there can be a phenomenally
wonderful easeful caring for the world even in the midst of great
tragedy that we don't have to sacrifice this valuable place within
and uh not sacrificed by the the strong human Tendencies for
anger for hostility for hatred for greed
for um jealousy and envy
for self-righteousness for
um you know to be caught up in anxiety to be caught up in fear to be caught in
ignorance these are common human Tendencies which tend to cover over tend
to restrict and are obstacles for this deep place where wisdom and compassion
can operate in a nourishing way in a healthy way so in uh there's a story that's told
by the Buddha kind of a fable and he talks about um that the ancient world
there are two acrobats and um and the AC the master
acrobat and The Apprentice and um and uh it turns out The Apprentice is
the name and the literal meaning of the name at least the way it appears to us and who know a little bit of Polly is a
frying pan and so I don't know you know jumping out of the frying pan or something why they name that that way
but um maybe it's you know you know irrelevant to the certainly
irrelevant to the story perhaps but the two acrobats and the master acrobat uh and
so the The Apprentice is going to climb up and do acrobatic Feats uh balanced on
the master acrobat maybe you know stand on one hand or a strong Master acrobat
is going to hold up um the with one hand the
The Apprentice who will do various acrobatic Feats um on this one hand of
the of the senior you know uh acrobat so so the
senior acrobat says um watch over me and
I will um and then we will both be safe
and I'll watch over you and that way we'll both be safe and The Apprentice said no that's not how it works um I'll
watch over myself and then we'll both be safe and you watch over yourself and
then we'll both be safe so in telling the story the Buddha said yes that's the way it is but he
doesn't quite then he goes on to do teaching which kind of little bit changes it even though he says uh he he
prefers the the the instructions from The Apprentice but he says yes and the
way that we protect others by first protecting ourselves is
by practicing the four cultivating the four foundations of mindfulness to cultivate our capacity to
be aware in an embodied way aware of our body to be aware of our feelings the
feeling tones that we have to be aware of our mind states to recognize them and
know them well and to be aware of the mental state
mental activity of the mind that either creates tension the tension of
attachment or releases that attention that that tension and uh and reveals the
beautiful qualities of the Mind the seven factors of Awakening the Deep Insight that leads to
Liberation and so the mindfulness that uh cultivating those four foundations of
mindfulness that's the way we protect others and um and I suppose the
protection the way we're protecting others we're protecting them from ourselves remember the analogy of the
acrobat is uh there there are two people who are doing these amazing kind of
interrelated interactive um Feats
exercises and for the people who we were in direct contact with um in the ancient
world of the Buddha that was primarily where the influence and the effect that people had on each other was directly
with each other there was no uh social media in the time of the Buddha and uh
the communication lines were all through people's uh uh oral contact with each
other so it was even you know it gets more complicated in our modern world but
in the ancient world the Buddha reference point was how we're relating to people
directly when we have contact and in that world we protect others when we
protect ourselves and um when we cultivate the four foundations of mindfulness we're
not going to give in to Greed hate and delusion we're not going to get into the kind of ways in which we get caught up
and intense and reactive to what's going on and then people are protected from
our reactivity um and so the Buddha said so
then that would have continued and this is where he makes so first he agrees and this is how it's true and then he goes
on to say something little bit more inclusive he says um by um uh we protect
others by protecting ourselves by cultivating these four foundations of
mindfulness we protect ourselves by protecting others when we
practice patience uh loving kindness uh sympathy
uh and um there's one more I forget what it is and um and uh so uh this idea of
kindness idea of patience with people the idea of um having sympathy for them
uh if we have those attitudes towards others that's a way of protecting
ourselves so the protection goes you know in both directions that there are
certain things we do for ourselves that protects us from the kind of
unhealthy reactivity we might have and thereby protecting others and there's C things we can do for others uh which is
has to do with healthy supportive uh attitudes of Goodwill
towards others that then that in return protects ourselves we don't protect
ourselves when we meet people with hate we don't protect others when we meet with people with kind of a coldness and
indifference not really understanding where they are we don't understand others if we
are um impatient with them or intolerant
the word kti that's usually translated as patient uh can also mean uh tolerant
of others certain tolerance being intolerant in English usually is kind of not a very good thing to to way of
being and so to um and that's how we protect
ourselves and um so but the so now in this ninth protection of the 10
protectors uh what's um uh what it is is mindfulness Sati
awareness that um and it it's significant to me that it's the ninth of
these 10 that um that be practicing harmless that's
the other one for anyway protecting uh um uh
harmlessness learning the Dharma well uh being devoted to the
Dharma uh being uh loving it uh there's
all these things that we've been talking about that that lead up to our support
and protect one of the greatest protections we have which is mindfulness and
um and so to practice mindfulness not just for the sake of
mindfulness but because hopefully at some point as we practice we know there's something valuable inside within
us we have we have uh access to a source
to a profundity to a place a
a a activity of of wisdom of compassion
of love of kindness of generosity of uh
non-harming of insight of being really grounded in a place of
non-attachment this is worth protecting and we protect it by being mindful
because if we mindful we'll see very the greater the mindfulness the
more acutely will see the movements towards reactivity the ways in which attachment
operates where we get involved we lean into we get caught up in we just even
justify reactivity and um and but to come back to that deeper place and to protect that
in doing that we protect others and we protect ourselves we do that and then we
have the opportunity to offer to others uh the good will the kindness that is a
kind of extern protects us externally for mothers it tends
to uh the opposite of these things intolerance impatience uh harming others
uh ill will U being unsympathetic to the
situation of others that doesn't contribute
to others wanting to care for us
it contributes to the opposite so um so
mindfulness is a protector and the more
we're practicing mindfulness more we stay aware the more we have the opportunity to protect something that's
really precious within and from that we begin protecting others and uh and have
the possibility of living a life where hopefully we're all protecting each other we all have a capacity deep inside
for beautiful qualities of being and if we want to find that in the
world and spread that in the world um let us become transmitters of it let us
be be people who demonstrate that this is possible and if no one demonstrates this
POS this is possible then how are people going to learn it
so thank you so we have one more protector for tomorrow and I very much appreciate this chance to talk about
these things and um May you protect
yourself and today if you can maybe practice mindfulness through the day
perhaps uh you'll you know whatever you remember to be mindful check in and
reflect on how you are and what just happened for you what's been going on the last minutes for you and see did you
lose your mindfulness and in losing the mindfulness did you get involved in a reactive way did you get involved in
something that ideally you would have been protected from some way of being
caught in a tense way or and maybe in that in seeing that maybe you'll say oh
yes mindfulness is a protector and um and it was it's wor it
would have been worth it being Mindful and been mindful so I didn't get so caught
up and if you didn't have any caught upness during the day then um the end of
the day you can celebrate thank you