good evening everyone how is the sound level for everyone okay can you hear okay
Abraham
okay it's a little louder um
yeah last week Diana asked me if I would give a talk tonight I fill in for her as
she teaches her retreat
I've really been enjoying what Diane has been teaching she's been
reading suitors stories about teachings that the Buddha gave to people
that um stories that about teachings that the
Buddha gave to people who came and asked him questions about what he was teaching
um you know who are sincerely curious about what the Buddha had to offer
all of those teachings were given after the Buddha had
fully awakened so it wasn't until after he had finally broken through all of the
the um Fetters greed delusion and hatred
that he could then start
sharing his knowledge with other people so that's
um what we've been hearing for these last few months these teachings from the time
that the Buddha had awakened
it said that when he awakened he could also remember his past lives lives that he had lived
prior to to the life where he woke up and
you may or may not
believe that but anyway there's these the whole set of
stories called the jyotica tales which are Tales that took place in the lives before the
Buddha woke up and they're often used um
in Buddhist cultures as ways of teaching
about particular type habits of heart and mind
particularly qualities of heart and mind that that one can cultivate
and that facilitate the opening of the heart
to let out the things that need to be let out and
to let in the things that need to be let in so
um so tonight I wanted to read one of these jyotica Tales this is one that I heard
about a little over 20 years ago I was on a retreat with Lee brasington and he
was ugh this was a retreat on concentration practice on the
absorptions and one of the things that facilitates that practice is doing
the Brahma bihara practice these practices of loving kindness of
sympathetic Joy of compassion and of equanimity
so this particular story that I'm going to read is one about compassion
and the thing that I liked about these stories is they were
they're kind of foundational you don't really have to understand all
of the Eightfold Path and the four noble truths and you know the 12 steps of
dependent origination these are just stories about simple qualities of heart
and mind that you can cultivate
so um
so I'd like you all to get comfortable
you know sit in a posture that's you have some sense of relaxation and
comfort but also some sense of alertness
I don't recommend that you use this as I listening to this story as a way of
falling asleep I'd like you to to be a to be awake for
it [Applause]
okay oh hand this particular version was written by a
man named Rafe Martin about 30 years ago and it says that it's for grades 9 10 11
and 12. so looking around the room I think you all are qualified
for this to hear this teaching and I don't know about people online but I'm
I'm assuming that many of you are so we'll start the story
once the Buddha was born as a banyan deer when he was grown he became leader of
the herd he guided his herd wisely and led them to the heart of a secluded Forest where
sheltered by the giant trees they lived free from danger
then a new king came into power over the land and above all things this King loved
hunting as soon as the sun rose he would Mount his horse and Lead his men on a furious
Chase through fields and meadows forests and glands
shooting his arrows madly he would not leave off until the sun had set
then the wagons rolled back to the Palace behind him filled now with deer or rabbit
pheasant monkey leopard bear tiger and
lion and the King was happy
his people however were not pleased Fields had been ruined by the Royal hunt
Farmers and Merchants have been forced to leave off their work in order to beat the jungles and drive the hidden beasts
towards the waiting King and his men Affairs of State too left unattended
people determined to bring all this to an end devised The Simple Plan
they built a stockade deep in the forest will trap a herd or two of deer in this
Stockade they said then the king can hunt all he wants let him hunt to his heart's content
we won't ruin our fields or Force us to leave our shops then let him be happy
Stockade was built and two herds of deer were driven within its walls
the gates were closed and the delicate animals charging and wielding in frantic
circles sought some way out but there was none
exhausted at last they stood trembling awaiting their fate
the men left happily to tell the king of their success
one of the herds that had been captured was the herd of the Banyan deer the Banyan deer walked among his herd
sunlight played on his many branched antlers his black eyes Shone and his muzzle was
wet the blue sky is overhead Green Grass Grows at our feet he told
the others do not give up where there is life there is hope
I will find a way and so he strove to ease their fears
soon the king arrived to view the newly captured herds he was pleased
he strung his Barrel bow in preparation for the hunt noticing two deer Kings below he said
the leaders of both herds are magnificent animals no one is to shoot them they shall be spared
then standing on the wall looking down over The Stockade
he sent his arrows flying into the Milling herds the deer became frantic racing wildly
they injured one another with horns and Hooves as they sought to escape the deadly reign of arrows
and so it went every few days the king and his courtiers would return to The Stockade
and every few days more of the gentle deer were killed many others were wounded by the flying
arrows still others were injured in the effort to escape
the king of the Banyan deer met with the leader of the other herd
brother he said shaking his antlered head sadly we are trapped
I've tried every way but all are barred against us the pain our subjects suffer is
unbearable as you know when the Arrows fly many get
badly hurt just trying to stay alive let us hold a lottery
each day all the deer One Day from your herd one day for mine
must pick a straw then the one single deer on whom the
lottery Falls will go stand near the wall just below the king
that one deer must offer itself to be shot it is a terrible solution
but at least this way we can keep many from needless injury and pain
and the leader of the other herd agreed
the next day when the King and his courtiers arrived they found one trembling deer standing
directly below them its legs and body were shaking but it held its head high
what is this said the king ah I see these are Noble Deer indeed
they have chosen the one deer alone shall die rather than that they should all suffer from our hunt
these deer Kings have wisdom a heaviness descended on the king's
heart we will accept their terms he announced from now on shoot only the one deer that
stands below and unstringing his bow he descended
from The Stockade wall and rode back in silence to the palace
that night the king tossed and turned a radiant deer pacing through his dreams
one day the lot fell on a pregnant Doe she went to her King the leader of the
other herd and said I will willingly go and fulfill the
lottery once my fawn is safely born but if I go now both I and my unborn
child will die please spare me for now
I do not ask for myself but for the sake of the child that is soon to be born
but the leader of the other herd said the law is the law I cannot spare you
the lottery has fallen on you and you must die there are no exceptions Justice
demands that you go
in desperation she ran to the Banyan deer she fell on her knees before him and
begged for his Aid he listened quietly observed her with
wide and gentle eyes rise sister said the Banyan deer and go
free you are right the terms of the lottery require that
only one need to die therefore you shall be freed from the lottery until your Fawn is born
I will see that it is done too Overjoyed for Words The Grateful
bowed and then bounded away
the Banyan deer Rose to his feet there was no other he could send in her
place he had spared her therefore he himself
must replace her how could it be otherwise
he walked calmly with great dignity through his browsing herd
they watched him as she moved as he moved among them his great curving antlers and strong
shoulders his shining eyes and sharp black hooves
all reassured and comforted them never had their Banyan dear King let
them down never had he abandoned them if there was a way he could find it
if there was a chance to save another he would take it not once had he lorded it over them
he was a king indeed and his whole herd took comfort in his presence
the courtiers were waiting with bows drawn Atop The Stockade when they saw it was the king dear King
who had come to stand below they called out O King of the banion deer
you know our King has spared you why are you here
I have come so that two others need not die now shoot
you have your work and I have mine
but lowering their bows they sent a message to the king
your majesty come with all speeds at The Stockade
not long after the king arrived riding like the wind with his robe streaming
behind him what is it he called why have you summoned me
come your majesty has been called look
the Banyan deer stood below then dear King and human King looked at
one another Banyan King said the dear At Last I know
you I have seen you gliding through the forests of my dreams
why are you here have I not freed you from my hunt
great king replied the Banyan deer what rule can What ruler can be free if the
people suffer today a doe with fawn asked for my Aid
the lottery had fallen on her and both she and her unborn Fawn were to die
the lottery requires that only one shall die I shall be that one I shall take her
place the lottery shall be fulfilled this is my right and my duty as king
a stone rolled from the king's heart
Noble Banyan dear he said you're right a king should care for the least of his
subjects it is a lesson I have been long in the learning but today through your
sacrifice you have made it clear to me so I shall give you a gift a teacher's
fee for the lesson you have taught me you and your whole herd are freed
none of you shall be hunted again go and live in peace
but the Banyan deer said great king that is indeed a Noble gift
but I cannot leave yet may I speak further
speak on Noble dear
O King of men if I depart to safe if I depart to safety with my own herd will
that not mean that the remaining herd shall simply suffer all the more
each day you shall kill only them they will have no respite
A Reign of arrows will fall upon them well I desire
Above All Things the safety of my people I cannot buy it at the cost of
increasing the suffering of others do you understand
the human King was stunned what he exclaimed would you then risk
your own and your herds freedom for others
yes said the Banyan deer I would I will
think of their anguish great king imagine their sufferings and then let
them two go free
the king of men paused and he pondered at last he lifted his head and smiled
never had I seen such nobility or such Resolute concern
how can I refuse you you shall have your wish
the other herd Too Shall go free now can you go off with your own herd
and be at peace
but the Banyan deer answered no great king I cannot
I think of all the other wild forefooted creatures like them I have lived my life
surrounded by dangers and fears how could I live in peace knowing the
Terrors they must endure I beg you mighty king have pity on them
there can be no peace unless they too are free
the king of men was again astonished he had never imagined such a thing
he thought and thought and slowly the truth of the Banyan deer's words grew clear to him
it was true he realized there's no real peace unless it benefits
extend to all
you are right great dear said the king of men at last never again in all my realm shall any
four-footed creatures be slain they are all freed for my hunt
rabbit bore bear lion leopard tiger deer
all never again shall they fall to my huntsman's arrows
so my teacher have you now found peace
but the banion deer said no great king I have not
what my lord of the defenseless ones of the air the birds great king lives surrounded by
a net of danger stones and arrows shall greet them now wherever they fly they shall fall from
the skies like a rain throughout your kingdom they shall know such suffering as can
hardly Be Imagined oh great king I beg you
let them go free release them also
great ones said the king of men you drive a hard bargain and are determined
it seems to make farmers of us all but yes I shall free the birds
they may now fly freely through my Realm no man shall hunt them again
then may they build their nests in peace now are you satisfied are you at last at
peace great king answered the Banyan deer
think if you will of The Silent Ones of your Realm fish my Lord
if I do not speak if I do not now speak for them who will they swim the lakes rivers and streams
of your land hooks Nets and Spears will there be ever poised above them
how can I have peace while they abide in such Danger
great king I beg you spare them as well
Noble beings of the king of men tears trickling down his cheeks
compassionate one never before have I been moved to think in such a way but yes I do so agree
the fish too are of my kingdom and they too shall be free
they shall swim throughout my land and no one shall kill them again
now all of you assembled courtiers and attendance announced the king hear my
words this is my Proclamation see that it is posted throughout the
land from this day forth all beings in my realm shall be
recognized as my own dear subjects None Shall be trapped hunted or killed
this is my lasting decree see to it that it is fulfilled
now tell me Noble one he said turning to the Banyan deer once more are you at
peace flocks of birds flew overhead and perched singing from amongst the nearby
trees dear grazed calmly on the green grass
yes said the Banyan deer now I am at peace and he leapt up kicking like a fawn
he leapt for Joy cheer Joy he had saved them all
then he thanked the king and gathered his herd departed with them back into the depths of the forest
the king had a stone pillar set on the spot where he had spoken with the Banyan deer
carved upon it was the figure of a deer encircled with these words
homaged the noble Banyan deer compassionate teacher of Kings
then he too lived on caring wisely for all things
so that's the story of the Banyan deer
and it said that in this story The Banyan deer was
the Buddha in a previous life when I first heard this story
it ended with the line never stopped caring
and when I heard that uh you know I I had sort of a mixed reaction
I loved the story I loved the compassion that it showed
and I thought does this mean I have to be compassionate all the time
it was a little it was a little bit daunting when I heard the story um
so I'm curious to hear how this story landed with you all what questions you
might have what comments what reactions
um
did you learn from the Banyan deer did you learn from the King
uh what was that like
and in the spirit of this story I won't limit it to just the people sitting in this room but if somebody
that's on on YouTube would like to uh participate as well you can enter your
comments and I'll ask bhupal to read them when we get to them
um but for now I
encourage you all to um step forward yeah so could you give the
microphone to Abraham
yeah thanks I was having trouble with the sound system I didn't hear all of it but I
think I heard enough but you also asked a couple of questions right there um
that I learned from the deer I think you described dear the story describes the
deer as walking very resolutely
with a lot of calm and dignity knowing what the situation was
and I think that in itself points to the practice
freeing oneself from from the pain and anguish
not freeing the pain and anguish is there but knowing what what is going to do
resolutely is a freeing kind of a freeing from excessive worry
but then to your question um
or your statement how does one that's a very daunting task how does one
embody that much compassion and it is it's a story and it's pointing
towards compassion but for me I take it more I think and maybe the five uh five
oh no I can't even think you know ah the trainings
not to take life not to harm anyone not
to steal not to lie not to abuse oneself sexually or others
and not to use intoxicants but the word is training there's no Perfection required
it's training so we fall we fail uh but the training is still to be all
compassionate I think that's how I see it great thank you
thank you I think the thing that came to mind when I heard the story was probably
the term or thought of leadership this is probably what you would want your
leader to to sort of embody um just sort of we all come from the
same drinking well or whatnot but I thought it was kind of um admirable rare
for the Banyan deer leader or King to sort of put himself at the same level as
the rest of his tribe and I think of kind of our political landscape and how there's a lot of tribalism and Division
and stuff like that but uh it was nice to nice to hear and get that sort of
symbolism
yeah now when I first heard it I you know I kind of thought
okay well the Banyan deer he's got a free pass he's not going to
get killed you know so you know that's pretty good
but then he wants his whole herd and then he wants the other herd as well
I mean it just you know it just keeps going that it isn't sort of like okay this is a good enough deal you know I've
I've struck a deal and this is good enough you know he's just always looking for
um more inclusivity
when I was read this story I was told that apparently in some versions that it goes on a
little bit further which is after all these animals are no longer going to be killed or harmed
they start destroying the fields you know they start going through the farmers fields and eating and everything
else and so the Village People Come Back To The King to the human King and say
well you know look at this you know this is this is not good and so there's a further deal that's made with the
animals that they can graze and eat anywhere in the forest and uncultivated
land but they're to leave the cultivated land alone so it it isn't you know it isn't just
the animals getting uh free but you know them also respecting
the villagers so it you know there's there's never an
end to it you know like every every action has some something to it so you know that
continuation of thinking and caring for other people
is is one of the lessons I get from this story
are there any comments online no okay
oh Sally
so I I was actually wondering when the deer was going to ask the king
to not kill humans to not go to war oh with his own kind
well there's about 550 of these jadaka Tales so that may be left for
another another story yeah but I thought that would be the you
know maybe the the capping request right yeah yeah
anyway yeah there was another part that I
noticed was the way in which the king went from taking great pleasure in
hunting to took
to still letting his uh subordinates
hunt for meat but that he he no longer took any
pleasure in it you know like it was like he didn't he didn't go there anymore and so that
kind of waking up to you know some something that we might
find personally pleasurable but actually is doing harm to others that that was falling away
and
and to build on that uh I I think
and to build on that um there was a falling away of his pleasure
and there was a developing of a reflective mode that dream comes to him
and the dream is powerful for him so there's a a whole direction towards
self-discovery and I think your point about
um you know when does he tell humans not to uh hunt each other
and of course that wasn't set up to begin with in this story it was only set up for the animals but I think
in a way that's kind of hinted at I don't want to apologize but I think it's
kind of hinted at by the deer starting to include more and
more types of beings in other words it's the Brahma maharas in the end it's all beings may all beings be free
from suffering yeah very good
the thing that that hit me you were talking earlier or someone was about the political divisions that we live in
right now and the tribalism and stuff and that very first step that he made of
well no it's not just my clan of deers but I want that other one over there and
even the choice of giving himself instead of the other clans or herds
female with the baby you know he was Thinking Beyond his own small group right there is a lesson
to look Beyond even though they they're still dear but they're not my dear it was no I'm going to go there
yet no very stupid oh
yes I I follow on that very much the sacrifice of each individual animal
each day going to the slaughter spot
and then the king willing to sacrifice himself the the message of
being willing to care for your community enough to sacrifice for your community
to me it was a very strong teaching here
and that that's care for your community to care for those around you is is a key
piece of wisdom here thank you
yeah I think one of the the things that um
I guess I hadn't I hadn't thought about it until I I've read this over a couple of times recently
um for some reason I I was thinking that
if the Banyan deer was the Buddha to be that this would be a lesson about him
learning something but actually it's more about him teaching demonstrating and teaching some
qualities to others
you know that sense of Radiance you know that the other deer and the and the human
King could just look at him and see that there was something
some something about him that was admirable
well maybe that's uh that's it for this evening thank you all
for coming and sharing um
and I think that Diane will be back next week thank you all
[Applause]