great so hello and welcome everyone it's wonderful to be with you this community
that comes together um from around the world cultivating our
hearts in kindness in Goodwill for the sake of ourselves and for the sake of
others as I shared on Monday last week I was leading a uh a residential silent
retreat at Spirit Rock and um teaching with my dear friend and teacher Sylvia
Borstein and and in her teachings it's so beautiful in her teachings um she
infuses meta kindness just infused with everything she says she does is just
such a beautiful inspiring way that she shows up and and that's who she is how she who she has become and one sentence
that she shared in her teachings um she she repeated that multiple times it
really struck me really struck me and that sentence that sentiment is
which is so true is I am the principal
beneficiary of my own good will of my own kindness I am the principal beneficiary
of my own goodwi that struck me it because it is
true it is so true we often think we're cultivating kindness as we do for other
beings may you be well may you be happy we cultivate compassion for other beings
who are suffering and of course um it might seem that we are and we truly are
others benefit as well well people in our lives people around us our loved ones our
family our friends and people at the grocery store
the checkout counter people behind us in the line people who who are driving with us on the highway you know people
benefit of course they benefit from our own Goodwill but we benefit the most we
are the principal beneficiary of our own Goodwill
because when our mind or hearts are
imbued with kindness with
Goodwill they become non-sticky our heart our mind becomes non-sticky we are
we are much Freer we have much more freedom we suffer less things become
non-sticky because we have our own Good Will that is turned towards us it's
turned towards others we don't keep stewing in resentments towards
others which of course who's getting hurt when we're resentful we're the
principal person who's becoming hurt when we're resentful or angry or upset
or reactive or or greedy or or you name
it you name a dozen unhelpful UNH wholesome states
of mind that hurt us the most heard us the most so as we
cultivate Goodwill as we cultivate kindness we are the principal
beneficiary of our own Good Will I think that is so profound so I want to
spend this this session this this day
um with the profundity of this teaching of this realization as we turn our
hearts to kindness so that is the preamble and I think I've said enough to
set up the stage so so let's turn let's turn to sit
together we need to
move so that we're sitting comfortably sitting upright with our back straight
as much as possible or if we're lying down let our backs be
upright straight the spine without as much Integrity in our posture as
possible
and relaxing this body relaxing this body relaxing
into the chair the cushion offering the weight of the body to the
Earth finding refuge in the Simplicity of this
moment
with each in breath bringing more ease bringing more breathing in more kindness
lightness lightness of heart expansiveness
friendliness and with each out breath breathing out kindness
Goodwill breathing in kindness Goodwill for this body that is mine that is
ours this body that's doing its best this
mind with every out breath breathing out Goodwill kindness to
others
thoughts arise as they will inevitably do thoughts
arise and we find ourselves thinking about the past the
future it's okay realize what's happening and don't kick the
puppy notice the puppy might be tired Restless the puppy of your
mind maybe call it oh dear Restless puppet it's okay come back sweetie come
come rest on my lap come take refuge in this
moment
calming
soothing Gathering collecting our hearts and Minds in The Refuge of Goodwill
Refuge of kindness if
someone comes up in our heart space mind space wishing them well and
returning to the
breath and and with each breath wishing this being this body this
being who is me
well
resting this being is doing their best and as Suzuki roshi said you're
perfect as you are you are perfect as you are and there is room for
improvement
may I meet this moment fully may I meet this moment as a
friend
now if you like turning this teaching that I am the principal
beneficiary of my own good will dropping this in as a reflection
into your body into your heart not your head but into your body and letting it
resonate that it is okay for for this being who is me to be
the Principal beneficiary it's
okay letting it be nourishing letting this teaching be
inspiring
and maybe to let this reflection resonate maybe the meaning or the scope
of the concept I will expand I am the
principal beneficiary of my own good will
you think about it just drop it in see different Impressions Reflections that might
arise hold some Reflections if you start to spin out please let it go just come
back to the breath and sit [Music]
silently
e
I am the principal beneficiary of my own good
will just drop it in your body your heart without thinking about it let it
work through you
I am the principal beneficiary of my own
Goodwill
I am the principal beneficiary of my
goodwi
and as we turn to bring this sit to a close
dropping this reflection one last time as if it were the sound of a bell
resonating in this body I am the principal beneficiary of my good
will let it touch your heart your
limbs every cell of your body and could perhaps for a moment the
eye [Music]
dissolve the beneficiary of my good
will and I can dissolve perhaps for a
moment
perhaps there is no boundary between I you me
them the beneficiary of my good
willll the I can be so expensive
impersonal
beneficiary of my good will me all beings
everywhere including this being who is me benefit from my good
will all beings be well may all beings be free
so everyone thank you for your
practice so there are so many ways at this teaching I'm the principal beneficiary
of my Goodwill and I decided the own was extra I don't think sovia was saying
putting the maybe that was my extra addition um I am the principal
beneficiary of my Goodwill there's so many ways that this can show up in our
hearts and our minds the more we reflect on it the more dimensions of this
teaching can come up so I'd like to invite us to explore this teaching together um in small groups and each
person is invited to ex to explore um what is one way that you can you are the
principal beneficiary of your Good Will in your life in your daily life in your
interaction with others with how you treat yourself um how you treat others
uh your mind your body just different ways so the invitation is will be in
small groups and the order will be uh it's do alphabetical order first name
and and each person the first person will explore well I realize that if I
have good will towards myself and if I'm not self- judgmental so much that that
that good willll really benefits me it's really a way that I can be in the world with more freedom and more ease so
that's one way this practice this this teaching show up shows up for me then
the next person can do an exploration well I realize if I'm really angry at someone and if I have good willll
towards them and perhaps see their side of the story yeah my heart lets go I'm
I'm less angry I'm less clinging to being right clinging to
being the righteous one oh and actually I benefit from my Goodwill to the other person but I benefit more because I
suffer or whatever it might be so the next person can say something or it can say past and you just go around and
round exploring together um not teaching not edifying but just exploring with one
another and trying to go deeper and deeper supporting yourself this is such a rich teaching and it's wonderful to
have this Dharma group that's interested in these teachings to unpack these
teachings with one another just honoring each other not asking questions not you
know not directing but just really bringing your curiosity your humility your
interest um your good will so that's my invitation for our exploration today and
I would love to hear what you what you discover when you come out on the other
side so I'm going to create the groups now and invite you as always to be kind
to yourself to one another and I'm opening the rooms now
here we go welcome back everyone so um would
love to hear from you what did you discover um in this exploration was that
something that became clear to you it revealed itself to you from this
exploration and you're welcome to raise your hand to share your um um Discovery reflection especially if
you haven't shared for a while and also I'm going to CH change the chat settings now and you can uh chat but put your
Reflections in chat either uh privately to me in which case I won't read your name or
to everyone in which case I will read your name so Mima I see your hand
please um I was really I shared in the group that I was really like I felt the major shift in my body when you took the
eye out when you took the eye out I felt like when we were saying I am it was
yeah I could see that but when we took the eye out it was like Global like all of a sudden there were no barriers we
were one and I was really moved by that and I'm still feeling like the reverberation of that um taking the eye
out how how big that is to take that out thank you Nikki thank you so much Mima
oh I'm so happy to hear your practice reflection and how U it impacted you
this invitation um yay I'm just delighted that was my hope that that
would be the outcome to because really this teaching about we take things so personally and
it is impersonal and yet if we try to get rid of ourself it becomes like a
fight but then when the eye just drops away ever so gently right it kind of
drops away it's like wow this is expansive there's this Goodwill that can
be expansive and beautiful for the benefit of this being and all being so
great lovely thank you Mima yeah bill I see your
hand hello hi um in the group I had just a a small
observation just occurred to me for the first time which is that that the love and Patience are so intertwined and that
you that I have to slow down to show concern for others and that the the
rushing and being impatient is is part of self-involvement so just a quick thing
thank you that's all I wanted to say awesome thank you how how did you say it
bill that impatience and and rushing is part of
self- involvement yes uh I mean I think you just yeah I think that's what I said
yeah beautiful it's it's brilliant it's so interesting and then we get to I I noticed that if I'm rushing I get tight
and just kind of my my vision my sense my body gets tight and my vision gets
smaller and my perspective gets smaller tight tight tight um yeah yeah the self-
involve the relationship between the self- involvement the self the eye that we dropped away so
gently um and and um kindness benev in
good well yeah thank you Bill that was lovely oh thank you
any other Reflections you like to share either in chat you can share them or raising your hand if you want this has
already been so rich [Music]
Sara hi and thank you uh this was a great practice uh and in our group we
had this conversation also about the or we talked about the eye the kind of
dropping and just opening the heart and letting the other the others in and I
was also thinking about this concept of nonself or not self that is very Central
in Buddhist teachings and sometimes um I start philosophizing about it so much
the Mind becomes like wow what what is it what does it mean what should I do how how can I achieve that like this is
so Grand I can't even think about it and and yet what you said made it so
achievable like it can be such a simple thing just like opening your heart and
letting the other person in and it just drops and um yeah and and this also came
to mind recently I listened to Joseph Goldstein talking to Dan Harris about Nirvana which is a great talk and and he
talk about these moments these maybe fleeting moments of experiencing Nirvana where this eye is
dropping and you you can expand and I really like that and just connecting it
to what you just said so thank you thank you so much SAR this is lovely yeah many
moments of nirvano and the self- involvement with with or um yeah self
how should I I want to say it positively because yes we want to take care of this this being who is me care for it be kind
to it dress it feed it you know it's not that we completely drop it away but sometimes we just we're too Ang we're so
concerned about how this self is perceived and seen and like it there's a
lot of selfing which is not helpful it's
it's the selfing is not the same as taking care of oneself one one's being
um and and yet it can drop it's not this High hoyy doy IDE it's very practical
and here I hear that it it made sense for you yeah that's what they're talking
about these Buddhists it's it's easier than I think like yeah just dropping the
yeah the self-c concern and just ah relaxing a little bit yeah this eye
beautiful thanks s I'm just abolutely delighted yay yeah as Sylvia was saying in this um
in this Retreat the first book that she ever wrote wrote the title was it's easier than you think and she said if
she had to do it all over again she would say she would have the title be it's easier than you think and the
subtitle would be it's harder than you imagine so so because our
imagination makes it kind of hard in a way but anyway so thank you for that and
Jerry says being vulnerable is a gift of Good Will and of beneficence and it's
not transactional especially when it is truly vulnerable beautiful thank
you Jerry yeah beautiful so thank you all thank you for
your practice for for cultivating your hearts your minds for the benefit
of yourself ourselves as we are the principal beneficiary I am the principal
beneficiary and then who is this IE ah
letting it drop so may your practice be expensive may it be
of service to yourself and all beings everywhere may all beings be well may
all beings be [Music]
free thanks everyone take good care be well