hello everyone and welcome
and I'm happy to be back here and
I was on Retreat last week at our Retreat Center in Santa Cruz
and that was very nice
so to begin with some comments relevant for the
meditation I believe that often enough
in different parts of the world different religions
that which is sacred is also considered to be dangerous or
potentially dangerous and so to approach the sacred with respect
because of that Danger so I would like to say something about
this in Buddhism that uh might sound like it goes against the
grain or contrary to what you've often been taught about Buddhism
and that is that uh desire
can be sacred but because desire is also dangerous
and that in Buddhism certain kinds of Desire
are the origin for our suffering and the origin for a lot of the
suffering that we see in the world because of that sometimes desire gets a
bad name or is considered to be only something let go of
let go let go let go is a kind of Buddhist refrain
and we want to come to the end of Desire there might be some truth to that
to some degree but having desire is a very important
part of the Buddhist path having some kind of Desire is a very important part of the Buddhist life
the Buddha advocated having particular desires
but as soon as we have desires we have expectations as soon as we have desires it all too easily slides into attachment
to the desire fear of the desire all kinds of things
can happen and so it's easy then to fall back on desire is bad we shouldn't have desire
but desire is important and as we meditate today
perhaps you can experiment with finding a desire
for meditation a desire for being mindful being present here and now
that is not just a simple desire not just following instructions from a teacher
like to be present follow your breath but rather
arises out of a deep wish a deep aspiration
a deep intention and that being present here now being
with a breath being present and attentive
is animated is motivated by
such a inter such a deep desire within us such an integral desire within us
for such an important purpose that the desire has a kind of sacredness
to it it's something to respect maybe even have an awe that we have this
capacity for a heart's wish not to get excited and not to get
spitting up in thought but the opposite
and where we appreciate this desire and appreciate that the Fulfillment of
the desire is not found through thinking
but is found through knowing being aware being present here
with a quiet heart Quiet Mind
a fullness of art a full mind which is full of the present moment
peacefully to know that the desires goes in that direction in a certain way
or that the meditation is foundational
be useful for fulfilling other desires that we have
so to assume a meditation posture
a posture that is participating
in the desire maybe the sacred desire to be present now here
gently closing the eyes
taking some gently bigger breaths
establishing a connection Here and Now
in this body
letting your breathing return to normal
and feeling resting in your body for a few moments
and then doing it again and again
and each time you return to your body resting see if you can rest deeper into your
body settle deeper
maybe with each exhale settling deeper
relaxing the body
relaxing the mind
and then taking a few moments to feel your way in
assuming there's a place deep inside where desires can be peaceful desires
can be peaceful and profound
desires that have no expectation or attachment
but desires which are Maybe
sacred Maybe integral to us
in and there be a clear
desire
for being present here and now
for being awake in this body and mind
desire to not have your thoughts take you away to other places other
times past and future at their events
desire or the heart's wish
to be here in the lived moment to find
the fullness the sacredness the vitality
that is being manifested
each moment stay close to that desire
as you stay present mindful Here and Now
foreign
when you find your mind wandering off in thought rather than coming back to the breathing
coming back to the present come back
to the profound desire where the peaceful desire
to be here to be mindful
that desire that has no demand no expectation
but a desire which is sacred or valuable
a desire whose byproduct is then to be aware
said settling back into the desire to be present
and then discovering that you are then present
and then coming to the end of the sitting
compassion involves having a certain desire for the
end of suffering desire for the welfare
and happiness of others desire for the welfare and happiness of
oneself there are different kinds of love
one is the love that
is activated that is animated
by what we receive from others the love we receive the care
Another Kind of Love is a love that we generate
to care and love others wanting their well-being
wanting to support and to serve and to care
compassion and love can have within them
desire sacred desire the heart's wish desire
for the welfare and happiness of others
to feel that desire that wish
to feel that well wishing no matter how small it is
it's even significant if we wish we had
good will for others just a wish to do so even if we think we can't do it
that wish is the beginning
and then to always find a way to give expression to that care
that good will many infinite numbers of Expressions but
to let it live in you and to manifest in you and at the end of The Meditation
it can manifest in expressing thoughts of Goodwill for the world
around you may all beings be happy
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be saved
may all beings be free
and may it be our desire to contribute to that
foreign
[Music]
so hello on this Monday morning here in California
and uh happy to be back
I was teaching a retreat at our inside Retreat Center this last
week with Bruni Bruni Davila wonderful retreat
and um happy to be back here at IMC I'm
beginning to feel here at IMC and IRC a kind of coming to life again more fully
from um you know that's kind of gone
hibernated or during the pandemic and it's quite lovely to feel they act the
energy coming back and the people coming back and it uh here at IMC maybe from in my mind
a little bit is represented by um we're starting up offering day-long
Retreats here in person on Saturdays and this coming Saturday it's a
wonderful teacher I just talked with Bruni Bruni Davila will be teaching one
of the first day longs here I think from nine to 4 30 so if anyone lives locally and would like to come
and meditate for a day in community that's a wonderful opportunity
so the topic of this of these weeks from the beginning
of the year what I'm teaching here is practicing with challenges how to be
with the challenges of life and the challenges can be minor to being
the most major challenges in life of life and I've been hoping trying to lay down
the foundation that's applicable to all these different areas and for the big challenges that this is
also a very important foundation so that with time we can learn also how
to be with a really difficult things that happen to us within us
and the topic this week has to do with um strategies
for working with challenges and there are two general categories of
strategies of working with challenges the ones are
dysfunctional and ones are functional one
are wholesome and some and others are
unwholesome helpful and unhelpful and for the and I want to
use the teachings on the five hindrances and present them as common unhelpful
strategies that people use to cope with to deal with challenges that come up
but I don't just want to do that I want to say that each of those hindrances has an opposite quality
which is a healthy way of responding to challenges
and to have these two working together to know the two as you get to know recognize how
hindrance is work in you it's a that itself is a prompt to think
about to like oh what's the healthy form of the same thing I'm being challenged right now by some
difficulty and my coping mechanism is a hindrance is there another strategy what's the op
what would be the opposite and how do I tap into that opposite in me so it's integral it's got It's not a
it's not a overlay or pretend or something on top of everything
and um and often I I enough I think in Buddhism
that when the emphasis is talking about letting go and letting go of
the dysfunctional things that the Mind does it's often a left there just like oh
like a like oh and um and partly because as the practice gets deeper and deeper
and deeper as meditation practice is really the practice matures in fact there's a profound letting go of
everything but to have this attitude we're supposed to let go of everything
right away that's not really appropriate um it's it would be like
you know if you were going to go swimming in a public pool you would go into a changing room and take off your
clothes and put on a bathing suit and um and uh and so
you decide well you know that's I just take off everything and jump in the pool by going to the changing room
um you know it's there's a time and place for for um
you know letting go of certain things and so to do it all at once you know we
end up undermining ourselves or diminishing the
fullness and the strength and the I would like to say power of a human being that can come from the opposite of the
hindrances our strength resides there and if we don't have it there then our
capacity for strength or energy can really flow into the hindrances and sometimes people put more energy into
the hindrances than they do in almost anything else so for example the first one
sensual desire is people who put more effort and energy
into their addictions than almost anything else someone has this really strong addiction they mean boy are they
motivated sometimes get out of their way and they'll do almost anything to you know satisfy their addiction it's a lot
of energy there and um but to have that have not that desperation but to have really a sense
of power and strength in the opposite of the hindrance is the healthy versions is
possible so first we have to understand this so the first hindrance is usually said
to be sensual desire the Buddha offered a separate list of the five hindrances only difference
being that the first one is Covetous covetousness wanting the things other people have and wanting something
someone else has so one is a little bit more the a strong desire for everything
in the world of sensual desire um not just for sex or not just for
alcohol or something but you know comfort and sensuality and uh in the Buddhist analysis of human
beings this is one of the fundamental characteristics of human life is uh is a
sensual desire and um and uh sometimes the
acquisitiveness sometimes has very deep roots inside of us in the desire to
survive to manage in this life of ours so you know it's uh these things can have deep
roots in US but the there's a lot of dysfunctionality and sensual desire and
acquisite but this one of the things it does it um it kind of uh
creates a very strong uh separation or shutting down or diminishment of our
full connection to others and to the world our connection to the world and to
others is through the lens of fulfilling that desire and some people will even confuse love
with a strong desire to fulfill it's not a strong desire to fulfill
their sensual wishes that person can provide me with that wonderful sensual possibility and and so
there's a strong kind of Drive that is you know fills our being fills
our heart the deep deep kind of Yearning and wanting and they can be confused
with love it can be seen as a Kind of Love but it happens to be that it's probably
more has to do with sensual desire than than what I think would be a heartfelt
love and um so a lot of what a lot of mindfulness
practice has to do with or say differently of foundation foundational aspect of mindfulness practice is to
really become an expert really become attuned and skillful in recognizing the
hindrances and working with them so recognizing all the different flavors and colors and shapes of sensual desires
that arise all the time and not to reject sensual pleasure
which has a place in life it's maybe an important place in life at times
but it's the the drive the addiction the the way in which we get preoccupied and
kind of lose ourselves in this world of central desire that makes it a hindrance and so when we have strong
strong challenges in our life some people try to cope with it by getting
something else escaping into a world of central desire uh or fantasizing about sensual desire
soothing themselves in a sensual way as a compensation for the challenge they're
in that could be useful at times but as a hindrance it's not useful and it's so
strong on the other end of what's healthy and functional
there are profound desires inside of us capacity for desire capacity if we're
wanting something that arises out of our our kind of heartfelt
desire that opens us desires that open and connect us here to this moment rather than narrow us and
close us down one that kind of if anything frees us from addiction rather than submerges us
with addiction and we often don't get this message in Buddhism because of the strong idea that
many people have that you're supposed to let go of all desire sometimes people even think that all
desire is wrong the Buddha did not say that there's certain kinds of desire which produce
suffering but they're also desired dharmic desires desires that connect to
the dharmic path the desire to be free the desire to be present compassion has desire and it care has a
desire and it's caring for someone and then so where does so when we're
challenged by life challenged by things to take the time to pause
having the faith that inside us deep inside there is a place of healthy
desire healthy wishes for for well-being for ourselves for
others for welfare and goodness
and to be present to be part of a healing process to be part of a
transformational process towards for ourselves and the world to be a better place
and if we could take the time when we have big challenges to especially if we're caught in the
hindrances to see if we can shift gears take a deep breath try to find this
deeper place where we have these healthy desires and know that their place of healthy
desires no that's part of it now don't diminish ourselves or pretend it's not supposed to be there
but health is our desires are also the channel or the support for our personal
strength our our kind of a power of sorts even if
it's very gentle power uh there's a Kind of Wonderful strength in the gentleness of the desire and the
wanting and it can be the fuel or the catalyst
for Agency for engagement to know what to do
not assertively not selfishly not aggressively
but like water that just flows and flows around things and eventually wears all
kinds of things down we can have this give birth and give rise to and give expression to these
healthy desires once we know what they are and we trust it and we know that it has
important place in our life in Buddhism we allow ourselves to have
dharmic desires until the dharmic desires no longer have a
role and then we can let go of them because they've done their job
so um so you might consider this today spend
this day reflecting and feeling and maybe talking with friends about what
you know about the deepest desires you have that do not feel dysfunctional they
do not feel like they're hindrances or diminish you or frustrate you or or add
more problems to your life when we respond to challenges with hindrances we tend to create more
problems we when we respond to challenges by tapping into
finding the healthy desires then we tend to be able to move towards
health and sometimes it takes it takes time to reflect and to think go for a walk or
spend time meditating or talking to a friend to
drop down below the layers of reactivity and hindrances and things that we have until we tap into
some of the deepest Wellsprings of Desire healthy desire within us
so what are your Healthy desires what is it that uh is it what desires
are valuable for you to stay close to especially when you have challenges that help you to help you go through a
challenge with um with um
without collapsing without being discouraged without succumbing to compensate the
compensate compensatory uh kind of or escaping
that the hindrances are so thank you
and um and I trust that all of you have
somewhere maybe silently maybe hidden for now have within you
beautiful desires thank you