good day friends I hope you are well in whatever time
zone and whatever location on this planet of ours you are
delighted to be joining you in this moment in time to continue to explore the five Aggregates this week together
so today we continue exploring with the
third of the five Aggregates um
often translated as perception or recognition and uh
what an important constituent of our experience to really
become aware of and turn towards and really see so I'll say more about it
when we uh when we turn to the um darmet
and for now let's uh let's practice together so
I cheat too find a posture that is comfortable for
you whether you are sitting
lying down or standing In This Moment In Time
the posture that is both comfortable and has a sense of integrity
allowing the muscles to be relaxed as relaxed as possible
and allowing the uprightness of the spine if you are sitting
to really come from your sit bones from a supported base that is relaxed
and well rooted and allowing yourself to be held up
as if by an invisible force as if there was a magnet a very gentle magnet
pulling up the top of your head ever so gently ah
you can let go and relax any effort
relaxing any effort
and being in the flow of both
feeling present
engaged in your posture the posture of your body the posture of
your mind let the posture of your mind also
be engaged with this practice not with thinking planning past future
wholeheartedly engaged relaxedly relaxantly
easily engaged letting this relaxed engagement
receive the breath in the abdomen
are you perceiving knowing any
tightness in the body or in the mind and the entanglement that needs to be
softened released
and as we receive the breath the relaxed and engaged mind and heart
let yourself know that you are perceiving the breath
recognizing how are you recognizing how's the in-breath
being recognized
this investigation doesn't have to be effortful just drop this question in
the body leaning into
their recognition question isn't so much that you start
investigating and how is it being done but just know then oh yeah
in-breath is being recognized as an in-breath your out breath is being recognized as
an out breath
there has been many in breaths and out breaths and we recognize it and
maybe there's also a slight quality about this in-breath or this out breath
in this moment in time that's maybe it's recognized as being long or
short or deep or shallow
or easily leaning into
this recognition perception Sonya that keeps happening
automatically bringing it to the Forefront a bit
Forefront of experience
such a fun sandbox this mind is hard to be a scientist of it what
happens if you lean into
recognition as if you're highlighting it and breath our breath
this is an empress this is an out breath
perhaps even more refinement this is the pause between the in-breath and the out breath
just the pause between the upper and the in-breath
recognizing in breath in the out breath
or rather recognizing the recognition of the in-breath and the out breath
and as we say stay embodied and open this fear of recognition
and awareness further
but the relaxed mind and heart let their be a recognition
of us of the Mind recognizing different aspects of aspects of
experience
maybe a sensation arises and takes the center stage
sensation of the body and you recognize that oh yes this is
the sensation of my fill in the black my thigh this is that
this is that
oh yeah this is the sensations of my hands touching my lap
this is that I recognize this
your thought arises or recognizing
this is a thought and recognizing that you're recognizing you're knowing what it is
you're not a martian on this Earth having these experience and you don't know what they are you're recognized
this is that I know what this is
this is that
so if you have a reserve of many recognitions before pattern recognition
that's what's happening all the time become tuned attuned to it in the mind
and we turn into become aware of this pattern
recognition it's happening all the time
in our minds recognizing matching this is that
fast
usually unconscious based on so many previous experiences
and also through the lens of the Mind the Mind state
in this particular moment
fascinating
your body and mind be relaxed as the stream of recognition flows through
your mind gets tight your body gets tight Let It Go just be with the breath
keep it simple
and sometimes you might even notice that there's a perhaps
some separation timeline between recognition
of what an object is and debate enough feeling tone Pleasant
unpleasant or neither
or sometimes one comes before the other the vadana comes before
for the last minute or two of this practice period Let's do an experiment
but if you wear a smile intentionally wear a smile which we know physiologically shifts
makes shifts in your body and mind
and see if having a smile on your face with this shift
physiological shift changes how something is perceived
at this moment is perceived your breath is perceived
me how Shifting the state of your body and mind shifts your perception
see for yourself
and as we bring this practice period to our clothes let there be a recognition of
goodness wholeheartedness that you brought yourself to do this practice this is
good this is good
planting seeds of awareness Awakening
compassion kindness towards ourselves and others May our practice be of benefit to all
beings everywhere
including ourselves [Music]
[Music]
thank you all for your practice
take a moment to switch over the recording
greetings everyone lovely To Be With You In This Moment In
Time and I'm delighted to be continuing to um
explore together the five Aggregates this teaching this important teaching
by the Buddha um the five condas the five heaps the
five constituents of our experience that our experience
the way we perceive the way we feel the world are in the world know
ourselves as being human and our experience of reality is really made up of these five constituents nothing else
so it's quite profound quite profound and by bringing awareness to these
aspects we become more awakened as to how the how this is made how this this Gestalt
of our experience this happens often unconsciously so so we discussed uh Rupa
first day Rupa body the first day and uh the second day we uh
explored vadana or feeling tone Pleasant unpleasant mutual and today we're going
to spend more time with recognition perception Sanya and before we um
move to Sanya there was a question in chat that I noticed afterwards um that I wanted to address regarding
um vedana that came up yesterday so there was a question and this actually comes out for a lot of practitioners so
I appreciate the question coming in but um sometimes it feels like the feeling
tone the the of pleasant unpleasant or neither Pleasant or nor unpleasant but
usually these two Pleasant unpleasant seem very strong seem very intense and and sometimes they they
feel mild so is that different is that what's what's up with that how does the
teaching extend to that so so it's actually the same uh vedana it's the
vedana is is feeling tone it's
first is so if if the mind was really really concentrated and this is possible
by the way to see and to practice with when the mind is really calm and settled income concentrating I've done this
practicing um in and and one can see that
um when and for example an object arises stimulus arises in the sphere of
experience and and um and awareness makes contact with it
Pasa makes contact with this object in the sphere of experience at first the vedana the feeling tone is
actually in the first mind moment after the contact is pretty mild it can be
very soft and then in the next mind moments it gets it keeps getting stronger and stronger and stronger and
stronger um so so it's the same vaginized just the same the different intensities that
one can see maybe uh no it's almost like you can liken it to the uh say if you're
trying to fall asleep at a friend's uh uh house
and and they have a tick tock you know a big clock that makes Tick-Tock at first it's just Tick Tock you know the vedana
of the unpleasant perhaps waiting is very subtle and and soft but as it keeps
going on and on and on and on it just becomes like more and more unpleasant I don't like this make it go away so so
it's it's that building up it's that Snowball Effect and you can become tuned to it at first so if we actually so this
is how we can use this teaching is that if you bring awareness if you bring your
knowing to the to feeling tone at the beginning if you know that oh this is just unpleasant you actually get to see
it before it gets out of hand and gets very strong and and puts into action the
and I don't like it make it go away I hate it I you know blah blah blah you know all of the stuff that happens but
uh that can happen in in an unstable mind when the mind gets uh unsteady but if you notice at the very beginning oh
yeah this is a little unpleasant this is a little unpleasant there's a little subtle unpleasant vedana then then
um there's a lot more freedom that becomes available which is why this this
teaching of vedana is so powerful in fact in the teaching of of 12 Links of
dependent origination dependent arising but really the sublime
teaching of the Buddha really that has to do with with freedom um it is said that the link between vedana
feeling tone and tanha clinging bad link between all the 12 that that between
those two that link is the easiest place for us to cut the the
um the wheel that going on and on and again and again in the sub-sara and suffering that's really when between
vadana feeling tone and tanha which is clinging clinging or pushing away so
that so becoming aware of tanha is really so so powerful in so many ways
for uh our freedom for our ease as human beings the way we go through life
okay um now turning turning towards um Sanya which is which is an amazing
topic so um again all each of the these could be
an hour-long uh talk so the time left so Sanya s-a-n-n-a Sanya uh perception
often translates perception or or recognition it's really it's it's a little different from perception in in
um uh Western psychology it there's a lot more to Western psychology
perception so for psychology psychologists out there this is much simpler it's actually as I as I
mentioned during the guided meditation is pattern recognition is this is that this is that whatever comes into the
sphere of our experience recognizing it as this is that like if you see a a um a
string on the road a a multi-colored string black and white string oh this is
a snake oh no this is just a thread this is that so it's that aspect of
recognition this is that this is x y z whatever it is so
so um so much to say but briefly to say yeah maybe a personal history that at
first when I uh received the teachings on the five accurate so I was a little confused by by Sonya this is like these
five you know the Buddha taught chose very very carefully they're they're very
few things that are included in this five Aggregates as the constituents are why is Sanya so important that it
deserves to be among these fives and um so I didn't quite get it uh years ago
and and the more I have practiced I've actually seen that this perception or
recognition is so fundamental in in our human experience and and and our freedom or
lack of Freedom really lack of Freedom it's the it's a linchpin it's a linchpin
and there's so many teachings anyway so um so so
our perception our recognition is really
um conditioned is really our recognition is conditioned by so many factors by so
many causes and conditions so really Sonia again is it arises it dependently
arises dependent origination right the the sublime teaching of the buddhistania
dependently arises from so many different aspects and and and and
dimensions of our previous experience that we've had
as as well as our state of mind state of mind and body
right now and it's dependently arising it's actually empty sunyata is actually
empty it's not fixed it's so malleable and and our perception really depends on
our perspectives so in the guided meditation I invited
you to to tune into it and and um and uh it can be so fun to actually
tune into oh yes this recognition is recognition of this is that oh this is inbred this is out breath this is the
sound of neighbor's dog this is that this is a sensation in the body it's happening all the time we are pattern
recognition machines and in fact this is what you know being an AI scientist I do
have to bring this in so so when we talk about artificial intelligence and also the power that nowadays AI has these are
the AI systems that we have are simply pattern recognition machines the
algorithms um are tuned to have a lot of data and
then to recognize new patterns and generate new patterns based on a lot of data that has been has been seen so so
in many ways this is what we do as human beings and and we don't examine our
pattern recognition and we just go through life and do the same pattern recognition we always did oh
um oh the sound oh I don't like it I'll make it go away or this thought of self yeah self-judgment yeah that means Baba
so so we just these patterns they just keep coming and we recognize them without any uh discernment without
wisdom without compassion so so being tuned to how Sonia is happening all the
time and how dependent it is on on the state of our mind and body and also the previous experiences so
so so um the uh the invitation I had for you and a couple of notations I want to
highlight um one invitation I had the very end I asked you to wear a smile to just I know
you might feel foolish and stupid doing that but but just do it it's an experiment this this whole body mind
this is fascinating so uh we know that physiologically there are shifts and changes when we were a smile so do that
and then see how your perception your Sonia shifts a little bit it does for me
I noticed that there was a lightness it was just a bit of a lightness in the the
way my state of this present moment was being uh perceived
another thing I invited you to tune into um was sometimes recognition can happen
before feeling tone and sometimes feeling tone can arise before recognition and and it's again
fascinating to to notice these the the the impact of that in our everyday
experience so it could be that say you're sitting in meditation and you hear a say a dog bark and oh yes
recognition this is dog park oh yes this is the uh dog of my neighbor oh a
neighbor whom I had challenges with does this dog bark is unpleasant right so
after the sunny after pattern recognition an unpleasant feeling tone arises in the mind and maybe the mind
gets grumpy um um and sometimes it can be the other way
around sometimes they can be a a feeling tone Oh yeah there's oh and plus something unpleasant is happening in my
leg oh my leg has fallen asleep this is that I know what this is this is familiar I'm
not a newborn if you're a newborn and your leg fell asleep you're like what is this I don't know what this is where you
would cry but no yeah you have recognition you have Sanya you know what these patterns are but then again A lot
of times I'm speaking fast because there's so much I want to share with you anyway maybe that's enough for this morning
maybe that's enough but so for the rest of the day I'd like to invite you to tune into
um this pattern recognition and how it is dependent how it's malleable we just
recognize the Mind recognizes things this as that willy-nilly in an automatic
way and it doesn't always have to be automatic if it doesn't lead to Freedom
um and ease and care and kindness for ourselves and others so questions so put
a question become more aware recognize your recognition
thank you all for your practice I look forward to continuing the series with
you tomorrow be well recognize goodness
bye