so offer you a nice new early uh greetings and and uh for those of you
in the United States warm greetings on this day we're offering
thanks and nice to see your names and the greetings here on the chat and uh so
so there's a lot of people many of you I know many of you names I've seen frequently
and um it's very
nice and it's nice to see the locations you are in all
over some of you I know have been to our Retreat Center I've been on retreat with
you it's been very wonderful thing to do and some of you maybe someday you'll
come on a
retreat h on the chats disappeared for me I don't know what that
is I wonder if I'm for there oh there's
back
so again good day and welcome to all of
you on this day of giving
thanks and um one of the things I am very grateful
for is my meditation practice pra this practice of being
present and um I feel like it's been a I do feel it's a gift not only is the
practice a gift I feel like I feel very fortunate to have received this gift in my lifetime and I feel very fortunate to
for uh what seems to move through or arise as I
sit and it leads to a kind of deep gratitude ude to life to being alive to
breathing to um all the all that makes it possible
for me to be alive and safe enough and
quiet enough to be able to sit in meditation and to open the Mind open the
heart metaphorically at least when I'm sitting open my hands be open-handed in
this World openhearted open-minded and um and it just seems
like such a fortuitous Fort fortunate thing to to have this ability
this capacity to this uh opportunity to do this kind of practice
so when I bow at the end of a sitting it's often for me an expression expression of gratitude because I
learned early on that um it was good to express it it was almost like you know
it'd be hard not to uh some emotions we feel um come to
fulfillment when they are expressed in some form and uh I feel gratitude as one
of those that um that needs some expression some movement that
goes maybe Beyond on gratitude for me is an experience
that um there's something beyond my
personal ideas of self my ideas of my agency ideas of
my all kinds of things that are operating here maybe when D Buddhism we call the
Dharma and uh and to sit and open to this
wider kind of um some people might call it transpersonal some people might call
it uh uh the deepest most intimate place that's
non-personal because in whether it's transpersonal
or deeper than personal it whatever it is it uh it
gives birth to gratitude so we'll sit today and maybe
gratitude can be uh not far away maybe we can begin by
considering uh in spite of the difficulties that many of us have in our lives and
difficulties that might not be far away as we sit to meditate illnesses
and injuries and all kinds of things that um was
still huh I wonder what that is there's a
beeping it's probably a car outside I don't know if you can hear
it maybe the if you hear it maybe it's a
little mindfulness
Bell I'm going to take take a look anyway see what I
can
okay so it's a car that does
so let's begin and to assume a meditation
posture that allows you to spend a little bit of time to
appreciate being in a comfortable posture maybe a safe
posture maybe a posture that can be an appreciation for this
body that does so much for us supports us so
much gently close the
eyes
and it's not so farfetched to be grateful for what supports our life for what we
receive and with every breath we receive the
oxygen that is essential for our living for every
exhale we're freeing ourselves from gases which would be problematic if
they built up within
us to receive greatfully with every
breath
and every sensation you have in your
body is in part a consequence of the food you've
eaten that generates the energy for this whole
neural system to operate it allows us to feel and sense
this
body and we have a
mind even for all its challenges it provides us still gets us about gets us through a
day the mental processing that's so sophisticated that we hardly know it's
operating that's needed for us to just to get around the basic activities of
daily life happening so much of it
happens unconsciously and kind of effortlessly
at times to sit
here finding gratitude in every
breath appreciation and thanks for the ability to sense and to
feel in the body for every
sensation appreciating and being grateful for this mind that we
have maybe for every thought that arises that every
impulse let it be met with
gratitude and a gratitude which is an
attitude a background
attitude by which we receive all
experiences
e
for
and in the times that you're pulled into thinking distracted from here and
now to what degree is that a self-
involvement self- [Music]
concerned and all too often when we're self-concerned there's little
room to receive the gifts of Life the gifts of the spiritual
life the gifts of our
practice and self- concern all too easily interferes with
an open sense of
gratitude
that we receive so much more than we
give that all that gives Keeps Us Alive is a again
gift
e
for
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to appreciate that when the mind is
settled not
preoccupied when the heart is settled and
open and when we're just sitting here at peace
calm then there is the space in the heart
space in the mind for greater
appreciation of our life of this
moment a greater receptivity to all
that makes it possible for us to live our
life to recognize that our whole
lives are built on receiving so much from
others from the world from the natural
world and when we're settled there's more room for
gratitude a thankful fness for all that we
receive so many people work to keep the food in our
kitchen electricity
on who work in the stores where we shop who grow the food
and
everything we touch virtually that's man humanly made is something that's been made by
someone for us to use to appreciate to interact
with the roads that were built
electrical wires connecting our homes the list goes on and
on things that people have done that made our life
possible to appreciate how much of our life has been
built on the work of other people built
on the gifts of the natural
world and to sit in
gratitude and with that open appreciating
heart we give thanks thanks and we give our well
wishing may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful may all
beings be free of suffering and oppression and
War
poverty in our
gratitude may we be generous to this
world may we wish everyone well
in words in deeds and in thoughts may we
make this world a better place for
[Music]
everyone thank
you
so I want to share with you um kind of story of
gratitude that comes from one of the one of the very significant Scholars of
religion professors of religious studies in the United States named um Houston
Smith and he was uh he did a great amount of work uh spending a lot of time
living in different countries entering into the uh uh some of the major world
religions and participating them in them and studying them in a very deeply appreciative way and having deep kind of
personal relationship with people in all kinds of religions and over his very long
career and um and uh he tells the story of
practicing Zen in Japan at a very strict
Zen Monastery and he was there for a month uh engaged in this practice and
ended with a week-long intensive uh Zen Retreat where you get some like three
hours a night of sleep very intense and um it was you certainly
challenging for him and um uh but then at the end when he was
going to leave he went to pay his respects to his teacher his the Abbott
goto roshi and um and he was a bit stunned by what he
was told he'd been working is a rinai monastery been working on Coons these enigmatic questions that you struggle
with and uh he'd been meditating a lot and um the Abbot said to him um uh Coons
these in enigmatic questions can be a useful exercise but they are not
Zen so he thought he'd been doing Zen and sitting in meditation he went on
that is also not Zen so I think Houston Smith was quite stunned and surprised and what he had
been doing he came to study Zen and some of so much of it was meditation intensive meditation and and um and
these Coons and those aren't Zen so what was he doing
um uh and so the um the Zen master then said to
him uh so you be flying home tomorrow right and um and then he continued don't
overlook how many people will help you get home ticketing agents Pilots cabin
attendants those who prepare your meals he bowed placed his palms
together um and bowed in deep gratitude then he did this bow of
gratitude to me and he said make your whole life
unceasing gratitude he said what is then simple simple so
simple infinite gratitude toward all things past infinite service to all
things present infinite responsibility to All Things future have a safe journey
home and he gave me a wonderful smile and Saidi glad you
came so so here this zen master identifies
the heart of Zen with maybe with gratitude and um for all that we
receive and maybe Zen is not
meditation but maybe Buddhism is not the meditation but meditation is what clears
the heart it clears the mind so that we can see and feel and experience this
life from a place where we're not self-centered self- preoccupied
self-concerned so it's so easy for us to be pulled into the world of self-c
concern that uh uh everything is referenced in relationship to Me Myself
and mine uh we are thinking about ourselves we have an attitude of self
preoccupation an attitude of self-c concern and not just it's reasonable to
have self-c concern reasonable to take care of ourselves and know where we are and what
what's going on but when we have an attitude of it it means part of our mind
is always preoccupied with self always preoccupied with uh what's in it for me
or I'm not enough or I'm a problem
or um I deserve more or I um you know I
need to make myself safe and and there's an attitude of that's a lot of emotions
that are centered around this uh self a cluster of um of
preoccupations that's centered around a fundamental attitude that we carry with us a mood or a state that's referencing
Everything To Me Myself and mine and um it involves tension it
involves uh shutting down it involves not really being able to connect fully to the
situation and so meditation is a way to kind of quiet the self-c concern the
self- preoccupation and a lot of the reasons meditation is de-stressing is because
there is less self involvement in meditation and so the source of stress
is not operating so strongly unless we bring it with us into the meditation
self-c concern am I doing well enough am I concentrated I need to get do better
so all this game of self that goes on so letting that that selfing mind become
quiet that attitude be decrease and then it can be replaced or
it can be filled in with an attitude of
gratitude grateful thankful um there's a Zen saying that to
uh move forward asserting the self is delusion to settle back and receive all
things is Awakening and there's so much that we are receiving all the time just to be
alive so many people who are working just like maybe how many of you are
working um in a way that supports other people so our lives are working to
support are supported by so many people and um every day those of us living in
you know the modern United States driving on roads using electricity
taking water out of a tap in our kitchen um the um having maybe insulated homes
having our heater heater systems in our homes keeping it warm all that has been
put in place by countless countless people the food that comes to our table has whole series of people have had
their contributed bringing it to from the ground up into our
kitchen and um wow there's a lot that's we receive if we're
self-concerned it's easy to complain there's not enough we want more it
should be different um it's been said that
um when we have an attitude of gratitude we can be happy
anywhere if we have an attitude of complaining we would complain even in
hell even in heaven that um there's no
the um um
so to enter into maybe this
day appreciating that the lowering of self- concern self- preoccupation at
least where we're preoccupied where we're not good enough we
don't uh we're not enough we're
the situation is not enough for us it's not right for us that for us it should be
different that quieting that so no matter what the circumstances
we are to appreciate the goodness of it the gift of
it not being able to appreciate the gifts that we receive I think makes
spirituality impossible because the spiritual States
spiritual Freedom The Awakening the practice of mindfulness the the deepening subtleness the is really a
gift we can't demand it we can't assert ourselves to it we can't we can't really
use it to build up the self because then the beauty of this
life the beauty of our hearts the freedom of heart the freedom of world
um is not really available so to see spirituality as
entering into a world of gift
receiving we receive so much and perhaps in receiving those
gifts that in the present moment we can also give give our Smiles give our
well-wishing give our deep appreciation for others and who they
are and in our gratitude and appreciation we can have a vision for a
better tomorrow that we contribute to make for all of ourselves all of us not just
ourselves May our gratitude May our deep appreciation help us work for a better
future better tomorrow no matter how difficult it
gets let's step forward to contribute in such a way that in the
future people have reasons to be grateful for us for what we
do so thank you very much and I look forward
to one more day on this topic of of attitude and um I hope that this day
goes well for you and and um and if you have the ability to
meditate extra this day uh this is a great day to turn into a mini retreat
for yourself thank you