Hello friends hello and welcome to happy hour hi and if you can hear me okay give
me a thumbs up is audio okay or audio is fine F great hi so my name is Nikki mapi
I'm in Mountain View California and seated olon land and welcoming you to happy hour and uh would love to invite
you to say hello to to uh warm up the space together so take it
away this is uh don in DC hi Don you in San Diego Hi
H IRC I heard Mima and I also
heard Way Wayne from IRC hi let me change my
name that's great that's great who else wants to say hi hello hello Bill in
Dallas hi hi Bill Claire in New York hi Claire hi Ottawa hi
Jerry Tom from Austin Texas hi Tom r Oak
hi Fred hi Neil I'm Eli from Vancouver British
columia andus hi Eli and I see k Kim waving hi
Kim hi hi Vicki from Oakland hi Vicki and hi Sarah from Toronto and fosil from
Darian Illinois sweet a I'm Happ here already with all the H coming
in what a sweet ritual we have anybody else wants to say hello
before we transition to meditating hello Mary from Oakland and
Ruth from Vancouver Washington sweet okay let's begin so I'm going to
ask you to mute yourself if you you are unmuted at this point and uh I Chang the
settings so that unmuting won't be possible and um also thank Neil for
posting information about uh Happy our Google groups in our chat if you're new
to happy AR we have a low trffic mailing list you're welcome to join it uh
information quotes Etc are shared and um also we have an A a little um breakout
room etiquette as a invitation to offer yourself and others um safety and care
so so with that I'm going to turn on the
recording for the sake of Audio Dharma
recording where are you here okay here we here we go there so hi everyone hello
again and welcome to happy hour so I'd like to invite us to
uh to continue with the practice of compassion it's it's
a challenging time in the world and uh whether we are having personal
challenges also um and also caring for others in
our lives in our hearts in our minds you can never have enough compassion the practice of compassion of course with
stability with equinity with the stable base of care so I like to continue with
the practice of compassion um it just it feels appropriate to me
so so let's let's practice together let's
shift into our meditation
posture arriving arriving arriving in our
bodies arriving in this moment in
time softening relaxing the
body
taking a moment of Refuge taking this time for
Refuge away from the busyness and the demands of the
world first to settle first and foremost to
settle
feeling our feet grounded on the earth as if we were a
well-rooted tree
feeling ourselves well rooted connected to the
Earth
and we put down in this moment let go of worries concerns just to
become more
available connecting with the breath the INB breath the out breath the sensations
of the body this moment of being alive however
it's showing up for us as if it were last moment on the
earth so precious not taking it for granted not just another moment of being
alive in the midst of many moments but appreciating the gravity of being
alive in this
moment and really inhabiting inhabiting our body inhabiting
our our Humanity our
fullness not the same patterns over and over but really taking our
seat and I take my seat in this
moment relax into it and yet really take my
seat as if my life really matters because it
does
taking a few minutes simply connect with each INB breath and out
breath with the entire INB breath and out
breath coming fully present
and we settle in settle in more with more gravity with more
gravity feeling our body's
weight presence sitting here in this moment and
time
I like to invite us to experiment with a different way of practicing
compassion it's related to radiating compassion but a little
different
so let's begin with is the practice of radiating and we
find our way into this other way as if your
body reverberating
radiating care
through the entire
world care that touches you first as it's
radiated and as it radiates reverberates throughout the world World in unseen
ways it impacts whever it comes to contact
with with your goodwi and good wishes with your care especially if
they're suffering having [Music]
challenges and brings sucker Comfort
ease and again in this
practice it's not about magical powers it's about
cultivating our own heart our own Good
Will and instead of feeling hopeless and helpless we turn towards care
compassion instead of Turning Away away from the problems of the world and
the problems of our life we turn towards them with
care
and I'd like to invite you to consider the same way that in Einstein's
relativity Theory every Mass every
object bends the space around it bends the
space that's how gravity is shaped and formed every Mass shapes
turns the space around it these gravitational
forces this is how they're shaped and now imagine that your presence in the world
matters through the power of your care your compassion your
engagement space of humanity curves it shifts it changes around
you and the more caring people in the world there are the
more this shift this curving of the space of
humanity happens and your presence isn't for
not it makes a difference trust that it makes a
difference the gravitational force of compassion
shifting a space of humanity simply by your presence simply
by your good will there's nothing you need to
do simply have embody the moral
Gravity the moral [Music]
gravity of Good Will and compassion ody it that's
all embodied with each
breath resting that it makes a
difference
it helps to add the phrases of compassion please do so by all
means may I may all beings everywhere
be free from suffering from sorrow from Pain have ease in the midst of
it I
care where your
pain I care for your
suffering I wish you ease or I wish myself ease wish all of us
ease all all of us be free from sorrow from
pain
we move to bring this sitting period to
close can we trust that are caring compassionate
presence in the world makes a
difference by having this trust we can actuate more change in the
world instead of feeling helpless taking compassionate
action for ourselves for others may all beings
everywhere be free from suffering from sorrow may all beings everywhere be free
including
ourselves everyone thanks for your practice
may all beings be free from suffering and sorrow including
ourselves so this practice today we
started with settling in the body with the breath and then we turn to the practice
of radiating compassion which is something that we've discussed before you might be
familiar with and then returned to this idea of
of how the same way in in Einstein's relativity relativity Theory where in
Mass shifts and changes the space around it it curves space that with our
presence with our moral weight of care compassion for ourselves and for
others we curve we sh shift the space of humanity and and trusting that trusting
that and in this way it's also not so attached to outcome it's not so so um
forceful sometimes the practice of compassion can feel if you're doing the phrases and really attached to them may
you be free from suffering may you be it can it can bring more anxiety and and this is a way of actually settling into
the moral Gravity the compassionate gravity of of of our being alive in this
time and caring caring and that can support and help taking compassionate
actions instead of feeling overwhelmed and um powerless so it
really it's a way of feeling into the stability the gravity of our
presence for more compassion and more compassionate action instead of veering
into empathetic distress so that's the wisdom of this practice this is what
it's supposed to bring up and again some practices might work for you some may not it's all good keep it if it works
for you and let it go if it doesn't so with that we have some time
for for engaging with each other in small groups uh in breakout groups and the
invitation I have for tonight is um Let's Go reverse alphabetical
order first name and the invitation to explore uh each person will offer a
nugget again exploring for your own sake the other two people are just holding you witness not not asking questions not
interfering not cross talk just holding compassionate witness as you explore
what does this mean to you this holding this this the feeling into your the
gravity of your own compass passion and presence um how can be how how was the
practice for you uh in this session how can you lean into it what was
challenging just exploring for yourself and the other two people will are holding you withness so it's basically
you're journaling out loud is you're journaling out loud and other people are not going to ask you questions or
interrupt just offering a nugget and somebody else will offer a nugget or maybe they say pass and then you go
round and round as much time as you have be kind with one another be
compassionate this is really a way to practice um the rubber meeting the road
in the small groups first we sit quietly on our own and now we engage it's not about educating impressing showing off
showing up we're just supporting we're curving the space together in this
caring space that we co-create together and it's also very fun so enjoy the the
space that you get to co-create with one another so I'm going to create the rooms
and I ask you to take care of yourself take care of each other be
kind and um okay I'm opening the rooms now here
we go
hello hello and welcome back so the rooms are closed everybody's back and uh
we have a few minutes for Reflections um comments
questions so what did you discover what did you discover in this practice and uh
yes the chat is open as well so you can raise your hand if especially if you haven't shared in community for a while
um and you can also type in chat your questions and comments if you type them
to me um privately if you chat them privately I will read your reflection
not your name and if it's to everyone I'll read your name as well Ruth I see
your
hand um it was towards the end that we were talking and I realized I love
animals and it's so much easier for me to be compassionate with animals and I've seen some dogs um from Ukraine and
I just it breaks my heart um the unconditional love that we get from pets
is is so incredible and it's so much easier for me to have compassion for animals than people I hate to
say yeah yeah thanks for saying that and and I appreciate the courage that it
takes to actually say this and verbalize it and and it's great that you know and
and your heart has a way in um and for many people animals are easier because
we you know they don't talk back right it's it's there's a sense of ease you
know they don't have opinions they're just unconditionally loving they don't
you know um so and it's okay to start their Ruth it's perfectly fine to start
there and I ask you not to stop there and just to say that's it that's easy
I'm just going to start where it's easy and end where it's easy please start where it's easy you and everyone else
who might be listening say yeah me too um but don't end there let that prime your heart start
with with animals dogs pets start there and when your heart is primed then do
bait and switch this is how this practice works you you prime your heart
with wherever it's easy and then you bring in someone who's a little harder
and then the fire of the heart we call it like dissipate and then you do it
again you bring where it's easy you the fire of yes meta compassion and then you
bring in so you keep doing that until it catches does that make sense is that clear yes I see you're nodding great so
please do that this is great that you have a way in it's not a problem it's great yeah any other Reflections or
questions and me think about this perhaps unusual way of of feeling into compassion as
this the weight the moral weight and and relating it to uh Einstein's relativity
which has never been taught and will probably never be or what might be but anyway this is just creative ways of of
practicing compassion Mary I see your hand please thank you
um what I experienced in our
time was especially toward the end when you talked about trust it was like that
that's tough we um and
then something else you said and so I'm checking this was shifted it for me in
that the way I understood or the way I experienced was the practice of to trust that to
practice compassion meditate on compassion extending
compassion that that creates a
stability that then allows the
expression of compassion in in different circumstances and whether they be small
you know like um the clerk at the grocery store or they turn out larger that that is
less important it is the cultivation of the
stability am I on how does that yeah yeah yeah yeah I appreciate the way
you're you're putting it I think um you're you're articulating something that I was trying to bring in which is
compassion together with stability and stability is another word for equ imity
because compassion needs to have equinity as a part of it this A sense of so let's call it stability right now
stability equinity this presence the sense of presence conviction gravity
that helps it not get overwhelmed not get reactive not get oh poor me I have
no control there's a sense of stability and weight in it that's what I was trying to bring
in and that's what what I hear you picked up and that's the sense of yeah it doesn't matter how little or how
small it is but the sense of stability of it helps it grow instead of feeling small and
Powerless thank you I hadn't thought of it connected at all with with equinity
so that that's another good place yeah thank you
great thank you Mary yeah Jerry says we discussed recent work showing that the
more one has been doing daily mindfulness meditation that uh more one
can enter into compassion even for those suffering a great deal and think of how
one might help them great I appreciate that Jerry thank you for that reflection rich I see your
hand I forget do you go by Rich or Richard either way okay uh I just wanted
to thank you for bringing up relativity uh because I so often hear people talk about quantum mechanics and
I just feel that I'm lost in a SE a delusion when I start hearing about spooky
particles oh that's funny yeah yeah tell you what I might have mentioned this
before um but if you want a good resource actually a great book I might have mentioned the book hell goand h e l
l g o l a n d hello Land by Carlo relli
who's a um renowned um Quantum physicist actually and he speaks beautifully about
quantum physics and how it connects with emptiness in Buddhism and U naran's
Theory so if you want a an um a treatment of a topic that's not filled
with BS then then I suggest that that book Richard thank you you're
welcome PMA yeah hi thank you Niki um so I might
my comment might be bit somewhat controversial but um you know the whole
compassionate and the equinity it really helps for me it helped me thank you to
you all um you know in giving the compassion to the slightly challenged and even the most difficult one but I
think um like today I was a little frustrated because I don't think just
having the compassion helps the world that's suffering right um so I feel like
it's just for me being compassionate and it's like okay you know um be at peace kind of a thing so um yeah I don't know
if we have something to say but yeah yeah so so what you're raising
is this concern that oh is is my my practice of compassion is it just for me
to become calm and and um uh stable and
and and is it desensitizing me even I'm I'm just going to make it even more controversial than than you made it it
actually desensitizing me from the the suffering of the world just because I'm becoming calm and it's all good so I
think it is important that we don't stop uh practicing with practicing passion
with ourselves that's where we start and we need to have that it's so important to have that otherwise we're like a
headless chicken like ah I don't know what to do like that is the first place P that's so important so thank you for
doing that for the sake of everyone because if you are stressed out and um
and not compassionate to yourself that doesn't make anyone it's not good for
you it's not good for anyone around you so it's not a compassionate move it's it's it's not helpful for the world and
yet don't stop there similar to what I was saying earlier don't stop there when you are
practicing compassion for yourself being calm and and stable spend a minute or
two bringing someone else who's who's having a challenging time or you're having challenges with to bring it into
the space of compassion expand your heart don't be content with just where it is stretch stretch a little bit do
that was that make sense um yes but um but I was more referring
to how is that going to help um the conflicts and the world that's
suffering ah how is that going great great question how is that going to so
you know um if you actually do that part of bringing people who are say let's say
you practice compassion for yourself and and then uh after you have spaciousness
in your mind and heart you bring people who are suffering in the world and you imagine them suffering and still your
heart has the stability to wish them well to wish them well then compare that
to you being a headless chicken and not even having the space to think about them to bring them into your
Consciousness right so in one case you're turning towards them in another case you're not turning when you're
turning towards them there's more likely and compassion includes the motivation and the the and responding to
to suffering so maybe you will actually call your presentative maybe you'll sign a petition instead of just saying oh
this is too much I'm just not even going there so it's a stepping stone it's not
where you stop but it's the stepping stone to taking
action thank you thanks for your question Fernand says in happy AR metal
practice feels gentle to me but in Daily life I resort to it as a quick fix for discomfort making me question if I'm
misusing it how can I keep its gentle Essence in Daily situations tell me how if you wouldn't
mind because it's I don't want to put you on the spot either and yet it helps me under to answer that question what do
you mean if you resort to it as a quick fix for discomfort um if you uh if if you would
either put in chat or raise your hand and just create put a little more context because I'm not quite sure what
you mean what what that actually means whether actually you are misusing it or
not I don't know need a little more information more data
here and here I'm GNA ask you to unmute if you want to you don't have to
but yeah sorry I couldn't figure out how to okay thank you um I think I mean that
I sort of I noticed a an uncomfortable thought or a negative thought towards a
situation or someone else and I immediately feel like my mind is running
to the breath or to um meta phrases and
it feels like there's a little bit of distress in how quickly my mind is running to it got it yeah thank you yes
thanks for adding more um Nuance to it so so trust what you just said what you
just shared about oh yeah it seems like there's there's a little bit of a distress and just I'm running into to
using uh calming myself through meta like a hammer I'm just like hammering out the uncomfortable situation like ah
I can't be comfortable can't and um so so trust that so trust so so it's
okay so you so my invitation is to um allow yourself to become comfortable
able with being uncomfortable can you grow sense of comfort with
discomfort um and and be with it really enter it instead of pushing it away um
and and it can it actually it's a way to stretch ourselves instead of it's a way
of so the way you're describing it again I so appreciate your wisdom like yeah I'm kind of suppressing my negative
emotions like I'm not GNA go there I'm just gonna like yeah yeah patch it over with with meta and it is very healthy
and and actually it's um it produces more insight if you feel comfortable
going into it doesn't mean you cond you don't condone it and you don't act out of it I'll give you an example a few
days ago I noticed I was really agitated and and there was this this sense of
anger that's coming up and I usually don't feel anger so it's not a very comfortable or or familiar feeling for
me so and there was a sense of wonder notic I like I am not quite going in there it's like no no no I don't want to
feel angry no no wait sweetheart let's let's check this out let's go into it
let's feel what this feels oh yeah it feels uncomfortable I don't like it yeah but and this is what it feels and then
it opened up it it shifted it turned like oh yeah no this is healthy this is
good this it's I'm not going to act out of it but it's good to let it be it has
there's so much to for me for everyone to learn from letting it be and then it
transforms and then meta or stability or wisdom can be explored through it so I
hope that's helpful yeah thanks Fernanda so we have come to the end of
our time together thank you all for your practice for showing up to cultivate
kindness wisdom compassion for all beings everywhere including our ourselves may all beings be well may all
beings be free and may we be a compassionate force in the world may we
cultivate our hearts and our actions our actions to to serve all beings
[Music] everywhere thanks everyone take good care
thank you going to stop the recording I'm going to