okay people welcome uh yeah nice to see the messages uh
streaming
um yeah and that's me writing when I when it's highlighted in yellow Insight
Meditation Center that's not my assistant don't have an assistant I have
lots of lovely people in the background but I don't have an assistant
chatting out good
mornings yeah anyway lovely to be with you um uh it's been uh sweet to be with you
this week and uh
um yeah that's uh that's it
so just uh on a dime just
begin with love some species of
Love gratitude or
compassion love and kindness
Joy
equinity or uh maybe it's that special species of
love that uh we call
grief
but find something that gives you some access to your heart just uh rest in that for a minute
or two as we begin
here
just like um irritation or hatred
or impatience
depressive mood just like all of that can flavor
everything so to can
love
in the light of uh of love and care and poignancy this
uh just this breath kind of a big
deal Kind of
Wonderful
the energy of uh care gratitude aliveness just sort of
suffuses the
body
need not be dramatic need not be the rapturous Delight geysers of uh
love may be very
subtle but uh body and mind tilted in the direction of
care
tenderness
gratitude for um finding a a path that
uh promises or a hypothesizes that
uh that any given moment is practice any life is
practice the possibility of uh love and freedom is
never we
closed
and we may not be able to think our way into Freedom we may not be able to
muscle our way into it to effort our way into
it and yet it uh be
us
the more stable our mind
gets the more unambivalent our love
gets
and when uh that which is not love arises
is don't have to
uh artificially force your way
into ease or forgiveness or Joy or whatever just
uh when the love is kind of sufficiently humming along
stabilized strong container
sort of drop the hate into that uh
love and uh the hate Burns
off
doesn't mean we can't say no or we can't say no to
something but the hate Burns off
may we be free from
suffering
so uh so thank you it's good to uh good to practice with you and uh
yeah thank you to uh yeah to everyone for you all for
sitting and uh practicing and uh yeah Kevin Julie
editing I maybe maybe others too Nancy scheduled
me uh the website Fe all the managing directors the board of directors the the
volunteer coordinate oh my good it keeps going right yeah it's beautiful thank
you so
um if uh if one um were were tasked with creating a uh a a
religion writing writing the holy books right be a very tall order
um you would have to write uh with uh with two considerations in mind how will
you be read but also how you will be misread you'd have to guard against um
misreadings that would legitimize bad
stuff and part of the the the Buddha's genius to my
mind is that his set of teachings provide very few
footholds for fundamentalism very few footholds
for the derangement of overconfidence it's an incredibly
nuanced path where in a way usually torical
force is not privileged over
nuance and so one factor balances other factors and we can't kind of fetishize
any one aspect of the path that's what I've been highlighting
this week just with pairings of teachings that maybe are not even
traditionally paired but on my own path of practice have been important
counterbalancing forces and so with the uh the last
um pairing I'm I'm highlighting uh that uh been circumambulating
often these uh past couple years of compassion
equinity so we talk about uh freedom and happiness and these things but a huge
part of our practice is actually um
experiencing Dua experiencing suffering with Incredible
vividness and part of why we don't squirm is we're developing okayness with imperfection
but part of why we don't squirm is so that we might perceive suffering
vividly and in in a sit for a you know
this morning in a retreat in a sense it's just for pretend
right if we're on Retreat and there's a lot of suffering
or something we could shift postures we could skip the sit we could
leave the retreat but we don't we don't
and we say and this begins to actually etch into our brain just how hard it is
to be human just how intense it is just how intense even a very blessed life
is and we see the movements of our mind the
ways that uh it desperately seeks somewhere
someone to pin the blame on when suffering is intense maybe it's blame on
someone else maybe it's blame on the self but it seeks to like hang the
intensity of that affect somewhere but we
don't all the blaming really just kind of blunts the
insight about the intensity of The Human Condition insight into
Dua which is um a huge huge huge part of the path and has huge liberatory
potential and so what happens uh to our heart when we open in that
way vividly to suffering
undefended well first we we sense how How Deeply we long to be happy
the kind of innocence of that wish and we sense How Deeply that's
shared by others no matter how different their nervous system is from our own it
can't be that different it can't be that
different and so we uh dedicate some portion of our our energy to alleviating
suffering how much is enough don't know doesn't matter that
much we start we
start uh marks said uh from each according to their ability to each
according to their need and we don't need a kind of
Authority or government to make us honor that it's
seea so we look uh to see where we can spend our love
well I'm sort of like a value conscious person you know I am sort of not not
stingy but value conscious you know and it's like and so I look like okay where
can we get a lot of bang for the love Buck basically
you know where can we spend our love
well compassion compassion entails a willingness to uh to
grieve one element of compassion is is grief that's maybe the first movement of
the heart but that's not the last word the last word of
compassion is love uh you recard say like uh in giving
compassion instruction says something like imagine the the suffering of the other basically an incredible vividness
until it's unbearable and then there's this
inflection point when it becomes unbearable to open to that depth of
suffering you pour all of your love into them
and sometimes it feels like if I open to compassion it's going to end in
suffering it's going to end in suffering rather than
love but uh maybe maybe compassion only ends in suffering when it's not
counterbalanced by equinity and so we grow
we grow in our strength uh so that we can love more deeply our love becomes
stronger but um even when our heart is very strong
vast love is at some point becomes
fatiguing the Michelle uh Michelle McDonald talks about
um flowers a lot you know nature generally and flowers a lot and she's
like yeah flowers open but they don't expect to stay open you know sometimes I
found myself prying open Orchid I know that's so bad that's
so not
Buddhist flowers open and then something has to
happen they have to close right but what's the closing of the flower of the heart it's not apathy it's not
hatred it's maybe something like equinity
equinity equinity is uh is about
uh refining refining our relation relationship to
helplessness refining a relationship to
helplessness the the kind of uh helplessness is sort
of in a way kind of foundational experience Primal
experience it's the experience that um that made us
uh howl as children and it's the experience that
still generates tears as adults now and it is that which our entire body
is oriented against H it is um the experience that
is almost unbelievable to the willfulness of the
ego you know nothing to be done no moves to make the ego all out of
moves so do you mean ungovernable for
real yeah and so aging
sickness mortality kind of um
uh narcissistic wound the kind of limits of the ego's
willfulness are highlighted and so part of um purifying
our love is deeply understanding helplessness which may be in the end just a synonym for
Dua and so we ask the question uh can we keep our heart open open
relaxed Exquisite on the other side of our
power can we keep our heart open on the other side of our
power equinity is um is love in the face
of the the endless ungovernable nature of of uh samsara the suffring of this
realm and uh but it's not a closing equinity is is
a it's a very quiet kind of love it's like the arousal system Joy or something
very high state of arousal equinity the arousal is the the the system is kind of
like turned down towards zero but the heart is still wide
open and one of the functions of this quiet
love is that it refines out maybe the
impurities in our compassion the grandiosity or the
compulsivity or this kind of simple intolerance of
suffering that masquerades as compassion but is not
it that's something that I know well you know in the face of loved one suffering
it's a kind of intolerance and an agitated effort
to dispel it right but compassion is a kind of um it may be
urgent but it's patient it is equinity that lets us rest
when there's no action to take it it lets us rest when only rest is
helpful it lets us rest when only rest is
helpful and then compassion is born again then
there's something to do and we do something these cycles of love and rest
love and
rest the rest purifying our love the love justifying the rest
and we keep
going
okay