so hello everyone hello from
Insight Meditation Center in Redwood City
and
it feels kind of homey to be here sitting here
so meditation
there's a lot of different languages and metaphors or ideas that support people in meditation
it's nice to have a range of different options because at different times different
times in a person's life different ways of practicing are relevant
there's a strong tendency here in the West for many meditation teachers to use
languages the language that has to do with being receptive receptivity to experience
and that's maybe because uh being assertive or being actively
going out to to have an experience to look at experience to address something what's
happening sometimes can feel like too much strain and too much work and too much
expectations and agendas involved and the idea of being receptive is to
drop agendas and and not to kind of assert the self but allow just things to
unfold and arise and we can kind of settle back in meditation just let things come and approach us
and um and then there's another uh kind of
approach that's neither kind of going towards or addressing or focusing on
something versus stepping back and letting something come to us
and that is the notion of being open and open is neither assertive nor
receptive neither going out to address to focus on an experience but
also it's not receiving it to be open is like being an Open Door
where people and beings and can just freely
walk back and forth and the door is untroubled by what happens
or like a house with all the windows open and the neighborhood kid who's throwing baseball somehow or others able
to throw a about right through the house from through from one open window in one
open window and out the other the back open window and nothing gets hit
nothing gets struck and so there's neither a stance of
receptivity nor a stance of going out to address something it's just allowing
things to be but being fully open so whatever happens
doesn't it doesn't strike anything it doesn't hit a window doesn't it's not
picked up is not just allowed to be without any reference
to Me Myself and mine without any reference to stories and what it means and what it means for me
and what I have to do and they shouldn't be there or this should be there or
um and there's all these layers and layers of ideas and thoughts and
uh uh Notions of what's right and wrong
that the experience can meet as it appears and that's like the window that's closed
and the ball hits it or but to just be open and open is like an open window and
whatever arises in a sense just passes right through us it doesn't remain it doesn't stay
it's not so we don't have to go out to address anything
and we don't have to be set settled back to receive it to let it come here
we just kind of are upright we are present
we're rooted here there's a kind of a maybe even a dignity and just here
present Unapologetic in a certain kind of way undefended for
this moments of meditation because of the openness that's so wide
that things just pass right through or things don't nothing sticks
nothing gets shattered because of that openness
so to assume a meditation posture and a posture that expresses some
modicum of dignity uprightness
an honorable posture for meditation
an alert posture within which we can relax
without losing that uprightness and gently closing the eyes
and taking a few moments to appreciate
sitting here on this spot this place at this time
they're kind of definitive acknowledgment yes
this is the place where I'm meditating
feeling the weight of the body against your chair or your cushion or
wherever the weight is resting
and then with a kind of definitive acknowledgment here you are here I am
in this body at this time
to take a few long slow deep breaths
feeling the chest expand the rib cage is move stretch
as you inhale the rib cage collapse return
as you exhale
and then letting the breathing return to normal
and as you exhale to relax the muscles of your face
softening around the eyes there's nothing you have to use your
eyes for when you're meditating the eyes can be take a vacation
eyes resting in the eyeballs
some people find it helpful for a few moments to imagine
the eyes are looking backwards and down
as a way of helping the eyes relax
and the exhale relaxing the shoulders
both feeling the softening of the shoulders and or
the gentle weight of the shoulders
who wait that supports this definitive experience of
being here and now
and as you exhale to soften the belly
and then centering yourself on the experience of breathing
being open available
to breathing coming and going breathing in and breathing out
like there's a window open
and the inhales and exhales flow in and out through that open window
feeling the weight of the Torso the solidity of the Torso
that's there together with the movements
of breathing in your body
you might as you exhale relax the tension in the thinking mind
the agitation or the energy in thinking soften
the thinking mind
letting thoughts drift by through an open window
of awareness without being picked up or without
them running into anything no judgments no for against
no concerns about what you're thinking
allowing the thoughts to strift by
maybe like you're sitting on the edge of a river and you
you see how the river flows by
whatever floats in the river is floating by no resistance
in a sense the river is open to let things pass through
allow yourself to be open for breathing
sounds thoughts
to let them Flow by
an unconcerned with what
appears in awareness as if it just is passing by
opening the doors of perception
opening the mind of the heart
no resistance to anything not picking anything up
without being for or against whatever appears allowed to
flow be the river
be the wind that blows through an open window
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to imagine yourself as wide wide open
available to experience the whole world
[Music] 's door just a door
all things occur nothing is met with resistance
or with picking it up needing to do anything or be anyone
each experience a loud to be itself
and so considering the people in your lives
and how letting them be who they are is a form of respect
maybe even a form of love
and your ability to be open to them can be an ability to allow them to be as
they are not need not needing to fix anyone
not needing to get anything from anyone even if it's just for a few moments
a few minutes
of allowing each person to be themselves
because we're simply open not receptive
not addressing the other just allowing all things to be
including yourself
and may it be that such openness
can equally be as much as it's open to let things appear
it's also an openness to allow the warmth the kindness the friendliness
the love in you to flow outward into the world
if we are an Open Door things flow in both directions
May the best that we have available inside of us
be what we offer to the world may we contribute to the happiness and
Welfare of the whole world may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
[Music] thank you
so this is the second talk on the on the topic of Attunement
and in other words for this could be Harmony
or balance and um and uh it's the topic is a relationship
to compassion and our connection to suffering and others and in ourselves
and to simply just experience suffering in the world or in ourselves in the usual habit habitual way of doing it
might not be in harmony might not be attuned well
and it is probably a little bit of a challenge to think about
being attuned to suffering but it's uh having just the right level
of connection just the right way of being present for it that we're not letting it impact us
negatively it doesn't strike the windows in our hearts so that they've shatter
and it doesn't we don't kind of close down or resist what's happening
and so um and finding ourselves attuned and I like the idea of thinking of it kind of
like tuning a guitar string so that the different strings are
attuned to each other somehow they exist in the right relationship to each other
so that uh when we're encountering suffering we can ask ourselves
how do we tune ourselves how do we establish a useful way of being aware
and present and an attitude towards this that's here
and I think it's a nice principle to think that every encounter with suffering is different
and requires a different Attunement what is this and as soon as we start looking and
thinking about Attunement then we're doing something very significant which is we're not just simply a victim of
suffering a passive recipient of it but we're actually have some agency part of us is
not caught in the suffering but is engaged in looking what's the right balance here how to be present
and so um today's concept of Attunement is being
open being open to suffering and in being open then also be open to
compassion as a response but uh to to it involves being mindful
uh and modern monitoring ourselves of what the impact is on us when we're in
the presence of suffering do we close down do we resist
do we attack do we get swept up in our thoughts and
sometimes people get distracted and they go into fantasy they start predicting
the future and and to really understand this is my
common habits of when I'm uncomfortable when things are difficult for me and then
ask ourselves how can it be I I be attuned and that's different than saying how can
it be present for it because sometimes we just present in a way where
The Experience strikes us it hits our wounds it it's our our
resistance it hits our judgmentalism our self-criticism all kinds of things can just being present can be kind of a
little bit and not taking into account what the experience the impact the experience has
on us foreign so we're monitoring ourselves
and saying how you know given who I am what's happening me with the situation how can I be open to this
open does not mean we you approve open does not mean you don't care
but open means that um you're not at first
um uh responding to habitual patterns of
resistance openness kind of means non-resistance
how can I not resist this suffering some of that has comes from the ability
to be uncomfortable there is a discomfort the stronger the the suffering is the more uncomfortable
it is and not a few people think they're responding compassionately to something
but it's really they're trying to uh make their own discomfort go away and
that's not really compassion so to be open to have no resistance to have no need
for oneself to change what's going on just to be open
it does not mean that we end up being passive it means that this is a preparation
for knowing what to do and the doing responding to compassion we wait a while
and that that while might just be a few seconds it might be minutes it might be
longer depending on the context situation we're in if we're reading about suffering in the
news and we're actually not present with someone who is suffering
and we feel kind of alarmed and kind of feel something strong
um the less we're connected to people and more its ideas and stories
the less the more likely we're not open in a clear free way there might be more
stories and opinions and judgments that come into play and but what does it mean to be open
to be open and allow the experience to touch us and move through us every open
to everything how we are as a way of seeing clearly as a way of coming
into some ability to be present without the reactivity that is so common
when we're in the presence of suffering so non-resistance openness
being open to the experience and that's something that uh
maybe it's not easy to understand how to do when the suffering is great but you might look for small areas of
things that are difficult or small sufferings that you're in or some other people are in things that don't require immediate
action and take the time maybe go sit down and meditate or take some time by yourself
or just take the time to seek okay given
this let's not do anything right now let's not come to any conclusions right
now let me just be open to this experience let me be present for it but
open like an open window an Open Door so that uh it it kind of let it as as if
it just flowing right through you as if you know there's no stopping it no
resistance no picking it up nothing to figure out nothing to have to think about in relationship to it just be an
open door to it people might not have to know that you're doing this because maybe other people will be
confused by this attitude that you have but I'd like to propose this is a
phenomenally respectful of others in the suffering in the world
to first and foremost be able to meet it with non-resistance
meet it without a non-picking upness without getting involved just kind of
let it be and make room for it lots of room
and as we learn to do this we learn to expand our capacity for discomfort
expand our capacity to make room for what's there not so that we can just suffer more
but so that we suffer less and are available to see and understand what's
happening in deeper ways I have been in situations that there's
some difficulty challenge going on suffering around me and I've rushed to judgment and
sometimes I've rushed to action only later to discover that what I did was
not what was needed if I'd taken time to be open receptive
present for it not not resisting it not rushing to
action to I would have seen what was needed and I would have known
what to do much better so
as a continuation of yesterday which was when we're in in challenging times in
the presence of suffering and compassion is maybe the healthy
response to the situation First Take times to think about it
think well and part of the thinking is to think how's the proper way to be
attuned to this and might just being open here open and and
non-resisting might that have a role right now
and probably has a role more often than not doesn't mean that every single time you
need to be have non-resistance and be opened but it's part of the skill it's part of
the repertoire of things that we're trying to do as we become attuned
coming into a certain kind of harmony with the suffering of the world so that we're in a good position to
respond compassionately this is a stepping stone to compassionate action not a rush to
compassionate action so um I'd encourage you today
to maybe it's a very private practice no one needs to know you're doing it
but look for occasions where you can be present for something
that's suffering something that's challenging for people some way in which people are having difficulty
and see if you can kind of take a few moments a few minutes to just kind of
not resist it it's almost like you open your heart wide open spread your arms
wide open and say here this can just come right through me
isn't it very different than saying here this can land here and I can hold it
for this exercise oh here and it goes this can just go right through
and uh and in that going through uh maybe you'll come to a wiser better
position to understand what yourself and what's happening
so thank you and as we go through these the acronym touch
for how to live in a tuned life so thank you