so warm greetings from Insight Meditation Center in Redwood
City and um I'm very grateful for Matthew who
came and filled in for me yesterday and I was under the weather a a little bit I had a little bit of fever on Wednesday
evening and little bit upset stomach I woke up in the morning and fever was gone and very quickly in the course of
the morning I after sleeping 12 hours I started feeling pretty
good so I think it's pasted and I'm happy to be here with you
all
um
so when things are when we're treated in an impersonal way
with then it can be kind of cold and we can take it personally and feel like it's offensive almost like somehow we've
been ignored or overlooked or not respected sometimes when things
are personal we get offended easily and we're holding on to some
idea or we're threatened easily some times when things are
personal it feels really Co cozy and comfortable and safe and then there's a third step which
there's no English word that I know of maybe make up a word something like underp personal or prepersonal or postp
personal and that's when things have become so personal so centered so
connected here that we stop thinking about ourselves we stop
assigning person to anything person personalness to
anything and things are just can be as they are in the coziness in the comfort and
the safety the of the present moment and in fact to really be in this underp
personal way is um it can feel that
taking things personally assigning personal value on the and what it means for me myself and I can feel like using
Co coarse sandpaper on very smooth wood it feels like it's a little bit too
much and what's nice is just to appreciate the Comfort the ease the
subtleness of our experience without the overlay of whatever it means to be to
assume or feel that it's personal this extra evaluation that sometimes is quite
wonderful wonderful so as meditation
deepens we start getting a feeling for how to meditate without taking it
personally it doesn't mean that it becomes impersonal in some cold kind of way it be it means that we go deeper
than what's personal the underp personal and um and we can just be
present uh in the Simplicity of the moment content
um and if we're not content then probably there's something
that we're taking personally something we're concerned with For Me Myself and mine some something that uh bothers us
something that we want something we don't want and so we're get using the cors or
sandpaper but if we quiet down then
um and let go of this content of all forms and just content to be here
there's this underp personal state where things just be in meditation
in a very very simple way that's very satisfying
so uh assuming a meditation posture and it's useful to take one that
personally for you supports your meditation
each person's going to have a different posture that's the right posture for them to meditate
in sometimes the variations are very small
and to gently close your
eyes and to feel at first how personal it is with the eyes closed to feel
yourself feel the sensations of the body to feel and recognize the thoughts
you're having
to feel what's happening in your heart the emotions that are
present and rather than judging them or reacting to
them feel how with the eyes closed how close they are to
you they are not someone else's in Sensations and feelings they're yours they're quite personal
and others might have similar feelings but yours are your
own and then to take a few long slow deep
breaths breathing in and inhabiting this person experience of
yourself Here and
Now exhaling and relaxing it relaxing everything in your
body exhaling and
releasing for
breathing in and breathing out letting breathing return to
normal you might say that breathing is personal you might say that it's
something different than personal it's shared by all mammals
all humans are doing the same movements it's something
Universal to breathe in breathe
out and as you're sitting here become aware of the temperature of your
body places where your body feels warm places where it feels
cool places in
between and feel feel the temperature of your body as something that's deeper
than personal it's nature the natural
movements of how the Body Works in the presence of certain
conditions the warmth the coolness the play of warmth and coolness
in the body and how breathing interacts with it
maybe in some more foundational way below the temperature there's the
solidity of the body the hardness the firmness against
your seat or the
floor the weight of your
body e
and out of that firmness and groundedness there's also movement in the body
the movement of the associated with
breathing small little movements of the body
and in Buddhist Meditation practice being aware of these properties
of temperature and solidity movement are three of the four
properties that to tune
into that are prepersonal under
personal it's a way of having our experiences without the
overlay of attributing a self or me myself to
it so intimate so cozy and content
to stay close to the these basic prop
Sensations properties that are at play in the
body sitting here
movement temperature softness and hardness
solidity the water element property is
cohesion anything that feels like it's stretching or being held together is considered to
be the property of stickiness or lubrication
stay close to these fundamental
Sensations as a way of being underp personal less personal than
personal or if you can't do that having a heightened
awareness of how you do overlay the per an idea of the personal
on top of your
experience
e
for
for for
gently taking de breath or two two deeper and on the exhale settling
in letting go letting go of the impersonal and the
personal to just being here in the body in the sensations of the
body so intimate with the body
that there's no room for judgments or ideas or attribute
attributing them to anything they're underp
personal just here the natural self the natural world
nature
for e
and as we come to the end of this sitting what if
love good will
is something deeper than personal something that resides within
us in a natural way that we don't have to
personally evaluate or it's not a personal reason to
love to be kind mind it's just the nature of the heart
nature of our inner tenderness kindness is deeper than
personal underp personal maybe kindness this kind of
kindness doesn't need a reason loving without a
reason loving without needing anything in
return loving without fear without
resistance the heart's good will may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello so in the Buddha's teachings on the the four foundations of mindfulness
on the section of mindfulness of the body he has an exercise on what's
generally called the four elements and the four elements are
usually uh called uh earth water fire and
air and one of the reason in this exercise is to become aware of our sensations of our body in
their Elemental uh properties Elemental
manifestations and one of the classic reasons for this meditation is to uh be able to
experience our our um our present moment experience
without the filter of self-identification without all that
comes along with taking it personally and making it mine or it's happening to me or this is my
experience and um to be able to kind of uh experience it directly without any
overlay of self to do so impersonally in a sense not not but impersonally sounds
cold so I kind of made up the term uh prepersonal or underp personal something
that's so intimate that uh it's so close in it's so intimate so settled here so
connected here that it we stay so at the the foundational level before the mind
starts uh bringing in ideas of Me Myself and
mine so um one of the so this exercise in the four in the four elements is
meant to be a element to freeze us from self self concerns
preoccupation now the elements um earth water air and Fire I don't know if it's
appropriate to call it elements because the elements kind of like it's the elemental table it kind of implies Some
solid like atoms some things molecules that's some fundamental things that uh
exist and um but rather that uh probably
the better translation of datu the the PO word is
properties and um because there's many things that are datus which are clearly not Elemental in terms of things they're
Elemental in terms of being fundamental like the building blocks of something but they're not things they're processes
they're activities they're uh things that are appearing and
disappearing and so uh so these have to do with our Sensations so it's not our
thoughts it's not our feelings about it but rather the sensations that might be
there uh providing information that helps us understand oh this is an emotion the sensations that tell us the
impact that thinking might have so the sensations to stay
there in the in the realm of Sensations the idea of the four
properties earth water fire and air is to give us a little bit of an
orientation of how to stay close in to these these different things so they uh
the Earth element is solidity hardness softness
firmness um uh maybe tightness sometimes so anything that kind of feels solid uh
or the opposite to kind of soft that range is considered the Earth element uh
uh granite rock is really hard soft soil the Earth is quite soft you put your
hand in it water uh the Water element is one of
the harder ones to experience but the way that the tradition holds it up is
that uh it's fluidity and with the kind of fluid fluidity where the the fluid
kind of holds together that's what fluid is it's kind of water has a very little of uh force that keeps the molecules
connected to each other um the spit in your mouth has more stickiness to it to
itself and um and you know so so things that hold things together keep things
kind of coales um so um it's a little bit hard
to feel and experience but maybe you get the idea and then um there's uh fire which
is a temperature hot and cold and um and
then then then uh there's the air element the literal word in poly is not
air we say air but it's wind and then it's easier to understand that
the elemental is level here is has to do with movement so any Movement we have in
the body um as we're sitting still for example and there's some kind of movement that's the the wind element
moving through us and um the
um so the um and it can be a delight to be able to
put to rest our self- preoccupations put to rest all these kinds of concerns about me myself and
mine and become so deeply personal with
our experience that the the idea of Personality personalist personalness Falls away and um so I tried the underp
personal pre-personal I see in the chat someone suggesting subpersonal maybe Underneath It All um
and um but this is where the the idea of it's so personal the idea of personal
personal uh Falls away it's kind of like some people may maybe have the experience of being in your home or in
your bedroom no one's around and maybe in your pajamas and you're cozy with a
cup of tea and there's no self-c concern about me myself and
mine and you know thinking about yourself you're just kind of cozy and settled and there's no other person to
bounce off of to compare ourselves to or be in interaction with and where you feel like it's just okay to be
ourselves so in meditation it can be this way where it's so okay to be ourselves that this is the maybe the one
place where we can drop the social world we can drop um the responsibilities we
have to do temporarily uh so that we can get
underneath to a deeper level of um of well-being of safety of of
comfort um where where we can be just be absorbed in the Simplicity of the moment
in the sensations of the experience There's No Agenda not trying
we're doing it for a purpose not trying to get concentrated or something but just kind of uh floating in the
sensations they come and go kind of diving into them sinking into
them and to have a a fairly good experience of this becomes a
wonderful uh um personal experience of an alternative to all the Me Myself and
mind mining that we go through the day with it can be exhausting how much uh
our self-c concern is part and parcel of so many of things we're doing all day long our preferences what we're trying
to avoid what we want what we don't want how we feel about things our opinions my
opinions um how we we are in relationship to other people it's uh
many people can get exhausted from all the ways in which we're navigating ourselves in relationship to
other people and with challenges that we have in our lives uh challenges tend to
evoke a strong sense of self because the challenges often has some personal quality I have to figure out I have to
it's happening to me or I'm responsible I have to figure some out and so this
emphasis on ourselves as the agent or as the victim or as something kind of
elicits more self some of that's okay but it's really nice to know an
alternative it's really nice to know that there's another way where we don't
take things personally but it doesn't feel cold we just are present for things
without measuring it against our idea of self or measuring Against Me Myself and
mine and what it means for me to to do this Four Element meditation
drop down into the Sensation that this deeper than personal is um gives us a feeling for
going about the challenges of our life without taking them so personally maybe they involve something
that has to be done but then we do it without the way of why me I shouldn't have to do it or
this is too difficult for me it there's a simpler way of engaging where the Me
Myself and mine doesn't interfere it might be there in the
background guiding a little bit but it doesn't interfere so some people uh find the
Four Element meditation very meaningful and in fact uh for this
insight meditation practice that I I learned in Asia um uh it kind of with
the heart of it was uh the Four Element meditation in that the heart of it was
to really drop down into the sensations of the experience not the thoughts of
the experience the stories about the experience not the idea we take how we take it personally the experience but
actually dropping down and really staying intimately present for the sensations and this gets really helpful
like within emotion uh what are the sensations of the emotion and to course and travel and
feel the sensations of the emotion what are the sensations connected to thinking
what are the sensations involved in activity and movement that we're doing and to spend some quality time in
this subpersonal realm of just the sensation patience is quite
freeing and the freedom of self that it provides then becomes a reference point
to much better understand how much extra self we bring along as we go about our
life including with our challenges so
um so you might if you feel
inclined uh see if you could find a way to settle in and some nice way at home
or somewhere for a few minutes here and there to see if you can be so at
ease that you stop taking anything personally it's just nature operating
through you just nature operating in this body that's here and in not taking it personally not
being aloof for cold but rather diving in to the
sensations diving into the the basic fundamental building blocks of
Sensations from which we build our interpretation of life and
um and see what that see if that teaches you something about a a less
self-concerned way of being in the world it's invaluable to do when we have
challenges because the challenges that um that we have
that um get mixed up with self
preoccupation those challenges become much more difficult but the less self there can be
self um the agitation of self uh the easier it is to take care of challenges
in a responsible way so thank
you um so the end of the week this Sunday at
IMC we're going to have a um community meeting I think the first in-person
community meeting since the pandemic I know many of you are far away but some of you are close by and uh we're having
it at about 11:00 which is um um you know after the
the usual Sunday morning program and there's no need to register to come to community meeting you can just come to
it you do need to register to come to the the Dharma talk um and uh so um and
uh we'll talk about IMC we'll talk about the pandemic we'll talk about uh our
covid protocol and maybe changing it talk a little bit about the vision of IMC and how we're going to go forward
from here and hear from you a little bit about what do you think um your ideas of
IMC and how we'd go go on from here and then in
um in about a month we'll do a similar kind of community meeting for the online
community and we'll do it on zoom and there'll be information more about that later mid April
sometime so thank you and um and look forward to
being here with you on Monday