so good uh good day everyone warm greetings
and to come and sit in meditation
for me is often a very what kind of a homecoming
but it's also kind of uh
um I don't know if sobering is the right word but it's a time to
settle down in a meaningful way into the fullness of life in all the
different aspects and since this week we're talking about challenges
even when I've had a major [Music] challenges with tragedies and things
I've always felt that coming to meditation was not an avoidance of
but all but there was a rightness
there was a satisfaction in sitting present for it all
that borders on being Pleasant but to say it's Pleasant seems to be too
much given the enormity of what's Happening so I say that it feels like a rightness
to it all it's right to sit in the middle of it it's right to
be with what's happening it's right to be
non-defensive non-resistant non-critical
non externalizing it's right to be here for these minutes
in the middle of it all breathing present
and even though it might seem disrespectful to the challenge we have
that sense of rightness can be a partner or be a sibling
or be the same as a certain kind of pleasure a certain kind of pleasantness
a certain kind of pleasant that it comes from breathing easy
a pleasantness or that comes from an awareness
of it all that is tender and gentle kind
supportive compassionate
or is non-again non-resistant non-critical non
not caught up in thoughts and ideas so sometimes in Buddhism we call this
wholesome wholesome attention a wholesome attention to what is
difficult where you know all the
the cracks of our preoccupations and thoughts
maybe we begin getting a glimpse of this feeling of rightness and
even a maybe we call it bordering unpleasant Pleasant attention
and when there are no challenges it's a time to train and develop our
capacity to take in
Pleasant big part of this practice is to show up
for what is happening but we often have a selectivity
bias sometimes to the negative
and there's an art to this practice of being present for what is
that takes into account what is Pleasant takes it into account enough that it has
a influence on us that it kind of settles us helps the
Mind want to be in the present moment so to
enter into your meditation posture
and adjusting your posture looking for a posture that has some modicum
of rightness feeling right
feeling right for the purpose of being attentive not right for the purpose of being
relaxed though that's nice
but for the emphasis is on alertness
gently closing the eyes
and taking some long slow deep breaths in a way that's right for you
feels like a good way of connecting to yourself to
your body how deep that is is up to you
and relaxing on the exhale
letting the breathing return to normal and scan through the body and see where
on the exhale you can soften and relax the body
and as you do so to feel whatever pleasantness or relief
that comes from that relaxation
and then to calmly
settle into the body breathing
where awareness has a light enough touch with breathing most likely
the physical sensations of breathing
or the place where awareness touches the body
where the touch is light soft
where awareness yields to the sensations of breathing
the movements in the body of the breathing
and is there anything Pleasant in the cycle of breathing the in-breath
or the out breath anything that feels Pleasant or
satisfying or or simply has a rightness goodness
in attending to it
without denying any unpleasant or
painful experiences in the moment
as you're aware of your breathing also be aware of what is Pleasant
and can you relax the mind that's mindful
so that awareness mindfulness of breathing itself has some pleasure in it some rightness
the awareness of breathing is open allowing receptive
kind gentle
or there's a certain Joy or Delight in the application of attention
that maybe is similar to Joy or Delight I'll be playing a musical instrument or
doing a craft
being involved with breathing with interest and giving ourselves over to it
where wherever whatever is unpleasant now
is included on this in the side with at the center
taking in whatever is Pleasant in the moment
without holding on to it or insisting on it just gently hear
when we tighten up around something resist
something when we become antagonistic towards
something afraid all those movements of mind
are unpleasant and that other unpleasantness
has an influence on us as in if if those things are happening
recognize it but don't linger there
look for what is Pleasant see if you can adjust and find a
pleasant way or to be aware to be present
let yourself be influenced conditioned
by what is Pleasant no matter how small it might be
so that you're less likely to be adding the unpleasantness of reactivity
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
is there a way that you can now bring to mind
people of your life known and unknown strangers and
known people friends and neighbors colleagues
bring them to mind or gaze out upon them in a way that feels has some
pleasure in it some positive feeling of
pleasantness to relax settle back
to calmly gaze upon the world where the gazing
has a kind of pleasantness in it or goodness in it
that you wish for all people to have
May everyone have the ability to
be aware pleasantly calmly
where they enjoy attending to others
where there's our rightness no there's no stress
where there's no resistance or worry mixed up with
the awareness of others
The Gaze upon the world kindly
into wish others to have
also to have well-being
to be able to come from a place of their goodness
their kindness their care
may all beings
know their own goodness may all beings
no how to tap into
the pleasure of awareness
the freedom of non-clinging
the warmth of generosity
the safety of non-harming
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
so to continue the topic of the Dharma of challenges
we will be challenged in this life that's uh that's a certainty
and how do we meet it how does the Dharma help us with it and so building on last week The Fourth
Kind of meaning of Dharma is Dharma as teachings and so for Buddhists the teachings of the Buddha
and so how can they be a resource a support for us and our challenges
one of them is to orient us in a Direction that's effective and
meaningful and to kind of take in the teachings of the Buddha maybe in their fullness
and to see sometimes you have to it's not necessarily what's predominantly taught
but the the overall
kind of uh foundation for what's being taught there
and so there's a two things that uh stand out to me that when I read the
sutas points to a very important Direction in which to help us in times of challenges or this
challenging life one is I'll start with a metaphor
because then maybe what I'll say will kind of
be more understandable less protests
and that is that if a person is an athlete
and say they're going to do a very important they're going to run a race
and it's important to raise them and for them
and they need to be kind of at their very top physical ability to do this
so in the hour before the race that person is going to take
responsibility for how best to be ready for the race
and they're going to be very focused on that and very intentional and so if they need to do something
they'll make sure that that can be done some of that is warming up some of them
might be doing gentle runs doing they're doing the very thing that they're going to be doing at the race but doing it
kind of slowly warming up a little bit faster and faster getting the body kind of limber and ready for it and the
system going and uh but they're taking responsibility they're not asking their trainer to run
for them um if they need to kind of set their mind in a certain State they might
meditate or do something maybe they even take a nap or maybe they just you know
do something like I don't know uh that clearly it takes them their mind off the race
so that they're much more can relax more deeply and not be kind of caught in some
tension around it and so they're very intentional and they're taking responsibility for doing
the thing that will take their mind off the race so the the athlete is taking is really
taking responsibility more than maybe anybody else they're not kind of looking at the weather every
every five minutes uh you know uh you know thinking about whether the weather's not particularly good and
maybe it'll get better and and they're just you know or they're not kind of going around complaining that the track
is not as even as they wish it could be and they're going around kind of to everyone say look this is not right then
no one can do anything in such a late time but you know if it's important to go and complain
they don't do that they take responsibility for how they're going to show up getting themselves ready
so what we find in the teachings of the Buddha is that the orientation that he
has can be a little bit like getting ready for life
and uh and taking responsibility for ourselves to get ourselves in the right
frame of mind the right capacity the right skills the right strengths so that
we can engage in life fully and it's uh and so there's a distinction
here that I think is useful the distinction of seeing the Dharma Dharma
practice as that part of uh life where we're
kind of preparing ourselves for life we're loosening ourselves up freeing ourselves up getting limbered up getting
ready getting wise understanding ourselves in a way that only we can take responsibility for
when we're in the middle of a challenge then the challenge has its own
uh dynamics that we have to take care of and do and address but in terms of the Dharma of the
challenge a big part of that is taking responsibility for our end of it how are
we participating and so um you know so like I can imagine that if a
racer is racing along and um and some fellow Racers next to next
next running next to him and says something really mean just to kind of trip up you
uh during their race um you don't kind of letting go argue
with the person and tell them that let's let's have a meeting and talk about this and work it out if you're in the race
you just kind of take responsibility for yourself in order to kind of kind of manage with your feelings so you can do
the race when we're in the world of challenges with our people and arguments and
difficulties we take care of the difficulty in an appropriate way and sometimes we do have the conversation
with people do say tell things to people but that what's important to remember is that
Dharma is always kind of taking responsibility for how we are
to see what we're contributing to the challenge to see how we're contributing to our own suffering and distress around
this even though the other person has caused a lot of distress the Dharma is
found by really centering here and finding out what are we doing and finding the freedom here
so that when we are in the race of life if we are in the middle of the challenges of life and what's going on
we're in a good place to be able to do that effectively and honestly and
clearly and and do what needs to be done in it not to avoid anything but to really be
able to come from this place of freedom and generosity and kindness and non-stress
so you find this tremendous emphasis on it's kind of a very strong individualistic teaching
that the Buddha gave this kind of really take responsibility for yourself
so that you can care for others it's not an individual it's the culture is very collectivist and connected to people and
what's going on but there's something we have to do here that's what the Dharma practice is found
it's a big degree we do it together with other people we're supported by each other we're
married each other and but this kind of emphasis on what are we doing here
what's our contribution and then when we do that another part of the teaching which uh is a phenomenal
and I think in the modern world we're learning how important it is for many circumstances
and that is um the willingness to feel pleasure
uh the Buddha's teachings is very very focused now we're both taking responsibility for what's happening but
also understanding that what we do conditions us
what we do uh creates a habit what we do creates an environment that then
conditions conditions us and if we do things which are unhealthy that kind of creates an unhealthy
conditioning within us and we're more likely to kind of feel often when we feel off we're more likely
to do unhealthy things and so in taking responsibility for
ourselves the idea is to find what conditions us positively do that do the things that create a good
environment for ourselves so that that influences us and it's not being Pollyanna it's just
not be coding over and pretending that there isn't difficulties in suffering the Dharma practice is the opposite of
that it's really being honest for what's happening and showing up but in doing so
how do we be present for this all this so that the way we're attending the way
we're being with our experience and ourselves is has a positive influence on
us is a positive conditioning so if we show up with stress if we show
up resistance and anger if we show up with um with um
with you know Greed for something that's going to condition Us in ways which are not really helpful and long
term we have to kind of condition but if we show up to difficulties with and
sometimes rather than showing up with positive States the best we can do is
show up with the absence of the negative ones we show up without giving in to anger we might be angry we won't give
into it we don't complain we might be greedy we don't give into it so it
doesn't it's the giving into and the participating that uh is what where the conditioning
is so um so a big part of mindfulness practice
is to be mindful for what's happening but we can carry along with us that
awareness that mindfulness of the present moment we can carry it baggage with us where there's as little
complaining a little fear a little stress or big going on or little kind of
sense of Duty and pushing and trying hard or expectation or wanting it to be
different all kinds of conditioning things we do that are reinforcing
something which is not so pleasant for us not not beneficial for us doesn't prepare us for the race
but can we learn how to be mindful even of great difficulties so that how we're
mindful is satisfying how mindful has a positive
influence on us even if all that is and it's not not a minor thing is we can
be aware of what's happening with clarity we're clear and open
and available for what's there and we can't some summon up kindness we can't sum it up
compassion we can't sum it up uh generosity or but it does feel good to
just kind of step forward openly and be aware oh yes
that's a good conditioning so it can seem like a big burden
to be involved in a practice that we have to take responsibility for
ourselves in it and that it's a central feature and it can seem like somehow
not a realistic spirituality to start
being conditioned by what's Pleasant the enjoyable
but it turns out that that
is a path away of preparing ourselves for being in this
world in a very realistic way and a beneficial way in a full way
that we are not prepared preparing ourselves if we show up with complaining
and anger and fear and distress and kind of clamping down giving up
there's all these things the Mind does that we give into or allow for
and it's a phenomenal thing to be beginning to reclaim
a certain kind of personal power certain kind of personal strength
where we don't succumb we don't collapse and we don't give in to things which are unhealthy for us and
unhealthy for the world and out of that grows the Lotus and Muddy Waters
if the all the complicated difficulty of our life the ways in which we're caught
up in in attachments and clinging and and unhealthy Behavior
rather than seeing it as being unfortunate it's the compost
from which can grow the lotus and um and ha and and I mean it becomes
compost if we don't participate in it if we don't grow it
but allow it to kind of settle back into the soil and Decay and and support the
growth of something quite beautiful so that's uh
uh you know the Dharma is also teachings and this is I think some of the central
teachings that from the Buddha that I think can challenge us can enliven us
can give us a directionality for being with challenges that begins this process
of showing up for challenges with a certain kind of personal strength
personal agency that um that uh
is so important and challenges is when we don't have agencies when we feel helpless and hopeless
it really has a powerfully negative conditioning for us and the Dharma says you're never
helpless because you can always show up and bring practice to it
even if you can't change what's going on even if you do all the preparations in
the world and you're at your Peak shape for the race you might still lose the race
but boy was it good to show up and be present to do the race in the best state
that we can be in maybe that was the winning not the literal winning of the
race so thank you and um May you look at
today as you go through the day look and see about how the state of your
mind how the state of your reactivity to what's going on in the world how you participate in anything you're
doing how you might be conditioning
yourself it has a what influence does it have on your state of being your state of mind
just study that and maybe to really get into that study I have some
conversations with people about how this works for you so thank you and um we'll go back have
another challenge tomorrow