you in San Diego hello
Hugh Peggy in Redwood City hi hi hi
Peggy in Montreal I heard both Jerry and Gabriel
yes right that's right both both both Canadians speaking at the same
time truly United
whether in Montreal or Toronto yes truly United the two of you that's that's
sweet um let's see now we're on YouTube and Karina says hi from Meno Park and
marann from Berling gameing Carrie says hello on YouTube hi great anybody else
before we begin it's Richard from Boston hi Richard welcome so all right let's let's
begin so I ask you to mute yourself if you aren't muted already and thank you
Neil for posting information about Happ Google Groups and uh if you're new you
can join the low traffic group that we have um where information and references
are shared and we also have a little um uh guide for supporting each other and
yourself during the um uh the uh breakout rooms so with that
I'm going to change the settings on so that unmuting won't be possible the
space stays quiet and changing chat settings and last but not least of the
Preparatory things I do is to turn on recording for the sake of Audio Dharma here we go
great okay so hello hello and welcome everyone
to happy hour so for today's practice given that it is
um in the US at least it's one day after
the Thanksgiving holiday which was yesterday here and uh on Wednesday we
did gratitude practice and and um I have a memory of of of uh the reports that
came back some reports that many felt better turning their minds and hearts to
gratitude after the practice we did so let's let's do some more of that let's
do more gratitude practice and again in holding it lightly uh there's no should you should
if the voice comes that you should be grateful for this just drop it let it be
a gentle leaning into um sense of appreciation for what arises or or not
maybe you just sit in sense of silence and appreciation for the breath
so so let's begin let's begin our practice together let's begin so let us
arrive together arriving in this body in this
moment however it's showing up whatever it's showing
up and letting our body relax into the
posture
letting our body relax into of the chair the [Music]
cushion and let us connect with the sensations of the breath the
body the breath being breathed within the body
calming soothing
stabilizing connecting with this breath this in breath breath this out
breath not the last one not the next
one taking taking a few minutes on our own to just settle
arrive take refuge inside [Music] Ence as much as it's available taking
refuge in Simplicity just being here sitting and being
breathed just this in breath just this out
breath
let the breath feel like a laabi calming and soothing the
heart it's okay sweetheart it's okay whatever is happening it's okay
it's like this right
now
nothing has to be different In This
Moment embrace ing bracing the body the heart the mind
just as they are with each
breath
e
and as if you were take a little
dropper dropper and dropper that had a drop of
color you Dro that drop of color in the glass and the
color dissipate kind of color the glass the water the Clear Water a
bit drop in a drop of
a reflection of something that brought you Joy today something that was maybe a moment
of connection with yourself or with someone else with something that you
[Music]
enjoy brought a moment of warms
appreciation ever so slightly lit up your
day don't have to be big look for the small me the usually
what we consider to be insignificant but tune into it
maybe somebody's kindness maybe a
smile and bring it this drop of color
into the body drop it in the body not so much in your head not thinking about it
but feel feeling feeling the feelings in your
belly in your limbs with your
breath
and letting this go coming letting the awareness come back to the silence
to the breath the body the Simplicity of it
all and appreciating the Simplicity of just being
breathed here the Gathering community
and now if feel like bringing in another drop of something else
today you have appreciation for that brought some
Delight is appreciation that is happened today in your life it was
available either today or yesterday it's
okay and relaxing your body not so much
thinking about it but relaxing the body letting the
heart open up to its own appreciation there's no there's no should here and if
nothing comes up it's okay can there be appreci appreciation
of just sitting here in silence in community and practicing
together
turning towards the good in our
lives
intentionally
letting there be an invitation for gentle appreciation for whatever might
have showed up in your day today
yesterday glad in your heart and maybe a smile shows up on your
face a little bit of brightness in the heart
space
letting yourself truly Savor whatever might be coming up and if
not it's okay too nothing your Rises savoring the
silence or savoring any gifts any
goodness turning to them
intentionally things we often take for
granted
as we
turn slowly
turn bring this sit to a close
together and we open up to appreciation for what's here right
now
perhaps a comfortable chair or a
cushion the food that has nourished you and maybe has been prepared for care
with
care the roof over your head safe from the
elements connections you have in your life with other beings with other humans
animals connection you have with yourself capacities you
have so many of
them
and appreciating yourself for having showed up the
practice trusting you've planted you've planted
seeds of goodness may your practice together be a
cause and condition for goodness in our own
lives for our own happiness well-being as well as all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may
all beings be [Music]
free thanks everyone thanks for your
practice
so a little gratitude practice little different from the one we did on
Wednesday slightly different tone flavor but but also similar so I'd like to
invite us now um the way we engaged in the small groups
On th on Wednesday together was to go around and each person would would share
one thing that has brought them Joy or they're grateful for and and that's such
an uplifting practice we can't have enough of that I think if I remember yes
um um Neil afterwards said we should do this every single time so so we're doing
it a second time so it's such an uplifting practice just to both to um
share to really reflect in the presence of others what has brought us joy what
has brought us gladness and and what we're grateful for either or and also to
to hold witness to what brings joy to others it lifts uplifts the heart it
uplifts the heart it brings so much joy so so let's go a reverse alphabetical
order groups of three I'll create and and again you're welcome to say pass you
can definitely welcome to say pass and please know that this is a mudita practice vicarious Joy practice as well
as gratitude practice and it uplifts the heart it uplifts the heart uh especially
if you have had a challenging time this definitely updates uplifts the heart so
so I will create the breakout rooms here
and invite you to um yeah take care of yourselves take
care of each other and yeah be kind be kind here we
go
I
okay hello everyone welcome back hi the rooms are closed and we have
a few minutes for any reflection you might have you can put them in chat if
you wish or um or you can raise your hand to share your
Reflections so
yeah
Reflections hello Ali I see your hand hello Nikki
than glad to see you and and everybody else
uh actually a lot of nature came in when we were like grateful about Joys that we
had and then this group and then uh at the end it kind of like naturally arose
for me with a couple other guys that I was in the group that I I I wish them that uh maybe all be on the Lighter Side
of Life whatever that it just like naturally came to me and it's I think
it's uh because of come and doing I mean partly the happy hour and thanks to you
and all the s i just naturally came out I never said that sentence before wish
the folks happier to be on the Lighter Side of Life there it is beautiful thanks so
much Ellie that's so beautiful this this natural wish what I'm hearing you say is this natural wish that just naturally
arose from from you having practiced and inclined your heart towards goodness
this natural wish for well-being and happiness of others everyone just such a
beautiful way to go through life wishing others well what a gift thank you Nikki
thank you thank you so much that's just so beautiful thank you thanks for sharing that ah that lifts my heart
Abraham please
hi Nikki hi folks um I just liked to the
reminder during the meditation I remarked upon in the group of you know it doesn't have to be this huge
incredible wonderful thing just to be tuned into the nice little things that
happen during the day that make the day special make it good was was so nice
because there's so many of them if you really are listening so so that's it beautiful
thank you for highlighting that Abraham exactly there's so many and yeah if we tune into them yeah
there's more good than Challenge and of course our minds tune into the challenge and take the good for granted that's
just the way we operate as human beings it's all of us it's all of us so it's
nice to turn towards the good this this silent This Whispering of goodness this
Whisper of goodness that's throughout yeah Jim I see your hand
going ask you to unmute and if it's possible to turn on your camera to see you you won't be on YouTube but it would
be nice to see you as you ask a question or
reflect yeah so uh so I'm in Old Vietnam B and um I really L the
meditation I re I really didn't share on gratitude I shared on my experience of
the relationship between uh attachment and safety because it's something I work
with in embodied healing for myself for my PTSD and what I came to understand was
the role attachment played and I also was lucky enough to find a medical doctor who flunked out of
school in her last year healed herself with embodied healing rather than the
medical mind mod and explained to us how important it
was to feel safety I think we're safe because my
door is locked or I have food in the fridge and I've been working on that
process and I reflected when you started going down that road not enough Dharma
teachers talk about this aspect of it because it really is a bridge between
Dharma and embodied healing yeah yeah to share thank you
yeah thank you so much for sharing um so important so significant the the somatic
the somatically feeling safe somatic really letting the practice be somatic not just um in our heads or thinking but
but embodied really embodied somatic and
um yeah it's so and and I'm so happy to hear that you have found ways to really
connect with that in your own practice because that is Paramount for every single person and in fact um you know
the Buddha uh put that first put mindfulness of the body first in the
four Sati panas and the four foundations of mindfulness the body is first it's
always first it has to be embodied um and and yeah and and um and many
Dharma teachers do try to bring it in um I hope I trust and I think nowadays even
more so with our understanding of how trauma lives in the body and how really the embodied sense of safety is
important and it cannot be emphasized enough Jim I know that when I really got
it in my practice years and years ago the embod my practice just shifted and deepened in
so many ways so thank you for bringing bringing it in yeah so important thank
you thank you thank you thank [Music]
you so so dear ones we have come to the
end of happy hour today and and one of you wrote to me happy hour gratitude
hour yes happy hour gratitude hour today and it's been sweet to practice with you
yeah I feel I feel happier and more uplifted for having um yeah practice
together I'm smiling more so that's that's always good so thank you all for
your practice for bringing yourself wholeheartedly um to to this cultivation for the sake
of both ourselves and all beings everywhere may all beings be well may
all beings be [Music]
thanks everyone I'll stop the recording