all right okay is this on yeah our teacher will be a little late
this evening she got caught in traffic so
far isn't that like some kind of Grimm's Fairy Tale or something
oh I see okay here's Diana
thank you Jim and many of you know we'll do a 45
minute sit now so um Jim will ring the bell that uh 8 15 and then I'll give a
short talk thank you
good evening and welcome welcome everybody
so tonight I'd like to talk a little bit about meta this practice of loving
kindness some of you know that I'll be teaching a retreat on loving kindness and so this
is a little warm-up for me I kind of like a dig into the topic and
and so I'm sure many of you know that meta gets translated in a number of
different ways classically or maybe commonly I should
say it's loving kindness but also we could use this idea of Goodwill
some people use friendliness some people use effort care Oh
warm-heartedness all kinds of different ways that we might understand
but uh but one thing that maybe distinguishes
meta from these other words like in in English this just love or good will
is that it has a quality or it's characterized by freedom
so it's this good will that has this quality of Freedom associated with it
there's a number of ways in which we might understand that you can't hear it so I think the volume needs to be a
little bit higher
there we go it's I don't know is this louder Maybe not maybe I'll just keep on
talking until the thing so there we go there we go that's you can hear now right yeah
so this Goodwill this uh sometimes this word love
sometimes that's not so easy or appropriate to use the word love because wow love sometimes has this a lot of
baggage associated with it but we might just
um also Define it as this heartfelt concern for the welfare of others for
the welfare of ourselves for the welfare of everybody so this heartfeltness this uh
yeah I like this word maybe concern for the welfare or care or something like this
and there's a way in which it's practiced probably many of you know this is a formal practice I'll talk just a
little bit about that but it's practiced in such a manner as to develop this care this
warm-heartedness meta so that it expands into maybe even
boundlessness or that it expands to unconditional
so this is what I mean by it's characterized by freedom is that it doesn't have limits
and it doesn't have conditions and I'll talk a little bit more about that but what does it mean to not have
limits or what does it mean to not have conditions
and so I appreciate very much that in this tradition there's this
teaching and this experience of we don't have to leave this feeling of warmth
this feeling of care to chance we don't have to wait until just all the right
conditions show up that the perfect person who deserves it has treated us
just the way we want or has done whatever we want and then we'll have this loving kindness no we can cultivate
this and develop it for everybody and of course that's a practice because
that's not the usual way that we move through the world or that we consider others or maybe even the way that we
consider ourselves so it's definitely something that can be cultivated
and there's a number of ways in which it can be cultivated a common way is to repeat phrases
may you be safe may you be happy may you be healthy may you live with
ease these are four common phrases and they're just repeated in the mind
silently to oneself and then that may you be happy so that
you who that you is kind of like changes as we move through categories of individuals
often starting with the easy being this could be kitten puppies babies
coach Mentor benefit or somebody who's really supported you and in which you
have an uncomplicated relationship so the absolute easiest
and then often oneself but then often a neutral person
somebody that we might see in a on occasion in the neighborhood and then a difficult person
and then to all beings so kind of like extend uh expanding more and more
individuals but there's a way in which that uh we
might think well how does this work and does it work does repeating these
phrases in a meditative state or even while doing things in our daily life or while
walking does it really have an impact
and there's this way in which it actually does and but there's some ways in which we can support this cultivation
this maybe expansion of this loving kindness this matter that all of us
already have we're not creating this de novo we're not creating this out of nothing we're
just maybe allowing it to grow allowing it to
expand to meet more and more people more and more conditions
and it turns out that one of the ways that can really support this cultivation
is to have a certain confidence that the practice works
because otherwise sometimes what can happen is we'll say may you be safe may
you be happy may you be healthy may you live with ease
I don't feel anything is this what you know what this doesn't
work what are they talking about I can't do this is does this work for anybody else
and so there's a way that we kind of like just stop doing this and the mind starts wandering or something
but there's a way in which we might think about this uh practice like saying these phrases
is maybe twofold one is we can think about neuroplasticity we might use this
language you know it's kind of like modern language in fact what we incline
the Mind towards becomes the inclination of the mind if
it's not a secret it's not rocket science we've all have had this experience ourselves
but there's a way in which also we might think about it as planting seeds
and so saying these phrases is just planting a seed and in the same way that with Farmers
right they plant seeds but they can't see what's happening Underground in the same way we can't see what's
happening when we're saying these phrases when we are repeatedly coming back again and again to these phrases
so somebody once asked does this mean that we fake it until you
make it is that what we're supposed to be doing and uh kind of like hesitant to say that right because we don't want to
be like faking anything in this practice right kind of all this practice is you know we're just showing up for what's
happening but maybe we might say there's a little bit of fake it until you make it with
loving kindness practice and I say that with a smile on my face because there's a little bit of Whimsy there
but this also we can say is just like having some confidence that even though
we're not like at that moment feeling anything in particular
might even be feeling bored I might be feeling aversive we might have been feeling the exact
opposite of loving kindness which is so often the case it's like may you be happy
and then I've had the case definitely when I've been doing loving kindness practice and oh my gosh I just oh these
like really the worst things that you can imagine would come up in somebody's mind about
the person who was just sitting next to me they had nothing against this person sitting next to me I just happened to be
on a retreat and this is just what kind of came up and Spilled Out this poor person
you know I don't even know who it was so there's a way in which we're doing
loving kindness practice and all of the opposite of loving kindness comes up the hatred that it will the aversion
but if there's a way in which we can just have confidence like okay this
happens too this is part of the practice and as best we can just to be coming
back to the phrases coming back to Our intention
so we're not trying to manufacture or cook up or engineer or trick ourselves
into feeling anything or having any particular experience
it's more that we're just like creating the conditions and which makes it more likely that
those that experience of loving kindness will arise and if it doesn't it's
perfectly okay we're just practicing plants the seeds may be germinating but
you know we don't see it yet so I like this expression that Roberta
has said about loving kindness is sometimes when we hear these teachings we might have this idea
like you know there's supposed to be this unconditionality or this boundlessness and there might be this
feeling like really do humans really do that is that even possible like it's just
instead it sounds like some rarified or maybe something that's been
passed down through the ages that doesn't actually happen feels unrealistic or a bit too much maybe too
contrived or something like this so um Robert Bay uses this expression
we don't have to think that we have to be the squeaky clean meta machine
so it's an idea that we're just cranking out like meta non-stop like a robot or
something practice isn't like that when we hear the instructions we might
think oh this is what we're supposed to do just say these phrases and then out
comes some loving kindness but there's a way in which it can sound
like dry or not only something that's just like supposed to maybe magically happen
but not only that it can feel like the rubber band points to this this the
way the reason why he used the word machine is it can feel like well
I'm saying these phrases there's a way that it doesn't have any of our own
self-expression or doesn't have any of our personality or doesn't have any of
how we practice showing up and so in some ways there might be some
hesitation to do it because it doesn't feel maybe authentic or it doesn't feel
it feels maybe stifling but it's important to know that there's
a way in which a we can modify the phrases there's nothing magic about
those particular phrases that I just shared but you're welcome and encouraged to
modify them with a certain parameters the parameters are keeping them simple
and not too specific for example not like may you get that job that you want
on Tuesday at 9 00 a.m you know right it's more like may you be happy so
something that more General like this but there's a way in which this uh the
loving kindness the manifestation the expression the arising
it's really unique for all of us because it's not just one thing
this meta isn't just a do I have it do I not have it
it's more like how does it getting expressed or how does it feel sometimes
it feels really like a physical thing some warm-heartedness in the chest
sometimes it feels bubbly and bright and maybe like joyful
sometimes it feels really calm and smooth
maybe sometimes it feels like it has this quality of healing to
it or loving kindness meta might just have like this quality of gentleness and care
so there's all these different ways these different aspects that can show up in these different ways that can be
experienced it's certainly how it shows up is different for everybody it's certainly
different during different times of practice maybe at the beginning of a meditation session
there's absolutely nothing and then maybe it shows up one way and then morphs into another way
but I just wanted to recognize that sometimes it can feel uh maybe even oppressive like I would say these
sayings these phrases over and over again but it's it's enormously powerful it's
gonna be really powerful and so I've been talking about the
conditionality unconditionality of meta
so then there's a way in which we might be practicing and we might be noticing that
well maybe we do have some conditions for the people in our family that we
care about or you know that we love but sometimes they're irritating sometimes
they we have like well you know when you do
that thing makes me feel less warm-hearted towards
you something like this this we're all humans right this is part of the human experience we all have relationships of
a number of different relationships or maybe it's the opposite maybe we feel
like there's people in our family that we feel this real attachment to
so it's not this kind of robber base expression squeaky clean there's this feeling like
of course like we feel so attached to our partners our children our family
and so when we might be practicing love and kindness and we might feel some of this oh I do have some of this
attachment oh I do have some of this conditionality for example if we're
using a friend or a family member as a the person we're doing loving kindness
and sometimes there might be this temptation like I'm not doing it right or everybody else is doing it or this
one maybe I should use a different category maybe I shouldn't use this person or something like that
but there's also an encouragement to just notice oh yeah this is what a
touchman feels like oh yeah this is what conditionality feels like
and to just be with that and just to recognize that's part of loving kindness
practice as well right is this movement
unconditionality this movement of boundlessness of course we need to learn
and be familiar with what are the conditions what are the feelings that are limiting what are the attachments
of course we do so just part of the practice is to
experience them and then there's a way in which we just can fold that into the practice too and maybe have some of this
loving kindness this warmth this care go towards this attachment go towards this conditionality that
we're having it's rather than trying to be dismissive like I can't do loving kindness for this
person or at this time just like oh okay there's that attachment I don't have to get rid of
this attachment I just need to notice it
be with it see it the same with the conditionality that we might notice
because there's this way in that with love and kindness practice we want to
include our Humanity we want to include our complexity we want to include all
the different aspects of ourselves and our lives which means it's not you know squeaky
clean nice neat and tidy all of our relationships have different aspects and
elements to them of course they do of course they do
and so there's this way in which loving kindness practice for some people just feels like I don't want to do that
and maybe they just don't even know why they don't like it but part of the reason might be because they have this
idea that it should be you know super clean ideal
and it's easy to see that I know I certainly did I heard about loving kindness practice first time I really
heard about it was on a retreat and it was really off-putting for me because it just all sudden put up all the ways
in which I wasn't being kind and to others and to myself and it made me just
feel bad so I didn't want to do it but there's this way in which we can
I don't know hold the complexity the messiness the reality of Our Lives
and for me that feels more fun and kind of a relief to like okay to put down
this idea that loving kindness has to be in one particular way and to recognize
that instead there's this learning process that happens with love and kindness practice
and part of the learning is conditionality and limits
so loving kindness practice it certainly has a role in Buddhist practice
there's a number of different roles in which it has in which we might work with
loving-kindness practice and maybe I'll just say is a really broad brush really
broad stroke I would say in Buddhist practice we can make a gross generalization and say
there are some cultivation practices and there's some Letting Go practices
you know that's a false dichotomy because often letting go is cultivating
and cultivating is letting go but just for the purposes of this I'll say that so
loving kindness it's part of cultivation practice the same way that mindfulness concentration
ethics maybe we could even say some wisdom there's a way in which those are
cultivated So Meta loving kindness friendliness
Goodwill is definitely part of one of those practices but interestingly
loving kindness meta is also related to effort
some of you will recognize that right effort is the sixth step in the April path
but when there's too much effort when there's this striving and this
tightening and like this really I gotta get this there's something that's gonna happen
and whatever practice we're doing most often implicit in that is
there's a me here who wants to get something over there
and that over there might be like later in time so there's this real sense of lack
a real strong sense of me a real strong sense that things aren't quite right or the way that they
shouldn't be and instead something else should be happening
whereas loving kindness practice is more about a sense of abundance
rather than like and it's really more of a softening of the sense of me having to
get something there's even less of a sense of me and a less of a sense of I have to get something
so they're in some ways like loving kindness practices is a way to it can be an antidotal way to work with the sense
of striving and straining which turns out not to work so well and
meditation practice it works in our professional lives it works for Education it might even work with
gardening in some of our Hobbies right so working and striving certainly Works
in certain situations and it'll work a little bit in meditation until it doesn't it can only get you so
far this is where the cultivation and letting go has to go so letting go of striving and straining is definitely a
part of practice so loving kindness practice is a way that can support the right amount of
effort because the right amount of effort this is such a delicate
thing in all of our practice then we might even say it's part of the art of practice is know when to lean in
and apply a little bit more diligence the more effort and when to back off
this is something only with experience we kind of learn but with loving kindness practice maybe
increases the sensitivity because 11 codes practice is an opening
and when there's a straining that's a closing so we could feel we're a little bit more
sensitive to this straining and maybe because it's 11 kind of
practices of opening and yet there's still a practice helps us to not have two lacks of effort
because we're keeping on coming back to the phrases so it's not like we're opening and then going to sleep or
something like so loving kindness is also can be a
support for the amount of effort there's also a way in which we can say
as I alluded to earlier like saying these phrases we can feel like
I don't want to say these phrases it's one thing to say it in meditation but I
don't want to say it you know off the cushion I I have important thoughts to think
I have I would need to be creative I want to be self-express myself and I
don't want to while I'm doing the dishes or walking or whatever it is I'll do these phrases
well if you have a meditation practice and if you've ever done some meditation in Daily practice and you looked at your
mind maybe you'll notice how often do we get like stuck right and
we're just kind of thinking the same thing over and over and over there's a way in which we get a little bit
entangled with something and there isn't anything new thoughts happening
it's not too creative it's not really moving things forward and it's not necessarily supporting our
life or how many times just even some of the we're trying to remember the grocery
list I know sometimes I'm doing this like okay Diana remember to get the ABCD
you know sometimes I do remember sometimes I don't
but there says many of the thoughts that we have aren't as helpful as we might think that
they are often we're berating ourselves criticizing ourselves with this like
under the radar this chatter that's maybe accompanying us
or maybe there's this way in which we're thinking unkind thoughts about other people or thinking unkind thoughts about
the situation I can't believe they let this happen it shouldn't be like this and who's in charge here or you know
we're trying to blame others or something like this so it turns out to have a living
kindness practice to be saying these phrases and just regular life
is a way in which it might be replacing some unskillful thoughts some unhelpful
thoughts it's an unhelpful thought patterns
and not only might it be replacing things that are unhelpful it's creating
the conditions in which there can be this sense of ease and connectedness
and warmth and care and our lives unfold so differently if
we have that sense of ease and care and connectedness this is what so many of us want
in our lives to feel like there's this some peace on some uplift and a sense of
well-being so there's a way in which it might make
a lot of sense actually to doing some loving kindness practice not only as an official practice
while we're on the cushion but also in our daily life to be repeating phrases
or while we're doing walking meditation so certainly we have a
mindfulness or Insight practices also be choosing loving kindness
practices and I know some people that have uh you know said okay for these
months all my practice is just going to be loving kindness
turns out to be really transformative it turns out to really
do some of this rewiring this neuroplasticity turns out to be a real thing
and it softens and loosens up some of the things in our hearts and Minds
to have a regular loving kindness practice but then maybe I'll end on this topic
sometimes when we talk about loving kindness when we're talking about meta
we're often thinking like you know for other people and often than the examples that I've been giving this evening have
been about that turns out it's so important to have loving kindness for oneself
and for many people this turns out to be not so easy
it's difficult there's many reasons why it might be difficult to really appreciate ourselves
and send love and care and warmth to ourselves
it could be you know messaging that regards from our family or from school or something like this
friends but I also want to just highlight that
there's cultural reasons too that there's a way in which uh it's kind
of like there's mixed messages it might seem that we certainly hear in the
United States we have this culture of individuality like we take pride of you know like I can do it I can
pull myself up in the bootstraps like we have this kind of expression it's not true in the way that we think
it is but that is kind of something like you know these Cowboys had to go out and
make do something we have this sense of you know I can do it
or or there's also we see more and more this idea of me first
but go take care of me and make as much money as possible or you know whatever
and okay yeah okay you guys are okay all right but really me first right we see a
lot of that so you might think like oh that promotes this sense of love for oneself but
it turns out there's also this message of
it's selfish to take care of yourself to do things for yourself
there's a way in which it's indulgent or
inappropriate to take time for yourself and that's why there's often there's talk about self-care we have to like
remind people you have to take care of yourself you can't just always be giving to
others so there's like both of these messages are just out there in the culture all mixed up and
we have received a number of different ideas in our minds
but it turns out that you know loving kindness for oneself this needs often is a real practice and
to work with this inner critic that's always telling us that we're inadequate insufficient more has to happen
you can't rest until a b and c and d have been acquired attained and then
have you ever noticed as soon as you get a oh yeah but then there's e also and then as soon as you get you know one oh
yeah there's this right it's never ending never ending
so meta for oneself it turns out to be a big topic
it's inner critic often makes it not so easy
maybe here I'll just say briefly that uh there's a it's helpful to just
start where it's easy absolute easiest babies kittens puppies whatever it might
be and then here's the tricky part
day with that category stay with just with kittens and puppies
people want to do kittens and puppies and babies and they feel good like oh
okay now I feel a little bit of meant to okay now I'm gonna use this meant to use
it all the problems in my life I'm going to use this as a tool or I'm going to shoot out to meta to everybody else and
that works a little bit but what really works better is to stay
with wherever it's easy kittens puppies babies or who whatever benefactor coach
Mentor teacher whomever is to allow the loving kindness to start
to Bubble Up and just stay with there stay with this category
and then what happens is it just starts to Bubble Up and then it just starts to
leak out you can't help it it just starts to leak out and it starts
to leak out and they say about yourself and other people without you having to
direct it so there's a way in which we often like we experience it but there
might be a way in which we need to fill up the tank so to speak
that might be a way in which we need to really roll around in it in some way and
there's a way in which often people have this kind of like this starvation of this sense of love and warmth and Care
inside and well-being and so allowing oneself to really drink
it up for as long as it takes as long as it takes
a day a week a month a year makes absolutely no difference how long and
then it just naturally flows out it just naturally flows out to ourselves
and to others often loving kindness when it's taught
it's not taught that way but Todd would do this category and then just for pedagogical reasons go to the next
category of individual then for pedagogical reasons whether you're ready or not the teacher goes to the next
category so the part of the discipline is to like maybe hear oh the teachers doing that
but I'm not ready I I want to stay here no timeline absolutely no timeline
for this to happen for this to work it's a living kindness meta
Goodwill friendliness warm-heartedness towards ourselves and towards others
really powerful practice I could talk more about it some ways in
which it supports Buddhist practice as well as well as ways it supports our lives but I won't at this time
instead I'll open it up and see if there's some questions or comments
does anybody have anything they'd like to say or ask
well I'll say something thank you for your talk
um I've made meta the practice that I do before I got out of bed in the morning
you know just as a way to prepare myself for meeting things and
the a couple things came up when you were talking one was like starting with the easy category
and then sort of sending out feelers to see can I like I wonder if I think you
know like what if I offer to this person what's that like this morning right now
and you know sometimes it's like yeah that's possible and then uh and
sometimes being surprised you know like oh yeah you know I didn't and uh the other image that came to me
was something Gil talked about um kind of like doing yoga there's there's
a way of doing this I don't know it's a sun salute or something if you put a phone book there used to be
these books called phone books and you could reach down and you could
touch the phone book and then each day tearing out one page
you know and like it takes you know I don't know a year or something to get one more inch but you
know it's sort of like just that very nice tearing out one page of the phone book each day very nice I love that
that's a great that's great thank you I was talking about like seeds germinating but carried out a book I love it thank
you yeah thank you anybody else have a comment
thank you for the talk um so and the way you explained it like
I am also like I find it very hard to be appreciative of myself I have this
tendency of criticizing myself a lot and when I try loving kindness it just
doesn't seem to work especially like you know in times of stress it can sometimes
be very difficult to stick to a practice uh which takes very long which takes a
very long time as in like you know if it has to spell to myself then if I have to stick to the practice for a very long
time especially in terms times of stress it can be like really difficult so how do I
kind of make myself stick to it when it's like not paying dividends on a
short time frame in in some way is it just like you have to believe in it and
stick with it or are there some other tricks which work for people in general
yeah yeah
yeah way in which uh loving kindness when it's uh use it for the easy B the B
the person that's the or person doesn't have to be a person getting puppies babies Etc we choose whatever is easy
because hopefully we might imagine that there can be some
warmth or some something that happens no guarantees right but usually there is
something that's a little bit pleasurable about it maybe we can feel a
little bit uh relaxing of the body when we think of
I'm just going to make this up a baby like a new baby in the family that just makes us really just so happy to think
about this baby so cute and and so to tune so we're doing love and kindness
practice but also to tune into like what's happening in the body it's
usually a pleasant experience to be like oh it's so cute and I wish the best for
this baby like they have this whole life in front of them and they're so adorable and so there's this uh can be this
relaxation experience it might be subtle but what happens is it grows
and so that pleasurable experience grows and grows and grows and can Encompass
the whole body so it's when you're saying it will take a long time it
won't be like something that you have to force yourself to do it might be you have to use some
you might have to use some effort to initially start the practice but with you stay with the easy being it
usually ends up being a pleasant experience say that and then maybe something else I'll just
say as an aside that um for a number of years I taught what we call like a happy hour or it's something
that's on on Audio Dharma and I did a series where I did the inner
critic and loving kindness like a series of I don't know maybe 20 short Little Talks
short being like 10 minutes five to ten minute little talks on this so if you're if this is something you want to look
into you get to look on Audio Dharma and there's a whole uh little series on this of a number of little things to do and
that includes guided meditations also so sometimes that could be helpful if we feel like I can't do this I don't want
to do this sometimes listening to a guided meditation can be a support
thank you yeah you're welcome yes sir one more comment here
foreign thank you for the talk um so one question is why do we
categorize as all this like myself others like friend and instead of saying
just all beings be happy uh if doing just that versus doing this
separate things um I'm trying to understand what's the difference
um yeah I think there's another question but yeah so the question is why categories instead of just all beings
yeah yeah yeah because uh all beings is more of a concept that's an idea that we
don't know well beings of course we don't so it's much easier actually it turns out
it's much easier to have like loving kindness for all beings because it's
we're not in contact necessarily with the people that get under our skin or
the people that we don't know so the practice is to be with actual
individuals in the beginning that we know because like even with our friends
or our family that we're doing right it's there's sometimes a little bit of difficulties in those relationships but
to still have loving kindness anyway and that's where the practice is
and so and then one of the individual one of the categories is neutral people so people we don't know but the
instructions are as best you can to find a neutral a single neutral person
something that you see in the neighborhood or maybe somebody that you see at the grocery store or something
like this so can you send Goodwills to an individual that you don't know and
that turns out to not be so easy so that's a real cultivation practice
second question is on how do we actually practice this you mentioned uh the the
people who do this for the whole month instead of breath meditation or other ones
and also like I think during the day repeating this so on a
practical instruction level or like how do we actually do this like
yeah when you remember you just bring to mind
may you be happy may you be healthy safe the veggies
um and you could start with the lovable you could start through categories or if
you're in your daily life and you could just when you see somebody on the sidewalk you see somebody at work you could just do it for that individual
or you could do it for yourself so there's lots you can play around with it in your daily life it's just when you
remember so you kind of like set the intention when I remember I'm gonna do these phrases and then of course you won't
remember and nor is it appropriate like when you're working or reading you're not going to be doing that as not necessarily but
sitting practice um instead of the breath meditation do this or
yeah okay and there's if you're interested there are
hundreds let's think about this we did this five days a week for three years yeah so there are hundreds of guided
meditations for loving kindness on audiodarma.org if you want to listen to
uh and it's still happening so there's on Audio Dharma as well it happens happen
tonight 6 p.m to 7 P.M so Monday through Friday 6 PM to 7 P.M it's loving
kindness practice uh that's on zoom and you if you look on our calendar you
you'll see MC calendar you'll see it so okay thank you
okay so I think with that I'll end so thank you for your attention and wishing
you a lovely rest of the evening thank you and if you have more questions you're
welcome to come up here and ask me