so tuning in tuning into that Joy of being together
we invite you all to notice how it feels in your heart notice how it feels
to be present with this virtual Sangha some of you have been coming for years
and appreciating the greetings just taking that in
making that into your heart
and when you're ready after you've had a chance to greet your friends
Global community to sit back in a posture that is upright alert and
at ease whatever that is sitting standing lying down and begin to turn your attention inwards
will you be doing any last little thing that needs to be done
before settling into the next half hour
in the tuning tuning in to your life's breath
your body your heart
and inviting inviting me this body relaxed
soften be at ease
making a couple of deeper slower more intentional breaths
and tuning into the sense of belongingness connection
with all of these other practitioners
and as the breath returns to normal
allowing that sense of connection belongingness to be sustained
feeling into any Joy
happiness contentment at being here with this practice
together
It Feels Right allowing a smile to come to your lips
I've been really noticing the embodied experience of being here now
feet hands the support beneath your seat
rooted here allowing the energy
off the breath to carry through carry through your body
each Opera
perhaps blowing on the Embers of any contentment
connection Joy that's present
settling in
connecting with breathing sensation
connecting with your heart
into the staining
sustaining the attention on each in-breath each out breath
each sensation or sound
dedicating the attention to the details the texture
at this moment
if you find a thought mood memory pulls the heart and mind
away into then and there
seeing how kindly graciously it's possible to return and connect
again with this moment this breath
and perhaps also celebrating the return of awareness
noticing and welcoming each moment of awareness mindfulness
and staying with
being with whatever is recognized before returning
to the primary object of attention
resting resting in the moment to the breath presentations
if the attention went rededicating yourself
to the complete total attention
study of each breath each sensation each sound
reconnecting and feeling the pleasure
of staying close staying connected
sustaining
remember each breath sensation sound to Ripple through
Ripple through your whole being
thank you
we have to be or flowing being that a stream of sensation or
sound
allowing resting
and last remaining moments of this meditation
the invitation is to gather up soak in any little goodness
happiness grew into Joy or pleasure mindfulness or
connection let them resonate sink in to your heart
basking what's good and being with with compassion all the rest
and then turning your inner gaze outwards
to all of the others in your life seen and unseen
I think generating the intention the aspiration
that through this practice through this life
May others experience benefit
noticing the feeling of generosity care in offering this wish
may all beings be happy may all beings be seen
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free from suffering
[Laughter]
thank you foreign
thank you for the sincerity of your practice
[Music]
foreign
so today is the second of a five day series that
talks about factors of mine that support meditation practice and daily life in a
particular way most important meditative stability and
unification in a wise way for the purpose of wisdom and Awakening and
freedom so yesterday I covered the crucial
fundamentals of mindfulness and practice intelligence and today we're going to start on five
factors of stability samadhi often called the five genic factors
today is the first two factors which in the context of meditation in the sutans and commentaries
are almost always spoken of together they are the mental factors of
connecting and sustaining that's the taka and the Chara
while we talking vichara are normally associated with formal meditation the ideas behind them can apply to daily
life so just to give a couple of examples
um the taka connecting also has the meaning of thought or thinking
directed attention and this directed attention can be directed towards and
applied to pretty much anything an analogy in daily life is making an
initial connection with another person first key step in forming any kind of
relationship right so making a connection is so vital to relating that it's taught as a skill
and counseling training and many other relational fields
so that's vitaka connecting vichara
sustaining is the process of maintaining being with that initial connection
to use a continuation of the daily life analogy we can connect with lots of
different people but if there isn't sustained attention connection over time
relationships won't flourish or develop or possibly even continue
Butera also means consideration which in daily life means keeping
someone or something in mind in American English it's often known as thoughtfulness
this quality is also a key ingredient to maintaining relationships good ones anyway right
the same is true in meditation
if we don't connect with and sustain attention on the object the object of
attention in meditation or connect and sustain attention on meditation itself
it won't develop and deepen okay
so now for the more precise kind of definitions of these factors these terms
the Pali word vitaka can be translated best is kind of a word cloud
in non-meditative contexts it can refer to reflection directed thought
thinking and even a little bit of kind of intentional thought very very um
kind of focused it has a quality of fixity to it
kind of like a tapping Bichara almost always appears with
vitaka about meditation it almost never appears on its own and its word cloud is smaller it's a quality
of sustaining that emerges from Big charity the verb
to go about an object to go about an object
and it's a continued examination a non-discursive examination of this
object of attention the breath the body whatever it is necta
and this consideration in this non-discursive way
deepens the relationship with object of of our practice of our
attention and with meditation itself
soon be taka and Bichara are foundational for
cultivating greater mindfulness and concentration
in a sense the sound of each word hints at their different functions
so if you listen sounds like kind of a quick pulse
vichara the Chara kind of hints at lingering it's longer
softer so in some similes
be taka is like placing your hand on a friendly cat or dog
vichara is stroking its fur
connecting is like a single Center Point
of a circle drawn with a compass and Bichara
is everything within the circle so there's the center point of attention
and then everything related to the object of attention
consideration going about sustaining
mitaka that initial application can have a bit of a fixed quality to it
kind of like a hand holding a bowl or a bell right
Victoria has a more moving about quality like rubbing a cough
or polishing the Bell
then vitaka is also like hearing the Striking Annabelle
can be like a Clank Bichara
is not just the Striking of the taka but the sustained ring
afterwards
so at first both vitaka and vichara are kind of
skills in a sense we develop these factors of mind
as our meditative practice deepens particularly when it has momentum
these mental factors begin to naturally emerge
as conditioned responses then a rhythm of connecting without
trying begins to build kind of like repeated Bell strikes [Music]
and then after the period of sustaining Bichara
begins to stretch out longer with fewer moments of vitaka the Bell strike
needing to happen persisting
sustaining
so together as these factors gain momentum the mind and heart start to
gain some meditative stability and perhaps part of why we talk on
vichar are presented together merely always in meditation is because they're
so interlinked connecting vitaka without sustaining
can feel kind of clunky like doing meditation by a checklist or
something like that can also feel disjointed or dry beechara
sustaining can stay with an object of attention once there's been a lot of connection and
reconnection with it but before that it can wander off in a cloud of vague
associations or something like that without this connecting and reconnecting
so it's worth noting that both of these factors connecting and sustaining mitaka
and gichara they're morally neutral they're not inherently good
it means relating to them with mindfulness and practice intelligence is
absolutely key misdirected vitaka and Vitara can help
create a phenomenon known as Yogi mind those of you who have sat Retreat are
probably familiar with this term Yogi mind is a phenomenon where the Mind
becomes preoccupied with or separates on something minor usually or blows
something very small out of proportion this can happen when concentration
starts to build Ruby taka and vichara but they're somehow misdirected or it's an object of attention an idea a topic
that's not so helpful and that little bit of concentration sometimes a lot of concentration can
magnify things in strange and funny and sometimes even unhelpful ways
a really kind of sweet example of this I've heard from other practitioners and
in my own life is after Retreat someone will come up
and start to enthuse about how they have designed in their mind a better meditation cushion
better meditation cushion and this is classic to do on a retreat any discomfort kind
of feeds these ideas so
at its worst the taka and vichar can lead to obsessive thoughts or spinning out
in ways that distort our understanding of ourselves and of other people
that's a topic for another time to really unpack it but just to name that the practice intelligence the
mindfulness of directing and where we direct things is important
there's a story from nasuta's very very famous um and powerful ruler
comes to the Buddha and here's a sincere practitioner he's deeply dismayed and asking why beings people who wish to
live in harmony and wish to live in peace so often live in hatred hostility
and immunity and he asks this question a number of
times in the Buddha and answering Saka the name of the ruler names a number of contributing
conditions jealousy avarice and greed desire of rewarding of wealth
and under the desire repeated directed thinking
born of a tendency to obsess many of us might recognize that last
part sometimes our minds just won't let go of something trivial or even unhelpful
right so this underscores the importance of discernment that mindfulness and
practice intelligence can reveal and asking the question non-discursively
every now and then is this even what I should be focused on is this object of attention or this way
of focusing way of sustaining helpful
or unhelpful beneficial or unbeneficial skillful or unskillful
and the key question might there be a way to direct and sustain the attention
so as to nurture what's most beneficial
then with that discernment there's the possibility of connecting
and sustaining attention on objects of meditation people topics activities
experiences that are life-giving nourishing conducive to Freedom
and that's a huge thing in life and formal meditation both this begins to
open a pathway to Greater Joy happiness peace
Freedom Awakening
so it's our last sort of aside vitaka and vichara can be directly observed in
daily life in our minds and I'll discuss this and continue exploring some of these genic factors
at IMC Tomorrow there's a half day Wednesday half day Meditation Retreat
it's in person only however recordings will be posted to audiodarma.org
so if you're interested in hearing more about this you can hear it there is also on-site a few practice
discussions slots available from people who come
so in meditation starts a wise deepening of meditative
stability and that in turn begins to manifest as
Joy or happiness contentment petite and sukha which are the third and
fourth genic factors and those will be our topic for tomorrow
so a joy to be with you Sangha thank you for your kind attention