it's nice to see all the greetings on the chat and
uh I'm sure there's lots of people who would rather not chat publicly or don't
know how or something and and but I see these wonderful good mornings as kind of
representing a large community that we are coming here these weekday mornings
and uh it's very heartwarming it's inspiring and and is uh inspires me to come down here and and
teach I love teaching um and
um teaching to me feels like an extension of the practice that we
do so one of the ways that um our own
practice can be inspiring or can be supported protected even is is if we
don't take it too personally the the momentum in the mind
to Define things or refer things back to ourselves in some kind of definition of
who we are or some kind of idea some kind of
feeling that uh lends itself to such ideas as Me Myself and mine this is
mine and then defining ourselves with these things it lends itself to
writing close to all our experience and kind of navigating it as if uh we're
kind of trying to improve the self or defend the self or hide the self or um
everything is kind of referred to ourselves and the idea of progress idea
of gaining something in practice um can have very much associated with Me Myself
and mine like I have to get something out of this or why do I do it that's a kind of
reasonable point of view but also it too easily brings along a lot of self a lot
of conceit a lot of kind of self- preoccupation which is one of
the great hindrances to discovering the Deep peace
that's possible through meditation the freedom that's possible and the idea that we would
practice meditation in a certain kind of way not for ourselves uh is confusing and is
um offputting for some people because of course I'm here and don't I count and
shouldn't I be taken care of myself but there is something very profound about not engaging in this uh
exercise of selfing of measuring things against some Notions
of self judging who we are what we're doing trying to get better experiences
for ourselves Gathering things to say so Gathering experiences so we have good things to say to our friends um trying
to make progress in meditation so we can prove ourselves some way and um so this is a delicate thing this
selfing and of course we want to heal ourselves of course we want to improve ourselves and that's the whole
Enterprise in Buddhism is to find to improve ourselves to heal and find Freedom to develop love and
compassion it turns out that the whole Enterprise the whole momentum of
practice can be a lot easier if we put to rest the ways in which we take
things personally the ways in which we consider our experiences what's happening to us that I'm responsible for
this that I'm making something happen or this is because I did this in the past
and and um and one of the opportunities in practice is to practice
sincerely but to view what's happening impersonally not impersonally in some
cold aloof way but impersonally in a way that allows for a deeper intimacy
without the filter of me myself in mind and so the art of practicing and seeing
things as being somewhat impersonal or non-personal or
transpersonal and uh to put to rest the Me Myself and
mine and for some of us it's hard to imagine how we can make effort without that idea of self and me doing it and
that's okay but to begin the process of uh lightening up loosening up the grip
of Self in relationship to lots of things so for example uh if there's pain
while we meditate there's a wise way of seeing it in an impersonal way just pain
without calling it my pain if the mind is wandering awful lot
just call it you know a Wandering mind as opposed to I am wandering off I'm not
able to meditate if the breathing doesn't feel as comfortable and easy as you know it can
be then it's just simply a uncomfortable breathing nothing more nothing less as
opposed to wow what did I do that I'm breathing this way and I have to figure out the solution and this is not a I'm
not being a good breather right now so instead of all the self- referencing kind of a matter effect kind
of like the way a naturalist we just watch what's happening in nature and record it
without judgments or without making it into something that it's not without
making it into herself for himself their self so may you sit this way may you be
the naturalist of your experience curious present
open available
without taking it personally without the added
effort of making it mine or making it something that defines
me or something that characterizes myself so to assume a meditation
posture gently close your eyes
and if in some way it's not about you being comfortable in the meditation posture but rather your body you want to
put in a in a assume a posture that your body feels as good feels that
is energizing engaging where the body feels like yes
it's
here and the next few breaths that you do breathing is something we share with
other humans and other mammals and other
creatures it's such a universal characteris istic of much of animal life
to breathe here
now this deep animal nature of our being that
keeps Us Alive is our
breathing to assume if you take a few long slow deep
breaths appreciating that this has been going on for millions of
years creatures breathing on this planet and relaxing on the
exhale then letting your breathing return to
normal maybe like a creature that has feeling safe
contented the breathing itself can begin to
relax
making space for breathing to breathe
itself and if you go into a place of
Nature and just watch all the elements of natures the creatures the plants the
sky the ground as part of the natural
world so as you gaze within to your breathing your body your
feelings your thoughts see them as part of nature
no need to take them personally or to make
yourself out of them no need to have whatever is happening
within be tied to me myself in
mind just nature being nature kind
of nonpersonal intimacy with the natural
world this is what's possible with being mindful of
ourselves mindful of our experience Moment by
moment
for
when you find yourself entangled with
thinking don't make that something to do about yourself as a naturalist just go
wow that's entangled see it clearly
in the Simplicity of what it is
wow nothing to do with yourself and begin again with your
breathing
for
[Music]
[Music] for
e
for
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
sometimes when meditation brings us a degree of calm
peace well-being sense of safety and coziness something in that
family the Instinct the ability for us to be have wish well wishing for others
wishing people well can arise as an act of nature not
exactly a personal decision we're inclined to meet people in a friendly way and respectful way
open way not asserting ourselves but
available and in this kind of way kind of an almost a nonpersonal way or
something deep within deeper than any notion of self
maybe from there there can be well wishing for this
world may all beings in this world be
happy may they be
safe may they be peaceful
may they be free and may they
know that I offer my respect and Good
Will from some deep place within where I'm available to support
this possibility may all
beings be free
[Music]
thank
you
e
greetings from inside meditation center and continuing in this 10p part
series on that's called the pro the 10 protectors or the 10 supporters or
helpers of 10 helps and uh this one today is
um uh in a skillful and Wise Way caring for supporting the
sa caring for and supporting the practice your practice community
now ever since we I was involved in this IMC song guide got involved many years
ago when it was just a small sitting group of Monday nights about 12 people
15 people came and I joined them as a teacher had been already in place for
maybe four years and uh coming out of uh kind of
monastic training i' had seen how phenomenally useful it is powerful it is
to care for the place that we practice in and um the uh it's a place where
we're supported location and friends and community and maybe teachings and
there's something in the Alchemy of practice that changes for a good way when we also care for the place we
practice in so because of that when uh we were just a small few people coming
uh it was easier for me to take care of the logistics it was very few things there was a key that opened and closed
the church library where we met there was flyers from Spirit Rock Meditation
Center that we put out to let people know what was happening there was very little inside meditation opportunities
in the Bay Area back then and um and um that was it someone with a key
someone took care of the Flyers and I could I could easily have done that myself but it felt like such an
important thing to provide people with an opportunity to care for the place they practiced in so we found someone
and I think the person who then uh carried the key open the place every
week uh I told them that they were the president of our sitting group gave them
some you know some higher level caretaking responsibility for it and
even though there was almost nothing to do I thought it was useful for people to step into a little bit of a leadership
role and I didn't know what was going to happen with that but and then slowly we grew and developed and it was remarkable
how many people step forward to volunteer and what part of the benefits
of volunteering was uh forming a sense of deeper sense of community and connectedness with other practitioners
and this idea of kind of caring for the practic center so there's more sense of connection Community also supports and
protects our own practice that uh sometime which is is not available too much when we practice just alone all the
time one of the important uh and so we come and become we can become in a sense
a protector of the S which is a powerful thing to do to be but more importantly
there's a way in which um being a little bit selfish selfless a little bit kind
of extending ourselves to support others uh is a protection for our from our
selfishness protection from us doing the practice in a little bit too self-centered ways too preoccupied by me
myself in mind it's my practice I'm going to get enlightened I'm going to get concentrated I'm going to you know
you know all these people are getting the way they just make life more difficult and complicated and but to
rather uh to see that we grow in in connection to the community we they
mirror who we are they Mir how we might be a little bit off or how we are confused and how we might might uh take
things excessively personally or it might be situations where our our uh
judgments of others come forward but being in community working with people becomes a mirror for ourselves and this
is one of the reasons first reasons I think that I decided to go live at a Buddhist center was uh I'd been
practicing Zen uh in college I meditated in zazen Zen meditation twice a day uh
on my own and um and but I would visit San Francisco Zen Center uh occasionally
uh once a month or something and I noticed something peculiar there that I was young I was about 22
and um but I had all these social games that I played you know I wanted to present myself in a certain way so they would think of me in a certain way um I
had some way I wanted to be seen and so I was talking and engaging in ways to try to get that response from people and
uh so playing the social games to try to get to reinforce a certain identity that I wanted to have and so when I went to
Zen with when I was with my friends I didn't even know I was doing this we were all doing it so it was all kind of
one big kind of social kind of thing where we were kind of we were good friends and got along well but there was
this kind of you know moving in and out unconsciously with this kind of game of self and
self-presentation but when I came to uh San Francisco Zen Center and talked to some of the more senior practioners
there a remarkable thing happened that I would uh you know do
this social kind of games of presenting myself in a certain way and there would be no response they weren't playing the
game and they were kind of a mirror and I was like wow then I really saw what I
was doing in a way that I hadn't seen before and so I thought this is
invaluable to have people mirror my the ways that I'm kind of off I want to see
this more clearly and so that was the first uh desire to go live at the San Francisco Zen Center to be around these
people who mirrored me in in ways that showed me where I needed to let go where
I needed to grow where I needed to kind of really take a good look at myself and see the things that were not necessarily
so um wonderful about me and I felt so lucky that I'd found a place to go to
have this mirrored for me that I would kind of see this about myself and even
though some of it was you know rather um embarrassing maybe or uh you
know little bit I would you know cringe about what I'd see in myself I was so
happy I felt much safer as a human being moving through the world when I was
being mirrored when I was being shown all the ways in which I was off and um
so that was a protection for me and I love this protection I felt safer being in such a
community and um so to be uh to have Community for support to know people
more personally uh to be able to witness people's goodness in a way that sometimes you don't see it unless you're
sharing and caring for the community life and um and
um and so here at IMC I felt it was always important to make it available
for people to be volunteers but never require it I
thought it was extremely important to not have any sense of obligation around it in any sense that you were less a
member of the community if you weren't volunteering so this art of kind of making it very available to people
people have all kinds of circumstances in their lives and people have busy lives they have personal circumstances
that keep them quite CH are might challenged by and they don't have the ability to the time or the interest to
volunteer at their local sa in the community um so the art of that finding
that balance of making it available but having no one had any sense of obligation was um kind of The Balancing
Act that we've tried to do here for these many years at IMC as we grew and
um and uh so to so whatever your community
Buddhist communities that you have that you practice in to offer some care to them and um so you know if you live
someplace where there's no no Buddhist community that you're directly connected to if this YouTube is your community
these years um maybe there's some simple way that you could volunteer for IMC in
the distance uh there are you know people help with technology or help with
managing some of the some of the zoom and different things that we do recordings and
um so that you know it's not always easy to find volunteer positions for people but it's it's essential for who we are
and but I'm not so I'm not trying to not get offering this of fishing for people trying to get people to volunteer here
what I'm trying to do is uh talk about this protector this protection we get um
when we protect the sa we're protected as well and the primary protection that
I celebrate is uh it's a protection from being excessively self-preoccupied
maybe even selfish and uh it's hard to see how that works and so to be in some
situation where you have to stretch yourself beyond your usual sense of self where you have to drop it and there's
all kinds of ways to do that besides supporting a sa so there's other ways there's other SAS there's other
communities uh I was struck by how much this was the case um having uh little
babies and toddlers boy was that a mirror for myself boy was that the place
where I saw ways in which I was self selfish maybe or self-concerned self-
preoccupied in ways that I had no idea because it was it those there were ways
in which I could do it so freely without in a reasonable healthy way no one could
see it I couldn't even see it but the demands of uh caring for young children
was such a good mirror wow and um I saw all kinds of things about me that were
challenging to see and challenging to let go of even but it was a fantastic s
fantastic way that I it was a protection for me to see things that about myself
that I haven't even seen in you know long monastic life so to find some ways so uh to be in
connected to other people supporting other people that uh steps you out of
the little world of self that you might have or um and uh stretch yourself in such a
way that some something that's not needed can be let go so that you find
yourself Freer in relationship to living this life where you not don't have the
windrag of self-concern you don't have the tension of uh conceit you don't have
the you know something you're involved in the world kind of in a more kind of
selfless way or impersonal or non-personal way or um without uh you
being the center of attention um and uh but the other becomes more
valuable and in situations where I've been that way in my life uh I just felt like so it was a freeing movement to do
that and uh and in some ways I saw more the possibility of freedom from self-concern self-
preoccupation um in supporting and helping others and working for others than sometimes I've seen in meditation
itself so this kind of going and going back and forth between meditation and having this challenge of how we live in
the world is a wonderful balance and
um and uh for some people this teaching about you know being you know doing
things more non-personally or without self selfishness and preoccupation needs
to be heard very carefully because it's not meant to be any denial or diminishing of the value of this person
that we are and U that's me meant to be kind of sacrificing of ourselves uh for
others it's meant to uh be able to step forward more fully and become ourselves
more fully uh rather than being less but this more fully way of stepping forward
um there's something that do the the shell the the ties of self-c concern can um
fall off as we do so so thank you
and um May you consider ways in which your support your care for
others uh May uh be a mirror for you to see yourself better and help you break
out of the ways that self-c concern is limiting for you so thank you very
much