welcome
welcome to our last day on this second
round of the Poetry of practice it's a
been a pleasure sharing these poems with
you this week and today I'll share one
more there's something about um poetry
and mindfulness practice that I think
goes together and that is the poet in my
view not being a poet myself but in my
view the
poet has to like feel into the
moment has to really be
present for what it is that they're
trying to express in order to be able to
like
distill the moment into some imagery or
to some words
or so in the same way maybe the poet is
particularly mindful is particularly
present when they're
writing in the same way that with our
practice that we are present for what's
happening like letting the
extraneous I don't know thoughts
experiences you know just be in the
background and instead to be really
present for what's
happening and maybe that's part of the
reason why
mindfulness practice and poetry go
together they both have
this property of
presence and
distillation
maybe so well that is an introduction
let's
uh do some meditation as you know I'll
drop in a poem after we've been settled
and I've had some amount of silence and
then I'll drop in a poem into our
meditation but again we'll start
by taking a meditation
posture a posture that
expresses Our
intention to be
present in this moment
taking this posture and can be helpful
to have a
few long slow
exhales there a way in which exhaling
kind of like supports the arising of
ease maybe in some way expelling some
tension or tightness
tuning into this bodily
experience bringing some presence some
embodiment to this moment
feeling connected to
grounded with this base this seating
base the
foundation two feet on the ground with
the buttocks
or if you're sitting in a chair or or if
you're sitting cross-legged
the buts and
two other areas maybe the calf the side
of the
leg what would it be like to tune into
the sense of
stability in this moment even if you're
walking and if you're lying down sense
of
balance a
brightness
and then tuning into the move movement
within that
stability the movement of the sensations
of
breathing the chest
[Music]
moving or the belly
moving for some of you you might be
feeling the sensations of the air going
in and out of the
nose
just allowing that experience to be
[Music]
known more of a receiving the experience
than going out and getting it
receiving in a relaxed open spacious
manner
it wouldn't be
[Music]
surprising if the mind was
wondering it's
okay you just very simply
gently begin
again it doesn't matter how many times
we begin
again this is simply the
practice beginning
again and again and
again
and can we imbue this
experience an attitude of care an
attitude of warmth an attitude of
kindness towards
ourself
no need to
parate
chastise instead an opportunity to have
kindness love for
ourselves as best we
can
as best we
can without insisting on
perfection