so warm greetings from
inside Meditation Center here in Redwood City
wonderful to have you as part of this and um
as an introduction to this meditation one of the great possibilities or
opportunities in meditation is to lessen our self-preoccupation
and being preoccupied with our ourselves our concerns our
worries our desires our conceits this is all it has a very much to do
with our discursive thinking a lot of that is fueled by discursive thinking it's perpetuated by it it's
strengthened by it it's um reminded of it
and I think not a few people will discover that if they track what their
discursive thinking is about that often oneself is a
a key character or is an important reference point for What the how the
the commentary discussion fantasies are going
and as the discursive mind becomes quieter and we become Stiller or calmer
and and uh and perhaps some of the uh strength of our desires our Ambitions
our fears anxieties our conceits become less and less
then something remarkable begins happening and that is that the
orientation that we come from no longer is so self-centered
it doesn't mean that we ignore ourselves but it means that there's a kind of a opening up
a receptivity a sensitivity that
others and their well-being their suffering
becomes as important as our own there's no
the line there's no hard and fast kind of barrier towards
giving kind of a non-preferential care whoever is in our environment and
whoever is in our circle of concern or in our in our view or something
and as practice deepens that Circle of concern the circle of how we care for
can become even Universal for all beings partly because
there's no restrictions there's no limitations there's no preferences put
on the heart's capacity to care the heart's capacity to be open and
available and we are part of that kind of universal
kind of care and compassion and love that but it's remarkable to be able to
drop so much of the self-concern we have and discover a very different orientation
that um how to live our lives it can be life-changing it certainly was for me
so maybe not easy but the hearing they said this is a possibility of meditation
maybe as we meditate today that can be a reference point maybe a reference point to when there's
a self-concern to pay attention to see what the the
tension the contraction the limitation that's there the blinders that are on
what's being that so much is being left out because of the narrowness of that Focus
and that maybe there's some way that the narrowness can be relaxed and soften
the prioritization that to be some often give to ourselves and our own experience and who I am and our judgments of
ourselves what we need um and just to relax that and relax it
and maybe with every exhale to relax self-concern
every exhale to soften and open up Beyond the limitations of self Me Myself and
mine and it could be in very small steps it could be simply that the next sale is a
willingness uh to for this new possibility this new way and maybe it's not easy to tap into
it or touch it but just being willing to do it is the beginning of a softening
and opening a freeing that goes on so let's see how this goes
so assuming a meditation posture
and um and part of the goal of a mind of a
meditation posture is a posture within which you can both be alert
but also relax and let go in your body in a deep way
and this combination of a certain intentionality of being kind of somehow some intentionality and
having a an alert posture and a posture that
provides enough support that the musculatures in our body can
relax in a deeper way than usual
and to close the eyes and to take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe on the exhale letting go of any thoughts reactions you might have to
what I've said or letting go of any concerns that you brought with you to the meditation
and if they're not easy to let go of to soften around them
to ease up
into
let your breathing be normal and to relax the body
maybe with every exhale this different part of your body can soften and relax
and as you continue breathing what is your discursive mind up to is it
already quiet or is it already can you notice that there's kind of some
kind of self-concern maybe an appropriate one an innocent one
but still it's concerned with oneself
if you're worrying about someone else is there some way that the worry
is in fact self-referential
in that maybe in that we're concerned about our own distress
or our own
or our responsibility or something
and then with every exhale
see if there can be a softening of self-concern self-referencing
the mind's movement towards viewing Things From perspective of Me
Myself and mine
even the idea of my body and my breathing my meditation
my experience can be subtly shifted to
the body's experience
the bodies experience of breathing
The Experience that's occurring now
without reference to self course it's happening
to you in a sense but to Overlay that with
the idea of me myself and mine is extra
is in some way a limitation on the open awareness the
open-heartedness the openness of just sitting here
breathing calmly relaxantly
letting go of self with every exhale
with every exhale equally letting go of self-concerned
as you will would letting go of other concerns
through deeper meditation
any direction of concern towards others or towards oneself
is not needed it's a limitation
to the settling and the opening the quieting
letting go of any thoughts about any by anyone at all self or other
just here available open receptive
present
here for what is without limitation
and as we come to the end of the sitting
there's a way of now opening our Circle of Care concern
compassion so that we're available
to care available to have a compassionate or a loving response
to whatever comes into view whatever we think about or meet or see
that translates to a universal
care Universal compassion for all beings not because we're thinking about all
beings or intending to have compassion for all beings
but because We Care without limitation
there's an openness a receptivity a sensitivity
that allows for compassion who are
whoever comes within View
maybe even for whatever comes into view including animals and
the nonsense non-sentient world
because we're thinking this or wanting this it's a byproduct
of our care being fully open and available
almost like a readiness or as a way of not limiting
no restrictions limitations no blinders
for our care and then to make a universal dedication
of Merit it's not so much the idea of all beings
that it's the heart of the dedication but rather
this way of being that's available and open to all to all
May our hearts be fully open
to have good will for whoever comes into view
comes into our circle of awareness knowing
May or care be available
to promote the peacefulness and safety for all beings
their compassion
be always ready and sensitive to care for the freedom
freedom from suffering freedom from oppression
of anyone who comes into our view
so that deep inside it's almost almost as if
or almost as if these words give expression to this inner freedom
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so this topic of this week aspiration
is something very dear to me my journey along Buddhist practice
it's related to the topic of intention and the wise kind of way of letting
desires bubble up from within from some deep wise place within
and um and to some degree the aspirations which
the deeper intentions with which we want to live our lives in some ways are among the most important aspects of Our Lives
and getting clarity about Our intention clarity about our aspiration
and using the word aspiration rather than intention uh
suggests also that we're talking about something that is can be grand or big or
Central intention might be something very specific
and that could be Broad in general but aspiration is a little bit more has in my mind and my breathing has more of a
wide broad largeness to it it's like really essential it's like the heart's
aspiration the hearts deepest wish or something and the reason to refer to it that is
that as we settle in meditation as we relax and calm we're calming the
agitations that are always going to be there if there is conceit if they're
self-preoccupation if we're being driven by desires for what I want desires of
what I don't want or if we're caught up in fear not all fear but a good part of
fear is rooted in our certain kind of self-concern self-reoccupation
it could be that it's a preoccupation with my emotions my feelings my reactions
that might look like our cons our preoccupation is with someone else
someone else is suffering and we're really concerned about them but what fuels it is our own distress
and if we're distressed there is a way in which that has its roots in our
self-concern self-preoccupation or some idea that that we have to take my
distress somehow seriously or something it's a complicated ecology this inner life of
ours and the degree to which known and unknown it's it's centered on
self-concern a self-attachment is actually quite large
so as we begin to as we as this practice maybe any spiritual practice deepens and
deepens and we're calming and calming and letting go and relaxing the
self-concern relaxing the anxieties and fears relaxing the desires we have
relaxing the hates all activities that take energy and take stress and takes
effort to some way even though it might seem like it's effortless that there's
no me behind it is there it's actually as we settle in quiet we see the effort
the energy that goes into it and that that effort can be softened can relax we
can begin to slowly stop it's not easy to do it's a slow process
but the goal the treasure that's found in the end of that process is an
experience of living a lie being alive which is not a self-concerned
not self-preoccupied I like the word preoccupied so really stressing that there's something extra going on in the
self-concern there's an attachment there's a tightening there's a a drivenness there's a
preoccupation and um and um and so then at some point what
becomes uh what becomes here for us is uh attention awareness presence
heartfulness that doesn't have the limitations that come with
self-preoccupation that doesn't come with and as we're less self-preoccupied
it's a simultaneous movement or a parallel movement is to not be
preoccupied with others and some people feel like they're supposed to be preoccupied rather as an
expression of their compassion their care it's it's an expression of their love and of course they're supposed to
be loving well yes but not all the time we're not required to do it 24 hours a day
it's okay and you can feel the okayness in meditation as we deepen to it's okay
to let go of all preoccupations all the effort to think can be concerned
with others and oneself and so there's a uh certainly
selfishness begins to dissolve but also a parallel kind of movement that to make
up an English word um other uh
other ishness where we're kind of caught up in creating others and the view of others
the interpretation of others are and there's so much of this otherishness that goes on where we are projecting
idea of other people and what they need and what they want and and I saw that through with raising
my children that I projected onto them when they were small kids going to school
my own challenges that I had at school and so as they got to be certain age and
went into the playground some of the terrible things that happened to me in the playground I got worried for them
they were going to have the same thing and I have to protect them and make them safe and it was a project you know to them it
was an utterishness of of making them into something that had more to do with
my thoughts than it was about who they were and so this softening and relaxing of
otherishness of uh and selfishness is uh one of the gifts of meditation
and it isn't that we're abandoning ourselves or abandoning others it's the opposite now there becomes kind of a
universal uh sensitivity Universal care that can be there that's not restricted
in any any particular direction and so as we have compassion for others
and are looking into studying the aspiration the desires we have for the alleviation of suffering
one possibility is that we check in and see is our compassion impartial is it is
it available to everyone is it unlimited is it not restricted it are we not are
we not being selfish sometimes there's a lot of selfishness in compassion some people do it
seemingly for themselves more than for the other to overcome our own distress
about people suffering we try to fix them or help them and sometimes where other-ishness we're
kind of making another projecting another and our care for others is more
still caring for ourselves because we're caring for that projection that we have of what's happening to the others and
what they're suffering might be like and so this deeper way which is not
actively concerned for self or others but 100 available
to be responsive and that's that is a kind of universal
compassion Universal aspiration that is possible and it has the expression that we're
caring for everyone concerned and so what's the best for everyone
concerned is a is part of this Universal care Universal aspiration of compassion
and it's important because if we're part of a group a couple or a family or a
neighborhood or work team or something things will go much better if if we're
not singling out one person to be or some some subgroup of people who are the
ones we have to care for the most and we have to kind of be selfless to ourselves or put aside other people's needs and
situations including our own so we can care for others everyone's equal player Everyone's an
equally Justified for our care and I know of
families where the parents
sacrifice themselves in unhealthy ways for the purposes of their children and
the children grew up kind of askewed because they didn't understand that part of what it being in a group is in a
family is is to compromise is to care for everyone to include everyone as
important players and having a role and respecting everyone's kind of needs and
finding a way to compromise or balance everyone's situation and if children learn that from an early
age then it's just second nature but if the parents poor all their concern into
their children without any concern for themselves the children get kind of a
skewed message so that that's what I use that as an example to all kinds of situations
and so this idea that we have you you know as we have a desire to alleviate
suffering to investigate to look at the nature of that desire the nature of the
aspiration and can the aspiration be Universal
where we're actually caring for everyone concerned and there might be a kind of a priority
given to someone who is the suffering the most but not at the expense of everyone else
in the room everyone else in the in that kind of connected and I think one of the brilliant things that we can do is to
take the time not to rush to compassionate action unless there's a real need for immediacy
but rather to take the time to look around and say what's best for everyone
here how do we care for everyone how does everyone how to go forward here
to relieve and the suffering that everyone has in this situation
and what I'd like to believe is the when we stop and do that kind of wider care
wider inclusion of everyone as our Circle of Care that this is actually a powerful
medicine for everyone involved the people who are suffering the most to
feel and sense that it's not just about their own suffering but there are others here also so that their Circle of Care
opens up so that they're not tripped up by excessive self-concern themselves for
their own suffering which is maybe horrible but it uh there's a way in which that's
maybe maybe beneficial for others to kind of include others in the picture if
they can and uh and appreciate that others are being cared for too and the medicine of universal aspiration that
um is not just a the universal aspiration that's the medicine but the
inner freedom of non-preoccupation non-attachment
non-prioritization non kind of
you know the absence of partiality that I think can be inspiring in its own
medicine for the suffering of the world so um
so to um so what I've to Summer summarize is that
you have Universal aspiration it's less it's a little bit less than
I'm suggesting that we try to have as a policy to have Universal aspiration for
all beings but rather we the practice is to
release ourselves from partiality release ourselves from limiting
we are our care and our love and um and the byproduct of that I hope
will be at Universal care a universal availability for compassion to be
concerned with the welfare and well-being of everyone who's in that Circle that uh that we're involved in
this moment whether it's a circle of two people a circle of four or 15 or
a hundred thousand you know whatever seems like the right you know you know range it seems appropriate for their
circumstance so um
thank you and may your Circle of Care be Broad and wide in all directions
and then we'll continue tomorrow thank you