so welcome um I'm Matthew
how are you doing maybe a little thumb pull
down okay okay pretty cheery for the YouTube folks FYI
um yeah happy to uh to sit with you
I tested negative by the way just in case you're looking at me like I'm a viral Vector uh just uh
so this is uh from from uh was listening to a talk from ajin sajito
and transcribed and you know edited down a
few things and I'll read uh just three three paragraphs here
so uh and uh in the Thai Forest tradition
um and has been in robes for close to um
50 years and I I recently sat sat with him
so um says I was visiting my elder brother yesterday his Alzheimer's and
also Parkinson's Parkinson's disease incapacitates the body and Alzheimer's incapacitates the
mind so this is obviously a very well yeah
it's a dumb messenger all this can break down
the physical body can break down the mental faculties can break down
still somebody is still in there he's unable to communicate hello okay
nothing happens just throw some words in nothing happens
obviously words aren't going to work here right so I just bring awareness over the whole
situation I make bodily contact I start gently massaging a leg holding a hand massaging
his hand sense of contact and then spreading awareness over a situation with good
will after about 10 minutes he starts to speak can't make much sense but at least
you can see he's encouraged to come out and at least start to say
something and I'm just listening encouraging and then I just start chanting metasuta
just radiating loving kindness this other hand comes over grabs hold of
mine three hands length together just chanting slowly met the sahagatena
you could feel the sense of ease and love and happiness because the energies The Body Energy the heart energy is
linking up so even though the thinking brain dissolves breaks down you can still have
a sense that of you know that I'm meeting this person there is a meeting place here
it's also not up to me to make something happen you know I cannot cure this person I
cannot change this person there's nothing I can do or say however much I like to
but he can still receive presence can still receive energy and still receive
love and kindness and as we're sitting there for about an hour or so
and then gradually his hand became stronger and stronger
you know this is poignant but also something very satisfying
because one feels the sense of wanting to do something being a bit worried wanting to help
feeling what can I do just relaxing
everybody gets to the end of their life sometimes people get to the end of their
mind before they get to the end of their life but that doesn't mean you abandon them
just made you abandon your wish that they'd be something other than the way
they are right now and then you can meet them you can start to do
that with people that are dying but it's more like you have to practice
that with people who are living rather we're been trying to make them
some way or another or you know you just hold with awareness
and loving kindness and Trust they will see that and the best will come out of that
so here is this uh
this this monk who has
stripped so much out of his life
and I heard him say that uh just in the the place he was staying he
just kept the lights down right because it didn't really want
the world always constantly jumping out at heart mind it was just like very
renunciate life dedicated to the cultivation of chitta
hard mind and and so much has been stripped out
but relating relationship
remains right care
remains and we talk so much about what is shed
on this path and and a lot is shed but we also keep a lot too
and there's something poignant to me about um
that that that ajan was speaking about his his brother
right this kind of the deep
mystery of the karmic bonds that we call family
right that kind of certain kind of reverence that that we have culturally for family and I I think for a good
reason for the most part but the kind of mystery of just being uh
being of them but distinct from them being a kind of expression you know so
much shared sharing their pain sharing their potential
sometimes we are the next generation is just a kind of
expression of the potential that was unlived in the prior generation
so we do our best to nurture the seeds of uh wisdom and love
that we've inherited and uh
was teaching college students this past week and um
one of them came up to me at the end of a lecture and said you know I'm uh
I'm practicing mindfulness I'm practicing mindfulness but I'm still afraid to die
20 or something and so yeah everybody gets to the end of
their life and that's a
a dhamma messenger classically something to wake us up everybody gets
to the end of their life and there are implications for how we live
of course their implications for how we live and
usually mortality you make mortality Salient in the mind and it it does a lot
of bad things to the heart generally when you meet it without wisdom Without
Love it can you see like so much of uh
the derangement of our culture is a function of unconsciousness around death
and the the fear around that can be marshaled for the most nefarious
purposes and generally it deforms our mind
but it need not need not it is a dhamma messenger
but in order for it not to make us more brittle
we have to take it into the heart and uh
away treating it as a dhamma messenger
Bertrand Russell said the world is vast that our own powers are limited
if all our happiness is bound up entirely in our personal circumstances it's difficult not to demand of life
more than it has to give and to demand too much
is the surest way of getting even less than is possible
and so as I hear this hear this talk you know it's like
okay let this um this dhamma messenger let it just like
let the finitude sensitize me to goodness
sensitize me to goodness that is one thing death can do is it sensitizes us
to goodness because it's all that matters then
is like the only currency that matters even a little and it is not a perfect consolation
but it is the only one as far as I can see
and a lot of uh a lot of the Dharma path is just becoming progressively
sensitized to goodness in oneself in others
and we just get more and more responsive to that we take our cues from goodness
we live in this kind of open feedback loop where as a Dharma practitioner
everything is teaching us right as uh that famous phrase from Majin Shahs
there is a lot of intimacy and illness you know like we just come to depend on
the kindness of others and we can live a whole life as a kind of aspiring to be
an Island Independent but in the end
the nurse will get us the brother will get us
and we come to uh rely in one way or another on loved ones
on caretakers and so the the kind of intimacy of the
body breaking down and the the kind of love expressed through the touch
is moving to me and so ajan arrives and the words they
just don't go anywhere we know that experience the words just don't go anywhere
as if uh like words words are the wrong language
now sometimes they're not sometimes words can be medicine and um
I know I think ideally the kind of talking about the Dharma is supposed to
be medicine but um
even that's not even so much about the words the words are just kind of a
thread from one body to another a thread
from one body to another making love visible in some way
that's the function of the words
and so in this case though
words don't go anywhere and we we see that and
often words don't go anywhere even though they feel words stories
conceptualizations can feel like the realest thing in the world
you know amidst the the
yeah in the in the kind of bubble encased within the The Narrative of our
life words feel more real than anything
and it can feel like happiness happiness is about kind of
rearranging the puzzle pieces of thought in our minds
and uh believe in the Dharma can get heady we
can get heady about what we're doing here and get kind of lost and Dharma abstractions
be tracking Dharma progress in this uh highly conceptualized way
and um and so the Dharma in a sense like our
our self model just recruits the Dharma as another way of reifying itself
as another way of becoming all too knowing
the kind of motto we bring to the world the self and other the Dharma gets kind
of recruited in as a another
facet of of this all too familiar story
and so we're encouraged to stay connected to
the body which in a sense is a we both know the body
but it's also we're connected to a certain kind of not knowing there's a
certain kind of openness where we're being asked to kind of put down all the familiar tropes and stories
and lines and words and
just inhabit pour the awareness into the body
we try to practice sometimes in a disembodied way but then we just get
kind of mired in complexity Cormac McCarthy from Blood Meridian says
uh a man's at odds to know his mind because his mind is uh he has to know it with
he can know his heart but he don't want to rightly so
that's not to look there we could quibble with that last part you
know and I will you know right but yeah sometimes to know to no
one's mind that all we have is our mind and we just kind of get lost in complexity
and uh and so we breathe we breathe
when we reconnect with our body
and our heart of course I I do get the sentiment of best not to look there
um but uh but we can feel into that we can feel
into that and that feels a little bit less like the mind trying to know itself in a more
like uh oh yeah this body can be felt the surges and since the the goodness the
sensitivity the receptivity can be sensed of the heart
and so the path the path really begins when we feel uh feel the Dharma in our
bones so our John's rubbing his leg holding
his hand massaging his hand very intimate and very embodied you know
when words fail okay embodiment heart energy transmitting
a Kind of Love through touch and
speaking another language rather than words
and we are kind of mammals you know
and touched as a lot to our system a lot
of times we don't don't even know you know so there's sort of like
oh yeah just like hard to even track what that does to the heart but there's
something soothed at a deep level in a gentle loving touch
a nine-year-old nephew tried out for a kind of Elite baseball team at least a
lead for nine-year-olds and uh did not make the team
close but did not make the team his best friend with whom he has some competitive
rival risk relationship made the team this is
just the world collapsing you know kind of for a nine-year-old and um
and so I'm like it's just you know quite upset and I'm like I'm trying like every
therapeutic way in to try to sue them you know it's like okay taking like all
these different attacks and uh and then uh that's uh you know I'm just
I'm just I knew it wasn't really working and you but I like trying what else am I supposed to do okay trying trying and he
says can you please stop talking
and uh okay okay and so he's got this swing in his room that like hangs down
from the ceiling and it's like this like drape of like nice Fabric or something
you just kind of get fully in it and you just you're just swinging from the ceiling and
it's like so I'm sitting there he's a kind of encased in this this uh this
swing and I'm just like yeah they'll just pushing you know
like simple simple kind of touch movement
things settling down
this is uh Nick Cave rate recent uh book which is describing the kind of
aftermath of uh the the death of his 14 15 year old son
died in an accident and um and he's like in you know in
morning hiding some kind of embryonic process after this
and then he finally goes out you know actually leaves his home so says uh
uh in conversation with somebody he says as far as the fans were concerned they saved my life
it was never never in any way an imposition and what you remember ultimately are the
acts of kindness the small but Monumental gestures
so vegetarian takeaway place in Brighton where I would eat sometimes I went there for the first time I had
gone out in public after Arthur died there is a woman who worked there and I
was always friendly with her just the normal pleasantries but I liked her I was standing in the queue and she
asked me what I wanted and I felt a little strange because there was no acknowledgment of anything
she treated me like anyone else matter of factly professionally
she gave me my food and I gave her the money and she gave me back my change as
she gave me back my change she squeezed my hand purposefully
it's a quiet act of kindness the simplest most articulate of gestures
but at the same time it meant more than all that anybody had
tried to tell me you know because of the failure of language in the face of catastrophe
and then ajan starts chanting chanting that that
and sometimes you know when you've done a lot of chanting when you've
said the metasuta when you've done the practice wherever it's like those those words they they kind of have this
channel in the heart mind and they sort of like evoke
goodness and such a fully full-hearted full-bodied way
and um and there is this sense of uh
of kind of plugging into this stream of Dharma love
it's like how far is that how far is that stream right now
part of why we practice is so that it feels very close at hand
very close at hand all it takes this is tilting the heart a little bit
and all those years all those hours of practice of rehearsing love
comes back
met sahagatena the Mind Made vast the Mind heart and mind made vast with love
and this is really a love that that can't go wrong
not so many species of love that can't go wrong a lot of kinds of love can go wrong
sideways in one way or another but this is a love that that cannot go
wrong because it does not depend on samsara being arranged in a particular way
and so the sense of actually plugging into that
and um and the sense that there's no
no unfolding that invalidates this love no
pain possible that that reduces it
and so it said it can't you know it's measure less it's measureless
and to be met in that way that's a true meeting that's a true meeting that's
heart heart resonating with heart and um
and how How Deeply we belong to to be met in that way because it gives
space for us in our you know
in our strength and our limitation and our confusion and pain and love make
space for all of it all of it to feel like yeah there's no line being
drawn between what belongs and doesn't
and so his brother's grip gets stronger and
and then goes on to say that was poignant but satisfying poignant but
satisfying it's not up to me says to make something
happen I can't cure this person cannot change this person nothing I can do or say however much I'd
like to one feels the sense of wanting to do something being a bit worried
wanting to help him feeling what can I do just relaxing just relaxing
it can feel so terrible not to be able to do
something it's almost like we don't give that enough
credit just how bad it feels to to want to help and to be to run into the
limitations of one's control and
in some relationship some relationships that are close I I feel like almost
almost haunted by the limitations of my power to free the other of suffering
and um and I see you know
I see the greed aversion delusion
and it might be subtle in them but there's something about it that I can just
almost not bear yeah it's way more evocative in them than it
is in me and um and there's a way in which for
when we love another person their suffering becomes a almost tragic
and um to be empathically connected to them and
to be to face the limitations of one's power which are nearly complete
to free them of that that's hard to open to
and the impulse to actually change them to
change the situation for me even just in kind of microwaves
like it just reaches a certain kind of fever pitch of just like
intolerance of the other's pain or the way it kind of like spins me
and um you know growing up it's like
the suffering of a of a parent or caretaker or something
that's not a cause for compassion that's like an existential threat right to see
very clearly the limitations of of of the person who's who's
protecting you right to see the kind of
omnipotence just uh dispelled you know that's that's
haunting kind of and somehow it feels like that
imprinting then that way of relating to the suffering of loved ones has like
carried through even in contact grown up now right but um I don't depend in the
same ways but the same kind of spinning happens right
in different kinds of relationships and then the kind of intolerance of
their pain can prompts me into action some kind of
intervention that masquerades as compassion but is
definitely not compassion has got a impulsive driven feel to it
afraid and the kind of white hot core of
willfulness willfulness this kind of frustration when we cannot change
another we cannot deliver them from suffering
and and the the kind of entanglement of that
the ways that in the kind of close relationships it's it's so easy to
become over identified with the pain of the other
and empathy care compassion it's fatiguing when the pain of the other
and one's own pain becomes indistinguishable
right I think as a Carl Rogers said um something like around
therapeutic exchange accurate empathy to feel the pain of the other as if it were
your own without losing the as if condition without losing the as if condition we
lose the as if condition and then it's emotional contagion and
we're just swimming in it right we're over identified with it
but um here we we kind of have to distinguish
the pain of the other from one's own pain otherwise we both drown
it's not up to me to make something happen
it's like a lot of relief can come in that there's
a certain grief maybe in seeing the limitations of our power
the inevitability of suffering right but there's
there is a
there's some relief and I remember when I heard that line when I was listening to the
talk it was just like oh yeah something let down in my own heart
and so we've really got to find a way to
to keep our heart open even amidst our powerlessness
to keep the heart open even amidst helplessness
which has got to be among the most kind of
you know aversive postures for a human to be in
but um a lot of relief in giving up on change
sometimes we nurture change and sometimes we give up on it
and on the far side of our compassion can either be despair or equanimity
equanimity and so compassion is love in the face of
suffering and maybe we think Equanimity is somehow not caring what do you mean how do you
give up what do you mean you give up yeah we give up
that feels like the end of love but it's actually just another species of love
it's love in the face of the endless ungovernable nature of samsara
that our care can never fully cure the first Noble Truth
and the kind of a certain kind of cutting through the grandiosity and the resistance and the
impulsivity around it okay how do I stay open how does my heart
remain open even amidst the limitations of my power on the other side of my willfulness on
the other side of my control
and so once you start to do this with people that are dying it's more like you have
to practice with people who are who are living who are living
um
the the Neurosis I feel like we get into trouble when
kind of the Neurosis of one collides with the Neurosis of the other
that's real pain right when our our kind of clinging clingings tangle up
right and so we do the best we can to clear our heart
um and to um so that the pain of the other does not
resonate and reverberate with our wounds but with our love
and um maybe in this way some of our
some of our the care that we feel becomes more bearable
less impulsive less uh a kind of way of engineering the shaping
the heart of the other and is a it becomes a kind of love that can't go wrong that's always going to uh
be of service the best will come out of that love and kindness and Trust they
will see that and the best will come out of that the best will not be perfect but the
best will come out of that
I offer this for your consideration
please uh take what's useful leave the rest behind
okay