I'm gonna talk about suta majama Nakaya 128.
as it's interpreted by ajan tsuchito no sujato
let me make sure I got that right yeah
and um so and I'm using his translation right I don't know Paulie so
there's interpretations of interpretations right and I'm so I'm
just sharing freely as I read through this suit uh kind of the things that
came up for me and what it made me think about and there's things that are both
directly said and then there's things that are demonstrated in the way that the story is told
and I think it's really worthwhile to um recognize that the Buddha taught not
just in the words that he shared but in the way he behaved
so for me and actually have two there's so much in the suit so there's I'm
planning to do one pass of it tonight and or this morning and another pass tomorrow night
um focusing on today the aspects of relationship and community and practice
and tomorrow on the Corruptions or the things that get in the way of community and and practice and the the suta is
called translated as Corruptions and um
Corruptions um let me see
there's a I don't see where it is right now but um the translation of Corruptions is essentially things that
don't belong that are kind of come into play and just kind of corrode or disrupt
um make make problems so I think because of the way I want to
share the suits I think that I'll give you first a whole just a brief summary of the whole Arc of the story
and then as I go through you'll have a map of sort of where where we're going
and hopefully it'll help you keep track and also as I'm saying I was reading and
rereading the suits on noticing what was coming up for me what was I noticing and I invite you to do the same
I invite you to be curious and interested in how your own mind responds what what associations your mind makes
and along the way I'll be opening up and inviting you to share if you want to share any of
your own personal reflections I think we have an opportunity to to
learn from each other in this way so the summary of this suta
is that um the Buddha goes out of compassion to
a Sangha that's in in conflict and when he gets there he tries three
times to Halt the argument and to um you know engage masuta
but he doesn't succeed so he moves on and then he visits a single meditator
um where he connects with him asks him how he is and then teaches him dhamma
instructs and inspires him and then he moves on to
um another a park where there are three companions living together and what is
described as with love living together with love
loving themselves and he asked them how they're doing in a
number of ways and I'll go into the details later right and you know are they getting along
are they living in harmony and um and then when he finds out yes they
are indeed he goes on to ask about their practice and how they are progressing in
their own meditation practice and then he teaches him about his own
experience with difficulties or blocks or Corruptions to his meditation
to help them find a way free from the Corruptions that are arising in their own practice
so you know right away we see the Buddha goes he's responding out of compassion
to a Sangha that's in conflict
at the time that he was asked to go he was staying in a monastery
and so we can kind of assume that I assume that it was
um you know he was being able to meditate practice that he had food and shelter and companions who were also
practicing and there was a mendicant who from
kasambi came and told the Buddha that at kasambi they
were arguing quarreling disputing and continuing continually wounding each
other with barbed words
so mendicant is someone who practices relying chiefly or exclusively on alms
to survive in principle mendicans you know there's a religion the multiple religious orders
but they have little property right and um many instances they've taken vows of
poverty in order that all their time and energy could be expended on practicing
their respective Faith preaching and serving Society
so a kosamba where they're quarreling and brawling and in deep disputes this
is another translation they say stabbing each other with verbal daggers
they're clearly not doing the other parts of being a mendicant right
so to help kind of provide a contrast I'm going to reference a different suta
where someone describes the Buddhist community of practitioners
when he comes upon them and he says because he's he's
referencing first this visitor how he's seen other community communities like
kambasa and then he he comes to the Buddhas and he says but here
I see biku smiling and cheerful sincerely joyful
plainly delighting with their faculties fresh living at ease unruffled
subsisting on what others give abiding with a mind
as aloof as a wild steer and then
um so just this huge contrast in what happens
in communities based on how we're practicing and living with each other right
so the Buddha has gone to kombasa he
consented in silence when he asked he just got up and went
and when he arrives nasuta says
he said enough mendicants stop arguing quarreling and disputing
the Buddha repeats this three times
and each time the I'm assuming it's the mendicant that
came to ask him to come it doesn't say explicitly that mannequin says to the Buddha wait
sir let the Buddha the lord of the Dharma remain passive dwelling in Blissful meditation in
present life we will be known for this arguing quarreling and disputing
so three times the Buddha says you know enough
stop quarreling stop disputing and three times the mannequin responds
wait wait you know you live passive dwelling and Blissful meditation
another thing to notice about you know the Buddha comes and immediately tells them you know wait and stop and they
don't listen is there's no reception for the Buddha there's no greeting of the Buddha when
he arrives there's no listening to the Buddha
so in the morning the Buddha robed up and took his bowl
and robe and entered kasambi for alms
and after the meal on his return from alms round he set his lodgings in order
taking his bowl and robe he recited these verses while standing right there
so the Buddha is quite Direct
he's in this in these phrases like a poem that he he speaks
he doesn't mince words it's very direct and I think this is also a teaching Buddha is not being
unkind he didn't yell he didn't kind of argue himself he just asked them to stop
three times so he's preparing to leave with clarity
and he says when many voices shout at once no one thinks that they're a fool
while the song is being split none thought another to do be better
adults yes adults pretending to be astute
they talk their Words Right Out of Bounds they blab at will their mouths agape and
no one knows what leads them on and then he he says in quotes yeah they
abused me they hit me they beat me they robbed me
for those who bear such a grudge hatred never ends
he repeats they abused me they hit me they beat me they robbed me
for those who bear no such Grudge so who don't go on in this way hatred has an
end for never is hatred settled by hate
it is settled by love this is an eternal truth
there's um a similar verse in the dhamapada
so I'll reference it here to sort of kind of you know Savor in this teaching
a little bit and it includes this explicit teaching
on how the mind precedes what happens so all experiences preceded by mind led
by mind made by mind speak or act with a corrupted mind and
suffering follows as the Wagon Wheel follows the hoof of the ox
all experiences preceded by mind led by mind made by mind
speak or act with a peaceful mind and happiness follows like a never departing
shadow hatred ends never ends through hatred by
non-hatred alone does it end this is an ancient truth
so we go back to his poem and he says
others don't understand that here we need to be restrained
but those who do understand this being clever settle their conflicts
so something in here is really important to me which is we do things are going to come up
when we're living and practicing in community we're going to have conflict differences
and so what he's saying is Well Be restraint be restrained about how you respond to
that conflict and and settle so being clever wise
settle your conflicts so the Buddha is encouraging us to deal
directly with conflict he's not saying be passive try and be nicey nice happy
happy all the time right in this he's implying and that it's natural for difficulties to arise
in relationship but that hatred and and operating from
hatred will not help right it won't end the conflict
another thing about this is the being clever so the Buddha
is emphasizing wisdom when he's using the word clever
wisdom is praised as the most the most right the wisdom that is praised the
most is not knowledge that one is acquired it's not being able to recite
the texts or tell people things the wisdom that is praised is a form of
penetrative seeing directly into one's aspect of life comes from the application of the
teachings right comes from experience in in the Buddha's teaching wisdom plays
a central role in the path to liberation not only does it lead
to Enlightenment right it is a result of enlightenment
so you know the Buddha the Buddha is really
um kind of referenced earlier the people
who were you know debating and talking and thinking they're right right that's getting caught and ethicative Views it's
but you know your assertions your intellect versus somebody else's and that's not the kind of the wisdom that
the Buddha is encouraging us to cultivate
so back to the poem the Buddha says Breakers of Bones and
taker of Life thieves of cattle horses wealth those who plunder the nation
even they can come together so why on Earth can't you
and then he goes on to say something else that's really important two lines I'll read one at a
time if you find an alert companion a wise and virtuous friend
then overcoming all adversities wander with them joyful and mindful
if you find no alert companion no wise and virtuous friend then like a king who
flees his conquered realm wander alone like a tusker in the Wilds
so again this is goes back to the Buddhist like he went to this community
in Conflict tried to help there was no wisdom there no engagement
there so he left he's going to go off on his own
and sometimes we need to do the same the one of the things about what the
Buddha did that I I think is really important is three times he invited them
to stop three times and I think this is also a teaching
right like sometimes how how often do we either keep trying and keep trying and keep
trying and we're beating our head against you know the wall and other times when do we walk away too soon
and I like this idea of trying three times it's a nice you know it's a nice
number and so like there's this balance here we're not just coming in and expecting
everything to be okay and fine right away but you know we try and we try we try again
but at some point maybe after three times we recognize okay
they're not here this this this notion of the king with a conquered Kingdom right it's like the boot is sort of like
the king of the Dharma right and then this little Sangha there's there's no Dharma happen
right there's there's a lot of conflict
and so he leaves he doesn't try and take them with him he doesn't try you know it's just okay I'm
moving on and at the same time when we find you
know Wise companions right it's such a blessing like it's such a blessing to come here and to sit with you all
to feel the support of sitting in community to go on a retreat and have the
incredible support of watching everybody else move their bodies and sit in
Stillness and quiet there's so much support that happens in that realm and there's times for
practice alone too
another way you know modern term for what the Buddha is demonstrating might
be the word boundaries he had boundaries he had good boundaries right his own
clarity about what he was willing to do and not do where he could help where he couldn't
help
maybe this is a moment to ask is anyone else having other associations or
thoughts that you would like to share it's fine if not just an open invitation
Martha will have a microphone right up there yeah if anyone has um anything else they're
kind of noticing or picking up on nope yeah oh great okay we got two
people thank you
I was just thinking um one reason for the difference or for the
conflict is a real attachment to the Views a real attachment to
you know not necessarily being right but they're what their thoughts are in their
argument and uh unwilling to let that go yeah absolutely
you can you pass it to her in the corner foreign
I'm not sure what I want to say but like okay
I'm not sure what I want to say um but I really appreciate this talk
uh it's resonating with me it's this
uh ego knowing I'm right yeah in a relationship or something and
then uh uh I'm just really hearing like no
so thank you beautiful beautiful
over here
I had a spiritual advisor many years ago who had a phrase that has helped me a
great deal in my life and that is being right is a disease
[Music] very very diseaseful
yeah great oh I love it I so appreciate you sharing
these Reflections because you know when we when we study together when we
practice the Dharma together you know there's there's so much wisdom and everyone is
going to see a little different or approach it and feel it a little differently and and that's that's
engagement with the practice which is the most important thing is to engage with the teachings to feel
them to allow them to to kind of guide you and and for you to notice too what comes
up in relationship to them another
um part that I wanted to reflect on because I think some people get stuck in
communities or relationships because they don't want to be alone
it's hard to leave people and you know I'm not endorsing quickly
leaving relationships right obviously but it's also important to remember that
it is possible to find joy and well-being when awareness is your
companion when you get to be the Tasker the elephant in the in the woods walking
confidently if you have you know the the elephant is kind of so you know the
biggest to Beast right in the wild so they have a certain you know gravity to
them and strength to them they're also slow and you know said to
have good memories and you know there's a lot of reasons I think the Buddha probably referenced elephants but
um you know if we're walking in that way in the world with that confidence
instead of fear it's easy much easier to find joy and a
sense of well-being
so the final line in this poem from the Buddha is it's better to wander alone
there's no fellowship with fools wander alone and do no wrong at ease
like a tusker in the wild foreign
the Buddha moves on and he goes to visit
a mendicant named bagu in a village
so as the Buddha approaches bagu saw the Buddha coming off in the distance
so what did he do he spread out a seat and placed water for washing the feet
when the Buddha came he sat on the seat spread out for him
and washed his feet and then bagu bowed to the Buddha and
sat down to one side so I mentioned this earlier but this is
quite a contrast right how the Buddha is being received in this setting is very very different
and I wonder what what in our modern day times what's the equivalent
of greeting someone in this way a respected teacher you know laying out a seat putting water
for the feet to wash well what might we do what do we do when someone we care
for we respect and maybe even Revere comes to visit
thank you you know I
offer them tea water to drink invite them to have a seat somewhere
comfortable ask them if they need food they're hungry
welcome them please make yourself at home please feel free to use my bathroom important right
and then if somebody really important comes I love the images of um
the Dalai Lama when he goes to visit places because the Dalai Lama
you know wherever he stays this is not so much necessarily the greeting there
is always this intense greeting actually I have a story about him greeting so he went to IMS in Massachusetts and Sharon
Salzburg was there in the back of the audience standing but she had a broken leg so she was on crutches and pretty
miserable and the Buddhas are not the Dalai Lama is coming with this you know whole
Entourage of people and security guards and all of this stuff and
but the Dalai Lama arrives and he looks around at all the people here and he
zeros right in on Sharon Salzburg who's standing in the back she says looking
pretty miserable and he goes right back to her and ask her are you okay how are you
dear that's so beautiful right so not only you know are we welcoming him when he
comes but he's that's caring for us right the Dalai Lama and then when he
leaves a place so if he stays at a hotel so I'm told these are stories right but
I believe them before he goes he has all of the people who work at the hotel
everyone who has served him stand in a long line and he goes and he
grabs their hand or bows to every one of them one at a time
I also heard a story about someone who was in an airport and that they were with a couple other
people waiting in some Lounge area and the Dalai Lama and his Entourage
walk by pass them right he's kind of they're off in this little corner they
go by and then the Dalai Lama turns around and comes back and Bounds to them so sweet
I have a quote from llama Rod Owens and he says at the heart of radical presence
is simply the act of love loving ourselves loving others and allowing
that love to be deeply manifested in the world in a real clear way
those to me those are beautiful demonstrations
of bringing the world man love to the world manifesting in a real clear way
so the Buddha having sat down washed his feet back to the sutsa
he says to the mendicant I hope you're keeping well mendicant
I hope you're all right and I hope you're having no trouble getting alms food
that's very touching to me this is the you know this amazing
teacher coming giving his presence to you and he asks you if you're doing well if
you're getting enough to eat
so this is like the Dalai Lama right his bowing his taking the time to Express
Care so I asked you how do you greet people how do you welcome them and how do you
how do you express your care for them what do you say
how do you let them know that you sincerely want to know how they are not hey how you doing
with a fine right but maybe something more than that yeah
so bagu says to the Buddha I'm keeping well sir I'm all right and I'm having no
trouble getting alms food nice nice
and when the Buddha hears that he goes on and he educates encourages fires up and
inspires bagu with a Dharma talk
nice like not just you know like Hi how are
you you know but like okay making sure he's okay his needs are met
and then the Buddha goes to practice he goes to the Dharma first he makes
sure you're okay and then he goes to the Dharma because making sure okay is the
Dharma right it's an expression of the Dharma
and so the Buddha educated encouraged I love
this fired up and inspired bagu so he's leaving bhagavuku is practicing by himself it's not described as being with
anyone else so this is you know it's okay right it's okay sometimes practicing alone is just the right thing
so the Buddha offers him the Dharma and then he gets up
and he sets out for the Eastern bamboo Park
at that time at the Eastern bamboo park there were the venerables on Ruda nandia
and Kim Bila please forgive me for buturing their names
and they um so the Buddha is approaching and
the park keeper sees the Buddha coming and clearly doesn't know who the Buddha is and he says to the Buddha
don't come into this park ascetic there are three gentlemen who love
themselves staying here do not disturb them I love that there are three
gentlemen who love themselves staying here that is so sweet
don't bother them
but anruda sees the Buddha so he lets the security person know and says come forth
venerables come forth our teacher the blessed one has arrived
and they go out and receive the Buddhist bowl and robe and one spreads out a seed
and one sets out water for washing his feet so
the Buddha sat on the sea spread out washed his feet and the venerables bowed
and sat down to one side the Buddha says to anruda I hope you're
keeping well on Ruda and Friends I hope you're all right and I hope you're having no trouble getting alms
food so keeping well I just thought I'd kind
of Define talk about what does it mean good or satisfactory
skillfully ably competently adeptly admirably excellently keeping well
all right cinnamon synonyms are satisfactory acceptable adequate good enough
fine reasonable unobjectable suitable right
and then getting alms food right getting so come or to have or hold
to receive and food right nutritious substance that we need in order to maintain life
and growth and they say we're keeping well sir we're all right and we're having no
trouble getting alms food okay now this is now the Buddhist
talking to a community and instead of going right into telling teaching the Dharma the Buddha says I
hope you're living in harmony appreciating each other without quarreling blending like milk and water
and regarding each other with kindly eyes wow
living in harmony appreciating each other living in harmony is you know I pact of
peace and Concord agreement you know consensus Unity
concert mutual appreciation Mutual right experienced or done by each
toward the others reciprocal reciprocated
returned interchangeable common
appreciation recognition and enjoyment of the good qualities of someone or something
valuing respecting prizing cherishing treasuring and admiration
and without quarreling so in the absence of quarreling
blending the action of mixing or combining things together mingle combine Mutiny join
incorporate interflow comex
so there's Something In this passage that sometimes um
people have a little bit of a hard time with and that's this idea of you know blending like milk and water
regarding each other with kindly eyes appreciating each other especially
um when they go on the Buddha asks you know they say indeed sir we live in harmony
as you say love this then the Buddha says well how do you live this way
how do you do that because we need to know right it's not a you know it's great when things are going well but if
we don't know what we're doing to support those conditions it's easy to take them for granted and
stop doing the things that are allowing it to happen to manifest
so they answer that they're doing well and they say in this case sir I think I'm
fortunate so very fortunate to live together with spiritual companions such as these
I consistently treat these venerables with kindness by way of body speech and
mind both in public and in private I think why don't I set aside my own ideas
and just go along with these venerables ideas and that's what I do
though we're different in bodies sir or one in mind it seems to me
so here's where people can get a little bit Tangled Up when they have been in a
situation where they feel like they're constantly doing for others and that it's not reciprocal
I made it very clear I pointed out the way the Buddha is asking and teaching us is not just to give
when it's not reciprocal when it's not valued when it is when it is
um in a way that isn't useful for us should be helpful to me to you and both
right but this community is living in a mutual way they're they're sharing
collectively in this way of relating to each other
and remember you know the Buddha earlier said if your companions aren't treating you well it's better to go practice on
your own right another
um there's this nice quote from a woman named Maria papova and she talks about
um kind of oh
codependence right because I think sometimes people are fearful of being codependent or being taken advantage of
and she says when you love truly love somebody there is no version of reality in which
what is good for them is bad for you no choice they could possibly make that is right for them and wrong for you
nothing they could give you that could make love more complete she says this is a difficult notion for
the Western mind to grasp too easily to mistake for the Psychopathology of codependence
too quick to slip into the tyrannical romantic ideal of merging at its heart
is something else together a kind of transcendent ego dissolution under which
the self ceases to be and becomes being
so back to the Sutra and then the venerables spoke the other two companions and they
added that's how we live in harmony so they're agreeing they're concurring with anruda
the mutuality is here appreciating each other without quarreling blending like
milk and water and regarding each other with kindly eyes
and Buddha says good good anruda and Friends
and then he says but I hope you're living diligently keen and resolute
so diligent having assuring care and Consciousness in one's work and duties
Keen having or shown eagerness or enthusiasm
resolute admirably purposeful determined and unwavering
and they say indeed sir we live diligently and then the Buddha
says again but how do you live this way and anruda answers
in this case sir whoever returns first from alms round prepares the seat and
puts out the drinking water and the rubbish bin if there's anything left over whoever returns last eats it if they like
otherwise they throw it out where there is little that grows or drop it into water that has no living
creatures then they put away these seats drinking water and rubbish bin and sweep the
refractory if someone sees that the pot of water for dishwashing drinking or the toilet is empty they set it up
if he can't do it he summons another with a wave of the hand and they set it up by lifting it with her hands but we
don't break into speech for that reason and every five days we sit together for the whole night and discuss the
teachings that is how we live diligently keen and resolute and the Buddha says good good on Ruda
and Friends so I'm gonna wrap it up
and tomorrow night I'll continue and the Buddha goes on so you can listen to talk if you're
interested or not right but the Buddha goes on and talks about the Corruptions that as they show up in meditation
and he only does that because he sees that they are living
in accordance with the dhamma the way we practice with each other in community affects our meditation
practice so I'll end with a quote by James
Baldwin the longer I live the more deeply I
learn that love whether we call it friendship or family or Romance
is the work of mirroring and manifesting each other's light
gentle work steadfast work life-saving work in those moments when
life and shame and sorrow occlude our own light from our view
but there is still a clear-eyed loving person to beam it back in our best moments we are that person
for another
May the benefit of our practice be for the benefit of all
thank you for your kind attention