greetings good morning good day everyone
welcome Sangha to our 7 A.M meditation and they're met
so I assume that you're able to hear me if there is a few responses in the chat
box that be helpful
I've been feeling very intimate to this morning's and to meditate and
practice together learning together
so thank you thank you for letting me know that I can be heard
so whipping uh using this list of r words in our meditation
in the morning and so uh last a couple of days we went
through relaxing and recognizing
and today in our progression I will add yet another r word
which is releasing and so there is a progression uh in our
meditative process where when our body mind and heart
become more and more relaxed and there's a surface of levels of
agitation began to calm down settle down
it's like the water become the mud began to settle down to the
bottom of the lake and so that allows for Clear seeing
and so we can begin to recognize what's in the field
and recognize the fish swimming or the oysters moving or the sea grass moving
um and just like that when the relaxation deepens there can be a sense of clear
recognition of what's Happening and maybe one of the important aspect of
our practice is to begin to recognize the forces of cleaning grasping and
craving and when those are recognized
at the same time they can be released so releasing
is this a dimension of kind of the movements that come when
there is a clear recognition of the forces of a grasping claiming
and the forces of a grasping cleaning have many forms of manifestations
um I'm using quite abstract a word clinging grasping craving
but in our manifest world we can begin to feel how it feels in our
embodied sense maybe there are certain kind of extra
um instructions somewhere in the body or there may be certain sense of
heightening that can be released
and so today and our meditation a kind of a
if you take on this a tours of three r's relaxing recognizing
and releasing whatever that may be released in terms of
extra tension and grasping and wherever you are it's perfectly fine
and it doesn't mean that you have to be somewhere in this sequence of ours or
the map of ours but wherever you are is wholesome
so let's begin to take a meditative posture
maybe take a first a few moments to just arrive at your seat
arrive in a space you're in
arriving Here and Now
as if you're entering into a monastery within yourself
a monastery of this body mind and heart
a temple Within
maybe there's a metaphor immediately evokes
some sense of irreverence
there may be some sense of quieting
as you enter into the Temple of this body mind and heart
take your seat right here
the initial face of our practice
involves relaxing the body
in however way that might manifest itself
we can do a body scan while inviting relaxation
or you can simply sit
and the offering and invitation to relax
it's helpful to relax the body
if there are certain parts of the body that tends to be
tightened
out something gentle
invitation to relax
relaxing the mind
relaxing the heart
maybe relaxing the mind refers to relaxing the thinking muscles
maybe muscles around skull
neck
some parts of the body were thinking
seem to be associated with
relaxing the heart
gently breathing through the heart
as the body becomes calmer
more is settled
it's natural that mindfulness
began to come to the foreground
present aware
and began to recognize the dancing movements
Sensations in the body
and temperature on the hands
warmth in the Palms
the touch points that have a sense of a pressure and
tingling of the body against the floor chairs
beds
recognizing each experience as they arise and pass away
being a relaxed and easeful field
the recognition comes naturally
there may be a slight height and declarity
our sensitivity
to the experiences in the body in the mind and heart
noticing any Pleasant or unpleasant experiences
arising and passing
and also noticing what happens
as the pleasant and unpleasant experiences arise
they're extra efforting that's happening
and that's a form of grasping
that can be released
my very tightening to the experience the object of your
experience
that is a form of grasping that can be released
are there forms of Leaning into
the objects of experience
that is a form of cleaning
that can be released
simple relaxed
recognition
with a relaxed easeful clear recognition
there arises Stillness
silence Within
yeah the mind that gets caught up in the stories
and the stories be released
and the mind is caught up in judging
comparing evaluating [Music]
of fixing and they'd be released
noticing what it feels like when the extra tension
grasping are released
maybe just a hint of how it might feel like
maybe just a possibility
in the opening of the heart
quieting of the Mind
maybe some sense of a Stillness
away into our Stillness
I go walking into a peaceful Temple
this process of a relaxing recognizing
[Music] and releasing
allow us to settle into deeper aspects of our being
that are otherwise constantly stirred up and hard to get in touch with
as you receive the sound of the Bell to signify the end of the sitting
together you're welcome to abide
in this Monastery Within to receive the stories
from a monastery Within
foreign
[Music]
exploring this theme of a multi-dimensional nature of the Dharma
practice and Dharma practice path and yesterday I shared this story from
Anne Gil's book a monastery Within about how does a 30 year old man who was
overwhelmed by his family life particularly the two children and wanted
to escape to the monastery to find a relief
but the Abba to send him out back out after a seven day solitary retreat
and the officer sent him back out to his family
and told him that [Music] um his family is his best teacher that's
where you'll find spiritual strength and the freedom
and so today will continue a bit in this dimension in
visiting and today and this character in the
story is not someone who was trying to escape from
from the monastery in fact that the person that was having a really good time in the monastery
but Abbas decided again to send him out because that's
his Monastery that's where his Monastery is and so
I'm going to read to this story and then I'll offer some reflections
the brilliant Monk a young man once came to the monastery
to ordain as a monk he had been raised in relatively
fortunate circumstances with easy access to education
capable smart and a friendly he succeeded in most everything he set
his mind to deeply reflective about life he had to study the teachings of the
major religions in his early twenties he decided not to follow the customary path of marriage
and a career leaving behind the life he had known
he ordained at the age of 22 and applied himself to the meditation
and the training the training the monastery provided
disciplined intent and intelligent he made quick progress in the spiritual
practice monks and nuns who had been there for years were in awe of how quickly he
settled into deep meditation within three months of entering the
monastery he experiences the first taste of enlightenment
immediately the app is grabbed the young monk dragged him out the front gate
without explanation kicked him out of the monastery
um later addressing the residence of a monastery the app is explained
the new Monk's realization was genuine and I'm quite happy for him
however in order for him to mature further along
the path of liberation he has to return to the world
to experience more of the difficulties and sufferings of life
to understand all the corners of his own heart
he has to grabble with issues of livelihood family
and community life furthermore
I expect that someday he will be a great teacher
but for this to happen he has to understand all those issues so that he
can have greater compassion and insight into the lives of his students
for this particular Monk this is not going to happen in the
monastery
this Abyss is a pretty dramatic
um
and reading this story I was asking myself you know what is
great Fortune hard to say right for This brilliant monk
um a smooth the fast track was quite nice you know quite nice
for a while and all the life fortunes
quite nice for a while yeah to the Dharma is
much bigger broader richer and deeper
and so having a deep meditative experiences and knowledge is great I don't want to
dismiss any of that yet as the story says
to understand all the corners of his own heart it has to Grapple with the issues of
livelihood family and the communities
and so for me what is pointing at is that The Liberation happens when the
majority of the whole being the holistic being ripens
and so there's no such a thing as a kind of a conditional liberation
you're only liberated if your neighbors dogs stop barking or
when you live in a constant 70 degree temperature the room
or when you can have I know what your favorite food once every
five days and so Liberation is not conditioned
whatever the conditions that we kind of hope that they have to be
into in this way maybe all of us are fortunate enough
that we're practicing Dharma with good enough conditions
in this world maybe having a livelihood a family and
communities to Grapple with and this is the monastery where we can
um engage in a way that has strengthen our
heart and mind and so today in particular I wanted to
maybe say a few words about practicing in the relational field
and so this monk in a rather secluded a monastery may not have had the chance to
deal with wide range of kind of relational field
and so for me I can definitely say that practicing in the relational field
whether it's in the family in local communities or in Dharma communities
I think so rewarding
that the very factor that we're here together in this virtual way we're creating a
virtual community as a social beings so we're living in
the relational field we always influence each other and the being influenced by
each other and so practicing in this relational
Dynamic has many many benefits and so for me I definitely would not
have been able to practice without the support of a communities
we mirror each other and we're married back by each other
and so right now and just knowing your presence right
here in This Global field that work co-creating
so uplifting so inspiring
and so in this way what kind of our practice is a collective path
even while each of us have a unique unfolding but there's a collective path is
unfolding right here in this relational field
and when we're practicing in the relational field it also offers great
opportunities for us to work with the challenges that come along
and we get to open the corners of our heart that are otherwise may not be touched
as soon as we engage in the relational field at the communities
will have will meet differences disagreements
likes and dislikes preferences like this yesterday's story where the 30
year old man so having a very hard time to accept to his older son's behavior and I
consider them as unacceptable unacceptable
and the story didn't make it very detailed elaboration about what the
behavior behaviors might be
how many times we are considering other people's behavior unacceptable
because we had a fixed abuse or something
it's not necessarily that they're doing anything harmful they're just different
I remember for a while when my son was young and he loves to eat with his hands
and I had this idea that it's not clean
but the Buddha ate with his hands there's still Billings of the people on
this planet eating with their hands is that unacceptable
is that I had to change my own view on this
and so how can we live with the differences without harboring
ill will anchor hatred aversion
how can we live with the differences while still being in harmony with each
other this is certainly not easy to do
that it's such a worthy dimension of the practice to open up to
when we become more and more skillful in our relational World relational fields
the benefit will Ripple out into the World At Large
it's such a beneficial Force for the World At Large
so may the collective practicing force that were engaged in together
bring benefit to all beings everywhere
thank you for your attention and deep bows to your practice and your
engagement and I'll see you tomorrow
bye bye everyone