all right well welcome back everyone uh my name is May Elliott this is the last
day in our five day series on the five hindrances and as I've shared getting to
know the 500 suits in our meditation practice is really essential for learning how to settle the mind uh and
five hindrances for those who need a review include sense desire ill will or
aversion restlessness sloth and torpor and doubt so today we'll focus on the hindrance of
doubt this might be doubting the practice or doubting ourselves doubting
our teachers and the traditional antidote for doubt um is Faith or Sada and Pali another
word we might use instead of faith if that word doesn't resonate for you is confidence or we could use the word
trust so in our meditation today we'll be cultivating confidence and Trust in
the practice so let's go ahead and find our meditation posture
um something that allows you to be alert and relaxed
tuning into a sense of the body
my felt sense of being here
setting the intention to land in this moment
and as we begin our meditation today I will actually engage in a reflective practice
um where we're actually allowing the mind to think but we're doing so in a way where we're present and we're
intentional about the topic about the reflection so let's start by taking a moment to
reflect on times the practice has been beneficial for you
maybe it was a time that you were stressed and the practice made you feel
more calm or maybe you were listening to a Dharma talk and had an insight about your practice and
or maybe you had a time where there was a you experienced a beautiful meditation state or there was just some general
a deeper resonance with the truth of the Dharma
so these are all different ways that you might have experienced the fruit of the
practice so take a few moments now to reflect on times where the practice has
been supportive for you
I might consider these we're reflecting on moments that are faith building moments
sometimes there isn't a particular moment for ourselves that inspires our
practice or that brings forth Faith but there's a teacher that we're inspired by
so we can also bring that person to mind how we feel around them or when we listen to them and we can lean on their
faith I might not have faith in ourselves but we have faith in in the teachers
practice so we can bring that person to mind as a representation of faith that might be
the Dalai Lama or it might be from an archetypal figure
the bodhisattva of compassion Kuan Yin or it might be a teacher that you know
or that you listen to online or in person maybe at IMC
maybe Gill somebody that brings forth your faith
so having reflected for a few moments on faith this morning or things that
inspired our practice or ways that we've been benefited by the practice we'll let
this reflection Infuse your your meditation today
um uh with some confidence um and remind you of kind of a sense of
purpose of why we're showing up here there's a reason we're doing this practice
so at this time we'll drop any uh reflecting we're doing um and we'll enter the more formal part
of our meditation practice where we can connect with our anchor so go ahead and
find the anchor that works for you the breath the soundscape the global sense of the body sitting
and just take some time to land
maybe having trust that focusing on your anchor can support you allowing this
practice to support you not needing to think of past or future
no need to engage in planning or fixing or regretting
can put all that down and have confidence
in the freedom that's possible by staying here
as we sit we're bringing just enough energy to the practice to make sure that we can be
here so that might mean bringing enough energy to bring the Mind back to the present if you've gotten lost in
thinking but we're not over exerting we're not
trying to create any special States or make anything happen instead can you trust that whatever's
arising for you in the practice is exactly the teaching that you need to receive
so can you have confidence in your practice uh confidence that the
Dharma is bringing you whatever you need whether that's a challenge or a joy
this is where where the learning is this is the learning Edge
so whatever is arising in your life in your practice is exactly the curriculum you need to
study in order to be free
and then trusting that whatever arises that you can meet that
having faith in yourself that you're able to meet that meeting your life with mindfulness with
kindness with patience maybe we can't do this every moment
one moment at a time we can cultivate these wholesome States in relationship to whatever's happening
staying in this moment with things as they are
can you trust the Dharma to allow things to unfold naturally
and at any point in the meditation today if you find that you're struggling struggling to be here
to stay with your anchor to stay in the body and you find yourself getting lost in thought
or falling asleep you might check to see if any of the other hindrances are present
you might ask the question what's beneath this there's a lot of
thinking what am I feeling right now
maybe sense desire is fueling the thinking mind
or ill will aversion
maybe the mind is like a pond overgrown with moss
filled with Sloth and torpor sleepiness
maybe restlessness is present
so if you notice any of these things can you recognize them clearly shining the light of awareness on them
and then feel them in the body get to know them what are they like
and if there are no hindrances In This Moment
take note of the absence of hindrance this is a really wholesome thing to
notice the Mind free from hindrance that is one of the conditions for the
arising of gladness so if the mind is free from hindrance
see if you can touch into whether there's any gladness in the heart Joy of being free
one analogy from James Beres about faith
lichens growing Faith to the process of learning to swim
so when we first learned to swim we might be thrashing around in the water
struggling striving to just keep our head above water
as we start to gain more confidence in the
water that the water can hold us things become a little bit more useful
you start to trust okay I'm not going to sink here I can trust the water
and in the same way we learn to express the Dharma okay I can trust this I can put faith in
this and eventually
we learned that we can just rest floating on our back in the water
effortless that ease allowing the water to hold us
completely
this is complete confidence in the Dharma
we can rest and Trust the Dharma
let me show up here we make the effort to be here to be mindful
and we can trust
may be selected goodness of our practice benefit all beings
so they may be happy healthy
safe and free from suffering may all beings know happiness and the
causes of happiness
thank you very much foreign
not sure if the fell sound came through for you this time original sound has
been on this week but I'm not sure um I love the term original sound it
sounds kind of like a a Zen koan like
what's the original sound of one hand clapping or something like that
so it's okay well now let's begin for those just
arriving my name is May Elliott and today is the last day of our series on
the hindrances um and today is the teaching on doubt
um so this hindrance can manifest as doubt in the Buddha's teaching like
does this really work well maybe I should have tried Sufi dancing instead or chakra realignment like I don't know
if I'm in the right place um or doubt in your teachers or doubting
yourself doubt in oneself is often often manifests as doubt in one's own capacity
or ability to do the practice uh Philip Moffett says my doubt is the
mother of all the hindrances because it can stop you before you get started
and so doubt is significant in that it has the capacity uh to make us quit
um and it can also stop the energy from our practice and agitate the mind
so some time ago when I agreed to undergo a period of more intensive
meditation training it was in a technique that I wasn't all that familiar with
and in that setting there was actually a good bit of pressure to learn the technique and as you can imagine feeling
pressured to learn a meditation technique is not a very supportive condition for learning to meditate
um so it's no surprise then that um but it was a little stressful right
and so I was wondering you know am I any good at this technique um again am I able to keep up with the
training um so one day I was I was sitting mulling over my sense of
impending insufficiency when something interesting happened so a thought
appeared in the mind and it said this is just doubt
that's it just said this is doubt and it was true all that was happening in that moment was doubt and I went oh
doubt is one of the hindrances um and I know I don't need to take the hindrances personally and so with this
recognition this clear seeing of oh this is doubt it was as though the magic
spell was lifted the naming of Doubt completely released
its power and the whole package fell away um so in that moment I didn't need to
let go of the doubt the mind's inner wisdom Let It Go
now prior to that experience I had many painful spells of Doubt where I was able
to recognize the doubt was present you know the Mind said oh no that's what this is
um but the doubt didn't release upon recognition instead I had to sit with the painful feeling of doubt and sense
it you know feel it in the body recognize and feel so I did the practice that I've been
sharing with you um knowing it's present recognizing it feeling it sensing the sensations in the
body feeling the moon that's present the unfed in a unpleasant feeling tone so
over and over again I practiced recognizing the doubt and feeling the dukkha the suffering of the doubt um
and part of this was really letting the Mind know fully the suffering associated with that form of selfing with that the
selfing of women of Doubt um so you want to zoom in a little bit on
this practice of feeling I've talked about about feeling you know
feeling a hindrance a zillion times this week I want to underline one of the reasons it's so important
um it's through being with the felt experience of the suffering of a hindrance to really being in the body
with the experience of anger or craving or restlessness or doubt that our system
can register oh this is suffering suffering hurts you don't want to do
this anymore I don't need to do this anymore um so through doing this our system learns
to naturally let go of a hindrance um it's kind of like like grabbing a hot
iron skillet if we do it enough times times the Mind eventually learns don't grab the skillet
it hurts and after a while if we touch the skillet and we don't have to think
ah gee I'm grabbing the skillet again I really need to figure out how to like go it's unnecessary instead the hand just
releases it so when I recognize doubt then the experienced upon recognition just you
know evaporated I didn't let go of the doubt it was inner wisdom that let go of the doubt
and that wisdom developed because I had spent so much time clearly seeing
clearly recognizing doubt and feeling the suffering of it you know I had I had touched that hot Skillet enough times so
when the Mind saw that it was coming it released it immediately ouch this hurts I don't want to do it
again so it's not that the release isn't coming from aversion it's coming from
Clarity knowing suffering and the causes of suffering it can release
I mean so when we become deeply intimate with our hindrances when we study our
hindrances fully when we feel them over and over eventually the cheetah the
heart mind learns that they're Duca and the inner wisdom knows to release them
so hopefully that that provides a little more understanding of kind of how this process can unfold and how much Freedom
becomes possible as we really get to know our hindrances um we're much less likely to be hijacked
by them if we know them really well so I'd like to shift now to discuss uh
two conditions for the arising of doubt and both are related one is expectation
and one's a value evaluation and it can go hand in hand so uh Temple Smith says the Insight
teacher he says doubt arises when reality doesn't meet our expectation of
where we should be at as in we think the Mind should be more
concentrated or we think the Mind should have less thinking or we should be less upset about X Y or Z
and when that's not the case when reality doesn't meet our expectations of where we should be at we feel doubt
about ourselves or we doubt the practice or about our teachers so our challenge is to let go of
expectations that we should be anywhere else than where we're at in our practice instead can we trust that what is
arising is coming right on schedule you know this is our new curriculum
well so when we don't meet certain expectations for where we should be at
often we're evaluating our practice you know that was the the second word that I'd mentioned
expectation and evaluation so I'm trying to assess or evaluate whether our
practice is good or bad or productive this tends to just be a cause for
suffering and it's certainly a cause for doubt um so for example in evaluating we might
go gee you know nothing's happening in my practice maybe it's not working
um or you know I'm so distracted in my practice you know I I'm you know I'm really just I'm a bad meditator so
that'd be an evaluation so in both there's this sense of evaluating what's happening there's not
nothing's happening I'm too distracted and and these can be these assessments
these evaluations um can really be a catalyst for the mind to doubt the practice or doubt your
capacity so for those who are wounded out in their practice which is most of us if
not all or it can be really helpful to remember I love that there's no need to
evaluate or judge your progress you can't know where you are on the path for
sure or why something's coming or how um how you can grow from it
so you know if if we go to a guitar lesson for the
first time we don't expect to be a grammy-winning musician the next day and that would be
ludicrous so at the same time you know we sit um but to assume that the mind is going
to be completely still without thoughts and that the heart will be you know radiating loving kindness
you know what that might not be realistic so instead we need to be
really deeply patient with ourselves you know if we're trying to chop wood
with an ax it might take a hundred strikes to split the wood and we need to be patient and if on the 30th strike we
think oh gee this isn't working why bother I'm just going to give up
um you know we're selling ourselves short but we're not not during that you know
if we're we're evaluating the 30th strike we're not aware of the way that
each strike loosens the wood it opens the crack a tiny bit bigger you know
each strike is a causal factor in the eventual splitting of the wood we might not be able to sense that or know that
um but that's what's happening and each strike that's not just splitting the wood a little further but
um we're growing in these secondary qualities who are growing in patients in determination of all of these qualities
these wholesome qualities are being cultivated in these moments where it could seem like the practice isn't
working so on the night leading up to the
Buddha's Enlightenment uh the demon Mara visited the Buddha to prevent him from
Awakening and Mara tried all sorts of things to distract the Buddha and he sent his
armies he tempted the Buddha with beautiful women and Mara's final
ammunition after trying everything he says to the Buddha
who do you think you are that you could be enlightened so Mara's final ammunition is to evoke
doubt who Do You Think You Are
at that moment the Buddha touched the Earth and said with the Earth as my witness I have a right to be here
and he became free so doubt is no small matter
um you know it was the last the last assault for the Buddha before Liberation
on the last effort of Mara and so will experienced out in our practice
it arises early in practice it arises late arises late in practice
so best thing we can do is get to know it so now I want to shift to the antidote
for doubt so as discussed in the meditation the classic antidote for
doubt is faith virtual confidence and we can use any of those words
um you know can we trust that whatever's arriving arising is arising right on time
can we trust that we're right on track and we trust the Dharma can we twist the
best and if you struggle with doubt build a daily Faith practice reflect on
why you're practicing recollect moments in your life when the practice was really beneficial for you
that's what we did at the beginning of the meditation so connecting with moments where the
practice has benefited us it's faith building you know borrow the faith of your
teachers um teachers that inspire you um to see the practice working in them
so you too can have confidence in it I saw a sign a while ago that said um
proceed as though success were inevitable proceed as though successful or
inevitable and so can we trust that if we just show up with mindfulness and
curiosity that the practice is reliable we can have confidence in it we can have
confidence in ourselves can we proceed as though success or inevitable
so lastly I want to remind you that if you're visited by hindrance this isn't a
bad thing it's not a mistake or a problem the hindrances are the medium by which
we wake up so in a way learning to be with the hindrances
um learning to do this without rejection is an act of radical inclusion
we're making ourselves whole because we're not we're not sending we're not
making any parts of ourself uh separate we're not pushing away the hindrances
so we're making ourselves whole such that there's nothing we're rejecting nothing we're excluding there's nothing
left out so I'd like to end with a poem by
izumiashikibu a female Japanese poet from the 10th Century it goes like this
uh watching the Moon watching the moon at dawn
solitary mid-sky I knew myself completely no part left
out I'll read it again
watching the moon at dawn solitary Minsky
I knew myself completely no part left out
thank you very much for your kind attention it's been absolutely wonderful to spend the week with you
uh may your practice with the hindrances be a catalyst for your Awakening
um it's been so lovely seeing your messages in the chat and getting to spend this time uh with a worldwide Sangha take
care everyone