so good morning everyone and oh hello
everyone
and delighted to be here
so it's possible to listen to two things at once to be aware of two things
happening at once we do that with music where there's maybe many instruments playing at once and somehow we hear them
all and can distinguish one from the other and when many of the instruments
in the orchestra may be stopped playing so there can be a soloist we're aware very aware of the
silence Around The Soloist and uh that allows the solos to
be highlighted and accentuated and then the whole Orchestra joins in
again or we can be listening to um something in our kitchen and maybe
listening to someone talking and then suddenly the hum of the
refrigerator goes off and now there's a
silence and we still can listen to our friend speaking and the voice of that friend is
highlighted by that silence that we also can be aware
of so in the mind as I've offered here is that there
are two different operating systems two different categorically different ways
of thinking there's what can be the world of discursive
thought uh distracted thought jumping around thoughts spinning
thoughts um where we have conversations where we
create stories and images and predictions of the future that
relatively abstract and kind of a filling it with the fullness of the
story life that we live and then there uh and that is more
like the hum of the refrigerator and that's possible
sometimes for that to become quiet and it doesn't mean we no longer have any
thoughts but rather thinking changes as nature it becomes thinking from a
different operating system a different place different Source within rather
than the surface mind now it comes from the deep mind and the thoughts there are
generally uh very much to the point very much about the present moment experience
understanding it in a very simple way recognizing it in a very simple way maybe they are very simple instructions
we give ourselves like maybe I should bring more attention now to the end of
my out breath I seem to be a little bit uh holding back from breathing out all
the way what would happen if I breathe all the way out relax the E the exhale
so it can happen almost preverbally it's almost like a sense or intuition uh or could be the very simple
thoughts uh it could be simple thoughts that ask a question and
um uh what would happen now if I tuned into the changing nature of my
experience what would happen or is there any wisdom
now about how I get attached what can I understand from this vantage
point so they can be very very simple very not long discursive just a few
simple words and when practice gets really quiet from that deep place it's
just simple uh thoughts words images of recognition oh that's what's happening
that's what's happening and there's a silence in the surface mind there's a silence in that
Minds that's discussing things or having stories and that can be
Exquisite it might be easier to feel that silence the turning off of the hum of
the refrigerator in the mind if we understand that we're not trying to get rid of all
thoughts thoughts themselves are not the issue it's the source from which we're
thinking are we thinking from Fear are we thinking from anger or desire
ambition confusion are we thinking from the
surface the control tower or are we thinking from a quiet
place where there's no stress place with free of fear free of
anger free of greed ambition free of building up a self
the self is so tied to the story making
mind so it's when we let go of thinking primarily we're letting go of that
surface mind and be attuned to the resulting
silence and quiet a quiet that lets us hear the solo
music that's so beautiful the quiet The Voice the
thoughts the that come from deep within from a peaceful place of no
stress so to assume a meditation
posture gently close the
eyes and taking a deep breath and relaxing on the
exhale relaxing
deeply
letting breathing return to normal and again as you exhale with a
normal like breath relaxing the
body from head to toe
as you exhale relaxing the thinking
mind the control tower any pressure or tension
contraction associated with thinking thinking that has tension as
part of it is part of that surface
mind it's not who we really are in our depths
as you exhale slowing thinking
down so whatever you're thinking you think more calmly
no hurry no reaching for
anything softening the need to
think
and as you're breathing soften your
belly soften your belly and settle
in to the pelvic
floor let your weight be
supported the weight of your torso supported by the
pelvis relaxing as you exhale into the pelv
this and from deep within is there a
place that is calmer more peaceful maybe more
still than how the surface mind
is the quietest most peaceful place
within and that's a relative
concern relatively more peaceful and calm
and in that quieter place within allow yourself to have very quiet
gentle thoughts about staying present with your
breathing quiet thoughts of
recognition that recognizes how the sensations of breathing
change as you
breathe
for
e
okay and as you exhale let
go of your discursive thoughts let go of thoughts which have
to do with stories of past and future
fantasy stories that judge yourself
and
stories that's beenin good and bad right and
wrong let go of the surface thoughts and let go into the depths of
your being the depths of
breathing
where the Deep Mind thinks gentle
thoughts appreciating The
Silence of the surface
mind
e
for
sometimes when the surface mind is quiet
silent quiet enough and we relax let go into the
depths of our
being the thoughts the C ni that we can be aware
of might be pre verbal
pre-image there's a
knowing without words and knowing without
images it might be followed by words or
images but there is a quiet place deep
within and the more peaceful that place
is and the more silence around
it the more we can rest in that pre verbal
knowing
for
e
oh
for
as we as we have been sitting for a number
of minutes now you might see if it's possible to relax
more deeply to release more
fully from the top of your head all the way down through your body slowly
relaxing like there's a wonderful flow of water that starts at the top of your
head and then flows down down through the body relaxing it
all with every exhale the relaxing
water moves down settles down through your
body
and for from the calmest quietest Place deep
within the place that's maybe nose
preverbally knows without the filter of stories and memories
and desires and
fears bring to
mind the people of your life the people you might be seeing over
the next days
week and privately so just you from deep
inside can you touch into a
tenderness a gentleness a warmth of Love or
compassion kindness care for these
people even not needing to act on it just to
feel it s so it's independent
of what you actually goes on in when you meet just a deep sense of
Goodwill well
wishing and may these words express your care for others
may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free
[Music]
[Music] thank
you
so hello and welcome to this fifth talk on wise
thinking I I I suspect that uh for much of my life I didn't think much about my
thinking I didn't uh took it for granted or took it as being what it is and
sometimes I in a way I took it to who I am if my thinking represented me and my interest my
thoughts my beliefs my opinions my emotions and uh it wasn't anything to
question or consider or investigate it was just taken for granted as a big
solid kind of event in its own right with
meditation uh I've learned to not do that but rather to be mindful of
thinking to investigate the nature of thinking what goes on as I think and the
Ecology of thinking and thinking is a composite thing it's made up of many different
component parts only one of which is the content of the
thoughts the very particular ideas or stories that are being uh
considered and this was really a great thing to open up to the wider field of
what's going on the emotional field the physical field what's going on in the
body energetically the tensions the Holdings the emotions that were the fuel
or the source for the emotions and um and uh this is a pretty
you know so that's included now when we do the basic introduction to meditation instructions here at
IMC and uh it's a whole this hour and a half on mindfulness of
thinking the um um and so one of the things we can begin discovering is that
there are different levels of thinking or different sources within from where
we think qualitatively and different kinds of thinking that we can
do and when we start understanding the range of possible ways of thinking kinds
of thoughts we can have not not so much the content but um where they arise from
and what's feeding them and fueling them and um we can at some point discover
that there's thinking that is free of any clinging attachment free of any
need whereas the surface mind the more usual way of thinking is operating from
need from desires from greed from aversion from hostility from uh
criticism from confusion from fear in some in or in uh uh it's
operating from stress it's possible to discover over a way of thinking that is
stressfree and for some people th this is the source of creativity and some people need to take
a vacation or really sometimes meditating is enough to awaken the capacity for creative
thinking that is flow can't flow when there's the limitation contraction of
any tension connected to thinking so we start feeling there's a different way of thinking a whole
different approach to way of thinking and it begins to put a question mark
about the value of the usual way of thinking is this really the best thing
to be doing is this really the best way to think and more importantly is the
messages coming from the surface mind that does a thinking is it really an accurate message is it true is it
valuable is it is something that I need to believe in or is it appropriate to
question it and look more deeply to see more deeply what's really going on
here and you know I found that the answer was often yes it is appropriate the question it is appropriate to look
more deeply what's really happening here more deeply within and so as we go deeper within we
discover that there's a place of thinking that um is comes out of a
stress being stressed free or some part of us some place core part or deep place
inside where there's calm or peace and that the way the nature of
those thoughts are very different they are very simple they can be
sophisticated in in because they can take in the whole of who we are that when whenever
we're tensed we we're always limited and we have so many faculties so
many abilities that come into play that when there's a sense of Harmony within uh then it that that all these
things can come together into an intuitive understanding or a well-informed
understanding that's uh we don't necessarily recognize all the data
that's coming in and that's why it's creative that's why it's know so much and can be so so uh
effective and that's deep is very s so it can be sophisticated but the content of the
thoughts the way they appear is not not complicated it's not a deep
complicated analysis and thinking and it's more it's a satisfying thinking it's satisfying in and of itself it's
very simple and even that thinking get quieter and quieter and sometimes it's
just this absolutely most rudimentary Act of recognition of what's
happening in the present moment calm peace
knowing Joy concentration
spaciousness settled just kind of very simple without
leaning forward or against not wanting or not wanting just knowing knowing
knowing and so much drops away of our life things just drop away drop away and
it just feels like the most satisfying place to be is in this very deep quiet
knowing that we really feel and are connected to are experiencing in a deep way and it might even be possible to
sense at some point that there is a kind of cognition a kind of knowing that
happens before uh there are words thoughts
images a funny thing can happen in in Con in in deep states of meditation
where it's possible to feel physically that uh kind of like a physical sense that a thought is about
to happen the image I had when this often has is like a surface of water and
the bubbles begin s growing up on the on the surface of the water and that thought bubble some some point will
leave the surface and and I could feel a little bit of pressure a little bit of
movement or something little bit of energy behind this the thinking and
because the uh the Deep attention is right there to feel and know and Rec
recogniz what's happening this almost preverbal knowing that impulse to think Fades
away I knew I was about to think but I I never knew never
discovered what those thoughts were going to be in other words thinking begins offline often in this deeper
place but something is we have a rich inner life that's deeper than verbal thoughts and images that we do and when
the mind is quiet we can sometimes sense this preverbal
knowing and um not that it's necessarily knowing accurately but it's knowing freely with
the depth that um that then we can because we're paying attention being
mindful there's a kind of a check and balance system we kind of feel oh is
this so and let's find out let's let's look more deeply or check the situation
out more and so but the important thing I wanted to highlight today is that it's
possible to let the surface mind become silent and it's exquisitely beautiful
wonderful to be in this world with a surface mind quiet and
peaceful but the Deep Mind present and aware and connected and consider
considerate to what's happening around us within us there's an intelligence there we don't need to have the surface
mind always thinking always operating always figuring out and the way that we can be present
for others and present for ourselves present for this world with the surface
mind quiet and peaceful and the deeper mind available is really
wonderful so to begin to recognize when the hum of the
refrigerator quiets in the mind the surface mind gets quiet we can still think but we're not
thinking from the place where the hum is happening the stress is happening The Silence of the surface mind so I want to
end with a story from my little Book of Stories uh called the monastery
within the the monastery work leader always appeared
peaceful this was not so unusual among the monks and nuns of the monastery he was unique however in that
he remained peaceful and calm even when the monastery was at its busiest for example when large crowds of
people visited to celebrate the Buddha's birthday if a person was needed to visit
if a person was needed to visit the hustle and bustle of the local market town this was the
monk the monastery usually sent when asked how he managed to remain peaceful he said I entered the monastery
for peace and quiet I had spent years in the harried world of Commerce and people
I longed for the silence the monastery was rumored to have I was delighted with my first weeks
in the monastery the silence was exquisite
however as I settled into the Silence of the place I was shocked to learn how
noisy my M my own mind was the real noise was
within it was the business of my own mind that oppressed me not the noise and
activity of the world now it doesn't matter to me where
I go I care the silence within
me so I hope that this week and talking
about these different aspects of thinking has uh opened a window for you
to investigate and consider your thinking a new way and just to to
question what your thinking is about is a step towards a kind of mental
Freedom where we're not caught in the grip of our thoughts we don't an automatic believe every thought we have
and think that we are our thoughts there is a deeper way of being deeper way of
living in the world that is not from the control tower of the surface
mind May that surface mind from time to time provide you with a nurturing
silence and quiet and may you discover how to operate in this world with the surface
mind quiet so thank you very
much so I have a few announcements and um first is I'm not going to be here for
the next couple of weeks I'm going to um take the next uh a couple of weeks
kind of more as a vacation time and we'll be going to uh
with my being with my family and don't know exactly what we'll be doing yet but I just want to spend some time um you
know uh not teaching and taking time off and uh so we have wonderful teachers who
are coming and uh Liz Powell who has not taught yet for this 7 a.m. she's one of
the teachers here at IMC and uh she's a wonderful teacher and
will be teaching next week and I think she's teaching about the Brahma viharas a wonderful preparation maybe
for the new year and then the first week of the new year uh uh Coto Coto conin
who has been here before will U will be here and I'll be here the following
second week of the year and my plan uh for the beginning of the year is last
few years I've always uh talked about um something to do with meditation practice and sometimes a long series on on it
what I like to do this time is go back to the basics that we use here at IMC
and for and do the kind of a maybe in-depth uh instructions on the basic
Insight practice that I teach here and um and so even if you've been a
practitioner for a long time I hope that as I teach it that uh New Dimensions
will become available for you and um so it'll be a week uh each on the the five
different areas that I emphasized in the intro introduction to meditation course breath body emotions thinking and then
practicing in life also I want to say that uh since
this is my last uh talk of the year and maybe I just mention that for those of
you who would like to support IMC um uh I did write an end of the year
fundraising letter that um uh might be interesting for you to read and if you'd like to support IMC
there's um uh you know there's a you can go to the Donate page on imc's website and
certainly I'm very appreciative and grateful for the support that our Center receives and and um thank you for any
support that you provide in all the different ways and uh so I'll put it here in the
chat the I think it went in I
tried and uh there it is yes um there's a link there hopefully I don't know if
you can get it but I I maybe it's not fully there the link but it's um it's on
the YouTube uh underneath the video there's a place where the year end for
Gil so thank you and uh may [Music]
your beginning of this new solar year that's today uh be uh a rebirth of all
that's good in you and I look forward to seeing you in a couple of
weeks