or not so hello everyone hello and greetings lovely to be with you wherever
in the world you are whatever time zone and to
um yeah to be together in this moment in time so would I like to invite us to do is to
transition actually into our meditation and I'll introduce the theme during the
guided meditation I won't say so much about it right now so and if you're new
to happy hour welcome you don't need to know anything uh whatever
whatever is needed will be presented I will be shared with you and whatever arises as long as you treat it with
kindness with interest curiosity and kindness then yeah you're doing this
practice exactly right it's all about cultivating kindness and Goodwill towards ourselves others and whatever
Mayhem might arise in their mind so it's about cultivating kindness that's that's
the main teaching and of course we'll we'll take different ways and different ways to cultivate it and play around
with this idea so so again even if you're visited by sleepiness and and whatever you are
distraction just be kind be kind be kind so only thing to remember
so let's begin let's begin so Landing Landing or posture Landing in
our bodies if you're sitting in a chair
bringing attention [Music] to your body sitting upright a sense of
brightness in your spine a sense of Integrity your shoulders
maybe rolling them back just a little bit opening the chest
making sure the bottom of your feet or in the Earth your hands on your lap
you're sitting on the cushion I trust you know what to do and lying down okay is okay if your body
needs it and then so is standing
I'm gonna assume that you're sitting just for Simplicity
Simplicity of instructions so feeling feeling your
bottom on the cushion on the chair and releasing
ah relaxing
there being a sense of release of your weight the weight of your upper body
your sit bones offering the weight of your head your
shoulders your trunk your arms your hands
your sit bones
letting your sit bones sink just relax be
pulled down by the Earth
you might feel this tiny shift release
and releasing the weight of your upper legs knees lower legs and feet
under the Earth
releasing giving offering the weight
of your body you don't have to hold it up trust gravity
Let the Body be heavy
and let their breath be light
receiving the breath in the abdomen lower abdomen
the body be heavy
and enjoy enjoy the breath moving through the body
just this breath not the last one not the next one just the same breath just this out Breath Right Here
spend some time to settle and arrive with the breath
this breath
your thoughts are rising past future it's all right
notice simply notice that thinking is happening right now okay that's what
mine to do they're like puppies they run around be kind be kind to the puppy thank you
thank you puppy and releasing you're releasing talls
biting the puppy to sit on your lap just
attend to the breath a pee of attention can be quite content
to here with a breath and it's going to run around again again be kind
the puppy of the Mind enjoy the breath in this moment
in a few minutes to collect and call settle the mind
foreign
take refuge you've chosen this time to settle
to make friends with yourself so do it
allow it to happen thank you thought not now
enjoying the breath Here and Now
and I agree with this breath just as one breath in the friendly way just one
breath then when that's accomplished okay this one more
breath but just this breath start here now just this breath
entirety of the in-breath entirely out breath can I be with you with kindness
and when you notice if and when you notice the mind is wondered
it's okay reconnect with the breath begin with kindness with yourself with kindness
not chastising not berating yourself
yeah this is how this works you let go you reconnect with a smile
oh just hear just this breath one breath at a time really
just this and you become fully fully present
just this in breath this out breath
and then let it go and then this one
is right here
foreign
foreign foreign foreign foreign
foreign foreign
foreign
was needed
what if everything you need
everything you need all the support
it grows to be kind wise all the support you need in your
life what if it's all here already
even if there are plenty of challenges seemingly the body and the mind
relationally whatever there might be whatever what if
this is enough not just enough but more than enough
the heart relax settle either sense of ease a sense of trust
and so Courage the heart having courage
and the kindness and the goodness that surrounds you inside outside
starting here
trust that as Einstein said
trusting making a decision to see the universe as a friendly place
taking on this perspective we can take so many perspectives on just taking this
on as if you're changing your glasses you can always take these glasses off later after the meditation just try it
on for size to see what happens experiment
be a scientist of your own mind
but so much thinking about it but just resting sense of confidence
but it's all okay it's always been will ever be
even if you don't understand this insight and if you just try it on for size for a moment
that you're playing your part
this interconnected vast Network
relax relax and be breathed foreign
love what is In This Moment always go back to not
liking it afterwards if you just love what is in this moment
kindly
you've been loving this struggle loving the challenges
the edges as well as the ease the good
s through something in this moment in your body that's challenging and tight achy
can you open your heart to your arms wide to it just love it as it is doesn't
have to be any different still welcome it fully loving what it is
see if the heart relaxes the body relaxes
foreign
and as we turn towards ending this sitting period
can we love what is
whatever showed up or did not show up during this period
no need for self-judgment even if self-judgment arrives can we just love
that too as a friend who's just cranky
but do we know they mean well they're just cranky can we love them too love what is
can we extend extend our hearts
or the appreciation with
goodness gifting our goodness together
to others their friends family our community
can we show up with goodness loving is best as we're able to in this
limited time we have each of us on this Earth so short
and offering offering our goodness collectively the benefit are of our
cultivation our meditation these seeds we plant the seeds we plant
and we water that will grow offering their goodness to all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere be well may they be free
including ourselves
[Music]
everyone thanks for your practice
so loving what is in this moment loving what it is
practice it's like putting on a pair of glasses okay let me try this on for
sides what shifts what changes and um and things can shift and change so
so we're going to have a chance now
to to show up with one another in small groups and whatever is said or not said
internally in the group can we love what is can we just practice
for just a few minutes in a small group The Rubber and meeting the road can you
show up with kindness with two strangers or maybe two friends
um and just show up with kindness loving what is in the moment even if it's back
pain which I'm currently loving um whatever is is arising she's loving
what is loving what is so so the invitation for the small
groups are gonna try to make them of size three for everyone and the invitation is let's go
um in alphabetical order each person will just share maybe one
short very short um maybe just 30 seconds or a minute what what what is it like what what was
this practice like and you can say I fell asleep I couldn't love anything this was the reverse like it's all okay
but make it very short so that the other folks will have the time to to share as
well or if your time comes you can just say pass I'm gonna hold compassionate presence I'm gonna love the silence and
you can perfectly do that no problem just show up with kindness that's for
yourself and for others and even if you're cranky or afraid show up with
kindness with towards the crankiness and and the fear it's it's
um this is a great sandbox a great sandbox this this uh lovely community of
just show up with kindness you can be silent and each person will say or offer
silence or just 30 seconds or a minute and then not asking questions not
directing just show up as you are supportively and listen listen listen listen
all right I'm gonna create the rooms and take care of yourselves take care of
each other okay be kind be kind and enjoy here we go
okay the rooms are closed everybody is back welcome back everyone
and we have time for uh Reflections um what what did you notice any aha
moments during the meditation any Among Us during the small groups
um discussions conversations um especially if you haven't spoken
recently or if you're new love to hear your Reflections both for your own
benefit and share for the benefit of others again this sharing is not from a place of ego and look at me it's more
like oh so what I discovered look at that in my common Humanity with others and can really help
the community that way Don please
um well uh first thanks so much Nikki Sangha uh uh one of my favorite parts of
the day um I was uh really sleepy I was falling
asleep and and then I thought oh no I'm just going to leave and I and I left and
then I thought oh wait if I can exercise then maybe that'll wake me up and so that's
what I did I was got back on and was doing some exercise and the video off
over loving what is
so yeah sometimes it's if you've just you've had um a lack of sleep and sleep deprivation
of course when you start to become calm that's where the Mind goes it's like oh you have this debt you need to pay
you're like no no I want to bet it like no you've got debt so so then opening
the eyes sometimes you know we say walking meditation movement meditation so meditating while you move so so
exercising is also movement meditation and when you're really present with the movement of the body so great you worked
with it beautiful thanks for that report yay awesome any other Reflections what came
up now please
uh well Nikki thank you for your your share and
um what I actually have a an aversion to for tomorrow's work because this is the
night before going to work tomorrow so I have this animal version at work
so when you actually suggested shifting lens or changing eye the eye glass
I said well maybe I could actually love worked for tomorrow and then it suddenly
it shifted and I thank you for for giving that Insight thank you so much
thanks for sharing that now which which you not I don't want to put you on the spot but I'm curious is this first first
just to say it sounds amazing and wonderful that you tried it and you were curious like oh yeah let me try it and
you tried it and then it shifted and and is there anything else you you were willing to share like how it shifted
like what opened up what thoughts opened up about work that were not available before
well I realized that the lens is always there to shift it's it's a matter of choosing what lens
to look and I am so grateful for this hunger and
to you okay thank you Nell you you nailed it
beautifully the lens is always there and we can always choose that's one thing
that cannot be taken away from us everything else can go but our freedom
to choose is our first and last freedom is is how we choose to see something so
thank you beautiful thanks for sharing your Insight with the community love it love it so thank you all thank you so
much for your practice um we're going to close and dedicate the Merit of our practice to to all beings
may all beings know that they can choose all all humans the perspective it's ours
to choose may all beings choose the perspective of Freedom including ourselves may we all be free
[Music] thanks everyone thank you so much for
your practice be well have a good week