so hello everyone welcome to this meditation session
and I'd like to start with um
uh an introduction but the introduction will be a little a bit of a rhetorical
device so I say that to you because
maybe rhetorical devices should have a warning in front of them this way of talking
uh may be hazardous for your habits
and or maybe hazardous if you overdo them
that um important part of meditation is to enjoy it
to find pleasure and for this meditation I would like to
uh and give you some guidance some instruction if you like to take it
on actually enjoying your meditation finding pleasure and one of the places in the beginning
to find pleasure is to find whatever pleasure there might be in relaxing
and if so um
and part of the reason to use pleasure is in fact to break our habits
some of us have habits of kind of a negativity bias
habit towards thinking about what's terrible what doesn't work
a habit to orient Orient ourselves around the problems of life and the problems we have now and how we're not
doing well and how it's difficult it's uh certainly reasonable to have
those thoughts occasionally and if you never have those thoughts maybe that's not healthy either
but um but uh
for today let's try to break those Habits by focusing on what's Pleasant
and the pleasure but don't chase pleasure don't have a high standard for what it
means even the absence of some
thing uncomfortable you had in the past it can be kind of a pleasure
and so maybe that's good enough so assuming taking a pleasant posture
not the most Pleasant posture you can take but the pleasant posture for meditation
the most pleasant pleasant posture you can find that also where the body itself
expresses being alert aware
amen
to close your eyes
or let your eyes if you don't want to close them let your eyes be relaxed and
looking down
and then looking for how to make it Pleasant that you really enjoy doing this
doing it in your way take a few
deeper breaths maybe slowly
and the exhale slow enough to enjoy it
and to the extent it feels nice
and as you dig deeper breaths adjusting it
maybe so it remains enjoyable and as you exhale relax your body
and look for where the relaxing is Pleasant enjoyable
even to the most minor degree
and then letting your breath return to normal
and even thinking of a normal breathing is occurring within a range
and as we breathe in
if you can look for how to breathe the normal
inhale that you enjoy that has some pleasure to it
maybe only a small piece of the journey of inhaling
the beginning the end the middle
and also seeing is there anywhere in the exhale
that you can enjoy there's pleasure
maybe it's the very very beginning of the exhale
or there's a smooth feeling in the middle of just or maybe at the end
maybe some of the pleasure of breathing very very subtle
is that it just before you breathe in
it's slightly uncomfortable there's a desire to breathe in and it feels good to begin breathing in
and the same as you breathe out the very beginning might feel that you
like oh this is good to begin
and as you breathe in and breathe out foreign is there any pleasure
more widely in your body that is kind of the atmosphere or the
weather around your breathing
in how you are in the weather of your body
are there ways you can relax the body more as you exhale
may be enjoying the effect of relaxing
in part of the function of feeling
pleasure enjoyment while you meditate
is so that you can be more in the present moment where enjoyment occurs
the embodied pleasure or enjoyment
over here and now
and then to enjoy relaxing the thinking mind
maybe on the exhale softening quieting the mind
and maybe there's found some enjoyment or pleasure in the mind
if you're aware of the spaciousness around your thoughts
the softness beyond the edges of your concerns
and as you're being aware especially aware of your breathing
maybe it can be more pleasant to shift where you're aware from
if you're aware from kind of the front of your brain
be aware of breathing from the back
or be aware from within breathing itself
letting the thinking mind become quieter for the purpose of better
sensing and taking in registering whatever is Pleasant
Here and Now in your body with your breathing
in the quieting of the Mind
allow yourself to feel whatever pleasure is here
if your body is beginning to ache hurt you might shift your posture
trust assume it's okay
to take in whatever degree of pleasure there is here
a pleasure which supports you being present in a quiet way
ever so gently slightly
turn up the corners of your mouth to a small half smile
and if there's any pleasure from doing that include that pleasure as part of
mindfulness of breathing
and then coming to the end of the sitting
feeling or imagining what it's like to be with yourself
when the body has a degree of ease
enjoyment within it
how and then imagine how you would walk around your home
informed by that ease or that enjoyment
how would you do ordinary household chores if you had all the time in the world
and you did them informed by the ease the pleasure
staying close to it not in a hurry to get the job over
but as a vehicle for continuing to feel the
pleasure
and if you're sitting in a comfortable chair feeling this pleasure and enjoyment
and you're talking with a friend and if you talked resting in this ease
or this pleasure how would you talk
there's a Native American expression to walk in Beauty
how would you live in Beauty how does it support you to live in
Beauty to have this reference point
of a sense of pleasure and enjoyment in your body
and how might you care for the welfare and happiness of others
if you cared in Beauty if you cared
informed by your sense of inner physical ease and pleasure
how might you I might your heart
wish well for others
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you so good morning good day
and um so we're looking at the strategies for
how we live our lives the strategies for how to be with challenges
and there are healthy strategies and not so healthy strategies
and I'm using the example of the five hindrances for the not so healthy
and the opposite of those hindrances for healthy strategies and part of the significance of taking
this point of view of strategies is that um
if we take the time to stop and asked ourselves a question what is
my strategy here what is my Approach how am I trying to get what I want how am I trying to take care of myself here
just that pause and asking that question will maybe get you to see more clearly
what you're doing habitually or unconsciously or unreflectively
and many times when there are challenges uh and if we're a little bit stressed in
it or very stressed that sometimes we're responding from kind of a gut reaction instinctual reaction or neurotic
reaction that we might have and we're so involved in that reaction we don't even know it we sometimes we
it's very easy to lose ourselves lose our our wisdom our Clarity our kind of
really be tracking what's going on and then we say things we later regret or we
run around in circles so just simply pausing and checking
asking this question is very significant and then we can answering that question
for ourselves we can say well maybe that's not the best way and let's see if there's a better way
so the hindrance of today is uh usually translated or one way it translates to
restlessness and remorse and wrestling is a kind of agitation
that is can be very compelling and they can come with a lot of
uh anxiety can come with a lot of rest or out of
force and power to keep us in its grip and uh and it's uh often arises out of
something we're thinking about with and we and the way that maybe we're having thoughts which are
predicting danger or thoughts something that are challenging and then how we relate to those thoughts
is part of the we're part of the power of restlessness arises and remorse too
and that's because uh and that is to we kind of squeeze the thoughts we kind of
get close in they become claustrophobic around them and uh and that's squeezing them uh you
know keeps them going and kind of like just keeps flowing and flowing
and um and remorse is the same way remorse is in Latin means to chew again
and this rumination is chewing again over and over again of what we've done what we regret what we feel bad about
and again the thinking has gotten close and constricted or tight or in a way
that feels uncomfortable and that discomfort and how we think about these around our thoughts is part of the fuel
that generates more restlessness and more remorse and when we do things when we're
Restless or filled with remorse we tend not to do them in Beauty
we tend it doesn't seem not a source of of working from pleasure it's very
uncomfortable and um and and restlessness is not
really a good strategy for dealing with uh with the with challenges it's almost
like avoiding it's like running around in circles and being trapped and not knowing what to do and and I just kind
of spinning out and uh it's almost like the absence of a
response um and um or if we do respond it just
kind of uh confused or or impulsive or not really attentive to what's happening
if we get lost in remorse we tend to shut down from a fuller picture of
ourselves where our whole definition of ourselves now defined by what we're remorseful about and there's a narrowing
and we don't have access again to pleasure or to or a sense of the beauty of how what to do that's beautiful or
so the other uh way of responding that's
healthy is um to be also I want to say this way so when there's restlessness and when
there's remorse there's a kind of energy or a way that we're animated
um that the where the energy for the activity is in the body that is off that
doesn't feel Pleasant doesn't feel enjoyable it's maybe tight or hard or constricted
or has pressure behind it maybe pressure in certain parts of the body
there's a whole other way of being animated there's a whole other way of where the energy comes from so the energy is not
agitated Restless not constricted and tight like we've been remorse
and that is a kind of energy that is that where we leave we're not caught by
the thoughts so we're not squeezing them or kind of we kind of let go of the squeezing of the preoccupation that
attachment to thoughts being and and the animation comes from
some place inside that feels wholesome that feels like a home within us
some place inside that has a kind of pleasantness to it a kind of pleasure a
kind of beauty to it a kind of ease and the uh the restlessness and remorse
is often we're very much often in the head in the thoughts and the ideas
uh sometimes restlessness can be purely physical but then maybe it's not the
hindrance of restlessness it might be more just kind of over activated
something but there is this other place source for something very profound about ourselves
it there's a another source for how we're animated it's my way of saying where our Vitality
comes from where active so rather than being activated
um react by reactivity we are
um we are supported by a flow of Vitality
we're supported by an upwelling of something that feels good even if
we're taking care of something which is very challenging huge challenge is maybe painful and it doesn't give us a sense
of pleasure the source of the energy the animation where we're coming from
it comes from a place of home it comes from a place of beauty comes from a place of maybe we will call it Pleasant
or enjoyable and we don't sacrifice that to take care
of things that are so terrible in the world we sit there they're horrible in the world we don't because things are
terrible if we pause to see where we're coming from inside
we say well maybe I can shift from the agitated squeezing tightening tense
place of restlessness and remorse and come from
a place of of um of flow a place of of
upwelling a place of of maybe inspiration
and for instead of remorse uh get caught in remorse when we've done something
that we regret or feel bad about is to the Buddhist approach is to learn
from that and then instead of remorse to remorse is to re-engage
um to go forward dedicated to doing better and if we identify with something we
identify with the one who is trying to do better not the one who did something
that was not good and uh and so
um so what are the functions of meditation is not just to make us come but to make
us more and more familiar with a place inside
that sometimes can feel like there's a lot of Joy sometimes can feel very
peaceful and at a home sometimes it can feel like there's Beauty there inside
something that feels really right at a homeness from which can flow out
animating energy we're not passive from that place but
the source of motivation from that place is very different than the sort of source of motivation when we're squeezed
when we're tense when we're tight when we're restless and filled with remorse
so as we learn to meditate the idea is to begin appreciating this alternative
source of how we can be animated and and we learn not to sacrifice it for
the strong messages we get from our anxiety our restlessness our remorse our
regrets our the strong messages we get from the pain
that comes from the second third and fourth arrows we shoot it ourselves that just makes things even more
difficult to get trapped in some restlessness arises because we feel trapped by all these arrows we're
swinging we're we're shooting and so to take time to pause to ask
ourselves what's the strategy here where's my source of activation source of energy Vitality coming from
am I activated that word in English usually means reactivate it's kind of like
activated in a not healthy way triggered or am I am I
um inspired am I right is it flowing for me is it am I responding from some depth
outside so to pause to ask that question
and if we've been meditating for a while and doing this kind of foundation all
the foundations that I'm talking about in this these weeks about how to work with challenges maybe it's reasonable to begin asking
that question and to begin switching over to being that way that's beautiful
being that way that maybe is closer to the place of pleasure enjoyment or at
homeness that we have here this human life of ours is very
important and it's well worth
an appropriate for us to begin discovering a different place from which
we're animated it's kind of like from the different Source within from which we live
the healthy place and to be able to distinguish that from the unhealthy places that we respond and
react to the world and
the world is a better place if you can come from this deeper Source
come from a place of beauty and come from a place of of ease and at homeness
it's not selfish to do this it's actually a contribution to the world we don't contribute to the World
by worrying we don't contribute the World by being angry and hostile we
don't contribute to the World by diminishing our value by by living under
the weight of you know I'm a terrible person we contribute to the World by putting
all that aside enough since seeing if I can find that very natural place within
its nature to have this upwelling place the upwelling source deep inside
that has a flow to it has a joy to it has a pleasure to it
and whatever pleasure we can feel is healing
so if your fear of going through a big challenge pause
and if you have that situation allows for it go and do something enjoyable
don't stay in the middle of the challenge and kind of feel trapped or feel like just kind of like it's spinning out and
more and more after if you've been in this in a
challenging Place psychologically emotionally for some time go find something to do that's Pleasant
go find someone's pet that you can pet with or go go do something that brings
you a sense of pleasure do an activity that brings you pleasure you know it may
be cleaning or cooking or going for a walk pleasure is one of the great medicines
it can be one of the Great Escapes and avoidance mechanisms and that's what
you know the pleasure of addiction does but hopefully it's not that kind of
pleasure you do you find healthy pleasures that you you can do
when you feel over challenged by situations try not to stay stuck
try to engage engage Your vitality your energy Your Capacity to do things to go
find the healthy pleasures and then come back and address The
Challenge from a different place so
thank you and I hope that today you can spend some time exploring
um where you're at Where Your vitality is Flowing from where how you're
animated and is it coming from a healthy place or not such an inspiring place
thank you