foreign
greetings on this first Monday of the Year 2023
we made it this far and um
happy to start this year this way with all of you as I have this last uh two years now
that um two januaries it's remarkable that we've had this time
together and a chance to do this kind of teaching and practice
so thank you for this chance opportunity for me so um
one of the things that I want to emphasize today is relatedness
that certainly just I just uh evoked our relatedness through this 7
A.M sitting this early morning and um
and there's a relationship that is here even if you're the for the first time here welcome
um you're somewhat in relationship now to what's happening here to my teaching
to me and I and me to you without that relationship what's
happening here today would not happen and um and one of the key elements of
Dharma practice is in fact to focus on focus on relatedness
not not in some large abstract way but in an immediate way here and now
so there's a we don't often focus on the relationship that exists
we often focus on the things of the world objects people
and so there's an object of our thoughts an object of our concern and we're focusing on that person said
this and that was wrong or that was great or that person's doing that or or we're focusing on ourselves as an
object me I'm I'm the victim I'm the the wonderful person delusions of
grandeur perhaps but I'm here and uh and things are happening to me
and I'm measuring what's happening to me about whether it's good for me or bad for me or something
and I don't want to diminish the role of that there's a
place for that kind of thinking for sure but uh when we enter into the Dharma
there's a new orientation and that is what takes precedence
is how all these objects including oneself are
relating to each other in between you and me there's a relationship in
between me and my breakfast there's a relationship that breakfast supports me
I take interest in the breakfast and and between the two uh you know the
breakfast occurs and um and a tremendous amount of our
life immediate life is occurring because of what's in relationship to us
what's in relationship to this mutuality um our life is uh is related to the
oxygen that's around us without that we wouldn't live that relationship of how
the or the way that we interact with oxygen is crucial for us to be alive
there's us there's oxygen into how we relate to it the connection
and you can go through a whole list of things like that and one of the important aspects of
Dharma practice is to stay close to that place of relatedness what is that
relationship and some of that time that relationship is are doing we like and we don't like
something we want we don't want something where open and aware of something or
we're shut down or we're asserting ourselves on something so it's how we're relating to
it is important how we're relating to ourselves we have a not so nice thought
and then what's the relationship we form to that thought we judge ourselves by it or we attack it
or something and we have a wonderful thought then we take pride in it and want to show off to
other people this wonderful realization we have and so what is that relationship and how
to keep that relationship be won that's where freedom is found
we're not necessarily becoming free ourselves we are freeing the relationship
between us and all things including ourselves
and uh so freeing ourselves from this preoccupation with self
measuring everything from the point vantage point of Me Myself and mine and instead looking at the relationship
the relatedness Is that relatedness real skillful or unskillful is it helpful or
not is it healthy or not those are to keep it really simple
is there an ouch in that relatedness or is there an ah
so I'll talk more about this but if for now to take a meditation posture
and gently close the eyes
and just sitting here quietly
in what way are you activated in your mind your emotions your heart
that could be seen as a way of relating to something
or a way in which there's a relationship with something
outside of you and yourself
the relatedness between
sometimes it's initiated by what's around us sometimes what's within us
when I came to IMC today I was being related to by the cold
and I had a relationship to that cold
so what what is the relatedness that's operating most for you now
relatedness is not necessarily what you do in relating
something might be relating to you
impacting you having an effect on you
the cold the warmth
and then perhaps you can take a few moments to relate to your body
with a gentle tender appreciation
probably your body is doing its at the best it can with how it is
we can take the body for granted in so many ways to appreciate the body
and the appreciation is a relatedness
maybe it's a more important that appreciation
than it is you doing the appreciating
just let there be appreciation
and then there's your body breathing there's a significant
impact on you that you breathe
breathing relates to everything about you that is living
everything you can experience has an experience in your with your body
depends on breathing to keep the whole show going
and how are you relating to the breathing
can you adjust that relatingness do something that's allowing and easeful
appreciative
is there some appropriate way that you can trust
the body breathing
and with that trust to accompany
your breathing the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out and if anything takes you away from your
breathing chances are
it's because of the nature of some relationship to something
not the something but the relationship you have hurry it has with you
foreign
one way or another you are relating to something
is that relating
supportive or unsupportive for you
is it beneficial or unbeneficial could it be more beneficial
could there be a right effort in the relatedness
there is always relatingness relatedness
how are you relating
or how are you receiving what is relating to you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
imagine that the way that you are relating to any other person at any given time or
group of people that the way that you relate was Is Not Invisible
like a musician has the instrument
musical instrument and as they're playing the instrument and in
relationship to those two things there comes music so for you
if there's the persons you're with the way there's you and
and if the way that you're related came out like music that people could
hear or came out as colors that people could
see or smells that they could smell
how would you think that the way that you relate would appear to other people
would it be beautiful would it be not so beautiful
would there be a sense of Harmony balance
or would it be discordant
to offer Goodwill kindness
maybe is the way to bring Beauty in the relatedness
beautiful music beautiful colors smells
it's a way of beautifying this world
and while people do not necessarily see with their eyes literally
the way we relate to the world has a big impact on ourselves and the world
and at the end of The Meditation is a valuable time
because maybe just maybe you have more of opportunity to
have a healthy and a sincere
well wishing for others
and so to spend the next minute with that well-wishing for individuals for
groups of people for everyone
may all people be happy
may all people be safe
may all people be peaceful
and may all people be free
and may all of us meditating together God into the world
to make a collective Beauty Collective music
through simple acts of kindness May our meditation be for the benefit
and the welfare of all people
[Music]
thank you
hello everyone and welcome to the first talk
of the year and beginning of another week of five part series
and uh what I like to do this week is to answer the question what is the Dharma
and I'm hoping this series will nice create a nice foundation for what will follow
um which isn't completely decided but uh I would like it to build on this
and um and so Dharma is uh some ways it's a
very important very Central word in Buddhism because it could mean Buddhism uh the Dharma sometimes sometimes is
synonymous with the word Buddhism the word Buddhism is a kind of a modern
Western invention um it didn't really exist that in that
kind of way and as an ism word um in in Asia in fact uh
uh even the word religion didn't quite exist and so in some of the Asian languages and when they had contact with
the Western civil Western culture they um had the kind of invent a word for
religion uh to translate religion into their language
and now so the word Dharma sometimes holds all of that but Dharma also has more specific
meanings and uh and the and has even in the
ancient times they said they had a lot of different meanings and um and uh uh through three a list of
three things that Dharma means that's I think very evocative that from the ancient commentaries is
that uh it's all kind of uh words that are built on
words that are built on verbs activities something dynamic and the first is uh pariyati
uh p-a-r-i-y-a-t-t-i and um
I'm not sure if there's one or two with teeth and uh pariati is usually taken to mean
teachings but it's based on a root word it has to do with obtaining receiving and
sometimes pariati is understood to be the act of learning so first there's learning which is an
activity the second is my
images means to practice which is also a verb and the last one is
adigama which is to obtain or to attain something to reach something
so these are so here the Dharma has three different activities and and so when having something Dynamic
not something static that's being emphasized and that right now the dynamism of what
Dharma means I would like to encapsulate that Dharma means relatedness
the ancient way of saying it back in the time of the Buddha was uh through a
little slogan that goes whoever sees the Dharma sees dependent
arising whoever sees dependent arising sees the Dharma
the powerful statement dependent arising means that things occur independent
Independence and other things the things that things are not independent they don't self-exist they
don't just simply materialize in thin air for no reason at all or no cause or no conditions at all
um they're always there because of some some preceding conditions some events
some occurrence that then is the possibility for the next thing to occur
and um so human life itself is clearly dependent on many factors in the present
moment and down Through the Ages that had to occur in order to there'd be this
physical physical and psychological mental life that we embody we experience we are
so you know where in some ways who we are as human beings could be said to be
a hundred percent dependent on something else existing for us to be
able to live breathing you know we have to ask to be oxygen uh
water there has to be water has to be on this planet uh how did that happen how
did oxygen happen um it was a conditions that had to build over millennia
millions and billions of years for it to be conditions right for what we have as
human life and those have to persist and so you know you can go layers and layers of in
the present moment if things Our Lives depend on and our psychological life our inner
life is dependent all kinds of things as well and some of them might be hormones and
our biology affects our psychology quite a bit uh what other what happens in the world
and some people their moods is completely attached to connected to wedded to
things in the world and what people do what other people are doing or substances how they feel are
completely dependent on having coffee or not coffee or or drugs and not drugs or
alcohol and not alcohol and and so how the mood and how we feel this can be dependent on many things exercise
and not exercise and um but it's in that dependency in
that not dependency in terms of like codependent exactly psychological term
but uh the fact that things occur in relationships to other things occurring
as well and that relatedness between things and that's how I would like to present
this idea of dependent arising today is it has to do with the relatedness
um that Dharma is the relationship the relatedness between things that can
be called things in fact in Buddhism uh I think this it's
fairly it's a fair thing to say that there are no things in Buddhism there are only uh Dynamic processes
Dynamic occurrences events that are moving and
act in action and process and um
and so um uh so or at least that's what Buddhism
focuses on so much is the dynamic aspect of life and in terms of our psychological
spiritual mental physical life it's very
much caught up and caught up and involved in this whole dynamic world of
relatedness in relationships that everything occurs through
partly because everything that happens even if uh happens through
the dynamic process the dynamic activity of perception
so a mountain might not seem so Dynamic it might seem like a real thing that's there
is changing slowly over time but not much in my lifetime Maybe
but the perception of the mountain is a dynamic activity and everything that we experience in the
world goes through our perception deeper than our perception it goes through our liking and not liking it our
sense of this is Pleasant or unpleasant partly because our evaluation of things
uh everything goes happen to us then goes through the way that the way that we know it do we know it with
contraction and tightness and assertiveness in greed or generosity or without it
and so there's this whole dynamic world of things that happen in relationship to
other things being there and that is that's the Dharma
Dharma is found there and and uh and then caring for it
because that is also where bondage occurs where attachment and
tightness where suffering occurs is not there's no inherent suffering that just kind of pops up in the universe like out
of the blue suffering occurs in relationship to
something else it's a way of relating it's a relatedness and um
and freedom is a shift in that relationship
so this idea that the Dharma is relatedness
is a paradigm change from I believe how many people live their lives
where they live their lives as if focused more on Me Myself and mind what's happening to me
my ideas my ideas of self
what's happening out there who those people are what they're doing but there's a paradigm shift of
appreciating what's happening between the people or between us and the world
and nature and everything that what's the relatedness
also within ourselves how do we relate to our inner experience
how are we relating to the outer experience that's where the Dharma is begins to be discovered
and that is all to do with things which are fluid and dynamic and because of that
they can be changed maybe not easily but that's what Dharma
practice the practice of relatedness the practice the practice of working with
this whole nation notion of things arise depend on other things is we can shift
and change the relatedness that the dependencies the dynamic the dynamic quality of it
so that what supports our hearts our minds our our freedom
is more present than what supports attachment and clinging and and
suffering so it's a paradigm shift and so you might try
stretching your mind to look at kind of an invisible world
the world between another person and you what is the
relationship that's being formed like especially if you meet a stranger maybe that's easiest there what's that
real how's that relationship before you get to know them are you afraid of them are you cautious are you eager are you curious
that's a way of being in a relationship as you talk with a stranger do you feel
more like closed down and pulling back or you feel more open and interested in
is there kindness is there friendship going back and forth or the opposite
what is happening in that invisible World kind of that maybe each one of you don't
necessarily see but maybe you can feel maybe you can sense
if that relatedness between you was music would it be beautiful music or not so
beautiful if it was color would be beautiful array of colors or uh this uh unharmonious
display of colors how is that the relatedness
so I would encourage you for today to look at this world that's
has to do with how you are in relationship to all things including
yourself what's the nature of that relationship and that is dynamic that is Shifting and changing throughout the day
and what kind of relating relatedness
what kind of meeting does things outside of you have towards you
how are things relating to you the air that you breathe how is it relating
is it you know me could say it's not relating at all but it does have a relationship to you
what is that relationship what is the relationship to the food that you eat how does it impact you
and um and maybe there's a way to do this Paradigm Shift here
that you really kind of are stretching yourself to be in the world from a very radically
different perspective than how you usually go through the days the perspective of what is the
relatedness that's going on right here and how do you want to relate what is
the beautiful way of relating so the Dharma
is this is what arises in relationship
and if you can see how things arise in a related way then you're seeing the
Dharma you see the Dharma if you see how things arise in a related way
so thank you and we'll continue this topic of what is the Dharma
tomorrow