so good morning everyone somehow I feel particularly happy to sit here today
happy and content somehow um which maybe I shouldn't be because
um I don't have a talk really thought out I'm just here and I debated
whether to just take questions today that seems like it's nice to do that
periodically and but there is something that I would like to talk about that I
think I'd enjoy talking about it just hasn't been formulated so I might bore you
as I find my way but it's just wonderful for me for me a wonderful topic of our
thinking and uh over the years of practice my
relationship to thinking has changed and as deep end and
expanded and all kinds of interesting ways for me at least and that um
and I would say that I have a very friendly relationship with
my thinking world my thinking that I think a lot of people can't say I couldn't have said that when I was
younger but also it's friendly in there I feel like mostly my thoughts are friendly
thoughts and really characterized by that I don't feel particularly challenged by
the thoughts that I have and I kind of kind of sometimes to lighten them and appreciate them and
and also um don't you know I've learned over the years of practice to not give a lot of
authority to them so that makes it easier to have a much simpler relationship to them
the the I think it's very easy because I've
had this plenty in my life of having thoughts that were compulsive
that there was stress involved and the Very thoughts that I had and um
into some point become free of that is a wonderful thing it's a possibility for all of us
though some people there's they're living so much so long or I did this certainly lived so long in thought
streams that were just taken for granted just assume to be normal that's what
life is sometimes you know this famous quote you
know I think therefore I am is um I think points to at least for
some of us that we identify with ourselves our thinking it's like who I am my thinking
and so if I think it it must be right there must be me or this must be the
real thing um certainly my thinking happens to me I
mean I take responsibility for it but I don't identify myself with it it's not like who I am it's just kind of like a
appendage sometimes and maybe no different than some of you maybe when
you clip off your fingernails once your fingernails are on I don't know where the counter or whatever you put them
whenever they fall they probably don't look at them so that's me
I better save them and you gather them up and you go around and you probably get a lock at the glass locket that you
carry carry with you and so you can show people like probably have it right over your hearts because then you show people
like about here look you know mostly once they're clipped you
know there's you know it's like oh you know I think for many people it's like a the relationship to clipped finger nails
uh you know is pretty pretty light pretty you know I bet there's not much
compulsion except like oh where's the right place to throw them away
and um so it thoughts you know but we can we have that kind of light easy
relationship with thoughts but we don't identify them because we think it it doesn't mean that's you doesn't mean you
have to Define Yourself by the thoughts that you have and so a big part of this for
mindfulness practitioners is in fact to learn to be mindfulness of thinking it's
not easy because sometimes thinking is the is the filter through which we see
the world we don't see the filter but over time you've become more you can
slowly become more and more cognizant of our thinking how we think different people think in different ways
some people it's clearly in words and a voice in the head that speaks some people it's in images a lot that
they think some people in other ways there's a that the primary way of knowing or processing or understanding
and um so to first become aware of how you know what how what is your way of understanding your life how to use
understanding arise for you and um and then uh notice whether it's
stressful or not ice that if this kind of feels heavy or dense or kind of contracted
whether it feels agitated the way that you know the way that you think
and um so and are there different circumstances in
your life where thinking is more likely to be stressful and other circumstances where it's actually kind of nice to think you enjoy
it maybe some people which when they're alone they enjoy their thoughts more some people in their
loan are oppressed more by their thoughts some people in the shower enjoy their thoughts because finally you kind of not
that's a place to sing and even if you can't sing and think it's going to be
um there's all kinds of different kind of scenarios so understand the different contexts for how we think and to begin
appreciating their differences and once you understand there are different ways of thinking and different qualities of
thinking then to appreciate that the way you think is somewhat optional that you
might have options that to think differently maybe think without stress stress
without compulsive compulsivity without um you know getting identified with your
thoughts this is who I am and um and so and then also to appreciate there
are different kinds of thinking and the one that I think Buddhism what practice wants to address the most is
what I call discursive thinking and this is a thinking that storytelling
the carrying on a discourse a conversation in the mind sometimes we're talking having conversations with other
people reviewing what we said yesterday to figure out a better reply that we didn't
give yesterday or planning ahead for a conversation you're going to have and what that
person says X I'm going to say why and but they say this you know kind of figuring out what's the best thing to
say in a situation sometimes they're stressful situations like you have to go talk with a boss in a difficult
conversation or have a challenging conversation with a friend or are you going to show up and have it and meet
with a one-on-one with a Buddhist teacher you know that would just for some people
they rehearse for that they're planning it out
and uh so so and sometimes that's where the opinions come we have opinions ideas
commentary to make about things wow look at that person those shoes are just not
not up to Snuff you know how how could those people wearing those shoes
or um you know on and on my son I just learned last night my son
is going to a kingdom party and uh so it kind of just that's only
something I learned about this last week a kingdom party we should all go to Kingdom parties no
I have no idea what's happened to that that kind of party but um but um
I didn't know what to think so I didn't have any commentary about it I was just kind of like wow
laughs maybe this is an anti-patriarchy party that would be nice
anyway so um so um he went to the basement and dug out
my wife helped him take out all the pink clothes that he had in storage because periodically in his life he liked pink
clothes and so he didn't forgot he had them so apparently that was
necessary for this party so um so commentary
judgments oh no I a young man should not wear pink that's
not quite up that's not right maybe it should be blue that's right so like mind
makes these stories right and lives in these stories and and those stories can be
perhaps very strong emotions connected to them very strong fear connected to
them very strong anger connected to them very strong kind of kind of criticism of self and
others and so the discursive mind the storytelling mind that can be can have a
huge impact on on ourselves and a huge impact on others
and on ourselves a story making mind is because it's often very repetitive we repeat over and over again the same kind
of story idea theme and um and as it's repeated the the
emotional impact of them gets repeated as well so if we're telling constantly telling
stories about how terrible we are then slowly that wears us away and you
know we start getting depressed or exhausted or just may shrink and contract in some deep way
if we keep telling our store sells stories which are lies about how fantastic we are delusions of grandeur
and then we start telling that to everyone else we might
believe the delusion the conceit around it which is also very stressful for at
least for others but for maybe for ourselves so the stories we tell repeatedly have a
big impact on us and so do we want to be careful of what we say
and we want to live in the storytelling mind our storytelling Minds a little bit of a
fantasy even if we're predicting the future or remembering the past some people love to remember the past
and it brings some people a great Delight which is wonderful and can be very very healthy part of their life but
sometimes the memories of the past are hard and sometimes the memories of the past are not accurate
and um and so you know are we weighed down by them are we
what's the effect these stories the discursive mind has and I think there's a lot of suffering
from the discursive mind a lot of stress that comes from that and so and to live in that as if that's
the way to be is I think unfortunate unfortunately how many people think or
just assume and it's never been questioned it's just this is the way things are reality has been built this
way and and the way I see the world through these stories must be true because I'm seeing it through those
filters and so it must be true so one of the phenomenal things that can
happen for meditation practice I think I think most meditation practice is the calming of the thinking mind
so that we discover that we can breathe and be alive and be happy or just
experience life without that discourse of mind running it's kind of like the hum of the
refrigerator has gone off and we didn't even know it was on until it went off and ah that feels good and so to have
the discursive running mind ah that feels good and not a few people that's why they cherish meditation because it's
the one place where that thinking mind gets quiet enough that it's not so stressful not so not so oppressive not
just kind of constantly churning and churning and so just meditation it calms down
quiets down and um but for our practice of
mindfulness meditation it's not just to have a quiet mind or a calm mind and get
that relief it's to have that calmness as a vantage point to be become wiser
about how we think to use that as a as a as a orientation
the calmness to then look at our thinking more carefully when the thinking mind begins again how am I
thinking what's the quality of my thinking what's the primary themes that what I
think not a few people only discover the regular the themes of their thinking
when they go into meditation retreats because for seven days maybe there's
very little stimulus that's usually Keeps Us distracted you don't have the radio or the TV on or
your computer on some people have multiple things on at the same time like
my son I I've seen him with three monitors that
he's tracking and he seems to be able to do it he's also figured out to listen to they
record all the classes in college and so he doesn't listen in class he doesn't go to class sometimes
and he says that professors talk too slow so I don't not interested you know it's like my mind wanders off and I talk
to people next to me or or I'm on my phone but what I've learned is that I learned
much better if I go to the if I listen to the recordings because I put them on two or three times
speed and then I have to really pay attention
and then I learned so anyway so like you might just say
that he shouldn't have three monitors on and tracking them all if he can you know who knows
maybe there's a whole new generation of people born with it you know being evolving into different brains
maybe most of us are the old version of them
Evolution continues right so um
but um but to see the repetition on Retreat to see how we we don't have the
distractions that we don't normally have or the interruptions to spend hours at a time on Retreat just left with yourself
and looking at yourself and seeing yourself and sometimes it's a little bit distressing for people or for some
people very distressing to finally discover what goes on in there I had no idea that this is what I was thinking
all the time this is terrible or wow I'm better than I thought I was
that's less often than the first and um
and uh to just you know and so some people discover how much they um are
afraid because all their thoughts who most of their thoughts are the themes is so much fear worried about this worried
about that worry about that some people discover how much they're trying to escape and run away by going into
fantasy some people discover how much they're driven by desire and their sexual desire because they
have fantasies of Galore and so it goes on and on so it goes you know so so there's themes and so wow I had no idea
that this is what what drives my mind and what goes on all the time if his mind is left to itself
that's considered really fantastic for inside meditation to start seeing Oh
this is how it is this is how it is and for the purposes of inside meditation there's absolutely no need
for shame no need even for embarrassment though it's occasionally it's embarrassing
the um the it just is you you want to be able to see it clearly and learn not to
Define Yourself by it and this defining ourselves by the thoughts we have is one tremendous
source of suffering so so then we slowly kind of begin to
not be so committed to our thinking mind discursive mind we're not so focused on
or interested in it and that makes it a big difference it's there's no switch to turn it off
so it's hard to kind of just say at the stop but it is possible to lose interest in it
and as we lose interest to it can kind of recede into the background it doesn't it doesn't have us by the throat or by
the nose and it just kind of does its thing and we can take you know be more present in other ways
also when we start seeing the quality and the characteristics of our descriptive word we're thinking all the
time it's possible to change what we think and um and to change the stream of our
thoughts if the thoughts are always ones ones of doubt try out intentionally thinking thoughts
lots of confidence think about the things that in your life that you're confident about
and uh and that could be the most mundane simple thing you can ever
imagine you have some confidence you know how to put on your shoes you know some people that's a challenge
but you know that's an example of something very simple you know you have confidence that you know which drawer to
put your silverware in you know you never think about this it's done on automatic pilot but to start
thinking about what you have confidence in that's small and then slowly expand
it and get a sense of what it feels like to think confident thoughts as opposed
to always thinking doubtful thoughts if you have mean thoughts cynical thoughts
um try out having kind thoughts it doesn't have to be insincere ones
maybe there are certain things you can be you had you have kindness for the neighbor neighbor's dog
when you see it you just wouldn't you know you fall in love or something so begin where you can and have start
having kind thoughts regularly and see what that's like now when I was
a new sense student Buddhist practitioner I would have thought anything like that
was artificial anything like that was kind of like painting a saccharine picture of the
world well maybe it is but it doesn't have to be
but more importantly um is it the better alternative
is it better to continue with the meanness is that it better to continue with the doubt
than it is to insert Maybe ten percent of the time where
thoughts of confidence the thoughts of Goodwill thoughts of kindness
and what happens how does that influence you how does that condition you how does that change you
so this began shifting our relationship to thinking and this shifting relationship to discursive thought
begins allowing us to not to put it down to not be identified with it
and then we can start with especially with the help of meditation start Discerning that there are other ways of
knowing that there's other ways of thinking than discursive thinking
and uh and it's fantastic to start discovering that
um certain that is that there can be knowing
something before you think it and maybe it's obvious to some of you but for me that was a great discovery
and as I kind of got wind of it wait a minute here why do I always I was focused on
thinking as being what told me what was going on in life and then I noticed that things are quiet
there's a knowing there before I think why do I think I have to think
what if I just maybe I just content with that knowing
and it turns out we know a lot of things without thinking so
um I think for all of you are going to leave when you leave here through one of the doors that we have
you know it's a door no I think I I bet none of you are going to try to leave Through the Windows
it wouldn't occur to you maybe I said I told you now some of you will try but
but you know you know that you know if you want to leave you go through a door but you I suspect you don't think that
you're not planning ahead you know now I'm in this building buildings have doors doors are the ways to get out but
you know doors big enough are they small enough but do I have the right clothes to go through the door you know that you
don't think about the door but you know it's a door that that's it knowing which exists
somehow in the cognitive mind that doesn't require active thinking
so a silly example but there's actually lots and lots of that going on all the time
one area that uh that's somewhat complicated in our life or what this operates a lot is driving
we make a lot of choices as we drive because we see something we know what it means but when we might be having a
conversation with a friend sitting in the passenger seat and we're mostly kind of thinking about that we're not
thinking about there's a pedestrian stepping in front of the you know into the crosswalk so slow down and stop
there's a lot of processing that goes on to make that act to do that but that all
happens in this kind of non-thinking world of cognition understanding and that's a good thing to do
my suspicion is that for most people this non-thinking place where we know
something tends to be wiser than most of our active thinking
it tends because a lot of the active thinking that we have is being fueled
by things like greed desires by ill will
hostility anger by fear anxiety by confusion and not to understanding
what's going on and and when it's fueled by that that has a very different effect on us when
our thinking or knowing is not influenced by those sources
and this deeper way of knowing can be influenced by these emotions these motivations but they're much less likely
to and that's less likely to be driven by them or pushed by them because of the
the strong compulsive way in which discursive thought spins
and runs and it insists and and demands almost on the Mind from the heart
and so to learn how to quiet the mind enough to discover what you know
before you think it is fantastic it also can discover that you still can
have thoughts but the thoughts are not stories
simple thoughts like it's a door there's someone else in front of me I'll
step aside okay let me step aside let somebody else go through the door those could be thoughts but it's not a
big story of who did what to who and so to and so it might be very boring
the thought you know let someone else go through the door first but the richness of how we have a a a a
valuable healthy relationship to the present moment and that people in the present moment
belongs closer to that world than the story making world that we're making up and living by and
worried about and um and so to be able to click quiet
enough the mind and start seeing this other way of thinking that's really simple that's present moment thinking
that simple statements in the mind or recognitions in the mind knowing the Mind something that has a chance to be
more connected to the deeper knowing Within in the teachings of the Buddha what
happens what he points out which I would concur with is that as the discursive
mind of desires and ill will and fear begins to abate
the sense that the that we're uh contracted or scattered or agitated by
the thoughts dissipates and thoughts and thinking can now seem
like they're happening in a very spacious way they're kind of there's there's lots of
room for them and some people actually talk about how feeling their mind has become expanded then open
and the mind starts feeling settled or calm and the atmosphere of calm the
atmosphere of expansiveness of Mind expansiveness of thinking creates a very different atmosphere
within which this deeper knowing can occur I think then the deeper and deeper
sources of knowing that comes out of some of the ways we can be in the world with compassion and love and care and
friendliness with wisdom can operate them so this whole Enterprise this whole
approach of becoming mindfulness mindful of thinking and really taking time to know how we
think and what goes on and distinguishing different kinds of thinking is a really important process for coming
to tap into the deeper sources of wisdom of peace and love which our hearts are
capable of and have those inform how we think to
have those be the motivation for thinking or that atmosphere for thinking rather than fear or anger or
repression or pain living in pain and what comes from all that
so um that process is a slow process it's a worthwhile process
is a process I think that occurs as we start practicing mindfulness in all areas of our life
and I hope that the time will come that you will say
that it's friendly in there it's a friendly place in there you don't
mind like you and your friends are like best you and your thinking are kind of like best friends
and um and you enjoy each other what should I do mostly
I want to say one more thing about this world of thinking that maybe also is a
nice experiment to do that in different settings different ways we tap into different cognitive and
processing parts of the Mind and so how we understand or come to
understanding when we're left to ourselves just to think about ourselves privately in our minds
it can be very different than how we do so if we're talking out loud so I found that sometimes when I feel I
felt kind of challenged by life circumstances that I find it useful to um I do mostly
do it when I'm driving is to talk out loud to myself start talking about what's happening in
my life it kind of review it out loud or describe what's happening or my
relationship to it out loud because I found when I speak out loud it's like a
whole different part of my mind or my heart is engaged and if only involved in
discursive thinking which feels much more for me much more limited in quality
other times I find that thinking quietly to myself not talking out loud
changes where I am if I'm hiking in the forest then I I have a for me that's
this place where I feel much more peaceful and it's very reassuring to be in those environments and so I find that
changes how I think um if um if I'm exhausted I think a lot
more interestingly after I take a nap and I've been oppressed by my thinking
when I'm in sleepy and sleep deprived and um and then I realize you know Gil
you're not you're not thinking very well there's not much hope for you here
take a nap and then I take a nap and then the biggest problem I have with naps is I
don't want to wait I wake up but I don't want to get out of bed I'm just so content just looking at the
ceiling but then in that contentment my thinking has changed and I have a whole
different way of thinking so um so where you think how you think when
you think and whether you think out loud or think privately to yourself
um is these are all different things that um and also you might sometimes experiment to do is to put on music
do you think differently depending on the music you hear these are all ways of breaking the
hegemony of the discursive mind all these ways of not kind of assuming
just because you're how what you're thinking in one way that that's the nature of reality this is the truth this
has to be the way it is don't let your thinking mind have a
negative influence on you be very careful about that don't give it a lot of authority
and if you want if you want to give authority to some deep understanding deep wisdom you have to really dip down
below that discursive mind this curse of mind is kind of like a it's kind of like
a static that interferes with our ability to
connect with the deeper sources of wisdom and knowing we can have and the deeper sources of Courage
as we live our life so that's my non-talk
I hope that was okay some of you I think some of you think so
it might be relevant so uh it's 10 30 we usually go to 10 45
so if some of you would like to ask questions or commentary or
testimonials
thank you Gil if you can say you're named when you free speak it's kind of nice I'm Carla
um this was the perfect talk that I needed today I've been struggling
with these oppressive thoughts because I'm going through
very difficult situation a rift with my best friend and it seems like I can't bring us back
together and so I have these repetitive thoughts
I should have said this if only she thought that and then I'm trying to peel that away I'm telling
myself okay I'm defending myself for a reason oh because I'm feeling
shame because of the things she said to me I've been accepting her point of view
okay I actually have nothing but good will towards her I could set that aside
but then the feelings of the loss the feelings of the hurt
they just keep coming back the feelings seem to be the source causing the
thoughts as opposed to we usually talk about the reverse just won't resolve
any suggestions yeah sometimes our emotions are the source for how we think
and sometimes thinking is the trigger for the emotions and it's fascinating to see that which direction it goes at
different times and for you it sounds like uh there's something deeply emotional to you have
to sort through or to heal or understand so I'm glad that you understand what it is because that's probably where the
work really is and um so how since you know since you understand some of them and see them how
they shift and change over time you're you're kind of in a in a you know
that gives you an important kind of options for how to work with this and
one thing you might try doing is spend the next month or so because this is an important relationship so you don't want
to be in a hurry necessarily to solve it so spend the next month every day
writing a letter to your friend telling her what you want to say telling her
about all this about you know how you're feeling what's going on your shame your despair your well you know just put it
put write it all in the letter to your friend don't don't um don't send the letter
so let it be uncensored uninhibited just write it there this is not a time to be
censored or be inhibited or just write what's in your heart and if you're real for example if you're Furious just write
the fury just write what's happening you know and then maybe each day
um burn it or throw it away but do that do that for a month to really see if you
can kind of really uh get these feelings and emotions really known and expressed
and recognized and because without them without being really well recognized and given some
expression some respect that way they might not have a chance to move on to the next thing
all emotions want to move on that's why they're called motions emotions they want to move on but we tend to
bottle them up we tend to restrict them and hold them back and we get or get stuck in them and so sometimes there's
something a safe situation like writing a letter we're used right so it doesn't have to be a letter to your friend but simply where you write it and write it
and then and then you know throw it away so you don't have to even
go back and read it it's just you don't do the next day do it again and see after a month of doing
that see what happens that's really interesting it's like
getting those thoughts out putting them on paper and then walking away from it yeah yeah and some people will do this
and actually uh they don't just kind of just kind of crumple them up and put them in the trash can they um they do a
little ritual each time like maybe I don't know what the ritual would be but I've known people who have buried it in
a nice place like like a funeral you know for something something that's
healed right to you thank you
thank you
yes please
hi thank you very much this is a very very appropriate topic for me to hear from
you today the wisdom was very very insightful and very effective
a lot of times fear uncertainty and doubt fear uncertainty and doubt about a topic
perhaps maybe Health maybe some other career or you know issues and so forth create a uh as you as you call a
discursive thought that just never ends and it always an end product of it is just you dragged
you down and emotionally and thoughtfulness and it goes from bad to Wars you know as you call it so how
about the role of fact finding in trying to alleviate this fear
uncertainty a doubt in addition to calming down head your mind great very
nice well I think the first Factor disco to be clear about is that you have fear
uncertainty and doubt because to see oh this is this I don't know about anything else but I know this
is true because it's easy to be kind of swept into the uncertainty or the doubt and
the fear and it kind of pushing us around guiding us kind of kind of creating the whole mood that we're in
and and we don't but the idea in mind first practice is sometimes is take the attention 180 degrees around and look
something directly and maybe what needs to be seen is not the issue you have
like your health issue the first thing you need to really see is oh here's a lot of uncertainty of fear and doubt
if you see that carefully well then you can start and then sometimes
it's actually good to have some analysis of it they really think about this a little bit wait a minute I should think about this or talk to a friend here I
have uncertainty fear and doubt does it make sense that I have this or
do it does make sense that I say all three together in one breath maybe uncertainty is ordinary normal
part of human life doubt maybe that's is in some ways is
doubt appropriate how is it appropriate maybe sometimes it's appropriate to have doubt
fear that's appropriate sometimes but maybe but I don't have doubt maybe I have
anxiety maybe I can not maybe I can have uncertainty without fear
maybe I can have doubt without fear what would that be like it might be that fear is influencing
both the doubt and the uncertainty and so you're kind of like a little package and as long as you have that
package all neatly tied together there's no hope for you
and so you have to kind of tease it apart and uh and like one of the great many
spiritual teachers talk about the importance of being comfortable with uncertainty
being comfortable with insecurity and of course there's a lot of uncertainty in this life
and uh and so if you're always looking for certainty some people are neurotically looking for certainly all
the times I don't know if that's your case and the fear is very important too if there's a health issue it's appropriate
to have some fear and but then you distinguish the fear from the anxiety
which has to do with fantasy and projections into the future what's happening in you and really stop
and look and and um and take a look to go to that 180
degree turn and really study that and um
and then um so that's the first facts to look at and
once you do their homework of doing that course do research
of course you know about the health condition and the situation and find out and try to be careful to use good
sources and try to be careful to be Discerning what you read
you know but there's a lot of claims a lot of people say this is how it is so you want to kind of always
on what basis what's the support for their claim and is this just an opinion to see the
difference between opinion and a well-supported claim is important I think so there's a way of critical
thinking and investigation research that is it I think a part of a healthy
appropriate life um and if a person if you just kind of some people don't never occur to them to
do the research themselves and you just want to trust the doctors but they have doubts about the doctors and and then
they just feel lost in the whole so please so that was a long answer was that
appropriate holiday above thank you yeah one more and then we'll yeah here
we go hi Gail
um the way you explained writing the letter with the discursive thoughts
would that apply to discursive or repetitive
worry and thoughts of worry or concern that
they're never ending yeah I think if if there's a repetitive discursive worry it's repetitive worry
over and over again because it keeps coming back keeps coming back it's a sign that something uh that that
we're not understanding the full picture of what's happening with us and so you want to be able to stop and find it
figure out some way to look under the you know look under the hood of the car you know look underneath and see what's
really happening here for us what's driving it and and what am I avoiding what am I not seeing
and um and so there's different ways of doing that but one possibility is to write about it some people in writing
about it especially if it can be uninhibited it's just kind of like almost like a stream of Consciousness
thoughts about the worry and stuff like that that's we might be able to start
seeing Oh that's what I'm feeling that's what's going on for me I didn't know that yeah
thank you so does that make sense yes great
and um you know and if that doesn't help you then
then you know after a while don't do it if it doesn't show it doesn't reveal
something or support something or and again also sometimes as Carla pointed out you know sometimes it's really
healthy to have these things expressed because otherwise if they're bottled up inside of us then it can be they can
fester in there but even just talking to a friend about something or talking out
loud in a car or writing about it it's kind of like getting it off the chest and then it can have a very different
life inside of us things can move again I mean I I do
think about it and I do discuss it um
but I thought maybe writing it is is another level of yes I think writing is
a good thing especially when I guess I keep saying try to do it as uninhibited as possible
just dream of conscious let it just flow don't worry if it's true don't worry if it's
you know if it's you're expressing ugly emotions or if I sound like a crazy
don't worry if I sound like a crazy lunatic yes don't don't cry yeah yeah
you're allowed to be a crazy lunatic when you're writing and also the grammar doesn't have to be very good
spelling too spelling spelling is you know the doesn't matter handwriting
doesn't matter yes
I didn't think of it as journaling but but that's I guess that's a big term like broad term I guess
I guess how I thought about it in my mind but there's a journaling technique that
um kind of foregoes what the intellectual enters in and then you just go more into what's unconscious
subconscious what's not accessible is if you just journal with no nothing in mind
in terms of grammar the way you're writing and you go fast it allows you to
go a little bit deeper nice nice oh so in terms of you know thinking and
access there's interesting things I find uh when I exercise
um uh I love to I just give freedom to my mind I think whatever it wants it's one of the few places where it's got
total freedom to just think because when I meditate I'm busy meditating so but I don't have I don't
my thinking mind doesn't have a free reign but uh it's exercise has a free
reign and then I discover things about what I'm concerned about or what's going on and it's got a very it's a very kind
of an interesting place where to kind of discover because I it's kind of like just a just a free time to think
and um otherwise you know you know my life is doing things and thinking about
talks I'm supposed to give or you know I'm doing things you know my mind but to have so I think it's a healthy thing to
occasionally have give to your mind complete freedom in a safe environment exercising is what I found is nice
but it might be other other times so thank you so it's 10 45 it's time to
end and I'll stay here for another probably 10-15 minutes if some of you want to come up to the front and
continue some of these questions or discussions you're welcome to come uh and um
thank you for being here