so good morning a good day good afternoon good evening
welcome to our meditation time together
and uh imagining that
what it would look like if there was somehow lines looking from space looking
down at the Earth and seeing lines drawn between all of us
a line from each of us to all the others and what a marvelous web or net they
would create and maybe it's a line of Goodwill
friendliness care so thank you for being here
one way of understanding meditation is that
it can be a continual Act of appreciating oneself
and appreciating oneself and sometimes is in short supply
and so we practice it we practice it not to override or to
pretend or to have some kind of pollyanish attitude towards ourselves
but we find a way to appreciate ourselves
even knowing that we have maybe false knowing we have challenges
knowing we have things that maybe are hard to appreciate
but to not Define ourselves by the our faults or what's hard to appreciate
do not limit how we relate to ourselves based on those maybe even because of those it's so
important to expand the vision to see how we can respect our basic
Humanity just like we would respect to everybody else and in that respect to
have a fundamental appreciation
for our value for being alive for being a person for capacities
for our potential and that we're as Buddhist practitioners we are living ourselves into our
potential to be free to be kind to be caring
to be not caught
in anything that we come across in ourselves or in the world around us
and to have the opposite of appreciation for ourselves is to be caught in
something so to a continual Act of appreciating
ourselves this morning so to take a
um to assume a posture
that is right for you that would support you to be alert and
present and support you to have this practice of
self-appreciation self-respect
and to Relax The Gaze of your eyes
soften the muscles around your eyes
and if it feels comfortable closing your eyes
and then approaching your body
settling into your body
with a gentleness
to awaken a greater sensitivity to to your embodied experience
being here with a body with the weight of your body resting on
the chair a cushion floor a bed
and one way to appreciate oneself is to appreciate that you care enough
about yourself that you're meditating
that you're engaged in this practice is a wonderful thing
and there's a way of appreciating how caring for your breathing
is a good thing and you might gently
be quietly and without ambition to breathe in a little bit deeper
Fuller breaths Fuller inhales Fuller exhales
depreciating your breathing feeling it more fully
relaxing as you exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal and if there are difficult States for
you emotions or concerns
it's okay to have them to be that way
maybe appreciate yourself with them
in that whatever preoccupies you maybe at the root
they exist because
you're important you're valuable your well-being counts
your safety counts
appreciating that something deep inside wants to keep you safe once they keep you well
and
and if you have some sense of that to rest there breathe there
maybe that's one of the ways to appreciate yourself as you meditate
and if the mind wanders off in thought
appreciate yourself as you notice that that's the
case when you wake up to the fact you're thinking
in with appreciation or with delight
Begin Again with the breathing with the body
with present moment awareness
okay
in the last minutes of the meditation time
see if you can rest or abide
in a relaxed self-appreciation
in appreciation which takes very little effort
from which you recognize that non-appreciation takes more effort more stress
relax allow
Ed for an appreciation of yourself
or appreciation for this expression of life
that exists here in you with you in this body
and then to end this sitting
dedicating our practice for the welfare of others
and I would propose that
the less we appreciate ourselves the less were able to dedicate for the
welfare of others the more we appreciate
here this life within us this heart within us
this being we are
the more we have to offer others the more appreciation the full Earth
the stronger the more understanding more resonating
is our appreciation of others
and finding a way to always appreciate
always meet others with good will
so that our wish for the welfare and happiness of everyone
can be that way for everyone no one excluded
may all beings be appreciated
may all beings be respected
may all beings be free of our
judgments and hostility prejudice
may all beings
know that they are cared for may all beings be happy
safe peaceful
and free and may our capacity to appreciate
others support this as a possibility
[Music]
thank you
this is so here continuing with um
third talk on the joy of compassion
and perhaps it's the easiest to understand
that this Third Kind Of Joy related to compassion
and that is the joy of appreciation and when and when we appreciate others
when we appreciate anything ourselves included appreciation has a kind of a positive
feeling to it it's an uplifting feeling it's an opening feeling it's a
it's a delightful feeling and the Delight of appreciation the
light of saying oh this is good this is valuable this is something I care for this is something that is important and
this is something that um is well done and this is
something I celebrate so this idea of appreciation usually comes with a
positive disposition a positive feeling and so it may be easier to find the joy
of compassion this way and uh and this means that it's actually
important to practice appreciation or find how to appreciate others if we're going to be compassionate
I think it's easy enough to feel obligated to be compassionate to feel
that we feel the suffering of the world or suffering of others and we kind of
are buffeted by it or oppressed by it or contracted or tense because of it and we
feel like I have to do something I have to be compassionate and so one way or the other there's a
headlong movement into compassion into doing compassion doing what seems like
the right thing to do doing the helpful thing but it's not as long we want to be we
want to be heart long moving in with a heart we want to ideally take time
so that we're not doing compassion out of obligation we're not doing it as a
should that we have to kind of now deal with things but we want to do certainly want to act
compassionately in the world but let that compassion be a flowering of what's wonderful within us a flowering of
something which is medicine for the world and the world does not need more people who feel the weight and the
heaviness of obligation and its responsibility and uh and it kind of headlong you know attack on the causes
of of people suffering or something the world needs us to address the
suffering but to do it in a way that's medicine for the world that's uh that
supports it that's healing for the world and and brings out the best and best in people
and so appreciation for me is one of those qualities to take the time to
appreciate and of course sometimes it's hard to appreciate others so that the the kind
of in the same categories appreciation I I think of as I think is respect
that to respect everyone to express their respect their autonomy their
dignity their value respect their potential the two even if we disagree with someone
even if we feel like what they're doing is wrong
we never want to condemn people we never want to have hostility towards
anyone rather we want to have respect and with respect or with appreciation to say no
with with respect and appreciation of who someone is and say you know I
appreciate you I care about you but no you cannot do this this is not right
um uh but the the person clearly feels that we're not condemning them we're not
closing them down we're not judging all of who they are it's like that you're now a bad person or a wrong person
always so if you can't find appreciation maybe we could come to find
a place of respect and that relates to ourselves as well that if we can't find appreciation for
ourselves can we at least respect ourselves respect our basic human dignity basic
human value autonomy um the um
uh and there are professions in the world
where the fundamental ethical attitude that people are supposed to have like
doctors or nurses and medical folks is to have always respect
the dignity respect for the autonomy of people that are supporting
they might not love them but but they still have that respect
and so uh appreciation respect taking the time for that
uh finding out where you know and sometimes that's all that's needed is a little bit of time
I've been struck many times by how easy it is to rush through the supermarket
line where the clerk is there and you know kind of just not really take time
to to take in the clerk um but then at other times where I take
my time and the you know the extra second or two to look at this the
checkout clerk in the eye or appreciate them or ask a simple question you know
how are you or um you know so some some little comment
uh that makes a human connection and how there's this can be a spark of kind of
familiarity or recognition of something really nice that happens that doesn't come with
any requirements that it means in means or anything else or implies anything
else than just a recognition of our kindness or appreciation
many people are not appreciated enough in our society and so one way to
cultivate appreciation great appreciation for others is actually to take the time to appreciate folks say
thank you that was well done or that was uh helpful or you know that wasn't that
was wonderful thank you or find ways to appreciate people and and say it
and find out what goes on inside of you that it resists the expression of
appreciation I know for me sometimes it's been embarrassment sometimes it's been well if I appreciate them they're
going to want more from me and I'm kind of opening up myself to kind of not be
taken advantage of or um or it'll seem policy in pollyanish or
something but learning to find a way to in a healthy way appropriate way to
appreciate people because a lot of people are underappreciated for who they are
and um and uh I think there's a
a huge kind of um starvation of appreciation in many corners of our
world and so to offer appreciation helps to kind of move and and oil the gears of
appreciation inside of ourselves and what I found is that as I've
appreciated people more it seems to be kind of natural to appreciate myself
uh not that I'm trying extra to do it but just there's more space to do it
more room more less kind of being caught up in the negativity of life in the
version of how things are appreciation is a beautiful thing
so that but it takes time and I'd like to propose that kind of
healthy compassion takes time slow down
uh wait before you act compassionately and see if you can
have a little heightened awareness a little heightened Attunement and a
heightened appreciation uh and in doing that
finding the joy that the light the positivity the lightness the ease the openness it's a
beautiful thing to be compassionate it's wonderful to find that wonderfulness
it's wonderful to find that beauty that sweetness it's medicine for the world it's
medicine for ourselves so um
so today if you'd like to experiment or stretch yourself in this regard see if there's simple ways and
underscore the word simple so so because it can get complicated if it's if it's
complicated or or really big the appreciation but in simple ways I
appreciate the people around you I appreci appreciate strangers appreciate people who are helping you in
clerks or stores or places of work or anything offer appreciation and see what happens
to you as you appreciate others learn about yourself as you appreciate
so thank you and I certainly appreciate that all of you are here that you're
listening you're engaged in this uh these this this practice and that in
certain ways we all support each other to show up here for these teachings and be together and and it's a I I feel like
it's a wonderful thing and and uh it's been one of the
you know Bright Lights of the pandemic as we went through it and now we continue it's just a wonderful
thing so thank you and I look forward to tomorrow