how about a sound check Kevin can you hear me okay
okay and here's Diana it sounds a little bit yeah a little yeah it's a little bit
loud a little bit echoey yeah can we turn down mic two just a
tiny bit Yeah number two I just keep on talking they're very oh no it's still a
little bit loud I wonder if uh no to kind of go down a little bit just
a tiny bit yes it's too loud it's a little loud oh
okay good I can't tell so just a kid yeah well it'll be okay
I think this is better does this is this better yep okay
thank you thank you will the gain may be different
how is this can you hear uh through the hearing assisted device when um when I'm
using when the microphone is on does it work yeah yeah oh okay there we go okay
well here we are here we are welcome to week two of the five hindrances and
we're using some references from The Wizard of Oz to kind of explore the
hindrances so last week we just kind of did a an introductory and talked about
just introduce the five hindrances which are you know sensual desire agreed
aversion ill will sloth and torpor restlessness and worry and doubt and we
describe them as energies so is one one way and we've offered a few ways to
describe them but one was as energies and so if you think about the energy of Desire or sensual desire if there's an
energy of Leaning forward into wanting right to pull something to you
versus the energy of aversion and ill will which is a pushing away right there's this backward movement or this
shoving away movement um with the energy of sloth and tormper
it's actually a lack of energy right not enough energy to be awake and present
um and there's the there's two elements of the sloth and topper one has to do
within the body and the other has to do within the mind the next set of hindrances is
restlessness and worry which is too much energy so it's a body that is moving and
agitated and unable to settle or it's a mind that's worrying and
spinning and sort of unable to Center and rest
and then there's doubt and doubt is um it's sort of like it doesn't know what
direction to go in the energy and that's so there's a lot of starts
and stops kind of a no momentum has really established
um and uh yeah there's just not Clarity there's no Direction so that's the
hindrances as energy we also talked about them as veils things that obscure
things that make it difficult to see clearly and another offering was as things that
hamper hamper ability to practice to progress to be free
so I'm I'm wondering if anyone had any Reflections from this week
about noticing the hindrances were you able to and take our invitation
to play be a little bit more playful with the presence of hindrances
instead of kind of feeling burdened by them
any thoughts guso Kevin and Jay you weren't here but you're welcome to chime
in there's Mike's if anyone wants to share
thanks Kevin
yeah something that came last week that I keep needing to be reminded of is uh
you know there's the hindrance and you see it and then uh my usual reaction is
a lot of aversion to having is like oh I see it oh my God it shouldn't be there
and um so yeah it was kind of caught in it um a lot for today until uh recent Sid and
then I was sitting there and we were starting and I was looking at the sheet and I was like oh yeah and then uh relax
about it um the feeling of it so
um yeah I'm ready to keep listening all right thank you Kevin
maybe I'll add like it's so fantastic that you recognize there's the hindrance itself and then there's our reaction to
it and so often we have a version to aversion and then we have a version to a version to a version and on it goes but
it's really great to notice that there's we have the hindrances and then then extra is wanting it to not be there and
autistic
so maybe I'll just briefly say a few things about we're going to move into now tonight talking more about
um desire and ill will and so you know we kind of are using the
reference of The Wizard of Oz the movie to kind of bring a playful and energy to it but
also to it's an easy reference to sort of exaggerations it just makes it so easy to see them so
for example well first of all I want to say there's kind of the the hindrance of
greed and desire but there's also something called damachanda which is
more of a wholesome impulse a wholesome desire so we don't want to imply that
there's no broom or space for desire in our practice it's actually an important
part of the path of practice without a desire to be free we would not practice
and Dorothy in The Wizard of Oz is kind of an example of damachanda she really
wants to get home she wants to you know go get home which we'll talk more about
what that means so um but some classic examples right
are before Dorothy goes to Kansas or goes to the Oz she's in Kansas and she's
quite disenchanted with her life and she sings the song Somewhere Over the Rainbow right and it's like over the
way up high there's a land that I heard of in a lullaby somewhere over don't you want to I didn't know
I might say that we're off to see the wizard but this one I don't think so you're not going to sing though
the sky Over the Rainbow the skies are blue the dreams you dare to dream really do come true someday I'll wish upon a
star and wake up where the clouds are far behind me um where troubles melt like lemon drops
above the chimney tops you know it just kind of goes on and and
um it's clearly an example of her wanting things to be better prettier you
know she has a desire a sense desire for pleasure so that's kind of a you know
more subtle way it shows up and then when we land in the Land of Oz the
wicked witch shows up right and when she shows up she says
um to to Dorothy I want those shoes you
know and then she says I'll get those shoes my pretty right and this very
Wicked way um later she even says uh well so she's
wanting I guess I'm combining there's the greed I want those shoes you don't
want to get them later she then is like threatening bodily harm to get the shoes the
aversion that oh well follows on the heels of the green and then I wanted to sort of talk about
the Emerald City itself so this is the home of the Wizard of Oz
and you know it's a really seen through rose-colored glasses you know by the
munchkin so they're singing the song we're off to see the wizard the wonderful Wizard of Oz we hear he is a
wiz of a whiz if ever a whiz there was if ever or ever was there was The Wizard
of Oz is one because because because because the wonderful things he does
so there's no content in this there's nothing really it's just all this
because because right um and and then just about the city
itself right um it's full and built on sense desire
right it's like painted horses right it's like everybody
everything's green right it's just like fancy fancy the first place they take
Dorothy and the friends when they arrive is to this like little fix it up Factory
where they get their hair done and the Scarecrow gets new straw and the lion
gets you know detailed tin man has all his rust removed so
um so there's an example of where you see you know uh sense desire
um two two other things is just to reference the yellow brick road itself this you know it's like there's often
talked about as the gold standards painted gold right light gold and
and I think it also for me represents the momentum of greed right there's this momentum of building and moving toward
what you want so then in aversion we've got that basic wicked witch right you know I'll get you
my pretty she kidnaps her tells her she's gonna kill her sets the timer takes the monkeys and sends the the Toto
the monkey's off to drown Toto in the river right I mean classic extreme you
know extreme on a less extreme a little bit more subtle disguised level I'll bring up the
wizard himself right it's sort of like a version or hatred disguised as a promise
to help he sends Dorothy and her friends to the wicked witch to get her broom
what what you know and he says you go do this bring it back and I'll give you all what
you want false promise sending them into life-threatening situation he doesn't
think they're going to survive so to me this is a real example of ill will
so with that let me turn it over to Diana for the Dharma perspective
that was fun Tonya I don't think I will ever consider this movie the same again
especially when you would be the witch that was funny loving this
and I think it's good right because the hindrances I know for me I felt like it was a failing it was something when I
got cut with him I was saying like something's wrong with me in the practice so this is a lot of fun to kind of bring some levity to it
so I'm going to say a few more things maybe build on some what Tanya said
so just to reiterate the desire that's being pointed to
is not all desire of course right we need desire when we're hungry we desire to eat that's you
know such a natural part of Being Human the desire that's being pointed to here is we could say sensory desires so it's
the desire to have sense Pleasures things that taste good smell good feel
good these types of things and it's a hindrance when it's getting in the way
when it's hindering so we don't want to say that you know having some pleasurable experience is
inherently bad that's exactly where we don't want to go it becomes a hindrance when we are
thinking that pursuing Pleasures it will be a source of lasting happiness
and then we find ourselves on this hedonic treadmill trying to find the next one and then the next one the next one and we never get to more freedom so
it's kind of like the opposite of Freedom right is just pursuing the next sense pleasure
so one thing that we might say then that's so much about Buddhist practice this
whole practice is to help make this distinction okay so what kind of sensory desire is
skillful helpful healthy and what isn't and often we can't see this distinction
when we're in the midst of it but when the mind starts to settle down a little bit with some meditation and maybe with
some of the pointing that Tanya and I are doing or pointing that you've heard in Dharma talks or read in books or
something can help support that but to help make this distinction between what is helpful
and so in order to help with this make the distinction part
of what we need to do is just really get to know desire this sensory desire this desire for
Pleasures with the senses so that it can stop being a hindrance
and that we can understand whether it's helpful or not helpful so it's part of like to experience it
this sensory desires just a part of the human experience and instead of thinking
like okay this is a problem I have to do something about it it can be like oh here's an opportunity for me to learn
something here's an opportunity for me to see what's my relationship to these desires
am I holding on and thinking and hoping that okay this is going to make me happy
or are we looking at the objects and getting obsessed with the objects okay
look at that oh it's so beautiful as soon as I have that it's going to be great and wow look at the toaster as
soon as I get the new toaster making this up of course right then it's going to make breakfast so much better and
then once I have a good breakfast and my day is going to be better and then I can do all this kind of stuff so I just got to get the right toaster not too big not
too small you know this type of thing and we kind of start getting obsessed with the toaster
and not even recognizing how much as Tony was saying how we're like leaning
forward and we're just filled with kind of like this desire we might even say greed and we're completely detached from
our own experience detached from everything that's going around while we're clicking around on Amazon looking
for the perfect toaster so can we experience desire
and using as an opportunity to learn notice how we often kind of get obsessed with the object and get disconnected
from ourselves or notice how we might be projecting onto the object we're going to think
okay everything's going to be all right as soon as I get this course can say the same with a version
everything's going to be okay as soon as I get rid of this broken toaster that's taken up all
this space on my counter and I don't have room for the blender for my smoothies in the morning and I have to
make all that noise to move it around and I wake up my partner right these things that we do
so there are a few ways that um to help like well what is skillful desire what
isn't and here are some ways to maybe work with this does it get in the way
does it hinter does it get in the way if something's important to you
get in the way of your meditation practice does it get in the way of
feeling centered in your body does it get in the way to what your priorities
are in your life sometimes we are so busy pursuing the
next dopamine hit or something like that that um we fill our days with that
on the things that are really important to us get neglected so that's one way is it skillful or unskillful we could ask
ourselves is it getting in the way is there something else that we could be doing with our time and our energy
another thing that we can ask ourselves is that when we finally get attain
achieve what we're designed when we finally get that new toaster
does it bring the ease that we're expecting does it bring the
happiness does it bring a sense of freedom or we just immediately often oh okay no
I got the new toaster it doesn't match the dishwashers and I got to get a new dishwasher you know of course I'm making
this up but there's a way right in which there can just be it's we get to what
we're after but there's no sense of ease or satisfaction it's just like as I said
kind of like this hedonic treadmill so that's part of how we can discern is
whether it's helpful or not helpful so part of working with sensory desires
just to recognize it's happening and then to notice okay this is helpful
or unhelpful then some other things that we can do
is to look at what is the experience of Desiring
how does that feel how does it feel in the body Tonya talked about leaning forward and I
noticed that when I'm talking about desired I'm talking about toaster I just my body I was automatically going like this and there's this toaster out there
my body was automatically going forward like whether we think about it or not our body is you know often expressing
these things but it can be really helpful to notice what is the bodily experience
because if we pay attention we'll see that there's a certain amount of contraction or tightness or
there isn't a sense of ease and openness and relaxation there's a little bit more
of a doggedness like okay I gotta get this there's a certain tightness that's associated with it that often we don't
notice because we're paying attention to the object oh look how beautiful it is those
curves and it's shiny and it looks so great
Tony is loving it by the way I'm talking about the toaster I'm laughing about the way that you're talking about The Wizard
of Oz and this is great I think right the entrance is right we need to bring some levity to them
otherwise it can feel like oh heavy and but
so what can we do some things also is to maybe essentially
direct the Mind elsewhere away from that object of Desire one way we can practice
just in daily life and that might be a little bit of a little bit of
Destruction in terms of okay just what am I doing right now
and can I be embodied and present with what I'm doing
because sometimes what we're what we're doing is different than the desire like what we're doing is we're like trying to
find what it is that we're designing here I am leaning my body for it it's um so instead can we just be
present for our experience but maybe I'm not explaining this well that um maybe
like to apply ourselves a little bit more diligently or a little bit more energy to what we're doing uh maybe
that's distinct from the desire let's make that distinction so that maybe um if we're
standing in the kitchen just to be standing
for a trump if we're putting butter on the toast after it came out of the bad toaster then we can just like be with
that maybe I didn't explain that well but essentially it's kind of like
distracting yourself away from the desire and just be with what you're doing
and then something else that we can do is a support for practicing with desire is something that's not so easy to do
and really easy to miss is to notice the sense of ease
spaciousness is there when the desire is gone
and often we won't notice when the desire just goes away but it might be
like 10 minutes one hour 30 minutes I don't know how long later we're like oh yeah I don't have that desire anymore
and then just kind of feel in oh yeah there isn't that little sense of urgency
or tightness that was associated with it before the more often we can do this notice
this subtle sense of ease and freedom after the desire a husband satisfied
because once the body and the mind notice oh yeah not having it is actually
a pleasant state and really supports our being open to what's happening and what we might want
to do with our life then there'll be more inclination to connect with that
but this is not easy it takes kind of like a commitment or a reminder to
notice oh yeah I had that desire before and it's not here now
as to see the notice of the feeling so now I'll talk a little bit about kind
of like the flip side so aversion and ill will first I'll make a little bit of
a distinction between aversion and AOL aversion is just kind of like this pushing away just as Tanya said like
okay you know I don't want this and then for me I would say it will is like I don't want this and there's a little
flavor of hostility in there a little flavor of like dang it go away get out of here you know
something like that with a little bit of a of a tone or something like this
so sometimes um we might might say like anger or resentment or having a grudge or
resistance these types of things or associated with aversion and ill will
and as we talked about earlier we might even say that fear is here too but fear
is a is a part of hindrances and it will because sometimes
with the ill will is because we are afraid that that's going to be
uncomfortable or we're afraid that it's going to whatever it is we're afraid of
so we have a certain amount of get go away because we think it's gonna um we're afraid of it we don't want it to
be around like like The Wizard of Oz oh there you go thank you who was afraid of the wicked witch coming to the Land of
Oz and so it's like go away Dorothy thank you Tonya you're absolutely right
that's absolutely right and then just like I was saying with uh desire old turning away or aversion is
not bad right of course it's healthy to have boundaries to say okay this is
acceptable this isn't I'm willing this is okay to have in my experience and this isn't I'm gonna walk away from
somebody who's yelling at me that's inappropriate for them to be treating me that way and to be walking away right
that's not a hindrance so it's the same thing for it to have the sensitivity of okay is this skillful
or unskillful is this helpful or unhelpful just in the same way that we're going to
do with desire and in the same way with a desire just
to recognize that the role of understanding it
requires that we be present when it's there so to have this how does it feel in the
body what is the mind doing when we have this sense of aversion again we will feel a certain sense of
contraction and in the same way with desire I should say there can be a strong sense of me here and that thing
over there there's a really strong sense that there's these two things me against
the world in some kind of way so that thing over there I either want it or I don't want it and there's a real strong
sense of me here and this can be uh vague when I'm
talking about this but if you tune in you can notice that when we're not filled with desire or it will that the
sense of me being isolated and separate and disdained from everything else isn't
so strong and when that isn't so strong there's also more ease more freedom and peace
so one thing that we can also look at for desire I'm sorry for ill will
is to if especially if this is like a habit of ours is to notice what purpose
does it have in our life what's like underneath fueling it
some examples might be that we have some beliefs that we have some
beliefs that maybe aren't so clear for example
I can keep myself safe if I push everything away that's going to make me
uncomfortable this is a way to make myself safe or maybe we can have this um
having it will gives me a sense of Vitality like when we're really angry or
mad and trying to get rid of something there's a energy that goes through and it's like it feels like we're alive there's a little bit of drama associated
with it and we feel alive I mean it might feel like if I don't
have that then what would my life feel like or maybe we might have a another sense
of well I'm a person that belongs to this group
and this group likes this and doesn't like that so I don't like that and I
really don't like that because I want to be part of this group and so it's a way in which our sense of
identity is can be associated with you know having some ill will or some aversion towards something maybe the
same way with the desire to so just to have a some curiosity about like
what's underneath what's fueling and to recognize that there's often some hidden beliefs about it
and then maybe the last thing that I'll say about uh ill will or aversion is we kind of
actively apply an antidote and the obvious one is loving-kindness
so if you have a loving kindness practice you can bring this bring it in I'm not going to go into details about
what loving-kindness practice is but I do want to say one thing I am not
talking about having loving kindness for the same thing that we have ill will for that's a really tall order
what I'm talking about is just changing the ecosystem Inside the Mind
into like soften and like disrupt the momentum so loving kindness practice is
to like bring to mind the easiest thing to have loving kindness for kittens
puppies babies grandkids pets this type of thing bring those to mine and you
notice how when you bring those to mine right then the the temperature of the ill Wellness version can come down
so that's Diana's little desire and aversion a little overview of that and
I'll turn it back to Tanya
you guys ready to do a practice great
so I'll guide you through the practice of raft it's an acronym I'll tell you what each letter stands for
R is the recognition a is allowing f is finding it and feeling it
there's two T's the first is teasing apart most simply put what's going on
from our reaction to it but it can be much more complicated and the last T is finding what we can
trust in our practice so I'll guide you through it but I just wanted to give you the lay of the land
before we start so taking just a minute to settle in I'm
going to drop in a question for you to kind of just see what what
answer arrives and the first thing I want you to do is
to notice whenever your answer arrives if this is something that's just kind of
too big to work with right now and if it is just ask yourself the question again okay
so the question is what do I think needs to be different in
my life right now
so allowing yourself to connect or choose an answer
that feels like something that you can work with in this practice and that's in this room without getting kind of
overwhelmed
so do you all have a sense of something that you think needs to be different in
your life right now it could be very small
yes yes great yeah Jay
they're all big no small [Music]
yeah I got laid off recently yeah but in the small area I could say
he didn't require okay
okay great great perfect okay
all right so now the first thing to do so you've got your thing
now just check in we're recognizing we want something to be different
do we want it to be better so is there some greed present
do we want it to go away is there some aversion present so is there a leaning
in or a pushing away so just recognize the hindrance
or hindrances
once we've recognized it if it's permissible to you
we want to allow ourselves to be in the company of the hindrance
to see if we can't turn toward the hindrance itself
and it doesn't mean endorsing it doesn't mean you know we're going to
give in to it but it does mean we're going to stop
fighting with it for a moment and allow ourselves to kind of turn Face
to Face and as we do as we find ourselves
turning toward see if you can shift your awareness into
your body see if you can find and feel where the
energy of the hindrance is manifesting in your body
what does it feel like what part of your body
or parts of your body can you notice it in
you might notice it in your throat your chest your hands
your shoulders your neck you might notice it in your eyebrows and
the little scrunch between your eyes
getting quiet enough to be able to receive the sensations in
the body connected to the hindrance
seeing if you can keep bringing your awareness back to the sensations instead of the story
ideas if you have a thought try and follow
them like a vibration into the body
notice if it's changing we'll do one of three things right
can grow can diminish or stay the same what's
happening for you In This Moment
breathing and sensing
being as simple as we can with the experience
at some point when you're ready
you can move to the next part of the practice
in the simplest part of this teasing apart is to see if you can't
first just acknowledge there is the thing that we think needs to be different whatever it is
and then our reaction to it and that's the wanting or not wanting the reaction
for me I find it very helpful to imagine a very spacious room
with a round table and as many chairs as I need
and with each thing that I see is part of this for example the thing that I think needs
to be different can have a chair a seat at the table and my response to it can have another
chair inviting them to sit down
see them separately
and as you do you may realize there are some other
things that are present here
perhaps there's an idea of you an opinion A belief that has to
do with why you think you need this thing to be different
maybe there's an imagined future that feels threatened and it too needs a
seat at the table
there could also be memories from the past
the way it used to be
or a different experience altogether that is somehow connected to this one
allowing everything to have as much space as it needs
some of these things you may not want to go near and that's fine
some of these things you might feel comfortable sitting down next to
another question you can ask is what is the purpose of the hindrance
here
what is it trying to do
you could also ask what's feeding or fueling the hindrance
what's keeping it going
and there's no need to create answers if there's an answer that arises
allow it to have a seat if not no problem
we're just trying to untangle not create more Tangles right so just simply allowing yourself to
acknowledge the different pieces that come to you that are part of the situation
and at some point if you feel settled like you're seen clearly
you can move on to the next part of the practice this is about trust
what can we trust about our practice
about what we've experienced or seen
what does it feel like to rest and Trust
can we remind ourselves that the hindrance is not Who We Are
if there's any sense of ease
try to orient toward that ease
just breathing gently with it
sometimes if I'm having a hard time resting in the sense of ease or trust I
might remind myself that this experience the hindrance or
whatever's going on is will change
that the way I'm feeling now will change probably fairly quickly in some way or
another
sometimes I just it's really helpful to remind myself that I'm not my experience I'm not limited by
what's happening doesn't Define me
and that it's nature really it's something that comes and goes in
all of our minds and hearts
and if it's really hard I might even put my hand on my heart
kind of feel the warmth of my hand there
breathing into my heart I might say something like may I be at
ease may I have well-being
may I be safe from harm
to taking a few more wait minutes to practice in a way that feels supportive
for you
[Music]
foreign thank you Tanya
so Tanya walked us through our recognize a allow F feel in the body
T tease apart with sitting around the table it was very interesting to have these different ideas sit around the
table and then to trust maybe some softening I don't think you
used exactly that word but and then even a little bit of loving kindness at the end
so we'd love to hear from you guys how was that how was that meditation or
maybe you have some questions about the hindrances in general or maybe even The Wizard of Oz
[Laughter] Tony I'll maybe I'll just say one tiny thing that I just imagined you watching
this movie with your kids and it made me just really happy when during that meditation so
I thought it was super helpful when you did the table I was like I don't know how many chairs
I can fill and then they kept coming and I kept adding chairs and it was just kind of nice I sat at the table for a
really long time and just recognized
I don't know if I put it in there I didn't want to throw on too much but it can also be helpful to allow the the
chairs to have relative size you know to like oh that thing is huge
that thing's kind of small and then there's the possibility of a whole new
set of insights can come I found myself starting to I was kept
moving over yeah good yeah okay we're here
yeah it can be as big as it needs to be and and allowing the space to expand as
well just if you feel you need more space it's right there yeah yeah very
nice
foreign yeah I really appreciated the um the meditation I think
between the two of you I was uh uh working through some of the stuff you
were talking about as you were talking and then part way through uh through the sit it
kind of just dissolved on its own and I just stopped paying attention to what you're saying I was just like appreciating it
um so it was really wonderful wise of you Kevin to let it just sit
because one thing I didn't mention but I like to say is we don't always have to
go all the way through sometimes it's the simple Act of recognition and that's all that's needed
like there's an almost an instant recognizing and allowing and it just dissolves
so you only go as far as you need to go you know in the practice sometimes
there's really nothing to tease apart so you can just you know it's just kind of letting yourself rest
so yeah thank you for sharing that or maybe it even starts with feeling in
the body maybe just like oh there's some tightness here and then there's a
recognition allowing or maybe there's just something in the body and then some allowing so all right f t is nice I like
this idea of a raft that's going to take us over to safety or something like this but it doesn't have to we don't have to
do that acronym in that order and I won't say what other words I have thought of other words that uh
oh never mind [Laughter] you'll have to tell me later
anybody else have a comment or
so um what if it's something that you wanted to fix a bunch of times in your life you
have fixed it before you're looking at it again how does that change
if anything yeah well I mean just for tonight part of it was trying to could
you feel there's what you want to change could you feel into just that feeling of
wanting to change it oh sure great okay so part of that tonight was just about
like this trying to get used to and recognize what the hindrance the not liking or the not wanting or the wanting
right feels like the impact of it so okay and so your question what if you've
already changed this thing many times and now you want to change it again
so can I ask you a question sure why are you asking this question
partially yes intellectual intellectual interest does it change the the model at all okay
okay is there an additional Insight that comes from thinking about some of these things do recur right and is there
wisdom and when you look at it a second third fourth time uh is there some additional
thing that comes that can be brought to bear mostly intellectual and interesting yeah
well I would say this is not an it's not an intellectual practice
no my question is it comes from yes but if you ask me why why the question yeah yeah yeah and so I would say experience
it find out you know what I mean like because the answer could be there's more there's not
more but you won't you wouldn't know that until until you did the practice does that make sense
maybe Diana if you have a a response uh yeah because maybe if something
that's recurring and you've done it before I would say pay attention to what's fueling it why is it recurring
but the uh when I'm saying pay attention I'm not necessarily saying dig and
figure it out it's maybe like Drop in like what is fueling this kind of like this dropping
in this question I'm doing this with my hands because it is more like an opening and like I wonder why this is occurring
so it's a spirit of curiosity as opposed to I got to figure this out and sometimes when we do that then something
new will Bubble Up and then we can maybe work with whatever the new thing is sometimes if something is repeating
there's a reason and there's something underneath it so that might be something I could offer
so we might learn something about ourselves some of our beliefs that we have that are fueling these types of
things and it's these underlying beliefs that are when we recognize them and allow
them to lose some of their Authority this is where a real transformation happens
yes thank you that's I thought of that too that's a great idea just bring this to the table that I do I've done this so
many times before okay you get to sit in that chair yeah put a bigger chair
okay so now I'd like to provide an opportunity for you guys to talk to each other
and about this and maybe we'll just have them be in one group together yeah
so we'll just uh we can go around this circle you guys will make a little
circle and then just one person will speak well everybody else is listening and then the next person will go the
next person the next person and we'll um do two questions and I'll give you one and then after I give you guys some time
then I do the second one so maybe spend two minutes on your description or of
what you're discussing two minutes each yeah sorry
um so the first one is what role
does the pursuit of sensory pleasure or ill will have in your life is this something that is a real dominant
feature that you're seeing showing up all over the place where you're like no I'm pretty equanimous most of the time
where are you finding yeah I my um ill will my anger gets me into a lot of
trouble or my shopping all the time gets me into trouble or something you don't have to share your deep dark secrets but
just this recognition what role do they have in your life
so and I'll just add it could be protective roles yeah very nice right it's not just that it gets you in
trouble but it may be it distracts you from something that's difficult you know
so just just to like kind of because maybe there's a better way to do it but still it's how it has a role thank you
thank you and maybe talk about the magnitude like it's really big or really small or
something like this then after you guys have been in a circle for a little bit then I'll give you a second question so
if you guys want to sit closer so you don't have to yell across the room
so two minutes per person yeah yeah two two minutes per person sorry I didn't
make that clear
thank you
hey you guys finished we finished around the same time so here's the second question
what meaningful or satisfying feelings do you have that are not connected the sensory
desire or ill will like what else in your life what are alternatives to sensory desire or ill will what are
meaningful or satisfying feelings you have which are not connected to sensory
desire or AOL yeah generosity gratitude
love you know these these types of things so what are some of the
I mean some of the feelings that you have and we'll just do the same thing going around the circle
thank you
thank you I actually started singing myself
it's not music is it is
have you finished did you all get a chance to share great you feel like
sharing it all about your sharing or meta sharing
you know what was the value of this time together for you
any questions
it all starts that uh I shared with Tanya like
before I like started this practice I had no idea how much like the this kind of like desire was like so much a part
of my life I'm like always trying to get the next thing sometimes it's books or yeah I don't
know it's what's amazing to see and how much a habit it is kind of like
okay I wanna start a new habit okay well then I must need to buy something in order that I
can start a gratitude practice I need a gratitude journal or I don't know I'm just you know it's just kind of it's
quite something so with practice it definitely has lesson
but sometimes I find myself
anybody else want to like talk about I don't have to as I said share any deep dark secrets but what was it like to
look at the role of Desire nail will and then after that to look at okay what are
some things that are nourishing and supportive that are independent
desire now well how was how was that like the contrast maybe between the two
[Laughter]
I was talking a lot about how anger and fear are really big for me
in my life right now and often it can feel like a really big
chair so what I do is I find myself sitting in a bench on a bench at a park
um watching the dogs and the kids and the Nate like the trees and the birds
you know you just kind of get lost in the nature of Life happening and it
helps me a lot yeah yeah stick yeah it's amazing right spending
time in nature it's like really you know how supportive for whatever is going on
even when you're really happy it's nice to be a teacher yeah thank you thank you
yeah yeah I had mentioned I don't know if it's distracting me from dealing with the
actual hindrances but it feels good so yeah yeah I I wouldn't worry whether
it's distracting you sometimes we need to spend time on side hanging out with trees and dogs and kids
well then um by abandoning the hindrances you know by by picking up the
nature you abandon the hindrance right so it's a beautiful thing it's wise
effort you know you're redirecting your attention
um yeah I I found it um yeah talking about
um kind of the challenges and then when you pose the question what doesn't I was like oh this is great
um it was really nice to compare and contrast um I guess the clinging the non-clinging
and keep things in perspective but I also found it really interesting
to listen to everyone else what supports them and I think I'm going to steal all your guys's things
hopefully it's given freely and um yeah and it was also really nice just
to be in the community
but um so there's you know generosity nature
um connecting with the Arts you know this creativity
um yeah and actually Gus did mention he joined the choir I started taking voice
lessons recently but I just go karaoke by myself I was like oh I think a choir would be that that sounds cool
yeah it's like uh joining your voices together that sounds interesting yeah
one of the things I realized is that um
sometimes you can get real learning you're going to recognize the term from orthogonal sources right I mean not
along the path of where you're headed but things that you don't really would not consider but
if you put yourself in those situations and if you are open to that learning will come in a way that is not
predictable a priori but being in them
uh is very helpful and that that was part of the I mean I was just mentioning
I decided a couple months ago that every week I'm gonna go do something with the Arts period whether I go see a symphony or a museum or whatever just do
something right because in the end it feeds my soul this is something I've known all my life but you
know I haven't done a lot of and so like no just just go do it and it may not be directly
predictable how that's going to impact me but it doesn't matter it it is something that when I do it
I feel awe and I feel Joy I feel gratitude and it's totally
separate from the the craving and the diversion right
thank you guys nice can I come with you
go to the museum yeah we can all go together
[Music] girl
okay sorry use the Michael yeah
um so I realized one of these one of my
um weak areas of practice with generosity I
could do mindfulness of breath you know body scans what all this stuff whether it's not having a regular
generosity part and it was not integrated and I remember you know listening to
some drama talks and Gil was talking the emphasis on it and some examples they give us great and I
won't go into that but the point that they wanted me to share is so I figured out okay in my budget
what can I do so I have some you know severe Financial limitations
and you know in my area there's a lot of homeless quite now it's even really
severe and sometimes even like food they would not take and but I figured out almost
everybody would take like a cold soda not Coke and those are really cheap if you buy
like three 12 packs they give you two for free in safe years and I can buy like huge amounts and it's pretty cheap it's like you know
40 cents a can or something so I throw it in the fridge and every day I'll put two in my backpack and before I
come home they have to be gone so my part of my mind is scanning for okay who can I give it who can I give it
and sometimes it's honestly a homeless guy some guy a security guard at the door like yourself travel friendship and
say hey you want to soda and it it opens the door to a conversation sometimes you know and you know if it's just a bridge
sometimes and sometimes it's the homeless guys love just it's not the coke even you know for them it's like
you see me you know they feel so invisible everybody's walking by non-stop he's got this thing on and
there's so many homeless people also overwhelmed you know and just this even if it's not like hundred bucks it's like
okay wow you know somebody sees me you know so and just in that I can't I can I can I can feel it because even when he
says that God bless you you can feel the sort of almost a grief in him of you know I need to be touched and so on
so you know it's been an experiment for a few months now and so far I'm loving
it I'm not stopped you know so it's still going well there's such a budget in my budget
what a great idea beautiful great idea I hadn't thought of that it's such a great
idea and I can imagine even if you're homeless maybe you don't have cold drinks very often either exactly yeah I
usually just give you know regular dinner list the cold adds an extra punch to it you know they're like whoa it's cold
it reminds me of a practice I did for a while which was to like literally
when I was approaching a crosswalk or a four-way stop to really stop early
like so that if there was any pedestrians there was a generosity of space
right this essence of offering safeness to people and it would create a
connection often that people would really like it they kind of would take it in make eye contact or or I just felt
Joy because it just felt like a sweet thing to be doing yeah
I think it's nice to be creative about how we are generous with others because there's there's what we do with that has
to do with objects and money but there's also what we give with our attention
which you're also describing right giving your attention acknowledging someone
you know yeah that's great
well anything else so it's great I loved hearing from you
guys yeah really really lovely really fun so um maybe I'll just do a very brief
summary of the key points and um and then we'll we'll wrap it up
so I think just the reminder reminder so you've heard this before is
to invite more of a sense of curiosity lightness playfulness
when you are working with experiencing thinking about the hindrances
just think about the Wizard of Oz foreign and remember we're not saying that all
desire is bad or that all you know aversion is bad you know it's is it
hindering is it wholesome is it skillful if it's not hindering
you know great right if it's not causing harm
you know just watch out for your clinging watch out for identifying with it right
um so you know some of the skillful things are to if you see like the most subtle
lay at level is you can kind of try and ignore the ill will and just kind of redirect your energy right or your
desire trying not to feed it so just don't you don't have to give it a ton of
attention is one method another is to reactively redirect your attention right
to or try and re-engage in a different way that isn't feeding into the desire
or aversion to notice what you're doing that feeds
it and stop feeding it if possible like you know
um we can you know feed a version if we
think that you know for example if we're being critical of something
maybe our boss who's you know and our co-workers appreciate that we're being
critical because we're speaking to a problem
wanting our approval of our co-workers or wanting to advocate for them can be
feeding aversion in that situation so we need to pay attention to like
what's feeding it and then make sure we check ourselves and that we're not engaging in things that are causing harm
it's helpful sometimes to to kind of pull away or remove things that trigger aversion and and desire you know like
maybe you don't go on Amazon you know maybe there's various things
that you do to kind of take a break right from the normal triggers
um and really notice when when the you know desire and aversion are present and
then when they're gone don't just not just when they're there but when are they absent
and when they're absent appreciate what it that absence feels
like usually there's a sense of more being at ease more being settled
there's not this and there's not that it's more
so notice that savor it appreciate it and try and sustain it so you might
notice then the mind oh my God it's so relentless pretty soon you can start to
feel and the mind will just offer this next thing you need to go get or do or get rid of
and if you're if you're staying close closer to the ease you can feel the dis-ease that starts to
arise with that and you might say not now not now
all right Diana you wanna you know I have uh here my my job now is
to remind about the homework but the homework that I have written down I don't think it's for this no the hinders
didn't get updated so um it's on the handout though right yes and of course I
only brought one of the two handouts so you know so I'll just make up some homework great
I think it could be really helpful to like before our meditation period to
remember tap into what you talked about those things that are supportive that
are not with desire and ill will going to the Arts being generous with the homeless spending time in nature just
bring those to mind before your meditation period and just see how meditation unfolds
just like how does that support the maybe some openness or some ease with meditation
so play around with that okay so here we are at the top of the
hour it was uh great being here with you guys practicing together
and we'll see you next week thank you