greetings everybody I'm touched to be
arrogant with all of you I've been a participant in this
Forum ever since it started and um it's really quite something that
that gill created here and that all of you and all of us
have helped to create this this family of
practitioners
so to begin the meditation
take your meditation and posture
upright a little bit more upright than usual may
be but even more important relaxed
to the extent possible
lowers your eyes
and take a little trip inside your body
starting with the feet
and wherever you scan through see if you can also uh when becoming
conscious of something like the feet relax the feet
and the legs
the hips
the belly
moving up to the Heart Center
and feel what the
predominant flavor of the heart center is right now
it might be open and receptive it might be anxious
fearful or lacking in confidence
or it might be brimming with joy or
it might be grieving
as you well know however it is that's just fine
because that is our lived reality
and if there is a key to Awakening
the key is to be able to cultivate
our lived experience and as you know our lived experience
occurs only in the present moment
we can't live in the past we may want to remake the past or dwell
in the past or uh recriminate
but that's not the door to Awakening and if we're an anxious type we might be
planning or thinking of what we're going to do next or you know preparing for the next thing
and so living in the future as you know
is not the door to Awakening either
so the simple profound ask
in front of us as we meditate is to just be here
with whatever arises
in the last series that I gave in February
the theme was opening the Dharma heart
and in my own experience this opening of the heart
has not been easy has not been terribly straightforward
and has taken a long time and still has a ways to go
so again you know don't uh sit on a realistic expectations for your
meditation uh saying that there's something wrong with you if you can't
just stay in the present moment this is a
a sort of wisdom really that we have to cultivate
because it is not innate
unfortunately what is innate in US
is reactivity either we're grasping
and wanting more of something that's Pleasant or we have a version that we're turning
away from something we don't want to experience
and the only way to
be able to make the choice of living even if it's just for a few
seconds in the present moment
is to um have well cultivated
mindfulness so that uh
our mindfulness as we cultivate it it comes
more and more continuous but when we're beginners
um you know it this kind of uh
awareness real awareness in the present moment not
someplace else not on the thought drains not in their recriminations
or the fantasies just being satisfied enough
with this moment that's the key
to be able being to learning to be able to um
have awareness mindfulness that is more continuous
and that's what allows us to go deeper in meditation
so we were doing a body scan and uh we've been in the Heart Center for a
while so now let's continue um
with the shoulders or any tension in the shoulders we might
be able to let go of or if it's
not possible to let go to soften around it
and going down the arms the elbows
the forearms the wrists
and the hands what might we let go of here
and now coming into the head area
take a moment to see if the head is
easily supported by the spinal column not
grouping forward not leaning back
because or to one side or to another
because if the head is not well centered uh with our
um source of gravity that creates additional tension which
makes it harder to be present
and now taking a long deep inhale
followed by a long complete exhale
and now following the cycle of the breath
I like to think of the cycle of the breath as um
an oval this is not uh Buddhist but I've found
it useful and the oval begins uh at the perineum
and goes up the back and then continues
over the head and over the
the fontanelle which is that little space between the bones of the skull
which is still an open Gateway and then down the front
slowly so at whatever rhythm
is your rhythm doesn't matter if it's fast or slow or medium
follow your natural breathing and if you like the idea of trying out
this oval going up in the back over the head and down in the front and
then returning to the perineum and starting over again please feel free
to try it out and if that's not your cup of tea
just do it your way that's fine
though Our intention for the rest of this meditation
is to um the extent possible
stay with the breath on the whole cycle of the inhale and the
exhale
and if a slight smile should come to your lips
that may Express the flavor of joy
which is nourishment for staying here in the present
in the last few minutes of this sitting
the invitation is to
discern or get in touch with the flavor
of your experience In This Moment
maybe it's sweet salty
bitter
however it is sour
let that be known and accept it
so we breathe in our
internal reality with things just the way they are
we don't need to change anything
to appreciate being alive
and as we come to the end of this sitting
let's take a moment to
offer the benefits of our practice
through all beings everywhere without exception
we have had the Good Fortune to embark on this beautiful path
and of course it has its ups and downs
but little by little we become more and more
able to be aware to dwell in our awareness in the
present moment and to be satisfied
with the gift of the breath
not needing anything else
so by the goodness of our practice
we open our hearts and radiate
good wishes to all beings
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
[Music] foreign
[Music] thank you
greetings everyone it's a a genuine Delight
to the back here practicing with all of you many of you uh
have been in this Dharma group since its Inception
uh in the spring of 2020 uh as I have been and um
I think it's it's remarkable um The Meditation community
that we've been able to create together and I do mean together
uh of course you know we owe everything to Gill who've initiated this
but the way this meditation group has evolved
has been in response to all of the participants all over the world
so um I would just like to honor uh everything that all of you have
brought to this community and continue to bring to this community
when I um was standing in for Gill in February
I talked about opening the Dharma heart
and um
and I made some reference to my own path and my own difficulties
and opening my heart
and um I I would just like to share with all of
you that if you find this practice not so easy you're not alone and I I'm with
you on that um
it takes up for some of us it takes a long time for some of us you know some of us are
Naturals and you know we uh become free rather or at least the the
initial stages of Freedom we can manage to do that relatively quickly
but for many of us um it takes
not just years but in my case decades
so it's really important not to set the bar too high
um because if we do we'll get frustrated and
we won't um we may be discouraged and we may quit
but I think all of you who have been practicing for some time if you look back on
how you were before you started practicing and then
how you developed over time chances are
um you've learned some things and chances are you're a little bit more comfortable in
this body and mind and at ease in this body and mind
then you may have been before you started
so for this coming week um a theme that I've chosen
is tastes of freedom
and freedom is a big word and there are many degrees of freedom
there's a whole gamut of a little little smidgens of freedom and
then something a little bit more substantial and then maybe a little bit deeper or
maybe a little bit more embodied and Lasting
um but for most of us it does take time
but I do believe strongly that even as relative beginners if we
can taste something of the freedom that's in store as
we can see in the suttas from Buddha's own experience and the
experience of all the arahans whether they're monks or nuns or laymen
or lay women or gender free you know
um
it is very very valuable to have even the tiniest Taste of freedom
so uh my program for the week is is kind of ambitious and I'll do my very best to
uh be as inclusive as I can and make it as
accessible as possible but we are going to look in look at
um this week four of the
um
and relatively advanced advanced I guess we have to say it Advanced states of
meditation that support our practice they support the seven factors of
Awakening they support especially our meditation
and in the suttas
um it is clearly
described that um Enlightenment doesn't come as a
thunderbolt out of the sky it comes from dedicated meditation
practice that is so uh artfelt and
continuous that we little by little make progress
in letting go of our attachments letting go of grasping
through what we like and what we want more of and letting go of being aversive
to what we don't like and want to push away
and finding our peace in this body and mind the way it is
right here right now in this moment
so I was um
pleased to listen uh to some of Ying's
teachings last week and uh the theme that
she uh spoke about uh namely the the multi-dimensional
multi-faceted um realm of practice
uh practice that includes much more than just meditation practice that includes
all of us all of our life and um
she's there shared some lovely stories from Gill's little uh Treasury
of stories called the monastery Within
and this is this is a lovely thing and in fact
it um Segways beautifully into
what I had chosen to talk about this week which is tastes of freedom
the monastery within um I think we can
we can say that the monastery within is who we are it's us it's
it's inside here uh it's not you know someplace else
and what that means is that
as our meditation deepens and we are able to little by little
step into States of samadhi
that's the monastery Within
that's what opens the doors to Freedom
and um you know as I as I drilled on in
the meditation and mentioned at the
beginning of this talk um
we need to be we need to cultivate patients to be able to really enter into that Monastery Within
and then um I was
um corresponding with Kim Allen who's going to teach next week
and she asked me what my theme was going to be because she didn't want to overlap and I told her
and she said oh that's great um I think that'll that'll work with mine nicely and so I asked her what her
thing was going to be and hers is savers
so mine this week is taste tastes of Freedom Savers or freedom
and next week you'll get a lovely I'm sure um
five days of teaching on the emotional tones of a teaching the the word in in
Pali is Raza and that means tastes are savers
so um with that I would like to
[Music] um express my appreciation
or the practice that each of you brings to this community
and that each of you all of us offer to everyone we come in contact with
and that radiates out of that Circle to wider and wider circles like a pebble
being dropped into a calm lake
so with this bow I
express my gratitude for your practice and end this talk
and I look forward to seeing you tomorrow
okay Mega we'll go ahead and uh if anyone has any questions on Zoom
you can go ahead and raise your virtual hand I guess and
we'll unmute you and you can ask your questions so give us some time for people to collect their thoughts
given you do the selection please sure we'll do Okay so we've got Luna
hey Luna you can go ahead hi
um thank you for offering this morning um I just had a little Flash
when you were talking about patients how how patience and Equanimity feel very
similar um but it's just a body feeling and I
don't know how so I wonder you have any thoughts on that
uh I think you hit the nail on the head um
you know they're in in this uh this volume of teachings there are many uh
dharmalists um one of them is the seven factors of Awakening
and um in that Equanimity comes at the very
end because it's the it's the highest of them all and in fact in every list that
Equanimity is part of it's always at the end because it's the ultimate in the Brahma viharas
um the four flavors of love whether it's meta or
um whether let's just say whether it's friendliness or Compassion or
sympathetic Joy or equanimity and there's also another list of the 10
parameters in which patients is highlighted as very
important quality to cultivate and for many of us it's not it's not so
natural you know it's easy to get ahead of ourselves it's easy to you know want some kind of
success earlier rather than later and so every time we find ourselves
becoming impatient or maybe actually if we've gone too far and we've become
impatient then we we can say oh welcome welcome in patients I know you
um I think I'm not going there right now kind of like you know if you meet Mara
the tempter um you you you slow down enough so that
you can recognize that you're impatient and then you can say no thank you
is that make any sense
yeah totally thank you so much pleasure
okay Hugh you can go ahead and unmute thank you Mark
um make uh early in your talk here said that um
a fontanelle is still an open Gateway
I've heard of some say that the Foster Mill closes in early adulthood
that you expand a a little more on that
sure um so what you say is correct if we're talking about physiology
so when we were babies we all had fontanels were wide open you know
and as adults there's still you know a little a little opening in there but I
was referring to and when I started talking about this I said this is not these are not Buddhist teachings this is
different so you want you won't find anything about this in the Buddhist scriptures about the chakras and you know the
openings to the cosmic energy and to the Earth Energy um
but I've done a lot of uh Qigong practice and have been very influenced by the
idea of um you know if if you really do sit up straight and your head is not you know
flopping forward or you know off to some angle and you're centered
and your perineuma is open and your fontanelle is open
then the energy the cheat
which by the way is one of the seven factors of Awakening um viraga
uh no Viria excuse me Viria um that can flow easily
and when that energy starts to be unobstructed it has a very uh
calming and purifying effect so you know when I'm talking about the
fontanelle or the perineum I beg your forgiveness because I'm I'm Gil would
never talk about this stuff all right thank you thank you very much
eat Gill Oasis no Meg I don't want to do Chico you don't need to teach Qigong
during the Retreats I just want to keep things simple anyway [Laughter]
I appreciate it I've been thinking about seeing quite a bit and thank you for trying to then
did I miss what you said thank you uh I've been uh member of Tai
Chi studies so I've been thinking oh yeah great thank you quite a bit and she
kind of is almost one half of my an important
part of my practice so but it's seldom talked about in our meditation group so
thank you for tying it in and and you know when I was trying to introduce this this meditation way of
staying with a breath where we stay with the whole cycle of the breath as this uh sort of oval of energy
going up the back across the top of the head and down the front and then back through the perineum to the
that is um called the Grand circulation in Qigong
and Qigong is the ancestor of all the martial arts
oh so the including Tai Chi
so the the she after it enters the donkey in and passes through the body it
comes out if onto now it returns back and comes back in the the donkey and
again yeah and you can you can feel it coming I mean a venerable analia when he
does this sort of introduction to meditation he invites people to to you
know uh straighten his mind but feel it coming up the back
and then it's up to each of us to to to know where we're most comfortable
uh concentrating our energy it might be in the Dan Tien the belly
and the advantage of the of that is that you can never overdo it
and for people like me it's off in the heart
but you know you have to be a little bit careful there because you know you can go overboard
and for a lot of people who don't practice you know everything's happening up here in the head and uh that's really
easy to overdo so you don't want to try to invite too much Chi into the head Center
okay after that
Megan I think we have one last question from um this came on YouTube uh if you
find it increasingly difficult to meditate should you continue to try
ah well
I mean it it depends um
I think I'm going to try to answer that for you this week by hopefully
giving you a few tastes of Freedom the freedom that comes when we stick with it for a long time
uh it does work and many people do get discouraged
because it's it's so difficult and you know honestly we are not programmed for
this our DNA is telling us oh watch out there's danger don't go there
it's you know it's there's a lot of uh there's a lot of
work to do to let go of that intuitive uh programming of being reactive
and clinging either to getting rid of something or getting more of something the clinging
is what perpetuates our suffering but to be able to start letting go of that clinging
we need to practice and you know if you're if your problem is that is difficult for you physically
you can try other positions um
but I would gently encourage you to stick with it and see where it takes you
does that work for you and she said uh thank you on YouTube
okay alrighty okay Meg I think that's all the questions we have for today so
um yeah thank you very much for your teachings my pleasure thank you all for being