hello everyone and Welcome to our meditation and um
it looks like some people are saying they still have trouble connecting if those of you have trouble connecting
if you could uh a couple of things kind of refresh your
you know any kind of link you any kind of page you use at IMC for
for uh connecting to the the site
and if that doesn't work and you still have trouble with if you know what some
link is in trouble maybe you can uh mention that in the chat I think someone
will probably see the chat for whose knows about the trying to keep update
the technology parts of all this so we'll look into it some more
so um so good morning
and here's a analogy that I'm fond of and it can be done in different ways but
uh the the way I'd like to do it is to imagine
a maybe a cold place or if you are living in a very hot place
maybe it's fine to have a hot place but in the cold place to imagine a
a small heater placed in the middle of a room in a hot place maybe an air conditioner
and and that little heater is works hard and it's
when it's turned on the immediate space around the heater warms up or the media space around the air
conditioner cools down and then as it keeps working slowly the
the temperature changes going outwards it's warmer and warmer the whole room
gets warm and the whole room gets cool and if it goes on long enough maybe that
the warmth of that coolness spreads out to other rooms in the house maybe takes a while but eventually it
spreads out but it begins first close in to where it's closest to
so in the same way when we practice mindfulness with the classic instructions to really
begin here with ourselves in an embodied way with the body with breathing
with our own direct experience it's a little bit like there's awareness is within us
and that awareness lights up or warms up refreshes
and meets what is closest to it which is ourselves
and in a sense We Begin filling ourselves with warmth they're filling ourselves with refreshing coolness
we become full in a certain wonderful way we feel connected to ourselves we fill ourselves out
and as that becomes it gets Fuller with attention with presence when we become
more embodied and connected to ourselves then the awareness has a wonderful way
in which it naturally is spreads and out into the environment and first it contacts what is close by
maybe the the people and objects that we're engaged with and have some kind of
direct contact with and with time it spreads further and further
but there's this Radiance or this kind of flow outward and when we come to meditate every
morning I think of it as we get to start all over it's kind of opportunity for
Fresh Start it's because the mind is often preoccupied by things
the past and future what's happening in our lives it's maybe a little hard to appreciate how the
Opera how a morning meditation daily meditation can be an opportunity for completely fresh start to kind of like
you've been forgiven everything uh everything has you can put down
everything every burden every responsibility forgive yourself for every transgression
and start over again in a certain kind of way and we start over again here
turning on the heater inside turning on the air conditioner turning on the
the flow of the classic language is more
like a flow of water in an under spring in an underwater Lake
kind of turning it on and let yourself become a fool with awareness
let awareness take in and make contact with all the parts of Who You Are Here
and Now so that that becomes a foundation where awareness can now with this Foundation
be ready for the world itself and then as you get ready for the world and go into the world then some of the
issues of your life can return and and be addressed in a much better way
but thinking of meditation as a kind of time to put everything down so you can start
over and doesn't mean the feelings emotions concerns disappear but we start over by
connecting to What's Happening Here and Now in our body in our breathing then they start filling ourselves with making
contact and awareness and presence with all of it and author goes
so to begin with a posture and maybe think of the posture as a
posture of starting over a posture of
almost like a ritual of establishing yourself
here and now in this place at this time
as if you can start over with no past and no future to be concerned with for
now and then gently closing your eyes
and then to
take a few long slow deep breaths to continue this ritual of letting go of
past and future [Music] letting go of concerns thoughts the best you can
and re-establish yourself here
letting go on the exhale
establishing yourself here on the inhale
and then to
let your breathing return to normal
and continuing this movement towards letting go and
kind of forgiveness and starting over with a normal breath as you exhale scan
through your body and find places you can relax soften
and softening your thinking mind relax the tension pressure to think
maybe there's a way of gently quieting the thinking mind
not taking it Taking it as given that you have to think in the intensity
by which you're thinking
you can quiet and slow down your thoughts
and direct your thoughts to being here in the body with your
breathing direct your thoughts to be interested
in your direct embodied experience in meditation
and if you're following the
rising and settling of breathing the inhales and exhales
maybe they will place in your body where the inhale begins
the first Sensations in the Torso of beginning to breathe in
that's where the heater or the air conditioner
begins radiating
and as the inhale grows
awareness spreads through the Torso as it just expands the rib cage is Oaks
stretch the belly expands
let your awareness spread through your body through your heart through your mind
as if you have a fresh beginning
everything here in yourself
with a freshness a newness your curiosity
almost as if you have no past and no future just this
and fast and future can return later
in meditation there's nothing to solve or figure out
instead we bring awareness
to whatever is happening as if we're filling ourselves with
awareness becoming embodied
as a foundation for being with whatever is challenging whatever is
happening in the present moment
foreign foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to imagine that your awareness that begins with you
because that's where your all your senses are the sense of hearing
and seeing touching smelling
did all the sun stores are here in this body feeling your body itself from the
inside out and that this awareness
kind of in a way radiates out as it hears the world around you as it
sees the world around you smells
as it considers and thinks about the world around you
and as you breathe in and out
spreading your awareness out into the world as if it can touch the whole world
and with whatever sense of calm or well-being or presence
whatever kindness or care or compassion that you find Within
let that also spread out into the world
with the idea that it would be marvelous wonderful for all beings
to have a deep connection to themselves to the
world that is such a way that it provides them a source of happiness and well-being and
safety may it be that this practice that we do
may be the way that we live our lives in known and unknown ways and
intentional and unintentional ways may it be for the welfare and happiness
of everyone may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we support this possibility
[Music]
thank you
I'll be right back I think I have to push a button on a different machine
nope now it worked
so hello and welcome to this fourth
talk about compassionate action and it's maybe worth
repeating that this talks about compassionate action
are building on a whole series of talks from before
that focused on the role of developing awareness as a foundation for compassion
and action developing Attunement with others and ourselves as a foundation for compassion
cultivating appreciation of others a deep respect also as a foundation for
compassionate action to cultivate the appropriate aspiration
a wish as part of compassionate action and with all that
we're ready for to act compassionately and so we don't want to be impulsive in
the compassionate action or unconsidered or or
necessarily think just because we identify something like Compassion or desire to help people or to stop
suffering that it's wisely considered to consider wisely
is an important part of the Buddhist practice to consider that profoundly to have a
profound consideration which means to stop and feel and have access to some sense of a profound Source Within
take the time what is the depths of your being say or how does that inform you or how
does that help you understand the situation and I like this expression depth of your
being some people might say whatever is heartfelt but even the hearts might not be the the
fullest or the wisest place from which to act in the world
but to really come from some take time to come from someplace deep within
and um and this the deepest place maybe is a place where we don't have divisions
for our care we don't have we're not partial we don't have uh distinctions between
those people deserving our care and compassion and those who don't the deepest place inside has quieted
this divisive mind that many of us can live in where it's partial it's preferential it's
it's some people are excluded from our care because we don't think they deserve
it or something but then the depth of our being it's
possible to care to be concerned with the welfare of everyone
and uh and the Buddha refers to this as being concerned for the welfare of the
whole world he talked about being concerned for the welfare of oneself
concern for welfare of others concern for the welfare of self and others
and which is what we've talked about the first three days this week and then he in addition to that talked about being
concerned for the welfare of the whole world and and uh
you know certainly the whole world is a big task to consider the welfare of everyone but to let the awareness uh the
care The Compassion the compassionate concern have no divisions
have no Us Versus Them whose justifies our compassion who
doesn't that's what I understand the whole world means there's no separation so certainly we probably care for the
people close to us because we're close to us we see them we know them we don't have to go out to now and
donate to every non-profit that do a good World throughout the whole world but there's
no division no separation of our care and this is phenomenally important
that um we no one's Cast Away from our hearts that when we engage in this complicated
life complicated interpersonal life that we're concerned about the what's
best for everyone concerned and this was a very important approach I
took when I was the chair of an Ethics Committee and we had to deal with lots
of conflict and sometimes with transgressions and harms that were done between people
and um and I would talk to everyone carefully and tell them that my my
concern was a search for what's for the welfare and for the good of everyone
concerned it was a little bit hard for some people to appreciate when they felt that other people deserved punishment or
deserved something terrible and um and uh and certainly some kind of
serious consequences sometimes are needed but to understand what those consequences how those consequences
consequences work for the welfare of everyone for the good of everyone so it
isn't just punitive and that's the end of it it's yes there has to be consequences they have to be
accountability there has to be something has to change but here is why it's helpful for you here's why it's good for
you here's why you need to do this it gives you an opportunity to grow to change to come to terms all kinds of
things and uh generally I've found that everyone
involved in these conflicts resolutions that I was involved in came to appreciate that uh that we're looking
for the greater good for everyone and it didn't mean that we it was compromising
the good for someone who needed needed more something it was really looking for the
for the how to benefit everyone where it's not a win-lose
situation and uh and to do this it takes a lot more attention a lot more reflection and
thinking and getting a sense of the whole picture and everyone involved and
the quick decision that this is wrong and you're bad and we're cutting you out
or we're somehow casting you from our heart or or treating you kind of in a
punitive way or something that does not take into account the the
the humanity of everyone involved the fullness of their heart their minds their psychology and you know what the
impact of everything will be but just take time to be in conversation with
people find out what's going on for them and what really in a deep way is their need
and so they can really grow and develop and become better people that was my task as when I dealt with
these ethic challenges and I think people came to appreciate it a lot and even people who were hurt or
or felt like they were wronged in the conflict they were in I think they came
out as better people because they understood that um that they were being
taken care of well their situation was cared for and and um and the proper
resolution was made but that the the welfare of everyone involved was taken
into account and sometimes everyone is not necessarily the parties and only the
party is in a conflict but also involves the people around it who know about it
and are indirectly involved or connected to the parties involved so how do we
care for everyone involved so I learned a lot about this in doing this conflict you know mediations and
issues that I for many years I was doing but um but also I think it's a natural
byproduct of a liberated heart a mind that is liberated from the divisiveness
liberated from attachment to it has to be one way or attachment to oneself or attachment to
one's family or one's tribe or whatever it might be and um
and so when we're involved in compassionate action in the world to be considered about it is who who
benefits from this and is there anybody who is harmed by
this is anybody ever leaving someone out of the picture are we focusing too much
on maybe the person who is suffering the most and and forgetting there's more
people involved in the ecology and the in the community of that's related to
all this and how is it that we can take into account the whole world everyone involved
and not yourself not just the other and to some very deep personal way but for a
whole community and that the community could be a family it could be
a place of work it could be a Sangha or a spiritual Community we're in it could
be a neighborhood it could be you know you know where where where that hole is
is a um you know it varies from time to time but I see it in the world of politics
that the divisions are so strong that so many times the other people are cast
from our hearts and we don't ask you know the question what would be best here for everyone how do we find a way
and the difficult thing about considering what's the welfare for everyone no matter how it is it actually
takes time the conflict resolution work that I did was not a time efficient process it
actually took a lot of conversations and I think not a few people who tried to be
involved in similar conflict resolutions tried to do shortcuts
and I saw that whenever shortcuts were done often the conflict resolution didn't work out very well
and so it might take a long time to find what's best for everyone involved but
the other thing I learned through doing doing this and while it might take a lot of time to do so
that it actually saved a lot of time in the future when these conflict
resolution when hurt when problems between people when
when compassion is not all-encompassing in its scope
so many times the amount of repair work that had to be done later was much
greater than all the inefficient time taken to to resolve it well the first
time so it might seem inefficient and seem frustrating to stop and consider the
welfare of all and do the consideration be in the conversations to understand the situation better to do the creative
thinking to kind of consider well how to do this so it benefits everyone
and um but down but uh it it makes it much more
efficient or easier or more time saving in the future as we go along
and um and so I don't know what's coming to mind right now is a very simple example this doesn't involve you know
conflict resolution it could be that someone is ill and it's
nice to bring them dinner or some food and it would seem like you're just
bringing them food is a good thing but what's that big for the bigger picture the welfare of all
well maybe make enough food for their caretakers maybe there's people paid caretakers who
are caring for them who are often neglected often not seen and often ignored from you know in the close you
know relationships that um you know we we have but maybe you know make enough
for them as well maybe for their family maybe there's more people and there
might not be so much extra work to make a bigger meal that can be then shared more widely
but it and that's a little bit more work to
make more might actually create a much better world that who knows what
benefits come into the future that are unseen and
so just a small example but there's many examples of this and so compassionate
action and not a rush to be compassionate to act compassionately not
narrow the focus to only the person who's suffering or challenged but how to
kind of take a deep breath and relax and open to the situation more fully take
the time and you reflect you know how is what's really
what really brings welfare for this person what do they really need how is it how do I do this for my own
sakes so I'm nourished and become a better person how do we do this so that it takes into
account the relationship between us sell then others and how do we do this
that it really takes into account a wider scope of an uh of a community the
whole world if you will um uh
and if you protest that this is too much work I'd like to emphasize again that I think
that in the bigger picture it makes life much easier and that's how in a way it has the
welfare for all concerned including oneself because of how we benefit in return
so in that process I hope that the compassionate action helps you become happier
more more contented more nourished more inspired in a wonderful
way may it lead to your happiness and freedom so thank you and uh we will continue
this topic of compassionate action one more day tomorrow and um
and I look forward to it thank you