so hello everyone and welcome
and we're coming now to the end of this two week series on the 10
protectors and to begin the meditation and and to that leads into the talk in
the last protection I'll tell a Sufi story there was once a a person who went
to a Sufi master and uh with a ring and said can you inscribe on the ring uh
some piece of wisdom that will be always be useful for me to carry everywhere where I
go and so the Sufi Master said okay and took the ring and said come back in a
week and uh after a week the person returned and the Sufi Master handed
the person the ring and inscribed on the outside of the Ring were the words this
too will pass this too will
pass the zen teacher Suzuki roshi summarized uh
Buddhism um in two in three words kind of phenomenal that this is three words
that he he thinks encapsulate all of Buddhism not always
so not always so this too will pass not always
so it won't always be the way it
is and um so in this meditation you might want
to consider this too will pass and if
something doesn't pass if you have IDE a that something is not changing at all
chances are that it's a memory or an idea maybe an idea that compares to
what's happening now with something else and in a in a way the memory might
not be a changing thing it might represent something that will never happen again maybe an
idea might be especially in comparison to something else might have some truth
to it but in the moment the time we're meditating those are ideas
memories and they too will pass even in the course of the meditation you won't
forget them but they these as thoughts as ideas as memories they too come and
go this too will pass and so as we sit
today uh you might sit with um orientation
perspective of how everything that's occurring also
passes every inhale comes to its end every exhale
comes to an end maybe most sounds unless it's a
drone constant drone most sounds will come and go some return immediately but still
they pass and maybe remember to also see that
thoughts pass ideas pass in the momentto moment flow of what the mind is
concerned with and thinking memories are part of this passing constant
passing and there's something profound about just allowing things to pass to be
in the place of attention where we just sub seede things arise and pass kind of
like we're sitting at the edge of a river and just watch the river go by and
anything floating on the top of the river comes and goes comes and goes
everything flows and when we're fully in that
perspective we discover that we become part of the river too we're just flowing
coming and going so this too will pass so to assume
a meditation posture and one of the paradoxes is that
the more stable and still you can be in your posture and
with your mind the easier is to see
that all things are passing there's just a constant flow a
river of experience just flowing through through and flowing
by occasionally with little Eddies big Eddies where we get swirl around and
around and no longer in the current but eventually everything
returns to the river of change flowing on this to will
pass for this these minutes here this two will pass
gently closing your eyes and notice that as you take some
deep breaths and relax some of the tension in your body the holding might
soften a
bit relaxing on the exhale might also soften something in the
mind letting the breathing return to normal and continue for a few
breaths to relax so some of the tension
passes so degree of
it Relax The Thinking mind soften in the
mind
and then settling into the body breathing
with the perspective that each breath each inhale and exhale comes and passes
arises appears and
disappears sitting with a perspective that
sees the passing of all
things that are occurring in the present
moment and if they're not occurring in your direct
experience they are thoughts ideas images
memories that those two will not always be present they'll
come and go maybe [Music]
return settle back and allow all things
in their own way to pass away don't hold on to
anything don't pick up
anything sitting
quietly watching the river of
change
for
e
[Music]
if you're not mindful we can be operating as if things
have some
permanence if we're aware directly now here and
now then all things are constantly
changing in the way that we experience
them the knowing the perceiving the recognizing the
sensing all coming and going the thoughts the
ideas
e
any tension or pressure tightness in the mind the thinking mind
and the mindful
mind relax as if the mindful mind
can settle in can settle with a pull of
gravity relaxing to
observe the river of change Here and
Now
e
here in our body and
mind to see the river of change to
see all that comes and goes and
passes is to be in a cleansing River a river that
refreshes
cleanses so we can be fresh and clean in how we return to the
world Let the River of CH
change dissolve whatever is tight and tense whatever holding there
is
e
for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to appreciate any benefits that have come from sitting quietly
any ways in which we might be calmer more
mindful more
patient any ways in which we have been cleansed of some of
our attachments and holdings and resentments
fears any ways in which we appreciate being
present with Clarity attention capacity
to offer attention and may we offer our
attention may we offer our kindness may we offer our
willingness to let go of resentment let go
of greed so we can gaze upon the
world with care with
kindness with an ability to see all beings in with friendly
eyes to care for their welfare and
happiness knowing that when people really know
happiness and have real deep welfare they will be
kind may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and may this community of ours sits together these mornings there so many of
us may spread for from out out from us into this world this
day acts of kindness and compassion care support the people around us
strangers people known and not known to us let the goodness of our practice and
our community spread out into the world for the happiness and Welfare of
all [Music]
thank
you
so we come to the end of these 10 talks on the 10
protectors and the final one is wisdom and but maybe appreciating that
wisdom as a way that protects us maybe it's we can think of pretty obvious ways
in which it does we go through the world wise and with our eyes open and
understanding of how to behave and how to be there's many ways that wisdom supports us and helps us protect
others and and the in this in this list of 10 protectors the Buddha gives a
particular meaning to it and um and so but I want to uh
appreciate it it's the last of the list of 10 so there's nine before and the uh assumption here is
that uh we have something to protect in ourselves and that's worthy of
protection worthy of caring for worthy of support and that uh there wonderful kind of one
aspect of these 10 protectors is that these 10 things
themselves are so wonderful that it's worth protecting them that somehow we
protecting the very things that protect us and uh and which helps us to thrive
we protect the very things that help us protect others that let us be someone
who serves and cares for the world around us and is safe for other people
so it's kind of a wonderful list so and I think of them sometimes these lists in Buddhism as being
Progressive one Builds on the other so the first
one is um uh that protects is just basic virtue basic ethical Integrity a basic
living by the five precepts we protect ourselves to some degree certainly from
ourselves uh putting ourselves in situations that uh are very harmful for
ourselves but also we tend to protect ourselves from others the world tends to
uh treat people who are ethical better than those who are unethical and um but the uh so the
begins with like many things in Buddhism it begins with the foundation of
Ethics um one when we have the foundations of Ethics then we're prepared for the next protector which is
to study the Dharma to learn the Dharma to take it in in some deep way if we
live an unethical life the Dharma can't really penetrate us the teachings can't really come in in some way because the
teaching the teachings kind of undermine the very motivations the very way of
being that's unethical but to be ethical kind of cre creates the kind begins creating kind of
the ability in the mind and heart to receive and understand the teachings so
studying the teachings protect us we understand what the teachings are about and then having good friends so we
understand the teachings enough that now we understand that there are good
spiritual friends beautiful friends who have are are are maybe more
practiced than we are and more rooted in the dharm than we are and uh and to love
them to care for them to have them these good friends in our lives so that they
can Inspire us they can guide us they can um help us understand the Dharma more and not just understand the Dharma
as teachings but understand how they get integrated into how we live our
lives so ethics then studying the Dharma then having friends who live the Dharma
good friends spiritual friends and then um uh being someone who's easy to
correct someone's easy to speak to if we have good arm our friends then if we
want to benefit from our teachers from our more experienced practitioners around us be someone who's easy to talk
to you're willing to hear what they have to say we don't protest and this is particularly important when we have the
benefits the wonderful Treasure of having people who willing to point out
uh our faults point out where we're off where we're causing harm in the world and stuff like that and this is since
time of the Buddha is considered to be a treasure to have people like that in our lives and so to have people somehow who
lovingly caringly care for us very much but they're willing to kind of help us
understand where we need to kind of focus on more to to not uh you know just
to really clarify and grow and develop and um so it'd be easy to speak
to and not be defensive so be virtuous so you can
study the Dharma study the Dharma so you can appreciate the people who live by the Dharma and have good friends uh have
good good spiritual friends so that and then be easy to speak to so they can
really help you and support you and then uh care for the sa care for your
practice community care for the community of of people who are supporting you and and um and so it's a
mutual relationship you're able to kind of practice generosity you're able to take your uh ethical qualities and what
you're learning and applying that applying it in a community that uh values it and that supports it and is
helping you you develop so then um uh you know caring
for your Dharma community and engaging in this process of integrating all this into your life maybe then it's easier at
some point to love the Dharma because loving the Dharma is not the Dharma
outside of you and this is the the sixth quality loving the Dharma uh but the
Dharma is really you and the Heart of it is non-harming to love non-harming so
much so that you love it that you love your capacity for non-harming for living a a peaceful life a non-harming life a
Dharma life and so so then uh we're protected by that by non-harming and important
ways it's a deeper way than just living by the the precepts and as we learn to live this
life the loving the Dharma we understand that if we love the Dharma we don't want
to do anything that harms ourselves we want to do the things that support ourselves we benefit so learning to
abandon what is unskillful unhelpful and then pick up and support and develop
what is skillful what is beneficial and helpful for us and that's one of the key areas of practice guidelines for
practice in Buddhism is to abandon what is unhelpful and and support what is helpful and this is also a protector to
live that way we're protected from causing harm to
ourselves and um and then to uh be content with what we
have uh it doesn't mean that you know 100% content contentment with living in
poverty or living in in uh in areas of abuse it means that when the basic
necessities of our life are are available to us uh don't be greedy for
more don't be discontented wanting more and more looking outside of yourself for
how to make yourself happy be content with some degree of the basic necessities and the way that it works
for you in your life so that you have more time to practice you're more more wherewithal to be present for your
experience as you live it rather than looking externally for more validation more pleasure more
something and then um uh we're protected by the ninth Factor we talked about
yesterday mindfulness and um and so this is a mindfulness and now really the ability
to be present really here with our experience that builds on all the others and then we come to to wisdom so
all that process all that if this is a path to practice that we understand of M
maturation then at some point we become ready for wisdom and the reason why this
is important to think of it as a end end result of all these steps rather than
offering you wisdom first is this particular wisdom that Buddha emphasizes
is maybe hard to appreciate it's a lot easy to protest and say it's not good enough it's actually dismissive it's
actually U maybe kind of uh indifferent to the world or doesn't understand how
the world really is for me so it really takes some deeper uh
capacity for attention and and finding a refuge inside
oneself not looking externally and so the wisdom particular wisdom that Buddha says that will
protect you is the there one of the protectors is to see I really see the river of
change see the river which things arise and pass away come and go and
um and if we're really kind of in that stream that is cleansing that's freeing
that kind of um uh protects us from the ways in which we cing and hold on the
ways in which we resist unnecessarily and painfully the ways in which we
um our attachments then spill out of ourselves into how we uh relate to
others and um and this idea of uh that Buddhism has of entering the stream is
partly entering the stream of this change constant change constant movement
constant coming and going that um is I think is playing off
with an idea that's a metaphor of an idea in Ancient India and maybe still
some areas of of India that you can go into uh a river
like the river Ganges to be purified and the Buddha wasn't uh so
interested didn't believe in this idea that a river physical River can purify you of your
inner challenges your inner ways that you're stuck um uh the inner faults we
have that uh for him it we are the river
that can purify we become our own protector our own purifier we become our
own Liberator when we can kind of allow that River of change inside of us to really
wash through US wash through US wash away our attachments dissolve the way
we're stuck dissolve the uh evaporate the ways in which we are afraid and
anxious and and tight and restricted there's something about beginning to
appreciate and sense and feel the way that all things are constantly flowing
through and the challenge in this is the is that um we have all kinds of things
that we recognize this is never going to change we have a loss and how can these Buddhists say that everything is
changing when this loss is permanent and um or we compare ourselves
to someone else uh you know I'm always going to be X where other people have
the advantage they are Y and so we're comparing ourselves to others and um but
these things when we close our eyes and sit quietly in meditation we come to
appreciate that these are all in the meditation the they have some truth in
the world outside of ourselves that we don't want to deny and be wise about but in
meditation we see that sitting quietly at home in our ourselves
here where we're kind of in a certain kind of way uh allowed to be ourselves
fully and completely like we're perfect just the way we are
that uh we see that loss in this moment is a
memory the loss is real but in the momentto moment experience of change it
comes to us as a memory in the how we compare ourselves to someone else I'm X and their y in the
momentum experience that's an idea a thought of the mind that makes a
comparison those memories those thoughts those ideas um they themselves come and go
they're part of the stream of change and if we understand that and
allow ourselves to see that see it then we're not going to have those weigh us
down they're not going to grate us us they're not going to um uh uh add salt
to our wounds we're going to see them just flowing and moving through and it's
hard to are willing to do that because it can seem like a betrayal to our ideas betrayal to our memories but this is a
cleansing a deeply cleansing process that um from time to time it's
good to go take a shower you know to we clean when we go back into the world
just like it's good to bathe it once in a while uh physically it's good to do
this inner bathing this inner uh cleansing that comes when the
mindfulness is stable enough strong enough that we can really be here in the present moment and just allow ourselves
to rest in the changing streaming flowing uh uh flow of experience moment
to moment moment where we see this too will pass this too will
go this to comes and goes flows and streams and here is what's this is the
experience that liberates us from our attachments liberates us from holding on
liberating us from freezing and holding what is there liberates us from having
to dip the pale a bucket into the stream of our life and then go car go around
carrying the bucket maybe for the rest of our lives and some of us have carried are carrying
many many buckets but the buckets is not the stream of
life we protect ourselves through wisdom through wisdom of change and
impermanence and inconstancy and if we cleanse ourselves
from that then we can go into the world and be a
better protector for the world and all these 10 protections maybe we can be
that way and how we care for this world that desperately needs more protectors
desperately needs people coming from this deep experience of love and kindness and support and wisdom may it
be that as we protect ourselves we protect the world thank
you