foreign welcome welcome
so as you probably know we'll sit for 45 minutes and then I'll give a talk
so we'll see you in 45 minutes
foreign welcome welcome
maybe I'll ask how is the temperature for you guys is it is it okay is it a little bit chilly is a little bit warm
it's okay okay just because uh I'm in a place where
these are blowing on me so I'm fine but I just want to check and see how you guys are
okay so welcome welcome
nice to see you all so today I'd like to give a talk about
this story that we find in the suit does that uh I don't know I kind of like it
it's uh a little bit silly maybe maybe silly is not the right word that
um it has these exaggerated portions of it which I think are kind of fun maybe that's the right word a little bit fun
and we might even ask like what is the purpose of having some of these stories that are fun
and I would say actually so maybe I'll clarify so we have this suit does he's
kind of like the scriptures we might say and then like maybe a thousand years later they wrote what are called the
commentaries and the commentaries are is where all this very colorful kind of
what we might say like fun stuff so it's not in the earliest strata of literature
it's not from the time of the Buddha but sometime later as they were filling in the backstory like well why
did that happen and they sometimes the backstory is some fantastical thing as as is the case here
and so I'm sharing this just because uh I don't know it kind of makes me smile a little bit that this story but there's
also some really good teachings in here so it's not just entertainment or
entertainment's sake but it can be entertainment too but also I like that
this idea that okay that Dharma doesn't have to be so dry and boring
can be dry and boring if that's your thing there's plenty of dry and boring things in there but uh and to be sure a
lot of it you know there's these lists and I actually love the lists but I want
to kind of like highlight that there's more than just lists and these uh Brutus teachings for Noble Truths they fold
path seven factors Awakening five faculties ten parties like you know all these
okay so this is a story of the Buddha talking with an ogre
this is how we translate this word yucca as an ogre
so and so uh these ogres yuccas they show
up in the poly Canon you know just a few times and they have different roles when
they show up and some of them are depicted as really devout followers of
the Buddha and some are depicted as demons that
like to eat humans and they're not necessarily malicious but they do eat
humans so so there's something about that I guess but uh
but we might see that in the case of this story it's we I might understand as
a rhetorical device or a literary device and that's this ogre
asks questions and it's the answering of the questions where we get some of the teachings but
we might learn something about the questions that get asked and in the same way we see
lots of uh humans as well as if there's going to be any non-humans that show up
um and any sutas they will often are asking questions too so this is the way
that I am kind of holding them as just this rhetorical device is a way to provide opportunities for that Buddha to
talk about something so
okay so this is from the this is that starts with the I'll start with the back story that comes from the commentary
right so this is uh like I said like a thousand years after the time of the Buddha so the Buddha goes to allavecca this is
the ogre's name olavecca I kind of just like to say it
yeah guys ogre so and I love olavika lives in alavi so it
does kind of have this like fairy tale kind of feeling right even just the names of these uh people so the Buddha
goes to visit goes to olivi to see alavaka the yaka
and alavaka is not there apparently he said a meeting of ogres
that is happening in the Himalayas kind of curious I don't know what the
meetings are about but uh so but the Buddha he shows up anyway he
goes to alavica's place and he knocks on the door and there's I
guess all of AKA lives in a big really big place we might maybe a mansion or something we might imagine and the door
keeper opens the door and says the blessed one has come at an improper time
so it's interesting that the doorkeeper recognizes oh this is the Buddha
and just says you know this is not a good time and the Buddha responds yes but if it
would not be burdensome for you I would like to spend one night here
and this was the case that the monastic sites and the Buddha's followers or they
would often be traveling and would just stay at people's places and you know
they would for alms they would have food that people would give them in places where they would stay so this is not an
unusual thing to happen so the doorkeeper says well it will not
be burdensome for me but the Yucca that's ogre is rough and harsh
and he doesn't even pay homage to his mother and father so saying he's not going to pay homage
to you because he doesn't even pay on his homage to his parents it doesn't respect his parents but the Buddha isn't
phased and he says to the door keeper I know his rough character
but that won't be an obstacle for me so if it would not be a burdensome for you I would like to spend one night here
the door keeper responds it would not be burdensome for me but the Yucca is like
a hot frying pan he does not have regard for his mother or father or for recluses and brahmins
or for the Dharma and when others come here he drives them insane or splits their hearts or grabs them by the feet
and hurls them across the Ganges River and then Buddha is completely undeterred
and says I know but if it won't be burnsome for you I
would like to spend one night here the door keeper says it will not be
burnsome for me but if I allow you to stay here without informing him
he may kill me so let me inform him so the doorkeeper left and to talk with
all of AKO so I you know I don't know how ogres travel I don't know if a door keeper with or I don't know how this
works but somehow he goes to wherever olafika is to say the Buddha is at your place
so while this is happening the Buddha enters olivica's house or
Mansion or whatever his Abode is and he sits down and gives a talk gives
a Derma talk to the people that are there so apparently they're maybe housekeeping you know servant I don't
know who's there exactly gives a Dharma talk to them and then um
then when the doorkeeper meets where alifakka says he rushed back to his home
in a fury and demanded that the blessed one leave so that's all this colorful black
backstory now we're getting to what actually happened what actually happened what's in the suit does so it's you know
in the earlier strata this is in the suit and it starts thus
have I heard for those of you who are um new to this very often suit does
discourses start with us thus have I heard this is
um kind of bringing to mind the idea that this was the Buddha speaking and somebody remembered what he was supposed
to have I heard on one occasion the blessed one was dwelling at alavi the haunt of the Yucca
olavika then the yaka alafika approached the blessed one and said to him
get out all right but by someone said and he went out
come in all right I'm a bus at one side and went in
on the second time a yucca olavika said get out all right so the Buddha walks out get in
all right so the Buddha comes in a third time get out okay he works out
get in so the Buddha goes back in so the kind of the backstory to this
like why all Africa is doing this and why the Buddha is allowing himself to do why he's doing this is because olivica
wants to make the Buddha angry because he uh has learned that he the
Buddha is like abides in loving kindness and when he as long as he has loving kindness he's immune to those weapons
that olivica might have so he wants to get him angry so they will no longer have loving kindness
and the Buddha has this idea why he is following olavika's demands is because
he knew that it was not possible to train a stubborn person with
stubbornness true right we kind of even know this in
our own lives can't train a stubborn person with stubbornness in fact there's a few
teachings about this that the Buddha gives that you can't teach somebody about ethical Behavior to
an unethical person and there's a thing and you can't teach
Faith or confidence to somebody who doesn't have faith or confidence
so this is kind of really interesting it makes for me when I heard this early thought about this public discourse then
I also thought well then how does this work how can you teach her how can people learn if they're stubborn or how
can they learn if they don't have confidence or don't have ethical Behavior
turns out that the answer is in the timing like if somebody is unethical but then
you want to support them behave in an ethical way you only talk about ethical stuff when
they are already being ethical because people aren't unethical 100 of the time
and this makes sense to me kind of like the burden is on the the one who wants to help or the teacher is to be
sensitive to what's happening to the other person and if you're sincere and really want to
help and support somebody then you need to be attuned to where they are and to
recognize when is the right time to say something when is the right time to share some wisdom you might have or some
ideas that you might have it's not always the right time and we know this and they go if I'm stubborn
right I'm not am I particularly stubborn no I'm not a particularly stubborn person
but I know that if somebody's like really pushing me you know then I just there is a part of me that just
doesn't like to be pushed around and so you know I tend to be like wait what's Happening Here
so we all have this experience okay so three times Olivia tells the
Buddha get out come in get out come in and then the um fourth time
Olivia says get out and the Buddha says I won't go out
do whatever you have to do so the Buddha's gonna say I don't care what you're doing I'm not going out
anymore and then Olivia asks the Buddha some
questions he says I'll ask you a question and if you don't answer me I'll
drive you insane or I'll split your heart or I'll grab you by the feet and hurl you across the Ganges River
none of those sound really good right drive you insane split your heart or get thrown across the river
and the Buddha replies this is Diana's country like I don't see anyone in this world who
could drive me insane split my heart or grab me by the feet and hurl my across the Ganges but ask whatever you want
so you know the Buddha he's not threatened of course he's not threatened but I've left this I've been um thinking
about this recently on a number of different settings different teachings I've been giving in some different places this
idea what would we do if the Buddha said ask whatever you want
you know like what would you ask what are some of their questions that we feel like that if we knew the answer
would really make a difference and what are some of the questions that we consider that the Buddha could ask
ask whatever you want
so Allah here's olafika's question turns out to be four questions
Oliver Oliver asks what is a person's best treasure
what practiced well brings happiness
what is the sweetest of tastes
living in what way is one's life called the best
so this first one what is a person's best treasure so treasure we might think of what you
know something that we value something that is uh
maybe like a resource and something about Treasures but like maybe even hidden
or maybe something that's you know not obvious or could also be something obvious like wealth or possessions or
something like this but Allah is asking what is a person's best treasure
this is an interesting question because I think Society right now wants us to tell tells us all these things what is
the best treasure if you behave this way look this way your bank account is this way you live
in this person drive or live in this location drive this car or whatever it is right we're we're being sent this
message all this time about what is makes a person valuable or or the most
valuable thing that they have or something what is a person's best treasure
and for me I kind of think this is and really humanizes this ogre right he's
concerned about wealth and security just like humans
so then the second question what well practiced brings happiness
so I appreciate that Allah he's asking well practiced brings
happiness what well practiced brings happiness so he's recognizing that it's not
something that can you can just get by snapping your fingers it's something that requires practice
so ellavika recognizes that happiness isn't something that just magically gets
bestowed upon a person but what what can we do what can we practice
what can we cultivate and develop that's going to bring happiness
that they and maybe we can also say ogres just want to be happy
just like humans right so this way but this idea that happiness doesn't
necessarily come from things that are easily acquired but maybe it takes some effort
for things for some happiness that's maybe more enduring or deeper or
more than just fleeting or superficial
the third question asks is what is the sweetest of tastes
maybe referring to a little bit of experiencing pleasure taste we might understand here like
taste to mean experience and this word right now it's just uh rasa is can be
understood sometimes as experiences so he's asking what's the most Pleasant
thing what is the sweetest of Tates what's the
what's the most Pleasant and then the last question is living in
what way is one's life called the best
so how to live the best life you might you know we ask ourselves this
question too we don't want to have a life filled with regret and remorse we don't want to get
to the end of our life and feel like oh I wasn't a good life somehow I didn't
reach my potential or didn't do what I thought was important or something like
this so for me I appreciate this that this
ogre he's just like us he's concerned with wealth of security happiness pleasure and living a good life
these are things I would say humans care about too chances are all of us in this room
care about these things also the Buddha answers all of the guest
questions in a very straightforward way
clearly and unambiguously and I appreciate this very much you might
maybe I should have said this this is all in verse right so um you know the English maybe does is a
little bit clunky this that's why the English feels a little bit clunky is because it's written in verse and then when it gets translated it's clunky it's
clunky and poly also but so the Buddha gives four answers to four
questions so one answer for each question faith
is a person's best treasure Faith Sada we could translate this as
conviction or confidence it doesn't have to be believing in the unbelievable or
something like this I'll unpack this a little bit but faith faith is a person's best treasure
the Dharma practiced well brings happiness
truth is the sweetest of taste
and living with wisdom one's life is called the best
so we might ask ourselves you know okay well what does this mean exactly
faith in what and what is the storm and what does it mean to practice the Dharma
and when he's talking about truth does this mean like speaking truth or finding the truth or what does that really mean
and if wisdom is important like how does one gain wisdom and what is wisdom and how would we recognize it
so Olivia asked and the door and the Buddha said
faith is a person's best treasure
we need a certain amount of confidence or conviction
to even start any practice we have to have this belief that's not
completely we don't have all the data in that this is going to be a worthwhile
use of our energy worthwhile of our time worthwhile of our resources
that requires a little bit of Faith or confidence or conviction
without that we will never start a practice right of course not so it's part of he's saying it's the
best treasure maybe because it's something that's kind of hidden like a treasure but it's also if you have the
confidence you can start all kinds of things
not only does Dharma practice or Buddhist practice or a spiritual practice but so many things in life
right just often require just a little bit of confidence to begin
and then when we put it down or we it slips then we just need a little bit of
confidence just to pick it back up again without the confidence we might fall
into like oh I can never do it this is too hard for me everybody else can do it
what's wrong with me or something like that and we could just slip into inaction
so this confidence is the best treasure
and that's we also could say that in the same way that treasure could
be like a type of wealth and there's a way in which the type of wealth can reduce
the suffering that's associated with poverty or hunger or not having a place
to live so there's a way that treasure can reduce suffering
it's not the only way that reduces suffering but there's a way in which also faith
can reduce suffering because it tests this it supports practice
and some of you will know that it's one of the five faculties I'm not going to go into this list of the five faculties
but it's one of five things that really support practice is having this
confidence or conviction so faith is a person's best treasure
I'm using this word faith feel free to use confidence conviction whatever you
want you don't have to use the word faith the Dorma practiced well brings
happiness so what does that mean the Dharma
there's a few things maybe some of you know rich is the teachings of the Buddha
practiced well so we learn things from the teachings and then more than just
having an intellectual understanding more than just memorizing all the lists
is there a way that we can put it to practice in our own life
is there a way that we can you know embody it
instead of just I remember I've heard Gill say a few
times he he had this expression I don't know if he still says it he used to say
nightstand Buddhists he's talked about all these people that had all these books on the Buddhism and the Dharma on
their nightstand and they would read them and that was sufficient for them and he said that
will take you to a certain distance but really you need to practice put into your life
what the teachings are including meditation practice ethical Behavior wisdom these types of things
so the drama is the teachings of the Buddha we also could kind of like summarize the Dharma as a path of
practice and many of you will know that Silas manipania is kind of we could summarize
this path of practice see the ethical Behavior
mental development meditation panya wisdom
is seeing things clearly and how things really are
as best we can as opposed to allowing our ideas about things to
obscure what's really happening say that's part of wisdom
and so the the Derma practiced well brings happiness
because there's a way it's not only that I mean ethical Behavior brings happiness it's the complete absence of remorse
I have regret this Bliss of blamelessness there's a certain amount of Happiness to
know that uh like if you uh see the policeman walking up to your door like oh you just know
that either they need something and you don't have to feel bad or something oh
my gosh why did I hear you're just like oh maybe they there's I can help with the neighbor maybe there's a problem
with the neighbors or something like this
and so but also Awakening this complete Liberation is
described as the highest happiness to the Dharma practice well brings
happiness it brings more and more freedom and peace and ease into our
lives and I gave the past month or so a number
of talks about what is the Dharma I'm not going to go through all of it now but there's a way in which just aligning
with or tuning into what's happening it's kind of the Dharma as well
as being having some clarity about what's actually happening what's
there and then the last one oh sorry one two
three the third one truth is the sweetest of peace
so what is like what is the most delicious you know what is like the most delectable what is the most
something that's maybe an Ambiguously delicious
and we might say that truthful speech that when it's done when it's kind and
given at the right time and it's done in a way that's beneficial kind of whether we are speaking it or
whether we hear it there's a way that it nourishes the mind and the way that food
might something that you're tasting might truthful speeches allows the mind to
kind of like calm to be calm right whenever we're thinking about uh telling a little white
lie or if we're planning to tell a little white lie have you ever noticed how much planning goes into that we have
to like rehearse it over and over and over again if we're going to tell a white lie or if somebody tells us
something and we're not quite sure is that true or not then we just kind of have this little agitation in mind did
they really mean that or there's something when we speak the truth
and we know others that are speaking the truth there's something that's really
calming about that it's really not agitating it at all as opposed to you
know agitating it's agitating when even with Little White Lies this is something to
I don't know just for us to practice with is noticing when is our speech
agitating trying to Maybe
say things that are stretching the truth or or maybe going around the truth or
something like this but again it's not truth just for truth's sake because the truth can be
hurtful also yes you actually do look fat in that dress right so instead we want to use it in a
way that uh you know I love you no matter what you're wearing you know that's kind of
the things that we say instead of yeah actually that's not so great or we would say you know blue really looks
really good on you I like blue and so rather than the red dress they're wearing or you know I'm just making this
up but this to say truth is really important but truthful speech doesn't
give us license to be rude or inappropriate and it's a
skill it's definitely a skill to learn how to say things that are supportive and beneficial
but also the sweetest truth is the sweetest of teeth
because the taste of Freedom peace ease is sweet also
no matter what degree of Liberation this putting down of the burdens that we have
experienced there's something that's you know has this flavor as sweet as something that
feels uh you know our our bodies Our biology are
through Evolution right we like things that are sweet and want more and it's the same experience and
touching into some of this peace and well-being that's possible with practice
so then the last one the Buddha says is living with wisdom one's life is called
the best then maybe I'll just say after this
alavica's next question is how does one gain wisdom
because he wants to live his best life and he asks a few other questions too
but for our purposes here I'll just stick to these ones and the Buddha response
like how does one gain wisdom and maybe I'll just say a few words like
how might we understand what wisdom is one one part of wisdom is uh having behavior just how we show
up in the world there's some real wisdom to that how we treat ourselves how we treat others
how behaving ethically taking care of our minds and our bodies taken care of
others taking care of our communities part of wisdom
as well as you know seeing the characteristics of
everything it's the impermanent
it's unsatisfactory and doesn't have a inherent essence
part of wisdom is seeing this and understanding this so all of AKA asks well how does one
gain wisdom so and then but it responds
by placing faith in the Dharma of the awakened ones if I'm a desire to learn
one gains wisdom if one is diligent and astute
so we can see that he's kind of referring back to what he was saying earlier when gains wisdom by placing
faith in the teachings of the awakened ones so you know having enough
confidence that you're willing to think about it or consider it and maybe put it
into practice and from a desire to learn there can be a way right in which
there's a certain arrogance like I know this I don't you know I don't need to learn that
but having a desire to learn is this curiosity this openness like oh yeah is
there something for me to learn here
what is it that I don't quite See Clearly or I don't understand that my life keeps on turning out a way that I
don't quite want it to is there something that I have I don't
understand from a desire to learn one gains wisdom
if one is diligent and astute so it is a practice where we do have to
practice I wish right I think all of us wish that
it were easy and fast and turn our life around or even have our life continue to
go the way that we wanted to go or whatever it is but it is a practice
so one last thing that I'd like to say here actually is that
it's not a um an accident that order that these
questions are in so it's part of the way that these
things get I don't know preserved or written a composed
that these four qualities are not only answers to avoca's questions these qualities of
faith I have to I am reading two things at
once Faith the Dharma well practiced truth is the sweetest of taste and
wisdom they're part of a sequence
the sequence of practice that it begins with
having enough confidence to begin than practicing the Dharma
having a commitment to the truth then this way we might understand the truth as in sometimes we might think of like
mindfulness as the truth okay what's really happening here even if it's
uncomfortable to see even if it's actually an uncomfortable experience but like if the understanding that we gain
about ourselves can be uncomfortable to learn things about ourselves it can be
hard and then live with wisdom so faith
practicing the Dharma having a commitment to truth and living with wisdom
kind of goes in that direction it's not perfectly linear we'll have a little bit of four altogether but that is kind of
like the path of practice maybe in a nutshell that the Buddha is teaching to olivica
the Yucca olivica of Olivia
[Laughter] Faith practicing the Dharma having a
commitment to truth and living with wisdom
so I'll end there and I'll open it up to see are there some comments or questions
about this and as I was talking I was thinking like oh yes and you know what I
don't think I have it in this version of the notes the question is well what happened to olivica after he heard all
that right right that's like such an obvious question and I don't have the quote here but
um How It Ends is that elephant decides he becomes a follower of the Buddha and
then he decides he's going to go teach all the other ogres Bachelor Dharma
so there we go so I don't know if he becomes awakened or what I don't know but maybe
it changes diet [Laughter] was he eating humans I don't know if he
was actually eating humans right because he was throwing them across the river or making them insane or splitting their
heart or something like this right so yeah there's another suit to where an ogre does eat humans but I don't think
this one does I know it's kind of it's kind of right so you guys are laughing and smiling
this is partly why I like this because it has a little bit of Whimsy to it but I'd like to open it up if there's
any questions or comments
hi uh thank you um so at first I when I heard this I thought oh this sound these are Universal principles but they also
sound very like Western I see I feel like everybody is chasing some kind of happiness or wisdom and truth and
whatnot but that was kind of I was like oh it's still relevant today so I don't
know if it's progress or sort of us sitting idle but it was nice to hear
yeah yeah that's the part of the reason why I like it too is right because oh yeah I can relate to this we all want
these things and even though it's couched in this kind of funny story and from thousands of years ago yeah yeah I
feel like myself 10 or 20 years ago I could still relate to it then and now and yeah
great thank you
yeah just a comment I was super surprised that the Buddha said faith I thought he would say love or
Compassion or something like that for humans greatest treasure so that was just like a surprise for me
thank you maybe I will say that this word faith said shows up in all kinds of lists
that's the list that you haven't really heard Derma teachers talk about there's just there's many of them and here's an
interesting thing about faith that uh as I said it shows up in lots of lists and
just like it does in this list it's always the first and almost always wisdom is the last and
there's all kinds of different things in between so it's this movement of Faith
towards wisdom which leads to Freedom so just this idea of a path maybe is kind
of what's so maybe it's like the kernel that starts everything before the love and the Compassion maybe kind of Rise it
has to start with just thinking that that it's possible maybe just start
thinking that it's possible to have love and come person and wisdom
thank you
anybody else have a question or
okay so yeah yeah I think Lydia also has maybe Lydia
and then bill thank you
I'll make it fast bill
thank you Diana so when you were talking about all this
four questions by Race by yaka
um I don't know how to link the first one but to me
practice Dharma is to know the truth
and to gain the wisdom is to know the truth also and it's
practicing Dharma filled all the three because
to me the wisdom of the Buddhism seems like the three characteristics you were
talking about and they're so tightly linked
um but but I'm not sure about the face like you said seems after
to be the seed and then you know one step at a time
and maybe he talked about faith because he was talking to an ogre maybe he started there
right okay we have to start you know with a simple what's you know the first step you might think about that
but I appreciate truth Dharma wisdom rights they kind of yeah they're all linked
and so I'm not quite understand what the ogre mean oh
um a troll like somebody that lives under uh an ogre is like a monster
a uh I don't know does anybody have a what's a good word for ocher shrekler now I understand
thank you Shrek thank you I wouldn't have thought of that
orc orc laughs
um well I didn't start with faith started with sort of desperation like
gotta be some way to be happy I haven't tried this yet whoever got to
lose right but uh maybe it's just this time there had to
be a tiny little bit of faith in order for you to come back the second time well it just worked
okay so then but then so your faith wasn't completely because you had no
data right you had this I'm like oh yeah it worked I'm gonna keep on coming back but still the the faith to think like
okay it can continue to work well yeah it was just sort of like
evidence though like yeah there we go that's the word I'm looking for evidence you had evidence yeah uh-huh and that's
exactly what's we're being asked to do we're not asked to just believe blind yeah yeah
although um and however hazy and unformed and
ill-defined a manner I did always
I have this idea that it was somehow important for us
for each person to try to become a better person
and go as far with that as you could and that it was also somehow important
for all people to try to form a better Society yeah
um and where that came from don't know still don't know maybe there's a little
bit of a faith element in that uh and kind of a innate
feeling that this is important does that sound like Faith or does it
sound like something else sounds like maybe it's that you have
faith in the human capacity or to do that and that it wasn't that it's
important that it's important somehow whether this importance is something we're making up for us out there
somewhere don't know but but that if there's such thing as a
purpose in life some reason for us to be here that's it
does that sound like something different yeah it sounds a little a little bit different
I think what's being pointed here it's like this idea of like okay I have this
little this makes sense to me and I have some a little bit of evidence that this is going to work and therefore I'm going
to continue that's kind of what that's being pointed to here um I have two more questions but they're
really brief one is which suit is this and secondly where do you find these uh
commentaries I have never seen them anywhere yeah so this is
110 apata
110 and the commentary to this is the only commentary that I know of that is
translated into English so that's why you haven't seen them it's because they're just not there they just don't
they're not oh they're still not translated that's right oh where do you find them
well this one this commentary is translated this is the only one have you seen like biker body he has this the
student about is like literally like four inches thick and the actual suit
does like you know quarter inch and the commentary is thrown oh yes yes yes yes
yes that that does have the comedy yes and the commentator is huge yes okay there's crazy stories in there I haven't
read them yet now now I want to thank you they're using this word crazy they're playful and fun I think that
they are so yeah you're welcome
okay okay so thank you all for your attention and I wish you all a good rest
of the evening thank you