hey it's nice to see everyone arriving hello
it's been nice to share this week and perhaps just before we get started with
the meditation I'll mention that next week it will be May Elliott
I think some of you know her she's a wonderful young teacher at IMC and
I hope you'll join her I don't know what her topic is so you'll have to come on
Monday so let's go ahead then and get started for
today finding your meditation posture
settling in for the sit this morning or afternoon or evening
I know we're all over the world and just gently closing the eyes
and bringing the attention inward
sensing into the touch points of the seeds against the chair or the cushion
the legs or feet against the floor or if you're lying it's what you're
lying down on just finding a place where you can feel
balanced on what you're resting on so there's very little effort to hold yourself up
if you're in a chair it's sometimes nice to sit a little bit forward not to be leaning back
of course if you need to that's fine but if you don't it's actually more stable
to be resting in a balanced position
on your own sit bones
and softening the eyes and the eye sockets
softening all the little muscles of the forehead and the face the jaw
down through the throat and the shoulders
putting the shoulder blades slide down the back
and releasing the arms and the hands so they feel natural
and through the Torso softening the chest area
belly releasing the diaphragm
letting go in the muscles of the lower back
the body is balanced the belly and the low back can both relax in the spine
just supports the weight upright
down through the hip joints
thighs
the Achilles the ankle joints and even the feet
so connecting connecting through the whole body and if there were parts that are sore
today or you couldn't even feel them very well that's okay
let me just have ease in the mind about how the body is right now it's fine
connecting in with the sensations of the breath
we've worked with the breath in several different ways this week
in the invitation for today is to connect with
gentle whole body breathing nothing effortful
but you're sensing throughout the body the way the breath
can connect spread and connect the different parts
natural breath
on the out breath we can continue to soften any parts that we
notice are tight and on the in-breath we strengthen the
sense of uprightness in-breath is energizing and that's the that bolsters the support in the body
the uprightness and then everything else relaxes around that
so when I keep saying relax we're not just turning into a lump
it's more that we're relaxing more and more around this upright support of the spine
or if you're lying down the spine is still the straight support
there's a way that the breath can feel like a bath or a massage
yes it just flows gently throughout the body
it can even flow through any thoughts or emotions that are there
and just emphasize we put the breath more on the in the foreground
and those other things can be in the background with the breath touching and
connecting those too
this way of resting with the breath
as our favored place of attention
will slowly generate some stability in the mind
if we keep our continuity of attention in a gentle way
and we can feel into the ease and rest of having a little bit of stability
just the Mind begins to gain even a bit of stability
bit of steadiness
we can gently now open the awareness a little bit wider
if it used to be kind of curved in around the breath
you just soften that curve so that the awareness includes sounds
other Sensations in the body
into the space of the mind we feel there are any emotions present or thoughts
you don't have to move the mind or just widening it
we're not going looking for things or just
opening
for the same amount of energy is going toward staying in the present moment
but we don't direct it to add to the breath anymore so it feels like the mind is becoming a
vast sky or a vast space in which all experience occurs
the mind is just there and other things can be noticed within it
this is the space element
the space element is not established anywhere
so it's free positionality time
of a particular View
of a focus like ourselves it's just there
it is an element also because it
connects all things by extending between them
and because it can be experienced all of the elements are experiential
so just allowing the mind to be this vast space in which
other things occur and notice the deep rest of that
clouds and wind and leaves and birds all go through the sky but none of them
touch the sky none of them taint the sky
sort of at the space of the mind just be there
and each time we get caught up in something that's in the
sky and we notice just open and become the sky again
even if this doesn't quite make sense that's okay too
just rest as well as you can with the openness to all experience
in the present without getting lost so resting with the space element
foreign
and as we move toward the end of this notation
connecting again with the sensations of the breath in the body
perhaps taking a little bit deeper breath and on the exhale sensing
the groundedness of the body sitting or standing or lying
so we're bowing the line to re-enter it's
orientation in the body in space
in time
but perhaps we still retain a lingering sense of a
large space that's possible in awareness
even as we reconnect with our own
back shoulders knees
the heat of the body we can still remember this sense of
being part of the sky and that's something that we can carry
with us throughout the day this breath
spaciousness [Music] largeness of Mind in which things are
happening so this is a great way to approach
situations that might feel a little bit intense um it's all weather happening within the
sky of the Mind or if there are people who are
challenging for us in some way if we just broaden awareness
they become a smaller part of the whole so it's a great gift really
to have the ability to touch into this wider mind
even in the everyday world that we live in as a way that we're not going to be so
reactive a way that we cannot take a larger perspective
are a way that we can be give space and feel compassionate for
someone else's caught up-ness
it's not such a usual way of being in the world in our intense
self-focused view oriented world
so it can be a nice contrast
and a protection for us and others
thank you
we continue to survey the emotional tones called rasa in ancient Indian
cultural understanding there are more than five of them but
this week we're touching upon the key ones for Dharma practice
and today's flavor is one that connects into all of them and is the direction
that they're all heading and that is the the Savor of peace
Santi in Pali some of you may be more familiar with the Sanskrit version which
is Shanti but in early Buddhism we would say sunti
in the Suites the flavor of Peace refers to the peace that comes with the
Fulfillment of the path so it's the piece of liberation and it also includes some Associated
qualities like Tranquility rest Purity
and happiness so peace could be thought of as a a
spaciousness and presence that can underlie any of the other flavors
kind of like a Baseline and it gets stronger and Stabler all
along the path until it reaches or full fruition I mean we can
so it's said to be like the like the string for a set of jewels which are the
other flavors that we're talking about for many people the idea of peace is not
so glittery or emotionally exciting the way the string is not as glittery as the
jewels but nonetheless it's there and it gives support to all the others so peace might
be the deepest and most pervasive essence or emotional tone that there can be in
these teachings there's a verse in the dhamapada
that uses the word well this translation says flavor it uses the word flavor twice
tasting the flavor of solitude and peace one becomes free of distress and evil
drinking the flavor of Dharma Joy and the word there is Rasa and Nepali
so this mentions the flavor of solitude and peace and it mentions the flavor of Dharma Joy
so those all go together this nectar of peace is woven so
thoroughly throughout the sutas that we could never talk about all of them here that have this tone
so we'll just focus on two questions um what is needed in order to attain this
peace and once a person has become peaceful how are they you know what is that like
so the prior conditions and the result of course even those topics are too big
but they give us some kind of focus for today um so it's possible to approach the
Peace of Liberation more from the heart side or more from the wisdom side we see
both of those in the suit that's so if we look at here's one that sort of
exemplifies the hard side also a verse from the dhamapada
a practitioner dwelling in loving kindness and pleased with the Buddha's
teachings attains happiness distilling of formations the state of peace
so we see some important qualities along this art Faith art-based path to peace
right so there's dwelling in loving kindness dwelling in meta
and then it says the person is pleased with the teachings so I associate that with having deep
faith in the teachings and also spiritual Joy sometimes we think we'll be happy once
we get liberated when I'm finally free then I'll be happy but the teachings are pretty clear that happiness is a
prerequisite for for awakening we're going to be happy before we become free
so that's something that we can cultivate along the path and then it also mentions the stealing
of formations so the Deep Tranquility that the mind can get into such that it's no longer making stories
too willing to let go so this is a path to peace through the development of the
heart through love and happiness and faith and then there also sutos that talk
about a path that sounds more like it comes from the wisdom side they're not so different but there are different
sides so there's a Sutra that says specifically
or one of going along the path toward Freedom one should not neglect wisdom
should preserve truth should cultivate relinquishment and train for peace
so this is an orientation that's more focused on seeing things as they are
seeing truthfully restraining the Mind from its habits of grasping and aversion
and reactivity and being willing to let go very deeply cultivating relinquishment
so this too is a path to peace more from the wisdom and
restraint side so what about the result you know how is
a person who is attained peace these students that talk about the flavor the essence of peace
what's that like so the Buddhist teachings as I read them
are clear that someone who has reached freedom and peace
sees things from a very different perspective than our usual ways
so this is a quote that I think captures that
when the tides of conceiving no longer sweep over one one is called a sage at
peace I am is a conceiving I am this is a
conceiving I shall be and I shall not be our conceivings
by overcoming all conceivings one is called a sage at peace
and the sated peace is not born does not age does not die they are not shaken and
do not yearn so this term conceivings refers to the
way that we imagine things to be or that we imagine ourselves to be
which is different from how they actually are we're concocting stories we're seeing ourself as a being that's
navigating a challenging external World we're Imagining the past and the future
and you know in a way that's conventional it's not that we you know it's not that that doesn't have some
value but it does work against being deeply at peace
and I think we can see that in our practice so you know worrying too much about who
we are what we are what we're not what we're going to be whether this is going to work can the future be like this was
the past like that so tiring so this this Sage of Peace who doesn't
do that in the mind is quite radical you know and it's not something that we can
really imagine or think about with our rational mind or you know even through
our emotions we can't quite touch into that but the teachings offer these sort of
inspirational and Visionary words so that something in us can feel and
respond to that something that's not part of our usual rational and emotional
mind something deeper so there's something in our heart that can know
what that is and move toward it uh kind of the way a seed knows which way to
send the root and which way to send the stem even when it's buried in the soil right it orients even though it's buried
in the soil so there's something in us that can do that too
here's maybe a simpler version of the same idea of seeing things differently
um it's a verse Victory gives birth to hate the defeated
sleep in anguish giving up both Victory and defeat those who have attained peace
sleep happily so giving up both Victory and defeat
those at peace can sleep happily so there's a way of being that doesn't conceive of winning or losing that's one
more conceiving that has to be let go winning losing being better being worse
or even being equal all of those are conceivings and you know like this age at peace
we're learning to see in a different way so our life is all about did I win or
did I lose did I get that or not did I come off okay or did I look kind of bad
both of those lead to suffering one of them because we have to defend it then and keep living up to it if we actually
succeeded and the other because we were defeated both of them harm us so giving up both
Victory and defeat those who have attained peace sleep happily
that's maybe a little more pragmatic way of saying that can we find ways in which we're playing this game and can we start
to soften and ease that you'll find it's much more peaceful
so although the full attainment of Peace may seem far off this flavor of Peace
can seep into our practice from the very beginning we've all tasted peace this
Savor of Peace in some form so you know I'll just mention a few that
are very very practical and see if any of them resonate for you so right when we start
we use basic mindfulness to be able to observe what we used to fall into
so for example if we're having difficulty with anger when we start mindfulness practice we're taught to
observe our anger can we see that we're angry at a given moment instead of just becoming that and acting on it right
there um that's the beginning of a growing presence of Peace something where we're
not getting caught so that's something that we touch into right away this idea of having an
observer being able to see what's happening in our mind and then as we go along farther we may
be able to feel our body a little bit better and then we can start feeling Equanimity or peace as ease in the body
we start to have an embodied sense of Peace So if we are feeling tight we
realize oh you know even if we don't connect in exactly with what view we're carrying or even what emotion we have if
we feel the tension in our belly or our throat we know that there's some cleaning there and just feeling that and
then being able to ease that that too is an embodied sense of peace that starts
to grow in US we can then we can if we follow that along and continue to try to find more
and more ease in the heart and the throat in the shoulders in the belly we will find more and more of this Savor
of peace and we'll start to be able to navigate our life better so that's a lot of the path we'll do that all along the
path and then at some point we may have experiences that are quite deep feelings
of Peace you know they they visit us at times we'll have a moment out in nature
maybe or on a retreat where we really something drops away and we feel
something very peaceful it may not last but we have that as a reference point so
our practice can take on a new dimension where we start to use our deepest experience of Peace as kind of a
reference point that we can touch into at times when we realize we're caught up and we can maybe even remember a little
bit a little bit of that Savor of that time that it was peaceful and that can
help us in moments that are that are challenging and then at some point maybe we gain the
ability to have this emptiness or awareness that's inherently peaceful be
in the background of our experience yeah the Mind still moves here and there and occasionally
gets caught up but we have almost a background or a baseline of awareness or
peace or emptiness or Equanimity I'm going to use different words because it appears different ways
and that's something that we carry with us through the world so all along the spectrum of the path
there are these ways that this the flavor of peace is there in subtle or or
more manifest forms to where the path is going
so we've looked this week at some of the main emotional tones that run through
the Buddhist teachings and looked at all of them but a wide range that captures much of the essence
of Dharma practice if we could move through this set of emotions carry these
Savers we might find them to be resonant and helpful in our path they're always
supportive of the path so we talked about love and compassion and care
sense of warmth and care that we can have in the heart we've talked about energy and heroism
having the strength to meet the challenges of the path it's not an easy path I know
and there are times when we can rise to that have a heroic kind of stance in a good
way there's humor ah we don't have that on
this path oh the this mind that we're trying to tame right
and then wonder and amazement we have no idea what we're capable of
what's possible in the heart and the mind what's wrapped up in there in the knot that we're carrying when that
starts to free we can be amazed at what's possible this human life there's so much
and peace it's all going toward peace
it all connects and is wrapped up in peace and that's what the heart really wants
to rest upon itself in peace so may you have all of these flavors and
Savers may they make your life a wonderful rich
experience for you and for all that you touch thank you for this week