so I I want to uh start my little talk tonight um sharing this little story
it's kind of like it's such a minor mundane thing but it ended up having a
big impact on me that even all these years later that I'm remembering so this is when I was a
retreatant at a retreat at our Retreat Center many of you know right there's a
retreat center associated with this this is the medit ation Center and then we have a residential Center in Santa Cruz
those of you don't know it's about an hour away hour south of here and I was
uh sitting in a retreat I have had had a lot of retreat practice I've had a lot of Retreats like you know I know the
things to pack and you know what to bring and I kind of like you know know how to get ready for retreat and I show
up and everything's fine for the first day and the second day and then the third I think it was the third day
I ran out of dental floss it's such a mundane thing right
but it's easy to do right it's hard to know how much is left in those little uh you know those little containers of
dental floss so at um IRC uh they have what they call the yogi
needs closet Yogi is a generic term for a retreatant and this is a place for if
you forget something because once you're in the retreat you're in the retreat you're not where you're in silence and
you don't come and go so it's not like you could pop over to the drugstore or grocery store to get something that just
doesn't happen so I went to this closet think like okay I hope they have dental flaws
and I looked in there and I was
amazed anything that you might need while on retreat was there freely
offered tons of dental floss toothbrushes toothpaste Combs they have
a shampoo and soap and conditioner and all the showers they had I made a little list
kind of remind me aspirin uterine cough drops tampons like anything you might
need just lots and lots of it it's just you just go to the closet and take what
you need you don't ask for it you don't tell anybody you just take what you need it's just freely offered
and I remember just feeling like so touched by this like I don't know I felt
like wow this is like some real generosity but also with generosity was
the sense of respect like people like to have these things when they're on retreat but also
this respect this idea that um I'm not going to steal everything and then go sell it on the black market and make a
profit or you know something like this or you know do something nefarious with
it or tamper with things in there it was just this closet that you opened up and
this there was these shelves and drawers of like just everything you can imagine
that you might need and just the imagination of somebody who took the
time to think like okay what might be needed tweezers okay we'll make sure there's some tweezers there that people
can borrow and you know hair dryers you like all this kind of
stuff so this this uh I immediately felt touched by the generosity but
interestingly it made me feel like oh I want to be generous I want other
people to have this experience this recognition of feeling cared for feeling
respected feeling like okay yeah you can be on Retreat and you know have this
sense of Simplicity like our lives on Retreat are very simple but it doesn't mean that we
don't take care of ourselves in some kind of way so I just there was a little Donna
box so I gave some donations right and it just it touched me I felt like
there's this way that all these things were provided to support my practice
like not my shopping practice but my Dharma practice right to spend the time
there on retreat in a way that would be fruitful and helpful instead of Fring
about not having something that I wanted
so IRC and IMC so this location and uh
our location in Santa Cruz they are built on this whole notion of a field of
generosity everything here and there is offered
freely what a beautiful thing even though I knew that and I had practiced
and this to be the recipient of it and with this dental floss right was a little bit of a different way like oh
yeah this is what it feels like to just be able to accept what's being offered
freely and so there's this way in which this community here it's not based on
Greed it's not based on having to get something or shaming or fear of stinginess or anything like that instead
this meditation Central Retreat Center is really offered with open hands with this recognition of the power
of uh different way a different economy economy that comes out of our
heart out of appreciation out of a wish oh yeah this is fantastic I want to help make this
grow and continue I want to help build this different way of being in the world
that others can be and some of you may know that this old notion of
generosity in the Buddhist tradition it's kind of related to this idea of
giving freely that is like this way of giving without expecting anything in
return not because we're supposed to not because we feel obliged or we feel a
little bit of peer pressure or we feel like uh well it's the tradition I have to you know none of that
but out of goodwi out of just wishing others to
have benefit maybe out of compassion wishing others to have a diminishment of not the
suffering of not being able to floss one's teeth regularly I know I'm going odd and on
about this but there's you know it's to the profound and to the very very
mundane so just this wish for the sense of well-being for for somebody
else so this idea of like giving freely also means without this concern or this
fear because often when we hear this word generosity kind of like brace
ourselves ready for the ask like okay there's going to be this talk about generosity that often there's like so
please give but that's not kind of like the Buddhist way the Buddhist way is just
like you know just uh to give if you feel inspired if it supports your
practice if you feel you like you want to contribute to the well-being of
others and the well-being of yourself I'll talk a little bit more about that then to then to
offer offer what makes sense to you what feels like you can offer whether that's
time love recognition mind money skills whatever it might
be because there's this way in which often um it's a little bit awkward for
teachers to give a talk on generosity but I thought I would because this time of year is when there's a lot of gift
exchange not everybody participates in that but there is and so sometime maybe
we are uh operating doing a lot of generosity and I want to talk a little
bit more about it but there's this way when we start to hear about generosity
not only are we afraid that there's going to be an ask but we're often
afraid of like feeling cornered like like something's expected from
us I don't myself don't like that I don't like when there's a certain
expectation so there's this way in which you often like shy away from these type
of talk talk about generosity or maybe we even um have these there's this kind
of like this cultural um or societal um attitude sometimes like oh I
should be more generous we have that feeling maybe or that idea nobody likes this sense of
like oh I should be something that's another reason like we might not like
this idea of generosity and maybe there's this sense of like oh if I if
I'm start being generous then it's never going to end we all have this experience you donate to one organization and then
forever more you were on their mailing list and uh decades later you are still
getting requests for more money so right there's this way in which we might really shy away from this uh whole
topic but one thing I want to talk about is is this build on this idea of things
that are freely given is to recognize that sometimes we
can view this idea of the notion of generosity as kind of like a
transaction maybe like a business action you're like a fee for service type of
thing or fee for getting an object or something like
this but the practice here like this Buddhist idea of generosity is to
explore for yourself your own
experience what is it like to give with no expectation of any
return what is it like to have like a different relationship to there's to
kind of remove that idea of generosity and there's just lots of ways you could
practice this if you felt like you wanted to take this on as a practice there's a number of
organizations that help individuals or communities that need help and so maybe
there's a way you could give time service money to those organizations who maybe are helping
others and most likely you will not be the beneficiary of what happens to those
other other individuals that are being supported by these
organizations soup kitchens places that support environmental efforts or supporting um
like in kind of more impoverished uh communities and with
agricultural or farm animals or you know these types of things what is it like to
just give for the sake of giving even if you weren't don't get a
tax benefit from it or nothing happens because this is tied into that
recognition that of course the actions that we do affects our mind and heart of
course it does like how could it not our bodies and minds and hearts and spirit
all this kind of stuff are um connected like we're just one being we're not like
these disconnected parts so there's this way in which this
kind like this movement of generosity is a way in which there's a
can be this sense of abundance actually in that moment when we're
giving there's this feeling of maybe even wealth like oh here here this is
here I'm offering this this is something that I can give freely and in that
moment there's this feel there is not a feeling of lack where there is not not a
feeling of insufficiency if so then that's a little bit different than the generosity I'm
pointing to I'm pointing to that which is giving freely and the Buddha pointed to this as
well it's was part of his um teachings that he often gave to people in the very
beginning when of their practice is just this movement of the
heart is to kind of like let go this movement of okay to give freely what one
can so in the same way when we have this feeling of abundance again maybe like a
mundane example is if we have a garden that's making like way too many
zucchini then with like just giving zucchini to all our neighbors or tomatoes or oranges on the tree or
lemons or something like this you know here in California we have plenty of us have Gardens and trees that have this
and I've been the recipient of many things for many people's Gardens and was just natural like oh here I have all of
this here take some lots of times people bring things here to IMC and leave them
just for whomever would like so in the same way when there's a
sense of abundance it's easy to be generous it's fascinating it works the
other way around also being generous gives a sense of
abundance this turns out to be true for so many of these practices we tend to think it only works in One Direction
abundance generosity but it turns out there's a relationship and so it works
in the other direction too so this giving freely often at that
moment there's a moment of a uplift and a moment of feeling good and sense of
well-being and maybe this sense of this wealth or having
enough there's also this way if when we're being generous we can pay attention
to like what is the experience like at that moment when the generosity maybe in
the moment when we think about it and then again when we're actually doing it there's this way that being generous
can like loosen up this tightness we have around this
self sense this sense of self it's kind of like a vague term can loosen up this
sense of like okay I'm there's a center here this substantial core to which
everything is happening and I have to protect it and
make it look good and uh bolster it up make it even look better than it I actually think it might be or something
like this we have this self that we're trying to really protect and polish and shine up and these types of
things but when we are being generous that's not
happening there's this way in which when there's this strong sense of self
there's then everything out there gets related to this so that's either mine or
not mine or um I like that or I don't
like that everything gets reflected you know has regarding this self but when
there's generosity there's a sense of oh here I it's just like
sharing and this kind of like this loosening up of this tightness this
constriction this ball that we often have the sense of in the center is the
way to more freedom because if we we to really look
at our lives all the difficulties all the anxiety the
restlessness the stress the suffering it's all related to this tight
little sense of self that uh we imagine is
there you can examine and see if that's true for yourself and so much about practice if
not ol of practice is about learning to see oh that self like what is
it where is it how is
it and you'll discover that it's actually not there it's just a it's a
sense that we have it's a notion that we have but you absolutely do not need to
take my word for it this is not a belief you need to adopt this is not I know
when I first heard these teachings I thought oh that's weird whatever I like these other teachings and so I'm just
going to be the person who likes these teachings but doesn't like that whole not self stuff that's perfectly fine you can put
it to the side I'm just kind of like dropping a seed and maybe an
encouragement to sometimes like kind of like look like oh where is that
self that's trying to look good feel
good be protected this can be a really powerful practice to sometimes just have this
gentle inquiry well where is it because we have this sense of self and there's
all these uh interactions that we think you're having relation to
this but actually what's happening is just a bunch of
experiences that's all turns out but you don't have to take my word
for it but generosity when when we're generous there's a less of a sense of me
and mine and there's less of a sense of uh
this self absorption self-centeredness that we often can fall into like we have to get enough or we
have to be enough somehow but instead when there's
generous there's generosity there's a sense of kindness a sense of
care for others maybe for ourselves maybe because we recognize oh that
little bit of Freedom that little bit of looseness that happens when we're being generous feels
good it's a can be like a uh a breath of fresh air
like it's a little bit of unburdening so but of
course we have to to pay attention right to how this generosity how we're practicing it right I'm pointing to the
generosity that is like freely given I have heard teachings that says
like if it doesn't hurt it's not real generosity I'm like oh that's not what
I'm pointing to here I'm pointing to the type of
generosity that's an uplift in the heart so much about practice can be
about this uplift in the heart that's needed just to make life flow a little bit
easier and when life flows a little bit easier then we can just naturally kind of do a certain amount of Letting Go
whether that's with physical objects or time there's a way in which it's just
easier to let go and this whole practice is about letting
go there's so many things that we're holding on to that we don't even know we're holding on to most of them Notions
or ideas or beliefs but this movement is all about letting go so of course generosity is
part of the practice but there's a way also that practicing generosity can be an
opportunity to learn a little bit about ourselves just to see like oh yeah how
does it feel for me when I'm being generous and is it easier or is it
different if to be generous with my time versus generous with
money like is money easy but I don't want people to take my time or maybe time is easy but I'm not going to give
money whatever it is is there something that we can learn about ourselves and maybe have a little bit of an inquiry
what are some of my beliefs about what's important what are some of my beliefs
about what's valuable and what's precious or what I um feel like I don't
have enough of or what I what do I feel like I have too much of and can um
freely give away so this way in which the practice of generosity not only can allow this
uplift of the heart but it can help us maybe see a part of ourselves that we wouldn't see or be sensitive to unless
we were practicing
generosity so maybe there's some questions that we can ask ourselves when we're being
generous when asking some generosity as a way to support greater understanding as a way to support greater freedom and ease in
our life one question
is is what I'm doing appropriate or the best
way how to be generous at this moment for
example maybe the question is like am do I am I aware of how let's see of what the most generous act might be or the
most appropriate an example is maybe there's a way in which um we
might be listening to somebody and we think okay this is a generous Act of my time my attention I'm going to listen to
them give them all my attention but then they are complaining and complaining and
complaining and complaining about a person a situation an institution right
there's no end to things that we can humans can complain about and then we start to notice as this complaining
continues this monologue they're getting a little bit more agitated or heated and
we're getting a little more agitated and heated so maybe being generous and just
listening to them is not the wisest thing to
do is there a way that we might realize oh that um there's a time in which we
maybe it's appropriate to interrupt in a way that's not rude that's respectful or
and this takes skill and is not easy to do but maybe there's a way we can think
oh it's so uncomfortable to say anything when somebody's complaining that we just then say well
I'm being generous I'm just going to listen to them I'll just say something that I
often do I I um will often change the subject not often I almost always change
the subject just to something completely different and often that's just
seamlessly we go a different direction and it turns out to be okay the skill is
finding what subject can seamlessly be used that seems like you know appropriate for that way and and uh
is not you know disrespectful for that person for me how I often I find that I try to
just like open up any ideas I try not to like find an idea I try to open up and
just relax and then often an idea comes up oh yeah and then I find a way in
which to of like direct the conversation another way with maybe it's my body
language too sometimes doing you know maybe not maybe not as obvious as
looking at one's watch but shifting one's uh body posture and you know people often can read uh
the bodily language that we're doing so I just offer that is maybe that's one way in which what we think is being
generous turns out not to be helpful for either them or for
us and so another question we might ask when we are being generous is just to tune into how does it
feel being generous in the body and the mind like literally really is there a
sense of openness in the heart in the chest is there a sense of in the belly
maybe there's a little bit of relaxation or warmth maybe there's a little bit of
lightness maybe it doesn't feel quite as heavy like the shoulders somehow feel a
little bit less like the load they're carrying is less and somehow or maybe
there's this non sentimental loving kindness this real
well-wishing this sense of warmth and kind of Radiance like may you be happy
like may this my Act of generosity support you and your practice and your
life and your family and others that you
meet or maybe is there this feeling of
depletion or a sense of weakness like okay I have to give this because it's expected or fear like oh what's going to
happen what are they going to think if I don't give and then you know that's kind of like more of a tightness or a
constriction or maybe we have a feeling of anger or confusion or maybe there's a
way in which it just doesn't quite feel
right I would say kind of like the Buddhist generosity is to be giving
freely in a way that there's a sense of open and uplift that's accompanied but
often it's subtle and so we might have to like just tune into the bodily
experience and so when we're being generous from this act of generosity another question we could ask ourselves
is like what's happening in the mind we talked about feeling in the body and in the mind what are the beliefs what are
the views what are the thought patterns the stories that are accomp happing
this do we have can we recognize that when we have
these Wishful thoughts in relation to be generosity for example we might have
this idea well in exchange for this kind of expecting you know X Y and Z I'm
expecting that you'll do this or that you'll stop doing that or you know that you
will understand the message that's underlying this gift that I'm giving or something like that so what are some of
the thoughts that we have or maybe we have this
um feeling like okay I'm being generous but you know I'm really doing this
hesitantly because I have this fear that then you'll just start asking me for
more and more and more and you know you'll deplete me and I'll have to say no and that feels uncomfortable so I
don't even want to be in that situation so I'm not even going to give in the first place
right these are all human things that we experience but what can we learn about
ourselves and what are some of the stories or beliefs or views that we've inherited from our family from our
culture our society or experiences that we've had and some of them maybe are wise and
supportive and maybe some of them aren't maybe some of them are obstacles for our
to be able to give freely so this idea of generosity how it's such
can be such an important part of practice and I also wanted kind of like name some of the ways in which this can
be an awkward topic to talk about how kind of like there's a in our society there's
often a um hesitation around to talk about it or even to be
generous I read an article about about recently how um more and more there's
when you do a transaction at a restaurant or a store something like I guess mostly at restaurants or eating
establishments there's this uh way would you like to leave a tip or like the tip is already put in I've seen this too at
a place that I've sometimes go like they already put in the tip and then you have to make an extra effort if you want to
change if you want less or more or none so like so some people are less and
less generous because they're starting to feel like yeah this is being expected of me so now that I'm expected I don't
want to do it so what are some of the thoughts that we have when we're being
generous and can we be kind to ourselves when we discover oh yeah maybe I do feel
stingy in these areas and but not in that area I think just understanding
ourselves is the beginning of maybe finding more freedom if we
don't recognize this about ourselves then we just go on following our patterns and maybe there's a way in
which we can stretch ourselves or honor ourselves in a way that feels uh a way
to support our practice support a sense of well-being support a sense of
abundance so generosity it's one of the Buddhist practices a key practice and might be
happening a lot this time of year so with that I'll open it up for
some questions or comments anybody have something they'd
like to say we would like for you to
use I like to think of Taylor Swift singing That's Rox star seem like
this you can't see them into the top into the top of okay thank you well but
when I go to Starbucks they want a tip I mean it's always the choice and they make so much money I don't feel any
obligation to and how often I go to Starbucks it's a lot I don't feel obligated I mean I do and I don't I feel
a little guilty if I don't leave a tip at the same time they're rolling in dough why should I tip them it doesn't
go to the server if it went to the server that would be okay but we don't know where it goes so and you're ask
give me this question sure anybody who' like to answer no I think the question is just for you to say oh yeah I don't
this makes me feel uncomfortable oh it does okay that's you are makes you feel
uncomfortable but what I like to do is if I see somebody sitting alone I ask if if I could join them because that that
really makes me feel good and they feel good as well they and they're surprised
because these days whenever I go to a coffee place or restaurant well casual restaurant people are
sitting alone and it well I don't feel obligated I just
want to to chat with them and sometimes they say no thank you so that's okay or they're reading a book I interrupt them
when they want to talk you just don't know but that kind of generosity I really
like it's nice that you ask and you let them say yes or no yeah right okay and
it's not an insult if if that's okay you maybe they you know for whatever reason that's why we don't know why the people
are there so very nice I like this I didn't ask a question I just told you something so that's all right it's all
right sorry thank you Janet anybody else have a comment or
question I just I could just give you the mic
please because then people can hear online thank you so much I just did a quick search do
Starbucks tips go to employees and the answer I got was yes the answer is yes
yes but it's in it's well i' rather give them a dollar bill rather feel
free but they're saying that they get a fluffy increase in their paychecks based on the tips oh okay so that was just one
quick search well no that's interesting to know because I kind of assume because I'm tapping on the little machine there
that it's who knows where it's going that's good to know but I still think
I'd rather to give them cash so yeah but this idea of like giving freely so free
you know not because it's demanded of us or we're feeling coerced or uh you know
or the expectations and just to feel like okay well how does it feel when you're being
like giving freely I think that's a a way that we can fold this into just this recognition
that you know the our actions the way that we're showing up in the world of course it affects our inner life how we
feel and what's going on in our hearts and
Minds does anybody else have a comment
or um I remember first learning that at IRC that the Retreats were offered on a
donation basis and I thought oh my gosh H how is that going to work and I
remember hearing that people said to Gil oh you know that might work in Southeast Asia but it's not going to work here and
somehow it does and somehow it does that's
right it's quite something it's a beautiful thing and there's uh more and more Retreat centers that have been
inspired by IRC they're trying to shift to uh Donna to all donation based so
yeah we'll see hopefully it'll work it'll be
aous oh Kevin you Marth as soon as you put it down
right that's how it works um I appreciate the advice on um
paying attention to how it feels in your body and
um also for changing the topic cuz
um yeah some some people like to go on and on so and I didn't know what to
do thank you
Kevin okay well I'm wishing you all a
wonderful holiday season and I'll see you I'll be here next on New Year's Day
just a reminder that there's there's nothing next Monday week from today so thank
you and uh safe travels home I don't know if it's still raining but uh if it
is travel safely I was so happy that it was raining today I was like oh yay rain
we need this so thank you