hello everyone welcome
and welcome to this meditation
and meditation is ideally
something which is a bit of a mystery
bit of an unknown unknown how any meditation will go
unknown what parts of ourselves will come into the Forefront
unknown what we tap into
unknown because there's more going on when we meditate
than our own efforts and our own even purposes and intentions
I came across a wonderful quote yesterday of James Baldwin
I am what time circumstances
history have made me but
I am also much more and this much more
we are much more than what we usually think we are
we are much more than our challenges
and part of this much more this willingness to take in
the fact there's more going on here than we we know
is to also appreciate or open up to
Trust that we can be aware
we can step out of our challenges enough
that we can be a clearly and calmly
aware of our challenges
there's a way in which we can bring a sense of agency essential a
sense of personal capacity ability
and introduce it into whatever is happening where we where otherwise we would be preoccupied
caught up and swept away in we would be identified with it this is
me this is important and there's a way in Remembering we're
much more and part of that much more which is opens the door to even more and more
is to pause and be aware to step back and recognize what's
happening to make space for what is happening and in
the making of space making room for it we are opening up we're taking using
agency in and to take in a sense maybe even taking
a stand here here I am just much more here than my concern my preoccupation
what else is here let's make room for more
and in this kind of this step this movement towards awareness to
know to step back to pause to in there
There's Something Beautiful Something wondrous there might even be something you can
start getting little hints of at first of calm
of clarity of non-entanglement
so to paraphrase James bald when you are what time circumstance and
history have made you but you are also much more
so taking a meditative posture a posture that has lots of
this room for that of which you are more
and this movement towards making space pausing opening up
Begins by consciously and intentionally assuming a posture of attention
gently closing your eyes and as you do so feel into your body
feel the vitality
that's there in your body
in another place where we take some agency some
stepping away from business as usual isn't consciously and intentionally
taking a few long slow deep breaths
it's a way of reminding ourselves that we can be consciously present
present with a degree of agency here I am and I will be aware I will be
attentive
in part of this taking agency pausing engaging consciously
is also to relax
as you exhale relaxing the body
letting the breathing return to normal and continue on the exhale to relax the
body consciously intentionally
not letting things be as business as you usual but to feel
a relaxed but clear
intentionality the choosing to be intentionally
relaxing
and then letting go of efforts to relax
except to take a few moments to soften and relax
your mind and if this assumed assumptions of
agency is a strain or tense
to relax soften
and with a relaxed soft agency
consciously intentionally gently
become aware of the body breathing
taking a moment to pause step back
and how are you as a practitioner how are you practicing meditation right
now
hardly at all because you're drifting in thoughts
complacently
engage nicely and present
how are you as you engaging in this practice
and can you ask yourself the question how
gently spaciously non-judgmentally
it's kind of open question of curious Discovery oh it's like this
and then with the same open relaxed
Spirit of discovery Begin Again with your breathing
or whatever else you're aware of here in the present moment
if you are caught up in your thoughts there might be a kind of unconscious
agency unintended agency in your mind
to do so can you redirect that reclaim that
through calmly gently but clearly
begin again with the breathing will you appreciate
a relaxed gentle but intentional
being aware
to gently take a pause stepping back
for an overview how are you in the effort to meditate
are you and to step back and pause where
there's an opening in opening to wider possibilities
checking in is there some way that you would like to now adjust your meditation
so that you can be more present
Here and Now
where the way that you're present
feels good it's a nice way of accompanying yourself
then again so we come to the end of this meditation
to pause to step back
to check in with yourself
how are you
how are you in
taking into account you're always much more than what you think
and can you ask that question can you
consider that way that question as a way of being
relaxed and open and curious
where how you are with the question is more important than the answers you get
asking how you are with an openness a willingness a
curiosity a kindness
where you're willing to accompany yourself as you are
even with what's difficult
and then to turn the Gaze outward to the world with the same question not looking for
an answer not rushing to an answer or settling on
the first answer how is the world
how is your world asking that question with an openness a
willingness to be present curiosity
making space for lots of possibilities
that would be not possible if you answered quickly
your world is always much more than anything you think
what is the way to be aware
that's available to the much more
and can you accompany this world can you accompany others
with this generosity of attention
with kindness
with making room and space
were so much of the joys and suffering can be held
with caring attention
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings
be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you so good morning good day everyone
so this week we I'm talking about challenges and um well for this is the kind of the
general theme now it's going to be for a while and um
and so the challenges are um
you know can be very challenging that's what it means it's difficulty which is difficult difficulty which we're having
trouble figuring out how to be with or it's not clear what to do and we had to sometimes we have to figure something
out or it can be overwhelming and it's a wide range of what can be called a challenge
and what I offered this week was that what I call a challenge to check in the
mindfulness check-in and um it has a number of functions one is to
have a step away from business as usual with a challenge if we're really caught
in it and and oppressed by it then and uh and really preoccupied we uh and
we're and we're focusing on some clear idea this is the problem
but to step away and not be caught in anything and take a pause a sacred pause
to check in and to have a different framework a different perspective in which to look
at our experience then the perspective we might have been using in that provides the idea that I
have a challenge so we can check in with how we are physically and we might discover that we're tense
or that our posture is kind of you know out of balance
and so we can relax the body we can bring balance to our body
we could maybe go and exercise in order to get some nice things flowing in our
body rather than feeling all congested we check in with the feeling tones the
sense of which things are Pleasant and unpleasant and generally when we feel challenged there's something that feels unpleasant
that's sometimes generated from how we're preoccupied how we're afraid or angry or upset or something
and um and it's a generous thing to feel our contribution how that's sitting in
US because as we feel it it allows something to make space and to dissolve
or to open up become clearer but also gives us a chance to to also
realize there's much more there's also pleasure here there's also some good feelings and we're realized we've been we've been
preoccupied or fixated on the unpleasant or we see the world through the unpleasant
but since there's more here what happens if we include what feels right and good
then there's the Mind state uh the emotion the attitude by which
we're operating and to see it as just that
oh that's an attitude that's an emotion that's a mind state that I have a mood
and um I'm with it I'm not it I don't have to see through it I don't
have to have those glasses on those lenses on there's another way
and then um and then the mental processes am I involved in processes that are keeping
me tight and contracted and grasping or am I touching into a practice for
example or mind States or ways of being that it clearly recognizes the challenge but
is freeing in the midst of it so asking yourselves this check-in
has a number of functions one of them is that because some of the
challenges we have are really big in some of the ways we can be with a challenge even a small one sometimes is
not productive that we might have to we might be giving ourselves a check in we might see that
and see oh I need to do something here I need to somehow break the trance break out of this this funk I need to break
out of somehow clear out so I can start fresh and so to do something that refreshes us
or to resets us and you know it could be a wide range of
things different people have different things that they want to do but this idea of having agency to shift
how we are to put ourselves in a more productive useful way is invaluable
to be stuck in the challenge and you know is can often what happens
when we're stuck in it we tend to uh ruminate and repeat the same thing so
just kind of strengthens it and strengthens it and it makes it gets worse
so something as simple as going for a walk or having a cup of hot drink
if you have if you and you know how to nap to nap for 10 minutes to meditate
for 10 minutes take a shower listen to music call up a friend and have a human
conversation with someone or go someplace you know in society that
you can kind of lose your preoccupation it's just nice to be there and you know
maybe you volunteer at an animal shelter and you go spend some time with the kittens and uh and that kind of pulls you out of
your kind of cottonness with whatever so by doing the check-in we find out oh I'm
really caught for example if you can't do the check-in because you're so caught up that's a
clear indication that an intervention is needed not an intervention that you escape
forever but maybe sometimes you escape for a little while so you can come back
refreshed in a good way the other thing the check-in does it provides a lot of information about how
you are that you then can kind of figure out okay with knowing this about me then now
I have a better sense of what I can do and uh and both of those just having uh
you know doing an intervention for yourself and and you know doing something different
or uh uh no understanding what's happening with you so you can be with
yourself or adjust yourself in a good way both of them involve agency
and you know and then our Buddhist scene there's a lot of emphasis on don't control don't control should be
controlling your meditation which has some truth to it but we also don't want to dismiss agency
and sometimes we dismiss agency because we have this strong emphasis on not-self
an agency is where the self operates but agency can exist without this kind
of self that's we've caught in um but we want to begin feeling and
engaging in our capacity to choose engage to that agency with what we do
because what happens with extreme challenges we tend to part of the reason we can freeze we can be overwhelmed and
we don't use our capacity for agency and so even just kind of going away
escaping the challenge for a while is an active agency to check in with yourself is an agent
you're using agency to do that and so then we slowly start discovering
by using that agency how to use it in a way that is nice is
useful we don't pile on self and self-identity and
shoulds and shouldn'ts and and you know I'm supposed to be able to manage here
the agency they that's almost the same as the agency to use attention
we learned to do that in a soft way in a gentle way in a kind way
we learned we learned agency that we enjoy doing
and this is what I want to suggest is it's invaluable to discover in challenges
to discover some way some pleasure some or some goodness some rightness
something you feels right and good and if you can do that in how you
accompany the challenge how you show up for it and attentive to it
where you have confidence in your
agency not necessarily that you know what to do but confidence you could always have agency the agency to do the
mindfulness check-in the agency to pause and not do anything and just look at the situation
the agency to ask for help the agency to tell yourself recognizing
wow I don't know what to do here this is overwhelming
to do that in a clear conscious way is almost in a way not to be burdened by it
but like wow I'm overwhelmed to start discovering how this sense of
doing can be freeing can be relaxing can be give you a
different place from where Source within from which to
act from because sometimes when we're engaging in
Challenge and we're coming from a place of being a victim or being feeling inadequate or feeling confused or
feeling angry or Feeling Just scattered
that will often make the challenge harder but if we can recognize we are that way
by doing the check-in we are beginning to find agency we're beginning to find another way
that feels good so anyway this mindful check-in has a
lot of functions and there's probably many more than I had that I've said and you're probably discovering it
but to take some time to experiment with this simple checklist
body feeling tones mind States and then these processes of the Mind how the mind
is behaving the operating principles is behaving in a way that is deleterious or
beneficial that's getting you caught and or that helps you
to have more space and freedom so uh
um so then uh thank you for all this now
for next week I'm off at the IRC The Retreat Center for teaching a retreat so
I won't be here and I believe Matthew Brent silver will be teaching
and um and then I'll be back for one week and then I'll be away for a while
but my plan is for the next months as I'm here that I'll continue this series
on challenges and even though there's a big gap with the idea that we're slowly building kind
of laying the foundation here and um and in that regard
I'd encourage you to look for manageable challenges
maybe even really minor challenges that you have and um and start kind of uh
bringing some of this exploration of the Challenger being with a challenge
that um that we've been laying out for these last few weeks
and uh and that you're going to be creating their own Foundation yourself for what we do as we go along so one day
you can maybe have a new capacity wise
capacity to be with one of them some of the major challenges that you have
and um so thank you very very much and
I will look forward to coming back and in a week or 10 days and um
and I'm sure you'll enjoy next week's teachings as well and there's a way in which
whatever Buddhist teacher is teaching either directly and directly is about how to be with challenges so
so thank you