hello and welcome to this Monday
morning welcome to participating in
this Wern California 7 a.m. meditation and this wide community of people all of
you coming together so I appreciate that you're
here and attending so one of the principles of meditation
that's fairly well known is that we are practicing
mindfulness awareness and concentration for the purposes of going
from a more activated state to a calmer State meditation is often associated
with becoming calm going from a stressful state to
distressing and becoming peaceful but the story doesn't end
there the purpose of becoming calm the per purpose of becoming
peaceful is not meant to be for its own purpose it's a nice thing to do for
sure but it has a greater possibility purpose and that is that when we are
calms and centered on ourselves centered in our body centered in
our in ourselves when we're
peaceful and awake with all the senses in the
body kind of a tighten sensitivity then that is a a access
point that's an entry point or possibility
for a deeper form of intelligence creativity maybe some people would call
it intuition maybe some people would call it a more more holistic way of thinking
or considering or being attuned to ourselves in this
world there's a possibility of a profound form of contemplation
consideration thinking that is the alternative
to thinking about the world not ourselves in a reactive
way reactive thinking is constricted and
narrow when we are not constricted not agitated not
activated then deeper sources of consideration of reflection is possible
within deeper sources of understanding some of the understanding might even
seem nonverbal deeper than
verbal so for this sitting with that idea in mind for this sitting if you
find yourself in conflict with anything while you're meditating agitated upset disturbed by
anything this meditation when you're in that state is not the time to think about it to solve it to
analyze it to review it instead as we're meditating if become
aware of how this is a activated state if you're critical of anything if you're
upset with yourself in any way simply consider it an activated
State agitated state more energized State maybe a constricted state where
the attention gets now narrowed onto the concern and see if you can relax deeply
relax it all not as a betrayal to it all but rather to relax deeply so when
the time is right maybe the end of the meditation then you can pick up the
concern and reflect on it contemp ated with greater wisdom with greater
capacity for kind of profound attention profound
intelligence and if you're not activated by anything even activated sometimes by
Fant good fantasies then we can just focus on breathing being simple here in the
moment so assuming a meditation posture
mindfulness begins in the physical activity
of placing ourselves in our meditation posture and taking some care and
attention to the little details of how we position our
body
and lowering the
Gaze maybe closing your
eyes and taking a few moments to feel notice become aware of
how it is for you to be breathing right now without any concern of changing
it a curiosity a discovery of how you are through how you're
breathing
and if there seems to be some tension in breathing
or overactivation with breathing very gently as you
exhale relax especially the end of the
exhale relax so the exhale continues for few brief
moments and as you breathe now with the
exhale with a gentleness throughout your
body on the exhale relax in your body in
the face the shoulders the
belly
and if as you're relaxing your body it feels good to adjust your
posture more you may do
so
and then as you exhale also to relax or
soften the thinking
mind the tension or activation it may be associated with
thinking
for
and and then settling into the body
breathing as if you're accompanying the body's experience of
breathing you're riding along with the movements of the body as you breathe in
and breathe
out
for and if you find yourself upset or activated by
anything about yourself your meditation about others about the
world Focus less or not at all on the content of the
concern but rather on feeling how it's an activated state
maybe a constricted or pressure
State and so then as you're
exhaling relax the activation relax the
tension until you can settle back resting in the experience of
breathing
for
e
[Music]
for
as you exhale relax
more maybe as you inhale notice where there might be some
tension her
activation and without ambition
without trying too hard on the exhale relax and
settle content to do so
incrementally
for
e
for if you
notice any activation or active
thinking any tension or pressure anywhere in your
system relax and as you
relax feel your way settle your
way into a way into a deeper piece deeper
calm maybe recognizing where deep inside you're the most peaceful
calist let everything settle
there
[Music]
e
for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting do once again as you exhale settle more
deeply maybe extending the exhale so there could be little little
bit more relaxation or relaxing so a little bit
more longer
exhale and in the longer letting go settling into
the quietest maybe the most comfortable
place deep within your
body and resting there the calest place
within considering the welfare and happiness of everyone that you
know having an attitude of wishing
everyone well even the people you have the most
difficulty with wishing them well happiness and
peace partly because you know then to for them to really have
happiness and peace they'll probably behave better
may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings everywhere be
free
[Music]
thank
you
warm greetings from IMC and on this Monday morning we begin
a new five-part theme and uh the the topic of this week
will be quarrels what the Buddha had to say about quarrels and
disputes and the overall kind of uh context for teaching this is that since
the beginning of the year I've been somewhat emphasizing or focusing on the
the teachings having the practice of uh challenges what are the things that what
do we do with the challenges in our lives and how do we be with them and practice with them and one of the big challenges is
the conflicts we have with other people and others in the world quarrels
disputes hostilities that exist that and so um so that's the topic
for this week and maybe it's somewhat topical that uh as world events take
more Center Stage uh it seems that there's no shortage of growing
divisiveness growing quarrels disputes that people are living with and
um and or worried about so taking a maybe a Buddhist perspective maybe a
different perspective than usual on this uh you'll find
valuable and um so the Buddha addressed quarrels and disputes quite a bit uh it
seems that just in our world just like in our world that was a common phenomenon in the ancient world uh the
ones that sometimes came closest to him uh in terms of his context his his uh
was the fact that the religious communities of his time the different spiritual Seekers and practitioners and
and teachers that they um it was an active active environment of debates and
people would actively debate uh in order to uh conquer uh their their opponent to
defeat them uh one such person came to the Buddha uh once and said um you know to
challenge him kind of challenging him in this kind of competitive quarrelsome kind of environment of different
religious teachings and asked to maybe kind of in a belligerent way uh or
challenging way uh what is it that you teach and the Buddha said um uh I teach
that by which we have no quarrels with anyone in the world and um and just hearing that the
person was somehow Disturbed upset uh disgusted and uh left right
away just walked away maybe realizing that um the Buddha was not going to
engage in doctrinal quarrels and debates so but it's also a profound
thing that the Buddha said you know I teach that by which we are not in
quarrel with anybody in the world and um so the question is what does quarreling mean but to be but uh be
arguing with people that there's there anything we have to argue about and quarrel about is there another
alternative and when Buddha talks about um uh
quarrels uh one of the one of the primary ways he talks about it over and over again is in personal terms how we
can look at ourselves to find out the source of quarrels in ourselves what are the conditions that we live in within
within us our psychological conditions that bring us to a situation where we are quarreling and arguing
argumentatively with people in a hostile way and um and it's a little unsatisfying to
have the Buddha always pointing back to oneself because aren't some quarrels um
interpersonal we have to also find a way to engage interpersonally uh in order to work out
what's going on understand what's going on and um and if we don't we don't quarrel if we don't confront people who
are doing Injustice or doing something wrong are we just going to continue allow them to do that and we just go and
meditate and get calm and kind of uh check out in a sense and I don't think that's what the
Buddha is teaching uh he's not someone who checked out he was someone who his
own way he lived his life he was constantly showing up and meeting people
where they were at and engaging people and um but he did it with such great
wisdom and care that we're still his his teachings were recorded and we're still some of us are still finding ourselves
quite inspire ired by him so he was an Effective Teacher so um quarrels so uh many
there's a number of uh uh uh examples or records of different people coming to
the Buddha and asking questions like why is it that people quarrel and um and one of them um and so
I'll talk about a few of them this week but uh the probably one of the oldest
versions of this maybe from the earliest time in the Buddhist teaching career where it wasn't so greatly developed yet
he has a very simple series of uh layers within us that are that as the layers
get activate each other higher and higher into more activated States we end up
quarreling and um and so he describes these someone comes and says you know why do people quarrel and dispute so
much and so the Buddha then gives the the condition within us that has to be in
place in order for us to be in a ready to quarrel and then the question is well where does that come from or what is the
condition that and then the Buddha goes deeper deeper layer inside deeper layer
and one way of understanding these layers that the Buddha describes is that he's describing layers of
activation reactivation the way we get reactive and that uh the more activated
we are more reactive we become the more we're triggered to become even more reactive to get more
activated and as we get more activated one of the effects it has sometimes on
our attention is that the more activated we are the more constricted the
attention is the more it becomes focused narrowed on a particular concern
particular topic particular perspective we have for looking upon the world and
we might be looking at it through the world through the P perspective of only our hurt only our anger only our
hostility we might be looking at it to the perspective only that person is wrong and and um or that person is evil
or something and or I'm wrong or I'm Miss whatever and so that it'ss Laro and
narrow the focus the thinking becomes Tighter and more constricted so the Buddha when he starts
going through the different describing the layers going deeper and deeper he's describing layers to get calmer and
calmer more and more settled and if we understand it this way then we understand that uh the Buddha
keeps looking at this from the point of view of how we can practice with it and not so we can become calm the
point is not to become calm or peaceful and then just like not care anymore and just kind of go on with our business not
caring about the fact that people are harming us or harming others or that we
have differences of opinion or but rather that as we get calm enough and
centered enough then um we have available to us uh a a much more
intelligent creative way of thinking our thinking is not going to be caught up in the constricted way we're focusing on
something our thinking is not part and parcel of the reactivity that we have
and and uh and rather than reactive consideration of the conflict um we have
access to deeper Wellsprings of understanding wisdom sensitivity that
takes much more into account a broader wider field of concern and consideration
than is is possible when we're deeply relaxed then then we're very tense and
everything's gotten constricted so in this earlier descriptions of the
Genesis of of quarrel the personal Genesis of it inside of us
um the Buddha says that uh the uh that in order for quarreling to be present
the immediate condition and for this in this teaching he's doing there's other teachings so don't take this as being
the final word or the only word maybe it has to do with the particular person he was talking to that he described it this
way um but the principle is what I want to emphasize here not the accuracy of each
of these points so The Bu Buddha asks you know someone ask the Buddha what's the you
know from where from where does quarreling come what is the condition from which it comes the Buddha answerers
it comes from liking and not liking having preferences about things we like
something we don't like something we prefer one thing we prefer something else and um if we can realize are
quarreling our disputes or arguing and argumented we might have a chance then
to notice that underneath that we have a strong preferences small strong things we want to have and not want to have we
like we don't like and then the question is where does that come from within us and we drop
down another layer and as we drop a layer it becomes a little bit calmer State and then from there it says that
in order to have preferences or liking and not liking the condition for that is
desire and now not all desires are wrong not all liking and disliking is wrong
but as we but they are activated States and so we notice that as we relax the
liking and not liking we notice we have a preference we have a desire uh desire not for one thing over
another but we have some deeper form of Desire that is calmer than the activated
state of acting on liking and not liking and um and where does desire come
from and the answer there is that it comes from and um uh things being either
Pleasant or unpleasant that um the um uh the experience of
pleasantness or things are something are comfortable or nice for us to experience other things are not nice or
unpleasant uh to be able to kind of be present for that level of pleasant and unpleasant is a calmer more open state
of awareness so quarrels is very constricted attention uh liking and not liking is
less constrictive there's more move movement and attention and it's more open dropping further the idea is just
having simple desire and aware that we have desire then we're not caught up in the object of Desire the object what we
like and not like and so we're more settled and relaxed we see we have desire if we relax the desire we see
that we're operating in relationship to things being Pleasant and unpleasant there's nothing necessarily
wrong with Pleasant or unpleasant but it's a what's nice about it is that we're much more settled when we're just
tuning into the direct experience Here and Now of how things are Pleasant and
unpleasant and then where does pleasant and unpleasant come from and then the Buddha says it comes
from sense contact just kind of the the sense feelings that we have in our body
uh there's sense contact from that there's Pleasant and unpleasant from unpleasant Pleasant unpleasant there
becomes desires from desires there becomes liking and not liking
preferences and once we have liking and and and preferences then there are we can get quarrels when we can't get what
we want it's a very simple maybe simplistic discussion but uh the
important point I want to say is is moving down through the layers and coming to a place where if we can just
be aware and a relaxed open present moment awareness mindfully present for
the sense contact just the the open awareness to sense contact as they come and
go then we don't have the constricted mind then we have this greater
sensitivity and from there we can tap into what the Buddha called um uh the uh
contemplation or thinking from the womb from a deeper Source within a generative
gestational Source within that is not a reactive way of thinking but something
that doesn't come from reactivity but comes from a deep wisdom deep inner source of con consideration of openness
sensitivity and from that place we can now consider the conflict that we have
with other people from a very different perspective than if we do it from uh
caught up in the argument and yelling at people so the Budd the reason the Buddha
focuses on on self uh really take a deep look at
ourselves is not to dismiss the fact there's conflict but that's where we can do the
most important work sometimes to come to a place where we are ready to enter into
the to discuss the conflict with someone in the best state of mind the best state of heart is possible
and um and so this is one of the reasons why meditation is so useful if meditation helps us to
deactivate uh we're diffusing ourselves um and um disarming ourselves
from our the kind of intensity of the way we're angry or upset that uh is not
going to cause anybody any good and we're trying to not deny what's happening or deny ourselves but then
come in from the best place possible so that's the beginning and
um thank you very much for being here and I hope that this discussion this
week on quarrels will make our world at least the local world around us a more
peaceful and um um and
um and compassionate world thank you