test
foreign how's the audio okay
great the uh the topic for the talk tonight is it's called the coral that kosambi
it's one of these um ancient stories that can tell us something about
conflict and communal and social harmony
first thing I'd like to do is if you're willing
if you can draw the mind to someone someone in your community in your circles
who who you think of as someone who is both effective
and their actions tend to yield Harmony
in the community if you can think of someone someone specific and draw them up in your mind
got someone all right and then also if you're willing
if with a word or a phrase some some quality or skill that they have that
tends to that that you would say characterizes their ability to bring forward Harmony
in the community and I'll just repeat it back so we don't need the microphone passing around just popcorn
Joy great patience
reaching out acceptance
self-care
write speech
non-threatening
generosity great maybe one more
compassion um that's uh whoever you have in mind
that's an inspiring Community thank you thank you for sharing those
so in some ways this um this is a talk that I've really wanted to give all week these last last few
weeks I've been studying that the Buddhist teaching on social and communal Harmony and we did a series
about that and uh 7 A.M last week
so I want to um I'm going to go through these two stories in light of in light of that set
of teachings and first I want to give you some of the background that I pulled out from
bikubody's beautiful book The Buddha's teachings on social and communal Harmony
just a few principles we want to talk about first and then we'll get into the stories and the first is Right View
Right View as the the Forerunner of Social and communal Harmony
um pretty easy pretty easy to understand how if we can't see out the windshield
our tendency to bump into things is significantly higher
but a clear clear seeing Right View wise View allows us to navigate in a way that's uh
hopefully doing less harm for others in the teachings it said that the the
Right View it's compared to how the dawn leads it's
the the the dawn is the Forerunner of the Risen Sun familiar image
it said that right view is the Forerunner to all the wholesome qualities
including the noble a fold path So Right View starts us off a little
disambiguation an important point that right View
um has much to do with a way of seeing
a way of relating to our experience more so than having the right view or the
right opinion about something does that make sense
the the essentials there the right view in in this context
uh it's two things one is that our actions have
consequences our actions are effective in the world they bear fruit
and the second is that we can tell the difference in some measure between
an action that's helpful and an action that's harmful so I think when we call to mind we call
to mind this person and think of think of how they tend to nourish Community that's that that's that right view
Instinct that we're tapping into this is a this is a person with a perspective and a way of being in the
world that brings help not hurt doesn't bring Affliction they bring
well-being
So Right View at the beginning second second is the quality of
reflection before during and after an action and how we can how we grow through our
experience I don't know if I don't know if any of us in this room have ever made a mistake
um today you know um
but the the Buddha held in very high regard this this willingness to and reflect on our actions in such a
way that we can we can kind of get a sense oh did I hurt someone here did I harm someone here or did I do something
wholesome and when you do something wholesome rejoice rejoice in it let it grow
So Right View and reflection and at some point
it's bound to happen that if we're living a reflective life
that the maybe let's say the habits of our character
May become apparent to us and this might this might show up in
challenging ways it might show up in really supportive ways good example of this is
living a living a reflected reflective life and discovering for the first time that there's anger in there
and wow I see I really see a difference when That's the basis of my action
um or hostility cruelty
when I act from that place is there a tendency to help or to harm
so we come into come into contact with these habits of our character
and then that gets to be what we reflect on
so
fourth sort of thing that we'll draw out from these stories is the power of good friendship good Dharma friendship
and the fifth is the importance of a Clarity of aspiration I'll say or why why is why is
it that we do this why do we put ourselves that ajan Shah has this
he's talking about a different point but this is this is the whole point of why we put ourselves through all this
difficult practice which I appreciate from someone who was a monk for so long
you know the practice is not easy so why do we why do we do it
so we'll pull out some of these things as we go through the stories
of coral and cosambi this reveals to me so one of the reasons
I love this story is that it reveals to me the Buddha as a human
who like dealt with difficulty in much the same way we deal with difficulty and actually gets to the
point where he walks away from a conflict realizes in this moment it can't be
resolved and when I when I saw that for the first time I was actually really touched
so how do we get there the way the story goes and this comes
from a couple of different places one is the the vinia
and apparently the back story is that there are some in the community of monks there was some minor infraction
somebody made a very small mistake and there was a disagreement about
whether or not it was actually a mistake so even even the person changed his mind
a couple of times first he was like oh you know that was kind of an error and everyone else said oh that's not a
problem and then he switched and was like you know I really think I I made him I I did not
make a mistake there and everyone else was on the other side
so um the way that the monastic Sangha creates Harmony again
if there's if there's a sort of offense let's say is that there's a one of the
ways is by way of confession you sort of lay it out there for your friends and the friends and the holy
life they say and then that is accepted it's pretty simple and then you resolve
to restrain yourself in the future so there's this minor infraction and then there's a there's a split
because he's he's now saying no I didn't do anything wrong and they're saying Oh Yes actually all of us agree that you
did so please
but he really knew his stuff and could make a make a good argument for himself
um and wouldn't he would not accept he wouldn't accept this so
um not only not only does he not accept that he made a mistake he decides that the thing to do is to um uh rally
a party on his behalf so he's kind of like drum up some help
to get people on his side and make a good argument doesn't this sound familiar
you know like make a mistake I'm gonna deny it and
then I'm going to get a whole bunch of allies you know it's very human
um so he goes about doing this and the the split just gets bigger and bigger
[Music]
so there's a certain a certain monk who must have realized that we need a little help here this is getting out of hand
goes and tells the Buddha and the Buddha the the monk says
something like please out of compassion for the community come come talk to these monks
Southern Buddha comes and speaks to the speaks to them
out of concern for the harm that can be done with the monastic Community is split
so this is this is a really big issue when the when the Buddha is thinking about the longevity of his teaching
one of the things that that ensures its longevity is a United Community
to carry on carry on the teaching generation after generation and if they split then all sorts of
things can happen so he hears about this he's thinking oh
the Sangha of monks is splitting how's he going to handle this
so he doesn't talk to everyone all at once apparently first he goes to the offending Monk
and tries to reason with this monk saying things more or less like uh
if if someone has he's saying if someone has done an offense someone's made a mistake but they have the thought I have
not made a mistake that should not be grounds for them not confessing and repairing he's like
trying to reason with this person on one side and then he goes and tries to reason with the others
doesn't work he leaves he leaves for a while and then he gets another report
another one comes and says this
another Monk comes and says for the Buddha now the monks are quarreling
arguing and disputing wounding one another with verbal daggers
it would be good if the blessed one would go out of sympathy
so things are really heating up and the
the Buddha the Buddha sits with the whole Community this time and he says very plainly
four phrases don't argue don't quarrel uh don't make Strife don't dispute
and then a monk stands up and says what on first reading I thought was kind of a compassionate thing to say he says more
or less obuda please don't worry about this you go be comfortable and we'll settle this ourselves
the Buddha repeats his repeats his admonition gets the same response
and then there's a third round
and here's a moment when the Buddha became profoundly human um
after the third denial this this monk saying oh please don't worry about this
please be at peace he says it in a really nice way and then the Buddha thinks
here this is this is direct direct quote I won't soften it these worthless men seem to be out of
control they're not easy to convince and he got it from his seat and left
and that that was kind of stunning to me just to see or hear the the Buddha get
up and reading around in some other some other texts the notion that I have is that he
recognized that despite his skill it
it was not the time that anyone could be shifted from unwholesomeness to wholesomeness he realized he would just
be wasting his time at the moment
so what does he do frustrated well he goes for alms and
then at the end of his arms around he has his meal he he utters some just devastating stanzas about
um how people can be with each other when they're when they're quarreling some of them are straight out of the Del
mopata and then he goes and he spends time alone he spends a lot of time alone
makes friends with a big elephant which is which is very very cool
um and then he arrives he he goes around
visiting some other monks there's one living alone and he kind of checks in on him and then he goes to this other scene
which is like the second story I want to tell you but before we get there because the
scene is such a strong contrast to where we've been just pausing for a moment and kind of registering how you are
considering considering the sort of conflict and quarrel that we're talking about
how that's relevant or how that lives in your lives
and taking a moment to register how in in that Community this dispute going on
the absence of Right View the sort of short-sightedness of or the
the lack of the reflective life it seems like right now in the in the midst of the coral the the blinders are
on such that the most important thing is being being right
rather than being free hmm
so we're about to see something very different
what I'm going to read you is one of the sweetest things in the video
it's these three months I I believe that the most senior of them is venerable honoruda and they're in this place
called the Eastern bamboo Park so the Buddha is approaching
and this is an interesting detail a park Warden apparently someone taking care of the monastery
um saw the Buddha coming and on seeing him said oh please
contemplative don't enter the park there are there are three people in here practicing and don't bother them
which is which is also this is a this is a moment of the Buddha being profoundly human
because there's not a there's not a sign on him that says uh I am unsurpassed
worthy one he just look he looks like an ascetic he's bald head wears a robe
and actually I think it it it's um looking at this another way I really
appreciate that this person called the park Warden is protecting the seclusion of these
practitioners I think that's very cool
so luckily the intervalana Ruda overhears this says oh it's okay Park Warden this is the Buddha please he's
our teacher comes in they pay respects and the first thing that the Buddha says
he calls them all the three of them anurudas they all share the one name he says Anna
Ruda in plural to refer to this group of monks and right away I get a little touch of
how this how this group is living harmoniously and he says a couple of initial things
checking in on them is is your life tolerable is alms around going okay
and then he says this really sweet thing are you living harmoniously
cordially and without dispute blending like milk and water
looking at one another with eyes of affection elsewhere it said looking at each other
with kindly eyes and the monks say yes yes we are living
this way not content with that and maybe for our benefit the Buddha goes on to say oh
well how are you living this way how are you being harmonious
and again just as you're as you're hearing what this part of the story the contrast of what we just
what we were just going through another root of response here the thought occurs to me regarding
his friends in the in the park it is a gain for me a great gain that
I'm living with Companions of this sort I am set on bodily acts of
loving-kindness with regard to these to their faces and behind their backs
I really appreciate that he goes on I'm set on bodily verbal and
mental acts of loving kindness
and then in this gesture of totally not clinging to any view he says why don't I
having put aside my own thoughts conduct myself in line with the thoughts of these venerable ones
and then I do any closes by saying our bodies are
separate Ponte but we are one as it were in mind
and then the other two repeat the same thing word for word it's just such a kind way to regard
there's so much respect cordiality
this next line took me and took me some time to really consider so what's going on here
I would have thought that's the end of the story it's like are you living well together are you kind to one another yeah
well how well these ways and then the Buddha has a follow-up question
he says but do you remain heedful Ardent and Resolute basically
are you practicing hard or or another way I'm hearing that is
are you are you clear on what you're doing and are you staying are you staying engaged
is Right View alive heedful is like um heat full of wholesome and
unwholesome qualities cultivating the wholesome abandoning the unwholesome Ardent it's one of these words that
shows up a lot in relationship to meditation and resolute
so not only are you kind with one another but are you practicing well
and then they they say yes then there's a follow-up I won't read the details of
the follow-up but when you when they're asked oh how are you Abiding heed-flarden and Resolute they have this
very interesting coordinated detailed way of all doing the chores
and what's what's relevant about that is that you could like switch out every task that they talk about with whoever
or whichever so there's there's this way that they can do it without talking even
they uh one of one of the things is whoever sees that uh this particular jug
of water needs needs filling uh whoever sees it will do it
but if the if they if they deem that it's too heavy for them they'll gesture over to someone else without speaking
quote so we do not break out into speech they're so protecting the meditative
mind that they've found ways to take care of their daily needs without without the disturbance
makes sense and then because they're really Intense
or that's just me making light every five days they stay up all night talking about the Dharma
that's the talk that they do otherwise they're abiding in seclusion
together in harmony it's pretty amazing
and I think these two stories are put together in the mahavaga and the vinya
in part because there's such Stark examples of conflict conflict and harmony
the latter being a really good example of good friendship good Dharma friendship
as indicated by its power to help us cultivate the
Eightfold Path
with the last couple of minutes oh you need to know how the other story
ends the Coral at cosine B ends
um the way this goes
the laypeople and in kosembi get really frustrated with the
quarreling monks and they they say more or less um
it's on account of you that the Buddha went away frustrated so we as a lay community
who the who the monastics depend upon completely they decide the the lay Community
decides unanimously that they're not going to pay respects to the monks and they're not going to feed them thank you
so that gets some serious attention and then the the monks the quarreling monks decide oh we need to we need to go
settle this with the Buddha so interestingly before the Buddha came to them and now they are going back to
the Buddha and while the while this is happening the offending Monk
I'm so happy for him he repeated he reflected again apparently he's reflecting on the the Dharma and he goes
oh was an offense
but he doesn't the and this this is a this is a an inspiring point he then does not hide it
he he goes to his partisans his allies says hey this was a thing will you help
me and then they go to the Buddha and then you see where it goes from there domino
effect he apologized he confessed he laid it open to the community and then they did
their Community transactions because the laypeople withheld food
as one condition yeah so with the last couple of minutes
before we do we have some conversation
you know I was um I was out walking here before the talk today
admiring the light and the Magnolias and the God there's so many beautiful
plants I live in San Francisco um
and the thought occurred to me while I while I was walking that sure we have we have we have a really Stark
set of examples here of like the Coral at cos MB and then this like really
coordinated beautiful friendship of these three monks and I thought sure
the you know the power of story is that you can enter into the perspective of any
one of these characters and see it from see it from their life so what's it like to step in the form of the Buddha and be
frustrated at these these people who are fighting I imagine parents or have this some some
experience like that or what's it like to be the the folks in the coral and coast and Coast MB that
um they're actually right and this other monk is just really being stubborn about the fact that
or what's it maybe the hardest is like what's it like to be the Monk who really believes that he didn't do anything
wrong but everyone everyone in the group is saying yeah you know this has been offense so anyway I think I think
there's some complexity to move around in there
but also relevant is the fact that I think for most of us living these
living these modern lay lives it's never that clean
it's never just like I've got two friends and we live in Perfect Harmony together and it's never like
the coral that kosembe you know where it where obviously there's some misguided action going on it's just never that
clean so I think that's where our our practice of
um ongoing ethical reflection it's just so necessary
and as as the as we as we learn from that experience
and then as our practice keeps maturing as our right View
I'm going to say purifies than our ethical sensitivity gets more and more clear
and then we Implement that new understanding and that new understanding but I don't think we're going to meet
with simple scenarios so we'll have to stay attentive I think
so thank you very much one little bit of encouragement from
monastic life um Zen monastic life at least we
we have this uh we have this teaching that the rocks and the rock tumbler polish one another
they're like we Bang into each other and have difficulty intentions but we all
come out a little more smooth and a little more shined
that may well be so I hope we can do that in a in a way that's peaceful peaceful enough
been supportive of your practice so now maybe if their comments questions
sharings
um just maybe for clarification could you tell people what
the vinya is oh sure thanks yeah the Vinnie is the monastic rules that the
the the monastics live by and there's the they're all these great
stories in there I thought I thought it was just a like a list of rules but there are origin stories for everything
every rule that came down so there's a lot of good literature in there
thanks thanks for asking
[Applause] hi um thank you for your story
um yeah so I had two thoughts so one was these months they dedicate their life in
this like higher spirituality and if they had corals and they couldn't get
over I was thinking how am I supposed to live in harmonious when I just meditate
like 10 minutes a day so that was kind of one thought I had and then the other
one is so I would like to live in harmony with all my friends and family
but like sometimes I feel like I need to have a boundary with certain people
otherwise I would feel like I get kind of taken advantage
of or could be viewed as like push over a little bit like if I'm constantly
generous and people don't appreciate my generosity or take it as like granted so
how do you deal with those situations because if I kind of stop being generous
and they protest and want to argue like how like what's the wise way to
navigate something like that great great thank you for bringing these up
um so it was I heard a little a little Edge maybe this is a little farther than you
meant but like uh if these monks practice so hard how is harmony possible for me and then
specifically um when it's time for boundaries yeah yeah thank you thank you for both
of those um maybe I'll start with the the second one first
and the I had two two things come to my mind to
to share one is this overarching principle in in
Dharma practice and Buddhist practice of non-harming non-harming and that in in the umbrella
of non-harming it's not just every other being minus me
we're in we're included too we're included too
um so they're they're all number of really helpful teachings on wise speech
wise action the 10 skillful actions um
those are just titles titles of lists but the things you can find
um there can be sort of food for our reflection about how to think even just
things to try out in terms of how to live skillfully with others especially when it comes to boundaries
in in living harmonious with others
it's difficult to overestimate the power of right speech
practicing practicing right speech that's true honest
useful not harmful
um there's a lot of freedom to be had there in addition to speech there's a there's
a teaching that I didn't give tonight but that I thought really hard about because it's so functional there was
there's a there's a sort of rubric that the Buddha gives to his son rahula for considering
an action and um in this very clear direct way
he gives rahula this way a way of thinking before during and after acting
this time does it look like I'm going to cause harm or does it look like I'm gonna cause well-being
okay so my reflection says well-being I'm going to go for it and then you reflect while you're acting
so pointing toward harm pointing to our well-being okay still looks good and then after
looking you look back and do the same thing if you happen to have gone astray and
harmed someone then you can share that with a Dharma friend and resolve on something else in the future
I'm describing it just at that rubric level because it it has such Broad applicability
and and it has this Advantage where we we are teaching ourself
how to live in a skillful way so it doesn't it doesn't offer a
prescription at all about how to how do I live in this harmoniously in this world
it's more like through through this iterative reflective process we come to see what what actually works
in our own life and then you can take these take these sets of teachings and try some of them
out yeah thanks for your question
thank you I was thinking about the different types of conflict and like conflict I'll have with the family or
friends or co-workers and then I was thinking what about myself here um you know sometimes I'm My Own Worst
critic and I was thinking oh we practice loving kindness I should probably do a little bit more of that with myself or
something but yeah I was thinking of the really the conflict and how it was with the other members in in the uh the
that's the tribe or whatnot and yeah sometimes I think well we always have conflict with ourselves it's hard to not
have a day or something without that yeah thank you for sharing I think
that's highly relatable
so in the story uh As Told I'll call it a third party came in with
a nuclear option and said well we're going to solve this problem even the Buddha couldn't solve the
problem so you know it's great to think that we'll always have somebody that can come in
with such a severe consequence we won't feed you if you don't shape up and fly right so sure how do we get to to a
point where we can catalyze the change in the community without you know uh causing such a a strong
uproar if you will yeah wow that's a great question
um a couple of things that come to my mind I think one of the one of the principles
that keeps communities healthy is having a healthier rate of change
so um having having this um
what you call the nuclear option I'm glad that that wasn't the fir the first thing you know I think the I think the
monks had to be ready and they weren't they weren't yet ready before before the lay folks did uh did
what they did there's a there's a really interesting teaching in this book
that relates to this when um it's on the individual level and then we can say something about
Community level on the individual level you may you may notice that someone is
doing harm um
if you there there's this this set of considerations one is like if I say something will uh will that be difficult
for me if I say something will that hurt them because they're prone to anger and
resentment and uh there's some there's some other
ones in there but the the the most important one is um is it possible for them to hear the
message and change and if it's not then the other two don't matter
um interestingly the Buddha goes through this and says says uh it may be difficult for me or it
might not be difficult for me that's not the criteria that rules out action and same thing they may be upset or not
upset really is there a possibility for change
in the community sense this is just me speaking from my
experience um from the time of living in Dharma communities I'm kind of surprised
uh one way or another something is going to happen
uh with with any given situation there's one way of considering this
Coral at cosambi not as the you know you could read it as like a failure of the Buddha or something
but I kind of see it as like the ecology just took its time
and soon enough because there's this will to Unity
um something came together it's maybe a little naive on my part I
guess I'm only going to take it as far as saying I've been surprised I've been surprised
in my own communities the level of distress or conflict that somehow has been able to resolve in an
unexpected way yeah and that gives me some hope
that's all I have at the moment though yes
yeah hi um two things um I think there's a story
uh the middle length discourse is about um a man who comes to put uh and just hurls
insults at him oh yeah he wants to have teaching and he just lets him know what
a bunch of malarkey you're giving us you know and the Prada says you know if somebody
comes to your house and you feed them are you polite to them and or or
something like that I don't quite remember it but if they don't accept what you have
to offer them uh you know I I went too far afield because
I can't remember the story perfectly but the end result was that the Buddha basically says you can't
teach someone who doesn't want to be taught even the but I can't teach someone she doesn't want to be taught nice
so whether we follow the vinaya or not whether we follow all the the code
is really up to us and I I find it Charming that these monks were
quarreling so much that they that they basically screwed themselves out of
their own you know ability to get food and continue their life
and that's what we do we quarrel that much and and and we push something to an
ultimate limit and I think that that's kind of cool to know that the monks are just like us
there they are I have I I someone recently quoted I think uh gu Kenneth to
me said you won't find Saints in the monastery because Saints don't need monasteries
I don't know if I'll take it that far there's some pretty inspiring monastics
well hopefully they have time for one last question right um thank you first of all for your teaching
it's very um it's a beautiful gift
um what struck me was this thing about is somebody willing to learn or is
somebody willing to listen and I'm in a situation now with my
supervisor and there's a way in regica well he just does he just isn't listening oh
yeah so is there an element of faith that's
or trust that continuing a dialogue that doesn't seem to be going anywhere may
actually lead somewhere you know what I mean it's kind of like I don't really know whether they're
willing I I don't really know whether they're willing to learn from what I have to say sure
um I guess I can ask the question am I willing to learn from what they have to say that's valid and that I I have some
um sensory or you know some felt sense of whether
am I willing to learn but in terms of being able to evaluate is this other people other person willing to learn
from me so do you have anything that you might want to say about that what's arising is a curiosity
I don't think it's not a solution um
it's it's a two-pronged question it's one is uh
are you clear about what you would want to say
and the second is um
it it's it's just like the it's just like the question you ask like am I am I am I willing to listen is there anything
here that you're not seeing there may not be you may have a really clear lay of the land and the third
thing is a kind of like a wild hair curiosity like
is is there something surprising that you can do in terms of communication
um I'm not I'm not advising this thing I'm about to say but uh
this uh teacher of mine told me a story of um oh she she um
she studied as a psychologist and was learning about brief therapy
and there's the there was this intervention where there was a couple there was a couple who's having a fight just every day fight fight same fight
every day they get home and have the same fight and their therapist was like okay
I want you to go home tonight I want you to have the exact same fight you always have but I want you to do it in the
bathtub and something about that broke the spell
and then a dialogue could open so it's not a
it's not a direct path but I I do I do wonder I do wonder if is
there some is there some like Quantum shift that's available through a surprise maybe give this person a gift
or something or something less drastic
thank you I think we've come to time
I very much enjoyed the evening with you um
talking about corals and harmony why don't we end with the dedication
so may it be that our Endeavor in the Dharma and our reflective life
is conducive to Harmony for us for others can be an inspiring light for ourselves
and for others it may all beings everywhere
be happy peaceful and free [Music]
nice to be with all of you foreign