Hello friends and greetings from Mountain View California unseated olonieland
this uh Friday morning here I hope you are well it's been a delight to join you
and delighted to continue and and practice together today with with why speech and um
and uh yeah let's begin with meditating together and I have some remarks
um or the dharmet so let's let's begin let's begin together so
ah arriving arriving arriving here in this body
turning our attention inward
letting go of whatever has arisen
before recognizing that this is the time this
is the right time this is the time we have set aside
for this cultivation for meditation
this is it this is the time In This Moment
letting go of this and that and the other the
entanglements and giving our hearts
to this cultivation right now
receiving receiving the sensations our feet
rooted grounded connected to the Earth
or sit bones and the cushion or the chair here here
hands on her lap her spine with a sense of integrity uprightness
representing the uprightness Within a sense of Integrity within a pride
without a type
on the uprightness supported by the heart
it feels so good to have a sense of integrity
so good
so happy making
have a sense of integrity in our hearts
and let it be represented by the posture of the body
not slumping a sense of Integrity if you need to lie
down again you can have integrity in your posture
the sense of alignment
Let the Body the soft tissue be relaxed and soft I don't have to be tight
now let the breath be received in the abdomen lower part of the body
bringing down the center of gravity from the head where it usually is
a lower abdomen and even your feet
receiving the breath receiving the breath just this breath
and when if and when thoughts arise
notice their internal notice their tone the tone of this
internal speech as we have been practicing together
this week
is it spoken with a mind of love and kindness
so beneficial that's it idle chatter
internal Idol chatter
is it even true said factual
it was a great Harmony or is it divisive
you're welcome to just choose one of those
to notice and for example if you notice that it is
Idle chatter okay title chatter I know okay smilingly
without any aversion you have known you have seen you have
shot you have shown the light of mindfulness on the inner landscape
and you let it go
size after all this is not the right time this is not the right time
it's chosen this time to give your heart
meditation
calm cultivation
calm inviting
seeing knowing letting go gently
not though not now
is this the right time for this internal conversation
this is the right time
is this the right time
for this internal monologue speech thought conversation
and knowing that it isn't all right time to be entangled with
thinking and planning right now the middle of meditation time Let It Go
not now
letting the breath and the Body Sensations of breathing
take Center Stage calm soup
nourish
the heart
we don't have so much time on this Earth
use this moment wisely this moment
here just here simple with the breath
foreign
and as we approach the end of this sitting together
appreciating appreciating and honoring
you're showing up your aligning your actions
with your intentions for cultivation or goodness for waking up for integrity
you've showed up you did your best whatever Rose
sleepiness agitations it's part of the cause and conditions
you did your best appreciating
recognizing your engagement and if there was
awareness Clarity for just one moment
yea celebrate this cultivation this goodness
we are always planting seeds we're planting seeds a flower
of times when we don't expect them so don't measure
your practice for Just What You observe now
take the long-term View appreciating the cultivation
of yourself of myself here and all the
dear Sangha members who've joined me all of us together
sharing sharing our good will our goodness
the benefits of our cultivation with all beings everywhere may all
beings everywhere be safe happy
healthy May the Abbeys and all being specially in areas of the
world where it is particularly challenging right now with natural disasters Wars
payments may they have peace may they have ease may they be free from suffering
may all beings everywhere be free including
myself foreign
greetings friends so this week we have been exploring a
wise speech together the different um
the different teachings the different questions that Buddha asks us directs us to ask ourselves
so I wanted to um to um do a quick review as I've already
done in the guided meditation and add the last one uh today which is so
important and that is is it the right time is it the right time to say what
I'm about to say it's at the right time and this is particularly important when
um we're saying something that is challenging for the here to hear it's
disagreeable and celebrity says but before I get into that I want to share
with you uh the six guidelines that I've said that I've mentioned they actually amalgamation of of different parts of
the suttas and and you might have heard only five and I'm giving six and you might have heard slightly different ones
so I've brought all of them together because they're also wonderful I couldn't just choose this and leave that
so in my thoroughness I've brought them all together and and uh so I just I wanted to share the the suta references
with you so so uh in uh
sn45.8 the Buddha defines also elsewhere as well it's not the only place defines
why speech or right speech appropriate speech as abstaining from lying from divisive
speech from abusive speech and from idle chatter so these four not lying and we
talked about truthfulness right uh divisive speech not abusive speech uh
and no idle chatter and then in an 5.198
he gives five guidelines for well-spoken speech for why speech is it Timely
true gentle beneficial
connected uh beneficial means connected to the goal of the path and spoken with a mind of Goodwill so usually those five
are the ones that teachers teach but in in another Sutton I didn't write the
reference it's elsewhere in my nose and it'll take too long to grab the Buddha also talks about is it true and factual
it makes the stick State distinction that is it true and factual not just
true um so that's another thing that I've tried to bring in the teachings today
um and in mn58 majima nikaya 58 which I
will talk about more today um he specially gives additional
considerations uh for saying what is disagreeable what is um challenging for others to hear and if
it's beyond fact if it's already true and factual and beneficial one still has
to wait for the right time so timeliness shows up in various teaching very
important so let's let's talk about that a little
bit so um in let's before I talk about this
um let's say you want to have a relationship conversation with with a
friend with a serious conversation and yeah all of these um
all the um uh guidelines we have talked about yeah they are met what you're
going to say is true it is factual it is what happened um it it's going to create Harmony in
your relationship you're gonna say it very gently uh gentle to the ear goes to
the heart um it's beneficial for your growth both
of you coming closer together supporting each other and you're going to be speaking with a mind of Goodwill love
for both of you but your friend is sick right now they are ill or they've just
lost someone or they've lost their job it's not the right time to have this
conversation of course it isn't um no matter how much you want to get it off your chest and just have it and get
it over with it's not it's not wise it's not the right time um similarly if you want to give someone
feedback or or it's not wise to just put it in an email and send it off and get
it off your chest it's kind of actually cowardly you you really want to to reach
out have a conversation with them it will reach actually Reach Out make a time you know set a good time there's
something I want to share with you just give them a heads up and then set up a time to either have a phone call or meet
with them in person even better and have the conversations just the right time create the right circumstances you never
know you know they might open the email they're very very difficult uh time in
their lives if you just don't know what's going on they might be at the funeral you know leaving your funeral
who knows anyway so the right time is it the right time to say what I'm about to say
um in addition to all the other things so even all the other things are are
um um met all the other conditions are met
so I wanted to now share a little bit about this where the Buddha really gives us teaching and it is so beautiful
um it's Maji manikaya 50 um see 58 as much money 58
and this is the setup so here's a little story so the setup is that
um that Prince um um
prince abhaya prince abhaya uh has gone
to uh neganta nataputa and liganton
apparently was one of uh um Buddha's Rivals at the time
so this Prince goes to them having a conversation and and then this is this
rival Buddha's rival uh says you know Prince you can go and refute the words
of gotama the contemplative Buddha and
you know if you refute his words then you'll become more Mighty people would
say wow Prince Abaya has refuted you know this wise man's uh words and the
way you can do that is go to him go to him friends and say
um uh Lord would you uh Lord Buddha would you um would you say something would you
say words that are on dear and endearing and disagreeable to others would you do
that and if the put it says [Music]
see and if the word it says um uh that he would say it then you would say well
what's the difference between you and the run of the male person who would just say things that are disagreeable to
people and if he answers no
um then you would say well uh gosh then
um you know it's that's you know you're you're afraid of other people you know
you won't say something that's disagreeable um and
um and basically it would be uh it would be in a you know either way you would
get them either way you would get them so basically just there's there's like more detail about this gets to
Devas and devitals without getting to the into the details but anyway keeping the story short uh to get to the point
um the Buddha that they're trying to set the boot up so so the so Prince Abaya
goes to the Buddha and says so would you actually tell would you speak things words that are unendeering and
disagreeable for um for others to hear and basically
the Buddha um is silent and essentially he says it depends it really depends and then he
gives this beautiful teaching and Prince Abaya you know bows and and it is is
devoted to the Buddha anyway so so here is the teaching and it's so beautiful basically
he says it really depends if if I know it to be
um and basically he gives this table of conditions that if it is
um if it's unfactual untrue unbeneficial and on endearing and disagreement to
others of course I won't say it because those other conditions are not met now
if it's factual and true but unbeneficial and un endearing and
disagreeable to others I still won't say it even if it's true and factual but there's no benefit in saying it so I'm
not going to say it if it is true and factual it is
beneficial but it is on endearing and disagreeable to others to hear I have the sense of
the proper time for saying it so waiting for the right time and then it continues
there are three other clauses if it is on factual untrue unbeneficial
but it's in endearing and agreeable to others this is an important one so it's
not true it's not factual it's not beneficial it's I you know but it's endearing basically you're saying
something that other people want to hear there's no benefit it's not even true and factual
um he doesn't say them beautiful right so wise so wise
um because sometimes as lay people maybe we say something that other people want to hear but it's like yeah it's not even
Bachelor it's not beautiful teachings a couple more of the words of the Buddha
um if if the atagata knows it to be factual and true
but unbeneficial but endearing and agreeable to others he doesn't say them
so in this case now we're raising the bar a little more it is true but it's unbeneficial and other people would love
to hear it um he still doesn't say them so if it's not beneficial even if it's true and
other people would love to hear it it's endearing and it's sweet still it doesn't seem because it's not beneficial
and I love this last one I love this last one so if the target knows it is factual it
is true it is beneficial and it is endearing and agreeable for others to
hear he still has a sense of proper time for saying them why is that because the
katagata has sympathy for living beings ah that just touches my heart so even if
all of those conditions are satisfied he still says it at the proper time proper
time why because he has compassion sympathy he has compassion through this word simply can be translated as
compassion because he has compassion for living beings a lot of compassion choose
the right time choose the right time so ah these teachings are so beautiful and
just so wonderful to be able to share them with you what what a joy what a delight so so
um I will put the guidelines The Amalgamated I've put all of these together and let's see if sometimes
um it doesn't let me up 200 okay I need to make it a little shorter
so guidelines here we go up still I'm trying to put them in chat so that
you have all the guidelines I think I need to cut and paste hold on
um the chat has a limit of 200 so I'm gonna have to put them in two different
chats so I'm going to post the guidelines here is the first
set the first three and I'm going to post the second three and here we go
these are the all the guidelines that I've shared with you and also put them
uh on the video and a couple of announcements are I'm going over time just a couple of quick announcements one
is that um uh megaler you'll be in good hands with
megaler next week she'll be uh joining you from Southern France and substituting for Gill
um deep dedicated practitioner you're in great hands another thing I also wanted to share with you is that um I'm uh
teaching the Sunday morning I'm subbing for Gail and I'll be giving a talk which will be both online uh and in person uh
most likely on samadhi on concentration and also uh put my website there's more
information on my website and I'm also teaching a day long on uh some ID
concentration on March 3rd which is on my website so I'd love for you to join me
um continue practicing together it's been a pleasure and a delight and privilege thank you so much for your
practice thank you so much for your cultivation dear Sangha it's always a pleasure to to join you in these early
mornings even though I'm not an early morning person I just I love joining you thank you so much be well take good care
till next time