okay so let's go ahead and start nice to see everyone
so we have probably heard at some point that the Buddhist path is about letting
go and this is true but there is a lot packed into that little phrase
what are we letting go of what is the act of letting go so letting go is actually quite
multi-dimensional it's sometimes volitional and sometimes not
sometimes we need to go toward or into what we're aiming to let go of and
sometimes we need to pull back from it sometimes we actively engage and
sometimes we just watch so in the series this week
we're going to be exploring seven methods for letting go that are useful
on the path and all of these message methods hinge in some way on discernment you know what
is the best way to let go of this whatever's happening so that's just a brief taste and we'll
get into that more but for now let's go ahead and and start
sitting together so finding uh
a spot that's comfortable where you'll be able to sit for a half hour or so
just allowing yourself to settle in to your spot
if it's comfortable to do so you can close your eyes
and really allow your attention to come inward
just sensing the body sitting
maybe consciously settling back a little bit sometimes looking at a screen we can
lean forward so just settling back so that the
posture feels very upright if you're sitting
and relaxed allowing your spine to be
straight
maybe Beginning by sensing the place where you're sitting your seat
against the cushion or the chair or if you're lying down you're
a place where you're lying against the bed or couch
just allowing that to support you feeling the support of what's what
you're sitting on building you're in and ultimately the
Earth just holding us up
and then softening softening into the body so softening the
muscles of the face around the eyes around the mouth
the eyes themselves in the eye sockets letting those be soft
the jaw
the place where the spine meets the skull letting that open [Music]
so the neck can release
and down through the shoulders letting those naturally drop maybe the
shoulder blades slide down the back
sensing the openness of the chest
down into the belly area letting that be soft
maybe feeling the spine in the middle and letting both the belly and the
muscles of the low back fall away from the spine
softening through the hips down into the legs
and sensing that the hands and feet are relaxed and open
and all of this is an invitation to the body but of course if the body still has
tension or if there's some pain today that's fine let's find the body justice as it is
so just inviting some ease also in the mind
bringing the mind also into the present moment the sense of releasing
ideas about the past or concerns about what we need to do
after this or what might happen and being willing just to be here for
this time
to establishing mindfulness
and allowing the attention to naturally move to the sensations of breathing
often when the body is softened and the mind has been brought to the
present moment the clearest Sensations are in the breath coming in going out
just allowing that simple awareness
to come into the Forefront of attention
so the invitation in this sitting if you'd like is to do a very simple
practice that many of you will know that's called noting
so that means applying a simple gentle label to experience in the present
moment like breathing in or hearing
or if there are thoughts thinking or planning
and it's not anything that we think about we just go with the first label
and if a word doesn't come then you just skip that one and label the next one
and the practice is really to help the mind know what it's doing and what what's
going on and experience
foreign
and if the mind has wandered away into thinking
that's fine we just gently and note thinking
and then continue with what is whatever happens next after that
just gently be in touch with the normal flow of different experiences that we
have
can be helpful to keep the breath in mind as an anchor or
a stable presence
place to return to but with the noting practice we
acknowledge that there are other things sounds and Body Sensations and thoughts and such
and that's all part of the meditation foreign
just seeing what's in the mind and the body
will tend to have a stabilizing effect
we continue to note something that's difficult
it tends to ease that
may still be there but we're able to be with it
if we continue to note something that's already peaceful or happy
tends to stabilize it and increase the sense of nourishment that comes from
you this is the effect of gentle present moment seeing
foreign
as to what's going on in the general flow of experience
has there been any shift in the course of this it
perhaps an increase in wholesome qualities
sometimes people think oh no not what I've been seeing in my mind
but sometimes we forget that mindfulness is a wholesome quality
so to the degree that we've had that and noticed that the mind is
becoming more wholesome over this time
I'm just sensing how you feel now as we near the end of
the sit in the mind in the body
we may get the sense of the protectiveness protective quality of
mindfulness the way if we know what's happening
in our experience men were less likely to get caught up or
go down a rabbit hole or move in a Direction that's going to be
harmful for ourselves or others
how powerful it is just to know
and what a gift it is to the world to have some degree of awareness and
some ability to direct our attention [Music]
so simple and so powerful
so being happy with this blessing that we can offer through our attention
foreign
[Music]
so it's it's very common for people to
ask how they can let go of something Troublesome or when wholesome that they
have noticed how can I let go of anger how can I let
go of obsessive thinking and sometimes people seem to think that
the the teacher is going to just tell them you know turn the red knob a couple of
times counterclockwise and and that should do it but as we think as we know from doing
this practice it's not quite like that not only is there no exact formula
but having someone tell you is actually less effective than discovering it for
yourself but the practices were engaged in do lead to letting go
we might in fact we might distinguish between the practices that lead to letting go and the Letting Go itself
so it's more like our job is to do those practices without to the degree we can manage it
without so much expectation or attachment to results and then the Letting Go will take care of itself
and we also have to be a little bit careful about the language so letting go is not the same as getting rid of
you know our practice does lead to the ending or yes getting rid of Duca
suffering or stress or struggle or discontent but letting go is not quite the same you
know in order to end dukha we might need to let go of a lot of things along the way
and it's not only what we let go of but what we let go into new things tend to open when we let go
of something so this week we'll be talking about
various actions we can do that lead to letting go and so the series is called
The Art of Letting Go the Buddha said that certain things are
to be let go in certain ways so imagine that you're trying to get a
container open the openness is the aim but you're going to have to do something for that to come
about if it's a glass jar then it's to be opened by twisting the cap
if it's an aluminum can twisting won't help but you can use a can opener
and if the container is made of fabric sewn together like a pillow then cutting
it will work or unzipping it if it has a zipper but you can't use a can opener on a
pillow so this is an analogy for the way that
certain unwholesome qualities of mind can be best released by certain methods
or you know certain instances of experiences can be let go of or the
attachment to them can let go let me Let Go by certain methods so in one teaching the Buddha talked
about seven ways to let go seven methods to open the mind and heart
and release various kinds of dukkha so we only have five days so we'll talk
about uh one or two of these seven per day and today we're starting with what's
called abandoning by seeing so the discourse actually uses the word
abandon sometimes that has a negative connotation for people because it's not
usually a positive word in English so we'll mostly say letting go but this word it's nice to know that this word
abandon is positive in Buddhist teaching it means and releasing the stickiness or the
attachment around something and when you abandon that then you feel Freer and lighter you can move more easily in a
sense so Letting Go by seeing has to do with
the directing of our attention there are some ways that we suffer that
can be eased by changing how we attend in some sense actually the the basis of
Dharma practice is our ability to at least to some degree direct our
attention if you couldn't do that you couldn't practice so for example you know right now you
can just try directing attention to your right hand
and now direct attention to your left ear
I think that's pretty effortless usually and somewhat possible to do deliberately
on the other hand when I started speaking again your attention naturally
went to my voice probably and you also know that if some part of
the body is painful it can capture our attention non-volitionally
so we don't have complete control but we have some ability to direct the attention and using that ability in a
way that helps our spiritual practice has partly to do with what we pay
attention to and partly to do with how we pay attention
so it's not actually that there are specific things that we should and should not attend to like a list I could
give you or do's and don'ts um instead the teachings are a little more subtle and they say that we should
wisely attend to things such that wholesome States increase in unwholesome
States decrease and similarly we should not attend to things such that unwholesome states
increase in wholesome States decrease right so unwholesome would mean that
there's an increase in greed hatred and delusion or various emotions and mind states that are associated with those
and wholesome is about the opposite mind states that are about non-green non-non-hatred non-delusion so things
like generosity love compassion wisdom patience integrity and if we're mindful
we can notice which of those sets is increasing or decreasing
so sometimes there are things that we just shouldn't put our attention on
because we're at this moment at least we're not able to find a way to be with
them without our mind going off track maybe every time you read an article
about a certain topic you become angry and then all you do is sit there and stew with the computer screen or you
start complaining to your partner across the room which probably affects their state of peace
so maybe it's better for you not to read articles like that you know just don't
put your attention there a more extreme case maybe would be someone who's in recovery from alcohol
addiction and such a person probably should not go into a bar it's better
just not to go there in our world there are many forces out
there that are trying to capture your attention it's not at all trivial to be
actively concerned about where your attention is going there's a whole science behind getting
you to look at things on an internet page for example and getting you to click on things
so we need to know about about this in our own mind and it's not something
exactly that someone else can tell you precisely or abstractly you know here's
a list of what not to direct your attention to or what to direct your attention to because it might be
particular to your mix of conditions so far more important is to develop that discernment about whether wholesome or
unwholesome is increasing as we pay attention to something and then of course things are going to
shift as we practice mindfulness and get more aware of our own Tendencies it's
not like we're going to have a don't go there list forever eventually we would want to find a way to be with anything
such that our mind doesn't tend toward unwholesome States and may even increase the wholesome
and the teaching the teachings that we have suggest a lot of ways that we can
be with things in a skillful way and in the interest of time I won't go into lots and lots of those that's the
that's the whole of Dharma practice but we could just name one to be concrete
which is that we might bring in the wisdom of understanding and permanence
so whatever we're being with with attention we can remember also this is
temporary and in that case then the lion might not be so reactive it might not allow the
unwholesome states to increase and we might not grasp at something pleasant quite so vigorously if we
remember that it too will Decay and break
or similarly uh maybe something painful can be endured more easily without
sliding into grumbling or self-pity for me if we remember that it won't last
or we could use the understanding that all people have difficulties pain or
difficulty is actually something that unites us all as humans and so
compassion might come forth so there's a way even that wholesome states can increase
as we're behaving something difficult so one thing that this practice of
abandoning by seeing encourages I think is simplifying our relationship to
experience if we launch into a long story about what we're paying attention
to and especially a story about me or about what other people should be doing
or why they should be not doing something and we're very likely allowing
on wholesome states to increase all that mental proliferation especially when we have thoughts about ourself right
so suppose you know suppose we hear a sound outside it's just a sound and we hear it but then we recognize it as our
neighbor's leaf blower and we remember a conversation that we had with them just last week where we pointed out that it's
disturbing when they use the leaf blower before 8 A.M and here it is it's only 7
42 a.m and they should not be doing that don't they know that I'm meditating is
their clock set wrong I'm gonna go tell them how terrible this is
or whatever the mind is doing and maybe you know maybe it will make sense to go say something to them later I don't know
but for sure In This Moment there's duka being generated in our own mind and can
we recognize that and you know maybe hear the sound in a different way
or in contrast you know when we see something in a way that increases wholesome States it doesn't tend to
spiral into a story about me you know we might be taking a walk and simply enjoying the scenery or silently Wishing
Well to the people and animals that we see or practicing with noticing the four
elements you know whatever it is that we're doing on our walk but this way of being it's just kind of simple and in
the present moment doesn't tend to generate those stories and anxieties about me
so abandoning by seeing means discernment about where a situation or experience is going is it going toward
or away from suffering and if we seem to be going toward more suffering then could we shift how we're
attending to that experience the suitors say that if we're very
diligent and conscientious about paying attention to things such that the Mind
avoids an unwholesome relationship and encourages a wholesome relationship
what will be let go is pretty amazing if we do that we will let go of
self-centeredness so that's worth doing so we're talking remember about the
practices that lead to letting go and seeing in a skillful way is one
thing that leads to letting go so letting go is an art form we don't we
don't exactly do the Letting Go part per se usually but we do have to be actively involved
in practicing if we want letting go to happen it's kind of like the way you can't
really set out to make a great painting instead you practice a lot and you just
keep doing it and then eventually something great might happen so with Dharma practice maybe the heart
will open maybe the line will be freed now just keep seeing in a skillful way
and something will happen so we're going to unfold all of this
more in the coming days this was kind of a general overview with a method that's
always useful it will be relevant in all the other methods and then we'll we'll talk in the coming days about some more
specific situations okay so take care