so hello and welcome to happy hour everyone lovely to be with you hear your hello
see your faces what a great way to start our practice together
so ah so um I'm landing I'm arriving myself is so
nice to arrive um together so what I've been exploring the past couple of weeks as you notice
is instead of giving a Dartmouth at the beginning is to just land into our practice together and and let the
guidance come through and maybe I say a few words at the end so let's do that I'm liking that that different that that
shift right now so let's explore together so let's begin let's land in our bodies
ready before meditating together
whether you're sitting in a chair
on a bench cross-legged on the floor or lying down standing
inhale the postures all okay
and bringing awareness into this body seated as always we land
with the body arrive with the breath with the sensations
the precursor to any session of
meta loving kindness Etc
the nickname of the breath sensations of the breath in the abdomen
receiving the sensations the abdomen expanding Contracting
our feet between the Earth
how lovely the bottom of the feet or your legs your sit bones
feel the connection points
foreign bath
let go into the sensations
receive them
it's hard to just empty the mind
so instead they give the mind the heart something
wholesome to ground itself with the sensations the breath
as an anchor
to fill itself with fill our mind and heart
foreign s the goodness of the breath in this
body
no need to be yanked the future or the past right here
cozy with the breath
foreign
entertaining upsetting it's okay smile at them all thank you
can you come back later please giving my whole heart to this practice right now
let go let go release such a delight to let go
so much ease the body and art
you don't have to figure it out right now right now let go
In This Moment
now let us consider
it's a reflection that the Buddha
taught to
everyone especially folks
first he taught generosity generosity of spirit
then ethics and then cultivation of mind and heart through meditation
so at this reflection as we bring this in we're going to work with it in our meditation
sense of generosity of spirit ah
you're breathing in sense of generosity kindness generosity for yourself for
others giving the benefit of the doubt
benefit of doubt a sense of
generosity of spirit where the mind the heart isn't tight
but spacious kind
as good will releases let's go
is gracious
and let sense of generosity of spirit
let yourself breathe breathe it in and out not as a concept
but just was all around in the air in the
atmosphere on this Earth and you're just breathing it in it impacted you just because
you're a human being breathing
let it Infuse you even if you don't even know what that means
expect the unexpected especially if there are challenges right
now in your mind and your heart let there be an attitude
this infusing of generosity of spirit
being breathed to your body into every cell
start here
don't try to figure it out
breathing in generosity breathing out generosity
let yourself be surprised release be generous
with this idea sort of tight trying to figure it out
that generosity breathe you
and your judgments arise in the mind I don't know what this means
what's going on it's all right Let There Be generosity towards these
thoughts these judgmental thoughts
let them be infused with generosity of spirit
was there a challenging thoughts and emotions arising
let them be infused with generosity breathe in breathe out
relax often see what happens
be generous with your spaciousness your forgiveness your
kindness
let there be space sense of generosity and space
spaciousness instead of contraction
in your heart and your mind
generosity also entails Let It Go releasing
and attaching the tight fist
release generous
with your thoughts with your own heart
there is anxiety tightness fear sadness can you be generous
with these emotions
like a generous friend I'm trying to shoot them away
they'll give them space spaciously it's okay
and now you wish I can stay here or if you want
is there someone in your life
right now some interaction that has already happened or might happen or you can be
generous too scared of generosity Goodwill
seeing the best in them
giving them the benefit of that
can you be generous to yourself not to chastise yourself
how can you be generous with this being
in your life as a practice for being generous with yourself and
with everyone else how can I be generous
true generosity of spirit
imagine yourself
in your speech being generous within your actions in your mind
with your good will being generous giving them space
notice how good it feels feel generous even if it's in your
imagination
so joyful Joy making
Act
imagining yourself being generous with your words actions sentiment perspective
with others
notice if your mind if your heart even if it's infused with a little bit
of Spirit of generosity if it feels happier or spacious calmer more still
more collected in your meditation instead of scattered
notice generosity
gladens the heart calms the mind
may all of us may all beings everywhere realize that we each have so much to
give we have so much to give
not just possessions and resources but our goodness our
our benefit of Doubt or good will or perspective generosity of spirit
so much to give so much to share may we all truly know our goodness and
share it with ourselves with all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
including ourselves
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your practice ah
this practice was uh as I mentioned um the Buddha tight especially to lay
folks um generosity ethics and then mental cultivation meditation so really
generosity and as a preparation for everything and then
ethical the sense of uprightness the sense of Integrity again as a basis for
for stilling the mind for for mental cultivation for meditation which is what
we do so it's important to bring attention to these two and in this meditation
really an invitation for us to feel the sense of generosity of spirit it's not
just about giving things and material but this attitude of generosity to have
towards ourselves and towards others towards our thoughts towards everything internal especially if
something challenging internal as well as external and and generosity is Happy
making generosity brings joy as a precondition for Joy so so uh I hope you
did experience that that bad feeling of just joyfulness and I certainly felt it
for me it was a sense of happiness in imagining myself being generous to to to
folks and just the spirit of generosity ah happy making happy making happy
making bill says love this meditation seems like generosity of spirit is closely
connected to patients and having fewer expectations of how things should be yes indeed yeah thanks for that reflection
Bill beautiful yeah so so I'd like to invite us now
with that having patience and a few expectations of how things should be for
us to take that sense of generosity into are small groups of interacting with two
other human beings with a sense of spaciousness opening
um and doesn't have to go any particular way we don't have to show up in a particular way or sound smart or
accomplished or anything and then the um the reflections the question that I like
to invite you um two questions one is what blocks generosity of spirit so you'll go around
just one each person will say we'll share one thing or we can also say paths what blocks generosity of spirit for you
is it lack of time being in a hurry you know whatever it might be what what blocks it
you go around once and then the other the the second question the round two is what supports
generosity of spirit what supports it maybe mindfulness maybe awareness maybe remembering maybe some you know for each
person might be something different that you bring in so you go around and round a few times so so I will make the groups
and as always be kind to yourself be kind to to others
um really breakout groups or breakthrough groups is where a lot of breakthroughs happen in terms of
um yeah our our practice is where the rubber meets the road so again you just
offer one thing not asking questions directly in the conversation dominating and make sure you leave space for
everyone as a part of your act of generosity show up generously show up with generosity can I show up with
generosity and interact with two other human beings here and let's Go reverse alphabetical
alphabetical order okay all right here we go
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back welcome back and
you have time for maybe one or two quick Reflections what did you notice either
with the meditation or the small group so what came up any aha moments you like to share especially if you haven't been
speaking lately Jesse
yeah thank you Nikki for this practice uh near the beginning when you talked about infusing the body with generosity
I had the sense of uh forgiveness and uh forgiveness is not something I
hear very much in Buddhist Meditation area like sanghas
but I hear about Donna and generosity all the time so I'm wondering if you could talk about the relationship between generosity and
forgiveness yeah they're they're so as as you mentioned as you've noticed
actually they're so tightly connected um and and it is a generosity of spirit
right of course it's your generosity of spirit is the precursor it's all related to to forgiveness and there's specific
practices for forgiveness and then there's forgiveness there's more specific teachings in different in
Traditions that Buddhism has borrowed from so we do teach on forgiveness but there isn't so much of it traditionally
um about forgiveness so so yeah I think it's kind of distributed in in the other
um another uh teachings yeah including generosity because Donna really Donna
isn't just giving money it's just it's it really infusing the heart and spirit it's just it's such it's a huge teaching
so thank you for bringing that in that that intuition thank you Nikki thank you
and Amy make it quick here we go whoops wait here I got there
yeah very quick so um one thing that came up for me that makes it challenging is
um capacity and so what came up on the other end was um boundaries so when I have it sounds
counterintuitive but when I have really great boundaries I actually have way more capacity to be generous so that was
really neat that feeling of insight there nice thank you for sharing that Insight beautiful yeah that sense of
having its generosity to yourself so that you know what your limits and what
your capacity is not to overextend and then knowing that generosity to yourself
kindness just then you can be generous instead of oh beautiful yay thank you
for sharing that insight for for everyone's benefit love it love it thank you all thank you for your practice
thank you for coming to happy hour cultivating yourself for yourself and others may all beings be well may all
beings be free including ourselves
thank you beautiful people see you on Friday