good morning greetings
and this is um sitting here in the
innermost meditation Hall of IMC
and this morning the reference point for the meditation
it will be intimacy and intimacy comes from a Latin word I
think intimus which means innermost or deepest
and intimacy can be it has two meanings in terms of meditation
one is to be aware from the most the innermost deepest
place within an intimacy
uh the place where awareness feels most intimate
where knowing feels most intimate the other meaning
is to have awareness be most intimate with our experience
that we don't stand far away we don't step back to watch or see things being
aware from a distance as we talked about yesterday but rather we get really close
and it's so close that uh it's a place where awareness and
Sensations meet and uh and really kind of feels really
going to be connected to touching in touch with our experience
and it's helped by the phenomena that Sensations
and sensing the sensations are inseparable
to have a sensation is to is to sense the sensations is to be aware of the
sensation and so this intimacy is right there to be right there where those two are the
same but the intimacy and mindfulness meditation can be even deeper
in that we go into we we kind of put attention inside of the experience we're having
so if we're experiencing the breathing maybe in the chest or in the belly the movements there
um almost like you imagine putting yourself in the middle of the breathing and the inside of the whole
experience and From the Inside Out being aware of breathing
it's a little bit more clear sometimes for some people around pain
that we can sometimes it's best to watch see the pain from a distance that's the
easiest way to have some equanimity sometimes it can be easier to go to that
innermost area of the pain to go inside the pain almost like you open the door and you
step inside of it because pain is not a unitary singular thing a singular thing
is made up of a variety of different Sensations and things and to go put yourself right into the middle of it the
heart of it and rest the tension there it's a very different relationship than
even being up against it touching it and sometimes when I've had extreme pain
the way that I've managed to stay somewhat balanced with it is to do that
that very thing I kind of let myself enter into into the middle of the pain
if I'm right at the edges of and touching it it's too easy to be in the reactive mode or thinking about it or
having an attitude or about it but if I put myself right in the middle of it then if something gets quiet
and the reactivity kind of Falls away or just there and then the pain becomes
something else or if there's pleasure not just to feel the pleasure
but kind of almost like go into it to feel its component parts feel how the
sensations of pleasure are dancing and moving and changing in and of themselves
so these two meanings of intimacy finding a place within where awareness
feels intimate to be aware that place there's a real intimacy from the inside
out that maybe is not felt if this in in the
head watching or the experience and then to kind of come really close so
close to the experience with awareness that you kind of sinking into it or settling into it
rather than even being against the edges of it touching it
so to take a uh upright
posture either literally or metaphorically
and to gently
close your eyes
and take some gently gentle long slow deep
breaths on the exhale relax into your body
settle down into your body like you're lowering yourself into
a very nice pool of water a bath
taking a deep breath in settling in
and letting your breathing come to normal
and on the exhales continue with the relaxing the body
and relaxing the face the shoulders the belly and each time you do
feel or love or imagine that you're
settling deeper inside the awareness is settling
deep to maybe the most intimate place within
and from a place of the innermost place from where you can
be aware or to feel sense your experience
become aware of your breathing
and find kind of what you think is the center of breathing
kind of the center of the innermost part of the whole experience of breathing
and let the awareness of that kind of intimacy with the breathing
not thinking about it
not being you who's aware of the breathing that's there
but all of you seemingly settling into the center of
your breathing as if there's an easy chair there in
which you can sit and from there be aware of
the sensations of breathing how those Sensations arise
as they're known as they're known their eyes
and if while you're aware meditating
something else becomes more predominant than breathing
bring yourself really close to that to the emotions
not to the thoughts but to the thinking mind
not to what you're listening to but inside
the listening in the Years sensations of listening
other sensations of your body that predominate
feel them from the inside out
with your ability to know and sense feel
be aware can you get be more intimate with the
experience be more intimate by putting aside your
stories your judgments your feelings of being for and against
what's happening almost as if you trust whatever is
happening in the present moment you trust that it's okay
to be intimately aware of it and from there breathing with it knowing
it deeply
foreign
thank you
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to appreciate in intimacy here with oneself
in whatever every way that feels like you're away
is there some place where you can rest your attention Within that feels like home or feels comforting
or maybe it's a place that you don't easily share with other people
but in the privacy of meditation
you can open to it you can settle in it touch it
maybe it's in the heart or maybe there's something deeper than
the heart someplace deeper in the body
it could be anywhere
the place that's most intimate might be a place where
we have the most acceptance of ourselves
the most kindness and
to ourselves
the most sense of belonging to yourself in a
in a generous way in a full way here
and without anyone needing to know in the privacy of your own meditation
from the most intimate place within where you're capable of
love compassion kindness
good will
to rest in that place let awareness settle and feel
where you can have kindness
doesn't need to be expressed or spoken or no one needs to know about it
nothing you need to prove with it or accomplish
just the simplest place of tenderness of warmth
the generosity of heart
and from there to gaze upon the world kindly
from there invite your the whole world into your
heart as you allow your heart to become bigger and bigger
than your heart becomes infinitely large
to be able to hold the privacy of your own meditation
all beings everywhere maybe all beings and everywhere as if
they're your relations your relatives
your friends your fellow Companions and the journey
of life
and to gaze upon them kindly wishing them well
wishing them safety and belonging and
a deep acceptance a deep
possibility of being able to share their deepest place
of intimacy with the world wishing that they too
could know and feel their own depth
and with that know the depths of others
may all beings be happy
may all beings
be safe may all beings
be peaceful may all beings be free
and may we stay close to where we can have these wishes
stay close to where we can gaze upon the world kindly and caringly
May our care kindness and generosity serve for the welfare and happiness of
the world
[Music]
okay so here we are at the third talk having to do with the locations for
awareness or the different locations for awareness
and um it's one thing to be aware it's one
thing to be mindful and know that that's there's only and
only know one way to be mindful one way to be aware
but um how we're aware
and where where where we are aware from can be a choice it can be variable can
be different and to be aware
to be able to have some you know a range of how to be aware and then to be able
to adjust how we're aware depending on the circumstances we're in is so important
because if we only have one way to be aware in some circumstances that way of
being aware is not doesn't serve us it doesn't really work
and so if we're only aware intimately the feelings and the emotions of what's
Happening and we're feeling our own suffering or other
people suffering and might feel overwhelming but if we can be aware
not through feeling and sensing but be aware in the mind's eye or in the knowing mind
Renaissance stepping back and having the bird's eye view of it then the impact of
the emotions that we have might not be as difficult as if we're living in them
but then sometimes if we're too distance and you know observing from
the head or from a hillside far away like I talked about yesterday
then it might be too aloof and not connected sometimes it helps to connect that way
and sometimes it doesn't and sometimes if we're a lot in our head thinking about things and we don't feel
what's going on for others or really ourselves then it's useful to know this way of being present intimately
and as we become more intimate we generally come in closer to where the
sensations are then and Sensations are closely also where emotions are and how they're felt
and there's two ways of being intimate coming in close one is like like there's
you know two things touch each other and sometimes I've given people the instructions to let awareness be like a
soft soft cotton gauze soft cotton ball and if there's a lot of uh very
difficult things inside pain or difficult emotions imagine that awareness is a soft cotton ball that
just gently Taps against the difficulty and then pulls away comes close in Taps and pulls away
and then it then we're there to acknowledge we feel we make space for how it actually is and really you know
commit contact so we're present but we don't overdo it by staying there too
long and knowing how to pull back and be a little bit further away makes room for
something to discharge and unravel settle for some confidence to be built
to begin feeling that we have some agency with what's going on we not have to just be aware in one way and then
stuck there so there's a this ability to kind of come close so then pull away come close
and pull away and then sometimes just be right there being really present
sometimes that intimacy is even deeper where we are going inside the experience
and inside the emotions in a sense are inside the physical Sensations we're
having and from you know to penetrate it inside it's almost like we're knocking at the
door or we push the door gently and it opens up and we're able to step inside
and um and uh and what that does is it's kind of like
a pen kind of like um from the outside um of
the you know outside it just seems like things are covered it seems like a
single single object like but if you unwrap it and go inside then they find
out there's many presents inside there's many factors of Sensations things going
on inside of it and that can be true even in a little square centimeter of
pain or or tightness or warmth or pleasure that we feel that it's possible
actually to kind of almost feel like you're going uh you're
not staying in the surface of it making contact but you're actually going into it and start feeling what's in the
inside there and really sense and feel it and that's true with
ourselves as well with awareness awareness can be as I've been trying to
say this week can be variable where where how we're aware where where we're
from we can be in the head we can be in the you know more distant aloof
we could also discover where does it feel most intimate where is the innermost
place where there is awareness knowing um
deepest places of sentencing ourselves and that deepest place of intimacy
and uh and uh to settle in there to rest in there and feel that takes
time to feel it and get to know it and let it expand and spread through the body
and then to know from there maybe the breathing will help here because you can breathe with it then
through it and into it as a way of staying connected
so to come close to the experience to sense it
and and that could be you know on everyday life experiences
where it's kind of at the kind of the largest life level where uh you you're
in a difficult situation and you stay and stay connected for a
while and then you choose to leave a while to regroup and then you come
back to go at a distance and watch the whole situation from a distance and then come
back if people at work are as a team kind of working in hard and hot and trying to figure something out and and you're part
of that kind of you know in the intensity of people huddling together and not managing to figure out what's
going on or some difficulty find some way to step away and look at it from a distance
see if that regroups you and gives you a different perspective and a different way of coming back and joining and
participating in many social situations I think it's a
useful skill is to step outside and get some fresh air and then come back in
so here we have this intimacy you know we're close close in and then we learn
how to step away uh one one place that people allow you to step away is you excuse yourself
saying I I need to go to the bathroom and most people are not going to
question what you're doing in the bathroom what you're doing is you're going to breathe
you're going to meditate sitting you know on the toilet door not using it but just uh just there's a
place to chill so in all kinds of circumstances this
art of coming in close feeling it being with it and then learning how to step
away and then finding the right balance and finding out what's the right distance
sometimes at the right distance might be not as far away as you could be but it
could be kind of you know it's like like a personal space how much personal space do you need
around people if they can come into your personal space and it feels like it's too much some situations it's good to be three
feet away so I mean it could be 10 feet away where's the right distance where it
allows you to be most settled and present in a useful way and the same principle applies then to
the inner awareness inner knowing and mindfulness that we can adjust how we're
aware and when we're really intimate and when we're not so intimate when we're feeling it and when we're more
cognitively knowing it which is most useful in different situations different ones are useful
so then repeating myself but it's such an important point if you only know how to be aware one way
then sooner or later that one way is not appropriate that one way is not going to
be helpful or useful it might actually be difficult or cause more problems because
some some situations feeling what's happening is not really the best thing
to do this other situation it is the best thing to do simple at times being more in the head
maybe even observing or thinking about knowing it in some cognitive way is the
best thing to do and sometimes it's a not that good thing to do and sometimes being far away imagining you're kind of
from a distance um and so all these different ways of knowing and locations of knowing
so for today um and um
if you can
if you want try intimacy try what it's like to really be in touch
with things and maybe even imagine you're actually going into it
it could be something even as simple as eating your food what would it mean to be intimate with your food rather than
eating while you're listening to the news or something and what's it like to be intimate with
sitting in a chair what's he how would that feel here intimacy
how would it be what's intimacy like in meditation what's a certain kind of intimacy
that doesn't cross an appropriate lines certain kind of knowing awareness intimacy as you're
listening to a friend they don't have to know that you're feeling intimate but what's a way of
being really there and touching feeling what's happening internally so you
really feel connected and um so intimacy
so thank you and um and we'll kind of continue and
kind of build on this tomorrow and I hope that um you
kind of can appreciate playing around with awareness in mindfulness and
knowing and sensing and begin living in the playground of these things
thank you