greetings friends greetings from Mountain View California land
to wherever you are in the world joining each other
this wonderful moment in time what whatever the conditions are it's
wonderful to just be an experience and have agency whether their challenges
difficulties um the full catastrophe it's it's a
privilege to be human with all its ups and downs so
delighted to be joining you and um
the theme for this week is why speech and
for the meditation the invitations are to notice our internal speech
because speech isn't just what we engage in externally but also how we address
ourselves how we do the narration all the internal speeches also speech so
so that's the general invitation and uh I'll say more about
um yeah I'll share more in the department so let's uh let's practice together
let's uh let's begin our meditation
so arriving arriving in this body
it feels comfortable to close your eyes or maybe have the slit open that's
perfectly fine too that's what's more comfortable
and coming and coming to this body this human body this amazing Miracle of
nature inclining your awareness your attention
in the mysterious ways we can do that
is awareness attention whatever it is
The Power Of Consciousness directing
inviting it to pay attention to rest on the body
sensations of the body
inviting the body to soften and relax might be helpful to
start say from the top and go the bottom of the body
notice the forehead it's tight
your cheeks your jaw
not forgetting the eyes let them rest in their socket
ah exhaling relaxing the face
neck and shoulders
the arms the hands let them give their weight to the Earth
relaxing softening the chest
with the next exhale the abdomen
oh sit bones sit bones
but the entire weight of the upper body be released
into your sitting bones
releasing the legs upper legs knees
lower legs
and feet
let the breath be received the relaxed Body Solid
spacious here
the body is tight the mind gets tight letters away here and there let the body
be relaxed heart can soften
and this spacious miraculous Moment In Time
receiving receiving the breath receiving the mystery
and those thoughts arise as they will inevitably do
notice kindly gently with meta notice their quality
thoughts of our inner speech if it's directed to ourselves
or about others is it even true as a different factual
politeness about it if the thought arises oh you can't do
this you're hopeless at meditation or whatever judgmental thought
might be kindly gently laugh
is it is it even true it's a different factual don't have to believe it
it's not even true it's just an opinion
and then can you release can it be released with a smile with friendliness
men giving our hearts to the breath presence in this moment
I have another thought that arises again noticing
perhaps we can notice if there is greed or wanting
in the speech or or ill will resentment if it's about others
smilingly after noticing we let go
after knowing in this way we let go and we come back
our anchor and we stay with the anchor
it's nourishing calming soothing
Gathering collecting
life-giving anchor of the breath
if you notice any greed or hatred or confusion in your
speech let there not be
aversion because we're adding more hatred on top of it
Let There Be kindness oh my inner speech I just noticed
aversive oh sweetheart oh sweetheart it's okay
they let that go let there be kindness instead
those are inner speech have blindness generosity and wisdom
that way you've noticed let go let go just here
with the breath in the body
foreign
sitting to a close together
letting go of any judgment for how must have been should
have been wasn't letting go and appreciating the goodness that we showed up we did our best
recognizing our inner goodness the co-created goodness
a meta with matter with kindness
and sharing this shining this light of mitta this night of goodness
ourselves and sharing it with all beings everywhere all beings
especially right now those who are affected by particularly challenging
circumstances or siblings on this Earth
natural disaster earthquake sending them our support in our heart
our compassion we are not so different
we're all subject to the same causes and conditions
challenges in this world we are not so different
from these siblings throughout the world
sharing our goodness are met our good will our Humanity and may all beings
everywhere be free from suffering
may all beings everywhere be safe happy
healthy may they have ease he all thinks everywhere
be free including ourselves
thank you all for your practice and hello again greetings
so the theme for this week is um
wise speech and it's both external speech what we
say in words what we write
for example even writing what we write in chat and just small the Nuggets of
writing or are also considered speech and
these days with social media you know the the one little comment or with a little tweet
our speech can have so much impact externally on the world
with the spread with its reach with the speed of dissemination
so speech is quite powerful both externally and also how it shapes our
world internally our words spoken or written they shape us they
it's the scaffold of shaping who we are how we think how we perceive
um fascinating researcher also about the impact of language on our perception how we actually perceive reality
quote-unquote reality based on the words we use based on our speech
so the power really appreciating the power of speech both externally the
impact it has on others we can hurt others we can
um great factions Wars yes Wars have started
based on words um and also our words can bring sucker
they can bring Comfort they can bring Unity they can support people heal people so words are so powerful
both externally and how they impact us they form and shape uh us and they shape
and form our Karma and karma in the way of of our conditionality
person we are the person we become we keep becoming in every moment that's our
Karma our words shape our Karma very important
so yesterday we began with the first guideline
not the Buddha gives which is is it true and factual and I added the Nuance of
factual if you missed yesterday please listen to it I uh I do want to add a couple of things
to to the true and factual because this is such an important
um such an important one before we um move on to the next one today
and um first one thing I wanted to add was uh I was not a good academic yesterday I
was so excited about the research that I forgot to give you the the references to where you could find it and the work I
talked about yesterday the Neuroscience research can be found in Nature Neuroscience 2016. it's the work that
was done in the lab of Tali charot and colleagues foreign
and today I wanted to add one more teaching about truthfulness and this is so beautiful
this is um from nikaya 61. it's where um the
Buddha is is teaching rahula um his son
and uh and this is what uh what the Buddha says so one day the Buddha came to rahula
pointed to a bull with a little bit of water in it
and asked rahula do you see this bit of water left in the bowl rahula answered
yes sir so little rahula is the spiritual achievement of one who is not afraid to
speak a deliberate lie it's profound okay but but then the Buddha continues
so little water is so little is the spiritual achievement of someone who's not afraid to speak a deliberate life
then the Buddha threw the water away put the bull down and said do you see rahula
how the water has been discarded in the same way one who tells a
deliberate lie discards whatever spiritual achievement one has made
wow they and continues again he asked do you see
how this bowl is now empty in the same way one who has no shame in speaking
lives is empty of spiritual achievement he's really driving the point home you
get this right he's just driving you know home and and in beautiful different
ways um
then the Buddha this is this is the last straw then the Buddha turned the ball
upside down and said do you see rahula how this bowl has been turned upside
down in the same way one who tells a deliberate lie
turns one's spiritual achievements upside down and becomes incapable of
progress therefore the Buddha concluded one should not speak at deliberate lie even
image even just so turning the ball upside down
incapable of progress incapable of progress as I mentioned yesterday commitment to
the truth is so fundamental so important to truthfulness to speaking the truth uh
internally externally that is is is the only precept that a bodhisattva
cannot break so it's and the Buddha basically says if you can't if you tell a deliberate lie if you don't have if
you have no shame just you cannot make progress you throw it away you just you're incapable
and and many of us perhaps were here that's like oh yeah I tell the truth yeah I tell the truth and yes yes for
most part for the most part telling the truth might be easy but those Nuance to
those particular instances where it's not easy where it's hard to tell the
truth those are the times to to inquire to settle in with our bodies with our
hearts like what is happening am I am I afraid of being judged this is my
self-sense in danger um do I want to show up in a particular way do I want to be perceived in a
particular like what what is the rub on those moments on those moments that's
telling you we just wanna you know a little bit not quite shade the truth
for our benefit or for all one another person's benefit or that or detriment
perhaps those are the times that that it becomes kind of sticky and those are and
in general maybe 98 of the time or 99 oh yeah it's easy we tell the truth yeah it's raining now so I would put those
tiny bits of time and and can be uh bring bring
um uh a brightness so I I remember actually years ago I
remember I noticed that when I got somewhere late for example I I would have
um um uh and and I had so there would be traffic and then I had left later than I
intended but then I would be ashamed to say actually I left later then and I would just say oh there was traffic that's why I'm late then I thought wait
that's not quite true I left later so I made it I made it the choice to say I
left I'm I left later than I intended I'm sorry and there was traffic so there was just a sense of truthfulness or a
sense of a brightness it just felt cleaner even though it was small but but
still it felt uh more upright yes I'm not just like and and then the question
really was oh am I like not feeling comfortable saying that yes I left later because I don't want to be judged I
don't want to be seen as someone who doesn't have it together or whatever runs late like no I I ran late and
there's a brightness to actually say that to to to not be um to not have that
shame or whatever it is so so having that that uh that inquiry
so I've spoken a lot again about uh the previous topic which is so important so
important um maybe I would just add one more thing uh
now actually I'll save this for for later okay I want to move on to the next um
uh question that we ask so the next question to ask ourselves is um
is my speech divisive is it divisive or does it create Harmony
so the Buddha teaches about why speech they're always things to avoid and
things to cultivate so this is what what the Buddha says abandoning divisive
speech one abstains from divisive speech what one has heard here one does not
tell there to break those people apart from these people what one has heard there one does not
tell here to break these people apart from those people so this sense of
breaking people apart one does not do that and and to and yeah this is kind of
maybe a old language but how often do we kind of you know speak behind people's
back or divisive speech and slanderous speech and um slanderous and divisive
speech is is based on hatred and ill will it has that as its root and it's
enmeshed with resentment Envy intention to hurt another wind respect and support
for ourselves and it actually carries doubly heavy
Karma because it involves forethought it's not only does it have the root of hatred and
ill will but also since it has forethought you thought about it ahead of time like oh yeah I'm gonna say that
thing about that friend the third friend to this friend of mine so that you know they're getting very close and I'm
feeling threatened they're getting very close and well they didn't invite me they went out to lunch on their own oh
I'm gonna just say you know you know they this person said something you know just that this it involves forethought
it involves some planning so it has doubly heavy Karma foreign
[Music]
he says thus reconciling those who have broken apart or cementing those who are
united he one loves Concord Delights in Concord enjoys Concord speaks things
that create Concord basically creating Harmony speaking what
creates Harmony um that's what the Buddha is recommending so so instead if you see oh
your friend you know your other two friends are now getting closer oh yes yes great Concord I'm so glad you're
you're becoming more friends you know she they they're wonderful this is great
so it's Concord creating Concord Harmony between people instead of breaking
people apart um
so so notice so today as you go about your day
um please bring in this this inquiry both about is it truthful is it
factual internally externally especially in those like maybe one percent or maybe
fewer uh percentage of the time when it's a little difficult to be completely honest
and then [Music] um and then with is is my speech divisive
is it um or is it creating Harmony and and and in all these cases really inquiring with
the body what's going on inquiring with the body inquiring with the intention with motivation what's going on what's
going on sweetheart well if if I'm tempted not to to speak aligned with my
highest values what's going on sweetie what's going on can we reconnect can we
reconnect with our um intentions can can we reconnect with our highest intentions so
so that is uh that is our time this morning thank you
so much for for your practice thank you so much for your practice may you be
well may all beings everywhere well a good care and we will continue
tomorrow