welcome welcome before I turned on the recording I was just I don't know having a delight
and how many of us are coming together for these practices it's such a beautiful thing we're doing together
thank you for that and today I'll continue on this
theme of faculties for fearlessness fine five faculties for
fearlessness forever and uh I'm sure we can make up
all kinds of alliterations but we'll start with a guided meditation and then
we'll introduce the fourth faculty and when I'm saying the fourth it's not necessarily the fourth faculty in the
traditional listing of the five faculties I'm choosing to do them in a
different order and to emphasize particular aspects of the faculty so not
in the most common conventional
way so start our
meditation just tuning into the
posture whether you're sitting on the floor sitting on a
chair or even lying down can there be a sense
of uprightness and not a way that is stiff
or forced but in a way that maybe conveys a
sense of respect for yourself for the
practice love ing the vertebrae of the spine to stuck one upon the
other and maybe moving the chin backwards just a tiny bit someone might
not even be able to see how much you move but it opens up the vertebrae or
the experience in the back of the
neck allows for a little bit more stability a bit more
openness this tiny
movement and then getting a sense of this
posture at this moment in general the sense of
uprightness the contact with the surface whatever contact whatever
surface the body is
contacting
ring into the bodily experience feeling grounded connected
we're here and the body is in this
configuration and can you make
this bodily experience be a
container a
receptacle right now for a sense of kindness openness
spaciousness in whatever way that makes sense to you
you can we connect with a sense of openness maybe some softness or
relaxation
in a general sense not bracing ourselves
against what we imagine might happen but instead to have an attitude
of welcoming and warmth and
care
and can we connect with an acknowledgement that practice is a
movement of kindness and
Care way to honor and respect
ourselves
and with this attitude of care and warmth bringing attention to any areas
of the body that feel particularly tense or
tight I often mention the eyes and the
jaw they often have tension not
always the shoulders can rise up or get tight can
we allow the shoulder blades to slide down the
back
and softening the front of the
body the chest the
belly
bringing attention to the back of the
body if you're leaning against a back rest feeling the contact feeling the
contact on the buttocks the back of the
legs and feeling where there's not contact on the back of the body
also we're just noticing nothing in particular needs to
be happening we're just bringing awareness bringing attention
the different parts of the
body different
experiences
recognizing that it can be [Music]
sounds just letting them be
there and then resting our attention on the sensations of
breathing the movements in the body as the body
breathes
the stretching in the chest and the release of the
stretch movement of the abdomen in and
out or feeling the different temperatures of
air as it enters and exits the
nose whichever of those locations is most comfortable most accessible to you
right now just rest attention there with this
sensations of
breathing
it's natural for the mind to wander unless you're in some very deep
meditative state
and so when we notice we just begin
again all judgments or evaluations of our
practice of ourselves that's extra and not
needed we just rest attention on the Sens sensations of
breathing
and we practice in such a
way that we're resting attention on the S sensations of
breathing and making
space for whatever arises making room for whatever shows
up might be sounds may be the bodily
experiences thoughts
sense of doing both resting with the sensations of
breathing and allowing room for whatever else is showing
up
[Music]
morning good afternoon good evening welcome welcome as I explore the fourth session
on this uh theme of faculties for fearlessness and as maybe I'll say again
that I'm not using going through the faculties in the traditional order and
in this uh exploration of the faculties and fearlessness I'm emphasizing
different aspects of fearlessness it's kind of uh started
with I wanted to do something about fear and but I wanted to do something
uplifting about fear rather than just talking about fear and and so this idea of faculties
of fear like how can we use them as a support because it turns out that
naturally humans have fear sometimes it's really obvious and sometimes it's
really subtle because there's a way in that risk is just a part of human
life in fact if there were a life that's not open to the uncontrollable elements
in the world and therefore not subject to fear then that life would be a Divine
Life that would be like a god right Not a Human Being because human beings have
risks we're vulnerable whether's accident disease
impass humiliation loss failure these things happen to
humans and if we don't like maybe address them or acknowledge them there
can be this effect this long-term effect of like perpetually feeling fear and
there's a way that we just become habituated to it and not even noticing
the different ways it shows up and then this um impact of this like uh continuous or
long-term feeling of this subtle lowgrade fear maybe with spikes of a lot
of fear is affects our ability to take
risks which includes things like feeling
deeply feeling love feeling the loss we all have
losses and also affects our ability to think uh independently and not just be pushed
around by whatever sources we have in contact with whatever news sources or
social sources you know maybe there's a little bit if we just are so used to having some fear then we don't say like
no wait I'm going to think about this myself and also having this maybe a
long-term chronic lowgrade fear really impacts our ways to express
ourselves with creativity or innovation to bring something new into
the world not that we have to share it but even for ourselves and there's this powerful book
that I really like I'll just mention briefly it's by David biles b y l and
Ted Orland and it's called Art and fear art and fear by David biles and Ted
Orland and this this way that they really talk about this how fear kind of like a robs us as some of our
creativity so and there's a way that it can render us you know this fear a little bit more like passive so this is
why part of the reason why I like to address fear then quickly I'll just do a review of
the preceding weeks the first week was Sati which I talked about noticing noticing our environment and noticing
our own experience then I did S as maybe collectiveness and
wholeheartedness bringing this centeredness or wholeheartedness to the
sense of no the resistance to the fear which is a little bit different
than do it to fear if you can do it with fear great but instead this sense of resistance to
fear and then yesterday was sadada or Sada is confidence and trust and this
confidence in the practice this confidence in ourselves just enough
confidence but also a trust to this natural inner process that moves towards
greater freedom and wholeness and then way this trust that
what's needed from us is to just get out of the way sometimes right sometimes
effort and now I like to introduce a fourth faculty and that is
Viria Viria is often associated with the power and virility of the warrior it's
this you know strength and hero and exertion to make extraordinary
accomplishments and we're not going to be talking about
that instead I'd like to focus on a different aspect of
Viria courage sometimes via can be translated
as courage and so courage is this capacity to face the
fear as best we can it's the power to stand one's ground
even though there's just exactly what we don't want is
there and being it's this courage is to be with the
fear and the resistance to the fear as best we can I've been talking
about how to work with the fear but it turns out we also need courage sometimes
we need courage just to notice or acknowledge that we have fear or just to
acknowledge that the resistance to the fear because it doesn't matter how many
Buddhist teachings we've heard it doesn't matter how much meditation experience we've had if we can't just be
with our experience in our daily life when these difficulties arise something difficult like fear and sometimes we
just need some courage courage to show up for what's
happening as best we can bringing with us the tools or the knowledge that's
available to us at that time time because let's face it sometimes when fear is up we don't have access to
our greatest wisdom always we don't have access to a sense of groundedness and
presence always so sometimes courage is what's
needed and sometimes this courage shows up as the capacity to avoid
despair sometimes it's courage to not collapse in this tempted sometimes to
surrender and this collapse sometimes it takes courage
to stay upright to be with our
experience there's this way and we can like um refuse to be open to new ex
chances or new experiences and we have this Movement we just want to be closed
down and isolate and be secluded and in this way we might feel a little bit less
vulnerable but we need courage when terrible things are
happening so that we can acknowledge them as best we can notice them as best we can gather
ourselves around the resistance to them as best we can and to have some confidence and
Trust as best we can and not only is courage needed when
difficulties happen but sometimes we just need everyday courage to
expand we need everyday courage just to change yes I've been doing it this way
for a lifetime yes I've been having these beliefs for a lifetime but maybe
there's something different that's available ailable maybe there's something
more something more beautiful and there's no guarantees
right that if we open up and allow something more that there won't be difficulties as well so it takes some
courage so then the natural question is okay Diana you're talking about courage
how do we develop Courage the buunis texts don't really
help us out here they don't have anything specific to help us with
courage they have the stories of the Buddha towards um right before his
Awakening had this determination he was going to sit and find the way to complete freedom and as he did so Mara
the we might say is the embodiment of whatever gets in the way of
Freedom Mara assailed the Buddha the armies some of you might remember
remember a number of months ago I did some 7 AMS on Mara so there's stories of how the
Buddha was able to behave with courage there's also this story of the
Buddha even before with the mara he recognizing that when he went to
meditate in the jungles sometimes he'd be afraid hearing sounds and thinking that some animal was going to come and
um eat him I guess attack him and he had the courage to bring
mindfulness to his bodily Sensations and to stay in those postures so we have
these stories but how do we develop
courage well one way is this connection between courage and
trust and I recognize trust is not always readily available either but is
there a way that we can connect with something bigger than
ourselves this might show up be different for different people maybe there's this way to take the refuges in
the Buddha Dharma and SAA we in fear is to help kind of have some courage can we
do some meta practice radiating sending good will out into the world and to
ourselves connecting with others in this way maybe there's some devotional practice whatever devotional practices
make sense to you some people do chanting practices some people do uh
bowing some people will spend some effort with setting up an altar and and putting on the altar
what's uh meaningful and important and uplifting for
them so this connection between courage and trust and this maybe openness of
heart and I appreciate that brne brown she's a I think she's a psychologist
sociologist I'm not exactly sure but she has this book entitled the gifts of
imperfection Renee Brown the gifts of imperfection and she writes that courage
is a habit it's a virtue and you get it by doing courageous Acts
just like you learn to swim by swimming you learn to Courage by [Music]
couraging so is there a way that we can show up for those small little
things the spiders for me it's spiders I used to be
really afraid of them but I'm so much better now can just show up with spiders so we practice with the small things
maybe connecting with things that are bigger than us the refuges devotion
chanting and certainly we come to meditation practice thinking that it will lessen some of the difficulties we
have or that we'll gain some wisdom we'll gain some new understandings maybe even have some cool meditative
experiences and for all the reasons we come to this practice alleviate the suffering that we have practicing with
courage is probably not high on the list but and yet at part of what we're
practicing is courage you might have some different
experiences and showing up for them even though it might be unknown uncomfortable
unfamiliar a courage to face things in ourselves that we haven't seen before
with meditation practice the courage to face things one more time even though
we've seen them so many times before so we have been practicing courage in these
small ways so just by coming back to the
cushion again and again coming back to the breath again and again is a way that we've been practicing
courage so this fourth faculty of Viria I like to emphasize this idea of
Courage it's how we one way to work with fear is to acknowledge and be with the
fear and I didn't start these this series on the faculties of
for fearlessness with courage because if it were easy to Have Courage then you
wouldn't you know then you wouldn't need any of the other factors but I'm starting I'm introducing it as the
fourth just this recognition that you might need other things to be with the
not only the fear but the that resistance to
fear so today may you notice all the small ways in which courage is showing
up for yourself and can we notice what does it feel like to be willing to maybe be a
little bit more vulnerable to show up and maybe a little bit more spacious
open way so I'm wishing you all a wonderful rest of the day today and I look forward
to seeing you tomorrow as we exp explore the last faculty for fearlessness thank
you