so welcome welcome everybody nice to see you all
so tonight I'd like to continue a little bit on a theme that I've been kind of like exploring these past few weeks
and maybe build on it a little bit or give a different emphasis
I know not everybody's been here the preceding weeks and that's perfectly fine you don't need to have been here
but maybe I'll just say some of the other themes that I've been talking about
so last week I talked about how clinging to views
underlies conflict like we have this idea we have this belief about something
and as soon as we hold on to a really tightly we set up uh me versus you US
versus them type of thing and to be clear I'm not saying that we
shouldn't have views what I am saying is that we should hold our views lightly
that they this would make sense to us at this time this is our current
understanding this is what makes sense to us this is the consistent with our
experience all that kind of stuff but it doesn't mean that we're like holding on
and saying that everybody else is wrong and I'm right of course that leads to
conflict and in fact if we find ourselves in Conflict we can just have this inquiry
what are we holding on to what view are we really holding on to that's
underlying this conflict and it might be something like I have this view that
everybody should be treated the same or you know it might be something like this which
for many of us it just feels like uh an obvious uh view that there should be
some equality but is there a way in which we can hold it
and say well maybe I keep on going like this with my hands because it feels like this is the way to hold them
can we hold those views and say well maybe the other person has
seen something that I'm not seeing or maybe I know something that they don't
know or something like this right so giving them the benefit of the doubt
week before that I talked about um sometimes we cling to views
hold on to them tightly as a way to avoid
being with what's actually happening I was a way to avoid of being with
difficult emotions or some inner turmoil or maybe we're not even sure what it is
we're avoiding we just know whatever it is I don't want to look at it and it's most likely not even a clear
sentence like that instead there's just okay I'm gonna holding on and getting
fundamental or dogmatic about some views allows me to not look at other things
instead if I have this idea that this particular view is the most important or
it's always necessary then I'm up to or I give
myself a a a pass to not have to look at what's happening inside
and then about a month ago I talked about the importance of making the distinction between views and direct
experience sometimes they get tangled up by the views or sorry a direct
experience is something that comes in through our senses seeing hearing touching tasting smelling
and of course thoughts is one of the senses in the Buddhist teachings
and we could say views our thoughts that are partially hidden or completely
hidden and so if that's part of what views are
well then how do we even know what our views are if they're hidden and I talked a little bit about how we
could do some settling practice allowing the mind to settle down and then these things become just a
little bit more visible or we can also do some inquiry practice
dropping in the question what am I not seeing or what view is
underneath this it's another way to potentially work with it
so building on that today I want to talk a little bit build on this idea of letting go
those of you have been around in the Buddhist scene this is nothing new right we hear about this
a lot in fact it's kind of like a central theme of this idea of it's
the opposite of clinging we know that clinging brings suffering
this is the second Noble Truth cause of suffering is clinging or
grasping or thirst craving we could use all these different words
it's the same thing it's maybe we might even say it's the opposite of letting go
and so just a reminder that you know that this practice is not about acquisition
we talk about cultivating having a bit more settleness having more
insights and more mindfulness that just naturally grows the more that we practice
but it's not about like getting things not like getting badges
I sat for so many hours this week or I went on this Retreat or something like
this I had this meditative experience
it's not about acquiring these things those are things that sometimes we do to
make ourselves feel better nothing wrong with that I suppose but it's also there's a way in which that
can kind of like slide into well having these Acquisitions quote unquote
might think that that's part of the purpose of practice but instead no we're cultivate our
meditation we go on Retreats Etc just as a way to support more freedom
less suffering it's all about this
and of course I'm using this word freedom and suffering in really broad ways
suffering might just mean a little bit of stress a little bit of uneasiness
Freedom can be complete freedom
Liberation Awakening can also just be more peace
or is less being pushed around by our minds and all of our experiences
so with great with regard to views says this particular language that we find in
the in the suit does about letting go of views
there's this poly word party nissiga absolutely no need to remember that word
but it often gets translated as giving up or relinquishing or giving away
this word relinquishing for me kind of feels like oh you have to pull it out of hands or something like there's like a
little tug like oh I'm not sure I want to give it up and maybe that's why sometimes it gets
translated that way but it's this word patina
is often associated with delight so it's this letting go
in the service of creating this inner wealth maybe this treasure
this sense of well it often says that it's creates the
conditions after this type of letting go there's gladness that happens
and some of you might be familiar with what sometimes we call the gladness pentad
I gave a whole talk on this I'll just mention it but it starts with gladness
it's a joy tranquility happiness concentration
gladness joy happiness so this type of Letting Go this type of
giving up or giving away with delight creates the conditions for the mind to
be settled creates the condition for this like Gathering Together of our
maybe different aspects of ourselves or different parts of our experience so
it's not a giving away or letting go that's it's not a
deprivation it's not like we're not having a loss of what is good
we're creating the conditions in which there can be more freedom
less suffering
so building on this idea there's also in this who does this other
poly word vosika that's often translated as letting go
different translators do different uh words different English words for these
different poly words I tend to like mush them together but there's something that's I think
kind of interesting about us letting go is that
pointing too often like letting go of a sense of control
so much we want to control things of course we do we want to be
comfortable we want things to turn out dwell for ourselves for others or our
loved ones you might even say so much of our life is a route you know trying to
get things to turn out okay it's another way of saying control them
but in the sutas and the Siegel Lovato which is um instructions for
householders in particular it says that the instructions are a
householder so in this case it would well I'll say it this way a householder
should let go of authority to their partner
let go of authority this householder should also Grant leave
to their workers at the right time so this way in which we might try to
control other people in the case here somebody who works for them say no you have to work overtime no
you have to take care of that our partner no you have to do this so
you don't have to do that but this letting go of control
of others of course we know it doesn't really work
but we try it anyway there's a part of us that maybe he's desperately wishing
we can control them and maybe there's even times in which the control
I mean we are able to influence them but right we don't really get to control
others and my Buddhas he recognizes that this is a lot of suffering here
so kind of building on this idea of not being not controlling others is so this
idea of letting go of this sense of ownership
because often the sense of ownership implicit not explicit this idea that we
can control it no this is mine this is my Striker nobody else can
happen and I get to say whether it's it's on this side or on this side
or something like this sometimes we don't think about that that
this sense of ownership it has this idea of well Noah then I get to decide what
happens to it and of course we have the sense that you
know this um these glasses are mine they're not anybody else's classes they
are mine they wouldn't work for anybody else chances are but there's a way in which ownership is
also just a convenient social contract
because I don't get to like if I donate them
they're not mine anymore if they break or throw them away or if
something happens to them there's a way in which the glass whatever happens to glasses
happens to them whether I own them or not we could say well Diana you're the one that's choosing to donate them or you're
the one that sat on them and that's why they broke but right we know this that we don't
really own things when we die they don't go with us
these things they die quote unquote before us objects
so this I don't I'm not trying to say that ownership doesn't exist we
definitely have this in the modern West but there's also right different communities
have different relationships with ownership
so this letting go it's about stopping demanding that things behave a
certain way stopping of the sense of
say no this is mine if it's not yours
setting up this tension
and so notice how these ways of Letting Go that I'm talking about they're all associated with this sense of self
me and mine so whenever there's a sense of clinging
it's a synonym for there's a strong sense of self no this is mine
I'm like this I'm not like that there's a way in which there's a little
bit of a contraction or maybe a lot of contraction and the exact same way that we might
hold tightly to a view that this case a view of a permanent enduring self
so if we agree that this idea of letting go of kind of like relinquishing
giving away generosity or no longer clinging is a good thing it will help
support this movement towards Freedom well then how do we do this
and I appreciate that uh in the guteronicaiah
can you tell that I've been poking around in the suit does so I have a number of like pseudor references today
that's there is this um this impressive list of uh 17 of these like undesirable
states that you don't want like defilements starts with the usual greed hatred and
delusion and it goes on with the contempt and I forgot to know all the
list I remember reading it thinking like oh wow anger you know some of these things in there
so as these lists of these 17 different defilements and then there's a practices
to do with them to help or to support to work with these I'll use this word
defilements but as a subset of like these
defilements is this idea well let's uh relinquish them let's let them go
and so I just want to read you the two examples
so it's maybe I'll just make this even more complicated so there's all these defilements there's
things to do with them including letting go and then there's practices to help with letting go or whatever it is you're
going to do with them mostly letting go here's an example
for the complete understanding finishing giving up ending Vanishing fading away
cessation giving away and letting go right trying to be as thorough as possible all these synonyms
of greed and then goes for 16 others two things should be developed
what to samata and vipassana
summative um settling down we could say It's
associated with Gathering Together concentration it's related to the word samadhi
and vipassana is this word Insight related to mindfulness this is good news for us right we do
mindfulness practice and there's a way in which the Mind does settle when we do this so it's naturally what's happening
another example is for the complete understanding finishing
giving up ending Vanishing fading away cessation giving away and letting go of
greed four things should be developed what for
loving kindness compassion
sympathetic Joy and equanimity
this is good news too because many of us have a love and kindness practice or if
not there's a way in which we are familiar with it or maybe there's a way
we can have our meditation and or our concentration practice be imbued with
this sense of loving-kindness and there's this recognition that this is what supports this letting go this
movement of relinquishing Vanishing fading away cessation
so I talked about how there's this movement towards letting go is hoping towards
more freedom but even though we know this and even
though we might even already be doing the practices that might support this letting go
there's a way in which there's some letting go that maybe doesn't happen
or we might or we might be using letting go in a way that's not helpful
so just like we have this sense of like we might want to say okay just
letting go or maybe a Dharma teacher might want to say oh just let go let go everything that's let go you'll be fine
but of course it's not quite that simple and so I want to like flesh this out a
little bit and maybe one say one thing that I'll say is that the here's another suit to quote
the Buddha says I don't say that everything should be
given up or let go but I don't say that nothing should be
let go when giving up certain things unskillful
qualities grow and skillful qualities Decline and
if that happens don't give up those things but when giving up certain other things
unskillful qualities decline while skillful qualities grow
so this wisdom to notice okay what's helpful for supporting this with
skillful kusala what's wholesome what's helpful what's healthy
so is there a type of Letting Go that's unhelpful
is there a type of Letting Go that doesn't lead to more freedom
we might think of some but I like to point to
this uh and maybe I'll like I'm gonna play with the language a little bit here
there's a way in which sometimes people abandon we could use abandon for one of
these synonyms abandon themselves
abandon themselves what does that mean what am I pointing to
many of us have heard that a key Insight is like into impermanence
to see the inconstant nature of things in permanent nature of
things but it feels a little bit like a cruel thing to do if somebody has a life
that's very unstable and I just experienced a lot of loss to say oh
everything's impermanent instead we would say like to practice
with stability so that they can create the conditions in which they can see the impermanence
or in the same way right at one of these key insights is a suffering
there is suffering and it just seems insensitive and maybe
inappropriate and unhelpful if somebody has tremendous amount of suffering just
to say oh they're suffering instead might be appropriate for them to
cultivate the opposite to be noticing where there's well-being and happiness
so in the same way I could say the same thing for not self another key insight and we can say that
if we want to point to not self but maybe somebody really
doesn't have a clear sense of self or maybe they feel like they don't have clear boundaries with others or so maybe
what's appropriate for them is to cultivate a sense of self some confidence Maybe
that could then can support some letting go some opening into not self
so there's a way in which we need to like maybe be sensitive to and notice that maybe some cultivating of the
Opposites of these key insights can be a real support for our lives
help create the conditions in which these three things insights into impermanence insights into
unsatisfactoryness duka insights into not self so I would say in the same in that same
vein this idea of letting go to not abandon ourselves because
sometimes we abandon ourselves in the sense that we might experience an emotion
that difficult unpleasant maybe it's exactly what we don't want
and it requires our attention and our care but instead we ignore it
instead we distract ourselves or whatever way we're just not present for
it so we're kind of like abandoning ourselves we're not being aware of our
experience we are like maybe discounting our
experiences thinking well I don't really it doesn't matter
maybe implicit in that is I don't matter or maybe there's this way we just have
this habit of turning away from our experiences and
not even present for our lives and we find ourselves kind of like
slipping our life slipping away or finding ourselves like wow what happened
the last few years or something like this or find ourselves sleepwalking through our life
I'm calling those like abandoning ourselves we could do it's like in general or
maybe when there's only certain experiences that we just
tune out turn away turn towards something else
maybe this is why we see so many people with their phones scrolling even Doom
scrolling right it's all bad news maybe but they're just doing it just as a way to distract themselves from what's
Happening or or maybe they yell at their partner or yell at the person who's driving or yell at the kids or just yell
trying to distract ourselves from our inner life like abandoning our
what are what's happening and to be sure there may be very good
reasons why we do this maybe it made sense earlier in our life it was a perfectly appropriate coping mechanism
so or maybe we have this idea as long as I have a spiritual life I don't have to
take care of all that messy stuff I just get you know I'm just going to strive and work and get awakened and then all
the messy stuff will disappear poof has it worked
right there's a part of us often that has this I think in the back of our minds of
course we come to this practice to alleviate suffering
so we you know partly want to turn away from it of course
so this idea of like abandoning ourselves we may be like discounting ourselves maybe our inner experience
difficult emotions or maybe something a little bit bigger like thinking that we
don't count when other people are
talking or having ideas or in groups thinking like oh well okay my opinion doesn't really matter so much maybe I
or somehow thinking that uh oh yeah it's
okay that that is wildly inconvenient it makes me feel really uncomfortable but
I'll do it okay anyway because you asked we're kind of like abandoning ourselves and saying you know what I need to have
some boundaries here this doesn't mean we have to say yes to everything doesn't mean we have to say
no to everything but is there a way that we can kind of have a sense of
yeah this is what's appropriate this is what's comfortable and here's what isn't appropriate what's
comfortable so this idea if we want to let go
but I'm saying in order to do like some of the deepest letting go that's possible
when it differs to make sure that we're not abandoning ourselves not letting go of herself I'm playing around with words
here a little bit but just this whole idea that sometimes we can take some of
these ideas of just you know hold things lightly as a way to validate
not really being with some of our difficulties
so how do we not do this then how do we not abandon ourselves
pay attention to ourselves noticing our inner life and for some of
us who have been disconnected from our emotions for whatever reason maybe this
isn't so straightforward maybe a mindfulness practice is part of
just getting acquainted with our emotional life
just even learning like the vocabulary of emotions
It's Not Unusual for people to just have a limited mad sad glad
I know one of those three but but you know that's our emotional lives are so rich and diverse
so one way to not abandon ourselves is to stay present for ourselves
have some curiosity what does it feel like noticing
and I'm saying this recognizing that there might be a really good reason why we aren't in touch with our inner life
because there might be some really difficult things there I like this expression that uh Jack
cornfield uses this unfinished business of the heart
and so is there a way that we can create the conditions on which that business can get finished
with care and respect for ourselves
not expecting it to be easy and fast or linear or
fun all the time but to still find this way to just be present for
ourselves with whatever's happening and not in a way that we're going to tip
into overwhelm it's absolutely the wrong direction if
we find ourselves always tipping into overwhelm is there a way that we can work with it where we don't and
where we don't tip into overwhelm but maybe just touch into
another support for not abandoning ourselves is just simply valuing
ourselves sometimes just our upbringing we've kind
of like been discounted or somehow think that we don't matter or we matter less
or something along those lines but is there a way in which we can
notice that we all matter every one of us
every single one of us it's one thing for me to sit up here and
to say this but it's another thing for us to really understand that or know it
anyway I say okay well that sounds nice Diana I have to be present for yourself and value yourself but how do you do
that here's the good news
it's the same practices foreign
[Music] this letting the minds settle getting some
gatheredness there's a way in which there's this inherent sense a little bit of
well-being that happens when the mind gets settled meditation practice
sometimes our meditation practice will have more of an emphasis on just settling down sometimes it'll have more
of an emphasis on mindfulness and just noticing what's happening and being really present for whatever's happening
two different kind of flavors and they interweave and if we want we can make
them really distinct but we can also just let them kind of flow from one to the next
the second way to kind of support us to not abandon ourselves so that we can let
go so that we can have more freedom this loving-kindness practice
compassion practice sympathetic Joy Equanimity these heart
practices and I used to teach blaming kindness
practices a few times a week for years had an impact on me too it was great
fantastic I love doing it but um it was not uncommon for people to
say well you know it's so much easier for me to do loving kindness or Compassion or for others but not for
myself in fact I would say that might have been
the most common comment
it's not surprising the wave you know we have so much sir
messages from our culture maybe that you have to be better do more
so maybe there's some intentional loving kindness practice for ourselves as well
as for others so these same practices that are
supporting letting go the same practice just practices that are supporting not abandoning ourselves
but there's a way in which to highlight or outline and
say explicitly not abandoning ourselves that might be a highlight for
what maybe there's ways in which we have been doing this which we haven't even noticed
or we were thinking like oh no this is letting go or Equanimity or something but in fact it
was a way in which we were disconnecting or turning away from our in our
experience so it's not like we have to necessarily
do something wildly different but just to bring this idea this notion into our
awareness into the way that we think about our spiritual practice and the way to
greater and greater freedom
so letting go and go of views which I've been talking about for the
past few weeks and today I'm talking a little bit more just about letting go but not abandoning ourselves
letting go so that we're holding things lightly but maybe with the when it comes to like
ourselves maybe we should have a little bit more cups so that there's we're just holding it maybe it's more like this
foreign like this I don't know
all these different ways but letting go without abandoning ourselves
so I think I'll stop there and I'll open it up to see if there are
some questions or comments
coming through I don't think it's on maybe the blue one we can turn up the blue one
kind of green those pesky batteries
oh so when those pesky battery chargers foreign
maybe this is just a stray thought that I had during your talk but about
halfway or two-thirds through you talked about
um not throwing yourself out but being with yourself
including during times of
difficult reflection things come up
and being with them instead of putting two distractions if I'm
rephrasing you correctly so what that reminded me of was
a verse from the Terra gotha or Terry The Voice the the tales of the Elder
nuns Terry Terry Gotham which goes
I Delight oh I had it
um
oh taking Delight in all difficult or unpleasant experiences
taking Delight in it that's I forget the exact quote is
better but but that's the gist of it of course is not how we normally
want to think of unpleasant experiences
so how can it be delightful
to be with that do you have a sense
yeah when I met my best
collecting on yeah I don't like this experience but
it's my experience it's it's me it's part of me
so in that in my in in that difficult way
it is something to be cherished in a way
part of honoring and respecting yourself not abandoning yourself you might even say yeah and it's also the springboard
from which growth can happen
so also there's this um
experience right when we there's something that's difficult that's happening and whether we're doing this
in an obvious way or in a subtle way there's we can be like pushing it away or
having a version wanting it to be different or and then there's this way in which we
just like put down the struggle and or just with it and just experiencing the
unpleasantness of it there is this delight to be to put down
the struggling with it and just to align with reality
this is what's happening and there's a there's this delight that
happens there with the just being mindful of it so the mindfulness has
this quality of I like this word delight which is not quite as strong as Joy or
happiness because I think that's a pretty tall order right but there can be this
the Delight of mindfulness of actually stopping
I'm using this word struggling wrestling tangling with trying to make it go away trying to control it all that kind of
stuff and I remember now it's our Delight in attention toward
all unpleasant experience what's the word attention attention a direct attention toward okay
so maybe the word is sought to you I wonder and I I'm thinking of some more
Nuance namely um if I may
really close attention well
we'll show you you know every little thing that's going on in your Mind Body
system including maybe contractions and only your heart or your throat
uh maybe not pleasant but oh yeah I'm
understanding myself better now yeah yeah there can be something sweet
about it even more difficult you know so I'm struggling with this still but that's as far as I've thought it oh
thank you thank you Bill and including this idea like okay now I understand something a little bit better about
myself maybe that's where some of the Delight is great thank you
okay so thank you thank you for your attention and for your practice if you'd
like you're welcome to come up here and ask me a question or something but I wish you all wonderful evening thank you