so good morning good day welcome back
it seems to be Tuesday
meeting again on the theme of social and communal Harmony
let's begin with the setting um this morning where we will uh for the
meditation we'll start we'll start with just a little bit of grounding collecting ourselves in the body and the breathing
and then um we'll shift to a meta meditation
and in a in a way that it's um very similar to a way that Biko
inalio teaches meta meditation will first generate the feeling and then we'll radiate in all directions
but first let's get grounded so let's find our
aligned meditation posture whether we're reclining
or sitting foreign
s right here
for our time together there's nothing else we need to do
welcome back to these senses this body
if you like a few deep breaths savoring the sensations that come
nothing to do
but allowing the mind to collect
this thought that that thought
just like raindrops all around
okay
yes the attention
is moving this way and that
to rely on the breathing each breath in each breath out
to call us back
foreign
shift
continuing with this meditation
we will switch the emphasis to loving kindness meta
if you have a loving kindness practice
you can start by arousing meta in the way you know best
and if we're just starting a loving kindness
practice
to very gently generate the feeling of Goodwill
with the support maybe you have a phrase
may I be happy
and saying to yourself internally and feeling the wish
that accompanies the phrase
may I be happy
may I be healthy
may I be safe
and may I live with ease
and then repeating at a pace that's appropriate for you
arousing this inner sense of Goodwill
foreign as we continue with the
phrases important to register
register the effect
it could be a lightning or brightening
or maybe a welling up in the heart
this wish for well-being
foreign
this Goodwill
the feeling of wishing well-being
it's like a light maybe a soft Candlelight
in the heart maybe a bright afternoon sun
the light filling filling us
and now we can radiate that light shine it out on all beings
One Direction at a time
first to the front we might even imagine there's a
a curtain in front of us
so the light can't quite yet shine on all the games
put in one swift motion draw back the curtain
and naturally without pushing the light shines forward
male beings in this direction be happy
may they all be happy
shining the light of matter now to the right
quickly drawing back the curtain may all beings to my right
all beings be happy
no need to push just let the light shine
now to our back just the same
draw back the curtain and let the light of Goodwill of Mehta
shine to all beings in this direction
and to our left
just the same throw back the curtain
and let the light shine may all beings be happy
allowing the light to shine in all four directions
no need to push
now also above
drawing back a curtain and letting the light shine upward
and so also below
all around
radiating in all directions may all beings be happy
you can rest in this nourishment
and when the feeling Fades if it fades arousing again
may all beings be happy
now as we come to the end of the sitting
May any goodness that's accrued any Merit any benefit
nourish us in our practice and benefit all beings everywhere
without exception may all beings everywhere be happy
peaceful and liberated
[Music]
foreign
so good morning again
what a joy foreign so the the topic for the week we will
continue with the Buddha's teachings on social and communal Harmony
ah just pausing and feeling so refreshed from The Meta practice
yesterday we talked about right view as the Forerunner of Harmony
mostly in terms of what uh Gill might call conventional Right View
translates as mundane Right View two aspects one that our actions are
consequential and the second is that we can discern
well it's beneficial what's helpful what's unhelpful the trajectory trajectory for the week
mostly we're moving from the personal personal practice to the social
though of course on inspection it's uh it's pretty difficult to isolate these two today we will extend this practice
of Right View uh and we'll bring it into
um clear practical terms for the purposes of cultivating communal Harmony
so the theme specifically for today is that for Right View to transform us in
our communities it takes our effort it takes our effort
I'd like to introduce this by um pointing out
it said that nibana the final goal of this practice is the
destruction of greed hatred and delusion and just to point out
the highest goal in this sense defined in terms of its social implications
the manifesting of a life freed of greed hatred and delusion
so I I'd like to look at the the social aspect of the Buddhist teaching through his teachings as a father actually
um they're a handful of sutas where he teaches his son rahula
rahula was known for later in his life of course being known as the Buddha's
foremost disciple of those desirous of the training he really wanted to practice
so I asked the question is desire enough is desire enough
um because body points out in this book social and communal Harmony he says the
process of personal transformation does not occur automatically for Right View to exercise a positive
influence personal effort is required he goes on a deliberate Endeavor to
harmonize our conduct with our understanding and intentions
a deliberate endeavor to harmonize our conduct with our understanding and intentions
so I'd like to I'd like to pull out some of these themes and look at them in terms of one of these teachings of the
Buddha to rahula one of my favorite suta stories it's called the Buddha's advice to rahula at mangostone
now the setup is that um Rahul is very young he is he's supposed
to be maybe seven years old he joined he joined the buddhistoric very very young
[Music] um and of course we know that he he's going to be known as the disciple that is
foremost desirous of training so maybe it meant all the more that his father the Buddha admonished him this morning
in the suta um about the importance of never telling a deliberate lie
he used he has this beautiful image of throwing away the water in a water Dipper and says that if we're if we're
willing to tell a deliberate LIE there's no evil we wouldn't do and we're throwing away our life in the training
so that's the setup before he says what do you think rahula
what is the purpose of a mirror what's the purpose of a mirror
and being an astute young one ragla says for the purpose of reflection
the Buddha says Ah so too rahula an action with the body
should be done after repeated reflection an action of speech should be done after
repeated reflection and an action by the mind
should be done after repeated reflection and then the reflection that he that he
that he explains to Raul he repeats nine times there are nine variations on this
so I'm going to read this whole paragraph because I think it's that important
and teaching goes like this [Music]
when you wish to do an action with the body you should reflect upon it
with this action I want to do lead to my own affliction
or to the Affliction of others or to the Affliction of both
is it an unwholesome bodily action with painful consequences painful results
when you reflect if you know this action that I wish to do with the body would lead to my own Affliction or
to the Affliction of others or to the Affliction of both it's an unwholesome bodily action with
painful consequences painful results then you definitely should not do it
but when you reflect if you know this action that I wish to do
with the body would not lead to my own Affliction or the Affliction of others or the Affliction of both
it's a wholesome bodily action with Pleasant consequences and pleasant results
then you may do that action with the body
so he's teaching a Labuda here is teaching a seven-year-old
a basic reference point by which he can begin to train himself in the ethical life
by which he can take his understanding of the consequential nature of action
to develop his discernment develop his discernment about what's harmful and what's helpful
in his actual life he's training ramula and Right View
what's interesting about this to me first of all is that it's not a
um it's not a complicated philosophy about causality it's something observable Here and Now
observing harm observing not harm something that would be evident to a seven-year-old child
and as a sound basis for our own development
of course the Buddha goes on to to encourage and admonish rahula to reflect in this way before
any action during any action and after any action
more or less saying rahula every action that you do analyze it in these terms and if you
find at any point in the process oh I'm going to harm someone stop don't do this
and if you reflect and to the best you understand this action will not generate harm
unbeneficial actions Affliction for myself or for others or for both
and go ahead every action I hear this and my eyes get
big it's a lot of reflecting to do we act a lot uh during the day
and at night perhaps um maybe it's that the monastic life is
one of relative simplicity maybe so there's extra time for such
circumspection but still we can aspire
I take bikubody's Point here that it takes it takes our effort to infuse our conduct with Right View
and maybe it's not every action but what we can muster
a second thing I want to bring up is is that
this observation of the world that we live in the life that we live
how often do we have to act on partial information where we really don't know
if we're if we're going to cause harm or benefit
the the layers of causality are so complex the request of this particular practice
I think normalizes the fact that we can't always know for sure but we can reflect as best we can
with the information that we have and if to the best of our discernment it looks like this this action that I'm
about to do will cause benefit rather than harm then I go ahead
and then while I'm doing it I still have time to reflect and then after yet again
and I think the recognizing that they're the part of the invitation is reflecting
after the action it recognizes that we don't always have the information at the beginning
and it also it also recognizes that sometimes we'll be wrong sometimes we do harm
so there's a significant variation in in these um in these instructions to rahula
for after you've done an action and the instruction is if you find upon
reflection after after acting that you have done harm
you have cost Affliction for yourself for someone else for both
then that the ask is that you quote lay it open
you confess it you tell a good Dharma friend you let them know
which I think in our in our more modern language it undermines shame
it undermines the closing off and the hiding of something that we've done
if that's available to us and healthy right now so we
We Lay it open and the second part is we resolve
to restrain ourselves in the future to do something different to try something else we continue with this
experiment of making Right View real through our conduct
and after an action impartial as our information might be if we find that we've actually done
something wholesome something beneficial for ourselves and for each other then I love this it says you can abide
happy and glad Training Day and Night in wholesome qualities
we can celebrate our goodness celebrate when it's gone well and in this way in a very very basic way
training ourselves learning over time ah this is this this action leads to harm in these
circumstances this leads to goodness let's go toward goodness
so you can hear already how our personal training in Right View and conduct
and this form of repeated reflection um
of course it's done through our restraint it's done through cultivation it benefits us and it benefits others
just a couple of quick examples first is uh I'm going to be going on a
family vacation sometime soon I'm gonna go see my family and stay with uh stay with my sister for a little while it
might occur to me while I'm there to uh cook my sister a meal
may occur to me oh this uh this arises in my mind I reflect upon it is this an action that
will cause benefit cause harm affliction or help
or can it be done in such a way that it leads into the wholesome and it's pretty easy to see that internally I'm doing
I'm doing something beneficial I'm practicing generosity relinquishing of attachment and stinginess
and it also comes along with this inner wholesome feeling
and then after I give the gift I might imagine reflect in the future
that uh I see the happiness that it causes her I
can see her being nourished say she had a hard week and oh I really didn't want to really didn't want to cook today oh
this wonderful thing my brother's cooked me a meal and then the joy multiplies
foreign on the other hand can take an example of something that
maybe we see is unhelpful to borrow an example from Gill say I slander a friend
and immediately when I do it say it was just absent-minded but immediately when I do
it I feel an inner ouch but also that friend might find out and end the friendship
think upon reflection if I had had the presence of mind to look ahead I would
have known this will cause Affliction this will cause hurt this will cause harm don't do this
because it only occurred to me after the fact I reflect back I see
this is an action that caused harm I'm going to confess this to a good friend and I'm going to resolve for the sake of
my my practice my inner life my social life my friendships the care that I have
for these people I'm going to resolve to not do this in the future so these are two simple examples
so maybe show something about how this practice of repeated reflection makes real our right View
foreign as I said the process of this mental training this inner training
it does bring about a sort of inner wisdom but it simultaneously conduces to social
harmony and to close maybe we can just think about the the social ripple effect
if you can imagine yourself 24 hours of action this one person reflecting in this way before during and after actions
how many interactions large and small Ripple out in beneficial
ways to create beneficial action beneficial impact for the people in our lives
and Beyond how much goodness is that and then we can
we can maybe extend that and say half of us do that today or all of us do that today how much
goodness does that bring into the world so our effort training in Right View
making our right view real tomorrow we'll turn to another aspect of the teachings on
social and communal Harmony dealing with anger hope to talk to you then
please take care may all beings benefit from our practice together
foreign