so good morning good day everyone Welcome to our
meditation session and
we're also considering this week the topic of Dharma dhamma
and it's a common uh uh enough uh in the world of etymology
to say that Dharma comes from a root word meaning to hold or to bear or to
support something sometimes it's said to come from an even kind of earlier etymology of uh
something that is in order and organized coherent
so the idea of Dharma being what holds us up
and what holds us up is maybe the the
how reality coordinates cooperates with itself to create all that we have that makes it
possible for us to be here and uh kind of a kind of a for us personally
the closest and clearest example of this support this
coordination cooperation that supports us allows us to be here is our
own body that's the closest at hand for us
and to allow the Dharma of the body to support us the coordinated processes
the natural order of the body that we interfere with
if we are too actively fixing or changing or wanting
it to be different than what it is to some there are times where that's a
fine thing to do but there are times when we want to be supported and Trust the supports oppress
so trust this coordinated cooperative
support that this body gives meaning that the body often knows how to move to
homeostasis move to health move to Healing
and a lot of the Dharma practices being very present for our experience
and that's really key to emphasize it be very present be aware here
and getting out of the way not interfering
and that can be counterintuitive for people who have a habit of always interfering fixing thinking it shouldn't
be the way it is and it's a remarkable thing to sit quietly you know
in a meditative posture being very present not interfering
and watch notice that they'd unfold even something is simple
as sitting quietly and feeling the body begins to relax to settle a little bit
the heart begins to be more subtle than relaxed agitation dissipates
maybe even the quality of characteristics of your thinking changes become slow or calmer or quieter
and this quieter way of being settled
is both uh comes from a little bit of trusting that the body
will support us and also comes with making space for
the coordinated processes The Cooperative processes of our body to
show themselves to be themselves so assuming a meditation posture
and I find Delight in the idea that the body supports the body
to all the different parts of the body support what's above it
holds the weight holds it together
gently closing the eyes and one of the functions of closing the
eyes is to I'll let the other senses we have
especially the sense of physical touch and
physical Sensations come into greater Focus
many people are I focused what they see what they look at
in closing our eyes so we can be body focused
feeling the body from the inside out
beginning a process of trusting the body trusting being present for it as it is
and gently in a way that's gentling for you
relaxing for you take some steeper breaths
and as you exhale relax into the support the body provides
letting the breathing return to normal
and the inhale let your attention fall or come to
different places in your body where there's tension or tightness
and on the exhale soften relax those parts of the body
release it from the release it from the tension
foreign
into your breathing
and sometimes in the breathing itself we can sense and feel the support
the naturalness of breathing and sometimes it's possible to see how
we're controlling it there holding it resisting limiting it
with this awareness practice we do be okay with all of it
don't try to fix anything even the control
make room for it in your awareness non-interfering awareness
and Trust something will find its way
with non-re interfering awareness that stays aware makes a room for what's
here as you breathe in and breathe out
a good percentage of our thinking probably could be understood
as being supported by mistrust
who are supported by an absence of real trust and
care caring for the Dharma here in US
the support the coordinated cooperative
amazing world of our body and mind
operating here
in this space of awareness
and then coming to the end of the meditation
the Dharma of support of coordination cooperation
is not just with our body but with in a sense the whole world
the Earth plants and the animals of the Earth
the oceans the clouds the air
other people
our life depends on this wider world our life lives in support and in
coordination with this wider world
and we live in relationship to this wider world
and it's possible for us to be supported by the wider world
and at the same time to offer our support for it
to care for it to cooperate and coordinate with the
wider world
With Attitudes thoughts words and actions
of good will wishing of support
ing the best for everyone
may it be that this meditation supports us
supports the goodness of our hearts to flow to the surface
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and in that freedom that we offer may we may we receive it in return
may we live in a Cooperative universe
supporting each other
to be free
foreign
this is the third talk on the topic of what is the Dharma
and um this is a very multivalent word in
Buddhism and in India in general in Buddhism there's many different
meanings attributed to this word or it's used in all kinds of ways and some of the
traditional classical commentaries have long lists of all the different meanings
of the word Dharma and but I started this week by talking
about how Dharma has to do with our the relatedness between things how things
exist dependent or in support of of other
things that things arise in relationship to other things being present
and so the Dharma has to do with that relatedness and it's nice to begin that
talking about Dharma to really emphasize relatedness relationships
first and foremost as opposed to Me Myself and mine
just you know independent of the world and anything else
and then yesterday I talked about how Dharma sometimes one of those many meanings
that it has is different variations of the word action conduct and often it refers to Good
Conduct but sometimes it refers to bad conduct too like monastics when they
during the transgression of their monastic rules is sometimes called the dhamma the Dharma
so but the emphasis here is action into the activity
and that in so many different ways this early tradition focuses on the dynamic
quality of life and and where maybe activity is a better word than action
the activity of Life the activity of of phenomena that everything is in motion
everything is moving foreign and then the uh
uh today what I'd like to emphasize is the meaning of that's a little more
common meaning for Dharma that's often uh called upon or highlighted
and that is Dharma can mean truth but that requires some explanation of
what truth means and and here in this Dharma consequence
a context the primary truths that we're looking for like the four noble truths are
truths of uh that of what what happens in the relationship
what the impact our actions have on other things so we live in
relatedness our actions impact are having a part of that
relatedness and so that um and so our actions uh affect the
quality of what transpires in the association
the connection the relatedness the the
support the the impact of what comes as a result of the action
and so Dharma has uh as truth has very important to begin understanding a few
things about um the impact of action the the
so the impact on others and impact on ourselves and so so that seeing the truth of that
is important because if you understand the impact of your actions then you can
adjust your actions so they impact you can take responsibility for it more so
if the impact is harmful you would stop doing if it's beneficial you would continue
and if it's a combination of both then we have to use our best wisdom to figure
out what the wisest way forward is but this care and sensitivity to impact
is a very important part of this Dharma as the truth to see oh what I do has
consequences and uh this is a very the simplest way
of describing the Buddhist principles of karma is that karma is the teaching that or
the idea the Insight the truth that some of our actions have consequences or all actions have
consequences one way or the other and uh and we have some choice about
what consequences we create in this world and the ones that again to simplify it
to kind of the core truth around this about this focus on consequence impact
of our actions is to really understand uh
what is harmful and what is not and to avoid harmful actions
to avoid causing harm in the world best we can
and avoid causing harm to ourselves
and this so this idea the truth Dharma is truth is a truth that we can
see and know for ourselves we can know if we're paying attention if
what we're doing is harmful and if we're very attentive we can feel
the harm not necessarily in the impact but also not only in the impact but also
in the in the activity itself that if we do something with hostility
that has a negative consequence maybe for others it has a negative consequence for us in
the future perhaps but it also has negative consequences in the moment because hostility itself
involves stress involves tension it involves dukkah pain
there's pain in the very na in the very activity of of hostility
agree the same way that yes greed can cause problems in the world and human
greed uh you know that's it's uh it's a Monumental that the
impact now on the planet of of the way the greed and desire of certain individuals many individuals all
individuals the accumulative effect and but the very Act of having greed
there's something very different in greed than just uh open-handed desire greed itself
is painful an activity which has pain within it has dukka within it
and so to begin seeing the truth of consequence
the truth of not only consequence but the then we see better the the
um the the where you know how it is
that what we're doing what it is that we're doing that has this negative consequence
and uh and so the truth of really seeing this here and this is one of the reasons why
mindfulness practice is so effective so important in Buddhism because mindfulness practice is not just
to be in the present moment to enjoy your tea and enjoy the sunrise the moment here
but more important is so we can see this really carefully in maybe even minutely
the impact uh of this relate in this related world that we live in how our actions
have impact have consequences and uh and to see that if I cling
any craving and clinging brings suffering at a minimum to oneself
and and many times to others as well and so
to be able to and so when we're doing this we're also entering into this world where Dharma in in the etymological
origin of the word means the kind of means that kind of a little bit of a
modern construction based on the etymology of different elements of it but it's the the uh the way in which the
coordinated Cooperative nature of reality so either supports us
or or doesn't undermines us and the Dharma the word
Dharma is often focused on it's often considered a very positive word not always but it's almost synonymous with
like the the um the uh the Dharma is the actions
which are healthy and wholesome and supportive and Dharma is the support that that's
offered the help that's offered the benefit that that's offered and so when we talk about the Dharma the
Buddhist Dharma and the big part of it then is that supportive that helpful and
beneficial action that because all action is in
relationship to other things it then has a beneficial consequences
for these other things in place whether it's within ourselves psychologically or
whether it's uh out in the world Dharma encompasses all of it
so um so a simple way of saying what I'm
saying today is that uh uh if car karma is the attention to the consequences of
our actions then karma is Dharma Dharma is karma
and the two can't be really teased apart so we have
um relatedness and to
be sensitive to the kind of the invisible relationships invisible and that you know you can't
you know the relatedness often can't be touched or seen literally we can can
know it and recognize it in the impact in the that goes on and in the source in
ourselves um but uh to start being attuned to that which is the relatedness in all things
to be to go out and look at a tree and and appreciate the relatedness we have
to the tree that the tree produces oxygen and takes our carbon
dioxide and converts it into oxygen again and we live independence of it
that one way or the other we live Independence on the clouds and the rain
that brings you know that for the water we we lit we we drink
and so to start looking at the at the relatedness and the mutual support and
the back and forth and um and to appreciate that how we
live in this world the actions that we do are they beautiful to walk in Beauty as
a Native American expression um the word uh good karma in Buddhism
literally the word for that is sometimes is beautiful Karma beautiful actions
to live in a world where our actions is related world with actions that are
beautiful and beautiful focuses also on the what the beauty and wonderfulness of the
impact of our actions so I want to review all this because I would like to propose
that uh this is a a radically different way of uh understanding the world
looking at the world being in the world participating in the world then an excessive focus on oneself
as a static thing as it's all about me and what I get for myself or an
excessive focus on the world out there but that uh or things that things have to be a certain way and uh
but it's uh more important than things is the relatedness
and when we have the relatedness then we have the ability to see the truth of how
our actions impact that relatedness and and spill over and for the path of Freedom that this is
where the domain this is the area of attention to go forward into Freedom
excessive focus on the self without how things within us even relate to each
other and the relatedness kind of takes it away a little bit from the sense of
self-appropriation everything into self um what is it
and um so for today if you'd like to have an
assignment to kind of carry this forward and explore it for yourself in a quiet way
made many sense you know no one has to know you're doing this um as you go about your day both
with the inanimate World The Living World the human world around you as you interact with them
um at give attention to the impact that you
have the consequences from what you say what you do and what you think
then the what you're saying what you do might be impactful for others what you
think might be impactful for you and see the truth of that that impact
and see if the truth of the value then of finding the way to non-harming
maybe being beneficial so Dharma I'm hoping you're beginning to
appreciate is this powerful multivalent Rich word that kind of opens up the world
um in in a wonderful way so
thank you