and it's so good to be with you all in this morning's I feel quite uh sweet and quiet
well begin momentarily for those uh who already joined maybe find a
sitting pasture that allow you to settle in it's almost like a creating a virtual
field virtual meditation field around the globe this way
and While others join us
so this week we are meditating with the theme of
Stillness and the movement and so yesterday we started with
Stillness and a movement in the body and today we'll still stay with uh
the territory of the body um but I will bring a bit more emphasis
around the Stillness and movement with the movements of the breath
and so that's what we will be doing today so if you're ready
please join me and we'll begin
settle into a meditative posture
whether you're sitting on the cushions or sitting on chairs or lying down
or even standing enter into the posture
as if you're entering into an ancient Temple
the Temple of this body this mind and heart
maybe just the word Temple already evokes
some foul sense in the body in the heart
maybe some reverence
tenderness and the quiet
making our seat Right Here and Now
in this body in this mind and heart
now practice happens Here and Now
and our lives happens Here and Now
taking a few moments to have a global sense of the body
and sense of this earthy body resting on Earth
initial moments of a meditation may feel like a lot of things moving
energy in the body still bouncy
and maybe the mind thoughts
are still bouncing around
no problem make space
to allow the movements
to move about and settle
donating to the Earth element in the body
enough about sense is the solidity
firmness of the bones
heaviness
no weight settling down naturally
giving to the wonders of a gravity nothing to do
simply allowing
the Earth element is grounding
stable
somewhat still
nature of the Earth element is to stabilize the body
and feel the whole body sitting like a mountain
quiet
and still
and Stillness of Earth element in the body
naturally highlights the movements of the wind element
that she
breath
air moving as we breathe in and out
and open the field of awareness to receive
the movements of the Bride
feel the movements since the movements in the body
torso expands contracts
Valley Rises and falls
you may also notice the broader field of movement in the body
vibrations tingling in the hands
legs
a life body
and dropping out of the concept the stories
healing and sensing the dance of the alive body
and feeling and sensing needs no words
there is a inner quiet
simply staying with a flow of movements
some Stillness may still be palpable
Pleasant
there is also the Stillness in the knowing
of the embodied experience
silent still knowing
no just the breath and shifts and changes
and Sensations shifts and it changes
there is a Stillness in the body
Stillness in the mind
and various movements in the body
and movements in the mind
the finto weather systems may come in
you know strong energetic field emotions
thoughts
receiving receiving with a kindness
wide open quiet field of awareness
present um Pleasant Sensations they're coming
and this is the part of the nature
being available to our lived experiences
or the kindness kind of attention
sitting like a mountain
a life Mountain
quiet still
are moving
while the sensations in the body in the body
comes
and dances
maybe there is a sense of all
a sense of openness
it's very body
nature
simply resting in itself
[Music]
okay
I'm so happy so happy to be with you so this week I've been
um reflecting about the great women Disciples of the Buddha
we started yesterday with um patachara so
someone who we feel um
I guess some kind of I feel some kind of affinity with
and today I brought another great disciple of women a woman disciple of
the Buddha and she's very different from
pattuchara and her name is
not particularly uh well known maybe in our scene
but I found her story quite interesting maybe fun and so I thought I'd bring
someone who's a little different today and so um bada is This Woman's
um birth name bada was also born out of somewhat of a
wealthy family and um this part of the story may be a
little similar to patachara when she was young
um she fell in love with um a thief may be very attractive Thief
and she was said it to be quite attractive as well so she fell in love
with the thief a Brahman thief and she insisted to marry the thief
and even though out of a lot of Despair the parents I guess
she's very stubborn and so they decided okay all right and so they didn't get
married um but after not very long after the marriage
the thief husband has stealing habit
and so this came up again and so uh he's been scheming to try to
steal all of the jewelries and valuables from the bot from bada
and um bada probably didn't realize this would
happen even though they married into kind of a well-to-do family there's no
need to do that um so she didn't think this would happen
but one day um the young man
um decided to take on bada out to a top
of the mountain and his scheme was
you know he's gonna Rob all the jewelries of bada and then push her down
the mountain to kill her and she didn't realize that and so they
went to the top of the mountain um but she's a very smart young lady
when they got to the top of the mountain she realized something wasn't right
and she realized that her husband was going to murder her
and so I she was quite smart she
got to the edge of the mountain and just before
she handed off all the jewelries to her husband
she pushed him down the mountain and killed her husband
this all happened to kind of such a in a short few minutes and
that was a shocking and she didn't expect it as she would kill anybody and let alone her her own
husband and so this was too much she didn't know
how to hold this and the burden of killing someone was
way too much and so she felt like she couldn't go
back to her lay life anymore and she couldn't go back to her family
so she decided the only way she might find peace was to join
uh spiritual community and so she became a Wandering ascetic
and so in those days there is this wandering ascetic order called The
Legends and then um and this is still alive in India and
this tradition and so she became a Wandering ascetic in this order
and it was said because this is ascetic order so people lived in ways that may
be kind of challenging and when she first got ordained into this
um order and she actually pulled all her hair from the root
as the new hair grew they were very curly so this word that
she's known means curly hair and so she's known as
the bada who had a very curly hair
as a very intelligent woman [Music] she spent the next 50 years or so
wandering around the country as a ascetic and visiting or the spiritual
leaders learned about the philosophies and
gained a lot of knowledge in those days when one King's knowledge and
um they will begin to engage in debates and
so she was very well known apparently she won a lot of debates
and so she became kind of in some way a spiritual leader
in that um she's knowledgeable and was able to
conduct a lot of debates and was able to win a lot of debates
now one day she was wondering around a place and that the Buddha Buddhist
Community was staying and
um she met sarepota sorry puta was a
a chief disciple of on the Buddha who was known to have a very analytical mind
very um I guess it's also means that he's
probably good at debates too and so um
got into a debate and during this debate
um asked all the questions and to sorry
Buddha and saripota was able to answer all of them
and she ran out of questions to ask in the end and this was kind of
I heard for her and so she didn't know what to do and
asare puto decided I'm going to ask her a question
and so sorry puta asked her this question
what is the one suppose this is one of those kind of
um quite maybe philosophical and Abstract
question and um
somehow uh you know she she does have this a kind of a sense that she knew the
standard answer like the god the infinite the Brahma just want to cut it
but she didn't know how to answer it she didn't have the answer
and yet through this question she had a sense that sorry Buddha might
be the one who knows and because at this time it's clear that
even with all this is 50 years of a wandering around being famous and able
to debate a lot of people she still hasn't really found a complete
peace in her heart so she asked sariputa whether saraputo
would be her teacher sorry puta pointed her to the Buddha
instead and so she went to see the Buddha and
the Buddha preached the Dharma to her
in the recount of this part of the story in the Legends of the terries that that
I began to read yesterday and about Candela Kisa said this
Buddha preached Dharma to me that Aggregates the sense fields and
elements a Buddha taught unpleasantness
impermanence dukka and the not self
it was asserted that bada just like the other wandering ascetic
that's known as a Bahia who was the foremost among the monks
who was able to get to the Buddha's teachings very quickly and she was the
foremost among the female disciples with the same kind of quality
so just with this teaching she was able to understand something
deeply and very quickly and at the end of this encounter with
the Buddha and the Buddha concluded their conversation with this verses
and he said
though a thousand verses are made of meaningless lies
better the single meaningful line be heard by which
one is at peace
so that was the end of condolences debate career and she realized with all this knowledge
she had and all this debates that she engaged in
those are really not that meaningful anymore so she went forth to join the Buddha to
become a disciple of the Buddha and this teaching reminded me that so
often we can miss that the teaching of the Buddha are not found
in the stacks of books um the analysis debates
or incessant thinking about them the concepts the ideas the stories
that we tell ourselves instead the teachings the point at the immediacy
of our lived experience Here and Now
the Dharma is visible Here and Now
immediate inviting to be seen for oneself
onward leading and to be personally experienced by the
wise and so she recounted her Awakening
through the slimes than being fully ordained this is into
the uh Buddhism monastic order I saw a little bit of a water
cleaning my feet Discerning that some water splashed up
some spilled down then at that time I realized all conditioned
things are like that then my heart was liberated all together
without cleaning then the Buddha adapted me for most of
those with a quick intuition
I love this word intuition it has a kind of a rawness in it
it's not based on some kind of a speculative views
ideas each of us being human
has this kind of intuitive capacity to know things as simply
intimately and deeply and this is where dhamma becomes visible
and this kind of intuitive knowing is only possible when we drop out of the
layers of Concepts and ideas
and all of our claimings to them
I may says story
Inspire us to live simply immediately
with the rawness of our life here and now
thank you everyone for your attention and I will regroup tomorrow
deep bells to you all