greetings everyone I'm delighted to be here with you again
I the theme um for this week is tastes of freedom
and uh yesterday um
we explored feeling and tasting as a way of putting in place
conditions that open the door to Freedom
today will evoke the power and the protection
of creating conditions of what's called or usually translated into English as
seclusion viveca and Pali
yesterday um when we were talking about
the key to the path to Freedom the door to Freedom
I talked about the dangers of
giving the reactive mind the upper hand of wanting more of
what we desire or what's Pleasant grasping or wanting to push away
um what we don't like what we're aversive to what is unpleasant
and so those two conditions are two of the most important factors and and the
Buddha able instructions on how to do meditations on these factors
but there's a third one so in addition to Pleasant I want more
or unpleasant get me out of here there's also neither Pleasant nor
unpleasant which is sometimes called neutral
and this one is a bit hard to describe the
flavor of or how it feels because we're not sure how it feels we're not sure if
it's Pleasant or unpleasant there's a there's kind of an element of maybe confusion
in uh that third um feeling tone of neither
Pleasant nor unpleasant and what this is pointing to is that all
three of the feeling tones Pleasant unpleasant and neither
are in response to what is often called in the
polytexts the three poisons
and these are serious poisons these are really what uh put the roadblocks in the
way for us on the path to Awakening
they are greed eight and delusion
so if we want to be independent in our practice
we have to overcome our uh instinctive
response to whatever comes in the sense doors
it's almost it's simultaneous as soon as it comes in the Mind knows or categorizes it
as pleasant unpleasant or neither
and so what we're dealing with is
um in each of these three poisons of course there's a very very very broad spectrum
on how they might appear in our consciousness
um if we haven't practiced very much uh we might be just extremely reactive
uh by Nature and um yeah and you know as soon as
something slightly unpleasant arises you know we're already
in in uh uh
Fleet Mountain getting bling mode
and if something uh delicious comes up then we're just already before we even
know it we're off on some fantasy but if what arises uh is neither
Pleasant nor unpleasant then we're not sure how to respond and
this is exactly what the poison of delusion is all about
that we don't know what is wholesome and unwholesome
we haven't learned to discern uh which way we should go at the fork in
the road that is in front of us in virtually each moment
so a lot of this path is about uh cultivating our capacity
or Discerning the wholesome and the unwholesome so that we know which way to
go when something like um green or hatred comes up
so to begin with
uh take your meditation posture
and then feel the connection of the body with
whatever you're sitting on or lying on or standing on
and then let your roots go deep down into the Earth
giving you a sense of stability
and drawing on this groundedness in the posture
we can begin to explore a little road trip through the body
by scanning from the feet to the crown of the head
little by little and every time we direct our awareness to a certain part
of the body we also use that moment to see if there
might be something there that we could relax a little bit or
soften letting go of tensions as we go along
so closing the eyes
and inviting our awareness into the feet
is there something there that we can let go of a little bit
and the same with moving up the lower legs
the upper legs
and the hips the Basin the pelvis the connection of the pelvis
with our support and with the Earth
sometimes the endings in the hip joint
and they get stuck and it's very useful
to let them grow go a little bit
and then bringing the awareness to the belly
and then it's called the Harlot and in Zen practice this is the center
of gravity for us physically but also as the center
of where we um invite the mind
so can we let the belly relax a little bit let it all hang out slightly
nobody's looking at us doesn't matter
and then gently moving up through the diaphragm
and Into the Heart area
how does it feel in there in your heart center
of a pleasant feeling or warmth and
bowing Maybe or perhaps an unpleasant feeling because
you just lost a loved one and
that's where your heart center is at now is doing The Grieving that it needs to
do and so we make friends with whatever
arises in our hearts
not needing to push anything away in order to be able to meditate
then coming up the spine
to the shoulder blades and if you can letting the shoulders
themselves would drop a little bit
inviting awareness into the upper arms the elbows
lower arms wrists and
fingers softening as we go
releasing as we go
now bring your awareness to
the head area and check to see if your head is well
balanced at the top of your spine
so that it doesn't require any extra energy
to keep your head upright it does require some
wakefulness but there's no physical constraint
in having an erect posture
if they had aligned with the heart and the belly and the Earth
what's it like inside the head area
what's it like in the thinking muscle
is it active is it producing stories or
living in the past or living in the future
and if so the invitation is to say to that mind that loves stories
and distractions say okay I see you but not now
I'm going to stay with their breath
and I'm coming to the jaw
listening the lips
the cheeks all around the eyes
forehead the scalp
softness
to the extent possible and if you find tensions in the body by
all means don't berate yourself for that because that will only make things worse
so if something is really tight and you can't seem to do anything about it
and be friends with that practice with that
and now egg a long deep
inhale feeling the whole length of the inhale
as you do it and then as you exhale
long bound release
and now all you have to do is stay with the cycle of the brush
simple right yeah simple but not so easy
so when the mind wanders off
as Minds tend to do then we try to catch that before we're
we've been in some kind of a fantasy for 10 minutes or
we've been in some sort of recrimination about the past
is going on and on and it's not the first time we've been through this particular screenplay
we just say no thank you
so just as we leave our shoes outside the door when we come into our meditation area
we leave our thoughts responsibilities lands
deceptions and stories out there with issues
and to the extent we can we stay stay with
the cycle of the breath fully present for the inhale
holy present for the out hail and for those little spaces in between
and if you should find that there's at the corners of your mouth
burned up a little bit into a half smile or even better the corners of your eyes
and a half smile
these use that as an entry
into a pleasant feeling for your meditation
that's really not only permitted but encouraged
oh
being able to sit here in our spot
on this beautiful planet
the Buddha talked about the place he sat as his
body mandala where he picture a beautiful mandala
on the ground and body of course means enlightenment
their connection with the Earth and then connection with their breath
allow you to inhabit this mandala
of Awakening
keeping ourselves secluded from the three poisons of greed hate and
delusion secluded from
reactivity
to our experience
we can be protected by this seclusion
and nurtured in a way that opens the doors
or putting in place the conditions
that lead to Awakening
and as we come to the end of this meditation
let's take a few moments to
open our hearts through all beings everywhere
any of whom are suffering
many of whom are caught in delusional reactivity
or in oppressive greed or in dishonest hatred
and let us offer the benefits
of our practice in all directions
may all beings be safe
and feeling that sense of safety may all beings be contented
with contentment we don't need anything else
so with that in all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you
greetings everyone lovely to be here with you again
and I just I'd like to just let you know that I'm not able to see your comments
in the chat on YouTube or in Zoom but they are very welcome indeed and I
will be able to see them after uh finishing the teaching
um
so the theme for this week is tastes of freedom
and last week Ying Chen talked about the
multifaceted multi-dimensional aspect
of the path of practice
and she read some stories from Gill's little Anthology the monastery
Within and of course the these the monastery
within is a is a metaphor and
it's a metaphor for our practice
and that the seat of our practice is inside
we don't have to go to some Monastery off in the mountains to
[Music] no seclusion
to be protected we have everything we need to awaken
right here in this body and mind
that's quite amazing
and the theme for this week is tastes of freedom
so as as I've shared before um the path to Freedom
is your past there's no carbon copy
there's you can of course uh see from people you admire how you'd
like to practice that doesn't mean you can do it
I met um children Suzuki roshi when I was only 21 years old and very troubled young
girl and um and yet
it was abundantly clear that
he incarnated Awakening and so that's kind of a mystery you know
how how does that happen um
so for many of us uh
um in this tradition the vipassana tradition in the terravada tradition
um the Buddha does not teach the importance of sudden enlightenment
sometimes his his uh in person disciples monks and nuns and
amen and women uh did
um wake up quickly when they heard him speak or when he was giving them a an instruction specifically for them
but you know most of us in the last 2600 years
we actually have to figure it out for ourselves and it's a gradual path
and so this gradual path also means
gradual Awakening which is why even before we become
enlightened and are free
free from suffering brief read hate and delusion
totally free than that that's usually for most of us at the end
of a very long dedicated practice
but even at a very early stage when we're
just beginning it's possible to have tastes of this freedom
and that's what I'm trying to share with you this week through these teachings
so in the theme of uh tastes of freedom
yesterday we explored feeling and tasting
as a way of putting in place the conditions that open the door to Freedom
and this requires very very very dedicated mindfulness
so as you may know in the factors of Awakening the very first one is
mindfulness or perhaps better translated as awareness
so on the whole path as we walk it
where we place our awareness is going to determine
how we find our way
so uh you may have heard the story of
somebody said uh you know he's walking along and
um and there's people in front who are uh about to give the Deep ditches on each side and
one person was just about to fall into the ditch on the right and
he'd say go to the left go to the left and then somebody else was about to fall
into the ditch on the left and he'd say go to the right go to the right so there's not a
uh an answer to how we walk this path
that is not contingent upon Where We Are and what our mindset is
so it's really um a big job for us to get to know
ourselves and I think also
um to befriend ourselves
you know if you're um trying to
train a young puppy and it's an adorable puppy you know puppies are adorable
um if you yell at your puppy and it's cold them uh severely and kick them and
just you know uh severe training
they're going to grow up to be uh and unhappy and maybe vicious dog
on the other hand if you give your puppy rewards instead of uh
beating them or kicking them or yelling at them then you'll end up with a dog that
enjoys being in your presence and will do anything you ask
because they're so happy to be with you so you know we need to to train our
minds the way um a skilled drug trainer would train a
puppy so vinegar doesn't work
um but sweetness is is a pretty good strategy
and um in uh
the the vest probably can and um there is
everything that Scholars have have analyzed there is one meditation
practice that most Scholars are very confident that the Buddha actually practiced
himself and that is mindfulness of breathing
and also when the Buddha describes
his Awakening and uh coming out of that he describes
um he describes the mindfulness of breathing
and so this is this is the practice that's not appropriate for everybody in
the world uh if someone has
nearly uh drowned or nearly suffocated to death uh
they might be too scared of the breath to want to go there you know not having enough breath
so uh it's not a hundred percent pertinent for all practitioners
awareness of their breathing but it is uh
it is a what's a Buddha
taught and practice themselves more than anything else
um so if we read the anapana satisuta which
is majima 118 uh it begins uh and and I'll read it to
you uh it's it's from my own translation um
what the Buddha says before he even starts to give instructions so in the
prologue there's a beautiful description of the setting and the monks all being
um and nuns being ready for these teachings
and then when he's beginning to give his instructions
this is what we need to pay attention to he says here
a practitioner gone to the forest
so far from noisy villages through the base of a tree
or to someplace empty sits down
in their meditation posture placing the body straight
having established mindfulness awareness
in front as the first priority
so we we could do um you know a whole two-week Retreat just on this one instruction at the
beginning of the anupanasati but it's it's very profound
and um so
before we even sit down we're cultivating emptiness
we are looking for seclusion from distractions
we're going to some remote place and when
our mindfulness is perfectly uh in place and well established then we
know we are sitting on our body mandala
um even the word forest in ballet aranya
the literal meaning so it is remoteness
so I think that all these instructions have
a lot to do with their uh metaphoric meaning
that yes it's it's good to go out in the middle of the forest but even more important
it's crucial to be secluded from our
distractions and so we wrap ourselves in this cozy
cloak or shawl of seclusion
vivecta and that's that that ability to stay
without jumping off in the thought train this way or going back into the past that way you're planning or thinking
about lunch or whatever you know it we stay and we stay and we
stay and that um quality of seclusion even if it's
just very brief is one of the keys to Freedom
so um I'll stop there
and um
if you'd like uh a little assignment for the next 24 hours
um you might try to keep track of
what takes you off on tangents and then also feel
taste the the flavor of your experience as you come back
uh to being in the present moment with whatever you're doing
whether it's washing your face or cutting the carrots or sitting
meditation so
thank you very much and we will now migrate to the zoo room for any
questions you may have thank you for being here
if anyone has any questions for Meg you can go ahead and raise your hand and zoom and we'll kind of call on you in
order
well I hope that wasn't as clear as mud but no mud low Lotus
yeah that was so clear that no one uh one has any questions about it
I just put on the gallery view is wonderful to see your faces and I I really appreciate your being here
thank you so much for your practice