greetings friends greetings to you
from wherever in the world we are joining each other in this moment in time
I hope you are well and uh delighted to be exploring practices and
compassion cultivation this week together so so as I mentioned on the first day uh
and as many of you know um cultivating compassion happens the
practice is offered in growing concentric circles we start with
ourselves then the next category where we expand our heart is benefactors and
dear friends which we did that yesterday uh we put them together those two categories and then the next category
which is a very important category in this exploration in this growing
expanding our heart is the category of the neutral being the neutral being
and basically this category is someone we don't know very well and when we
cultivate compassion for them we tune into sense of compassion for
someone we don't know very well and the significance of this is that this
person can become will become the standard for all of humanity and this category actually some people find it
easier uh sometimes than the other categories even because we don't have any history with this person so it might
actually turn out to be easier so so you'll see for yourself so let's uh
let's practice together let's begin together
ah Landing in this body notice if you need
to shift or move to be more comfortable to to sit upright
what does your body need in this moment to be comfortable
you feel grounded to fear here
feeling your feet on the earth your legs on the earth if you're sitting on a
cushion creating your sit bones
your bottom on the cushion
the magnet to the Earth
and connecting receiving the breath receiving the breath
in the abdomen let us receive three deep diaphragmatic
breaths to help us arrive arrive fully and settle
maybe breathing in in five counts holding in
for three counts and letting go for five counts available
here we go together
and this time breathing in one two three
four five holding one two three
releasing the breath one two three four
five and one more time in your own timing
not letting the breath be natural but continue to connect with the entirety of
in-breath the pause and the out breath
getting embodied
and now bringing to mind bringing to Heart
someone you've seen you've met
perhaps you have even interacted with but you don't know very well
this person could be maybe someone who works at a grocery
store [Music] Barista homes made your coffee or
or maybe even a neighbor you've seen walked around
you've seen them but you haven't interacted perhaps past to seeing them or saying hello
bring this person to your mind and see them as clearly as possible
or feel them as much as possible and we had this interaction
maybe they're the receptionist at the doctor's office if you're still going through
the list to find someone it's okay to have a little bit of liking
or tiny bit of disliking it's fine it doesn't have to be completely neutral this neutral person but someone we don't
have a lot to straight with
relatively neutral person bring them to mind
now this this person just like me
their life is dear to them
just like me they have a very
compelling [Music] internal life
the life of the Mind likes dislikes
thoughts just like me they have hopes and dreams
aspirations just like me they suffer they have
suffered their body aches
because they have a body their body ages gets sick
has gotten sick they've had pain they've had loss in their life just like me
they might have lost people they love at disappointments defeats
they felt lonely sad depressed
they've also felt Joy happiness just like me
they're people they love
and hold dear and this being is an object of affection
of someone else so someone really loves and cares about this person
they might even like something we like if we like particular vegetable or
flavor of ice cream let's imagine the two of us liking the same thing just for
the sake of imagination or frozen yogurt or whatever it might be
your food
they are not so different this person and I
We're Not So Different than just as I wish to be happy
just as I wish to be happy this person just wants to be happy
as well they don't want to suffer just like me they don't want to suffer
they want to be happy
for the purpose of this particular practice it's okay to use our imagination for a moment perhaps imagine
them suffering in the same way we have if we've had an illness or disappointment
or loss
maybe you've lost a loved one and they too have lost their loved one we both
grieve together in the same ways
and just as we want to be free we want to have ease and peace and not
suffer we wish them well
just as I don't want to suffer
and have ease I wish you freedom from suffering I wish you ease
just as I wish to have peace and strength and resources
to ease my challenges I wish the same for you
keeping them in mind connecting to their image to their felt
sense their Humanity just as compelling
their life just as dear to them to other people just as yours is
they are a dear person
and knowing that they too suffer
from that place of Good Will and acknowledging difficulties in pain wishing them well
may you be free from suffering
may you have ease and ease in the midst of your challenges
your difficulties I wish you well
continuing to engage
good will this person compassion for this being
using your creativity and Imagination
to create a sense of acknowledgment and connection
without getting lost in stories stay with the feeling
I wish you well I wish you ease
I wish you AIDS and peace to face challenges of your life
difficulties and pain
I wish you freedom from sorrow and suffering
I wish you well
aging with compassion feels good feels wholesome
gladdening of the Mind and heart to hold someone else with care
acknowledging their challenges see if you can tune into it
instead of tuning a radio
and notice you your mind gets lost or distracted
stay with the image of the person
and stay connected to the phrases
stay connected to the feeling of kindness and Goodwill
may you be well may you be free from suffering
I wish you peace
and the heart feel expansive and sharing it's goodness it's good wishes it's care with
someone it doesn't even know
can the heart feel expansive its own expansiveness it is available
bearing our Goodwill
with a fellow human being
care for their challenges
and as we bring this said to her clothes
and appreciating this being who is me  ourselves for
showing up for practicing from cultivating kindness compassion
or inviting our hearts to feel expansive feeling
its own goodness its own capacity of Goodwill
and sharing that good will that care kindness with ourselves
others in the Sangha sharing the goodness with all beings
everywhere may all beings everywhere have ease
may they be free from sorrow suffering male beings including myself be free
foreign
readings everyone greetings
thank you for your practice and I just asked if you would put a word and chat
about what's arising for you and I'll bring you a few of these words in so many beautiful offerings
warmth and tenderness neutralities ephemeral yes I'll talk
about that in a moment just like me yeah open-hearted hard opening warmth
love for Neighbors a smile both of us all of us deep good will
indeed thank you thank you all for these beautiful reflections
as they keep coming in yeah
so as we continue to explore the practice of cultivating compassion this
week and and the systematic way that it has been taught
um as we start with categories that are we're more connected to better connected
to ourselves our benefactors dear beings and then we move to this category that
we just explored in the meditation which is the neutral uh person neutral person then we
connect cultivate our care for someone we don't really know we don't have a lot
of experience with a lot of background a lot of history with their
um and this category is a very very important category
because up to now the categories as we expand the heart categories are people
we know we know ourselves kind of we keep discovering ourselves but we kind of know ourselves we spend more time
with ourselves than anyone else oh our benefactors are good friends Etc so it's it's it's
um so far we've been in the known territory and now the neutral person is is the
cusp is a very important transition to the next few categories it's really the
building block it's this the the most important step to the next expansions of the heart so important to step
this category this neutral category and and as we engage with with the
neutral person which you might have noticed after a while practicing with the
neutral person they don't stay neutral anymore our hearts start to care Hearts start to
expand and I have lots of stories which which I have shared before practicing
within neutral category for a while and and the person becomes so dear becomes
so dear um like like his sister like I I in a
way that I would in my heart my heart wouldn't know the difference between who used to be the neutral person who I
didn't even know I hadn't spoken to a word um and and my best friend
um my sister it just know there's there's no difference in my heart
um so these categories are very very and it's not just me this is this is this is the classical teaching
um that actually I'll I'll give you since I shared with this with you I'll I'll tell you there
is a there is a um there's a test you know when we have these mid final tests
the final exam of practicing um uh these practices of the heart let's
say compassion when you practice it intensely for a
long time say on a retreat or a really dedicated dedicate your heart to it for for a period of time
um the the test is um we haven't got to the people we have challenges with but the test is when
um uh you imagine that that you know this is
from classical language you imagine that you're on a trip and the bandits and and you're on a carriage you're in the
carriage with your with your dear being you know dear person
um and with your neutral person and the person you're having challenges with the person who's really pushing your buttons
the four of you are in a carriage you're going somewhere and the bandits stop you and they
get you out and they ask you okay um which you know one of you you have to
give up one of you one of you you have to give up uh whom whom are you gonna give up and then in your heart you try
to figure out whom are you going to give up are you going to give up yourself well you're you're dear to yourself your
life is dear your your dear person of course they're dear to you you're a neutral person you realize oh yes you
practice with them they're dear and then you're the person you have been challenging you've had challenges with also not condoning the challenges we'll
talk more about that tomorrow but but you know there is there's an affinity there's a lot there's a care there's a
love So you you're not able to choose anyone uh at that point that's the real
the blossoming the blossoming of this practice but the point really is that
these categories as you might have just explored you might have realized even today with the short short time that
we've done this is that these categories are ephemeral
they they they keep changing they're transient they're Anita they're impermanent it's it's we don't see
people as they are we see people as we are so so when we have kindness compassion
uh ease gentleness we tend to like people we tend to it's so so we and and
we can cultivate it's not just that it's this is the way you are and you can't shift and change and this is the way
you're for the rest of you like this is the cultivation this is an absolute cultivation or attitude and and the way
our stands towards other people um neutral people people we have
challenges with again I'll talk a lot more about that tomorrow so so so uh we'll save that because that's a very
juicy category and yet the this category of the the neutral person is really the
step the the um the the necessary step to to to work to to expand our hearts and have
Equanimity and peace and care for the people um we have challenges with but staying
with this category today few things a few other things I want to say so so our hearts shift and expand
and the person who was once relatively neutral is not neutral anymore we start
to care for them and as I mentioned I know for me and and many many many practitioners who I've interacted with
this is this is true this is what happens oh I remember once I practiced um with a someone who looked at the uh
worked at the laundromat and every time I walked by that uh uh the not laundromat the
cleaners yes cleaners every time I was curious if she was there she was like oh
my goodness my heart would leap this this neutral person had become a dear friend I was so happy to to take my
clothes there so so um he's the heart is so expansive the
heart is so expensive who we decide to care for or not it's it's all it's so
elastic it's so elastic and another thing of course we realized that we're
all the same we are we all want to be happy us human beings we want to be
happy we don't want to suffer all of our lives our our internal lives are just as
compelling to us my life this richness of thinking or this and that and the whole day I have thoughts and intentions
and and aspirations oh yeah other people have them too duh it's you know if we
stop to realize I realize how similar we are and through that common Humanity we
can have love and care for one another and again as I mentioned briefly earlier
another importance of this category is that um that neutral person becomes the the
stand-in for all of humanity so when we expand to all beings at the end it's
it's there there are our hearts connect with being with this person as oh yeah
and this person too and this person too and I'm not so separate from that person so
um this is profound practice and when I discovered this in I was not born a
Buddhist um and I've discovered these practices it's just my heart my mind I would say
my mind has been blown but my heart has been blown so powerful so powerful
um another thing I want to bring in today is I had mentioned uh I yesterday about
the the near enemies of of compassion
and yesterday uh I talked about um empathic distress empathic distress
or or falling into grief as a near enemy or as a masquerader of compassion
something that feels like compassion but actually it's not compassion it's it's very different from it today I want to
talk about another near enemy another uh near enemy or another
masquerade or something that masquerades as compassion but it's not compassion and that is pity pity is not compassion
at all so the simplest way to understand the difference here is pity is where we
have a less than you know like oh poor you oh you're going through this hard
time oh poor you oh so we have this I'm up here I'm I'm not going through this
I'm I'm okay and oh you poor you so there's a less that there is a comparison like I wouldn't I'm not going
through that or I would never go through that versus there's a separation basically there's a separation you're separating yourself from the other
person from up here like oh poor you I feel I feel compassionate but for you
but this actually is pity foreign
yes we're equal I feel your pain this this could be me this was me this can't
be me in the future or I feel your pain We're Not So Different this can happen to me it's it's their sense of there's
no separation there is a um kinship there is a kinship in this
feeling of of kindness of this feeling of compassion and warmth or as pity
there's a sense of uh putting in in our minds perhaps even not not
um realizing but but but look for that look for that when you're having compassion for
um or someone whether someone you know you care about or someone you don't know notice if
there is that that [Music] um that kinship that lack of separation
so I'll talk more about so so tomorrow we will explore the next category which is
very important category people we have challenges with and and I want and in
preparation for tomorrow I want to invite you if you can for the rest of the day to engage a little more with the
neutral person as you're walking as you're sitting as you're going around
um just maybe imagine you know you're sitting you're making yourself a cup of
tea imagine this neutral person making themselves a cup of tea and as you're enjoying your cup of tea imagine this
neutral person enjoying their cup of tea you're not so different or maybe you're both like green tea I wish you well I
wish you well um sister brother my Ken I wish you well so let's practice
with that um the rest of the day as a preparation really this is the stepping stone to
work with people we have challenges with and that's a very juicy and very
important category so important for us so so let's uh
yeah let's try to engage our hearts and their in expansion today so thank you so
much Sangha thank you for your practice for your engagement for an expansion of your heart may you be well may you be
happy may you have ease and may your hearts know their capacity for for
brilliant expansion all right looking forward to being with you
tomorrow take care