one and I'm here in the meditation Hall and uh in Psych Retreat Center
and I feel very lucky to have a but in eight nine people here some of
the residents and some of the people who 've been part of this program that came down to teach for a couple of days
I've been very fortunate to be here I miss patachara I said I would be able to be with her
these two days but the technology doesn't work so well
so this works much better here foreign
[Music]
at some point in my meditation practice on retreat I learned an interesting uh
technique and I had an image that went along with it so the image would kind of come up
when I use this technique uh kind of the back of the mind and that
was that um the image was that of a horse that had escaped from its Corral
or something or they needed to come back to the barn or something
and so a writer would go down another horse and go out to find the first one and
then would ride up right next to it okay almost you know brought it together
and then the new horse with the writer would gently make a big curve big turn
180 degrees around and the Stray horse would then just follow along and come
back to the barn and so that image was how I worked with
some of the uh thinking that would come up for me I would start thinking about
something and rather than being opposed to it or rather than being troubled by
it it was just a horse that had kind of gone off and uh and I would come along and
imagine myself kind of coming up next to it and just letting it continue to think and letting it kind of just keep going
but then I would kind of you know over a few seconds I would kind of turn it
around and kind of bring It the whole thing back to being grounded and centered here in
my body back in my breathing and uh and that was such a harmonious way of working with my
distracted thought that uh you know it's been something I've done ever since it's been quite wonderful to do
um it's very different than how I was when I was you know a new meditator when it was a
little bit of a war between me and my thinking you know like this is terrible that it's happening and
or it was a little bit of a whack-a-ball kind of exercise whereas I pounded out
of existed somehow that I was thinking but this harmonious way of just coming around and just kind of bringing it back
and one of the Arts of that was that was it coming up next to the horse next
to the thinking and all that was coming up next to someplace in the body that
was um uh either that was associated with a thinking it was somehow Pleasant
or somehow um kind of like the right place to be or the place where it felt that I'm
connected to this event of thinking and um and so there was not just so I
was little I was I was stepping away from the content of my bonds but I wasn't stepping away from thinking
that could continue but I shift the orientation from the thinking about the
content to something it felt right to me felt kind of some occasionally kind of cozy sometimes
a little bit uh Pleasant enjoyable or bright sometimes a sense of aliveness a
Vitality that was kind of cozy or connected in my body so this idea of learning to shift the
attention not from one thing to another but shifting attention within what's
happening to some aspect of what's Happening that feels like a better place
to be centered and so we're not rejecting anything or letting go of something necessarily but
we are shifting the perspective we're shifting with how we're aware of it and one of the important places is
around thinkgeever it's so easy a company called the contents or if there's a lot of emotions it's so easy
to um somehow it could also be involved in the thinking the meaning the memories
the projections into the future of what this emotion is about but even there's there's some place that
feels like a good place to attend attention to being in relationship to the emotion so places
feels right yes it feels alive in a very good way feel
Pleasant enjoyable all right same thing with pain
now to reject the name not to kind of fight it but is there some kind of harmonious way of being present for it
but by not necessarily being with the what's most difficult about the pain but
something that feels like a rightness to it and they kind of agreed with that
with pain sometimes for me and I'm not saying it should be for other people it's a way of kind of working with a
pain in the horse kind of is uh what feels often the most right thing to do
is to sit in the middle of where it's most painful and there's something about sitting
there that changes the nature of the pain for me where just go okay now I can
be here but if I'm not there in the center of it then um then it's uh then I'm still kind of
the thinking mind and the reactive mind kind of has a Freer reign
so this is what I'd like to suggest for today that if you sit here in meditation and um and something arises that takes
you away from the present for your breathing present here um not to fight it or even let go of it
but think of it as a horse and where do you ride up next to it to accompany it
with the place where you're up against it when it is something that feels right about the composite the whole experience
of whatever it is what is it that um that you can feel that has a ripeness A
pleasantness aliveness in that experience that supports you to bring
the horse back home back into the body back in here and present
so taking a comfortable alert posture
and then play closing the eyes
taking a few moments to feel experience how you are right now
all the different ways you might be at any given moment
now allowing at all to be there where could you Center yourself that
feels the most right or the most Pleasant
the most sense of being alive in a nice way balanced way
maybe on the exhale relaxing around that spot
Amy centered on that spot taking a few long slow deep breaths
to settle in more fully here
and letting the breathing return to they were wrong
[Music] where is it in connection to breathing
root feels most right to Center their attention
where in the breathing does it feel most Pleasant
most alive most clear
foreign no matter what happens during the
meditation ask yourself that question given what's happening
where's the where in the all the different parts aspects of the
experience music most Pleasant
alive right yeah be aware of it
the body and the feelings emotions mind States
where it feels like it's most right to feel
there's a gentle turning to be more fully here
coming home here
foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
we appreciate that we are multifaceted many different
components of what makes up our personal experience in any given moment
components of kind of how we are
the meditation practice is one of the practices that shifts that
from being stuck maybe in the thoughts ideas concerns
to being somehow energized and an agitated way
to being able to focus on how we can feel grounded and centered
embodied maybe a little bit more connected to our
hearts
more centered here
and have more fluidity to be able to move between the component parts of ourselves
you know at the end maybe to move the attention to the Heart Center
to the place within your body where you feel compassion your care love
kindness sometimes felt as a tenderness
sometimes a warm sometimes is a kind of inner strength
you breathe with that Heart Center [Music]
into [Music] gaze out upon the world
from your kindness
Your Love to end the meditation
with directly establishing a connection with the meditation [Music]
in Goodwill for the world around us good will for the people we know we
don't know people whoever it's easy to learn and
people who is not so easy and then they they say Goodwill
to extend that Goodwill intentionally purposefully
choicefully with words that are something like
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
male beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you [Music]
thank you
um
hello everyone again and I'm greeting you from the inside retweet
Center here in the Redwood in in Santa Cruz County right now I don't think it's
raining there was uh the major entryway highway to Santa Cruz
was just entry into Santa Cruz side of it was blocked with big landslides yesterday
it's kind of dramatic at times here in this area usually lots of landslides
but we've been safe here at IRC and comfortable and
um it's nice to be here a nice degree I'll review on YouTube get
a little taste of the retreat center here and you don't see much of it now but maybe at the end of it I can we can
zoom out and show you the more of the meditation room
so this week the series is on the Dharma of challenges
and uh it's Following last week where I
um you know the week was on a question that and the topic was what is the Dharma
and I offered five different meanings of the word Dharma
and um and so I'm building on that and now how each different meaning of Dharma can be
an approach to how to work great practice with challenges we have and this is still laying down a foundation
so it's not getting into details but the foundation of a series now as we
go along here on uh working with challenges and particular ways of working with it and I'm kind of a little
bit I'm not sure exactly how this is going to unfold over the weeks so I've been hoping that it's a bit of a journey
into a kind of a deeper deeper connection to oneself around this topic of the
challenges we have of being human beings and um
so the
um one of the meanings that I talked last week about with what Dharma is is
Dharma as action and there is a places in the ancient
texts where the Buddha is called the teacher of action that come about and or
in his teaching is a teaching of Acts of action kamavada
and um kind of related to the word terravata with the same bada at the end
and um so a teaching of action and there's one way of understanding the Dharma and even
understanding uh Insight practice that um it's a practice of action it's a
acting if there's a doing we do that involves Insight practice
meditation and sometimes it's useful to emphasize that it is an action is a doing
uh because um otherwise sometimes we don't recognize we are doing something and
sometimes we have language in this tradition of not doing anything just allowing and just being
and um but there's a way which that also isn't doing um if we stop doing we do a lot of we're
busy in the mind and very active and we choose to stop it all and be still
there's a way that's also a doing um it's a doing of stopping
and then we do that we don't stop our life life continues and there's all this
Vitality so if you're sitting in meditation upright um then there's action involved in being
present for that posture present here for this uh if some people will practice you know
non-doing just radical kind of letting go of all the normal doings of the mind
and the body just be still but there's still the doing of of being aware of
that to be is it doing of action the action of of awareness that maybe we're
not doing but it's being done it's action happening it's really happening
and the reason why I would like to emphasize the action in relationship to challenges
is that uh when we're challenged by life in simple ways and deep deep ways
that the challenge part of it something inside of us as as uh sprung into action
we've been activated in some way or maybe we find ourselves thinking a lot
about it and trying to figure out the problem solve perhaps we're physically
activated in some way we want to run away or want to attack something because
we're really something is wrong or we want to shut down I kind of sometimes my kind of default
of uh when I be challenged is the ostrich approach the challenge kind of
like sticking my head in the in the sand and kind of like pretending it's not there some people's default is to attack
you know get angry and blame some people it's thrown away and shut down all kinds
of things and those are all actions and some people they're commenting is
just being out and about and projections and Fantasies and ideas what
if or what could have been or what and all these are kind of actions and um
and uh so we're already doing something and it turns out when we're really
challenged uh it's not often it's very good for the heart and the mind and
their whole psyche um to feel like we have some agency that we can do something and we can act
and if there were the challenge big challenges you know challenges squared to challenge a couple challenge is when
we feel it's too much and you feel like giving up it's hopeless and the feeling of hopelessness is one of the great or
helplessness is really one of the great uh maybe the greatest challenge within
challenges feeling giving up or feeling there's no no opportunity to do anything
and uh in the dire mom there's always something we can do
and uh and maybe we can't do something to fix this challenge but we can't find
where we have some agency what can I do here what can we how can
we Act and I remember many years ago I talked to a woman she was going in for a major
surgery and she's had a lot I had a lot of surgeries and one more time
and uh I taught her to do on a kindness medication
and uh after the surgery she told me Gail that was so helpful because in the
past I felt once I'm on the gurney and they're laying there waiting to go into surgery waiting in the hallway or
whatever she's waiting um I feel helpless like my life is in the hands of someone else and I just
can't do anything but uh now I I felt empowered there's
some something I can do I can do loving kindness and she felt so engaged and so
um um empowered or did she had her agency back
at this crucial moments in her life of going into surgery so she could you know
Define what we can do in a situation and learn we don't have to be helpless
even uh you know when it's time for people to die
that uh that does not necessarily a time to give up there's a time to let go in a healthy
way which is also an action and it if we learn the value of letting
go then um it's an action which is invited we appreciate doing it we see the value of
it okay now I can let go of so many concerns and so many things now there's an opportunity to do something else here
not to be kind of snow and under or covered over with
um with sense of helplessness hopelessness even though the person
might be dying you know that's kind of a challenge or a crisis for some people but if it's happening anyway then a
Dharma practitioner finds what action can I engage here that meets this nicely
and so one of the actions that we do in Mind Quest practice meditation for
example is the choice to sell to not do so in our physical body we
choose not to move the body too much within reason you know maybe you have to move it if it's uncomfortable but to be
still for a period of time we might have a choice to uh still some
of the thinking mind that there are some of the things we think about that we realized you know I've done this
a lot I don't need to do this anymore and so there's a healthy appropriate way
to say I stopped I'm not doing this that is an engagement of our agency of our
choice so we can do and there are things we can't have choice about stopping and we have to
learn to practice with that and so for someone who's doing mindfulness medication one of the doings
one of the actions with you is to meet it with attention made it with
investigation meaning with curiosity to be present here and um and that's
something we do that some I think sometimes people under uh value
the action of showing up for our experience okay here I am with it that's taking agency that
said you have something to do we're not helpless when we bring attention to something
right the um and sometimes what we can do is um is be present for the experience of
challenge but learn how to be present for it in a useful way
and one of the ways is to realize when we're challenged the more challenged we
are probably accidentally it's a way of saying in that sometimes the challenge is we see it out there maybe it's like
an object it's objectified somehow but I propose that the this the bigger
the challenge is the more we're activated with our thinking mind our emotional Minds our fear or anxiety or
concerns and um and that activation
uh is something to bring attention to but to bring attention to it
uh in a careful way to explore and discover where am I activated what's Li
what's activated here and where does it feel most right to bring the attention where does it
feel most within it where where would in this how I feel is most grounding
both centering where and how I'm feeling now which I'm feeling so agitated so unstable
is there some place where it feels Pleasant it's enjoyable to have the
attention and so I remember yesterday uh when we had
some trouble with the um technology and making it work uh I sat down and I was a
little bit you know more activated more energized uh spinning a little bit than
I usually am when I sit down to do the YouTube and um and so as I sat there uh I I
brought my attention to the the way I was energized a little bit agitated and
where it was most Pleasant was in my arms there was a flow of energy there of
um of you know usually my arms I don't feel that strongly when I meditate the upper arms but now there was a flow of
energy there that was part of the activation but it actually felt kind of nice that flow and liveness and tingling
there in the upper arm and so I wanted to be present for how I
was and but I wanted to also be present for it in a way where I wasn't going to
spin out more in the thoughts and the ideas and the concerns but to uh but to
be present for in a way that um entered into it in a way that allows
for a deeper connection or a subtleness so or having a calmness in the middle of
the storm and so finding that place where it was pleasant or or that's sometimes too high
too high a bar to find but to find where it is um
feels a ripeness to it and I love this idea of where is the
brightness so it feels right and it feels like they're given how challenging it is and what's going on given it
whereas that feels like the right place to be present to be centered or be attentive to it and um and that's I find
it's just to ask that question it gives us is the beginning to uh
um take on agency I can do this I can do something
so the Dharma has action that Buddha was a teaching teacher of action
and we're learning how to act to engage to do in a way that is freeing that
brings peace that brings a sense of well-being and and that path to that
goes through can go through uh learning to feel confident in our capacity with
agency even if we can't solve the challenge we don't have to give up our
finding a way to be present and alive in a way that we feel like we can do
something and we don't have to feel helpless so uh it might be interesting for today
as you go through this that um you explore this for yourself that you know
if you feel challenged by things first look and see uh recognize if you've been
activated and you are already acting you're already engaged so it might be
like um you know this is hopeless and hopeless and I'm a disaster
that's an action that's a doing so see when you're challenged what
you're already doing and find one of two things or both what
you can do instead that gives you a healthy agency to do something appropriate here
and the second is um to be more present for how you feel
challenged but to feel where does it feel most right
what aspect of your psychophysical experience maybe even it's kind of pleasant in the middle of this very
unpleasant event that's going on where does it most common to connect to it
and uh maybe it's an exercise today you don't want to choose the most difficult challenges of the day but maybe there's
some small challenges that would be interesting to explore this with
and um so thank you and um I'm a little bit aware also that
yes last week was a foundation for this week and what's coming but in fact the
last week of the year of 2022 I talked about right effort is also may be a very
important foundation for what's coming the prequel for it you didn't listen to it you might want
to go back so here I am at IRC so thank you all for
being here and I thought I would take a couple of minutes here uh just to introduce you to our wonderful Retreat
Center we have um and I don't know can you um uh zoom out we see the whole meditational
and then again obviously it takes a I don't know there's a delay between going from our
computer to zoom to YouTube it's longer than the delay when I go directly to YouTube from IMC
and um so I don't know if you can look out the windows but we have wonderful redwood
trees just outside and now we have this wonderful Hall we're on the second floor of the building
and when we moved into this building bought the building and it was unfinished it was an unconstructed kind
of Unfinished space up here and we walked into the space up here we all felt this is the place for the
meditation Hall that was the one again it had had a presence here that ah this
is it and now it's it now it's our medication on and we have a few people here who live
here and we've been involved with IRC for a long time I wonder if any of you would like to come and introduce yourself to the YouTube Community
um partly because uh you're very important for this wider IMC Community
you're part of what supports it all and keeps you all going supports me and anybody I know asking you kind of
out of the blue but anything you'd like to come and say hello yes elizo says hey hello this Powell is a managing director
of our Retreat Center and um a long time practitioner and they
trained not to be a teacher that's what she was here for rules of teacher training
good morning everyone I'm really happy to be here at IRC with
uh some of the many many volunteers that help make IRC
happen there are people who reside here who take care of
the building and all of the Retreats and
all the people who come here to volunteer and then there are just hundreds of people who volunteer who far
and see them are here too who make sure that we have good volunteers and um
I'm kind of sitting here make sure that we have online Retreats that happen or webcasts that happen in our retreats so
just wanted to acknowledge all those people and say that volunteering here is a really great joy thank you
Michelle please Michelle Sterling has been a resident
volunteer here before uh when you first start opened up and she's recently returned to do another round
thanks hi everybody that's pretty good introduction I can't think of anything
more to add I'm really glad to be here I just moved in two days ago
I'll be in the kitchen probably a lot and I love being in there
great oh you want to come fantastic
introduction
thank you so here's the same name and then she's been here now for about nine months and
a wonderful member of our community who's been working hard and uh the admin
side of it all and the housekeeping side of it all and and um
the reason I come down here I smile when I see from you thank you for those of you who couldn't
hear me as I was walking up I was asking for my introduction yeah I am thankful to be here uh the
first time I walked into this Retreat Center almost the year ago it was February of 2022. the walls views of
compassion and that's something that's definitely very very present and I
continue to feel that during my time here so I hope you all have a great afternoon morning evening wherever you
are thank you
hi everyone um I'm getting me and I've been here for
almost three years and throughout the pandemic
um I was away for three months or a retreat
um it just came back what am I and just feel like
gratitude [Music] for this place
and um
it brings me a lot of joy to think uh you are
um the circle of IRC Communications Browder and all over the world
um yeah so much
so much love thank you
can be dangerous
so thank you and uh thank you again Lee
and Kristen and your channel and the other year helping and some people who adhere some people come here to
volunteer and help and I think some people come here to practice and some people come here to
teach all kinds of things that go on here and uh it's a wonderful and
wonderful to share this with you and and um someday maybe some of you will come
here and practice with us thank you