good evening come here good evening everyone
how is this sound is it too loud or too soft is it okay
it should be a little bit a little bit louder just a tiny bit louder that's kind of what I was thinking too
that uh so let's see how did you did it is it
louder but uh okay maybe yeah here we go thank
you thank you sveta
nice to see you all or to believe right that I just realized that Autumn is this week right it's the
Equinox or wow the Equinox the solstice
one of those things one of those Sun and Earth things
so tonight I'd like to start with a poem a short poem it's by Rosemary traumer it's called
Moose musculus this is the Latin name for a mouse
so you don't know Rosemary Tremors she's like one of my favorite artists a poem poets and I'll say that often her poems
have a little bit of Whimsy to them and I like this and they're not complicated they're kind of straightforward and
you'll see that's the flavor of this poem too but I like what she's pointing to here
so the Palm goes like this today fear is a mouse
that scuttles between thoughts and feeds on whatever it finds nibbles on my
certainties gnaws the coding of my circuit trees and pulls the stuffing out
of each moment those are its droppings in the hallways of if whole ways of my mind
I thought it was worse when fear was a tiger a badger a wolverine but the mouse
of fear Finds Its way into everything makes nests inside my minutes discovers
passages in my inner walls then scratches against them at night
it never goes near the traps I've said no it's scampers around them it's soft
feet pattern it's small it's small dark eyes noting Everywhere I Go
so this idea of this little mouse that's going Wherever She Goes
sometimes fear can feel like this it has its uh
excuse me here for a moment
sometimes fear can feel like this that it's um
following us around getting into little nooks and crannies of our days
I don't know what's happening with my voice it's and I'm not sick this is just something that happens with my allergies sometimes
earlier today it was fine so fear
often has a large role in our lives bigger than we realize
especially if we kind of like uh broaden this whole idea of fear to include
things like apprehension or anxiety
or dread or worry if we kind of like expand to
the meeting to include these types of things we discover that actually maybe this little mouse
is all over in our lives is showing up in so many different ways scampering
around scratching at night
in the way in the poet she talks about fear seemed easier when it was a tiger or a wolverine sometimes it seems like
it's easier when it's really big and we can point to it and it's right here and
it's obvious when it's there and it's obvious when it isn't there but this idea of a mouse of a way that you know
often when there's mice we don't see them we just feel the
effects of them so fear turns out to have actually a big
role in our lives and some people might even say like if we even wanted to
expand it even bigger and say that maybe it's we would say fears that they're rude to underlying all conflicts
or maybe even some of our sorrow there's this role that fear has or this
way in which it's blocking us from intimacy or you know getting close to others and
instead creating this sense of disconnection
I don't know if that's true if all of conflict has fear underneath it or if all sorrow has fear underneath it to
revolt hesitation about intimacy has fear underneath it but I think it's
worthwhile examining questioning for ourselves
yeah what role does Fear have in our lives what are the different ways it shows up
how would our lives be different if there were wasn't this fear dread apprehension worry
anxiety
so I'm talking about some of these things that are in our life but also fear can show up in a really subtle way
in our practice that is when we're practicing we have a meditation practice whatever meditation
practice you do there might be a way in which you come up to the edge of what's
familiar and start to touch into something different
something unfamiliar I know that when I one time I was
teaching an introduction to meditation class and sometimes there would be people that really didn't have any experience at all with meditation
and this one person on the first day maybe it was the second
day I don't remember that this person was like quite alarmed
like after I had done a little guided meditation and as she was sharing she's like this
feels odd this is uncomfortable I feel like it's a complete out of body experience and I was talking with her
and asking her to share what it was the experience was and it turned out it was
really calmness but she was so used to having this kind of this certain amount of anxiety inside
that this calmness felt like that she must not be present if there wasn't this
certain amount of calmness but it had some fear for her
I know for myself that I've had fear with on especially on some of these long Retreats when the mind gets really
settled you know months of on Retreat practice and silence and the mind gets into
places it hasn't been before like oh wow what was that
there's always for me I don't know if it's in this case for everybody the initial point is like whoa what was that
and then this uh I feel like the mind is like is this familiar is it not familiar
and if it's not familiar there's a little bit of you know this hesitation this uh not this willingness to like
just go for it like whatever is new just trusting it and going right into it
and on one of these uh really long Retreats that I sat Joseph Goldstein was one of the teachers
and I remember him giving a Dharma talk where he shared that one of his uh
biggest difficulties in practice and in life was fear
and I remember sitting there being like so surprised those who don't know Joseph Goldstein
he's uh probably one of the most senior if not the most senior person in this
tradition he helped bring it from India and Burma to the West
so you know he's been around for a long time decades and decades but not only
that he's like a really strong tall person you know then he kind of walks and moves a little authoritatively so to
hear that even he had a lot of fear I thought wow and at the time I thought like
I don't have any fear why does he have fear I had no idea how much fear I actually
had so I don't know what I'm I think about Joseph often when I see fear like oh
yeah okay at least I'm in good company here
but so maybe it's uh the fear of the unknown but maybe it's also the fear
when we are in our meditation practice look at this fear that maybe it's things
like oh maybe this uncomfortable sensation in my knee or my back is never going to end
you know we kind of like project into the future or
or maybe we have this uh fear that I'll never get settled or this mind will
never settle down and I will never be able to feel a certain amount of ease or
calm like the Mind likes to do this likes to come up with these different scenarios
so maybe one of the first ways of the stage of practicing with fears even to
acknowledge its presence this won't be sufficient to make fear go
away just to have this intellectual understanding but it's where we start
maybe it's not it doesn't have to be the very beginning but it definitely has a role and it's tempting to think like
okay if I just understand it better if I figure it out it'll go away if I get
underneath it what was it from my childhood or my the way that I was
raised or something that happened earlier in my life that's causing this fear and certainly that can have a role and
can be supportive but there's often like when the fear is being experienced right there it's not
we don't have the opportunity we don't have the wherewithal we don't have the time
to do is that type of investigation or inquiry
but instead we can just notice that
there's fear shows up in all kinds of ways some of it's subtle
for example it might be some fear that's really driving our ambition
our motivation what's propelling us maybe there's some fear underneath that
or maybe there's some fear that's underneath our anger
whether we're angry with ourselves angry with other people or just however it shows up but maybe there's some fear
underneath that or maybe there's some fear underneath our sadness
so there's this way that fear can show up or support all kinds of these some
uncomfortable emotions and aspects of Our Lives
and uh Ezra bada who's a zen teacher he says well actually we could just boil it
all down to just three fears again I don't know if this is true but uh it's
been interesting for me to think about this so he says that there's only three fears
and that these like underlie all of our uncomfortable experiences
number one is the fear of losing safety and control
yeah we don't like to lose control how much of our life is trying to control control ourselves control other people
control anything we can yeah I noticed that with my mindfulness
with my meditation practice when I first started being mindful I had no idea how
much planning I was doing I didn't realize that I would have spent all my time just planning planning planning
and it wasn't until I actually noticed oh there's fear underneath this planning
like I'm trying to be prepared so that no matter what happens it's going to be
okay so you have all these contingency plans that are coming up and well if
this happens then I gotta have this and that and you know so then I would like have a big backpack that I had to carry
with me everywhere you know just in case you know all these things you know this fear of boredom or
you know whatever it might be so this fear of losing safety and
control I have a nice first aid kit in my car which is probably a good thing to do I
want to say but you know maybe there's a little this fear of uh being unsafe for
I like to think it's because so I can help somebody if they need it if I happen to come across an accident or
something I'm the first one there I don't want to be feel helpless
so a second fear that Ezra beta says is a fear of aloneness and disconnection
and we could say well maybe serum over this impacts our relationships with
people maybe some of our relationships with ourselves or also our relationship with death
this fear of aloneness of death maybe we don't want other people to die
we don't want to die and then the third fear is this fear of
unworthiness not being good enough somehow being
inadequate or insufficient and the things that we'll do to maybe bolster uh
the view that others have of us you know wanting to look good in such a way
maybe there's this fear of main feeling like we're unworthy or
seeming like that we're unworthy to others
so there's sometimes people like to lump things together and sometimes people like to split them apart things just
like anything and I'm one of those people who likes to just lump things into categories so I kind of like this
idea that there's just these three fears because it also uh
kind of I find it interesting to think well are there some fears that don't fall into those three back buckets
and of course we can get into well it depends how you define safety and control and you know all these kinds of
things but part of why it's helpful is because it's
um gives us something maybe to point to instead of fear just being this big
black box something that's mightily uncomfortable
and that we would do almost anything to not have that experience maybe having a few little labels or
flavors of it makes it become maybe a little bit less of a black box
because there's a way in which we often of course we don't like fear and we
often are trying to like flee from fear or avoid it
and maybe I should say also that um you know there's lumping together but
maybe I'll also just tease apart I made a little bit to this uh the difference between fear and anxiety
for the most part I'm kind of like putting them together but we might understand that a
difference is is that fear is more about something that's a known
and it has it's been a specific object or specific experience
most it's either something that's imminent or maybe something that's far in advance whereas anxiety has more of
this unfocused fear maybe it's this excessive fear that that's a little bit higher
than what's necessarily the object if we knew what it was would be related to
would be appropriate for that then maybe as an aside I've just noticed
you in my mind and some other teachers who have noticed this also that uh maybe
it's after the pandemic but how many people are talking about their anxiety
how many people are just feeling uncomfortable I see this and my role as
like a teacher on retreats or in other settings or practice discussions and people are sharing with
me how their practice is going and this word anxiety comes up a lot
so just this recognition that I think this is maybe a time a season
this time of post-pandemic and everything else that's happening in the world in which it's not so uncommon
but as I was saying fear involves this like this unpleasant sensation so it's
an unpleasant experience and we might be able to like tease those apart between the physical Sensations which
maybe it's a heart pounding or maybe there's like butterflies in the stomach
and then there's those reactions to those Sensations which might also be some clenching or some tightening or
bracing or something like this so those are like what's happening in the body
but also what's happening in the mind is usually there's a constriction of the
awareness like we're just focused on one thing and not in a way that's Pleasant
sometimes when we're focused a sense of concentration can bring with it some calm and ease but this is a constriction
where the awareness shrinks down in a way that is unpleasant
feeling stuck maybe or there isn't a sense of ease or relaxation or malleability instead this
really shrinking and again part of this teasing apart and
this way is also so that we can work with it I can notice okay there's the what's
happening in the body and there's what's happening in the mind and those are two different ways in
which we can practice with fear that we can work with it
so because if we have if we don't notice that we have fear
and then there's just the aversion to fear which of course I think is a natural response I think it's part of
our biology fear wouldn't be effective as a way to protect us which I'm sure
evolutionarily is why we have fear if it weren't uncomfortable so it's inherently
uncomfortable but part of this what perpetuates fear is this idea of
fleeing or trying to run away from it if it's happening right then if we're
feeling fear but part of what happens when we're trying to run away from the fear is we run away in our minds into
our minds but when there's fear the mind is kind of
constricted and there might be this Whirlwind of stories or maybe it's not
even clear I got to get out of here what is this happening or there can be this disorganization in our thoughts or a
sense of a franticness to them so it's part of the way reason why
aversion which often turns to this idea of fleeing just perpetuate perpetuates the fear is
because we're just feeding maybe this uh
that thought this rumination or this uh way in which we're kind of like stuck in
a certain way of thinking so what are some ways to practice with
fear there's a number of different ways and I'd like to
say that also we have to recognize that of course there's different intensities of fear so different practices might be
appropriate with different intensities things that are just mildly
fearful for me there's a thing about spider webs
that I don't like I just I mean let alone spiders right but the spider webs
I'm getting much better much better in fact the other day I just was cleaning up some spider webs and I felt rather
proud of myself but you know those aren't really terrible ones you know a few years I can
work with those in a certain way but uh you know some of these
existential fears fears of being alone fears of being out
of control fear of death you know they might need a little bit more
care with how we practice with them but here's one way to practice both with
the minor ones I'll use the word minor less intense and it might be available for some of
the more intense ones too and that is to bring attention to the body
but the body in a particular way I would say more like the whole body so not like
a focused in but like the whole body the whole bodily
experience so one way to do this is just to pay attention to posture
and just to notice you know is there an alertness is there slouching is the hip
out with your head on your hip or you're tapping your foot or I don't know are you with the shoulders down and like
this this or if you're walking to feel the maybe the pressure underneath the feet
because there's this way in which a more generalized mindfulness to the body
helps to get away from this constriction that's happening with the awareness instead this uh kind of like opening up
to be with the entire bodily experience
and there's a simile that the Buddha gives but we could say is uh definitely
an example of being mindfulness of the body with fear and this is a simile of a person
who has a bowl of boiling oil
on their head and they're walking
towards the stage for a performance is going on a dancing performance
in my mind that means there's music and in my mind that means other people might be dancing
an audience and then just to make it even more stressful that there's
somebody walking behind the person that has oil on their head with a knife
saying that they're going to chop off your head if you drop any of the oil so
the oil will burn you then off with that fear right there's a way in which all
this fear and so walking that way you really have to pay attention to the posture but you
also have to be paying attention to what's going around you like it's any of these dancing people around you gonna
hit you or run into you or something so maybe this isn't a great simile
because if I were to imagine that I think I would be really tense but the point is to like you just to not
to be aware of your surroundings as well as your posture and to still be able to
move so this is kind of like a simile that's giving of this mindfulness of the body in this way of way to work with fear
there's also a way in which mindfulness of the body can be
um have this sense of openness that sometimes teachers will talk about this
and I've practiced this way sometimes it's really a lovely way to practice is
to like maybe expand the idea of the body
to you like I don't know maybe like six to 12 inches from the body
and this can be really Pleasant actually so it's uh not the usual mindfulness
practice but just to still be aware of
what's Happening but with the body just a little bit expanded
turns out that the Mind likes to be big and open and so doing this with the with
the body just encourages the mind to be a little bit more open and then it naturally will want to kind of collapse
down and focus on one thing in particular because that's a little bit easier but there's a way which in just to be a
little bit mindful of the whole body including just a few inches off of the body
and I know that sounds a little bit odd and but it's worth just playing around with
if you'd like to explore something like this
so there's a way in which we also that being mindful of one's posture or like
the whole uh bodily experience so it can be a way that we can like maybe like
relax into this sense of being embodied because so often the fear is we're lost
in our mind about what might happen not all the time sometimes there's fear or you know imminent danger
but for most of us probably the things that we're afraid of or have fear about are things that are going to happen in
the future so there's a way just to feel embodied
like I'm here now if I'm right here
and to like feel the experience of breathing and to just feel the sense of
aliveness or presence that's inhabiting the body
and there's a way that that can be comforting and grounding and settling
so mindfulness of the body is one way to practice with fear
and I'm pointing to this mindfulness that's a little bit more of the whole
body more generalized as opposed to a really focused way
so then a second thing that we can do with uh with fear of course is loving
kindness practice there's a way that you know
love I'll just say generally love warm-heartedness and fear definitely have a relationship with one another
because um there's this book right it was written decades ago the now the author
slips my mind but this idea is the title of the book is love is letting go of fear
so there's this way in which if we can cultivate some open-heartedness
some warm-heartedness then there isn't fear there or the fear
greatly lessens and so there's a few ways to do this and
one I will say one is just to have this be a regular practice not waiting until fear arises
there's a loving-kindness practice I'm not gonna I'm going to the details
of that for those of you who are interested I taught for a number of years and it's uh now Liz Powell teaches
that's with Nikki mergafori but five days a week There's a
loving-kindness practice on on zoom and you if you go to the IMC
calendar you'll see so there's hundreds and hundreds of recordings and still going on most days
but there's this way in which uh with loving kindness practice
that we can just bring to mind that absolute easiest
absolute easiest way to bring some openness or care to the heart
for some this might be internet things that we saw these little kittens or
puppies or babies there's a reason right why there's so many kitten videos so it's because uh
people like them and puppies and it's perfectly fine to use something like
this for practice to like feel into the open-heartedness
and the warmth and the Delight and connect with that Sensation that
experience and then allow that experience to get as big as it would like
there's different ways to connect to it and there's different ways that uh to allow maybe that experience to grow of
this care or Delight or love or warmth or respect or however you might experience it and I'll just say briefly
one way is just to be repeating phrases for example may you be safe or may you
be happy or may you be healthy like sending some good wishes to this lovable
being and it can be that simple it doesn't
need to be lots of different categories or different phrases or something like this there's a way in which the mind and
the heart when they're experiencing some openness and warmth the fear just
naturally dissipates
so even if we're having a fear of an individual let's say I wouldn't recommend that we do loving
kindness for that individual that's a tall order and then we're just setting ourselves up
for maybe feeling feeling like oh I can't do this and then I even maybe seem to be scarier instead just do some uh
loving kindness where it's easy and then so it related to that is
something that we can do when we're experiencing fear is that we can just
have this inquiry into about what's happening in the mind I talked about the body I talked about
the heart and now maybe we could say about the mind as I said often fear has this
constriction like there's this uh shrinking of the awareness
but we could also if we remember if we can remember we can just have this gentle inquiry
is there any wisdom here I mean maybe the fear is like really wise and can we
appreciate the wisdom can we say is there any self-respect
here and can we appreciate that also okay this fear is part of us maybe like
setting boundaries and way that we're taking care of ourselves and can we tune
into that is there just care in general care for
ourselves care for somebody else or care for something that's really important to us
and tune into that because that's a way this uh care or
self-respect or wisdom are also ways in which we can broaden the mind
I'm pointing to all these different ways in which we can get out of this collapsed feeling that often happens
with fear because when we're practicing with fear we don't want to collapse and surrender
into it nor do we want to repress it and pretend that it's not there
but is there a way that we can work with it acknowledge it but not be overwhelmed
so mindfulness of the body and just kind of like maybe a general way
loving kindness practice either that one has done regularly as part of their meditation
practice but maybe even then when there is fear
recently I was uh on a walk in this place where I know that there's some
dogs that they're behind a fence but I can see them and they can see me and
they they love to bargain like run and run and run and I have a little a fear
of dogs here's what am I having been bitten a number of times I have this uh
fear of them and I was trying to like look at them and like may you be happy
but you'll be healthy that didn't work very well
yeah and somebody recommended that I then was on a walk with somebody else in this
same place and they said what if you don't even look at the dogs that are barking and running and stuff
like this just like ignore them like look the other way and it turned out that was very helpful so I think dogs
maybe if you're looking at them they're interacting with you more but I don't know that I had learned more about the psychology
of dogs then but so is there a way in which we can open
our hearts our minds and maybe have a little bit more ease in the body when
there is fear as a way to practice with it and then we might discover
that if we have experienced some fear and we have worked with it maybe this is
a minor one spiderwebs dogs that are barking but behind a fence
is there a way that then we can be a little bit more confident
because it turns out that really a tremendous way to work with fear is to
trust that you can do it you know trust that okay this is fearful
it's mightily uncomfortable but that's okay too
and so part of the way that we can trust ourselves or trust that being uncomfortable with fears
is going to be okay it's just to have experiences with some
of the more minor fears in our lives fear of
what is the person that checked the grocery store clerk gonna say or think
when they see all the things that are in the shopping cart you're gonna think like they might have some comments about
wow why is she buying so much of that or something like this I don't know just these minor fears whatever they might be
so fear it turns out has a big role in our lives it might be really subtle
might be underlined some really and really otherwise
unrecognized and comfortable experiences it might be really obvious things that
we have fear of but it's really worthwhile spending some
time acknowledging for ourselves just even acknowledging the role of fear acknowledge that we don't have to be
completely free of fear it's just part of the human experience of course it is like how
could it be otherwise of course there's fear and then is there a way that we can
practice with it I I was talking about kind of like how the mind gets small but
it turns out our lives get small when we have a lot of fear
because we're trying to avoid all these things that cause a little bit of fear and
and then trying to avoid that it turns out to be so many things
because you're avoiding this well now you have to avoid that because that might lead to this which might lead to that and our lives just start to shrink
so it's a way in which to make not only our minds and hearts bigger but our lives bigger and if we're willing to
take some risks take some chances do something new go somewhere new that we
haven't before enriches Our Lives bring some
some beauty some depth some richness to this experience this Human Experience
so fear and how to practice with it so I think I'll end there and uh
open it up and see if there are any some questions or comments about what I've
said here
thank you um thank you it was a good topic just what I needed to hear so um my question
is what if you're dealing with crippling fears
and I have tried to pay attention to the body it just
doesn't work my mind's run away the fear takes over and
so what do you do then and I like what you said about trusting oneself
but if the mind's already gone how do you bring the trust back and then
what does it mean for the stimulus for
what has caused the fear yeah because somewhere you have to do a little bit of
problem solving to deal with that fear um
so it all becomes this complex mess I'd love to hear what you have to say about
that yeah no can you keep the microphone because I have a question can you say a little bit more what happens when you uh
bring awareness to the body what happens I can't I can't no it doesn't work
the hearts pounding and you know every attendant feelings there but that idea
of stepping back and observing what's happening doesn't happen it happens when
I am not that afraid yeah yeah but when I really need it the tools fail me yeah
yeah yeah and is this something that's like debilitating for your life or that happens a lot or is it just like uh
occasionally it's incidental yeah yeah yeah so I thank you for asking this this
is a really good question I would say for Fears like this sometimes
mindfulness is not the right way because exactly as you said it's not going to work right we just there's certain types
of fear where it just uh leaves us our wisdom leaves us and for something like that there might
be uh it might be appropriate for um to work with different modalities other than meditation or mindfulness
something like [Music] um limited exposure therapy or something
like this you know I'm not an expert in this but I know about this or there's
number different modalities so I'll just say this I just kind of want to normalize your experience and it can be
frustrating when you hear somebody like me say like ah just be mindful of it and you're like no that doesn't work
I would say for those but it turns out to be really helpful to like uh make a
real effort to work with the minor fears like to intentionally work with minor fears this does have an impact so I will
say that so I offered you know spiders and spider webs or dogs or something like this so maybe there's something
that isn't uh crippling that you can practice with
and so that's one thing is maybe to like be intentional another thing is actually
to just have a loving kindness practice to have this just be a regular part of
your life or in your meditation practice not so that it absolutely is going to
make the fear go away but there's something about a loving kindness practice that
um makes everything easier there's it maybe brings a little bit
more of the confidence or a little bit more of the
decreases the intensity of the fear or something like this so is that helpful
kind of like this yeah thank you I I tried loving kindness for a long time and it worked maybe it worked I can't
tell but after a while it doesn't work anymore um
I think I remember talking to somebody I can't remember who I spoke to
she's a part of the IMs community and she had said that
if all that you can do is send loving kindness to yourself for months at end every time you sit
then that's enough and
so it it changes after a while it's like oh I don't actually need it maybe I'll
send it to somebody else and then maybe that doesn't work so yeah I don't know if I just need to like
stick to things and keep trying and yeah
I don't know yeah right I I love and kindness practice I I think I gave a
talk on this not too long ago I'm with you it's not always easy and it's sometimes fun and it feels like a drag
sometimes I went really I'm supposed to be doing this but if there's a way you can find them which it feels uh
and like I said where it's really easy then there's a way that it can be a
little bit uplifting and it creates the conditions in which things can get
metabolized or processed in a different way and we
don't understand or necessarily know what's happening but there is a way that it can really be
portative so just an encouragement I guess okay thank you I'll try it again thank you
okay so there we are at the top of the hour so thank you all for your kind attention and if you'd like I'll stay up
here if I have some questions so thank you and I wish you knew a wonderful rest of
the evening thank you