so good morning and before we officially start at 7 I
want to just appreciate the all of you are here and the names on the and the
locations and just the last one that appears here for me is Abby from Denver
and Zach and Portland and Marie Massachusetts Mikela
High Santa Fe and Mammoth Lakes Kathy a beautiful
place to live in Mammoth Cindy hello from the
Redwoods Jamie hi nice to see your name and
greetings here we go and from Denmark far away Anja
Ana from Florida Henry hi and Boise Rita
hi Los Cabos Mexico hi Al
Alexa and Kathy Mets from Berkeley hi Parisa and it's a lot of names I'm sorry
to skip over just just kind of doing it for Monteray blue
dun Dana Santa Barbara charlesy
hi it's wonderful so my friends it's nice to see you all or well see you see
your names and your
greetings
so good morning good day hello
everyone [Music]
and one of the radical acts in any human life given the state of the world
is to be friends with everyone maybe it's a tall
order but to be friends with the people that we encounter I like to believe that a lot
of what Buddhism Buddhist practice entails is in spite of us being here on
YouTube today that a lot of it is personal a person-to-person
meetings and in those meetings may we be friends with people we encounter we
might not agree with them but we can be friendly and so one of
the people to be friendly with with and towards and is
ourselves and meditation can be understood as a as a deep practice
of friendship towards yourself a continual Act of
friendliness and if that's too high a bar
or at least be safe for oneself at least not be the opposite of a friend and so
what would it be to be a friend with all the complexity of our who we are in our
inner life and our life experiences and our reactions to the world
what is it to cast a wide gaze
upon ourselves such a wide gaze that we can take the whole
in and view the all of it the whole in a friendly
way and one of the purposes of this many purposes is that the attitudes with
which we move through the world
affects our breathing and um that's just a moment affects our
breathing and so to breathe with ease to
breathe in a relaxed gentle way to breathe peacefully
is one of the great experiences of life and to and our attitude affect our
breathing anxiety affects it anger affects it desire affects
it but to be to meet ourselves with friendliness and
safety creates a more relaxed breathing and the easeful
breath in turn nourishes and nurtures
us has a profound impact on ourselves
and perhaps then supports our ability to meet others in a friendly way kind
way so assuming a meditation
posture and giving some care to adjust the
Torso so that there is some space in the chest and the rib cage
around the diaphragm for the breathing to be
unencumbered so sometimes sitting in such a way that the
or laying if you're laying down such a way that the
spine uh is a little bit more
erect especially the upper spine in such a way that the chest
curves outward a little
bit assuming a posture in such a way that the belly is not
scrunched the belly is not restricted
by being curved over into it but kind of an opening up in the air
of the belly concave belly so the belly hangs
forward and has a chance to
relax and maybe also it's possible to roll the shoulders back a little
bit and maybe adjust in the head and the
neck so the back of the neck is maybe a little bit longer than
usual lowering your gaze maybe closing your
eyes
and with as much calm as you can find a calm attitude a calm
approach let your attention roam around your body just taking it in as it
is beginning to having this broad gaze taking in all of who you are in
this body with a calm
attention slowly moving around the
body and then taking a few long slow deep
breaths and as you exhale to
relax the
body letting the breathing return to normal
and calmly and slowly move from the top of your body down through the face shoulders belly
hands legs calmly and slowly move
through relaxing each area as you
exhale
e
for
then calmly and gently bring your attention to your back
rib cage and feel the movements there of
breathing movements of the spine the rib cage the
ribs maybe a subtle lifting or
expanding or if not there maybe the lifting of the shoulders as you
breathe
maybe noticing if there's any movement in the collar bones as you
breathe and how's that movement in the collar bones different when you breathe
in and when you breathe
out and what's the experience of breathing just on the front front rib
cage high up just below the collar bones
maybe an area where there are no muscles that are doing the
breathing the high rib cage just gently moves with breathing in and breathing
out some parts of the body just passively follow
along with the
breathing and then calmly slowly becoming aware of where the
experience of breathing feels most comfortable to feel
in the body maybe movement of the
belly maybe in the area around the diaphragm or solar
plexus the chest the sensations of the air going in
and out through the nostrils wherever it's most
comfortable maybe even
easeful take in the comfort take in the ease
even if it's quite modest let
yourself feel whatever
pleasure however minor there might be as you breathe in and breathe
out
here if there's any tension or pressure in the thinking
mind each time you exhale let that tension melt
soften settle ever so slightly with each
exhale
for
e
for [Music]
for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to to see if you can have a bird's eye view of
yourself and gaze upon it all calmly
peacefully or perhaps a global feeling of the sensations of your
body feeling all of Who You
Are
maybe in the way that you would take in all of a stranger who seemed friendly and safe
and may be in need of
hospitality and so to be your own
host l allowing yourself to be as you
are in a friendly hospitable
way letting yourself to be just who you are as you
are
and now to expand your horizons to the people that you'll be
encountering
today nearby and maybe currently not so close
by and to imagine yourself being a host for them
that your very presence is a presence of hospitality
friendliness and with uh
and as expression of friendship friendliness Wishing Well a
well-wishing a generalized Good
Will May all people that you encounter today that you think about
today may they be happy
may they be safe may they be
peaceful may they breathe
easily May their minds and hearts be calm safe
settled contented may they be free
and may our contact with them support this
possibility may we encounter all beings in a friendly
[Music]
way
thank
you
so hello on this Monday
and I'm sitting here in Redwood City the Insight Meditation Center and delighted
to be in this kind of time
together so for the I I thought over the weekend about
different themes to do for this week uh for this 7 a.m. YouTube
tube and we've been doing this now for a long time many we can say years now
since the beginning of the pandemic and I've done many themes and
uh this weekend and thinking about what to do I couldn't um I thought about different things but
none of them really had a spark for me none of them really were something that I could feel felt like I could come here
and embody or feel a deep heart connection to
so um I think what I'd like to do is to fall back on a certain default that I
that might be interesting for for you since some of you have been listening to me here for a long
time and um do something maybe uncharacteristic and and that is to talk
a little bit about myself maybe some of you'd like to know more about me mostly here in the the 7 a.m.
sittings I talk about the Dharma occasionally I'll mention something autobiographical but um maybe some of
you don't know much about me and might be interesting to hear a little bit and to make it um interesting for
me um I think that uh maybe talk a little bit about the
background uh of my life in a way that brought me to practice and and and
brought me here to IMC and even here now teaching with all of you so I hope that
that's interesting enough to hear this and and feel a little bit apologetic that it's not giving you some specific
Dharma topic to chew on and and uh maybe that'll come out of as I talk to you a
little bit about my life so
um so I came to the Dharma first time
probably first contact with it was when I was probably 11 years
old and um my family my my mother and the father and myself uh my father was
working in Italy at that time and otherwise we had a home in Los
Angeles and uh and we had the summer my father apparently had the summer free
from work and so the decision was to return to Los Angeles um I think with a ticket that
was paid for by his work uh by going uh traveling uh to uh the East and along
the way there we stopped in Thailand and well first we stopped in
India and in the way in India my father um read I was reading a book I think it
was called The Wonder of India and he commented to me that one of the characteristics of Indian religions was
to be very um inclusive that uh somehow all religions
can all the different forms of religion in in India could somehow be held together and seen as you know one big
maybe uh harmonious religious family and
um and I was really inspired by that I but I I I grew up in a non-religious
household um my parents were atheists but they were disinterested atheists it
wasn't like a big deal for them it just um you know it's like a if um you know I
was originally born in Norway and you know they have a Pantheon of Nordic gods
you know like that from a thousand years ago they God Thor and Udin and uh those
never came up in family discussions there were I don't think my family believed in Thor or Udin but it was
never a topic of Interest it just didn't occur to them so in the same way being an atheist was in that kind of way just
didn't occur to talk about something like religion or gods or things like that but uh hearing the statement about
how ecumenical things were inclusive they were in India I was kind of inspired by that Harmony that that
seemed to imply and then we uh went to Thailand
and there I remember seeing the in Bangkok there's a big statue of the reclining Buddha it's gold I don't know
how long it is but it's probably 40t long at least and uh and I remember seeing the
Buddha he's laying it's not just looks like a sleeping Buddha but it's a Buddha uh in the posture in which he died he's
laying down he's laying down on his right side and and the usual statues he's he has one hand underneath his uh
cheek and he's kind of resting on it and um and uh I was inspired by that
statue uh but not religiously I thought oh that's the ideal way of sleeping
sleeping on your right side and so I think that quite a bit then I would that's how I slept kind of inspired by
what I saw in that statue and um when I was 14 the my mother brought a
copy for herself of Herman hess's sidartha I read it and was inspired by
it by the what I felt was the Simplicity and the peace and the non-c contentiousness of uh that life that uh
the Buddha was represented to live in that novel so these things didn't make a big
impression on me um but uh then I think the next big impression was that when I
was 18 I was traveling around Europe by myself and um except for people I would
travel a little bit with a few days and I came to this uh great Cathedral
Monastery called the Mon Mon San Michelle it's on the the uh coast of
Normandy or Britany and it has architecturally it looks a little bit like a Disneyland Palace uh castle
that's rising up on this from this Hilltop at this little island and Rises up with spires up into the
sky and um and I went went through it uh on a tour that they gave and um and we
came to the oldest uh and the whole the whole time there I was spent the night there in the little Island at a Pax
Christie hostel that had a feeling there was like little I'm not like exactly like a cave
but a little ancient feeling kind of stone building where there was a wood table
and wood chairs and we were served bread in the morning like we were you know at
the Last Supper or something and there was a priest there who was very friendly and talked to us and it just felt like
we'd I stepped into it kind of Timeless almost like I was in the monastery
already and then the next morning I went into the tour of the monastery and the monastery had been built around a very
simple one room Stone maybe Cottage or stone Stone Chapel at the very top of
the hill and slowly over the centuries there was added to but as we to took us
through that original Chapel as soon as we stepped into its a cool quiet
peaceful space something in my body shifted and everything got really peaceful and quiet and i' never
experienced this deep peace and quiet and even though the tour kept going I try to linger as long as I could in that
Chapel to feel that that experience and that made a huge
impression on me and maybe that's when uh uh I don't remember that time when I
was a teenager but maybe it was after that that I spent time wondering if um I
could join a Catholic Monastery and become a monk uh even though I was an atheist there was something about the
atmosphere of that life and getting up early and walking around the kind of what I imagined was architecture
peaceful uh place that kind of represented that experience and it was
like that experience I had in the chap app and uh I wanted to have my life kind
of dedicated devoted not to God not to religion but that to that experience of
peace that experience of a deep sense of calm that I had that it felt so healthy
it felt so holistic it felt like this is like some you know I couldn't imagine
anything better than this but I didn't do that I went to college and I went to college during the
Vietnam war and uh I was draftable and uh during that time in the
dorms the first year there was intense debates about war and the Vietnam War
and I was always the extreme pacifist in the discussions and I don't know where my pacifism came from but it was really
clear that I would not fight that that was impossible for me it wasn't like I I could give a good originally I couldn't
give a good philosophical political religious reason for why I would not
fight pick up a gun it just was kind of by disposition impossible for me to do
something like that but then I defended my my um my my
pacifist stance with my friends and um and I uh found myself uh
disturbed by what I discovered about myself and that is that I had the strong
position that involved if necessary to be involved in Civil Disobedience um passive Disobedience to
stand up and protest and and interfere the harm being caused in society and the
world and um and so uh but what I discovered was
that I was afraid to die and I thought that if I take my belief seriously uh I
have to have the same courage as a military soldier who goes into battle I had to be able to put myself In Harm's
Way in order to uh be involved in in protesting or working for a nonviolent
change and um and I I was afraid to die and the
dissonance between what my beliefs were and what I was capable really Disturbed me a lot and that became where I started
to search for some approach some way of living something that would help me deal
with this fear of death so I can live with my ideals and that was when I first kind of
somehow thought about Buddhism that Buddhism had an answer at the same time
I was at U was going to college at University of California of Santa Barbara which is right on the coast and
you can see from the coastline of the University you can look out and see um oil platforms and just before I got
there there was a massive o oil spill on the Santa Barbara beach so that was kind of current and I was
began got interested in um Environmental Studies and I actually became an Environmental Studies major for a
while and uh and first I was going to studying the science of it all and I
felt science uh is not going to solve this problems it's a political issue so I started studying political science and
U that was interesting but uh that uh I thought that's not going to be enough just politics is not going to change
this and in the language of 1973 or so it was a um what needed happen was a
change of Consciousness and that's where I started looking well who where what what what orientation what teachings
what way of life uh can really help us change our Consciousness so that we can
have the change that would really help this world of ours and so then I started
looking around and U and the things that spoke to me the most was Daoism and Buddhism
that seemed to speak to a ra you know radical different way of living in harmony with the world rather than um a
disharmony that over consumes over destroys over um you know
um abuses the world in order to support our lifestyles and um and so that was my
beginning so this thing about uh looking for a solution to the fear of death looking for a solution to social World
ecological issues I began being oriented towards Buddhism and Eastern
religion and um and then I dropped out of college and I'll pick up that story
uh tomorrow so hopefully this is interesting for you and and if it is I'm
very happy to continue telling it thank
you