so good evening uh so I'm Maria
strotman and I'm sitting in for Diane and I'll be here for a couple of more
Mondays um I am uh a retired scientist
businesswoman I've been around IMC since oh I don't know a little over 25 years
and it is a delight to be back here in the in the in the
hall and I feel very strange to actually be here without a mask
tonight but isn't it wonderful so
um I'm going to begin by telling you a story a brief story I was last uh Sunday
well I guess that was yesterday seems sometimes the days seem very long so I was at Stanford mall and I I had just
come out of a a place where my husband and I had brunch and there were these two little blond-headed kids they were
about five or and seven and they came rushing up and they were running around a car playing some kind of Chase me game
and they had pastel clothes on and everything was sunny and their parents
were maybe 20 or 30 feet away and so I immediately looked out to make sure there weren't some cars that were going
to hit them as they were running around this car and thought how bright and sunny everything was and and the thought
arose they're not afraid they're not acting paranoid
they're not worried about whether they're safe they're not aware of their
surroundings they're not looking around they're not listening to bombs fall they
don't feel the noise and the Thunder and the dirt in the air and all
of a sudden everything in that picture became very dark and I felt the stabbing
in my heart and the thoughts of
the and I was very grateful for them that they were able to run around that
car and participate in the sunlight and not be
afraid and I was grateful for me that I could be there watching them run around
that car and and Delight in them running around in that
car and be happy they're not in the Ukraine or Israel or
Gaza and I thought about how that burden is entirely different for so so many
other
children and that led
me to say and I'm here I'm here thinking all these
thoughts I am in touch with just being here thinking these
thoughts and it reminded me of of the beginning of the
dhap all experience is preceded by mind led by
mind made by mind speak or act with a corrupted mind and suffering
follows like the wheels of the cart behind the hose of the ox all experience is preceded by mind
led by mind made by mind speak or act with a peaceful
mind and and happiness follows like a never departing
Shadow he abused me attacked me defeated me robbed me for those carrying on like
this hatred does not end she abused me attacked me defeated me
robbed me for those not carrying on like this hatred
ends hatred never ends through hatred by non-hate alone does it end this is an
ancient truth many do not realize that we here Must Die For for those who
realize this quarrels
end one who recites many teachings but being negligent doesn't act accordingly
like a cow herd counting others cows does not attain the benefits of the
contemplative life one who recites but a few teachings
yet lives according to the Dharma a abandoning passion ill will and
delusion aware and with mind well freed not clinging in this life or the next
attains the benefits of the contemplative
life how how do we live a life of non-h
hatred how do we live a life of of non-h hatred how do we see how do we
live how do we bear the
unbearable it is not my intention to be in any way political
tonight so if you hear anything political be sure it is in your
mind it is not in mine
one of the one of the chief intentions in my life has been to be openhearted
from from the day I first walked in here my intention has been to be openhearted
and I can assure you that 25 years ago or more when I first walked in here that
was not readily available to me the heart was not open the heart was
very much closed and scaled over and protected and
unavailable unavailable and what practice has done
is made it very possible for me to be hurt thinking just the thoughts of the
suffering of those children who I don't even
know and practice has led me to a place where I am eternally grateful for the
practice for the ability to see the possibility of non-h hatred to see the
benefits of a contemplative life to live in the place where it's
possible to open my heart and not be consumed
Med in who's right and who's wrong and who's we and who's
they I'm going to read you another story yesterday um Gil gave a talk on
non-harming if you didn't hear it I really recommend that you listen to it and he was he was also very careful to
talk about non-harming and not about what you ought to do and the
interesting thing about the way he spoke about non-harming was that it really had to do with action he took the point of
view of action and my intent is is very much
parallel to what he had to say but I want to come from the place of
what do you hold in your heart because what you hold in your heart is what you will produce in the world
world what you hold in your heart is the condition for the next moment it is the
condition that the Mind uses to create the next moment it precedes leads and
makes your experience what you hold in your
heart so this is uh this book is a book of poems by Naomi shihab naai she is um a
poet who lives in uh San Antonio Texas she is half Palestinian her father is
Palestinian and uh half
Latina so this this story is a story about her
son see if I can hold it here it's right in front but sometimes I can't find it
and it's titled someone I love someone I love so someone I love so much cut down my
Primrose patch it looked like an oval of of overgrown weeds to him in the front yard
near the Black Mailbox on the post he did not know that for weeks i' had been
carefully tending and watering it as a few primroses floated their pink heads
above the green Mass unfurled their delicate bonnets with dozens of buds waiting to shine we were on the brink
everything popping open despite the headlines all sweet flower beings from under the ground remembering
what they were supposed to do he mowed it down with the old push lawn mower I
was out of town he didn't ask his father who knew how precious it was to me his
father was in the back while this was happening and didn't see there wasn't a second thought why would we have had
such a tall patch in the yard what does my mother do when she comes out here with the old shovel in the butt bucket
in the mysterious sacks of Rose food food in her pocket bending to the wild tangle of Jasmine on the fence the
Dutchman's pipe the happy oregano the funny cacti crowded together in
complicated profusion like a family the miniature chilies what does she do why
is this here he just cut it down it wasn't easy
he must have pushed really hard to get it to go when I stood outside in my nighty the
next dreamy sweet morning at dawn after returning home on the midnight plane watering my blue bonnet Snap Dragons
butterfly bush Lantana wanting to feel tied to Earth again as I always do when
I get home rooted in soil and stone and old the kishan bamboo and trees a 100
Years of memory in their trunks and bushes we didn't plant and the healthy esparanza never losing her hope and the
banana Palm just poking out their fine and gracious greeny Greenery when
suddenly I saw what was gone what wasn't there not there impossible I was so
shocked I let the hose run all over my bare feet the cold stun of Fury filled me
sorrow rising and pouring into questions who could do this why how could
anyone I thought of the time my daddy came home to find every head cut off his
giant sunflowers right after they had opened their faces to the sky only the
empty stocks remaining his disbelieving sorrow as he went to his rooms and laid
down on the bed and closed his eyes and thought I will not mention this I am too
sad to mention it this is the pain of people everywhere the pain this year
deserves but at breakfast I went a little strange like the a lady down the street who shows up at people's doors
with a snarling dog and a hammer in her pocket I went wild and Furious and he
swore they just looked like weeds to him why hadn't I warned him why did I only tell
Dad I pointed them out to you weeks ago I said he said I don't remember flower
things like that and it was the season of blooming and
understanding it was the season of hiding from headlines wondering what I would do if the whole house had been
erased or just the books and paintings or what about the whole Reckless Garden
or then it gets Unthinkable but we take ourselves we let ourselves think it now and then to stay human the child's arms
or legs what would I do if I did not love him who could I
become if I did not love him who could I become
if I if I don't allow myself to love who could I
become if I don't allow myself to feel who could I
become if I callous my heart over and say those
people who could I become how filled with hate could I
be how righteous and angry could I really
become the answer is pretty righteous and
angry and it's a little
frightening we are always all the time becoming something know we like to think
that we are something I'm this person I'm that kind of person I want to be that kind of person I'm going to be
better I'm going to be but the truth is we're always
becoming we're always different than we were but we're never who we think we
need to be or what we want to be we're always just this person this person that shows up in this
moment that is created by Our intention and what we hold in our
hearts which makes what we hold in our hearts really important really important
because all of life is a becoming it is a process breathing is a
process thinking is a process we are not nouns we're
verbs we're verbs we we're we're action we're
happening we're not finished
products so how can we respond how can we respond when what we
see is not what we want to see
how can we call for and demand Justice we
Americans when we can't even pass we we have a totally dysfunctional House of Representatives because we can't even
vote for a speaker really we can't we can't pass any laws because we can't agree age on
who's going to be in charge which is about power and not leadership anyway I mean that what is this
about we can't seem to do that and before you say well I'm not those people
right away you hear those people in me it's that division of that that we
that we buy into of those people and we that somehow we have to break we have to
break that cycle of putting other people in some giant box where they're all the
same there are those people and they're my people and me and we're all like this
and they're all like that which we know isn't even true we know that but the
emotional connections that we make around usually just one
thing that varies what that one thing is and all of those people are those
people people and my people are over
here we even do that within
ourselves there's there's that person that I don't really like and then you
know there's this ideal person that you know someday I'm going to be and we get consumed with
self-criticism and and non-acceptance of oneself and anxiety over who we're
not so the truth is nonh hatred really doesn't begin on a global scale it
really begins right here in our own hearts in the way we meet every moment
in the way we meet the news that we
hear just before I left home my husband and I for some crazy reason
were watching CNN and you know all of the particular
Talking Heads were talking about the war in Israel primarily and
uh I bet it wasn't uh 30 seconds in before I was in
tears and I thought well you know buck up here can't be crying you
got to be ready to meet the world and I said no no I want to meet the world with
that heart I want to meet the world with someone in 30 seconds can cry because
this is too painful I want to meet the world with
that person because there are different kinds of pain you know there's physical pain
there's psychological pain there's emotional pain and and what is pain you know pain
isn't a now nether it's it's it's another one of those processes it's it's a concept pain is a concept and it's a
signal something needs to be paid attention to something needs to be paid attention
to and how we meet that pain what do we what do we do with that pain do are we
do do we resist that pain do we say no well usually what that does is just
get make the pain stronger in some
way you the the people who research pain at Stanford have discovered that there
are two neuros circuits associated with pain one is the physical reactive
circuit where the physically you react to whatever uh or the body physiologically reacts to
whatever the source of pain is the physical Source but there's also an emotional neurocircuit associated with
every pain you know if you slam your hand
there's an emotional neurocircuit connected with that well that's kind of interesting so
when you when you think about that you realize that there is always some minor or very large
emotional compound component to every pain that you
experience so the question how am I every time you experience pain is a
very useful question it turns out the answer to what
do I do in the to respond to what is unbearable is exactly what the Buddha
said you do to avoid all suffering to put an end to
suffering you establish mindfulness he didn't say you sit down and meditate
although he advises that that's a good way to establish mindfulness he says establish
mindfulness establish mindfulness there are four things you know mindfulness of
the body mindfulness of of emotions mindfulness of the Mind mindfulness of
Dharma establish mindfulness here I am there's pain I'm sitting here
watching TV I'm disturbed by this it's hurtful for me establish know that
you're here know that this is happening don't just gloss it over or try to get rid of the pain know that it's here see
it because in seeing it you're better able to say I see
things clearly here I see what's happening here I understand what's happening here it leads to understanding
you're less likely to misinterpret the emotional content of what you're
seeing you're more likely to get to the place where you begin to trust
yourself which to me has been one of the most important an benefits of my
practice after 25 years that I am beginning to trust
myself Hallelujah who
knew I get these uh I don't know how often they come actually I get so many
emails that it's better if I don't know how often some of them come I had I was
recently on a 3-week retreat and I came back to 1,500
emails and I finally got through them after two weeks but one of them that I found was
one from Jack cornfield and this is a little brief present uh piece
of one that was in the last few days actually mindfulness is the means by
which we can bring our full caring presence to the
world with balance and understanding we can experience gain and loss Pleasure
and Pain War and Peace the joys and Sorrows that make up human
life the open and compassionate attention of mindfulness liberates us from reacting to and being caught by all
things in the world instead we offer the world our peaceful heart we we respond
with care and courage and in doing so we embody the
presence and Liberation we wish for all sometimes this is called
mindfulness sometimes it's called love that's his
quote mindfulness is the means by which we can bring our full caring presence to
the world full caring presence so it's
another way of describing just what I began with with the dhap the opening of
the dhap if all experience is led by the Mind heart mind here if we think of it
as heart mind then showing up becomes an
act of mindfulness of Faith Of Love of caring for ourselves and the
world showing up just as we are not the ideal us but just showing up as us
that's what presence is it's showing up and knowing that we're
there who who is here I'm not over there I'm right here
this person Maria is here and she's had a really weird day
she so some of the things have been you know good and some of the things have been kind of
weird and here she is fairly stable fairly stable
mind and knowing that I am here on this DS and I'm speaking with
you and I see you and I register I am here speaking with
you and I'm aware that you are here it's not complicated the
mindfulness doesn't have to be intense or psychologically clear I just have to know what it is I'm here with
you and what am I feeling how am I feeling those who well I'm stable I'm a
little shaky about that not so good about this I'm pretty good about
that we grow to understand the difference between the triggers that set us off thinking about something that
isn't that takes us away from this moment into the past of the
future the difference between triggers and signals pain is here oh no not again
this is the same as last time I thought this was over and off we're we're we're off doing something else with the
mind and or pain okay do I need to move
oh this is a about oh yeah it hurts it hurts to be open to this I get
it totally different or I can say oh that makes me
so angry anger is here but it isn't me I
can just see anger I can put it up here and and okay anger is going to be over here in the left hand corner of my
visual anger is here I got it got it I'm just not going to spend all
my attention there because it hurts when I'm angry it hurts when I'm angry and I
don't particularly like that yeah but I'm still angry well okay just sit there for a
minute and I'm going to look outside at this oak
tree or I'm going to notice this tape going down here is kind of crooked wonder who believe that tape down that's
interesting look it's the same color as that air freshener all of a sudden the anger doesn't have
as much power still there just not as much power I don't have to become as
entangled in it I can see it it's just seeing
it knowing what kind of pain is there seeing what the pain is I don't have to
be different I don't have to not have any
triggers the there's a there's a book uh called
lessons in chemistry I don't know if any of you have read this book but it it is
it's a novel uh have any of you read it yeah okay I love this book it's about a
woman chemist who runs a fowl of her male advisors and you know of course she
gets fired and she's brilliant right and she ends up teaching uh uh cooking on television but
she treats the women who are taking this class with a great deal of respect and you know some of them go off and become
microbiologists and stuff but apple is doing uh a series of
this book and the first it just started this weekend so of course I'm watching it because I loved this book because I
totally identified with this woman and she gets triggered this this
scientist and watching this happen and watching my own reactions and seeing the
trigger come up in me and go you know but I did a lot of work that that
trigger doesn't trigger me anymore and I could sit there and just
go wow
wow wow and the pleasure that came from just not being
entangled with that Ang anger
anymore is just unspeakably wonderful took a long
time took a long
time so the question is how do you meet pain well you don't know if you don't
watch it if you constantly try to get away from it you don't have to analyze
the pain dig into it you know there are lots of people who give you instructions about sitting with the pain and you know
becoming befriending you don't have to befriended just know it's there figure it out watch it see how you react to it
what kinds of pain do you react to so that you know yourself so you know
how that works so that it doesn't hold you it doesn't tangle you
up so that you're free of entanglement so that you're free and then you can trust yourself and
you can trust your heart to be
open it's always a good idea to check whether today's pain is associated with
the present the past or the future that's how you recognize a
trigger or you know something that leads you into the fantasy ideal self of the future
kind of just look at that what happens is we slowly develop
Faith or confidence call it confidence we slowly develop
confidence and confidence leads to ma to to more effort and effort leads to more
mindfulness it's it's really it's a wonderful Circle and mindfulness then
leads to a a steady stable mind which
Sade and then you begin to understand things as they are it leads to
wisdom which leads to confidence which leads to more effort it feeds
itself these are the benefits of a contemplative life
I brought with me I couldn't decide so now I've decided what poem am
going to read you this poem is by uh aah leemon who is a current poet Laur
laurate and this was written to her poetry students I'm sure it's called the
end of poetry but it actually fits the life of a mindfulness student like
me enough of OAS and chicky and sunflower and snowshoes Maple and seeds
Samara and CH enough carcuro enough of
thus and prophecy and the sto farmer and faith and our father and Tis of Thee
enough of bosom and Bud skin and God and not forgetting and star bodies and
Frozen Birds enough of the will to go on and not go on or how a certain light
does a certain thing enough of the kneeling and the rising and the looking Inward and the looking up enough of the
gun the drama and the acquaintances suicide the long lost letter on the dresser enough of the long and the ego
and the obliteration of ego enough of the mother and the child and the father and the child and enough of the pointing
to the world weary and desperate enough of the brutal and the Border enough of
can you see me can you hear me enough I am human enough I'm alone and I am
desperate enough of the animals saving me enough of the high water enough of
the sorrow enough of the air in its ease I am asking you
to touch
me don't talk about all the high ideals and all the things you want to achieve
and all of the concepts of the worlds and the the things that you want to
believe allow yourself to be
touched that's the home of non-h hatred allow yourself to be
touched those are my thoughts thank
you does anybody have any comments or questions [Music]
or complaints yes do we have a microphone
here
yeah I um you may have to yeah turn it
down when the microphone is you it's is it okay now that's good great I um I I
was in progressive radio and I've always been
I um
a news freak and a political junkie and I'm having a diff
very and I haven't even for me not to turn on the news every day is just it's unheard
of and I I haven't turn the news on in the last three or four days because I can't deal with
it I feel like I'm uh and I'm a very sensitive man and I I feel like I'm
living in an uncivilized world I love children and when I heard what
they were doing to the children I'm very easy to cry like you I
I just I I can't I don't know how to deal with it and you know your your reading
tonight was wonderful but I just it's just so hard it's so hard to be present and deal
with this and how do you do that how do you do that I mean it's just so far
removed D from what I am you know and it's just I'm having a difficult time I
really am and and I uh I don't know how everyone else feels but
um this craziness is just it's I don't know how it's going to stop but
um there is um there is no question
that um it is crazy and that there is brutality in the
world and I will not defend it ever and
uh and I also know
that if if we point to
anyone they can point
back there are no Heroes they're no Heroes right
now uh I read a couple of days ago that that the US had appointed a former mid
East expert whose name unfortunately I don't remember uh as a
humanitarian Aid Ambassador sent him off to the Middle East and I thought well at
least were appointing somebody that besides sending the warships you know
and uh and The Invasion That was supposed to happen two days ago hasn't happened yet which is probably because
they don't know how to deal with the underground tunnels and um Biden is going to uh Israel on Wednesday and you
know it's it's like things are moving but the last number I saw of
children that were killed on both sides was 749
children for what for for craziness for for making a
political Point nobody was served by this nobody
was served and
um nobody will be served by an Invasion
either one of one of the things that that Gil talked about somebody asked him a question at the end about well you
know what do you think about this I I don't remember exactly the nature of the question and he referred to tikot Han
and and the this what he referred to is written in up in tikn Han's
book being peace and the uh tikn Han was uh in
Vietnam and and supportting both North and South Vietnam peoples and refused to take sides and so
he wasn't trusted by anybody and his monks were called killed by
both uh but he refused to take sides and what gilded yesterday was neither take sides
or not take sides he basically said I I
just I just want to talk about non-harming
and where we find ourselves is in dealing with the
unforgivable how do you keep yourself from developing
hate so the approach I took was I'm not going to solve this by
choosing somebody to blame and so what I can do is come
here and talk to you about keeping your heart
open that that when you make a one degree
turn it looks like nothing until you get far enough
out you know that's all I can say about it it is
not
uh yeah I think next week I'll talk about
forgiveness yes I don't interrup anybody else wait we we do need to get the um
microphone I think yeah anyone else something to say I really
don't want to interrupt that I just have a little comment at the end thank you H anybody
else anybody else com okay should com first no you
do no I just wanted to and I just came from Costco and they do have the book
I'm sorry Costco has the book oh it's I know we should be supporting independent book sellers but it's 19 something he
had a few copies so anybody wants to get it lessons in chemistry the being oh lessons in chemistry yeah not that no
lessons in chemistry sorry yeah the book I talked about before or
take chemistry lessons in chemistry lessons in chemistry
yeah okay
so I didn't want to talk about myself but Maria it's fantastic to see you I've
been coming here um it got to be on and off till I moved to Half Moon Bay and then now I'm doing coipasa but since um
about 2005 and this place has really helped me get a lot
better so when I first heard what was happening it just smashed me down but I
feel a lot better now and and it's cuz I'm doing something
that I I'm hoping will make some kind of a difference so if anyone is interested
I just so happen to have some little Flyers that are giving people details
about a a legislative effort that just started today and it's a ceasefire
resolution and more Congress persons have signed it and if anyone has an
interest on the issue especially for folks who live in
paloalto we could you know call her email her visit her office on Emerson
all that information is here okay please talk after the after the talk okay yes
so she clearly has everything you need so thank you you're welcome I'm going to read something that ends with hope that
was the other alternative so this is also by Naomi shihab naab and it's called Uh shihab n it's called wandering
around Albuquerque uh Airport terminal after learning my flight was
detained 4 hours I heard the announcement if anyone in the vicinity of gate 4A understands Arabic please
come to the gate immediately well one pauses these days gate 4A was my own
gate I went there an older woman in full traditional Palestinian dress just like
my grandma wore was crumpled to the floor wailing loudly help said the flight service
person talk to her what's her problem we told her the flight was going to be 4 hours late and she did this I put my arm
around her and spoke to her
haltingly sewe the minute she heard any word she knew however poorly used excuse
me she stopped crying she thought our flight had been cancelled entirely she
needed to be in El Paso for some major medical treatment the following day I said no no we're fine you'll get
there just late who's picking you up let's call him and tell him we called her son and I spoke to him in English I
told him I would stay with his mother till we got on the plane and would ride next to her Southwest she talked to him then we
called her other Sons just for the fun of it then we called my dad and he spoke to her for a while and Arabic and found
out of course they had 10 shared friends then I thought just for the heck of it why not call some Palestinian poets I
know and let them chat with her this all took about two hours she was laughing a lot by then telling about her life
answering questions she had pulled a sack of homemade mimu cookies little powdered sugar crumbly Mounds stuffed
with dates and nuts out of her bag and was offering them to all the women at the gate to my amazement not a single woman
declined one it was like a Sacrament The Traveler from Argentina The Traveler from California the lovely woman from
Laredo we were all covered with the same powdered sugar and smiling there are no
better cookies then the airline broke out the free beverages from huge coolers non-alcoholic and two little girls on
our flight one African-American one Mexican-American ran around serving us all apple juice and lemonade and they
were covered with powdered sugar too and I noticed my new best friend by now we were holding hand hands had a potted
plant poking out of her bag some medicinal thing with green furry leaves such an old country traveling tradition
always carry a plant always stay rooted to somewhere and I looked around that
gate of late and weary ones and thought this is the world I want to live in the
shared world not a single person at this gate once the crying of confusion
stopped has seemed apprehensive about any other person they took the cookies I
wanted to hug all those other women too this can still happen anywhere not
everything is lost thank you
all may you all enjoy a warm open
heart