you're welcome through our meditation time and welcome
all of us together into this meditation community
thank you for being here and to offer thanks to for all of us
being here in a certain kind of way I'm thank myself for being here
can be uh could arise from a deep appreciation
of each other what we're here for our potential
our goodness it's a it can be a very profound thing to be
grateful and gratefulness at the heart in the heart at the heart of it
doesn't have to be something that is contrived or
something that's obligated or something that we plan and intend to have it's just a welling up that happens from
deep inside a deep appreciation and deep valuing and
and um and thankfulness and I say this because
uh desire in Buddhism has often had a negative reputation
and the most extreme version is that the desires the cause of suffering and we
need to let go of all desires and this is a misunderstanding of the
Buddhist teaching there are certain desires which are problematic certain desires which cause
a tremendous amount of suffering it tends to be the desires to have a lot of attachment clinging to him compulsion
with them so that's sometimes called craving clinging grasping
there are other kinds of desires that well up from deep inside
that have nothing to do with clinging craving grasping nothing to do with obligation nothing to do with
you know logically kind of putting things together and constructing a
desire to have and one word for that that I like is
aspiration we can have and partly I like the word
aspiration because it's related to the English word respiration and so
um to aspiration Aspire aspiration kind of means to breathe out
when we eat when the breathing is most easy when we have an ease full breath
then what is the heart's deepest wish what's the deepest source of
um desire what to be most what do we most want when we're most quiet we're most contented most satisfied
we're not afraid we're taken care of we're settled there's no biological needs
there's maybe no social needs at the moment and things are just settled and taken
care of in a certain way or been put aside what is the heart's deepest wish
the aspiration and it's from that place that the Dharma
practice the intention to practice Dharma can be it's that place where compassion can
arise from and that is to be respected and that is to be loved it can be loved it is love
that is delighted it's it's a comes from some kind of profundity and beauty
and that supports meditation practice that if you can sit quietly and calmly
enough to hear the quiet Voice or the quiet impulse
of the heart's deepest kind of aspiration free of clinging free of need free of
compensation and I feel the heart's desire for
Freedom the heart's desire for real presence the heart's desire to be awake to be
aware to be here and let that be the motivation for practice to let that
be kind of the support that kind of
Parts the Waters of distractions parts of the Waters of
preoccupation and fantasy and thoughts so we stay on course we stay right here
present so assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes
and then taking a few deeper breaths
and as you breathe in to prepare yourself in the inhale to let go on the exhale to release and
relax the body
and sometimes it's possible to relax more deeply if we hold our breath just for two three
seconds maybe first hold it at the top of the inhale top of the exhale and then the end of
the exhale hold the breath a little bit feel your body and then this like almost like a space
that's been created to let the body relax more
by holding your breath for two or three seconds you might also feel the gentle
wish of the body to breathe in to breathe out that you can
give into allow to happen
and then to let your breathing return to normal
continue for a few moments to relax deeply
the face the shoulders the belly
and almost as if with your awareness you can reach inside to touch
the deepest place inside of you that you know to gently reach in touch that depth
and let it relax soften the deepest place within
and in whatever deepest place that's accessible to you can you find there
the aspiration the wish that motivates your meditation practice
maybe there's even a physical embodied Association sensation
with that wish that motivation
and then having the impulse to be present to be mindful
who did it settled in your aspiration
arising from your aspiration that keeps you steady the breathing with
the mindfulness as if you're gently parting the Waters
of Destruction and thought anything that takes you away
is gently gently Falls away
or evaporates away with the strength and warmth of your aspiration to practice
foreign
mindfulness supported by a deep aspiration
a deep sense of importance and purpose
where aspiration is the foundation
aspiration instead of Destruction
foreign
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to relax deeply again a few rounds of breathing and relaxing
maybe there's a way of a deeper relaxation
at the heart of your being
relaxing anyway you're bracing yourself or
or leaning ahead of yourself
and letting the attention drop deep inside
what is your deepest Dharma wish what's your deepest wish
related to meditation to mindfulness to Buddhist practice
and there might not be a conceptual answer
it might be the answer might be more in a feeling or a sensation
something that brings along a yes yes this is right
this is good
and from whatever depth of aspiration that you know you can have
take in the suffering of the world but take it in not as your own
take it in as something that you will hold or care for or
not put it in the in your heart so that it hurts
but it put it in the softness of your hands of your awareness here let me hold the suffering of the
world for a little bit not taking it on
not having to do anything about it to just welcome it here into the softness of a
cupped hands or cupped hands of awareness
and gazing upon the suffering of the world
is there that the place of aspiration of care
kindness is or that is there kindness care
compassion a deep wish May the suffering of the world
be alleviated may this suffering that I witness and
know May beings be free of it
and may I and maybe my small way may I contribute to that
so that together as a community as a Global Community the whole world
may all of us contribute to the welfare and happiness of each other
may all of us
hold each other tenderly so their space for the heart's deepest
wish of care may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you
so today I'll talk about the fourth element of compassion
aspiration and this is kind of one of the kind of really core elements of compassion kind
of what really begins to have compassion take shape take form
then that is the wish for uh others to not suffer
the the aspiration that the suffering of the world
be be be remedied be fixed alleviated
and um and I use the word aspiration purposely because it's not a very
commonly used word I believe different than desire different than wish
has a lot of associations and and part of the associations is the associations
of obligation that we should there could be a sense of of with it
with a desire the desire to you know to help someone there can be a lot of self
self baggage around self and success and being seen being appreciated being a
good person showing that we're a good person all kinds of things come along with that
but aspiration has for me a sense of arising something deep inside
that we Aspire for something but it's held very lightly there's no attachment
or clinging it's uh but just the aspiration is very simple and because it has the word aspiration
is related to the word breathing it's related to the word like respiration has to do in Latin with to breathe
um and um I think of it I think I think Latin literally means something like to breathe out
and but to breathe easily to have a relaxed easy comfortable breathing where
there's no uh the breathing is not engaged you know tightened up and faster
and bigger in order to run or to fight or to get a job done or something or to
protect oneself everything is kind of soft and relaxed so there's in that easy
breathing there's room for this easy aspiration to arise
and to have this aspiration to alleviate to support people on their suffering to
alleviate the suffering or to care for them in their suffering to have it come from such a place is precious
that's what makes karuna the compassion of Buddhism sweet kind of a pleasure to
it and um and uh and it just makes it kind of a source of Happiness just because
the feeling comes such a good deep place inside but we're I'm introducing this now on
the fourth day of these five elements because each of the previous three are
setting the stage for allowing the Simplicity of aspiration to come
in in often in in the world when people talk about compassion many people
recognize it as a wonderful and inspiring ideal but very few people have a really clear
sense of what it is in its simplicity there can be a lot of it's kind of a
general it's a vague idea and that can come with idea yes we want
to feel people suffering we want to uh you know have empathy for them feel
their self we don't feel their suffering and want to go out there and help them but with if that's not done carefully
the feeling other people's suffering could just make us miserable and if we're not doing carefully wanting
to support help someone can come along with a lot of complicated desires and attachments and confusion
so to begin this by being aware where we're present for the people in
the world but we're not entangled with our thoughts we're not like
proliferating thoughts and memories and Fantasies and expectations and and
selves and me and you there's something very grounded and simple in the awareness that is going to then begin to
take in another person others and then to um
when we're with someone who's suffering to find out how to be attuned to them how to be in harmony with them it's so
easy to lose Harmony if we have a headlong rush into caring for them fixing them and having the I need to
help I need to fix them I have to I one of the most complicated things is to feel responsible for the suffering of
others but to be attuned to the suffering to find a sense of Harmony that's very
contextually situated that takes oneself one's personal situation to account to
others so we don't lose ourselves we don't give ourselves up in the contact with others but we attune
ourselves to what's happening and then to appreciate and respect others respect ourselves
we don't respect people if we're trying to fix them we don't respect their
autonomy if we take responsibility for their suffering we don't respect and appreciate other
people if we take too much the notion of being I'm the helper I'm I'm like
a little bit Superior I'm the person who kind of knows it all or I'm capable to do it and I'm going to take care of you
who doesn't know what to do and can't know what to do and and so it's a little bit condescending even that you have
helping sometimes so to have this respect and appreciation
of others then when we encounter suffering then
maybe we allow for this deeper aspiration to arise it's one of the most beautiful things
that a human being love care kindness that is an aspiration
that arises from the depth of Who We Are that has no pressure in it
it has no assertiveness in it no hurry in it
no requirement in it and no obligation
but it's the it's the it's the warmth it's the glow it's the it's the calling
it's the maybe yearning or deep kind of deep
desire that we have and this is one of the beautiful things to be able to discover
this deeper deeper desire we are human
desirlings desire is an intimate and integral part of Who We Are
and to discover how these desires benefit us fill us with goodness fill us
with a sense of wonderful vitality and animation
um that is a wonderful thing and we're not supposed to give up all
desire and be deflated and but this deeper deeper place it's almost comes from a place or does come
from a place where there's no ego no conceit no
locking into an identity this is who I am this is who I have to be no fixed
identity that we hold on to it's it's deeper than any identity we can have
um this deeper place this Wellspring and um and so there's compassionate wish
that others not suffer and uh I've been the recipient of that
this is where someone didn't actually help me but I felt their wish their their
compassionate kind of care and recognition of my suffering and they're um and they're kind of a
good feel that they there they wanted it to be different for me and that was their wish but
um there was this kind of beautiful love that just feeling that from that person changed my life this is when I was quite
young and being with a Buddhist teacher a young teacher Rebecca Zen priest and
uh in my suffering feeling this beautiful clear simple thin field uh put
on put put upon I didn't feel like I feel the person who maybe would have helped if it was appropriate
but it was just this this um this simple beautiful aspiration this
wish that kind of resonated with me or it um there was an Attunement that
really kind of um I felt touched by that Attunement
so to so this is the kind of in since the beginning or the heart of of compassion
is a desire and to become wise about desire and to know the difference between desire which
is neurotic desire which is obligation desire which is forced with assertive
desire that comes along with fear desire that comes along with desperation all
those fall fall away the The
Parting of the water and this beautiful deeper place of aspiration
and um and uh and then one other part of the
art of this whole kind of karuna deeper as compassion is learning to trust
that that's okay to learning to trust that yes
it's okay to have a deep desire for the welfare of others
that doesn't come with anger doesn't come with desperation doesn't come with force and obligation doesn't come with
the kind of an of a uh kind of the clinging or the drive the compulsion I
have to fix it I have to do it it's up to me
it comes from a very different place comes from some place that feels yes
yes if I can if it's in front of me if it's possible
from this place of freedom from this place of deep
heartfeltness I will now consider acting and doing
something if I can or what can I do and that's a topic for tomorrow action
and how can action also have these qualities of this depth that I'm talking
about today where aspiration comes from how can action have some of these qualities of non-attachment and
non-assertiveness and non-clinging so
awareness Attunement appreciation aspiration and then tomorrow we'll do
action that which completes kind of the the five different aspects or elements that
make this karuna in Buddhism so thank you and um
forward to tomorrow