there hello welcome everyone to happy hour
it's lovely to be with you makes me happy to come together in this way and
also greetings to everyone not just on Zoom but also on YouTube for joining us
as well as on Audio Dharma folks who will be joining us later um
if not in time but asynchronously so so for today's
practice I wanted to um offer a quote from
Lynn twist Lynn twist is the author of a
wonderful book called The Soul of money if you're not familiar with this book
The Soul of money by Lynn l-y-n-n and E twist t-w-i-s-t
just a lovely book and um and there is a quote from it and many wonderful quotes
but the one that I wanted to share for us as the inspiration for our practice
and we've we've worked with the theme of enoughness many times before and just the sense of
scarcity versus enoughness and and this quote from her really
um Nails it so here we go
um for me and for many of us our first Awakening thought of the day is quote I
didn't get enough sleep the next one is I don't have enough time
whether true or not that thought of not enough occurs to us automatically
before we even think or question you could think two question or examine it
we spend most of the hours and the Days of Our Lives hearing explaining
complaining or worrying about what we don't have enough of we don't have
enough exercise we don't have enough work we don't have enough profits we don't have enough power we don't have
enough Wilderness we don't have enough weekends of course we don't have enough money ever
we're not thin enough we're not smart enough we're not pretty enough or fit
enough or educated or sex successful enough or Rich enough ever before we
even sit up in bed before our feet touch the floor we're already inadequate
already behind already losing already lacking something and by the time we go
to bed at night our minds race with a Litany of what we didn't get
or didn't get done that day we go to sleep burdened by those thoughts and
wake up to the reverie of lack what begins as a simple expression of the
hurried life or even the challenge to life grows into the great justification for an
unfulfilled life here's the the last part of it this
internal condition of scarcity this mind said of scarcity lives at the very heart
of our jealousies our greed our prejudices and our arguments with
life quite profound and
um and I appreciate in some ways maybe we see
some of our attitudes in some of what she says maybe not in everything or maybe in all of it
um but there is this sense of scarcity the sense of lack
um that I know too when I go to bed some at night oh okay I got this done great
great their sense of you know I tried to remind myself of of the the beautiful things in the day and of course there's
a there's a sense of I didn't get that done and that done but usually I try to turn towards what's what's good what
what were the gifts of the day what what I'm grateful for and yet I think I for
me as I read this like I had the sense of oh yeah this this sense of not enough and it's not enough time not enough this
not enough that so I wanted to bring it in for your consideration if you identify with any aspects of this not
enoughness and how can we turn our minds turn our minds from scarcity to to
enoughness what actually we have plenty of what there is good what what good
there is in our lives already the sense of plentifulness already here the time
we have the resources we have the goodness we have the love we have what
is already here so that is the invitation for for today's practice
so with that let's land our bodies and meditate together
so arriving arriving arriving in this body arriving in this
moment
and what if we arrive with a sense of enoughness whatever has been accomplished or or not
but today whatever there is or isn't
whatever is happening in this body
how do we turn into enoughness
however the conditions are can we tune into the enoughness In This
Moment and to the perfection in this moment
not into what's lacking but what is good what is plentiful
so let's start with our bodies
feeling our feet on the Earth
gravity is enough it's reliable
we never think of that do we yes gravity thank you
feeling our bottom on the seat on the chair the cushion
the sitting here is enough it's plenty
it's wonderful it's awesome
the fact that we can do this could sit and be breathed
with as much health as there is available in this moment it's enough
it's enough it's plenty
to appreciate what is with every breath feel grounded in our body with every
breath just this
give thanks in our hearts for what is here already
we usually don't notice
appreciating opening senses with calm with
with peace with gratitude the spaciousness and peace there is
already there's so much peace inside we just keep staring it up
and we appreciate this breath his body however
it's showing up right now
recounting the goodness of having been able to eat today
breathe Digest
have as many organs working functioning
so many sight hearing
smelling tasting touching cognizing
and if your body's enough parts of the body are
peaceful without pain appreciating appreciating this
wonderful
and appreciating welcoming some blessings in your life
maybe loved ones friends relationships
colleagues bringing them too hard for a moment
maybe one being or a group your choice
letting it fill your heart the goodness of it
creating your wealth such wealth
imagine if this person is being this group was not part of your life for a moment
how empty perhaps how challenging it would be and now
bring back feel the wealth of their presence
plentitude
plenty fullness of this gift
let your heart relish it
ways in which this relationship nourishes you
because you're happy comforts you perhaps maybe even challenges you in some ways to grow
unspeakable wealth
and stay with this being if you wish or you can open up if you like to
to invite another blessing in your life
for a moment imagine your life without it
and then bring it back in it's here wow what a blessing
let your heart relish with gratitude the joy blessing of this gift
let yourself say thank you
Hallelujah
stay with this if you were sure he can invite another blessing into your life
something that brings you Joy
imagine your life without it first
it's appeared not here anymore
and now bring it back it is here part of your life
continuing to support you nourish you bring you Joy
let your heart rejoice in its goodness
stay with this or invite another aspect Another Blessing in your life
you know the drill imagine your life without this never happened it's not here
and then bring it back it is here this blessing
let your heart celebrate with gratitude with appreciation
kiss the Earth for your good fortune
let this practice be a celebration of all the gifts you have
physical emotional relational
opportunities
whatever it might be
physical gifts mental gifts our body and your life
relationships knowledge
skills values
may be celebrating this positions thank heavens I'm curious
I have this gift of curiosity or whatever else it might be humility kindness
good with words
whatever it might be imagine wasn't here
and appreciate that it is
or no and stay with this of course
and if you wish try on something a little more
exploratory you don't have to use the invitation
you can always go back to the previous invitation no invitation is bring to your heart to
your mind your body and area of life that you often perhaps without
questioning your mind goes to not enough scarcity not enough
feel that in your body not enough
you know what it feels like this not enoughness in the body this lack sense of lack
physically ah now let it go let go
perhaps explore invite creative ways
the sea to shift the perspective
to see the Plenty plenty the blessing
the goodness that's already here
that's present it's not just the lack don't look at your life through a straw
I only see lack picked a straw away
what is here already
there is so much fear already so much
so much
we feel scarcity we feel greedy we want more and more and more
ouch
return ah is what's here so much is here
calm peace generosity
release through our hearts release
into peace and abundance
there is so much here so much in this life already so much
so many gifts
earn your fullness your abundance
as we bring this meditation to a close
let us rejoice celebrate in the goodness
the goodness of seeing goodness
the goodness of seeing fullness our gifts our blessings
so our hearts feel full generous abundant towards ourselves and
everyone else such a beautiful place to live from to
live out of with intentionality
may all beings may all beings everywhere
no truly no appreciate their goodness Their Blessings
may all beings everywhere including ourselves be well and be free
it's everyone thanks for your practice today
so so tonight we turned towards the practice of knowing our goodness
knowing appreciating the blessings and the
practice we did was bring blessings to mind First Imagine our life without them
they're not here and then bring them back and really appreciate the sense of fullness
and living from this place really appreciate turning our minds intentionally towards
what's good what's what's beautiful it's as the Buddha said whatever you turn
whatever you Ponder and frequently reflect upon becomes the inclination of
your mind so if we Ponder Upon Our lack there's
not enough we need more we need more as Lynn twist says in the quote I read
we become more greedy we we have jealousies prejudices as she says
arguments with life that would be our orientation and instead if we turn to
what's here there's so much here already so much
your hearts feel full abundant grateful generous the opposite of of greed is
generosity generosity towards ourselves towards life this brief
short life where we are here appreciating living it fully from a place of fullness
so so for our small group practice today
I'd like to invite us practice with a joy inducing
gratitude-inducing practice we've done this before and it never fails to bring more joy and gratitude and that is going
around and the question is what are you grateful for what are you grateful for
what are you grateful for what brings you Joy what are you grateful for and
we'll go alphabetically first name when your turn comes you can offer something or say pass you can just hold
silent presence that's perfectly fine offer one thing authors will hold it
with generosity with happiness for you this is a half this is a modita practice
too happiness for the happiness of others and then the next person you'll
celebrate what brings them Joy what they're grateful for and round and round
so so let's turn towards our fullness and each other's fullness let's celebrate
our own fullness and celebrate each other's fullness so wonderful to
celebrate fullness of others it's so beautiful to to be able to do that to
celebrate yeah other people's blessings yay as if they were our own practice
so be kind yourselves be kind to others no questions no directing
to show up as you are just offer your heart if you like or offer kind
generous space holding gonna open the rooms take
care of yourselves take care of others and enjoy