right over there oh I love it oh yay oh you're our neighbor then I love it
welcome neighbor thank you that is so great
so we have folks who are enabled to IMC and folks who are joining
from another continent in time zone like now from Japan love it love it and of
course East Coasters and West coasters and all around this is awesome this is so great Okay so
so um oh and hi so Yoon from South Korea we're
definitely very International this this morning I should say given your time zone this is terrific so let's let's
begin let's begin um thank you Neil for posting information about happy hour Google
Groups if you are new to happier we have a Google
group a mailing list where information and data and data but information is
shared resources references and you can keep in touch with the community as well
and at this time I change the settings all the chats will only come to host but I ask you to keep that channel quiet
um because it can be quite distracting to receive chats while I teach but I'll open it up afterwards
and last but not least I turned on recording for the sake of Audio Dharma
here we go great hello and welcome everyone welcome to
this edition of happy hour lovely to be with you wherever in the world you are
joining us from those are you're on Zoom or YouTube
um and I mentioned it earlier but I'll say it again now apologies for not having had a happy hour last night if
you try to log in on zoom and we're unable to um there was a confusion about the date
for our invited guest speaker so so thank you for joining today
so so for today's practice
um I'd like to invite you to start practicing together settling with the
body with the breath and I'll invite us to reflect with some Reflections
um in the meditation so I'll introduce the theme in
um in the meditation itself okay so let's begin
let's arrive let's begin
arriving arriving in this moment in this body
Letting Go Letting Go releasing of whatever has come before
whatever busyness planned movement it's all great
and yet we intentionally relinquish as we enter into the Sacred Space of our
practice it's like taking our shoes off before entering into the temple
our proverbial shoes of walking in the world engagement in the
marketplace take that off
take our shoes off with humility we enter into the space to the Temple of our practice
with wholeheartedness
feeling your feet on the Earth bottom your sit Bones on the chair and the
cushion hands on your lap
connected well rooted
and connecting with the breath allowing the
attention kind attention awareness to receive the breath in this moment in
breath and up breath
let the breath be soothing nourishing comforting
steadying knowing the breath the entirety of the
breath
those thoughts arise parts for the past and future it's okay
and we know that we are thinking with kindness
maybe with a smile noticing that the puppy of the Mind
has gone off sniffing playing [Music]
be lovingly lovingly notice where the puppy is
NAFTA knowing where the puppy is
we release we invite the puppy to release
the bone
might seem like a juicy bone thinking about this figuring it out
or sometimes it's a dry bone
sadness self-judgment
Letting Go letting be
inviting the puppy back to our lap be with the breath
comforting soothing settling
foreign
to bring the mind to your heart
Just As You Are feeling the breath connected to the body
now having taken some time to stabilize so we're not leaving the body in the
breath while embodied bringing to heart to mind
someone who's a relatively neutral person in your life you don't know them that
well they were standing for all of humanity
could be someone that a story clear get a store a neighbor
a barista the coffee shop someone you've seen but don't have a
strong positive or negative much of much experience with this being
yeah of course sometimes we develop a little bit of liking or slight dislike
with even with a simple transaction such as buying groceries but
that's okay as long as you don't have a history with this person bring them to mind to your heart
this person this being
not like you just like me
wants to be happy it's not going to suffer
this person is being just like me
as hopes and dreams aspirations
there are people this person loves or has loved
cares about
cares for maybe children Maybe
parents friends loved ones
he may be a caretaker a caregiver
is being just like me it's an object of affection of someone
somebody really cares about this person
they look at this being affectionately through affectionate eyes
just like me this person has had laws physical pain disappointment
sadness
we may have both experienced the loss or pain or illness in it
similar way in our lives
best like me this person has hopes and dreams
experience Joy happiness and laughter
Delight
just like me they want to be happy
this perspective of common Humanity wishing them well
may you be well your fellow human being
may you be happy these are the short form phrases for
meta may you be well may you be happy
or you can say the four phrases may you be safe
may you be happy may you be healthy
may you have ease
I'll experiment with the short form tonight
hello dear fellow human being just like me so I wish for myself happiness may you
be happy
may you be well
mentioning this being this being who's alive
breathe just like you experiences Joy and Pain
just like you they're not so different from you
just as you wish yourself well-being wishing them well-being
my dear sibling in humanity I wish you well
nice fellow sibling in being born living and dying
as a human being may you be well may you be happy
knowing to engage with the phrases and engaging with the image with the felt
sense of this fellow human being
may you be happy may you be well see how your whole own heart
and feel uplifted through wishing well sharing your good will for someone
else it's uplifting happy making to us know this for yourself
not my telling you
and I would fight yourself into a space of matter
and see the two of you interacting
it's a neighbor maybe you're both walking the person at a grocery store see
yourself interacting maybe even talking exchanging kindness
at the checkout counter may we both be well may we both be happy
as we are linked in our interconnection
may we both be well and happy May Our Lives flow with ease or both of
us we are not so different
in wanting to be happy and not suffer in our basic Humanity
may we both be well
that's our lives intersected with
you fellow human being may be making me a cup of coffee if you're a barista or
or helping me ring up my groceries thank you
thank you for your service
may you be well may we both be well
thank you foreign foreign
let's return to bring this meditation session to a close
maybe in your heart connect with this being with their Humanity
their lives are just as complex and compelling
to them as yours is to you
the landscape of their mind their heart their lives is just as
compelling rich filled with ups and downs
it's yours is if you could step into their lives for a
moment in your imagination see your see you in that interaction you
had
now from this perspective receive your kindness receive your good will
if you were them looking out of their eyes into the world unto you
Save The Good Will the kindness of this fellow human being
this customer whoever it might be this neighbor
and returning the Goodwill wishing you well wishing you well
and now shifting perspectives again coming back to your own perspective and appreciating this moment in time this
interaction you had with another human being
so many interactions like this throughout our day we touch each other's lives
perhaps seemingly mundane interactions but not so mundane can we enrich them
with Good Will with kindness
enrich them with kindness with appreciation
with gratitude
gratitude for yourself or having showed up for this practice as best as you're able
to today thank you meek for showing up for
this cultivation and let us offer let us share this
co-created goodness in our practice with all things everywhere may all beings
everywhere who just like me want to be happy and not suffer may all beings everywhere
say happy
May the happiest may all beings everywhere see three
including myself
[Music]
to you all so much for your practice
so today we started with the body and the breath
to tell the soil to calm the mind to settle
first then we turn to practice with what is called a neutral person someone
who's a standard for all of humanity and I invited you to
to then also shift perspectives at the end from their perspective from your
perspective both of you together and also the appreciation of this person
touching your life perhaps in a moment as they did if there was an interaction
and the sense of gratitude appreciation for so many such interactions we have
with so many beings throughout the day throughout our lives and this is one of
them where interacting with each other right now by showing up in this Sangha
in our practice so as an invitation for engaging women
in the breakout groups the invitation is to explore that to take that sense of of
the common Humanity to take that into the small groups together
we all just want to be happy not suffer we we've all have
we all have hopes and dreams and challenges and dukkha and sufferings and
stress it's The Human Condition can we can we
bring can we exchange can we get into the space with that sense
and the invitation is if you like you could get into the group just hold
presence hold compassionate silent presence you don't have to say anything but it's it's a Sandbox for for the way
of interacting so you can so the invitation is to
perhaps say something about how this practice was for you maybe there aha there was an aha moment or not maybe
it's okay to say I was distracted the whole time that's perfectly fine too not
a problem um no right or wrong or you can just offer silence
so let's go enough in Reverse alphabetical order and each person has the chance to share
maybe just one nugget not too long so that other people will have a chance to
share and then they will come back to you I'll come back to you or you'll go around a few times just what was this
black practice like for you and I'll do a sharing before you go in I there was a lot of happiness and joy
and actually a lot of gratitude came up for me I imagined someone yesterday was a barista at a coffee shop I had not met
her so before so she was new and then by really bringing her into my practice
there was a sense of gratitude thank you for making that cup of coffee for me it was really good thank you for the time
that you spent crafting this decaf cappuccinos lovely thank you
so so that's that's one of my practice reports to inspire you with yours so
here we go I'm gonna create the rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other here wake up
foreign
will close in about 30 seconds we'll wait until everybody is back
we will wait with kindness for all those who are back already from groups and
those who are still in the group
and the breakout groups
hey the rooms are closed now everybody's back welcome back everyone and we have
some time for um or reflections
what uh what aha moments perhaps you had
questions complaints realizations especially if you haven't shared in a while in the big
group I'd like to invite you to step forward if you have shared please step
back make space for those who perhaps haven't been
present or raising their hands so not necessarily calling them shy ones
but evening out the space with invitations
we haven't heard from you in a while would love to hear from you Christine
thank you Nikki that was uh it was good for me tonight my group I wanted to say we sat in
silence and that's the first time I'd done that in a breakout room but even though we
didn't speak there was that sense of um acceptance and gratitude for each other
just sitting there tonight so I just want to say to both of them thank you from here
thank you so thank you thank you Christine oh that
that moistens my heart that makes me feel very tender or actually with tears in my eyes how sweet
to be in this space of sitting in Silence with with kindness for one another and
gratitude oh thank you for sharing that oh just makes me so happy hmm
thank you Amy Aloha Amy please
thank you um yeah I really liked the practice today of the person we know yeah we
don't know it felt slightly less complicated than Sometimes some of the other meant to practices we can be doing
and um and that was actually something on theme I've already been playing with where I've been feeling a little bit of
tension when I bring up someone that I really do love and care about just like
because there's just little touches of unease or like a moment where they said something and I received it icky or
things that um have becoming up and I think I realized today that I want to
play with like forgiveness practices around that was like a real nice like moment of realization that I need to
maybe pause when we're doing this and if it's not happening then maybe I can send
out yeah if it feels okay um to do so like make it become a
forgiveness practice then and then I did a little of that and then I was like oh wow I did lighten like I just wanna I
feel yeah a shift so yeah
beautiful I I so appreciate the wisdom of what you just shared Amy
that oh yeah I noticed Alina a little bit of oh something didn't quite land right I love this person and yet ouch
just a little bit of ouch and and oh what if I turn to forgiveness like
there's a wisdom inner wisdom that says oh yeah that's the medicine that's needed right now instead of just like oh
pushing it away like oh you know you're just being sensitive and it's nothing and oh ouch that went super North right
oh yeah and we do that a lot of times we do that we try to just like uh bulldoze
our way through difficulty and yet the wisdom the inner wisdom oh what if I turn to forgiveness just forgiveness
here just moisten is this this tender
um area and oh yes beautiful oh yeah there's a Clarity there's a flow there's like almost as you were describing it's
like feel like like there's just a little bit of obstruction obstruction and then oh yeah then there's a flow of
metal oh yeah I can now it flows well that's what was needed beautiful I
really appreciate how you describe that and one more thing I wanted to highlight is sometimes actually it is
easier for the heart to just bring in someone we don't know really well we
don't have a history with it's easier for The Meta to flow um and sometimes actually that's easier
for some people as a place to start than the easy person because there are no easy persons in in somebody's life so
I'm just saying this because you brought it up and it's a great opportunity to mention that yeah starting from neutral
is great if if that works better for some people so awesome thank you so much
Amy you please
oh you're still muted okay yeah thank you Nick you were wonderful
on meditation in in our group we were discussing How uh
we as we go through our day we we meet people who were nice to us and we we've
seen better to them and sometimes we meet people who maybe are not so nice or
who maybe are jerks and and they don't get so much better and that uh how but
how that sort of sets us up or in a position where we decide who gets the
medal oh a lot of matter for you uh not so much for you and you you jerk no matter for you
mentioned that uh he has he hasn't wrote to live in a world where he feels better
for everyone where he is rich people and by the way he it's it I I sorry I'm
interrupting you but but uh just feel a little bit of tenderness you know it's best to let let Neil share what he
shared himself if he if he you know but it's okay to say someone in the group said blah blah blah but not identify who
said it so sorry I'm going to interrupt you and allow Neil if he wants to to share what he shared in the group does
that feel okay just at the center in terms of boundaries of what was shared in the group for for specifics to stay
in the group but but I appreciate what you said Hugh that was lovely
that was so profound that is so profound that oh gosh yeah we keep we deciding
and in fact people who are not being very kind probably they're hurting so much oh God because hurt people hurt
people in fact but we're deciding oh you don't need meta in fact the person who's not being very kind
is the person who needs the most meta because they're hurting the most so yeah
I so appreciate the the wisdom of what you brought in like yeah it feels like
we're deciding anything else you want I'm gonna invite Neo if there's anything he wants to do and but anything you want
to say about your your own observations here yeah yeah
um your answer that was was my um uh offering and then someone else in the
group said that they felt that they have a right that they were that they deserve
to be uh they have a right to be in love with with everyone and to have a a world
full of lovers rather than to live in a world um where with people that
urges that are haters or or be one themselves you know beautiful oh thank
you that is so that is so beautiful yay oh how inspiring I am so inspired to
hear what um what came up in your group it sounds like a beautiful beautiful exchange and
reflection you had and I'm touched equally with the beautiful conversation
equally with the the silence the group that sat together in an appreciative
silence both are so beautiful thank you you thank you so much for for bringing
that up oh it was so lovely and Neil I see your hand is up so please
you said plenty all I want to say is Claire has a really cute dog
no right I've nothing else to add about the group but just wanted to mention
that Claire oh my God
oh my goodness Claire oh oh my God yes your dog is oh my goodness
very sweet thank you for sharing your dog with us oh she got a bath tonight so oh
that's that's her that's her happy hour meta dog oh my god oh she's the best
so cute thank you my name is Dolly she'll be back
Neil says she looks extra fluffy she does Dolly looks lovely thank you all thank you and a couple of Reflections
I'll read and then we'll close thank you all this is just so your Reflections
have been so touching and beautiful tonight thank you um
this one is anonymous uh there was common Humanity in my group in terms of
the daily confusion that comes with interacting with people yeah yeah
thank you for sharing that of course and that is that there is a place of common Humanity of course
and yeah one of you feeling joyous and grateful
with appreciation to the Sangha and the teachings yeah beautiful well this has
been a very rich period of practice all this has been so
um so uh enlightening just so appreciate your practice your engagement
yeah yeah and uh and yeah and I'm gonna sit with
especially what came at the up at the end about yeah the cute dog too but but also like you know we make these
decisions as we go through the through life like you know this person doesn't deserve you know uh
not nice no matter nice meta Etc and what if we choose to just be ha live in
a world of lovers not haters because it's really our perspective that that makes that possible so especially if
somebody's being unkind or or Hasty or you know can we give them extra dose of
meta extra oh gosh you poor dear you're really suffering right now aren't you uh
may you be well may you be well anyway thank you all thank you so much for your
practice your engagement um what a beautiful Sangha thank you all
may you all be well may you be free and and may I practice serve all beings
everywhere including ourselves foreign
take care