Okay so I'm a rusty I've been away quite a bit
from here and so all the buttons to push and things to check and uh
the settings were set were not proper in the software part of this YouTube
broadcast this morning so I I wasn't able to get it up and running until just a few minutes before seven
so thank you for being here I'm delighted to be with you and
and the last two weeks I've been involved with it teaching the Dharma teaching practice
in outdoor settings first 24 7 in the Santa Cruz mountains and
where I even slept Outdoors under the stars and taught and practiced in a
Grove of trees in a wonderful Meadow and then this last week in Colorado and
the mountains outside of Boulder at nine thousand feet and beautiful places to be
practicing and in Colorado practicing together with moose who were in the area
uh so my friends the
I think that uh well mindfulness practice the awareness practice we do
when in mindfulness uh it is very simple but in being simple it's both very
radical and it's also um uh you know maybe sometimes hard to
appreciate the Simplicity of it so the Simplicity of it is that
it's just to know very simply what's happening to be aware of it
but to be aware of it the Simplicity of it is to be aware of it without any reference to oneself
meaning that it isn't the usual self the usual me and my concerns my orientation
my projections my values my
fears my judgments that is doing the awareness
there might be uh self-concerns there might be concerns
about others but the radical nature of awareness is that we can know those but we're not
living in them it's more like we're living in the awareness we're living in the simplicity
where the awareness is kind of like um if you look into the sky at a bird
going through the air the the space the bird flies through
is not the bird but it allows the bird to fly through space it allows us to see
the bird and um the so awareness can be almost like that
it's uh it's the awareness they can know if we're self-concerned or measuring what's
happening through the filter of ourselves what I have to do who I am how good I am how bad I am
but we don't believe in those or we don't latch on to them because the awareness
is not appropriated as self we're just aware just like space
and um and so uh and the reason why this is so
useful is that when meditation is about myself
meaning when meditation is about self-concerns and measuring myself and judging myself or
trying to accomplish something for myself we're limiting our capacity for freedom
and for joy but if we can just step away and just keep it so simple just aware
then uh there's something joyful about that there's something free freeing
about that so that's the so it's radically simple
but challengingly simple so what I'd like to offer
uh is um is um
a little sentence you can tell yourself as we go through this meditation
and it's not to deny anything about yourself it's actually to be acutely aware of
everything that goes on but uh but to have the sentence
it's not about me it's not about me the awareness is not
about me just being aware not about me right now just to be aware of what's
here just to be aware of what's here and it's not about me
and now if that's troubling for you to say that then don't do it but you might
if you can find Freedom in that if you can find even some joy in that
then maybe say this sent little sense it's not about me and then
come back to your breathing and be with your breathing and to use that sentence not as a mantra
but if your thoughts if your concerns start going into something about me
myself and mine then say it's not about me right now
in these next 20 minutes that we have for this period just for now me can come
back it's not about me it's just to be aware just to be aware
not about me so to
assume a meditation posture that's appropriate for you
in one of the four dignified postures
sitting lying down standing
or walking and to
adjust your eyes so that your eyes are the
engaged in a way or not engaged in a way that's relaxing for you
most commonly
is commonly to close your eyes or lower your gaze with
half open eyes
taking a few deep breaths through and relaxing on the exhale
and then to let yourself be as simple
with your awareness mindfulness as you as you can
the simple knowing of breathing
simple knowing of sounds and what happens in your senses sense doors
simple knowing of your emotions or what goes on in your mind
as if there's no past and future it's just the Simplicity of this moment the
experience of this moment and if you find that your
your thoughts maybe your emotions are somehow connected to
identifying it as Me Myself and mine self-concerned in any kind of way
tell yourself it's not about me for these minutes meditating
it's not about me it's about being aware
where the awareness is not about me either
awareness is wider more spacious
than me
where the knowing
has a quality of effortlessness
knowing is simple just knowing
without laying on top of it feelings
senses or ideas of I'm the one who knows
it's not about me in being aware
if your thoughts are about yourself
remind yourself that meditation is not about yourself
not about thinking about yourself or concerned about yourself
it's simply to be aware of what's here
and if what's here is thoughts about self
to be aware of that simply
almost like those thoughts are not really you they're just thoughts
foreign
the idea of it's not about me
is to remember that awareness can be wider broader
Freer when it's not
pulled into or participating on our self-consciousness
our self-preoccupation self-judgment
we're always in a way
larger or Freer than any thought or idea
contraction we have around ourselves
and when self-preoccupation limits our capacity for joy
limits our capacity for love
and we see that then the expression is not about me
can be an opening into this wider world of freedom and joy and
love
may it be that our practice
is one that brings joy and compassion and love into
this world as medicine
for the problems and challenges this world faces to support all beings on this planet
may we help create a safer caring
and Freer world by learning how not to be
excessively self-preoccupied self-concerned
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
may all beings be safe may all beings
live in peace
[Music]
thank you all
and I'll take this moment to um
mention that if you have trouble logging on today to this YouTube channel
which I did as well it was because the settings for
broadcasting onto YouTube were were set wrong they weren't the public it wasn't
on the public setting so it was being recorded on YouTube but not publicly available
and it took a while for me to discover that I think it helped to to understand the settings
and partly because I've been gotten Rusty and doing this YouTube broadcasting and
and um so um
you know it was we need to go public I think a couple of minutes before seven and so hopefully uh just for those of
you who tried before that the problem was not with your links the problem was that um
it hadn't been made public yet
so I return here to after being away for a
couple of weeks with many momentous events happening and
this country and around the world and and the earthquakes the the the
the fire in Maui and just the tragedy of it it keeps growing and more we learn about it
and um for anybody who lives in Hawaii and in
Maui and I send my condolences and my love and
and um and people who are maybe here in
California dealing with a flooding in Southern California and
and they're in your in our hearts no
so um
and I hope but that uh this
practice that we do is really for the benefit of this world
and that in the ways the way the way in which it benefits ourselves
makes it possible for us to be to offer
the right attention support love Compassion Care
for this world around us and maybe it's just the very local world of a few people around us maybe it's
broader worlds but that this practice does
um Orient us to live in a way that
um doesn't add to the harm of the world but actually it adds to
uh ways in which we can benefit this world so in the last uh I don't know a few
months when I've been teaching here I've been teaching about compassion and I
kind of wondered if I had been finished with this series but in thinking about it these last couple of weeks
I wanted to do one more week maybe a concluding week on compassion it felt important to actually spend a
whole week on the joy of compassion the happiness of compassion and uh and perhaps for those who have
been listening to this series on compassion that um as you start understanding the Ecology
of all the different pieces of compassion and how they come together that we can understand and appreciate
that there is the potential for our
compassionate relationship to the world to be one that brings joy and happiness
or a sense of lightness or sense of sweetness or something that feels quite
right there's no sense of rightness that um lightens us perhaps or
makes the suffering of the world not so heavy and oppressive for us to live with
and this is one of the great aspects of compassion is when compassion is free
of any kind of attachment any kind of self-preoccupation any kind of way in
which we get caught in identified with the suffering
or any way in which we are the suffering of the world somehow
gets uh gets um doesn't move through us in a way that
feels free and doesn't move through us in a free and light way
that when it doesn't that um the full potential of compassion and how
beautiful and profound and important it is to have it Islam is limited
so I want to talk about that this week the joy of compassion and I'd like to do it by uh trying to
evoke or point to the joy of the four different supports or foundations or
elements that that are there as part of compassion if compassion is really going
to fulfill its full potential and many times when we have compassion
and it can be genuine but it hasn't really um moved into its full potential and maybe
even feels overwhelming and we you know overwhelming and difficult to have compassion and there's compassion
fatigue for example that um it's these different elements haven't
really come to fulfillment so I've talked about how the four
aspects that come together to really benefit the compassion is awareness
Attunement appreciation aspiration and then action
and each of those are associated with a kind of joy that kind of delight and
happiness and so for the first a healthy
compassion comes with a well-developed sense capacity to for really being aware
and and to learn the art of being aware
without identification or being aware without adding into the awareness
judgments and evaluations of Me Myself and mine and this is where
kind of the knowing the awareness the recognition the mindfulness can operate with a kind of
um a certain kind of effortlessness
because to apply effort to being aware is all too easy the idea of I'm the one
who's applying effort and because of that all these Associated ideas of what I'm
who I am and why I'm doing this and and judgments about my capacity and all
kinds of things come along independent of that just many people go around with a lot of self-concern
everything is measured but how this what this says about me or what this how this
is for me or how this is against me or how I'm a victim of this or how I'm a
consumer of it and I just want to have more or um and and um and some of this of course
is not wrong but when it limits us when it actually contributes to further suffering and
more attachments and limits our capacity to serve the world in a Freer away then there is another way
and the other way is to learn how there's certain kind of way to be
mindful that has a certain quality of effortlessness a certain quality of it's
just awareness to just there that just arises and and to kind of enter into or return
to a clear sense of attention to the present moment
that has no self-efforting making oneself do
something but rather it's an allowing it's an opening it's a relaxing into the awareness into
the knowing um this is where uh knowing or awareness
can start providing feelings of Joy or happiness that are lightening up because
because so much of the self-concern and self-preoccupation that we live our
lives with dampens down the joy dampens down the freedom that we have it limits
it quite a bit and some other idea of joy that people
have and happy Pursuit of Happiness is that pursuit of a happiness where we
that we build up the sense of self where the self gets praised or the self
gets aggrandized or itself gets you know proves itself as being somehow wonderful
in the eyes of others or something and some of that unhappiness as people have is also connected to the sense of
self and that failure and not good enough and and um feeling that somehow we're wrong
and and the radicalness of this awareness practice is how it points to
the possibility of being alive of being aware and present outside of the
limitations of these judgments and evaluations of ourselves that we live
with so the Simplicity of awareness maybe even the effortless quality of it
um is or some kind of way in which it's not really self doing it maybe there is
a kind of activity of being aware but there's not a sense that I'm the one who's doing it or it's about me
um and so the freedom from self-preoccupation the freedom from this constantly be concerned with ourselves
is why some Buddhist teachers will say that if you want to be happy have
compassion for others live for others and it's not exactly because of living
for others that the joy comes but sometimes the reason they say this is because the joy comes from not having
the tight contracted agitated painful ways in which we live when we're
self-concerned and so we're kind of loosening up that and stepping out of it
and now forgetting it this is self-forgetting that compassionate
service can provide and uh is maybe why some people do it
and um and but if you only do compassion
compassionate work in the world to forget the self but haven't really addressed you know
it's almost like it can be a distraction from self and they could certainly can be a lightning and easing up that happens
when we kind of forget about ourselves or forget about our we were distracted from all this
healthy awareness practice um learns how to be to honestly be present
here for ourselves what the for all the different kind of
ways in which this mind works and the even the self-preoccupation self-concern and evaluations we make
but to see it to know it to be aware of it without identifying with it without
adding on top of it more attachment more self on top of it it's almost as if we're beginning to
hold Who We Are Who how we mind works and identifications we have in a lot
with lots of expensive space and we identified a little bit more with the largeness of space than we do with
the smallness of self identity
and so to cultivate and develop awareness practice and have that awareness be ready to
encounter the suffering of the world this kind of free awareness light awareness open awareness spacious
awareness non-self non-self-concerned
non-self-referenced awareness where we know ourselves well
and we start knowing the world of the round us others then compassion has a chance to be
present and to share the joy of Freedom the joy of awareness which is free the
just the joy of being aware and the final Joy of awareness of mindfulness practice
that I want to emphasize is that um
is that um
the joy of having an awareness practice that
had the joy of the faith the joy of the appreciation of knowing we have a practice that can meet
our own suffering and meet our own selfing our own self kind of challenges that we live with
and aren't we lucky to have a practice that helps us to work with us to work through it to find a way with it to find
Freedom with it it's not always easy it takes time
but there's a joy of knowing that you have a practice that has bring so much good to oneself and to others
so the joy of awareness as we get a sense of that possibility the sweetness of awareness that
then we can find um then we're in a better place and ready
to experience the joy of compassion so
then we'll continue on this theme and I'm happy to be sharing it with you
thank you