okay welcome uh welcome folks
um yeah nice to say the names
okay I will uh uh
Let's uh that's it that's it
let's just imagine it was you not me
guiding this meditation
and let's imagine that you
were deeply at ease no social pressure
but you had to decide how to guide
and you know many techniques but you're
actually in deciding how to guide us all
having to really contact the field of your own experience
to find where the inspiration is
where the aliveness is in you
is guiding a meditation a little like narrating one's experience in a way that
is hopefully useful for another
and so as we begin just uh
gently scan your experience
to see where the inspiration is where the aliveness is
which phenomena are useful for you to pay attention to
right now
maybe it's the breath or the body
a feeling tone or objects of the Mind
but maybe it's something no one's ever heard of before
planning letting your own wisdom
shape your attention in this moment
receiving your own wisdom
when you have your sincerity
the rest is really detailed
when you want to know something when you want to know experience
the rest is details
when you're willing to be softened
rather than hardened by experience
the Restless details
letting the world blow through awareness
so I'd open receptive
nothing for phenomena to Clank into
phenomena Clank into the solidification of self
flank into solidification of
clinging
and we relax
open
we don't have to catch and cage
some thought
feeling sound
like a safe way to open to hold anything
including what you call your life
and then of course something clanks into self-cranks into clinging
we hear the sound of suffering
but there's no shame in that
there's no shame in that we were designed to suffer
and we were designed to be free
just letting life run through you
foreign
okay let's get this here with you
um I hope you did a good job imaginarily guiding that meditation
in my Stead um
so uh faith energetic vigor
mindfulness mindfulness oh my goodness that word
a word Nietzsche said um words are like Pockets into which
many things have been placed and mindfulness is most definitely a pocket
into which many things have been placed and um
sometimes it is it's used as a kind of placeholder for all of the Dharma
sort of like all these different concepts smuggled under the umbrella
of that word and
other times you know um attempts to to kind of monetize
mindfulness make it uh change its meanings to it's been made
more compatible with greed hatred and delusion in in some depictions of it I would say
sometimes uh I've thought that um
understanding mindfulness is not the starting point of practice but
the fruit of practice that we don't you know of course we have
to begin with a definition of mindfulness but um
to know what that is is is not actually where we start but where we wind up
so from classically from the Sati patana what's right mindfulness here on
monastic dwells contemplating the body and the body Ardent clearly
comprehending mindful having removed covetive covetousness and
displeasure with regard to the world
um there's a lot to say about that but one of the things I want to note is that
they're are multiple dimensions of the construct you know it's not it's not just it's not
just narrowly one one feature that's right it's it's um contemplating
body or you know feeling and feeling Ardent clearly comprehending remove
having removed covetousness and displeasure is a lot yeah a lot of
facets of mindfulness and so what I thought okay if 15 minutes
to talk about mindfulness the lot that one might say but I thought
to highlight this dimension that to my mind uh mindfulness
describes a state nearly diametrically opposed to
the Hallmarks of distress yeah
that that what mindfulness depicts is like really almost the opposite from the
kind of characteristics that are shared by many different states of distress may
we say suffering and so obviously suffering distress
comes in a million flavors but there are shared characteristics across a range of
states of distress and when I was reflecting on this it's
um was able you know just with can name a
few features so in states of distress generally not
always generally thoughts become
absorbing and imposing thoughts feel really
real they feel
um they feel like the realest thing in the world
and we know rumination that kind of like chewing
that embeddedness in thought bubbles is is known as like a trans diagnostic
risk factor so for a range of different states of distress psychiatric
compromise rumination is a risk factor
in states of distress the the kind of space of experience Narrows
a kind of claustrophobia in states of distress uh are our
attention becomes fragmented it's pinging from memory
to present moment emotion physical sensation to prognostications about the
future it's um it's a very unstable you know in
the kind of field of experience
in distress there tend to be alterations in physiological arousal
we tend to be really flat or hyper aroused or we're
a blend of kind of Frozen and then Super
impulsive in states of distress there there tends
to be a lot of experiential avoidance meaning a kind of unwillingness to make
full contact with one's inner life kind of bracing and guarding
patrolling the inner landscape to see what's safe and what isn't
there's there are often compromises in distress tolerance so the unpleasant
features of any human life become especially distressing especially sticky
uh the pain the pain is a pain
these difficulties tend to be deeply personalized so when we're really
distressed you know it's like that distress becomes a commentary on one's
life one's worthiness one's being
in states of distress there there tends to be rigidity in the
um predictive models the ways that we
are using this moment to um to make make predictions about the
trajectory the vector of our life and there's a kind of failure to learn
and revise the models we are models of of self and World become impervious to
new information in states of distress we're not learning what's important to
learn we're suffering but we're not learning about suffering
so that's a very vague kind of sketch of like some of the shared features of of
distress a wide range of distressed States
okay what are the Hallmarks of mindfulness
a reduction in experiential Fusion like a reduction this metacognitive awareness
we are no longer living within the bubble
defined by that thought this is another way of saying there's a
kind of dereification thoughts feelings
feel less real in other words they feel less
um they are no longer these pure descriptions of the state of the world
true descriptions of the state of the world the state of the self
they become less real yeah or maybe they they become more
infused with space phenomena become less intimidating
that that phrase from the satitana putting down covetousness and displeasure this is really I would say
related to equanimity um a kind of
um a conjoined factor with with mindfulness Sati
uh this kind of um
non-interference with the arising and passing of phenomena
um in mindfulness is um is is a state of distress tolerance
it's a state where we're not so intimidated of those pockets of our
inner life that are charged with uh affect
we can approach what was once avoided
these are Hallmarks of mindfulness and the mindfulness there is a attentional
stability attentional stability and mindfulness that's different that's not exactly the
same as samadhi which talk about tomorrow but there's there's at least a modicum
of attentional stability we're not pinging around everywhere
and um there are many regulatory benefits of
um this stabilized malleable unified attention
is a Hallmark of mindfulness the opposite of distress
in mindfulness we are [Music] um
draining the moralism from our inner life
who what we took to be a sign about Who We Are
about or worthiness or something
no longer points to anything or anyone it's phenomena blowing through and so
there's less and less room for the moralism about what we think or feel
about uh what arises in the field of experience
there is uh in mindfulness a kind of hypo hypo egoic state
the energy and tension of self is relaxed
and in this kind of this receptivity the self is not really home based it's just
there's just okay wide open
and in that openness we're not really making a home anywhere
or we're awake
and so uh so many ways to suffer some features
these shared features of distress
and the facets of mindfulness
are the facets of mindfulness represent a
kind of diametric opposite of those those Hallmarks of distress
to offer this uh for your your consideration and um
yeah may we uh where we we
learn about the causes of suffering the causes of ease today
okay folks um it's good to uh good to be with you and uh
see you see you tomorrow yeah
okay thank you