Hello friends hi if you can can hear me okay give me a thumbs up audio is
working fantastic hi I'm Nikki in Mountain View California unseated oone
land hi good to see you and uh yeah
let's begin as we always do with our expression of warm-heartedness by
greeting each other in the space so whoever wants to say hi take it
away hey this is Don from DC hello sa hi
[Music] Don NE in rainy New Hampshire I Neil in
rainy New Hampshire good evening it's Fred in Oakland hi
Fred bill in Dallas hi Bill and hi John who says Kia Ora hello IMC folks from
New Zealand on a stormy spring afternoon sweet joining us on YouTube anybody else
wants to say hi in Minneapolis hi who was that Carlos in hi
Carlos welcome and Barbara and Alam hi Barbra and Hugh says hi from San
Diego Claire from rainy New York Claire from rainy New York oh yeah
I heard in the news you East coaster especially New Yorkers quite quite a bit of rain
yeah yeah anybody else wants to say hi Sarah says hi from Toronto we're
International also on Zoom not just uh New Zealand sweet hi Sarah or
Sara rather hi Mima from yaka Valley Hi
Mima and hi Neil from Houston we have two Neals with alternate pronunciation
spellings same pronunciation different spelling sweet well let's get started
let's begin and thank you Neil for posting
information about happy hour Google Groups if you are new to happy hour we
have a low trffic um mailing list where information is
shared and also uh there is a little document we have uh that you can click
on uh in order to orient yourself if you're new to how to support yourself and
others in a small groups interactions so so with that I changed the setting so
unmuting won't be possible so space stays quiet changing chat to host only
but please keep it quiet otherwise I can get distracted while I'm teaching I'll
open it afterwards and and I'm going to turn on recording for the sake of Audio
Dharma all the pre preliminaries there we go great so hello
hello everyone lovely to be with you and this Friday or Saturday if you're u in a
different time zone it's already morning or afternoon the next day so so for today's practice
cultivating meth uh kindness Goodwill the practices of the
heart I wanted to um combine two
invitations one is an invitation for rest for deep
rest um as a way to share kindness with
ourselves to be kind to ourselves we don't always have to be doing doing doing so this is
um opening up to rest is an expression of kindness and
I want to couple that actually with the intentionality of engaging with kindness
in our choices we always have Choice points we always
have choices that we make in sometimes unintentionally sometimes intentionally
and I want to bring more a awareness to um to what's called in Buddhism volition
or volitional formations or Saras we talked about it this past week for those
who showed up to the 7 a.m. it's it's this sense of even mild or subtle
volitional choice that we make in our minds um all the time all the time so
bringing more awareness to that we can choose to be kind
gentle generous grateful Etc or we can choose quote unquote choose sometimes it
doesn't feel like it's a choice but really it is a uh byproduct of many many
choices we've made in the past um or choices that we've been engaged with
perhaps through our upbringing and we can start to notice it not to to self uh
flatulate and say oh I'm being mean to myself and just adding more salt to the
wound but just noticing and perhaps ever so slowly bringing more kindness making
a choice to slowly slowly change the uh
the flow of our future choices so ever so gently so but but it requires that we
first bring awareness to our choices in every moment not these big
Life Choices choices yeah those too of course but in these small tiny choices
that we make every moment how we react how we behave
so so with that let's make a choice to turn towards our
practice so sitting or lying down or standing
however it's comfortable for you
and letting the body making a choice a conscious
choice to relax the
body Relax The Mind relax the
heart
and let our posture to have a sense of integrity
uprightness and yet have a relaxed choose to have a relaxed attitude
relaxed posture in the heart a spacious posture in the mind
and with this spacious stance in the heart
mind receiving the breath Sensations in the
optimate one breath at a time to invite ourselves to
settle take refuge in this moment in
time
taking Refuge in quiet is deeply healing and
restful and we choose to
release thoughts preoccupations plans
overdoing can you release all that and make a
choice choose to be simple choose to rest invite the heart and mind to rest
and be at ease in this
moment
now we choose rest refuge in Simplicity as a radical act of
kindness to this being who is
me
release release release as an act of Med
especially releasing what's not helpful right
now War less care
Simple Kindness instead of pushing this being
to do and accomplish and doing and doing let it
rest let her him they
rest just as you
would lay a beloved child on their
bed a little baby let them
rest same gesture of kindness choosing this gentle gesture of
kindness for yourself
as if each breath was rocking was
rocking lovingly rocking yourself in this crib with each in
breath and out breath
and we choose and we choose
ease and we choose non- entanglement with thinking
wanting [Music]
worrying and we choose to put it down for just this moment put it
down and then this moment and then this moment stringing
these moments together not picking it up
choosing not to pick up the unhelpful patterns of the
Mind training ourselves in this supreme
training
Ching [Music] e choosing
kindness choosing
non-reactivity choosing
Peace In This Moment In This mind and heart planting
seeds
as a famous Swami said years ago the natural state of our mind is
peace and quiet we just keep stiring it
up we choose to release stirring it
up putting it down with
kindness
PE
as we turn to bring this guided meditation to a
close to sit together let us
choose nonjudgment no matter how the spirit of
practice was distracted sleepy doesn't matter can we choose kindness
appreciation for this practice or this opportunity for ourselves for the
community or the technology all the goodness can we
have a moment of appreciation cultivating ease kindness good
will for ourselves can we choose to be
generous and sharing our Goodwill with all beings everywhere may all
beings be happy may all beings be free including
myself [Music]
everyone thanks for your
practice so I'd like to invite us if you would if
you you would put uh you wanted to share a word of
reflection it's coming up for you in this moment how are you doing what's
happening [Music] um yeah and what's my one word hard to
choose one word there's happy okay three words there's happy there
peaceful yeah and easeful
ah says Neil can also share your Reflections privately if you want with me just read your your
[Music] um reflection not your uh name curious
about ease says Amy precious
TI gentle says pink feel like a gentle
R [Music] relaxed say Audrey
you letting go says Aurora I love these Reflections bringing
them into the um
space I like the peace and quiet quot says Jerry yeah me
too so keeping with this theme for choosing kindness choosing peace and
ease I like to invite us to see if we can stay in this space as we engage with
fellow practitioners not from a petty place so this can be really interesting
practice it can really stretch us if you tend to get into a heady place when you get into a social situation what if you
stay in this quiet space and in a container of fellow
practitioners when your turn comes explore maybe a few words come
from the space of quiet exploring for yourself for your benefit not for their
benefit not trying to speak to them you're just exploring out loud and maybe just silence comes up in which case you
hold yourself with care you choose silence and peace and you're held with
care silence and ease it's all good can also
um yeah you can you can explore the space
of relating with in a different way this can be really opening because we usually
get into a space we want to talk we want to share we want to share our opinions and in this relational space what if we
get into relational space with the intention to hold our peace hold the
peace and ease choosing peace um knowing that the other people in the space are
making the same choice so oh what an interesting exploration together you may
not say a word you might say a few words it doesn't matter see what feels
authentic and if it feels awkward maybe say that yeah there's peace and
there's some awkwardness just explore for yourself see what this could open up
it can unhook the Habit patterns we tend to have in social situations this can be
really interesting exploration can be a very quiet gentle exploration like a
Sandbox relational sandbox be curious yes
so so allowing again inviting us to engage small groups as
you speak offer a reflection about what's arising how you're feeling how
this is this exploration of choosing peace and kindness is feeling was
resonating for you again it's for your own exploration offer a nugget and put it in
the space for your benefit then let the next person do an exploration one nugget
the next person and then it comes back to you so you go around and around a few times it's not a long monologue you can
also say pass yeah you can just smile and or not even smile and just say pass
and maybe yeah maybe everybody passes maybe the second round you want to say something or not just share silence
together it's going to be so interesting anyway explore dear fellow fellow
practitioners I'm going to create the
rooms inviting you to explore [Music]
and and let's let uh let the order be R
reverse alphabetical order according to first name and I'm opening the rooms
and take care of yourselves take care of each other and here we
go
okay everyone welcome back welcome back hope you
had an interesting opening different um yeah learning opportunity
in in the small group group so so we love to hear if you like to share how
what did you discover either from the practice or from the exploration in
small groups especially if you haven't spoken recently anything you like to bring into
the uh community space would be
lovely
I've been enjoying your your your talks this week in the morning and um uh that
the subtlety of how watching the mind is uh caught my attention and
u i i I didn't catch today so I missed that but I wonder if you have thoughts
on a little confusion about I'm going through some some difficult moods
emotions or around grief and so some may be like necessary to just be with it as
opposed to avoiding it completely which is impossible but how does that so is it
is it that watching the mind even though it's painful difficult sometimes
unpleasant to just be this is a good opportunity to watch though what what
might might get out of watching The Mind the subtlety of what it what messages
there may be there W yeah thanks Peter um so many
different different options for for especially with with being with grief
when there is loss of course grief is a natural response of the mind and heart
and of course sometimes grief can be complicated or contracted because there's resistance to the grief to the
loss and and the various stages of of grief with bargaining and anger and just
you know the the the challenging emotions which again could could be considered a natural part of grief and
yet um they're of they often get
um uh more it gets more challenging when there's more resistance and there some
perhaps um if if there's lack of kindness or if there's more is more
clingy so it can be helpful to see those but not as you said not trying to do
this in order to get rid of so make sure that that you don't have you don't end
up with this um project of oh I'm doing this practice in order to get rid of
grief uh didn't hear that but but sometimes it can become a a subtle
second agenda um and it's wonderful because I did hear more that there is
this intention of learning from what am I learning if I observe my mind my heart
in the space what am I learning what am I learning about the patterns of this heart and mind what am I what can I
learn about um the the response of a
human being to griefing in general so it's both the personal and then the and then
Universal and can I take on this this seeing this clear
seeing as it is intertwined with kindness this curiosity which has
kindness with it so it's responsive sometimes it can lean into
the kindness and sometimes can lean into the Curiosity and there can be more of a
a a fiercer compassion like oh sweet hard you're really wallowing this okay maybe this is not helpful and sometimes
it it's helpful to say okay stay with this stay with this so always having compassion and kindness meta and
kindness intertwined in the Curiosity As You observe the State of Mind does that
does that help more questions yes thank you yeah thanks
Peter beautiful challenging opening to be human to go through all
these um yeah emotions and states of mind and heart that we all do at
different times yeah thank you any other Reflections or
questions anything in particular about choosing choosing peace
choosing non [Music]
entanglement choosing to put it down when you start to steer it up noticing
that oh yeah the mind is just thinking and just like a you know like a dog that doesn't want
to let go of a juicy bone it just like okay sweetie you can put it down it's all right it's not that juicy it's a
hollow bone really Jean yeah Nikki I was just feeling that
way like I'm just itching in this really uncomfortable way to like check my
email and um yeah I'm in that Loop and it's it's just so hard to not do
it yeah it's like it's 701 you know I'm gonna go for the email so it's interesting you said
that this is great actually Jean let's let's try something out if you're up for it this is great so um as as this
itching is coming up I'm going to ask you to M if you want to to try this out so so let yourself and if anybody else
has some kind of an itch that's happening right now I want to go do that now or I want to go watch that whatever
Netflix thing right now just it's okay you can still do it but just play around with with it for a moment just play
around so so so feel into this this clinging
this wanting this this Loop like like I really want it and just with kindness
just really really let let it be really let it be felt and really feel into
it breathe with it breathe around it trying to deny it you're not trying
to get rid of it you're not suppressing
it and you're not giving it energy to let it
proliferate you're just being with it just observing it it's like a little little child that's having a tantrum
just patiently being with it okay breathe be stable
breathe keep breathing keep watching
it breathing Let the Body the mind be calm spacious keep watching it as it
jumps up and down maybe throws a little tantrum smile
keep watching you can be with it and whatever
you decide is fine just see what's happening any any Reflections
Jean I think somehow talking about it out loud to you um and maybe you
responding it's sort of broke and I just it like I thought it would give me
relief to do to push that email and it it sort of broke and I just felt sad
just felt the sadness um in my chest and behind my eyes and I don't I don't want
that anymore right now I don't want the email anymore I don't have that drive
it's sort of um let me go and I just feel kind of sad now but um I think that
feels better yeah it's inter it's a different it's a it is a real relief kind of yeah
thanks for speaking to that now now it it might actually be that this is a
moment of insight and and thank you for playing you know inquiring together
in real time because it's both help also helpful for the community where these things come up because um in maybe that
gen in this case it was the sadness that was the Lynch pen of the agitation
but it wasn't seen it was kind of it was the energy behind and when we really pay
attention to what's on top this this energy of wanted wanted and then oh it lets go
it breaks as you said and we get to see what's what's underneath and and we can be with the sadness can I be with that
too with the same way with the kindness and generosity and uh see what's there
what's yeah what's the lesson there thank you
thank you yeah ah
great and maybe one last reflection here from
Mima I want to to share something it's um I feel that by coming to happy hour
and I've learned so much from you and how to speak to myself um I almost want to cry right now
because I come from a really rough background most of my life that um to be
kind to myself was something that was foreign and through happy hour and
through some your your teachings I've learned like I could get the teachings
from like the Dharma talks and stuff like that um Dharma seed but to hear you
you speak to yourself and to speak to us that way it's warmed my heart so much
that I speak to others that way now as well because that's how I speak to me now and so I am just so touched that
I've learned that um yeah my family members can't believe transformation
because of this the sweetness the kindness the the words and they're genuine I feel them it's like all that
other stuff like you told Gan right now was covering up that the goodness the kindness the comp passion that I just
want to thank you from the bottom of my heart for that and everyone else thank
you thank you Mima and now I I have tears in my eyes oh thank you so much
for sharing your reflection and and and the
beauty of your practice your transformation I am deeply deeply touched thank you oh it means the world
to me yay yay I'm celebrating you I'm cheering
you on me mom may you continue to cultivate this voice of kindness for yourself and for the sake of so many
beings Oh What a Beautiful note thank you to to end on to end on tonight thank
you Mima thank you deep
gratitude yeah [Music]
yeah ah I'm booed I'm I'm my heart is full thanks M my well my heart is full
from this practice and all of your sharings and now I it's over full it's overflowing happy dance yay Nikki happy
dance one more kind voice in the world yay
sweet so thank you all thank you so much for your practice for your goodness for
your cultivation we do this work for not just for ourselves clearly but for all
beings everywhere in ways we cannot fathom how they get touched may may all
beings everywhere have goodness have ease may
they be free including
[Music] ourselves thanks everyone
be well and now I'm going to invite you all if you would unmute yourselves for
cofin is goodbye how fun thank you all thank you Nikki thank you everyone