hello everyone and no warm greetings and
sitting here with you wishing you all a
meaningful meditation or a satisfying one
even when it's not satisfying though it can be quite beneficial sometimes even more beneficial
because the very things that make meditation difficult are often the very things that
mindfulness it's useful to bring mindfulness to might be very important to be mindful of
and and learn something new find a new way
be with oneself in a productive way with the difficulty
so one of the
common descriptions of mindfulness practice you
find here in the west is that it's a form of acceptance practice
and uh and maybe so and I'll talk more about that later but right now I'd like to offer you
a very important Baseline orientation for doing Buddhist
Meditation for doing mindfulness practice that is akin to Acceptance in a certain
way but doesn't require doing something and often people have the impression
that a meditation is a lot about doing sometimes acceptance is understood as a
as a ceasing of a lot of the doing that we do and in a sense that's what I want to
emphasize today that as you do the meditation today
um rather than trying to Focus so much on being mindful
rather than focusing a lot on some ideal like to be compassionate for yourself or kind to yourself
focus on non-harming
being attentive enough to track what your mind does
the thoughts the attitudes the motivations the the
actions you want to do and simply avoid
anything that could be seen as being harmful even if it is the harm is not
strong but certainly any thing in the in the
category of aversion hatred ill will
towards yourself or towards others towards the meditation any movement of greed and desire which
causes stress and strain any copying caught up in
all kinds of thoughts about doubt and confusion and
fantasy and all which kind of interfere with the
kind of deep intimacy a deep capacity for being at ease Here and Now
so what would happen to this meditation if you're attentive
to avoid causing harm the harm that comes from being alienated
alienated from yourself when we're caught up in Lost in thought
so if any of those movements of Mind happen
let them be don't be involved in them don't get behind them
no need to be critical that they occur just let them be
the Buddhist question is to let thee or not to let be that is the
question and often the thing to do is to let be Let It Be don't get involved
so assuming a meditation posture
a posture that feels good for you
but also good because it brings a kind of alertness to the body
and maybe with the alertness of the body
no alertness in the mind
gently closing your eyes
and begin by remembering or sensing imagining finding
what it might be like to have a mind and attitude
of non-harming
a mind that's not harming because
it has a strong connection to a sense of ease
a sense of Peace Within imagining that kind of mind and heart
and taking a few long slow deep breaths and as you exhale
relax into that possibility possibility of non-harming
a heart that doesn't want to harm
and if any harming Tendencies arise it could be annoyance criticism self-criticism
some subtle attitude of that of that in which we undermine
ourselves let that be
don't be involved in it
relax on the exhale relax into
so you approach the place within
that's at ease and at peace not in conflict with anything
breathing in and breathing out
approaching meditation as a practice of non-harming
foreign
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
perhaps consider the benefits that come from non-harming
what this world would be like if there was a heightened dedication to
non-harming
what it would feel like for you to live in a world where you were
confident you would not be harmed
and perhaps how you would like to support others
and have the experience of not having to worry about being
harmed
and perhaps that's one of the gifts you can give
a dedication of living a life of not harming
may it be that others can rest
assured that they will not be the recipients of
hate and ill will meanness meanness and bullying and
snide remarks
May It Be
that all beings may be happy
may be safe maybe peaceful
maybe free
and to be able to live
without an ongoing worry of being harmed by anyone
including by themselves
then may we that be dedicated to creating such a world
by living it with a dedication to not harm
[Music]
thank you
and while I'm waiting for the recorder here to reset so I can push the record
button as mentioned again that tomorrow that
when this is over it's that um hit the quarter to the hour 7 45 in
California uh I'll open a zoom room and we can have a
7 A.M community uh meeting
and um I thought it'd be nice partly because I'll be away for the following month and
then nice to check in and say hello and maybe answer questions you might have
we'll probably do a breakout group I'll post the later today the zoom link
and what's new in the home page of imc's website I'll post it in um
in the calendar and also tomorrow morning I'll put it in the chat
so another announcement is that this Sunday this Sunday IMC is going to have
a potluck kind of a we call it a potluck picnic from 11 o'clock to 1 00 p.m here
at IMC after the morning meditation and teaching so those of you
who live close enough it's a chance to come together in community and um
we'll do it outside and and then thank you for that
so continuing uh the theme of appreciation
as a foundation for compassion a form of appreciation part of this the
next appreciation more valuable and richer is our ability to accept people as they
are and this is a nuanced kind of topic
because of course there are people who do things that we can't accept
and and so you know we're not condoning or allowing
them to continue to do things which are harmful but
so one of the aspects of acceptance but at the same time it's profound for
some people to be accepted as they are there are people plenty of people in this society that are not accepted for
basically you know for who they are and and um and so
um to because it goes everywhere they go there's people not accepting them not including them marginalizing them
ignoring them because somehow they're not accepted they
the non-accepting people might think that they're not being prejudiced or not being hostiled but the subtle ways in
which people keep silent or Overlook them or ignore them or prioritize other people to give their
attention to and the some people it's quite dramatic
that how they're not accepted some people it's subtle but it takes its toll
over a long time and because it's such a common phenomena in the world of people in some way or
they're not accepted not that we don't make room for them we don't include them
in our efforts to be inclusive of
be friends to befriend people that it's such a powerful thing to do
and some people it's rare they rarely get accepted for
themselves for how they are and to have someone who sits down with them and just there and accepts them as they are
um I've known homeless people who said when I sat down on a bench with them and
just talked with them some of you could see something inside of them relaxed and and at first they felt kind of cautious
and I remember one person who said oh I can go I don't have to be here as if they
didn't belong there but I reassured them it was okay and and we had a nice little
conversation um and um so to accept people is a profound thing
but how to do it in a way that is appropriate for oneself and for others
is part of the art of it and uh so it's a little hard to know all the ins and
outs of when acceptance is appropriate and not but I'd like to propose that one of the
kind of first criteria first kind of entry points to a radical acceptance of
others is to be dedicated towards not harming them
to have that as a clear guideline so certainly that can be any kind of
intentional harm that we would that we do for them if we have hate we have ill
will we um complain about them we blame them we
criticize them we mix night comments about them
many many forms of harm are caused by words we speak and So to avoid causing
harm and um and uh
and then we also harm by our attention if who we attend to with our attention
who we notice who we who we don't notice who we ignore and and to notice a little bit how we're
using our attention socially who do we prioritize who do we zero in on and who
is not included in our attention then is are we causing harm by exclusion By
ignoring uh who is it that feels ignored who feels marginalized in the room and is
there some way to include them and in the conversation if they're standing there and and um and and you know not
being actively included so so as we move along in this
investigation consideration of non-harming uh it's also taking other people into
account what is experience like for them what's happening for them
what do they need and for people who are causing harm people who are saying things that are
mean or people who are doing other things um is there some way to accept them that
gets underneath the action they do and so this common idea that we accept
can separate the person from their actions then we might be able to have some way
of not accepting the actions but accepting the person and not being hostile to the person
saying no to the actions but saying yes to the person so for example one might might say that
without being angry back at someone who says something mean to us we might say
oh wow that that those words they stung I feel hurt by those words they were
difficult to hear and um and I you know and I care for you but
not the words so that kind of turning it around
it's little difficult for people then to continue saying harmful words if you
kind of tell people the impact has had and then immediately turn around and appreciate them in some way or hold them
in some view of kindness or uh have some acceptance of them as a
person and what needs to be accepted in people so it might not be the whole person but
the person saying mean words it might mean what needs what needs to be accepted is that they're scared or
they're lonely or they're pretty upset and frustrated and so just you know oh
those words you spoke they stung and um and you know I wonder
if you're feeling you know sad or tired and and can I do something for you can
we kind of support you can I bring you some some coffee or something to change the language to not to buy in
to the tone of voice or the attitude or even the strategy that people are doing
that you don't like or is hard for hard to not participate in not to gauge it in
those on its terms but somehow uh you know step aside from that and return
to the person addressing some aspect of the person that maybe needs acceptance needs needs
support needs something that maybe undermines the the uh pulls
the the energy away from the harming Behavior so this is not easy to do
um but uh if we're dedicated to a life of non-harming then just that itself might be seen as
an acceptance but it could be naive but if we really try to understand
what's going on for the person so you know we want to appreciate people
what can be appreciated we want to understand them what's really
going on here what's going on on the surface what's what's deeper than their behavior that we don't like
what um you know what can we respect can we
respect the person not the behavior and then can we kind of be here with an
accepting way and I've been in situations where people have been angry angry at me I think it
wasn't Justified but they were angry with me and sometimes it has been Justified
and um and my ability to be accepting of the situation accepting of the person's
anger making room for it not accepting it because I condone it or I approve of it
but being there and allowing myself to experience it allowing myself for that
to be there so that something different can happen so it's not a fight between that person
and me so one of the nuanced the deeper ways that this topic of acceptance uh works
that I think is uh kind of key to all of it working is um is we accept whatever the
situation is whatever it is and that's a radical thing to say we accept it into
awareness we allow awareness to receive it to know it
and that's it very different uh what we might do in response what we might say
how we might evaluate the situation is a different
activity within but to allow it to come into awareness
so awareness doesn't shut down that somehow with our awareness we're not already resisting or stopping or or
attacking there's something about the peaceful experience of allowing yourself
to be aware of something they'll be accepted into awareness
and that hopefully allows us to respond uh in a wise way and will know what to
do and and uh and maybe in making room to allow ourselves to experience it to
be aware of it that um that the other person will feel
something's different going on here um this is not different that's not what I'm not what not what I'm used to
when this is someone who so someone who's sad and upset for example not
doing harm um they're they're surprised by someone who has the ability to be calm and
peaceful and attentive to their sadness and
and so we're able to accept the sadness and open to it so we don't have to fix
it right away or or you know get too involved too quickly
so accept the acceptance acceptance this kind of acceptance and
awareness allowing awareness to be accepting I think gives a lot more power to our
appreciation and respect of others because then where there's a cleaner Channel cleaner kind of transmission of
of appreciation and a clear transmission of respect that we give
so elements of appreciation depreciation
itself gratitude valuing people
then there's understanding people uh without understanding there can't be
depreciation can't be that deep there's respect to respecting people again giving the treating them as
valuable human beings valuable enough for us to pay attention to
and as we pay attention to pay attention with an accepting attention
so that something deeper can happen in our acceptance and um
we know what to accept in the person so one more time tomorrow and the last
element of appreciation and thank you very much for being part
of this and and I look forward to our time tomorrow