okay I think I'll begin now welcome
it's uh such a pleasure to be practicing together these mornings or as I said
it's maybe it's not morning for you or maybe you're watching these later
it's uh meaningful to practice together and today is the third day of the series
of poetry of practice and as I mentioned a little bit on the
first date there's a way in which we can practice where there's a lot of
specificity of directions like we're following the instructions as precisely
as we can maybe we hear the echo of a Derma teacher or some reading and a Dorma book
maybe even a podcast that we heard and we're really trying to follow the instructions with a certain
amount of maybe striving or maybe even some straining with some directionality like I'm gonna
go this direction and I'm going to do this and that can be tremendously helpful and
valuable in a support for practice foreign
that type of practice there's also another way
practice that is maybe a little bit more diffuse
and softer so it's a more of a Feeling
[Music] sensing our way maybe tuning into and
becoming sensitive to what's happening and feeling into where the next moment
of Freedom or ease well-being can be found
so rather than going one particular direction feeling into what's needed in
the next moment to help support this opening softening
sense of well-being and contentment Peace and Freedom to arise
so we're still practicing with the same intentionality but in a different way
and in this series The Poetry of practice I'm pointing to the second way there's more this sense of sensitivity
Attunement and feeling into what needs to be next maybe with less of
a sense of following instructions
and more just feeling our way to the next moment
and maybe I'll just add this before we begin this guided meditation the Buddha spoke about right before his Awakening
that his mind was malleable so I'd like to think of this word
malleable as a way in which there's this sense of feeling into becoming sensitive
to as well as the sense of directionality and intentionality
so that is an introduction well I'll guide us a little bit during
this guided meditation and then I'll drop in a poem a short poem
and I'll talk about a little bit after the guided meditation
so we'll take a moment to settle in
feeling the experience of taking a meditation posture
and feel and feel body in this meditation posture
like to sit or whatever posture you're in and to know that you are in that posture
what does it feel like becoming sensitive tuned to
the body in this particular configuration
in particular we might tune into the sensations have been connected
grounded to that which is supporting us
might be the sensations of the feet on the ground
the legs in connection with the chair the mat the
couch bed wherever we are whatever we're doing
on the buttocks being in connection with the seat cushion chair feeling the
pressure against the body feeling this connection
with that which is supporting us
opening the uprightness of the body
the spine
and if you're using the back rest feeling the pressure
of the chair against the back
and bringing some attention to the face this is a place where
so many nerve endings and the phase has so many different ways it can be expressive
but there's also a way in which the face can hold attention or tightness
check in with the sensations around the mouth the jaw
and the eyes
tuning in to any tension or tightness
and allowing any softening that might occur with this attention
it's okay if it doesn't soften but if it does just allowing that opening that
softening to arise
oh and then tuning in
to the sensations of breathing
the experience of the body breathing
feeling the sensations at the nose the chest
the belly whatever feels comfortable and
accessible for you right now
what does it feel like could have an in-breath
or that what are the experiences
what does it feel like to have an out breath what are those experiences
and of course the transitions between in-breaths and out breaths
what is that like
and setting the intention for the remainder of this meditation to be one
of openness softness sensitivity to what's happening
as best we can as best we can
foreign
[Music] as it's apt to do we just very simply
gently Begin Again tuning into the sensations of breathing
foreign
so now I'm going to drop in a poem
absolutely no need to do anything with this poem
just allow it to enter and
that's all
the poem goes like this it is foolish
to let a young Redwood grow next to a house
even in this one lifetime you will have to choose
that great calm being this clutter of soup pots and bunks
already the first Branch tips brush at the window
Softly calmly immensely
TAPS at your life
Softly calmly immensity
foreign
thank you
foreign foreign
foreign
[Music]
so again welcome welcome for everybody
it's lovely to practice together
so this idea of poetry of practice
and there's poems prose do does as well but poems there's
a way in which they often use metaphor and I really evocative way and this is
part of what can make poetry be so powerful maybe speaking directly to the heart
because it's using metaphor so maybe not the usual Concepts or labels or language
that we would use to describe something but instead sometimes in poetry there's a way in which there's a pointing to
something rather than saying it or labeling it directly
so maybe there's a way in which the heart and the mind have to like look in a particular direction
in order to understand what the poem what the poet is pointing towards
and we might say in some ways all we're ever doing when we speak about
something is to point towards it when it reads there's a difference between the labels and the words that we
use then the actual objects or experiences
and there's something about poetry that doesn't try to pretend that it's not doing that whereas in our usual language
we might think that the map it's the territory for example that the concept that the word is the
actual thing that's important so in some ways we might even say that
practice this meditation practice this Buddhist practice is so much about highlighting the difference
between the words the labels that we assign to something
and the actual experience of that something
so here's the poem that I read during the guided meditation
I'll name the name of the poem and the poet at the end here this morning
but for now just feel into this poem
it is foolish to let a young Redwood grow next to a house
even in this one lifetime you will have to choose that great calm being
this clutter of super pots and books
already the first Branch tips brush at the window Softly
calmly immensity TAPS at your life
so this poem begins with it is foolish to let a young Redwood grow next to a
house this poet grew up in the bay actually I don't know if they grew up in the area
but certainly lived in the Bay Area and practiced with the San Francisco's end Center
and this roll of trees and for the body sorry for the Buddha it
was the booty tree but uh for this part it's a redwood tree
and ancient India these Bodhi trees were Majestic
and certainly here in California redwood trees have this same sense of majesty or
Mighty or dignity there's a way in which being in a Grove of redwood trees any of
you have been there no there's a sense of it being in a cathedral so this poet is pointing to trees the
powerfulness of trees as well as maybe the the specialness the dignity
powerfulness of trees and we could say in this poem it's represented practice
so it's foolish to let a young redwood tree grow next to a house and we could
say that a house represents the self is that we that which we build and
create and feel like we have to support and hide behind or hide within or get
lost within and and the Buddha certainly use this in some other poems that he's used that we
can find in the domapara about talking about the house Builder being you know
the self and the house itself being itself but a house can also represent like our
attachments those things that we are tangled up with
and so I was can literally be a house but maybe not necessarily
and then in this line it is foolish to let a young Redwood grow next to a house
foolish and Paulie this word is foolish is the same word as child
so it's a way of just not knowing better yet and the Buddha called people fools who
didn't recognize that what they were doing was a source of suffering
so this idea of planting a redwood tree
brightness next to a house a sense of self
then the poem continues even in this one lifetime you will have to choose
this notion of maybe I'll just say some of you might know that IMC inside
Meditation Center is in Redwood City there's a reason why it's called a Redwood City there's a number of reasons
but one is um this redwood trees there and in the front of IMC is this really
big redwood tree maybe I don't know what the diameter is maybe eight feet something it's really big
and this red Retreat over the years has been growing and growing and the sidewalk around it was like buckling and
it's really getting distorted and was you know creating a tripping Hazard for people
so IMC worked to level out the sidewalk and I had to call them the city to help
with this uh I love this so much the city came in looked at this redwood tree
looked at the sidewalk and they just decided to reroute the sidewalk around the tree
just recognizing that trees are powerful and they grow and there's no stopping
them because no matter how much concrete you put down on a sidewalk so you'll be in the same way maybe this
poet knew this had this experience for themselves and it was the same way in which practice
grows it's the nature to grow and it disrupts
our sense of self disrupts our attachments
so this idea of that if you don't want anything in your life to change if you
don't want any disruptions then don't plant your practice next to
it so this poem continues by saying you'll
have to choose between that create a great calm being and this
clutter of soup pots and books that great calm being
you could say his Awakening we could say it's practice you could say it's just regular meditation
and then this clutter of soup pots and books maybe this poem is a little bit
autobiographical maybe the poet has a lot of books and likes to cook
but clutter is the opposite of calm maybe there's a sense of things not
being cared for or being neglected and we might ask ourselves
what in our life is the opposite of calm
what is what do we have what have we filled our life with our sense of self with that's the opposite of calm
so this problem is not asking us to let go of our soup pots and books
necessarily but I would say it's asking us to let go of our grasping to them our
clinging or craving our compulsion to like shift our relationship to the
objects of the world and allow that relationship to be disrupted by this growing practice
Palace growing tree and maybe it's asking us to soften and
let go of all the ways that we limit and Define ourselves
and to let go of those objects and experiences that we're using to bolster and protect
[Music] maybe even inflate sense of self that we have
so this disruption of course it doesn't have to be violent it doesn't have to be
some big giant painful things it's the way it might just be this simple
gentle dismantling of this house this sense of self
that we're so trying to hold on to so maybe it's something as simple of
softening of resentment or a grudge and starting to feel and see more
clearly how this leads to suffering or maybe it's about softening our
preferences for how we think other people should behave or how we should behave
this way is in which we're dismantling a little bit to this
sense of self then this poem continues
already the first Branch tips brush at the window
I love this you know the branch tips right this is what's uh visible above
the ground it's maybe obvious when there's the roots of the trees or what disrupts the
sidewalks off often and they're not so visible but there's a way that just brushing at
the window maybe there's this way that sometimes we can just really feel
practice leading our life it's not necessarily always Pleasant and
maybe it only happens under certain conditions just like the brush tip the tips brush only when it's windy for
example but is there a way that we can become
sensitive to and notice or maybe we've already noticed the way that practice is affecting our
life or maybe this is a question
in what ways has practice brushed up against your life
maybe you're not cursing at the driver that's going to slow in the lane in
front of you or Cuts you off or doesn't use their blink or whatever it might be
and then this poem ends with softly calmly
immensity TAPS at your life
immensity Without Limits vastness without a sense
of how things should be maybe without a sense of self like with no limits
and first the practice is brushing against the window and then it's tapping a little bit more insistent and the way
that we can't really maybe ignore it
so maybe there's this shift in emphasis and maybe we're starting to choose oh that
calm beam the tree practice or versus this clutter of soup pots and
books so I'll read this poem
one more time here it is foolish to let a young Redwood
grow next to a house even in this one lifetime you will have to choose
that great calm being this clutter of soup pots and books
already the first Branch tips brush at the window softly calmly immensity TAPS at your
life this poem is called tree and it's by
Jane hirschfield I'll say this again and the poem is called tree
and it's by Jane hirschfield and I offered my interpretation of this
poem but what's your interpretation I offered one way we can look at this but
part of the beauty of I would say practice and poetry is that we each find
our own way nobody's way is exactly the same
nobody's interpretation of this poem will be exactly the same what is your interpretation
how does this poem relevant to your life today
so thank you thank you for your practice and I'll see you tomorrow