well as I um
do when I come here I in the meditation I think about what are these are these different things come up
into my mind what I should talk about
and then I let him go
I try not to grab onto any of them
but one thing that strikes me is that um
we're all sitting together here
and it just feels to me like uh that we're that it's a stream of awareness
that we're sharing that maybe this sounds far-fetched to you but this is how I experience it that there's a
stream of awareness in here that we're that we're sharing
or maybe it's just my stream of awareness or not just my stream of awareness it is
my stream of awareness
what could be greater what could be
more vast more imminent
more pervasive if I want to think of something to talk
about that's true what could be more true
than this I don't know if I should say my stream of awareness this stream of awareness
and I say it's in the room but
it is in the room it's bigger it's well I can see the room
I can feel the space of the room I can see all of you
or except looking at different senses I can taste a little bit of something in my mouth so the awareness
has all of these qualities of the five senses
your five senses your hearing
you can hear right you can hear something maybe I hear something I don't think I have tinnitus but I
always hear of something in my inner ear that's
a great teacher calls it The Sound of Silence
I can definitely see you can see right you can hear if you're kind of examine your tongue
you can probably taste a little something there
and certainly we feel we feel our bodies
we feel hot or cold
and we are there's some feeling in our body some feeling
like you could say it's an emotion perhaps but some feeling that we have we have a
feeling we always have a feeling if we look look at it
and we have thoughts
and that's it that's all we got we have the five sense perceptions
thoughts and feelings
is there any is there anything more that you have than that
it's kind of amazing isn't it it's all we got
and it keeps going in this stream of
feelings thoughts Sensations tastes see
ing hearing and it goes on and on and on is
this stream
and sometimes we get really busy try to create a better stream
what we want we want the best stream we want a good stream
that's I think I re that should be respected we want a good stream we want to be happy
we want to have well-being so that's something else that I think is
in US there's this stream of awareness
and I talked about a feeling before well
there's something in us that wants to be happy that one's well-being that's probably
why we're here
it's probably why you meditate you want to have well-being
trouble is we want more well-being than is what is so amply provided
so amply abundantly provided by this stream
we want more
but I really respect that we want well-being
that we want to be happy that we want ease
we want all kinds of things that we should have it's
kind of our Birthright
and that's love that wanting that
I want you to have well-being nice to see you
and I want you to have well-being and I want all of you to have well-being it's just natural
if we aren't obscured by
by the uh odious
quality of comparative thinking competitive thinking
where I was originally trained there was a saying
that stuck in me all it's just
all these years comparisons are odious
compared to comparisons destroy our well-being
measuring ourselves against others
making a thing
out of me or me making a me and a you
and comparing measuring
everything's going so well the stream of awareness is going so well and I want to be you know happy and I want you to be
happy and I want well I want there to be well-being and ease and and then
oh then all of a sudden I compare myself to someone else ugh
what a buzz kill
the Buddha said a couple of things about this but one
that I remember word for word
is he who sees through
the deception of
more than less than or equal to
will not suffer
so the Buddha is saying
in a way this is the secret to life
if you can give up or not indulge in
comparative thinking you won't suffer
and we all know that's what Buddhism is all about right
how not to suffer but we do it anyhow
and I'm not saying I'm not going to do it and I'm not saying you shouldn't do it and I'm not saying
you shouldn't suffer or that I shouldn't suffer
or maybe we can be at ease with our suffering we can allow the suffering
to be there in the Stream of awareness
just relaxing and let the suffering be
you know if we want to get rid of suffering I don't want this suffering
I want to yeah that's a lot of me
that's a lot of control
and it brings more suffering
so there's comparative thinking
Maybe or something else comes along that makes you suffer makes me suffer like a
habitual pattern arises
an affliction
there's one school of thought it's called The Yoga Chara School
that says there aren't just those seven things the five sense perceptions
and and um
thinking and feeling
but there's an eighth one afflictions
inflictive an afflictive mind that we have an afflictive mind that we turn our
thoughts and our feelings and our Sensations into a me a self
and I don't know if this is interesting to you
maybe it's kind of academic I don't know it is to me it's interesting
there's an afflictive Consciousness a me Consciousness that suffers
so to bring it back to Earth
we probably mostly from comparative thinking we have anger
hatred
jealousy it all has to do with other people
self-doubt I'm not as good as
fear anxiety
so you have your own afflictive thoughts
and feelings I hope you know them
I heard a fellow a great teacher today saying
so it takes the these afflictions they come in many shapes and forms in a different circumstances
but he says they're really just they're just in each of us just one or two maybe one
so when you think about your suffering over the years
and years and years and years and it's kind of the same suffering
I was talking to a friend of mine today about that I I think that's a very interesting
thought there's only one or two seems like there's such a variety
come up in this situation and we think about our our life of suffering and you know how it was suffering in high school
and suffering when you know we were you know
College suffering and
midlife suffering suffering these days
and it kind of has the same flavor my you know your flavor is going to be different from your flavor but
but it's based on maybe some something that happened in the family
some habitual pattern that originated in your family
so
just let it be let let that Consciousness be
just let it be
and letting it be is like this love
that wants us this essential love that we have that once well-being
that wants us to be happy that wants us to Beauty so be at ease with suffering just let it be
fight with our suffering don't have to get entangled with our
suffering
letting it be my darling
suffer all you want go ahead
treating your suffering holding it
with warmth
it's not your fault we all have this
eighth consciousness
actually the yoga Chara School I'm getting my numbers confused
five sense objects thinking is six and then the afflictive Consciousness is
7. so yeah and then the yoga charter school
has another another Consciousness that they describe and the Buddha
also described this in a Sutra all of these things
and it's called the Elia vignana
it's beneath our Consciousness it's a storehouse consciousness it stores all of our Karma
it's like it's um I think of it like a some ground some some vast vast ground
and it said when we do something I could do something quote unquote good
it goes into our Elia vignana and it becomes a seed
we do something bad it becomes a seed so the alive vinyana
I like this I think it's it makes sense to me
it's a ground that holds all of these seeds of our Karma
and then something happens
and a seed sprouts you never know what's going to happen
look at all the things that happened to you today
you never know what kind of karma is going to arise tomorrow you might want to
love someone hug someone you might want to be irid you might get irritated or
afraid of someone or you know all kinds of things happen you might start feeling lonely
insecure it's coming from our Elia vinyana and then the
afflictive Consciousness makes a me
out of that I am insecure
I'm full of Rage I want
and all of those suffer and it's all part of this flow of
awareness it just keeps flowing
and we can embrace it all with
with love
by love I mean by allowing it just allowing it to flow
I'm not going to try to stop you
I don't know what's going to happen next but it's okay with me
there are thousands of thoughts that keep coming through my mind
Let It Be who cares so what
there's a saying the greatest transformation
the greatest transformation is non-transformation
just letting it be is the greatest transformation
we work so hard sometimes to create a better me or get rid of a
worse me a bad me
or we work so hard in so many things that have to do with comparisons with others
makes me sad to think about it making making trying to get people to
like us and say with good things about us think well of us and
I know a guy he's a scientist and he he just really really wants to be so
he's a great guy but he really wants to be successful
any he wakes up at night thinking about
this this this stuff this these projects that are going through his mind and he's really nervous about he wants them to be
successful
I hope he accepts that and lets it be because that's the way it is for him
without trying to
become anything special
do anything special
because really what could be more special
than this
this past
awareness is as big as this room right we can sense this whole room
and we can sense so many things
I was meditating this morning
trying to remember what was going on um
it wasn't exactly this but it was something like what's the meaning of life
what's the meaning of this it wasn't exactly that it was more of a feeling looking for something some kind
of something I was looking for
some discontent was there
what's the meaning of life what's the meaning of your life what is the meaning of your life
is it your work your relationships your
it's really got to come down to just this just this
there's a Buddha right here
just this he's sitting right in the middle of it and he has so much there's so much
meaning in that Buddha
serenely sitting in the middle of
just this
just relaxed
is this enough for you
I have a
an ink drawing on my altar made by our Suzuki Roshi's son her witso
Rochelle
and it is a very simple
it's a carrot a couple of carrots in front of a rabbit
the carrots are orange and the rabbit is but it's very simple just an ink drawing of this carrot with of this rabbit with
just it's not complex the eyes are dots but they're very awake dots
so it's just this simple rabbit with these carrots in front of him
and the calligraphy says I have enough
I have enough
with whatever is happening right now
with the vast space of awareness
and the feelings in your body and the thoughts in your mind
and your eyesight your sounds you hear and all these things
and your afflictions
and your welcoming of it all Your Love
welcoming it all owing it all to take place and to flow
freely flow
whatever is happening allowing it to happen is love
without getting in the way of it can you do any better than that
I had a dream the night before last that I walked into
a pet shop and I saw these
little puppies doggies in cages on a Shelf
looking out Yorkies they look like small dog like Yorkies or
chihuahuas and I felt very bad for these doggies
as I always do when I go into Pet Shops
and then the the sales girl
said the owner the roshi isn't here right now
and when she said the owner the roshi
something completely changed in me and
it made this place this Pet Shop seemed like
kind place a realized place like the
the realization the Blessed realization
of a great master was perfuming this Pet Shop
and then I looked at the dogs again and the dogs were not troubled whatsoever
they were just sitting there completely at ease
so wondering if you have any uh comments or
protests or questions about anything that I've said
anything coming up for you that you'd like to talk about
David I like what you said about that Reservoir deep inside that holds
accumulated past karmas I think that's a lion
um it seems to me to be how things are at one level
can you take off your mask so I can hear you yeah at one level you see how your mind works and
where your attachments and aversions are and
you work on letting go of them and in a way you do but there's some
stuff suffering deeper down that you haven't really fully worked it out of yourself
does that make sense yeah oh now that sounds like suffering is
that what you're talking about uh disease no I mean they lead to
suffering but what I'm talking about is patterns patterns yeah that um
accumulated I think it's really interesting that it's just one or two things does that make sense to you I
hadn't thought of it that way before yeah I think it's amazing if you think about it think about that
I didn't recognize you behind your mask but it's so nice to see you yeah
um think about it it's just one or two
things for instance um
I don't know what it is for you I was talking to a woman today about this and she said oh that's right that's
what happened to me when I was a little girl and I felt that way since I was a little girl the same
very similar dis ease has come up in so
many different forms hers was like being uh left out of the popular group in sixth
grade but then she identified well it's always feeling a little bit left out of this
and that and this and that all through her life and that was her thing but uh
you might recognize that but it doesn't matter that that's just I just very interesting but um
but if we just don't fight with them and allow them to be
as they arise from this
structure of the LIE of vinyana becoming this and that if we just allow them to
float up come into fruition grow into whatever
they want to grow into mature blossom into a full-fledged affliction
they free themselves they always free themselves they're gone right I don't even know what was bothering me
if anything was bothering me an hour or two ago but I know things always you know they're always changing they're
always liberating themselves can you think can you remember a thought
you had a minute ago so everything is always freeing
itself so we don't have to worry so hard so much about I gotta free this I gotta work on this I gotta you know
we drive just relax and let it be and welcome with love accepting allowing
there are other ways to work with afflictions this is a very gentle way
the way of the path of accepting the path of equanimity
is the path of accepting
there are other ways
one way is to get rid of them
if I think a loving thought if I think a meta thought I can't think a hateful thought
can't you can't think two thoughts at the same time for example is another way
a way of getting rid of that's a Hinata way
this is another way of accepting allowing
which I really like because it's so big and generous and warm and compassionate
and calling on what's deeply intrinsic to Who We Are
we don't have to manufacture anything
compassion is here in that acceptance
Love is Here we're naturally compassionate I don't want you to suffer
I just don't I don't want myself to suffer
unless there's some comparative thinking
some odious comparative thinking I want you all to be happy and I want myself to be happy and there's this generosity
this openness that was intrinsic
and there's this awareness that's intrinsic
so all we have to do is relax and simply
be ourselves be our perfect selves you're perfect all Just As You Are
I'm perfect this is it's so nice it takes all the pressure off
the greatest transformation
is non-transformation
the Buddha tried so hard
with ascetic exercises is stomach was
you said a sunflower seed couldn't fit between his spine and his stomach he was just it
just almost died by the river and he did all these yogic exercises we need all
these concentration exercises going through all these genres and finally he just thought of himself as a child
and he's relaxed
and then he said this is profound
this is peaceful
just to be
and he said this is Luminous this is Luminous
the light is on your light is on
your light is always on well when you go to sleep it's not on but it's
it's always on we don't have to use a flashlight to find our light it's
on couldn't be more obvious
that's our refuge
we don't have to manufacture a refuge
we are we have awareness
luminosity we have love we have compassion
thank you