so hello hello welcome Happy New Year this
this um this transition that we call the new
year um yeah maybe I'll speak a little bit about that before we transition into our
practice so so yes in some ways it's you know every moment every every mind
moment every moment it's a continuation and yet there is a goodness there is a
value um who to Transitions actually
um psychologists uh studies tell us that
when there is a transition when there is actually the new year or even a new
month or even at the beginning of a week or Monday for example they're they're
very psychological effects that we can take advantage of we can take advantage of there's a sense of a fresh start
there's a sense of a fresh start even though yes we all know that every moment
really can be a fresh start and instead of
self-flagellating and and beating ourselves up for say having been X Y and
Z or not having been X Y and Z we can just begin again at this moment a fresh
start in this beginning every moment um the New Year's Day every moment fresh as
the spring yes and there is a goodness there is a
beauty in this in this um convention that uh yeah the year changes
there's a Convention of a fresh start so let's let's appreciate the goodness of that the
psychological because we're yes we're all we're uh Spiritual Beings we're
Divine beings and we're also psychological beings and these were not immune uh us us dear lovely fragile
strong human beings were not immune to the psychological effects so let's take
advantage let's take advantage of of this this Fresh Start effect this
fresh start of the new year so so with
the idea of the Fresh Start yes and still the first week of January and today is the first Friday of course if
you're in a time zone like Mario Christine in Australia it's already Saturday but uh but uh for those who are
still Fridays is the first Friday of of uh 2023 so it's still a fresh start
still a fresh start so with that theme of a fresh start
um both as a convention beginning of a year beginning of the week Etc
um as well as every moment of Fresh Start everyone connecting yes maybe
today you know had the intention to be kind to myself it didn't quite happen I wanted
to be kind to others and didn't quite happen but it's okay it's a
what does a fresh start require in each it
well many things but one thing that it does require is mindfulness is awareness
a fresh start as a support for meta requires mindfulness it requires
awareness it requires connecting with intention of course for a fresh
start but more than anything else it requires awareness mindfulness in in
[Music] um Nepali the language of the Buddha Sati s-a-t-i Sati mindfulness awareness we
need to grock like oh yeah this is this is what's happening this is where I am this is what my intention is this is my
what my values are this um so there's a sense of connecting connecting awareness
connecting connecting not heavy-handed it doesn't have to be
heavy-handed it's supportive it's just arriving being here
being right here not in the past not in the future but being right here
connecting connecting so in this first Friday Saturday of the
Year let's connect let's connect let's turn towards connecting
with awareness connecting with um Sati mindfulness as a basis as a
support for kindness as support for loving kindness a support for compassion the support for
Equanimity support for all support for all these beautiful qualities of the
heart first we need to have a sense of connecting connecting to this moment connecting to
this body connecting your head here right here Awakening does not happen in the past or
in the future it happens in this moment so so let's connect together
to this body to this moment ah the freshness of this moment this
freshness of this moment beginning again and again and again and again
how delicious how amazing to be able to start again and again so
so with that let's uh let's meditate together let's meditate together
so I'd like to invite you to land in your seat
sitting upright that's possible for your body or if your body needs to lie down
or if it needs to stand up see what this body needs In This Moment any adjustment
that it might need if you are sitting you are sitting let there be a sense of
Integrity to your posture the bottom of your feet if you're
sitting on a chair the bottom of your feet be flat on the Earth
your hands on your lap a sense of Integrity a sense of
Integrity to your body
the spine straight but not tight maybe feel that
there is this Invisible Thread connected to the top of your head
vertebrae by vertebrae ah pouring you pulling you up
it's happening on its own lend the flesh the
soft issue of your body can relax soften
you're being held up
letting your belly relax soften
receiving the breath in the abdomen however
it comes short long shallower deep
relaxing relax offering the weight of the lower
half of the body to the Earth with age out breath
letting go of the weight of the upper body into your sit bones
especially the weight of your head neck shoulders
as if the weight was a river flowing onto the Earth through the Earth
one with the Earth
the Earth whole too supports you
you can relax
let go of any tightness
holding for the next half breath
questions
receiving receiving this moment
however it shows up in this body
whatever Sensations of the breath
and other Sensations
connecting with this moment as it is experienced
so delicious and wonderful to be connected
through awareness through knowing to This Moment's experience right here
intimate intimacy with this experience
of Being Human being breathed
Sensations even thoughts are rising and passing
knowing knowing that you are sitting
and breathing from the inside
and if thoughts arise and take you to the past and future no problem
and you realize this has happened let go of the balloons of thought release
lovingly relieved smilingly and begin again a fresh start to
reconnect reconnect
the freshness of this moment it's like spring
this moment of Being Human it's enough
it's more than enough it's magical
one moment of awareness clearly knowing connecting
here
just this is enough
just knowing paying attention
right here intimate is the foundation of goodness
Foundation of kindness to oneself to others
staying with awareness
they relaxed body and mind and heart
foreign
so nourishing just to be breathed and no
and no
Sublime
and if there's agitation or sleepiness or anything else knowing that too
knowing that befriending whatever is present
knowing intertwined with benevolence kindly knowing whatever
is arising this moment is like this
you can no boredom with interest agitation with love
let me get to know you your heart your body dear mind at this
moment fresh as if I'm meeting you for the first time
beginner's mind
let me know you let me learn your ways with patience with kindness
let me know let me know
the mind is busy let me know you
dear agitated mind
without getting tight the opposite let me relax
and know you soothe you
Stillness let me know you wandering mind let me know you
what is so juicy
that's pulling you away dear my dear heart let me know you
and connect again Fresh Start in this moment all I know
relaxed knowing is the foundation of goodness relaxed
curious kind benevolent knowing
it's the foundation of goodness
nothing no experience internally is a problem
don't make it into one get to know it get to know it with
kindness curiosity interest benevolence love
get to know this being who is you
Sensations thoughts patterns to know
a fresh and new each moment lovingly
beginning and now every moment infinitely
Maybe this image is aspiring to you inspiring it's an image of yourself
beginning in new and new and new each moment fresh
timeless timelessly
with a sense of freshness as if spring
it's arriving each moment awareness kindness
benevolence curiosity mindfulness infinitely
eternally starting anew
the inner spine always and forever
foreign
no need to be bogged down
with moments squandered whatever mind State I may not have been
helpful Begin Again Always Forever
yes yes we can yes we can
as we bring this practice period sitting period to a close together
offering the goodness from all the moments we started Anew
connected with awareness with knowing
with kindness benevolence it's a foundation
offering the goodness of even one moment of connection infinitely
more than zero offering this goodness to ourselves as a gift to all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy
we all may all beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so we have um time for
Reflections questions comments how was this period of practice for you
did you discover something new I might have been interesting for you
different opening or maybe something's confusing
you can type your questions in chat if you want I've opened the chat now and if
you open if you type them or reflections of course just type them to me privately I will
not read your name you type them to everyone then I will read your name so
you can also lift your Zoom hand because it's your
physical end I will not see you there are many of you on the screen so I will not see you but uh yeah what did you
discover Graham says thank you and YouTube you
are welcome Graham thanks for joining us on YouTube
um Jerry says easy to start but it got more difficult at the end with distractions
okay no problem nothing is a problem get to know the mind but
that is getting attracted to distractions what is Juicy about it
Laura asks I was struggling with sleepiness how do you recommend dealing
with that what is the advantage to continuing to meditate as opposed to just going to bed
ah okay good question good foundational question Laura
um well it really depends um what the source of the sleepiness is
if you are tired if if you have sleep
um if you have lack of sleep sleep deprivation Etc then yeah maybe actually
taking a nap is is the wisest thing to do however a lot of times actually
um sleepiness is not just
being sleep deprived Etc sometimes it's masking something else
it's masking agitation sometimes when you're agitated or even remorse or even
sadness or a lot of different hosts of of um
emotions and mind states that can actually be masked with what's called
sloth and torper it's one of the five hindrances in in Buddhism and practice
so then then just actually going to bed is is not helpful just taking a nap is
not helpful learning how to skillfully work with it and recognize it is more uh
is is wiser um so you have to recognize actually what is happening and
um they're in in a list of recommendations from the Buddhist
teachings their long list of things suggested you know there's there is uh I'm going to bed taking a nap is the
last one first is you know you can actually open your eyes a little bit with a little bit of light in not that
you're staring at it and you're just letting your eyes open up a little bit foreign and you can open up your eyes
just a little bit or you can stand up you can do standing meditation uh that
brings in energy you can have some not at night I don't recommend this but if
it's during the day and you're meditating and you're sleeping you can have some green tea you can go for a
walk fast walk bring up the energy many many different things one can do
one can actually just can just just sit up a little straighter than that actually just a little bit of shift in
the posture can bring up more energy there are a lot of things we can do and then the last thing on the list of
recommendations from the Canon as well picking up if nothing is worth then take a nap so
foreign let's see a few other gosh let's lots of
things are coming in um yeah thank you for the message that new
beginnings are always available even when going through a huge live transition yes
another person asked is that why you say not to drink caffeine before sitting in the morning uh
uh well I don't think I've said that but
um are you saying in general you've heard that don't drink caffeine before sitting in the morning
um it's it's [Music] um
basically no excuse me this is a longer uh
you know longer treaties longer longer conversation about caffeine can caffeine
tends to agitate the mind and I've had many people who've gone along Retreats who
've been drinking lots and lots of coffee on retreat they they're still used to it but they try to reduce their
coffee and then they realize wow when they drink coffee their mind is so agitated just a very very different
state of mind [Music] um
let's see I thought I heard you say that once I asked another I'll ask another time I
don't remember saying that but but in general the as I shared the uh the uh
caffeine can agitate the mind in this way in general and and yet so many of
and and to say actually sometimes a little bit of caffeine like with green tea can be skillful just a little bit
but but I've discovered and also other practitioners have discovered that strong coffee can agitate their mind a
little too much on the body too and see for yourself be a scientist of your own mind don't take any of these
um and face value um and YouTube couple of comments thank you
I needed this tonight I had heard so many tragic stories today uh and another
person grabs a standing meditation helps me be more energized yes great fantastic I love standing meditation and walking
meditation too
and one person says after my mother died a few weeks ago I'm so sorry to hear
that I've been feeling Despair and having many realistic thoughts this
practice today gave me moments of feeling that maybe I don't have to answer any questions about what the
point of it all is but maybe the questions of meaning itself is almost
absurd within the ceaseless flow of life as it simply is moment to moment I felt
relief thank you um thank you for sharing that insight and
I'm so sorry having lost your mom so difficult
yeah and and thank you so much for sharing this beautiful Insight this there is a Grace there is a beauty there
is the ceaseless flow of life as it simply is you've put it so beautifully
in your words thank you for sharing that with me and the whole Sangha what what a
relief and life is it's so magical mysterious this this and
amazing just amazing this experience of knowing and so beautiful that you were
able to touch into that by just the Mind connecting with the experience of this
just this just this is enough just this is enough don't need to know all the
answers yeah thank you
so the time has come Dear Community for us to turn
to practicing in small groups together so the um invitation to today with the
small groups as we practice together um turn
groups of roughly size of three first is to just show up show up however
you are show up however you are and
um with kindness with presence with a sense of presence really showing up with presence for one another and this might
be actually be more quiet time to get together in small groups and not so much talking so much but actually
the invitation I want to have is can you show up in this so in this small social
context but not feel so much Social like I have to say something I'm expecting no what if you just showed up with
awareness showed up with awareness internally externally you just showed up internally
externally with awareness and maybe words come up and you say something
maybe it's the stream of Consciousness oh I'm feeling myself sitting I I'm
aware that yeah that I'm feeling a little nervous with two people in this
room right now in this breakout room you can just be a stream of Consciousness or it can just be silently holding space
there's no nothing needs to happen nothing needs to happen socially nothing
needs to be said nothing needs to happen so notice notice if there's this drive
of wanting to make something happen wanting to say wanting I just sit with that sit back with that and just be kind
just know just know if you're just talking to fill in the space the silence
sweetheart sweetheart sweetheart tell yourself sweetheart pull yourself back
and just sit Silence with others maybe few words will come
even comes but a sense of it can be actually quite magical to just be in a
state of awareness with others flowing together the sense of flow
together so all right and make space for each other of course
it's inviting a lot of presents this could be magical this can be quite an
experience so try it out be kind be kind curious be in
your body be in your body not in your head be in your body okay all right take care of yourself
take care of each other here are the rooms here we go
the rooms are closed now everybody's back welcome back
everyone and uh it's seven o'clock but I wonder if maybe one person can tell us
how it was if there was it was different from usual or if it wasn't someone who
doesn't usually speak I like to invite you to move forward foreign
person says thank you so much Nikki this was lovely oh yeah great beautiful
good to see you yay any other reflections
well I don't see anyone jumping in so so I think there's a lot of presence and
silence here and so this is great we'll just keep that and and we'll dedicate
the Merit may all beings everywhere be happy and free including ourselves
thank you all thank you so much for your practice be well be present