so hello hello and good evening good morning good whatever time of the day
you're joining um from in right now
so let's um let's just start practicing together so
what I've been exploring the past a few sessions and then the the uh the
Dartmouth instructions will come through the guided meditation but I'll keep it
pretty light tonight I think that's what my heart is called to keep it pretty
light in instructions with a lot of silence for us to settle together so
so with that I'd like to invite us all arrive to land to land in our bodies to
land in our chairs cushions come together
and meditate
let go foreign let go of
wanting to meditate wanting to do
something in a particular way but step into the possibility of
just being not doing but being
letting go letting go let's start by letting go
of all the busyness that have that might have come for this moment
letting go of thoughts plans right now they might be darting back and forth
smilingly say thank you I'll engage with you later
please come back later right now I'm going to give my whole heart this
way of being just being so cool
this mysteriousness of being without asking questions trying to
figure it out
I'd just be be a body be a body that breathes
with all magical Sensations
foreign
[Music] flower petal foreign
gently gently blow it away as if you're blowing a kiss to this thought
[Music] later thank you
settle in with breath foreign foreign foreign
foreign foreign
foreign
it's okay it's okay
just take refuge foreign
simplicity here now
foreign foreign
foreign foreign foreign foreign foreign foreign
foreign
foreign foreign
just here is enough just being here is enough
foreign
expectations [Music]
from you by you and yourself all the demands all the shirts
and they're all released [Music] take them back put them back on later
but right now what if they're all released you don't have to be anyone
you don't have to do anything nothing is needed of you expected of you
but to just be be
human as poignant as
beautiful as broken as it is to be human to just be
nothing is
B just to be alive in this life of yours
whatever it is In This Moment
but if you breathed with that with this
let it Infuse your heart your mind your body this letting go
of expectations of shoots needing to be someone
to do is Drop It In This Moment
experiment see what might open up
nowhere to go foreign to be
nothing to do
be free foreign
foreign
freedom to yourself in this moment as an expression of mitta
the freedom from planning moment Freedom From the Past
put it all down
Freedom From Your Role your responsibilities
your chores
put it all down in this moment in your mind in your heart
foreign
you're not releasing It All Forever but just in this moment putting it down exploring experimenting
what is it like to put down expectations of yourself
of the world of others foreign foreign
foreign foreign
foreign
being simple is profound beyond words
foreign foreign
foreign
foreign this
sit to a close together
letting go of any expectations and you should for what this period of practice should
have looked like Let It Go of judgments letting go of
expectations it was exactly what it had to be
even all the causes and conditions I preceded it let go let go of shirts let go of
expectations In This Moment an offer all of us let us offer
goodness of our practice goodness of our heart showed up as best as we were able to
share that offer that to all things everywhere
may all beings be well may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
so the theme foreign
expectations letting go of shoulds of
demands of just letting go letting go that sense of no one to be nowhere to go
experimenting offering ourselves this release release from expectations
release as a form of meta because we often layer on so much on ourselves and
the society does the same and of course many of that is appropriate for who we
are and and what you know the wholesome aspirations we have in the world the rules we have the relationships not to
not to let go of all of that however it's experimenting in this
moment with this practice what if I let go of that I can bring it all back on you know in 30 minutes after this
meditation is over but what if I let go of expectations on myself what can I if
I let go of it as much as possible what happens do I notice the weight of it how
much of it is extra how much of it is appropriate how much of it is extra this
big driven to do and be and whatever it might be the
the shape of it in our constructs a nice psychological and life constructs but
just noticing that difference if I put it down oh wow
it's different it's just it's it's profound to just be
you just breathe you just live this life simply it's profound it's beautiful
nothing needs to happen so that was the invitation to explore
that a little bit as much as might have been available or not it's perfectly fine
foreign like to invite us now to turn
to explore this question of doing being becoming and letting go
of that just for a minute as an exercise in this practice offering this Freedom
radical freedom to ourselves um as an act of meta to um to explore
that together in small groups in conversation what was that like what did
you notice um and the answer might be I fell asleep I was
and I was so relaxed I so I let go so much I wasn't even here that's fine not
a problem you can also offer your silence your presence and when your turn
comes to say past so let's Go reverse alphabetical order
um share just one thing one reflection about this exploration and the next person the next person then you can
after everyone has gone around then you can open it up for a conversation in the
time so not asking questions from one another
but just keeping it simple and light letting each person be in their experience just offer from your own
experience that's all if you don't want to offer you can offer silence and kindness offer kindness
offer freedom to each other no expectations see what what it's like to
take the spirit of this practice into the breakout rooms no expectations no
expectations of your of yourself so gonna create the rooms I'm opening them
up take care of yourselves take care of each other here we go
so everybody's back welcome back everyone now let's just take one or two
Reflections um what did you notice either in the meditation or in the uh
conversation about this topic of the heaviness and noticing the heaviness or
letting go of expectations oneself especially I like to invite those who haven't spoken recently to pull forward
if you've spoken recently and happy hour pullback get make space for others you can type in chat also or raise your
head Christine please well thank you Nikki that was a great
meditation tonight in my group we had a lot of quiet time and we were content I
was content there was a an element or a embracing just being content and quiet
tonight so and we were seeing how expensive the weekend so to say thank
you you know a lot for that tonight so I enjoyed that thank you
thank you Christine lovely just lovely brightens my heart with
contentment and I am content but if there are any
other Reflections um burning ones
we'll make some space otherwise
I think that was a lovely one to end our session with a sense of contentment yeah
letting go of expectations so so thank you all thank you for your practice
thank you for coming from so many different time zones and places in this
amazing world for this cultivation may all beings be well may all beings be
free completely free including ourselves [Music]
thanks everyone