so hello everyone and
welcome
and uh the topic for this week is changing
perspectives for awareness and um
the um
so often we are aware we might be mindful we're aware
with intention or without intention but we never question the perspective
with which we're aware the orientation and
some people are very much aware and with their head or their thinking
some people are very somatic and aware with or through their feelings
so this we can and so without questioning I think this is the way it is and when we do mindfulness practice
we can begin questioning the way that we're aware not so much to feel that one way is
necessarily better than other all the time but to have a range of perspectives
range is a way of being aware so we can know how to shift it according to what the need is
uh so for today
I'll offer you a little guided uh imagery
to begin this meditation to maybe give you a sense of a
perspective that's sometimes useful so to
assume a meditation posture
gently closing your eyes
and to take a few breaths deep breaths to settle in
to relax into here
and then to let your breathing be normal
and take a few moments here kind of uh
Broad awareness of your posture whatever posture you're in
be aware of whatever is happening for you The Experience that's within the posture
emotions thoughts feelings Sensations
the way you would check in with yourself if someone asks you how are you
and then to and now
imagine
the room that you're sitting in if you're sitting indoors if you're Outdoors imagine the location
you're in with your eyes closed see if you can reconstruct a bit
the location in which you're sitting the windows the walls
objects in the room where the door is
in your mind's eye either visualizing it or just with your thoughts recalling the
different parts of this room that you're in
and that as if you have a bird's eye view of the room
now imagine yourself sitting in the room Just the
Way You Are from a distance
kind of seeing the room from a distance with this person in it who is meditating
maybe uh a fly on the ceiling
what it would look like to look down upon the room and see this person there
and maybe in the room around you there's Stillness
there's no movement in the room except for maybe you breathing
there's a lot of space around you
it's visualize or sense the space the distance
between objects in the room and you
and from this distance imaginary distance of looking down upon
the room and you meditating
recall how you were feeling at the beginning of the meditation
and what's it like to be aware
of yourself from the distance of like a fly in the ceiling
in the context of this room to be aware of yourself from a distance
or some things easier to be aware of
something's more difficult
but might there be from a distance of the ceiling less identification
less activation or entanglement just seeing everything feeling
everything as if seeing it from a distance with lots of space around it
or you can imagine that you're a bird high in the sky looking
down in the building you're in
and from that distance what's it like to be aware of yourself
be aware of the dramas of your life the concerns and fears of your life
the stories the events
to be aware of it all from a distance maybe high in the sky
one person among many people
on a great planet sitting quietly meditating
and now imagine that you zoom back into your room
maybe a fly on the ceiling just as close head now closer in
aware of this person that's you sitting in the room
and now to zoom even closer in
and settle into your usual way of meditating with yourself
but this time baby with a little bit more
openness equanimity spaciousness non-involvement
just allowing things to be quiet and simple whatever it might be
a sense of non-entanglement without being bothered by anything
whatever you're feeling or thinking just something else to be aware of
with a kind of babies ease or distance
as if you're aware from far away
foreign
thank you
come here
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to engage your imagination a little just enough
to imagine that now you turn your gaze out to the world
maybe with the bird's eye view
gazing kindly and all the people in your life
in your neighborhood in your town
in your province Wherever You Are
see if you can gaze upon them with a gaze that's like rain gentle rain
that
brings kindness care respect
seeing everyone as important valuable
granting everyone their dignity and
a broad wide gaze of kindness of care compassion
the broad view the bird's eye view
through which the heart's love can
flow outwards wishing everyone well
having good will for all beings
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and may we follow or get the Gaze of kindness
to be kind in this world
[Music]
[Music] thank you
foreign so hello and welcome to the second talk
and um it involves changing the this week the
topic is changing our perspectives or locations for how we're aware
and I'll give you um somewhat no known well-known Chinese
story of a very skilled painter
I had a very big canvas and on that canvas he was painting a
very realistic life-sized tiger and um and he was um
so in there with the details of the tiger doing the doing it all and then when more or less had finished
the tiger the artist stepped back 10 feet to look at this big picture and
what he had done and it was so realistic he got afraid and ran away
so when he was close up the details of it didn't bother him but stepping away
the full picture seemed too realistic for him the opposite can also happen
that we can be frightened by being really close up to something and when we step back then we
are no longer frightened the um
I once took my son to the San Francisco Zoo and there was this big room you will
go into and and it went under the room was a big cage with very thick solid
bars behind which was a lion and my son was very young so I was
holding him carrying him in there and the way it worked you could actually get very close to the lion I think maybe
we're three feet away and um and looking at it and the lion roared
and these solid Bars were between us and the lion but boy that I don't know if I got
afraid but I certainly got a lot of respect for that lion so much so that I
turned around and left and from outside the big door going in I could look back on the lot on the lion
and you know it's just a lion in a cage and I felt a little bit sorry for it being there
so you know how close we are how far away we are makes a big difference and so learning to shift our
perspectives in some ways sometimes with the help of the imagination to get a different perspective uh either being
really close to being a far away today I want to emphasize this being far away
sometimes if we're sitting with a lot of difficult emotions like a lot of fear
and we are kind of caught in it and concerned with it reacting to it and it
just seems too much in there it just seems like we're overwhelmed by it sometimes that's because of the
perspective in which we're being aware it's difficult enough what's happening but where the awareness is kind of in
the fear caught in it or entangle with it or wetted to it kind of right up
against it close it's almost like the fear takes over the whole room because the room of awareness
is so small so with an act of imagination we can
spread and expand our awareness maybe imagine that we're standing 10 feet away
and looking at ourselves and from 10 feet away from there we can feel the
fear we can see the fear we can be with the fear we can't be with the fear close in
but step back 10 feet I've known people who you ask them to step back maybe on the hillside that's
maybe 300 yards away or something and look back at themselves can you be with
your fear from that distance and they say oh but that distance is okay and then they have a little bit more
Equanimity a little more space less reactivity to their fear and it's a whole different thing
the same thing with pain physical pain sometimes is easier to be
aware of for really close in which is a topic for tomorrow or it can be easier to be aware of if we
just open up really wide and imagine that we're seeing the whole landscape
and the fear is just one little piece of it and then we might realize that how much
we were reactive to the fear and kind of living right connected to it kind of as
if it was the most important thing it was a crisis and this has had to be dealt with or something but to step back step back step back
take that backward step so that we have some distance and some spaciousness around the pain and the pain is still
pain but some of the intensity of it goes away because some of the intensity of it has to do with our reactivity
you know pain is a complicated phenomenon it's not a unitary single thing
same thing with emotions they're not unitary single things there's a lot that goes into the construction of pain the
constructions of emotions and some of that has to do with how close in or how far away uh how much
space how little space we feel like we have for what what we're experiencing
so finding ways to open up to be spacious to create lots of room
and one way to do that is to imagine that your your eyes your inner eye your
perception your sense has taken a backward step really far away and looking back on you in a situation
now this could also be used to be disassociated and aloof from the experience
but that's not what I'm suggesting what I'm suggesting is getting this bird's eye view of yours
what's happening with you step back enough so that you can have some non-reactivity
in the awareness so you can be less entangled or reactive to it
and then you can start seeing it more clearly and then you might be able to see not only what's happening you know
the the emotion the pain or whatever but you might also be able to start kind of
working on understanding your relationship to it all the reactivity itself
one of the first times when I had an aha moment around this kind of Shifting of
perspective was um in in when I was in college I was
on the balcony it was looking back through the window and some friends
talking in the in the living room of the apartment we were in and uh and I couldn't hear what they
were saying but they were expressing themselves quite vigorously with their hands and their I think they
were having a good time but it was like quite animated with their bodies and and I kind of gazed at them without
being able to hear what they said and I could feel how I was just kind of marveling at their communication and and
kind of appreciating them in a different way in a nicer way but maybe than I had
if I had been involved with the conversation or if I'd been knowing what they said and I was thinking about what
they said that that distance kind of made a difference it changed the perspective and it wasn't like it was a better
perspective it was just a different it was nice to have that difference or I've been in in groups of people that
have been having a lot of difficulty and arguing talking hotly and things and
then for some reason had to step away and then when I came back I stood from the distance watching the group kind of
in their whole you know upset way kind of talking and I didn't
feel like I was in the upset anymore I could just kind of watch it and I could watch it with kindness with compassion
and and take it in and get a bigger picture of what was going on oh I see what's happening here so and so is like
this so-and-so's like that then looks like they're missing each other and and I got a whole more useful perspective
than if I'd been in the frame itself so in your in meditation this can be
done if you might be in the middle of The Fray You might be so preoccupied in
thoughts and stories and what happened earlier today or what's planning for tomorrow or the emotions might be quite
strong and difficult and and if you just kind of show up for your
experience with an usual attention you have that might not be the right attention
for you to have some kind of balance as you're with it and you might be too close it might be
too claustrophobic too tight not enough space and um and so learning how to step back
the backward step that creates space the the resting back with awareness to make
bigger awareness for the situation imagining that you're far away looking
down uh on your on yourself and then maybe then being able to see
what's going on in a clearer more peaceful way less identified with it
I think that this intensive identification where we have a sense that I am the fear I am the story I am
the experience tends to make our lives kind of claustrophobic kind of narrow and tight
and sort of step back wide enough so that we don't feel like we are these
different things and um and uh it can be a really helpful
sometimes in meditation of course it's possible to do that then be disassociated to kind of be aversive
and and be so far removed from experience that you might feel a little bit kind of calm but it's a really uh
disconnecting with the experience it's not a crime to do that it's okay it
might be have its function as well but the idea is to find the place of
being clearly aware of what's happening in the present moment and being able to do so with some degree of equanimity
some degree of non-reactivity and one of the tools for this is to get
the bird's eye view to get a different perspective and and how far back how how far away
you need that varies from situation to situation sometimes you need a lot of distance
like up in the mountain and in doing so you're enacting a little
bit what the meaning of Equanimity is the poly word for Equanimity is upeka
and it means something like having a higher view an overview looking from
above and the Buddha actually used that metaphor sometimes of standing on a hill
looking back down at the Town bustle of the town and from the hillside we're not
in the hustle and bustle we were peaceful and nice
so so to cultivate Equanimity and non-entanglement non-reactivity
and so one of the ways to do that is to imagine your stepping away stepping back getting a
distance so you might try this today in your life you might uh it could be some simple
things like if you're in a room with people and if it's you know the polite and it's not impolite to do so or
awkward to do so you might see it further away from people than you normally would and see what it's like to
have that kind of more distant view as opposed to being right in the middle of it you might
you know if you're in even one-on-one with someone uh you know without them thinking you're
pulling away you might physically kind of sit a little bit differently so you're a little more distance and see if
that distance creates more non-reactivity in space you might um you know if you're really
caught up in some preoccupation maybe go out into an open field or a wide park or
something where you get help with the imagine with the awareness expanding and
becoming much more Broad and open so it's easier to feel that there's more
space and distance from the entanglement the caught upness with what's going on
to find ways of changing the perspective and for today the perspective of having
kind of a bird's eye view that large view of the situation
and uh see what that would how that helps you and also see how it begins helping you
understand that you have a choice of the perspective that you use in being
mindful some people never occur to them they have a choice they're mindful but they're just mindful in the same way
every time and maybe that same way is not the best medicine for some situations we're in
so thank you very much and um may your
capacity for awareness bring you much delight