good morning good morning everybody
and as I say every day maybe it's not morning where you are so just a warm
welcome greetings
Okay so today is the last day of my stories of
Mara these letters that Mara is sending to the leaders of his army
but of course we're going to begin with a guided meditation today
so be like feeling this transition to a sitting practice like taking a few
moments to find a comfortable posture and
take your time to notice how you're sitting and
like feel your way like what does it feel like to be sitting right now
and to do that in such a way that your awareness is light and open and spacious
adjusting your posture anyway and that feels like it would be helpful
and with the awareness being light just noticing sometimes we have a tendency to want to
really hold on to whatever the object is that we're noticing
can we just be soft and gentle still connected
but with some ease some spaciousness
and we're just sitting here
and in this moment you don't have to be anything for anybody you don't have to
be any particular way we're just sitting here
allowing yourself to arrive to land
In This Moment take in your seat
whether that's a literal or figurative seat
but noticing if there's this really subtle pressure we might say that there's a
right way to do this and you have to get it right or
see if you can let go of any Nuance or subtle idea like that if
it's there and instead just tuning into
how things are at this moment
is there a way you can allow
what's here
maybe receiving or allowing that chair the cushion
matte sees a bench couch whatever it is allowing that to receive
the weight of the body
while also maintaining uprightness
this can be a subtle shift
the movement of the pressure against the body
it's in contact with the seating support
allowing the weight to the body
to be received by whatever it is in contact with
and having this uprightness
and just noticing allowing any patterns of tension
that may be in your body
sometimes when we notice tension then there's this plethora of thoughts
to get rid of it it needs to be different can we just
allow both that thought pattern
and any tension in the body
just for now
can we let it be how it is
and then naturally
noticing the body breathing
the experience of breathing
and noticing with the quality of kindness and allowing
however the breath is
can we just notice
what would it be like to just abide
with the flowing sensations of breathing
without anything to do
we're just abiding noticing
allowing
being sensitive
to any Notions that it has to be different
it should be different
can we soften those Notions as best we can
as best we can
okay
foreign
[Music]
thank you
foreign
noticing that we're lost in thought
just very simply gently Begin Again
that the sensations of breathing
or begin again with the sensations in the whole body
the bodily experience
with the attitude of kindness and allowing
yet with a commitment to this meditation practice for this session
so softness allowing isn't the same as casual
or half-hearted
foreign foreign
foreign
all right
thank you
[Music]
foreign
good day hello I love you
joining us on the fifth and the last day of this series that I'm doing on these
um letters from Mara to the leaders of his ten armies
Mara as many of you know is this character that we find in the Buddhist
teachings and I'm not concerning myself with exactly what Mara is or how he works I'm
just uh inspired Maybe by some of the things that are getting pointed out in
these letters from Mara to his uh armies are often topics that we don't talk
about so much in Buddhist teachings and Derma talks and yet
these things that are Mara that get personified as Mara are things that get
in the way things that might hinder us or obstruct us in our ways towards
freedom and then to be sure these letters from Mara are nowhere in the poly Canon these
were written by ajan punadamo in the arrow River Forest Hermitage up in
Northern Ontario and so in the public Canon we do find
just a mention that Mara has these 10 armies and then who's in the ajanta
lineage uh kind of set in contemporary times these letters which I think are
delightful and a little bit cutting just in the way that they're pointing to in a
way that feels a little bit uncomfortable sometimes this Human Experience
so I've been excerpting portions of these letters and I will be especially
be doing that for this last one that I'm doing today which is a long letter and has a number
of different uh sub-categories to it but I'll just be pointing to one and the art that that's being pointed to
today in this letter from Mara is the 10th Army which often gets a translated as self
praise and denigration of others I'll just be looking at a little portion of that so here's this letter excerpt
that's written by
to my bold and Powerful 10th Army greetings your task is crucial yet fortunately for
us it is also easy generally humans have a most
unreasonable attitude of taking themselves quite seriously
they seem quite unable to mentally disengage from the eagle ego perspective
let them think of themselves as truly wonderful and righteous fill them up with pride this is the task of you
the first division of the tenth Army self-praise fuels all the defilements it
is a Masterwork of delusion humans look into the mirror with rose colored
glasses they become quite unable to see their own faults and bristle with
indignation whenever these are pointed out to them and self-praise of course
also fuels attachment and sensuality after all because if someone as
wonderful as me deserve a little fun
self-praise also fires up anger the fierce anger of the self-righteous who
knows their views and opinions are correct and everyone else is an idiot
it's also it's so amusing to watch two humans egos Clash
the forces of the tenth Army have a special role to play in these difficult cases where an individual shows signs of
spiritual progress if they begin to free themselves of the
coarser snares of my other armies we can often use their own victories against
them by encouraging a spiritual Pride
and arrogance whisper in their ear about what wonderful Spiritual Beings they are
look at me the great holy person this is a trap that has caught many fish
however you should be aware that there's also a large number of humans that have
a very negative self-image both the positive and the negative
version suit our purposes quite well so if you cannot convince them that they
are wonderful then encourage them to kick themselves for being such losers
remember there are three kinds of conceit I am better than you
I am worse than you and I am equal to you
any one of these is still a conceit I'm still reinforces duality in fact there
are signs that in the modern culture the negative form has become predominant and
a great many humans don't like themselves very much
encourage them in the opinion that they are as individuals inadequate
wow ouch this is like so painful to hear like this idea that there's this Mara
creature quote unquote out there who is encouraging humans to feel like they're
inadequate as a way to obstruct their spiritual progress as a way to get in
the way of having greater Freedom greater ease and greater peace
and we don't need to imagine this Mythic Mara Mara character
to recognize the role of the inner critic that it might have in our lives not everybody has this as a dominant or
obvious feature but many of us do so this inner critic this almost like a
sub personality that's inside of us that's constantly putting us down or
ability belittling us and with self-judgment or blaming ourselves
nagging at ourselves having this sense of Shame for who we are and how we do
things with this quality of harshness
and when this inner critic is up and running it's not always there but when it is there's this feeling of inadequacy
this sense of not being enough I'm not worthy
who I am or how I am is not enough somehow and there's so much pain
so much duka that is caught up in this structure
for some people it's such a prevalent and ongoing part of their inner experience it might even be difficult to
conceive that it might be otherwise and some people feel like it's just them
they feel like everybody else must have it together everybody except me
but I assure you this is such a prevalent form of
one's inner life and it's important to know that we're not alone in this right it's even
written by ajan punadamo which I think his letters were written number of
decades ago so it's understandable that people have this inner critic we learn it from
society from family from school but it's important to not blame ourselves
for having this dynamic as part of our inner life
right that's just the inner critic trying to pretend that it's not the
inner critic because the inner critic always shows up using the first person pronouns
I'm not good enough I need to do more so it's difficult to recognize you might
think like oh this is just the way it is but it's just the inner critic
and you might even ask yourself right now what is the picture
you hold in your mind about how your supposed to be
do you have this sense of how you're supposed to quote unquote supposed to be
is there like this unnoticed image propelling you towards this idea that you must have a
certain appearance or status or livelihood or you have to be Charming or
funny or Lively or intelligent like all these things
you might even say with regarding to meditation is there a picture in your mind of how you should be when you're
meditated or because you're a meditator you might have this idea oh yeah I should always be peaceful and calm and
wise never having more anger or sadness or
anything like this so without any judgment without any
Judgment at all can we notice what are some of these ideas or pictures in our minds
because we want to step out of this tendency for the inner critic to judge
and evaluate us and instead to like step into
curiosity noticing allowing
and this is the way that we can work with this inner critic
is with this openness this curiosity this allowing this warmth
so some ways might be do do some loving kindness practice so bring in some
kindness into our mindfulness practice and to give the inner critics some space
right because if we're trying to get rid of it or make it be different then that's just the inner critic showing up
to trying to pretend it's something else working on the inner critic
so it might do some loving kindness practice some of the deep friendliness
towards ourselves we might imbue our meditation practice
and to be sure when the scenery of the inner critic is up and running it might
feel like there's like loving kindness is ridiculous I can't even do that that's not what's going to help
but just this recognition that when the inner critic is up and running and we
believe it when it has this certain authority to it to recognize that that is just the one
perception at that moment that's like the mood at that moment it's
not truth even though it's trying to be very persuasive
instead it's the thoughts of the inner critic is just this tight habitual way
thinking about things and some loving kindness practice allows us to set up
these different habits of thinking different orbits of thinking
and when these alternative different constellations of thoughts and experiences arise the inner critic just
runs out of energy it just loses its power
so it's not that we have to get rid of that inner critic it's more that we're just fueling
cultivating developing alternative but then the inner critic just kind of
drains itself of its Authority so one way to work with the inner critics with loving kindness practice
in any way that feels appropriate and nourishing be careful sometimes the
inner critic gets in there with love and kindness so it might be just loving kindness only rare it's easy
only where it's easy the second thing we can do with living I'm sorry with working with them inner
critic is to bring mindfulness with some kindness and in particular I
would say mindfulness of the body bringing into the tangible felt
experience of this moment with some kindness some openness some
spaciousness allowing but again will drain some of the
Authority or momentum behind this inner critic so can we just let the inner critic be
there recognize it's there and cultivate love and kindness and
cultivate mindfulness of the body with some warmth and spaciousness
so with that we end our series on letters from Mara
where I looked at a subset of the letters and excerpted some of these letters from ajan pundamo
I wish you all a wonderful weekend thank you