welcome welcome everyone nice to see you all nice to practice
together I've been away for a number of weeks I
had the great Good Fortune to sit along Retreat and
so here I am now I feel like well maybe I should say something like profound about the retreat but uh
nothing's arising so uh but tonight I wanted to talk
a little bit about something that I played around with and
kind of explored on this retreat but I like to start start here with this
idea that it's very common when the most Retreats like if it's a
week-long retreat or something that there's a standard formula of the instructions that are given in the
morning and one of those instructions is mindfulness of thoughts
this idea of you know if we just that's part of the human experience and we can
bring mindfulness to everything so let's bring mindfulness to thoughts
and so there's a few ways that this instruction is given first is to notice what is the
experience of thinking
so our thoughts is it something like images that you see
or or it sounds that you hear like is it a voice or what is the experience
completely independent of the content like what does it just like to think
and putting our Awareness on that on the form or the experience helps us to not
get lost so much in the thoughts [Applause]
and then if we recognize that the thoughts like are really persistent and just uh or compelling and we're just
finding ourselves completely lost in thought to maybe have a little inquiry
well what is uh is there an emotion under here that's fueling the
like what what's what's giving the quality of these thoughts to be so
compelling that we find ourselves lost in them
and maybe we might even give the instruction well notice if there's a particular theme not some the exact
content but a theme a lot of planning say I had no idea what I've planned or I
was I never didn't consider myself a planner until I started meditation practice wow we I do a lot of planning
quite something or maybe we do a lot of fantasizing of like oh wouldn't it be
great at this or that you're like imagining something that's better or maybe do a lot of reminiscing or
um ruminating about something that's happened in the past right there just might be certain flavors or themes
the types of thoughts that we have and part of the reason why we give this
instruction to have mindfulness of thoughts is this recognition that
whatever is happening in in our experience whether it's a thought or a
bodily experience sounds whatever it might be there's a way if we like honor
or respect that it's here
then there's a way and that we kind of like brings us into the present moment
brings us into our experience so it's like recognizing oh it's here it's
actually happening right now there's a way that this tuning into presence can just be a gateway to a
direct experience and direct experience is a gateway towards greater freedom
and I want to talk a little bit more about that but maybe I'll start with
okay with mindfulness of thoughts but what are thoughts
like what are they have you ever thought about this
so there's a few ways we might think about thoughts one is these are like ideas
and they have like an ideas that have maybe like a certain like a power behind
them that allows us to be creative or allows us to innovate or you know do
something in the world that might not happen if we didn't have those thoughts that's one way to think about it
another way to consider thoughts is their occasional nuisances
they show up and we're trying to meditate and we just feel like we can't get settled because the mind is just
going incessantly with thinking and maybe the thoughts are even a little bit troubling
or maybe there are nuisances because we're trying to sleep and can't sleep because there's all
these thoughts going or maybe another way to think about
thoughts is this capacity that humans have like this self-reflection and it's part
of what distinguishes us from plants or some of the animals
and not only that this self-reflection allows us to plan and to communicate
with others what our plans are and even to like maybe organize groups of people
together to you know do these plans
or maybe we can take like a scientific approach and say well thoughts are just these neurochemical processes that
involve a lot of neurons and some organized fashion or something like this
there's a number of different ways we might think about thoughts but I think for like our purposes for this
idea of this wanting to have this movement towards greater Freedom greater ease
greater peace in our lives one way we can think about thoughts
is if you can write it down it's a thought
just this right if there's a sentence that you can make out of it it's a
thought and there's something about that that kind of like simplifies it for me I've
kind of like find this uh happy or I'm sorry like it there's a way
that kind of like takes the power out of them or the mystery out of them in some kind of way oh yeah I can write this down it's a
thought and over New Year's
I did a thinking of thinking about uh okay so is there you know like
some reflection I want to do start the new year that's kind of a
tradition might we often do as with uh some other people and uh
and my like uh what I wanted to offer was or what is something I'm working
with this year this idea they're just thoughts
they're just thoughts and there's a way of kind of recognizing you know that thoughts come and they
thought thoughts go they are powerful but they don't have to be
they don't have to be powerful right it's kind of when we believe them or give them Authority or something like
this but otherwise they can just be one mental event
so one thing about thoughts part of why they can be powerful and maybe not so
helpful way and sometimes it's not helpful is that they're very often like discursive right
it's not like we have just one thought it leads to another which leads to another or another another and off we go
but not only that they're very often like self-referential have you noticed this have you looked at your thoughts
It's All About Me I'm gonna do this I'm not gonna do that
I should do this I can't believe that person said this to me
I'm gonna make sure that this I don't know I want to do this or that it's it's
quite something it's really quite something on this Retreat I was looking like okay
I'm gonna see is there any thought that isn't self-referential because so much
of it is like oh there's a sound and I don't like it right there's all this kind of a
self-referential stuff so but there's this way also this uh the the
self that's getting referenced this is I think a really important it's distorted
our thoughts are distorting them it's not really how things are and I
heard this from somebody else and I really liked this idea that there's all these assumptions about
how we are there's all these uh views about how we are that maybe we're true
at one moment but aren't necessarily true at that particular moment but yet we're kind of like dragging it into the
present moment and so I heard this uh idea that it's like you
um turn on a TV program in the middle and you there's this assumption that you
already know who all the characters are and everything and that you're just gonna go along with whatever's happening
but this pointing to the direct experience reminds us that well you know
maybe that me that's getting referenced isn't uh quite accurate isn't really
what's happening at that moment that's something as I said it's kind of getting dragged from the past
so we have these views we have these views about what it means
to be a person in general as well as what does it means to be this particular
person one that we take ourselves to be
and so these views are thoughts too of course they are
right and often we we could also use this word beliefs
and we might say okay well belief view are these the same
for the purposes of what I'm going to talk about tonight I like to say that they are the same
and so what what is a belief what is a view one definition could be an acceptance
that a statement is true or that something exists
and we could see how that relates to this sense of self we have this sense of of course there's this me that has to be
protected and bolstered and enhanced and you know all these types of
things but a belief it's a thought and a view
but what makes it maybe different than what we would say just a regular thought is that it's partially hidden
it's not so obvious to us something that's like operating a little
bit underneath the radar maybe I'll distinguish like beliefs and
views from opinions because opinions have like a solution they're offering
like okay here's a solution to a problem that's an opinion I suppose I believe or a view is more just like a statement
that this is true or this exists or something like that so I'll make that uh distinction
and so we might also say that views are this
mental events that happen cognitive activity type of thoughts that aren't
quite seen and and when we see it in ourselves these are you know based on our experience and
based on facts it's of course we have these views of course we have these beliefs
when we see them in others let's see them as uh unproven and rigid
and narrow and oh they're just conditioned by their experienced or idiosyncratic or maybe even a little bit
weird or something so it's very interesting right how we hold hours
but you know of course this is the way it is but when we see other people's
views we tend to be discounted discount them but not our own
and that's so much about what practice is about is to help see some of these views that
are influencing Us in so many ways and we're not even aware of it
of course right it's that views show up in the way we behave
what we think is valuable what is invaluable or what's worthwhile what's helpful what isn't helpful right all
these things are based on views beliefs
and so one thing is interesting that maybe we
don't really notice is that our view about views our beliefs about beliefs
because I'll offer that the I also heard this from somebody else is that the
quantity and intensity that we hold our beliefs how many we have and how hard
we're holding on inversely proportional to the amount of Freedom we have
but we might be thinking like no I have to hold on to these it's it helps make me safe and that's why you Orient to the
world or into the have this view that um
has to be quiet in order to meditate or even the view that I have to meditate a
lot in order to have greater Freedom or greater ease and or everybody else seems to get this
meditation thing but I don't know it doesn't quite work for me or where the Dharma is going to answer
everything for me if only I could just uh I don't know figure things out or
learn Paulie read more suit does you know or something like this like we have these views that often are limiting
what we think is possible for ourselves or even what's possible for others
makes sense that we have them of course we do but what's being pointed to you is can we hold them lately with Open Hands
instead of you know grabbing on to them maybe some other views we might have
that to show up in some of the ways we practice and I know I certainly had this
View this uh I think this used to be a commercial I'm not sure but this
expression no pain no gain you know that that more suffering the better right I
don't know the things that I put myself through you know thinking that I had to with meditation practice or a long
retreat practice or things that uh just was painful just swimming in the Duke uh
kind of like thinking that oh I have to figure this out and just rehashing the most painful things like
during some of these meditation sessions some of that comes up and it's unavoidable but there is a way that I
kind of had this view of I deserve to suffer a little bit or that I had to get
to the bottom of it and the only way I could get to the bottom of it is to think about it incessantly and then recognizing that actually there is no
bottom as long as you were thinking about it right there is no bottom
so maybe this idea of no pain no gain and I do want to you know acknowledge that there
certainly is uncomfortableness in practice physical discomfort
learning to meditate but there's also the discomfort of so
much about practices like we gain some greater understanding about ourselves
about the world and it's not always what we wish right
I wanted to like this idea that oh I'm such a planner to have when I I was like so disappointed in myself I felt like oh
Diana I thought you know you could be more in the moment or something like that but I wasn't in the moment
beginning of my meditation practice absolutely not and I felt embarrassed about it and felt
like it was this deep secret I didn't want to share with anybody
so what views do we have and importantly what is our relationship
to them are we attached to our ideas
or do we hold them lightly and often we don't know this until they
get challenged and so we meet somebody who has a different View
where we find that we feel like we're some resistance or
reluctance to like do something like that just doesn't seem right
maybe we can't even quite put our finger on why it doesn't seem right
but some views about views we might have are having strong beliefs makes me a strong
person there might be a way in which you know that might be in there because I did
that okay I have to hold on because if I don't have strong beliefs I will be easily fooled people will take advantage
of me but there's also this way right in which
we are whatever we're like really holding on to limits us
I'm not saying throw away all of you so I'm saying hold them lightly
yeah this is my current understanding this is what makes sense to me right now
this is what I'm resonating with right now instead of like this is the truth
or yeah that's or this is my current hypothesis I'm trained as a scientist right I love that kind of thing right
right or maybe we have this belief a person is defined by their beliefs
defined by their views and I want to be defined this way so I'm going to hold
really tightly to these views or another one that where not only people are defined but what tribe they belong to is
by what their beliefs are and so I have to hold on to these beliefs and Views
because I want to belong to this community again there's nothing wrong with sharing
beliefs with other people it's just can we hold them lightly instead of this divisiveness
because as I said early earlier that's the number of beliefs and how strong we are holding holding holding on to them
limits us amidst our freedom because again there's
so many of these unseen views that are influencing us influencing our Behavior
these unseen views are the way are the reason why sometimes we do self-de
defeating behaviors things that don't serve us because there's a view underneath there
there's a belief that we don't know or aren't that we're still believing in
some kind of way so
how can we see some of these beliefs or some of these views how can we see the Unseen
it's part of what practice is about part of it was what I talked it opened
with was this idea of noticing our thoughts but you know some of our thoughts are on the surface and easy and
some of them are not so easy
so one way or maybe I should say noticing thoughts isn't the only way to work with thoughts
it's often what we're teaching it's often what you don't if we teach introduction to meditation or on our
Meditation Retreat it's what we're teaching but there's other ways
and so but before we like uh
examine or explore some of these other ways part of it is that we have to
notice that we have to put down some of the views we have about what does it mean to do Buddhist
practice what does it mean to meditate because we might have this idea that
well the Mind should be completely devoid of any thinking that's what real meditation is and
I don't know have you tried it right
I you know with some real concentration there the thoughts really do get quite
and I'll talk about that in a moment but when we have these types of ideas that
the thought of the Mind the thinking should only be one way then you know we kind of set ourselves
up for the inner critic to get really loud because that's not what our experience is or frustration or
disappointment or those kinds of things
but for some of us the idea of maybe like using the Mind during meditation
doesn't doesn't feel quite right and maybe it feels like that's a little bit
of a shift that we feel uncomfortable with because often there's the teaching
is is that we're just noticing thoughts and this is great this is really powerful
but maybe I'd like to offer maybe there's something that we can do besides just noticing
that can really support us with this
but before I I talk about that I also want to notice that sometimes we might have views that well a good meditation
is when we have this experience of like not knowing
maybe where there's this hangout in this maybe vague fluffy cottony
space that feels comforting maybe maybe for us that's the what we
have this idea about what meditation is and this idea that we should do anything else doesn't feel comfortable
or maybe we have a view that we have to actually figure things out and that's what meditation is about you sit down
and find the answers to whatever is needs answers
or maybe your views about what meditation should be aren't maybe so clearly
articulated or aren't so obvious but it's worthwhile considering
what views you have about meditation
so how to and how to see the Unseen views I'd like to offer this idea is to
do it inquiry practice and again I want to say this is not straight up mindfulness
but it can be really like augment or Turbo Charge or something like this the
mindfulness practice so what is what am I talking about this
idea of dropping in a question
and this could definitely be doing meditation but it can also be in daily life and but it's really important like how
we drop this question in is dropped in with a like this sense of
curiosity and this openness and there's a way that can we receive an
answer instead of okay I gotta figure this out what is this it's very like you know
different instead this kind of like just dropping and maybe just opening to see
if something arises something may not arise
it may it may not but it's the idea of opening to The Answer instead of
figuring it out and so and bringing this maybe this a
certain amount of curiosity to it but not only some curiosity like some warmth
some care like oh what what is this
so here are some questions that might help with this
is there a view here that I'm not seeing
I said obvious straight question or maybe
what view am I holding on to
or what belief is operating in the background
or maybe what am I resisting what am I avoiding
so it's just the dropping in of the question as I said maybe an answer arises maybe
an answer doesn't arise but part of the reason
we want to maybe like explore and play around with this is that if you feel stuck
in your meditation practice and I would say maybe even in your life
it's because there is one of these views that's underneath that somehow is maybe
sabotaging you know unknowingly or I guess yeah like
there's a belief or something that we're holding on to that doesn't allow this movement forward
but often we just don't know what those are so an inquiry practice is to drop in
this question is there a view here that I'm not seeing
and as I said this can be during meditation it can be in daily life
and in some ways this reminds me of like you know the Zen of this koan practice
co-wan practices you're working with something that doesn't quite make sense but it's the same idea of like kind of
like opening up to something might arise something different might arise
so having this inquiry is there a view here that I'm not seeing
what what am I holding on to what belief am I holding on to
and there's often a reason why they're not seen is because they're uncomfortable or they're protecting us
from something that's uncomfortable so if you start to feel squirmy restlessness
this is a good sign this means that you're like in the right territory
if you started to feel like whoa I don't want to do this and you get up from your meditation or something
this is a indicator that you're in the area where maybe something new which you
know isn't always Pleasant is in the neighborhood maybe about to arise so if we're always staying in
what's comfortable you know we'll always stay in what's comfortable
so how to see the Unseen one is to do an inquiry practice
another one is maybe to do a settling practice what I'll call a settling
practice which is a little bit different than just mindfulness and you may say this is
more like a samadhi or yeah I'll just use that word somebody
for those of you know kind of like a gathering collecting settling
maybe I'll end with this um with this beautiful simile about
settling that the Buddha offers in the samyukta Akama
and it goes like this I I yeah it goes like this it is just as someone who is panning for
gold you know panning for gold I I've done this go up to the Foothills here and you ever get a little pan and water
and dirt and try to find some gold right
it is just as someone who is panning for gold and who places a horde of sand and Earth into a trough and then rinses it
with water so that the large pieces emerge and the contamination by solid stones and hard
chunks flows away with the water so you're just describing you know putting some mud in there is what I'm imagining
the miners did here and the 49ers did here in California
yet there remains sand that is interspersed among the gold and by
rinsing it again with water the sand flows out with the water and after this
the gold becomes visible yet there is fine sand
interspersed with soil and by rinsing it again with water the fine sand and the
soil flow out with the water and after that there was gold that is pure clean
and without add mixture yet there still appears fine dross in
the gold and I had to look this up what is dros I can't imagine having to translate this
word from Poli to English so kudos to the some of these early translators so dros is the residue that's left on
the surface of a molten metal I didn't know this so
so then there's so you get the gold away from all the dirt but still there's this dress on it so then it goes from the
person who is panning from gold to the Goldsmith and then the simile continues after a
Goldsmith places the gold into the furnace Heats it up eating it and blowing on it until it melts in order to
remove the dross and the contamination but because the gold that is visible is
not light not soft does not send forth Brilliance and would break if it were
bent or straightened the Goldsmith places it again into the
furnace Heats it up Beats on it blows it turns it around casts it
and then after that they'll go this light soft and Brilliant and it will not
break if bent or straightened and then according to one's wish it can be made
into an earring a necklace a hairpin or a bracelet
or whatever one wishes I like this idea of settling right that
there's uh you know we could think about it in one meditation session but we can
also think about like our whole meditation practice you know like over the years right we start to see things
some of these jewels start to become present that as we start to like with
practice with time with repetition we start to see some of the Finer Things that we hadn't seen
before and this there's always this value and getting rid of like these really big
things that are don't help us even to see the gold and then even to like purify the gold
so I like to leave with this idea that thoughts right there are constant companions
you can work with them by noticing them
and beliefs and Views I'd like to say are a type of thoughts
and what makes them different than thoughts is that they're often unseen
and these unseen parts are often what is uh if we feel stuck some way or we feel
like we're not uh having if we find ourselves uh doing
things that aren't helpful there's like some view under there and so one way we can do them as an inquiry
practice or settling and I could say also mindfulness will as
well but you know it might take a little bit longer because mindfulness is kind
of like passively maybe less uh directly kind of like purifying and moving away
all the obstructions so like to offer you with that leave you
with that and now open it up to see if there's some questions or comments
um these are really interesting topic and I was kind of curious
as to um have you heard people say um how they viewed their thoughts
because I know for me it's usually like pictures of action but I'm wondering do
I wonder if people see their thoughts differently yeah I mean like do they see
words or like you said sounds yeah yeah yes I definitely have like when I teach
introduction to meditation we talk about this and we like kind of like take a little bit of survey okay who who has
and definitely some people tend to have them more as like a voice that's speaking and then the question could be
is it your voice is it like a parent voice is what's the tone is it warm or
is it you know you know harsh or something like that as well as like little mini movies that can be seen and
then the question we could ask is is it really clear and high definition or is
it kind of sepia you know Brown and not so clear and and then the question
another question we could ask is well or maybe there's types of thoughts that are images and types that are sounds
so this could be a great way to kind of like shift our relationship to thoughts because otherwise we just tend to
believe all of them and think they're authoritative and get lost in them but to have this curiosity this exploration
helps us to let me shift our experience or shift our relationship to thoughts I
would say yeah because um I know for myself do you want to use that microphone um I know for myself my
thoughts are always telling me to do do do do do because that's how it's brought up right you just you keep going you
have goals and you do do do do do but I'm wondering if people have kind of and
it's not like an unkind voice in my head but um I would like it to change you know not
always happen to be like so productive yeah to be a little nicer right yeah
yeah yeah so I really appreciate it yeah great thank you
thank you Diana do you think that um
the inside in our theravada tradition
they are kind of thoughts also I would say that insights are seen
through some of our beliefs some of our core beliefs are they
thoughts I I think they become thoughts but
they're they're more experiential
there's more than one type of insight maybe I'll say that too right some of the really transformative ones yeah well
they're all transformed that's part of the definition of an Insight this is I would say an Insight is
um maybe we could say it's a thought and recognition that lesson suffering
and some of the insights we have are like psychological like oh now I
understand that I do that because uh this happened in my earlier in my life
or I want to get that or something like that so we have those types of insights but some of the insights particularly
into the three characteristics and permanent not self-suffering those ones
that are like really transformative life-changing I would say
um I think those tend to be more experiential but then they as we try to
understand what happened we put thoughts on top of them
I see because sometimes those um the small
insight for me it's um it's like
some simple things during the daily life you know I I just looked things at a
different angles and I thought well is that a thought
coming through um so I don't follow my habitual
patterns anymore and I see the different angle different way to do things
so um yeah I think you're right probably that's a clarification
or instead of thought
okay I was just does it matter if it's a thought what would be the uh
what impact would that have on you if it were or if it weren't
I don't think it matters that thought or not however
um you know by studying this what is mindfulness of the thought
what are they like you said is such a big range of it
another thing I was wondering is the intuition you know is the you're talking about
um dropping to the inquiries well sometimes I have the intuition is
that part of the insert coming through the inter inquiries yeah
yeah we should often let's say intuition I
thought thoughts it's a different type of knowing I was saying like
thoughts are right if you can write it down it's a thought but intuition is not something I mean you could say I just
have a feeling I just have this gut feeling or something like that but it's a little bit different
I see
so I have a question for you not and it doesn't need to be answered
if you don't want but I was really intrigued by your notion of getting into this place of being uncomfortable
and curious because I've been in some groups and there's a phrase that I've heard so much in the last 10 or 20 years of I'm
not comfortable with that and so do you think there's some
beneficial and non-beneficial and comfortable absolutely I would say but it's
different when you're in groups or not I would say with oneself if you start to
feel a little bit uncomfortable and you want you feel stuck and you're doing some inquiry and you start to feel
uncomfortable that's a good sign that means that you're getting close to something that's
uh is causing the stuckness you don't want to see or don't want to know or
something like this and it's a yeah there's resistance to knowing it or
seeing it or something and that's why there's stuckness but I think yeah interpersonally I don't know I guess we
kind of have to depends on the relationships and stuff like that I would say yeah because I
so maybe a view that I have is that I think there's sometimes that
if a group gets into that uncomfortable area there may also be something to learn oh yeah you know what I mean it's
it's it's kind of like a group can really avoid you're like don't go there you
know that sort of thing so that that's what's been going on for me so that's
what I resonated with yeah thank you thank you for saying that maybe I'll just offer this something that I learned
like a long time ago maybe all of you guys ever heard this too but I uh use this in groups
there's like these three uh phases forming storming norming maybe you've
heard this right and so there's like the storming part is like when it's uncomfortable and just recognize it oh that's just part of what it means to be
a group but then you get to the other side of it and there's greater intimacy and understanding and stuff so maybe
that's what you're pointing to yeah thank you John
okay so we're at the top of the hour I want to thank you for your kind attention and for your practice you're
welcome to come up and talk to me if you'd like afterwards but otherwise I wish you a lovely rest of the evening thank you