Okay so I'm wondering if we have sound now
and okay we have sound yeah
wonderful so um so welcome I'm at inside Crete Center
today imc's Retreat Center in Santa Cruz County in California
and then I'm teaching here for the week and um so I want to so hit this is the place for which I'll do the the Broadcasting
and um happy to be here maybe uh end of the
week we can zoom out or Zoom around and you can see the meditation a little bit more those of you who'd like
and um and uh
I also that we have here uh three people attending you know all these years that
I've been doing YouTube uh from IMC there's always been a loan a couple of times uh one person came a
technician came in one of our Sangha members who helps a lot with it and here we have uh two of the resident
volunteers at IRC and one of the big volunteers who comes here to help and so they're sitting here in the
meditation Hall with me and so it's nice to have company here
so um welcome to the beginning of the week and um
last week we did a series of teachings on different ways of being aware
and for this day I would like to suggest another variation on awareness that can
apply to all the different other ways that you're aware but that is um
to the the choice between letting the awareness be very light
and having awareness being I don't know if heavy is the right word but a little bit more intense or serious or weighty
and sometimes the idea of lightness kind of like awareness has a very light touch
for what is it's being aware of can be very helpful because anything more than
a light touch can be sometimes too much effort being made
and the Art of uh effort is to make a have a light touch a lightness to the
effort but to be committed to it so it's continuous and really stay there
and so um a light touch and a light touch with the
how awareness touches the breathing the sensations of breathing a light touch
and how we know it and the knowing of the sensations that if there's mental noting a light touch with a noting
so that'll be the kind of the
the addition to the meditation this morning so to take a
triple alert posture and to gently close your eyes
and to take a few long slow deep breaths
exhaling relaxing on the exhale
and the part of this one can be nice with taking a few deep breaths at the beginning
is that when you stop doing it you can appreciate the lightness or the more
simple way of breathing then it's not intentionally taking deep breaths
so you might try that now kind of return to an ordinary breath and appreciate
maybe that ordinariness of it or the lack of that extra effort and force
to deep briefly breathe deeply
and just with a light touch be aware of your breathing
a light touch that doesn't interfere with your breathing doesn't have any agenda with
it just there feeling it coming and going
and as you exhale without making a lot of effort just a
very light effort almost as if the lightness of the effort is part of the medicine
as you exhale lightly relax parts of your body
being content with just a little bit of softening at a time
softening in the face
softening in the shoulders
softening in the belly
and then settling into your breathing
if it's easy enough to feel this have there be a light connection
with your body and the movements of breathing
feeling that parts of that part of the movement that feels free
the movement that feels like it
the movement it feels like its moves easily lightly
even if it brushes against tightness
pressure
and with this emphasis on lightness
as you exhale to lighten up on them in the mind
maybe a sense of soft touch in the mind
and if there is anything that's heavy or challenging for you as you're sitting
here thoughts or feelings Sensations
see if the mindfulness of it can be light
almost like mindfulness is a soft feather The Gents gently
brushes are called across whatever difficulty there is
where awareness is a soft cotton ball that gently touches what's heavy or
difficult and then gently pulls away
lightly touches briefly with no Force no insistence
just a gentle almost like a gentle hello
whatever a mental effort you're making to be aware
mindful here in the present moment
can that effort have a lightness to it easing up so there's any ease
in how you're encountering whatever is happening here Moment by moment
with a light touch of awareness you can sometimes feel as if whatever
the experience is of the moment that it is touching you lightly
and if there is any suffering or
distress or fear or difficulty
when we can feel it lightly the light touch
the feather touch then there is more room
for compassion for care
for kindness
to touch our challenges with a light touch of awareness
so there's a room for a tenderness
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to bring to mind some person or animal
for whom it's easy for you to have a warm regard
love or friendliness kindness
maybe an admiration of a kind
so someone for whom is easy to have good will
think of this person or this animal
with a light touch so that the awareness of it is not mixed
up with desires and fears and
it's just very simple the lightest Touch of Goodwill love
that needs nothing in return
that's asking for nothing
love with a light touch
and then that light Touch of Love imagine that
it has a door that you can open a wide door that opens up and
the same light touch of love or care kind
can be extended to all the people in your life that you know
they don't have to know you're doing it
a light touch of kind Regard in all directions
and with a light touch a lightness of heart
opening your good will up in all directions to all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
male beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to our Monday
Gathering and uh um today I'm at the insect Retreat
Center it's lovely to be in this meditation Hall and um
the topic for this week is compassion and uh to talk about it in a particular
way building on two weeks ago that theme was compassion as well some kind of building
on this and last week the topic was different ways of being aware
and the importance of that for compassion is that if we only have one way to be aware
that mode of awareness might not be the best and healthiest way for us to be
present for suffering in ourselves and suffering in others it might be for example if someone
mostly is aware through feelings and that's the only way they know how to
know anything is through the vehicle of feelings some of the suffering world might just
feel too much and our own suffering might feel too much
it's important to feel but it's also important to find the awareness that we
can be present for something where we're not weighed down by what's the experience is
and um and so if someone who feels a lot might be able to shift a little bit into
an observing mode maybe observing kind of from a little bit of distance or they might be more in a not feeling
so much but kind of a clear mental recognition of what's happening and that
the feelings are still there but coming into the mode of recognition knowing oh
this is pain this is someone's sadness that then um
it might be uh easier to be present for it might be
able to find a place of a light touch being present in a way that has a certain degree of ease or lightness in
the awareness itself then that becomes the that lightness or
that ease or a little bit of calmness around how we're aware that makes a room for compassion to
arise rather than distress to arise rather than fear or alarm arising
and so the mode in which we're aware can affect how we're how we're how we can
have compassion and then also if we're compassionate the
mode in which we're relating to things the mood in which we're aware can affect how we enact The Compassion how we live
from that compassion and so the compassion has lived in a way maybe it's not so heavy or doesn't come
from a sense of Duty or doesn't come from a sense of of you know doesn't mix up with fear or
ego or all kinds of things that can be there so what I'd like to
um do this week is offer you um
what I'm calling the seven factors of compassion and they're the same as the the common
Buddhist list of the seven factors of Awakening and so the first one is mindfulness so
the mindfulness factor of compassion the investigation factor of compassion
the effort factor of compassion The Joy factor of compassion
the Tranquility factor of compassion
um a concentration factor of compassion and and the Equanimity factor of compassion
and um and what's kind of lovely is that when
we live from compassion the seven effectors awaking follow along
and the first one being mindfulness there's a way in which coming from a compassionate Place responding to things
compassionately brings with it mindfulness mindfulness built is kind of comes along without any real having to
work at it people only practice mindfulness there are times where it's going to work to
you like it feels like you're doing the mindfulness you don't care I would drift it off that's to come back and had to do it again and
um but when compassion is in the Forefront there's a way in which mindfulness can follow effortlessly it's
not like we have to work it at um at being Mindful and so so same thing for
the other factors so I'll to make this easier to understand this I would like to um
give a kind of a school playground example
say you're visiting a playground and there's a small child maybe a five
six-year-old child four five four five-year-old child who's playing I have lots of fun in the playground
but then the child trips and scrapes her
um maybe she scrapes her knee she's wearing shorts and so the knee rubs across the
asphalt and gets scraped and maybe it's dirty and there's a little gravel and and so she's quite stunned and shocked
that uh you know she was having so much fun and now suddenly she's in pain she's confused she's upset and in pain
and a relatively common school yard kind of injury
and so she comes running to you and um and so you feel her distress you
feel her see that she has a wound but this you've you've had this for yourself in playgrounds you've seen it
before this is a kind of common thing she'll be she's going to be fine what she needs is someone who just cares for
her is present in a calm way and begins taking care of her in a nice way
and um and so you decide that this you should you know she calms down and say you're going to
um with compassion and care you want to clean her wound because it's gravel and
grit in there and um and so but it hurts it hurts for to touch it even with a
flow of water so you get maybe a soft cotton ball or something or and that's
moist and you're very likely tap the wound in order to pick up some of the dirt
that's there and you do it with um you really don't want to hurt or you care
about her you want to settle her you wouldn't want to agitate her more so there's this love and care to do this as
carefully as you can and so you bring your attention into that um you know it to you're paying attention
to her very carefully to see what the response will be when you touch so you can pull back quickly if she's if it
stings her too much and so but you know just very gently and you that you're very careful about how quickly you do it
the pressure you put on on the wound there's a lot of attention
what's driving the attention is the compassion the care for the girl
What's um what follows in the wake of that care is a lot of mindfulness
a lot of attention there to really be present to take in the situation
no one needs to tell you be aware pay attention be mindful come back to the
present moment that just follows along with this deep
motivation to care for this person and to be attentive in a nice way to not cause you know more pain for her
and not only do you have to uh you know there's a lot of awareness and attention there
there is what in Buddhism is called investigation which is to be very discerning
about what causes more pain and what causes less what supports her what doesn't support
her what kind of tone of voice to speak what kind of voice not to speak partly
taking in the cues from her and as you speak and as you say things and and so
there's a lot of care not only in being present but in making distinctions between what is useful here and what is
not useful The Compassion takes the lead and this idea of kind of being
considerate about you know what what could hurt her more or what's going to hurt her less
um it's kind of effortless it's like obvious of course if you want to carefully care for her a wound and to
clean it and put a bandage on of course you're going to try to pay attention to the way to do it that causes the least
amount of pain for her at least amount of distress tuning in to all these little factors
and what what's useful and not useful and um and so that what what's in the
lead here is compassion so one way to develop mindfulness
is to be compassionate one way to be compassionate is to be
mindful is to develop Your Capacity to be aware in a light way in a calm way
and open way so that then the tenderness the warmth
of your heart has a chance as a room to be there when we're aware in a heavy way or
strong way or if we're angry and we're being aware the anger doesn't give much
room if we're full of desires if we're full of fear there's not much room for
anything to arise in the field of awareness but if we can learn the art
even with fear and anger and distress the art of having a light touch a
lightness an easefulness in the mindfulness um just that you might find that there's
more a little more space to have care and love and compassion kindness for
yourself for the distress you have and for others for the difficulty they have
and then once the compassion is there to let that be in the Forefront to act
on that to live that way to have compassion maybe not in such a way that everyone knows you're being compassionate because
that might be a little bit too much for some people but uh but you care you're
bringing a caring and a kindness to your things to people and the events and then
then notice that as you do that is there
can you notice the ease easeful way in which you are aware you're mindful
can you notice the kind of the matter of fact obvious way in which you're investigating you're making distinctions
between what makes it what supports the situation and what doesn't what's helpful and what's not helpful
that compassion is wise compassion um when we act on it or live motivated
by it brings along a lot of different factors that support
the compassion without even sometimes even needing to think about it
provided that we don't get locked in with the Compassion or alarmed or fearful or
dutiful and the compassion is doesn't become heavy
when there's a lot of suffering in the world and we might feel obligated I have to be heavy I have to be serious my
compassion has to be strong now Paradox of all this is that the best
form of compassion that we can have is not strong compassion it's or heavy
compassion it's light compassion it's calm compassion it's compassion it has
lots of room for things including lots of room for yourself and it's that kind of compassion that
brings along with it attention attentiveness mindfulness and that
brings along with it Discerning about what's helpful and not helpful or that question looking and seeing what years
are helpful I'm all with a light touch
all with a kind of light touch that is sustainable for compassion over a long time
and that's one of the things we're looking for in compassion is sustainable compassion because compassion that is heavy or
strong or that's too tight to connect it with other kind of challenges we have
we'll have compassion fatigue we'll get exhausted very quickly if you know but
this lightness a light touch so maybe think of uh living a life of
compassion you know it's more like a marathon than a Sprint
and so Marathon also you kind of start off with a kind of a light run and um
so um so the seven factors of compassion said
that follow along follow built on compassion and today I mentioned too
mindfulness and discernment or investigation and you might see as you go about your
day-to-day maybe try to have a light touch with your awareness but to have a light
Compassion or a light care or light love or kindness that allows there to be room for
attention awareness of what is happening in this field of
kindness what's happening in this field of compassion and then maybe start seeing how
mindfulness can follow compassion how discernment follows and see how those
work together and and and maybe you'll find that it's even
easier to be mindful and develop your mindfulness if it's Guided by compassion
then it's Guided by a sense of you know it's good for you or something
so um thank you and um so we'll continue from IRC
tomorrow and thank you for being here