greetings friends greetings from Northern California where
I am unseated olonieland where it's rainy and about to get light through the
clouds greetings to you wherever in the world you are dear Sangha it's lovely to
be with you in this moment in time um lots of Happiness of heart to see to
see you um on the chat joining happy making
so so we're going to continue our exploration today we've been exploring
the theme of life as Improv and uh today the theme we're going to
explore is the theme of non-attachment to outcome non-attachment
to outcome a very um um Buddhist
um frame which also shows up in in improv too so so as we explore it in our
meditation here is the invitation to consider because often we think of non-attachment to outcome in our life
as a teaching but what if we actually bring it into the frame of our
moment-to-moment experience moment to moment training uh as we train ourselves
in meditation and sometimes it can be confusing for for people when we when we talk about
non-attachment to outcome when we're meditating um the question comes out well do I just
sit willy-nilly let anything come up no not exactly we have a particular
perspective we have a particular way attitude way uh a bigger container but
in the small ways whatever arises we have flexibility we are not attached to
okay I want a deep state of concentration now and needs to happen and if it doesn't happen if thoughts
arise then we're destroyed and and angry at ourselves at
circumstances but there is flexibility of oh okay this is what's arising right now how can I skillfully work with this
what what kind of a gift what gift does this quote-unquote distracting thought have
in this moment to teach me something to teach me to train me how to work with it
so non-attachment to outcome within a larger framework of of our heart having
an aspiration having an aspiration having an intention but
not attachment to moment-to-moment outcome having flexibility within that
so the bigger container and the moment to moment so so with that
let's practice together let's meditate together and all relate it and then I'll
look at this through the frame of improvising our life from that frame and
relate and connect the two together may be of service
so let us arrive let us arrive
with the aspiration with the intention
of connecting connecting to ourselves
connecting to goodness cultivating goodness
cultivating wise choices wisdom kindness in this moment
with the aspiration for service for peace for freedom
aspirations for not suffering and not causing others suffering
as much as possible aspiration for flexibility
for ease for gentleness
and any personal aspirations you have In This Moment In Time
for your life please add them bring them in them
and let these intentions aspirations
imbue your heart space of our mind in this practice
aspirations not expectations expectations can be tight
then aspirations there's a lot of room for gentleness and wisdom
expectations are demanding and give rise to self-judgment
so let there be aspiration in every moment
connecting with the breath with the body
receiving whatever arises In This Moment
reconnecting with aspiration
letting aspiration be nourishing calming
enlivening
Let There Be aspiration without a fixed detachment
in your heart your mind be like water
flexible
finding other ways to be wise sort of budding budding heads with
challenges of finding ways to be wise
kind to yourself
foreign
what if we dropped in aspiration for not suffering but be more daring aspiration for
happiness the Patel was known as the happy one
operations for happiness for joy without attachment to outcome that we
need to have Joy by just dropping it in it's an aspiration
without attachment to outcome
and there be a lightness lightness
the respiration for joy happiness slightness
body not heaviness of attachment see see what it feels like in the body
it's of lightness with your inspirations
uplifting light
your thoughts about the Future Past arise
and we meet them with lightness of our heart of our aspiration
for happiness joy non-suffering freedom
In This Moment
sense of uplift in the heart and the mind
you allow your whole body to feel your aspiration
be infused to every cell
aspiration not expectation
and as we turn to bring this
sending to a close reconnecting with their aspiration in
our heart inspiration for waking up
freedom freedom from suffering causing suffering
through wisdom kindness
for joy and happiness like the Buddha the happy one
wishing happiness goodness
ourselves our hearts our minds every cell of this body
a wish aspiration not attachment
lightly an uplift in the heart gushing oil for ourselves
for all beings whose lives are as touches
bringing them to heart and all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere
be happy have well-being be free
may my practice the goodness of the seeds I plant
may my practice my aspirations
without attachment be of service
to all beings everywhere including myself
[Music]
thank you for your practice friends
and we have a minute of transition and if you
are inspired to share with one word
what's arising For You In This Moment we've been doing that the past couple days and bring it into chat
[Music] that would be lovely
as I transition the recordings here
Hello friends hello greetings greetings lovely To Be With You In This Moment In
Time having just practiced together I invited
you to if you wanted to to put a word of what is arising for you
um and bring it into the space
and I'll read a few of them these yes warm relaxed awareness
love genuine presence ease calm abiding waking up
thank you gratitude relief release appreciation openness
smile-hearted a bit more calm beautiful so many beautiful intentions again and
and aspirations and what's arising joyous anticipation life is amazing
aspiration beautiful
thank you so much for your engagement your engagement with this practice and
engaging with each other in this way this really inspiring way to to also
um to support each other caring not clinging aspired to be wise
thank you for for all the reflections
and letting go a hair I love that letting go ahead beautiful yes
letting go ahead beautiful so so the theme for this week
um is uh life as Improv Buddhist teachings that actually they
are are infused in in the practice of
improv comedy as as a practice not just as a as
you know it can look like an explosion of of hilarity and fun which it can be
it is but yet it's it's a it's an internal practice um to to really make that happen
to The Observer to the eye of the Observer and we we've talked about the
first day we talked about the attitude of this this this sense of lightness the the bringing of of emptiness with
fullness this sense of life as infinite game as an infinite play the slightness
of co-creating yesterday we talked about yes and yes
and this meeting meeting the moment was yes and and adding to it instead of no
blocking blocking life blocking energy and being in conflict with what is which
never helps and today
as introduced in our practice the idea of having an aspiration having a sense a
frame and a non-attachment non-attachment to outcome in the moment
because attachment to outcome of wanting things to be a particular way in a particular moment is this this tightness
can can make our time our hearts really tied our our hearts heavy our bodies
heavy there's a sense of heaviness instead of oh finding possibility
finding like like being like water our hearts and Minds being like water finding possibilities
um that oh okay my my aspiration is is this and yet in this moment okay this is
what's arising um instead of being in conflict with it what can I can I
um accept what is can I accept what is still keeping with the aspiration but
not attaching to a particular outcome in this in in the way I imagined it to be
so okay so this is the Buddhist frame and now let me switch for a moment to The Improv
frame so that we look at it from a slightly different frame for a moment especially because improv is really
relational mindfulness that's how I see it it's relational mindfulness it
um it it's how we really interact with others with the sense of lightness and
all these other um aspirations so
so the the the word that
uh Keith Johnstone who's a seminal um teacher in in improv and the author
of the um the book empro uh the way that one one many many
Concepts really many beautiful Concepts that are related and this concept the way he brings it in the word he uses is
chivalry chivalry and chivalry is really non-attachment to ideas in relational uh
improver relational mindfulness so this is how he defines it
chivalry means not clinging to your own ideas your own status because in different
games you know people assume a status you know maybe their higher status or lower status that's another concept from
from um improv or even your own life as a character you know so basically Cheryl
Remains Not clinging to your own ideas chivalry is daring to give up control
players should allow themselves to be changed by other players be happy to be
forced to change and change such an interesting concept right in in
this relational uh way of being in this really improv or
relational mindfulness so so the way this shows up is say if you are an
improviser and again we're all improvisers in our lives we improvise everything
um but saying in in an improv scene if two improvisers show up and one
improviser has this idea of okay this scene is going to go in this direction so they say something like oh I'm I
don't know I'm tired today and then expecting something else from the other person like oh yeah this is what this
scene is going to be about person a has that idea but person B has maybe a different idea so if person B says oh
um oh I'm sorry you're tired let's let's you know go and rest I'll put this
person a had a different idea I thought maybe this person B would say oh let's go and then play anyway the point being
um if we if we stick to our idea idea if we are not chivalrous if if we are if we
cling to the way a scene needs to be then there is a block and this person is pulling this way this person is pulling
that way it's like ah life is pulling that way this person is pulling that way uh there's a lot of conflict what if
like what if and the invitation is say okay well that's the idea I had but ah
not attachment to outcome chivalry in the Big Frame the Big Frame the aspiration here is is
lightness a co-creation it's a co-creation with kindness with chivalry
is the bigger frame so without attaching with my idea that yes we're definitely
going to go and play but oh no the scene is going to be about something else okay let me be changed let me open up to what
this invitation is and see how within the frame of my aspiration aspiration
and the scene how this can how can I be changed and shifted and then the other
person with the same idea will be shifted and changed so if both people are willing to be shifted and changed
and play and co-create together it becomes beautiful in improv the scene
becomes fun watchable it becomes joyous whereas if the two people are stuck in
there like they're pulling it to go this way and this other person is pulling it to go this way and budding is like Ugh
it's torture to witness it's really torture to witness and also feels
torturous um internally he's like you just keep putting this like attachment this is the
way this is the idea I had just ah chivalry so so again now back to
the end of course this is all within still the Buddhist dream the Buddhist teachings of
non-attachment and and within within our practice especially relationally as both
as we relate to a moment so we have this aspiration for waking up for for causing
causing as little harm as possible causing no harm uh Letting Go a hair as
as little as possible freedom and and we have these ideas and and especially
relationally we have some ideas as to how something's going to go and then oh it's not going to go that way okay so
how instead of instead of digging our heels in like this is the idea I had
this is what I thought we were going to do today like can we be flexible okay
all right begin within the frame it doesn't mean that we're going to to
compromise our integrity it's not compromising our integrity in any way at
all but within that frame can we be flexible can there be flexibility
both relationally and in our minds and actually that it's flexibility and
finding ways to to work with challenges with the
hindrances with our suffering instead of digging our heels in it's not going the way I wanted it to go it's not the way I
want it to be a different way we get stuck we get more and more stuck in our suffering
um can we say yes yes and okay yes this is what's being offered in this moment
it's not exactly what I had in mind um I I wasn't planning on getting sick
and or having body aches or this or that or I don't know the storm happening yeah
like this is not exactly but yes and okay this is what's happening and what is the wise way to open to it
wholeheartedly to wholeheartedly with wisdom kindness with integrity and
without attachment to outcome with aspiration keeping the aspiration but without this fixed view that things have
to be in a particular way so so I'll give one quick final example say not
just relationally but say in your practice say a hindrance or Rises okay hindrance
of sleepiness arises if you have a stance of no it's like oh
sleepy sleepiness I hate it I'm a bad meditator it's as terrible this is awful I'm awful
nurses another way to work with sleepiness is yes and okay yes this is a
different state of mind okay sleepiness is here it doesn't mean succumbing to it but it means okay how can I wisely work
with this so one can actually study sleepiness it can still be here but one
can say yes and let me study what is happening in my body what's happening in
my mind what is this like can I be aware and and
um have awareness kind awareness in every moment and actually you might fall
asleep for a millisecond if you're aware and it will be a very deep restful sleep
in the middle of your meditation then you wake up completely refreshed um and you'll be you you would have
cultivated this this this ability to be with the hypnagogic state
mindfulness instead of resisting it resisting it resisting it and res and finishing your meditation feeling
terrible exhausted and and angry so there is this yes and can be such a
helpful stance internally with that with whatever is arising internally as well
as relationally in in improv in in improvising Our Lives
so thank you all for your practice for your
attention for showing up supporting yourself and being open to to exploring this this these different Con well
similar and slightly different concepts of to bring in some freshness some
freshness some different perspective as to how to improvise Our Lives internally
externally with the perspective with the aspiration for cultivating kindness and
and joy and lightness and freedom and wisdom and may you be well may you be
happy may you have lightness and yes the invitation today oh yes I always like to give invitations
um in relational whenever you have a relational um relational so internally can you have
chivalry can you have non-attachment to ideas aspiration Integrity but not
attachment can you find ways to be flexible and see how that feels internally versus digging your heels and
it's got to be this way I don't like the way it is um so
thank you all take good care be well and
uh see you tomorrow