foreign
Let's uh set
yeah
the silence beckons us
yeah we we can uh place our attention
in a simple way with the breath with our body sound
the darkness behind our closed eyes
with a phrase a mantra art practice
when we don't want the mechanics of our
attention to blot out the beckoning of Silence
before he died Leonard Cohen wrote a few lines of poetry or referenced
listened to the hummingbird whose wings you cannot see listen to the hummingbird don't listen
to me listen to the mind of God that doesn't
need to be listen to the mind of God don't listen
to me
um maybe in that instruction is complete
for you maybe
the practice is uh listen listen to the mind
of a Buddha
but the emphasis is on receptivity
untrusting trusting awareness
of hearing the silence beckon us
the movements of our mind
quite a bit like the body of an animal plowing
and totally blameless
we forgive our mind we forgive some sorrow
when we rest
suspended silence
we find the reconciliation between spiritual
urgency and abiding patience
there are practices to uh rest from the endlessness of our
coping
coping with the intensity
The Human Condition
and just kind of give up trying to sort out
all the pleasantness from the unpleasantness The Hope from the fear
the prose and cons of me
when we're not coping anymore
there's nothing to do but be awake
foreign
okay it's good to uh good to sit with you
so
silence and Noise we uh
live in a very noisy World Realm
and of course the blessings of Technology
but the ways we drown in it and so much of technology has functioned
primarily to scale greed in delusion
and um we've kind of drowning in information
but can't make much sense of anything
line from uh Jennifer Egan's novel candy house
um she says knowing everything is too much
like knowing nothing without a story it's all just
information it is
um very very easy to lose a plot
the plot of our life it's very easy to
take on that kind of prevailing values of the moment of the context
and um and when we're when we're pretty happy
when things are going okay our things can be kind of fun
yeah things we often take to be important they can be kind of fun I don't want to dismiss that
but when we're unhappy when things are breaking down almost nothing matters
except the heart there's just
zero consolation from ownership
when there's not wisdom delusion fills the vacuum
so maybe we we know the experience experiences like like we have on Retreat
especially maybe a little little Whirlpool of suffering
yeah the day is going all right we're doing our practice whatever like okay there's a whirlpool
and we get spun out about whatever
and uh and on Retreat you know the blessing of
retreat the blessing of continuity you get to see
how little that the kind of House of Cards we built we get to actually see
the collapse when the house of cards that seems so meaningful the story that seems so
meaningful we get to see a collapse and we we see how little it actually
meant right but um some whirlpools are 10 minutes long
and some are 10 years is that from uh
poet David White um said some years ago I found myself
working with a room full of particularly thoughtful managers we were looking at all the way as humans
find it necessary to sacrifice their own sacred desires and personal Visions on the altar
work and success out of this a woman wrote the following lines she
read them slowly from the back of the room unaware stricken we all were by the
silence she created she said 10 years ago
I turned my face for a moment and it became my life
possible for that to happen and it's possible for us to wake up
and so we asked the question how do we um keep from losing the plot how do we
remember and we
we take our Council from death
I am of the nature to age
to become ill to die there's nothing I can do
to escape this okay okay take it in the kind of remembrances yeah
we take it in and we see what in our mind holds on and
what let's go we see what Falls away
and so much of what we do mean in our life
in the busyness kind of it maintains its momentum only in light
of immortality we tacently are assuming
immortality it's the only way this little thing
matters because if I knew in this moment yeah
this thing ends The View would be different
so we bring the contemplation to the surface not to scare ourselves but to
sense into what we care about what will matter what
would make life feel more complete we're Complete because even if we were
to live carelessly for a thousand years it would not feel like enough
it would not feel like enough it's almost like the image I'm having is that kind of the Hungry Ghost with the huge
belly and the tiny mouth and trying to get sustenance you know and maybe we're like that with life with
time you know What would
make it feel like enough we we ask ourselves uh this question
saw this interview with uh with Roland Griffis who's a psychopharmacologist at
Hopkins and I knew his work long before he got famous for doing
um psychedelic research he was a kind of drug you know abuse liability researcher and
very uh kind of well-respected and I didn't know long-term meditator
and then um
then got into a psychedelic research and
um I was um quite sad as he was recently
diagnosed serious aggressive disease and um saw an interview with him and he
says the interviewer says um you talk about your cancer almost as if
it's a gift does that mean you don't have any regrets about what's happening
and Griffith's response was my life has never been better
if I had a regret it's uh
I had a regret it's that I didn't wake up as much as I have without a cancer
diagnosis it's been incredible
so to live in alignment with our
with our deepest value is what we care about it takes something powerful
nuclear powered really keep remembering
and it takes um takes energy takes
wisdom renunciation the the Buddha famously described anger
as having a honey honey tip and poisoned root
and um in this life there is a lot of honey and
a lot of poison and how do we remember that the honey is
tied to the poison
how do we not be conned by what doesn't matter
we recall our death
and there's something about that contemplation where I can almost just feel like the energy draining out of the
defilements and it just feels like too much to
nurse the dense
stories or old resentments or the Envy or divisiveness or whatever is
just like okay don't have time for that
and so maybe maybe what I'm saying is that uh
what's been said a million times is uh death helps us let
go it helps us let go
of fake Refuge fake happiness
death of course is a letting go right where
in a way in each moment we practice we're practicing uh practicing
or the enormous letting go of death each time we surrender
to imperfection
each time we uh stop coping each time we open to a
certain kind of helplessness yeah
we're practicing dying
and uh
in a certain way rehearsing our own death both as a preparation
and as a
a way of clarifying what's going to count and in the wake of that kind of
surrender that the the Dayton with the first Noble Truth
uh the Dharma makes a lot of sense
death helps the Dharma make a lot of sense
to offer this for your consideration and please uh pick up what is useful and
leave the rest behind yeah we were speaking one-on-one there's no
way I would say exactly all of this to each of you so we each need to Wade through
the words of others to find a what's useful
okay