so once upon a time someone asked when's
a good time to be mindful and uh the answer was it was
when it's the best alternative when it's the best option
one of the phenomena that happens as we start practicing mindfulness we start
discovering that it's often the best option
and it becomes the better option the more we practice it and part of the reason for that is as
we're practicing mindfulness we start seeing what our mind stream is doing
and sometimes occasionally our mindstream is not that high quality
it it's not doing something that's it might even be harmful it might even be a
drag what goes on in there the topics the concerns the attitudes
and and that's our circumstances mindfulness is a better option and what mindfulness does is it kind of
interrupts the the freedom of our kind
of unhealthy mind streams from just perpetuating themselves freely which if we're not mindful they can do
and if the unhealthy Minds ruminations and thoughts and ideas go freely that
actually reinforce themselves to become stronger and stronger but to be mindful is to considered to
always be helpful always be a wholesome beneficial thing for the mind to do because it's a way of in to some degree
stepping out of that mindstream and seeing it and the more clarity we see oh
that's not a cool way of thinking the more clear more clarity that is
without judgment and criticism just oh look at that that's not cool
we're interrupting that mindstream to some degree we're stepping out of it for a moment
and then as we do so you ask the question what's the best time to be
mindful I think it's right now because it's the better alternative it's
a better option sometimes we're thinking about something that's not necessarily harmful for us or
for others but we've thought it ten thousand times and uh and maybe mindfulness is a better
option uh maybe uh um and as we as we step into that out of
the mindstream into mindfulness we start discovering over time that
there's something else available to us that's not just simply redirecting the Mind stream like for me I do redirect mine sometimes
I'll be thinking about something I say you know this is not useful to think about or you know I'm going to give a
talk later in the day and I start thinking about I don't know something nothing to relate to the talk and it's
not such a nice it's not bad thoughts but it's kind of I don't know ridiculous
thoughts and uh and I said you know I think I I
think I'm better off thinking about what to talk about when I come to IMC and so my mind goes there for a while and that
seems better so sometimes you can redirect the mind and um and uh and I'll often do that in
the course of the day and it isn't repressing anything it isn't um you know
pollyanish to think something else it just seems like very matter-of-fact and straightforward and of course I would do
that choose the better option but as I as the mindfulness becomes
stronger if there's something else that's possible to discover and that is there's a there's all kinds
of um wonderful States wonderful capacities or or qualities inside that can arise
that are nothing to do with our mind stream what we're thinking about and concerned with
that there's these wonderful inner qualities that bubble up almost as if
mindfulness makes space for it that can you can't have space for it if
you keep thinking and you might have a habit of having the most beautiful Noble
and inspiring and healthy thoughts that anybody's ever had in the history of humanity
and you have a a real record of usually doing the all day long and uh and you're just proud and engaged
and inspired by what you're thinking about then you just want to keep thinking it so please do if you want
however that cons you're constantly filling the space with those thoughts and and so
there's no Inner Space for something else to arise to develop and as we get a sense that mindfulness
makes a space or something beautiful to happen within us the question when is the best time to be
mindful takes a whole different there's more evidence there's more understanding oh
now's the best time because even the most beautiful thoughts of I mean this is going to be the Great American novel
or you know whatever well it might be but there's even better things
more wonderful things and there's the qualities and capacities we have inside
that are you know when they become strong
some people might want to describe them as divine
and maybe that's what the Buddha did when he called five particular states that we have inside
named after the Indian God Indra and so of Indra so of of of of God or
Heavenly or something and and if you don't get a sense of this kind of divine association with these
five qualities that are your own personal qualities that you have um in the usual English translation of
these which is called the five faculties so five faculty seems nice but isn't that kind of bland oh yeah I have five
faculties you know you know but if you have five divinities within I mean like what you know some of
you might be now alarmed or running because but anyway these five Divine qualities
like what's that and um these five are also sometimes
called five strengths something you also don't get from the word faculties
and the difference between these two words the India and the powers the Bala
is um just linguistic according to the Buddha it's not uh they're the same
thing and so these Divine qualities are also wonderful strengths or powers that we
can carry within us so what are these so let me before I kind of
name them for those some many of you know what they are I want to continue this analogy with the mindfulness
so as we're mindful we discover what our mindstream is up to and sometimes we see it's up to
something unhealthy for us something not so beneficial maybe even harmful for ourselves sometimes it's just a waste of
time and sometimes it's actually wonderful to do and the thoughts the concerns the
questions we have they're inspiring we're inspired by it it's really healthy and uh and to see those clearly those
options gives us a chance to choose which of those options we pursue
and it makes a difference if you see those three options in front of you you know like see three foods in front
of you one's poisonous one is tasteless
and one just is so satisfying uh dish like just like maybe it's just like
your the favorite Mother's dish growing up or something that represents parental
love or something it nourishes you in so many more ways than just with food because of the love
that you associate with it so poison Blend or this food that
conveys love what would you choose well you know I think not so many people
would use the poison and but but the love thing
and when we choose the love food the food that associated with kind of maternal or paternal care or
grandmotherly care or something then something different happens within
us something inspiring something nice something oh this was good I feel I remember something wonderful from my
childhood and to this day I still remember when I have toast with cheese on it I remember you know I remember my
grandmother and her and her love it's like wow and um so the same thing can happen
internally as we see the the Smorgasburg Borg of different uh
mind states that my different thought streams and we have inside if you see that you're just always kind
of in a complaining mind state that's kind of like getting into the territory of poison actually
if you're always filled with hate then and hostile and you're kind of full of
resentment you might not want to believe this but it is a kind of poison for our hearts or Minds
if you're constantly greedy it's kind of a poison to be caught up in that that
does all these things do negative things to our hearts our minds our body
uh generosity love wisdom
kindness they do a whole different thing and some of these positive states can really Feed
Us in a wonderful good ways and now is for our benefit
so as we do the mindfulness practice we start seeing the range of possibilities
of what our mind can be up to in any given time and and first it happens maybe in
meditation in meditation you start seeing you know you're you start thinking about um I
don't know what you know could be lottery tickets and you're kind of like trying to guess how to calculate you
know what are the most likely numbers to win the lottery this next time and what are the lucky numbers and it in a
40-minute meditation after 20 minutes you realize you have 20 minutes I've been thinking about lottery numbers
and it's it finally Dawns on you what a waste of time I don't think I'll do that anymore let
me switch and just focus on my breathing and you focus on your breathing and it feels good and relaxing and by the time
the next 20 minutes are over you feel settled and relaxed and quiet and wow
that's so much better to have done that rather than spend all 40 minutes of meditation thinking about numbers
lottery numbers so maybe that's a silly example but I think meditators as they meditate start
seeing what kind of thinking is not useful to do sometimes they discover that there's no good thinking in
meditation they have much better things to do than keep thinking just let the Mind get quiet and calm and so in
meditation we start making choices what we pick up what we perpetuate and
what we put down and uh and uh after a while we developed
some um confidence not only that we can do that but some confidence that there are
better choices than spending the whole meditation uh guessing lottery numbers
or whatever it might be that we spin off in there are better choices
and we start having confidence in that so that it's not after 20 minutes we switch gears it might be after a few
minutes we switch gears I know something better not only we have confidence in it we're
actually inspired I'm inspired by the other possibility of meditating of these other states of
Minds that can happen these other directions we can go into and so after a while there gets because
of familiarity with the territory of meditation not only is our confidence there's trust in a different thing that
we do some type some people without thinking about it trust resentment
trust complaining trust grumbling all kinds of things because what the Mind does most of the time but we come to
meditation we start seeing that the usual mind streams we live in are not so useful
and so we start trusting putting them down and trusting something else
and when after a while they become inspired by this how lucky I am that I have this practice
that allows me to change the Mind stream or do something else to have a practice that seems to settle the Mind down to
some degree and I have access to something else we might even say we start having faith
in this book this potential and this possibility and over time this sense of Faith or
confidence in this becomes stronger and stronger until
it becomes a thing it becomes divine
it becomes a strength that we have and it makes a huge difference to have this confidence in the practice
because sometimes practice is hard to do sometimes our mind streams are very challenging and there's all the lawyers
of the mind that will argue that against it you have to you have to kind of you
know plan Revenge that you're required to as a human being
aren't you you deserve it or do you have a right to it or whatever but you have so much confidence in what
can happen when we don't get caught in these unhealthy mind streams that the faith and the confidence will
override the lawyers and will choose the healthy direction
so this confidence this faith that we have in the practice can get stronger and stronger and stronger
and it becomes something that feels really inspiring and wonderful to have it and maybe it's divine in certain kind
of way as we start seeing more clearly the choices the mind can make
then we put effort into doing so and that effort of choosing the Healthy
Mind streams or the healthy states of mind or choosing mindfulness it it does involve some kind of effort it involves
choice as we repeatedly make that effort even like the effort to sit down to meditate
day after day as we sit and meditate the effort to return to the breathing return to the breathing
at some point that effort Factor gets strong at some point that effort factor
and the mindfulness together starts giving rise to a certain kind of
Vitality that begins carrying us along some people would call it Chi
this kind of inner Vitality that's there and some of you probably kind of an
ordinary place to feel that maybe for some of us is if you start a new exercise practice you know maybe
bicycling or running or something and it first it's really hard and the body screams and says stop
but as you do it and get into it and get conditioned sometimes you start feeling this wonderful vitality and joy in doing
the exercise for a while until you get tired or something but you know there's kind of something kicks in a vitality
and when you stop doing it the you know the end of the exercise the Vitality
remains for a while it's really great so the same thing can happen with the mental practice of
mindfulness that there's a Vitality that gets Unleashed that gets opened or released
or awoken and that Vitality is called Viria in
poly it's a and then there's uh as we practice mindfulness
um mindfulness is one of the things we choose to keep doing we see the mind gets distracted and we
come back and we're mindful again over time that capacity to be aware
becomes a second nature so much like we're strengthening a muscle and you just stay aware
some of you maybe have had this experience if you do a good session of meditation at home or here
and then you uh for the next few minutes after the meditation or maybe longer
than that you kind of feel like you're kind of like really here you're really here you kind of notice
your feels fresh it feels like you're not automatically rushing off into distraction again and getting busy
you're going to the kitchen to make breakfast and it feels like you're just there in a relaxed calm way and you're
very present for the experience of breakfast and preparing it then it's
calm and and the maybe even the kitchen Sparkles a little bit because you're paying attention you know you're there
in a nice way and so the awareness that gets kind of
built up during and meditation persists after meditation is over until
you get caught up and then maybe you start reading the news and that's all it takes
and um but also awareness can become a strength
awareness when it has kind of a life of its own it's there and present for you available for you
without having to do a lot of work to make it there it's just there as kind of a natural quality
and you have to protect it by not getting distracted but it's kind of the stronger it becomes
it's kind of divine it's a fantastic capacity
and then as we're becoming less and less distracted what we're overcoming is being
fragmented being distracted we're kind of beginning beginning to kind of gather ourselves together and being oh kind of
wholehearted whatever we're doing or or just kind of complete in ourselves being
here right now which is samadhi which is the uh what's called
concentration in English but samadhi the state of being undistracted such a beautiful feeling like you can
engage in washing your dishes and you're wholeheartedly everything is there as if
this is the only thing to do the most valuable thing to do is to be there with doing the dishes
what a rare thing in many people in our distracted world we have how many people do the dishes and will
automatically turn on the radio a TV show in order to get input and get the
latest news or get something going and or automatically going through their
mind and start going through the to-do list they're going to do and what they're worried about and they're hardly
present for the dishes there's no samadhi of dishwashing but there is dishwashing samadhi
which is such a pleasure wow because the alternative is to be distracted the
alternative is to be fragmented and split between what we do and so as we learn to be mindful and the
mindfulness is stronger and we're choosing to be present more and more there's a unification process that goes
on and we learned about how beautiful it is and it turns out that unified feeling of
being fully present to what you're doing at the moment can be divine
or spiritual it's very just just that is a spiritual state in Buddhism
and um and there that can be a strength concentration can become so strong that
it's actually hard to shake it off sometimes and you carry it with you more than just carrying calm with you you
carry with you a unified State as you go through your day
and then as you keep doing the mindfulness practice and you start seeing all those things you start seeing
what's wholesome and unwholesome mind streams seeing that you have faith and
confidence seeing the strength of the mindfulness seeing the strength of unification
then then there arises wisdom and one of the key forms of wisdom is to
really appreciate how valuable it is to make the choice to go in the wholesome
Direction and to avoid the unwholesome you see how it benefits you you see how much changes
when you do that you see how healthy it is and so wisdom becomes stronger and
stronger as well and you see have this wisdom that you bring with you everywhere and it helps you to make
these choices that keeps you these spiritual qualities presence
so now I've gone through the five so there are there's confidence there's
vitality there is awareness there's a unification and there's wisdom
these can be uh strengths that we carry with us they're they're spiritual or
Divine qualities we come along for the Buddha
these five qualities are part of the description of what
changes in a person as they mature in the Buddhist practice that these five qualities get stronger
and stronger and stronger someone is fully awakened has these all
these five qualities to the maximum strength possible so if you want to know what what is it
you know what what's it like to be in fully enlightened
they have really fully strong fully strengthened Faith confidence Vitality
awareness uh unification and this wisdom vector
and um and the Buddha he talks about these not so much something that you practice
but something that arises out of your practice and this is what I was saying earlier
what's the best you know when's the best time to practice mindfulness when it's
the best we know when should we practice mindfulness when it's the best option we
start seeing that there are other options that are better than what we're doing and one of them is to practice a
mindfulness and awareness that begins allowing these five qualities to grow and develop
and emerge and as they're there to establish ourselves in them to recognize them and
make room for them to recognize them and and kind of be in them and not to take them for granted but to
be present for it so um uh he doesn't say practice faith
he doesn't say practice vitality he doesn't say practice awareness he
doesn't say practice unification or practice wisdom we do Buddhist practice
the practice of recognizing what's happening our mindstream the practice of choosing what's healthy making the
effort to do so we we make the effort to let go of our
distractions there are there are things that we do but there's also what is done to us when
we do so and these five spiritual qualities powers are these things that get born
within us and grow and develop over time and um and it's fantastic
so practice facilitates practice supports the arising of these things
and um and they become you know
you know they represent or Define or characterize some of the strong spiritual States
that we can live in when we do Buddhist practice I don't know if these five states are
inspiring to you but the alternative to those five
hopefully is the opposite of inspiring I mean there's so many you know to not
have confidence or they are worse do it be you know to be kind of have a lot of doubt about
your abilities or about anything to be caught up in you know skepticism around it all and
it's you know not so helpful to uh not to have vitality
but to actually be uh Have Your vitality drained which so much of our society these days
supports in some of the ways in which we participate in our technology and our society and the beliefs and the politics
and everything can be draining and do not be aware
be careful you have an accident next time you drive your car or lots of accidents all kinds of things
happen we're not aware to not be Unified
to be fragmented and broken and Scattered it's not good for us
and to not be wise to be foolish probably most of us don't want to be
foolish and uh it you know it's usually not a useful thing to do
in Buddhism there are no there are no sinners in Buddhism some religions have these big important heavy categories
Sinners and Saints um the the the closest the Buddhism gets
to it is there are fools
and uh and then the wise people so I don't know you maybe still don't like those dichotomies but
um but uh the thing about being a fool is that you can still become wise
and um whereas in some religions where the sin thing you know you know a sinner
there's sometimes not much help but we can always always you know
become wise in this practice so
um so there's this wonderful term that I
came up with that represents a very important Concept
in early Buddhism but translate it's my translation is
um profound generative attention
profound generative attention there's a profound way of being present
really be present for our lives mindful aware here
that allows the the emergence the generation
of wonderful qualities within us these Divine things that can come
somehow inside we have these capacities and for the talk today it's the five
faculties the five spiritual Divine Divine States five strengths
of confidence Vitality awareness unification and wisdom
what a wonderful thing and if we if these are there to support us
if we want them to support us it's good to recognize them
and they're operating all the time and the chances are
that there's a lot of activities that you do in your daily life where these five are present
and that encourage you to consider where in your life you these are operating maybe maybe unbeknownst to you
it could be that washing the dishes you never thought that was a spiritual
practice but in fact you have confidence that you can wash your dishes you have confidence you can wash your
dishes well without breaking anything you have confidence you can wash the
dishes in such a way that it feels wonderful to have the whole heartedness
of just doing the dishes and not being distracted by 10 000 things while you do it they have confidence for that
you have and you're willing to put effort into new dishes you know there's without some effort
dishes don't get done don't get cleaned so you are putting effort into it but is the effort you're making is it
the best effort you can make is there beautiful effort is there
vitality and way of washing dishes just this inspires you or you and patients
this idea to do dishes is to do them as quickly as you can get it over and you're kind of like you know multitasking and doing
but you know how you know what is it like to discover a nourishing effort in washing the dishes
what kind of awareness has to be present so you can do do dishes
that has this nourishing effort that comes with confidence
is there any wholeheartedness that you can do the dishes with
that is as wholehearted as
doing activities that you love doing that you do wholehearted because you love them and you're so interested
can you give yourself over to something that's one of the things I learned from Zen practice being in the Zen
monasteries I learned this wonderful art of giving yourself wholeheartedly to
whatever you're doing and because I did that and uh in the
monastery sometimes especially when I worked in the kitchen there I would work in the kitchen for a couple
hours and then I would go to meditate in the meditation Hall just literally walked from the kitchen to meditational
and sat down and because I did my kitchen work so wholeheartedly and just fully for the
activity when I sat down to meditate I was already concentrated and my mind was already undistracted
boom it was fantastic so to wash dishes with that wholeheartedness
and maybe some of you do it already and then the wisdom
to understand that it makes a difference how you wash dishes
if what you want just to evoke and live from the from like when Buddhist in Buddhist terminology and Buddhist
orientation from a spiritual place and allows spirituality to flow and move
through you the Divine or the strengths that come through you it makes a difference how you wash the
dishes and if it's true for dishes
it's probably true for a lot of things you do throughout the day how you drive
how you speak with your friends how you do your work how you
you know just you probably pretty much everything these five spiritual qualities are at
play and to ha and to recognize them to learn to recognize them learn to have them
make space for them have them grow and develop so that this profound generative
attention but there's a tension that that gives this profound generative capacity to do
its work that is not our doing it's not like the
ego that's making something and we're allowing something profound within us to
to emerge this is part of the gift of this practice
so I hope that made sense and um I hope even more than makes sense I hope
that this inspires you just to explore what I've said today in your daily life
and see if uh if you can discover these five qualities in your meditation
practice and your mindfulness practices you go through through your day but also in the
activities of your day um because if you do that in your life
daily life then you don't have to go to a monastery like I did
so thank you so we have about five minutes before we stop and maybe get
ready get ready for the potluck if any of you would like to ask a question or make a comment or a testimonial about
this um please
hello my name is Seoul um yeah I just have a question about being mindful because
um I like throughout the day I am sort of required to multitask
I didn't put my hearing aid in so if you could lift it up this way yeah okay can you hear me now much slower yeah okay
um so for my job I'm sort of required to multi multitask a lot so like when I'm
in the meeting I'm supposed to answer slack messages and read through email so this is kind of expected for my role so
yeah I'm just wondering how what's the best way to deal with so many inquiries
throughout the day and making sure that I fulfill my work duties as well so I I
I you know I I'm not sure what to say for you so I I what I say might be a
Miss but what I learned uh was sometimes it's possible to multitask
wonderfully um I was uh in the monastery I was the
dishwasher and you know and I did that for a lot of dishwashing the dishwashing machine and it was like multitasking you
know it was like a dance spinning and turning and doing this and that and what I learned and then also worked as a Fest
uh fast order cook in a restaurant after the monastery where I did multitasking Galore
and and what I learned was um uh don't have any resistance let go
of the resistance let go of the you know the just give myself over to it completely and um
and so I don't know if that works for what you do but just don't resist you just give yourself fully to the
multitasking you have to do as if um you're a soccer player who has to
multitask because on the field they have to pay attention to so much
um so I don't know if this look at your resistance that's what I did and that's what I found and letting go of my
resistance thank you behind you
good morning Gill good morning everyone I was wondering if you could speak to the process of feeling like you're
really riding the wave of somebody and these beautiful factors of Awakening and I always kind of think of in my practice
like I'm surfing the wave and then I slipped and life happens and I get
caught in the wake and just beat up by The Reef is this a common occurrence for other
people's practice it ain't quite bother so you have somebody you're caught the wave of samadhi and then what comes
along uh maybe their mind or life and then you trip or hit something and then you
caught up in the wave and tumbled up are you tumbling at all yeah well you just get it back on the
surfboard and paddle out yeah okay so this is very common occurrence for everybody else
that's the what else can you do that's it well there's one more something you can do that's important is
uh you know you tumble in life comes over you tumble in and you lose your practice or your somebody your
mindfulness and certainly start again start again but what you can also do which is important is to spend some time
reflecting what happened and learn from that and maybe there's
things you need to learn maybe there's reasons why you keep tumbling maybe it's not the maybe it turns out the waves are
kind of you know mild it's just that you're I'm not saying it's your situation but but uh maybe
um some you know someone that keeps falling off their surfboard because not because of the Waves because they're
trying to show off and to the people on the beach and after they said well why do I keep
falling off what's going on oh I'm not paying attention to the waves I'm paying
attention to the beautiful people on the beach and um and so then we learn okay I have to stop paying attention to people on
the beach so so you also want to learn so the more you get tumbled around by
life the more useful is a step back and spend some time reflecting on it and see what happened there and what kind of
changes what what is your contribution to that then and what kind of Behavioral changes are needed
and if someone's always falling off their surfboard you know into the waves maybe that maybe
what they need is a bigger surfboard or maybe they should stop surfing
the last one please um I find you know when things are going
easy it's it comes natural to be mindful for me but when I'm surrounded by let's talk
about like a political figure where there's hate Division and all this stuff
coming at me or I see it written on Facebook or something it's very hard for me to stay mindful I
just I don't know how to approach it I want to you know put some positive stuff out there but then you're attacked and I
don't want to withdraw from this kind of hate so I so there's many things contribute
to that but get based on The Talk today I'd like to say that it's because one
reason why you get swept up in that is because you lack confidence in something
healthy if you you lack confidence in something healthy if you had confidence in Love no matter
what like love it all there always has to be love if there's not love it's not worth
it and when there's all this hate and anger and fear of making that comes from politicians or when they're doing crazy
making things um uh if you have confidence that love should always be in everything
then if you have confidence in that then as you find yourself drifting off into
being angry you're upset you wait a minute hold it I really believe in love that's really
what's helpful or I really believe in peace I really believe in non-reactivity
that's really where I want to be centered come with me I don't want to live in a world where I'm going to be
triggered and lose my my commitment to love or lose my commitment to peace or to non-reactivity
so I would encourage you that what needs to happen is to figure is to
reflect on the deepest values you have and find a way to have more confidence in them
so that when these things come to you you're ready
because you're you you're established in that in your confidence wow thank you
okay one more but then we'll stop so you started out by saying when you go
into areas where you feel anger and negativity to kind of say is that the
best option or is that the best so so what do you do uh if you're
you're going in a direction of anger and all these feelings come up like maybe it's a relationship with
somebody and um that you know they're powerful feelings
you're absolutely so that's a whole and I don't want to suppress them I mean it's not like of
somebody who cut me off type of thing yeah yeah so I think a huge part of
mindfulness practice is in fact learning how to be present for difficult emotions and how to be present to them without
further reactivity and how to make space for them without giving in to them without participating
in them or acting acting through them so if there's sometimes you see that meditation is a fantastic place where
the volcano of anger can flow but uh but you don't participate and
just allow it to flow and but be really honest to yourself just don't don't don't keep telling the
stories of why you're angry don't review the stories just be present oh this is
anger this is a volcano of energy this is what's happening this is what's
happening this is what's happening let's feel it in the body this is what's happening let me open in the body and
feel all this what's going on this is what's happening and and you know and so
we start seeing more and more clearly what is happening as we're angry and we're making space for it as we're angry
but in this posture of meditation it's we're safe we're not going to lash out at someone
we're not going to say something that we later regret we're not going to hit someone because you're not supposed to
move when you meditate and uh and uh and then as we do this and
practice with this and be present for it we start understanding more and more deeply what's going on and what are the
inner triggers for us for this and not a few people for example with anger find out that the anger is really
a surface phenomena symptom of something deeper and so then to be able to sit
present and mindful and look and watch and observe our anger and start seeing
in the cracks of it that actually I feel really hurt or I feel really sad
that's more primary and once we realize the sadness and the hurt then it's a
whole different game and then that needs our attention too and and the fact that we're angry begins
to recede because it's not that important compared to something much more important so uh mindfulness of emotions is a huge
part of what we do in this practice here and and learning the instructions of it learning how to be with it is uh is one
of the great gifts of this practice and it's really essential because of
course of course in this life that we live we'll have all kinds of difficult emotions and um and so the kind of
confidence and vitality that I talked about today uh the five faculties
that confidence gets in faith gets really strong when we learned how to be
mindful and through these difficult mind States difficult states of mind we can have and we learn we've learned oh I
don't have to give into it I can allow for it I can find a way through to the other side
wow this is fantastic of course I'll choose to be mindful rather than go along with the anger or
whatever it might be does it make enough sense great thank you
okay so thank you all and so we have this potluck you're all welcome to come and since we do have a
potluck and it'll take a few minutes for some people to set up maybe the set of people can go go now and those of you
who want to stay if you want to stay in here and just turn to one or two people near you and say hello because just to
welcome them and