so good morning everyone or good day
and it's raining here which is quite lovely I'm very fond of the
rain though I think I'm fond of all the weather maybe because being in the
weather means being outdoors and it's just a
wonderful connection to uh feel the world through the outdoor atmosphere
air weather
ground I was happy coming down here today
so becoming wise about thinking is not only useful for
ourselves it's also useful for this world of ours and I'll talk more about
that later today but but one way of becoming wise about thinking is to have a clear sense
of the source of thinking where inside of us does
thinking begin what triggers it what energizes it what influences its
mood and and qual characteristics of the thinking that we
do before we start thinking before there's a thought
what is the environment in which thinking will occur what's the emotional state we have what are the beliefs we
have what are the fears or desires which are motivating or influencing how we
think and are we thinking and from where are we thinking from where do thoughts
arise many people if you say it's comment that someone seems stuck in
their thoughts they might point to their head they're all up in their head meaning they're just thinking a lot about
things and uh is in fact for you the
location for thinking in the head and might there be other locations from
which thinking might arise my teacher in Burma if you asked
him uh where thinking occurs he always would point to the
heart there are some people who would point to the belly and uh and for them thinking
arises from their relaxed belly soft peaceful kind of floating sense of
belless and it it it uh has a big impact on us where our thinking arises from so
in this meditation I want to I guide you through an exploration of
thinking and maybe that's it'll be more talking for me than usual but it's such
a phenomenally important skill and knowledge to
acquire this about thinking that it'll support all your future meditations and maybe your
life so to assume a meditation
posture with the taking your posture
is it when you already begin being mindful mindful of the sensations and
feelings of your body so that you line up the body in
such a way that the body Fe begins to feel harmonious or
aligned and you are attuned to your
body
gently taking some deeper breaths comfortably deeper
Fuller and as you exhale to relax into your
body
to relax down into your sitting bones if you're sitting
upright relax into your spine and hip
hips as you and your head all the bones that rest against a surface if you're
lying
down letting your breathing return to normal continue this process of
relaxing maybe with a notion of deep
relaxation the different parts of the body I'll point to maybe you can feel them
deeply the muscles of the face relax as you
exhale the
shoulders the rib C rib
cage and deep in your upper
torso and the belly releasing the belly to the pull of
gravity
centering yourself on your breathing breathing in an easy natural
way and if it's not that way don't be bothered by how you're
breathing instead accompany a breathing which feels strained or
constricted or just accompany it it's
okay
and then feel your way into your body feel your way to
where the location is for your thinking whether you think in words or
in images or whether you think in without words there's but there's a
cognitive knowing that maybe you feel is
wordless where is the center of cognition for you
is it in the center of the head behind the
eyes is it in the Torso or the
belly if it's in the head is in near the front of the head behind the
forehead or the back of the head if you see images do those images
appear in front of
you is there any sense of a
projector that's projecting the
images
a location for thinking may come with a sense
of pressure or
contraction feeling that this is a place where things are dense
or
tight there might be a directionality as if that location
is leaning forward or pulling
back sinking down
or ready to soar
upwards allow yourself to think if thinking wants to
happen but don't focus on the content of your thoughts see if you can
recognize the location we're thinking
occurs or if thinking occurs everywhere where's the center of
everywhere and what what Sensations come along with thinking the thinking
mind
e
independent of what you're thinking
about does your tendency to think come along with a wanting
something a general feeling not a thing but a general attitude of
wanting or an attitude of
aversion or an attitude of
fear or
confusion an attitude of
overwhelm
discouragement and if there is some attitude that is there and almost precedes your
thinking it's okay okay for now for it to be there but feel the location where that
occurs make room for it feel it know
it know the attitude more than knowing what you're
thinking
about breathe with
it
e
if you stand on your tippy toes reaching up as high as you can with
your hands into the air high up stretching yourself up and hold that for a
while your whole body will be tired
tense wobbly but then if you
relax feet firm on the ground maybe even sit down maybe even
lay down all the tension all the holding the body is no longer
needed and feeling the support of the floor something deep inside can relax
that can't relax stretching upwards on your
toes in the same way we can live live our lives and kind
of psychologically as if we're in our tippy
toes allow without changing your posture as you
exhale relax your whole body relax internally
externally as if your conscious mind
your awareness is has a chance to sit down
relax lay down deep to the deepest place of relaxation
within feeling your way into your depths to the place where things are
most peaceful and relaxed calm for
you
whatever degree of calm or relaxation that's available for
you that's calmer than you are otherwise relax and to that
place of calm or peace as if your mind can come to rest
there maybe with every exhale settling more into that place
deep inside of Peace
calm
gently breathing with the location in your
body that is calm or peaceful or at least calmer or more
peaceful you than your usual thinking mind almost as if you're going below
your usual thinking into a place that's more
intimate more [Music] safe more at ease than your thinking
mind with every
breath let
go
and from this calmer depth within you listen carefully
carefully bring a careful attention and from
here are there is there a different form of thinking that arises for
you see if it can be a thinking that you don't latch on to you don't get involved
in you just allow it to appear like
a water flowing from a
deep into the surface from a deep underwater
spring what deep thoughts are
there as you get out of the way to let them flow as they
wish
in the way that your usual thinking mind would get quiet if you were listening to
a very faint sound in the distance let the usual thinking mind
become quiet for a little bit so you can sense or listen
to some of the quietest the quietest source of thinking
within maybe not listening to the content of those
thoughts but what does it feel like what are the sensations and attitudes
and moods associated with thinking from the
the
depths
a profound
understanding is that no matter what you're
thinking thinking is not who you are really it's not who you
are who you
are is found in that within you that
awareness which is independent of your
thoughts in the way that if you're listening to someone speaking maybe listening to strangers
speak not to you but to each other you would clearly feel like you
were independent from what they're
saying
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting again on the exhale settle into the deepest place of
calm that's available to
you and from there think thoughts of good
will for the people in your life
thoughts of appreciation and
well-wishing
may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may we remember to care for for
others from the soft depths within us
[Music]
thank [Music]
you
so hello and welcome to this third talk on wise
thinking and one of the reasons why this topic of
mindfulness of thinking wise thinking is so important is that the way that
we relate to our thinking
is also related to how we it's also connected to how we relate to anything
that comes from outside of us any information ideas content and specifically what's been on
my mind lately is the way that we relate to Media the way we relate to our
screens uh everything that comes through a screen one way or the other represents
someone else's thinking someone has produced it designed it thought it
out and so in that sense we're we're constantly living in someone else's
content of their thoughts that they've created for us and in some sense maybe that was
clear as when we are reading something that someone has put their thoughts on paper but when we in uh watching screens
and videos and consuming news that we
have um you know how do we relate to it and I would like to propose it's an
unhealthy way of relating to it is how many people relate to their own
thinking where the consumers of information consumers of opinions even
if we don't like them or approve of them we take them in we react to them so
often as a society as a whole for many people their thoughts are the same way there's no sense of of um
of uh distance from their thoughts or sense of questioning their thoughts or
mindfulness of thinking what's really going on there there's a way which many people are just living in their thoughts
carried by their thoughts influenced by their thoughts uh un uh without any reflection without any awareness of how
much we're being influenced by them we have an opinion and or a bias or a um an
advertisement or a projection that we want to convey to the world and it's just second nature we don't even realize
we're doing it and uh we carry a lot of our thinking carries
ourselves uh our self-concept sometimes the way that we talk and think is kind of like an
advertisement for ourselves our desires what we want and it's strategizing we
have a whole you know marketing maybe uh Department in our mind that's trying to
figure out what we want and get so what we can learn by becoming
independent of our thinking see our thinking clearly what we can learn from thinking
learning how to think from a place of uh deep within us that has no attachment
that has no fears that the place of that's free of
stress the place that's free of wanting and not wanting the deepest
Wellspring of relaxed thinking that we can have where it's easy for us to be
independent of the content of what's being thought so we can be
independent of the unusually odd things that we might be thinking through the day and a few of us have odd things we
think but we don't think about that because we're living in it just so obvious and
um uh unhealthy things we don't think they're unhealthy because it's just second nature that we should be upset
with ourselves or feel shame about ourselves and have thought like that or that it's second nature to want to get
what we want um to have what we we want and so there's a lot of strategies about
you know of course I should think about and try to figure out how to get what I want because uh that's just natural
that's how it should be so we're not independent and so to learn how to step
back and be independent of our own thoughts so that when we do think we can
think more wisely more creatively more objectively more
connected to the deepest Wellsprings of compassion and care and
kindness if we learn to do it with ourselves and then we can apply that to
Media apply that to how we are we don't become consumers of news consumers of
what's on our screens but we become um in a sense we become independent of
it where we have a sense that we're not consumers taking things in we're more
The Producers we certainly hear and see what's being presented in the world and
what comes around us but we're rooted in deeper place where we're the producer we're the we're the we're in a deep
place of creativity and responsivity that can be free of
attachments free of fear free of
confusion so so the application of mindfulness of thinking into daily life
is huge for our society there are people who are uh spending billions of dollars to try to
take your attention hostage or to hijack it to keep it for themselves and keep
you engaged and and uh and engage from that um surface mind or some from the
mind of desires the mind of fear the mind of
aversion and keep that activated as we engage in this world out
there so to discover the source of
thinking with inside of us and there are two general sources there's that place
where we think location or attitude that with which we're
thinking that comes along with attachment of one form or other the
attachment to self very strong sense of Me Myself and mine in it my
needs my need to prove myself my need to get what I want my need to be safe of
course we should be safe but if we're caught up in the need for that then we
are thinking from a kind of I call it kind of a surface way of thinking it's
doesn't have access to the depths of who we are and so to um so that's one source
the source of thinking that I often point to my head for this uh swirling
idea of Concepts ideas things that come from how we put words together into
language and grammar and that build things all the way until they build to Wars between
people the Second Source of thinking is a thinking that arises out of being
deeply relaxed deeply at ease with
ourselves this is the source of creativity if we're tense it's very hard
to be creative in creativity has to do with a holistic way of thinking a thinking that
somehow we're relaxed enough nothing is constricted nothing is narrowed down
that happens when we have any kind of tension or attention or attachment thinking that occurs when we're deeply
relaxed and open so that our senses are are are open and Avail available or
sensing to uh all the different capacities that we are open to a broad range in a relaxed
subtle way and I associate that with the belly and if not the belly then I
associate it with a wonderful feeling of warmth and and Delight in the chest
where thinking is just a pleasure to do and uh because of the creativity The
Joy the delight and just being alive and letting this Wellspring uh font of of um flow of you
know Pleasant creative uh unattached thoughts thoughts that are not in under
the influence of anger aversion reg not
influence of regrets and shame and despair
and thinking which is not under the influence of our desires and our wants
our conceits thinking which is not under the influence of being confused or or lost
in our life there's so many ways things that influence our thinking as we learn to be mindful of
thinking in a sense to step back and say oh that's I'm thinking
now clearly consciously with a Act of
awareness where we find ourselves independent of our thinking where the knowing that we're
thinking maybe it's a kind of a thought but it can be a thought that comes from that deep
Source oh boy am I thinking a lot now the
control tower is going wild people in the control tower are having a party and
they're not watching the planes landing there's going to be an accident
soon but to to have this thinking from the depths within or from the peace
within that recognizes the other place of thinking
non-judgmentally but non-judgmental does not mean without evaluation without
assessment without understanding oh that is not a useful place to be
thinking to lose myself in this kind of surface mind that's caught up in
attachment I that's not useful to be able to see that and
evaluate that as wisdom the wise thinking to judge it means to say oh
what a terrible person I am or how terrible is what a bad thing that surface thinking
is chances are that kind of thinking where we're putting a value like that on
it that's just more of the surface thinking the thinking from the
depths can understand but has no
criticism and no attachment to anything that it sees it's it's phenomenal to
switch operating systems from the surface mind that's one
way the other is being driven by Something That We're attached to to the Deep Mind the deep
thinking which is free of of of uh any
kind of attachment or for many for or much Freer from
attachment so I hope that this uh contrast of this idea of finding the
location The Source from which you're thinking gives you access to a deeper
understanding of your thinking and how to be mindful of it and how to kind of step away and be independent of it and
this idea of then relaxing into the depth of your body and really being at
ease so that the creative thinking the depth thinking thinking from the depths
which is so holistic can animate your life and help you with this task of
becoming independent of your thoughts and that's only a step away of
learning how to be independent of the news that you're reading the opinions that you're
hearing so you can be wise about what you're hearing what you're reading what
you're seeing so thank
you very much and we'll continue
tomorrow