so hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour so um before we begin uh
couple of announcements one is that um as
the year 2023 uh comes to a close and as the New
Year 2024 will start pretty soon um uh there will be a transition so I will
step back um from uh leading the Fridays
um I'll only be leading Mondays and Wednesdays so so um I'll be stepping
back from Fridays and bruny Dava is going to step in and um each Friday's uh
happy hour so delighted to welcome bruny and please welcome her when you see her
this Friday on a couple days and she'll be going forward oh um Carly asked who's
the third party this being is being sent to it's just YouTube we all always do
this but this is the new version of Zoom so it's asking you to accept it so Zoom
has changed nothing has changed about happy hour it's just being sent to it's being streamed online on um YouTube so
no reason to to uh yeah just zoom change change so no worries
um so okay so with that I then one more
announcement is that um uh I will be away I'll be um the East
Coast teaching for the next few weeks so I will be um out for a while so you'll
be great hands with with a wonderful group of uh uh substitute teachers so so
with that now is transition to practicing together so as the year is coming to a close um
this is a good time for reflection um especially reflection around kindness
um I had a conversation with a friend the other day and um a good Dharma
friend and we were reflecting on know as you go to bed every night to to perhaps
consider contemplate whatever your state of mind
is whatever your state of heart is if if I didn't wake up tomorrow morning if I
didn't wake up tomorrow morning um and the theme relates to rebirth death and
rebirth because in some ways 20 23 the year the old year is dying the new year
is is being given birth to um so along the same lines if
if whatever my state of mind is whether I'm um filled with meta and kindness for
others myself the world whether there's brightness in my heart and mind or
whether there's anger resentment what is this the state of
mind that I wanted to if if I didn't wake up tomorrow is this is this what I
want to be what I remember what I go to bed with there's a sense of is this how I want to be closing out uh this phase
with so and it's never too late we always look forward to the new the next
year you know New Year's resolutions next year next year but no let's look at the endings let's look at right here
right now uh cultivating our states of mind and heart for for kindness and uh
yeah compassion so that's a reflection I wanted to share so let's uh let's
transition and let's uh start meditating together let's start meditating so
arriving in our chair arriving in our seat arriving in our sit
bones arriving allowing ourselves to sett In This
Moment and ask what is my state of mind right now what is state of my body state
of my mind state of my
heart and trusting that you have a choice we all have a
choice how do I want to turn how do I want to Incline my mind In This Moment
how do I want to be in this moment maybe if there's suffering in
this mind in this body maybe I want to have more kindness in this
moment with each breath breathing in kindness breathing out
kindness and if you're having a challenging time for whatever reason maybe the body maybe
emotions can you breathe in a little more kindness to this body In This Moment Like a soothing
celf
and if there's any agitation or disturbance anxiety sadness anything
that's that needs more care can you breathe
in more kindness more care
around it through it with all the patience in your
heart
and we greet our minds our hearts our bodies with
friendliness with every
breath
and now can we radiate out this kindness with every
breath bringing to mind to Your Heart a
friend or benefactor or someone for whom
kindness care Rises with
ease with every out breath radiating your kindness towards this
being this child this
pet
letting your heart be subtly subtly uplifted just a little
brighter through this act of generosity with your kindness giving them a gift of your
kindness your
goodwi
and now for the third part of this practice session after
having shared sh our own Goodwill with ourselves shared it with someone else
others now let's imagine ourselves completely open to
receiving a gift the same way that when we were children
perhaps we're open to receiving gifts from from
Santa our hearts were opened we didn't say no we don't want gifts of kindness generosity we received gifts we accepted
them the same innocence of accepting
generosity let yourself receive receive the generosity of
Goodwill could be either from your friend your benefactor this child or pet you're
imagining or it could be from an archetype from Buddha from
[Music] quen from a being of light from the
universe this gift being the gift of Goodwill just let yourself feel
nourished by it this bright light of Goodwill and
kindness given to you opening your heart your whole body to bask in it
just nothing you have to do to earn or deserve it it's here it's
provided for you let yourself trust
it for just this minute at
least if it's possible it's always
possible
and whatever state of mind you have right [Music] now what is the state of mind is this is
this the state of mind you would wish to [Music] have is if you went to bed and did not
wake
up can you invite more kindness brightness receive generosity of Good
Will towards yourself share it with others we have a choice to how we
conduct our mind our inner
thoughts our inner life how we live
it for the last minute or two of this practice let
yourself relax inviting in breathing in
kindness breathing out kindness
receiving and sharing with
the
may we cultivate awareness mindfulness of our inner
life may we cultivate goodness kindness
compassion internally and externally may all beings everywhere be
happy may all beings everywhere be [Music]
free everyone ah Sun an interesting practice
right when we connect awareness mindfulness of our state of mind right now what do we want this state of mind
to be right now especially if we raise the stakes and think oh is this the last
if if this were my last moment if I went to bed like this and didn't never woke up is this the state of mind I want to
have and then how how do I do I let go do I forgive do I bring in more kindness
what what's the wise action so so with
that i' uh like to invite us if you would like to um explore this theme how
it it lands for you um and exploring from your own
experience you can explore this meditation you can talk about this meditation how this meditation was for you or how this theme impacts you
um again you're speaking from your own experience uh sharing one nugget
allowing the next person to share a nugget and then the next person and and
you're asked to not comment on each other's experiences and it's okay to share what you're exploring as long as
it's within this context of the practice and and um
yeah and uh holding each other with kindness if it's If This Were the last
time you saw each other um in this way how do you want to be remembered how do
you want to be how do you want to leave what gift do you want to impart what
gift of kindness um do you want to impart on people um Maya Angelo has famously said
people are not going to remember people will not remember what you said but they will remember how you made them feel I'm
paraphrasing but it's essentially that so how how are you going to leave people
with kindness touch them with kindness and and your Goodwill in the small
groups so with that I'm going to create the uh the small groups the breakout
rooms and you are invited to um speak in Reverse alphabetical order um be kind be
generous yeah be kind be generous that's all and take care of each each other
here we go welcome back
everyone so um have a few minutes for Reflections um comments questions for uh
yeah how this practice might have been or anything that came up in the uh
exploration in the small groups the floor is yours oh and you can also put um your Reflections in chat if you type
them to me they'll be private I won't read your name and if you type them to everyone I
will read your name and you can also raise your hand just like
Mima thank you Nikki um what I've noticed in this practice kind of brought
more things closer for me to be able to see is I noticed the kindness acts like
gestures towards myself like um I mentioned in um in the group that um I
have a walking buddy and every morning she hugs me when I see her like I'm just and I'm so much more receptive to these
kind gestures and I could feel like my heart light up and it radiates throughout my body um I noticed um I had
double vision and my son went to get my hand to help me um and it I felt his
tenderness like so the I don't know I can't even it just like touch me and
he's a grown man but I did tell him I said I notice your tenderness like you're so gentle with me and I had not
noticed it before so I feel like it's made me this practice has made me much more receptive to
kindness and also much more aware when it isn't there yeah so it's um it's benefited me
tremendously and made me much more aware when it is
there thank you for letting me share that thank you Mima for sharing this
this is a sensitivity training yeah and isn't that
wonderful for us to become more sensitive as human beings it's just
oh yeah and and of course it makes us um as it makes us more sensitive it's also
strength because then someone might think oh then things hurt some more well
yes and then and then at the same time there is do it's a choice do we want to
be a rock going through life not feeling anything like that song I am a rock I'm
an island I don't feel anything right I don't feel no pain right we can be an
island we can be a rock not touching anyone not being touched and yet we can become more sensitive feeling when
people are touching us or touched by us and we get touched by them this sensitivity this tend and it's beautiful
so beautiful ah thank you thanks for sharing this Mima
yeah Maran yeah I came in late sorry about
that then I lost my internet so it if you had to continually accept me into
the room I apologize no no it was all good in fact I had to um I had some
problems with and I mentioned at the beginning but I'll share it again there were some issues at the beginning so I
had to restart Zoom a couple of times and people were thrown off so that that people are affected so thanks for your
patience and here you are thanks for making it Maran and it was it was uh hearing that
just for Guan yen to give meta for one minute one possible minute
was was very very powerful um I thought and big problems can I don't know be
helped by that for one minute and who knows what a what that Catalyst could be
a one minute of meal like that so thank you for that very much ah thank you Maran thanks so much
for sharing your experience and how powerful that um invitation actually
implementing that invitation was for you and and um it's it's amazing right
because sometimes if we think of this practice as oh it's hard I can't do this and then we think oh I can do this for
just one minute or just one I can or just 5 seconds I can do this for just one second I can let this love in I can
accept love for one second and it's okay I'm going to shut down in one second no problem but in just one second I'm going
to open up and let it in and and that can make a huge difference because we can yes we can um and that one second
will become two seconds and a minute and then five minutes an hour and then that's who we become more and more and
more thanks Maria thanks for highlighting that
yeah yes s
please hello and thank you so much for this practice um there was this beautiful reflection in our
group uh about this practice tonight
uh specifically but also in general this a space uh that has been created uh
through time and is allowing for this possibility of openness of meta kindness
and um and it was a very beautiful reflection I felt like as you were
talking about reflecting um at the end of the year uh
I feel like this can be connected to that and just the appreciation of having this possibility to sit here and hear
your teachings and these beautiful teachings which I'm still trying to understand what happens
but something happens and and you can see it throughout the day and since last
time for example i' I've been singing this it's a beautiful day in this
neighborhood and it's just and I see what's happening in the neighborhood it's really H something's happening in
me and and I it comes out and and it's just uh unbelievable sometimes so so
thank you thanks for this space I I really appreciate it ah thank you so much Sara John for
being part of the space and being a a member of the sa um showing up and
supporting others and supporting yourself with this practice and yes things happen and it's a beautiful day
in the neighborhood right it's just it can be a beautiful day in the neighborhood outside and inside and when
we see beauty when we we get to see more and more and more Beauty um in the world and we
become beautiful our minds become beautiful our neighborhoods become beautiful so on that beautiful note um
yeah I want to express my appreciation for our happy hour and this space this
neighborhood that we are co-creating together it's not just me um it's not
just the it's not just Liz and bruny who will be joining us so I'm going to announce again so for those who um uh
maybe came in late so after 3 and a half years of teaching Mondays Wednesdays and
Fridays I'm going to step back and um on Fridays I'll still be teaching Mondays
and Wednesdays and bruny davia who's who's uh been one of the substitute teachers she is going to be uh serving
holding Fridays moving forward so that happy ARA can continue to be five days
days a week and of course Liz is continuing to hold it um Tuesdays and
Thursdays so so that was the announcement and the other announcement was that I'm going to be on the East
Coast teaching traveling so I'm away for uh couple of weeks to three weeks and
then back and then away again so I'll announce it but you're in great hand in
the next few weeks with wonderful substitute teachers so with that announcement out of the way I want to
express my appreci for The Saga it's we we co-create this space together all of
us it's not just the teachers it's all of you coming and showing up and practicing and and um supporting each
other so much community group wisdom we teach each other we teach each other we
deepend each other's practice we teach each other so thank you all thank you for being this beautiful happy aranga
and spreading your love may we all wake up may we shine our light in the world
um may we all be happy may we all be
[Music]
free thanks everyone