so good morning everyone and have a good day good evening Wherever You Are
and uh welcome then this uh Fourth of July Independence
Day I wonder if we could almost uh
claim it as a Buddhist holiday for a different uh definition of independence or liberation
and so here we sit on the path of liberation
and in the teachings of the Buddha uh the idea is to
see in our direct experience perceive in our direct experience
the Dharma so that we become independent in the Dharma we don't have to depend on
anyone else to tell us what the Dharma is because we've really seen it for ourselves
so uh for today what I'd like to emphasize
is and maybe building on the idea of aspiration and what I'm going to teach
offer you for the meditation maybe can be aspirational so you don't get caught
up in the idea of success or doing it right or something and um and the idea is to
um see if you can for maybe only a few moments at a time
maybe more longer as the meditation goes along maybe you can quiet
your discursive thinking the thinking that is telling stories that's explaining things having
commentary the um the mind that's having fantasies uh
and uh reviewing things remembering things what happened remembering conversations
having conversations with people and that's why it's kind of called discursive thinking I think they're holding a discourse with yourself
and this is a higher order kind of more active agitated complex form of thinking
that kind of um can take all the
the air out of the room or if someone is really goes into a room of other people and is so loud and so assertive about
their opinions and their views there's no space for anyone else to speak and so the discursive mind fills the
space and but we have other deeper ways of
understanding of knowing and even kind of deeper more subtle more satisfying
ways of thinking and there's a lot of knowing there's a lot of understanding that can
happen if the thinking mind becomes quiet and we listen more deeply to what is
here what do we know what what is happening what are we
feeling what do we understand what deeper understandings are coming that are not coming from the same
place that discursive thinking comes from discursive thinking comes from
pressure from tension from a certain degree of attachment from anxiety from
a ambition and desires and again they fill the they fill the
room so there's no chance for anything else to happen so as we sit today meditate
that maybe um with the every exhale
maybe you can let go of your discursive thoughts it doesn't mean that letting go of all
your thinking what remains are very very simple thoughts of recognition of understanding something that doesn't
involve you thinking and reflecting and examining and wondering and
constructing and the advantage of dropping below this discursive mind is a discursive mind
it's like a puppeteer with strings all over all over and that has effects on our emotions our
body our tensions we carry it has a big input impact on us this
discursive mind that is not always so useful and to drop below that
and let that become quiet to give yourself a chance to hear and recognize
the knowing that arises the feelings the understanding that can be there the
connection to ourselves that can be there um in a kind of non
um assertive way non you know it's almost like what's there
if there's no self-preoccupation what arises without the self
trying to make something happen or figure something out so with every exhale to quiet the
thinking mind maybe you all the way to the end of the exhale where there's silence at the end of the
exhale the Stillness that the momentarily there is a Stillness of the Mind
and then to listen to sense to feel now what is there
and maybe that's a con persist into the beginning of the inhale so it's very
brief and but the more you can kind of become concentrated or settled on the breathing
the more that that begins to quiet the discursive mind
so we'll see so that's the aspiration so to assume your meditation posture
and to gently close your eyes
and to spend a little bit of time with your body maybe swaying back and forth and forward and backwards
just to kind of slowing down and finding the midpoint of upright and balanced on
the sitting bones
and to help you kind of move out of the stream of discursive thoughts
it can be helpful to take a few long slow deep breaths
maybe three quarters full so there's an intentional engagement with breathing in deeply
intentional involvement with exhaling fully
connecting to the body as you do so
feeling a more embodied connection
to the present moment
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and to continue systematically scanning through the body
and relaxing part of the power of discursive thoughts
that that drives it is comes from our tension that we hold
and you probably find if you find yourself in a lot of discursive thoughts and look around in your body
you probably find that there's places of tension either in your body or in your
brain or your mind
fuel for discursive thought distention stress
pressure contraction so relaxing the face
around the forehead and the eyes
relaxing the jaw maybe letting the teeth fall a little
bit away from each other the upper and lower teeth
and then as you exhale to soften and relax around the
shoulders
perhaps softening and relaxing in your chest in the Heart Center
and perhaps better softening in the belly
letting the belly hang forward and
down
maybe a softening of the hands and fingers
maybe a relaxing of the thighs and the legs
and then finally feeling whatever pressure or attention
there might be that's associated with thinking in the area of your brain or eyes or
Jaws or shoulders
then as you exhale to soften
gently settling into your body breathing
and feeling the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
and then to
almost like linger with the exhale
letting your thinking mind discursive thoughts quiet
with each exhale
and at the end of the exhale and peace breathing becomes quiet for even moment
feel and sense see what is there underneath the
discursive thought
what is it you can connect to and be with
understand what knowing arises
that's deeper than discursive thought
and no need to think about what that is just let it appear and disappear Let It
Come and Go whatever is there
no need to get involved in discursive thoughts and figuring it out and analyzing or judging
there isn't so much you stay close to that deeper understanding or feeling
but rather stay close to that the absence of discursive thinking
letting go with every exhale
quieting with every exhale
foreign
and then bring this meditation to a close
aspiring that whatever depth within you that you can access
aspiring for that to be for the good that is there to benefit you
it's there to benefit the world and others and the quieting of this excursive mind
may it be for the welfare and happiness of everyone self-included
by being able to listen to the deeper voices the deeper goodness
the deeper love and generosity that's within
their practice be for the welfare and happiness of all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so for this second talk on the aspiration
that comes along with compassion that the desire to
for people not to suffer people not to struggle and be in danger
be challenged and unnecessary and difficult ways
it's such a wonderful idea it's a wonderful occurrence to have this wish this aspiration
an aspiration where we're not self-preoccupied we are available to care for other
people to have care for them to have concern for them to have wishes for them
that their welfare is at least as important as our own and may it be that they are happy maybe
that they don't suffer and so this is Instinct this movement towards
compassion involves a wish a desire that precedes acting and the action part
that's the the whole topic we'll do at another time for a whole week
but before the action there's the wish the aspiration the care the
and there are times when we have that wish but it's not for us to do anything we we learn about someone far away we
read about someone in the news and we have compassion we wish them well we want them we hope that this that we
would like the suffering to go away we Aspire for it but maybe it's not our place to do
something about it it's not our opportunity but there are times when we have been
the opportunity to act and to do something and they're also this idea of acting and
and doing things for the welfare of others is also a wonderful antidote to
self-preoccupation and which is often can often be so the
word of the operating ideas self-preoccupation self-occupations really caught up in in oneself and
spinning around in self-concern and self combinations and criticisms and desires
and all that that there's so much tension there that just generates more and more of the same and to be able to
step out of that current of self-preoccupation one of the ways is to care for others to be available to be
aware of others through it be attuned to others to appreciate others and to feel
the empathy and and connection to their struggles and their suffering
and um and uh and then to Aspire that they're
suffering somehow they don't suffer they don't suffer as much so sometimes with the kind of a headlong
kind of throwing yourself into compassion doing it from sense of Duty or we should
the aspiration can be somewhat simplistic or can be limited and the
most common way to do that can be is to feel that I'm responsible and I have to
help end that suffering to help it to stop and uh and the only thing that counts is
somehow stopping it so um and sometimes we can do something for
someone say that someone is um you know is chronically hungry
and so it might be important to feed them and I don't want to say it's you know I
don't want to diminish the value of feeding people but if all we do is to feed someone
then the the condition situation by which they're always hungry is always
going to be present and this hasn't been addressed and so in some ways we kind of
perpetuate the system the conditions the psychology all whatever's going on that
is perpetuating their challenge The Compassion that simply doesn't want
to stop that particular you know what we see directly in front of us but understands that it's something deeper
is going on here there are wider conditions societal conditions there are personal conditions or psychological
things going on and to really help someone we want to be able to go underneath
and see more deeply what is really going on here and what is it to help someone
to help themselves what is it to help someone so that the conditions are there that they don't keep falling back into
the same difficulty over and over again and so um this is to understand this is to uh
to undo this is to uproot and what Buddhism specializes in is
doing this psychologically looking deep within ourselves there's definitely a time and place that's very important to understand the
wider conditions of the persons in the social conditions family conditions societal conditions and have some way
important way to address those as well so that the perpetuation of people's challenges are not just kind of repeated
because of how Society operates but the but the specialty in Buddhism
and here in meditation is this also to become aware of more deeply in oneself
and then because we understand ourselves so well maybe begin understanding other people as well to understand what is the
underlying psychological causes for the tension people carry the stresses they
hold on to they're overwhelmed that they have the emotional pain they're
experiencing and more often than not there's something that people something deeper
is operating some deeper fear some deeper attachments some deeper conceit ideas of self some deeper desires that
maybe sometimes are not healthy desires to have and so to Simply address the suffering
um without looking at the underlying conditions means the underlying conditions are
there and present to to show up again and again and again another few people are confused by how
yes the suffering has ended but then it revisits them the next day
there are people who have uh regularly move away from jobs away from people
because they find the situation is difficult some people move away from Buddhist Meditation centers or Buddhist
practice and to go find something else and for a few moment a little while the new thing whatever they find the job the
persons the practice the religion is exciting and wonderful and has a lot of problems but sooner a lot enough they
run into the same problems because they brought it with them the underlying attachments the fear the way
they're closed what they're avoiding begins to show itself and then becomes difficult
and sometimes in that difficulty the situation outside is blamed to the situation outside is supposed to fix it
for them and if it doesn't we're going to go somewhere else and so the idea of of helping people
supporting people to begin understanding Underneath more deeply what are the
underlying causes underlying psychological conditions for the suffering they have
and that of course helping people to do that it should be is a delicate thing to do we don't want to be people's you know
therapists we don't want to be kind of assuming we understand what's really
going on for them but there is a ways of being present for people and listening and being in
conversation so that we kind of we kind of discover what's going on in a deeper way with
them as a way of helping them understand asking simple questions or being just
being a very good listener an active listener and listening and reflecting back what you hear or or commenting
briefly about it just so they know you've heard it and some people when they know they've been heard understood
open up more and more and um and so we're not in maybe
addressing the surface suffering but we're helping to kind of begin uncover
deeper suffering that's there so this uncovering
this uprooting this undoing this understanding of something deeper
and and one of the things that active listening does being present for people
is that we offer to others what we can offer to ourselves in meditation that is
a listening that begins going deeper than discursive thoughts that what we actually talk about and say
might be the tip of an iceberg or something really deeper that's going on and so if someone's talking about some
challenge they have in their life and and they're simply saying sounds
like that's really hard um that's now points into something deeper and there's opportunity then for
people too because yeah it is hard I'm afraid or I'm troubled or I'm discouraged
and and then that is beginning to touch something that's deeper and sometimes I've seen over and over
again that we don't necessarily have to help people and solve problems for
people but sometimes it just helps people to be seen and to be known in
this deeper way so if we fix people's surface suffering and problems then they don't get seen
if we oh just you do this and that and this and then you'll be fine and or come with me and we'll just go
out and have a you know you know an exciting time at the movies or
something and it's more of a distraction than trying to deal with the suffering there might be relief
but there's not release there's not freedom and this deeper level of understanding
of of uncovering um is a um and for people to be seen
understood recognize listened to in this deeper way that itself is the medicine that itself is a phenomenal support for
softenings lessening overcoming the suffering people have
so this um you know the aspiration to understand to uncover to support people
to um to undo or uproot what's going on
much more deeper that's a movement of that's an aspiration of of compassion
that maybe has more lasting value than simply
uh in some surface way alleviating the
suffering that someone has especially if alleviating it it just means it's temporary and it'll come back
the next day it'll come back over and over again until something deeper happens
so not a few people we I think the in this world have this recurrent
theme a particular kind of distress anxiety frustration anger
that keeps reoccurring and so if we meet them with our
Compassion maybe is to hold whatever the surface is with a certain kind of equanimity acceptance and non-reactivity
so and listen deeply support them so that see what else is going on here
what's going on more deeply so the aspiration the compassion and
aspiration is a concern not just with a surface suffering but the deeper causes and
conditions so that we're not just feeding people who are helping people to
grow their own food you know as a metaphor
so um thank you and thank you for uh being
here on the fourth of July I wish you all here in the United States
a relaxing and happy and stress-free day
and um I'm gonna go home now and go out with a hike in the mountains with my wife for
this morning which seems like the perfect thing for me to do so thank you