good evening seems to me that the volume can be just
a tiny bit higher I'm like having to strain my voice just a little bit there we go thank you
nice to be here with you all to practice together
so I feel like I just want to keep on
sitting so some of you know that um when you go
on Retreat especially on the long Retreats Retreats that are like a month or longer
but also in the shorter retreats that it's not uncommon for there to be
like a bowl or something that uh participants can write down a question
and put in the bowl and then the teachers kind of go through and
you know organize the questions and we'll answer some of them some of them they don't answer because they feel like
oh that's not quite related to what we're talking about here but they'll answer them just in the hole in general
so everybody can hear the question hear the answer
it was kind of interesting is that sometimes people participants are writing questions these really you know
complicated philosophical questions
okay maybe this is what they're thinking about maybe this is what their Retreat is about
but as teachers we tend to not want to answer them well some teachers do they want to
because the point is to practice not to think our way to
some greater unders greater I don't I wanted to say greater understanding but
it's not that when we're on Retreat the emphasis is not on
education smart on just being with our direct experience
with what's actually happening whether our mind is like all over the
place or whether we're starting to feel settled or whether we're just going to really dislike that person that sits
next to us because they're doing whatever it is that they're doing you know whatever our experience is the
practice is to be with it and in the sum in the same way sometimes
uh many of you know that uh Gill and I we teach us who to study class and sometimes uh people are saying oh wait
so if this is true then wouldn't it feel like that and I I don't want it to feel
like that for example some of these insights like
to impermanence the sutas are filled with this and then like a really deep Insight not
just a thought but like a experiential knowing that things change
I mean we all know this on an intellectual level but there's a way in which we can know it in a deeper
experiential way and then some people might say well if this is true that everything is
inconstant in permanence then impermanent then wouldn't it seem like
things are chaotic or uncomfortable or something
like this or same with the if there's no self then how does that work wouldn't
that that seems scary and I don't want to have a not have itself
so there's two different ideas are that one of these two examples that I'm
giving are pointing to how sometimes we might think that practice is just about
gaining the right knowledge understanding things correctly where in fact really it's being pointed
to our experience what's actually happening but sometimes it's not so clear the
difference certainly before when I before I started meditation practice if you had said to
me well it's not what you're thinking about but it's what you're experiencing that would have thought yeah okay
whatever but it's not until you have a meditation practice I think that you start to
really understand the difference between direct experience
and thinking about something in fact I would say such a big part of
practice is making this distinction even though it may not be apparent or obvious
I would say this can be transformative if we can consistently reliably make this
difference is what are my ideas about something versus what is
it feel like is it a pressure is it a stubbing is it a tightness is an
openness is it uh tingly is it
seems like it's flowing or does it feel like it's stuck that's like I'm using really different
language to describe kind of experience right than some intellectual understanding
and so maybe I'll also add here that often when
we are upset or troubled it's we're not necessarily upset or
troubled about the experience about it being tingly and spacious or constricted and maybe there's a stabbing Sensation
that taller but uncomfortable but tolerable really when we're uncomfortable it's our
thoughts that are about the experience oh because I'm having that stabbing
experience in my knee it means that I won't be able to sit in
a on the floor anymore in a cross-legged position I'll just sit in the chair and that's kind of a bummer people
will wonder what happened to me I used to sit on the floor and I have to sit in the chair and I'll have to explain and I
don't know why we make all these stories
so often the the um the idea about something kind of like
it's like a label that we can like slap onto our experience and then the label
doesn't change it's just a label it's a word pain our experience might be all over the
place changing and being moving and morphing and going away and coming back
but we're having a relationship with the label not with what's actually happening
this is where a lot of our difficulties and our life stem from
of course we do this I want to say we are socialized educated to think
about you know when to Value ever thoughts and we have plenty of experience of the
way that we think about things helps us to solve problems helps us to plan helps
us to communicate so that we can put the plans into place so we can see where there's this real
value in thinking it's a radical shift to come to this
practice and to say even though I've been rewarded you know either when my uh
career or my education for what I'm thinking to say well actually it's a little bit
different here and I'd like to point out a little bit
how that Buddha points to this to this importance of actually just tuning into the experience
as best you can right as best you can I am not saying that thoughts are not
important I'm not saying that thoughts don't have a value and I'm not saying that you should never have thoughts when
you're meditating I'll get to kind of like the real thoughts have but before I get there I
want to talk about the value of just the direct experience so in one of these suit does the Buddha
he categorized some of the others not he categorized all spiritual leaders in his
time somebody had a question about spiritual leaders and he said well
there's different types and he said well there are some that are
relying on their sacred texts the oral transmitters at that time right so that were
um that brahmins who had the dominant religion at the time of the Buddha they
memorized all those texts and there was that was the role of the priest to do a lot of this memorization
so there were those who had just memorized who knew the text then there were those that had just a
lot of faith that they believed in maybe they don't know the text but they have this feeling of just faith maybe a
little bit of devotion it might be the words of a particular teacher it might be a God but there was a just a belief a
faith there was a third type that we're using reasoning and logic and maybe would be
more like a philosophy or maybe even a lot of us certainly me too I do a lot of
you know well wait if this means that and that should mean that and so let's uh one so one two that's a
third and then the fourth are those who rely on their experience
so teachers that are relying on these four different ways that the Buddha talked about less than and then he put
himself in one of these categories and he says
there are some mendicants you know some men against practitioners
or teachers I would say there are some mendicants who having directly known the
Dharma for themselves having reached Perfection and
consummation of direct knowledge Here and Now teach the fundamentals of this spiritual
life I am one of those mendicants
so he's highlighting that his teachings come from his experience
and not only does he highlight like the importance maybe of having direct
experience because that's how he had it but he goes on others to criticize other
people who seem to have like this Blind Faith and another suta there's a a group of a
whole bunch of brahman's come to meet the Buddha it says long
suit that kind of like sits well why they even came to meet him but they come to meet him in their evident discussion
and there's this young Brahman uh who keeps on interrupting interrupting the
conversation and the Buddha says you know these are
you're interesting me but you're also interrupting your senior Elders in your community so you're being rude
and the senior Elder say don't say that to him he's actually quite smart and competent even though he's very young
so then the Buddha turns to him and says something along the lines well do you
have a question and this young Robin says well we know
the truth because we believe in our scriptures
and that have been passed down for generations and they are true and everything else is not true
well has anybody actually seen what these are in these scriptures does anybody
actually directly know what are in these scriptures on this from this young Brahman says no
and the Buddha says okay that's fine well do you know anybody that knows
somebody that knows these teachings have this direct experience
no the Brahman replies and then the Buddha said well isn't this
kind of like blind people leading other blind people who haven't seen for themselves telling
other people what its practice is about what the spiritual life is about
some harsh words but again the Buddha is pointing to that
the are the importance of seeing and knowing for ourselves
and he doesn't put forth some physical metaphysical views right he's not saying that um
let me back up and I'll say that he's not uh he has this idea that people who have
views and are just putting it forth as okay this is the truth
he says well there's a different ways in which people do this
they have the these ideas about what happens after death
what is the nature of the universe is it infinite
or not and says it's impossible to know these answers so these are can just be views
and then I'd like this expression he says that um these views are for those
who do not know and see so if you don't have direct experience in other things then you tend to be more in your head
and be thinking about these things that really don't have answers
and he's highlighting that this does not bring you to Greater Freedom this doesn't bring you to Greater ease trying
to figure out the answer to some of these things so he says these speculative views are a
Thicket of use a Wilderness of views a contortion of use a vesselation of use a
Fetter of views I don't know exactly what all these words mean like a contortion of views
but it sounds like wow this is complicated right and it's not that some
has spacious and easeful and he continues by saying well these
views are beset by suffering vexation Despair and by fever
if you're trying to find the answers for some of these things that don't have answers
it's troubling to want something that can't have but
also to feel like your happiness depends on this or your future happiness depends
on this and the Buddha goes on and he said so having these views does not lead to disenchantment
dispassion cessation peace direct knowledge and Awakening
so it's not the way towards Awakening
so what is what is part of the way
I appreciate very much that the it occurs to me as I'm talking here I'm
giving like all these ideas and I'm talking and I'm saying well don't be concerned about ideas but here's a lot
of them so there's a little irony here and kind of what I'm saying here
but I'm trying to like pull from the suit does some like quotes or what the Buddha is saying to support this idea
of it's really about our direct experience as opposed to our thoughts
our views our beliefs and making that distinction such an integral part of
practice so here's something else that the Buddha
says he describes the Dharma that is the teachings or we might even understand
the dharmas the way things are
saying that the drama is directly visible immediate
inviting one to come and see applicable and to be personally experienced
the Dharma is directly visible so something that
you can come in contact with you can see
it's not some complicated philosophical idea
and I would even say you don't have to go on super long Retreats and meditate forever
it's directly visible and immediate not something that you have to like figure out later
and the Dharma can just be knowing what the experience is right now
as opposed to our ideas about it so being able to like tease apart their experience from our reaction to it
it's also saying that the Dharma is inviting one to come and see
he's not inviting one to go and see go you know another time another place
you'll figure it out it's actually pointing to no no no whatever the experience is right now
whatever it is Pleasant unpleasant neutral
we can get in contact with it and see the Dharma the way things are
and we can start to see like oh these things are changing
of course they are our experiences are really changing and the quieter the mind gets the more that we can see the change
or we can see oh yeah actually this experience is not a source of lasting happiness
might be a little bit of pleasurable but not a source of lasting happiness so seeing the Dharma just in our
experience whatever the experience is and then the last thing here is saying
it's to be personally experienced by the wise so not to philosophize about
but to experience and I appreciate that he's saying by the wise so here wisdom
is getting defined by somebody who's having direct experience who's tuning
into what's ever happening right now
so I just said that you don't have to sit long Retreats necessarily sitting
meditating regularly certainly helpful sometimes I talk about long Retreats I
like to do long retreat practice but I don't want to give the impression that that's the only way to go forward or
something like that because that's a trap to think like well okay as soon as I go on a long retreat
which we'll have to wait until my life situation changes then I'll be able to have some real insights you don't have
to wait Buddha he's saying you know he's inviting us to come and see ehipasico
come and see but he's also saying well it's not the easiest to see if it were
then everybody would see the drama and become enlightened and we'd all live happily ever after something like that
he's saying the Dharma is profound hard to see
peaceful and Sublime unattainable by mere reasoning
subtle and to be experienced by the wise
so this is part of why we meditate is because it's subtle
hard to see because we're so often thinking that what we
want is like out there it's like outside of our experience either with our thinking or just getting
focused on the next moment what's going to happen next or lost in fantasy or memory or
something like this but
I like this that he's saying that it's peaceful and Sublime
so tuning in and being with what's actually happening without
adding these big commentaries on top just allowing whatever the experience is
to be there that act of allowing creates some of
this peacefulness and the sublime is the the not wanting things to be different
so part of the reason why that Buddha is pointing to direct experiences because
Awakening Liberation enlightenment
greater peace greater freedom is associated with direct experience
rather than just thoughts or views or beliefs or ideas
and one of the ways is having insight
I want to make a distinction between insights and thoughts and beliefs and Views so insights might be something
that happens with our mental capacity but
for me that one way that I understand the insights differently is that we all know that people die we
all know that pets die we like you ask anybody they won't know this
it's not until somebody you love dies that you really understand it right
there's like a different understanding that comes from the experience
that's what's kind of pointing towards Insight Is this different type of knowing
that goes beyond just maybe intellectual understanding it's like knowing in your
bones or blood or something like this
and then I'll add one other thing about Insight in the context in which we talk about it here
and insight is this knowing experiential knowing that also reduces
suffering so there's
this recognition of something that with that recognition that really
deep knowing there's a letting go of something
and there's some greater ease and peace it might not even be immediately clear
what is let go of at that time but this is part of what Insight is
and the Buddha he described before he was awakened how this had an impact on
him uh said that
he attained liberation by understanding like having insight
into the rising and passing away of experiences seeing how experiences are
going coming and going and rising and passing away
but not only that there's this little expression saying their gratification their danger they
escape so gratification is sometimes our experiences that our desires are
fulfilled and we feel like okay I don't I'm not Desiring anymore I don't have that sense
of lack I that's I feel certain ease here it's true we have pleasant
experiences and our desires get fulfilled of course they do
so to recognize that that's kind of like the gratification to recognize of course they do
they create the conditions for pleasure and joy love all kinds of beautiful things
and it's a little bit of the dangers that it's sooner or later this
gratification is going to end what is Pleasant may just become neutral
feeling eating your favorite ice cream at the fast at the beginning is great and then
it just becomes you know you're a little bit The Habit like okay I better finish what's in the bowl it's not so great
anymore and then if you had to eat it even more it starts to become uncomfortable right unpleasant
so this dangerous sooner or later this gratification part the pleasure part starts to end
and then to the extent that we were attached to that pleasure like oh okay I
finally got my desires fulfilled now I can be happy I'll be happy as long as this stays
the tighter we're holding on the more difficulties we're going to
have when those things change when they go away of course sometimes we hold on and we are our sense of self gets uh
involved about it or the I'm the one who has this
and nobody else has it and I have this or something like this
but things change they rise and they pass away
so then the escape from them is to step out of this attachment and
craving to allow the experiences to come and go
and not be adding like these thoughts or ideas or views or beliefs that would get
put on top of them or labels that we're putting on top and we're no longer with our experience by
being with the label can we just step out of this habit of trying to get it touched or holding on
in some kind of way sometimes it's subtle really subtle
there's two ways we can do this one is with a sometimes with a meditation practice as the mind quiets
then some of the letting go just naturally happens to get into some of these absorptive
states there's a lot of Letting Go and it's a not a lot of agitation from the
experiences the other way is Awakening
is the Escape right there's Awakening there isn't craving there isn't agitation
so meditation
as has been saying supports this a way to get in touch with our direct experience and to also see how some of
the thoughts we might have or the ideas that we have
they aren't the way forward because thoughts beget thoughts which beget thoughts which we get thoughts and we go
right into these thought streams we start to get really disconnected from what's actually happening
I'm not saying that we don't need to plan I am not saying that we don't need to solve problems
I am saying that there's a way in which sometimes we're adding on to our direct experience we're holding on this whole
narrative it means this about me or it means this about something else or the
universe or something like this that's extra
we don't need it it gets in the way
so maybe I've been talking about the upside of you know we're working with direct
experience and I just want to mention a little bit more specifically some of the downside
of just relying on thoughts and philosophy and ideas and beliefs and
Notions that we have so first of all again I want to kind of
acknowledge thoughts are important I'm not saying we shouldn't have thoughts in fact I would say they're very powerful
and can be beautiful right humans have written love poems
have cured diseases we've eliminated pain in a lot of
situations that otherwise would have been pain my Tylenol exists now right that is the work of somebody's thoughts
and planning let me fix explored outer space ocean depth I mean all kinds of great stuff
that has come from thoughts and planning but many of the views opinions beliefs
stories thoughts that we have are the basis of our suffering
I should be mindful all the time having a thought like that is can be a
basis of suffering because chances are you're not mindful 100 of the time
or yeah my practice won't really take off and until I'm able to sit still for
an hour and I can't sit still for an hour so I don't know maybe there's no hope for me or something like this oh
so many thoughts that we have they're just aren't helpful in fact I would say that they're part of
our suffering but I would also say
that holding views having these ideas about what practice is or about this
idea that we have to figure things out part of the downside of them is that it
can lead to some complacency in our meditation practice
if we're thinking that it's just about solving problems or ruminating
or figuring things out then we will spend our time on the cushion
figuring things out but if we have this idea no actually
direct experience is important then we'll tune into what is the experience
of breathing what is the experience of sitting in this posture what is the
experience of hearing those sounds
and maybe I'll just say this one last thing too also this um if we have this idea that
we just only want to have views we're like really holding on to some of our ideas
this might be an indicator of something bigger that's happening in our life that is a certain amount of
arrogance I could maybe use that word that we think like okay I already know what I
need to know or I don't need to really tune into what's happening I'm smart
enough I can figure it out or maybe it's a certain amount of clues-mindedness like
I don't really want to learn anything new I just want to be quiet and I hope
that I feel some relaxation I don't want to open up any new
experiences or new ideas or maybe clinging to views is a part of
wishful thinking too we might have this idea sometimes it's
like if we think something enough then it will be so if we convince ourselves
it'll be so of course that doesn't work so well
so this idea of thoughts thinking views beliefs
versus just tuning into
experiencing whatever there is to tune into and
experience and I recognize that for some people
their experiences really difficult and overwhelming
so there's ways in which we can work with that that's like tune into your experience and then come back out open
your eyes for example so that we don't fall into overwhelm
but it's not you won't be able to work with it by avoiding it and just thinking about it
if we could all think ourselves to create our life we would have done it already
and maybe I'll end with that and to open it up to some questions
somebody have a comment or a question that they'd like to say
um when you talk about like Insight could you elaborate a little bit on the difference between Insight versus like
wisdom or if they're the same or just if there's any difference between them yeah
thank you that's a good question I would say different teachers at different times would say different
things this teacher at different times would say different things so
um I would say I would say all Insight is wisdom but
not all wisdom is inside so some wisdom is just recognizing
um that oh yeah I'm lost in thoughts so there that may not be like an Insight
but that's just recognizing oh yeah most in thoughts and I remember that when I'm usually doing this it doesn't have a
good outcome or something like this you know is that helpful yeah yeah that
helps anybody else have a comment or a
question
I was also thinking that um part of why I I mentioned earlier the
kind of the irony and I'm giving all these ideas to say oh it's not all about ideas and I was thinking that also
for me in my life I so much thought I could think my way
through in my early 20s well I have a question here I just was having a hard time and I
just would go to the library and like okay there's got to be a book here that has the answer
and I have a lot of books but uh
turns out not to be the answers that I thought they would be
uh I really am um
excited about this idea of teachers being or you know Wise people
being a result of direct experience so
and I know you're saying it's not necessarily experience out there
but aren't we then just cultivating experience
and how does that relate to being still I don't know it's a hard question
to ask but just that makes me want to just go and experience everything and I think that's a little bit too
wild and crazy um so why do you think it's wild and
crazy uh because I don't I think
there's there's a seeking and a distraction that happens with that
um perhaps not enough reflection and
insight and the balance between those two things but
yeah so searching after stimulation right it just gets exhausting and
doesn't necessarily lead to some greater understanding so when I was
um thinking about experience I was using words like
warm or cold or tingly or stabbing or spacious or closed
or tight or um
relaxed I don't know those kinds of words so I
I'm when I'm pointing towards or this idea of direct experience I'm really talking about like
really kind of like basic experiences and we can turn whatever it is whether
it's after going out and experiencing everything we can just be with them and
then we would just notice oh this uh energetic or more
bubbly or I don't know what it would be to follow that so it I wouldn't say
it has to be only certain types of experiences but
if we're really with our experience we will notice the downside of
certain experiences like oh this always comes with some tightness and
tiredness when I am in having these certain types of experiences or
something like that is this helpful yeah I think I think
really it sounds like getting really in tune with kind of that somatic experience yes something yeah yes thank
you not uh the thrill right feeling right thank you that's
right because we do use this word experiences like travel brochures are filled with this
word or something like that or you know experienced like Jimi Hendrix you know like what does that mean that's right
that's right thank you thank you
and Diane I think I see a parallel between what you said tonight about
distinguishing between reasoning things out and
understanding the benefits of direct experience and it's something that
both you and Gil taught recently namely that when you look at
the Four Noble Truths you see the parallel
when you look at the Four Noble Truths instead of thinking
about the second Noble Truth is suffering is caused
by craving instead just experience
just just at A fine grain level be aware of notice
craving and notice suffering
and when he have a lot of awareness of your moment
by moment experience and how things change you know the the Insight really sinks in
better something like that so maybe you want to
say it repeat you know restate it a little bit better I
said it very nicely we can understand the four noble truths is to recognize oh there's suffering
this word suffering we could say stress or dissatisfaction one way we can understand the four noble
truths to say and there's the arising and the cessation so just to see the experience oh it's arising and it's
going away and there's a path that leads to the cessation to the ending of the
suffering and that's in contrast to thinking about oh they're suffering
what's causing it oh it's caused by this but then what's caused by that and that's more of a
might be a cognitive activity as opposed to just experiencing the raising and
passing away and and Bill I did get the idea for this Dharma talk based on uh
the class that you were in on Thursday [Laughter] yep so you get I don't know that was
nice that you uh caught the connection there yeah I I want to add that
the reasoning part has been tremendously helpful to me
uh oh yeah craving causes suffering and then I when I can see oh
how I'm leaning into shall we say a a social situation morning at the
turnout will leaning causes suffering maybe both directions
so pull back so that the reasoning part has been helpful but
but I see what you're saying yeah yeah reasoning right we need it it's important and it's helpful it's an
integral part of our lives and I would say practice too but sometimes we get
disconnected from the experience or think that okay I just have to learn more I just have to understand better
and then I'll become awakened or somehow something like this but yeah thank you
thank you Phil okay so we're at the top of the hour
the vector wish you all a wonderful rest of the evening and if you'd like you're
welcome to come up here and talk to me but otherwise be safe and thank you