readings and I'm very glad to be here with you
so in our training and emptiness
for this meditation the aspiration for us
is cutting through the ignorance of selfishness
and self-referential thinking
so if that's okay with you I propose that we adopt that as a common
aspiration for these few minutes and as always We Begin by
going to someplace empty as the Buddha told us to
seclusion we take a break from our worldly
concerns and we create physical seclusion
and mental seclusion
so we invite all of our worries and concerns
to have a seat outside of our meditation space they'll be okay out there
they don't need us for this meditation
so assuming your meditation posture
and if you're comfortable closing your eyes I really really recommend that
I find it much more restful myself to listen to a guided meditation than to
look at one
and take a moment to
investigate your posture
how can you sit in a way that feels
settled relaxed
hopefully a bit empty and at the same time
being in touch the flow of life inside of us
and outside of us having some
awesome energetic quality in the body
I like to think of the energy coming up from the Earth
and it may or may not go through the Lakes but coming certainly coming up from the base
of the spine and allowing the head to be well
balanced certainly not I mean you might want to
bring it back a little ways and then
connecting our posture whether it's sitting
standing seating lying down
connecting with their breathing long slow deep breath
and if you've found it beneficial if you imagine the flow of the breath
coming up from the base of the spine along the back
taking a slight pause between the inhale and the exhale at the crown of the hitch
and then gently letting the exhale come peacefully down the front
so in a way we're nourishing the settledness and the energy of the
body by the way that we breathe
bringing this intentionality
to our breathing attending
their breathing with mindfulness with care
and full awareness
the Brava vihara's the Divine abodes are excellent reparations
for the gradual descent into emptiness
we spent these first few days
relying on meta which is sort of like the mother of all four
of these Divine abodes
so again offer your whole body
a sense of exquisite friendliness
warmth accepting whatever it is
whatever way it is however it is
this precious body is what allows us to practice
and now I miss also to the mind
however our mind is it's I'm confident that we're doing our best
and that's fine that's good enough
thank you mind for your effort
and today as a way of maintaining a sense of
spaciousness in the mind
will transition to the next of the Divine abodes which is compassion
so first wishing ourselves may I be free from all harm
may I be free from cruelty
we offer ourselves the well-wishing of being held
in compassion and we also do the holding
and now we off open up and offer this beautiful
feeling of care kindness
and compassion to all beings everywhere we're suffering
the Buddha tells us that basically anything
that is instructed
ends up being suffering because it doesn't last
it's fleeting so as long as we're involved
in what's going on with us with the world
with others there may be even if it's going okay
there's no guarantee that it will always be okay
and we can extend our well-wishing to our own suffering
especially if we're experiencing pain
or health challenges are
emotional deceptions loss
and we reach out imagining all the beings in the world the humans
who are also experiencing some form of suffering
and we send our heartfelt wish that they too
be free from Barn from cruelty
for the suffering
and connecting with the nobility
of this form of kindness
well-wishing or any being who is suffering
and keeping that as a backdrop for the period of the meditation
to begin with we can experiment with
leaving the words behind and incarnating
compassion and our own body and mind
boundless compassion as we breathe in
and breathe out
our compassion is immeasurable
Unlimited
and we can liberate our hearts in mind
through this boundless compassion
getting our compassion go out as far as it wants to go
and feeling it as Unlimited
endless
and from this spacious compassion
we can invite contemplation of Infinite Space
so again coming back the mindfulness of our energy
we take in not only
rounding energy from the Earth
but today we'll focus on
receiving
the energy from Infinite Space
No Boundaries
so imagine yourself a little speck on planet Earth
sitting here but allowing your mind
to inhabit Infinite Space
it's space that's holding everything in the universe
and it's empty
and we too can be empty of ignorant claim to the self
I'm sure In This Moment each of us is free from cruelty
we don't need to obsess with our body or the bodies of others
we don't really need to obsess with accumulating more and more possessions
and with this spaciousness of the Mind dwelling and boundless compassion
and mindful attention to whatever arises
losing a peaceful heart
no need for the burden of selfing
thoughts arise we have the wisdom
but let them go
a mind that's like space is a wholesome and healing place to be
tasting the freedom of emptiness
the beauty of compassion
as we come to the end of this sitting
we appreciate the goodness of our practice
even or imperfect practice
and we continue to offer well-wishing
of compassion to all living beings including us
may we and all beings be safe
and protect it being safe
may we all dwell in kindness
contentedness at ease
may we abide in peace
and may all beings everywhere be free
into out that's all about together
thank you
uh I I want to express my uh deep appreciation
um to um both Gill and venerable analio
or their teachings on emptiness which I'm borrowing from
quite a bit this week
and um so today is the fourth in the series
of training and empty nuts and the step after what we did yesterday
and the discourse we've been studying
um is Infinite Space
so Monday we focused on really becoming aware of
the inconstancy of everything that's conditioned
and because we and everything are just a flow rather than solid
um we're essentially empty
and what the Buddha stressed they need to be empty of
is empty of ideas of a self
and then on
Tuesday we we went to the part of the Congo where
he begins teaching Ananda about how to enter into emptiness and he starts with
the example that they're all there meditating together and
uh what what is not empty is the Sangha the monastic song The meditating there
and so that is the presence and he stresses
the importance of knowing not only what's present but
also was absent and he gave the example of
uh the Sangha there and that all being absent of all kinds of animals
and in the same way when we tend to reify anything we should
all we should always know that it's empty of itself
and then yesterday um
we move to the next step in the teaching which is to uh quiet
down on the details and meditate on
the Oneness of the Earth
so this is a way of electing the mind
and the step after that is Infinite Space
and um I'd like to just make a little aside
that I learned that this week NASA has uh
celebrated its first year of the uh James Webb Space Telescope
in space and it has performed far beyond expectations
and in fact has revealed in um
our own Cosmic backyard images uh
of galaxies that were that arose
very close to the Big Bang to the beginning of the universe
and before this telescope in space
foreign ERS only had a handful of images of
early galaxies in the first one billion year years of existence
and now um they have hundreds and it is totally astonishing because
what they're seeing is clouds of
uh forming Stars that are swirling around
black holes so in the midst of
the space of the universe there's all this flow happening
and the fact that they could go back so far and see this the earliest
time of the universe it was like having um baby pictures of
the universe the cosmos and
in fact what these reveal is
how things were at the beginning of time so in a way
uh they they have the time uh in the early part of
um the cosmos is now available to humans in the form
of images extraordinary
so I'd like to spend um this the rest of his talk
uh reading to you um continuing from where we left off
yesterday in the uh shorter suta on emptiness
and I think um it would be nice just for you to listen
uh if you like you can close your eyes but I'm hoping that
uh dropping deep into the suto will be useful
the buddhisms again and uh not attending to the perception of
forest or perception of Earth a practitioner clearly knows
this field of perception is empty of the perception of forest
there is only this that is not emptiness the Oneness dependent on perception of
Earth thus one regards what is not there as
empty however as to what remains there
one clearly knows this is present
thus this is the genuine undistorted
completely pure dissent into emptiness
one attends to the Oneness dependent on the perception
of the sphere of Infinite Space
through the perception of the sphere of Infinite Space
the Mind gains confidence becomes settled
remains still and is inclined
towards release one clearly knows thus
whatever stress there might be
dependent on the perception of forest that is not present here
whatever stress there might be dependent on the perception of Earth
that is not present here there is only this measure of stress
the Oneness dependent on the perception of the sphere
of Infinite Space one clearly knows
this field of perception is empty
of the perception of Earth there is only this that is not emptiness
the Oneness dependent on the perception of this fear
of Infinite Space thus one regards what is not there as
empty however as to what remains
one clearly knows this is present thus
this is the genuine undistorted completely pure
dissent into emptiness
you remember that in the beginning of this discourse the Buddha affirms that
he often abides and emptiness
and this is what Buddhas do and also Aura hunts fully awakened once
the Buddha often refers to this as um Pleasant abiding when he's meditating
and it's important to know that uh
this can also be done not just in seated meditation but in any
of the four postures sitting standing walking or lying down
we can imagine spaciousness
and emptiness as medicine
for the Fetter of conceit
so with that um
I'd like to um suggest that we
in as many of our daily activities as we can see if we can
perceive spaciousness and remember
that everything is empty of itself
thank you for your attention thank you for your practice