warm greetings from meditation Hall here at Insight
Meditation Center uh and I'm delighted to be here and I'm
delighted to in a certain virtual way to be with you all where you are and that
um to feel the the net the interconnected net of
all of us spread around the world I'd love to see a map with um each of us the
place we're in and then lines from each of us to everyone else in here sitting
here and how those would crisscross and what kind of net that would make so thank you for being
here this morning I was thinking about what used to be called maybe still
called Russian dolls these uh series of um dolls of
different size that if you uh the outer ones you can pull them apart and then the smaller ones are
inside and they get smaller and smaller until you get to the smallest one which is uh is whole you can't pull it
apart and uh sometimes in uh Buddhist
spirituality people can have the sense that we're made up of all these
Parts all these layers and part of practice is to deconstruct them to let
them go to quiet them down to uh to settle deeper and deeper in until we can
get to some core a core of Peace a core of Freedom some place of deep inner calm
or deep inner sense of wholeness or honesty or Integrity or well-being
that doesn't dismiss or deny or condemn all the other
layers it does create a different reference point for understanding the different
layers but as practice goes along rather than the the um the goal of practice is to
tap into some deep inner place of Peace uh that the peace the freedom the
Joy of practice uh begins be becomes the outermost
doll and uh and so everything is everything is within that the largest
container the largest sphere that holds all the different ways that we are is um
is uh uh Joy or letting go or peace all
those things are kind of synonymous and um and so it doesn't mean
that so we we it's kind of like we can be operating on these different layers at the same time there might be a place
within us that does feel very sad or hurt or angry or challenged in some
way uh but there are these other uh places that could be at the foundation
we might feel at the very bottom of it all we might feel a place of peace or it
might be that to at some point that that peace at the bottom of deep letting go
opens up and it becomes the the largest of the Dolls it's what large a sphere that holds it all and it creates a very
different context for being with the things that are challenging it's almost like the
challenges are no longer challenges they're still may be painful but they
are not something that we're identifying with or or uh caught in and not being caught in it we can
hold it with greater compassion hold it with greater care and love and and uh and if uh if we are identifying
with anything it's with uh that which is peaceful so to assume a meditation
posture and to lower your gaze or close
your eyes and if
you feel yourself with the largeest sphere that holds it
all whatever way you are not trying to look for peace or calm just whatever way
you are right now allow yourself to be present for
it be aware of it appreciating that this is the present
moment experience
even if you're thinking about the past and future or how you're feeling relates to the past and
future for now just appreciate that here and
now this is how you
are gently taking a
few deeper satisfying breaths just deep enough to some degree
of satisfaction very modest
satisfaction exhaling a little bit more than
usual maybe giving you a better sense of
completion in the
exhale
letting your breathing return to nor
normal and for a few rounds of breathing just so you can surf on the
breathing or let the movements of breathing massage your
body
and whatever you're thinking
about can you lighten up loosen up around it a bit by relaxing
the thinking
mind and then take a further
step on the exhale to let go of what you're thinking
about maybe imagining it drifts away like a thought
bubble
maybe letting go of your thoughts that is also a letting go
into whatever calm or subtleness there is in your
body
whatever is beginning to come or become more settled settling
process let go into
it
for
if you're holding tight in your fist a
stone and if you let go of it you'd probably drop the
stone If instead of letting go of the
stone you let go of the
gripping and if you're holding the stone with your palm upward the stone won't
drop it just held lightly in the
hand as you let go of thoughts do you let go of anything you can let go
of don't let go of it let go of the grip the tension the
pressure
for
let go gently
steadily maybe with every exhale let go let go of any
[Music] holding
clinging any way in which you hang on to thoughts or feelings or
ideas any way that you're preoccupied by
anything expectations preference
is let go
relax lighten up and as you do
so let go into whatever calm or
peace that might be
here
however small it might
be
tension grasping clinging pressure
are all things that make us smaller limit the range of
attention to let go to relax let go
into the wider space beyond the edges of your what
you're holding on to beyond the edges of what you're
thinking
as if you're stepping into a very big room after being in a very small
one with every exhale let go relax
into the widest sphere beyond the edges of whatever
you're feeling and thinking where there might be some modum
of peace and calm that holds it
all
for
e
beyond the edges of whatever is troubling
you or deep deep down inside at the core of
everything might there be a calm or a
peace a place of non-identification
nonreactivity
that helps you to not identify with what troubles
you helps you not identify with what is going
well that allows you to be at ease on
troubled by the layer inside which is
troubled without preferences for the layer inside which
has
preferences
in reference to peace
calm in reference to that which is beyond the
edges of your thoughts edges of your feelings edges of your
body let it be the outermost
sphere that allows and accept all things
peacefully
e
for
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to take a few moments to let go or to
stop whatever you're doing that could be called meditation maybe still keep your eyes
closed but allow yourself just to be without anything
more without any intentional practice of attention or
Focus
and if there's anything here that's enjoyable
Pleasant let yourself be nourished by
that and if and if anything is here here is
unpleasant difficult let that be the TR
The Prompt for compassion and love and
care and then with your inner
eye turning your gaze outward into your
world the Places You'll Be Today people you'll [Music]
encounter people you might have communication with people you're likely to read about
in the news
or for with whom you receive an
email and in that world imagine that you are experiencing
them all from that place of
Peace calm the wide
[Music] sphere or from the center of all things
within and gaze upon your world with Good
Will as if everyone you encounter and think
about is in fact your
friend even the difficult friends and wish them all
well may all the people that I encounter today may they be
happy may they be
peaceful may they be
safe may they be
[Music] free thank
you
so hello and we're here for the fifth talk about
um my my story and kind of encountering Buddhism and the plan is to take it up
until I um I guess started teaching at here for
IMC and then I'll make an announcement the end of this talk about what the plan
is for next week that's related so
um so I was ordained at 1982 as a priest
as a monk at the San Francisco Zen Center and um I felt very comfortable happy to
be um monk uh the monastic lifestyle worked really well for me and I was happy in it
and um the Simplicity of that life dedication to practice and the idea of being of
service to this world and not service in general but I really wanted to address
the suffering of the world as deeply as I could it was a bit of a shock a few
months later when the Abbot gathered together all the people who had had monk ordination at the San Francisco Z Center
and had decided that he was going to change the name to no longer being monks
but now being priests and uh I was stunned like I I
didn't want I didn't have no interest in being a priest I thought I was going to be a monk over time I've come to really
appreciate this idea of being a priest because it's much more clearly uh
involves being in the world uh serving people being involved in lives of people
and monk isn't so obviously that and um and so you know now in my as a Zen
priest I'm happy enough with it but that was ordained then in 1982 and oddly enough uh within a year
by the April or so um there was the that I uh ordained me I had a scandal uh an
ethical Scandal it was fairly serious and it took some months for that to work itself out for San Francisco Z Center
eventually he uh resigned and left but um uh when I got the news that he was uh
uh when people got the news of his scandal of his ethical breach breaches
actually then um uh many people felt deeply betrayed deep deeply hurt and uh
it was very hard for the community maybe because I'd been the Zen Center for 5 years and I hadn't invested as much as
other people had um I didn't feel so hurt by it in fact I had the opposite
expression uh experience and I'll tell you how that happened
um the uh somewhere around uh uh little over a year after my ordination so was
like in maybe March of February March of 8 4
83 um I was beginning to feel that zenen was a little bit too ingrown for me a
little bit too self focused maybe or claustrophobic I felt a need for fresh
air um I felt I felt happy about my Orin ordination I felt happy about my teacher
and happy about most things but I had this feeling that's that uh that
something was a little bit too insular and it was healthy for me to kind of Step out of that insular bubble but that
was hard to do back then because there was it was a little bit cultic back then in this in the sense that um there was a
feeling like only at zener was the truth really there like Buddhist truth and anybody who left was leaving that truth
so it's a little bit hard to leave so I was uh thinking about these things and
then I was sitting uh talking with a at sent Center talking with a friend and
the first time I told someone this feeling that I had and as I was telling her uh one of the
senior priests from Zen Center Senior teachers came over to me and tapped me
on the shoulder and says you know uh I'd like to talk to you and when you finish the conversation you can come over to my
my room to my apartment so I finished my conversation with my friend and I went over to this priest uh to talk to him
and I thought maybe I'd gotten in trouble and uh because no one had ever
asked me to like I have to talk talk to you and it was kind of serious kind of
request and um instead what happened was he he uh the the news uh of this the
ethical breach of the Abbot had not been told by everyone it was only a small group of people who knew and the
decision was to go around and tell people individually key people or you know at Zen Center individually before
letting the whole Community know and I was one of those people and a and as he
told me I felt delighted because now I was free to leave and I'd been invited
by my father was going to work in Japan for a year to come to Japan and I had
told them no I don't want to come to Japan because I have um uh I have to you know I have to be
practice a tent Center so I called him up and said now I'm ready to go and uh
and so then he um so I was free to go to Japan Jaan I went to Japan in order to
study Zen and be in the monasteries there and I was there for a while uh uh
and there's a lot to tell you stories about Japan but then I went to
um I went to um um uh I had to get a new visa for
Japan and uh to stay in Japan I had a tourist visa originally and I was going to go spend some months living at a Zen
training Monastery so I went to Thailand it was the easiest cheapest way to get a new
visa for staying in Japan and uh went to Bangkok and I applied for a Visa and I
waited had to wait for the visa to be approved and so I decided to go to I had
the address of a little meditation Monastery outside of bankco and I went there and said I'm going to stay here
until the Visa comes and I'm going to ask the Abbott to teach me whatever meditation he has he has and just do do
what he says and while I'm here just it turned out to be a Vasa Center I knew
almost nothing about vasana it turned out that the way they practiced was to practice all day um and then once a day
I would go see the Abbot and it was given a little Hut at the edge of the monastery on top of kind of the swamps
it was and um little Hut on stilts and um I I practice for 10 weeks
without um getting the Visa and um and then I decided Well I'll just go back to
Japan anyway with a tourist visa and um but those 10 weeks was a 10 we uh
intensive retreat in Zen practice the longest I done was seven days and to do
it for 10 weeks um really made a difference for me and one of the differences was I got much more
concentrated in than I ever had in Zen in a different kind of way and in that
concentration I touched something very seemingly very deep inside a little kernel of something that uh seemed like
the truest place and it became essential for me to
touch that place again it wasn't logical or rational it was just this deep kind
of feeling deep kind of urge or kind of necessity that I felt and um I did go
back to Japan Jaan I finished up the year in Japan living in a Zen Monastery I came back to uh California I
had no money and worked for uh for think about four months I was given free room
and board at the San Francisco Zen Center so I could do this and so all the money I had from working was um went to
um uh saving up money and I think after those four months I had about $2,000 and then I bought a ticket to go
back to Asia this time to go to Burma because I'd learned the practice I had
uh I'd been given in Thailand the headquarters for that the source of it was this particular Monastery in Yun
Myanmar and um and so um I went there or I tried to go there um but it was very I
didn't realize this but actually the Burma was closed when I applied for a Visa so I was waiting for Visa nothing
happened uh I went to um the teacher in Burma upand was going to practice in
Nepal I practiced with him for a month in Nepal which was very fortuitous because uh people like Joseph Goldstein
Sharon salsburg John Travis other people um or came to practice with them as well
so that's where I got to meet these wonderful teachers as kind of friends practicing together I practiced in Thailand uh
month longer retweets there waiting for the Visa I finally reapplied and um and then eight months
after I've first applied for a Visa I think I um I finally got a visa to Burma
I think because Burma finally opened again to let people come Burma only opened it wide enough to allow people to
have t tourist visa uh Not Tourist tourist visas for one week or uh
meditation visas for three months I don't know how many countries have meditation visas
and um so I went and uh and then I entered into the
life of uh the Intensive life uh of intensive Retreats uh in Burma um it was
I I meditated for eight months all day long um you know so the longest I'd done
before that was those 10 weeks in Thailand and now I did this for eight months and uh that was uh uh one of the
highest points in my life um I I uh it
was both difficult and something I deeply loved something that was challenging and experienced tremendous
amount of joy and um and uh and it was I think I would say
it was transformative it kind of shaped me uh in a way that uh continues to this
day and so I thought I'd finish this uh
Series today up at until a time in which I was going to uh start teaching here at
IMC but uh we're running out of time so let me leave you there this kind of a new phase now that um coming to uh Vasa
practice and really diving into it in a deep way and uh in a way that
then eventually brought me here to teaching at IMC so what we'll do for next week is I
think I'll just continue this story and um and when I finally reach uh um
beginning to teach at IMC I thought I would continue uh for however many days
that is um to little bit the history of IMC uh not uh because this is also very
important because I want to convey that not the Bland history of IMC but rather
the values that uh were infused into this community and are here for this
place that may be expressed through the history and um in a sense it continues
my story because um you know my dedication for now the last 33 years has
been IMC and then coincidentally um I was wanted to say
that uh um in uh being there the end of the year
I've written the end of a year letter uh for IMC and uh this year I wrote a little
different different than I have done in other years where um I've you know uh the end of the year letter usually just
talks a little bit about IMC and and it still does that but I wanted to have for
the letter to have a little bit of a Dharma purpose as well some a little bit of something memorable Dharma wise um in
it so uh if you'd like to read uh imc's end of the year letter and uh maybe help
care for IMC that in the way that these end of the year letters usually suggest
uh you'll find it on the what's new section of imc's homepage um in the bottom right hand
corner there's a little box that says what's new and you go there the items there and you'll see the end of the year letter from Gil and um so thank you very
much and I look forward to continue this on
Monday