welcome everybody
and thank you for being here and I especially want to thank you for
your practice for your sincerity
I was thinking today that if I were looking for a word to describe or characterize our
far-flung meditation community of practitioners I think I'd pick
sincerity so let's begin by taking a moment to
recognize Where We Are in this particular community
with each person sincerely doing their best to practice
meditation and to walk in the footsteps
of the Buddha so I'm sending out to you
a silent expression of appreciation or the sincerity that each of you is
bringing to our practice together if you like
feel free to make take a moment to do the same
so far this week we've cultivated three of the wholesome mind states that
prepare the mind for awakening or allowing the full impact of this
Dharma practice to come alive in our own hearts
these qualities of Mind are receptivity softness
and being free of self-centered preoccupations
free of the hindrances which function as barriers
obstructions to Awakening
and when we have just a brief moment on the thinking mind is taking a break
from all the commentary I think perhaps the most natural response to that is gladness
because now the mind is ready for the sunlight fresh air
and spaciousness of the Dharma to reveal itself to us
Moment by moment so let's begin
by setting Our intention for this meditation
so what is your deepest wish for how this practice could
benefit both yourself and others
and now taking your meditation posture
feeling the contact with the Earth and sending your roots down deep into
the Earth letting it support you
lining the spine so that the energy flows freely
you might think of opening the lower chakra in the perineum
to receive the energy of the Earth and the topmost chakra at the crown of
the head or there's a little space between the plates of the skull
opening that to the heavens allowing the energy
of the sky to come inside as well
it's good if your posture gives you a feeling of stability
and now begin relaxing the body scanning down from the head
relaxing these shoulders the arms
the hands and the fingers
the Torso in the belly the hips
the legs the feet and the toes
taking a long deep slow breath
and relaxing into the process of breathing
and as we stay with the breath we can
let the bread awareness of the breath be slightly in the background
and just do a few minutes of loving kindness meditation
creating a set space where we're protected by this warm-hearted feeling
of well-wishing towards our self and all beings
may I and all beings everywhere be safe
and protect it
may all beings everywhere including me be happy
be peaceful and free
and with this warm-hearted well wishing
we bring in the wisdom to vow that we'll sit
quietly quiet body
Quiet Mind leaving our preoccupations outside the
door and now bringing the breath back into
the foreground and connecting with the breath
the flow
breathing in noticing the felt Sensations
of the beginning of the breath
and the continuation of the in-breath the pause at the top
which gives way to the out breath
and as that flows down with a pause
at the bottom sometimes I enjoy thinking about the
cycle of the breath as a as an oval of energy and Flow
so closing the eyes you can imagine
the in-breath beginning at the base of the spine in the back
and reaching its end at the top of the head and then the out breath
flowing down the front of the body reaching its end
in the perineum
or just staying with the breath flowing in
and out
and giving your breath as an offering to your mindfulness
as a beautiful non-static object of meditation
constantly changing perhaps you may feel it flowing up the
back and down the front
if it feels right to you lighting a little candle of gladness in
the heart
breathing in welcoming gladness
breathing out spreading gladness as far as it wishes
to go
but if you're struggling with loss depression despair hopelessness fear
I trust you have the wisdom to know that repressing your emotional state is
counterproductive and if that's the case recognize your pain
perhaps you can appreciate just being here in a safe space
breathing
inviting gladness on the in-breath
radiating gladness on the out breath
and like all these wholesome States like loudness exist on the in a wide
spectrum so if you're really free of the
hindrances you might feel elated but if life is difficult right now
then you might just be able to access a little hint
of gladness and that's fine
that's to be honored or you could try these metaphrases
may I live with an open heart
May whatever clouds my heart he dispelled
so if you feel that support would be beneficial to you please go ahead and
do the well-wishing of living with an open heart
and letting whatever clouds there be dispelt
perhaps we can be satisfied just to be here
a sincere practitioner in this spot on planet Earth
breathing
breathing in welcoming whatever gladness may be present
and allowing yourself to feel it and breathing out
hearing it with all beings
and by staying contentedly
with the flow and ebb of the breath allowing yourself to perhaps
glimpse their freedom that is possible
when the mind and the body settle down even for just a moment
perhaps you can be glad that wow this Freedom Is Possible
even for me
and in this openness breathing in
radiating gladness inside breathing out
radiating gladness giving it away
foreign
and as we come to the end of this sitting
with a mind that has benefited from appreciating some of the goodness
in ourselves and in our world and through the goodness of our practice
may we are Center of appreciation and gladness
now radiate our heartfelt wish
that all beings everywhere be safe
may we all be happy
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free and may our meditation practice
help us to contribute to the safety happiness
Peace and Freedom of all beings everywhere
[Music]
foreign
friends I'm very glad to be here with you
and this is the fourth talk this week on the theme of opening the Dharma heart
the early polytext talk about opening the Dharma eye
when a follower of the Buddha awakens and fully penetrates and realizes the
Dharma from themselves and what's necessary for this insight to
happen is to understand the truth of how things really are
the wonderful artist Mark Chagall said if I create from the heart nearly
everything works if from the head almost nothing
and I believe this is especially true for everyone who has suffered greatly
I talked earlier this week about this Dharma practice as a process of
sculpting ourselves as though we're creating a beautiful work of art
where more and more through our practice we've become a force of beauty and
goodness for both ourselves and others so I think I coined this expression
opening the Dharma heart which by the way is not canonical
because for me uh opening the mind was not enough
for getting ready for the insights that give rise to liberation
I had to progressively little by little for a long time
learn how to open the heart and this wasn't going to happen if I
couldn't fully accept myself warts and all
so the heart had to open for the mind to be able to settle down in my case
to be comfortable resting in moments of emptiness
and to open the doors and windows to let in the sunlight and spaciousness
of the Dharma like many of you I'm a creature of this
Western culture and it's quite intuitive for me to
distinguish between the mind and the Heart but this may not have been the case for
the Disciples of the Buddha it's fascinating that chitung
the word in Pali that means mind also means heart
and even today when you ask someone in the Indian subcontinent to point to
their mind most people will put their hand on their heart
so this week we're talking about the qualities of mind that the Buddha held as valuable
in preparing for awakening we've seen that we need to cultivate
receptivity making space in the mind to receive the Dharma
we need a soft mind which in Pali is moodu
and when I talked about this on Tuesday I mentioned that the etymological root would
means not only soft but also happy
and then I went for a walk afterwards and I had sort of a mental light bulb
and I said to myself but of course when the mind is soft even temporarily
if it really doesn't have sharp edges one can't help but feel happy
so it completely makes sense actually that the root of this quality could evolve into either softness or
happiness and yesterday we evoked the quality of
having a mind that is free of preoccupations again even just temporarily
and likewise uh the absence of the hindrances is naturally a source of
gladness because we're no longer slaves to our preoccupations
what a relief we can be here
in the present moment with more agency when the hindrances are not pushing us
around and moments like that are really moments
of freedom and this taste of Freedom
leads naturally to the Quality that will evoke today foreign
word for today's wholesome quality is udaga which comes from the prefix good
and the word Aga and UD means upwards
and AGA has a number of different meanings as an adjective it means highest
foremost supreme ultimate superb and as a noun Peak top
conclusion result
so this may sound a little abstract but in fact udega is usually translated as
elated or inspired it can also mean enraptured or exalted
and this kind of intense Rapture is an early phase of deep concentration in
meditation
and in this context I think it's important to recognize that there may be
dangers if when we experience uh being elated like this it
can be pretty um and rapturing and uh
it could become a preoccupation in itself if we uh cling to the intense
pleasure that it produces and I think uh this quality the way the
Buddha was intending us to um welcome it is
more equality of being inspired in a way that allows the mind to settle
so that the dregs can filter out and we have uh
the genuine Clarity to be able to uh receive these insights
so we don't want to be captured by being unladed
um and as I said earlier um all of these wholesome qualities exist on a broad spectrum
and they're of course easier to access on a long Meditation Retreat
but it's worthwhile uh tuning into and recognizing even
subtle occurrences of them during our daily meditation and daily
life as the Buddha teaches in the dhamapada
all experience is preceded by mind led by mind
made by mind speak or act with a corrupted mind and
suffering follows as the Wagon Wheel follows the hoof of
the ox all experience is preceded by mind led
by mind made my mind speak or act with a peaceful mind
and happiness follows like a never departing shadow
that we are constantly creating our experience by what we focus on
and the news is full of disasters and unethical Behavior
but it's worthwhile taking the time to make space in the mind for what inspires
us perhaps we can think of
the courage and generosity of all the rescue workers
in Ukraine and turkey and Syria and elsewhere in
the world who risk their own lives to help others
and in our meditation practice even if we have
short moments of receptivity softness and malleability
and the freedom from being pushed around by our preoccupations just a tiny moment
of that is worth celebrating
and for me to have confidence that this dharmic path I'm trying to
walk is the right place to be brings me great
gladness I know that I'm in good hands
I know I'm on the right track and it's okay
to walk this path even with imperfections
so I I hope you can take that in and Trust yourselves to be
um worthy practitioners don't uh
be impatient this Dharma path is made for slow
Bloomers as well as fast bloomers and there really is
um space for all beings to be here
so we can be inspired by tasting and
celebrating even short moments of being free of the
hindrances so as you open your hearts and Minds in
your meditation practice and in your mindfulness throughout the day
be sure to honor those tastes of freedom and let them bring you gladness
so that's your homework making peace with who you are
and recognizing and even letting yourself be inspired by
whatever Taste of freedom are offered to you
Moment by moment
thank you for your practice
may your day he sprinkled with moments of
gladness and may your practice inspire you