foreign
it's a a treat for me to be here with you all in in this role and uh
many of you know how much I love this Sangha
and so I have this nice feeling of being surrounded by friends
and I'm very grateful to you for that so I'd like to let you know that I'm
speaking to you from a very remote part of the south of France
where the internet is iffy at best I think the sound is going to be okay uh
is it okay so far um but the the video might be a bit
choppy so
um let's begin this meditation by
formulating Our intention what is it that motivates you to
practice meditation so take a moment now to articulate
your heartfelt wish for this meditation
and now assuming a meditation posture whether you're sitting or lying down
find a position that allows you to have some stability
and also ease
and as we get settled feeling the support of the Earth
which is holding all of us
aligning the spine relaxing softening the face
the shoulders arms the belly the legs
and this week we'll be beginning with um a little bit of meta meditation as a
preparation for insight so the invitation is to bring to mind
a benefactor somebody who's always been a positive force for you
it could be a little child a dear friend maybe a pet
or a teacher maybe even a teacher you've never met and when you see this being you feel
nourished and glad
a smile may come to the corners of your mouth or to the corners of your eyes
now invite this being to come and sit in front of you
and you look into each other's eyes
and a little flame begins to warm your heart
as you enjoy being together it's a warm two-way connection
and you open your heart and you wish them well
may you be safe and protect it
may be happy peaceful and free
and naturally they are simultaneously wishing you the same thing
and so together you can take that warmth that exists in your relationship
and experiment with radiating out that kindness that you have for each other
in all directions
may we and all beings be safe and protected
happy peaceful
and free
and you've created this warm safe space with this benefactor and if you like
now you can invite them to come and sit beside you for the rest of the meditation
and now keeping this little flame of kindness alive
we bring in some wisdom namely consciously putting all our
worries grievances fears wanting
outside our meditation space no need for them here
perhaps close in the eyes that's comfortable
and connecting with this body breathing
and the connection itself may have a flavor of warmth and friendliness
breathing in silently welcoming the present moment
breathing out thrusting present moment
resting the mind to take refuge in just being here
breathing
being here breathing in and breathing out
with a little flame of friendliness in our hearts
we receive the sensations of the breath
and trusting that for this short time it's wholesome
to let the thinking mind take a rest
that it's enough just to be here
in the protective presence of this beautiful
far flung Sangha
knowing the whole in-breath
knowing the pause after the in-breath
knowing the whole out breath and then the pause after the out breath
and this tender knowing of the cycle of the breath
takes place in the context of a warm heart where a little candle of benevolence
keeps radiating
breathing in silently welcoming the present moment
breathing out trusting
what arises in the present moment
as we breathe in welcoming as we breathe out
trusting
and if the Mind should wander all right here we go again
and with a smile and smile is very important we come back
back to this body breathing
and back to the warmth of breathing while radiating kindness
as far as it wants to go
breathing in welcoming breathing out
radiating kindness
and if the corners of the mouth want to turn up in a smile
you can welcome that on the in-breath
radiating kindness from the heart
on the exhale
foreign
and breathing out dwelling in the ecosystem
of benevolence and inviting receptivity
it's a joint project that we're doing together here
creating this ecosystem of benevolence
which may help us to become more receptive
and at ease
and as we come to the end of the sitting through the goodness of our practiced
may we from our Center of kindness and receptivity
now radiate our heartfelt wish
that all beings everywhere be safe
obviously this world is not safe for everyone
but it can still be our sincere wish
that we can pour energy into
may all beings be happy
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
foreign
am I unmuted can you hear me
looks good okay wait sorry for the technical glitch um I'm being hosted at IMC and uh I I
couldn't unmute myself to begin uh uh right on time so apologies for that
but we'll we'll be prepared for that tomorrow so uh greetings everyone I'm really
delighted uh to be here with you all uh
the theme for this week will be on opening what I'm calling uh the
Dharma heart and as many of you know I'm a big fan of
Gil franstal's teachings and so um in the
last series that he gave last year at the end of December was called ready to change
he introduced us to five qualities from the brahmaio
which is Maji manikaya 91. and just to give you a little background
and put it up as you may know was born into a culture that was dominated by
brahmanic religion rules caste distinctions
and in teaching something different the Buddha was proposing something quite revolutionary
so often when you see uh discourses where there's a conversation
with a brahmanas often a a contest of who's the better debater and who's got
the the angle on the truth but in this one um the brahmana ramayu who was 120 years
old and at the end of his life he was the oldest the wealthiest and the most
respected brahmana in the land and he became convinced that the Buddha was fully enlightened and was as he said
the incomparable teacher of gods and humans
so when the Buddha came to his uh part of the land the Brahman brahmau came with his great
retinue of uh disciples and bowed down to the Buddha
and kissed his feet and he asked the Buddha how does one become an aura hunt
how does one Attain completeness
I was one a silent Sage and how is one called a Buddha
so the Buddha
gave ramayu um what we call Progressive instruction
starting with the importance of virtue and pronunciation
and then when the Buddha saw that romayu's mind had the five qualities
that ensured that he was ready for enlightenment the Buddha transmitted his deepest
teachings and
remind you became enlightened on the spot and he exclaimed at the end
magnificent master gotama you have made the dhamma clear
ing upright what had been overthrown revealing what was hidden
showing the way to one who was lost holding up a lamp in the dark
and then everybody was amazed at this you know famous Raman
went forth then as a lay disciple of the Buddha
so this week I'd like to further explore these five wholesome qualities that
prepare the mind for insight for awakening so that we can cultivate them
and the verse of these qualities uh is in poly called Kala
and it has many different um nuances in poly
Gil translated it as being ready receptive
and available but the root of the word actually means
accomplish and the commentary on this uh discourse
speaks of Carla referring to someone with a sound mind
so it looks like um having this quality of a mind that is
color means that one has done a sort of mental Fitness training and is prepared to wake
up so earlier we began our meditation by
articulating our deepest intention for what brings us to the meditation
and if we want to cultivate mental Fitness then intention is very
important because knowing what we're aiming for helps us keep our Focus as we walk the
path so uh if you permit I'll share with you
my own intention um which I come back to when I meditate and
and sometimes when challenges come up during the day I say to myself
may I be a safe haven of kindness and emptiness
for all beings
that's my aspiration so sitting and attention will be
different for each of us depending on how we got to where we're at today
uh in my case having lived through an abusive childhood marked by
violence from my father and a mother who did not protect me
it's been a long path including being incarcerated in a mental
hospital for almost two years when I was a teenager
so for me this sense of safety is Paramount if I'm going to relax and let
go on meditation instead of dwelling in the past or going off into the future
so I aspire to be a safe haven for everyone I come into contact with
and then the kindness and emptiness um play the most important roles for me
in becoming this Safe Haven kindness because there's no situation
where kindness towards others or towards oneself is not beneficial
and I guess it's maybe kind of hard to under to imagine emptiness as a foundation
but I do believe that its emptiness and perhaps this is ironic
um it provides me the foundation that allows for being benevolent with
others and with myself empty of Me Myself and mine
empty of fixed ideas and wanted to be right or to be seen as accomplished
because when the mind wanders away from the pristine Simplicity of the present
moment and Spins off and thinking who's at the center of all
that well it's the little me
the little girl who wants to be liked who wants to be protected maybe even loved
and there were people who hated the Buddha but that didn't bother him in the
slightest the jealousy the hatred that was their problem
so how about if we had a mind that was empty of needing approval
sound like a good deal it would be a good deal for me
because the mind is if it's not full of all these self-referencing
and fix the ideas wonderful a mind that like the Buddha can dwell in
emptiness allows us to greet everyone as a friend
including ourselves to greet each moment as a friend
so I think mental Fitness is being ready to receive
and if we're already full with lots of ideas opinions and a needy ego there's
not a lot of space to receive so walking this path
can be seen as a process of emptying little by little emptying the mind of
everything that's unwholesome the early text talk uh about opening the
Dharma eye and this is what happened to ramayan
so what I'd like to suggest to you for this week is that we can prepare
for the Insight that is opening the Dharma eye by beginning to progressively open
the Dharma heart
daring to open our hearts and to let the Dharma
take us where it will
thank you so much for being here today and I look forward to being with you again tomorrow
thank you