so uh so good morning welcome uh
um yeah Gil um Gill is uh feeling under the
weather he's okay but uh was just feeling tired and um a little feverish
and so um he's resting and uh asks him
when to step in so here we are um
okay uh so let's uh yeah that's that's it together
just letting all the thought and feeling come to rest here
and take its place amidst awareness
letting gravity have you
the dependability of the Earth's support
and the breath
that soothes what's overactive and vitalizes what is flat
to pay attention is to pay attention to change
everything in motion
no such thing as things really
nothing on
everything momentarily rented
but we cannot open to a Nietzsche
the changingness of all things we cannot open to in each
from a place of fragmentation brittleness
so we establish a sense of Refuge
the center line
kind of inner safety stability
that's unrocked by
changing conditions
foreign
we find a Kind of Love
that's flexible enough malleable enough
to absorb the the body blows of Being Human
ordinarily we have our
our home base from which we
gaze Upon Our Life gaze upon phenomena
as if the view were outside the flow of change
but this River has no banks
whatever vantage point we take as ground
is just more change that we're not noticing
and so we start to join the river
of change the River of Life
in a sense nothing can be protected
but nothing needs our protection
it's a radical openness
the mesh of our being is one of my teacher says so open
that uh experience flows through
we literally practice this practice
and of course bits of our experience congeals
become solid needs their protection
and then we melt back into this uh River
wide flowing
unobstructed
foreign
okay it's good to uh good to see with you
um so Gil um Gill let me know that uh the
theme was was mindfulness amidst change mindfulness of change
and to um
as I said in the instructions to be mindful to be mindful
is to be mindful of change there's really no such thing as
mindfulness of stasis there's no
um mindfulness of a of a thing or even a person it's only the process
by which phenomena comes to be
comes to pass so bikubody says a niche impermanence on
reliability and each does not mean merely that everything
comes to an end it means that something deeper and more pervasive namely
that conditioned phenomena are in constant process happenings which break
up and perish almost as soon as they arise
now um before
I start talking tough about uh letting
go
talking tough about um about letting go and relinquishment and a Nietzsche and
all of that I I just should admit that I don't
really like change yeah
that in a way my fantasy deluded fantasy
is that I could get the world just how I like it and kind of
hold it still and hold it that way forever
and I suspect that um
you know the Buddhist teacher that doesn't like change that's a little
ridiculous but I suspect that's actually why I got into the path that um
I get into practice because I knew I knew intuitively that everything would
change and I knew that um my heart was unprepared
that I needed to prepare my heart for the changingness of all things
there's a study from a few years ago researchers recruited about 20 000
people to do a series of studies and they asked half the participants how
much they believed they would change over the next decade terms of personality
and values and preferences and then they asked the other half how
much they actually had changed over the past decade
and what they found was when they did this across all ages but what they found
was for example the 50 year old predicted much less change across their
50s and the 60 year old had actually experienced
in their 50s and the authors conclude people it seems
regard the present as a watershed moment at which they have finally become the
person they will be for the rest of their lives
history it seems is always ending today
the Assumption of permanence
it said something I've alluded to it said that our brain is a kind of prediction
machine and as fragile creatures amidst uh
unimaginably vast forces we must be making predictions
and we are relentlessly attempting to
make predictions that minimize the gap between our
model and what comes next our model of self and world and what
comes next in other words
we're trying never to be surprised
in each moment we're trying not to be surprised by the
next and not to be surprised by
five years from now and we see this in meditation the the
way we maintain so many reference points we keep tabs on samsara
the reference points of self and other past and future likes and dislikes
where I begin where I end what does this back pain mean what does this heartache
mean what does this fluttering anxious feeling mean what does this mean
for the trajectory of my life what does this mean
and we're trying to trace out this moment and ensure that it has us on a
kind of trajectory that feels okay
and that's so innocent but we can wind up living in those kind
of narrow claustrophobic models we've created
trying not to be surprised
it's harder to grow and learn to update our sense our models
and I find change is always a little bit startling you know even when you think you're
prepared for it change is always a little startling because the Assumption of permanence
does run deep it runs deep and the Buddha dwelled on the three
characteristics
change unsatisfactoriness or incompletion not self dwelled on the three
characteristics because in a sense the default assumption we we live in is the opposite
the opposite of the three characteristics we fantasize about a durable pleasure that
might structure our lives and end are seeking
we fantasize about tying up all the Loose Ends of Being Human of
of gaming out samsara of managing uncertainty
of living forever
and we fantasize about taking a kind of um taking refuge and an identity
arriving and Landing finding a home in self-view
and none of this can work in the end
but before the three characteristics are liberating we often have to grieve them
grieve them and so when Gill mentioned last night
that this is a theme the first thing that came to my mind
um was you know to deeply enjoy
periods of stability deeply enjoy
by knowing the tenuousness of it all
in those those windows of of relative stability
we enjoy but we enjoy not thinking it will go on forever we enjoy
deeply even more deeply because we know the tenuousness of it
that this moment is held together by causes and
conditions that we will never see we could never fully appreciate
the millions the the everything of the causes and conditions
that converge and create this moment this breath in this moment
and so we come to enjoy gratitude not in the artificial
way of you know sometimes feels
uh fake or something but is like no this is uh wow this breath yeah
this goodness this person this love
the path is uh is a dialectic of of Tranquility safety
seclusion and on the other hand letting the world rush into our heart
and uh making peace with imperfection
but we cannot really acclimatize to a Nietzsche from a place of fragmentation
right on this and so we
establish a sense of of inner stability of Refuge
of seclusion of protection
John Halifax said her line came to mind that um strong back soft front strong
back soft front it's such a beautiful encapsulation strung back
saffron we cultivate stability we have our Sila
Sila are honoring of goodness
we have our devotion to Buddha damasanga kind of Devotion to uh to love
maybe we have a sense of um of lineage lineage of being in the kind
of stream of dhamma
is a a meditator yesterday as a college student
told me that that they're I guess in music he's a musician a
classical musician and um nine Generations back is Franz list or
something like that you know kind of the Proto he's the Protege of the
Protege of the Protege of nine Generations back you get this classical
pianist students right and um
What's um what's our lineage
so there are stabilizing forces and um
and then there's uh then there's equanimity and that our heart
uh doesn't um depend on samsara
that um Anita of course
um can be is heartbreaking
but um the momentariness of change
that River with no banks actually comes to feel can feel like a refuge
and because we we know ourselves as part of that River as made of change
it's like uh nothing can collide with
our heart
so I offer this for your consideration
and uh
yeah appreciate what's uh just caught a
glimpse of the the chat before I started talking appreciate it what is happening there
so um yeah may you um may you all be well may we be well