go okay all right all deployment plural can I say that right
preliminaries are done so hi hello and welcome everyone to happy hour it's so
lovely to have you and from so many different places on this Earth so many
different time zones so so uh
let's start practicing together and I'll share the theme during the guided
meditation and I'll say a couple words about it later so let's just jump in let's just jump in together
so finding finding your ease finding
finding your seat finding your seat on this Earth
bringing awareness actually your sitting bones let's start there today
sitting Bones the connection of your
bottom with the cushioned with the chair and your feet your legs with the Earth
picking your seat
taking your seat
and letting your sitting posture
sitting
or maybe standing or lying down whatever is appropriate but I'm gonna assume sitting for now
your paws should be informed let it rise up and it have a sense of uprightness
sense of dignity taking your place on this Earth
just as the but I touched the Earth it is said
the night of his enlightenment when he was being assailed by Mara the
personification of doubt challenges
hindrances and he touched the Earth's Earth be my witness I belong here
taking his place on the earth a human being just like us
it's called the Earth mudra could see it on lots of statutes that put a touching their Earth
with his hand let us touch the Earth with our feet other sit bones
touching the Earth this Earth be my witness I am on this
Earth
breathing living contributing interconnected taking my place on this
Earth let there be a sense of a brightness of
taking your place you matter you matter I matter
I matter I am part of this
amazing mystery called life I am Stardust
it's amazing that I exist this being who's me
let the breath his body knows how to breathe this
mystery of the universe that is you
now let the breath breathe you breath knows how to breathe you already don't make it into a project
breath knows how to breathe you so relax soften enjoy
the breath being received in your abdomen and your sit bones
your hands and feet in your spine
in your heart
and let your heart rest with the breath picking your seat
nowhere to go nothing to do releasing thoughts
and the to-do list making Refuge
the Simplicity of this
and if thoughts arise not treating them as a problem
or distraction perhaps with amazement wow
this mind and think and think of so many thoughts
and memories wow the sense of awe appreciation
for this mind and then thanking it
thank you dear mind thanks for trying to take care of me entertain me
think you're amazing and invited to soften and relax in this
moment resting with thought resting with the
breath
with appreciation
yes this breath
in this body how amazing the body knows how to
breathe so much more
receiving the breath with awe with appreciation
feeling embodied settled
let yourself enjoy the breath relax apply to your laps enjoying the breath
it's okay to enjoy the wholesomeness
be enjoyed
and if there is a little voice that says no I'm not supposed to enjoy my meditation
As You Are let go of that
misguided Puritan
judgment thanks for your help but it's wholesome
to enjoy and practice
foreign
delightful reward
in this cultivation
the happiness of sitting and being breathed and knowing
the happiness of awareness simply knowing
it's delicious
even if we are knowing to God we're knowing what's challenging
not pushing it away not fighting with it but just knowing it
knowing what is present there was a delight to knowing even knowing dukkha knowing challenges
body can relax the heart can relax
knowing this
the light of knowing and nourishment of knowing
the awesomeness of knowing
pleasure of knowing whatever is arising in the Here and Now
breath Sensations whatever it is relax
enjoy knowing
pleasure of mindfulness
if opening to all phenomena thought Sensations emotions is too much
and stay with the pleasure the pleasure of knowing the breath
and nourishment of knowing the breath Sensations Here
and Now
calming soothing
settling
relishing the pleasure the Delight of awareness
Here and Now
your mind knows this your heart knows how to do this
such a respite respite from the busyness of the day our
lives just the pleasure the loveliness of knowing this whatever
this is the breath the sensations
in light of knowing that you're thinking and thought is happening in this moment
really needing the knowing
as we explore as we open our hearts our minds to the Delight the pleasure of
knowing
of being aware of being mindful without resistance
without pushing away aversion knowing whatever is here
breath Sensations thoughts pain
there is a delight pleasure wholesome pleasure in knowing
and meeting this the truth of this moment
not resisting
making space for knowing permeate
to hold whatever is you're such a delight
how much are Delight
and into the last minutes of this practice period
let us experiment experiment with wearing a little smile
meeting yourself with knowing knowing whatever's present in this
moment
it's a gesture of kindness geshire of appreciation for the knowing
knowing what is and see how a smile might shift
as if our arms are wide open embracing the moment
knowingly it's like this WOW amazing
yay let your heart smile
even if it's knowing challenges pain to come
it's a gift to know
and moved upright we have so much more capacity than we
give ourselves credit for
as we approach the end of this sitting period is practice
saying our own goodness appreciating and we showed up we did our best
even if there was one moment of awareness of knowing yay infinitely more
infinitely Lovelier and zero moments of knowing awareness
appreciating this being who is me has showed up the support
myself and others in this cultivation
trusting there is goodness plans seeds have been planted seeds of goodness planted and together
sharing this goodness with all beings everywhere may all beings taste their own goodness
the goodness of knowing
may they open up the mystery to the awe
tiling a seat on this planet however challenging it might seem
may all beings be free may all beings be well including myself
thank you all thank you for your practice
I'll say a couple of words about what we did tonight
so I invited us to first start with selling with the body
a sense of connection of the sit Bones the feet with the body with the Earth
and the sense of letting our s letting us take our seat on this Earth just as
the Buddha did letting there be a sense of a brightness of awe that we are part of this amazing
world this and this body knows how to breathe it has so many capacities and
then I invited us to feel into the Delight the pleasure first with the
breath and then knowing there is Delight there's just built-in delight and joy
that we often miss to know to to be aware in the Here and
Now that no matter what it is we are knowing breath Sensations thoughts Etc and again
at first we get our training wheels just knowing the breath knowing the perhaps
the comfortable areas of the body then we open up more and more to other phenomena and and then when we even know
dukkha when we know suffering when we know challenge pain in the heart or in the body there is a light I know that for myself
and I know that from many many practitioners there is the sense of delight to know actually to meet what's
challenging so they're pushing it away or or not going to deal with it being afraid of it all but seeing it just
knowing it always like this oh there's a sense of a brightness there's a sense of strength pleasure Delight
and another thing that I invited us to feel into and bring in was enjoying the
Delight the pleasure of of practice the breath the body because sometimes
Buddhism get gets this bad rap about being a joy denying practice like you're
not supposed to enjoy your practice you're supposed to concentrate on
couldn't be further from the truth and so much longer talk but but um
enjoy without attaching without grasping like I want more but when it's here of
course enjoy it take Delight in the Delight that's present now if you I want oh that thing
that just happened I want more of that no that will be cause of suffering so don't do that but when it's here just
enjoy and Let It Go like the poem uh I'll maybe I'll grab it
when you're in in breakout rooms or one who kisses the joy as it flies
um lives in eternity's Sunrise so with that I'd like to invite us now
turn to turn to practicing in small groups maybe groups of three you'll be
about six or seven minutes roughly and and the prompt is
um again you can pass when your turn comes you can just say pass and and hold
um silence hold kind silence for yourself and for others you don't have to share
when your turn comes and let's Go reverse alphabetical order and when your
turn comes um if you want to share something about how this was for you oh yeah I related
or it wasn't or I related with but the body but not with the cow or wow was
amazing it actually lit up or I slept the whole time I just woke up it's
perfectly fine there are no wrong answers it's just showing up and and and
being held witness with community and holding others witness so
you'll have the chance to maybe share for a minute the next person if they want they'll share for a minute the next
person for a minute and then you have a chance to add some more so so let it not be a long monologue just a nugget and go
around and run and again you can always say pass and we share from our own experience we don't ask questions or
give advice uh just I statements um so creating a a offering each other
kindness this is really where the practice meets the rubber meets the road
offering each other kindness and um and acceptance what whatever they say
couldn't couldn't be greater couldn't be better um not you know asking questions or
interrogating okay so I've created the rooms again take care of yourselves take care of each other what a great
opportunity to to uh chat with a couple of other
um practitioners about this practice again The Prompt has to do with how is this practice of finding joy and feeling
into the joy the light of knowing knowing what's here right now and also wearing a smile I
forgot that wearing a smile at the end all right here we go enjoy take care of each other take care
of yourselves opening all rooms
five more seconds and while we're waiting okay I think the rooms are closed okay everybody's back and
and uh great so we have some time for for reflection especially if you haven't
shared in a while or love to ask you to pull forward uh Richard your hand shut
up what's up
mute okay um I tonight I I wish I could have heard
the summary of The Meditation before the meditation
because you know the because it's almost like I keep on getting
my attention is always torn between let's say my breath and the instructions
and I think for me it would be easier to hear the general outline ahead of time
so it would be easier to like follow it
yeah yeah okay I appreciate hearing that um and
and yet there are advantages I I I I see both I think there are advantages and
disadvantages to both and sometimes I do it that way and sometimes I do it the other way so yeah thanks for for your
feedback Richard I appreciate that for you hearing the the instructions while I'm giving them out loud for some people
actually kind of not overloading at the beginning but just giving it piece by piece like oh yeah
here we are but but I appreciate both ways thanks for sharing that Richard
foreign hi
um the part I really liked was when you said you don't have to be a Puritan it's okay to enjoy it
which I took to add to my practice and also um you know just like why can't I
just add some warmth to the breath here instead of it just being clinically the breath
and then I was also applying it to like oh I don't have to be a Puritan and be
so serious when I'm getting through my list of things work I do all day it's like ah this would have to be a
Puritan I love that yay yay thanks Susan so having descended
from one it's in my bloodline
yeah yeah and and also it's it's again in the west it feels like it's so much
part of the perceived Buddhist teachings to be so serious and awakened and
whereas actually they light and joy and pleasure are really important part of
the path really important um so yeah thanks Susan I appreciate I
appreciate how that how you share that really uh uh clicked for you yeah may
you have joy may you enjoy all everything you do during the day not just the breath but everything everything on your to-do list
Kenneth please um yeah so um
I enjoy sometimes not knowing because you have some nice Buddhist tricks
like will said loving kindness out to other everybody else for 20 minutes and then all of a sudden we'll send it back
to us we'll go whoa and that that really works so as I call
it a Buddhist trick um I have a a little this is not a big issue but sometimes I wake up and I
don't feel good so I do uh Tomlin practice
I don't have trouble stopping it it just wants to go on and on you know
why is that a problem wait so just just for references when you
mentioned tongling just for for folks who may not know what that is that's a beautiful beautiful Buddhist uh
Tibetan Buddhist practice of of taking in breathing in the The Suffering of
other suffering of herself suffering of the world suffering breathing and suffering and and and imagining that the
heart transforms it into peace into into sucker and then breathing it out in such
a beautiful practice so with every breath it feels like oh we're bringing peace and goodness to ourselves to
others it's it's a lovely practice it's breathing with breathing with suffering and transforming it so that's what Ken
is talking about what's the problem for it wanting to continue to go on I'm not sure
it is a very nice breakfast I love it oh it's a lovely lovely so so but I'm
I feel like a problem can you just go on or is it a problem let's explore that I
cuddle babies at the hospital no and I use Tylenol with the babies all time
because I'm just breathing out love and kindness to them and breathing in I don't know some kind
of suffering so I I don't know it's just once I started it in the morning if I'm half asleep it just goes on and on and
on shouldn't I stop this at some point oh my God are you kidding me I'm just I'm
loving and other I see other hearts and thumbs up showing up on on um on Zoom like people I I think we're
all supporting you can keep keep doing it it's lovely that it's become so
I'm still free so lovely that it's become natural for you so oh my goodness this is this
actually let's celebrate it and and their mind that them peace of mind that
comes and says oh um shouldn't I stop this the answer is why are you asking me who are you making
a problem on it from something that's actually a beautiful cultivation you've
cultivated it so much that it's now become an automatic response to the
suffering of the world it's I I give an example of my own practice I've done these practices that they just
show up like when I'm doing nothing or I'm swimming or I'm just breathing or I'm sitting it just shows up or even the
words sometimes show up safe happy healthy ease they just show up like oh
how nice they're comforting and they show outside so this is this is the
fruit of your cultivation Ken enjoy it thank you so much for sharing that all
beings support you in in doing that that's that's lovely
great that's lovely yeah so Claire I see your hand
oh I think that was maybe okay all right so so I Claire disappeared all right so
let's let's close let's close and uh and dedicate the Merit of our practice
um oh actually you know what maybe before we close I do want to ask you questions if anybody wants to reflect on
this um did any of you feel did any of you feel into or or have an opening or an
aha moment into that what I was guiding you especially the you know the big topic of tonight the Delight the
pleasure of knowing it's just so pleasant or was that just the doll again
of course we know that or was like wow there's pleasure here in knowing whatever it is
was it a dahlia of course or was it an aha moment for anyone well I wonder
let's see I see a thumbs up is that you want to talk or are you just giving a thumbs up and I'm not quite sure who's giving the thumbs up and the long list
of people uh you want to raise your hand maybe that was just a thumbs up
so which one
who is it all right Neil okay Neil you get the last word I'm going to choose C
it was like what is she talking about I I
you know right right in fact it was what is she talking about and when is this meditation over right so there was like
frustration restlessness all kind of like bundled in you know that said you
know I felt very peaceful and it was all kind of nice right but but when you were saying that I'm like
I love it so so that it that that peace and and it kind of being nice it's well
well when you were saying it it wasn't right right you're saying it definitely like left me frustrated right but but
afterward right which I must be honest this isn't the this isn't the first or the 100th and
first time that that you know that's happened right I hear the instruction and I'm like this is dumb right but then
but then like maybe it works you know so
yeah and so so so no no your track record Neil with your
with you know the the goodness of your practice and you know this reflection of this is dumb you know it comes up a lot
and the frustration and and maybe what in this case what I would invite you to oh actually I missed there was a diff
there was a reflection there I love the Delight in knowing it was a huge opening oh Mary uh thank you Mary I didn't see
your reflection earlier thank you for that so um yeah so so with what you said
Anil I think what I would invite you is to to get to know the frustration
because there is a no so so what if you actually know the frustration instead of
right so so that's where the Aikido I think some of the Aikido movements of of
awareness and mindfulness like what was it actually just to know it oh yeah I'm frustrated in this there's frustration
there's arising ah wow there's a delight in turning out of it and actually
knowing it instead of being in it yeah so that's the invitation I'll give
you if you decide to continue to practice with this so so thank you thank
you all for your practice and and uh how wonderful and and may you may you open
up to the Delight to the pleasure of knowing may it open up for you there's such a joy to know may all beings be
well may all beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone see one