welcome to uh a Friday morning here in
IMC Insight Meditation Center in Redwood City California
and I'm here welcoming you all from my own home
is about half an hour away from IMC
so good and to see the chat messages flowing in
okay
they're so sweet to have being with you this a whole week in the morning mornings for myself
this enjoying reading the chat messages and feeling a sense of
um Global Sangha here all together
so we will begin momentarily um
diving through our meditation
and so if you like to join me [Music] um please find a posture that's a
supportive of her um meditative for practice for about half an hour
yeah to begin maybe you just if your eyes are still on the computer
screen is allow the chat messages to flow
through soft eyed
feeling a sense of a Sangha right here
now we're practicing together as a community
an ancient tradition
and when you're ready you can gently close your eyes
or look down softly
allow our energy in the thinking
planning to turn inward
this meditation is an explicit
form to gather our attention
collect our attention
so we're entering into here and now
deliberate and kind
of feeling and sensing the global
sense of the body sitting lying down
in different dimensions of our being heart mind and body
began to come together as a whole
maybe a sense of all Gathering into
and through the posture we're taking
the pelvic floor the lower half of the body
feel steady set out
grounded
earthy body resting on Earth
from a grounded a place there is a natural uplift in the Torso
all the way through neck head
and it feels as you've all aspects all around
Within ourselves and out outside of ourselves
are gathering here through the body
what a wonder that the Earth's element is naturally grounding
settling and relatively unmoving
offering grounding for our heart to mind right here
the Stillness in the body is a felt
right here
borrowing an image on my teacher
like a stones in the riverbed
quiet Stillness is felt
maybe there is a hint of it
are just a hint of a possibility
however it may show up for you
Stillness in the body naturally highlights the movements
without looking for or searching
it's natural the movements of the body to be known
movements of the breath
the sound vibration of the sounds
tinkling Sensations
maybe on the fingertips Palms
areas of Stillness in the body there is a movement
in the body
feeling and sensing the movements
feeling and sensing is a raw
Direct without the need for
words ideas
whatever you feel is just right
letting go of the judgments comparisons
evaluations
resting in the Simplicity of your experience
noticing
rather than knowing capacity or the knowing
of the movements can be quiet
and distill
emotions and thoughts they may pull through
you may feel it somatically energetically
as some sort of movements wavelets in the body
and just in the energetic field
there is a Stillness silence
in the knowing
in the feeling
in the sensing
emotions can be strong
or mild and soft
however it is quietly
lovingly receiving them
being available
[Music] shifts
changes in the inner ecology
of our being
this Stillness and quiet that you feel
do not need a location
may feel pervasive all around
while the movements in the body mind and heart
are happening
if the Mind becomes busy
this body is a refuge
you're always return to the felt sense
of the Earth element
s in the riverbed
movements of the breath
a quiet humming in the body
being available to feel
sense deeply
in this line that my their drama buddy
said in the last Retreat stayed with me
our practice is not about
feeling good
instead or cultivating
a capacity to feel deeply
and feel and sense the depth of our being
the vastness of our being
noticing not the Stillness and the movements
have no boundaries
Flux Of happenings are just a flux of the happiness
center of a Stillness is everywhere
maybe this is a hint my hint of a hint
my hint of a possibility
just being easily satisfied
however it is for you
the dance of Our Lives happen in all forms
all kinds of shapes texture
being available
warm welcome of all forms
in a warm welcome that's all forms in all beings
deep bounds to each other to ourselves
into the possibility of a boundless
loving quiet hearts
[Music]
foreign
for me to transition into
a Dharma talk the dharmette and today I brought
a story of a modern day Giant in the terravada we discussing
and I use the word Giant to describe
how she was a human being with immense heart mind qualities
immense goodness in her heart and mind
even though physically she's quite small
and so this is the story of dipaman
I'm going to show the pictures some of you might know her or
no aphaher or maybe have read the book or heard the stories about her in various
Dharma talks and so why dipama
I want to start with a story and this is a story told by
Maria Monroe who's one of the senior teravada practitioners in the western
teravada scene and this was the time when dipama and
Maria were on an airplane coming to the United States from India a flight was
very turbulent at one point the flight hit an air
pocket and dropped as the drinks and stuff all flew up in
the ceiling and um
you know it took a moment for the airplane to finally settle to kind of a stable air
and so Maria kind of screamed a bit and diploma was sitting right across the
aisle from her and so she reached out and took her her hand
and it just held it and then at some point
and a deep amount whispered to her the daughters of the Buddha are fearless
this is Steve among The Fearless daughter of the Buddha
so what was her path how did she come to
this possibility of fearlessness
and so she was born 1911 in India and passed away in 1989 that her life
actually overlapped with mine and so I kind of there is some sort of a
warmth in my heart um connecting to this and so she got
married when she was 12 12 year old and maybe this was
kind of the way back then and she moved with her husband from
India to Burma because he had a work in Burma
and I in the early years maybe not just early
for a couple of decades she wasn't able to conceive to have the babies
was not until mid-30s she began to be able to conceive
that was a daunting period as well she lost two babies
early on shortly after birth and I was only able to keep one daughter
and this daughter's name is Deepa and so she's known as the mother of the of the
daughter Deepa and so her name is known as dipama
and so you can see this was immensely painful for people
and so she got very sick she had heart disease high blood
pressure other things so she was bedridden for many months she couldn't
get out and her husband was a very kind soul and
very gentle and kind and loving and so uh he um
not only had to take care of the deepama and the Deepa but also had to work
through time in order to keep the family going so one day he came home
not feeling well and died
so this was a a Breaking Point
and dipama was in her early 50s without health
work support and had to support her young daughter
and without health and so she didn't know what to do anymore
and ever since she was a little girl so she always wanted it to meditate so she
decided that she had to go visit a meditation center in Burma uh she didn't
know what else to do so she sorted out all her belongings
and give it to her neighbor and asked them to take care of the depot
and in her own mind she thought she would never return probably
and so she went on to her first Meditation Retreat
when she arrived at the center she was offered with some basic meditation
instructions and a room and so she began to practice
and very quickly she got very concentrated and she was so concentrated that one day
she didn't realize a dog was biting her leg she couldn't move she just saw a
thought she couldn't move for her leg but she wasn't aware that the dog was biting her leg
not until she turned around and looked dead the dog
while the kids and you know the dog bites made her very
weak and so she was sent home and she didn't complete her first
retreat and yet just with some of this basic
meditation instructions and she began to practice at home
whenever and however she was able to do it and she also had an opportunity to
um meet a teacher who actually spoke her own language in her home state
I didn't mention that you know and she was a living or in Burma and and she
didn't speak the local language that was yet another challenge
and so this new teacher whose name is anagarika munindraji
I taught her meditation
um and so with this instructions she progressed rather quickly and
dramatically within Sometimes some period of time
and the Dharma began to transform her in ways that
she could never have imagined first her blood pressure was gone
high blood pressure was gone and she was no longer so sickly all the
time and she had much more energy
and this uh offered such immense trust and faith in
the practice and quickly she had a deep insights into
the Dharma and so she just gave herself completely over
to the practice and so this was um what was that in the
um descriptions about her as even as a widowed a single mother
trying to undertake her spiritual path within the confines of a patriarchal and
a hierarchical buddhistamanastic system Department never doubted that she could
reach the highest to go at that time and place there was no such
thing as the woman's Liberation movement dipama simply liberated herself
and so she once remarked I had no fear
and I am at peace now
and so that was such an immense transformation that became possible for her
and that's in the midst of the ups and downs the turmoilers of her life
and indeed a deeper continue to face all kinds of challenges
uh after this period of life in Burma
in 1967 56 year old
Burma and Burmese government asked all foreigners to leave the country
and she had to leave with her daughter to go back to India
and so they moved into a tiny small apartment in Calcutta and that's where dipama
began her Dharma teaching career in this tiny apartment
maybe one of the most significant equalities of dipama was
embodied the Dharma and she taught her students
whatever you're doing be aware of it ironing nursing cooking
[Music] nothing is outside of the practice domain
and so one of her students said she's the patron saint of the
householders I was a very athlete uplifting for me
and in a way that kind of she's a Superhero
woman in my heart if I'm allowed to have a superhero in my
state of I guess a field of consciousness and so her teachings in some ways change
the how I practiced I remember shortly after giving birth to
my son I realized that my life was more or less kind of turned upside down with
diapers bottles sleepless nights and hormone changes in the body and all
sorts of things and it was a phase of my life where I
had so much enthusiasm for retreat practice and it was very clear that I couldn't do
the kind of retreat practice that I used to do so that was devastating to me
but I remembered dipama and she taught the nursing mothers to
practice while they were nursing she taught the busy students to practice and where they were in school
and somehow remembering the stories opened myself up
to a whole new way of practicing that I never imagined
I began to realize oh there may be kind of new possibilities for me here
and I decided that I wasn't going to wait for the next retreat
and the practice can start where I was
and so that was um kind of a turning moment for my Dharma
Journey and my practice began to expand
gradually and little by little I wanted to say emphasize on this word
gradually because it wasn't like it was life-changing in the moment it was a
gradual process and it's still on voting even to the state
but as I opened to all these different forms of a practice in my life and
um it enriched my practice deepened it
and I had so much confidence and Trust in it
and says this were the teachings of the deepama a profound householder Drama teacher
and she was said that um A's path wasn't attached to a particular
place teacher lifestyle or the monastic model
the world was her monastery
and she was a teacher for many or as she taught some of the senior
Western teravada teachers in our own lineage in Jack cornfield
Joseph Augustine Sharon sasberg
and she had taught a three-month retreat in inside meditation Society
but I want to wrap up this week's great women disciples stories of the
Buddha by saying that
stories are not meant to intimidate us ask us to become them
or something like that I'd like to read the afterword in this
dipama book that I was showing that's written by Jack hornfield
who summarized the point that I I was hoping to make much better than what I
could come up with and this is what he said
simply beings whether they are the Dalai Lama Mother Teresa dipama
or a thousand unknown simply beings living among ourselves
share the same fundamental characteristics of selflessness
great compassion and a peace each one of us can carry deepamas Legacy
in terms of having that much peace and love
it takes its own time yet it's possible for anyone
in the end the point is not to be like dipama or some other great Yogi or Saint
you might read about or hear about the point is something much more
difficult to be yourself and to discover that all you seek
is to be found Here and Now in your own heart
thank you everyone [Music]
[Music]
it was so good to be with you all this week and you will be accompanied by Diana
Clark my Dharma sister and so uh you'll be in good company
and so be well everyone