wow just hearing the announcement that you feel the vibrancy of the community
and so welcome welcome joining us together here physically in IMC and also on
YouTube so knowing that we have a broader Sangha all around
and I also uh mentioned that the potluck welcomes everyone
um because it's us getting together to celebrate the significant occasion
and so you have value can stay around and join us afterwards
so today the topic I brought with me is the Buddhist teachings on the four Great
elements or five and sometimes there's six and so I'm just gonna say elements
okay and this is uh in some way it wasn't
planned but I was kind of just happened to follow on Kim Allen's 7 A.M this last
week's meditation and the elements as well
and so for those who didn't get the chance to participate on the 7 A.M and I
just offer a little background on this teachings of
the element and the four or five or six
elements are often known as the earth water
Fire and Air and then sometimes the fifth would be the space
and sometimes the six is the Consciousness and today we're just mostly in the four and five territory
first of four and five and that the fire element sometimes is
translated as a heat element so you see those words as well and the error
element sometimes is translated as a wind winter element so you may hear
those interchangeably and these are the basic elements that
make up the world we live in and the planet we're living the Earth underneath
of us and as well as this body his body is made of this set of elements
and the different Are Spiritual and religious Traditions often relate to the
set of elements in quite significant ways you probably know this and that the
indigenous people are often called the stores of the Earth they protect the Earth
the land like protecting our own bodies
our own lives and so 2600 years ago in the Buddhist
times people also knew about this elements and
there are some significance in the culture as well
and so I wanted to share some teachings specifically from the Buddha about the
elements and I'd like to start with the teaching that the Buddha offered to his son
rahula and for those who are interesting studying sutas and as a story is
documented in number 62 and the rahula
and we decided that this teaching was offered to rahula when he was kind of a
young adult maybe late things or early 20s
and one day and the Buddha got up in the morning and ready to go for armstrand
and then so when he got up and then bahula got up as well and Then followed
the Buddha and to go for arms round and so here they are you know the Buddha on
the front rahula on the back following him and this is the one rahula has been in
the monastic community for more than probably a decades now and
so it was said that he was ordained as a young boy seven-year-old boy
and kind of the you know the father brought him into the monastic Sangha a
monastic community and um
so here they are and the Buddha walking the front and the leader of the community the
enlightened the awakened being and rahula the
um young maybe handsome young men following the Buddha
and I get a sense that there may be a certain attitude and
rahula was talking with behind the Buddha as the Buddha had a little sense
and maybe rahula has some something you know going on so the Buddha looked back and said to
rahula rahula you should truly see any kind of
a form at all past future or present internal or external course or fine
inferior or Superior far or near all form with wise
understanding this is not mine I am not this this is not myself
and so I want to just pause and say a few words that I wasn't going to offer this teaching this is a kind of a
separate teaching altogether but here the form refers to the material aspects
of our beings that you know material body and the bones the Flesh and
uh physicality of our bodies and so the Buddha said I can you should
see all this and that is not from the perspective of I mean mine
and I get the sense that um rahula might have heard this teachings before
he asked only form the Buddha went on told the rahula that
well also don't take your feelings or your perceptions your mental Fabrications or
even Consciousness to be I Me Mine and so this is known to be the five
cleaning Aggregates it's not self-teaching which I will not do today
if you're interested some other time or you can look at look it up and
but this is the bridge of this story um
the Buddha may have had the sense that the rahula is and was caught up a little bit by who he
was and how he was related to the Buddha and who knows you know we don't really know but the Buddha might have sensed to
something going on here and what happened next as rahula decided
I am not going to go to the village for obstract so so he thought who would go to the
village for arms today after being advised directly by the Buddha so I'm so
human so you know you're a teenager you got a
advised by your parents what are you gonna do and I still couldn't follow
them around nope no way so I turned the bag
sat down and started meditating instead of going for
the food I smell protest
and so right then and there and
and there's a great disciple of the Buddha sarepota Sarah hula and
he told the rahula that you should do mindfulness a breathing is this practice offers a lot of benefit
and later in the evening came out from the meditation and went to see the
Buddha I guess he's got a question to ask and
you know he knew the Buddha would have Buddha would have the answer for him
and so he wasn't holding The Grudge so much and so he got up I went to see the Buddha
and he asked the Buddha how is it to that mindfulness of
breathing when you practice it there will be a lot of benefit but the interesting thing about this the
Buddha didn't answer this question right away instead the Buddha offered him the instructions
on how to practice with the elements first
so nabuda pointed out that in this body there are Earth elements so we can feel
the Earth Earth elements that are solid hard the bones you know our bones our
teeth and hair and it's our Earth element right here in our bodies
and there's water element you can feel the moisture or the oil and the on the
hands and a fluid in the body as I talk I feel the saliva in the mouth
in the mouth this is a water element and there is
Air element we breathe in and out the movements
and there's a fire element and so the Buddha offered the teaching
and in quite a lot of detail with all the examples of what this is in your
experience in the body in the elemental nature and the Buddha and each of the
instruction with a statement Earth element is just Earth element
the water element is just a water element and the fire element is justifier
element Air element just Earth adjust air
element a space element just a space element
so what is the Buddha pointing to with this teaching
and seeing our meditation we offered this briefly and kind of really feeling and sensing
into our experience in this Elemental way the Buddha is teasing this kind of
and the concept of the body with all this Elemental aspect of our
being which we can experience it directly Here and Now
and also the reason that the Buddha offered this teaching
is that the Buddha knows our mind very well and those how our mind works
so often when we experience something that are quite immediate raw Elemental
oftentimes our mind immediately will follow along
with a different kind of reality virtual reality
and we may have a little moment that we feel some dryness and a skin
it's just a water element just the dryness the Earth element just Earth element the
water element just water element oh we don't stop there you know what
happens right away oh I really should drink more water
I haven't been drinking so much water as I'm aging that's not good for me
and I have been using this moisturizer for a while it probably hasn't been working for a while
maybe it's time to search around and see a better brand there's a lot more
you know I don't know new ingredients and new technologies that are working and next thing you know wearing the
Amazon land so
that's how our mind works you know kind of we slip off from this raw direct
experience and and I lump into
and as stories of our experience about our experiences sometimes it's not even
about our experience anymore but about something totally different
and that may be filled with desires identifications aversions
and so that's the and that's the thing that Buddha already knew very well how our mind works
and so um and often and you know what I'm telling
in this particular example is quite a mild and benign version you know and
then sometimes I can see that in my own mind the stories can be much more
dramatic much more exciting or disappointing and and what's more is
that often there can be a kind of a storyline underneath of it
that I'm never good enough I should be who somebody else I should
be something other than who I am how I am is that there can be this kind of a
storyline running through this and so by offering uh this instruction
and to practice over the elements the Buddha is offering us an opportunity to
live more in line with the reality of our lived experience
and rather that in the virtual realities that we're constructing our mind and heart
and so the Earth element just as Earth element not more complicated than that
maybe that's what the young rahula needed before he get to the instructions on
mindfulness of breathing maybe got caught up a little bit you
know by who he was and how he looked and his identities
and so he needed some instruction to kind of drop out and those
um beliefs and ideas in the head and then drop more directly into the
embodied experience foreign
that the Buddha also offered in satipatana suta which is one of the
seminal texts in the Pali Canon that spoke about how the practitioners
to how the practitioner practitioners with the practice in order to become
free from suffering and many of the theravada meditative
practices are taught based on on this text nasati patana
and as a one of the mindfulness of the body instructions
um that is this and the practice of what the the elements
so it's not just rahula where you know we may get caught by the stories of our
experience and it's common that when our mind and
heart are not trained we tend to go into our stories and beliefs
so when we are in touch with the realities of our bodies at the
elementary level we can begin to see our experience just as they are
and so some years ago I had an experience in working with this
particular practice and so it's a period at the time that I
was practicing on the Society of Elemental element practice and some Associated
practice rather continuously for a few weeks and so one day I was dropping my son off
at his swim practice and it just right around the swimming
pool I saw all those little kids running around and and all of a sudden there was thoughts
came to my mind I was a little girl is so cute this one is a little clumsy and I just
you know all of a sudden I thought wow this thoughts is here
and maybe just because there was some continuity of the practice and and all
of a sudden what I saw was all the kids turned into
skeletons the little skeletons running around the swimming pool
and immediately I noticed a contrast in my mind
that is all those little preferences likes and dislikes faded away
and that what that moment was a powerful moment I just realized wow this practice has a function
it has a potent function it can kind of pull us out of the
stories the likes and dislikes and the Habit mind and highlight
for us their presence in the absence as it was really a powerful moment for
me now recognizing wow this practice really has some strong
potency for us that was also quite humble to buy it
and so I and the other thing I wanted to say is
when there's a highlight on is becomes available what also becomes available is
a sense of a choice and that's the moment that we can choose can choose to follow the storyline
probably usually not go that well or we could choose to drop into our
immediate experience and so that's another form of empowerment that this practice can offer
that when we pause when we see things directly in the Raw
Elemental way we also began to have choices we can make wise choices
it may seem quite innocent sometimes that we have this kind of thoughts and
and some may even seem harmless after all I just kind of you know a few
fleeting thoughts in the mind yet when we reflect deeper
our ideas our beliefs about good and bad inferior Superior
beautiful ugly when those Harden into beliefs
they've been such dividing forces in our societies
and so this practice um offers something
to take us out of that divide that can really separate ourselves from
others and so um
by practicing with this it has a direct impact in our own our well-being and
also the World At Large the well-being of the World At Large
and also I want to say that this example doesn't mean that we should flatten the life just by only seeing elements
uh after all there is richness in life
in fact I would like to say that by practicing with elements
there is much life aliveness and the richness that can come forth
through experiencing um the ever-changing dynamic of the
elements there is a dance of the elements right here in our being
can you imagine that we don't have Earth element hearing the body it'll be all floating
around I know or without air element who can't even
live and the air element animates us that's how we can move we can walk we can run
even just lift our hand that's Air element in the body
and the water elements is a cohesive cohesiveness brings all of those
elements together like you know the the water sprinkle on the flower to need
need the doll kind of brings it together into something that we actually sit here with a sitting posture that's a water
element holding us together otherwise they'll just be dust sand here
and so there is all this dance and that elements are working through us that
bring a liveness and richness in our being so through this practice we can really
get a deep in touch with this and this is also to see that when we're
experiencing uh in this Elemental way we can also come
to realize that this is nature this is a nature of the nature just like
the mountain the trees the flowers the Earth were on
those are nature this is the Earth element resting on
Earth and so there is a nature within us there
is a nature without right around us
so when we have this kind of a realization um our relationships with ourselves
and that is all around us can begin to shift and change
if we care about this body this being
we care about the beings all around we care about the Earth we stand on
said this the Earth is you
you are the Earth when you realize there is no separation
you fall completely in love with this beautiful planet
at this very moment the Earth is above you
below you all around you and even inside you
I'm just gonna pause for a moment what's the feeling in your heart when
you hear that
in the Love Letter tikna Han wrote to Earth he says this
we often forget that the planet we're living on has given us all the elements
that make up our bodies the water in our flesh our bones
and all the microscopic cells inside our bodies all come from the Earth
and are part of the Earth the Earth is not just the environment we
live in we are the Earth and we're always carrying her within us
realizing this we can see that the Earth is truly alive
we are a living breathing manifestations of this beautiful and generous planet
knowing this we can begin to transform our relationship to the Earth
we can begin to walk differently and to care for her differently
and I would like to extend this even further
besides the Earth underneath of us all of us
other beings ourselves our nature
animals animated inanimated
all beings all things we live in a network of connectedness
we can't live without them just as how we may transform our
relationship with the planet maybe this practice offers a potential and a possibility and
how we relate to each other related to ourselves
related to all beings
in this way we can go beyond the self-centeredness
and this is what the Buddha offered to rahula
and thus should be seen where the wise understanding that this is not mine I am
not this this is not myself and instead we extend our heart to mind
where the botanists boundless love compassion
sympathetic Joy and equanimity and that's what the Buddha instructed
the rahula Maybe by dropping away in a sense of I
mean mine the heart can open and so following the element instruction
the Buddha taught rahula to meditate with love
meditate with compassion meditate with joy
and meditate with equanimity and so the heart is ready
the element practice sets a stage for our heart to open
and to welcome all beings everywhere
so may this teaching offer this possibility to all of us
and to live with the reality of our own nature
and to love and care for all beings everywhere
so thank you everyone
so we have a few minutes if there are any questions comments
Reflections that you may have you're welcome
um I can't remember if I read middle length discourse number 62 before
or not so uh but now I want to read it
or go back and read it as soon as I have an opportunity at the time
uh I also uh wanted to say that like I think everyone here I was really divided
by the image you brought up of looking around and seeing everyone as skeletons
whenever and I don't know if I can be detached enough whenever I'm
noticing I have a preference or you know a like or dislike towards someone
to look at them that way I don't know if I can be that detached but so what I do instead if I remember to is to look on
other people especially if I'm noticing a preference or dispreference and seeing a fellow
sufferer that's what works for me beautiful beautiful so there are ways that we can
shift our Perceptions in a way that is supportive
for cultivation of a wholesome in wholesomeness in our mind and heart so
there are many ways that we can see that can be supportive great thank you yeah
someone in the back
okay um yeah so thank you for sharing your story there's a camera right behind you
um so you share that uh before you went to the swimming pool with your son you
saw the skeletons and before that you had weeks of um practice I'm just curious about what
kind of practice you were doing for a week was it just like meditation like all day every day or yeah so so it was
as part of a course I was taking and that and this said of element practices
were part of and seeing things in this different ways are part of the practice
and so I was quite consciously kind of practicing just
um wherever I was around and doing things and in this
particular moment I think it was just natural momentum of the practice came
live I wasn't intentionally trying to do anything but just came alive it's like oh wow
there is this way of seeing and then I highlighted something and so um it could
be sometimes uh people do and you know seeing something as skeleton as explicit
practice um but I think for me it was really working with the elements somehow that
just arose yeah thank you
any other questions or comments
there well we do for the YouTube for okay
excuse me all right hello YouTube um I really enjoyed what you had to share
today and I wanted to share uh an experience that I'm having
that is related just because it so reflects the importance of our honoring
Mother Earth each other the elements I I feel minimizing to say
elements but even so um I have begun working with a beautiful
team of women who are doing something called surf therapy at some point I will
be posting something here and the focus of it is being in the ocean being near the water
and that connection the ways that it heals us the ways that it lightens us
all the magic that goes on there and so the timeliness of connecting this to my
practice I appreciate very very much and just the reminder to all of us that
we can live it yes go out and live it and feed it and nourish it and I think
that that's one way to sustain and ride the waves of life too yes thank you very
much yeah beautiful thank you for that reflection and what you brought it to me was also
sometimes it's just working in the garden on kitchen can then Touch the
Water the Earth and really can kind of shift and change on
our heart and mind and so sometimes I just go you know get a handful of dirt in my hand feel the
Earth so yeah that's of a simple ways for us to keep
um connected with this
maybe that's oh that's enough all right yes one sec
there you go
so maybe that's enough and um those who can and join us right after
this I have a potluck or just a hand around together as a community
and so may you have a wonderful rest of the day and be well