so hello everyone and welcome to this Monday morning in United States
we're doing a holiday called Labor Day in
it's to celebrate to appreciate all the people who
offer innumerable labors for our our well-being the well-being of
our society to make everything run so I guess it's a
time of gratitude thank you
so um
there's a metaphor for mindfulness sometimes it's not just a metaphor but uh actual practice
and that is uh listening and sometimes there's listening
meditation where he uh rather than focusing on the body or
focusing on breathing it's focusing on the sounds that are around
and some people find that it's more relaxing to be in the present moment
with sounds partly because with sounds we don't uh there's less this idea of control
less idea of trying to make something happen or some idea that we're supposed to have better sounds in order to you
know listen and um and uh sometimes listening is a
little bit outside of the ordinary flow of self-consciousness of
self-preoccupation of and it's kind of self-conscious kind of
orientation we might have about how we go through our lives and so that can relax and
and settle and there can be a feeling of just receptivity of no defensiveness no just
trying to justify or apologize or just allowing the sounds to come
and um and uh
and so it's a kind of a and it's l and then uh listening can be
intentional but as we relax deeply uh it becomes more hearing
the difference between listening and hearing is listening there's a active engagement
with hearing and hearing can occur without
intending to hear just their sounds and there's hearing and so to move from
listening to hearing is also part of this relaxing so and as a metaphor uh then
the mindfulness practice is understood to be a form like listening
maybe sometimes in the form of sensing and the sensing that we do has that same
quality of non-defensiveness non-control just allowing things to arise and
um and there also there's a movement from intentional sensing to the
intentionality settling down relaxing because we're not going
anywhere else we're not we don't need to intend to sense because we're just resting in the sensing experience of the
body or of the breathing some people find that the idea of listening
deeply to what's within allows for kind of different sensitivity a different
curiosity a different way of getting out of the way and being connected to what is subtle
signals subtle messages subtle experiences Within
so we'll use that metaphor today for meditation so to assume a
h meditation posture
and we'll start first with sounds and then listing within
so lower your gaze or
gently close your eyes
and taking a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing on the exhale a long exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal
and continue as you exhale to let your attention roam around your
body to see where it feels good to soften and relax on the exhale
and then to also bring the attention into the head the center of the head the
area of the brain between your ears
sensing feeling whatever Sensations there are there in that area
and if there's any tension or pressure agitation
on the exhale soften relax
if you don't feel that part of your body much that's fine just to relax around it to soften
as if you're letting the
mind the brain expand and open
and settle down
and then open your ears to the sounds around you
maybe on the inhale being receptive
to sounds even if the sounds as they
Sounds of Silence
the inhale being receptive on the exhale
resting with the sounds resting in the receptivity
on the exhale relaxing the effort to try to listen or
searching to hear sounds
and if you find yourself thinking it's okay
but let go of your thoughts so you can
create more room and in the mind to listen
not to chasing sounds just allowing whatever sounds want to
come
whatever sounds you hear sounds of my voice
we don't interfere with the sounds as they travel to the ear as their first
heard in the air we might have thoughts and judgments and
reactions to sounds but that's a second step in the mind
the raw sound itself arrives and is there
sounds are always in the present moment
and then if you'd like you can continue with the sound meditation mindfulness of
sound or the attitude of listening
using that as a metaphor settle into your body
and listen to what's inside of you
sense the body sense the breathing
with the same non-interfering receptivity of listening
Let It Be The Raw Sensations or breathing of the body
without getting involved or reacting stay close to the first step just the
listening to the sensations listening to changing flow of Sensations
in the body
listening to sounds listening to yourself
let it be a very simple practice as simple as it could possibly be
just listening and nothing else
all right
and then coming to the end of this sitting
to gently take a few deeper breaths
relaxing on the exhale
and now listening metaphorically
to the sounds of the world to the suffering of the world
there is a saying in Buddhism called listening to the suffering of the world the cries of the world
and now to do so with despair or anxiety
but as if listening is part of the medicine the world needs
the world needs there to be people who listen deeply to
what's happening witnesses to the challenges
and to have meditation practice be a foundation from which to listen and see
in a caring way to first and foremost to
understand before we Act before we speak
and even before we speak to extend our well-wishing our Good Will
out into the world may all beings with no exception
may all people with no exceptions
be happy be safe
be peaceful be free
and may our ability to listen to people well
support the possibilities of the happiness and
well-being of others May our listening
be of benefit to this world
[Music]
doing this good day and welcome to this Monday first talk of
our next series and Following last week's discussion about why speech I'd like to do this
this week do wise listening and I thought it might be nice to do it
in the same five guidelines for speech
and to apply those to listening listen in a timely way
listen uh in a truthful way listen uh with um
I a a nourishing way a pleasant way a a
listen to a way that really really can touch people's hearts in our listening
listen from the heart and then listen in a way that's
beneficial listen when it's beneficial know how to listen in a beneficial way
and then to listen with Goodwill so that's what we'll do
now listening is a meta both a practice in itself and a metaphor for practice
and um and there are times when we're communicating where it's not literally
listening some people are deaf and so not literally listening but there is a ways in which we receive
into our life into our self the communication that other people are
providing and um and that could be with an email or this that could be sign language or
other ways that people communicate and there's something about being
receptive to that in a deep way where we're sensing or feeling our way
um observing in a deep way what is being
communicated and it said sometimes in therapy that a
good part of what of successful therapy is the listening skills of the therapist the good a good part of the skills of
being a good friend is their listening skills of the of the friend to really listen uh to people
it's also sometimes very closely associated with spirituality the people who listen to the Buddha if
his first disciples were called literally called the listeners and uh and not the followers but those
who listened and back in the time of the Buddha there was no written communication there was no radio or
there was no TV and monitors all the communication happened orally people had
to listen or and or just or use their mouth for all the news and all the
knowledge all the education all the the uh entertainment and music and songs
and poetry were found received someone speaking them and so knowing how to
listen and I believe because of that people listened in a different way 2500
years ago because if uh they wanted to they it wasn't like you could go look up
the a poem later to review it or teachings later to review it you had to
either memorize it yourself or go find someone who did who could recite it but
so those is to to really listen deeply enough to hear it and it goes deeply into the memory banks is actually an art
a skill that uh many people in the modern world uh have lost or have never
developed and um in the I think the rules of Saint
Benedict the Catholic order the rules begin with the word asculta Latin for
listen so this listening is something really really significant
and the qualities of listening that make it really healing or beneficial is when
we can listen without inserting asserting ourselves into the listening
that our agendas our desires our wants are rejoinder to the conversation what
we think and we're kind of raring to go like a thoroughbred out of the uh
start of a race just waiting for the start button we're ready to speak but rather we're hold we're listening as
if what we're hearing from someone else needs to be complete we're interested in
the whole thing in a deep way to let it register to hear almost as if we're
listening between the lines uh the
the there's a kind of a little story I've heard maybe made up of a of a man
who's having trouble with his marriage and um and the therapist tells him you have
to really listen to your wife so he does that comes back the next week and say well I listen but nothing you
know changed and uh the therapist said uh you have to also listen to what's
between the words I was a bit you know what's not being said
and so this ability to kind of listen and to the words the feelings the
attitudes the concerns the history the context there's so many things to really
take time to feel and sense no that can't be known if we rush to
judgment rush to speak so in this in in the Buddhist mindfulness practice
uh listening that is a kind of can be as a as a model or an example of how
mindfulness can be that mindfulness then has similar qualities to listening we're
not asserting ourselves we're not inserting ourselves into this situation we're receptive we're taking in the
situation deeply we're letting it register we're feeling it uh you know
how it impacts us in many different levels on our mind in our hearts maybe
even in our belly and really feeling and listening and what's happening here and
doing the same thing with with another person how is it coming from their
background how is it coming from their context since the world that in society where is it coming from the context of
their Joys and suffering of their life how is it coming from their hearts how is it coming from their belly and what's
happening for them so to listen deeply
is uh uh is a powerful thing to do and for people
who are doing mindfulness training developing the capacity for mindfulness this is a kind of a ready-made
kind of uh possibility for developing your mindfulness in in
communicate in communication in in the world in your relationships with
others if you want to develop greater mindfulness I simultaneously develop
greater skills to listen there's a story in my book that Monastery within of a
young person who um Family moves away for a year to some
distant country where there's a Buddhist Monastery and the young person goes and
learns about meditation and finds it very meaningful but then after the years
to return to their own country where there is no Buddhism though meditation no one seems to know anything about
meditation and um and the young person asks the abbess now that I come back to my home
country how can I continue my training and meditation and the episode
ask around for the person who is the best listener
in your community and then learn from them so the city of listening is a kind of so
akin to listening well is so akin to mindfulness so it's a way of developing
mindfulness in daily life in our relationships and so for today the idea of timely is
it listen at the right time and um probably it's always the right
time to listen to someone to listen deeply and um and uh but if they but if uh but
if we only listen to them and they're not interested in us or interested in our response at some point you know of
course uh at the time that listen is over but
the the time to listen also is not just to listen passively but to listen
actively and that's often the key to good listening is not to be a passive
listener letting just people speak but show them that you understand them
active listening often allows you means that you kind of uh say oh I understand
um you're having trouble listening and and that's a challenge for you or I understand oh look you have a lot of
trouble at work I hear that and that must be hard so just little things that show that you're listening and you're
attentive I have been a conflict mediator and in
my life as a Buddhist teacher and the one thing I've learned is that
um conflict gets resolved much faster if the party is in a conflict understand no
that they have been heard and being heard means people have
listened and have understood and so I think a nice kind of guideline is that
that kind of like always the right time to listen and there's a saying I've heard that
says that you know God gave us
one mouth but two ears so we can listen twice as much as we speak
and um so you can probably adjust that saying in different ways but the um but the
idea that prioritize listening more than speaking
because then when you speak the speaking might be much more effective you won't have to say so much if you
really you don't have to repair so much you don't have to explain yourself even more or clarify if you've listened well
and really understood not what's what's happening with others then when you
speak it's a it can be
easier to speak for the five guidelines for speech
so um so for today if you'd like to uh
practice this trade in this during the day next 24 hours uh you look for
opportunities to listen well and if you're mostly alone but you're
listening to a podcast or the radio or something that's actually an interesting place to train in listening uh in a good
way watch your mind see what you're doing as you listen how much are you
losing yourself and losing some kind of deeper way of listening how much are you
judging or reacting and losing a deeper way of listening kind of below the words
that are spoken even or the fullness of what's being said
so it could be you know just listening to something on the news that's particularly useful place to
listen because the news is often offered in a way that can be to hook us in or
get a little reaction from us and so to listen a deeper way to listen to politicians in
a deeper way and uh but listen to your friends your co-workers your neighbors
um see what it's like to listen it's in such a way that the people
you're listening to understand that they're being heard um before you come back with your
rejoinder and of course this doesn't always apply if there's a just a fun light back and
forth that's going to play full but anytime there's a little more serious conversation
to listen deeply is a wonderful practice so thank you very much and I look
forward to tomorrow