hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour hi and if you can hear me okay give me a
thumbs up ideas good terrific fantastic so hi I'm Nikki in Mountain View
California unseated oloney land welcoming you to happier and uh as
always we begin with saying hello from wherever we are welcoming ourselves
welcoming each other so who wants to warm up the space with with their
Goodwill saying hello take it away uh bill in Dallas hi hi Bill
Leslie in Santa Cruz hi Leslie
great in San Jose hello pretty in San Jose
thanks Jesse Center phone that was Jesse and Padma yes hi hello
Jesse and Padma
I wait I didn't quite hear the person who said hello
it was Gus Hi Gus good to see you long time no see I saw you yesterday IMC
that's nice welcome welcome to happy hour great who else was saying hello
oh we have lots of hellos in chat Amy Says Aloha from Oahu and Yaman they have
to remind me how to say your name again I seem to have forgotten Yemen or Yaman
um tell me where this dress is says hi Alan from Connecticut hi Alan and hello
Leslie from Santa Cruz in the sunshine yay Neil in New Hampshire Terence from
sequin Yeoman says that's good the first one Yamin right okay good thanks and
Hugh says hi from San Diego that is so great and also welcoming our friends on YouTube who are joining us at the same
time so I think the space has been warmed I feel I feel warmed up and high path from
Sausalito so thank you Neil thank you for posting information about happy hour
Google Groups if you are new to happy hour um please know we have a low traffic
mailing list where information references uh
Etc are shared on that mailing list and it's a way to keep in touch with the
community as well it's I like to say it's low in traffic but but high in heart and also at this time when we
transitioned from warming up the space and saying our hellos to each other um I changed some of the settings so
that unmuting will not be possible we keep the space quiet during the meditation
uh and also I change the settings so that um chats will only come to me but I ask
you to please don't send me chats when I'm teaching because they can be quite distracting I will open it up afterwards
for comments and reflections and last but not least I'm going to turn
on recording for the sake of Audio Dharma and you're gonna notice the recording being turned on
here we go okay all right hi everyone lovely to be
with you to practice with you to hear your hellos from different places in the
country and the world our International Sangha
so so for today's practice ah I'd like to invite us to
um meditate together and uh I will invite the
gentle Reflections I'll drop them in gently as we practice so
so let's uh let's begin let's arrive in our bodies
let's take our seats we take our seeds
on this Earth In This Moment In Time
let's connect to ourselves to this body
taking refuge in this moment in the wholesome
intention of our heart turning away from the busyness of the day
all the demands
thank you not now turning turning towards
seclusion of our heart this delicious seclusion
quiet restful connecting
so setting Our intention
at the beginning again it's a gentle intention it's not
hard it's not harsh it's a gentle releasing
the demands are are what they are will return to them of
course we'll return to them but now we say not now we're gonna take a little break
a little respite to connect and nourish
nourishing calming soothing this gesture of
picking Refuge
letting the breath move through the body receiving the breath
this receptive stance
no need to control the breath let it be just as it is simply receiving
welcoming Let It Be soothing like a lullaby
calming the entirety of the breath foreign
to entertain you to warn you to do what they usually do and say thank
you so much thank you thoughts please come back later I'll be waiting for you
right now I'm taking refuge and the ease and the nourishment
the rest the rest that is afforded
the Simplicity of this moment spent with the breath
yourself enjoy the breath well enjoy sitting in this moment
how lovely that this is what I get to do right now
as my practice I get to do this yay
it's not just celebration
foreign
to accomplish but to just be relishing the sweetness
of just sitting and being breathed
right here right now
foreign
racing this moment of our life the grace of this moment of our life
being alive right here right now opening our heart to it with a smile
whatever this moment is there might be pleasantness of sitting
being breathed it might be challenges in the body and
the Heart there's so much grace
being aware being alive being present right here meeting this moment
I want to invite you to explore something view it
and see how you can make this work for you try it out of her size
foreign
personification to this moment
the present moment and it was personified as as an angel a graceful
angel that meets us
be fully open to meet greed with a smile
we may not quite understand all the gifts all the grace that this Angel has
if the word Angel doesn't work for you try something else that works for you and Buddhism we have Devas which are the
Angels or or a good friend a dear friend
I like the angel because it's a abstract it's a Grace of goodness that we can
just meet
imagine every moment you're meeting then open heart with a smile
ah the grace of this moment of your life
with all the gifts that it has challenges too
the challenges are gifts as well help us learn help us grow
help us expand ourselves so meeting meeting the goodness
angel of this moment of her life with a smile with Good Will
with kindness open-heartedness
Opening Our senses
appreciation foreign
silent gentle angel of this moment comes and greets you sits next to you
the two of you together gaze at your life In This Moment open
your hearts embracing whatever is here
presence and good will
the angel shows you how it's done
foreign
relate as well as you can embracing opening up
this moment of your life you're Rising meeting you being met
will have possibilities
more spaciousness
Witness and you realize
its Angel is your life the moments of your life greet it kindly
greet them kindly
wholeheartedly
not really foreign
foreign
your mind was thinking wondering
being distracted no problem no problem smilingly let go reconnect with the
angel of this moment of your life she's waiting for you
embrace and fully open up to
sit with so much goodness
really present
foreign
[Music] with kindness Good Will open-heartedness
wishing ourselves well and this moment in time
foreign
ourselves well may we meet may we meet
This Moment In Time this moment of Our Lives
this Angel the grace of this moment with with open-heartedness
with presence
may I meet this moment as a friend as an angel
do you love goodness
thank you foreign
[Music] foreign
love
and I meet this angel
my heart open knowing that
this moment she is precious there will be a day there will be no more
this moment
may I meet it with kindness of the appreciation
with the humility
kindness towards myself and others thank you
thank you
foreign
[Music] as a friend
it's an angel of goodness
as we turn to bring our Center close
meeting this moment
as a friend without judgment
without self-criticism whatever happened or did not happen during this practice is okay you showed up you did your best
all that matters appreciate yourself for having me showed up
without attachment to outcome you've planted seeds they're going to take time
to flower foreign
together let us
appreciate our goodness their goodness and with generosity offering all the
co-created goodness our good will
to all things everywhere they all thinks everywhere be well meet this moment
of their lives with Good Will with kindness with open-heartedness
may all beings everywhere be well may all beings everywhere be free
including ourselves
thank you for your practice everyone [Music]
so what we explored today was a variation that we've never done we
always explore things in a different and new way that's what's fun about practice
it's not always the same and sometimes some practices work for you sometimes they don't sometimes you have to adapt
and adjust them it's all good and sometimes wow something opens up that hadn't been accessible before so you
know yeah yes this is my way in so the invitation to explore today after
we got settled as usually we do the breath and the body
was to explore this friend this this this moment of Our
Lives this moment of our lives right here as as a friend as a good friend or as an
angel because the idea of an angel for many people not for every has a sense of Grace a sense of goodness meeting the
unknown meeting the mystery being open to the mystery to the goodness then
there are few people for whom that doesn't work you can use good friend or Deva which again means angels in
Buddhism but there's a little different um but basically this idea of appreciating this the grace of this
moment opening up to it meeting you with kindness with Goodwill which is really good will
for ourselves so it's basically practicing meta and Goodwill for ourselves but in this indirect way
and also um appreciating that these angels this
this this these this grace of this moment is finite there's finitude so can that bring more
of an appreciation more grace of oh yes let me appreciate this moment of being alive not take it for granted
um but mostly turning with kindness with gentleness with with meta with Goodwill
can I meet this moment with good will no matter whether you know what whatever is arising maybe the angel is bringing
challenges for me to meet but there is Grace in that too
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back welcome back everyone
and it's nice to see some Smiles as you come back from connecting with one another and uh we have time for
Reflections questions comments aha moments challenges and
especially if you haven't spoken yet in Community I'd love to invite you to pull
forward if you have spoken recently to pull back so that we we hear from a variety of
voices so what did you notice with this practice what
what a rose for you anything you'd like to share for the
benefit of not just yourself to be held witness but but for the benefit of community
really helps Jamie [Music]
hi Nikki hi that was uh extraordinary thank you so
much uh the invitation the angel I imagined being with me was
an angel of death and um you know I you said something about
the the angel you know having Beauty and possibilities that you didn't even know
and so that was my conception of the angel and I experienced really profound
gratitude and acceptance and forgiveness
thank you wow thank you so much
for sharing your practice with everyone Jamie profound and beautiful
thank you so much wow
beautiful angel of death possibility and Beauty yeah beautiful
thank you ah
um Bill shares in chat I used to find smiling during meditation as artificial
and forced it has started to seem more natural now yay bill this is so great
this is so beautiful the moment is smiling back at you your
meditation is smiling back at you as you've been hanging hanging with it for for more than three years now yay that
just makes my heart Happy Bill yay and also what you've shared is heartening to
those who might find smiling during meditation Force like Ugh
it was like it's too much but hearing that oh yeah it can shift here is Bill
it's shifted for bill so it can happen for me too how awesome is that so so that is inspiring thank you for sharing
that any other reflections questions challenges too are welcome
Peggy please hi everyone thank you Nikki
um I had trouble thinking of the present moment personified as an angel but the
angel part worked and um and that sense of meeting I know it was just a really
warm sweet presence and it was playful too but I liked that and yeah
beautiful thanks for sharing that great and I love how you say okay you know as
a present moment as a nature didn't quite work but you know I made it work in a way I made it work for me as as
this sweet meeting and it was it was um uh playful and fun and joyous and so
that's lovely you made it work for you that is fantastic thank you Peggy for sharing that that's lovely and the
playfulness I love that's awesome thank you lovely thank you
[Music] he shares My Angel um was Jiminy Cricket he represented
everything that is wholesome kind and accepting in me oh that is sweet that is so sweet
yeah and here is a reflection anonymously sent
um thank you for providing me with a solid moment of refuge and Trust in myself in what was otherwise an agitated
day ah thank you so much for sharing that that's beautiful to witness and
hold and celebrate and and for me too this this this practice
just so much joy and Delight uh my body was achy and fatigue and just through
this practice there's so much more ease and and heart with you it's such a gift
and maybe I'll share with you a a practice report from me as I was guiding
and I was you know I always guide you from from the depth of it it's not I'm not just
saying the words I'm in there with you practicing with you that's how it's the guidance is coming up for me and for me
um this meeting this this angel of this present moment was so over
overwhelmingly beautiful and at some moment I wanted to burst into tears this
grace of being alive this grace of this angel that is this moment of my life and
I'm meeting it here I have a privilege to meet this moment even though it has challenges or whatever it is but what a
Grace and there will be a day but there will be no more of these moments but wow
wow amazing so and how amazing it is to practice together all of us in community thank
you all thank you so much for showing up supporting yourself each other all
beings everywhere with your practice may we all be well may we all be free
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you so so much be well
and