warm greetings warm greetings everyone hello Sangha good morning
just reading the chats as I set up my computer here
thank you so much for the sound check everyone it's great
so hi my name is Dawn for those of you who we haven't met virtually or
otherwise oh and Neil I'm happy to be here this morning with you I'll be here this week
and um Kim Allen will be here next week
so we are right close to seven o'clock I'm gonna pop out and get something and
at seven I will be back to start the meditation but meanwhile just really nice to see
all of you foreign
good morning again good morning and this week
this week we're going to be talking about I'll be exploring inner and outer Harmony teachings of the
Buddha that um talk about cultivating qualities of mind and heart
that support the practice internally and practice towards freedom and also
support beneficial relationships so we'll start with a meditation
so whenever you are ready and done greeting each other
even as you're finishing up greeting each other the invitation is to look
around your Spades notice Where You Are notice your external surroundings maybe
the walls or the sky and the trees if you're outside
take a look behind you and um tune in
tune into your surroundings the soundscape around you
and then settling in settling into a posture if it feels
comfortable and alert
noticing that you're seeing softening your eyes
maybe allowing them to close
and checking in checking in with this body
noticing any Sensations first maybe the sensations of your skin
touching cloth or air noticing any textures
warmth or cold pressure
lightness
and noticing the whole body
or the surface of your body meets the world
and perhaps taking one or two slightly deeper slower breaths
together releasing any excess tension
allowing the mind the attention to rest inward
I'm tuning to the sensations of your life's breath
or to the sounds around you and resting resting in this moment
perhaps noticing their eyes and fall of the belly or abdomen
the flexing of the rib cage
the sensations of air in the back of the throat or the nostrils
we're tuning in to the whole body breathing
as you're settling in setting the intention and intention for
this meditation cultivation of mindfulness
perhaps may this be of benefit
or whatever intention works for you
foreign
allowing the mind the heart
to rest in the flow of the moment
if mind wanders natural
see how kindly of how much friendliness
you can invite the return of mindful awareness
the tuning Andrea tuning
to the sensations the Felts and
breathing of the moment
allowing these to carry you carry you in the moment
and do not last remaining moments of this meditation
the invitation is to notice appreciate any little
flicker of well-being kindness pleasure relaxation
any of the benefits benefit of this practice
even just the commitment the consistency of showing up
being here
and Gathering those Gathering those together in your heart
and turning your internal gaze outwards
outwards to the others this life touches
imagining sharing those benefits with each and every person and being
you come into contact with and even those further out
casting your inner gaze and opening your heart far and wide
[Music] May others
be happy
may all beings be safe
they are beings everywhere be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
thank you for the sincerity of your practice
foreign again everyone and a warm welcome to
those who tiptoed into the YouTube room a little bit late
happy to have you all here happy to see many familiar names and
people I've run across either in person or virtually great
so this week the exploration the theme is on
cultivating qualities of mind that are conducive supportive to Inner Harmony
and outer Harmony peace of mind
but beautiful ways or helpful ways of moving through the world
and I'm going to start with a story and it's a story many of you have probably heard before
battle back so we're in ancient India
and there are performers kind of buskers these days they would be called
who perform for a living and there are these two bamboo acrobats
a senior acrobat and his assistant a woman and the way that the trick works
is um the assistant has to climb up on a very tall bamboo Pole that the main acrobat
is balancing either on their clavicle right here or on their forehead
and if you can imagine supporting supporting a person just with a stick on
your forehead or your clavicle so much attention is required
so the senior acrobat says to The Apprentice okay so here's what we're
gonna do you look after me and I look after you and will perform
our tricks and then we'll get down safely and collect our feet
um that though the other acrobat The Apprentice
she looked at him and said no no no that's not how it's going to work
we are going to it would be better we're going to you focus on yourself
and keep yourself quiet and calm and safe and I'll focus
on my balance I'll look to my own balance you look to your own balance and
that way we will support each other by supporting ourselves we'll
finish our trick and collect our feet so it's a little bit audacious for in
Ancient India for a woman to countermand a senior and a man
but the Buddha heard this story related and
said actually you know what the assistant the assistant was right each person needs to be mindful and
reach out for themselves we'd not reach out for themselves but look out for themselves look out for their own
balance and in that way the mindfulness will keep
each other safe not just in acrobatics but in life
however it's also true that the senior acrobat was right that it's important
that we look out for each other as well the way we look out for each other one
might call it external mindfulness a broader field of mindfulness
and that takes place through mindfulness of ethical virtue and
kindness and compassion consistency so both were right
and and this talking about here
the importance of the Primacy of
mindful awareness as a foundation the foundation for keeping ourselves in
balance and an important foundation in how we're showing up with other people
right so the foundation of all other virtues in some sense is reflexive awareness
being aware of what's happening what we're doing how we're showing up what the impact is
in a sense this is internal and external mindfulness writ large right mindfulness
of how we are in the world and how we are
in ourselves so in the ancient teaching the Buddha
talks about other beneficial qualities too which I'll cover in the next four days
they are Goodwill or loving-kindness a kind of sharing or non-stinginess
which is a kind of virtue and the consistency the consistency of
showing up in these ways over and over and then the last the fourth is wise
View so we'll cover each of these in the next four days
meanwhile just to set the stage
a wise person the Buddha says a wise person of great wisdom does not intend or practice for their
own Affliction for the Affliction of others or for the Affliction of both but rather
they practice they think of their own welfare their own benefit the
welfare of others the welfare of both and the welfare of the whole world
that's the intention so as many of you have been
participating in these Zoom sessions for now years you're well aware that the
early Buddhist teachings are about cultivating qualities qualities that help create these healthy
harmonious mental sort of states or culture or ecology
within us and these same qualities
when wisely developed also help us show up
in a way as I said earlier move through the world in a way that can increase the Harmony in our
lives in the micro cultures around us whether they're a band of ancient
Indian mendicants like the buddhaled around India or at a modern Meditation
Center or family workplace or neighborhood the same kind of principles apply
and this combination of the internal and external meditation
cultivation is really helpful as a basis for True
spiritual maturation insight greater freedom of the heart of the Mind
and also more of a sense of connectedness satisfaction friendliness ease with the
other people in our lives even the other animals in our lives
one of the teachings um I drew from and it will draw from over the next four days is known as
sarania dhamma in Pali dhamma or Dharma is one of those words
that can be many many things here it means something like qualities or principles factors
there's also a kind of a word cloud a range of meanings for saranya
so feeling into your body feel how the different English translations I'm about to give
land in you courteous
polite friendly
thinking happy rejoice
Gladden to be compatible
they're just feeling those the resonances of them
together this phrase means principles or factors of compatibility
friendliness or cordiality it's often it's the teachings I'm
drawing from one one way they're called as the principles of cordiality or Concord
some of you may also hear the word sarna Nepali in saranya
and this is kind of a happy coincidence the
word sarna means Refuge many of you have heard that Buddha I'm
sorry sarna so
it doesn't appear to be a direct derivation in the language but rather a
homonym that the word for compatibility or friendliness among people also
happens to sound like the word for Refuge so in my mind
that means that these are
kind of linked this this happy coincidence it means that cultivating
these qualities helps our minds our hearts our Behavior become a refuge for
ourselves and our ways of showing up our attitudes ways of relating can also be a refuge
for other people can be a refuge for those around us
this does not mean sacrificing your own welfare many of you have probably heard a very
modern simile you can picture yourself in an airplane on the tarmac getting ready to take off
the flight attendants come out and they show the seat belts and then they talk about in the unlikely event of needing
oxygen masks will drop in the instruction if you have a companion
especially a child or an older person is to put your own mask on first
breathe and then help the other person put their mask on
so put your own mask on first in the practice in fact the Buddha kind of
ranked motivations for practice and practice which is not for one's own
benefit or others benefit is kind of at the bottom like why do it it's not worthwhile
worse than useless I'll just say euphemistically for how it's described in the discourses
for practicing for others but not for ourselves is a little bit better
it's really worth noticing that practicing for one's own welfare even if
you don't have others in mind ranks more highly
look to your own balance first then the sort of highest motivation the
most excellent motivation that the Buddha praised is to practice for one's own welfare
and for the welfare of others a variable
so their mission should you choose to accept it over the next 24 hours is to
perhaps notice how mindfulness meditation benefits you
throughout your day benefits others or maybe benefits both
just check in once or twice or notice throughout the day
can talk about it with a friend notice it informal practice and we'll be back tomorrow
to continue to explore inner and outer Harmony through talking about the process of
inner and outer kindness Goodwill
so thank you all very much for your practice it's a real Delight to see you
all the names and the greetings in the chat
please enjoy your practice