okay well I did not expect to be giving a talk today um I
have a few notes from a another talk I
gave um so I am Hillary and um I hope
that she will bear with me as I I don't know quite what I'm GNA say thank you I
have some some fans
um I know it's probably whoever was going to speak might have thought to
speak about Thanksgiving today because it's coming up for those who celebrate
that um or for those who honor um the
Native Americans uh who have been here for thousands of years and and how um
how with each prayer they teach rather than imploring a deity or
God please do something for me there is a thankfulness a gratitude a
thank you and so I'd like to just offer that as a beginning um to feel deep
gratitude for this place that we have this Dharma Center where we can come
together um in peace
and really want to uh honor how important sa is especially with all the
things that are going on in the world right
now so starting with gratitude but then
wanting to acknowledge that there's a lot going on that's heartbreaking
I don't know about you does anybody wake up in the middle of the night with this
dist tread and fear just raise your hand if that's true for
you okay not everybody that's wonderful those of you who didn't raise
your hand somebody come up here and give a talk you were farther on the path
perhaps than I so the the
the poem that keeps coming to me in the middle of the night is uh by Wendel
Berry the Peace of wild things when despair for the world grows
in me and I wake in the night at the least sound in fear of what my life and
my children's lives may be I go and lie down where the wood Drake rests in his
Beauty on the water and the great Heron feeds I come into the Peace of wild
things who do not tax their lives with forethought of grief I come into the
presence of Still Water and I feel above me the day blind Stars waiting with
their light for a time I rest in the grace of the world and I'm
free I spent a lot of time outdoors in nature
I'm in the E chency program and I find such Solace um and such peace in nature so I
really recommend that
um and I would imagine that a lot of us wanted to gather here
together for some kind of Solace for some kind of
sharing the grief and the suffering not to do this alone but do
this together
um I know that there are a lot of feelings that
are coming up right in all of us and some of them are
um are are just very hard to hold Just Popcorn style if somebody could just
people just name some feelings that are coming up for you right
now anger anger sadness sadness fear fear sadness
sadness grief grief gratitude gratitude
joy joy happiness
happiness appreciation energy
energy frustration frustration uncertainty
uncertainty love love
connection wonder
wonder so a lot of different feelings coming up right now a lot is
here and our practice is here to help us to find that centeredness that inner
peace when there's lots of Chaos in our personal lives and in the world
and it feels to me like this is the great
teaching of Buddhism it is when there is chaos when there is
uncertainty when there's fear when there's anger when we don't
really know the way forward we stop we pause
pause we take a breath and we close our eyes and we see
if we can find some inner
peace and from that place we can then
respond wisely in the world and not from reactivity of fear
and in anger and retribution
and this is something that is wise for all people to do and
all all organizations All Nations
everyone right to pause for peace to feel some
peace and to have compassion for all [Music] beings right I remember tign not
Han in the 60s he was exiled from his country for choosing
peace and not choosing sides knowing that all people suffer everyone on all
sides when there is not
peace so how do we make peace
with what is what we're feeling that's what we're here
for and we have feelings for a reason because they're here to tell us
that something is right or something is wrong something
needs sometimes something needs to be
done so what what do we do with these feelings I mean we
[Music] can go into our fight
fight Freeze and I don't know how many of you are
feeling um what do you feel some sense
of anger who is feeling that right
now okay okay and how many people are feeling
like you want to
flee just run away and you may have be raising your
hand more than once and how many people feel
Frozen you can't move okay yeah so I would like to Just In
This Moment like acknowledge that a lot of us may be feeling kind of frozen or
feeling like we might want to run or we might want to say some things that might
be a little unskillful in this moment and just let your
body find a little bit of movement one of the things that can happen in our in
our practice we sit still and we hold these feelings
in and if we are really feeling fear and
anxiety and anger it can really lock those feelings into our
bodies and we can be more and more traumatized so I invite you just to
bring in a little bit of movement to unfreeze might be a little rocking
[Music] motion might be from side to
side just let your body find what it needs to do and you can close your eyes
you don't have to feel self-conscious but just find a
little bit of motion so these emo
emotions have some place to go and then
you might find that you feel inclined to take a deeper breath in and
out find a little ease in the body and then you might find that
placing a hand on the heart or placing a hand on the belly
or find your place your way of bringing some compassion
to whatever you're
experiencing you might just practice or just just invite
you to uh explore with your eyes closed
you might even try just stroking your hand down your [Music]
arms
you might like to just cup your your hands around your
face or if your mind is going and thoughts are woring around in there you
might even place your hand in your forehead in the back of your skull I
love to do this when I am my thoughts are
racing just feel the the comfort of your own hands
offering you
support and then you might just bring your hands down to your thep tops of
your legs your thighs perhaps just rubbing your thighs a little
bit maybe even just holding your
knees just to let yourself know that yeah I'm
here there's part of me that can support this part that is
feeling a little bit out of balance and then you might place a hand
on your heart and you could also place a hand on
your belly just feeling the warmth of your
hands or maybe they're cold the warmth of your body and just
sing whatever is
present and just feeling the support of your [Music] own your own kindness your own
compassion and we also may feel some sense of guilt I'm okay In This Moment a
lot of people are not but having compassion for being a
witness to all that is happening we too suffer along with all of
our our fellow human beings and all of
our more than human beings we we too are suffering and
deserve
compassion and then just noticing
actually let's just give ourselves a
hug one of the things that I do is I teach mindful self-compassion courses
for 6 weeks 8 weeks and it takes a long time to begin
to learn to be able to take in compassion a lot of us don't feel like
we are worthy of that everyone else is worthy of our
compassion but we're not worthy of our own our own self- compassion and we
need to know as the Buddhist said you are are as worthy of love and compassion
as any other being on the
planet so there is a lot of of sadness and
grief and anger and other feelings I invite you just to put your hands up
like this and choose a hand to put the side
and the grief the anger those hard feelings choose a hand and maybe just
curl that up a little bit not in a fist not tight but just like you were holding
a little bird that was wounded in your
hand and then with your other hand come up underneath that hand and cup it cup
those feelings with whatever compassion love
[Music] kindness might be present in
you to hold
both so there's a practice in and mindful self-compassion that's called
meeting unmet
needs and so invite you just uh if you feel like you want to close your eyes
for just a moment or just have a soft downward
gaze and I'm going
to just invite you to so be present for
an emotion that is here for you right
now just one that you feel that you can hold without feeling
overwhelmed and seeing if you can just name name the feeling
what is
this and noticing what happens when you give it a
name if it feels like it's magnifying it's getting
bigger that's not actually what where the intention is the intention is just
to meet that feeling and say I see you so what is that for me if I say the
word fear I will feel more fear it will magnify and so that's not helpful so I
might say something like oh unease unease is
here so it's honoring the truth of how I'm feeling with
without becoming overwhelmed by it and also noticing how we're seeing
the feeling how are we relating to it if I say I am afraid that becomes an
identity I become blended with that feeling I feel like that's all that I am
and then I feel overwhelmed so if we we can instead say
something like unease is
present there is unease here or there is anger or sadness or
whatever it is so just giving it a
name and then seeing if you can feel where it is in your body maybe it's in
several places you might just kind of scan your body from head to toe and see
where does that that feeling live in
you and find the place that it might be strongest maybe it's in your heart in
your chest or in your belly or forehead just finding that place and
seeing if you can bring your awareness to that place and notice how close you
can get to that feeling without getting overwhelmed by
it maybe you need to just
stay a few inches from it or a few feet or maybe you need to to be really far
away bringing your awareness out as far as you need to to not feel overwhelmed
by the feeling and then to see if you can bring your awareness
closer and see if if you can get a little closer just around the edges of
that feeling perhaps and then seeing if you can
[Music] bring some warmth some kindness perhaps
putting a hand soothing hand
there and perhaps there are some words of support that might be helpful for you
to
hear perhaps it's I'm here I'm here for you I care I see you I feel you
you and if you feel like you need to bring your awareness out you might bring
your awareness to parts of you that actually feel okay what parts of you feel okay right
now and see if those parts can hold hold this part that
feels sad
afraid
angry and see if you can just allow to be here for just a little bit if you
feel like it's overwhelming feel free to open your eyes look around the
room feel your your
body connected to your
seat feel your feet on the
floor so just letting yourself
soften around this this feeling
bring some warmth some soothing and
allowing softening soothing and
allowing and then feeling
into an unmet need that you have right now what is the need that you might
have maybe it's a need to
feel peace safety
compassion and seeing if you can actually either through your hand
through your breath breathe this in feel
this this quality that would be nourished ing right
now seeing if you can feel that in the air that we breathe together all of
our good intentions all of our good wishes can we collectively breathe them
in from each other and breathe them out to each
other you might even if you feel inclined to
open your eyes and look [Music] around perhaps make some eye contact
with someone in the room and sense some loving kindness some compassion from
yourself to someone else maybe a
smile to know that you are not alone we are not alone we are here together in
loving kindness and
compassion and I'd like us to think about what is
it the world that we want to live in the world that we want to inhabit that we
want to help create and again again I invite you to
just popcorn Style say some words what is it that you want in the world you want to bring into the
world peace peace rest rest kindness
kindness Gess gentleness care care
understanding understanding patience patience
humor acceptance acceptance
respect respect gratitude
gratitude inclusion inclusion Toler
tolerance connection
connection self love I love that you know there all of
these qualities that when we speak of them do you feel like you're lifted a
little bit just by saying just thinking about so I'm going to invest because we
have about 15 minutes left I'm going to invite us for about 10 minutes to get in
groups of maybe three or four gather with your with your community
and you're welcome to talk about anything that you're feeling right now
if that's feeling like oh I'm feeling just this unease or let but I invite you
and I invite you then to as you share that maybe the first round then the
second round go around and say what is it that you would like to see more of
and bring in if you would not like to participate you're welcome to uh sit sit
with me or just sit quietly and for those who are on Zoom I invite you to
journal if you don't have someone that you can share with so I'll ring the bell in about 10 minutes and so feel free to
connect with each other but I just wanted to um close for
the moment for those who um are online and um
those who might need to be going somewhere else um I'm so my heart just just full
just seeing everyone so connecting and creating community and
sharing um we we need to be with each other to help each other hold what is
here and I'm I'm just going to end by um reading lyrics to a song it's so
beautiful in these arms by Jennifer Baron and if you haven't already um gone
online and um onto uh YouTube there's a
beautiful beautiful video of her making this um I really recommend it so I'll
just read one little part of this song I cannot turn my eyes I cannot
count the cost of all that has been broken and all that has been lost I
cannot understand the suffering that life brings war and hate and hunger and
a million other things when I've done all that I can and
I try to do my part let sorrow be a doorway into an
open heart and the light on the Hills is full
of of Mercy the wind in the trees it comes to
save me this silence it will never desert
me I long to hold the whole world in these
arms may all beings be happy may all beings be safe may all beings everywhere
be free so may the benefit of our
practice the peace the the centeredness the groundedness that we
find in this practice may it support us as
we are encountering all of our own
individual suffering and also the suffering of all those around us bearing
witness to this may we
be light and love and compassion in the [Music]
world may it Ripple out from us in all the small ways from a
smile to a thank you to a helping
[Music] hand may it Ripple out into the
world and grow and
grow thank you so much for being here thank you for your
practice really really feel uplifted and nourished by being with you