hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour hi and if the audio is okay
give me a thumbs up you can hear me alright fantastic wait
so welcome to happier I'm Nikki merkafuri in Mountain View California
and seated oloni land and uh as we always do we start by saying hello
warming the space with meta with Goodwill just connecting with each other
um before we transition to uh meditating so so who wants to say hello take it
away New Hampshire hi everyone hi Neil hi I'm Stephanie I'm in Los Angeles
hi Stephanie I'm Vicki in Oakland
hi Vicky I'm Bill in Dallas hi Bill
Maryland Fairfield oh hello Marilyn who's in San Mateo California hello
Susan San Jose oh sorry Jesse go ahead Jesse centerfill hi Jesse Christine San
Jose hello Christine both Christine and Jesse from San Jose Neighbors
I'm Nancy from Virginia hi Nancy
audience hi who was this
hello Claudia hi Claudia welcome great
and let's see we have a few hellos on uh chat father says hi from Chicagoland hi
fazel Jamie at home not in your car for at home in in Novato Larry in Seattle
and Amy Says Aloha in Oahu that just sounds so fun to say aloha in Oahu so
great I feel the space has been warmed with our meta with our hellos and and hi
Elsa Jerry from Toronto and thank you Neil for posting information about happy hour Google Groups if you're new to
happier we have um a low traffic Google Groups that
um participants share information and Neil shares quotes and references Etc so
you're warmly invited to join it's pretty low in traffic and high in heart as I like to say so at this time I
change the settings so that um the uh unmuting unmuting oneself
won't be possible this space will stay quiet and the um chats will only come to
me but I still ask you to keep that channel quiet so because it can be quite
distracting they get chats and I'll open it up afterwards and last but not least
I'm going to turn on recording for the sake of Audio Dharma here we go
great okay all right hello everyone it's lovely to
be with you it makes me happy just lifts my spirit to just sit with you in this
virtual Zoom space um and I say this not just sharing what I
feel but also bringing it so that you feel into whether it's true for you also
whether there is a difference from say five minutes ago 10 minutes ago when you
were on your own or whatever you were doing in your space but now actually yes you are here you are
in Sangha you are with Sangha and your practice actually has already started
with with the warmth with heartfulness with oh yeah seeing each other on the
screen and just sharing my talk with willia these are fellow practitioners that right there that awareness of this
sense of Goodwill and your own Good Will is is part of our practice turning
turning our our awareness into our goodness on into our own intention our
own um our own wholeheartedness
even if the day might have been hard or 10 minutes ago oh this has been tough or
hard day in your body and your life but still
bringing goodness into into your um heart space into your mind space so
so I'd like to tie that in into our
practice today or meditation today and
um maybe I'll just say one more thing before we transition to practicing together and that is
um awareness awareness simple
magical incredible power of knowing um
is the precursor of kindness and it's a particular kind of knowing
right it's a particular kind of paying attention mindfulness awareness Sati Sati in poly
it's a particular way of paying attention that is the precursor to meta
to kindness to cultivating goodness so so turning our awareness to Turning yeah
our awareness to awareness um that's one thing I'd like to invite us to to uh
to become more aware of just a simple way of being and paying attention so
I've said plenty let's let's practice together let's practice together so
arriving arriving in your seat
whatever this body needs In This Moment uh maybe rolling your shoulders back a
little bit ah sitting or lying down or even
standing sleepy you need to stand up with your
eyes open that's fine or if the body's hurting you need to be lying down
or sitting up and for now I'm
for these instructions for these invitations I'm going to assume you're sitting
ah feeling your body feeling the uprightness
of this body Landing Landing releasing
feeling your feet on the Earth
foreign
your sit Bones on the chair or the cushion
feeling your hands rest on your lap
and letting go letting go of entanglements thoughts whatever has come
before and this moment making space
to be aware to know the breath to receive the breath
with kindness with kindness towards yourself
letting each breath each in-breath each out breath
each precious in-breath and not breath
be received not taken for granted to be received with kindness as a gift
of kindness
look
thank you
and can there be a kind knowing knowing whatever is
arising with kindness
whatever is arising whether it's pain in the body challenges in the
mind and the Heart
not believing not pushing away not condoning but just
knowing with kindness
as if the breath
is imbued with kindness
breathing through parts of the body that are challenged
breathing through the heart if there is
pain suffering sadness
The Knowing knowing knowing is both kind
compassionate and Powerful
thank you
knowing knowing with kindness
is powerfully uplifting nurturing
let your breath be present right here with the knowing
softening relaxing breathing around breathing into
with the knowing
practice of kindness not separate from the way you know
and from this breath that's so intimate kindness so intimate intertwined
with both
knowing can be vast spacious allowing
so vast
relaxed receiving receiving
and now ING with kindness
knowing the breath letting the breath Infuse whatever is present
I'd like to invite you to try on a perspective try it on for size
and if it doesn't work you can let it go and just be with the breath
kind knowing
of engulfing everything into with kindness so here is the invitation
if you'd like to try this perspective on the perspective is
the universe is conspiring to support me
the universe is conspiring to support me help me
including all the guests all the opportunities all the meetings
chance meetings Etc as well as all the challenges all the
difficulties
all the difficulties to challenge to stretch me this being who is me
to fully inhabit the being I can become
to grow in ways that I cannot even imagine be of service to myself and others
drop this in if you if you like and just sit with the breath
with kindness you don't have to think or ruminate about this perspective not at all
just let it be dropped in and be with the breath be with the knowing of
whatever Rises maybe it's just silent inside great
maybe thoughts Sensations
Etc rights Within this way of knowing with kindness
with his perspective I don't precise if you like
us being here with the breath knowing with nights
whatever Rises
foreign
just knowing simply let go
uh of thinking ruminating about the perspective
it's already been introduced just be
foreign
simply knowing whatever arises with kindness
awareness imbued with kindness spacious receiving not thinking ruminating
just knowing letting go very simple keep it simple
and as we turn to and this
practice period together
Let There Be kindness and knowing with kindness your own wholeheartedness your own goodness
for having showed up support yourself and others
if there's any judgment about oh
then do it right you were sleepy distracted Let It Go Let It Go
know even that with kindness thank you judgments you're trying to be
helpful I don't have to believe you all thank you you know you're trying to be helpful
and it's okay be kind to myself
appreciate that I've showed up see the goodness in the engagement the effort
and together all these moments of mindfulness kindness that
we've planted the seeds for turning and
offering offering goodness the goodness to ourselves to
others to all beings everywhere trusting there is goodness in this cultivation
may all beings everywhere be well may all beings everywhere be free
including ourselves
so much thank you for your practice everyone
so say a few words
um so in this practice at first I invited us all to
to settle with the breath receiving kindness knowing kindness and
knowing awareness imbued with kindness awareness imbued with kindness nothing
not something separate practice of meta not something separate but but imbued
and and we also played with the breath being intertwined with kindness
breathing through there were challenges in the body and the heart and the mind making space and
then and I invited you to imagine to have the perception of of knowing as
spacious just knowing it's not so much incisive going to knowing this and that
and kind knowing is very spacious to know to know it's kind gentle and then I
invited you to take on this perspective as if you were taking a drop of ink and dropping it in which is
oh this this consideration of what if what if the universe is conspiring to
support me in all the gifts and all the challenges included to become
fully myself to expand my heart and kindness and compassion and humility all
the ways I need to grow to become fully fully the being
I I need to become to be of service to myself and to others just to put that
perspective on but not ruminate on it not to start thinking but just drop that in and then go back to to this kind
knowing and see what shift that might make maybe something maybe nothing that was the invitation
so what I'd like to invite us actually in our exploration in in the uh Smalls
in the groups into small groups and instead of actually uh it's both we're
trying to provide and create safe spaces for each other as well as Brave spaces
for each other to be brave with one another to be brave with one another and explore together we support each other
um so they save slash Brave spaces the invitation is to explore
um if you take this Pride this perspective on even for a moment even if maybe there's some aversion towards it
you can say it that's perfectly fine and if you take it on then how might it transfer something that you're
struggling with or seeing some gift that you haven't appreciated or um so so it's an interesting perspective
you don't have to believe the perspective I'm not offering the perspective for you to believe it and say this is the way it is but we're just
playing around it's sandbox there are million perspectives you can take right this is just another one let's see how
we can shift and and and um and change our perspective being a
scientist of your own mind how might something shift with this perspective so
the invitation is Let's Go reverse alphabetical order you can offer
something like this perspective wow I loved it when I brought it on then I see
this in that you know this challenge I'm having this this net this neck pain I'm
having yeah can I show up with kindness It's stretching me because I usually lose my patience with it but it's really
stretching me in a way that I don't want to be stretched but I can see the goodness in it or I can see how I'm
becoming more compassionate towards others with physical pain that I didn't have before something like that or no
I'm just aversive I don't feel like the universe is conspiring to surprise it's all fine or just I didn't even hear it I
was distracted when Nikki introduced that it's all good so the invitation is share one nugget a very short brief one
make sure others have time to share whatever they want to share you can also
say pass say pass I'm here holding compassionate space for others later you
can add something but make sure everybody has time to say something maybe just offer one nugget not a long
monologue just maybe 30 seconds or a minute say something and then the next person and then next person then I'll
come back to you okay so be kind take care of yourselves take
care of each other and explore this perspective there's so much to learn from different perspectives we can take
on like different cloaks we can wear some of them are helpful maybe something should some of them like no not this one
and it's perfectly fine just explore be curious be curious all right
created the rooms and can be kind take care of yourselves
take care of each other all right here we go
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back we have a few minutes
for um reflection so how was that what what did you discover what was
surprising any aha moments challenges especially if you haven't spoken recently or you usually don't speak I
love to invite you to step forward um
Stephanie please hey it's been a while since I've been
here and spoken so glad to be back but yeah it was a great practice I have been
struggling with some very unkind thoughts lately because I've been dealing with the insurance companies and
that's just a nightmare but um The Meditation really helped me out tonight and the group was great as always so I'm
glad to be here and I'm gonna try to make it part of my schedule again great great lovely you're back Stephanie
um wonderful that you're back in that that it was supportive for you work dealing with insurance and loss it's
yeah challenging yeah with compassion for yourself and compassion for all the people who are working within
the system and ugh that's it that's hard too that's hard too yeah thanks
Stephanie other Reflections how was this practice for you this uh this practice of taking
on this New Perspective what what happened did it shift something did it
not love to hear from you exploration Susan
please hi yes you know I've dialed in a few
times and I have to say it's very inspiring and comforting when we share
our thoughts about what has you know this session has been about and other
people have had the same experiences difficulties and thoughts that's so
affirming and it just makes me feel a lot better
so I thank everyone for that beautiful lovely thanks Susan yay it's the power
of community really the power of community is so special and that's one
of the things I love about happier because we are on Zoom those who can join us on Zoom of course there are
folks who join us on YouTube but being able to be in these small groups are powerful as as you've both uh Stephanie
and you Susan have attested too beautiful maybe I'll make space for one last
reflection especially if it's related to um to the theme if you tried the theme
on and if something else something an aha moment or a challenge
um showed up
Neil please I'll just throw that
the interesting thing about this statement is that it doesn't matter if it's right and the universe really is
helping or not what matters is your life is better if you can act as if this is
right that's what matters you know so it's sort of ironic
but marvelous too
honestly I couldn't have said it better yeah I think those are the Buddha's
words [Laughter] yeah that's
that's exactly it that's um we don't have to believe that it's true but act as if it is and it
transforms our perspective instead of oh poor me I have to go through this thing
this challenge this difficulty this uh pain the sorrow this loss is like okay
yeah it's it's this is the way the universe is conspiring to support me to
stretch me to stretch me to to tenderize my heart to make me a Kinder more wise
person above and beyond what I could possibly imagine yeah exactly thank you Neil beautiful
here I see your hand is up make it quick here we go
yeah I thank you every everyone in in our group was it was touched by the
thought that the Universe wants us to succeed because if we succeed when we succeed the
universe succeeds and if when we don't realize our full potential a little bit
of the universe gets deflated beautiful beautiful
yes yeah I love that that Insight also there's a sense of oh yes I am a part of
this universe I am a part of this I am a part of this and and me fulfilling my
full potential which may not look like what I think it is challenges are a part of it yeah it's conspiring to support me
so that I become more fully myself yeah beautiful thank you who Okay Maria we
still have time I see your hand just went up was that accidental or intentional all right maybe I'll make
space for one more
Maria question I was wondering if you think
that the environment has any impact on the meditation like is there any
specific environments you would recommend Ed before they start a meditation
your voice breaking up so much but um what from what I heard you say was a
question about the environment about meditation what should be an environment and the meditation is that what you're
asking uh yes sorry my connection is kind of bad it's all right
um so so Inu it's um or when we start to practice it doesn't
matter where you're sitting or standing or walking um some people think that if it's more
silent and I wonder if you're asking wondering about silence versus non-silent but especially with the
practice of of kindness cultivating kindness it's often nice to practice say
on the subway or on a bus or when you're driving and not with your eyes closed
but but wishing everyone well so so there are different ways of practicing that can be done anywhere so you don't
necessarily need a very very quiet space that is that can be supportive for a
particular way of cultivating um a calm abiding cultivating peace but
you can actually practice in any kind of environment does that answer your question foreign
I don't see you anymore either oh there you are I think you just muted okay there Maria
sorry my connection is about the es that answers my question thank you
so welcome glad you're joining even with a bad connection all right dear ones thank you for your practice thank you
all for your cultivation may may we act as if may we take on this perspective
the universe is supporting us through the gifts through the challenges for us
to become fully fully ourselves fully awakened and the universe to be more
awakened and and more amazing all of humanity along with us
um really fulfilling our potential so thank you all for your practice
may we all be well may we all awaken and uh
share our goodness foreign [Music]
be well take care everyone I'm gonna stop the recording I'm going
to stop