hello everyone and welcome to this week's
time together to sit and to explore the Dharma thank you for being here I'm delighted
to be back after being gone for a month and um
feels very kind of like a homecoming in a certain way to come back to IMC and
sit here and and to be able to be together with you this way
reflecting on the Dharma so thank you and um
some of you I'm sure remember that uh in the weeks that I was here before
being gone for a month the overall topic was compassion
and that I had divided uh compassion into five different aspects
with the idea that if we're aware of the richness of these different aspects that compassion becomes more embodied becomes
more considered more wholehearted more wise and considered
and practical useful and if we don't have these five things in mind it's very easy for us to have a
narrow idea of what compassion is and maybe have it be a call to action that
maybe isn't always so wise so these five were
General categories are awareness um Attunement appreciation aspiration and
action and action being the last one we often associate compassion with the need to
act quickly or that but to have this be the last after if there's time some kind
of deeper consideration and then I was going through each of these five five days on each of them
and now we're at aspiration and um
an aspiration is a beautiful quality I love the word aspiration and I'll talk
more about that later but for now and maybe perhaps we can consider
aspiration as a kind of Desire that uh fuels a certain inspiration a certain
motivation that is not tied to the outcome
it's kind of a little bit like a a wish that certain things something happen
and come with me or we act you can act on an aspiration it's not just wishful
thinking um but uh it uh it has a kind of open-handedness an
open-mindedness to it that um both it sustains can sustain in action
and not have us tripped up around the expectation and the of what will happen
or should happen so the same thing with sitting and meditation that we can have aspiration
for sitting and being present there's many aspirations for sitting in
meditation but in mindfulness practice the aspiration to be mindful to be present with a kind of a Clarity of
awareness to what is here including if that means if there is a
lack of clarity and a lack of to be ability to be present a lot of distractions
um the aspiration to be present is even for a moment to recognize clearly oh I'm really
cloudy here in my mind or fuzzy and there's a lot of distractions and a lot
of thoughts and in that moment of recognition is the beginning of this if or fulfillment for
that moment of the aspiration to be present and then to Aspire to let that
aspiration the desire to be present to come from a deep place inside that's why the other so that we keep
coming back to that we keep being fueled by that and the fact that the aspiration comes
from the words uh for breathing in Latin maybe with every breath
every inhale the aspiration to be present that maybe is uh
found with every exhale so to assume a meditation posture
and to gently close your eyes if that's comfortable
and to take a few long slow deep breaths
relaxing on the exhale relaxing the body
the Deep inhale that aspires to be connected here to yourself
and relaxing the body and the on the exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and perhaps before anything else what is your aspiration
sometimes we ask what is your inspiration or intention
what's your intention to for meditation but what's your aspiration
inspiration
and um and if you kind of drop in this
as deep as you can Within is there an aspiration and inspiration
in Latin aspiration means literally means to breathe kind of out
and inspiration I guess means to breathe in the two words are closely related
and then to relax further in your body
maybe on every exhale to relax the face
on the exhale the shoulders
on the exhale the belly
and perhaps also to relax the thinking mind
any contraction or tension
any tightness or pressure and thinking
or in mental efforting is there any mental efforting
that you can relax and soften maybe let go of
and then to sit quietly breathing with your body
allowing the body to breathe
which your body has done for a long time
and accompanying the breathing body
almost like you're making room in your body for breathing too
do its thing
and every inhale maybe connect to some deep sense of
aspiration might be a clear
wish or desire to be present to be here
to be kind to be generous in being aware at the present moment
or it could be an aspiration it doesn't have any words
it's there but it's not a clear that lent doesn't lend itself to a words
or clear idea and on the exhale
to be inspired to follow through on that aspiration to
give it space and room support you
to be here and mindful and present
perhaps your aspiration is modest
and that is it's something that can be fulfilled
with each breath
or can be fulfilled in a time it takes to breathe in or to breathe out
no bigger goal just this to be here
with some degree of clarity recognition
hear this now
thank you
what might be the aspiration the desire
that's carried along with each breath
foreign
and as we come to the end of this sitting
the dedication of Merit that's often done at the end of
practice is an aspiration
an aspiration for the goodness the benefits of whatever practice we do
that we share it with others and it isn't that we lose it then
because it's shared with others it kind of gets magnified the benefits
because the heart opens generosity that
has room for others care and love
and may it be as we aspire
that not only our practice but our lives
are lived for the benefit of all including ourselves
recognizing maybe even that such an aspiration
does a tremendous benefit to ourselves to have it breaking through the shell of
self-centeredness and self-reoccupation
may it be that our time together this day meditating
in this community may we as individuals and as a community
consider ways that we take the benefits from this meditation
with us into the world so that we benefit
bring benefit for others with us with an aspiration a care and attention
to doing so may all beings
be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
and may we Inspire to see this happen to support this happen
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone again and um topic for this week uh exploration of
compassion is the role of aspiration in compassion
a common definition of compassion is to
recognize suffering in the world and to have a feeling for it to have a
kind of uh some kind of resonance with that suffering to feel it to have some Son
sympathy with it or empathy with it and
to have a desire for that suffering to be alleviated and that and is a hugely important part
of compassions and a desire for it to be alleviated
it compassion can exist without necessarily we being the person who is
going to alleviate the suffering but it's still the desires there
and um but in certain circumstances they make sense that we have the desire to do
something we have the ability to do it it's appropriate to do it maybe sometimes it's no one else who could
help with the suffering that people are experiencing and so we offered to do something
and so the common definition does involve a desire but desire is a kind of um
somewhat vague word or somewhat broad word and so I prefer to call it aspiration
and part of the reason for this is that I think that generally to Aspire to
something to Aspire to do something it doesn't come along with Duty or
obligation an aspiration comes from someplace deep inside it's an inspiration it's a welling up of uh of
of an inner desire that is offered arises freely or arises
without need perhaps or without a lot of ego or
self-centeredness it has a kind of a deep Source Within and there's a kind of open-endedness to
aspiration uh it's different for me different than hope we're wishing uh
aspiration wants to see something happen but knows that it might not
it's not aspiration is not attached to the outcome
and to act in the world of compassion act compassionately from aspiration
maybe as a wonderful gift because it frees ourselves from that tightness and
the pressure of accomplishment of succeeding and and sometimes when we're
compassionate to others it's enough for them to know that we
have the desire the aspiration to help we're we're making the effort to help even if we don't succeed
the idea that someone cares about you cares enough to make effort to support
you sometimes it's the medicine that's what's needed more than the outcome
and so aspiration is um the other reason I like aspiration because the word is
connected to breathing and so it has this kind of in my mind this idea of
having a deeper Source within our body within our heart that's different than
anything that the Mind comes up with the thinking the logic the analysis of the situation
it has some kind of deeper upwelling to Aspire
and to take the time when we're in the presence of suffering or feel it to not
rush to judgment not rush to obligation not rush to something has to happen here
when that Rush is motivated by our own distress our own discomfort our own
sense of uh self centered kind of obligation or that our
own need to do something but rather take the time to relax with it than to be present and see what is
the aspiration that flows out of us what's the desire the wish for that that
is uh that has this kind of open-endedness this freedom to it not something that
puts us back in bondage or puts us and clamps us down or Narrows us but
something that actually feels like now our breathe now we can breathe more easily as opposed to getting stressed and tight
and our breathing becomes more contracted and and tight and narrow
so aspiration and um and so
this week I'll talk about uh five different these different aspects
of aspiration and um the um
and for today the simple idea is that part of the aspiration when it's
compassionate is to want suffering to stop our own suffering if someone else is
suffering to want it to stop but to want them to have that desire
that want wanting to to no longer be there is a because we know
that life doesn't have to be suffering all the time we don't have to be living
always under the pressure or the tension the hurt the pain the stress of what uh
you know life brings us and our own struggles and all this
difficulties and heartbreak that we can have that there is a there is an outcome
there is a way of coming into a very different relationship to this difficult world we are in
one in which we don't contribute we don't enact we don't
um add to the difficulties of life the kind of suffering of the stress the
suffering of contraction the suffering of that comes with attachment and
clinging and we can learn and practice that we don't have to do that
there's another way of being and as we learn that then we learn how to have aspiration
that's free of attachment aspiration is free of force
assertiveness aspiration that's free of conceit it's just a puke it's a beautiful
quality that have a compassionate aspiration and um and then and to be motivated by
that beautiful aspiration is very different than being motivated by obligation or or sense of Duty that
responsibility that many people get caught in in a way that's not beneficial
so to have a wish to to to not just simply be present for
experiences we encounter in the world situations not learn just to be mindful
of it not care but to where mindfulness where the
awareness of it comes along with a care and I learned yesterday that the the
word aware awareness comes from the kind of
anglo-germanic source that actually means to care and and so I looked it up
in my native Norwegian and sure enough in Norwegian in English sometimes what's
the W in English is a v in Norwegian and
which is that means ta means to take is the where take where
take care is what it means and so I love this idea that awareness
means to care to take care and um
and so to care and in that caring to care enough also
about ourselves so with when we're in the in encountering suffering and being present for and being aware of it we are
taking the time to look for where is the aspiration here where's the inspiration what desire
comes out of inspiration around the suffering to just the
inspiration for it to come to an end to stop so um
so I would encourage you to spend some time exploring your desires thinking
about when you have desires desire to end to stop something that's painful and
suffering and to see the quality of that desire is it does it come along with something
that is actually stressful actually that feels you know that it's a grading or or
somehow diminishes something inside of you the desire that because of the need the attachment that's there
or is this encounter with suffering and the desires that were born from it uh can it is there some place where there's
a sense of aspiration or inspiration that supports the desire to stop or to
bring this to an end and um
the um so those are my thoughts today and um
maybe from having been away for a month on a silent Retreat maybe that I don't
have many more words and we'll stop early today and I do look forward so happy very
happy to be here and look forward to continuing this series on aspiration in
relationship to compassion over these next days and I will be here on the fourth of July
so I don't know if what you all are doing but I'll continue for the whole
week so thank you