been learning good day
hello everybody all right
I'm seeing the chat messages coming in so good morning everybody
so we'll get started
let me start my recording here
yeah warm greetings from everywhere good to be with you all
um hey my day here is
um Thursday so we're going to um move to another phase of our stonus and
the movement Journey and so today we'll be incorporating
maybe expanding from where we were uh in the Stillness and movement journey
to include the mind or the thinking mind
in our practice so maybe if you follow along uh we'll
begin right here where we are
I'm gonna give a sound for Belle to start
[Music]
Begin by entering into this body and mind
and heart maybe this entering as an orientation
of attorney inward
maybe there is a sense of immediacy
and sense of a presence coming forth
each morning we enter into this Temple
Temple of this body mind and heart
with the reverence with care
tenderness
Here and Now is where we enter
and in which to feel
settling into a posture
sitting lying down standing
on the posture that expresses a kind of an inner alignment
Inner Harmony
the inner commitment to the practice
maybe you're feeling the lower half of the body grounding on Earth
and torso is uplifted
there is a totality that combines
steadiness balance
and uplift wakefulness
right here
and right here may be already feeling a sense of a Stillness in the body
expressed in the pasture of the sitting
sitting like a mountain
maybe just a hint of it or a hint of a hint
possibility as one of my teachers often says
what's the fat sense of the body sitting here
Earth element solid
all moving grounding
the movements it's very natural to be felt
with the Stillness in the body being in the background
the movements of the breath
expansion and contraction of the Torso
temperature change as you breathe in and out
like a breeze or sing through
a tall mountain
of the Stillness and the movements
are present
the flow of the breath enlightens
as a whole body giving life
it's such a Wonder
a life Mountain
you already notice the movements of the emotions bubbling up
Rippling
a sense of a Wonder sense of all
curiosity
the emotions may have a somatic imprints
or maybe bubbly energy in the body
that's related the joy happiness
in the emotions
feeling and sensing
the embodied field of emotions
maybe thoughts or coursing through
it's related to emotions
healing and sensing those movements in the mind
whether there are emotions or thoughts
and just different energy forms that we can feel
and sense
notice the feeling and sensing
as a flavor of quiet Stillness
right there
letting go of the stories
content of the thinking
resting in the felt sense
there is a Stillness in the body and Stillness
in the mind
and there's a Stillness in the knowing in the feeling and sensing
and there is a movements in the body
movements in our mind emotions
thoughts
images words
without pushing or pulling
resting in the still quiet
field of knowing
Sensations in the body may be very different to right now
the breath has changed
being available to The Wonder of Our Lives
Right Here and Now
being available to the blossoming
of the inner being
without wanting
not wanting
references judgments
whatever is here in whatever form
and be received but I'm a kind loving
still filled
and sound May flow through the sound of my voice
the ambience sound
noticing the difference between the content of our thoughts
versus the felt sense of thinking
it's in the embodied field
winking we have a somatic energetic feel to it
it's present immediate
the mountain is often detached from the body
all that stuff out sense in the body right now
the in the movements movements of the breath
you know where some energetic shape shifts
as I transition from a quiet sitting
to talking
and as you shift I'm quiet sitting
to listening listening to the stories and words
you listen from a settled
quiet open
and loving field
and allow the words to drop in and flow through
without grasping to anything in particular
but whatever might touch you and Center in
[Music]
so we're transitioning um to another
story um the
great women disciples the stories of the great women Disciples of the Buddha that
I've been speaking about to this this whole week but I remember I I kind of forgot one
thing that I meant to say so I'm gonna put it in now
um so and that is I forgot to say that
this stories that I've been sharing up to now today that it's best to not to
take them as some sort of absolutely absolute truth so
many details of this stories were kind of pieceded together from parts of the
poly Canon and commentaries
and so there's um no way that we can be really definitive of all the details and that
that came through so we hear this with some
light-heartedness and at the same time
and maybe each of these stories have a certain aspects of the teachings
that are meaningful and inspiring for us and that they are supportive for the
Dharma path maybe that's good enough to consider taking some aspects of this in
and for the parts that are harder to connect and
um are not connecting at all we can simply put aside
and this is a kind of an art of learning how to study and work with teachings that are
offered in all different forms and so in the ancient Buddhist
Traditions or maybe maybe almost all of the spiritual traditions
storytelling has always been a very vibrant part of
the teaching mode and so because they touch us in
some ways that may be quite different from Simply receiving a set of
instructions for example you know
um
yeah I'm noticing my internet it has a little issue so I'm just switching to a
different internet right now um hopefully this would work
so today I yet another day I'm bringing in a story maybe some of you would have
already heard this this is a story of isakutami and maybe what I'll offer
there'll be some New Perspective here as well even if you may have a herd and the
story of the kisako gotami so kisakotomy is said to be born in
um no cast of family and she's also very frail and weak and
she's said to be quite skinny and Haggard
the word Kissa means sagio or Haggard and so that's what she's known as and so
kind of a very fragile woman and because of that it was very hard for
her to get married and that was a challenge itself I
suspected for young women in those days but there's one day a rich Merchant
um a young man somehow saw her and they saw something different inside of her and they fell in
love with her and I he decided to marry kisakutan
even though the family didn't seem to buy in with this decision
nevertheless the young the young man was quite persistent and so they got married
and um in those days and maybe even today for
um some of the parts of the world when a
young women get married and they go to the husband's household to live
and that was that was tough for akisakotami because the in-laws often find faults in her and
it was very challenging even though the young couple seems to
love each other very much at some point
kisakotami was pregnant with a young boy a baby boy
and when the little boy was born this changed her life
the young boy was energetic vibrant and
very cute and handsome and all the grudges that the in-laws had
with her went away and so you can see how uh
how much this meant for kisakotami in a way that this young boy wasn't just
praying a new life into the family but also had a given hisakotami a sense of
Life of her own and her her own existence now depends on this young boy
so she was very happy for a while and very contented for a while
that did not last a very long one day the boy got sick and very sick
quickly he died and you can imagine the death of this
child of her kisakotami was more than the death of the young boy
the son because Kisa gotami had
kind of her life depends on this boy so it's as if her life not taking away
in this way um
the whole family was distraught they all turned against kisakotami
blaming her accusing her you can imagine you know all the stuff that would come
up in situations like like this and even her husband began to reject to
her this was too much for kisakotami and a
very short time kind of the whole life changed from upside down
maybe it was hours and days and so she started hallucinating and began to
imagine things and so she refused to accept that her
son had died she imagined that she was that he was
just as sick and needed a medicine to bring him back to normal so he carried this young boy in her arms
and start running from one household to another asking for medicine and to bring
her some back to life and everyone as she met said no your son
was dead and there's no way that you can bring her back but at some point and she met this one
um maybe wise compassionate um family
who told her well maybe you should see a physician who
might be able to offer you a medicine to treat your son and as a physician is the Buddha so you
should go see the Buddha as I get the sense that this wise person
that sense to something within her had some sense of hope or wisdom
incor and so he sent me to the Buddha
now had such a hope a possibility sense of a
hope and possibility so she ran to the ananta pentecas
monastery where the Buddha stayed in the middle of assembly that the
Buddha held she ran writing from the in front of in front of the Buddha
in total Despair and back the Buddha please the Buddha give some medicine to
my son and the Buddha stopped his teaching right then
and kindly without dismissing her without
blaming ridiculing and he responded with this verses
that the kisakotami recounted later in the Legends of the terries
and this was said the Buddha is killed in crafty speech
said bring me a white Mustard Seed collected
in whichever home where people dying is unknown
okay so the Buddha askedame to collect white mustard seed from any household
that didn't have death in their family but in those days the households people
live in are kind of generations you know generations of people live in those
house households and it's pretty impossible to find a house that doesn't have anyone died in
that so kisakotami went to each house
while first asking for the white mustard seed Mustard Seed is very common in Indian
Cuisine and so it's one of the spices pretty much everybody uses so that was no problem
but when she get to the second part of the question that was unexpected by
kisakotami so was there any death well mustard yes
we have Mustard Seed yes we have but How about if there's any death in the
family and everybody said yes there was death
so he came she came back to the Buddha empty-handed
this journey itself was a powerful teaching right there and then
as she already got a sense wow no one escapes death and this is
inevitable so she said in her poem
throwing away my baby's corpse I went to the Buddha
having seen me from distance the Buddha said this to me
better than a hundred years of life not seeing how things rise and fall
is a living for a single day seeing things rising and falling
this is the condition of the entire world
the impermanence of all that is
eyes
and she realized the truth of what the Buddha was pointing to
and so there's a story reminded me and many years ago when I did the Sati
center chaplaincy training and I was going on to the patient gowns
in the Kaiser Hospital and also meeting with cancer patients
and their caregivers I remember very vividly each time I went
and then going back home is like being sent for mustard seeds and again
and again I came back empty-handed
who doesn't get sick and who is not going to die
and that was that hit me very strongly wow but this is the truth of Our Lives
and so there is a reason why these are called Divine Messengers
directly and the deeply they start challenging our grasping or under tight
grip we may have on on things that are Ever Changing
and for me this is still ongoing on voting process
and yet each time I meet this there is such a secretness that's unfolding
I remember uh in the days when I was meeting with the cancer patients that I
was with each time sitting with them my gratitude
towards everything kind of deepens little by little
and also I started witnessing the possibilities of liberating right there
and then they Advance the cancer patients are
moving through kind of the faces of a traumatic experience from the
beginning and to maybe um of surviving modes
and in some ways also in some kind of thriving mode that is not necessarily
about defining uh death but about how they
live each moment and so we had a coined a term that
um we called this group can Thrive group
and so uh and there is some part of our lives that it feels vibrant and thriving
in the midst of maybe meeting with illness and faith and
the death and so maybe this teaching from
kisakotami offers this possibility for each of us
to bow to the secretness of Our Lives
and not to grasp on anything but open to the possibility to thrive in
the midst of all challenges and difficulties
even even the facing of a death
so thank you everyone you have a wonderful peaceful day