we go great so welcome welcome everyone it's
lovely to be with you lovely to to feel your presence from various
places and in the world um
so for for tonight for today's and this moment uh happy hour I wanted to uh
invite us to engage with uh with meta with meta for
um meta for the body metaphor the body can be quite a powerful
practice engaging with meta Good Will appreciation kindness
um for for this body that we call ours and yet
it's not exactly ours it's made up of so
many causes and conditions um but have made it so and we can't it's
not exactly ours and what I mean by that is that we don't completely have control over it we can't say okay stop digesting
now or or heal faster or or don't get sick or or whatever it is you
know we have limited control over this body there's some you know yeah we take care of it we we hopefully appreciate it
we tend to it and yet um it's above and beyond we take it to
be ours and yet it's above and beyond so um might be helpful sometimes with in
our meditation as I perhaps will will guide and suggest tonight is to see this
body this hard-working amazing miraculous body that breathes and
digests and hails itself when we get a paper cut we wouldn't know how to do it
um but um we consider it perhaps sometimes as a
not just as a friend as a friend maybe sometimes having a hard time it's doing
they're doing their best and they're having a hard time they're having challenges perhaps
um it also has the Beloved other as a beloved other I'll I'll say more about
that through the uh meditation so
so I think that's all I want to say I don't want to say more there be more
that will become um yeah there would be more through the meditation that I will share so let's
just practice together let's do it
so I'd like to invite you all to arrive settle
in your bodies thank you
arriving here in this body in this moment
arriving with this body this friend
who's been working so hard trying
support you the immune system has been working so hard
all day keeping the pathogens out of its Kingdom
your heart your muscle your spleen kidneys all
these amazing parts of the body the tissue
blood flowing the bones
all these functions this amazing body has managed to perform today
breathing seeing
hearing still doing that hearing sitting
speaking earlier making words cognizing reading
maybe sometimes we expect even more just more oh gosh your back is hurting to
your body expecting more more and more what if we
set it all down set it all down let the body rest right now it's okay
sweetheart [Music] it's just okay
to be to just be
rest and be I feel appreciated
inviting the body to relax soften just be
letting the breath be soothing comforting
nourishing this body
let's let's go through the body
with appreciation with meta
we won't cover all the functions on all the
miracle Miracles that this body is
it will touch into a few
Let the Body be relaxed so receiving receiving appreciation
receiving being seen known
sort of mud liking [Music] its size or function or this or that
it's aging or whatever it might be loving it just as it is loving it just
as it is just as it is this body
starting from the top of ahead
and we love our head the top of the head actually let's start
with the hair just as it is short long thin brittle bald
non-existent can it be love it just as it is appreciated
this miracle of nature
grows regenerates or not
and then the brain however it functions
fast law creative
appreciating loving it just as it is
we often associate our our mind in the west with our pain
not a one-to-one mapping at all
but if you do perhaps chastise yourself for a
Wandering mind can you love and you love the functioning
of this amazing miraculous piece of machinery
just as it is
love your body your brain just as it is thank you
letting go of wanting more or different In This Moment
bring it all back the wanting more different later but right now see
what it feels like if you just let it go if you let it go
this love what is appreciate deeply appreciate what is
appreciating your eyes a function of seeing
whether they're getting weaker they've gotten weaker or they're sharp or not
whether they're healthy or challenged
loving these eyes just as they are mentor
wishing them well since a good will as if they were a beloved other
these amazing gifts bodies endowed with
moving down your nose the olfactory function
strong weak non-existent doesn't matter
appreciation wholeheartedness
your mouth tongue tasting
your teeth
whether they're challenged working
well need support still
appreciating what is
maybe you had a some food earlier today you were able to
taste it amazing
or smell it amazing
the ears the function of the ears hearing
appreciating such a gift it is and how your life would be different
if it weren't here whether hearing the ears
are challenged working well
the function isn't receding doesn't matter are not here at all Still Loving
what is what is
moving down your heart your lungs
breathing breathing area airing
distracting oxygen spreading it
through the body through the blood
amazing thank you
so much that is working in your body
even if they're challenges
wishing your heart well shooting your lungs well as if a beloved other
your stomach
liver kidneys
your microbiome how these organisms that help you survive
we have a sense of appreciation meta kindness
gratitude for this body
arms and hands you've done so much today
thank you I appreciate you
I usually take you for granted but not in this moment
may you be well
and moving down kidneys growing area sit bones
so many amazing functions
thank you buddy
upper legs knees lower legs and feet
movement ambulation
walking jogging running Maybe
balancing
as much as it's available
appreciating legs feet
loving and wishing well
that's good well for this body that is nature
is born it's from nature it's nature
appreciation for this body my body as a whole
both the parts and the totality
with each breath wishing well
foreign
and we love and appreciate this body just as it is
having meta kindness Goodwill for the bodies
stepping stone or having meta for ourselves
and we wish ourselves well as being who is me may I be safe
happy healthy
may I have ease may I be well
and as we're praying this practice period to a close foreign
sharing our Goodwill not just for this body this
being this person who's me but her all beings
those clothes those near and far wishing all beings well
may all beings be safe happy healthy and at least
may all beings including myself be free
thank you for your practice
so what we did tonight was turning our appreciation our love
our meta towards the body really appreciating not taking for granted the various functions of course there's so
many many more functions and um and that as a way of appreciating
because sometimes again we have this attitude about the body when it's challenged or it's aging or sagging in
the way of ugh not liking it or just or hating it or it's as if it's letting us down this
body as if it's personal but what did we completely turned that around into appreciation into just love and
appreciation for all these amazing functions or what actually works what has been
working profound instead of turning into what's not working and what is a challenge and
what's the problem and this sense of appreciation love
gratitude meta for the body is a so way in there's a way in for meta for
ourselves which which many folks find it difficult having good will for ourselves
but we start with the body kind of it's like a side door we enter through the side door because maybe it's easier to
have appreciation for our eyes oh yeah I can see yeah maybe I need glasses now
but yeah it still works pretty amazing then as a doorway from mental for
herself so so
changing the settings in the chat if you have any Reflections that you'd like to
share you can type to in chat to everyone or it's private you can just
type to me and I'll read your reflection but not your name you can also
um raise your Zoom hand if you'd like to share an aha moment or a challenge or a
question whenever you says my body thanks you Nikki your body is welcome
yep
your Reflections you like to share for your own benefit and benefit of others
Claire I'm you see I I don't think you can see
me I had to change devices but I think I'm I'm just a picture on the screen but
I wanted to share because this is a topic that's been very important in my life I have two family members who were
severely disabled in accidents through no fault of their own and have managed
to not only survive but live very happy productive lives but they taught me to
always be grateful for what I have um because I am I still ride a bike and
I'm not young by any stretch um and I'm still an active cyclist uh
and I'm so grateful that I have been given this wonderful body that works
very well for me uh but I work hard at taking good care of it also so I liked
your topic very much because it rang very close to things that are important
to me yeah thank you Claire thank you so much and especially for also bringing in but not just your own relationship but
also the the relatives who've had very challenging um bodies who have been very challenged
in their function but they have they have been living very full lives yeah
beautiful historical great thank you for that Claire yeah any other Reflections or questions
or complaints or anything so welcome before we turn to um
small groups
Neil says it's better thanks for asking wait that's probably
was that for me that might have been for someone else whoops okay no problem
oh no that was a direct message also never mind it was in public [Laughter]
I hope you're a bit I'm glad it's better Neil whatever it is is better okay you're raising your hand now
yeah I really enjoyed this meditation someone asked me I had a bad headache last night I missed class so they asked me how I
was doing um yeah it was just you know it the concept that you know whatever's not
working well you know is really doing its best anyhow
um you know even at it feeling miserable you know I've been having a lot of back problems in the past I don't know like
too long um you know but thinking thinking oh I hate my back is really just so terrible
right it just right and you know this thought of thinking gee you know my
back's doing its best I you know you know I wish I could do better it wishes it could do better do what could I do to
help it you know it just makes life you know so much you know more pleasant
so right right and this you know I've had thoughts like that and this meditation seemed to really Foster those
it was it was really quite lovely beautiful thank you so much Leo well
well said it's yeah exactly I could couldn't say it better yeah
um thank you and I'm glad your headache is better yes of course yeah yeah it's great yeah
um one of you asks how to offer a meta to those we hate um foreign
[Music] it goes through concentric circles so you start with with someone that's easy
for you to have metaphor and then yourself if that's
more challenging so someone that was easy than yourself then someone who um is neutral
someone you don't either like or dislike you know very little about um maybe someone you know Barista at a
coffee shop Etc and then after you do the neutral category then that becomes
the stand-in that it becomes easier than to move to people you dislike because
um it's kind of a gradual so you can't kind of just jump into doing meta for
those users so so I suggested the person who asked that question do a little more gradual uh cultivation and they're
actually a recorded guided meditations on Audio Dharma that's not the theme
tonight for offering method to those who are challenging we don't say those we
hate but those we have challenges with um so please look uh on at
audiodarma.org and search under um meta for for those we have challenges
with and you will find many guided meditations that will support you
um another person asks how is meta for the body related to reflection on repulsiveness of the body ah
I'll say very briefly so um there are practices of uh asuba in Pali
so it's translated as repulsiveness but that's not a very helpful translation
actually um it's kind of it's the not
attractiveness not because we often you know look at the body or body of others usually it's like oh it's attractive and
there's Sexual Energy and especially when it's inappropriate so that practice really is a way for us to to bring
wisdom that oh it's just the body it's just oh yeah it's just functional it's just a functional body you know that leg
that oh yeah what a beautiful it's just a functional body is just walking
um and then there is more to it when you actually start to see if there's again more desire and and more if there's a
lot of Desire then you start to see that oh yeah it's you know the leg is made of of skin and sinews and Flesh and Blood
you start to see it as its functionality in order to actually see to kind of cure
yourself of this infatuation you might be having with with someone's body so
it's a very Wholesome Way it's not just so that you start hating your body or other people's body it's a very skillful
very clever actually set of practices which I have practiced actually
um and offering method to the bodies is a sense of appreciation for the
functionality it's it's again it's not falling in love with its beauty it's not that so actually these two practices go
together quite well and I can say a lot more I can lecture
on this for hours but time is limited and the time actually has come for us to to transition to small groups the person
who asked that question I hope that clarified it for you a little bit
and it was helpful so so you're welcome
um so yeah I'd like to invite us to engage in um
raise small groups with with uh fellow practitioners and something actually I
uh is listening to um this this interview
um uh it was on NPR about this yeah was the about the um Harvard uh adult study
that has gone on since 1930 so it's almost like 90 years anyway and some the
scientists scientists have written a new book about what is the biggest measure
of of of health or healthy happy life and it turns out to be surprise surprise
relationships relationships so here in happy hour we have the opportunity for
relationships in this next section to just relate to have a conversation uh
with another a couple of fellow practitioners in the space so I encourage you to engage
and um the uh the
reflection for the the small groups tonight is
um is about the relationship to the body how
can we you know how can you how how do you how can you how do you aspire to to
have a a metaphilled relationship especially with a part of your body that
might be challenged that might be challenged how can you love and support it instead of hating it and disliking it
and pushing it Etc as Neil beautifully said it is doing its best
so as always invited to maybe share a reflection and then
um uh maybe you also hold space maybe when the
your turn comes you say pass and then the next person says something and then the next person says something and then
it comes your turn so each nugget let it be short so that there's time and space
for everyone to share something um then again if your turn comes you can
say pass and um and the next time comes to you maybe
there's something you want to share so so with that be kind to yourself
um be yeah be kind to yourself be kind to yourself be kind to each other all
right I'm going to open the rooms here we go
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back
and uh it is seven o'clock so um
let's um let's let's dedicate the Merit and close on
honoring the the your time I'll stay a couple of minutes after after our
cacophonist goodbye on Zoom is there any Reflections or questions you'd like to share so so thank you all again for your
practice for for cultivating your heart for your own sake the sake of
all beings everywhere may all beings be well may all beings be free including
ourselves thanks everyone be well see you on
Friday