greetings everyone I'm delighted uh to be back here with
you on this friendly virtual tour
of tastes of freedom
so on Monday we remembered that by
staying in the present moment and then feeling and tasting
our experience in the present moment that's the key that opens the door
to the path to Freedom so as the Buddha says in his
introduction to is great teaching on the very first
thing the practitioner does is to establish
awareness grounded in the present moment
so with that we have the ability
to discern which way we want to go when
the present moment is offering us something that may be tempting but unwholesome
or something maybe less seductive
but more wholesome
and yesterday we explored the factor of viveka
that cozy seclusion which protects us
from harmful distractions and gives us the power
to avoid these three poisons of greed hate
and delusion and it says wholesome
so yesterday I talked about you know living leaving our
um responsibilities and
lands and perhaps reforminations outside the door together with our shoes
as a way of establishing viveca this
Independence
and today we'll look at viraga
usually translated as dispassion and this is born
of the seclusion of viveca
the seclusion is like you know we're wearing a white cloth
that keeps us pure or that is it has the magic qualities of
being able to deflect arrows or evil
and viraga literally means Away From Desire
so in this case desire can include aversion because
on the one hand we might want more of something which is the usual desire or
we might desire for something to go away or to stop
and so both of those kinds of Desire uh
are not helpful on the path to enlightenment
so this brings us to the uh
Dharma factor of the uraga fading away
so to begin take your
meditation posture with
if you can a sense of confidence
maybe some determination to stay here to the extent possible
in the present moment knowing that when the Mind becomes
distracted the wise thing to do is to not go there
and to come back to the breath
so inviting a little bit of energy into the spine
and living
gravity do the rest
feeling if you can the gravity of the Earth
which is holding you very securely in place as our planet hurdles
around the Sun gravity is something we can trust
sitting and being here with whatever arises
is also something we can trust
you may have seen statues of the Buddha with the mudra of touching the Earth
in which the Buddha takes his right hand and with his fingers downward
touches the Earth for us humans who may not
be sitting completely flat like the Buddha was and having longer arms than
normal humans if we attempt in the position we're in
now to touch the Earth if we're sitting we might have the tips of our fingers just moving forward
slightly to touch uh the thigh
so imagine touching the Earth
and when the Buddha touched the Earth that was his response to Mara
you may have heard of Mara who is the temptress with a temp door yes it's a
male uh who um is jealous of the Buddha and wants to
do everything he can to and so when the Buddha was about to
become enlightened Mara started firing all kinds of I remember is a god
he has Supernatural Powers but he's not you know a good guy that wants us to
remain deluded so we start spying firing arrows at the
Buddha but the Buddha's presence is enough for those arrows to
turn into flowers and then seductive young ladies and they have no effect
either and uh and the Buddha says um
I'm going to until I'm awakened and
um and then Mara being seen for who he is
um shrivels up and disappears
so that's the power of the State of Mind of taking the Earth as our Witness
that we have every right to be on this path to Awakening
nobody can take that away from us not unless we let them
so take a deep breath but first of all close the
eyes thrusting that you're going to be okay the eyes closed
and take it deep slow full breath
on the inhale and then on the exhale
and see if you can visualize yourself from space now the Earth is just a
little marbled and you're just a little speck on the marble
with your fingers boarding towards the center of the Earth
you're really well grounded
and now we'll do brief scan from the feet to the crown of the head
and today I'd like to invite you to do that scan
with a feeling of mid Dot meta is the unconditional friendliness
of greeting each moment as a friend
so during this body scan we will greet and touch with
our awareness each part of the body that replace our awareness
in with his warm loving feeling of friendship and appreciation
so glad you're here feet so that I may walk or so glad that
you're uh here Billy
Etc rejoicing and being alive
so let the attention come down to The Souls of the feet
and open your heart to The Souls of your feet
with love take that love and bring it up your legs
and bring it through your pelvis
taking a moment to shower everything
in the belly with friendliness and acceptance
and now invite that shower of loving awareness
open to the Heart Center
again recognizing that however we feel
it's okay because that's what our experience is right now
and then the lovely feeling of warmth
let it Revel up to the shoulders maybe it will encourage you to release
the shoulders a little bit downward and then pouring deliciously
down through the arms and into the hands including the hand
it is touching the Earth
being alive now we invite
our awareness through the neck and into the head
area
softening the jaw maybe inviting a gentle smile
softening all around the eyes and the forehead
the scalp
and now letting our awareness radiate throughout the whole body
from The Souls of the feet to the top of the head
warm radiant awareness
and if you are so inclined
I invite you to take a vow that if the Mind should wish to go off on a thought
tangent sometimes we call these thought drains
or pleasure boats uh
that we evoke the quality of
dispassion Independence
it is born from seclusion
and when the mind and I don't say if I say when because this is what Minds do
um starts thinking again it was off on some tangent whatever it
is to have the mindfulness well enough in
place to see that and when you see that temptation to go
off on a trip somewhere you express
viraga dispassion or Independence
by just saying No thank you
and come back to your meditation object whatever that may be
the uraga is the factor of being willing
to let on wholesaling qualities abate let them fade away
by choosing not to reinforce them
so with the help of the breath
come back to right here in this body
in this mind
keep practicing like this
if the mind is somewhere other than your lived experience
in the present moment then with all the gentleness and sweetness you can
mustard invited
to come back to being right here with you
with the breath
and for the last few minutes of this sitting
if you've had even the briefest Ace of fading away
of Temptations know how healthy this is
let yourself appreciate the goodness
of letting all those distractions abate
even if it's only for a second
in our body scan we
invited getting in touch with
the different areas of our body by showering them with loving kindness
so now if you are so inclined
the invitation is to
take that loving awareness
and radiate it out in all directions
just radiating the goodness
of being here in the present moment
to the north East
the South the West above
and be loved
may we and all beings
be protected may we and all beings
be peacefully contented
and maybe be free
[Music]
foreign
thank you for your practice
greetings everyone happy to be here with you again on
this um
bus tour of a taste of freedom
but we began with was um recognizing that
um establishing mindfulness establishing clear awareness in the
present moment is the key to be coming free
and the reason is that if we stay with
our experience from lived experience we'll see what's happening
not only in the body but in the mind and as soon as the mind starts heading
in a direction that may be unwholesome we can take corrective action
because we've learned the to discern what's wholesome and unwholesome
and even if we're a beginner in meditation [Music]
if we begin our sit by making a vowel that will do our very
best not to move once we get a nursery
that is a huge help in getting the mind not to move
if we're you know sort of changing our posture or you know getting comfortable
or you know moving around in any way
any kind of movement there's a very strong chance that the mind will be
moving also so what we're trying to um cultivate this week in tastes of
freedom are these very Advanced dharmic factors
that are essential for studying the mind
and setting the body is a big step in that direction
so that's one thing you can you can try out and and it you may find
that it does help the mind to settle down
and on Monday we explored feeling and tasting
as we place our awareness in the present moment and that feeling
um allows us to determine the feeling tone vedana
of whether our experience seems to be pleasant unpleasant or neither
and then in addition to the feeling tone to take a look at the emotional tone by
tasting the present moment uh and um
the word for this in probably is Raza and it literally means taste
um but it's it was used in even in the ancient times in um
theatrical treatises that you could have little plays or whatever that have a
different tastes as part of them and so it might be sweet it might be salty it
might be uh bitter it might be sour it might be umami
um and so if we can sort of figuratively uh use the idea of taste to
um go a little bit deeper in Discerning our present moment awareness
uh what how the mind is we'll have not only the feeling tone of
just the very basic blessing unpleasant neither but we'll also have a sense a more
um in be more in tune with the the flavor of our feeling
and that can be uh you know that that can be subject to any kind of figurative
uh use you'd like to use it for so that was that was Monday
um becoming free uh from grade eight and delusion
um by placing our awareness very steadily in the present moment
and then um yesterday we evoked the protection that is offered
by the factor of viveka it's usually translated as seclusion but
it really means um Independence
and uh and what it means in terms of meditation
is being secluded from unwholesome Habits
so if we have you know a habit of you know it's getting to be uh
breakfast time and we start thinking about what we're going to have for breakfast that's taking us away from our
meditation of being right here
and so when we see that we're tending to go off on some kind of a
Frack of distraction then that's a door opener too because it
gives us the choice to say no thank you and to come back
and those of you who have been meditating for some for some time
I'm sure you're well aware that there's a lot of coming back to do in
this practice and you know you just got to be patient
with it and keep coming back and little by little
you know what you'll start to get it you know the mind will start to realize that it's okay to say to say statistics excuse me to
stay centered and undistracted
for more than a minute or so
and today um I'd like to introduce to you uh the
next Factor which is called viraga in Pali and it
literally means um away from
design so V is away from and then Raga is a
desire and it also means uh die like the diet
for changing the color of a cloth so away from the dye uh the cloth being
being washed repeatedly and out in the sunlight drying the color gradually
Fades away and in the same way as we practice uh
cultivating seclusion like not getting so tempted by distractions of the Mind
um we get more and more adept at
um having moments of viraga where of uh this Independence takes the form of
being comfortable with letting things abate
you say okay here we go again another you know another thought train and then with the decision to just like
okay let's just let that one slow down and go
away so um
so that's um this passion and I I do have a
passion for etymology uh in English and in French and in Bali and so
I am going to take us on a little detour um
and I'd like to talk about uh
rumination and so I I went to [Music] um
the great Gospel of Wikipedia and it the rumination comes from the Latin ruminare
and uh ruminari means to chew again
and um you know the there's a whole group of
mammals hoof to mammals that are ruminants and what do they do
so um rumors are buffed herbivores
grazing or browsing mammals that are specialized models that are able to acquire
nutrients from plant-based Foods by fermenting
it in a specialized stomach prior to digestion through microbial actions
the process typically requires the fermented cud
D to be regurgitated and chewed again and so rumination is the process of
rechewing the cud the further breakdown plant matter and
stimulate digestion so
um there's a there's the the same thing is happening
in our minds when we ruminate it's maybe not quite as gross as um
regurgitating the contents of our stomach but um
there is now um there's been an article recently in the
American Psychiatric Association um that is about the cycle of repetitive
thinking and how it is that that gives birth to anxiety and depression
and uh as I shared with you in last February I'm kind of an expert in
um pathology of anxiety and depression
uh so let me read to you now what the APA says
in this article on um repetitive thinking
rumination involves repetitive thinking or dwelling on the negative feelings and
distress and their causes and consequences
repetitive negative aspect of Illumination can contribute to the
development of depression or anxiety and can worsen existing conditions
so viraga is about
you know when you're tempted to chew your gut like going to the past and relive the past and have that argument
again or how you could have done that better or what they did wrong you know or going into the future planning what's
going to come next because you know you've got to be perfect right uh so you you know you've got to keep
thinking about what you have to do you have to have your list you know in order
you know we can let go of that we can let go of all of that
it can abate it can fade away
just like when a stained cloth
is washed and put out in the sun to dry
esteem can go away the stain of greed hate and delusion
so that's uh that's the dormant for today on miraga
so um if you'd like a little homework assignment for the next uh 24 hours
if you see the Mind wanting to go down some unskillful track
that you pause and uh
and very sweetly invited to just gently fade away
thanks but no thanks I'll see it right here
hey thank you for the teaching Meg um so we'll take some
time here to see if anyone has any questions that they'd like to ask can you put it into the zoom chat or
raise your hand and will ask you to unmute
questions are welcome
or comments or complaints
okay got a bill with a question so let me go ahead and
thank you Bill you can go ahead and come on
okay yourself okay now I can do it um no questions just
um uh thank you for uh the kind of reminder I need most to just gently come
back and um and uh let go of those pesky
um determined thoughts that um uh aren't helpful uh that's really all thank you
Meg sure my pleasure
and then next we've got Layla go ahead and come off mute
Meg I just I wanted to say I'm so glad to see you back because I had missed
seeing you in the chat and I every once in a while I would ask someone does anyone know how Meg is
where's Meg so it's lovely to just feel you in the
community and thank you for sharing your deep experience and your practice I I
really appreciate it thank you so much for sharing that you
know um I disappeared because I was so
overwhelmed uh that I was making myself sick you
know I just needed to do less and um so I had to I had to drop it for a
while and um anyway I'm glad to be back too
okay Pat
a mute here how do I unmute you're unmuted already oh okay thank you
for trying to figure this thing out just to thank you so much
um I'm a body worker and the somatic
work that you do is so helpful yeah yeah yeah it's such a grounding
body keeps the score doesn't it the body keeps the score I think some challenges of my own this
this helps a lot thank you so much my pleasure really
um I gave this books and me we've got a question in chat from
Mariah um she says okay no complaints thank you so much Meg for
these timely teachings I wonder if you would be willing to speak a little bit about working with practicing with
trauma what does one need to change in one's practice
oh thank you Mariah that's a beautiful question
ah well most um from the survivors like myself
need to go through very very extensive and deep
Psychotherapy um psychoanalysis uh or
um as Pat was talking about um uh things like
um sensory experiencing
um you know the the bodily approaches uh to letting go of trauma so that's you
know that's kind of the the truth for most of us
um but that's not enough uh for where we want to go as Buddhist
practitioners um
we're not satisfied with just being okay with trauma
um so we we go from being a trauma victim
eventually becoming a trauma Survivor and in my case what I had to do
to make that shift was to really dig down deep in my
soul and my heart to forgive my parents
for harming me and
that required on my part
finally seeing that they had done the best they could
and their best was really not very good at all for a child especially an eldest
child who was the designated family skate goat
but that's the best they could do you know so um
I also um went to a really nice uh recreated Spirit Rock a long time ago with Joanna
Macy and she had us in a circle where we evoked our ancestors
and you know realizing that my parents childhood was undoubtedly
more difficult than mine and that the trauma is can be hereditary
it can be or the the the abusive Behavior can be hereditary
uh because if you don't know any better but also because you know
um as as the uh a guy from San Quentin says the hurt hurt
so if we've been hurt you know sometimes the the the the reaction to that is to
go out and hurt other people so uh and then he also says
um but the healed heal so this is this is you know the beautiful motivation of
letting go of our drama so the letting go like like all the
kinds of Letting Go that we're doing in this practice
is Progressive you know and it's not overnight and it has its ups and downs and it may take decades
uh but it is happening and you know if we look back
uh we can see progress so um Gill has helped me a lot also at one
point uh you know he was he doesn't usually uh
give you a devastating assignments only a few things you're ready for it
um but uh
at one point um he said to me uh Meg it's great that
uh you're no longer uh from a Survivor you're just uh I call my
Victim now you're a trauma Survivor but
why don't you just forget about being a trauma anything you don't have to relate yourself to
PTSD it doesn't have to be part of your identity
so that was a kind uh um teaching that he gave me
and I won't go into the the one that that um
burning apart but fortunately I I came back together again
anyway so I I hope that answers your question a little bit it's um
yeah it's it's forgiving is what allows us to
make that shift from identifying with
having had a dramatic experience
and in the state I have a friend who's a beautiful meditation teacher
uh Francisco and his experience with trauma was not because he was abused as a child he was in a devastating car
accident and just was you know in pieces afterwards and just constant extreme
pain day and night and I think I don't know if he's ever
affirmed this to me but my impression is that he was able to let go of his trauma
through the depth of his practice by really going deep in meditation
so uh Francisco if I'm misrepresenting you um please forgive me but I'm letting
everybody know that I'm not at all sure if you actually said anything like this
they're probably say okay big
okay thank you Megan uh Marlene asks is it really enough to Simply keep returning to the Dharma
and she said I missed you also Meg all right thanks
it's nourishing to teach also I remember I I taught last June I I almost a year
ago I think it was um and afterwards I was just blown away
because I had so much to learn from my own teachings but actually this is recorded in Nepal
account and there are examples of um monastics who teach and who become
awakened from teaching that that is that happens so um anyway thank you for giving me the
opportunity to teach it it is an enriching experience at albeit a
humbling one yeah so I actually make she was asking
um is it enough to Simply keep returning to the Dharma sorry I think I may have kind of misrepresented it it was a
comment when it actually was a question um from Marlene so
I tried to answer it that way oh okay okay great well maybe uh maybe I missed
the point um so you know it depends on your faith
really if you have faith in the path if you know that the tempter is Mara and
he is doing everything he can to get you to give up if you want to turn away
um you know it's up to you to want to practice and so we have to come to terms
with what is our deepest intention and if our deepest intention
is to put an end to Greed hate and delusion in ourselves
uh the way to do it is to follow this path that the Buddha
so beautifully laid out for us does that answer your question Marlene
I'm not sure she said anything in chat but I think that's uh
anyway Kevin thanks for asking again and thanks for um pushing me on it I appreciate it yeah yeah no problems
um so Robin also asks um and and let me know if you're kind of like on a uh you know if you're running out of time
Robin asked uh she says uh hi Meg thank you um and then she asked the room uh
ruminative type thoughts seem to be serving some purpose as in solving a
type of problem it seems that one both has to let those thoughts go
or encourage they're not reappearing but also to find underlying issue and let
that go is there anything in this way of thinking thank you Robin
great question Robin um I'm reminded uh and by the way I during
this week I'm kind of I'm borrowing a lot from Gil I had the Good Fortune to be on a two-week retreat with him
um in May um
but one thing he said was that he found it very useful to set aside
time every day to just uh sit back and have a cup of
tea and sort of you know look out the window or maybe sit down by the river
and watch the water go by without any agenda and just see what bubbles up
and that having a practice of doing that on a daily basis
gave him the latitude to let things like what you're saying uh that
you know these rumination types of thoughts they might be serving some good function
they'll come up and you'll see them and you'll you'll be enriched by that and and have some idea of what you want to
do with it sort of like lucid dreaming um
you know where you go to bed saying that you're gonna you have a question that you want to answer and you ask your
dreams to please fill you in and then in the morning you analyze your dreams and you get the answer to your question
um so you take time out to just do nothing you know and relax
the cup of tea or something and see what comes up
and then when you're in meditation you're not so tempted to go off on
a ruminating tangent because you know you'll be able to do it later
is that helpful okay and then also Marlene uh said Thank
you at Marlene and Robin both said thank you for um
for the comments on their questions
so I think that's all the questions we have in chat and uh um um so that'll kind of uh bring the Q a
to an end so thank you very much Meg for the time and the teachings
my pleasure thank you all
and uh if folks want to come off of mute as they uh you know and uh have any
Greetings or well wishes feel free to well thank you very much everyone for coming
thanks everybody good to see you all hey
thanks everyone hi Meg good to see you thank you thank you lovely to see faces
yeah it really is thank you so much Meg that was beautiful
foreign