okay welcome sweet to um see all the names
warm uh wishes to uh each other to me
um
okay let's uh settle in
as we settle in
they're kind of gentle effort not to fit this moment into everything
we think we know everything we know about ourselves
that meditation about life
but instead
kind of stance of uh not knowing
openness
it's so easy to take up the
residents in the familiar place of self
this is what I do when I said
sort of occupy a place
and look and my breath my body
listen whatever we do
maybe the instruction as we begin something like
don't locate yourself
and don't try to re-establish
all the familiar reference points
who what where I am
we just open in this new way
Gail sometimes says there's the what and how meditation
what we are attending to and how we're
attending
and sometimes we emphasize the what
so much the breath that we lose track of the how
and in the urgency of the what
get tight or incarnate
a certain kind of meditator self
some traditions really emphasize the what other meditative lineages
emphasize the how
maybe we can do both
foreign
we take good care of this moment
and let this moment take care of us
sense of being held by them
other ways we
locate the self
let's let it dissolve into openness of this moment
you don't need to know who you are to be awake
foreign
so we're we're exploring
uh this week how death can inform life they
the um implications for a Dharma practice
and yesterday was emphasizing neither over learning nor under learning
from mortality uh in some sense it's the most epic thing
in other where's not such a big deal
William James said uh the death is the worm at the core of the Human Condition
that turns us all into Melancholy metaphysicians
melancholy metaphysicians
um so I'm trying to to weave what you know
one of the core Buddhist teachings with this theme and
over the recent years really have become
acutely aware of the role
the future the sense of our future
plays in our inner life and
from the simple kind of recognition that so much of our thinking is essentially
the heart and mind coping with Anita
coping with Anita and a niche is usually usually
translated as impermanence but connotes unpredictability unreliability
uncertainty and were always trying to
predict the movements of uh an entropic world
right so much so many of the kind of movements of our mind
just abstracting away from this moment in order to understand
what's coming next and the Buddha said the world the world
trembles in all directions skills translation
the world trembles in all directions and even when we're thinking about the
past it's often in service of learning something that will help us
predict control or future
so we settle down we take a breath right
but the impelling force of the future of the coming
is is called is strong and
it's almost hard to conceive what a moment would be
outside of the sense that's something
comes next
as I said something I just like pause because I wanted to feel
the sense of oh yeah
something comes next it sends woven so deeply into this
moment something comes next
and so I say all this because death is an invitation
to contemplate futurelessness
contemplate futurelessness
something comes next something comes next
and then it doesn't and if there were nothing coming or if
we maybe we could say if we didn't care about what did come
there would be nothing to do but be awake
we call this samadhi nothing to do but be awake
no the kind of um busyness and strategizing the vigilance
and fear and worry all of it involves a future
and in our preoccupations and our our tending and vigilance and strategizing
our energy is moving in all these different directions what we want
what we're avoiding and the sense of futurelessness
simplifies everything right contemplating mortality helps us
sense this
and we do it as a kind of thought experiment okay this moment just this moment right in some ways that's what
every meditation instruction is
our mortality allows us to actually get a kind of visceral hit
of no future
and maybe you can actually sense intuitively how differently
the world might feel if we were not preoccupied with becoming
with uh just hope and that might be
then if if uh if all we had was this moment
however long this moment is all we had was this moment
I don't think any of us would doubt the Dharma
awareness what matters so much
there would be nothing to do but be very very awake
the brain brain scientist um writing about
this theme a Halloween Slater
she says the essence of our theory is quite simple our main contention
is that meditation gradually brings the practitioner more and more into the present moment
thereby progressively updating temporally deep predictive processing in
the brain we contend this not only reduces
episodic future thinking and decision making but can also explain the more
unusual experiences reported by meditators including the loss of self-other Distinction and the cessation
of time if awareness rests in the here and now all mental processes that involve
abstract and temporally in deep processing
should logically Fall Away including a sense of self time space and body representation
we suggest that meditation Reigns in the mind's habitual tendency to abstract
away from the Here and Now until all phenomenological distinctions
stop metaphorically
we suggest that meditation prunes the counter factual tree
ruins the counter factual tree Coulda Shoulda Woulda
the sense of what could have been what might have
been the alternatives to this moment
the counter factual tree is pruned
all the kind of I remember I don't know what I'm talking about but I went from
when I was a kid in class like potential energy kinetic energy right
um it's almost like um the potential energy of the moment
dissolves and whatever is here is here
it says uh a contemplation of futurelessness we put
all of our hope into the present moment
and all of our hope into the present moment
and so we have to put down our life
to put down our life center our heart awareness what's here
very um early in uh in practice
I got the instruction to sit sit sit
like a dying person and uh
in a lot of ways uh to hear that right but um
one of the ways I heard it was sit like a person
without a future
and nothing left to do but be awake in a
moment like that
and so the fragility of our body contemplation
of its end all of this can rather than frenzy our mind can
settle us invites the contemplation
of a futurelessness or to live this moment
is if it were all there is
office for consideration and uh
of course when we when we do this when we sit in this way when we practice uh
contemplate futurelessness know it
um it also clarifies the kind of life we wish to lead
and so these different Realms these Realms of like very deep surrender and
then organizing a Dharma life they speak to one another
so we'll keep going tomorrow thank you thank you all sweet to uh to
be with you