e
so good evening I think the volume's a little bit low
right I take me well let's
see you didn't think it was low I feel like it's a little bit low for
me how how is
G okay let's see how how is this is that's a little bit better I don't want to have to strain my
voice feel like I'm yelling at you guys okay so welcome welcome
everybody especially for those of you haven't been here before really warm welcome
and I think many of you know we have a 45 minute silent sit now so I'll ring the bell in about 45
minutes and then I'll give a short
talk
e
good evening and welcome welcome everybody nice to see you
all so today I'd like to talk a a little bit more about kind of a topic that I
introduced last week it's perfectly fine if you didn't hear last
week but it's not unusual that when we're meditating especially for a longer
sit you know 45 minutes we might notice there's this thought there's this
like uh narration this uh inner dialogue or inner I don't know conversation maybe
that's happening something like uh I can't meditate or well I've been practicing
for so long and still you know here it is after 45 minutes when is this dang
Bell going to ring anyways right is she
[Laughter] awake so at the same time like I can't
meditate or what's my mind is out of control or maybe at the same time or not
the exact same time but within the same minute there might be somebody like well
I'm sitting up straighter than that other person or I'm quieter than that other person or whatever it might be
right there's these ways in which we have these thoughts where we're comparing ourselves to
others sometimes we think that we're better sometimes we think that we're worse and sometimes we think that we're
the same you know however it is it's uh pretty common to compare
ourselves and it's also pretty common that in these comparisons we come up uh
feeling not so good there's a way in which we're kind of like beating ourselves up there's this inner critic
that gets activated and it can be pretty persuasive be seem to be pretty
authoritative and pretty loud this inner critic we I've talked
about this a number of times a number of different settings but uh I think it's an important thing to just talk about
because it has such a big influence on us whether we recognize it or not and
we'll talk about that a little bit more later but first I'll just spend a
little bit moment describing this inner critic it's this way that this maybe
this inner voice that's constantly putting us down belittling us it's has this self
judgment as negativity like you can't do this or
gosh this is you won't be able just you won't be able to do it or it's so it's
just awful some of the things that we say to ourselves you're a loser or you know whatever it might be we would never
say to anybody else but sometimes we say to ourselves blaming ourselves for any
experience of discomfort or noticing how the mind is seemingly out of control and
can't quite get it to settle down there's this way that this inner critic
kind like is nagging at us wanting us to behave differently and be better somehow
not maybe it's not even clear exactly what this better is and there's
fascinating for me it's a little bit fascinating how it also comes with this sense of
Shame somehow like this feeling of inadequacy is like we shouldn't be this
way there's something like inherently wrong with
us of course none of these things are true but we believe them we believe so
many of our thoughts of course we do we're having these thoughts I'm having it it must be true and so much about practice is
seeing how we don't have to believe our thoughts and I'll talk a little bit more
about that today but I also just want to point out also one more other thing
about this inner critic is this um has an a tone of
harshness it's not a kind warm loving thing it has this this uh this
environment or this climate that gets created of harshness as opposed to like warmth and
kindness so this feeling of inadequacy of not being enough or somehow The Who I
Am or how I am is not enough it's of often based on
comparing and whether that comparing is explicit or implicit there's a way in
which we're comparing to this idea we have about how we should
be this idea about how other people
are or maybe it's an idea of how have been in the
past so is there's this comparison like it should be maybe we have this glorified ideal out there
somewhere and then we have our experience and noticing the Gap and something wrong with me terribly wrong
with me or this sense of because I'm not worthy because I'm not uh meeting
whatever I'm getting compared to whatever I compare myself to well something that I want want to
introduce is this whole activity of
comparing I'm talking about how we compare and we find ourselves falling up short but also this activity of
comparing to others or to how we used to be whether we think that we're better or whether we think that we're
the same but it's just the activity of comparing is one way in which we are
creating a sense of of me sense of I am like
this and this is subtle but it's also
pervasive and so we may be so accustomed to it that we don't even notice it but
this sense of I'm like this and there's this reification or this solidity or this
sense of I'm like this and I'm always like this there's something about my
inherent meanness we have this idea like just to be me means to have this quality I'm I a
terrible meditator I'll never be able to meditate correctly or somehow for me I had certainly this
idea that whatever I was doing wasn't enough like I had to do more like I had
to work harder or get more education or
work longer hours or move up the corporate ladder back when I was in Corporate America you know there I had
this feel like it always had to be more it's exhausting have you
noticed some of you might have noticed this right but not only does this way of kind
of uh comparing for me I kind of had this idea that it just wasn't enough somehow
doesn't matter what I compared myself to and at that time I'm not even sure I would have been able to articulate this
to you it's something that now looking back I can see so clearly from this vantage point but from that when I was
in the midst of it it was just natural and of course I mean that's because all
my peers right had this feeling too this is how often organizations work they
have this sense of you have to do more but the sense of me also is this when we
compare is this solidification like I'm like this but also what comes with that
is a sense of I'm like this and you are like that we are
separate there's and this distinction between us is very clear these these aren't like
necessarily um explicit thoughts that we have but inherent in the sense of me is
a sense of separateness and of course we are separate right I'm here in this uh body
and with this Skin Barrier and you guys are over there each of you in your own so I'm not saying anything that's you
know metaphysical or I'm just saying that the sense of being
separate sense of being isolated sometimes this gets
highlighted and sometimes it's not even there it's really fluid and if we think
about it with our thinking mind of course we're of course separate I don't know what Diana is talking about but what I'm pointing to is
experience not thoughts experience so for
example when we're doing one of our favorite activities
gardening Sports
hiking doing jigs up puzzles drinking tea with our friends
coffee whatever it might be there isn't this inherent sense of or really strong
sense of being separate we're just doing what we're doing we're just hiking we're just in
nature we're just drinking coffee as opposed to these other are
times when we have a real sense of I'm inadequate I'm not enough or something
like this inherent with this is a sense of
separation and this and probably you've noticed there's a sense of Dua with this
right and Dua representing this word has such a really wide range from this really subtle very subtle very subtle
sense of H something's not quite right
to just these horrifying terrifying experiences on the other end of the
spectrum and hopefully you're not experiencing over here on this end of
spectrum where things are just the absolute worst but there's often this sense of like dissatisfaction like
things aren't quite right need to be better want to be a little bit more
comfortable so the Buddha pointed to this sense of this comparing and the
sense of me that gets created with comparing making a me and comparing are
exactly the same thing kind of looked at from different aspects and there's this way that this
making a me we could also say is making a self a self is this thing that uh has
this inherent existence that is separate from everything else again I'm not saying that you don't
exist that would be silly to say something like that I'm pointing to this
what I was pointing to maybe earlier is like this sense of separateness and this real distinct sense of uh I'm
me and Buddhist practice is not anything about like destroying the self or
exploding the self or dissolving the self or erasing the self or emerging the
self with some big uh Unity of with something else that's not
what's being pointed to at all instead what's being pointed to is a
type of understanding about the self that brings
Freedom a type of understanding that brings ease a type of understanding that brings
peace and sense of well-being that's what's being pointed to with all these
teachings and so when we start to understand like deeply like in our
hearts and minds and maybe even in a way in our bodies then we realize that well
actually there isn't anything here here that I have to
protect I have to defend that I have to worry about and there's this way that uh when
we recognize that fear just gets released because we don't
have to protect and defend so what there isn't the fear there and there's this
Freedom that arises this beautiful
Freedom so we might say if we've listened to this talk so far like okay
comparing is making a self or a me and this is about understanding a self so we
can find more freedom Buddhist practice ice we would say is about that then we might say okay then I just need to stop
comparing we can't this is what humans do this is part of you know The Human
Experience only the most realized people don't compare so instead we do like what we do
with everything in our practice that seems like an obstacle or a
difficulty we use it as a Gateway we use it as a a stepping stone
for a greater understanding it's a Gateway for some different type of
practice so instead of getting having this idea like oh I shouldn't be comparing I shouldn't be
judging this is what humans do of course we do right part of it is like this
discernment is this helpful not helpful is this person going to help me or harm
me you know this is just how we're wired they amount of judging that we do right
some of the judging we do is extra so we can make a distinction between judging and discernment but
there is a way in which we are always kind of like comparing so how do we use this when we
notice that this is happening how can we use this as a way to deepen our practice to find a way to Greater ease and Peace
and Freedom so one way is to just when we
notice that this comparing is happening I'll talk a little bit more about that in a moment but when we notice that this
is happening and part of it could be because this inner critic is really loud
I'm lousy I'm a terrible meditator I don't even know why I come to these meditation centers or I mean obviously
it could be the other I'm the best one here I don't even know why Diana is there teaching I should be the one
that's teaching or you know sometimes we have these ideas like what does she know what does the teacher
know we all have these types of ideas right I could do a better job something
like this so here's one thing how we can make this as a gateway to Greater
Freedom when we discover that we're doing this comparing is we can ask
ourselves how does this comparing impact how I see myself and others
how does this comparing impact how I see myself and
others the act of comparing maybe You' noticed that you're already seeing yourself in a dim light but how does
this act of comparing also influence how you see
others so whether or not you answer that question just asking that question can
be enormously helpful how is this impacting me a because asking that question means
that you're not completely lost in it you are aware that this comparing is
happening and asking the question kind of reinforces this a way of not being
completely lost in it recognizing that it's happening so to ask the question
reinforces this is something that's happening this comparing but but it
also highlights or maybe reminds us that when we feel bad about ourselves when we
feel good about ourselves when we're comparing ourselves influences what we
experience and how we interpret what we
experience we all have this experience of getting up on the wrong side of the the bed I like to give this example
because I think all of us know this the way in which we're cranky we haven't had enough to sleep eat or we haven't had
enough sleep or that person is doing that thing that annoys me so much and I'm getting like
angry and then we just notice that everything starts to irritate us our
tempers are short and we just notice all the
terrible things that are happening
in contrast if we have this great sleep we're on vacation we have fantastic
meals spending times with our loved ones we're so happy to be where we are maybe
it's like aesthetically visually beautiful we at the beach or in the mountains whatever it
is have some ease the same person doing that thing
that irritates you oh yeah okay there's that person's doing the thing that irritates me but you don't get so angry
about it or we might notice these ways of like
we're saying to ourselves oh there you go again
you're whatever like I'm trying to think like this long list of things that we say to ourselves for me sometimes I find
myself SC Diana and but I say it out loud like what I'm tryed to like focus
and I have like some work to get done and I find myself like you know doing something else and like oh yeah yeah
yeah you really have to do this I sometimes I find myself saying Diana out
loud and that's like it's a little wakeup call yes get to
work so when we there's this sense of ease then maybe we just say oh there
okay that's from my case that's just doing what Diana does doesn't have to
mean anything that I'm an inherently bad person or inherently uh little bit
unfocused or it doesn't have to mean anything it just means that that's what's happening at that
time but there's this way that also asking this question how does this
comparing impact how I see myself and others highlights this that the way that
we are looking at experience effects
experience so we always have lenses through which we are
looking we may not even recognize this there may be a way we think well I'm just seeing the way things are of course
we are of course I am but how can it be that sometimes the exact same
experience and if I wish I could give a good example off the top of my head
or maybe it's you know putting the dishes away in the dish or putting the dishes in the dishwasher that way that's
not quite right you should have the plates all going the certain way or something when our people that we share
our households with there's times in which it irritates us and there's a time in which that exact same thing doesn't
irritate us which is the real way they do
it right it's impossible that doesn't exist the only thing that exists is the
way that we are perceiving it at that moment but another moment we might
perceive it differently so the lenses through which
we are looking influences what we see not only how we feel about it but
what we see we might notice oh yeah they other irritating things when we're
irritated or when you're relaxed and happy maybe you've been on a Meditation Retreat and you've had some real ease
and have some time to settle in then you go for walking meditation I know I've had this experience a lot going out for
walking meditation and just think like wow this plant is so beautiful I never
noticed how these leaves are this particular shape and it's bushy and you
know things that ordinarily you just walk on path but after on Retreat there's this way they're just beautiful
or the color of uh somebody's jacket I remember one time on this Retreat just think like that is that color blue is so
beautiful that person is so lucky to have that jacket that's that color right just these things just you know you
become more sensitive to so asking this question when we
notice that we're comparing asking this question how does this comparing impact how I see myself and
others does a few things one it helps kind of create a little space between us
and the comparing so we're not lost in the comparing two it reminds us that the way
that we see things influences how we see things but three it might
also bring some insight that there's always a way in which we are viewing
things and that way changes so that means that the way
things are changes of course it
does but sometimes we get stuck in this idea that things are a certain way and this is just the way that it
is so we're always looking through one lens or another maybe it's the one of
irritation maybe it's the one of peas or maybe it's the one of boredom or whatever it is and that using that
lens affects things and if we intentionally switch to a different lens
we will start to notice things differently and this is partly how meditation practice
works so that's one way we can use this comparing as a
Gateway and another way is that we can notice that I talked about how this
is like a human thing that we all do humans compare themselves to
others there's a way that we can tune into yes this is very often painful to
be comparing ourselves to others not only because sometimes we don't show up in the best light but even if we do show
up in the best light in the comparison we decide that actually we're Superior and better than whomever we're comparing
ourselves to then we have to always protect that and make sure that they don't think that
we're inferior somehow we have to project this idea that uh or protect or
project that we're somehow better yeah yeah yeah I got it I I know how to do this you you don't have to teach me
anything actually I know it all that's a little bit of an exaggeration but there are these subtle
ways in which we often are think that we're
better so there's this suffering this and might be subtle or it might not be
subtle that always with this comparison whe what whatever the outcome
is of that comparison even if we think that we're the same there's this way that we always have to evaluate am I still the same did they if they do that
do I do that so was this busyness that's associated with it so one way that we can use this
comparing as a gateway to Greater freedom is to connect to the common
Humanity of this experience oh right this is what it
means to be human humans do this and there's a way that we can just
say oh yeah just like that person there and that person there and that person there and that person there and that
person there and that person there right everybody does it just like
me there's a way that can be kind of connecting we're all trying to find our
way with this and sometimes people are deciding that they are superior and they need to
somehow for whatever reason need to let us know that they consider themselves Superior we can say okay this is this
person doing this comparing it's the human thing we could say like knock yourself out but I'm not going to buy
into it I'm not going to buy into this idea that I have to be inferior in order for you to be
superior we could just notice this is what humans do we don't have to get angry at them we don't have
[Music] to be disappointed in them or make them be different we can just say yes I can
see that you are doing this comparing I do it too and it could just
end there could just end there without having to agree or disagree with
it so these are two ways that actually can be powerful ways to work with this
comparing as a gateway to Greater freedom but what if we find that we
can't even do this working as it with a Gateway because we're just completely lost in it and this what this idea of
this gateway to Greater ease or stepping stone just feels like just not
accessible CU sometimes when we are in the midst of comparing and we are sure
that we're Superior or better because this person like certainly we wouldn't do
that or we think that we inferior if we don't have access to maybe use this to
the practice that's okay this is what happens too it's also as part of the
what it means to be a human I want to talk about what are some things that we can do when we
notice the first is you have to notice and so part of a mindfulness
practice or meditation practice is getting to know like what the Mind does getting to know kind like this
inner dialogue getting to know this inner voice and to recognize when this
comparing is happening and you just have to just notice
it you might just start doing it again but then notice it again and then you might
start doing it again and then notice again and this can be your practice maybe your just mindfulness of
comparing and we shouldn't underestimate how powerful that alone can
be can like oh there's comparing oh okay that's interesting and then maybe we just do
what we're going to do next and then oh yep there's comparison that's inter interesting one thing that can be
helpful and can be powerful is to count
them I can't do this this is ridiculous oh that's comparison that's comparing
one see that person is making so much noise then I'm not making oh that's
comparison number two and then just count and there's this way of counting
it starts to feel it takes away some of the authority and
the I don't know negativity what and it can it starts to be kind of fun like wow
327 you know really no wait 327 328 you know
like or you can't remember but it's a way to kind like shift our relationship to it because often when we notice that
we're doing this we have this idea that we shouldn't and then there's this aversion and then the aversion kind of
like sticks us to it when we're get tangled up in it so the counting is a way that kind of like
normalizes and maybe UND does some of the aversion to it so that's one thing
to do first you have to notice and then just start counting how many times it comes up and that can
shift the second is to notice how it feels in the
body like really how it feels in the body and this can be really subtle
I talked about how there's a real distinct sense of me versus the
world so there's a subtle sense of contraction there's a subtle sense of
like this sense of a limit that's like me and here's my boundaries and there's the world and everything that's on this
side is there a way that you could feel into that feel into either this subtle
sense of contraction or feel into this sense of
being separate or having a limit or maybe the sense of comparing is if
you're noticing there's a lot of like the superiority con seeit maybe there's a sense of this even if I find myself to
this in my body like puffing out my chest a little bit maybe you might even notice like the chest gets puffed out or
if you're noticing that the outcome of the comparing is that uh of
being inferior you know notice that the shoulders and the head might droop a
little bit these might be subtle or they might be obvious but just to feel in the
body and to do this with a sense of kindness and curiosity like wow okay how
does this show up in the body not so that we can chastise ourselves but just
so that we can notice because again kind of like
transforming the comp comparing into a sematic
experience is a way that we can interrupt this momentum of
comparing so tuning into the felt sense to the bodily experience is a way that
takes some of the power out of and the and the this Loop that we find ourselves
in out of this comparing and then maybe there's a way that we can invite the body to
relax what when we notice how this comparing gets felt maybe there's a way that we can invite it to
relax and some ways that the way that we would relax is to bring a little bit
more spaciousness or openness and that can be literally or
figuratively figuratively is maybe we might to be focused in on maybe we feel
this contraction this tightness right here in the chest and to bring to
relax can be to bring more spaciousness is to literally just maybe open up awareness to the whole
body to recognize that you're sitting and this is what it feels like to sit if
you're standing that's what it feels like to be standing so open up awareness
a little bit to the whole body open up be beyond the
body this really kind of like loose spacious awareness it's really big and
that is just receiving experiences most notably exp
receiving sound or maybe there's like a a a
sensation in the knee or the back or something that arises is there a way that the awareness can be really big and
relaxed next and then like maybe this uh twinge in the knee might arise a sound over
there might arise and we just let these experiences arise and then pass away
while we're just keeping awareness really relaxed and open often we do mindfulness where we're like on one
thing like the breath in particular feeling the breath perfectly legitimate way to practice but there can be really
wise and helpful to practice in a different way to really open up
is there a way that we can use wisdom practices so I talked
about mindfulness notice the thoughts mindfulness of the body opening up the awareness but also we can bring in some
wisdom practices to help us with this comparing and this also can really help
uh with our bring more Peace and Freedom and ease and this is to remember that
our experience is always changing we know this if we've every
time we've looked at or meditated we've noticed that things are always changing
every meditation session is different it might have some similar
qualities but the actual session is different and of course actually all of
our experiences are changing otherwise we would there we would be I
guess blocks of concrete or something right something that's always changing
and so we can remind ourselves of that we can remind that uh things there's
this inconstancy things are changing and so
we might be comparing and can say well we're not always inadequate we're not
always feeling in adequate we're not always the best we're not always best
better than others we're not always comparing and so just to bring that in
that this uh this flexibility that it's not always like that it kind of like uh
drains out some of its Authority like oh yeah this is just what's happening in
the mind right now this comparing is just what's happening in the mind right
now in a few moments it'll be different might come back to comparing but then
it'll be different and it might come back so there's a way in which we can like grab onto an experience that's
happening in the mind think like this is a problem I have to fix it I have to make it go away but if we notice like oh
yeah our thoughts are always changing then we can maybe relax a little bit around it and that we'll see that it's
changing rising and passing getting more intense less intense going away and then you know we
start thinking about yeah what's for dinner you know or whatever you know other types of thoughts that we're
having and maybe one last thing that I'll say about uh working with this
comparing is remember that comparing are just
thoughts they're just thoughts how many thoughts do you have
in a day a lot
how stable or solid are thoughts they're not right they're wispy
right we can't like grab onto them we can't point to them precise really we
could like just blow them
away so these compains they're just thoughts thoughts come and go there are
dime a dozen you'll have many of them you might have a thought the sky is
blue you might have a thought the carpet is soft you might have a thought there's
a blue line right here these are all Just Thoughts like how come some of them are you really
holding on to and some of them you're not this is a question to ask yourself
this is part of the human Habits Like We grab on to some of them and then we make them mean something without recognizing
that actually all thoughts are are ephemeral all thoughts are insubstantial
doesn't mean they're not helpful it doesn't mean that we don't need them but it does mean that we don't have
to hold on and grab on to them thoughts are helpful and
useful until they're not so we need them but there's a way in
which we are often kind of like repeating repeating or kind of like obsessing in a certain kind of way and
that's extra you don't have to do that so this idea of
comparing that we humans All Humans
Do often when we do this compared not always but not for everybody sometimes
we come out feeling like this inadequate in some kind of way this inner critic
gets activated in so many different ways and there's a way in which we can
recognize oh this is just comparing we can use this recognition of comparing to
connect with other people this is what humans do doesn't mean I'm a bad person and just because this person is
comparing themselves to me and they seem to have come up with a particular evaluation doesn't mean we have to go
along with it doesn't mean other people have to go along with our evaluations either
right and we can work with comparing we don't have to make it go away we can
recognize that when the comparisons are shown up a certain way it influences
us actually everything influences us but maybe that's a whole other Dharma talk
but this idea that it's part of the way that we make this
self and we can use notice our comparing as a way to maybe soften the sense of
self so there's more ease and freedom we could do that with mindfulness practices or with some
wisdom practi IES so I think I'll stop
there and I thank you for your attention and maybe I'll open it up and see if
there's any questions or comments and then I'm recognizing that
I'm tethered here but the microphone is there so thank
you I don't know if anybody has a comment or a question or something they'd like to say
okay maybe Bill if you have something or you don't have to but uh you're included
in the people are in of course um well going back to uh being on Retreat and
then you know suddenly everything looks beautiful I'm it's kind of trivial but I
remember Gil once saying on r Treat Retreat even you're walking maybe at
Spirit Rock out in the uh Wilderness Area next to it on the
Hills Trails and you see a a crumpled candy wrapper that someone had
littered onto it even that can look beautiful
yes thank you Bill thank you right it's amazing right there are times we might
like think like oh my gosh how can somebody leave it there and I make it a whole story I'm always thinking that so
I but I try to remember that story g s that's good thank you Bill thank
you
yes hi thanks for the talk so you talked about comparing and I guess you may have
answered a question already but my question was so how do you confront um these feelings of inadequacy or shame
name um I think he sort of said to sort of focus on the feeling in the present moment but I sort of noticed that with
myself and and some of the people I sort of compete with in sports and whatnot and and just sort of having feelings of
like inadequacy or or whatnot and constant Loop of comparing then he talked about counting I was like I'm not
going to get past two or three it's exhausting but there's a feet I wouldn't attempt yeah yeah so I I will say that
I've given a number of talks on this so you could look up a like inner critic and I've done a number of series on it
but here's one thing that I didn't say that I'll offer right now often when the inner critic is up and running there is
this um there's this part of the voice it's like oh I'm doing it wrong or I'm not
enough or something like this but if we could ask this
question how am I right now you just ask that how am I right now
there's this way if how am I right now and which which we can like tune in to
like how we are and feel how we are that is a way it's like it's an act of kindness and care to just turn towards
ourselves and how am I to do it with some care with some care instead of just
feeling like I'm this feeling of inadequacy or something like this so that's one thing is to just ask cuz
often we're asking like how could I do it better or what am I doing wrong or there's these types of questions that
are sometimes uh implicit in the background but to change the question to
how am I and then we might discover I'm sad I'm lonely I'm hungry I'm and that's
just how it is but it interrupts this feeling of inadequacy thank
you thank you um his question brought up for me one thing another suggestion you
made uh which was something like now I was struggling to remember exactly like how to phrase it U but it's something
like how is this act of comparing affecting how I'm relating or affecting
the situation or how I'm relating to others uh and I want to remember that but it doesn't
feel uh easy to remember in my mind this uh unless there's like
a neater way of you know more succinct expression or
something yeah a succinct way is to notice the yeah I I could give like a
talk on this I I'll say this succinctly and hopefully it'll make sense and if it doesn't we might have to work with this
a little bit there's the the way of looking like what is the way of looking
like what is the lens that we're looking through because the way of looking affects what's being seen so if we just
ask ourselves what is the lens I'm seing things through maybe it's another way or what frame of reference am I using or
something like this yeah cool thank you welcome okay okay so thank you all for
your attention and I'll stay up here if you have some more questions otherwise I uh wish you a wonderful rest of the
evening thank
you
e