great hello and welcome everyone it's lovely to be with you it's lovely to to
see you and feel your presence from all the different time zones you're
joining in from and uh just makes my heart smile too
feel connected to you oh it's lovely community so
um so for today's practice um coming home coming home to our bodies
coming home to our to our heart and treating ourselves
um kindly this sense of I'm home I'm home
I'm home which can be a concept but we can bring up anywhere even when we're
not at home to feel at home to feel at home in our bodies to feel at home
in our minds to feel at home with who this person is to feel at home
and it can be helpful to borrow the sense of being home from actual sense of being home or maybe
you feel home at nature or maybe there's a particular place in your home that you feel particularly cozy and at home about
um I um know that there have been times that I felt completely at home in my bed
there's a sense of coziness and comfort like oh yeah I'm home I can ah I can
rest I can um let my heart relax it's okay it's
okay it's okay sweetheart it's okay dear their sense of rest a sense of ease sense of nourishment kindness
um that can can accompany this feeling of being home
so the idea of being home in our heart being home in our bodies
bringing this sense of kindness uh and ease so that's the theme that's
the invitation for us to explore and um have more invitations in the guided
meditation so let's begin let's begin so
foreign so settling suddenly in your body if you need to move and shift
to arrive to settle in this body
coming home as if we were a turtle with our home
carried on our backs our body being our home
coming home to our body coming home
as our thoughts might be might have been going to the past and
future inviting our thoughts our mind to come
home to the body come home with kindness It's a generous
it's a generous invitation to come home coming home
collecting ourselves collecting ourselves coming home
feeling our feet our legs if you're sitting on a cushion on the Earth
feeling your hands on our lap feeling our hands touching one another
coming home to the sensations that are easily felt
help ground us help make us present coming home
coming home to the amazing sensations of Art
body on the cushion or the chair inviting our body to relax we're home
we're home I am home
I am home I'm home
if it feels right maybe even saying it out loud once dropping it in I am home
I am home I am home
coming home to the in-breath
this in breath is home my home
don't leave home be at home
is out breath this one just this one is my home
stretching stretching your heart your mind your awareness
at home inside within the out breath this out breath
in breath this out breath
expressions of my home I am home
and if the mind a p of the Mind wonders
to a thought to plan past future
come sweetheart come home kindly so kindly lovingly
with all the love in your heart invite your awareness to come home
your body here here come home sweetheart hello
resting being nourished with the breath
a calm peace a loving presence
of being at home in yourself
and I love being home in my body my heart with the breath with
this breath
loving being here so much just here
nowhere else being home stretching stretching my heart my mind
feeling nourished In This Moment nowhere else to be nothing to do
no matter what is arising what is present in the body and the mind and heart
cultivating the joy the nourishment of being here at home
and my own shell the joy of being here
just here not fomo the fear of missing out which
is common in our culture but the joy of being here the joy of missing out
cultivating the joy of missing out being right here at home
Jomo cultivating Jomo
so nourishing this moment
peace
breath lovingly here nourishingly here
softening the body relaxing the body
any tension or tightness is corrected finding our way home again
this moment lovingly present here
simply nourishing or heart her mind with kindness and presence
watering the flower
that is me with care coming home
this breath
and if there are thoughts their self-judgments are rising
challenges it's okay welcome them home
the home of your heart is not a dungeon it's a castle of
kindness trust it drastic
let yourself be at ease your home of kindness and let everything
be here judgments thoughts emotions can relax
there's plenty of room and this Castle they can all be here
and you can rest
um
coming home being at home
no heart our body
our spacious mind home
[Music]
and as we start to turn
to end this sitting period together
shading even if just for one moment you felt at home you're feeling at home
and your body and your heart in your mind
maybe in this moment you appreciate the joy
of being here just here this amazing
moment of being alive in this body being home
in your heart
and this life that is yours all the ups and downs the gifts the
blessings and just being home
the sense of uprightness dignity
claiming reclaiming your home
this is my home I am at home
I'm always at all it's always here
never too far may I remember
as I remember In This Moment
and I'm home and may I love
myself give my self-permission to be home
from this place of love and acceptance
for myself
invite others to feel at home with me to feel cared for
to feel relaxed at peace
offer them my home
my ease my goodness
may I know may I remember
to be at home with love with care for myself may all beings everywhere feel at home
their bodies and their hearts with love and care may all beings including myself be at
ease may all beings wake up
including myself [Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
foreign thanks for exploring this this idea of of meta kindness
cultivating well-being there's a sense of coming home coming home with kindness
special the spaciousness coming home offering herself
ourselves a sense of home and others as well the same way that
maybe we come home from a long trip oh I'm home ah how nice to be home
ah my heart's relaxed
that sense of ease and tapping into that
remembering how that feels offering that to us ourselves to kindness care being
home at our bodies this home of ours this mind of ours as I
said does not need to be a dungeon what if we see it as a palace
of kindness with plenty of space
so so with that practice I'd like
welcome back everyone the rooms are closed so we have some time
um if you have Reflections actually I'm going to change the settings so that you can type in chat if you like if it's uh
only to me if it's private then I will read your reflection not your name and
if you want to type it to everyone you can do that or you can raise your Zoom hand if you haven't shared in a while
would love to hear from you your reflection not just for your own benefit but to afford the benefit of everyone
what did you discover with this practice of meta loving kindness is being home
coming home to the body the Mind claiming our home
right here right now in the present moment Ali please
hi Nikki hi Ellie hi nice to be here and then actually in our
group all three of us were kind of like really resonating with your phrase of um home I have arrived and I brought that
uh saying from tikknot Hall and that's what it says you know there you have it it's the different normal centers I am
home I've arrived and we were just like kind of like uh flowing with love into that phrase
I am home I'm arrived beautiful lovely yeah all three of us
thank you thank you so much Ellie this is lovely for me to hear yeah thanks for
sharing that and also sharing that from uh technology I hadn't connected
um but also yeah technatan as I am home that's right I'll I'll tell you now since you you shared this I'll I'll tell
you guys where the inspiration from today's practice came from because I was away as you
might know I wasn't here for a few days and uh I just arrived late last night
from a very intensive trip and today as I was this morning as I was or
stretching and being on my yoga mat and just lying down I had a sense of oh I'm home I I
actually said out loud I am home and oh my heart just relaxed feeling that oh
yeah I'm home ah I'm home it's so nice to be home so there was just a sense of
arriving in my body in my heart and and the moment the moment
and then realizing actually in many ways this this home I carry my home with me
always and yet there's this sense of inspiration from being at home this this
memory of being home that we can take so that's uh that's pulling the the uh the
curtain back what's with with the inspiration for today's practice was for my own practice
to happy hour other Reflections what did you discover
anything else you discovered I see if someone's puppy that just made
me happy to see your puppy being at home such a sweet cute puppy yeah
oh sweet any other Reflections about this
practice what worked what didn't all good Dawn
um all right thank you Nikki thank you tsanga good to see everyone the um you
mentioned the uh something that affected the thoughts are not a dungeon and I was sort of right in
the middle of like sort of this negative thoughts and and sort of this and it really did feel like a bit like a
dungeon like I couldn't get out and it was um anyway it sort of gave me a little bit of perspective and to think
of it sort of like they're a little bit broader and anyway I just wanted to thank you for that ever
thank you so much really appreciate you you reflecting on how this invitation
actually in in real time was helpful as there were challenging thoughts oh it
really does feel like a dungeon this the getting collapsed in it and then opening
up oh yeah there can be that realization can bring in a lot more ease and spaciousness lovely thank you dot and
now I see your hand please um there's something something happened
in meditation and he said absolutely this is a castle
uh something shifted actually those negative thoughts and and and unwanted
thoughts they used to have funds on me and suddenly with that kind of space home
they melted away no no more fans they just come and go
so I don't know if that makes sense but yeah it absolutely makes sense thanks so
much for sharing that now this is beautiful that just makes my heart so happy yay beautiful thanks for sharing
that insight and the way that your heart your mind found
in more space but just realizing actually this is a castle I usually
consider it you know my mind has the pattern or the tendency to think of it as well kind of collapse but actually if
I realize really how spacious it is the difficult self-judgmental thoughts
they ah they relax they Melt Away there's a lot more space this is a
spacious Castle so remember that now this is something that works for you this is something that works for you and
it's always here it's always just remind yourself when it gets crowded or cramped oh sweetheart dear dear Nell this is a
castle your heart your body your mind is a castle this is great thanks always for
sharing ah bar price your hand
thank you um for me when I think about home it's the
the warmth of the community of being it's not so much my house because I've
only lived I I'm not living in a place that I've been in for years and years
and years and yet I'm home I'm home because I'm surrounded with
people I love and you know my friends and family my
community it's like they are the that sweet the sweetness
um that makes my heart feel at peace
beautiful thank you Barbara I love it it's
um it's not so much that home is a place but home is a concept home is the sense
of love the sense of Care community that surrounds you so anywhere is home
exactly that's exactly right and and here in the Sangha too
yeah yeah that is just beautiful exactly so so well said and as you said this
it's also reminded me of something um also something that I think maybe happened earlier today in my own
practice because for me you know I've lived here for a few years but not that long and and sometimes I've said that um
this may sound strange but so so my mom who passed away some years ago she gave
me a carpet and being Iranian being Persians carpets are really important to us so so lying on the carpet she gave me
that's home I feel surrounded by her love home is where this carpet is where of course this you know the carpet Bay
burn in a fire but there's just a sense of being surrounded and cared for by by
the community by love so that's home and may we all of us so thank you Barbara
for bringing for expanding that even further that the idea of being home so
we can be we can feel at home in our bodies in our minds in our hearts
in our communities and can we feel that this is a castle this is this is a
castle love I love castle of love spreading raw love held in love uh being
at home and the last reflection here says my body is my temple I feel like a
beneficient monarch within this body of skin oh that is sweet beneficence
monarch so thank you all thank you for your practice thank you for your Reflections
thank you for supporting yourself supporting one another may we all feel at home in this body in
this heart in this mind for this limited time that is our lifetime may we really
truly every moment feel at home exactly where we are may
all beings be well may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music] thanks everyone
[Music]