a warm welcome everybody and to our 7 A.M Pacific meditation and the dharmette
so good to see you all my name's Ian Chen and this week
uh I'll be um thank you for this week's of journey
together um
yeah it is a very happy to see you all this chat messages in the in the chat
box in front of me flowing [Music]
so good morning and good day um this week the meditation theme that I
brought in is that of Stillness and a movement
and still Stillness and movement in wider variety of ways
and we'll begin there and so if you like
to join me and to take a meditative pasture and please feel free to do that
we'll just take a few moments to set her in
maybe a few long deep breaths as you breathe out
arriving Here and Now
entering into this body and mind
maybe the immediate sense of this moment
as we settle in is that of a movement
maybe there are dancing energies in the body
movements of the breath
movements are the waves of emotions
just noticing this mindfulness is already here
take a few moments to just welcome [Music] a wide range of movements
in our experiences
inviting settling resting down
noticing the lower half of the body making contact with the floor
chairs or maybe the whole body making contact
if you're lying down
your body is supported by Earth
and there is the Earth element in the body
that is heavy
firm grounded
maybe a sense of earthy body resting on Earth
right here you may already notice
a kind of a relative a Stillness
with the Earth element in the body
steady stable
relatively unmoving
there is a Stillness in the body
there is a movement in the body
and rest your attention the Stillness of the Earth element in
the body sitting like a mountain
steady quiet
and still
maybe the whole body as a sense of resting down
relaxed soft
sitting like a mountain
the Stillness of the body May highlight the movements
the movements of the Bride
tingling Sensations
vibrations
or stations
you can open to receive
the movements in the body
as well as the Stillness
as if the wind blows
in the mountain
maybe the Torso gently sways
belly Rises and the falls
you feel the dance of the Stillness
I got the movements In This Very body
resting in the felt sense of your experience
feeling sensing
Stillness
and feeling and sensing
their movements
letting go of stories
ideas
just to this
sitting like a tall mountain
still quiet
meaning this very body there is a natural quality of a
Stillness and the movements
by being away with the Stillness and the movements in the body
our mind saddles
and become quiet
if you like to play for the rest of the day this dance of a Stillness and emotions
the invitation is to pause
maybe throughout the day to notice Stillness
and the movements In This Very body
[Music]
foreign
welcome again everyone I'm so happy to be with you let me make
sure I have my recording on here okay I think I'm all good
ah so this week
I brought a set of Stories of the great
women Disciples of the Buddha then
and this I guess there's a five women I'm going
to bring forth uh this week I came from a wide range of life
situations backgrounds um
yeah to each of them are in their own ways of experienced
wide range of challenges and losses in their own lives
and not only that they also have experienced all kinds of difficulties
and challenges that came from the broader culture and the society that
they live in and yet they were
not disabled by them or hindered by them
and so this heroic women Rose beyond all of the difficulties and challenges and
the pain that they experienced and they were transformed by the Dharma
and so the first four women I'll be speaking about uh were from the times of the Buddha
and they were considered to be awakened individuals
and the last one I'll be bringing in is a modern day women disciple
and I hope and that this stories would Inspire and uplift Us in some way
that each of us know that um for ourselves that The Liberation is
a possible for each of us so the first woman I brought in the
story of the pachara and so many of you may have heard of
this um but we have patachara statue
in IRC and so this is um maybe why I
chose to begin with the party so there is a bit of Affinity
with the IMC and IRC community
statue is sitting in inside Retreat Center our retreat center right now and
so for those who go there to meditate um they see this
so I like to tell a little story about party Chara's life
and her Awakening Journey
and there is a collection called an apadana and I will be drawing some of
the verses from this palikana collection and this is translated by John Waters
and it's called The Legends of the teres teres are senior female Disciples of the
Buddha and so they are considered to be Legends um
and so patachara was a born out of rather wealthy family Jose he was born
into a well-to-do family and as a young woman she fell in love
with a servant's boy of her family and in those days
um the Casta system is quite strong and we're not supposed to marry an outside
of their own Caster system in this um in some ways it's a remaining
to be a quite strong system in different parts of the world uh in India
particularly even now and so but you know she fell in love as
a young woman and they ended up running away from the household a house that she
was born into and so they had to leave and
lived in some Villages a little far away from katuchara as a home
and along the way um she had given a birth to one son and
then with the second one in her womb she's are ready to go back to see their family
she's really missing their family and so um but she was recounting this
experience and she said my husband was not pleased at this thought
and so then when she was on when he was on a journey I snuck out of the house
alone to go to savati which is where her
family was living and so she decided to go on her own with
a second child in her womb and was basically a toddler in her hand
and this time running away from her husband had to go back to visit the
family but that the husband caught on
um and began to chase after her and in this process her labor pain began
to happen and right around that time she recounted that at the time for me to
give birth to the second a baby in the womb a massive ring Cloud arose there
and then my husband having gone to find the grass even
though her husband caught up with the family um pachachara decided not to go back and
they continued to go so this ring Cloud came and a ring storm
came and the husband went to go find some grass to make some fire and maybe
Sheltering some way but he was killed by a poisonous snake
and so pachachara said then miserable and helpless
in the throats a painful childbirth going toward a relative's house
seeing and overflowing stream so having lost a husband you can imagine
that uh you know now he has she has a newborn in the hand
and a toddler and there's no way going back now
but there is this overflowing stream that's right in front of her because of
the ring storm and so she had to carry this newborn across the
flowing river while keeping the toddler on the other Riverbank for the time
being she couldn't do take both in one shot
and then when she had put the baby on the other side and nurse to the baby
and ready to come back to the other side of the uh the stream to get the toddler
right in the midstream this is the weather
patachara be counted she said I turned and Osprey carried off
my wailing baby then the current
swept the toddler away my other son
what happened what happened here so she put the baby on the other side of
the bank but the Osprey saw the baby and dived on and picked up the baby and
left the flu away and so she was yelling and screaming and
waving I tried to get the baby down but this screaming and yelling the toddler
thought oh Mommy was calling me to come so he started walking towards the river
towards the flow and then the toddler got swept away
this is just a wedding [Music] 24 hours
she lost her husband her baby
and her toddler just like that
and she was overwhelmed or overwhelmed by the grief the loss
and so now she had no choice but to go back to
sabati to go visit um her family
there's no other way now right and yet on the way to go visit uh sabati
um people saw her on the way and she inquired about her
family and someone told them the whole family
was killed because of the rainstorm the last night the house collapsed collapsed
her parents and her brother all died
with English 24 to 48 hours
so she's gone mad I I feel like this is the kind of a pain that
The Logical Minds just can't hold
it's kind of beyond what our mind can hold
and so she's gone mad uh Sheen
uh rise sobs and began to wander around uh
kind of like a crazy woman
and she said I grew pale and the thing helpless
this was the and the state of a being she was in
the clothes were torn and the people began to throw stuff at
her and thinking this is a mad woman and in the midst of this and the Buddha
was staying at a sabati the Ananda penticas Monastery right then
and she was wandering around and and saw the Buddha
far away and this was at the time when uh there's a moment on that
some sort of Consciousness came back to her
and um and when she finally saw the Buddha
and she began to recount to this whole experience to the Buddha
and the Buddha listened to her compassionately at the end of her recount
the Buddha said this to her
but little water do the oceans four contain compared with all the tears that one
shed by sorrow smitten and by suffering distraught
the Buddha put her sorrow and a grief in perspective
the ten thousand sorrows and a grief that we experience even the four great
oceans couldn't contain at all and so the Buddha continued
do not grieve child breathe easily
you should look after yourself why uselessly torment yourself
there are no sounds to give shelter and there is no shelter with the family
and those words penetrated her mind deeply for her this is uh this was truth
she saw how fragile it was
and she was relying counting on the Family
and the children and the parents one by one
was swept away right underneath of her feet
and so she knew the impermanence of all things so deeply right there
she experienced the celebrity so right then
she knew the truth of Anita
in permanence she knew the truth of dukkah
she knew the truth of claiming to dukkha clinging is is Duca
and so right then and there was a moment of a transformation for her
and so is she entrusted to herself to the Buddha Dharma and the Sangha
and that ever since that day she practiced the diligently
and this poem that's translated by
Franco um speaks to her Awakening experience
I like to read this poem from terrigata
plowing Fields with plows sowing seeds in the ground
caring for children and wife young men getting wealth
why is that I battle in virtuous conduct
doing the Buddha's instruction not lazy or proud
have not attained release having washed my feet
I watched the water the foot washing water
flowing from High Ground to low with this
the Mind concentrated like a thoroughbred horse
taking an oil lamp I entered my heart
looking over the bed I sat down on the bed
taking a needle I pulled out the wick
as the flame went out the mind
was freed
so this was possible for patachara even after the ocean of the sorrow and a
grief well and not only patachara become became
awakened as she was known to be the one who taught many other nouns disciples
and I'd like to um evoke maybe a sense of inspiration
through patrachara's story
and there is a pachara statue in IRC and for those who
go to IRC to do the retreat practice maybe wander to the walking hall right
now and just stand right in front of Chara for a few moments
may this uplift all of us
May Awakening be a possibility for all beings
thank you everyone
and we will continue tomorrow with another story