so hello and welcome everyone welcome to happy hour lovely to have
you joined from wherever in the world you are joining from what a joy um to be
with you and and the hellos at the beginning always give me Delight um
whether you say your name you bring your voice into the space or whether you type
them in chat um yeah we're worldwide s very sweet so many different time zones
so so for tonight's practice for today's practice many time zones for today's
practice I'd like to um tell you what um have something in
mind but I'm going to to introduce it while we're practicing together just very gently and slowly and I'll say a
few words about it afterwards so so with that let's sit together let's go into
start practicing together so so arriving arriving into your sitting
posture whether you're sitting on a chair or a [Music]
cushion
feeling your feet on the earth feeling your sit
[Music] Bones on the
chair feeling this body sitting the sense of presence of this body
here this body sitting and breathing all these various Sensations let them
support and ground you in every
breath and as you start sitting in this community together see if there's
something you need to let go of first you need to put down something some thoughts some
rumination something from the day this residue of emotion perhaps entanglement with
something that has happened today can we put it down just for a moment you can
pick it up later but right now can you put it
down it is possible to put it
down just for this period of time to take refuge in this
practice yes you can yes we can having
trust and connecting with the breath with the body just to
settle relinquishing everything
else
e
and if you try to put something down and take refuge and somehow it's very sticky and it keeps coming back then turn
towards it fully and get to really see it in capital
letters not losing your seat but seeing it
clearly maybe you're annoyed or upset or sad or afraid or whatever is
arising and then try to see the self sense how it relates to you the way you
think of yourself the way you're perceived how it might feel unjust to you how it has to do with yourself the
self this self-conception and see
how we feel more contracted more tight when
the sense of self
is more solid me me
me my perspective my thoughts my
needs and see if you can relax a little bit relax that just soften your body
relax your body
maybe imagine your self sense the sense of this being who's you kind of
floating being a little amorphous yeah there's a being here that is breathing
and sensing in this moment just the raw sensations of feeling and touch and
knowing but can we soften let our identity be a bit of bit
light a gas or or or like smoke or it's kind
of light not so substantial not so
solid Vapor Vapor like light
dissipating just staying with the raw sensation of breathing in sensing and
hearing
F this breath in breath and out
breath Simplicity of this moment here without a sense of identity and
story
and can we have can we bring a sense of kindness compassion for this being for
this being who is me who has this sometime has this tight sense of
self the sense of identity this clinging this tightening
around an identity or what we need or who we are how
overseen all of that that whole gamut how painful that is how painful it can
be can we have compassion oh dear heart dear being who me
okay as we hold this this Folly this
this Folly of sense of self that we cling around and tighten around become
self-righteous holding what's called ignorance in Buddhism not knowing how
much suffering really holds this tendency of the mind to do that holding it with
compassion not with judgment not kicking ourselves for doing
this but with compassion so sweetheart this hurts it's not [Music]
helpful and and it's hard it's painful I know it's okay it's
hard I hold you with care I hold you with compassion this this tendency of the
heart in mind let it soften some more let these
Tendencies soften some more as they're held with compassion and
kindness comp passion helps them not become so solid
solidified
same way would have compassion towards a child that throws a
tantum causes so much harm to themselves by screaming and crying and
being tied about something about a toy seeing ourselves in that way with
compassion yeah it's okay it hurts not needed and this is what children do this
is what the sense of self does
by seeing it holding you compassion can soften it loosen it instead of adding more insult to
injury or more self-
recommendation to our
selfing
and bringing kindness compassion with a heal like a healing sve wherever it it's
needed on your
own
and can we have compassion kindness for our self as if you
could perhaps separate out and see step out of your identity and look at your
identity the way you take yourself to
be step out of and have compassion for this self this sense of selfing me my
needs my thoughts my priorities my my my step out of that and have compassion for
it sense of tenderness because someday you will step out of
this we're wearing our identities like a cloak and we will leave them behind someday all of us do of course
can you step out of it right now with your perspective and have compassion for
it oh dear being who is
me who will not be someday in this
way this perspective might help you have more compassion hold it more lightly
it's not so solid
as we bring this meditation to a close
together having compassion and kindness for this being who is you who tried
their best with being present with having kindness with seeing the sense of self and the Suffering The tightness it
can bring if any judgments are arising because you were distracted the mind was
distracted and sleepy whatnot it's okay let that go because that too is part of
selfing self judgment it's right there it's in the term let that go have
compassion kindness self self self oh dear dear
being who is me ah relax have lightness around it and
may this practice we have engaged in together wholeheartedly bringing our
heart our intentions our goodness together may it be a cause and condition
for freedom for happiness of all beings
everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be free including
myself thanks everyone ah thanks for your
practice so practice I invited you to consider
today after we settled a bit and the body with the
breath was to uh try to settle to try to
to sit to let go of if there was something that was bothering you you're
ruminating on know some some something that was kind of sticky and then and
then if that was impossible if it was really sticky to actually come back to it and see it very clearly like really
see it in large capital letters and by the way this is a practice you can anytime anytime it's very
powerful and then seeing how that that thing that is bothering us oh seeing the
sense of self seeing this sense of personalities the self sense the selfing
like I'm annoyed this person did that because it made me look bad oh look at that I'm concerned about how I looked
bad or or whatever it might be right just hearing your own seeing your own stories it's we all have them you know
no shame it's it's just a part of Being Human and yet seeing how this this self
sense can make us tight it really makes our perspective really really narrow and
then I invited us to to relax to relax the body as a way to relax the mind and
then to relax the mind the self sense like a gas kind of let it be a little fluid and just come to the present
moment Sensations just present moment without a sense of self without a story really cuz that's another way we can
practice with this to release it and then finally I invited us to bring a sense of compassion and kindness for how
this self sense the story uh that we make about various things this this
entanglement brings suffering makes us tight brings brings more suffering and
to hold it uh hold it all with kindness and compassion so that was kind of the arc that we
did and um yeah can see the empty of Self in
this way it's so so fluid you know these stories the and we can change and shift
our perspective anytime so I'd like to invite us now to to engage with one
another in small groups to support each other to explore this further so the way
we're going to engage is again for our own sake we're not speaking out loud for
the benefit of others educating them informing them telling them we're just exploring for our own sake and letting
them hold witness kind compassionate Witnesses um and and and there's a lot
of value to either journaling or or speaking out loud something that you're working with and you can offer a nugget
Let's Go reverse alphabetical order according to first name you offer offer nugget explore for your own sake this
practice tonight not something happened today or yesterday or this past like here tonight in this or this morning
depending on your time zone um uh this so exploring it when I did this when I
explored something that was I was upset about and I saw you the sense self that
what it says about me and how I'm seen or it's always happens to me it's like me me me like I saw that and I chuckled
like oh that's interesting so exploring for your own sake and when or maybe when I relax my body oh yeah that that sense
of self relaxed a little bit so exploring out loud how this practice might have worked or not I have no idea
what she was talking about I don't know I was distracted the whole time I fell asleep that's fine too you can explore
it and then the next person will offer one nugget then the next person again offer explore not offer explore a nugget
then I'll come back to you you can explore some more we'll go round and round and please don't ask questions don't um direct the conversation you are
exploring for yourself and if somebody said something you did not understand don't ask a question they're exploring
for their own sake it's not your responsib your duty they're exploring forther so be really be real respectful
caring caring for another and just holding compassionate presence not an
inquisitive presence but a compassionate patient presence Let Yourself Go that
self that wants to be a be seen in a particular way can you let that go in this exchange try to be seen as smart or
be seen as this or be seen as compassionate or just let that go just just just be just be just be yeah this
is this is the Supreme practice doing that in in community you know so okay so
I'm going to create this everyone and we have a few minutes for uh Reflections or
questions about this practice um what did you discover as you were practicing
this um during the meditation or maybe you discovered
something while you were in the small groups and also I'm opening up chat so you're welcome to put your Reflections
in chat either to me privately in which case I will not read your name just your reflection or um you can put them to
everyone in which case I will read your name as well and I see your hand Jerry
what's up well um thank you uh Nikki it's
always a pleasure to be here and I was commenting in my group that I had been away uh uh from my home doing work uh in
the capital of Canada Ottawa and uh I was not able to be here last week and I
felt a deep longing for the nurturing that I get here so a big shout out of
thanks for that and it really was quite helpful because um I was when you said just let
go of whatever you're doing uh just for an hour and then you
book ended it at the end with well there will come a time where you let go of
everything death and so it became a very powerful way of sort of wow uh I did
enjoy letting go for an hour and then I thought really there's nothing to hold on to and it was quite freeing so thank
you so much ah thank you so much for Reflections Jerry first I really appreciate you you um yeah speaking
about the nurturing of the the nourishment that happy AA provides for
you and for so many thanks for naming that and bringing that into the space and also for how the um the invitation
to put it down for an hour and then the reflection of yeah you're going to put all of this down this personality this
being who that is you all that just ah that that how that provided a sense of
lightening for you thank you for saying that as beautifully and as clearly as
you did yeah beautiful trans transmission from your experience thank you
Jerry yeah um see Bill says I've been wanting to
work on the I me mind really enjoyed this thank you Nik you're welcome this
is great Bill I'm delighted this this practice uh was uh supportive to you na
says I love the idea of identity as a coat we wear and one that we will gently
put away when the time comes indeed yeah exactly and then a couple more
Reflections requests actually let's see um one person says I struggled deeply with selfie today I've been worrying
someone will get mad at me for a mistake I made it has been extremely painful and
I wish I could just leave it behind like you said yeah um interesting to see
the I invite the person who wrot wrote this and others who might have you know this might make sense for is to see this
you know if you're upset if you're afraid that somebody might get mad at you because um and then see more clearly
that it has to do with this this this fear is is perhaps in a way self-
protection of self- protection protecting this self this identity the way this person is SE seen or the person
is perceived or the way he so so try try to see that try to see you don't have to
leave it behind because leaving it behind is like trying to push it away I'm not suggesting that that that
becomes aversive that's not what I'm suggesting here I'm suggesting that you just see it clearly that's all you do
you see it very clearly how that self sense is stuck is kind of the Lynch pin
and and relaxing your body not trying to push away the self sense so so it can be
tricky and yet um there there are ways gently gently
gently another reflection I recently ended a long-term romantic relationship as I navigate this major life change
I've been trying to find my independent sense of self again how could I approach this in a Dharma compatible way is there
a way to go about this kind of transition without selfing so hard yeah what a great question yeah it's
[Music] um yeah you know
the maybe I will use some different words I think the independent as as the
person who wrote this trying to find your independent sense of self maybe
maybe what what comes to me is that in the Dharma there is a sense of after a while when we're practicing in the
Dharma we become really really mature in the Dharma and we grow a sense of trust
in ourselves and Trust in the Dharma and it is said that we become independent in
the Dharma the sense of Independence so it's not self-independence but independent the Dharma which comes from
a sense of self trust trusting in ourselves so that's how I suggest the
person who wrote that question a sense of trust in yourself sense of care for
yourself that land there so it doesn't feel like so hard to try to come up with
an independent sense of self and Kevin says there was quite a bit of
selfing throughout but coming back to the main group I realized the final minute of discussion was so loving and
wholesome there wasn't any sense of self in that minute yay yay oh that is so
beautiful that makes me so happy because when we experience that for one minute
the sense of love and care this expansiveness of that can be so opening
and so healing it doesn't have to be the full 30 minutes of the meditation it's just that that minute or that second
when something is just loosens a little bit thanks for that Fred I see your
hand thank you Nikki um I want to ask if I'm understanding correctly that there's
a there's a paradox inherent in the stepping away from the self or
self-consciousness I guess is the way I'm thinking of it and
to to leave a state to leave a state
where I'm viewing myself with any number of qualities you
know that then have some you know some veence in the world
in terms of what other people think or what I'm thinking about it the best route to leave that is in fact to just
be in my body to to the first step is just to sit in what
is physically present in respirating and digesting and all of those things um I
mean it does seem paradoxical to me but that's that is what you're saying isn't it that's one of the things I'm saying
exactly Fred that is one of the things I'm saying so one way is to to loosen
that get away from that if especially if there's proliferation proliferation just to come
to the Simplicity of bear awareness what's called bear awareness here and now the breath the sensations just this
being here that's one of the things I'm saying exactly and then there's another thing I'm saying
also I'm also saying that when you bring a sense of compassion and kindness
instead of this the self-loathing or fear or whatever it is this this
tightness that's another way to shift to shift our perspective with a sense of self that also loosens and opens it
so there's a couple of multiple methods but these are two I'm highlighting thank you thank you friend
thank you so much for helping highlight it so clearly beautiful so this can be a practice of a
lifetime it's it's um this is a practice of a lifetime
um and hopefully maybe it it showed itself to you perhaps for a millisecond
that oh yeah I could see this maybe through coming to the sense of presence here can loosen a little bit the selfing
and and and just say there's no there's nothing wrong with having a self-concept
we're not saying that here um but we're saying that when that sense of self becomes contractive
contracted really contracted it causes suffering that's all we're saying here
that's all that's the the teachings so there's so much G here um m i see your
hand and this is the last reflection we're going to take before we end um that really help me Nikki thank you for
this evening um it helped me when you said um if it because it was sticky and
I was laughing so hard because I it wouldn't leave me alone and I couldn't Let It Go um but the moment you said
turn to it I could see the self that helped break it the minute I turned it
it was as if it was shattered glass like it all and I thought how many times did
I cause the suffering because I don't see the selfing I'm not and this is going to help me tremendously so I want
to thank you for that yay oh thank you so much mimo that
makes me happy to no end to hear how you um how the Insight arose for you and the
your beautiful description of turning towards it and seeing the selfing and
like shattered glass wow beautiful oh getting chills as you describe it oh and
I see other people are smiling and happy for your Insight as you're sharing it and bringing it into the space that is
so beautiful that is just oh celebrating our insights um together this is
lovely and Rosa says wow this evening really resonated for me thank you so
much Nikki you are so welcome or go on others on uh on YouTube as well joining
so thank you thank you mimo for that beautiful reflection what a lovely note to end on for um thank you all for your
practice may this practice support and open you and be gentle be kind to
yourself not every practice lights up all the times uh at all times but but uh
this is an important practice so thank you for coming bringing yourself
cultivating your heart for the sake of all beings everywhere may all beings be well may all beings be
[Music] free thanks everyone and be well