so good day everyone and welcome and as I we did yesterday today
I'd like to again offer a different approach to our morning
practice where the emphasis is not on the usual purposes of meditation
might be to become more calm or settled or peaceful to become more concentrated
to become um to see more clearly in a certain way uh to have some pleasure or
even Joy or Bliss sometimes in meditation to put those ideas
aside and uh to learn a skill of mindfulness which uh is realistic and
one that teaches us a lot and which is useful very useful for guiding us as we
live our life and that is to imagine um two
baskets one on each side of you and
whatever is going on for you whatever you're thinking whatever you're wanting
whatever you're not wanting whatever your uh impulses are your attitudes are
whatever that is happening to you whatever is arising out of
you sitting here in meditation
discern whether it is good for you or not good for you the
good not good is vague that it's beneficial or not beneficial that it's
uh that it is healthy for you or not healthy and when you're not
sure maybe it's neither then just leave it alone
and if it's healthy or beneficial for you or
has a rightness to it put it in one basket if it's unhealthy for you if it's
brings an ouch for you or feels like it diminishes you it brings a stress brings
some kind of feeling of of um not being supported or being critical
harsh put that in another basket and just put them there in these baskets and maybe at the end you have
some general sense of which basket is most full and this ability to discern between
that is invaluable so that's what I recommend for this this
sitting so to begin you would maybe lower your gaze or close your
eyes and then
consider whether hearing this instructions for me for what we're doing
today whether your reaction to that your response to that is a response that
feels good to you or feels healthy for you or feels like it inspires you in
some way or does IT contract you or bring up judgments or disappointments
something which doesn't feel that good maybe reasonable to have those things but still that doesn't feel so healthy
to have them so put them in one
basket and as you continue just consider notice your what
you're thinking what you're wanting not
wanting what you're doing what you're intending ending how you're reacting to anything
that goes on here and
now and then put in one of two baskets putting aside any
pursuit of staying with what's beneficial holding on to it intentionally doing more of
it just allow things to unfold as they do and as they occur
put them in one basket or the other or just leave them alone if they're
neither beneficial or not
beneficial
for
noticing if how you are and what you're doing as you sit here
quietly is it wholesome or UNH
wholesome is it does it allow what's Best in you to
open up or does it close you or does it bring stress or does it
bring sense of well-being and this can be very
subtle the quality the manner in which thoughts are
thought or about what you think about be subtlest wants and
aversions what you don't want what you want and if there's no wanting or not
wanting no thoughts nothing that seems obviously beneficial or harmful
just let be without a need to do
anything but be fresh and Ava available to
notice when you're involved in doing something in the mind the heart the
body which is either beneficial or not and if it is put it aside into these
two baskets and be fresh and available to
see what comes
next
for
and even if what you're thinking about seems
nice maybe the degree to which it is a
distraction from being aware and he is seen as not
beneficial
for and if it helps you stay on track with
this exercise you can very peacefully
quietly identify with the thought
beneficial not
beneficial as you put things aside into the respective
baskets
for
e
our body and mind
are very fine instruments sensitive
instruments that have the capacity of picking up
registering when what we're doing is wholesome and when when it when it's not
wholesome when our thoughts motivations
attitudes in some way harm ourselves even in the very subtle
ways undermines us deflate
us limit us or when they ins our thoughts
attitudes and feelings are more on the inspiring side beneficial
side bringing a alert and good
energy even the very most subtle ways we can pick
up we can register so we can know what to let go
of what to stop
doing so we can know and see how to be present
in a beneficial way way that leads to happiness and
freedom and all the signposts for freedom and
happiness are found here in our own body and
mind
for and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to wish well for this world that we live in for the people we know the strangers
we'll encounter the people all over this world
to wish them well and because we wish them
well we want to be a person who does well well in the
world that we are a conveyor of
safety well-wishing
Goodwill that we ourselves contribute to the welfare and happiness
of others even just because we respect them
we
are safe for them we bring a calm or a
smile may it be that this practice that we do supports us to enter this
world in an easy way light-handed
way that genuinely contributes to the welfare of
all beings may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all beings be
free
[Music]
[Music] thank
you
e
so so this week the top topic
for our discussion our consideration is nonviolence and um it's I think the one
of the fundamental ethical principles of Buddhism is not to harm and it's
represented by the very first precept which is usually said uh to not to kill
but it's a little bit more comprehensive it's not to uh harm any physically harm
any living being and
um and this is such an important thing in this world that we live in and I
believe that as we meditate this becomes more and more obvious or more and more the
orientation we have is do not want to cause harm and there's are two reasons I
can think many reasons for this one reason is that as we meditate we
become we develop a heightened sensitivity for what the cost is to
ourselves when we harm others intentionally deliberately that uh uh it's very
stressful for the our own system it's Al it uh involves a diminishment a
narrowing of our scope it involves uh uh
being involved in anger and greed and ill will uh delusion even involves
speaking up stress and so you can feel that once we start meditating we
start feeling that the effect that UNH wholesome Behavior harmful Behavior has
on ourselves and so part of the motivation not to be
violent Not to cause harm to others is that that the cost we see the cost is too high for
ourselves and um another reason is we see the cost is too high for others and
we start feeling uh a kinship with others there's something about sitting
quietly and having the thinking mind become quiet the mind that objectifies
the mind that is caught up in thoughts and ideas about people and projections
into the fure future and all kinds of ideas of conceit that interfere with our
body and heart's capacity for sympathy for empathy
for understanding uh what it's like to be you know you know we put ourselves in
other people's shoes or and we get a sense of you know what their suffering is and how terrible it is for people to
be harmed and and um devastating for some people
when there's violence committed towards them and um and at some point it's so it
almost feels like a violence to oneself the knowledge and the perception of seeing harm being done to others
especially being done from our by ourselves and so there's a kind of shift
that begins happening when people spend a lot of time meditating doing mindfulness is there tends to be a
movement towards uh wanting to live a life of non-harming and one of the definitions
in the teachings of the Buddha for what it means to be an fully enlightened
person that person will not deliberately harm any living
being and will not kill any living being someone who fully enlightened is
incapable of killing and uh if that's what you know
so some of you might want to become enlightened but if that's what enlightenment is do you want it is it
still attractive to you or do you have some other idealistic idea that you have
about what enlightenment is or do you feel like Enlightenment is only kind of a freedom from your own suffering so you
don't suffer but you never thought about it as something about it changes your relationship to other
people and um and if you take this path of of Dharma the Dharma path what will
happen is that uh it's an ethical path you'll grow in your ethical
sensitivity and the increasingly become someone who lives more and more ethically even in subtle
ways and one of the manifestations of this is not only not wanting to harm
anybody um but not capable of deliberately doing so so someone who is
a well-developed Lous path uh would not be capable of of being a soldier for
example if that meant needing to kill others or go into
fighting if it means being a um uh you know being a medic uh driving an
ambulance maybe that's very different maybe that's something as you know Soldier could
do and um so uh so the the the rationale the
reason for nonviolence at in the of the most personal way that it the reason for
it is not logical it becomes from this deeper sensitivity we have that uh you
would have for example uh you know if you have a young baby that uh of course
you don't want to harm the baby you'll do everything you can you know if you ever received in your arms a newborn
baby and the care and the tenderness that I think most people will hold that baby um not one to harm it in any kind
of way U being very gentle is phenomenal and that's just kind of built into our
system that that's what we do for many of us and that sensitivity there can be
spread and developed towards all beings everywhere now then the question becomes
what about when there are terrible things happening someone attacks you attacks your
family um violently even coming to kill them shouldn't you be able to kill them
back shouldn't you be able to defend yourself and
um and there's a little problem I have with this kind of rationale this pushing back around the value of
non-violence because it it suggests that the the B the the choice is between
being violent or nonviolent but there's another
possibility the choices between being violent and and
um uh learning developing oneself to be skillfully
nonviolent to um taking the time to train
ourselves in nonviolent forms of communication non-violent forms of
behavior that so that we can uh defend ourselves um without having to resort to
violence many years ago someone came to me a woman came to me in Palo Alto and
lives in paloalto which is a relatively you know comfortable Town
safe time Town even back then there were some dangers and she uh asked me if uh she
told me she was thinking of getting a gun to make herself safe and I didn't feel like I was I didn't want to be in a
position to decide whether she should or shouldn't be getting a gun but uh I did
tell her that I thought it was very sad uh to get a gun first and foremost that
first there's a lot of uh trainings a person can do in self-defense that
doesn't require a gun and um and maybe those forms of self-defense don't work
100% of the time but neither does a gun work 100% of the time um but uh to be
well trained in nonviolent forms of self-defense or maybe self-defense that
does strike out in order so we can escape from someone um so we don't have
to resort to guns that takes time and effort for a
country to avoid war uh to in defending itself takes a
lot of preparation to make the war to set up uh nonviolent forms of defense
and sophisticated forms to live in a world where we don't have uh we don't
have to resort to violence takes Decades of planning that uh you know the first
time uh I gave a talk on the Buddhist teachings on
non-violence and all this was in the early 1990s in the first Gulf
War and then periodically there's been uh you know it happens again and again war and War and
war war has been part of my life my whole life I've never had never really
been in a war zone um little bit of a distance could see the country that war
kind of or something distance once I saw a mortar explode but uh it's been part of my life
uh my parents experienced VI violence during World War II my mother did in
World War II um my parents-in-law were Jews in the concentration camps in
Germany and barely survived and um they lost their parents in the camps the Vietnam War was huge
growing up in their early 60s and uh having to do uh this ridiculous duck
drills in school in in second grade first grade because we were supposed to
protect us from the nuclear Holocaust That was supposed to be happened when the Russian Americans went
into nuclear warfare with each other and the Vietnam War and you know
and goes on and on um the violence that you a huge impact on me personally that
shaped me was um uh Israeli bombing of
the Palestinian refugee camps in Lebanon in about
1982 and um uh I that I I read about that and saw pictures of it when I was a
deep in meditation practice deep in our Retreats and doing Zen Retreats and that changed me uh where I just that really
kind of one of the reasons why I wanted to uh become a Buddhist teacher in order
to uh respond to the world uh with uh nonviolence to try to make a better
better world for all of us to respond to the suffering we have so there can be
Alternatives but to expect Alternatives uh you know you can't uh uh
to close the gate of the Corral once the horse has gotten free doesn't help to
begin thinking about nonviolence when the violence is already in full blow is
H doesn't work but there has to be planning ahead of time lots of it
preparations for it and um nonviolence takes time time
preparation and struggle even um one of the things that I've seen
is that uh sometimes violence and violent speech can have an immediate
effect sometimes the effect the person wants it stops what's happening uh we get what we want maybe
but the repercussions and the consequences we have to deal with for years afterwards um are not taken into
account and are very expensive very difficult nonviolence the difficulty is ahead of
time before the problem and then if you find a nonviolent way of dealing with a problem
then there there aren't the same repercussions and there's not the after effect of having to clean up and deal
with it afterwards um you know there for Generations Generations people suffer
when uh there is war the children who experience it and their children experience it um you know
my um you know that that my children knew
their grandparents who survived the Nazi concentration camps uh is a big impact
on them and you know they were born many many years after World War II but it
still has an effect on them has an effect on me and um and people are still dealing
United States with the repercussions of the Cil war and um people still dealing
with the repercussions of World War I even and all these things that go on and on um and um so violence is an easy
solution the obvious solution for immediate
survival nonviolence is a fantastic
solution provided it's done in a sophisticated way in a caring way
where we do the work up front not the cleanup cost
afterwards and um so if you go back and look at the Buddhist teachings you
see that uh over and over and over again he emphasizes non-harming this is a
central feature of what he's teaching and what he's getting across um so I'll read a couple of
things before we end one who neither kills nor gets others to
kill neither conquers nor gets others to
conquer with good will for all beings has no hostility for anyone at
all has no host hostility for anyone at
all somewhere else he says in Dap there's the verse Victory gives birth to hate the
defeated sleep tormented giving up both Victory and defeat the peaceful sleep
delighted all tremble at violence all fear death have en likened
others to yourself don't kill or cause others to kill all tremble at violence
life is dear to all having likened others to yourself don't kill or cause
others to kill just as you want to live just as you don't want to be harmed so
others don't want to be killed don't want to be harmed care for them
instead so um so we ourselves are an instrument who
can discern and feel both the negative costs of violent and
harmful action and we can feel the the tremendous
benefit from action which is not harming it it's beneficial and caring for others
may we choose the latter thank
you