well a warm good day to everyone very happy to be with you this
week and yesterday we discussed how generosity is one of the
foundational virtues that help us cultivate wholesome states of mind and
one invitation from yesterday was to notice forms of generosity throughout
the day if anyone would like to type examples of generosity they noticed
yesterday into the chat please feel welcome to do that and I'll read a few
of them aloud in a few minutes um they are examples uh that not
only show generosity but also frequently contain an attitude of kindness and
Goodwill towards ourselves towards other people other beings in fact towards
everything we experience and I'm dedicating this week's talks to beautiful qualities of
Mind wholesome qualities of mind starting with generosity and including the four Divine
abodes or Brahma viharas these are wholesome places for
the mind to hang out to dwell the intentions that motivate the
Divine abodes of good will compassion appreciative joy and
Equanimity are relational they seek the well-being and happiness of other others
and in doing so they actually support one's own well-being and happiness uh so
today we'll focus on this wonderful intention of Good Will towards others
meta in the ancient poly language and often translated as loving kindness
friendliness or benevolence I'll read a few of the examples that you typed into the chat
and as I do that you might want to begin the meditation with these beautiful
examples of Goodwill of friendliness loving kindness so one person shares
someone wrote me a long email letter another kindness from my son
towards my old dog my grandson's taking care of Grandpa who balance is poor a
friend's flexibility Christmas cards full of humor and warm
silliness yeah beautiful making books with grandchildren during a busy dinner
with a long arm stapler fun for me and my kids um Cindy's daughter made them
cinnamon rolls and it took most of her day that's wonderful so so as we settle
into the meditation holding these beautiful forms of kindness in our
hearts and sitting lying down standing
whichever posture you're in settling in
with a way of meeting conditions just as you experience them in this moment
noticing Sensations in the body perhaps and
deliberately consciously meeting that whether it's Pleasant or unpleasant or
neither meeting any Sensations that are arising
with as much benevolence as is available to you right
now these bodies need tender loving care very
often and they return tender loving
care
meeting the State of Mind the heart moods emotions with
kindness our feelings come and go Pleasant unpleasant very difficult
very joyful greeting it all with
friendliness if the mind is preoccupied with something meeting that with Goodwill
not viewing thinking as the enemy as Gil was so eloquently pointing to last
week meeting it with some thoughts just letting them
drift by if others are very
preoccupying perhaps inviting them to drift into the background for now and
and promising to pick them up
later if they're important they'll
wait what would it be like what might it be like to receive everything that
arises in meditation as you would greet a
friend whether this friend is bringing happy news or is sharing their most
profound difficulty with us receiving the friend
with a heart of
caring
in a very kind simple way receiving whatever is arising in
Awareness In This
Moment whatever is most
prominent
feeling it sensing into
it allowing it to be
known
and knowing what's arising at its own pace there's no need to go
out looking for things there's no need to
dig and there's no need to push away simply allowing experience to
arrive some will arrive and stay for a while some experience will be
fleeting receiving whatever arises with
benevolence with
kindness even what's unpleasant what you thought might not
be part of meditation but actually is part of
meditation taking your time
resting with what comes into
awareness
and if it's useful to you perhaps silently inclining the
Mind towards wishes for your
well-being they might sound like what I'll offer here or they might be your
own unique wishes may I be free from
hostility free from Affliction from physical
suffering may I be free from distress
from mental
suffering may I live happily with
ease
may I be
well may I be safe
happy may I live with ease
allowing your heart and mind to send these kind
wishes to all of you to all of your experience nothing left
out wishing for
well-being freedom from harm inner and outer [Music]
harm happiness and
contentment and
ease
if there are difficult conditions that are arising restlessness
Pain any kind of difficulty receiving it with the same
kind of goodwi knowing that prior
conditions sometimes result in these
ways and causes and conditions come and
go sending it a kind wish may I be calm and patient with
difficult
conditions
and if as you receive what's arising in Awareness what's most prominent is
thoughts of other people in your lives allowing that as well and perhaps
sending them wishes for well-being
for safety for
happiness and for ease or particular wishes that apply to
their [Music]
situation
for
yesterday I shared and all of you shared about generosity and how it's considered an
important strength to develop in order to begin to ready the mind to fully take
in the teachings of the Buddha and move towards freedom from
suffering aan suito uh lists generosity as one one of three fundamental
trainings of the mind that we need in order to benefit from the Dharma the other two that help us get
started on the path to Freedom include cultivation of Virtues
ethics and the cultivation of renunciation which I like to think of as
letting go of unh wholesome impulses in favor of what's
wholesome so one of the wholesome kinds of States
we can let go into is the first of these
Brahma viharas these Divine abodes and that is meta in the ancient poly
language So Meta can be translated as Goodwill as loving kindness friendliness
benevolence and it's a quality that tends to develop naturally over time with dedicated regular practice of
meditation and mindfulness and sometimes people are surprised to find it welling up
spontaneously um find themselves just feeling almost close to tears from
feelings of kindness or feelings of compassion that well
up so it's also a quality that we can deliberately cultivate by inclining the
mind in meditation and daily life towards these silent wishes of Good Will
that we were offering in the meditation some of us uh offering goodwi kindness
friendliness towards oneself or others um both really as well as good
will towards all experience so greeting what happens what comes up in meditation
with friendliness and there's this quality of kindness that rests on this fundamental
kind of willingness benevolence towards other people and towards experience um
the the first phrases I offered to you were from uh suta called PTI Sam
Maga sorry that's a mouthful and it goes may they be free from
hostility free from Affliction free from distress may they live happily
acharia Buddha was a monk who took ordination at
the age of 26 um after resigning from the military after World War Two and he became a
prolific writer who established the mahab Bodhi Society of Bangalore he
established schools hospitals um hosts and in addition he
wrote 150 books so this is is one of the generous people in the last century in
the beginning of this Century who offered a lot of support to people
around him and to us in an essay about meta he pointed out that the aim of meta
practice is to grow boundless with practice and
to overcome all social religious racial
political and economic barriers meta is indeed a universal unselfish and all
embracing love so that's pretty amazing to hear that we begin to understand that
this practice of friendliness a kindness is aimed at nothing short of complete
freedom from suffering for all of humanity without exception it is the medicine that can
heal the world and this is why we cultivate ated it's the ultimate in ethical
conduct so I thought I'd read aloud to you Gill's translation of the
meta and it offers a flavor of how thoroughly we can develop this loving
kindness this Good Will and it also points to the benefits of meta how you
can reach the state of peace and no longer be caught in round after round of
stress suffering so I'll I'll make a few notes as I read it the first section is
actually talking about ethical conduct to reach the state of Peace one
skilled in the good should be capable and upright straightforward and easy to
speak to Gentle and not proud contented
and easily supported living lightly and with few
duties wise and with senses calmed not arrogant and without Greed
for supporters and should not do the least thing that the wise would
criticize notice that the last line is actually talking about renunciation letting go of unh wholesome behavior and
should not do the least thing that the wise would criticize
the next section describes the meditation or reflection we can do that leads to a collected mind somadi a
collected mind that's wholesome and if you practice meta very
sincerely it does reach uh levels of concentration and Sade so one should reflect may all be
happy and secure may all beings be happy at heart all living beings whether weak
or strong tall L large medium or short
tiny or big seen or unseen near or distant born or to be born May they all
be happy let no one deceive another or despise anyone anywhere let no one
through anger or aversion wish for others to suffer
and the final section has to do with making a total commitment to meta to Goodwill for
everyone for society as a whole as a parent would risk their own
life to protect their child their only child so towards all beings should one
cultivate a boundless heart with loving kindness for the whole world should one
cul CV at a boundless heart above below and all around without
obstruction without hate and without ill will standing or walking sitting or
lying down whenever one is awake May one stay with this
recollection this is called Sublime abiding here and now one who is virtuous
endowed with vision not taken by Vi use and having overcome all Greed for
sensual pleasure will not be reborn
again I love this Su I memorized it about 16 years ago and I for many years
I would say it every every morning first thing in the morning mentally recite it
and reflect on what it was saying uh living in the ethical way
described in this muta is actually wholesome behavior and it has a number
of beneficial results increasing happiness and peace of mind uh the mind that no longer gets
stuck in remorse worry and restlessness over time this cultivation
of meta is wise speech it's wise action and it's wise livelihood in other words
as a whole wise conduct that enables us to progress in this practice on the path
to Freedom so by behaving in an ethical virtuous way and also letting go of unh
wholesome behaviors the result is inner happiness and
goodwi as expressed in another translation of two lines of the muta may
all be well and secure may all beings be happy that's really wishing for the best
for everyone not only does this ethical Behavior Uh you know or virtue result in
your own well-being and the opportunity to make progress in the Dharma but it also means giving a gift to other people
and other beings and that gift is fearlessness and security two beautiful
words in paully Abaya Don and Kema Donna
giving those to others can you imagine giving every every being fearlessness and
security the planet would operate a lot differently if that were given the meta is also in poly called A
parita and A parita is a spiritual formula that safeguards one's
well-being protects us against all dangers and is said to rescue one from
mishap and Misfortune I it doesn't really for me it doesn't need to be a spiritual formula
it creates an inner state that makes it unlikely that you'll
do things that have unfortunate results it makes sense to me that when you're
coming from a place of Goodwill towards other people you're not harming them you're not doing unethical
things other people are much less likely to want to harm you they're much more
likely to greet you friendliness and with Goodwill in return so I hope uh that you enjoy this
cultivation of kindness and friendliness uh for yourself and for
other people for other beings and maybe if you are interested in treating this
week as a retreat you can cultivate these wishes of Goodwill these wishes of
benevolence all day today for you know anyone you encounter send them some silent wish for their health and
happiness their safety uh their ease and they'll they
won't even know that that's what you're doing and that's one of the joys of this meditation you're silently sending these
things to other people and other beings all day long and um by doing this you're
really growing your own practice in your own heart uh so actually I there's a good
question in the chat where do I find the written copy of the meta Gil published a book called the
issue at hand which is available on the IMC website you can uh link to resources
and find the books that he's published and I think that one uh is available
free of charge offered freely and um the metas is printed if if I recall
correctly close to the back cover or the last few pages and it's really lovely
practice to memorize it and practice with it every day so I wish everybody a
lot of uh well-being and happiness today and for any of you who would like to
continue this as a retreat um you can also join the evening happy hour tonight
I'm offering happy hour and others are offering it tomorrow night I'll offer it again Thursday and I think bruny is
offering it on Friday Nikki usually offers Mondays and Wednesdays so you can
join in continuing this practice from 6:00 to 7:00 Pacific time um if you're
up at that that hour so thank you very much and have a lovely day wishing you all
well