so um thinking about what to talk about today uh just seemed like somehow to
maybe for my sake just to say something that's uh touches on my
heart's ache around uh the war in Israel and Israel and Hamas that started
yesterday and um and I was not going to talk about it directly talk about
something else but that I associate with a response to it but um um but that's kind of you know
sitting on my heart not least because
uh I have distant relatives who live in Israel I have friends who have relatives
in Palestine and so this idea that it affects you know people in all
directions is a kind of a big thing in the way that these things kind of Ripple out into the world out into Generations
to come it's very painful to consider the consequence of these kinds of fights
and wars and then there's so much these wars in in the world I mean there's it's
been going on for a very long time Wars around the around the world but we have big ones we have Ukraine and Syria and
Myanmar and one of the considered one of the big uh armed conflicts is um the the
drug wars in Colombia in uh in Mexico U many many people are dying
there every year and um and the way that uh such conflicts uh
trigger rage in people anger that just perpetuates the very thing that U maybe
they're trying to stop perpetuates conflict perpetuates the justification of
violence and so um you know and so to sit in a in the
mid Buddhism we talk about the middle way uh and then often we kind of find
the middle way meaning between extremes of all kinds of things and um and so in
terms of conflict a very impactful kind of a middle way that uh
happened many years ago now at IMC when we were used to be in poo Alto
there was a um horrific murder of a young girl and the murderer was
sentenced to death in California and so we had a discussion about death penalty
and there there were different sides maybe he talked but it just an open discussion around it and when we got
near the end of the discussion this person stood up and said well uh I find
myself on both sides because uh both my parents were
murdered and it was by one of my close
relatives so for him for that person who was like oh no what I think he was maybe
in in favor of the death penalty but that meant for his relative so he was kind of stuck in the
middle of this and for me that that kind of middle way of holding both in one
person both sides and the pain of that and so how do we find a way in the
middle way how do we find a way that doesn't continue divisions how do we find a way that that
um uh that creates peace more than more
war so um it starts I think in simple ways it's one of the ways that it starts
is by uh living a life where you we don't lie and this is one of the first uh
spiritual teachings that we think that the Buddha taught to his son rahula and so I was thinking about this teaching
last night and this morning so I thought I I would share it with you and um so what what uh many people
don't know is that Buddha had a son and uh by the time that his son was about
seven years old six or seven years old um he apparently was mostly under the
care of his father and we don't usually think of the Buddha as a father and uh we think of him as monastic was quite
removed from kind of Parental responsibilities we don't know much about how he was a father but uh his son
came joined became what was called the novice Monk and um and so then lived that life
until he grew up and when he Contin then when around 20 years old you're allowed to ordain as a full monk so he was a
novice for 15 years 13 years and then became a
monk and uh at some point point in the son's youth maybe we're still pretty
young um it seems that um rahula told a
lie that's the only way you can this this story make sense and uh and so um the
Buddha they I think they go they they're they finished having their they go out every morning with a bull in order to
collect arms for the food they're going to eat that day and I think some somehow maybe that just close to finishing their
their meal they'd wash their bowl each monk is supposed to clean their own Bowl
usually and um and so they were sitting there and then the Buddha said um you
see how little water is left in this bowl here and uh Rula said yes and the Buddha
said um the monastic life of someone who uh deliberately
lies is as trifling or is worth as much as a little bit of oow in this
water so I can imagine his son gulped he's been
busted and then but the Buddha doesn't stop at that he says and he turned the
bowl threw the little bit of water out of the bowl and then he said the monastic life of someone who
deliberately lies oh no a little differently so I'll say this time they
actually the monastic life is someone who deliberately lies and has no shame about
it is uh is like uh this bowl which has no water in it there's no substance in
it nothing in it and then he goes on and says it again he says something like uh and now if you
turn the ball upside down so that to be gu last little drops fall out or something
something he said the monastic life of someone who deliberately lies but has no shame about
it is like a bowl that's upside down and in the fourth time he says then
he picks up the bowl and he says you know shows see it's all it's empty now of anything at all and the Buddha said
it's you know that the monastic life of someone who liberate lies but has no shame about it is um is hollow and void
just like this bow is so I imagine that was three big gulps this s side so in my imagination
of this uh because we don't know what in the text um the Buddha didn't say this in a harsh way or an angry way and but
he also didn't um you know didn't go let it go
unnoticed that his son had lied he was you know as a maybe a parental way
addressing this directly and um and I think what one of the things that's important here is that um
this word for shame I think in the Modern English in California at least that's a difficult word shame and it's
very it's a very heavily loaded and it's uh many people many people struggle with this word shame and and a tremendous
amount of pain and suffering and self-criticism around this word which much of it which is very
unnecessary but there is a place for a certain kind of healthy remorse certain
kind of healthy uh having a bad conscience about
what you're doing uh what you've done and uh without that uh we're not going
to correct for ourselves we're not going to get the message and you know boy I really blew it I really made a mistake
and so some kind of feeling of something is off here and exactly how we should
try uh call this in English I went to dictionaries yesterday and and um
wondered is there another word besides shame that we could use I wonder could we use disgrace doesn't feel disgrace
does that work better or um and some of the dictionaries the word lah in p and
also Sanskrit um can also mean bash they dictionary say mean bashful
embarrassed and that doesn't seem quite right either someone who deliberately lies but
doesn't feel bashful embarrassed might work but that kind of you missed kind of the the the
ethical feelings of this is something unethical here that happened so regardless you know there's
that would emphasize that so it isn't that he he delivered the lied that was a
problem what was the problem was he felt no regrets No Remorse he didn't feel
like he didn't recognize he had done something that was off that's what was the real thing because if you recognize
that you've done a deliberate lie and have some kind of remorse some kind of Shame then there's a possibility of
doing something about it making a corrective and we'll get to
that and for a monastic the idea of a monastic life in Buddhism Buddhism in
general is more a life than it is a philosophy it's a way of living the Dharma is a way of living and uh and
it's kind of um most represented by monastic life for the monks and nuns
because that's they're giving them over entirely to living a Dharma life that's the whole idea and it sometimes it might
look that the monastic doesn't do much but actually they're busy all day
long meditating being honest not being
greedy you know just kind of um being of service um processing their challenges
in the monastery I mean it's really you know it's a way of kind of being immersed in the Dharma life all day long
it's quite a wonderful thing and it's also kind of non-stop so if someone
wants to really live that life you can do it in Daily in in household life and
outside the monastic life as well but in monastic life you're constantly reminded
to do it stay close to the truth stay close to the heart of what man IC life
is about in Buddhism hard of what Dharma is about and that is
non-harming it's a dedication to not causing any harm both in the world
around us but also to ourselves and that's part of the reason
why you know the four noble truths that address suffering and the end of suffering uh is Al so Central because uh
suffering just another word for harm and and the and the ending of suffering is the ending of whatever
we're doing in ourselves whatever psych whatever psychological processes we have that contribute to our suffering is what
we're overcoming we're changing with the four noble truths so to to discover how
not to even harm ourselves um and then to understand that
there's a intimate connection between not harming ourselves and not harming others not harming others not harming
ourselves you can't can't really do one without the other and that this is at
this is what the heart of the Dharma is about is finding that possibility it's not necessarily easy
but I'm still remain tremendously inspired by this and uh I feel like it's a guiding
principle for my life that this is the life I want to live the life of non-harming and uh so here is uh rahula
deliberately lying and which is uh causes lying causes a a tremendous
amount of harm um it's harmful for the person who lies and harmful the person for the
society the community that has to live with those lies it creates divisions it
creates hurt when the lies come out it creates mistrust when we just people discover they've been lied to the person
does lie um uh the reference point for the impact it has on a liar that the
Buddha has I think or buddhis Buddhism provides us is maybe something like what
it was like for you to sit and meditate today or maybe some today maybe you didn't have a good
meditation but maybe some point in your life maybe you had a meditation where you felt particularly calm and centered
peaceful and felt kind of like now I'm really in touch with myself I'm arrived I'm here I'm not thinking about other
things other concerns I'm I'm arrived I'm here I feel peaceful and good and um
and uh you're unlikely to turn to the person next to you when you open your eyes and just lie about
something if you did I think you'd just feel so awful inside something inside of
you that had been built had been kind of you settled into while you're meditating
suddenly has been squashed it's been closed like the some something in your heart closes that with that lie and um
uh or or there's tension builds up or you might kind of start getting calculating well if you know if I say
this slide then I'll have be careful and some someone once said that um it's
better to be honest because then you have less to remember because if you tell a lie you
have to remember it and then do it again and um so the
impact it has on the liar in from the Buddhist point of view is said to be
huge for someone who chronically lies Chron chronically tense chronically
fighting a fighting with everything around their life they're not they're so agitated they don't see the impact it
has but it does have an impact and the impact is huge and uh so and if the dedication of
a life is to not cause harm like it is for rahula being a a novice monk then um
you know of course not just the Buddha as a father but also as a guide for training people in that life he has to
say something so he said these things about the and then he went on to say make make an
analogy uh for this for lying that uh uses a a war
analogy and it's I think it's quite evocative to use this analogy when you consider all these wars that we have in
our society and the people who are Waring the people who are constantly fighting and arguing and and um hating
other people that way of life for some people to be that way so the story is that um you know the
the Bradley tanks of ancient India were elephants and uh they had these big war
elephants that were trained to fight and they were trained to stay tame and and
uh tame and I guess calm enough to go into the the middle of battles uh so
that the person sitting people sitting on top of them could fight uh you know
in the middle of battle from this height and um and then also I guess they were also fighters these these big tusks and
legs that could kick and stuff and so the Buddha talks about there was this
elephant that um you know was well trained and knew how to fight and was
trained to go into any situation any kind of battle uh and to do whatever was needed in order to
fight and so recognizing this then the charioteers the elaters would take them
into battle and in in fact the the the uh elephants were so well trained that
they would just do exactly that they just fight no non-stop would do whatever it took to fight up until the point
where they got killed and uh and so then he go so that's the example he gives and we
probably see people like this in our in our Lives who don't stop for anything and then uh and then the Buddha
says someone who tells a deliberate lie there's no evil they're not capable of
doing so the elephant is no no no no
killing they're not willing to do once they've been trained that way so that's the kind of dramatic contrast for this
idea impact lying has so I can imagine that rahula is
thinking twice now about what he did if in fact he lied and uh and so he's
getting us getting you know has gotten his the Buddha has gotten his attention around
this then the Buddha switches gears and he gives rahula some
teachings first he asks the question he said what is the purpose of a
mirror and rahula says the purpose of a mirror is reflection so you can see
yourself in the mirror um in the same way the Dharma is
a mirror where we reflect in and how do you see
how do you find that mirror by reflecting on your
actions if you want to reflect you want look at your actions to see if I do any
act physical act through my body through my words or through my mind does it or
does it not cause harm in the world does it not cause harm to self or others
that's the Dharma question he's offering the Buddha you should reflect on everything that you do all actions you
have and reflect about whether or not they cause harm that's a tall order to
go around with that question all the time and does that mean that we're going to be busy remember I said monastics
have a busy life they're not sitting around they're busy kind of monitoring
themselves saying it and that's part part of the purpose of mindfulness is um not just to be calm and you know manage
with our stress but part of the purpose of mindfulness in the teachings of the Buddha is to be able to monitor
ourselves enough to see is what we're doing in body speech and mind is it
afflictive or not does it cause harm or not does it C cause stress or not in
ourselves and others and some people could be quite dis quite uninterested by this aspect of
Buddhism because it's much more interesting to talk about great states
of meditative absorption the Bliss and the calm and you know Bliss out you know it's you know and you know and if it's
not so great to do life meditation like this tremendous states of you know meditative absorption then I'll just do
psychedelics you know and that you know for a good time but uh in fact what the Buddha is
doing suggesting is um yes in Buddhism we have wonderful states of meditation
can be attained but that's not the the point to have those States the point is to have an ability to really track
ourselves to be able to live a life of harmlessness the result of that is a
tremendous inner peace so that's the reward from being able to do that but um but what means to
that is to have the self-reflection of body speech and mind think about it don't go through your
life not mindful don't go through your life mindful without questioning what
was the impact what was the consequences of what I've done here so this kind of reflection constant
reflection so um so then the Buddha says um if
um if you're going to do something in body speech or mind before you do it
reflect uh is this going to cause harm in any direction myself or
others and is what I'm going to do is it wholesome with good consequence or is it
UNH wholesome with detrimental consequences so afflictive just means
harm uh so is it cause harm or not harm but the second criteria was is it
wholesome or UNH wholesome means that um is the in doing it is it is it Nur
nourishing is it wholesome is it healthy for my whole psychophysical system to do it is it healthy for our society is it
beneficial for the people around us nowadays um just yesterday this
weekend I think maybe you saw it too that there studies that um uh parents
who yell at their kids growing up uh they are are impacting the kids uh
similarly to what it's like to be uh physically hitting CH young children
children gr up being hit uh and being uh yelled at have similar kind of impacts
on their trauma growing up their sense of abuse Growing Up So how important it is not even to yell at
people and uh you know mean words to people uh is not wholesome the person is
being mean it's also not so helpful for our society what goes on around
us so these CR budha offers these criteria is it healthy for you to do
that this is it healthy for others in the long term so not just right now but
in the long term so I've told this story many times of yelling not yelling at my son but but um I I Ed my I called it my
strong voice and um and it was uh rarely
used but um the um it was kind of like like you know seeming every other thing
had wasn't working terms of the the behavior the kid was
doing and so so I finally I just have to use my strong voice I said you know so it was kind of deliberately thought
about and considered it wasn't like just suddenly screaming and I would just say
in very strong Stern voice no and and that was effective okay okay
that okay good
until I heard exactly the same voice voice of my older
son uh using the same thing to his younger brother and then I said oh no
what have I done and that was I never used a strong voice
again that that way find other ways to you know
to to deal with parent
issues so um the uh um so then he said so before you do it
then the Buddha said while you're doing saying something doing something
or even mentally your thoughts around something you should be reflecting thinking about cons uh tracking yourself
monitoring yourself is this causing harm now and sometimes we only know uh about
this causing harm once we start because like some of the people we're talking to
we we're we're involved in uh we don't know what will affect them something that is innocuous
for one person is because of their background is very harmful causes a lot of pain for someone and so sometimes we
have to ATT track and pay attention in the moment and not just treat everyone like they're ourselves and think just
because I can say that and this has no impact on me it might have a huge impact
on someone else who has a you don't know their background and what they've been through so while you're doing it
important to track pay attention and it uh is it causing harm to yourself to others uh is it healthy
for yourself is it healthy for others what are the long-term consequences of this and if you find that it's unhealthy
and afflictive then the Buddha said you should stop don't do it just stop just
stop what you're doing and then the last one is interesting then he went through it again and he said be uh after you've
done something you should reflect on the same way but after you've done it if you
discover that yes it it was it hurt someone it was harmful yes it was
unhealthy and had deletar long-term consequences then you should go find
someone that you respect a wise person that you respect and tell them what you
did I don't want to use the word confession because that has a heavy and
some people in the west I think that the translation sometimes use confession but the poly word does not mean confession
because you know it's they were Buddhists
not not the people who use confession and um and so it was uh uh it
simply just says you want to go and acknowledge what you did it's more like an acknowledgement uh what you did and U so
me I'll read it to you and this is maybe for some people
the most difficult thing to want to
do um oh here here this translation is different it says um you should lay it
open that's a nice expression lay it open just be open about it put it out there lay it open to your teacher or
your wise companions in the Holy life oh here's the word
confession so again maybe I'll skip it because it's not the the P doesn't mean
like the way we associate what what we associate with the word so having said it having said it revealed it and laid
it open you should then undertake restraint in the
future so we do make mistakes we do do cause harm there are in intentional
unintentional ways in which we hurt people and uh to lay it open to someone
it makes a big difference because it's kind of like when you say it out loud you not you're not squirming around it
you're not kind of pretending it's not there you're not kind of like to trying to belittle it or or also you're not
holding it by yourself sometimes when we we we hold our sense of guilt by ourselves all
alone it tends to build unnecessarily big there's way too many people this is
why the word shame is so difficult uh to even for me to use it here today because
so many people have this private shame that they carry with them all the time there are some people feel shame just
because they breathe you know just they never do anything wrong but just that somehow they're they were born wrong so
they carry the shame with them or feel that way and um but uh when we do when
we do some cause harm in the world to carry the guilt to carry the shame privately and alone sometimes can be
very difficult and kind of the tension can build and and in some ways even make it worse for ourselves continues the
harm but you lay it open to someone else who's wise who will receive it well
who's not going to make you feel shame or not make you to feel he's not going to belittle you or be angry with you um
is a really a healthy thing to do and then you're accountable a little bit then you know if you really commit
yourself to not doing it again in the future you know oh you know my wise friend you know knows what
I did before and they're going to their eyebrows going to go up if they see me do it again I don't want that to happen
or you know or or now I know that I'm accountable to someone so maybe they'll
call me on it or maybe we'll have be maybe we need to have more conversations to understand better what what's
happening to me what's going on for me a wise friend will engage you with
respect with kindness um and honesty in order to find a way with what
happened so that's what the Buddha has said to his son after you know lying is not
good it's not good for someone who wants to live the monastic life lying deliberately with no sense of
Shame no sense of remorse no sense of conscience and and uh and this is how
you should live this life you should live this life uh monitoring yourself being
reflective some of you might think this is a a headache now to go around
monitoring yourself all the time about your actions but just like with learning
how to practice mindfulness after a while it becomes second nature it's like riding a
bicycle if you had to always be learning to ride ride a bicycle from scratch every day time you ride a bicycle why
would anybody ride a bicycle but you know you learn the bicycle and then it becomes easy look my
own no hands and uh you know it's becomes kind of second nature and you can do all
kinds of things while you're riding a bike even talk on the phone and um but um uh so the same thing
this monitoring of ourselves that mindfulness does become second nature you carryed with you all the time and
it's such a be it's like a treasure to have this it's a gift to be able to attract yourself and to monitor yourself
in this ethical way not causing harm is also a tremendous gift because then we
become a gift for society our society needs a lot more examples of people who
live a harmless life and to live a harmless life that is
not silent when there are problems in this world so the Buddha was not silent when
his son lied and whether you think this was good parenting or not that's an open question
but um but he did he wasn't silent he wasn't just sitting there like meditating pretending nothing happened
he addressed it directly and uh and I'm pretty sure the Buddha was doing the very thing he was
talking about doing before during and after speaking to his son this way he
reflected will this be afflictive harmful or not to say it this
way uh is this a healthy thing for myself and for him and will have good
consequences or bad consequences in the future so you know so this monitoring
always this monitoring going on and um so his son stayed in the
monastic life and when he was about 20 or so uh he became enlightened himself
self and then continue living this life the monastic life apparently to end of end of his
life so um so this importance of Ethics or life
of non-harming is a good thing to remember when we have so many examples of people
who are causing harm and uh where the heart it's you
know and sometimes these cycles of harm and violence um it's hard to know chicken or egg
where did it begin who's
responsible but it's easy to see how it just keeps going these cycles and this Palestinian and Israeli cycles that have
been going on for so so long you know from the distance it looks so
unnecessary something's not working and um so exactly what kind of
self-reflection is needed is hard to know it's what to say from a distance is
hard to say but um this idea of the middle
way that cares for everyone involved is has compassion for everyone
involved is looking for the best for everyone involved so what's what's Ben
most beneficial what's healthy for everyone involved that is the way forward I
feel um and um without without that I think there's not much hope we'll just
continue the Cycles on and on forever so
um thank you so we have about five minutes before
we normally would stop and then we'll have the tea that uh will be set up and you're welcome to you're invited to stay
and hang out it's a wonderful time to meet people and have community but in this last 5 minutes uh maybe it
be nice uh to turn towards maybe a couple of people next to you maybe groups of three and just say hello and
introduce yourself some of you might be new here for the first time it's nice to be
welcomed and um and the way it works here at IMC even if you're new here for the first time at least for today you
belong here so you can welcome the people who've been here for
years you just an equal footing that way and then if you want to share something
about this talk anything at all that uh struck you uh you're welcome to talk a little bit and then at some point we'll
go have our tea so please thank you and you don't have to stay if you don't want to but
it's