well hello nice to be with all of you again
it has been some time you know so I feel I feel the the pleasure and the
privilege of being back with this robust
so kind IMC 7am Sangha great guy great gratitude to Gil for
inviting me back uh this week as you might see the theme
will be the part of these the Perfections I saw these recently described as the
noble qualities that are accompanied by
compassion and skillful needs
so we'll talk quite a bit about the parmes over the next over the next five days
but first let's um let's meditate
the focus of this meditation will be the the first part of me of generosity
so even as we're taking the posture
giving the posture setting up the posture
calling in calling in
generosity giving
the support that's given by the the seat holding us up
the relaxation of the face as we close the eyes
maybe rolling and aligning the shoulders
and a few deep breaths really connecting with this body
this body that accompanies us through so much
settling in yeah
there's something is there something in the posture that
expresses an attitude of generosity
the kind way we regard the spine
or let the belly loosen
the space we give for the breathing to come in and out
rather than controlling the breath
something you may experiment with
is to see if you tend to meditate with your hands
Palms down see if it Taps into any of your
generosity to turn them up open Palms open-handed
that gesture of giving and receiving
not only generous with the body
generous with the mind and mental activity
what kind of attitude am I bringing to distraction
wandering
or to the senses the sounds that are just coming and just
going Sensations
emotions whatever is coming
can that too be regarded with an open generosity
by this time some of the
needs or impulses of the body are the habits of the Mind
may be making themselves known
welcome dear friend I have some tea
stay as long as you like
is there some way that a generous welcoming or hospitality
allows us Stillness to accompany the movement
foreign
foreign foreign
and for these last minutes of the sitting
if the attitude of generosity has been favoring the side of giving
how now with the sight of receiving
maybe it's receiving the support of what's outside of you
community leave in your chair
may be receiving something inside
your intention to practice or the results of this half hour of
sitting any little buds of goodness
so a minute just to receive with generosity
[Music]
foreign
thank you very much everyone uh hello again
[Music] um I suspect we had some folks joined while we were sitting to
reintroduce myself my name is kodo very very happy to be here with the 7
A.M Sangha thanks to Gil for the invitation and the topic for the week is the
10 parties the 10 Perfections uh Tennessee well-known teacher
introduces them this way he says the ten Perfections or part of these
are the Buddhist teachings that are probably the most useful for bringing the path of Awakening into everyday life
there are a list of qualities that you can develop in any situation he says as you're working with your family at home
at the office as you're driving as you're meditating and the qualities are these
so generosity virtue
third renunciation fourth discernment or wisdom
fifth persistence or energy sixth is patience
seventh is truth ape determination resolve
ninth Goodwill and ten equanimity
it's the word parame relates uh to the word paramam which means something of
foremost importance it really got my attention at tennis robiku says that these are the most
useful for bringing the path into everyday life how many of us wonder how best to do that
so I remember when I I first encountered these teachings I was practicing at a Burmese Dharma
Center here in the U.S and what I heard was that for the
practice to ripen an Awakening that is for the practice to develop into
just the sort of Freedom that I was looking for the teaching was that all of these
paramis needed to be sufficiently developed and I thought oh
I thought this was all about concentration I thought this was all about meditation mindfulness
but what this opened up for me is the opportunity that any moment whatsoever in the day could be a moment for
practice and you can hear the broad application if you hold this in mind as I list them
again so giving ethics renunciation wisdom
energy patience truthfulness resolve
Goodwill and equanimity So the plan for the week is to discuss
the parmes in pairs and why is that in part because 10 part
of these divided by two equals five days um also
one of my hopes is that because we because we discussed two parmes each day two Perfections each day
that we can see something about how one wholesome quality is supportive of another wholesome
quality to say this another way one wholesome quality brings others
along in the way we talk about in the suit as Right View being the Forerunner
um one way uh in this regard that I think about the part of these is um you might
know someone who has a good friend that brings out the best in them one good quality brings out the good
qualities in another one of the ways the parmes are talked
about is um is like each one being a bucket
that's being filled with water to strip drip drip drip by drip drip by drip
slowly patiently and because of these parames mutually support you might think of all these 10
buckets very closely together and when the water of one fills up it spills over
into the next our giving supports our virtue our
renunciation supports our wisdom and so
so the what can I say
practitioners have been making sense of and relating to the Buddhist teachings for a long time and that means a lot has
been said uh so I like to I like to relate to one
specific teaching that can represent the practitioners of a specific time
so a lot of what I'm going to say this week is inspired by Reflections on a
text called the treaties on the parmies by acharya dhamapala
all that I'll say about dhamapala other than being prolific is that to me he seems like someone who did the very hard
work of reflecting on his tradition in such a way that he could respond skillfully to
his times and that way he sort of reminds me of The Dalai Lama
so the the application of the parmes
is every day it's it can be in all sorts of things and the tradition regards the
great potential of these practices is nothing short of complete Awakening actually of buddhahood
so let's begin with some of the basic principles of the parmes that will apply to to a discussion of all of them we'll
hear these sorts of things all week first is that the the Pyrenees the
Perfections they're both practices and their virtues
so they are both actions things we can do and they are the
results and say the sort of Tendencies the qualities that arise over time as
the basis of those practices so part of these can be both we practice giving to develop generosity
we become ethical by practicing ethical conduct and so on
What's um something that's beautiful about the part of these being both a practice
and a virtue practices and virtues is that we we are
were allowed is that the right word um that's not that's not exactly right but
we get to practice them imperfectly
we get to practice as best we can and this we can trust that this is developing Something Beautiful in us we
practice renunciation imperfectly but we're growing in the skill growing
in the tendency so as dhamapala says the paramis they're
Noble qualities which is giving renunciation Etc accompanied by compassion and skillful
means and when mature untainted by craving conceit and views
here we hear again how skillful qualities bring each other along the skillful skillful qualities of
compassion the skillful qualities of skillful means which is a form of wisdom the form of discernment
bringing along our generosity maturing our generosity
good let's see so
let's say you hear the word Perfections
and your first thought is oh great now I have to be perfect in these 10 ways in
order to be a card-carrying practitioner let me say at the outset that it's not
what not what I'm hoping to emphasize or propose instead of Perfections as
um measuring sticks that we have to say oh I must be perfect now
instead maybe consider that these can be 10 powerful powerful reference
points for wholesome growth as if the Buddha and the teaching the
teachers are saying oh look here look here there may be something useful here to to examine and practice and reflect
on for example in a very plain way how's my generosity
is that accessible to me is that something that lives in my life what role does it play
and here's the part where we don't have to be perfect you also reflect on the opposites
how's the opposite of generosity showing up in my life and taking a real honest look and just
seeing it's almost like play experimentation what role does stinginess play in my life Wow check
that out so consider them rather than demands of perfection as these high leverage points
just like our meditation we have this we have this reference point of the breathing for many of us or
if it's another object same same works we don't demand that the Mind stay with
the breathing a hundred percent of the time we we get skilled instead of the process
of attending to the breathing seeing the mind wander and bring and the mind coming back
and we get skilled in this whole process but all the while we have this really useful reference point of the breathing
of the body
so one of the keys that I'm going to emphasize throughout is that dhamapala
encourages with all 10 of the parmes a certain method of reflection
and that is um to reflect on the drawbacks of their
opposites the drawbacks of their opposites and then
to to also reflect on the particular benefits of
that quality so you'll see this you'll see this fleshed out as we go
but I want to emphasize this at the beginning because this sort of reflection what's the drawback the
hazard the the harm in the opposite of generosity versus the benefit of practicing
generosity to reflect in such a way as precisely where we will discover where the
practice can live all over our life in so many situations
and it's also where we can start to notice the paramis supporting one another
so just a couple of minutes on Donna paramita giving
teaches that Donna's function is to dispel Greed for things that can be
given away and let's take up this approach so the drawbacks that he talks about
um we might recognize is the drawbacks of possession are clinging to our possessions particularly the sort of
worry that that can generate you can think about how um we may have something that's quite
dear to us but it's subject to loss we may have a beautiful teacup that's subject to breaking
um our possessions can not only spark clinging in us but others may want them
um it can they can give rise to conflict they can even give rise to enemies he
says not in all cases of course but these are the possible drawbacks of clinging to our possessions
so we're meant to reflect on someone we can give our things away to as a best friend
someone who someone who's helping me to rid myself of my possessions that I'm
clung to and also helping me to develop this opposite the quality of generosity
so beneficial the other side is the practice of giving that we're encouraged to arouse joy in
three cases in the case of a dear person asking us
for something in the case of a neutral person asking us for something
and the case of a hostile person asking us for something all three Were Meant to
arouse Joy because if a dear person asks us for something we can arouse some Joy on the
basis of oh this one I care for so much is asking me for something and I have the opportunity to give
if someone uh neutral to us an acquaintance we might not know so well asks us for something we can arouse Joy
knowing that um giving so often
um supports develops um a relationship
and I love this encourages reflection on the arousing Joy Based on a hostile person asking us for something
and this is the rationale that if if um he says my foe is asking me for
something though he is hostile to me by means of this gift he will surely become
my friend I hope that's true I hope so
in all three cases arousing joy and also arousing loving kindness and compassion
when we give one good quality brings another along
so a few words about Sila virtue in the practice and the quality
the function it said is blameless conduct that's the ideal that's where where
we're headed and we practice it imperfectly dhamapala has a series of beautiful
metaphors in order to communicate the power of Selah the power of the practice of Sila things like a fragrance that
pervades all directions a staircase ascending to the heavens
a highway leading to nibana and he says even the Waters of the Ganges cannot
wash away the stain of hatred but the water of virtue is able to do so
so he communicates the power of Silo with these rich metaphors
and we can think for ourselves of the bent the benefit of Selah as a protection
it has a basis for our own security and one of the ways that Sila and generosity supports each other
is that when our Sila when our virtue is well developed
then we're said to be we're said to give the gift of fearlessness
to all beings no one need fear or distrust me
so as an encouragement to bring the practice of the parmes into the everyday into your day today
uh what I would suggest is to for yourself reflect upon observe and take
note a few very very straightforward questions where does giving
generosity show up in my life today and where does its opposite show up where do I notice that
what are the conditions for its arising and do the same with virtue or ethical
Behavior if you know the list of the precepts or the 10 skillful actions how does virtue
play a role in my life and where does its opposite show up and it's again not for any sort of
judgment or push toward Perfection that we're practicing the Perfections
but right now just play experiment get to know what is what is this mind what is this heart how does it how does it um
manifest in the world so we'll begin here the beginning of the
session tomorrow there may be some time to to share in the in the chat what you found and then we will proceed with the third
and the fourth armies Perfections pronunciation and wisdom
thanks so much for being here it's a joy see you in the morning