okay people um [Music]
yeah nice to see the names uh streaming over there in the chat
um very sweet okay
well uh we'll set
very gently put your heart into a kind of Dharma
posture
no way in in yoga doing a a pose Asana
very deliberate about how we get into that
pose
same thing with a kind of the Dharma pose of our heart just uh
get lined up
foreign
the Dharma path is one of the coming progressively sensitized to goodness
being moved by it
being moved by your own goodness
for whatever reason we find ourselves in
this uh this lineage of wisdom love
in so many ways for a human life to unfold so many ways to suffer
in so few ways to be free
and wisdom and love
that actually is a path
some hope and wisdom and love
no techniques uh way as we Marshal
attention kind of efforts we make
are infused seasoned with uh
the felt the sense of uh presence
love
meditative techniques can be uh recapitulation of our anxiety
vigilance
or self-correction
we let the mind marinade and uh
images signs of wisdom love
and maybe then we use our attention in particular ways
often useful to connect with the affective circuits of your body
the surges of feeling emotion of impulse motivation
the building blocks of the
moving towards and moving away
that characterizes so much of our life
equanimity with feeling
that's so intimately tied up with our freedom
this feeling that Tangles us up with phenomena
is the fuel of the the push and pull of aversion grasping
it's feeling that make experience feel dense a burden on the
heart
so we practice letting the Winds of feeling blow through us
interesting that nothing will be blown over
and uh surges of feeling seemed to beg us to
think
to place the feeling in the context of what we want what we don't want to tell
story about this moment about this life
very innocent impulse
but sometimes we experiment in meditation
with not making anything mean anything
not over interpreting phenomena the push and pull
in other words we start to trust awareness
Trust the logic of the Dharma
our our understanding comes less from seeking answers more from
surrendering surrendering to not knowing
surrendering the
stories we use to Grapple with the intensity of the moment
well the ways we cope with feeling
by thinking
relax
as Faith Buddha dhamma Sangha
foreign
okay um so uh
wisdom
the uh the Buddha says uh just as the
lion is the ruler of the Jungle wisdom rules over
mindfulness concentration Faith energy
um the the last of the five uh
faculties so wisdom
philosophy the word breaks down as love love
of wisdom and I'll say more about the the Buddhist
definition of it but uh in one scientific uh Team
uh characterized it in this way as as having six components nothing sacred
about six could be five or seven but um they picked six and uh six six facets so
wisdom as pro-social attitudes and behaviors
emotional homeostasis self-understanding
value tolerance dealing effectively with ambiguity
uncertainty and social decision making
uh so I offer that just a kind of way another lens from which to understand
okay what what is wisdom and often a practitioners ask Dharma
teachers questions yeah and uh often boils down to something like
how do I be wise and
that's a question I can't really be answered by another person
wisdom is uh it can't be mimicked and
it's improvisational and it emerges out of our own
intuitive connection with ourself
and our ability to make good predictions
about happiness wisdom is about making good predictions
about suffering and happiness for ourself and for others
given given everything I know about
me and you and everyone we know
how should we live given
Anita anata how should we live
given the vulnerability of our species to Greed to hatred to
delusion to violence given the vulnerability of our species to violence
how should we live philosophers
sometimes distinguish knowledge that
from knowledge how so knowledge that
the universe 14 billion years old verse knowledge how
how to ride a bike and
Dharma Insight wisdom is mostly about knowledge how knowledge
how to do what knowledge how not to suffer
heard a story of uh this beloved old uh
monk in Thailand who
apparently saw a satellite in the sky and asked uh his younger
you know younger monastic to explain like what what is that you know what is
going on there and um and the younger younger monk had
to explain the Earth's rotation the Earth is round the you know all these
things and um and that was all news to this old
monk yeah it is about the shape of the earth and its movement
he didn't know any of that but he knew how not to suffer
how not to cause suffering
so the the Journey of uh of wisdom
from a kind of latent potential
the the dots inside us that haven't been connected
latent potential to Insight to embodiment and generalization
generalization meaning wisdom that's operative in all spheres of our life
is a tall order wisdom operative in all spheres of our life
the right we all know their zones contacts relationships moments
particular currents of of feeling of thinking
where we lose we become alienated from our
our wisdom and uh
we want to keep a kind of relationship with the the
failures of the of generalization the way is our wisdom doesn't generalize
to all contacts and was talking with a friend just a couple
days ago another long time Dharma practitioner and just having a very very
Frank conversation for the the ways that um our wisdom has been
actualized and generalized and the ways it's not
and it's inspiring to see the ways in which
we have not generalized the wisdom to all
corners of our life it's actually motivating
so the process we we start um start by thawing out the top layers of
of delusion and that takes that just takes time it
takes time where we just I think naturally are kind of confused
about the nature of Happiness confused about what we actually want confused about what a good life
would be and maybe we we find ourselves getting what
we want but then it's not what we thought it was and this kind of recognition the cycle
that uh that getting is always different from wanting
so wrong View wrong View
um feels almost visceral it feels almost visceral like it's in our tissues or something
and we have to thaw out and in that process of thawing out which might be
months or years there's a lot of Kicking and Screaming
that happens a lot of Kicking and Screaming as we're thawing out
as we're starting to replace the kind of uh
boards on the the the are our uh boat our raft or whatever
we we find we we can't just um
replace all the boards of the boat uh that we carry on at once it's a gradual
gradual path and we can't even really pick up
new ideas initially we have to almost like make our body mind more porous so
that new information can flow in this is um
some of why we emphasize not knowing emphasize surrender emphasize putting
down all the familiar reference points of liking and disliking good evil us
them we make the mind more porous
malleable stable we
get settled get happy enough
and um usually we think we have to get wisdom so that we can be happy and that's fair
enough but um but happiness often actually precedes insight
happiness precedes in sight when we're suffering we're just looking
so desperately for ways out it's hard to learn it's hard to learn we
can do it we can do it but it's harder to learn
um happiness a kind of positive mood actually modulates our Attention our
cognition and broadens The View and so whereas suffering pools the
attention Narrows The View makes resolution feel kind of urgent
um happiness sense of well-being broadens The View
we become receptive to new information and wisdom often feels like it arises
out of almost like out of our peripheral vision not out of our intent gaze
ramdas says the quieter you get the more you can hear
and uh the function of samadhi
quieter you get the more you hear and so
um
the wisdom wisdom the actually
creates the sense that the oh okay the Dharma the Dharma is real it's real
it's been realized it becomes real
and our Insight feels
Insight feels freeing feels um
it feels like it resolves it's like something consistent in our being all
the way down from conscious thought to subconscious competition something feels like
um something comes into true
and sometimes we think that's the end of the
story but most Insight needs reinforcement the light from the Stars dims
where we need to to consolidate and to
re-practice to re-discover we need to be reminded of our wisdom
this is why we have kalyana mitta spiritual friends were way more suggestible than we think
and it's really important to have this kind of steady inflow of goodness into
our heart we keep practicing to to nurture protect
our wisdom Joseph Goldstein just summed it up simply when we practice wisdom grows
when we don't wisdom waves
we have to keep suffering we do keep suffering and we keep a conscious
relationship to our dukkah this is what inspires us to grow and
deepen and we we try acting from our wisdom
try acting from our wisdom even sometimes when we don't feel it what would a person be like yeah I okay
I knew that Insight around self kindness what
I don't feel so kind right now at all but what what
that person do now if they were living from if I were living from this Insight
from this wisdom from the self-kindness how would I behave now let me do that
let me try that on so um
we prepare the ground until the soil bar delusions and habit-wise view
we get still gets quiet stay open to the peripheral
vision we consolidate and grow our insight
wisdom wisdom
to offer this for your consideration and uh
yeah it's sweet to be with you think about you wherever you are
um yeah okay well um I wish you uh wish you
all well and um I'll be back in a few weeks here so
if this was annoying don't don't come I guess
would be my wisdom you know anyway um I'm not sure on Gill's schedule I
think he's back I hope he's back um but it's possible I'm confused
anyway uh it's always um lovely to to uh step in for him and
uh feel connected to you all and so it doesn't feel like uh
um uh uh doesn't feel like a weird awkward substitute teaching kind of gig it's
like oh yeah we're friends so I love that
okay people um I wish you uh wish you all well yeah