good morning everyone happy Mother's Days
to everyone involved
today I'd like to share some Reflections on a teaching that's been very important
to me has made a big difference in my life and um
it's the topic of views views
of views and the teachings have a very naked negative rendition and all the
discourses views are not rendered as positive things
so they are qualified the views that uh
we work on are things called right views
or purification of views
and this is particularly wonderful to me because well I think that this practice
is about meeting all the needs the deepest needs
that a human person can have and coming into contact with what we
need the most and being able to have relationships
internal and external that help us settle open up
and come up to the fullness of our being fullness of here
fullness of being together and so views are usually
found in kind of a classic teaching of something called Sila
somebody and ponya words these are poly words that can be
translated to ethic ethical conduct samadhi can be concentration or
meditation and panya's wisdom and Views are usually in the category of wisdom
because views can be the beginning and the end of the path
that's one of the potent things about them we start working on our views
start relating to our views and branching out widely releasing views
lessening views finding views that are helpful and then this amazing thing begins to
happen that without views then there's just this
viewing the seeing this knowing
and this knowing that I'm talking about the knowing that we develop the knowledge and vision of this tradition
is is very gentle it's about
Gil says something like be still and look at everything and gaze
at everything kindly gazing at everything kindly and the
kindly part is really important because they're kindly kindly part is
where the settling has happened in order to be able to look at views um
so first there's Sila and ethical virtue and what we get from
practicing with our ethical conduct is we as
we find some safety we find where our need for
safety is met and our need for non-harming is also met
and then that allows us to settle down and and really start relaxing some of
the deeper things inside of us that are a little fragmented we kind of lead
fragmented lives mostly we're usually coming and going in our
minds usually coming and going in the world we it's part of the worldly life to come
and go to reach to push to want to not want
and so samadi is of coming together it's a
centering it's a not being out there not being then and there
and once we find that we have this foothold this place of rest
this place we can begin to take note of our view what we see
more easily and we begin to notice those views that are lead us to
wholesomeness to the goodness what leads to compassion what leads to
Joy authentic Joy and and there are different views the word
views and Pali which is ditty can mean pretty much the same thing that it does
in English it can mean the view the opinion the belief the
metaphysics the history the stories all these things that we've inherited that
we brought along and Views can also also means in poly
some well it also shares the meaning of having being out of view
of you a beautiful Vista the top of a mountain at the edge of a cliff
and then it has a very interesting view that's in Pali that um we don't have in
English and that is Here and Now being here and now
and and that's what we get to we get to this place where we're here
and now with this tremendous clarity
this tremendous Clarity that can see here and now in a way that's not normally not available because there's
so many filters that we live with that we need in fact
so it's a lot about removing the filters and we start to do this by settling down
by doing what we just did we meditated we were quiet
and then we can begin to notice all the things that also come up
and it's very different than when we are able to just kind of
be there fully let's say that you were standing in line
over there in the bathroom and there's a long line and you want to get back here to the meditation to be on
time and so
there's a little concern there's a little worry there's a little preoccupation there's a little back and forth going on
in you it's also possible to maybe you heard some teaching about
being quiet and receiving the moment and
being massaged by the present moment and receiving the goodness that's here
and you decide to be still while you're waiting for the bathroom
just list just still taking in
your feet on the ground the body shifting
the space people come in and going
the sunlight those are a whole bunch of other things
than the concern to get to the bathroom to get back to sit here and be on time
and so that's the fullness that I'm alluding to the moment gets like thicker in a way as
we begin to quiet down and release our views our thinking
in their different views some that really hold us back
fearful views long habits long ideas that we picked up from somewhere
some flashbacks and stories and so these begin to settle
and what we do is we can begin to take care of something that's a little deeper
inside we begin to we can begin to take care of
well maybe that view is not really necessary we can kind of begin to put a question mark on views
and we come back to the present moment and then we can take another look at that
view and slowly that can begin to see that that doesn't really help us
and so there's this kind of massage that goes back and forth it's very organic
we can sense the effect that it has on us to go back to that same concern that same
preoccupation and begin to sense what it does
physically emotionally and then we
begin to see that well maybe it maybe I don't need to see it this way
maybe I can begin to question it a little bit differently
and this helps a lot because it leads us onward it leads us onward to
to go a little deeper into what is going on here with
how we frame things how we see things how we exist here
it's been very very important for me to let go of views very intense views
through a lot of work because I have found myself more
belonging to the world we all have this deep need to belong to
be at home we see the Buddha statue pointing to the Earth
on the night of his enlightenment he was pointing to the Earth because
the Earth was his witness he belonged to the Earth he is of the Earth
there was no separation nothing could take him away from his
connection to here the fullness of here
and then there's the stability also in his gaze it was a kind of a kindness in his gaze
there is a sweetness that comes and we cultivated with our practice we like we
did just now and so we do this and the more we do
this the more we can accept things and see things
so many of us maybe have looked at emotions here with one of the guided one
of the many teachings that we do in secular mindfulness and in our inside tradition is we we look at emotions
and we look at emotions as as phenomena as events
and it's very very helpful to look at an emotion as an event
as opposed to how we usually feel emotions our
emotions mirror emotions become the emotions
there's something very different as if we learn to step back a little bit
and sense it understand it from a sensory point of view
and that's a very very big place that begins to open up that's why
being with emotions is so such a potent practice it's this huge place because when we can
look at our emotions that way when we can treat our emotions that way we find this Refuge inside
there's this space that opens up and suddenly the emotion can be
understood better and it's not about doing anything to the emotion it is not about trying to fix it which is really
hard right because um it would be really nice to just stop
certain emotions like fear anger shame
sometimes there can be even too much joy that can be inappropriate
and so we don't really change them but we
can see them know them sense them
care for them kindly attend to them kindly attend to them
kindly let them be so that in that space that opens up
these things can get untangled in what gets untangled is not necessarily
to our inner something we we do that's one of the wonderful things about
a mindfulness it gets untangled by
by well something called insight
we begin to see and sense that the emotions
are in this flux first of all we see that they are us they are in something
we know they're an experience that's happening and that we can know them
so it's something very cool that our mind does we can know something
and we can let the something be and when that space opens up which we
that we do with emotions all the time when that space opens up then
this this untangling begins can begin to happen if we can be steady
if if we can be caring in fact we if if we can really just be
there not fragmented not pushing away but actually find some sort of Center
some sort of foothold some sort of nurturing or kindliness
if you can be kindly to some of those horrible emotions that come
from life if it can be kind to them
they unravel there's this unraveling that happens
and it unravels because these things want to be felt and seen
because there's a lot in them that has a lot of little sticky parts
that we keep us attached I that fear it's like we almost can't even see that
we are not the fear sometimes we almost can't even see that we're not
the shame sometimes but if we bring this caring nurturing
stance that our tradition teaches us this is a tradition of tranquility and
serenity as well as insight if we bring this tranquility and
serenity to this stuff these real knots of ours
they begin to kind of slowly unravel because they're physical things
their emotional things their motivational things
their cognitive things and we get insight into
oh wow when this happens this happens
wow when I when I when that comes into my
Vision this happens when that comes into my mind I do this
when I feel this way then I really go down that rabbit hole
wow and it's cool like how how this happens it happens because
you see things are not solid that's one of the big problems of views
or one of the big interesting Revelations of having Right View
or having a purified View a purified view means that we can see
the emotions see the object and we can know we're seeing the object
and that they're two different things and when we can see these two different things we then begin to see that we have
this overlay of Concepts and how we see
the emotion how we see my anger how I see my anger I begin to see how I see my
anger and then I can I can know that and I can take that
stock and kindly receive it and one other thing I see is that it's this
is changing how I'm looking at it changes and the thing the anger is also changing
and so suddenly things are not so fixed we're in this kind of stream moving
flowing world and that's amazing because it's like
we're more here we're we're more alive and more we're more intimate with
ourselves we can be more intimate with ourselves and we can be more intimate with the
world which is very nice let's say that you are
at the beach one day it's an off day it's a Sunday afternoon
like today and we're at the beach and we just came out of meditation so we're
very relaxed we're not yet worried about Monday and so we just really take in the beach
we've just really take in the waves we take the foam of the waves
the air the flowing gentle breeze the Cool Breeze
and there's the maybe a little Birds little bird legs
and we're just really taking taking all these things in we can really just if we're settled and
just there in some sort of Joy enjoying this
and it's very cool because you're just registering these things
and you're just registering it's it's like a Marvel
you're not really thinking about these things that's a different thing someone asks
you did you see that wave did you see those waves oh yeah those were great waves but it
wasn't because you were analyzing the waves it could be analyzing the waves but then that keeps you in a different
little frame as opposed to a very very broad frame or you just registering
everything in every direction which is what mindfulness does
and then at the beach you can go into another layer there's the building blocks of
your experience are also available and then
how that comes into view is that you see that they're
is sand and that you're knowing sand
and what begins to show up is the quality the essence of sand
hardness wetness
moving air shifting Sensations
and that's a whole other deeper level of experience that is available to us just
like in standing in line when we were standing in line you could have been thinking about getting to the
bathroom or you could have been really fully here being in the moment taking in
everybody around you and just having a different experience one's not better than the other it's
just a different experience and then the different experience where there could be a greater intimacy and a
fullness fullness of the moment and that's very very sweet because
because we kind of don't live that way for the most part
we kind of live in a different way and so we are not in a certain way
really fully even here at times many times the world of the Mind
is a very very very captivating world to be in it's almost like a virtual reality
in a certain sense there's this little story that someone told me my Aunt one of my aunts from
where I was born sent me this little story of just this little electronic story about
a a woman who was having lunch this was in Spanish
so some woman in Latin America was at a restaurant she went into a restaurant to have lunch
and she was busy planning her next big project at work and uh
also planning some other things that she needed to do her vacation and um
she ordered her lunch and then this she heard this voice from
like below her it's how the story put it can I have a piece of bread please
and she looked down and there was a little boy asking for a piece of bread
and and of course she you know she kind of
felt the Pang of that and so she ordered him a piece of bread they brought him a piece of bread and uh
and then she kind of really wanted to get back to her her world and then the boy asked can I
have a piece of a little bit of butter to put on it please and so she offered him the butter and
and then he asked her what are you doing and she said I'm sending emails
and he asks what's that uh and she knew that he would not
understand the boy had was a desperately poor boy in Latin America
you see this everywhere where I come from and where I work and where I live a
lot and so this boy said what what's it what's email and so she was trying to
explain to them and she couldn't figure it out how to explain it to him and then she said you know it's like virtual reality
it's like a virtual reality that doesn't really exist where it's like letters and
notes but it's more like a virtual reality and then she and then he she explained and then
he said oh I know what virtual reality is virtual reality
um I live in virtual reality too I live in the idea that every that it's
going to be Christmas today and that we're going to have gifts and presents
because um where I live my mom goes to work
every day and um my sister goes to sell her body but she
comes back with her body every night my father is in jail
and my little baby brother is crying from Hunger
and so I live in this virtual reality too and the woman kind of came to
and and came to to see and to sense how how
she was how she was missing the World by going
back into her world of vacations and in her memories she was remembering suddenly a vacation she had had in Italy
or something and she was missing the world she was in
the world but missing the world and not be able to have compassion for the world that you live
in so it's a very different experience to
live in a world where where it's a virtual reality
you're not being we're not receiving all that's here
we're not unwinding all that could be Unwound and open up the heart to what
the heart can open up we're not knowing the spaces of the heart this is a path
there's this great book by Goldstein this little cute little yellow book a path full of heart it's the prettiest
little book it's very short but it's a path full of heart
this is this is a path full of heart in the way to release
release all the Cravings classical word
clinging that we have the thirsts that we have
the wantings the unquenchable wantings
and then the fears and the shames and the flashbacks
the way to unwind these things is to is to when it's time to do this practice
to remember that there can be two things
very simple at all time there's what we expect there is this
glass and I know that I'm knowing this glass
and just in the time that I told you that I wasn't really thinking of the glass
the glass looks like it's here right but there is all this there's all this shifting and changing at every moment
with this glass there's the glass there's I could bring
it up and have water I call it a glass
but we could put flowers in it and then it's something else
so it's a convention that I'm overlaying on it so I can be very rigid this is my
glass nobody use my glass for flowers
that's rude or just know that this is shifting
and I'm thinking about the glass but I'm also thinking about you I'm also thinking about what I'm going to say I'm
also thinking wondering if you're getting me all this stuff is going on there's all
this shifting and moving happening in just this class
and when I enter into the world of just what I know and what's being known
the sensory experience is completely changing
and so is my internal experience my knowing of it is also shifting and
changing so there's this constant movement of arising and passing
a rising and passing it's not constant
and that's very very relaxing for those things that are not easy to change
in US that really softens things up
because it gets really hard in there sometimes
in that heart mind were really locked no this is
not true this is how this is you don't know but this is how this is
but is it so what I'm talking about uh is the
beginning is what's referred to in the tradition is the beginning of ipasana
beginning of insight when we are in that flowing world when
we are beginning to sense and know and see and feel and
touch and experience and look kindly at how much flux and flow is happening
then we have insight vipasana the V they tell me means you're
really seeing you're really seeing we're really seeing through
and it's very nice to really see through in this world to to connect deeply to
this world to connect deeply to the people around us
and equally important maybe as much to connect to ourselves really
deeply to really find ourselves where
there's a rub where there's a stuckness where there's a repetition that just
won't stop that keeps holding me back it's really nice to find
that oh oh that's that's that and then to be kind toward that
to care for that to let it be nourished by the calm
that's available there's a lot more benevolence here than we usually
Avail ourselves of and so we open up broadly to this
goodness we can
and then it's a new world it's the same world it's this world
but it's very very broad it's very very full
it's very very free of the concepts that I've overlaid
today being Mother's Day I was reflecting about
being with my mother a couple of weeks ago and
and it was just kind of amazing how I can be with her now because
I can see this person my mother
but I can also let her be a person
let her be her whatever she whatever she is and that's just an amazing reality to me
now my mom and I like many mothers are you know have a very have had a very
difficult past I'm a queer man and um
she's a Latin American woman um very Patrician upbringing very
patriarchal upbringing I grew up in a Latin country and
so The Stance was no you're gay no
we're going to beat that out of you so my uncles tried to beat it out of me
um and then my mom just refused to accept me and
um I had a stepfather who also was kind of pushing me out of the house so I kind of
left the house pretty early and led a semi-homeless life at a very young age
because that's just how it was for everybody it was a different era the
country was in a different place the world was in a different place around the issues of being gay being queer yeah
that identity was really not what it is today and so for years I would just hang up on
my mom because then when we started to talk again she would ask every time was when are you going to get married when
are you going to get married when are you going to get married so just have to hang up like for like 10 years like I would just
hang up I would keep calling her because she's my mother I'm Latin so we
come from a big Latin family but I was not connected to when I was a teenager because we didn't have all these nice
apps but I'm very connected to because they raised me so this is all of this has happened so
there's been eons of forgiveness and moving through
and letting go of views and anger and resentment
so it's a long process having insight into what is
but it's a magical thing really I was with this woman I was telling Gil about
this I made a joke I don't know if Gill liked it but I said Gil I think I'm in our heart
he did not laugh we take the term our heart which is an
awakened being in our tradition kind of seriously but then I said to him you know how they say Gil that that when you
are when you think you're really enlightened to go spend a weekend with your parents
so Gil I just did that I just spent three days in my mother's house
staying in her house which I didn't stay in for 20 years
I was in her house and um we had a great time
because now um I see what is arises in me I am
responsible for what arises in me the young Francisco that comes up around my
mother when she talks that way that's in me but it's my ability now to view this
to see that this is coming this old Francisco this young Francisco's are
coming up they're coming up and I can see them I can see them and I can kindly
see them and they settle it settles and this is
my internal work and then I let my mom be herself
she does things and and she's not my mom only she's also
just a person that was getting old now and I can have compassion for my mom in
a way that I never thought I could and we relate in a way that I never thought was ever going to happen in this
lifetime and that's a beautiful thing In This Very life to be healed with my
mother after a pretty checkered past and uh my
checkered past our difficult times are no different than anybody else's that's
another one of the great liberating insights um that
pain that I had with my mom the difficulty being semi-homeless as a teenager for four years
that's my story and it's you have your story you have and it's relative mine is
not worse than yours I came to this Insight again another view
via physical pain I had an accident and then a rare degenerative disease and
then a big reconstruction of my spine and then I was rendered disabled like didn't walk
for four years and with severe symptoms that I still manage but you can see that I hide them
pretty well or I manage them pretty well and then I realized one day I thought
this is so terrible I I was a young person when it happened and I was homebound I lost I couldn't work
and um so for a long time I pitied myself
and it was a big change when I realized oh
I remember now when a cold was a big deal so I realized pain is relative
so everybody else's pain is that is like their pain and it's serious to their
relative experience it's Unique to them mine is not worse than anybody else's
that Insight was very helpful because then I just was a lot more
relaxed and accepting and at ease with a very difficult reality that's taken a lot of
care and attention and medical care to handle
but views are very liberating that the right to view the purified view
can be very very liberating so
now I don't want you to manufacture anything I talked about emotions a lot so that
you could see that that that you already those of you who know mindfulness of emotions already
know what I'm talking about hopefully and if not maybe our previous if you're
new to the practice you can see through you can ex you maybe had an experience in our meditation of being with
something and letting it move caring for it being kind toward being present being
at ease with it giving it space and attention
letting it Move Along everything is kind of in this flux
so if anything I could invite you to maybe consider your relationship to the
present moment to how things are how things come and go
and um and enter the present moment
with into as much fullness as is available that's what can come by
paying attention to your relationship to how to do one thing at a time
what is your relationship to just doing one thing at a time
what unveils itself
there's much that can be unveiled
so happy Mother's Day to all the mothers happy Mother's Day to everyone's mother
and may you go in peace I have a great day maybe enjoy a good
lunch mindfully taking your time with the food
even there automatic patterns can be seen and not
be automatic maybe just going a little bit slower with somebody you can be with them there
even more than usual lunchtime is going to come up
and I was told that gill has been giving questions to at the end of talks to see
if people wanted to have like a little in-person breakout group
uh outside and uh so what I what did I say
okay
so that's not where it is oh yeah that's where it is
so what does it mean to do one thing at a time to you
or what could it mean to do one thing at a time to you
so I think that if you choose to go out in outside in the courtyard and
mingle a little bit and if you want to have a Dharma discussion what does it
mean to just settle on one thing at a time to you
thank you so much for your attention