great so hello and welcome everyone welcome to happy hour lovely to be with
you lovely to see you so first I would like to make an announcement
and um the the uh Happy announcement is that
um happy hour is going to be continuing to be offered five days a week uh and uh
yay and with um with uh Diana stepping uh out
stepping away as the uh co-leader for Tuesdays and Thursdays uh Liz Powell
um has accepted our invitation to step in
um as a co-leader and take over the Tuesday and Thursday yay and
um those of you who are on the happy hour Google Groups I've already received
a note earlier today thank you for sending that out Neil uh in some bio
background about Liz and and and you've probably already met her at uh happy
hour she's been a regular sub at happy hour she's lovely deep practitioner
deeply dedicated to service at IMC and IRC and just so absolutely delighted
that she will be stepping in to support the Sangha and she's excited to to be
supporting um all to cultivate these beautiful qualities of the heart so
please give her a warm welcome when she comes in in the chat as well as in the
Google Groups uh and warm meta-filled welcome we're just absolutely delighted
yay that she'll be supporting happy hour so so with that important announcement
out of the way I'm going to invite us to start meditating together and the theme
will be will be introduced during the meditation so let's begin together let's
sit together so arriving ah arriving
picking our seat taking our seat on this Earth
picking our seed in this moment however it shows up
it's not a mistake it's not a problem [Music]
this is what is presenting itself this opportunity for being alive for
learning for growing or cultivating for serving so opening
our heart to whatever is present right now and relaxing around it
relaxing your heart our body
calming soothing settling the heart foreign
just this breath Justice in breath just this out breath
foreign
Arts preoccupations not David thank you please come back
later not now I'm giving my heart to itself with the breath in the body
might be helpful to feel a particular part of the body maybe the hands or your
feet or your abdomen to help get settled
foreign
and the breath simplicity
of just sitting and being breathed
release release smilingly
thank you not now
I am doing my best I am doing my best
take heart foreign
foreign
foreign foreign
foreign foreign foreign foreign
foreign
foreign foreign
to imagine you are at this gathering this party
is convivial Gathering of beings the many beings
men many beings those who
are born have passed away those who are alive and those who
haven't been born yet you're in this gathering this
communion this party of beings past present and future
perhaps you're dancing [Music] with those who passed away
you may know them you may not know them other people other beings in this world
who are alive you may know them you may not know them and those who are not born yet
people to come
this amazing fabulous party
talk with some people [Music] you sit down with some people maybe you
you chat maybe you talk about something tender
maybe you cry together and then laugh together your lives are intertwining you realize
your life is intertwined with all these beings at this party in more ways
you realize that you this being who is you this
moment in time this one being in one dimension
foreign this moment now
but intertwined interconnected
in ways you cannot even imagine
doing your part doing your dance the dance that only you can do only you
your Eunice you are needed at this party foreign
than you are Come As You Are show up as you are
wearing wearing only your goodness your Goodwill
your appreciation for yourself and for everyone else at this party
perhaps as you meet with those from your past from the past
some appreciation for them gratitude
it was in the presence in the present time alive in this world
Midtown Goodwill may you be safe
dear beings may you be happy
may you be healthy may you have ease just as I wish it for
myself I wish the same for you may all of us and well-being
and those who are not born yet wishing them all the goodness in the world
they'll have their own challenges surely just as you have yours in this generation and those in the past
celebrating and we are all intertwined we are in
this together sharing meta for yourself or others past
present future any way that works for you
leaning into any aspect of this image that works best for you and
definitely seeing yourself as the heart of the party and you are part of this of
course you are you're a human being you're not separate
as much as sometimes you might seem or feel you're not separate
that's a delusion may all beings be well
may my love be of service with each breath stay embodied
share your meta
with each breath foreign foreign foreign
foreign
foreign foreign
life the thread of our life
in this fabric of humanity intertwined with all the other threats
this important thread every single one important unique
doing our part intertwined
dreaded may all beings smell threads
be well be free including myself
aching your place making your seat
foreign
bring this sit to a close acknowledging
her place
and all of humanity I am alive I am here
and sharing our goodness the cultivation of our practice
however it was and miss it without judgment offering
our goodness to all beings everywhere serve everyone
my own Awakening and everybody else's may all things be well may all things be
free including myself
thank you all thank you for your practice and exploring this
this image is practiced with me using
different perceptions perspectives can be quite opening in the way of you know
for especially caught in our little problems or big problems that just
opening it up oh yeah wow I am part of humanity past present future
contributing how can I show up as best as possible opening opening our
perspective our perception foreign
as we engage in small groups together the question I'd like to
invite us to to practice together with really break out groups or breakthrough
groups this is a break out roomed or break through rooms is
where we can have these conversations or whole space or just hold space and some of the people you're
in the party with in this imaginary party with guess what some of those people are present in different parts of
the world and are going to join you in these uh breakout rooms so you're going
to dance with them you're going to appreciate their uniqueness and you're going to bring your own uniqueness and
wish them well they wish you well so showing up and and the prompt is um if
you like to share something about this meditation practice if there was an aha moment a challenge and there's no right or
wrong maybe just fell asleep and that's perfectly fine um show up as you are show up as you are
with your full Humanity with your beautiful full Humanity with your um your Melody
you care for yourselves take care of each other let's Go reverse alphabetical order
and um what else um
um yeah make sure you just say you know maybe a minute of sheriff or uh few
sentences and and leave space for others leave space for others to to uh to share
without asking questions without directing the group really just show up with what you want to share and then
step back let somebody else share and you can also hold Silence with meta just
a great opportunity to practice together okay I've created the breakout rooms and
um I'm going to open them up and take care of yourselves take care of each other here we go
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back welcome back everyone we've got uh
minutes for maybe just one or two Reflections you can type them in chat or
raise your Zoom hat especially if you haven't spoken recently I'd love to hear from folks who may not have spoken just
balancing the voices a bit so what what did you notice what came up either during the meditation or in the
small groups
Aurora please I'm daring myself to speak today
um I read this roomy poem this morning that
this just came up and reminded me of
um this exercise somehow so this is just a little bit of
it on every trip have only one objection object objective to meet those who are
friends inside presence if you stay home keep the same purpose to meet the innermost presence as it lives in people
I don't know I just felt like like in my group I
hope my group members goodness it felt really sweet
um that feels really sweet thanks for sharing yeah yeah beautiful
your experience is the sweetness inspired by the roomy poem translation and the uh
and meditation the pain thank you Abraham
be our last reflection oh sorry I don't know oh you didn't
intend to read it seven o'clock uh actually no that's fine I'm actually experimenting with with 15 minutes but
it's it's all good but please go ahead Abraham what's up I really liked your um
your direction to see our uniqueness in
a vast field of beings whether we knew them or didn't um as you know and a lot of people share
might not but you know as I've been losing my hearing and I used to be quite a musician and an
actor and very extroverted and involved with people and I've been uh struggling
with um you know I should just retire to a room
and um I just I like what my friends are saying to me about the joy that I bring
and how the friendship I have and how friendly I am and it warms my heart and
frankly I would rather be a super friendly human being than a really great musician so um
I just really like that emphasis on seeing ourselves and taking in something
and having that offer to others so um I liked it thanks
ah thank you Abraham thank you so much for sharing that
I couldn't have said in any more beautifully than you just did and to paraphrase you I'd rather I think you
said something like I rather um gosh how did you say busy I'd rather have meta I'd rather be known for my
goodness and kindness and Good Will than be a great musician and just be known for that and beautiful
and I feel moved thank you so much for sharing that and also it reminds I see
people are giving thumbs up and hearts it's quite lovely um and and it reminds me of um I think a
quote by um who was it who said this uh I'll solve the quote and I'm sure one of you will
remember who said it [Music] um African-American woman poet uh but
people won't remember what you say but how you make them feel so that's that's what's remembered and
it's the author of the even the case Bird Sings oh my God I
have these associations but I can't remember her name uh drawing a blank anybody anybody in chat
um Maya Angelou my Angela I actually went to see her um and uh yeah many many years ago when
she came to Berkeley it was it was quite powerful so yes people remember how you make them
feel and how we remember how we make others feel and vice versa beautiful so
celebrating meant to thank you all thank you for engaging with this practice and
showing up to the party of humanity with with your meta with your good will
nothing else needed just wear that cloak that's all that's needed so thank you
all thank you for your practice for your cultivation for your showing up may all beings be well may all beings be free
including selves
thanks everyone be well