hello everyone and welcome so we're here to
meditate for 30 minutes one of the associations many people have
with Buddhist practice is that it's important not to become
attached that we're supposed to somehow let go of our attachments
and this of course has some truth to it but it leads people to sometimes
um let go of things that don't need to be letting go let go of
the things don't have to be let go of it's our attachment to them that we let go of
the clinging to them but also sometimes people confuse
holding on to the things which are healthy and appropriate to hold to have to stay keep close
with attachment with clinging and there is a healthy way of holding
things closely to prioritize certain things to emphasize
certain things to hold on to certain things in a non-clinging way
and one in this family of things that are sometimes not seen as appropriate
is uh safeguarding there are some things that are worth safeguarding protecting maintaining
and maybe even developing and so wholesome qualities
wholesome sense of being alive and think ways of being that feel peaceful and
calm or wise or peaceful joyful happy
connect even and so in meditation sometimes there's a deepening sense of intimacy or calm or peace or inner
well-being of some sort or other some people feel that they have a connection to a spiritual dimension of
Life a Dharma dimension and all these might be very wholesome to
have and part of the path to practice something that supports the ongoing movement
through Buddhist practice and these should be safeguarded
protected to some degree not with attachment not with holding tight or not
with the kind of disappointment and grief if we lose them but we also don't
have to be casual about it we don't have to kind of they come and go as they wish
when we feel something positive useful significant through say meditation
practice through mindfulness practice there's an art
to keeping that close to appreciate that this has priority in
our life and not to give it up easily by doing something
that overrides it or pushes it to the side some of the things that we do in daily
life maybe are not as important as the kind of spiritual connection we feel in
meditation uh or when we're present and calm for our life
and so to safeguard that to not give it up easily is part of the art of this practice
so meditation can also be this way that as we settle
into meditation but you want to safeguard protect the
the mindfulness that's developing the sense of calm or subtleness that's coming and so in meditation we mostly
watch our mind and are very careful not to become
interested in thoughts and stories ideas and feelings which maybe does maybe has less
value for us than staying close to the ongoing practice of meditation being in
the present mindfully with the breathing so we're allowed to safeguard we're
allowed to prioritize we're allowed to um
stay close to something and not give in to whatever whim that comes up in the
mind so assuming a meditation posture
and maybe rocking a little bit back and forth
or forward and backwards in order to help you find a midpoint if you're
sitting upright where you feel balanced and aligned in your body
if you're lying down then maybe there's a way of adjusting your back or your shoulders
your shoulder blades that makes it a little bit more comfortable or alert for you to be
on your back and
lowering your gaze and if it's comfortable for you
to close your eyes
and then as if you're gently
stroking a cat or stroking someone's hair or
gently
cleaning a surface with a soft cloth gently
allow yourself to take a few deeper breaths
maybe there's a smooth movement of breathing as you breathe in a little bit
more deeply than usual full more fully than usual
breathing in more deeply and then a little longer exhale
a gentle m kind of flow of releasing letting go and
settling
and letting your breath return to normal
and continuing to relax remember every exhale
soften some part of your body
as you exhale softening the thinking mind
maybe a quieting of thinking
and somewhere within you maybe somewhere deep in within
below where you're thinking below maybe even some of the difficult maybe emotions if there are
might there be a place of calm or quiet
or a place of some kind of sweet intimacy or
gentleness Within or some way of feeling sensing yourself
here alive and breathing
that feels good to you that's worth safeguarding
and to have that support your mindfulness
and your present moment mindfulness supporting staying close
maybe to a wordless place within
that has a wholesome quality or a welcome feeling of being alive and
breathing
perhaps safeguarding or protecting your attention
to this place so it supports
your ongoing practice of mindfulness
foreign
safeguarding your practice is to not allow your mind to drift away
in thoughts concerns which are second best
at the at the best to being here close in
safeguarding a way of being that
feels more connected or intimate
foreign
and as we come to the end of this meditation
is there some way that you're settled or calm or quieter
some way that your inner life has shifted or changed
that feels satisfying or feels right feels good to be this way
maybe the mind is quieter and
more grounded here in the present
and consider as you come to the end of the sitting what are the ways that you can
easily appropriately Safeguard how you're feeling
keep it close in close by so it's not completely lost as you
go on to the next thing that your life will be about
and as we finish this sitting May whatever benefit we've received
through this visiting any way that we feel more settled and more connected or
content anything any benefit we've received
may we also consider how we can share that with the world or how we can
based on that that we might
offer a more kindness friendliness generosity to the people we encounter
that we somehow walk through the world
benefiting the world with how we are friendliness our kindness
our respect for others may all beings
be happy may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe
and may all beings be free
and may we somehow contribute to that possibility
thank you
foreign welcome to the second talk
on a 10-part series on the the poly word
is translated into English as the protectors that which we can rely on or
call upon for a certain kind of protection safeguarding
support and these things support and Safeguard
our inner life and our outer life and um it's a way of living in the world
protected from harm inner harm that we cause ourselves and outer harm
and um so it's an interesting list that the Buddha came up with for this purpose
yesterday it was a virtuous conduct that if we live with a life that doesn't
harm others or harm ourselves there is a kind of protection we're protecting something that is protect worthy in
ourselves the sense of Compassion Care respect we have for ourselves and others
and also we tend to lessen
the anger hostility and even violence that others will
harm that others will do to us and um
so the today the second from the list is to be
well learned and the ancient language the literal meaning is to be to have heard a lot
and and why it says that isn't it why it's worded that way is in in the old uh
in the time of the Buddha there were no books there were no people weren't reading and um and so the only way for
learning something what information was to hear it so to have heard a lot means to be well learned
and um and so for people who are doing Buddhist practice this I think this implies that
learning learning about Buddhism learning about the Dharma and this can be you know
have benefits and be distractions to do this too much learning too much studying
of Buddhism and it's a distraction it becomes sometimes an abstract exercise and philosophy and
Doctrine but there are many ways in which learning about the Dharma uh
teaches us where to be oriented the values we want to have the practices we
want to do the ways of being in the world that protect us from ourselves and
protect us from mitigating the possibility of harm from
the world around us so for example it's one thing to learn mindfulness it's another thing to learn
how mindfulness is integral to the Eightfold Path to write view write intention write
speech right action write livelihood right effort write mindfulness and then
right concentration that these learning these and learning how to practice these or bring them
forth into our life helps develop the mindfulness more strongly it gives a kind of feat to the
mindfulness it also um uh
shows us more of what we bring into bring ourselves into the Dharma more
completely so that the mindfulness can be more effective it can be more
effective in recognizing what's going on inside of us outside of ourselves and so we're living a life a life a
lifestyle that is more beneficial so studying the Dharma learned the hateful path provides that kind of support
some people come to Buddhism with erroneous ideas
some of them which are can be harmful for them I've known people who've come to
Buddhism from a religion the religion they grew up with where the
understanding was that if you're part of a religion you had to believe everything the religion said and there was no
questioning it so they come to Buddhism and they think well now I have to believe all of this
and some of the summer Buddhism is hard to believe for many people and so then they're struggling and and maybe I can't
be a Buddhist but if you study Buddhism you realize quickly that uh there's no need to
believe all of Buddhism that Buddhism has a pragmatic practical side that is
the emphasis which is you we study Buddhism in order to help us on the path
to Liberation to freedom freedom from attachments and we can a little bit pick and choose within Buddhism what we want
to study what helps us and supports us so I've asked vast supply of teachings
and practices in Buddhism and then we are responsible for our own practice and
how to navigate the different choices of practice and finding what is most useful for us finding what teachings are most
useful for us so for example learning well might be to learn not only mindfulness practice but learn loving
kindness practice or compassion practice or Equanimity practice and and then knowing when those are
useful to practice and when they're useful to support us um it also helpful to know learn that we
don't have to believe all of Buddhism some people come to Buddhism and believe that the precepts are these hard and
fast rules that you if you commit yourself to the precepts that if you break them you're kind of doomed it's
kind of like you create so much bad karma or sin almost if you again people coming with other religious ideas and
and using them to understand Buddhism and in in Buddhism the precepts are
actually literally called trainings and so to learn their trainings rather than Commandments can make a huge
difference to how people approach Buddhism Buddhist precepts
so um part of learning is to learn the
importance of the motivation for which we're practicing and so then learning motivation is very
important then we do the inner work of ourselves what is my motivation is my
motivation useful and um and what motivations does Buddhism encourage us to have and why
does it want the motivations for example to Liberation Liberation from suffering
there are some people who feel like the end of suffering is not really spiritual
even it's the end of suffering is nice it's therapeutic but it doesn't connect us to what they think is a spiritual
world of deities or Cosmic ultimate meanings and
different things and number why does Buddhism early Buddhism put such a big emphasis on the
end of suffering as being really the ultimate goal of the practice
and so that might you really know that can give can help kind of refine how a
person's involved in Buddhism or maybe decide that Buddhism is not for them they have other purposes they want and
there's other completely worthwhile religious practices orientations that the person could have but by learning
learning the teachings of Buddhism studying them then a person can know oh this is actually not for me and I think
I would rather have some other approach to how to live my life so um to study Buddhist to study to
study well and also in daily life to not take things on
on faith to not read something or learn something and have opinions about it
without having studied it I know in my life I've had opinions about things that I actually didn't know
so much about and then I felt quite um kind of uh
you know kind of you know quite
concerned about myself that I would do this and so one of the purposes of
reading and studying is so that we don't rely on unfounded opinion even if
opinions seem logical or seem like a lot of people believe them there are all kinds of opinions opinions
that travel around our society around politics and and economics and racism and all kinds
of things some of these opinions and ideas don't even present themselves as opinions and
ideas they're presented as the truth and if some person of authority says them then they must be true
but to go behind underneath and see where does the ideas come from and what history do they have
and it doesn't mean you have to do an extensive study of something but even if
even a small study of a kind of a summary of some of the background for
some of the opinions people have can be eye-opening and it can be a safeguarding the truth
safeguarding ourselves from holding on to opinions tightly Without Really
knowing or if we keep the opinion then we're better informed and so then we're
safeguarding the truth the thing when we say I have this on
um you know I believe this because I read it in this book or heard this teacher say it I believe it because I've
reasoned it out my reasoning leads me to believe this you know so the the Buddha emphasized
some something called safeguarding the truth being really clear about the basis upon which you have an opinion or a
belief that's the same it's true for Buddhism itself on what basis do you believe uh your your beliefs
this is something you know from experience is something you know from a book um and so to say that as opposed to saying
Buddhism says or the Buddha said you can say the Buddha said in a particular
and uh and it kind of creates a little context for what you're what you're doing
so uh uh I like to think that this uh teaching
on um learning a lot learning well uh is away from not a way of becoming
complicated and filling our head with ideas but it's guided with the idea that if
you study well it actually allows the the mind to become simpler quieter not
simplistic but uh wisely simple wisely uh
uh appreciating the depth and the great value
of showing up with the Simplicity of being with mindfulness and Care in situations
of all the situations in our life and so safeguarding
our inner Simplicity of being or any inner sense
of being at home with ourselves at peace with ourselves and something study to learn a little
bit about oh the beliefs we have that take us away from that and understanding a little bit how it's
appropriate to find a Simplicity of being to rest in and to be with
that there's so much goodness that flows from that and then the Simplicity of
being that protects some of the most beautiful qualities of Who We Are and so they can be shared with the world
so um I do recommend that people who want to
do a regular Buddhist practice spend a little bit of time sometimes studying Buddhism
getting the basic ideas and one of the consequences of that is that even if we
don't understand all the teachings now as the practice continues as we our practice matures we'll be able to
identify and recognize what's happening to us because we have the language the context the concepts to oh this is good
this is what's happening so one example was that um
um you know uh I had learned a little bit about meta kindness loving kindness just the ideas
of it and at some point in my meditation practice on Retreat this unusual feeling
arose up in me and at first I didn't know what it was and then but because I had learned about loving kindness which
I had no idea about before I started Buddhism I said oh this is what it is
and having that simple recognition made it come alive and really let it grow for
me so part of the purpose of being well studied in Buddhism
well enough is to learn the basic ideas so that when it's appropriate we can
recognize them and see how they grow in US so for and again when one example would
be to learn what the seven factors of Awakening are and then it's as you practice at some
point each of these seven factors of Awakening might appear for you and you can wreck oh this is what it is that
this is useful this is something to safeguard so um
so these of these 10 protectors the second one now is being a
well-studied well learned and um and then I'll continue with this series
tomorrow thank you