hello everyone hello hi if you can hear me okay give me thumbs up yes fantastic
great hi I'm Nikki in Mountain View California on seated oloney land
and welcome to happy hour so who would like to say hi
um you're welcome to unmute yourself or put your hello in chat as a way for us to warm up with friendliness and and
warmth
a loss is Bill from Dallas
yeah from New Hampshire hi Neil good evening to you
I'm Mima from Yucca Valley the high desert I love Yucca Valley I've enjoyed
my visits there beautiful hi Padma from Belmont hi Jerry from Toronto we're
International Aloha from Oahu hi Amy
um Leslie hi from San Jose hi Eric and Craig from Florida welcome and hi Sarah
from Toronto our Canadian contingent and Desiree from Michigan sweet
hi Fred in Oakland hi Fred good to see you
and Carrie says hi from Chile Philly on on YouTube
sweet any other hellos
expression of hi Aloha meta
okay we're going to get started then time to get started so thank you Neil
for posting information on Zoom about rpr Google Groups we have a low traffic
mailing list and also there is information about how to offer yourself and other folks safety and and
care when we transition to small groups after the meditation so at this time I
change the settings so I'm muting won't be possible so the space stays quiet
and I also changed to chat settings but I ask you to keep it quiet even though
you can still send me chat but it can be distracting to receive chats in the middle of
Chang so let's keep that quiet and last but not least I turn on
recording for the sake of Audio Dharma
hey here we go all right hi everyone
welcome to happy hour so
this week for those of you who also attend the 7 A.M uh
teachings or that Gail usually does uh this week I'm substituting for Gail
and I'm covering um a teaching on
um what's called the five Aggregates anyway the five heaps the five candas
now What's um what I wanted to discuss tonight is
actually related to something I I cut I shared this morning 7 A.M
Pacific time and um and it's um
it's about our perception so today this morning I talked about perception or
recognition this this uh amazing
um capacity this constituent of our
experience which is recognizing which is perceiving
um what arises and and what arises in our
field of experience to recognize that to say this is that basically we're we're
being pattern recognition machines in many way given given our background our
history our mind States it's dependently Arisen based on so many factors this
recognition this recognizing this is that this is that that that's what the
Sanya or this this recognition recognition in Buddhism it points to a
different a little more simple much simpler than the concept of recognition
or perception in psychology so how does it relate to happy hour huh
the way I like to invite us to practice with this today is
recognizing that our recognition is
very shiftable changeable it's not fixed it's
not inherent in a particular person or object or situation
um it's malleable our recognition or classification of something as friendly
or unfriendly or good or bad it's it's very very malleable
that it's I mean that's the one of the primary teachings of the Buddha which
really relates to um this concept of emptiness which thing we
when we hear that we think of nullness but it's really it's this codependently
Arisen it's dependent um that that our recognition is dependent on so many different things
including our state of mind including how we've primed ourselves
things are not fixed they are malleable they're changeable
there's not a truth or reality with capital r out there it's all
phenomenologically determined and so is our level of Freedom our level of Happiness we've talked about happiness
is a choice you make and in many ways our perception our recognition
is is primed is primed through our experiences primed through
how we um we cultivate our mind and hearts
if we turn towards friendliness if we turn towards a perception of safety
goodness kindness happiness that's that's the perception that arises that's
the state that arises it's this is really really powerful we perceive
things people thoughts objects our own behavior
um in a more friendly way and there's more freedom then we don't perhaps judge
things in in such a judgmental way there's more freedom
from clinging from becoming identified
[Music] um and fixed in a particular View anyway that's all
a long a long short dormant so I'm gonna leave
that as the uh priming or or our guided meditation then you don't
have to have heard my talk this morning at all everything you need to know is
share it with you right now both in the dharment as well as the guided meditation some you can let all of that
go all of the thoughts and Concepts go
let's turn let's turn to practicing together let's arrive together
let's turn
let's turn our awareness to this body In This Moment In Time
regardless of whatever has been happening just before this moment
maybe you were busy full agitated it's all okay not a problem
and we bring can we intentionally bring a perception
of spaciousness can we intentionally recognize
that there's a lot of spaciousness around
there's a lot of air around us space around us
letting ourselves recognize to assess your space outside our bodies
Our Hearts can relax I know this there is space inside
and more space with each in-breath and hot breath as we settle
I think the body the mind the heart relax can be put down if there
are preoccupations instead of being stuck in a loop
turn to perception of openness and ease it's also here
that is here as well with each breath
you can always pick up the entanglement later
we can choose to perceive
spaciousness ease and sense of refuge and heart and mind in this moment it is
available
and we expand this perception of spaciousness
to include
the perception of a recognition of
relative safety you're probably indoors
protected safe enough from the elements
and of course there are always there's not absolute safety in this world and yet we can tune
instead of tuning into perception of lack of safety we can choose to perceive
to recognize that there is safety
it's an inclination pattern of the mind we can
turn towards that recognizing the comfort
able enough perhaps where you are sitting meditating
opening turning this knowing this perception to
including the Goodwill that
is available for you many people in this world
have wished you well wish you well now
are friendly towards you care about you
could just be a few people you don't need a crowd but
turning towards this perception perception of friendliness
be a child a pet
this recognition of goodness
let yourself smile and enjoy it it's recognition of good wealth
you have choice but you choose to lean into to recognize
let yourself Savor recognition good well kindness generosity
around you
for you or others wherever the heart feels uplifted
in its recognition in its perception of goodness
may have received support
kind words a smile
so many ways of receiving goodness
letting your heart be uplifted by recognizing goodness
around you and your own goodness to recognize it to receive it
to let yourself receive it
it is to an act of generosity to let us receive generosity
an act of Good Will to let ourselves receive Goodwill friendliness care
now if you like letting yourself recognize turn towards perceive
the goodness in in you not shying away from it
turning towards a perception of goodness kindness generosity care
and let it nourish your heart uplift uplift you
and now if you like you can stay with these two recognitions receiving and
and giving of goodness meta Goodwill
generosity of spirit or if you if you like you can know
turn to the perception perceiving recognizing
the conditions for happiness are being happy that are available in
your life our minds usually turn to what's not
here what's challenging what's difficult perceive recognize
the conditions the supportive conditions or the mind to
be at peace uplifted with gladness
with contentment
maybe a roof over your head Maybe friends family
living in a situation that's safe enough
no world wars right now
stable period
no lockdowns the world is relatively normal
so appreciating
who to eat you're supported in so many ways
and now recognizing that your support for
enough Health that you can show up
and listen comprehend follow understand
this practice
recognizing the conditions to support happiness contentment of the body
even if there might be illness old age present but well enough well enough can
you recognize that
recognizing the wholesomeness of the conditions and you have a precious human birth
so much opportunity to wake up go through the support as well as the
challenges of your life Christ for the middle of Awakening
of growing in compassion
recognizing goodness of even challenges
the way they stretch you you get stretched opened up
softened tenderized
and as we turn to close this meditation together can we recognize perceive goodness
in ourselves in our community in our circumstances having been able to show up
come together in practice
you're listening to this leader on Audio Dharma the goodness of being able to do this
listen to this and join many others maybe not in time
but in in spirit
may all beings everywhere benefit
from the goodness this co-created goodness may they benefit me they
recognize goodness
may I recognize the goodness in my life
may practice be of service to all beings everywhere including myself
thank you
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so recognition recognizing perceiving can take so many different
perceptions on it you can choose and put on a grumpy perception through
the lens of grumpiness you can put on a a perception choose a perception of
gratitude appreciation kindness so I'd like to invite us to engage
in small groups with this perception with choosing perceptions
recognition what we choose to recognize how we choose to recognize and
let us engage again in small groups we're exploring for our own benefit the
two other people are just holding Witness [Music] um they're perceiving goodness you're only
speaking exploring for your own benefit you're not speaking for their benefit and if you're listening and you didn't
even understand what they said it's okay don't ask questions you're just holding witness let them explore it's we're
serving each other in this way in this beautiful way so give it a try but just really give it
a try as one of you reported on Monday I just really appreciated that sense of
safety okay let me explore for my own sake how was this practice what did you
recognize from turning to recognizing choosing to
perceive goodness what shifted what happened please offer one short nugget let
another person offer a short nugget really or rather explore a short nugget
the next person explores the short nugget but it comes back to you and you go round and round a few times it's not
a long monologue after you hear others you get inspired to explore some more
and let's go in alphabetical order according to first name closest to the
beginning of the alphabet so so take care of yourselves take care of each
other be kind and lean into the perception perception of of goodness how
can we lean into that okay I'm gonna open up the ropes and see what you
discover let yourself be surprised here we go
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back welcome back everyone
and uh chat is open if you like to share any questions or Reflections about what you
discovered either in the meditation or when you were exploring with in small
groups also if you haven't spoken in the large group for a while I invite you to
pull forward raise your hand bring your voice in and if you have recently spoken uh please pull back let others share
reflections
bill
um but I was struck by In This meditation is something that I've noticed to me before which is that the
negative stuff negative perceptions has such a strong pull
you know and there's a a very Twisted sort of enjoyment of thinking of all
these things that are wrong and it's it's not healthy but it's it's just it's
the poll is so strong I don't know if I have a question here this is just making
an observation thank you thank you Bill this is a terrific observation this is
this is called an Insight what you just shared it's an Insight that comes from
practice when you really pay attention and you see wow there is such a strong
pull there's this habit pattern of the mind going there and then oh my there's
also enjoyment even though it's not healthy and really it doesn't feel good but the mind seems to be enjoying being
in this uh grumpy negative state of perception this is so profound to know
this to see this clearly as you have been because many people go through their entire lives and never really see
this clearly and seeing it clearly is the first step for this pool to become
weakened because when you see the pool then it starts to lose its its um its
hold its energy its power it happens little by little so this is just
terrific I'm so glad you've uh observed this for your own sake and also shared
it with the community chair says I like the idea of saying a challenge as something to bend into
and to see it as a gift to have this challenge yeah they are
they stretch us they mold us yeah and it's a gift to be alive to have
challenges to grow through Vicky on YouTube says I'll share that I feel more ease after doing this practice
much less grumpy oh that's great it's sweet
yeah they're Reflections before we bring our time together to a close
anything else you noticed Fred I saw your hand show up and
disappear please raise your hand if that was
intentional
yes sorry my fumbling fingers oh good um
so I'm aware doing this meditation and often others like it when we come back
to reflect upon our own goodness um that there's just not as as much
juice in it when I consider myself and I can think of you know friend or
family member and you know if I wanted I could establish some sort of critical
distance from them and say well of course they they they reap all these benefits from from their theirs uh
unselfishness their generosity um that the sort of you know the wives selfishness is at play with them but I
don't do that with them I I just admire their their presence and their action but I I just find it harder with myself
not entirely you know I mean I'm I'm realistic about it I see that
um you know I can I can do things that are um that are kind and generous but I
cannot step into the sort of full-throated experience of it like I
can for a beloved family member or friend thank you for notes for seeing this and
verbalizing it so clearly eloquently Fred this is common and and
um so I so appreciate you bringing into the the um the container of this
practice of our community today so a couple of Reflections one is since you
already said that for you it is easy to do it with people with other people to
care that you care about friends and family to just rejoice in their goodness too without being critical and and just
Rejoice let your heart be uplifted in their goodness so yay that's available fantastic so so it's like a you know in
math how we do kiwi-d we reduce the problem to already to an already solved problem so so this solution is already
available so what what then I suggest is to take to step away from
yourself to see yourself as your friends and loved ones and and relatives see you
so take that third person perspective because you can already do that your heart your mind already knows how to do
that and Through Time rejoicing in your own goodness from this third person in fact
put yourself in a group in fact this would be the step so so take take Fred's
perspective seeing your friend and then your friends family multiple ones and
then uh add yourself to them add yourself to their group so it's a group
that you're seeing the goodness of and if it starts to you know it's kind of like a skillful
um it's like skillful bringing group together so that that energy of rejoicing is going towards you I know
yeah towards you too Fred oh he's he's such a good person generous kind look at
at his goodness as well as this other person so so a heart can rejoice and
little by little turn towards yourself as an individual and then turn to
yourself as yourself but break it down to these
um multiple steps thanks that's really helpful thank you thanks Fred this is exciting
yay thanks so much for bringing this in I am rejoicing in in your goodness and
the goodness of your question Fred and your practice may you so take so I invite you to
rejoice in my rejoicing of of of your goodness and generosity and kindness
yeah yeah so dear ones Let's uh let's dedicate the
Merit of our practice together may we perceive goodness in the world may we
grow through our perception our recognition help goodness grow in the
world may all beings be well may all beings be happy including ourselves
thank you thanks everyone be well
gonna stop the recording and the lives