so hello everyone
so for those of you who didn't hear earlier
the week that when this finishes at around 7 45 we'll switch over to a zoom room
and those of you who can stay will have a community meeting just a gathering and
maybe talk a little bit about the Dharma or
our community and I can answer some questions maybe do a breakout group we
meet each other a little bit and um hopefully uh somewhat simple and
friendly time together that's a little different than being on YouTube I'll post the link later here in the
chat and also it's posted on the IMC homepage you'll find it two places there
one is under the bottom right where there's what's new and then on the calendar
IMC calendar for today
so excuse me
so in some conventional way
meditation involves an inward looking
being really present here for oneself and uh there are variations of
meditation that operates somewhat differently but it still involves a heightened development
of of the development of heightened development of personal qualities
nothing else of our capacity for awareness
and so there is a kind of focus on this apparatus we are as a human being that
or and I'd like to propose that in the
field for the for the practice of compassion that it's invaluable
for us to be deeply connected to ourselves in a positive way
that the rush to be compassionate without having first established a
healthy relatedness to this being that we are can lead to misdirected compassion and
lead to compassion which can even be harmful for oneself and our compassion for others so much
richer if we have established a healthy relatedness to ourselves
and so um we sit and meditate and so some of these things about appreciation we've talked
about this week can apply to oneself to so to appreciate oneself
to um understand oneself understand all the
aspects of Who We Are and not be limited by any understanding
so that the appreciation is not limited by self-criticism or
shame that we carry or regrets or resentments we carry
and then to to understand ourselves so depreciate ourselves understand
ourselves to respect ourselves to to view ourselves as a valuable human
being maybe not because what we have done or not done in our lives but because
inherently being a human being is a precious and valuable event
and to Value ourselves to treat ourselves worthy of Love of care of
respect and to respect ourselves to respect our potential
and then to have some deeper acceptance of ourselves and a kind of acceptance
that we're willing to accept and to be open to be present to allow for all of
who we are to exist here and to allow for it all with non-harming
we're not going to harm any of it we're going to see it and know it and in
this deeper appreciation for ourselves then be able to hold it all
and um and uh and do all those things then when
we're ready for compassion we are ready for something more and there's one more step in
appreciation which I'll talk about later but for now I'd like to kind of offer a
summary for all this when we sit to meditate and
that is to sit and meditate with gratitude gratitude is often closely connected to
appreciation and we appreciate and then we're grateful for what we appreciate
and to be sit and meditate in gratitude in a thanks Thanksgiving to ourselves to
this life to be born to our situation and of course it's hard sometimes to
feel gratitude for a situation for ourselves a situation we found ourselves in
but to sit down to meditate to have the ability the capacity to sit meditate to
lie down to meditate to be able to sit quietly
and have the ability to turn the attention inward is a
phenomenal gift it's a rare gift in this world that people actually take this kind of time
to connect to something deep inside it's uh we're entering into a world that
few were few people actually spend much time in the world of care the world of
of the Dharma the world of the non-harming the world of waking up and
being present wow this is phenomenal very few people have this take the time
have this opportunity for this so even if you feel like you things are difficult and challenging here for you
yes they probably are and what a gift to
sit down a few people have this thing that we're doing now for the next few minutes you
might know a lot of meditators so it doesn't seem like it's a rare gift boy is it rare
that you enter into this kind of inner world for liberated world that we're pointing to
in the Dharma so to take a meditation posture
that's a suitable for you
and gently close your eyes
and adjust your posture posture suitable for you
to do this sacred work of waking up to what's here even if
what's here is difficult
and to begin offering a kind of self-care begin offering yourself a willingness to
enter the sacred world of attention by gently tenderly taking a few deeper
breaths and relaxing on the exhale
taking a few long deep breaths
in really relaxing more on the end of the exhale letting go or releasing of all things
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and consider that the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
is is a thread Through Time
through all our experiences
which provide us a grounding and in being aware
being aware of the breathing
is a way to not be caught in the thoughts the mind
the feelings we have but to gently
stay grounded in continuous
to move through time with time
without stepping out of the flow of time into our thoughts and feelings
this gentle massage
that supports Us in being aware
his time the mind wanders away in thought each time you remember
to reconnect to the here to be aware each moment of mindfulness
each breath you breathe a time for gratitude
for appreciation
for a kind of inspiration
of gratitude
for this precious opportunity to be alive
to be breathing to be practicing
waking up waking up from suffering
to meditate in gratitude
regardless of the difficulties you have
can you establish your awareness practice
with gray with an element of gratitude
is there something about Here and Now that you can be grateful for
that supports encourages you invites you
to stay present for breathing your body
to your capacity to be aware and present
foreign
and then to end this sitting
with a question
what are you grateful for
that in recognizing and acknowledging your breathing becomes easier
a gratitude that allows something to relax
at gratitude about some fundamental way in which
you are alive
and then being grateful
perhaps finding an inspiration inside to share your good fortune
with others maybe and wishing them well
wishing them to share some of
what you're grateful for your benefits or your fortune
your good fortune to practice a path to the freedom of from suffering
May others also find a way to that freedom
may all beings be happy may all beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free and may each of us in our own way
contribute to that in the world May the goodness and Fortune of Our
Lives serve for the welfare and happiness of all
[Music]
thank you very much and um
so good morning everyone and
or hello wherever you are in the time zones and uh
so um at the end of this um
our teaching here I'm going to post a zoom link for our community meeting
those of you would like to stay and it's also found on the imc's homepage under
what's new and a calendar and it has a password and the password
is a theme of this week which is appreciate so um please remember to appreciate when you
when I enter the zoom room s
so we come to the end of the week focusing
on appreciation as a foundation for compassion and there's one a more element that I
associate with appreciation that is inevitable as invaluable
and I'll introduce it this way that um
without there being love first I worry that compassion is not really
compassion that love is a
yeah I is a necessary component of compassion
and I say that because of sometimes people feel an obligation to care for
others they feel alarmed they feel worried they feel upset about suffering
in the world suffering in others they feel fear and relationship to it
and they carry with them a strong sense of obligation like I'm supposed to I
need to or a strong sense that I have to address this and deal with this because I'm so
uncomfortable and they're addressing suffering they're trying to uh
bring that suffering to an end and so the actions can look like
compassionate actions but they're not informed by love they're
not informed by a deep appreciation valuing understanding of others
and these first four themes of this week I'd like to suggest are also in really
necessary for healthy love that there's an appreciation of others
there is an understanding of them there is a respect for them
and there is a certain kind of acceptance of them in in Love Without a healthy dosage of
each of these can easily become skewed it can easily become problematic
and there might be other important elements of love but uh those four I
think are really invaluable and um and leads us to a kind of a
healthy love a healthier almost like love is almost like appreciating the beauty of others it's appreciating and
valuing the wonderfulness of a connection of a of a feeling of warmth
the feeling of closeness a feeling of delight the feeling of
of real appreciation for the the wonderfulness of people
the sense of gratitude for them and grateful to be in their presence and
happy to be in their presence love is many different things and uh and for each person maybe what
love is is is different and love is different in different situations so I offer it to you as a as a reference
point for your investigation for your uh you're really grappling with compassion
considering it deeply and that is without love there can't be compassion
so that's the the last uh element of appreciation is love and we know that
love has a big range of what people mean by that and maybe I'd suggest that there's uh
not only a wide range but also a different degrees of strength than
different forms of love and but still some form of love needs to
be there for uh for compassion and so how do we love people
can we have love for others without some love for ourselves if we don't have something like love for
ourselves then um can we do we does our love arise from
a healthy place there's our love for others arrived from some place that
people Delight in our love and our appreciation of them if love comes from Fear if love comes
from a sense of loneliness or love comes from the desire for the other person to
provide something for me then love is maybe not really suitable
that love is not suitable for compassion which is a genuine respectful care for the suffering of others
I've known people for whom um uh the source the reason they loved
others what they called love the reason why there was a strong attraction strong orientation towards a
strong desire to be with him was uh was because the other person
provided love the other person loved them and valued them and delighted them
and it wasn't exactly the other person they loved what they loved was how the person treated them what they got from
the person made them feel good and happy felt needed or something
and maybe that's a form of love but is the love that is not coming from need
the love is it that's in a pure appreciation of the other person independent of what we receive and
return from them and so with compassion the care the
loving that come loving care for others suffering that brings that brings
appreciation of them and understanding of them and respect for them and an
acceptance of them um that uh all those take precedence in
where the source of Love is in us that yes we appreciate them there's a
gratitude there's Delight there's seeing the preciousness and the inherent value
of others the worth of others and that is what we Delight in that is what we
love and appreciate one of the teachings of Buddhism is that
as we develop a greater appreciation for our own Beauty in capacity for Dharma
beauty within that we have eyes to see the beauty in other people
and if if no matter who we see even our Nemesis that do we have the capacity to
see something in there that's beautiful in their hearts and their minds and can there be some kind of love for
that that's not naive love for that that we still protect ourselves so still find
some way to to care for ourselves and to not Overlook the fact that their
behavior is unacceptable but to see the beauty to love
so the the uh these four these five qualities of this week
um acceptance understanding respect acceptance and now
love is the acronym for oral the uh that means to to listen or having
to do with listening and uh I chose this acronym because
um uh can there be appreciation with how they they kind of uh receptivity of
really listening deeply to someone they're kind of listening that happens before we speak
the kind of receptivity and taking in people and their situation that that
happens prior to judgments and ideas and solutions and all this to really just
listen deeply so that we can appreciate them
Delight in them respect them in deep ways
so uh so love what form of Love Can you have
that is realistic that doesn't have such a high bar
that uh your gosh you need to gush over them or do you need to somehow forgive
them or you need to somehow um uh
like them even is there some kind of deep fundamental love that's possible
when there is some degree with you when you find something to appreciate in others
you find understanding of them in a deeper way that you find respect for them
you find acceptance of something there what is that for you
so I would like this last talk to be more of a challenge to you than offering
you finished complete ideas and the challenge is
what form of love is needed if you want to have compassion for the
world and what form of love is in that form of love is needed for
compassion what form does that take that's appropriate for you that's right
for you and and so rather than agreeing or
disagreeing with what I said what I'd challenge you to do is to find a find
how it's this can be true in your terms in your way
how is it true for you that something called love is the important precursor for
compassion and what is the nature of that love so that's the challenge and uh I'd like
to leave you with and maybe you'll have something to say about that in our community meeting
and so I'll post now the zoom link it'll take me a couple of minutes myself to
get into the room so some of you probably get in and just have to wait for me and so let's say so here is the
there's a link there it is oops
so did it come through
I don't know if it came through
why is not do the return
there we go no I said I don't know if it can't didn't come through did it
also uh not yet well I'm going to do it over in the other computer as well so as
I said it's on the IMC home page under what's new uh the first item there
and also um and maybe for some reason I'm not able
to send Chats on this computer that I have here so I'll do it over the other computer
and then I'll be there in a few minutes and um and um
and thank you for today very much