so greetings welcome good moment to you
all it's morning and uh on the west coast and as
uh as I was waking up this morning I saw out the window um the waning the waning
moon was rising and Venus was leading this bright this bright light in
front of the Moon and I couldn't help but think of the the closing metaphor from our our time together
yesterday the four Brahma viharas is like the Sun at different phases of the day and the
equinity is like the cool light of the
Moon that was touching touching to wake up to this morning I hope you're all
well uh so the theme of compassion we will continue and today we will get
into um what I I think is a useful topic compassion and not
self we can hold that in the background for some time while we settle
and meditate together in this
meditation uh what I will invite us to do is first
to um include some meta some loving kindness
or benevolence into our settling process so as as the body and the mind
are actually starting to settle including including the attitude
of benevolence in whatever way feels right for you and then after some time of settling
with meta in this way um we we will call to mind a
specific being to whom we would like to offer Compassion maybe not someone who's
having the greatest difficulty but someone someone who
um you this morning when you check in with yourself it feels right for you uh
to wish them well that may they be free from suffering and then the third piece of
the meditation this morning will let go of the image of another
person and simply let the the attitude the feeling the wish uh of compassion
radiate in all directions so just a bit of explanation before we
get started so let's find our way into the
meditation
posture
and right from the start as we're settling in with the body and the
breathing inviting this attitude of
Goodwill if it's helpful directing it to yourself maybe with a
reflection may I be
happy
and letting ourselves be nourished by any goodness that comes from that
wish
scuttling bringing the posture into
balance letting the breathing come into its own
balance and wishing
well may I be
happy
every breath like a wish for
well-being breathing
kindness
now a gentle shift and
focus calling to mind someone you would like to offer compassion
to an offering
that's within your capacities for this
morning to whom you would like to offer the
wish may you be free from
suffering may you be free from
harm practicing making that intention making that
wish offering it and then registering what
happens in this body and mind and then
again
may you be free from suffering and
harm
may we be free from suffering and
harm practicing this
wish staying mindful
throughout so that we can offer peacefully and clearly
knowing
may we be free from
suffering
and now letting
go of this specific person or
being sensing the attitude the felt sense the
intention the wish of
compassion rather than directing it to a specific
being opening ourselves to let compassion
radiate in all
directions
shining like the gentle light of
Sunset
shining the gentle light of
compassion on all beings in all
directions to the
front the right
behind to the left
above and be
love
and in the last minute of this
sitting breathing ease into the
body breathing relaxation into the heart and
mind letting this being here be nourished by
our
practice
may all beings everywhere no
ease and have the causes of true
happiness
[Music] so welcome
again thank you for practicing
together my my mind feels uh quite still and
wanting to appre wanting to stay in the meditation of compassion
but now is the time to reflect on the Dharma
together Suzuki roshi the founder of San Francisco Zen Center um is quoted as saying that when
the mind is compassionate it is boundless in poly the word is
[Music] aam uh boundless without
boundary understand is without
measure so the far enemy uh in the visim Maga the far enemy of compassion is
cruelty it's it's direct opposite compassion is the
wish that beings be free from suffering cruelty is the wish that another being
be harmed and uh chances are rather high
that if one were to look clearly into a heart and a mind when it's in a state of
Cruelty you might may find what we colloquially call um some
measure of othering some uh self-concern some dominance of the
concept of self and in contrast in a in a mind in a
state of compassion in one that wishes that no heart harm come to any
being there's this sense of openness and connection and
care and even
love so maybe a more subtle and perplexing topic is the meeting of
compassion and not self we practice compassion and harmony with not self this is a a question I
sometimes feel when uh when practitioners learn about the teaching of not self they start to think oh W can
I can I practice both of these at the same time can I be can I be nobody and
love all beings wait but if there if I'm loving all beings am I making beings it
gets it gets confusing quickly so to start to clarify this we'll we'll take a short Excursion into
some not self teachings and then I would like to share just two examples of what
for this morning I'm going to call empty love that's love that's empty of
self-concern compassion that's empty of concepts of self so let's move first into
this teaching on not self it's important to clarify because
there's this really common misconception about not self and I
appreciate again venerable analo here um he offered this this teaching that I'm
going to summarize for you uh that the the teaching on not
self very um very easily edges over into being
misunderstood as nothingness but there's uh nothing here
there's no one no one here nothing here and this is a misapprehension so instead he offers not
self to be understood this way that uh in this body body and mind no there's no
permanent entity that we can find if we look at our body if we look at our mind we look at our heart there's nothing
permanent we can put our finger on and there's no one in complete
control uh one small and sobering example is that uh however much I might
wish it to be otherwise this body of mine will age and soon enough it will
pass away there's no permanent here and nothing in complete control I can't stop
the aging from coming so is there no me the question he
poses um so while there's not a permanent entity not something that's in complete
control what continues is a process of causes and
conditions and this process isn't nothing um in the process there is a
continuity and actually this means that I have some responsibility so good example let's say
that a few minutes ago I said something harmful I said something that hurts someone the me of right now is
responsible for those words I can't simply say uh no self here wasn't me
there's no self here there is a continuity and I'm
responsible so venerable an alio Likens this continuing flow of causes and
conditions to a river flowing changing no Essence but a
continuity and our our meta and compassion practice are just like that too there's no Essence to them uh but we
feed this uh River of wholesome intention and wishing for the the
well-being of others to really drive this point home
about not self uh a second example he offers that
uh um we know we know in our uh contemporary understanding that in what
we perceive as matter solid matter is actually largely empty space so I just
knocked on my desk because of Zoom you can't hear that mostly empty space this
desk but it doesn't mean that I can walk through it it's still functional so feels
hard the second piece is that I I could in theory take this desk and chop it up
into teeny bits and turn it into dust and I would never find the the core the
essence the desk of this this desk
functional and just a matter of causes and conditions and this is precisely the
teaching of not self it's both both emptiness nothing
essential and there's a continuity of conditions emptiness and
conditionality this is the teaching of not self two sides of the same
coin so this understanding is um presented in the context of early
Buddhism and of course the dharm has been a long and complex conversation so
understandings have changed over time
so I I will say this morning that our compassion doesn't
require a um an attachment to a self our
compassion actually doesn't require selfing activity but interestingly and beautifully our compassion heals selves
our compassion uh nourishes selves and nourishes
beings so I think this this understanding um shines a very different
light on not self and compassion
um it seems very clear in looking at the teachings that the Buddha the Buddha's
the Buddha asks of us to work at the practice of seeing clearly but the
Buddha never asks us to be a
nothing so what might empty compassion look like compassion that's free freed
of self- attachment uh I love offering the
example of the Buddha himself in that the Buddha was confident he was strong
he was clear in speech the Buddha was meticulous in his actions and he worked diligently for the
benefit of all beings the Buddha was certainly not a nothing and didn't see himself as a
nothing even though he saw not self to its
depths and compassionate compassionate the Buddha was compassionate after his Awakening he
said to have taught or responded to teaching requests out of compassion and then he interestingly he gives two exam
two reasons why um he continued to go on Retreat
after his Awakening one was for a pleasant abiding here and now and the second was out of compassion for future
Generations I love this I'm inspired by this notion that we can conduct our lives in a way that's a a gift to Future
Generations even distant
ones so I I see in this I see in the the model of the Buddha someone who was
compassionate someone who was confident someone who was really effective and totally
free totally free of entanglement with self-reference uh he offered a sort of
care that wasn't overshadowed by I and me and mine and the light of his
compassion wasn't darkened by clinging and demand and
expectations rather his sort of empty
brilliant love sort of free compassion he offered radiant and even
joyful and what a blessing it is to be this way in the
world and then one more example of when I think of empty
compassion I think of Suzuki roshi there's a a story from a a short
collection uh collection of stories about Suzuki roshi called remembering the
dragon and its anecdote about Suzuki roshi by his students and I want to I
want to share one with you it makes reference to um a couple of things that should be explained first one is it
makes reference to a sort of something called a show sound which is a formal Q&A public ceremony usually at the end
of a retreat in a Zen context and the other other thing that
should be explained is um it talks about serving meals in the Zeno serving meals
in the meditation Hall and this is a reference to the monastic style of formal eating uh where
you Ser you you serve food and eat food in a way that um allows you to stay in
meditation continue in your meditation so you'll hear those two
references and this story uh comes from Ed Brown and you'll see in in this this
little anecdote uh or I see I see in it in Suzuki Roshi's way a sensitivity to
other beings and such skill and Care along with a Clarity of vision and
a a confident compassion it's the bringing together of just these two
things so here's Ed Brown when I was at tasahara in the
1960s I was having a lot of trouble with anger actually I was not having much
trouble with it other people at tasahara were having trouble with my anger I thought it was good to be
sincere and if you felt angry then be angry don't cover it or repress it then one time I was talking with
Suzuki roshi in his cabin he said well Ed you can get angry if you
want then after an impeccably timed pause he politely added but
don't I felt permission to be who I was while being instructed to reign in my
anger Suzuki R Ro she was for the most part quite polite once at tasahara a
student asks him why haven't you enlightened me yet Suzuki roshi answered politely I'm
making my best effort and Ed Brown continues I remember
that once during a showan a public formal Q&A ceremony a student asked what
do you feel when I serve you food in the zendo and Suzuki roshi answered I feel
like you're offering me your entire being your most perfect
love your entire being your most perfect
love so my hope is that we carry this question with us today how can I
practice compassion in a way that's free of the entanglements of self attachment
and may it be so and may this River of causes and conditions spread care and compassion
for all beings without exception and tomorrow we will turn to
some teachings about compassion and Awakening be well thank you so
much