okay welcome welcome folks good morning to uh to those for whom it's morning
um I'm gonna presume I am Audible
and uh guide a guy to say it anyways lovely to see
so many familiar names YouTube crew going strong
ah to Sangha okay
um let's uh let's sit together
and when someone says to you let's sit together start meditating
what do you start doing
what gets tight what loosens up
to where do you retreat in the headquarters of your own
perspective
and if I
told you to stay just where you are
but stop meditating
what would you stop doing
and what cannot be stopped
thank you
I told you to stop being aware you couldn't do it
as we begin whatever cannot be stopped
rest there
foreign
just open receptive
and we don't let the fact that we can direct our attention direct the attentional spotlight
to the breath or to whatever we don't let the fact that we direct the
attentional spotlight distract us completely
from the openness
of awareness
from a kind of awareness that
in no way depends
on what we call me okay
foreign maybe what I'm trying to say
as we begin with wise View
we launch our efforts from Wise View
it is a often useful to
draw some line that distinguishes the
object of attention
from everything else
however wide you draw that Circle may be useful to draw it
and often useful to draw the circle right around
the sensations of breathing
receiving the rhythm of your own breathing
this breath that some sense registers everything else
and so to attend to the breath is to honor the rest of your life
being nourished by uh cycles of your own breath
just because we draw the circle of attention around sensations of her
breath doesn't mean that everything outside
that Circle is
suspicious
all experience is equally innocent
be treated as such
and gently inclining towards
inside the circle of attentional space
letting your mind take its cues
from the cycles of the breath
foreign
okay there's two uh nice to sit with you
so um I forgot to introduce myself I'm Matthew
um uh yeah happy to um
that's not a good introduction on Matthew I teach meditation
um I'm happy to uh I was happy when Gil asked me to to uh spend time with you
all and um yeah we'll um I'll be here this week so
so I I thought to do a list of five uh
and um the five faculties five spiritual Powers
um uh faith and energy mindfulness samadhi
concentration wisdom and uh when
if you look at that list that's a powerful powerful combination of forces powerful
combination of forces so so faith
um the path really begins not so much with faith but with a
doubt and the doubt is
um this isn't gonna work out
that launches us into the sincerity of practice and the sooner we realize that
the better this isn't going to work out the way I've been approaching
my life the way I've been trying to govern some Sarah this ungovernable
realm this can't actually work out
and that recognition sets us on a kind of
course and so how how is how is Faith born
usually we understand suffering as an effect suffering is the effect
of craving clinging but suffering is also a Cause
causes things
says faith has a supporting condition I say it does not lack a
supporting condition and what is the supporting condition for faith
suffering should be the reply
and Gill puts it this way
um just as one first must know oneself to be lost in order to search away for a
way out of the Jungle so one must know one is suffering in order to start a process that frees one from that
suffering between knowing one is suffering and starting to walk a path to Freedom
there needs to be adequate confidence in the path and in one's capacity to walk
it this type of faith is not dogmatism it
has a certain kind of respect for the empirical Sensibility
the Buddha was very sophisticated on these questions and
we know that uh you know again and again clinging to views is one of the
Wellsprings of suffering and whatever the opposite of fundamentalism is
the Dharma is a path to it
uh ajan ajanamara says um belief fills
um belief fills the unknown with certainties Faith trusts the implications of your
experience trusting the implications of your
experience I was
I was interviewed a few few days ago
about dharma's stuff and um the interviewer asked like how did you
get into practice how did you become committed to to the path
and it struck me that um it's a little like asking why did you
fall in love with that person so when you ask somebody ask a couple
people okay why'd you fall in love tend to give very
kind of superficial answers not very believable
you know they say things like well we both like spicy food or something
it's like okay that's nice yeah like spicy food
too it's like I'm not so sure you know why you fell in love with that person yeah
and uh who knows why we fall in love
with anything it's often seems to me quite opaque to oneself
and a faith faith is a kind of form of Falling in Love
it's not so much a commitment to these propositions agreeing with these tenets
or something it's like Falling in Love and
yeah the heart in some sense of recognition the hard
returning to its native ground
Emerson said the the definition of spiritual should be that which is its
own evidence and teachers
teachers try to nudge Us in this direction yeah but um you can't force anyone to fall in
love with anything and
you can never really know where love is going to go but you know that you have
to see through
now just as one doesn't fall in love with a static person you cannot hold
the another being still the sense of the path and the love
for it that evolves too it changes to um
Maggie Maggie Nelson says uh whenever the lover utters the phrase
I love you it's meaning must be renewed by each use
as the very task of love and of language is to give one in the same phrase
inflections which will for uh which will be forever new
I take refuge take refuge in Buddha dhamma Sangha I
love you these phrases are renewed renewed new
inflections each time
as uh as a teacher I see people across a certain
threshold where the faith is stabilizes or it's strong enough that
there's no there's no going back to leave practice would be uh to abandon
One's Own Heart and there's a certain kind of Security in that because up until then
there's a certain a wobble maybe in the path
and I associate
associate Faith with relaxation with relaxation
with a certain kind of ease we relax into our faith
and one of its gifts is that where
not um excuse me we're not compulsively looking for
evidence that we're on the right track we're not uh just trying to Ping to some Metric
the of our okayness that that this is our path it's like no that's actually settled
heart has returned to its native ground and we become naturally just less
self-absorbed in faith in our confidence it's less about me more about
path or kind of humble efforts to walk it
as we we develop this um this confidence in our practice
confidence in our heart in a sense
um on each the changingness of all things becomes at least a little bit less
intimidating faith means that however however life
unfolds we we know our practice will
will be there and uh
yeah we have a certain a confidence confidence in the potency
of awareness and love and there's a certain kind of coziness I
associate with that yeah it doesn't mean that that uh
samsara the cracks in samsara have been healed by any stretch
and um of course experience will be difficult times
sometimes overwhelmingly so maybe
but um our faith the the Dharma confidence in
it will always be at least a subtle
consolation and often profound one
and so we breathe a little more easily and
rest and keep going
affair offer this for your
care consideration please pick up what's useful leave the rest behind
okay so uh so thank you thank you all
right check the chat here um
Okay I uh yeah I wish you wish you all uh well and um we'll uh
we'll see you uh same time tomorrow okay thank you