good morning to everyone it's wonderful to see so many people here so um this morning what I would
like to talk about is uh inhabiting Our
Lives how do we inhabit Our Lives how do you inhabit your life does that have any
meaning for you and and I'm going to begin by reading a
poem by Jane herfield this is uh her new book called The
asking and um this poem may sound a little abstract to begin with so just
just sort of get the feeling of the poem don't worry about it too much I would like my living to inhabit
me the way the rain sun and their wanting inhabit a fig or an apple I
would like to meet my life also in pieces scattered
a conversation sat down on a long hallway table a disappointment pocketed
inside a jacket some long ago longing glimpsed half recognized in the corner
of a thrift store painting to discover my happiness
walking first toward me then away from me down a stairwell on two strong legs
all its own also the uncountable wheat stocks how many times broken beaten sent
between grindstones before entering the marriage of oven and bread let me find my life in that
too in my moments of clumsiness Solitude in days of vertigo and hesitation in the
many year ends that found me standing on top of a stov top to take down a track
light in my nights asked sometimes answered questions I would like to add to my life
while we are still living a little salt and butter one more slice of the edible
Apple a teaspoon of jam from the long simmered fig to taste as if something
tasted for the first time what we will have become
then to taste as if something tasted for the first time what we will have become
then now the title of this is I would
like so what this poem opened up for me was the idea
that we sometimes get lost in practice and thinking it's something that we do that's separate from life you know well
I'm going to go practice now I'm going to go meditate I'm going to met I'm going to do meta I'm going to do this
practice I'm going to do Equanimity practice now and we make it separate
from what what's going on when it is in life that practice
really occurs that it's not separate from
life and that the way to be free of suffering is to be free of suffering in
life not when we're sitting on the cushion not that that's a bad idea by the way I'm happy to be free of
suffering on the cushion thank you very much but it is in inhabiting our Liv
lives that we really live our lives being present for what's
happening and we we talk about well I lost myself in that I lost my way you
know I lost track of time as if we in fact lost something and
maybe we did that piece of time occurred and will
never occur again
that snippet of Our Lives we just
missed it's gone that's into that one sometimes we engage in a a deliberate
mindless activity in my 20s I wore out decks of cards playing
solitire because I just didn't want to look at what was going on in my
life hours hours SP playing Solitaire now you know you can do that
electronically you don't have to wear out decks of cards anymore but sometimes we do that we just life is too much I'm
just going to I'm going to ignore it I'm going to go do something that allows me not to be not to think about it so I
want to make a clear distinction between inhabiting one's life and be
being controlled by thinking about one's life which are two entirely different
things and the suffering that arises from them
are different sometimes it's just laziness
you know just I can't be bothered just can't be bothered can't be bothered with living
you know I just well I think I'm just going to sleep this one off just going to go sleep through the day
because it's just I just don't I don't have the energy for it thank you
and we forget how delightful is the taste of that fig Jam or I still have
the taste in my mouth just barely of what I had for breakfast and I'm going
to tell you about what I had for breakfast later one of my examples it had chocolate in
it sometimes we're lost in anxiety frustration anger the emotional storms
of life were lost in them where the emotions take
over and that kind of loss is different it's very
intense but we are lost the part of
us that's willing to be present for it is
lost something takes over from us and we're not really registering it it's I
can't help it it's beyond me many are the ways that we abandon
ourselves we leave ourselves alone at the shopping center you know bye kid
I'll be back later we abandon
ourselves and yet one of the most common questions I get from people is how do I
bring mindfulness into my everyday life okay so I've been meditating for a
while how do I bring it into my life the most common question maybe after what do
I do about being angry and the answer is you just pay
attention you just inhabit your life so what does that mean what does it
mean it's it's it's a puzzling question so it reminded me when I was thinking about this it reminded me of another
poem and eventually I remembered that it was a Jane herfield poem once again very short poem called uh why bodh sappa went
to Motel 6 so here it is where is your home the interviewer asked him here no
no the interviewer said thinking it a problem of translation when you are where you actually
live now it was his turn to think translation
problem okay now I read that few times and then I said
oh the monk was saying I live here wherever I am I live
here and the translator and the interviewer was saying you know like where do you live as if living was where
your home was you know physical domicile but in fact where you live is
here where you live is right here right now in this moment you live right here
this is the only place you can live is right here you can't live anywhere
else because here is where you are alive and that's that's the secret of
bring mindfulness into your everyday life is being aware of the fact that
right here right now is the only place where you are
alive it's the only place who exists
everything else is
concept the problem is not so much about being mindful as it is just being aware
so I want to just remind you that mindfulness mindfulness starts with there's an object okay here's the object
we know the object and then there's the knowing that we know part and that's the
awareness it's the registering of it
so excuse me I hit the microphone so I know I'm sitting here we
all know that we're sitting here or walking we're we're here we know this but it isn't until I feel myself on this
cushion this nice soft cushion that I am aware of
sitting it's the knowing it's the registering it's the keeping oh yeah
yeah that happened and to get into the habit of registering what's happening with you me
check this getting into the habit of actually
registering what's going on with you is the becoming aware of being alive in
this moment that part it's that part that you want to
cultivate and that's what we're not used to doing we're just sort of kind of floating
through life you know I know this is happening I'm driving I'm but it's the noticing
something it's understanding that practice is not distinct from our lives it is our
lives it it it's actually kind of hard to talk about this because when I first started
meditating I remember early on maybe I'd been meditating for a few months and I said I went to Gil and I said you know
I'm I what I'm noticing is I'm inhabiting more of my life but even then
I did not know the extent to which that could be
true after many years I don't think so much about being
mindful I just am mindful it's not so much a practice of
mindfulness it's it's just being aware I'm I'm oh this is what's happening this
is what's happening this is what's happening this is what's happening and it it doesn't take
thinking about it that's the point it doesn't take thinking about it as a
practice it becomes a habit of
being like my noticing as I was talking that chocolate was in my mouth still
that little faint amount of chocolate was in my mouth another way of talking about it is
being present for what is true okay so this is a an act of getting
it out of our head so often when we're talking about it we'll say get into your body and notice that the information is
coming to you through your senses eyes taste hearing
feeling smelling this is how we're getting the information about what's going on in this moment and all of that
is true but if we think about it in a way
that doesn't require us to think about it but
just feel our way into the moment perhaps using a presence as a word not
as a noun but as a dynamic flowing sense of I'm here in
this moment then we might notice we might be aware of something in this moment that we aren't otherwise aware of
because we're not consciously thinking okay now I'm going to listen so I know what I hear in this moment or I'm going
to look and and really see what I'm seeing in this moment but that we're kind of open it's a it's a way of doing
open awareness to just consider presence in this moment
does it mean to be present in this moment what do I understand by that
what do I understand by presence in this moment and don't worry about an
answer keep an open it's an open question because the idea is in fact
just to be open to what am what am I what am I taking
in that I'm not thinking about taking in because you are you know the the
conditions of this moment you are not in control of you decided what you're going to wear
today you decided to come here today you transported yourself here today
you're here you chose your place in the room you didn't choose an infinite
number of other things last night I chose what I was
going to wear this morning I wore something entirely different because that just last night it was all black said no
I don't want to wear all black today because the conditions
changed conditions are changing all the time so we can't predict so how can we
decide ahead of time here's what I'm going to be aware of it's just wasted energy more things
to think
about so what am I aware of when I'm not not thinking about what I'm aware of
what do I just feel in the air I like to to consider what the
energy field is that I feel and when I first asked myself that question I said energy field what the hell am I talking
about and so I just sat and and decided how much space it felt like my body was
occupying you know what am I aware of so I was sitting here and one of the things that's true when you sit and meditate
with people is there is a different feeling when you meditate alone and when you meditate in a group I'm sure most of
you have felt that it just feels different there's something different that happens when you sit in a
group and uh I just went on a it's been a few months now September I went on a
3-week retreat and as it happens because of conditions that were
not planned I was sitting in the front row and so I was sitting right in front of the teacher's Das and Gil was sitting
there and I could tell when Gil was in the room and when he was not in the room because he had such a great ability to
just sink into concentration it was delightful to sit
with him just delightful because I could feel that
energy not because I was looking for it
oh and so that came to mind this morning as I was sitting here in the room with all
of you and I there was there was like a pressure coming toward me I went
wow [Laughter] wow almost like I was basking in the
energy coming from the room it wasn't that I was looking for
that it was just as I left myself open to the
energy it was I was concentrating on my breath and then I said so if I don't stop at the skin what do I
feel and it was like a blast
furnace well that's delightful that was there all along but I was not aware of
it so there are many things that you can be aware
of if you are open to being aware of them and that's why I say it becomes
just a habit of presence of just being
here and not off in your head that becomes more
prevalent as you allow it to be
so now tied up with with this is the intention tied up with the presence of
inhabiting your life is the intention so somebody said to me the other day that
they felt the that uh they had a uh something
that they enjoyed doing and they would become so absorbed in it they would lose themselves in it for hours and they
would didn't even know uh what had happened what had transpired and they had a product at the
end and that was delightful but but they felt that they had to develop by to
develop her spiritual life she had to give that up she had to give that practice up whatever it
was and um that may be
true but what struck me is that it would be very H very
sad to develop a spiritual practice independent of what made your heart
sing and that the the idea that you lose
yourself in something means that it is detrimental to your spiritual practice
somehow just is what set me off thinking about this how do we inhabit Our
Lives doing what we're doing being who we are and not becoming something else
in order to be a spiritual person I have to not be me just doesn't work
doesn't work because the other part of awareness
is the only person you can be in this moment is you you can't be someone
else the other part of being alive is the only person who can be alive for you is you you can't be the ideal you you
can only be you so give that
up meet this moment with you
the you that is here so the intention you might say well I want to
be more mindful in life I want to be more spiritual in life be very careful about that
intention being more mindful is not the final
intention being more mindful is on its way to something else that you really
want so ask yourself as soon as you come up
with an intention where is this leaning where's this
leading what is it that I'm truly yearning
toward you know for years my intention in life was to be openhearted because when I began this
practice I was pretty much steel trap closed off
and uh and then I got to the point where I
realized to be openhearted I had to just be open that was pretty scary be open be
open that felt very vulnerable and eventually I got to the point where I heard the B
part my intention is to be what
wow that was much more freeing in the end much more freeing sometimes just
listening to your own intentions opens up for you what it is you're truly
wanting what it is you're truly leaning
toward and that seeing clearly what is the intention of my life what is the
intention why am I doing this practice I'm doing this practice so I
can be at peace H
now every time I sit down and I have a a meditation center where session where
I'm Restless it's not working but that's not actually true
because somewhere in that I want to be peace is how can I introduce ease into
my life and being able to sit with irritation and restlessness and say
ah restlessness is here is how to come to a place of ease
whether you are agitated restful
peaceful concerned anxious but ah anxious is here anxious look at that so
that you can see things rising and passing and not get hooked by them so now I'm going to tell you about
the chocolate so I decided uh I don't know a week ago on a whim I
was going through we were planning last night we had our family gift exchange celebration because our close family our
daughter and and grandchildren are leaving town for 3 weeks going to New Zealand so we decided to have our
celebration last night and as I was going through the cookbook I found a recipe for chocolate
babka now this is a um a really wonderful uh bread in the Jewish
tradition it come it's a it's a Kala that has uh chocolate in it and the the
you you make the dough and then you roll it out and it has a a layer of chocolate
that you put in it or you can put cinnamon or there's all kinds of things you can put in it and then you roll it
up and you slice it down the middle so that the all the filling then shows on
the outside and then you braid it and bake it okay it's very elaborate lots of
steps I had some of this last summer that I bought at a Jewish Bakery and I loved it and I've been looking for it
and there was a recipe and so somebody who's never made bread decided she was going to make this so I
did and so in the process of doing this uh I learned all kinds of things about
what you should and should not do and I looked at on the internet watched people make it you know and said oh yeah I
could do this I could do this well I'm going to skip all the beginning
stuff and get to the part where I was the rolling out the cold dough and it they all of the recipes give you two
loaves and the reason they do that is it's a lot of work if you're going to do it make at least two that's the explanation
I saw but all the recipes call for two loaves now it turns out this is fortuitous because you know I learned on
the first one and then I could do the second one so as I was rolling out this cold
dough uh one characteristic of the dough is it's made it has eggs in it so it's a
very rich dough and it's very elastic you know you don't think about
roll in up bread dough anyway pie dough that I'm familiar with but bread dough
so there I was rolling it on my piece of uh parchment paper second one I did not
use parchment paper it was twisting and as so I was
aware of oh this is never going to work I don't know what I'm doing why is that happening that
way I was thinking about am I going to get this done in time now I was also
trying to get this stage done and get it so it was Rising because I had a practice Discussion Group an hour later
okay so I had this hard deadline I had to get on Zoom and I I was doing this oh
am I going to get done on time so you know just add a little tension so I was watching all of these
thoughts coming and going but I didn't grab on to any of them I didn't say I
didn't spend the rest of my time thinking about all the things I tried to do that were ill advised is just I
watched the thoughts coming and going and I watched when Oh that's oh I can see now that's the way you do that I
watch little pieces of satisfaction I got the first one done you know and it was yeah kind of
looked like what it was supposed to look like the second one I pull it out
whipped through that took about a third of the time to do the same thing looked
beautiful because I'd learned so much the first time so it isn't about not learning from the
past you can learn from what you do but you don't need to drag any of the
extra stuff with you you have to well i' I've did I did this wrong before and I know what to expect and this is going to
be a failure because this happened before it's just every moment is
fresh and there was a moment when I looked at the piece that ID rolled out and said
wow that actually looks like the picture look at that and there's just a
moment of huh but only a moment because you also don't spend a lot of time
gloating because you know the moment has changed already and now it's time to
find out whether the next step you know what happens in The Next Step there's a lot of freshness to just just being here
for what's happening just just here just just
here and uncertainty you know there there's there's uncertainty there's
uncertainty okay at one point I remember thinking
you know there's I'm doing this because it's supposed to be fun I thought it would be fun am I having fun I asked myself am I
having fun and I could I could say yeah I'm
having fun even even in the frustrating times when it looked like you know I
have to cut the dough over here and Patch it over there which is usually a
mistake it was fun to be doing something new that I wasn't particularly
good at that I didn't have to be good at that it didn't have anything to do with
being me I didn't have to be a master Baker I didn't have to be anything but
somebody playing with the dough somebody doing something somebody doing something and being aware of the
smell of the chocolate and the feel of the Rolling pen and the just just
this and because you know all the ingredients
were luscious and things I don't normally Grant myself it was going to be good no matter what it was it was going
to be by definition unless I burnt it was going to be good so I didn't worry
about the outcomes just this just
just and it was was fun not always
pleasing I wasn't always happy the fun part was in being there
being very alive making just alive just really
there and one moment after a next you know you may often heard a teacher talk
about keep your mindfulness continuous it isn't continually find something to
to be mindful of not continually look for objects to be mindful of or or to carry this object with you although it
can be the continuous part is to never G give up being
present don't give up being present and when you find you've lost at the very
moment that you noticed you've been lost is when you are here be really happy about
that that's the very moment when you're for sure here you're in this
moment you can notice judging I'm judging I'm judging okay
judging so you don't have to hold on to the Judgment you don't have to say this is
good this is bad you don't have to create more levels of anxiety for
yourself by judging yourself about oh how can I be angry I should have been over being angry by
now I found myself one uh for for two days last week wanting a sweater that
was on a flash sale for two days I wanted that sale I wanted that sweater I
don't have a blue sweater I really want that I just watched the wanting for two
days I put it in the cart I had it all ready to go but no I'm
not going to do it I argued with myself I carried that sweater around with me for two days and just watched that
wanting and then I let the time expire I couldn't quite tell myself to make the
decision I just I'm not going to do it so I didn't quite Reen renounce it but I
had a lot of experience wanting my watching myself
want this is what wanting is wanting wanting wanting wanting and
seeing how it felt watching some when I'm close to
grabbing and when I'm back so you might
argue I see wanting I cut out wanting it's all over that's one way to look at
it but another way to look at it is to see wanting and to know that I can
survive wanting and that I can be at ease with wanting without condemning
myself and adding more layers of suffering to
wanting I can just want and I can let it
go and now as I have more times in the past I know what it's like to want and
let it go and I can open the refrigerator and see the ice cream and let it go I can want the ice cream and
no I don't have to eat it and I don't have to be the person who cannot resist
wanting sometimes I don't resist sometimes I do resist but I understand
more about how my mind works around wanting because I was present for
wanting
another aspect of being present is to be present not only for what's going on
inside us to be present also for what's going on outside of us that is impacting
us those other conditions that we don't necessarily that we certainly don't have
any control over so one of those might be the people
in our lives that we notice that person is particularly irritable
today so I'm going to avoid that person or I'm going to make space for that person or I am going to be
particularly forgiving of that person's irritability today or if I don't think I can do that
I'm going to not be there today you we might manage our
relationships with someone by being aware of how they are not
blaming but accommodating my way of being present in this moment is to be aware also that you
have an existence in this moment you have a way that you are in
this moment not blaming not judging this is how you are in this
moment and just as I allow myself to be a certain way in this moment however it
is I need to allow you to be as you are in this moment
also and how difficult that can
be or even further a field there was a
um there was there there's a person who is the Minister of culture for the
Palestinian Authority lives in rala and on day two of the recent War he
was happened to be in Gaza and he wrote a diary entry that was
published in the Washington Post and I read it and he talked about what it was
like to be there he was visiting his father and his mother-in-law and uh he was there with
his family and his his wife left immediately but his son his 15-year-old
son he decided to stay the minister decided to stay with his father and his
15-year-old son decided to stay with him and
uh it was a very moving account of what was was going on and they were staying
in a particular Camp which was in subsequent days heavily
bombed and my feeling about that was I kept thinking about this person and his
son and saying oh my God that's being bombed what's happened to them they didn't have to be there they were they
they they belonged somewhere else and and it was interesting to me that I had somehow made a personal connection with
this person because I I knew something about them having read this this
account and uh one day last week I think when they were
doing the prisoner exchange or hostage exchange there was another account
written he wrote about he the his trip with his son as they left they decided
to leave and as I read that account about they're leaving I realized I was
crying in relief in relief because I had been so
tense hoping that he made his way home this person I didn't even
know that condition existed in my life for those two or 3 weeks I can't even
tell you how long that has been that condition
was impacting me all of that time but I was not particularly aware of
it until I read the second account I had thought about it and I was aware when I
thought about this person and and wished for his safety and his son's safety so I
knew that it was impacting me at some point but it was only in reading the second
account that I realized how deeply affected I I was by
that and how how relieved and how grateful I was to know that this person
was alive this
person you know not not a nationality not an ethnicity
not a political position person but a person a specific person that I don't
even know we are impacted by so many things and it
is really useful to our understandings of what it
means to inhabit Our Lives to sometimes inquire how am I being impacted by what
I don't even know who I don't even
know and just occasionally say huh sometimes it's in a Joyful Way that
we're being impacted and we don't know particularly because we're not used
to looking for that particularly the person on the corner
that is always smiling how much we miss them when they're suddenly one day not
there so be aware
of someone who Smiles don't let it don't let it not be
noticed and the one morning last week I was got up I was making my coffee I looked out and there was a blue sky and
kind of puffy clouds and the Sea and there was the fresh green grass out and
and it's said to me like the the pictures you draw in first grade you know of a of a
sunny scene and then I but I went on to make my coffee and I thought no look at
it register it go ahead and register it because that's the awareness
part register it so I looked at it yeah it is
pretty and then I made my coffee it isn't that it becomes something else
it's not like like adopting another practice it's just allow yourself to
register what's going on in front of you register the color that attracts your attention register the sound that you
hear ah inhabit your
life it gives you freedom from being who who you used to be from having to be who
you have been it gives you the freedom to be just who you are right
now right now to taste as if something tasted for
the first time what we will have become
then what we will have become then
this is what I hope for you in your lives thank you very
much