going so so hi I'm Nik Mountain California and at all land hi lovely to
see you all lovely to be with you so um
yeah if you like to say hello and and bring your voices and and uh yeah start
with uh kindness and and greeting each
other hi I'm Claire in New York hi Claire
Maran g hi Maran and I also heard Jamie hi hello both of
you from Toronto hi this was who was it from
Toronto uh NE from Toronto Canada hi NE
welcome NE in New Hampshire hi Neil good evening and hi now from Japan good
morning to you good yes morning uh I think it's morning I keep forgetting hi
Ron from Palo Alto he from San Diego uh Pat says hi from
saso and yeah Frank Frank from San Diego
turns from squ Washington and we also have John and Nate and wosa on YouTube
saying hello hello Ali from Oakland hi
and Alicia from East East Bay hi Kevin
from a prao place of Goodwill I love that I'm Megan from pal to desire from
Michigan Fred oh my goodness the hellos are going faster than I can read them hello and John says hello from New
Zealand oh nice okay I'm I'm I'm just going to smile as they keep rolling all
the hell are rolling and and um yeah very sweet oh Z also from Kawaii
great is Amy here Amy usually joins her from Maui um
Amy usually puts in aloha aloha as well very sweet okay great I love it we're
very International very many different time zones so my heart is so warmed up
yay yay very sweet audio is not a clear sound but understandable every word with
no delay okay got it thanks Maran thanks for that feedback see if there's any other feedback in in the chat uh can you
mute everyone that might be I'm GNA mute everyone there we go everyone muted I
think that's what the problem was it should be better okay it seems like video is a little better to that's
perfect Says Megan yeah great the video seems to have improved also a little bit okay we're just go with the causes and
conditions so thank you Neil for posting information about how I Google Groups if
you're new to Happ it's a low um uh traffic mailing list where information
and resources are shared also later we'll have the chance to engage in small
groups and um there is an invitation for you to take a look at the document that
that um is supportive of how to support yourselves and support each other so
okay and now I'm going to change the settings so that um let see the space
stays quiet and unmuting would be disabled and all the chats will just come to me but I still ask to keep that
the chat um um quiet because it can be quite distract me for me to receive
chats um while I'm teaching and last but not least I'm going to turn on recording
for the sake of audio Dr all the preliminaries here we go great
so so hello hello hello to everyone tonight specially the hell are
very sweet they're coming fast and and lovingly not fast and furiously but fast and lovingly from different places in
the world very sweet um so so for today's theme I'd like to invite
us to um to engage with the practice of
um bringing loving kindness meta m in
meta loving kindness also translated as friendliness um care warm-heartedness or
acceptance there's a sense of open-heartedness bring bringing
kindness with together with self-enquiry
self inquiry or inquiry so inquiry um is
one of um the seven factors of Awakening um one
of the factors in P it's D of which is inquir which is which is interest which
is this curiosity where you being interested in a topic you're you're
curious you're asking questions in a very gentle way and yet it's it's a an
open mind that is intered so so I'd like to invite us to actually bring these to
um teachings together tonight we haven't done this at in happy hour before so so
here is the invitation there's so many ways that this could be approach and D vicha is is actually this this
investigation this this um um uh um
character this this um uh CH too or a mind factor it's a mind
factor it's a mental factor of in investigation curiosity and it could be turned external and it could be turned
internal internal external it could be turned to ourself whatever we take
ourselves whoever we take ourselves to be it could also be turned externally
looking at phenomena uh external phenomena so it's it D this this Factor this factor of
Investigation is both internal and external so tonight or this morning if
you're if you're in Japan and Australia uh in this moment in time with this
practice today we're going to explore how can we turn with this sense of
acceptance and kindness and generosity of spirit internally and externally how
can we do that um and not to make it a big project but it's um yeah that's
that's that's the theme that's the theme so so let's explore see what comes up
and as I always like to say whatever arises as long as you turn to it with
kindness as long as you hold it with friendliness yeah you're doing this practice right and let's say your mind
is sleepy or distracted and as long as you you are with it with gentl with kindness with
with friendliness um you're doing this practice right and if frustration arises I can do this practice if you turn to
towards frustration with with acceptance with kindness holding it instead of adding more salt to wound then you're
doing this practice in this session right so bringing kindness with whatever
arises okay so with that Preamble Let's uh let's practice
together let's practice so like to invite you to land in your
chair in your cushion wherever you're sitting standing lying
down whatever supportive to this body in this
moment arriving arriving fully
arriving fully arriving in this moment arriving with this body
is softening relaxing the
body
letting the feet give their weight to the Earth
completely the legs lower legs knees upper
legs and sit all of them giving their weight to
the Earth or believe
me inviting your left to release
holding chest as well releasing its
weight neck and shoulders arms and
hands relaxing Rel this
m think the body knows how
knows how to send
winding we don't have to fold [Music]
up soften
forhead
and if thoughts arise it's okay we invite them to
relax same way that we're offering the weight of our body to the Earth offering
the thoughts to the Earth putting them down
down SLE them being these helium balloons bringing weight on
them offering into the Earth softening relaxing mind
heart the body and letting awareness connect with
the
breath receiving breath
this in breath this
Opera right here not the prevest not the [Music] most can I be content with just
receiving this breath in breath and the mind rest and feel
nourished
can each breath each and breath each other be received
with friendliness attitude of
friendliness this breath like a good old
friend has been with you supporting
you all your
life and this breath be received with a sense of
appreciation quiet gentle appreciation and
trance
and more can we bring a sense of kindness appreciation
receiving the breath this in breath this out breath also with a sense of
Interest yes the
breath we've known this breath for a long time and
yet each breath can SL be slightly
different as it is experienced in new in this
moment a sense of Interest gentle
curiosity
where's the breath in breath out
breath well sense openhearted open heartedness warm
heartedness
appreciation and interest as if you see a
friend you just saw them minutes ago but
now you see them with fresh eyes sense of friendliness acceptance kindness yet
interest are they
see if there can be a balance of meta kindness good
work friendliness this sense of curiosity the mother chain
interest might lean into one more and then the other it's okay no
problem may not always be balanced it's
okay learning figuring out our
way
without it getting too tight let be relaxed we gu to
tight let go lean more into the
friendliness now i' like to invite
you have this same sense of friendliness towards yourself as if you're stepping
out of
yourself and seeing yourself as a dear
friend kindness good well friendliness this friend
friend doing their best continuing to learn and
grow you know their whole story their [Music]
challenges their pain their sorrow you know their gifts you know
their values breathing with this friend who's
yourself
kindness
bringing the same s of Interest curiosity you don't know
everything about this trend about this being who you continue to
discover can there be a gentle interest
curiosity continue to learn about this [Music]
person learn with
them discover how to love support help them
grow help them deepen in
wisdom
maybe you have a question self-reflection question [Music]
question you can drop in not try to answer it from the head in place but just to drop it
in be something else something like how can I help you deepen how can
I help you deepen your practice how can I support
you how can [Music] I help you thrive
in your heart in your mind in your
Humanity how can I love you to
be to accomplish to be to live your fullest human potential on this Earth
[Music] incs whatever version of the question
might be Al for you drop it in try to answer it just drop it in and
hold a kind gaze as you breathe with this being
who's [Music]
yourself love it loving self
inquir
just dropping in the question just holding yourself with kindness with meta
not thinking about the answer but listening listening deeply listening
deeply also a form of care a form of
love
the inquiry could simply be what do you need
sweethart
and remember to drop in the question so much thinking about but breathing
kindly yourself
I'm asking the questions in
helps Orient
us
as we bring this per period of meditation practice to
close let us meet with kindness whatever arose or did not
arise with interes in kindness even if it's judgment or
frustration can there be kindness and interest oh why is this
arising it's okay I some the interest instead of
taking it on face five trusting that there is co-creative
goodness as we practice together May our practice be in cause
and condition the wellbeing waking up
freedom of all pleas everywh including
[Music]
yourself
practice so this was an invitation to
bring meta kindness friendliness together one aspect of d one aspect of
Interest curiosity inquiring um and there's so many
different ways we can do this practice and and today the invitation was turning
first towards the phenomena internal phenomena is the breath and C ating this
sense of friendliness and then uh curiosity about the breath as a phenomena and then turning towards this
being who is me and um perhaps asking the question what do you need sweetheart
which both has a sense of kindness support curiosity interest and there's
so many different versions of of this question and also to say one more word
um about this yes the there are teachings about um not self or in
personality and yet we need to really love and know the self really know and
love the self before we can let go of the self we need to come first and then
when we know and love the self little by little these these um perhaps
unhealthful patterns ET sat they drop away but they need to be seen first we
can't squash them
unexamined a few words
so yeah let's uh invite us to turn to
uh okay the rooms are all Clos and everybody's coming back hi welcome back
so uh would love to hear um Reflections how was it what did you discover you can
especially if you haven't spoken in a large group for a while you're invited
to share your Reflections either about the guide of meditation or or the um
um inquiry in or or the group breakout group and can also type them in chat you
can either type them to me directly in which case I'll read your reflection of
your name it'll be private or you can type it to everyone in which case I'll
also will be public so
Ser oh thank you so I was having a really difficult
time hearing you I don't think I was the only one um and uh at a certain point I tried
to just tune the volume down totally because I was feeling frustrated because I couldn't hear
you and that didn't help
either yeah so then you know because I really tuned into a lot of physical
pain and um and you know the question that I Rose
while we were sharing was I didn't feel any pain at all yesterday you know I I I was in New York
City I hadn't been there for three years visited with my sister we did a lot of walking but I was not experiencing any
physical pain at all and I don't get how there could be such a huge shift
from one day to another you know and feeling so much physical pain I I it's
like it's something that is really is like I have that's a major
question for me actually it's a major question for me how could there be such
um shift you know from from one
day to the next yeah so but and that is that is the body Serena that is the body
so having humility about the body going through its own um you know its own
process so I'm hearing a sense of almost frustration or or am I hearing that
right I well I heard the frustration definitely because you couldn't hear me well and I'm sorry the the audio was
challenging and and yet as as we as I said at the beginning and I really
invite you sering up because everything is an opportunity for practice can can you bring kindness to the frustration
can you be with can you be comfortable with being uncomfortable this is the marrow of the practice it's not about
being everything being easy and comfortable that's not the direction we're
heading okay well obviously I need more training and feeling comfortable with
the very uncomfortable because start start right now start my de with with
physical pain you're having my dear can you have can you um bring a bit of
friendliness just a bit Right In This Moment instead of think I need more training in the future how about right
here that's what I'm inviting you to try Serena it's this this practice is not for the future it's for right here right
now there's pain in the body there's frustration you didn't hear me can there be some opening to it like okay it's
like this right now I don't know is that possible just for for
5% not require relaxing into it right
exactly exactly that's it thank you so much
thank you Serena hi
please hi think that was a beautiful meditation thank you and uh as I was
meditating today I realized uh one thing that came to mind this whole acceptance and being loving
to myself I found myself having a sometimes like when people I'm very
close to or I love bring up things that I've done that they were not happy with it makes me so defensive and I imagine
myself I feel like this U imagine myself having a conversation where something's
being bought up but but it was just so much more accepting of what they're bringing up and me explaining to them
that I'm also human and this was my intention doing it and I feel like when you can love yourself and accept
yourself and not expect Perfection you can bring such a loving Dimension to relationship and uh that is
just such a gift so hopefully I'll do more of this meditation and implement it
more of the time but thank you so much for a beautiful meditation today beautiful thank you so much for the the
um very clear and wise reflections the really the inside aha if there is love
and care for this being I can bring it more into the relationships and then also I can bring it more into the
relationship towards them because they are doing their best because and so it
it it becomes more generative hold holding all the um yeah the the
messiness of Being Human together
great Jerry says it was a welcome place of kindness and friendship in the world
today of geopolitical events where there seems little kindness so big shout of
thanks thank you Jerry [Music]
rich I I found myself over the weekend getting very angry over events the
Middle East and I turned to doing compassion stuff
meditation which did calm me down and sort of changed my mental emotional
state but am I doing anything for anyone else by doing
that great question so so here's here's something to reflect upon I think what
you can actually in in the way you're practicing especially with what has been
happening geopolitically is is compassion 360 Dees I think that's how
you can do something for for everyone because by doing compassion but just for
one side then it's it's not very wise our compa compassion practice is 360
Degrees um everybody's suffering in in different ways causing suffering causing
cing I mean I can say that historically this group has been um has
been suffering and this group refers to both size right ouch ouch historically
they've been suffering like ouch so that way you can actually reduce this hatred
in the world starting with yourself that yeah both sides are suffering are causing suffering to each other it can
be it's complicated it's messy and can I have a stance of
compassion 300 60° thank you for bringing that in
sound um Megan says I'm grateful for the warmth and kindness the meditation
brought to a day in which I thought so much Sor I appreciate the idea of approaching whatever is with kindness
and learning like not trying to control it comes
out so it's
um what also one thing I wanted to mention um is this this practice this
inquiry with curiosity also where there is pain or there is suffering that can
be Cur a kindness and a um a gentleness of in quiet because there's so much we
don't know there's so much we don't know internally externally and having a stance of humility instead
of being a know it all when we know everything um is not really helpful it's
not path to to lessening suffering in the world including [Music]
one so so before I dedicate the marriage I wanted to also correct something I
said earlier uh which was um I mentioned and this is kind of technical but I want
to mention it so so D of CH which is one of the factors of Awakening
translated as interest curiosity investigation um is is actually not
listed as one of the CH in the Abid some of you are like what is she talking about don't worry those who know the
Abid dama and the mental factors it's not a mental factor it's is only listed as one of the seven factors of Awakening
just wanted to to correct the the the the accuracy pedagogical but again
practically makes no difference it's just something I said I want to come there so thank you all thank you for
your practice thank you for coming here to cultivate your hearts and Minds for
the sake of all things are may all being be happy may all being at the conditions
of freedom and
happiness thanks