so hello hello and welcome everyone to happy hour lovely to be with you and to
to feel your presence so
so for this week what I wanted to bring um for our consideration as we engage
with the practice is a quote that I ran into this week
and this quote is often uh in
um an inappropriately credited to to
um gyote if I'm saying his name right in German but actually is the person who wrote it
is not and I'll put a link to this later so that Neil can share it
with the with all of you but here actually you know what I can put the
put put it in chat right now because some of you are visual so you might want to actually see the quote sir while I
read it if you prefer you can also there it is so the quote is
I have come to the frightening conclusion that I am the decisive element
it is my personal approach that creates the climate it is my daily mood that makes the
weather I possess tremendous power to make life miserable or joyous
I can be a tool of torture or an instrument of inspiration
I can humiliate or humor hurt or heal
in all situations it is my response that decides whether a crisis is escalated or
de-escalated and the person is humanized or dehumanized
if we treat people as they are we make them worse
if we treat people as they ought to be we help them become what they are
capable of becoming wrote this in the book called teacher
and child a book for parents and teachers so now you get a sense of the orientation as a teacher
um I found I I was struck by this quote the power of this quote especially the way
it starts I have come to the frightening conclusion that I am the decisive
element and it is so true we we know this our
approach our um our attitude as as he says I ca I
possess tremendous power to make life miserable or joyous you know and happy hour we've talked in the past many many
times about this quote which is the name of a book happiness is a choice you make
is a choice you make so he continues I can humiliate or humor hurt or heal
in all situations it is my response that decides whether a crisis is escalated
the person is humanized dehumanized ETC so so
to realize really to realize the tremendous power
that we have in our choices that we have a choice we have a choice as to how we
respond to any moment to any situation
we we have we have choices we have a choice
and the more we practice the more we practice with cultivating with turning
our minds our hearts towards making a wise a kind a
humanizing a compassionate choice that choice becomes more readily
available to us in the moment it and you know this you know this from
your practice you know this that if your mind has been swimming in
thoughts of kindness generosity good will oh that becomes more available as a choice in real time
and if it's been swimming with rumination and and difficult thoughts of
anger and why me or whatever the the version might be for your makeup
for your thought patterns and the heart is less less primed less primed
to uh to that wise choice to to really taking our
our seat of power to make to make wise compassionate choices so
so I wanted to seed our practice with that quote tonight and let's sit together we'll sit with a lot of Silence
tonight um with calming the mind with the breath I had some new invitations this past
week that you found very helpful I'm going to bring those back in to study the mind first with the breath the body
and then turning towards towards kindness towards Metta so so with that let's uh let's arrive
let's arrive together let's arrive in this body in this moment
and first let's turn to our breath in the body breath in the body
letting awareness relax letting the body relax first
relax relax relax to your body the more relaxed we are the easier
the practice becomes the more the Mind relaxes if the body is
relaxed and let's actually begin with
3D diaphragmatic breaths to arrive and settle
taking a deep breath topic it up a little more
holding the breath a little bit a few seconds and then Letting Go ah
a sound arriving in the body another breath then topping it up at the
end can be supportive holding
sailing third one
now let the breath be natural relax the body and receive the breath
making an intention a relaxed
the persistent intention to connect with just this in-breath the entirety of it
and now make an intention to connect with this out breath the entirety of it
renewing the intention to connect to receive to relax and receive this
in-breath again relax and receive this out breath
so every time we reconnect with the intention
relax and receive the breath
foreign
that the mind is wandering on and has gone off to a thought or plan or
whatever it's okay it's really okay
sort of self-flagellating and judging yourself for the time you've been gone
celebrate that now you're awake you have a choice 50 50.
instead of beating yourself up choose to celebrate yes this moment of awareness again reconnecting
with awareness with the breath and the more we celebrate we Delight
in the moments that we come back the more they happen and be more ease will enjoy as the
practice becomes instead of feeling like a failure
everybody's mind drifts it's okay celebrate the coming back
reconnecting with the intention to be with Justice in breath in that breath
and then this one
foreign
let the breath be nourishing
let knowing the breath be comforting relaxing
foreign foreign
foreign
Ty of this in-breath from the beginning to the end of it like a beloved friend
connecting receiving the out breath from the beginning to the
end foreign
foreign
has been wandering we have a choice it's not a frightening
conclusion but a joyous conclusion that we have a choice
can either berate yourself for having been distracted or you can celebrate
the light that the mind is now awake and aware
how wonderful to have a choice foreign
this fear of awareness be more spacious to include the breath the sensations of
their breath in the body as well as whatever else arises sounds
could be thoughts Sensations emotions
and if it gets too much can always let the breath be the anchor connecting
with the breath and if not you can let the awareness be spacious and
and whatever rises in this fear of awareness
mind has a choice you can be kind accepting
not judging not aversive not pushing it away
not resisting reality
being present being present kind with kindness towards whatever
arises sphere of awareness the practice can be very simple
instructions can be very simple how do we choose
to be with whatever rightness
even if difficult thoughts or emotions foreign
leaning into wise kind kind choice kindness presence patience
maybe even wearing a smile meeting reality meeting the moment as it
shows itself now
may I meet this moment with kindness whatever arises In This Moment Man Meet
it with kindness may my heart be filled with loving
kindness good wealth
expanding expanding the sphere of awareness
just internally but letting it be external me may I be kind may I meet
just whatever arises In This Moment In This heart and mind with kindness but all that I meet all the
people beings that I meet
may I meet my world with kindness the world with kindness
as much as possible and available to me
may I Meet myself with kindness
and as we turn to bring this this period to a close
I Meet myself with kindness in this moment for however this practice period was or wasn't
I've done my best I showed up
and not choosing to judge or rate or compare
choosing to appreciate choosing to be grateful for showing up
planting seeds planting seeds of goodness kindness presence it's all we
can do and may these seeds we have planted
together may they ripen and may they support
the happiness well-being Awakening of ourselves and
all beings everywhere may all beings be well may all beings be free
[Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your practice foreign
today
um it brought in a quote at the beginning which really talks about
our choice how much choice we have in every moment and choice and by actually
turning your mind towards wise choices in the moment we seed them
to arise in in challenging moments so that the wise and kind Choice can arise
so in the practice I invited us to to be with to First relax
receive three three diaphragmatic breaths just arrive and then we did
um being with the breath being with the breath the intention to be with the
entirety of the in-breath entirety of the out breath and then after settling for a while we
opened the sphere of awareness to include everything and may I meet whatever arises not just distractions
with kindness and the breath with kindness but whatever arises and then we expanded it further may I meet all
beings all all the world with kindness so
um that's what we did that's basic rundown so so now
um the invitation is to meet ourselves and each other and with
kindness in small groups this is where the rubber meets the road it's lovely to
practice with our eyes closed and it's also lovely it's so insightful to meet
others again showing up with kindness with with patience for ourselves
speaking from our own experience only using I statements not commenting
comparing asking questions from others just showing up this is what I noticed
or we can also show up with silence perfectly fine not to speak just be kind
and share your compassionate presence with others and
the prompt for today is um with this practice did you notice a moment of choice did you throughout the
almost 30 minutes we practice together did you moment did you notice any moments of choice did you and by
actually saying them out loud letting yourself be held witness it can um
it's empowering to say yes I did notice I had a choice actually and I leaned
into actually in this moment I leaned into berating myself and then the next one I didn't or whatever it might be
um no right or wrong answers or you might say I was distracted the whole time didn't notice at all perfectly fine
nobody's judging you please don't judge yourself just showing up and sharing our
practice supporting each other in this community of kindness community of
Goodwill so be kind to yourself be kind to each other and I'm going to create
the breakout rooms and oh and let's go uh let the order be uh reverse
alphabetical order according to first name yeah just so that it's fun reverse
alphabetical order first name uh and oh and then say just the Nugget so that the
next person has time and then the next person I'll come back to you you can you can add more but make sure everybody has
time to to share so just share a little bit the first round okay
here we go welcome back everyone
their rooms are closed and we have some time for Reflections I
just changed the chat settings to be everyone you can share your Reflections
in chat either to everyone or privately to me in which case I won't read your name just uh your uh reflection or you
can raise your Zoom hand especially if you haven't shared in the community for a while would love to hear from you Nancy
I just unmute myself is that how yeah perfect okay well I was sharing with the
group um that this meditation just felt very
sweet to me and maybe uh in an interesting way just sort of a
celebration of myself and all of the work I've done
uh just sort of diving into challenges and not resisting reality and
I've been through um three and a half years of um there's more people in my family dying
where I was always the person uh that had to clean up the mess and I kept just
diving in and and um just being sweet to myself because
um even if I'm not live with you Nikki I I listen almost every day and practice
with you so thanking you and um it was a
lovely just a lovely night for me very peaceful sort of just quiet Joy uh wow I
I really um you know uh done the work and can hold it
myself and others in love thank you beautiful thank you so much Nancy thank
you oh I'm so glad you were able to join live tonight so that we get to see you
and benefit from from the the joy of your practice celebrating
um celebrating your own generosity for yourself and your generosity for others
what you describe this sounds to me as as deep practice of
generosity to others to step in
in when it's really hard as you said clean up the mess and when someone passes it just could be so much right
emotionally and and stuff and family and friends for you to
be stepping into the fire is such an act of generosity over and over and over
again and and and and and now allowing that generosity also to be shared with
Nancy Nancy dear you've been generous yes this is so beautiful it just makes my
heart so so happy that you're sharing is 360 degrees and beautiful thank you so
much Nancy just makes my heart so happy thank you for your deep deep practice of generosity oh beautiful
I'm so glad I came to tonight as well and I see not just you I'm so glad I came as well this made my day
not their reflections Amy I see your hand
uh so in the practice um when my mind would wander
um I would bring it back I would choose to bring it back and I was laughing with the group because recently I've been using the song Baby Come Back as a
anchor to bring me back to the breath because it seems so sweet and it's also
playful and light and it takes away the Judgment from it um and so that's one way I feel like
I've been skillful to like choose the response and then another is I'm seeing
somebody who I feel like some can be a little negative sometimes and every time I feel like the critical part of
something coming out I just send him meta and like the situation meta and so
it's become a prompt of choice or I'm not I feel empathy but then I don't get lost in the critical I just said my time
wanting healing and stuff like that and that feels like a really healthy choice a more supportive generous Choice thank
you oh beautiful thanks for sharing both of those Amy I love the the um the using
the song Baby Come Back because it is it is light-hearted right you're calling your mind baby like hey come back it's
just kind of sweet and playful and fun yay sort of Yankee gets back oh you are
oh so there's a sweetness and also the very skillful this of sending them and
sending the situation this entanglement sending the situation meta all all those
who are entangled in this situation may you have eaten may you be well so skillful so creative and skillful
beautiful thanks for sharing that Amy yeah lovely and Serena I see your hand
thank you so much yes I too would like to report that um
uh I really got an experience today of um
this practice bearing good fruit very good fruit and um
and my sister was extremely nasty in a phone call
and uh uh
and I was able to just go get back to her with a positive message
you know and it was like a reflexive it was like
it was really wonderful that I was just able to not even think about it
that I could just get back to her with something loving
so I'm I'm really very grateful that I've been doing this work ah
thank you thank you Serena thank you for sharing this oh so so happy making so
gosh um it buoys my heart to no end that through
your practice through your practice of meta and and you know you regularly come to happy hour so so as a regular happy
hour practitioner that this kindness this kindness has become love has become
a reflexive response oh my Heavens so powerful it gives me chills when that
when our community here does report these success moments of oh this was
really hard today just you know daggers came at me and then kindness naturally arose it's you know
it reminds me of there is a there is a story of of the
Buddha um at the night of his Enlightenment that Mara sent was was
throwing uh arrows throwing arrows and as the arrows came to
came near him they became flowers flower petals and they fell so that is really
and you know when people send you daggers through the power of of radiating meta kindness that reflexive
kindness it changes it shift to situation so and you're reporting that
Serena yay thank you so much thank you for your work thank you thank you thank
you for your practice well this is absolutely delightful this it makes me so happy and one question came through
but it's off topic so I'm not going to take that question this evening so so I
want to thank you all for your practice for your continued practice whether you show up live whether you listen later
whether you practice on your own but however you practice yay May there be
more kindness more Good Will more love in our world um may all beings be happy may all
beings be free including ourselves things [Music]
everyone thank you so much be well stop the