readings friends greetings good morning from Mountain View California where it's
rainy forecast uh it's forecast to be um yeah a storm another storm coming to
Northern California yes yay
hope you are well wherever you are wherever in the world you are greetings
greetings looking forward to continuing our
exploration and our practice together this week um and the theme we are exploring is
improvising Our Lives improvising Our Lives
lessons from improv or our practice on the cushion and in life
so so saying yes
saying yes to what is saying yes to what is
that would be the theme of our meditation and offer more reflections of
course so let's let's begin let's practice together
ah arriving arriving in the body
arriving in the body arriving in this moment in time with an attitude of yes
an attitude of yes in our hearts yes yes
to this moment yes to this body however it is
it may be feeling great it might be tight and
icky hurting whatever is happening
the body in this moment can we say yes
can we say yes to all of it
with an open heart yes
exploring experimenting with
this perspective shift in perspective just a tiny bit
see how it shifts and changes our experience
starting with the body saying yes
to however it's showing up
there is tightness
achiness Etc
opening up these areas saying yes you're here
yes accepting the truth of the moment
this is what's arriving right now yes
instead of blocking pushing away which brings more agitation and
tightness a mind and heart
saying yes to the body relaxing softening
saying yes to the breath
each breath each in breath each out breath individually
see if the acceptance the saying yes and come
from your heart from your body not from your head
your heart taking a stance of yes towards whatever is arising
foreign noticing where there are these subtle
no's no to experience
In This Moment
and first can you say yes to the no
accepting full yes to the resistance seeing what happens to the resistance if
there is any this attitude of yes
it's not to be forced
or sing no's to become a yes but accepting those with a yes see what
happens
maybe the heart softens the body softens some more
and then there can be a genuine subtle soft yes yes
whatever is arising
and being curious light-hearted exploring the different
tones of yes
how does a subtle yes feel in your body a gentle soft
yes
like the gentle arrays of
Morning Sun
yes yes
but if you turn the volume up and you're internal yes
what does an enthusiastic use the fortune yes feel like in your
heart yes
whatever is arising In This Moment
explore be curious
as if you are shouting yes yes delightedly
to your life
appreciatively receiving how does that volume feel
volume of the heart it's experiment
you can change experiment with another volume
it's one to ten maybe a five or maybe a one
a whisper
explore your heart discover
and if you explore in volume one of yes let it be very
subtle simply a stance
that accompanies your awareness awareness imbued your mindfulness imbued
with the subtle yes acceptance open
ing to experience very subtle simply knowing
if there our stories thoughts
future oriented past oriented not here not present
can we say yes we see you we see you yes
yes acknowledging
ah letting the heart relax and it's seeing
see what happens my heart May settle into
yes to the present moment
not planning Future Past
right here yes to what we truly know
right here right now
now and then you can drop in the word yes into your heart
that the driver reverberate soften settle
open up the brightness
not like a mantra with every breath now and then dropped in
tune
our attitude your perspective
yes
and as we bring this meditation to a close
can we have our hearts say yes
yes as if with
Arms Wide Open embracing what
this moment is with this practice has been this morning however it's been
thought of the past future distractions pain or
fully here doesn't matter can we say yes yes
I showed up I showed up I'm here
I showed up doing my best yes
yes saying yes to your life
yes to the causes the conditions that are yes
and trusting that or planting seeds
of openness non-resistance
open-hearted acceptance curiosity
seeds that will flower in their own time support us
support others and offering offering
generously saying yes offering this goodness trusting there is goodness here
co-created with all of us and
offering this goodness to all beings everywhere may my goodness may my cultivation my
efforts be of service
I just to myself my own life but to all beings those whose lives I
touch directly and indirectly
me my life be a source of good yes to this life
may all beings everywhere be well may all beings everywhere
free including myself
[Music]
thank you for your practice friends
and as we take a brief pause
if you like to share a word or two a what's a rising For You In This Moment
after this practice to take through to take with you through your day you're welcome to do that
let's begin and greetings all thank you for your practice
and a moment ago I asked you to uh share words that are coming up after this
meditation on yes and very few of them bring them into the
space peace openness open gratitude for my
life yes calm smile relax energy positivity I
want to play one of you says acceptance calmness yes grounded cultivation
open heart so many beautiful so many beautiful reflections
thank you so much simply sacred acquired yes yes this too kind sweet
Pekka Equanimity beautiful thank you so much
so so I like to offer some reflections foreign
of this week which is uh inspired from the practice of Improv
which actually is a for me it's it's it is a deep and sacred practice you know
on the outside it can look really it's funny and silly but it's actually
it is a practice so
the uh there are many teachings in in the Canon of Improv
yesterday we started with the attitude this attitude of curiosity interest
lightness this just the sense of curiosity and the fullness and emptiness
in in our language in in Buddhism coming together with this this
um with with the lightness and also with with the actions in the world
so today we turn through um we return to
[Music] um What's called the teaching on yes yes
and which is the equivalent of that in our practice
is acceptance is accepting opening to experience not blocking experience but
being open to experience because if we block experience even if experience is difficult and challenging if we Block
it's becomes harder it becomes much more difficult
um but accepting there is a sense of opening of softness and it allows possibilities
so so in improv and and all of yeah let me just talk about improv for a
moment so an improv with teaching on yes and there's a concept of yes and
and the idea is that if you block so there's the concept related to that is
the concept of blocking versus accepting so so blocking is when
an offer is made for example if you're interactively if you're in a relational
situation as we often are in life saying improv if you're in a relational
say scene and playing with another player and they make an offer they they
make a you know made-up offer because improv is made up you're improvising and
our lives are also made up there's a lot of improvising
when when a player makes an offer to you for example says you know it gives you
an imaginary I don't know saucepan and say oh here take the saucepan whatever
if you say oh this is not a saucepan or oh I don't want a saucepan or a if you
block if you block if there's energy of blocking energy of no energy of no oh
that pretty much kills the interaction that kills the interaction and you can
notice that in your own life um you can we actually often notice it
more in others when they block our invitations or block our offers
um you want to do this no I don't want to do that do you want to do that no I don't oh ouch
kills the energy whereas the idea of yes and
um save if for example you're offering you're inviting someone would you like to do this and say yes I would love to
do something with you and how about we do this because this is what I have energy for this is what I have time for
so there's a flow in the energy of life there's a flow in the energy of
interaction there's a flow in the energy of the moment yes and yes and so an
improv concept of yes and is the most fundamental rule of improv you yes you
say yes to what's offered and you add something to it you add something it's
the and instead of yes but but we often do yes but it's yes and yes this is a
you know this is a cooking Implement and and yes and oh I needed one I'm about to
make eggs or whatever or yes yes and yes and there is a sense of this Spirit of
generosity so blocking so we often block the energy
of life even even when things are difficult when we push them away say for
example um as I was guiding and leading this meditation I had a lot of aches and
pains and tightness in my body and I've learned through my practice that if I
tighten around them no I don't want this pain why this pains is terrible I get stuck I get stuck in in that or stuck in
life whereas yes yes yes okay all right yes there is there is this tightness
there is this pain there is this discomfort yes I open up to it my heart opens up to it my heart opens up to it
and it softens it's it's acceptance it becomes part of the experience and it's not taking Center Stage so there's a lot
of wisdom in saying yes and in the in
the with the wisdom of acceptance and and
through improv we can see it from a different perspective because we often see it from you know from the dharmic
perspective it's usually a similar perspective that we have and acceptance opening
versus from the the inspired by improv this way of saying yes and yes and
um there's a sense of opening even to the challenges in life even to the child
it's not always easy and and and and Roses
um and yet can we open up to what is instead of
blocking it no no no no no or coalescing around the the difficulty
with make giving it central stage um there is so much possibility and
openness there's so many routes and there when we say yes it opens options
it opens our way of seeing it opens our perspective it opens um it opens lots of options the same way
that in improv saying yes then you have a lot of options yes and let me try this
yes let me try that yes all these options whereas when we say no or resist
or there's there is this blocked energy in our heart just kind of kind of gets
stuck in in the uh in the blocking so
concept of blocking versus acceptance and the yes and so so the
invitation I have for you today is to try saying yes is to try saying yes
um to to what is to try saying yes and the yes could be a
very subtle yes of yes I acknowledge yes it is like this right now yes yes and
can you add can you have more creativity instead of just ending with the yes can
you invite your creativity we all have creativity as human beings can you say yes and yes and
when invitations come in can you say yes and instead of no can it
be a yes and yes I'd love to do this and I can do it in this way or yes I'd love to do this and let's do it that's
embellish it yes and can we bring more creativity can we bring more possibilities
um to to our lives today especially relationally relationally with others or even our own
Hearts when something comes up maybe it feels like all the same old same old uh
no I don't want to do this uh oh but yes yes can I find a way to say yes and and
make it more creative and find other ways can we challenge ourselves this is
such this life is so impermanent and precious and
and it's amazing to be conscious for anything to exist at all but here we are
with all these opportunities these Myriad opportunities to learn and grow
even when things are difficult as they often are and it's okay it's okay it's
part of being a live learning growing so may you be well may you may you say
yes Softly oysterously may you explore today saying
yes and yes and thank you so much for your practice for
joining for your exploration see what it feels like today to improvise your life with the yes and you're improvising it
anyway so you might as well try some different new fresh tools and see what
happens you might like them and keep them thank you so much may you be well may
you say yes and I'm looking forward to continuing the series with you tomorrow