so I think uh it's all set up here for now
I couldn't get uh the IMC internet to work
and even though we do have electricity here and much of the neighborhood around
here including at our home there's no electricity so uh
a little bit found my way this morning at home at candlelight which was kind of sweet
and um and then other things happening so
hopefully this works and uh hopefully the connection is strong
enough so
so welcome and um
one of the teachings of the Buddha that I
love very very much appreciate for tremendous value on
is that for there to be
for us to have care to care for the welfare of
oneself for others for self and others and for
the whole world it's not one or the other not self or others
but they're all all four of these areas have a kind of equal value equal weight
and uh it might seem a little strange to put the whole world and give it on the
scale and put oneself on the other end say equal weight for both
but it's true for each person that uh what's important is not the weight of
the object of our attention but rather the way in which our
attending or a care spreads from us
and sometimes I think of love or care or kindness as being a light
deep in our hearts deep in our body and if you turned on the light and you
could slow the flow of light particles light waves
so you could just kind of track how fast they spread from the center you would see that they would they
actually kind of touch what's closest first and then they go to what's next closest and it spreads out from there
and uh and so um the
and we know that in kind of Galaxy time that it takes a while for the light of the sun to come to us so the light that
bounces off the moon to come to us it's we don't see instantaneously we see a little bit delayed
so our love we turn it on goes through us first
and so it's indiscriminate it Cares For What
for where it cares for what it lands on but then it spreads and grows beyond
that and in that through regard what it touches first
is given equal weight to what it touches later
what the touches first is just as appropriate for its care
as anything else to not have that be the case
to not have that could be the case is
to turn something off in the heart to not have care for oneself
actually takes more work than to care
this implies that care is maybe different than what most people think it
might be it's something very very simple
and this is why as we become quieter and certain way simpler in
meditation the care the love the kindness
will more naturally just be here and not maybe even intentionally
directed to oneself but rather encompassing oneself
so let's uh meditate and think of a process of simplification
into this present moment Here and Now
and to gently close your eyes
and bring your attention establish your attention here in your body
enough to familiarize yourself with how your body is now
and if kindness and care doesn't so much care doesn't matter what
it lands on it just cares for where it lands
see if you can just be aware of your body as it is
without judgments or wanting it different
just taking it in being aware
registering how your body is now
and then within that body to take some long slow deep breaths
imagining that as the body expands so does your kindness your care your
love for this body touching it all
friendliness good will foreign
as you exhale you're relaxing down to the very source
the little light bulb went in within
where kindness begins and then as you inhale
that light of kindness radiates out through your whole body and
Beyond back and forth as you breathe
relaxing as you exhale
and then
letting your breathing return to normal
he's sitting here simply sitting here gently
with the light of Love or kindness
good will care for yourself and for others
radiating out within
maybe riding on the waves of breathing
whatever awareness senses nose feels
in the body and mind as you're meditating imagine that the light of care
the light of love is included is part of the awareness
so that you're touched with love touched with care kindness
not a kindness for any reason you don't have to deserve kindness
but rather because it's the nature of light to light to shine and light things up
it's the nature of the heart's kindness
to touch everything with its kindness
in a Simplicity of being
love does not need to have a reason does not need to have an object
love just is part of the Simplicity of being
kindness friendliness meta
can irradiate
just like a candlelight when lit
radiates
without discrimination for what the light lands on
it can land on anything
that you're aware of
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to let there be some good will
even if it's good will that's a wish
a wish for welfare some kindness some love
for yourself
Maybe with with thoughts speaking to yourself
or the hard feeling for yourself
somehow let all of Who You Are
no your kindness for yourself your
friendliness your respect
not so maybe not because you deserve it you probably do
but from that kindness that care and simplicity of being
which loves just because it's the nature to love
nature to be kind and respectful
and to have that land on yourself
wishing yourself well wishing yourself happiness safety
and then to have that kindness
radiate Beyond yourself out into the world
without leaving yourself behind
almost as if you become the magnifier
for the heart's capacity to care and to love
as it spreads through your body and Beyond
and then to wish well for everyone
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings
be peaceful may all beings
be free
and May many people many beings
as possible no that there are others who care for them
who are positively inclined ready to be friendly
ready to support their welfare and happiness
let people know that they're not alone in this world
there are people who care
and may we be some of those
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone and
for those of you who are have been facing big weather challenges
I hope you're well and um
today here in California at least locally here where we are looks like it's going to be clear skies and no
winds or rain yesterday we had been here in Redwood
City in town a number of large redwood trees fall down fell down went right across the street from here
somehow miraculously fell across the street in a way that not even a car was damaged
Park cars parked there and um
so there were three big between here and my house there were three big big trees that came down and lots of small things
but now it's a quiet day so we have these challenges life is full of challenges
and I think part of what it means for many people to be challenged is to be a
little bit activated to be preoccupied to be concerned more than just that it's
a puzzle to solve uh puzzle challenges can be fun and that
can be engaging and you know creative and to engage the mind
but uh human challenges can be seen that way but human challenges often come along
with some way that we're activated and activated reactivated
something gets kind of energized and and stirred up and and that can often be together with
emotions it can often be together with imagination where imagining what where
this is going and what's going to happen if it if it just continues and and that activation reactivation
creates a certain mental focus engagement it kind of
engages muscles and all kinds of energies which in a time of immediate
crisis are useful perhaps but as an ongoing basis
um limits us and complicates our inner life so that
some of the simpler yeah maybe quieter innate capacities we
have get drowned out and um
and one of those is our innate capacity to love
and I use the word love here as a broad umbrella term
for a wide family of human intentions sentiments attitudes
that we have and so some of these words that I use are
care kindness friendliness good will
even respect depreciation generosity they um
friendliness maybe I said and so all these together kind of belong to this
family of love and they have to do with a positive attitude towards others
or positive ad towards anyone and in Buddhism we put a lot of emphasis
on the practice of loving-kindness of Goodwill and one of the classic ways in which is
practiced is Goodwill towards oneself and first start there and then for
people who are benefactors and then friends neutral people and even enemies
are included and we often call them difficult people rather than enemies
and um and there's always an object for that meta
but one of the profound things that can be discovered through this practice of
inside practice meditation practice is that love kindness care Goodwill compassion
can exist without there needing to be an object it can exist without there needing to be
a reason to do it and probably it's fair to say for most
people that love is triggered by an object something
that we adore something that we really value something we really appreciate and and um and it kind of stirs our hearts
or inspires Us in some way and kind of opens our hearts and all this kind of
love or Goodwill flows because the object is so wonderful I know some people who um in doing
loving kindness practice to kind of awaken that capacity they'll think of
puppies or they'll think about some very cute little animal that just stirs them
up in a nice way and makes them kind of but it's always that with an object
and the miraculous thing is that yes we have the capacity for love
and that capacity doesn't require an object maybe it's easier with an object
partly because there's more energy sometimes around a love for an object
because then the object lives in relationship to us and we have a relationship to it that
somehow when we exist or our sense of self is kind of kind of pulled into it that often
activates or stirs a a little Ecology of things that are in
addition to love love as well there's nothing wrong with having an object but also it's easy
sometimes for our desires for our aspirations our dreams in relationship
to those people those kind of to be activated as well which maybe gives a richness and a depth
to that love but it's possible to have kindness care
compassion without an object without a person that it's directed towards
if the ma if the heart and mind if the if we're settled enough here
that we can feel and allow for the the warmth
of the heart to the warmth of the place that loves to just kind of be shining
just kind of be unobstructed and it's almost as if and maybe it's the
case that our capacity to love is often eclipsed by being activated by challenges by
concerns by desires and all that and the question is how can we
deactivate ourselves enough so that it's not eclipsed
so when we feel challenged then it's possible to remember oh
I have this innate capacity for kindness for love for compassion and it's not present right now
and then justification can come along well of course it's not present it's too dangerous right now of course it's not
present um the person doesn't deserve it that I'm with of course it's not present because I'm
Justified being angry I'm Justified being filled with
resentment or something because it was so horrible what happened of course it's not present I feel so
hurt and so you know so disappointed so betrayed
and I would like to propose that um without diminishing the fact that we do
have these feelings of betrayal of hurt to fear
they don't have to Eclipse our capacity for love
in fact if we allow it too much to Eclipse it that it's too easy for
selfishness conceits self-preoccupation self
to kind of take over in a way that's actually not even healthy for ourselves
but we but if we can relax deactivate quiet down
not become activated by your activation
maybe we can come back to that place where there can be some modicum of Love
or kindness and um and the most fundamental
I like to think that the most fundamental kind of capacity for love
begins with a wish for someone's welfare the intention for love the wish for
having kindness so in the middle of a challenge that this doesn't require you know our full
100 attention to be safe
to ask the question where is the love where's the kindness
and if it's not available um to take the time
to deactivate to take the time to maybe go for a walk
meditate talk with a friend um do something that you know what to do
that lets your activated system calm down quiet down a bit
and certainly not continue doing the very thing that keeps you activated and
reactivated and um and you know without aversion for
the activation without condemnation but with this principle that yes we're
looking at coming back to the Simplicity of being where a basic Goodwill basic
kindness and friendliness has a chance to shine that doesn't need a reason
and because it doesn't need a reason it has the capacity capacity to shine
its Good Will equally on everything it can Shine the Good Will on our
activation on our anger on our sense of betrayal on our hurt
on our enemies on our you know all of our just you know all
maybe maybe we're disappointed with ourselves in a challenge maybe we made a
mistake but that Simple Kindness is there just
to hold it all all of Who We Are we have this capacity Within
for unconditional kind regard we have this capacity within for an
unconditional um good will
regardless of what's happened regardless of what we've done regardless of how we think
about ourselves and that that should live within us
the capacity to Love Without A Reason without that justification just that the
nature of the Heart To Love is a phenomenal thing
and so where's the love where is the kindness
in the middle of a challenge where is it and just that question carrying that
question with us might be enough to for us to recognize little hints of the
kindness that's there but if there's none it's probably an indication
that what's important to do now is not to stay in the middle of
being activated but finding some way to deactivate enough
do you reactivate enough cannot caught in the cycles of activation and reactivation
and this is where meditation comes into play mindfulness comes into play
this is where learning to relax comes into play relaxation is a skill that we can get
become good at by practicing it and then to come back to the challenge
with some kindness some kind regard some good will
so the challenge is not the only game in town there's another game there's another
perspective there's a perspective of love
so um as you go through today
and you run into challenges ask yourself the question where is the love
and if there's not available how are you activated and what can you do that's realistic and
reasonable to deactivate enough that there is this unconditional
kindness kind regard for yourself for all things
as you find your way with the challenge so thank you very much and I wish you a
lot well with this exercise of Good Will kindness and love
and um it's a very worthwhile thing to do
thank you