so good evening again my name is Maria strotman I'm here for
Diana and um you know I've been part of IMC for uh
a lot of years that's IMC not the dis the
institution or the uh the building but I AMC the sa and some of my
longest running IMC friends are in this room right now and others that I don't
know as well or at all and so there are things that I think
about the people that I know and that I don't know and and really what I know is
that we are all here we all came here and meditated tonight and beyond that there's a great deal of
speculation views ideas about who you are your ideas about who I am why we're
here what we might mean why we're here I might have said
that
twice tonight's talk is going to be on the Dharma of
hearing and like all of the senses what gets in the way of actually hearing is
what we think about what we're hearing what we think about what we're
seeing what we think about what we're expecting what we want what we might
want all of this gets in the way one of the things I want is the iPad I left at
home with my talk on it but that's okay this is going to work because all
of my devices are linked which means it's on my phone in little tiny print so
we'll see how this goes so when I uh was taking training for Zen
hospice project one of the things that we did was we wrote down something unusual about ourselves that we didn't
think people would know we wrote it on a piece of paper and we put it in in a basket and then everybody went around
and picked from the basket and tried to guess what this obscure thing who this belonged to and of course everybody
wrote the most outrageous obscure thing they could think about about themselves
and of course very few people guess correctly about what that thing was true
of because we don't really know one another we have all kinds of ideas you
know I don't like yellow therefore if you like that this isn't true by the way this is an idea if I didn't like yellow
and you were wearing a yellow shirt I might say there's something wrong with
you so today I got an email from Liz
Powell who who manages the sign up page for people who want individual practice
discussions and she she sent me two people that are signed up for tomorrow
and she said here are your two people and I thought well that's great she I know people are signed up but I don't have their names so I wrote back and
said I don't have their names and she said well yes it's in the text and I said well you used to do that but these
don't have it and she wrote back and she said well here are the two names but they are in the text
I thought well so I went through and read every word and the problem was she used to
send it in a different format and it was a different format than before and sure
enough the names were there just in a totally unexpected place so I couldn't see
them and they were obvious once she told me where to find them
obvious but I couldn't see them and so sometimes when somebody's
talking to me they'll say something to me and I can't hear it I'm
listening but I can't hear it because I'm expecting to hear
something else because I'm busy planning what I want to say to them because there
are all kinds of reasons so the question
is how do we hear when we're
listening how do we hear people we actually don't want to hear that's the
real trick we think we want to hear them but we don't really want to hear what they
have to say maybe because we don't want to hear something about us or something
about them we don't want to hear it today I had U an Audiology test you know
to get my ears checked and they put you in isolation in this room and then they send these little tiny sounds to you and
you they three little beeps an interval of time three little beeps and they they
either start out softly and get louder or the other way around and they test each year differently and pretty soon I
found my mind trying to decide whether I was hearing it or I was hearing an echo
or I was well you know the intervals were about the same and so I could
imagine it was happening and I didn't trust my mind
could I trust my hearing if I couldn't trust my hearing or my mind how did I know whether those
beeps were there or not and to to watch your mind go through
all of these machinations and realize this was and I was listening
hard I could I could feel the energy in my body listening hard and then I said no listen easy
relax just you're not passing a test like you
know it's going to change your life here listen if you hear the beeps push the
button all of this energy and how hard I was listening it
turned out how hard I was listening wasn't the answer I needed to listen
easily lightly in a relaxed way I thought okay
huh and on the way home I passed this corner at the corner of El Camino and uh
Embarcadero and there were two people out on the corner and one was waving an Israeli flag and the other had a big
sign and the sign said ceasefire free Israelis and Palestinians
from the hamus
uh what do we call them
um terrorists and I thought okay I know what they want I I I get their message
and then I thought do I get their message do I know what they want to
say do I really know what they want to say because what I'm what I'm reading
and what I'm hearing is something that I either agree or disagree
with that's the first thing I hear something I'm agreeing or disagreeing with not a mental decision but that I'm
interpreting what I'm hearing based on my
bias I'm interpreting what I'm
hearing we don't we're not really conscious of the fact fact that we're interpreting what we're
hearing you know it's sort of uh yeah I'm I'm really paying attention I want
to know and it turns out you know as opposed to this very quiet environment I
was in when I was listening really hard my sense right now is that
everything is really loud big noises big noises lots of
yelling lots of yelling and it's really hard to hear when everyone's yelling I
know I came from a very very noisy family everybody yells all the
time and one of the things I discovered in my hearing test today was that my
left ear which has had a hearing aid for about a year is used to having a higher
volume and when I was doing the test of words in noise
I've lost the ability because I've retrained my brain to have a higher volume sound in my left ear with the
hearing aid with without the hearing aid I can't hear as well as I did
before voices words in loud noises but with the hearing aid it's
great because my brain has been reconfigured to work with the hearing
aid our brains have been reconfigured to work with our
views that's it's just that's those are the triggers that's how they work that's
what humans do so part of the problem for us is
keeping that in mind when we're listening that what we're hearing is affected by what we're
thinking about what we're hearing
and what are people hearing they're say they're hearing but but but but or well but me or they're hearing y you blame
blame blame blame blame or
why someone the other day told me that she was really
sad and she wanted to know if the Buddha had anything to say about how to be in
Conflict how to be with conflict without getting really
angry and you know if that indeed is the problem or
the challenge how are how do you
hear how do you hear what is unacceptable to you without becoming reactive angry hurt
sad depressed
hopeless how do you hear it as something more than noise and why would you why would you
just not turn it off so in thinking about that I thought
well so what are the sources of conflict sources of conflict have to do with beliefs or views that you have economic
in inequality uh non- diversity of uh
ethnicity culture money ability ways of dealing with the
world tribalism a division into me and you Us
and Them um a lack of security feeling safe
all of these things are very human characteristics and they give rise to conflict
and it's important to understand that these things are are all conditional
they're just conditions they're not in any way
truths they're sort of acquired and developed
conditions they're not absolutes they're
conditions and they can come down to Greed hatred and delusion me
mine is greed Me Mine hatred not mine not mine go away not
mine delusion ignorance we just don't know don't know confusion
confusion and we have certain reactions we have triggers that you know that that
sets you off could be a yellow shirt it could be language that is used we have
uh we have the inner triggers which have to do with self-criticism self-doubt oh
I'm doing it wrong again oh I can't believe this is I'm falling into this pattern again outer ones that have to do with
anger and resentment these are just reactions to
conditions and I'm not talking here about whether things are right or wrong
or appropriate or inappropriate I am simply describing conditions and
reactions these things happen these things
happen so then what kind of responses do we have we have intellectual responses you know I'm going to debate you to the
death I'm going to tell you I get my facts lined up and I'm going to talk to you about the facts of
life and in that case things have to be right or wrong I have to if I'm right
you have to be wrong we attack the other or build up ourselves you are the enemy therefore
you know you're you're slime and I am right therefore I'm Angelic and we we
set that up in our arguments uh we negotiate and usually in
negotiate the idea is you get more you get more from them then you get from yourself that's that's sort of you know
the the win-win thing is usually not on people's agenda
and uh compromise is really looked down to if it's a question of
Purity compromise is unacceptable and we often go into the
negotiation with the idea that we're going to change somebody else's mind but we rarely think of it as changing our
minds and if you notice all of these things have to do with views this is this is how I'm viewing the world this
is how I view the world and the other the other form of reaction
has to do with retribution punishment you know you've harmed
me and has to do with how I feel about things that happened in the past okay now I've lost my little
thing this is the problem with going with something as small as this okay
so I'm going to give you an example
so this is a poem by a leon uh who is the current poet
laate for the US uh and this is called the contract
says we'd like the conversation to be bilingual that's the title of the
poem when you come bring your brownness so we can be sure to please the funders
will you check this box we're applying for a grant do you have any poems that speak
to troubled teens bilingual is best would you like to come to dinner
with the patrons and S Patron will you tell us the stories that make us
uncomfortable but not complicit don't send us the one where
you were just like us born in a greenhouse no no no that's what we want to hear from you but the garden don't
tell us how you picked P Simmons and ate them in the dirt tomatoes and ate them
in the dirt watching V vultures pick apart another Bird's bones in the sand
no we don't want those poems tell us the one about your father stealing hubcaps after a
colleague said that's what those people do tell us how he came to the meeting
wearing a poncho and tried to sell the hubcaps back to the man don't mention your
father was a teacher spoke English loved making beer loved baseball tell us again
about the Poncho the hubcaps how he stole them how he did the thing he was trying to prove he didn't
do okay I like this poem because what she's saying is don't invite me because
I'm Brown don't invite me to tell the stories that make you feel
good don't make my brownness your
cause just see me as I
am hear me talk if I want to talk about my father let me choose the reason I
talk about my father you don't get to tell me why I talk about my
father you know there sometimes we get the idea that that inclusiveness is a matter of checking off the boxes when it
really has to do with seeing me seeing
you really hearing and not just listening not just
listening one of the things that happens is we get into the habit of collective collectivizing people you know all of
these people are the same we forget that we're collections of
individuals which is why I began the discussion here with we are a collection
of individuals but all I really know about us is that we all came here to meditate tonight and I don't even know
that for sure I just know that we're all in the room claiming to meditate maybe somebody came here just
because it's the only quiet place they thought they could come at this place time there are all kinds of reasons for
people to come someplace and the assumptions may or may not be
true and in Conflict one of the challenges is just
hearing one of the four foundations of mindfulness is when hearing just hear
don't bring everything you know to the party just see just
hear so one of my props that I did bring with
me this is uh the Buddha before Buddhism which is a translation of the the uh
book of eights that gilded I love this book you can tell I've got stickers
everywhere and now I have paper clips as well to distinguish from the
stickers so this is from uh so there are only eight SE eight sutas in this and they're all written in kind of verse
form sort of like the dapada and the one I want to read you is
this one the light is really dim here tonight I'm having trouble seeing not because of
view but because the light's not quite sufficient for me let's
see oh see oh this is sweet Jim thank you all right
so light I am right here okay let's
see lusting for debates and plunging into assemblies they take each other to
be fools they speak relying on what others have said passionate for praise
they call themselves skillful wishing for praise while debating in an assembly they become anxious refuted they become
depressed criticized and shaken they seek their opponent's faults one whose Doctrine is called
deficient and by the judges rejected despars and Grieves the inferior debater
moans I've been defeated renunciant are elated and deflated by the disputes that arise
among them seeing this you should abstain from disputes they provide no benefit other
than being praised wishing for an opponent you roar like a
hero nourished on Royal food run off o hero to where the fight is as before
there is no fight here if grasping to a view and disputing
they say this alone is true tell them in this dispute you have no opponent
here you have no opponent thank you Jim you have no opponent here I'm just not
going to fight
you I hear you the other day I was talking to a
friend of mine and we had a disagreement about a group of people that she maintained
would do something and I said you don't know that and this is probably my best friend
friend and she was getting very heated about how naive I was being and I
thought you know we don't have to fight about this so I just
stopped and sure enough that was the end of it we went on and everything was
great we didn't have to fight about whether I was naive whether she was right or
wrong we didn't have to fight about it we didn't even have to agree to disagree
which was her suggestion you actually don't have to
take up this is right or wrong you actually don't have to take it
up I'm going to try to do this without your light Jim because I think I
can
so this is from the greater discourse of the dead end they say their own Doctrine is
perfect they say the doctrine of others is inferior quarreling so they dispute
everyone saying their own opinion is true if it is inferior because of
someone's contempt then no Doctrine would be the best
because no Doctrine goes without somebody thinking it's inferior this is because many say the doctrine of others
is inferior while advocating their own if any Doctrine people worship is true
as is the path they praise then all doctrines would be true and Purity would belong to them
all H so should someone say I I know I see
see it's just like this some believe Purity comes through views but if they
see what good is that for them going too far they say Purity comes from something
other something outside of them seeing a person sees only names and appearances
having seen one knows only these whether one sees much or little this doesn't
bring doesn't bring Purity say the skillful if you if only only what you
see and experience can be true then it's dependent on what you see and experience all truth is dependent
just on your experience it seems like there's something wrong with
that they are not an enemy to any Doctrine those who are free from viewpoints not clinging to the world
they have no self reproach not forming opinion not shut down and not desirous
they are sages wise ones who have laid their burden
down you know it feels like if you just say well I'm not going to have an
opinion then I don't have to fight with you then everything's going to be Rosy
but that's not actually what it says it just says you don't have to
fight you don't have to to claim that you are always right you actually don't
have to say this is right and you are
wrong now that brings us to my dear
friend Joseph Goldstein how do you get around this problem how do you get
around the views that you hold the beliefs that you hold the values that
you hold what do you do with those you can't ignore them and be an integral
person you have them the trick is mindful
awareness to see them to see ah this is my value and to see the other person and
see that they hold also a value and to see we're both in this room
we're both on this Earth there was a I saw an amazing quote
in one of the poetry books I was going through today the title of the poem was
um an Israeli says to a Palestinian I had no idea they shared some of my
same's aspirations really how could you not
know that it's because they were categorized as some something else something not
human in fact it's amazing how often we dehumanize people as an in an effort not
to feel them not to be touched by them not to be touched by their
arguments and it's not a conscious process it's very simple we just say
they're wrong and we become
self-righteous or they're not like me and therefore they must be wrong
that's kind of a red flag you sort of go wait a minute they probably are thinking the same thing and we can't both be
right so the ability to be present for
the fact that someone else holds their views as strongly as I
do that someone else burns with the same fervor that I burn
with and they experience the same
burning and what is it that this person is experiencing what do they
actually believe what do they actually want what do they
actually believe when I look at them as a person
and not an institution or a group of
persons how do I hear them how do I hear
them how am I listening how am I listening am I
listening with an intention to hear
them or am I listening with an intention to have better arguments next
time how am I listening so um this is a Buddha Dharma
magazine which is a Buddha Buddhist publication comes out four times a year
and the most recent issue is on Buddha nature now Buddha nature is a a Buddha
concept that is uh more commonly spoken of in the Mayana Buddhist Traditions Zen
and uh Tibetan Buddhism Traditions pure land Chinese Buddhism and less so in
tradan Buddhism so what I want to talk about is not Buddha nature but Joseph
goldstein's response to the question of what did he think about Buddha
nature so let me let me pull up the page because he's Traden right so first of
all so he wrote a book called one Dharma in which he he talked about the
similarity of all forms of Buddhism and what they had in common versus their differences so some of these terms are
used more often in the uh later Traditions I think a popular
understanding of some of the later traditions is that we're already enlightened and we simply have to
realize it that might imply that it's more accessible than it actually is whether we phrase it in terms of we're
already enlightened and we just need to realize it or we're not yet realized and we have to get there the task is
formidable okay so that's how he set it up and he went on a long retreat and he
argued with himself so an important consideration here is when you're
hearing you also are hearing the argument ments in your own head the
arguments you have with yourself where you're trying to understand something for
you those arguments are going on in your head and you need to be able to hear those arguments also so here's what he
did and I found this quite wonderful let's
see there's only one Dharma we may not see the unity of it all all the time but
it's not like there are two dharmas out there first let's
see he asked a question about him being a monk and he says I wasn't a
monk I'm on the wrong page
sorry
see I had this all written out but I don't think I can read it off off my phone so I have to find it
here maybe I can find it maybe I can read it all
right in one Dharma when I was struggling with trying
to reconcile the different views the thing that helped me the most was the phrase I used metaphysics as skillful
means not as truth statements skillful means not truth statements I finally
realized I was asking the wrong question it wasn't a question of who was right it
skillful means means not to see each of these positions as statements of truth
but is skillful means for not clinging because in my understanding and practice
in several Traditions to me that is the essence of the free mind the minds
that's not clinging to anything as I or
mine if you think of your beliefs and your views as being I or
mine that's where we get entangled clinging to views clinging to
views is the problem not whether the views are right or
wrong so if you hold the view lightly and say huh what do I learn from
that view and what do I learn from that view then you come up with something
that more closely resembles a wise attention to conditions in fact I think somewhere
here yes he
says in earlier years I remember getting into these intense Dharma debates
totally convinced I was right and that my view was the Right View and passionately arguing it and
believing it one of my favorite mantras these days is who knows when I'm fully enlightened maybe
then I can say I know but until then it seems best to keep an open mind in this
regard I have a new definition of enlightenment okay what is it lightening
up we could think of the path as the process of the lightening up from the
more superficial levels to the most profound levels because basically
lightening up means letting go of all self- reference which of course is no
easy task so that's what I want to leave with you
with the way to be with the
unacceptable is to lighten up and to say suppose I look at it this way and
suppose I look at it this way what can I learn from this how can I hold all of
this and not have to choose something as right right or wrong that sets me on the path
toward ill will greed and delusion I wish you all
uncertainty and the freedom that comes with it thank you but don't leave your iPads at
home so are there any questions comments Rotten
Tomatoes
I just like to say thank you so much for you're addressing our our situation in
the world and listening thank and hearing thank you thank
you it's it's hard it's hard
to be challenged in in your
deepest places of what's right and wrong in the world and to not
react and so the the tools that we have are the tools
that allow us to to see as clearly as we can see oh this this is what's
happening oh oh this is what's happening oh look how I'm reacting to
that oh that really
hurt yeah thank you I took that test in
Middle School the hearing test and I had the exact same experience you described
I thought God I'm so neurotic if I was just a normal person I could just listen and answer the
test and then hearing you say that rather than drop my decades old judgment
I thought oh she's crazy too well you know it's uh yeah it's easy
right it's you say well that's that's that's not acceptable to behave that way so now in my defense I said well
I'll just let it go and that's that's the part that I
think we need more more freedom around the the part
that that basically lets us off the hook a little bit you know I was talking to
my husband today about how often we refer to okay what's happening now with the war and there are kind of two
approaches or more now more than to you can not read anything you can read
constantly reading constantly is probably uh just foolish not reading at
all is in denial and somewhere in between is a place where we say this is
happening and I'm not prepared this is
happening and I don't want it to be true no matter what else you
believe this is happening and I don't want it to be true and and today as I was thinking about it I realized that
what's up in the news is is happening in the Middle East but there is
still war in Ukraine and you know there was and those people aren't getting any
relief uh and I remember when that was upfront and that seemed like the most
crucial thing and what's true is that people are suffering everywhere and we were talking about end
of the year donations and I said well you know let's let's feed people let's you
know people need to eat I'm sure there are people here who need to eat and you know there's suffering in
the world and we can't we we don't have the means to end all suffering in the
world but the the response that that is to lose all hope or to become angry is
simply not useful it's not skillful so I'm I'm sort of reminded of
of the the the listing of things for for speech for for why speech you know is it
is it true is it useful is it timely is it
kind and that pretty much goes for everything that's the way we
listen that's the way we make decisions about what to
do there's no right or wrong sometimes things are skillful and
sometimes they're
not but it's not because things are
necessarily right or
wrong there there is a poem that is haunting me I don't know whether I brought
it this is a poem by naom shihab n who's a a person that I read some poems from
last week and this was written uh uh at the time of the last war in Gaza for
Muhammad side of Gaza age 15 there is no stray bullet S no bullet
like a worried cat crouching under a bush no half hairless puppy bullet dodging midnight streets the bullet
could not be a pecan plunking The Tick Tin Roof not hardly no fluff of pollen
on October's breath no humble Pebble at our feet so don't gentle it please we
live among stray thoughts tasked abandoned Midstream our fickle hearts
are fat with stray devotions we feel at home among bits and pieces all the wandering ways of words but this bullet
had no innocence did not wish anyone well you can't tell us otherwise by
naming it mildly this bullet was never the friend of life should not be gr
granted immunity by Soft saying Friendly Fire straying death eye who have we
given the wrong weight to what we do why have we given the wrong weight to what we do Muhammad Muhammad deserves the
truth this bullet had no secret happy hopes it was not singing to itself with
eyes closed under the bridge a bullet is a bullet is a
bullet it has no good
intentions so have good
intentions and I trust all will be well good
night