hello everyone and
welcome I don't know if it's uh not as light here on YouTube some of the lights
are not working here at IMC today so it's uh darker here for me but there's a
like a broad out a spotlight so maybe there's a little bit more light and you can see well
enough so one of
the the name for the people who were the title or the reference word for people who were
the direct Disciples of the Buddha is that they are the Savas and
the word savaka means the ones who heard the
hearers and um so so I me back in the ancient world there
was no books so there was only hearing if you any any learning you do uh was uh
you had to hear it and um
so but there's something I think very profound about learning the art of
listening learning to listen means that we don't assert ourselves in the middle
of the hearing we're attentive we uh kind of
clear uh the chatter in the mind the static in the mind so that we we can
hear well in the ancient world where you couldn't go back and refer to
books or transcripts of something um if you want to remember and consider what
was being said you had to listen well enough to be able to memorize it or to really learn something about it and so
it was a probably was kind of second nature in the ancient world to listen
with a higher uh attentiveness or a certain kind of sharper ATT attentiveness than
we do in the modern world because of this need to kind of let it register really deeply so we can remember and
have it as a reference and um
so this metaphor of listening can be metaphor listening can be used as a
metaphor for meditation that uh the kind of attention we're bringing to ourselves is uh to
listen well to listen without uh uh the
the static and chatter of the words the images that come up in the thinking mind
that interfere with our ability to perceive to sense to feel to
to to hear to see with the inner eye the
the our experience and um and to see
without interference of bias judgments commentary but to really be a good
listener to listen first to find out what's there first to give if you're
listening to a friend to really hear them out to hear what's going on maybe
active listening where you may be ask questions to find out more you want to really know uh your friend know what's
going on so the same thing when we sit down to meditate we really want to know our experience know what it's like to be
here and it can be inter it can interfere with meditation paradoxically can interfere if we're focusing too much
on becoming calm or centered or uh uh
somehow settling our agitation or or trying to attain
something uh it can interfere with our ability to really listen well to see to
really attend well to sense and feel more fully what is here what's going
on so to be a listener to oneself to be to really take the time to see sense
discover what is here and it's a little bit of a paradox that
if instead of focusing on becoming calm or becoming concentrated or becoming
settled um if we just really get to know carefully attend carefully listen
carefully to what's here that movement is itself settling uh calming if we listen well if
we listen without interference without expectation without wanting something
from the from the listening just to listen just to perceive just to be here with what
is so for this uh meditation we can um maybe use this
metaphor of listening uh as a way of being present for
oneself so assuming a meditation
posture and either either lowering your gaze or closing your
eyes and without doing anything more than
that notice how you are as if you're sitting down with a
friend and taking them in as they are today at this time ready to listen to
them sit down and just kind of notice yourself how are you what's happening
within you is there anything you can perceive
about yourself if you read your posture anything about your posture that
reveals your mood your attitude State of
Mind
anything about how you're
breathing does it inform you at all about how you
are and the task is just to notice not to fix not to judge
but to notice so that as time goes along you can be a better
listener a better companion for yourself as you
are how are you emotionally
how is your thinking
mind if your thoughts were in a foreign language so you couldn't understand what you're
thinking what would you perceive about yourself as a thinker right now
what would you notice about what thinking is
like
and then in the middle of how you are Center yourself on your
breathing as if the breathing are the words that you listen to when you are
listening to a friend open clear
attentive at the center of all
things is
breathing breathing in and breathing
out
for
perhaps listening through a deep
listening listening from a deep place
without commentary or judgments or
agendas just what's here listening with a quiet
mind or if the mind is not quiet listening deeply to what is
thinking
for
if you were to live listen deeply to how you
are is there something about how you are that you normally don't
acknowledge is there some truth about the situation about
yourself that you can listen to acknowledge
attend to
kindly without any
reactivity an acknowledgement and deep listening what is this that you might
normally Overlook or avoid
for
and as we come to the end of this sitting to maybe reflect
on the value of listening well to others
to listen before offering our own
opinions our own stories to listen not only for what is being
said but listen to what
people's where people's speaking comes from inside of them
them what's the emotional or Source
the motivational Source what's behind the
[Music]
words to listen with respect to listen with respect for what
is behind the words even if you might not agree with it or find it
Pleasant to listen
well to listen as a
way of bringing kindness and love
respect to listen well to bring people a sense of
safety that you're a safe person for
them to listen well so that you can better enjoy and
appreciate something good about
people May our practice of mindfulness support
us and bringing non-conflict into this
world may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all all beings be
[Music]
free thank
you
so good day everyone then continuing the list with
the of tenfold list the Buddha gave on the 10
protectors and it it might be just as useful maybe more useful to call these
10 supports and uh life can be quite challenging and uh the challenges can be
unexpected and um our inner life can be challenging and uh inner life can be
unexpected just all the ways it shifts and changes sometimes
seem ly for no reason and so it's good to have supports
it's good to have supports to uh find our way and and U not be overwhelmed or
excessively challenged uh Goods have supports that uh keep us balanced and centered and and
attentive in a clear and wise way so
the the fourth of these supports so so far it's been um uh having a virtuous
conduct behaving in such a way that our Behavior doesn't U challenge us and
doesn't make things more difficult than they need to be to
learn um to learn the Dharma to learn good skills in life to uh be studied and
kind of prepared for what we're doing um understand the bigger
context the and the third is having good spiritual friends having surrounding yourselves or
having reference to uh friends that bring out the best in us who have our best wishes in in mind who uh want to
support us who care about our well-being and but to do to do so from a place of
Freedom Place of uh not demanding or expecting or judging us for who we
are having good spiritual friends and today the the support is um
is um being easy to speak to be someone who
uh who it's easy for people to say things to you and uh in bod's
translation of the this particular suta uh he calls it he defines it as easy to
correct and um in the Buddha's commentary or discussion about this
point he describes it as being um easy to be in to receive
instructions and respectful of the instructions we receive so whether
instruction sometimes maybe is feedback uh is uh is um
people telling us uh difficult things that uh are difficult for us to hear but
maybe we need to hear that maybe sometimes people have criticism of us
have critiques of us and so to be e uh uh easy to speak to
so it's an act of generosity towards others if they want to come and speak to us about something that um we're
generous to them we are willing to receive it we'll take it in as and available for it
not to be defensive automatically not to be offensive because we don't like what we're hearing not to immediately uh meet
criticism with criticism or with shutting down or with anger but uh to
have the ability to be open to be to hear what's being said in an open
relaxed way um while so we can really know what's going
on we can track ourselves what's going on in ourselves and we can track others and what they're saying
well and uh in such a way that we're actually safer uh there is a way of protecting
ourselves by being angry and then people just want to go away or they shut up or they stop what
they're doing but uh the relationship is damaged that way and long-term safety is
not attained uh long-term safety comes from really knowing what people are thinking
and feeling and processing and working with it to be angry and get getting someone to shut up and so they never
talk about difficult things again um I think makes the situation much more difficult and challenging because then
we don't know what's underneath and what people are thinking and what's driving people to what they want to do so take
to have the capacity and the the wisdom and the skill to um to listen first
to be easy to speak to and um and
um uh it's it can be very challenging to do this uh it can threaten our sense of
self that we're capable that we know everything and there's nothing anyone
needs to tell us and the fact that someone needs to tell us anything is a sign that um somehow we're they think
we're wrong or bad or they're challenging their self image of being um
you know uh quite capable and knowledgeable and and um and we're more
in the person to be talking than the person to be receiving uh the idea what what they're
saying is is feedback about us can touch some very diffic difficult sore places
inside um it we can interpret it in ways that it's much bigger deal than what
it's actually being said we can interpret to mean that we're fundamentally flawed and and this is the
proof of it we can interpreted that people are being mean and um and
unfairly critical and of course sometimes they are but even if they are do we have to
take it personally do we have to uh is there any need to
reply uh is it um there's a whole other art to there's an art to receiving
criticism where we don't believe it we don't accept it but we also don't fight
it uh we might listen carefully and then we might say uh I'll think about it but
I don't think I agree with you and um and well that's interesting what you're saying and um I'll have to think about
it because doesn't seem quite right to me and um and that's kind of gentle way
of saying you're not behind it exactly but you are respectful of what's being said said and maybe there is some little
uh piece of it is true or or what's true is that the fact that someone has
critiques of you maybe maybe what's true is not the words but behind the words
why are they doing this maybe they feel challenged in the relationship maybe they're afraid maybe Something's
Happened that has created a rupture in the relationship and and this is their way of trying to establish a
connection so so this idea of easy to speak to um
uh uh people are comfortable in speaking to us people are uh don't have to be
afraid of us when they speak to us so this is a tremendous support and
protection because then if there is something we need to hear about ourselves something some way that we're
of people are comfortable to come and tell us and this is this is considered
in the budha tradition a people like that are a treasure it's a really phenomenal gift
and tremendously valuable to have people come to us and say you know you said something and that didn't quite work or
uh that was challenging or I think that what you did um C hurt the other person
or I think what you did was um you know I what you what you said there what you
did there has been difficult for me to listen to and I feel hurt I feel afraid
um you know can we talk about it um uh I've known people who have are so
reactive and so tense and so immediately attacking anybody who comes and says
anything to them about who they are personally that no one wants to talk to
them and um and I've known you know as a teacher I've known people that way and
who I've known for years and years and um it were very difficult as a te and as a teacher to get through the the barrier
that the wall that's there and um and then at some point when it felt really
important that uh to say something um uh to one person I finally said I knew it
would be difficult and in fact the person uh became very angry for about a
minute very upset and uh and then the person quiet down and thought about it
and came back and said oh now I understand what's happening
with me and other people I didn't understand and um and that was a turning point in this person's I think the
person's life and within a few years the person ended up uh dying and I think
that that conversation we had um was a was such a big turning point that it
contributed that person's ability to die peacefully and people would come all kinds of people came to sit with the
person and because it was so wonderful and pleasant and to be a with person who no longer had that reactivity and and um
defensiveness and anger so to um so you know so I think
she was quite lucky to have someone um finally be able to speak to her and say
something and it's unfortunate if we have to wait until crisis before we're willing to hear some feedback from
people there is some people who actually invite feedback and say please if
there's if you see anything I say or do do that is not right uh please speak up I welcome it and maybe just do it at at
the right time don't do it when I feel grumpy or or when I feel kind of under
the weather but I want to hear so easy to speak to available for the community
to say anything and to have the inner resources inner
strength to not take it personally and to be able to stand up for oneself and
necessary um this is not being a pushover for what other people have to say but it's also not being not not
being uh in Conflict for what they're saying and so this is a protection
because then we don't end up in Conflict it's a protection because we can um uh
we can learn about what we need to learn about ourselves and even if it's not about ourselves we're learning something
about the relationship we have with the other person and maybe there is where work needs to be done and um and if we
take it personally and then attack back the relationship stays ruptured but if
we hear it acknowledge what we've heard maybe even repeat back is this accurate
what I've heard uh then uh it settles people they know they've been they've
been understood and then you can say well you know I don't think that's right and
here's my understanding of it or I don't think that's right but
before talking about what you're saying I just want to say that uh you know I
care about you or we're friends and I want to find a way to have this conversation to maintain our friendship
um because sometimes what's going on is underneath the person's criticism there
is something that uh different that needs to be addressed some challenge in the relationship and uh and uh to be able to
listen and hear that what's underneath it sometimes uh is invaluable and that
also supports everyone it also is a protection for oneself and for others
and so this being easy to speak to is not a lightweight thing to do I believe
it's a phenomenally significant powerful thing to do and I like to think of it as
part of the one of the fruits of doing mindfulness practice this kind of deep
way and be able to monitor ourselves know ourselves track what's happening in the uh as things are happening that it
supports us to have this capacity to be willing to hear even difficult things or
to um so um if you want to be well
protected if you want to be well supported um be easy to speak to become
a good listener and uh listening both to people around you but also
listening to yourself listening not only to the words but listening uh to where
the words are coming from not only listening to the words but
listening to uh where those words land inside of us and this will make us easy to speak
to and find support and protection in being this
way so thank you and I would encourage you to look for opportunities even the
smallest opportunities even things where people say things that are relatively mild in criticism or feedback or
something's difficult to hear um uh experiment with uh being just rather
than closing down in a sense turning towards the person you don't have to do this physically literally but as if
you're stepping forward and kind of being available with Open Arms to hear tell me more um turn towards the person
and rather than away and and um you know and this this uh uh expression tell me
more is a powerful and effective way of
um disarming people when necessary and a powerful way of learning more fully may be what we need to
hear so thank you and um May may we all be good listeners
today