so welcome [Music] welcome so today I'm going to continue
this exploration of poetry and practice and this has been such a rich
uh Endeavor for me some of you know that I'm certainly not trained in the Arts
I'm trained as a scientist so I come to this appreciation of poetry laid in life
and and so not as a scholar or anybody that's you know done any
um formal training or investigation but I just want to share like this
person's understanding interpretation of them
so and I like to use poems that have a lot of imagery because there's a way at least
for me that this uh imagery um it does it it touches us differently touches me
differently than just words than just uh something very
specific and explicit and to be sure I appreciate all
these different time different ways in which we can communicate and
share what's going on with us as individuals or ideas opinions
views but po poetry has this
distillation this of this pointing that I find really meaningful and
impactful and today's poem has a real gritty quality to it it's not all
beautiful and I mean I think the poem is beautiful but the content and I chose
this today partly because that's the truth of The Human Experience some sometimes it feels
gritty sometimes there are rough spots sometimes there are difficulties like
real difficulties and for me I think part of the practice the beauty of the
practice is to invite those parts of our experience
in not to just wash over them and pretend they don't
exist so well that is a short little introduction let's do a guided
meditation and I'll do a little bit of guiding get it get us settled and then
I'll drop in the poem and just a reminder with this poem
you don't have to do anything with it just allow it to touch you and maybe it
touches you and maybe it doesn't and that's okay how however we receive these
is perfectly fine perfectly fine
okay so maybe taking a big exhale as I find myself doing as I start
to settle in and with this
exhale can be a sense of Letting Go sense of a settling
in the neuroscience just tell us that these large exhales activate the
parasympathetic nervous system which is a way of you know this relaxing and
soothing so perhaps what we've been doing naturally the scientists are catching up and telling us it's good for
us
and then bring attention awareness to the experience of This
Moment The Experience includes how we what formation this body
is in how we're situated in space more specifically
the activity of sitting literally or
figuratively taking a meditation posture meditation
stance and how does it feel at this moment to be in this
configuration right now
some things that might be obvious is the pressure against the
body where the body is in contact the chair the cushion
the ground couch bed whatever it might
be feeling the pressure on our
feet as we're in contact with the Earth ground our legs if we're
sitting the
butex the back if you're leaning on a chair
maybe there's a very slight pressure of the hands that they're resting on or if
they're touching that if the two hands are
touching each
other
doing a broad sweep of the body noticing if there are obvious
places of tension tightness
contraction and just resting the attention
there
it might be that the simple bringing attention to areas with
tension allow the tension to dissipate let go
soften and maybe not there's no guarantees
but can we invite into our experience whatever is
happening in those areas of tension or tightness without insisting that they be
different but creating the conditions in which something different
might arise
bringing a quality of curiosity and care to the
attention
and noticing that the body is
breathing resting Awareness on the sensations of the body body
moving while it
breathes alternatively some of you may be resting attention on the feeling of the cold and
warm air going in and out of the
nose
right now there's nowhere else to
be there's nothing else to do we are just here now with the
experience of
breathing
can we bring a quality of care and
warmth to our
experience as if this mattered what we're
doing as if it were
important not in the sense that it has to be done but in the sense that it's
valuable
inhabiting this experience being
embodied not thinking about it or looking at it but
experiencing the sensations of
breathing
it wouldn't be surprising if the Mind wandered away we
don't have to make it be a problem we don't have to make a story about what that means
we just very simply gently begin again with the sensations of
breathing
what would it be like to give yourself
over to being with the
breath letting all other experiences being in the
background while in the
foreground is the sensations of inhales and
exhales
so I'm going to drop in a
poem there's nothing that you need to
do with this poem just allowing it to be
received you don't have to try to make sense of it evaluate it analyze
it just allowing it to
land in your
experience the PO goes like
this there's a bluebird in my heart that wants to get out but I'm too tough for
him I say stay in there I'm not going to let anybody see
you there's a bluebird in my heart that wants to get out but I pour Whiskey on
him and inhale cigarette smoke and the  and the bartenders and the
grocery clerks never know that he's in
there there's a bluebird in my heart that wants to get out but I'm too tough
for him I say stay down do you want to mess me
up you want to screw up the works you want to blow my book sales in
Europe there's a bluebird in my heart that wants to get out but I'm too
clever I only let him out at night sometimes when everybody's
asleep I say I know that you're there so don't be
sad then I put him back but he's singing a little in there
I haven't quite let him die and we sleep together like that with
our secret packed and it's nice enough to make a man weep but I don't weep do
you
I'll read this poem
again there's a blue in my heart that wants to get out but I'm too tough for
him I say stay in there I'm not going to let anybody see
you there's a bluebird in my heart that wants to get out but I pour Whiskey on
him and inhale cigarettes smoke and the  and the bartenders and the grocery clerks never know that he's in
there there's a bluebird in my heart that wants to get out but I'm too tough for
him I say stay down do you want to mess me up you want to screw up the works you
want to blow my book sales in
Europe there's a bluebird in my heart that wants to get out but I'm too
clever I only let him out at night sometimes whenever everybody's
asleep I say I know that you're there so don't be
sad then I put him back but he's singing a little in
there I haven't quite let him die and we sleep together like that with our secret
packed and it's nice enough to make a man weep but I don't weep do you
[Music]
so this poem was called Bluebird by Charles P
Ki again it's called Bluebird by Charles
Bowski okay so welcome good morning good afternoon good
evening I'll start by reading this poem by Charles
Bowski called Bluebird I admit that I didn't even know
until last night that uh Charles Bukowski was actually a well-known poet this you know poetry isn't something
that I've studied it's more something that touches me on the and I save
poems and I heard this poem just recently and somebody was reading it and
I felt really touched by it and it wasn't until last night that I
discovered oh this Charles pukowski person is actually a really well-known
American poet so the poem goes like this it's called Bluebird by Charles
bukovski there's a bluebird in my heart that wants to get out but I'm too tough
for him I say stay in there I'm not going to let anybody see
you there's a bluebird in my heart that wants to get out but I pour Whiskey on
him and Inhale cigarett Smoke and the  and the bartenders and the grocery clerks never know that he's in
there there's a bluebird in my heart that wants to get out but I'm too tough
for him I say stay down do you want to to
mess me up you want to screw up the works you want to blow my book sales in
Europe there's a blue bird in my heart that wants to get out but I'm too
clever I only let him out at night sometimes when everybody's asleep I say I know that you're there so
don't be sad then I put him back but he's singing a little in there
I haven't quite let him die and we sleep together like that with
our secret pack and it's nice enough to make a man weep but I don't weep do
you wow for me remind say this is
Dua Dua and so many different levels right this this conflict between
this uh the speaker in this poem I don't know if it's
autobiographical I imagine it is that has this tough exterior he talks
about how he's too tough and too clever and but yet he also has this sensitive
tender vulnerable emotional core that he's struggling to
protect and this real separation between what this
individual is showing the world being a tough guy and what's being experienced
inside some vulnerability or happiness right often we think about
bluebirds with they're the bluebirds of Happiness so we might imagine that this
person kind of like uh earned his living as a poet is kind of this gritty uh misanthropic kind of
character but really maybe there in was inside was
something that didn't quite align with what was being presented to the exterior and what was being presented as being
appropriate for his uh view of himself his
identity it's also a reminder for all of us that those individuals who seem to be
tough on the outside maybe even ourselves sometimes to have a gentler
tender side inside at least I want to believe this I
don't want to believe that people are just you know through and through of this
uh roughness about them we might say that the Dharma is
this part of the path of uncovering these positive qualities inside of us and then this
path of uncovering ing these in some ways we meet all the difficulties of our life difficulties
that are in our minds right the ones that we make up and everything that seems to obstruct or get in the way of
aligning with or discovering or finding our way with
experiencing the beauty the tender the vulnerability the emotional aspects of a
human experience so this poem has this refrain there's a
bluebird in my heart that wants to get out sometimes we ourselves have refrains
things that are we repeat to ourselves stories about ourselves stories about um
what it means to be us and I'm using this word stories not to be pejorative or to say that they're not true but to
maybe highlight that there's a way in which they're fabricated there's a way in which we are um creating them based
on experiences we've had but they are created nevertheless that is they aren't
expressing this some inherent truth about
ourselves so this reframes these things that we repeat to ourselves and this
poet here he's writing there's a bluebird in my heart heart that wants to get
out it's very powerful this maybe tenderness or things
that we feel like are inside of us but somehow we don't know how to get in touch with or Express or incorporate
into a view of ourselves but something I want to highlight here is that the poet or the
speaker in this poem is making a real distinction
between himself I'm assuming it's a masculine
person and what's inside like there's this Bluebird
inside and then maybe there's this rough exterior outside and this is part of what the
dooka of The Human Experience to is like thinking that or breaking up our
experience into like sub parts that somehow are like in conflict with one
another like this part of me wants that this other part of me wants this other
thing but part of Dharma practice is is this integration like integrating I mean
this wholeness and discovering that maybe
there isn't these different aspects these different parts to this entity to
this being but more there's just different
experiences without having to create identities and sub identities without having to say you know there's this
Bluebird character that's different than this other character instead we might say that oh
there's moments of vulnerability there's moments of tenderness there's moments of
sadness there's moments of singing this blue bird there's also moments of being
too clever moments of being too tough the moments of
hiding things from other people in our life maybe even hiding them from
ourselves and there's this way like one way it's kind of this um sub characters
that get created often is an inner critic of ourselves and that's kind of like help creating this divide between
these different aspects and then this poem The speaker is saying to this
Bluebird you stay in there I'm not going to let anybody see you stay down do you want to mess me
up I know that you're there so don't be sad this is a way in which sometimes you
know the inner critic we speak to ourselves with a sense of
harshness a sense of you know somehow you're inadequate or inappropriate in
some way ouch ouch this is Dua this is really
dooka and then sometimes our activities you know the way that we show up in the world is an expression of this I'm using
the word inner critic there's so many different ways we might consider this but in this poem The Poet is saying he
pours Whiskey on him and inhaling cigarette smoke and only let him out
sometimes but I haven't quite let him die
so these activities that the speaker of this poem is using about uh pouring whiskey and cigarette smoke and not
quite letting them die there's these ways of kind of like squashing down like
maybe this a certain aspects of his experience the tender happy vulnerable
side but there's also ways in which can do things that aren't so obvious as
drinking and smoking and other things that are unhealthy for
us but there's a way that we can use spiritual practice
itself as a way to avoid our inner life
we use these spiritual ideas and practices to sidestep some of our unresolved
emotional issues for example I love Jack cornfields expression and this
unfinished business of the heart some of these wounds that we
have so there's a way in which we might using this practice that's supposed to help us you like integrate and become
whole with all of our experiences but we actually use it as a way to avoid working with what's so difficult
there's a way in which we can disconnect from our feelings or not look at the big
picture or Shield us from the truth because we're just being mindful of each moment or reading the next Dharma book
or something like this to be sure there's nothing wrong with spiritual practice in fact you know I would
support such a thing but it's sometimes the way that we use
it to not be in touch with the grittiness of Our
Lives kind of chose this poem because the grittin is like so obvious we don't
have to work very hard to imagine
it and to be sure like working with spiritual practice is better than some other defense mechanisms better than uh
drinking whiskey and smoking cigarettes I don't know exactly when this poem was written but I'm imagine I know the poet
was born in 1920 so you know maybe 1950s 60s 70s I'm not
sure but I'd like to end with a maybe a um a challenge a
query what if they're actually is no
Bluebird and no tough
exterior what if we just put down stop the reification of these entities of
these experiences and it's just this
experience and and then this experience and then this experience what if life is
just a collection of experiences and of course we want to make meaning out of our experiences but
is there a way that we kind of are trapping the bluebird inside trapping having this rough
exterior that can only be rough by creating the these entities with what
are just in fact experience expences one after the other maybe these creating
personas or characters is
extra and is part of what is
Dua so the way to happiness is not to finally let the bluebird out to not
finally let go of the toughness or the roughness the way to happiness is to
kind of like let the bluebird and the roughness
integrate maybe the bluebird and so much not doesn't want to get out doesn't want to escape this uh character instead it
just wants to
integrate so I leave you with some of these thoughts with this poem Bluebird by Charles Bowski
thank you and I'm wishing you a wonderful day thank
you