okay so let's go ahead and get started
we'll sit together as usual so finding
a posture where you can be upright and also relaxed
closing the eyes if that is okay for you
we would generally favor having the eyes closed in these kinds of meditations
and just allowing the attention to come inward
sensing from the inside what it's like to be sitting
or standing or lying down whatever posture you're in
maybe taking a couple of long slow deep breaths
really filling the lungs and then on the exhale just
allowing the body to soften letting the air
go really all the way out
just allowing the breathing to become natural again
and touching into the place where you're sitting your seat
against the chair the cushion the bench whatever you're lying on
and feeling the contact that's supporting you
can really get a sense of the groundedness of the body
the stability of where you're sitting
the way the body is somewhat similar to what it's sitting on
Earth sitting on Earth
and then senting into the body itself
the structure of the body is supported by the skeleton the bones
I'm just sensing maybe the
the bones as you're sitting so you can feel the sit bones and the spine
okay perhaps you feel the shoulders
maybe the shoulder bleeds against the back of the upper back
down into the arm bones and the hands resting somewhere on each other or on
the thighs
solidity of the legs and the feet there's a structure
to this body particular shape
and infrastructure
regardless of our state of health there is this
internal structure
you can imagine the body in its meditation posture
as a mountain a mountain that can't be swayed even by
strong winds
this is the Earth element
the quality of solidity of hardness of literal strength
that's naturally present it's not something we're creating and so we're
just tuning into that dimension of the body of the
physical experience
and as we said still like the mountain we can connect also now with the
sensations of the breath like a gentle breeze flowing across the
face of the mountain the breath the body
together
connecting with the present moment
this energy of Earth Earth Energy that can support
persistence in the mind
so we aim to stay gently connected with the present you know through our normal
mindfulness practice maybe a bit longer than usual
without any push or forcing just with the natural strength of the
Earth Energy in the body let me apply a little bit of persistence
the way the Earth inexorably stays in contact with
what is touching it
we can sense the strength of the Earth element
it's a strength that has no aversion in it no
coercion in it it's just there
like the strength of a mountain
and we sit with the breath with the body
with whatever thoughts and emotions are there
willing to be with that
we can rest in this centeredness
as we stay with the flow of experience
it all flows across and through and around
the Earth element of our sitting posture so sitting now quietly for a little
while
thank you
foreign
into a world of its own creation
we can feel the ungroundedness of that
and return our attention to the simple presence of the body sitting
the Earth sitting on Earth and feel how that re-grounds the mind
and brings up a sense of Persistence of staying in the present moment
as we stay with the quality of the Earth element in the
background of our meditation the fruit of this is moving toward
equanimity the sense of balance
acceptance being able to be with anything Pleasant or unpleasant
without getting thrown off kilter so sensing into that
deep presence that is not swayed by
experience the Equanimity of Earth
so now broadening the attention to include the whole body
as well as the emotions the thoughts maybe letting the attention still with
the eyes closed extend out farther into the room
hearing the sounds around you
just having this sense of centeredness
more balance I'm considering what a gift this is
when we can carry this around with us throughout the day
so easy out in the world to become ungrounded
we're reading things on the Internet or getting caught up in the events of the
day and sometimes even just one person being
connected with the Center of their being being grounded with their feet on the ground
can influence a whole situation a whole interaction to be more grounded
more connected so the cultivation from this practice
today we hope will have some positive effect
in the world as we carry the energy of Earth with us
as a gift are more than helping just us it can
radiate out and be of benefit to many beings even in
ways that they don't feel consciously
but it's there supporting them
maybe so
okay sorry about that video image I think I fixed that
um so now today
this week we've been talking about flavors of the Dharma
so the Paulie and Sanskrit term is Rasa
which could also be translated as a saver and it's meant to be the emotional tone
of uh often a work of art um but it can be extended into the realm
of spiritual teachings and people who are familiar with
culture in the era of the Buddha would have understood these rasas and so in
the case of spiritual teachings this flavor is you know more specifically something that would support the
Eightfold Path and you see these in the uh in the sutas
so we're picking out some of these flavors and highlighting them this week so yesterday was love or Compassion or
care and today is quite distinct from that and equally important so it's the tone
of energetic engagement and persistence which is sometimes even called heroism
in the Indian world and the poly term for this is Viria and
the Buddha talked about it a lot this quality is named in the most lists
more so even than mindfulness um probably there's no way to read the
sutas honestly and not get the message that Viria is important
so this quality of energy or effort or
the flavor of heroism has several different dimensions
it's not just one thing it's kind of multi multifaceted
so one of them we talked about a little bit in the meditation which is persistence or perseverance it has to do
with not giving up with being steady and ongoing
sometimes we can have an energy in our practice of being on and off
you know we're on to it for a while and then off where we sit for a while you know a
week or two we're good at sitting and then we're kind of not into it for a
month things like that so this quality of virio when that comes in it it brings a
consistency and a steadiness and an ongoingness to the way that we practice
and then another another dimension is confidence
so that doesn't mean that we always feel self-confident this practice has many
changes in that area but nonetheless it's clear that we're not going to put
energy or effort into something that we have no confidence in you know if you if you don't have any
confidence that um I don't know uh Pink Elephants are
going to help you in your practice you won't put energy into trying to find a
pink elephant something like that so you know we have to have some sense that mindfulness is helpful for us the
cultivation of meta is helpful being present even when things are difficult is helpful that will help us put energy
into those practices so this sense of confidence
and then um there's also the dimension of
self-control or self-mastery in a positive way so we one of the first
insights people often have in practice is while my mind is really crazy you
know when you first sit down doing mindfulness practice we realize oh you
know I'm trying to stay on the breath and I can't even do it for one breath wow this is how my mind is and hopefully
we continue beyond that and keep doing the practice but there's a an element of
Viria is that the mind has become somewhat tamed somewhat trained it's not running all over
as we have more of Beria in our practice and there's also a way in which life
becomes more purposeful you know we're clear on what we're doing even if we
don't have a grand plan Grand aim maybe it's even better not to have that sometimes there's a sense of doing what
we need to do at this moment having a larger picture of wanting to be ethical in the world things like that those
those are also qualities that come in as this with this flavor of varia or
heroism or energy so various images you know superhero images
in the Good Sense Rosie the Riveter things like that
um the suit has talk you use words like um striving
being unremitting and generating Zeal for our practice again all in a in a
good way um one of the chapters of the dhamapata has a lot of verses that glorify heroic
efforts so I thought I'd read a couple of those just so we get a sense of how this sounds and the teachings
Glory grows for a person who is energetic and mindful pure and
considerate in action restrained and Vigilant and who lives the dhamma
through effort vigilance restraint and self-control the wise person can become
an island no flood will overwhelm so
you know there is that side of it and it can be an ideal you know that we can
look toward not not always achieve but it's a useful kind of energy
um and yet I when I looked across many sutas I found that there's actually also a
range about how much of effort is needed at a given time so it's not that we're
supposed to put out maximum effort at all times it's more nuanced than that so
I wanted to offer a few examples that convey the range of this flavor of
heroism in the teachings can be helpful for us in trying to navigate the
different changes in our practice so there is we have to acknowledge there
is the support for strong effort so about the the Buddhist Quest own
quest for awakening there was a time when he made this declaration I know some of you have heard this
gladly would I let the flesh and blood in my body dry up leaving just the skin
tendons and bones but if I have not attained what can be reached through human effort human persistence human
striving there will be no relaxing my persistence
from this heatfulness of mine was attained Awakening from this heedfulness of line was attained the unexcelled
freedom from bondage so that was the Buddhist declaration now
he was ripe he was ready sitting under the Bodhi Tree clearly we're not expected to do exactly
that but on the other hand were not expected only to relax and accept which
is sometimes what we're taught just relax just accept just be with everything don't try to change anything
um and that's good for those of us who are kind of a little too
[Music] a little too striving in our way of approaching
um but we may think of times in practice when we have deeded strong effort
there may be times when strong physical Sensations comes strong emotions come
and we have to bring forth a lot of strength and attention to meet those mindfully
or we might be caught up in a powerful wave of sleepiness and torpor and a lot
of effort is needed to stay present if that's our you know that's our aim to stay present we may need to bring up a
lot of energy to meet that so what the Buddha is quoting in that quote I I understand is very extreme and
I I worry a little bit when I see people kind of moving toward that on retreat but we can't deny that the suitcas
really do support strong effort at times on but moving through this range there's
also a suta that explicitly talks about being very careful to balance our effort
so there's the uh the Sona suta story of Sona who is a monk who has been doing
such vigorous walking meditation that his feet are bleeding and he's walking
and walking and walking and then he gets discouraged of course because he's trying too hard and so the Buddha gives
him a beautiful teaching about tuning his effort the way we would tune a musical instrument like a stringed
instrument so if the strings are too tight then we can't practice well and
the instrument doesn't sound good if the strings are too loose the instrument can't be played either so we need
something that's just right in tune just the amount of right amount of tension on the strings so that the instrument is in
tune and playable in the same way when we have the right amount of effort in the mind we're neither overly aroused
nor overly slack in the language of the suta then the mind can reach stability it can become concentrated
um there's also an image of a Goldsmith working to purify gold and there are
times when he has to sprinkle water on at times when he has to heat it up and times when it's better just to look on
because it's good as it is but there's always this tending to it and keeping it
in balance and in the same way as we work to refine our mind a time time to time we
emphasize concentration or effort or Equanimity or acceptance different things at different times
so we have to kind of keep Vigilant and tune our energy and effort to keep to
the task at hand so then moving you know continuing to
move through this range there is a time for no effort at all
so consider this interesting verse from the sutanipata one Insight is that effort is the basis
of all suffering the other Insight is that by the complete Cooling and cessation of effort
no more suffering is produced every form of suffering grows out of
effort eradicate effort and no more suffering is produced wow how about that so
um this is not a teaching for all time um we do need effort
but the passage is talking about a particular point in practice where the mind has become so still
that any movement creates some kind of tension some kind of strain
so in when the mind is in a state like that it has to let go of intention itself it has to surrender completely
any form of effort so it might be that relax and accept is the deepest instruction
but that we don't get there until we practice for a while
so we have a path that goes from persistence and strong effort maybe
toward letting go as another aspect of effort
so we have also from the dhamapata absorbed in meditation persevering
always steadfast the wise touch Nirvana the ultimate rest from toil
so by persevering we touch the ultimate rest from toil
interesting there's another Suitor that says perseverance leads to happiness
so again we have effort leading toward ease effort leading toward happiness and
can we feel that in our practice maybe it's kind of like riding a skateboard we we push or we won't go
anywhere we have to get on the skateboard and then YouTube forward and push but at some point it's appropriate
to Coast and then we might have to push again later but it's kind of how it goes
um so it can take heroism in our practice to stay with challenging experiences we
don't want to fight against them we will probably hopefully learned that that doesn't work so well but we don't want
to crumple in the face of strong experiences either the job of a hero is
to meet the meet the moment to meet the situation um so there's that balance don't fight
but don't crumple the attitude of heroism can also get us
out of slumps or periods of complacency or practice is feeling stagnant or like
it hasn't changed much for a few years maybe it will help to make a a clear
resolution or to look more deeply or to ask a key question alter our habits in
some way which takes some persistence um
sometimes heroism is about really doing something radically different go on a long retreat
drop everything and go practice for three months who knows
um so something wholehearted I think there's a wholeheartedness to this
quality of area whatever wholeheartedness looks like at that moment being fully there with your
experience meeting it clearly and strongly and meeting it with acceptance backing off and surrendering
but there's a wholeheartedness so that's the flavor of today Viria
energy heroism [Music] it has so many wonderful uses and I hope
it will be a it's a beautiful exploration for you thank you