so I came down here today much more interested in hearing from you than
hearing from myself so what I thought would be nice to is they hear if you have any questions or
any concerns that are up for you and that we want to kind of look at through uh Buddhist practice lens
and um and then if there's no questions at all that's going to be risky for you
because because then I'm going to ask you a question
so you'll protect yourself if you ask questions
if you could use your mic it's nice if you do a new answer ask if you would say your name first so just so we get to
know each other a little more
yes I would not surprised Alex you're up in the front here no
no I was just saying oh oh oh you often have you know
you often have questions but we won't put you on the spot
so I have a practical question name Elaine mccreight
do you have any Insider tips
do you have any Insider tips on how one gets to attend a residence a retreat at
IRC how any insight about how you get to
attend the Retreats at IRC well there's um oh I can tell you the secret
how to manage to attend it so there we have a retreat center in Santa Cruz that
holds about 40 retreatens and one of the heartbreaking things for me is how many
people end up on the waiting list for those Retreats and don't get in and I really feel bad about it because you
know it would say I don't take lightly people's intention to come on retreat and um
and uh and there's a lot of people maybe it's even their first interest to be on retweets who don't can't come because
it's such a long waiting list and then they lose interest or get discouraged and don't apply again or something
so but it's the nature of it so some Retreats we've had before the pandemic we had some retweets there were so many
people applied that we could have put on six Retreats and you know it was like 260 people applied or something
so um and now it's dropped now considerably since the pandemic no so now there's only about 180 or something
so um so uh
so uh we're trying to we try to address this in various ways one is the wish to
have a second Retreat Center so we can accommodate people more and the other is um so the secret you
know if they get in the secret is that it's a lottery
and if you don't get in in on the uh the first time you apply in the lottery then
the next time you apply the computer remembers you and you have two tickets for the lottery
the next time you apply if you didn't get in you have three tickets and the next time you don't get in you
have four tickets the computer doesn't give you a fight anymore tickets however
uh there's it pops up on the roster that
this person has four tickets or sometimes they have four plus so maybe that's what it says four plus
and so um and so then if we have four you know four plus or something then we
see what we can do to kind of work the system for you to kind of
bypass the lottery or something and um so that's just keep applying but you
can't work the system you can't apply to every Retreat to get a lot of tickets because if you get accepted to a retreat
that you can't do uh then you start over again at zero tickets
so you can't you know just try to work system uh just only apply for Retreats
that you can do and that's you know So eventually you'll get accepted so I'm
very apologetic that it's that difficult and you have to try so many times and but if you persist that it will and it's
difficult for some people some people can't persist their life changes their work changes and so to be able to be
free and plan ahead is hard so I I feel very apologetic and
so thank you may I add a related question so
um I have done and and really feel grateful for the um online Retreats I've
done so I'm sure it varies enormously but could you sort of what's your sense of
the the depth of both the residents and the
online Retreats oh I love online Retreats this is a one of the great uh
gifts of the pandemic when we couldn't do uh residential Retreats and we started we offered a lot of online
retweets here and before the pandemic if you had said like you're you know
you're going to be on YouTube or you're going to be you know these online Retreats you know I kind of like didn't
believe in them I'm a little bit of a Luddite or you know you know having computers look I have a like now and I I
used to sometimes if I brought an iPhone or phone into the Dharma Hall I'd hide it from people
and a little bit hiding it behind the Bell but you know it's it's like you know I think last time I was here I even
pulled it out to read a quote so things have changed and um and so one
of the things that happened in the pandemic is that uh I learned how profound these online Retreats are and I
think they're really significant I feel like what I learned from during doing many of them it's kind of the Missing
Link in our in our practice world because some people go and retreat
and they have certain significant level of experience on Retreat and but they don't learn really
how to apply that are integrate into their lives and it becomes a split between Retreat practice where they have
certain depths in everyday life where they go home and they're just I don't know
they're business as usual at home and but when people did online reads
most people practice from home and even sometimes with family members or housemates in the house
and and so learning how to harmonize with home life learning how when there's a Plumbing Leak there's you know that
you have to call the plumber during the retreat and how do you do that how do you take the trash out so it's part of
the retreat how do you um and it was it was fascinating at the the beginning of the online retreats
to have all these things that took people away from their home
you know out of the practice in a sense so for example there'd be someone a family member somewhere else was having
some crisis and they had to go to the hospital or there were family members in other countries they were having challenges and they had to address it
that they probably wouldn't have done if they were in person at the retreat center and I just delighted and felt oh The
Retreat just got bigger and I told people you're not leaving the retreat you're taking the retreat with you and
you're expanding what we understand Retreat practice to be for all of us that now you're you know taking care of
someone in India or taking care of someone in the hospital or your neighbor or you're taking care of the plumber who
comes you're practicing with that and so so that's the missing link so the people who practice at home got a sense of what
it's like to engage in some serious kind of presence mindfulness care compassion
love with the life at home and harmonize their practice with life kind of in home
in a way that they didn't really figure out how to do by going on Retreat away and then coming
back so I strongly encourage home Retreats and the other thing I know I was
surprised by there were some people who did uh their very first Retreats was online
and I thought well how's that going to work you know their home there's no they're on the example of the other practitioners on a retreat and I don't
know well they have the discipline and it was phenomenal the discipline people had and how much people gave themselves
to it wholeheartedly and I was so inspired by people's intentionality and
dedication and how transformed they were so that's the other it may be secret
if you don't get into IRC Retreats don't worry just do the online retreat
it's those are much easier to get into thank you
to bounce off of that question and and I certainly really uh concur the online
Retreats were tremendous but you were one of the few people who offers them some of the other Retreats
we don't have online and I know you have to have practice leader discussions and
things like that is it possible to give this talk to some of the other teachers that you just gave us because
to let them know how how important and beneficial the online Retreats are great
so our ability to offer online research right now what we do we don't we don't really offer on anymore online Retreats
that are only online Retreats what we're offering now is hybrid Retreats and so we're offering
um uh what that means is that there's an in-person Retreat and the same time it's
being broadcast for the people who are on the online version of it and then we have the the teachers that are teaching
in person are not offer are giving the teachings for everyone online and in
person but the the um uh the practice discussions that
happened one-on-one with a teacher or in a group setting with a teacher uh it's a separate teacher who's not there who
offers the group back discussion individual practice period for the online people so that's what we're doing now so the
issue there's two issues that we have with offering more one is
in order for us to offer more of these online Retreats we have to have more service leaders everything is run by
volunteers and we're actually stretched to the Limit with uh and probably more
than we should in in uh in the available volunteer efforts we have fantastic
volunteers of service managers and tech people and at the retreat center for cooks and managing and so it's amazing
with what we have and the Goodwill that they carry on their volunteer work and helping everyone but we have a limited
number and so we can't we can't offer all the Retreats we want because we don't have
the resources people resources for it so that's one and then the other thing which is so maybe
um influences a little bit is that and this is kind of difficult to say and
awkward for me or uncomfortable for me in many ways so I so you'll see me
uncomfortable kind of and that is that people want to sign up with Retreats
that I'm doing not so much for other teachers for online that we have great teachers but then if we don't have
enough people signing up then it just kind of doesn't quite work or or the service leaders are not as interested in
volunteering for the other teachers so that's kind of sad and bip is very human I guess that
there's that kind of issue going on and so it's so both those issues if they can be addressed then we'll try to offer
more so
the other way you can get into Retreats at IRC if you're able to another Secret is uh if you're if you uh can be
available the last day or very close to the beginning of the retreat like the few days before
um by that time very few people can be available at sort of notice so we'll go through the waiting list very fast so
you could be like 120th in the waiting list and sometimes get in if you're able
to get in you know keep your calendars clear but you know it was no guarantee so so
it's you know it's that's awkward to keep your calendar clear but then not get in
Conrad good morning everyone my name is Conrad
I don't know if I have a question I'm going to explore something out loud with everyone but what's been on my mind and heart is loneliness
and I just graduated from the imc's chaplaincy program and I've been working
across the street and uh in assisted care living with a
group of people and there is a deep need for connection um this is what's kind of going on in my
life and I had a friend commit suicide last week and I think what's on my heart is engage
Buddhism and I think there's this tendency for us to want to kind of Chase
Enlightenment or awaken States and I think this is good I I kind of
want to make a pitch and see if there's anyone who's actually interested in I might say volunteer network to go and we
can just read to the elderly um those who have dementia just sit with them
answer the opportunity for us to practice engaging with aging sickness and death
three of our greatest teachers in Buddhism right I think there was a question originally here but I'm kind of pitching it out
loud as I'm talking about it um because of that need that's what's on my heart so I'm just kind of curious
you don't have to raise your hand you could come afterwards and chat with me if there's something you might be get interested in engaging with
um I'll wait and show it afterwards but that's what's on my heart I want to share with the song guys so thank you
all anyway thank you Conrad very much and uh I like to say that uh
that the art of this of this yes yeah
that um I mean this is kind of like a dream come
true that you would just uh interested in this and interested to see what this comes out of our community that people
would do that kind of Engagement and bring their practice into the world that way and um so that's just you know fantastic
it's an important part of what I've wanted us to be about but uh the um and I've kind of been
waiting a little bit for people to come and and do this because there's a limited amount how much it can come or
should come from the leadership here at IMC and um so to have it come out of the
community it's much better and part of the art of this is uh to let it be an
inspiration and generosity and love that someone people want to do and not to be
obligation not to be a should but rather really feel that inner inspiration to do
this kind of Outreach into the world and that's my hope that as people practice deeper and deeper and go and Retreats
and things like that that it becomes more and more natural to start living in the world with this generous spirit this
compassionate spirit and and that we will be agents to change the society Society we know it needs to needs
dramatic changes in so many different ways and there's way too much poverty and racism and oppression and
discrimination and and um because you know the political divisiveness and there's all these
issues that we should be addressing and um and one of the ways that you know
there's a number of things we are the number of things we are doing at IMC that comes out of IMC but they're done
kind of quietly and um and like one of them is we have a chaplaincy program training that
Conrad's has just finished that's why he's you know he did kept did his training and now he's
and because he did that he got invited across the street at the nursing home there to come and care for someone and
now he's coming that inspired him even more to do more of this and um so yes yeah
I love that idea and I would be happy to help but I do also have a question that kind of relates to the idea of Aging
so I recently my name is Amanda and I recently started to explore Buddhism and spirituality about eight
years ago when my dad died and I had a child so that was an interesting time in
my life and I've since then like really feared death and I've always tried to
figure out how to manage that and this idea of living in the life or living in the moment focusing on the now
but what's interesting for me is I have two experiences in my life that always
make me fear death more and the two things I love the most which is travel in the ocean so anytime I'm on a plane
or anytime I'm in the water I always think about dying and it's so overwhelming for me and I was just
wondering if from a Buddhist perspective you had any like approaches I could take in my mind in those moments because I'm
in the water I'm like shark shark shark shark and I know the chance is like so small and same thing on a plane I mean
there's a bump and I'm like this is it this is it and it's really bad if I'm alone so I fear getting on planes by myself
and in the water I always want my child to come with me because then I take on this motherly role and I'm not afraid because I'm protecting them
but just anything any suggestions you would have in terms of what I could say to myself in those moments so that this
idea of a death you know situation where it's not going to happen doesn't consume me so significantly
I love the question and I feel like I want to be careful how I answer it
so I don't know maybe I'll speak too much but let's see what comes out
um in in a number of languages including in in the Buddhist language Pali the word
for fear uh is uh very etymologically kind of linguistically
connected to the word for danger in my language that I grew up in Norwegian the the word English word fear
is related to the and the pronounce pronunciation Norwegian is
danger you know so and fear comes from the word danger and etymologically in Pali the
word Baya means fear but also in context means danger there are real dangers in this world
and to have some concern some fear around dangers in the world is probably
completely appropriate and the Buddhism has never said you're not supposed to be afraid like there's all these things
that Buddhism clearly wants to you to overcome greed hatred delusion make
that's supposed to be uprooted but there's no idea you're supposed to uproot fear
so there's a kind of the idea of respecting fear even have a reverence to fear
um I've lately I've been reading some people's idea of reverential fear that especially in terms of the the
natural world so a reverential fear of the ocean and um and then there's uh uh phobic
phobia of the fear which is very different and the the difference I think
is that one is out of respect uh the reverential fear is out of
respect for it and Care can I think of something important but then uh if it's an excessive kind of
horror at the dangers of the world that because we're so intimidated or so
fragile or Tender in ourselves then maybe it's time to look at
ourselves more and and so some fear of airplanes seems
reasonable to me some fear of being on the ocean I think is very reasonable to me I once sailed
on a sailboat across the Atlantic and the year before I knew for a year I was going to do that and um I would go I
would have a certain kind of reverential fear of doing that then I would actually go down to it was Atlantic but I went
living on the Pacific so I would go to the Pacific sometimes and have a little conversation with the ocean and
kind of prepare myself or address it or something and to be ready to go
and um and so so so one thing is to learn how
the appropriate fear how to just be a companion to let it be a companion and learn how to let it be on your left
shoulder and it come tags along and it just there to help help you be safe
um and it's the don't you know not it doesn't not a symptom of something that's necessarily wrong it might be a symptom of something
that's right and maybe even a deep deep kind of wisdom connection to the
natural world that there are dangers and we have to be respectful of them and find a way to live in harmony with them
but then if it's excessive fear uh that really paralyzes us then it's probably
something really deep we need to attend to in ourselves and and uh
and so it's appropriate to really spend time with your fear if you're able to
some people go into Panic some people with trauma Their Fear triggers them and worse and worse and so then it's helpful
to have support from others to have other people accompany you and help you
with the psychological tools to really be with the fear
and uh but if you're able to be with your so there's practice here is a practice not to avoid fear but to
practice in the middle of the fear if we have the right balanced middle way
to do that and um and so if you know look for
opportunities to be afraid this way take lots of plane trips alone and
uh and just and and sit with your eyes closed and really take in the fear
really be with it and if you have the tolerance the capacity to stay with it without spinning out then uh the task is
to help the fear feel safe and that's kind of counter-intuitive for
some people because you know the fear is just fear but if when it's when it's
kind of uh deep roots in our own fragility our own tenderness sometimes
it has to do with even sometimes our life experiences growing up or other times where we learn that somehow we uh
to have an excessive fear or reactivity to things that were dangerous and so to
learn and so to help the fear feel safe allows the fear to begin to relax but if
we're trying to fix the fear or solve the fear or psychoanalyze the fear it's not going to feel safe
so to look for an opportunity to have some of that fear maybe you know go find
a boat that's docked somewhere you know in the in the somewhere and just sit on
the boat and that's you know it's not going to go anywhere it's well moored maybe you feel safe enough but maybe
just enough of the fear comes up and then sit with a fear and and see what happens and
um and there might be layers and layers of of your emotions your beliefs your
attachments that are waiting to be discovered underneath that fear and you might find that the issue is not
the fear but the issue might be um the fear of the ocean it might be
that um you're afraid of dying but maybe you're afraid of the pain of
dying oh no it's going to be terrible drowning must be awful if it's not you're not afraid of being dead
but it's the how and so you know but even that opens a door for some people to kind of begin finding other
relationships to it or it's fear of leaving my kid behind I mean I think a
primordial fear of an of a parent is dying before the kid has grown up
and that's reasonable but um but then how do we learn to hold if you let if
you help the fear feel safe so it can be there then we can maybe learn to have the fear accompany us and not limit us
accompany us but not give a rise to anxiety fear but no anxiety fear but no
freezing up fear and no agitation
and um and then I think if we learn to have this wise relationship to fear then
by osmosis the people around us especially our children can feel oh this world is not such a scary place
where the parents are really scared all the time anxious all the time then at the very young age the kids learn that
this is this world is a dangerous place and they grow up anxious and the earlier they pick that up or any
of us pick this up in childhood that the deeper it's rooted in our hearts so that
you know then it takes a while for if you do use meditation practice to kind of get to the root of it it takes a
while to settle so that was a long answer you think that are you satisfied that answer is that
yeah you're satisfied okay good
my name's Caitlin uh I this will make my relationship sound a
lot worse than it is but I've noticed over time that while my husband and I
are still growing we seem to be growing maybe in different directions a little bit and I find more distance kind of
between us and I guess my question is how do we ensure that we still grow together at the same time
well I think the primary way is to be honest about it so be honest about it and find a way to
accept each other as you as you are and if you can't accept something to be
honest about that and find your way with that I'm a great believer in talking and being honest and exploring it that way
and but it's not but they're saying it that simply as I just did maybe
doesn't uh indicated that sometimes these
conversations are very difficult to have and not people might and very some people don't want to have those conversations and so what do you do when
the one of the parties doesn't capable those conversation doesn't want to do those conversations
and then you have to have this conversation in a stealth way
you know indirectly or or you have to figure out what what what does the other party need to hear or need need to relax
and to feel safe or feel heard or feel you know so that there can be some space
where a little bit of a truth-telling to go on and um
and sometimes if the other party doesn't want to grow and doesn't want to talk about something
um then sometimes the person who wants to grow it can be useful to go talk to a therapist there's a couple counselor and
really start looking at your what's going on for you because um I think one of the great tasks of any
relationship at least from a Buddhist point of view and is um how do you keep your heart completely
open regardless of what's happening to the other person and so that's a personal exercise and
there's a lot of challenges to that but I think Buddhist practice it's like let's say we're up let's let's be let's
be up to that challenge let me keep my heart open no matter what it doesn't mean that we don't set boundaries it
doesn't mean we don't say no it doesn't mean we don't take care of ourselves but to always have this orientation how do I
keep my heart open here and these challenges so that's the personal work that can be done
um so and then if you understand each other if you understand that if you both agree to
understand each other oh just the other thing is someone doesn't want to talk to you about their relationship what's going on then become a really good
listener offered to the other person what you wish you they would give to you
and so if and sometimes that's a stealth way just really listen and make sure
they feel it understood that they understood that they have been heard and then something sometimes can relax
in the other person that then they become interested in you so this so these are just ideas that may
or may not work but um I love that you're asking the question because this is a probably
important in many many relationships so is this satisfying enough now yeah yeah I'm not that satisfied with my
answer but but is it satisfying enough for now
you already thought about all these things yeah yeah well Ben is not satisfying
[Laughter]
thanks uh my name is Steve um and uh recently earlier this summer I
attended a retreat a three-week retreat in a different tradition in uh in a
Shambhala Tibetan tradition and which I found very interesting and
very useful and I was wondering if you could speak just a little bit about sort of mixing practices in different
Buddhist Traditions great thank you so I've done that I mean I don't I I my
first training was in Zen Zen Zen Japanese Zen I did that for many years
before as I found that became a foundation for me to do the vipassana practice so I benefited a lot from doing
both and so that's a that's not exactly mixing but it's how they work together
and um so uh uh
often if you've been in one tradition for a while if you go study with another Buddhist tradition or even other form of
spirituality religion even that it can help you then look back at
the practice tradition you've been in and see it in new ways and uh and some of it you might see how
beneficial it was you might see how it really works well and you might see oh you know that there are there are
challenges there for me that's maybe not quite right for me but there's a deeper understanding so I think I often like to
suggest to people if they even done a good number of years in one Buddhist tradition step outside for a little bit
do something else in order to get a better a better perspective of the
tradition you can come back to your tradition but you maybe have a richer better perspective of it
some some uh different the questions about different Buddhist Traditions right some Buddhist Traditions
complement each other um I think oh I think every Buddhist tradition every Buddhist center every
Buddhist teacher has strengths and weaknesses I don't can't imagine that doesn't work everywhere I mean in spite
of what people think and uh and so uh you know you take the
strengths that are there and benefit from them and if you feel there's a weakness it's you know then that's where going someplace else can complement
complement it so in our vipassana tradition we have a strong tendency to
um encouragement to practice with different teachers and I like to think of the different kind of Circle of
teachers as being a that's the whole package and um and so you want to go and
practice with different teachers because they have different ways of um different teachings different
strengths that they're offering and it's the total package that is nice not just always with one teacher
and um and so with different Buddhist Traditions as well and so I I've known people who have practiced here at IMC or
practice with the San Francisco Zen Center that they'll go to the other one and find it really beneficial some
people have done a lot of a pasta practice then gone to the San Francisco Zen Center because it's close by and
they found that practicing a community there in a semi-monastic setting was really a significant complement for what
we do here and I've known Zen students who have found the coming year was a really great compliment for what they
learned at Zen Center so there's all kinds of ways that they worked worked support each other and
work work and um and the one thing that I would warn about that is against bouncing back
and forth too much and especially if you're a new practitioner for someone who's relatively new to
practice I'd recommend that you you stay in one tradition like at least for in a
good strong way at least for a year because the the things that people are
working through the first year or so of Buddhist practice is kind of the same for everyone and it doesn't really
matter so much who you're practicing with and um but once you've worked through
the hindrances enough for your mind is learned to be not so distracted and so agitated and you're quieter and you have
some sort of inner connection to the Dharma now from practicing then it uh you have a different eye to
understand the different Traditions so after a year of practice you might come up surface and look around and check out
the different Traditions see which one feels like it really works for you is best for you
and you might decide who I'm staying here where I am or say oh that was great thank you but now I'm going to go do
something else so is that uh okay so will in the back
if you wait wait for the mic
hi I'm will um I was wondering um
how do you maintain hope in the face of an ever-changing world
how do you maintain a Hope and Faith in an ever-changing world it's a great
question um I mean Buddhism puts tremendous emphasis on the fact that we live in an
ever-changing world and uh and um
so one of the ways to do it is don't hold on to Hope and Faith
but take a very honest look at the hopelessness and the faithlessness
what is what where does that need for Hope and Faith come from in you
know what's the sense of Despair or anxiety or hopelessness what's really
happening deep inside because addressing that might be more important than
uh provide some people get hope and what they're doing is they're just putting a
they're laying it on top of their hopelessness and not really addressing the hopelessness it's kind of like and
for a while people get inspired they hear some wonderful teaching or someone that's the solution that's the hope but
they haven't really dipped down to what was going on deeper inside so that's at least in our tradition I
think the emphasis would be let's take a deeper look what's underneath there before you look for Hope and Faith
and and one of the remarkable things that can happen there is that let's I I don't know you well
enough to know if this it speaks for you but but just so just keep that in mind it's not a statement about you
but the um hopelessness and a feeling a sense of you know
faithlessness or deep doubt or something are not the absence of something
they are activities themselves they're mental actions that are happening the
mind is doing something to provide or the heart's doing something to well up a
feeling of hopelessness the mind the heart is doing something to have feel they have I have no faith in
anything it feels like there's an absence but that sense of absence or that sense of loneliness that Conrad
brought up or that sense of of um meaninglessness or that sense of uh you
know despair that people can have those are all activities of the mind there's energy there's activity doing
something and because it's an activity before it says it's Dynamic and a broad mental
process it doesn't have to be there it can be settled it can be it can be
addressed directly it could be uh you know as it feels safe as it feels
met as it feels understood and seen there's like with the fear
remarkably it can begin to settle and unravel so that as I like to say some of our
problems will not be solved they will be dissolved so something like a feeling of
hopelessness doesn't need to to discover something to have hope in
it turns out hopelessness itself can dissolve and then there's no need for hope
that's pretty radical isn't it so I'm not asking you if that was a
satisfying answer but it it it is my answer Intrigue you
I think what you said was true sorry I think what you said was true okay great so okay thank you
so I saw I think this person over here was first and then
hi um my name is favad um this has been such a beautiful question
asked I feel uh um I'm asking a very mundane question
um which is really um more about uh practice
um I've had attention deficit most of my life um and so I particularly struggle
as I meditate with concentration and and I tend not to be hard on myself about it
or any such thing I think I I'm good with it um but would still really
um appreciate if there is uh um if there are things that I could do to bring more concentration uh into the
meditation so sometimes even a half hour session I'll feel no more than a minute
or two uh of having been able to focus on the breath periodically I'll gently bring the bring
my attention back but concentration feels to me uh I can't speak for anyone
else's subjective experience more of a more of a challenge for me are there ways I can work on it so I think that's
a profound question thank you nothing mundane thank you and uh there's lots
lots of lots to be could be said so I don't know what would what to say to you that would meet your circumstance
but I'll try try to to say something that um it's it's a little bit
unfortunate that the word samadhi is translated into English as concentration because it's all too easy if we go with
the word concentration to think that they need to kind of like a have a laser focus on something and it's kind of a
mental kind of Act of kind of zeroing in kind of you know like maybe you know
there are times we have to do that in life but um so so it's that reinforces
the idea that that's what we're supposed to do in meditation the word uh samadhi
can can also kind of mean unification
and I like to think of samadhi as as the process of becoming whole
so if the task is to become whole as opposed to a task is to become zero like
a laser what does it take to become whole and um and how do we become whole so
that the mind is not jumping around distracting us from that hole because then we're as soon as we're
distracted we become partial we're not whole anymore so so one of the ways to become
concentrated is um in this in this holistic way is not
to focus on anything but to rest on it
so with the breathing rest on the breathing and or or to be even more kind
of specific and helpful maybe is um uh think of the um that as you
imagine as you inhale breathing is focusing on you is arriving and once there is making
contact with you and the exhale you offer you are you're offering yourself
to the breathing and you just rest with the exhale so receive the inhale and then just rest
there with the out tail and that's where the resting can be and then over time that resting might
begin opening up a little bit sense of wholeness sense of inclusion in the
experience and so then that sense of inclusion of the present moment begins to spread out to include more and more
and you have a feeling that everything's included and then when the mind starts going off
into its thoughts when there's kind of a strong sense of wholeness or inclusion it's like oh look at that the mind is
wandering off but I'm not wandering off the mind the mind is thinking but I'm
not living in the thought I'm not identified with it it's just oh and then it sometimes that you'll see the thought
just arise and you watch it you know come and you really have a clear sense of being a watcher or being clear
mindful of it and it just kind of dissolves it kind of like a cloud that dissolves in the sky because you're not
participating in it you're not feeding it and um so does that Intrigue you
definitely that was a quite helpful uh I do tend to I I think think of
concentration as the inhales and the exhales and that resting concept
really intrigues me thank you great thank you so it's it's kind of time to stop but I
saw a couple of people when asked a question so what I'd like to propose is that let's take a little you know even
just a two minute break if some of you are ready to leave now please and thank you for being here and if some of you
like to stay to continue this kind of the questions just maybe come up closer or just stay where you are and and then
we'll continue in about two three minutes or so so thank you everyone
so anybody want to ask a question yes please hi my name is pinja
um I have two questions and related so I if I heard it correctly I didn't know a
little bit louder the volume is here so oh okay if you hold it like this yeah um
so if I heard it correctly just now um there's no program for for high
schoolers yes there is there is yeah I see well I think I think there is
there's supposed to be uh we've had it for many years a team we call it teen program it's high school and I think
it's starting up again but uh you can ask Hillary she knows okay okay yeah so uh um this the second question is like I
have a teenager at home at a high schoolers so I do feel nice she has anxiety on like a GPA on staff you know
it's hard for me hearing to hear both that there and here I wonder if uh Lauren
or something
my hearing isn't what it used to be
yeah they they I think that's so you have a you have a high school student at
home yeah she has anxiety I think about GPA about college applications that so I
feel like um we we tried uh to net her um
and try to introduce this meditation or
this uh practice to harvest difficult difficult
for her to uh to participate so do you have any suggestion how can she benefit
from yeah how can she benefit meditation yeah you know this thing about
high school students aren't they high school students like a
different species I had two of them growing up through in
our house you know so so um I think it's hard what you're asking I think that it's very important how the
parents care for a teenager and uh and I
think uh I mean I don't know there's so many different teenagers so many different
psychological needs they have they need to be addressed and some of them need to be in therapy even and it's really
serious but it's hard to grow up in the society this Society does a lot of people a lot
of disservice and there's particular ways in which growing up locally in the
peninsula has a lot of different very unique stresses to it about success and
and um and what success is supposed to look like and getting ahead and
things so if the parents are relaxed
about and just love the person that clearly if the kid feels that what's that what's coming from the parents that
the parents just want them to be happy and accept them as they are and there's no need to go to college there's no need
to to get ahead and be a doctor or something but just find find what what
works for you and take your time and we will support you with that whatever you do and take a gap year if you know if you
would like to do that then really kind of relax from all this and get a better sense of what you want I think the
parents to convey that they're like that they're not tied in the parents are not tied into the popular culture about what
success means and what you have to do to be good and to just show that you will love the kid no matter what that
sometimes counts for a lot um and um
and then the other thing I I uh someone gave me advice when before my kids became teenagers he said
when when uh your kids become teenagers um uh they're hardly going to recognize
that you're home you're almost like you don't exist and but he said but that's not true
it's even more important that you stay home it's even because they'll it's even
more important that you're present because they are noticing somehow and uh and I noticed that with my my
littlest son when he was even quite young and um and uh oh sorry I learned the saying
recently that I thought it was really true and wish I had noted when I was a parent of young kids
adults want to be listened to young kids want to be seen
and um and so when I remember once when my kid was a little toddler
I think he could walk then but he was on the living room floor with me I was sitting next to him watching him and uh
he was playing with blocks and he was humming a little tune and after a while you know just sitting
there watching you know so I have things to do right so I thought well he doesn't need me
he's happy he's engaged he's humming so I got up to do something else he immediately stopped humming
and the fact that I was there watching him made a huge difference for him it was
meaningful for him but I thought he was couldn't care less that I was there he was ignoring me
so this idea that uh especially you know these kids are not paying attention they are paying attention deeply
in maybe deep more deeply than they know so so to be be present at home in a way
don't be distracted when you're home and be and even if they don't notice you're not distracted they're distracted
by their oldest technology be there and be available and uh my you
know my wife told me when my my sons were teenagers he's you know that it was
you know I didn't have much chance to talk to them I'd ask them questions at dinner and you know they're looking me
like I'm stupid and you know like if they weren't gonna you know I get one one word answers
how was school today good [Laughter] and my wife said oh you just have to be
around and just be around and available and at some point something comes out
so if for a daughter who's has a lot of anxiety I don't know when she's ready to
share but be available and she does yeah so I don't know so that I I can't
you know know your specific situation so I probably missed you but those are the
thoughts that come to mind very helpful action thank you
so so you had a hand before Kirk there
oh thank you my name is Kurt and Gil uh this was fantastic all these
questions and answers um and so my question relates to um
the woman that was sitting up there talking about growing away from I think that was when it came up your response
to her was uh along the lines of uh keeping your heart open
and so my question to you is can you give us some guidelines some suggestions
some ideas about how to keep our heart open because because
I need to hear some some of that great very nice thank you and um
so I'll offer you a principle that applies in many different situations like similar to what the question about
Hope and hopelessness is that Buddhism has a lot of ideals we live with a lot of ideals in our life
and so it's an ideal to have an open heart to everyone ideals can be oppressive
you know so you know you know like I'm supposed to do this and now it must be a good Buddhist I'm supposed to keep my
heart open and you know so so but the um the principle is ideals
are good to have as a reference point as a possibility it's an inspiration
but in mindfulness practice study what keeps you away from the ideal
go the go the other direction rather than living that rather than forcing yourself to be the ideal understand what
gets in the way and the principle with an open heart is it's then it's kind of
like the natural state of the heart is to be open we have to do something to close it down
and so if you understand how you close it that's the real work because that's
what's important to understand and and because then um when you open it you've done the work
that keeps it open uh if you use a crowbar to pry it open
uh first chance when the Crowbar goes away it's going to snap close again so it really understand what keeps it
closed so and then I you're next I think right
here and then over over there okay I'm sorry if I'm not doing it in order
go ahead hi I'm Amy and um I guess my question has to do with
um big change in your life and also um identity and I know in Buddhism
there's non-self and non-clinging and and also fear so I've had really big
changes in my life including moving and um
um I'm about to get married and um hopefully try to get pregnant so
there are all these things and um it's stirring up a lot of fear well some of
that fear is completely appropriate if you weren't afraid if you weren't
afraid I'd be afraid and it's all happening in a very compact
time frame and I feel like um I'm fighting there's the pressure or
stress of the thing themselves and then there's the second Arrow of me wishing I
wasn't feeling this way and feeling like I'm almost miserable and I
feel so much contraction and fear in my heart and
um I don't want to feel that and I'm it's also things that I've really wanted in
my life that when I take a step back and I'm calm I I feel good about them and
it's it's the path I'd like to be on I see I see and as part of your what you
call fear is part of it grief yes so you're grieving the loss of some
things including some of your dreams is that right Dreams yeah tell me your dreams some of
the things you really want in your life or no it's more that those things that I have wanted are happening and I think
the grief is the life I had just myself yeah so so there's a healthy way to
grieve and maybe that wanted a healthy way of Grieves is to spend some time
with the light that you've had like when my when my mother died a year
ago I spent time hiking in the Hills here thinking about our life together and my memories of her and and reviewing
it and if my mind drifted off got distracted by other things I'd come back to my mother and just I really stayed
focused on that and so maybe there's uh give you some quality time with your life as it's been appreciating it
remembering it crying about losing it maybe and understanding it more
maybe it also deserves a little ritual because when people get married they usually do a little ritual right I mean
some people just go down to the Courthouse which is a ritual maybe but
uh but if you could you know to agree to what you're doing at ritual to get to get married maybe do a ritual of Letting
Go or saying goodbye or offering your respect to the life you have to really have a there's a there's a way of saying
of there's a respectful healthy way of letting something go
or or moving on or saying goodbye to us and there's a healthy goodbye and some
people can't say goodbye you know if you know there's I've known people who they're gone
yeah I know they were leaving but they left before they had to say goodbye right
so say goodbye to your life and maybe you do it with some friends and talk about it and respect it and
don't have a bachelorette party I mean you can do that if you want but uh but that's not the same thing do
uh do a you know a respectful and and if you deal with your
grief that way the fear might be a lot easier and um and and uh and as I said some of
the fear might be appropriate it's actually healthy uh respectful fear well this is a big
deal there's a big responsibility this is not an easy thing to step into and um and a respectful fear appropriate
fear is one that inspires you to do your best the neurotic fear that gets in the way
is when you get Frozen or get caught and and reactive and if you can distinguish
healthy fear that inspires you in a certain way from that that doesn't then um maybe you the
fear doesn't have to be so problematic and uh and so you you know you're you're
afraid of the of the marriage and but you can know it's healthy to have some
degree of it so you can tell you're a partner today I have the fear of things back as opposed to feeling like oh there's a
problem here is this uh okay answer yeah it's very helpful I think sometimes
you wonder if you need to listen to the fear and just completely run
and I don't mean like the running bride away I just need fear is always a
message so I think it's always good to stop and listen to fear but uh don't run
unless it's a mountain lion well but you're not supposed to run from Mountain lines
this is then tall look at it and yeah and so um so um
the uh I think I I think of these these these kind of difficulty emotions fear
angry anger loneliness I like to see them all as Messengers and so we want to
listen and find out what's going on some deeper level and there's wisdom in fear as well
so and there's also
you know attachment and so part of the listening to something like fear or anger what's
the message sometimes it's the message about the world out there and what's going on but sometimes the message is is
that boy am I attached to something and I needed to find out what I'm attached to
so I don't know what your message is but okay if you run and don't get the message that's unfortunate
thank you
hi I'm mariksa and my question is more a practical one I'm recent like a meditation like like
this year and sometimes I find it difficult to like the gentlemen there to just be with
a breathing and I tend to have a monkey mind like a lot of thoughts
so what I've been trying to do is uh concentrate in one word like it means
nothing like one the number one yes so I don't know if there's a good technique
or I'm just like cheating like doing push-ups on my knees instead of doing it
all my toes uh but um I don't know if I if that's okay just
is it well is it I said helping you with it with the monkey mind it does like you know instead of content
internet instead of latching into the thought and going into the monkey mind just I started like doing one one
repeating it yeah yeah I think that's why I think that's a a great thing and then once you're settled
enough then maybe you can settle into the breathing because the the one is quieted the if it
quiets the monkey mind I think that's great I'll use the word here oh you're gonna have a okay so oh yeah okay I'll
finish this question and then we'll go outside the um the
um I use the word here when I'm here oh no h-e-r-e okay
um and so I'll use the word here for the same purpose man my mind is too busy and I can't
be present I just say here and then I rest here what's here and then that's that's works really great for about half
a second and and I'm happy for that half a second and then I'll say here again and then I
get three quarters of a second you know here and then eventually it settles down and
and I'm here so so that sounds good to me thank you yeah so do we have to we
talked about the family program so we have to make room for it so thank you all very much