foreign [Music]
and for those of us here locally and we're kind of in a low between storms
and maybe meditation practice for some of you is a lull between different kinds
of storms a kind of uh this Sabbath or
a sacred pause in the middle of busyness or
preoccupations so welcome
in Japanese Buddhism in Zen a monk is some especially a young Monk
is sometimes referred to by the title of an unsweet
u-n-s-u-i-un sui and it's a combination of two words
cloud and water and uh so it's kind of a maybe an
affectionate way of referring to a young monk who is to practice being like clouds and Waters
not offering any resistance to anything but kind of flowing freely and
reluctantly between things or around things or through things or
um that offers no resistance but also takes the path of least resistance to go
forward so uh it's interesting to take this as an
analogy or metaphor for what we do with our awareness when we meditate
that too there is a kind of way that using awareness being aware being
mindful is something we do
and so that while we do that we can cease stop quiet being involved
in all the other things that the Mind usually gets involved in
so it's interesting to you know settle the water of awareness onto breathing in
the body but then to notice that this to doing the activity of being
aware gets interrupted by things gets interrupted by our thoughts and our
preoccupations gets interrupted by our reactivity to
what's happening if we don't like it we don't or we really want it
and this interruption in the activity of being aware of being mindful
is to be noticed but then bring back the flow of awareness the flow of the water and just
kind of flow around recognize bump up against whatever is happening but just let let the awareness be like
water that flows around and comes back to the to the bottom of the lake the quiet
place of the lake in your body with your breathing being aware with your breathing
flowing with your breathing so maybe this metaphor is Meaningful
so to assume meditation posture
one that allows certain kind of feeling of aliveness in your body
whether it's repositioning your hands and arms so that they're not completely
passive but also not active
kind of alive even for some for as simple as turning
the Palms up to the ceiling if usually your palms are down can give a little bit of a liveness
so a sense of being vitality in the body
closing the eyes and then feeling whatever Vitality or
energy there is in the body even if you're mostly tired and
exhausted where in the body is there some
aliveness some vitality
and letting him taking a few long slow breaths expanding the body and expanding
into that place of Vitality
almost as if you can expand it
taking a few long deep breaths and relaxing
settling into the body
letting the breathing return to normal and the more held or tense the body is
the more difficult it is for the awareness to flow like water
the more things are kind of frozen frozen water
so as you exhale relax the muscles of your face
it might be helpful to drop your mouth open slightly
and then float it back together
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders softening
almost as if something is melting in the shoulders and flowing down below into the chest
down the arms
and relaxing softening the belly
a global softening of the body in the exhale
and for two or three breaths on the exhale relaxing the thinking mind
softening in the mind
quieting the thinking mind a bit
and then having your awareness
settle into the body breathing settle into how the body experiences
breathing
and the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out maybe can be seen as the undulations of
the waves on the ocean maybe a gentle rising of the wave
rising up on a wave and down the other side
awareness floating riding the undulations
where there's a kind of Vitality in being aware
if we're offer
a little effort or see awareness as being something we
gently do we do it and there's a vitality and
aliveness and being aware
where awareness is maybe like water flowing over through with your breathing
and if your mental vitality goes anywhere else into your thoughts
your reactions notice that the flow of awareness has
stopped or hindered
diminished
begin again with the flow of awareness flowing through or around
offering no resistance to anything
finding the path released a wrist resistance
around and through and under
back to the breathing
keep flowing with your awareness gentle calmly
let's being aware be an activity a gentle doing that flows along
so your mind does not get caught up in other doings
notice when awareness stops or is lost
and find a way to flow around your thoughts preoccupations
keep it flowing even if it has to continuously flow
around something it touches it
feels it knows it then flows on and on
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
the path of Harmony for love
is to flow where there's receptivity
to flow where there's openings to flow around and over
but never to assert never to push
path of kindness or friendliness is soft like water
but always there available flowing
ready to flow into where there's it's welcomed
and when it's not it just flows around
never disappointed him
a kindness that needs nothing in return like water that just flows
and may it be that our care our kindness or love for the
world flows through US freely and openly
generously
because it nourishes us it's healthy for us it is us
and may it be that our good will are well wishing
flows in the path of least resistance
to touch all people with our care our kindness our
friendliness May the world know that we care
that we wish that all beings be happy
that all beings be safe
that all beings be peaceful
that all beings be free
and may our good will support that in happening
[Music]
so today I'll continue this theme about what is the Dharma
Dharma is a powerful word in Buddhism and it has many meanings
but when I study these teachings of the Buddha
I see that one of the primary ways in which is used as a
reference what it refers to uh not maybe what it means literally but
what it refers to is action things or something dynamic
it doesn't refer to things that are static especially when the word Dharma is used in the plural
and the singular sometimes it means teaching and uh the Buddha's teachings for
example but in the plural when it's first a Dharma it's often refers to action
something that's active and dynamic and um and this goes along with what I
taught yesterday that one of the meanings of Dharma or what it refers to is the relatedness of all things
that things exist in relationship to other things they come about in relationship to other things
and this relatedness has to is only related because there's a dynamic
relationship between them there are some ways in which the functioning of one thing
impacts and affects the other thing that goes on and so things that live in relationship
to each other because they're Dynamic they're more activities than they are things
there's more verbs than there are nouns in how Buddhism kind of focuses focuses
on the Dharma and so one of the clear places that I'm
inspired to see this is the Buddha near the end of his life talked about
uh I gave the instructions to um um take the Dharma as your Refuge
as your only Refuge as your Island as your support does your Refuge
and then he went on to say take yourself as your Refuge as your only Refuge
and saying the same thing to saying these right next to each other one after the
other take the Dharma of The Refuge and take yourself as a refuge Refuge uh kind
of implies a kind of a a equivalence between those they're kind of like
referring to the same thing seemingly especially when he says and no other Refuge well then it only works if the two are
the same Dharma and yourself and how could that be well then he goes on to say
um and how do we do this by practicing the four foundations of mindfulness by practicing mindfulness of
the body mindfulness of feelings mindfulness of Mind States mindfulness of
of the dharmas here the fourth Foundation of mindfulness
and this fourth Foundation of mindfulness is referred to as dharmas that's referring all to things which are
Dynamic that are active many of them are mental actions mental activities we're doing the hindrances for example
and uh and those are all actions of the Mind activities of the Mind the seven factors
of Awakening things like mindfulness and investigation of dharmas uh
effort and joy and Tranquility concentration Equanimity these are all
functionings of the mind so they're not dynamic and generally when dharmas refers to
activity It generally refers to healthy good activities Good Conduct whether
it's things we actually do conduct that we engage in or whether it's the activities of the mind that we wouldn't
necessarily call them actions if actions are limited to a person who does something but there's the functionings
of the Mind and um and so when uh there's an
emphasis on all things are changing in constant impermanent
um you see that yes of course that's what we're pointing to when we're pointing to the in constancy of things
not that they necessarily come to an end which certainly part of it but that as
they are they're Dynamic peering and disappearing kind of like waves that come and go and come and go there's
these activities that are not fixed and not static we're not stuck
and so this idea that dharmas in the teachings of the Buddha
repeatedly refers to something which is dynamic and active and and an activity
is actually kind of the good news of Buddhism because it means that when
nothing is Frozen in place it's kind of like there's no Hardware
operating here it's all software and we can change the software
conditions can change the choices we make can change and and so because it's all you know in
relatedness all the actions we do relate to each other certain kinds of activities
that are unwholesome unhealthy they the way that they relate to what follows is
unhealthy greed and hatred has a negative impact
generosity and love has a very different impact uh mindfulness is an activity of the
mind even though it might feel sometimes just being aware is like mostly and not a doing
and it feels so like so restful not to do just to be aware is if we're resting in Awareness even so awareness is a
firing of certain nerves in the brain it is a certain activity that's going on
um but it's not something that the self feels like it's doing and it's such a relief to feel like
something's beautiful thing is flowing but that we're not we're not the one who's doing it
so the um uh so we're so but when we do
mindfulness what we're doing is bringing in conditions that allows things to settle bringing in
the conditions allow us to see clearly what's happening uh bringing in conditions that allows us
differentiate between the different kind of mental activities that are going on so that we do the ones that are
healthiest for us the ones that are the right effort that's from teachings from
last week another place we see this Buddha emphasizing this idea of
Dharma being activities is in this teachings of seven factors of
Awakening there's a teaching called there's what the second one is usually called an English investigation
but the the ancient word has the word dhamma Dharma in it and it's um vichaya
means to distinguish or differentiate it's the differentiation of dhammas
when the Buddha explains what it's differentiating its uh mental activities the seven
factors of Awakening again the Eightfold Path the four noble truths the the five
faculties the four right efforts that the mind has ability to distinguish
between what is healthy and not healthy as activities of the Mind
as what's wholesome and not wholesome and this is the ability to see
clearly in the mind the activities of the Mind what's happening in the mind is part of the gift of being very
settled and present and quiet almost like we're not doing anything and then we start seeing much more clearly what's
happening there the activities Oh my mind's going down the lot the going down
that old well-dug Canal of wanting of
Desiring and I've seen that that doesn't take me in a good direction I don't have to do that anymore
I could take the Vitality of my mental energy of awareness and let let it flow
someplace else recognize what's happening and not get caught in it I could focus on something else instead
I can focus on contentment that feels healthy when I do contentment
then I settle more so there's this gentle kind of action
that goes on in this practice which you know I referred back to last
week right effort right effort is an action and we're learning how to act how to do
so it borders on or or some people would see it as almost like a not doing
it's so peaceful it's so relaxed it's so flowing maybe it's like flowing water we don't
see that's flowing because it's so clear there is an activity
that onward leading flow to what's Awakening through this practice
so the Dharma meaning activity dynamism
action um it means engaging
and so this is a also kind of a paradigm shift for some people just like focusing on relatedness is a
paradigm shift as opposed to post focusing on me and you focusing on the relationships
so the same way rather than focusing on nouns when things are fixed this is how
it is I'll always be this way uh it'll always be this way the situation will always be this way
um is to uh start being attuned to where the activity is where the flow
is where the dynamism is where that change and is happening it's always
happening anyway and so to be attuned to that to Surf
with it to flow in it to participate in it and if we're flowing in a river
and the current is taking us against uh dangerous Rapids then we learn how to
swim over to the other side of the river where the water is peaceful flowing peacefully
we learn the terrain we learn the route we learn how to use the flow of change
but it's always changing so what I'd suggest that you do today is
if you're interested in an assignment is to um
to become a little bit more or quite a bit if you can aware of how you
freeze how you stop in the river of change River of Time how
you get preoccupied by Things Are fixated flowing doesn't mean you had to just can
don't have to focus on certain things but then we we focus on them with the
flow with the Mind itself shifting and changing and flowing the mind doesn't freeze the mind doesn't get caught but
is involved in a flowing Gentle Way where we are like unsweet we're like
clouds and water the Japanese word that flows with with the flow of Life the
flow of time that flows with uh the movements and activities of the
Mind choosing what's heavenly so the dhamma the Dharma
a very important if it's not the literal meaning it's often what's being pointed
to it's pointing to action to activity to dynamism and and that's where it's in
dynamism and activity in action that the Dharma is found more than
um assuming that it's only in Stillness only in peace or quiet or some thick
State nothing fixed always changing always flowing
so I hope you can see the difference between
being stopped stuck and gentle flowing along without all
things even if you're sitting quietly still in meditation and your body's not moving everything is still flowing
so thank you very much and we'll continue this tomorrow