so hello
welcome as the good mornings were coming in in the Stream or the hellos the good
days good moments I could almost
um sense us in a circle I can imagine such AIG group we would make a big
circle um sometimes at the end of Retreats at
IRC at Insight Retreat Center everyone will gather in a more like an oval and say we've been
practicing together for a week or something in silence and then there's a there's a
moment of appreciation where we we scan the room and make eye contact with
many of these people for the first time or the first time in a week and I had I had a similar similar
feeling of connection and and Community as we're getting
started thank you for taking this time for your
practice the theme of the week is
compassion compassion in our medic meditation compassion in our daily lives on and off the cushion they
say let's start today with on the cushion and begin with some
meditation we'll do a meditation that I I consider one of the one of the ways we take care of the
the the foundation stones of compassion it's a it's a simple
meditation of uh knowing the quality of the mind and if there's anything
hindering compassion and well-being Wishing Well we release it it's that
simple knowing and releasing so let's find our our way into
our meditation
posture
letting our awareness move its center of gravity as
it were from the
eyes or the face back into the whole
body
and letting Let There be let there be a measure of settledness
here not there and then But Here and
Now
Here and Now where the senses live
letting the attention gather here and
now the sensations of here
the body the
breathing the
Earth
settling here with a clear
awareness here with a breathing
sensing as we settle you may become aware of some
inner companions
maybe influences in the mind that are drawing you
away from here and now to there and
then
our innocent companions asking for our
attention
is there a simple way [Music]
available to recognize and
release
returning and resting Here and
Now
and when our inner companions take us by the hand pull
us to there and
then to respond with
kindness a tiny inner smile
and we let go
releasing and
returning
is the body starting to
soften the skin starting to
relax La in the muscles
is the heart moving toward
tenderness
again and again returning to here
releasing there and
then with the groundedness the
fullness the presence of Here and
Now
in our last minutes of this
sitting
studying Here and [Music]
Now inclining toward tenderness
peacefulness by all
beings everywhere come to know that measure of
peace that comes from letting
go
[Music]
that
so welcome again to this um second day on the topic of
compassion yesterday we um we talked about practicing with this distinction
between um contemplation of suffering so dwelling and suffering taking it
on and the fullness of the practice of
compassion in short a practice that's both sensitive to suffering
and has this wish for others to be free a sort of practice that entails a a
vision of a life that's free from suffering that inspiring
potential so today a little shift to
um a question that comes up a fair amount and maybe maybe the this group
doesn't need so much convincing on this question but um it comes up often enough
that I'd like to address it and that is um
is meditation and Retreat particularly is that
permissible like with so much so much to care for so much going on do we do we even do
we even dare uh
so that's the uh that's the question I'd like to turn this um this morning I'd like to open with a
story regarding um someone I've known in
uh who worked with Doctors Without Borders so I was surprised to read that
Doctors Without Borders uh as the as the name might suggest they're a collection of
positions and support uh that um that give Medical
Care to um to some 70 plus countries in
2021 63,000 people working on this together to bring Medical Care to those who need it often in places where the um
medical system is um not not so
strong so this person uh this person I spoke with is both a doctor and a Dharma
practitioner so both both a physician and a longtime longtime um
meditator so uh we could say she was she was sort of on the on the front lines
with this she was seeing seeing patients just day after day caring for them day after
day and she started to notice that she would she would finish she would go back to her room and in so many words she
would she would just break down so to speak she was so
upset uh and she realized I can't go on without
rest and the words that I remember her saying I knew it was time to go on
Retreat so she knew she needed seclusion in order to continue and needed to rest in
order to continue you offering care and this uh this points to one of the essential skills for us when we're when
we're practicing compassion and that is mindful monitoring how much is too much and how
much is enough how much can we give wisely but we might
um how do we how do we recognize that for ourselves and I I believe we all have a sense often we know when when our
pushing has gone too far for too long I think I think there's there's really
something to be gained in um practicing with the sensitivity of
recognition um so this this friend this physician notice she she started to lose
the ability to function as well and so needed seclusion needed
rest I think for many of us one of the way one of the ways that we recognize too
far is by the upwelling and the prevalence of the hindrances these states of mind that are
uncomfortable in themselves and are um called hindrances
but they're also called obstacles and for the sake of our conversation this week we can think
about how these how these might be obstacles to our compassion obstacles to our uh to our
own wellbe and our ability to care for others uh it may be that when the when
the hindrances are active that we can't see clearly we can't see as clearly
anymore what needs to be done for others we can't help quite as well and
we can't see quite as clearly what's going on for us how to help
ourselves so this is where seclusion comes in Meditation Retreat that sort of deep rest that we
we give ourselves in a way giving ourselves time for Stillness and awareness and
attention to work on us to work in
us and what we what we see what we see when um when we when we take up the
practice of seclusion meditation and Retreat over time what we see is an unhindered mind an unclouded mind or a
heart that's free of obstacles I'll say in a few words that a
a mind that's free of hindrances is very closely associated with a concentrated mind and a concentrated mind is very
powerful very powerful so this deep
rest the one of the influences of meditation and Retreat is we know we uh
we know well from just even beginning the practice is
the mind starts to feel at home with itself it's a it's a state in which
we're resourced enough nourished enough to be able to see clearly inside and
offer ourselves to others so this is one of the one of the
functions of retreat such a simple practice isn't it
taking time complex to take time challenging to take time that's so much
so many um so many needs and responsibilities but it's worth
reflecting on how we can bring this into our lives then once we once we have
um taken the time to to uh meditate just as we did this
morning such a simple practice just as we did settling ourselves here settling
ourselves here and then when a hindrance arises to know it and let it
go can be really beneficial can sort of help our practice of being here to to
get familiar with these five entrances you may know them well one is sense
desire that is the sort of compulsive desire that has a a grip and a lean in
it the second is ill will if uh if sense desire is a lean in ill will is that
push against sloth there's a great met
metaphor in the text for sloth and torper and that is um uh like algae has
grown over water so you can get this this visceral sense of sort of thick
slimy mckiness of how how sloth and torper can cover over the
mind and then the fourth is agitation if sloth is too little energy agitation
might be just a little too much and then doubt uh is um the fifth doubt about how
the practice should unfold what what should I be doing in the practice or doubt that I can do the
practice these different manifestations of Doubt so these these are like the big
five they're not the only only things that call us out of here and now in to
there and then um but getting to know getting to know these five we get to know a lot of
the territory of the mind and how do we do this with this
simple practice um remarkable that mindfulness
mindfulness is regarded as a medicine for all five of these sort of qualities
and conditions of the mind just by feeding mindful attention
we we undermine all five of these hindrances one of the principles of how
how the hindrances work is they don't survive without feeding they don't they don't sustain
and grow without feeding so in a way if we instead of
feeding our compulsive desire or ill will or doubt let's say we give our
Focus to mindfulness mindful attention and just that is
enough and we can come home home to ourselves you might find some other
creative ways to uh to relate to the mind uh in relate to the
hindrances I think one can be characterized as a sort of
self-compassion that um that knows a hindrance as a hindrance and then just allows that
hindrance to be there not uh not getting pushed by the hindrance not getting pulled by the
hindrance not pushing it away not pulling um just sharing the space Oh
there's a hindrance there it is let's see how long it
lasts because if it's not if it's not being fed it it um soon enough it won't
sustain sometimes our creative response to the hindrances might be might be just
that just allowing it to be there at other times a hindrance a hindrance
calls for a response that's more firm more strong where we in a in a in a manner of speaking set a
boundary and we say no not now not now now is for here not for
there and then and there's a little more firmness in the way we respond there may be other other
creative ways that we that we do this but the the point of um the point
of practicing with the hindrances is
um to remove those obstacles from Clear Vision the vision
that knows what we need the vision that knows how we can best help
others and it might be fair to say that the more we become skilled with our own hearts
the more options become available for supporting
others and then it's quite natural as the unhindered mind the concentrated mind settles that the heart grows tender
the heart becomes open for compassion when it's not being pulled and
pushed so seclusion
Meditation Retreat taking time for deep rest my uh my proposal for the day is
when thinking about compassion we can give it we can give it all of our best
effort and then as I said yesterday when it's time to rest really really rest
really rest and in our practice of mindful awareness giving deep rest to the body
the heart the mind coming to know the ways that we get we get uh clouded over
so that we uh can best give this heart to the world best give this heart to
ourselves may it be may it be that mindfulness supports
compassion tomorrow we'll look um we'll look at what's considered the root of
compassion and we'll turn our attention a bit to meta loving kindness practice so may you enjoy this day of
practice please take
care