e
so hello everyone and
welcome and it's helpful when we sit down to
meditate to have a bit of an attitude or an approach
that we're doing it for the first time maybe with a certain amount of
momentum or familiarity but still that it's a it's new it's something new to
discover new to be uh that we don't really know the
maybe the subtleties or the depths or the corners or the attics or the basements
of Our Lives that might show itself in any given
meditation so just to meditate as if it's fresh and
new a new entering a new world not assuming or bringing with you the
expectations or the assumptions from before and in that regard it's helpful
to think of meditation as a form of
curiosity but a form of curiosity that doesn't stimulate more thinking but the
opposite a form of curiosity that is a keen interest what's
going on here that quiets the mind and the
analogy that I like is that um if you're in say the
forest and uh you you hear a sound that's unfamiliar and it's very
faint and uh maybe it's the sound of the river that you need to
find and you find is that the river what is that or there's a sound of a bird and
you would um um to be able to listen kind of acutely or carefully
fully your ordinary thinking might quiet down you might stop thinking ordinary
thoughts there be maybe some very simple thoughts about the sound but something
inside of you gets very still and quiet and connected focused to the
hearing and things got very quiet and um and in that kind of
way uh we can ask ourselves the kind ofas question that I act asked myself when I
was in Burma practicing there was the question what is
this what is this whatever was happening what is this and uh and even if I kind of
recognized it something that I know knew like maybe it was the uh tingling in my
chest I could have just said tingling in my chest and be done with it but this kind of checklist approach to
mindfulness to awareness just kind of recognize what's there and move on um uh
is limiting so I might recognize as tingling in my
chest and then I would ask what is this and but I did it with a way to make my
my mind would get quiet and in order to and I wouldn't be looking for an answer it wasn't like I
was asking a question so that I answer it with some more thoughts or descriptions or ideas but I asked the
question to quiet the mind so I can move into it and feel it more fully so I can
open myself and allow myself to receive it more fully what is this to really know
something well to know something experientially to know something in the
through the senses um because the sense data the sense how we things come in through the
senses is the gate by which uh all the experience of the world and ourselves
begins and then we construct it we interpret it we uh apply names onto it
and it gets complicated very quickly in a way that takes us away from the
immediacy of this sensory experience that we have and what I learned in Burma
practicing there was how Central the sensory experience was to this practice
of AAS the ongoing flow of
Sensations and so this question what is this and then in letting things in that
Curiosity what is this but to to do that sometimes I would
do it with say it in my mind and sometimes I would just it was just kind of an attitude but an attitude that let
something get quiet a quieting a
stilling to feel to open to to
receive to float on whatever experience was so even if there was a lot of
thinking going on even there I would say what is this not to discern what the
content of the thoughts were and why I was thinking what I was thinking but again what is the sensations of
thinking if I had a strong emotion what are this what is this and let everything
get quiet so I can feel and sense the sensory nature of the emotions so the Curiosity that quiets
the mind so sitting upright or
sitting or lying if you're lying down lying in a way that adjusts your
spine a way that works for you but aligns the back the
spine so optimizes the feeling of alertness in your back while taking care
of whatever might be an issue in the back
and gently closing your
eyes and beginning with curiosity and the question what is
this what is this experience of being alive right now in this posture with the
eyes closed
not to answer it with words but let the thinking mind become
quieter as if if you're quiet enough what is here will reveal itself
to you you don't have to go looking or figuring
out what is it that wants to be revealed what is
this and if nothing comes there might still be the
pleasure of that Curiosity that openness that
receptivity that comes with that question
for
and taking a few longer deeper breaths relaxing with the
exhale
letting your breathing return to
normal and Center yourself into a receptor mode Center yourself in
the breathing to be receptive to breathing the bod sensations of
breathing with a question what is this what is the body sensations of
breathing what is it as a way of quieting the mind and
being more sensitive to the experience of
breathing
for
what is this as an entry into the ongoing flow
of present moment experience with the Mind becoming
quieter
Stiller to better perceive the lived
experience of Sensations in the
body
e
for
as a way of opening more fully to the experience of here and
now you could ask ask yourself the question what is
this don't look for an
answer let the question open you to the experience of
here
for
e
and then as we come to the end of the sitting to ask yourself
now with a quieting curiosity what is this
what is this experience of being
alive and if you let the body answer that question what answer does the body
provide
then with a quietest mind maybe a calming M
heart to look open up to the world around
you in your neighborhood your home your
town what is it to have an open
heart what is
it to Value the people around
you what form of receptivity and
attentiveness comes out of meditation out of
mindfulness that allows you to take in others in a deeper
way not as projections of our complaints or desires or
opinions but to kind of be sensitive to the humanity of
others in all their shapes and
forms and to end the meditation with a wishing everyone
well may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and perhaps inspired to have this
well-wishing knowing that combination of Happiness safety
Peace and Freedom brings out the best in peace
people even the ones who are difficult may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be
[Music] free [Music]
thank
you
so hello and welcome to this now series that I'm giving about my Dharma
life and um and I left off yesterday with um
having gone to Insight Meditation Society in Massachusetts for three month ret
treat and up to that point I've been kind of going back and forth some between doing Zen practice at the San
Francisco Zen Center and doing Insight practice um uh in
Asia in Thailand and Burma and then I the first time I practiced with the Western teachers was at three-month
retreat in IMS and um and then I went back to Zen Center I
had been ordained as a z Zen priest there Zen buunk and um in the course of
kind of the of of um growth in that kind of
role uh at some point uh someone is ordained there as a priest uh has this
position of being the the called the um head student the head monk of a
three-month practice period at the monastery and and it's considered to be kind of like the the transition into
starting to train to become as zen teacher and you do your first Dharma talks there and um and so I was invited
to have that role and it seemed like a wonderful continuation of or comp kind
of a completion of my zen training some people see it as a completion uh all your kind of basic training now been
done and um so you're also you're a little bit the model student and a model
practi ier and so you go to all the meditations and uh you do all the
rituals and uh the job the head student has is to clean all the bathrooms the
public bathrooms and do the trash and the compost I loved it it was very nice
and so I went back from IMs I went to do this three three-month retreat at tasahara Monastery in the
wilderness and um it was wonderful as a way of continuing what had happened 3 months imagine being 3 months in Long
silent Retreat and then not going back into the business of the world but being able to go into the kind of monastic
life and the quiet of the winter where there was no public coming into
tahara and um so I continued with that but during that time I began feeling
that um my future was not to stay at Zen Center uh I can't articulate exactly why
but just didn't seem right to I'd spent 10 years of of intensive practice and
that period of time felt like it had completed there complete cycle of
development of growth and it felt appropriate not to continue in the kind of more intensive Buddhist and practice
environment and to kind of go out into the world a little bit now but uh I had
no interest for a career or conventional job or anything at all and I thought
well I'm going to have to support myself some way and I had this probably naive idea that if I got a master's in
Buddhist studies then maybe I could teach Buddhist studies at a community college classes in Buddhism or something
and make enough uh you know income to kind of get by in my simple monastic
lifestyle and um so I applied to the University of Hawaii in Manoa in
Honolulu to uh do a masters in religious studies with a focus on Buddhism and the
reason I went there was twofold um someone had given me a book by a professor in the philosophy
Department a Sri Lankan man named David kalupahana uh about the the middle way of ngaro
narina was one of the very important early Mahayana philosophers of
India and um and David Kalapana had a very different orientation towards how
to study kapana study narina most people studied this philosopher this maybe second
century philosopher um through the through the lens of later Indian
interpretations he said no no we shouldn't do that we should understand him through the lens of the earlier
Buddhist texts that ngagara would have read and been influenced by and for and
and that was these early poly sutas early poly discourses of the Buddha and
I thought that was a brilliant move and I really like David kahana's take on all this so I wanted to go there to study
with him also there was a zen teacher wonderful uh teacher named Robert Akin
roshi who was also right they lived he had a a Zen Center in a house right next to the
university so I went there to study with the Zen master the zen teacher and do  study with him for two years and to
do this master's program there and and um and a master's program in Buddhist studies turned to be lots of fun for me
in the 10 years that I'd lived this kind of more monastic life I actually hadn't done very much study of Buddhism uh very
little reading and and um and now it felt like a kid in the candy store and
and I just had a great time with the studies and um and so that was nice and
um and then uh after two years it was over and I said whatat do I do now and
again I had no conventional career in mind I wasn't didn't feel like I should go back to again to the more living at a
a Buddhist center anymore so what do I do I didn't really have any idea I wasn't really I wasn't a teacher
yet so I thought well it was fun to do this master's program why don't I apply for a doctoral program in the San
Francisco Bay Area because I wanted to be close to my Buddhist teacher in my Buddhist communities I want to be close
to San fris Center and also by then I wanted to be closer to um the burgeoning
world of U Spirit Rock there was some Vasa teachers there Jack cornfield and others that I hardly knew but I wanted
to be kind of closer to that scene that and um and I didn't expect to get
accepted to a doctor to a doctorate Pro program but I was accepted and to my
surprise and Not only was I accepted but there was to my surprise there was a um
a for me a very large um scholarship uh
for living for Roman to you know I think I was it was a lot of money back then it
was $8,000 a year in 1990 for me to live on and that was enough for me to live on
and go to school and um and I quickly discovered that um a doctorate program at a major
research University is very different in a master's program and master's program was kind of like um just kind of like
just just great surveys of so much of introduction and surveys to mucha
Buddhism and the doctoral program was now to kind of bore down into the details and do a lot of analysis and and
um often uh critical analysis of texts and te you
know and um and um it wasn't so much fun the way that I had before
but one of the motivations for me was that uh when I my undergraduate degree
was in Agronomy at the great agricultural School University of California at
Davis and I was part of a team of a group of uh other students who were kind of the um uh uh Alternatives in
agriculture we called it Alternatives in agriculture kind of activists on campus trying to get more organic farming
studies trying to do to do different things that were more alternative to Conventional commercial um fertilizer and pesticide
centered Agriculture and um and uh we had
wonderful adventures at University uh promoting that but one of
the things that uh were a surprised for me when I studied the agriculture the science behind
farming is that uh I came kind of as a fundamentalist organic farmer with a lot
of rece received ideas about about farming and especially fertilizers that
were erroneous and um and I was kind of shocked that uh I was capable of kind of
very dogmatic opinionated ideas about farming and things and it wasn't quite
right when I started studying my doctoral program it was in the religious studies Department to do Buddhist
studies um I remember that and I said you know no I'm doing religion here and
um and in religion um I think there's even more dogmatism more easier to succumb to this
is the truth this is really what is and I wanted to be really careful not to fall into that trap and I wanted to be
able to have the foundation to understand my assumptions to understand where the beliefs came from to
understand how to interpret um experiences meditation experiences so
there wasn't overlay of dogmatism on top of it and uh and I've certainly seen a
lot of fundamentalists in Buddhism and I would I didn't want to be one of those and so this study so turned out to be a
doctoral program at a really major research University and religious
studies um in some way served really well to develop kind of a better critical mind in the best terms of that
expression a mind that could analyze or think about things and question question things in a deeper way and I kind of
felt that when I was there that that kind of questioning was other form of
Liberation it was kind of an intellectual Liberation that was going on so that was kind of nice and um but
then a number of interesting things happened along the way uh just around that
time uh um just before leaving Hawaii to come
back to California I think it was still 1989 uh I received a phone call that it
was out of the blue for me I wasn't expecting it uh from Jack cornfield who I only knew a little bit and I'd never
practiced with him but uh he knew about my practice and and uh he invited me to be in his
next teacher training and uh it was one of those remarkable experiences where I remember
standing looking at of Windows uh he was talking to me on the phone and I literally kind of viscerally uh had this
Fe sensation in my body of the puzzle pieces of My Life coming together and it's like a click click click and I wow
this it all fits now and um I can't necessarily explain that but that was the physical
sensations of it and then later in a rational way I saidwell I don't know if I'm going to become a Vasa teacher but
it'd be foolish not to go study with Jack cornfield so I started that training at the same
time that I started my doctorate program and then I when I came back to
California I had a little bit trouble finding a place to live so I ended up living back at the San Francisco Zen
Center in San Francisco living in the in the temple and it was nice to be there but
then um my zen teacher Mel whitesman was the Abbot at that point at some point he
took me for a walk and um and uh he did
uh we had an interesting conversation uh first he asked me about there was two major abits at Zen Center at that time
and so he asked me about my relationship with the other one and I said uh that um
um uh I trusted his the other ones I trusted his Dharma his teaching but I
didn't quite trust him but then he asked what about me talking to himself to about himself and
I said well you um um I trust you but
I'm not quite sure about your Dharma and then he did a remarkable thing we were walking on the sidewalk and he turned
around and faced me and when I said I'm not sure about your Dharma he said uh he
went put his hands together almost like with a clap and said um that's and that's where we'll
meet he wasn't he wasn't a upset he wasn't concerned he was kind of delighted that I didn't quite see eye to
eye to him about the Dharma I said that's where we'll meet and um and it was not like we were going to meet and
he was going to convince me something that's where he wanted to meet me and like was felt like a really respectful
thing and also in Zen when you put your hands together in this you know Act of
respect and then um and then uh later in that walk he suggested that I start
training with him specifically or studying with him to prepare for Dharma transmission which is to become a foen
teacher and um and I kind of said well I think it's too early to talk about that
but why don't I come over and start studying with you and so I started studying basically for that purpose but
I kind of had put off a decision and so here I was practicing studying a PhD in
Buddhist studies involved in becoming training to be as be PNA teacher with Jack cornfield
and training to be a zen teacher with Mel whitesman all at the same time in
and then in 1992 kind of when all this was going on in addition that's when I uh got married
and I'd met my wife uh some five years earlier when I'd come living at Green
Gulch when I came back from Burma and had met her there on the farm she was farming there and and uh and we got
together and we went to T together and she went with me to Hawaii and and um
and then when we came back from Hawaii she went to UC Davis to get a masters in botony and I went to graduate school in
the Bay Area and in 1992 we were married so this was a then the last
thing I'll say going to leave it um as part of the homework for teacher training with Jack horfield uh we were
supposed to have a sitting group that we taught in weekly group and as it turned out there was one in paloalto that met
Monday nights uh with about 12 to 15 people who came and the person who
facilitated it a wonderful man named um um I
know in this different flow I can't quite remember oh Howard noodleman he
um um had gotten sick and so he couldn't lead the group anymore he wasn't
teaching it but he was facilitating it and uh Jack suggested that he invite me
and so he invited me and then in August 1990 I went to started to teach this
little group and which grew to this what we are now IMC and so that was uh this
wonderful combination of uh things happening then
and looking back at it now it seems like I was doing a lot but it felt very
spacious and just all matter of fact and it was a diff you know 30 years ago it felt like Looking Back Now a whole
different era and there seem to be lots of time for everything compared to now
where we live in a very different world and it feels like now um there's you know my time is filled in a way that it
wasn't back then so that's uh brings it to a certain
kind of conclusion uh when I started to teach and um I'll continue a little bit now in
my life as a teacher so thank you
e