so good morning to all of you and welcome happy to be here with you and
for those of you who are attending online hello and welcome it adds a kind of richness to
have you along online and um
so we could say that today is momentous day
in that it's the last day of 2023 and tomorrow or at midnight we
usher in 2024 and
um I think there's a may be a tradition of people wanting to give inspiring
hopeful messages for the new year and it would be nice if I did that
today and maybe I
will you'll have to decide but
um as I think ahead for 2024 I think that we're going to have a
lot of challenges what's coming and um I mean the level of the
speed in which the climate is changing is surprising the people who
were warning us that it was going to change it's happening faster than we
expected it looks like we I know it's too way too early to tell whether we'll going into drought
again in California but the snow levels are quite low again all across the western parts of this
country and um you know we can list all these things and changes
some of the wars that are being fought currently today we don't see any end for tomorrow
they'll continue into 2024 and some of them might get worse
might expand and stretch and the ways in which the wars spill over across their
borders to other borders to other countries around the world to create more and more division uh seems to be increasing
and that'll probably continue into 2024 and
it's there certain reasonable scenarios for this country is that the
presidential election will be very difficult and we don't know who will end
up being president elected president in
November chances are that there's going to be a big part of the population is quite challenged and upset by
this so as we look forward to some of the challenges that are coming in
2024 one of the things that is important to consider is to prepare ourselves for
this to prepare ourselves for November so it's not a shock and surprise so we're prepared we're ready for whatever
comes we're prepared for the challenges of this country that who knows how much
stronger they'll become and um so to be prepared and I think this mindfulness practice we do
Buddhist practice is a preparation is meant to be a preparation for the
challenges we face in our life most commonly it's talked about the
existential challenges of sickness old age and death but the Buddha frequently enough
address the social challenges of our time of his times and how the practice was also meant to address those as
well so we make this big turn in a sense
tonight at midnight or 10:30 at IMC and
um and we're making a lot some of us are making a lot to do about
nothing because nothing actually happens on midnight today I mean nothing
real in the world I mean it's kind of an odd New Year's time some cultures have
New Years at a time where it kind of corresponds with astronomical changes like it make more sense to wouldn't it
make more sense to have the New Year's on Solstice you know oh that Mark something
real and um not only doesn't it Mark something real it actually marks kind of
a fallacy that um you know it's the end of the 12th month of the year but we call
it the 10th month in Latin December you know it's kind of a
confusion that uh you know and November is a ninth month and
October is the eth month and and then uh we called um then you
know September the seventh month so we're
confused in our language at least and then we come to this you know New
Year's it's a convention and it's an unusual convention that was somehow invented by
people probably men a long time ago it's do not not even a lunar
calendar that goes on so in a sense in some very real way
as an existentially thing new years does not
exist it's a convention it's a convention a concept
ideas that humans somehow have created and much of the world lives by
it and much of the world has other calendars as well one of the great things about living in the Bay Area is
that you could celebrate New Year much through the year because there's so many different
cultures here with different calendars you you know for a long time the Chinese New Years was maybe still big but was
big and it was a big alternative to the Gregorian calendar new year but now
there's all kinds of other ones as well and there's the Buddhist New Year that happens in
April so you know we could just keep
celebrating so it's a convention but actually conventions are
important and that's the emphasis for this talk today that conventions are are
something that we create in relationship to each
other and we either participate or don't participate but if we participate in the
conventions we're actually participating in a way of relating to each other to
the world and we might think it's silly emphasiz this around the calendar but
it's actually true it's one of infinite number of conventions of bridges of uh
networking that reaches out to how we're actually connected to other people for those of us who speak English
here English is a language which is connecting all of us as I speak we share
it it's a bridge it's a relationship Rel language is all relational there's there's a
relationship ship that's happening with all of you as I speak relationship that you happened to you as you listen to me
and there's a relationship that all of you share in being part of this together listening to this together through the
English language what is being conveyed through the conventions that we
share what's traveling on the for you may use this language on the
wavelength of or the the sound waves what's being carried along with
it I watched a movie last night with my family and boy was there a lot of
swearing and it wasn't just swearing it was actually talking meanly to other people it was like really heavy that I
mean they were emphasizing it in the movie so it was kind of like part of the movie right but wow how can people be so
mean to each other and in the way they were talking they were conveying so the
relationship was something really unfortunate something painful something harmful was being conveyed in the very
words they spoke and then a little bit as part of the purpose of the movie was to show a
transformation of people and you could see that at some point after the transformation a few of these people
happened that their language became much softer and Kinder and there were little Tears in their eyes and as they spoke
and cared for each other so that was very nice but uh but we have so many ways in which
we this network of relatedness is happening and one of them that we all
share here in this country is uh this change and for some of us it's not going
to it's kind of like you know doesn't really matter that much I mean think we kind of do something at my
house that at 9:00
with the excuse that that's like New York Times Square kind of kind of time we don't even turn it on to watch it
just like okay and um and then it's important for our
children and one of our neighbors who knows that wants us to do it for the children which is my wife buys
M&M's and she on the at the kitchen table where my kids eat breakfast it's
the new year is is written out in M&M's so it'll say you know 2024 my kids
wake up and and U and they get M&M's you know the one you know they're
21 and 25 [Laughter]
so in my neighbor who loves this tradition I think it's about 60 wants us to do it she's not coming
over for the &m she just likes the idea so it's a tradition that we have and it's a way of relating to each other
and caring for each other or loving each other connecting that we have this tradition that we do so there's something in this new year that you know
knits our family a little bit together that's nice so these
relationships so For Better or
Worse Buddhism is a religion and as a religion
it tends to offer fundamental for Buddhists fundamental
Universal orientations values understandings of this life that we're living
in and what I'd like to suggest is that uh through the Buddhist
lens this world of ours is not made from
atoms it's not made from electrons or protons it's not made of quarks and
goans and these subatomic particles that's not what this world is
made of most fundamentally that the world is made of
relationships between things nothing exists without being in relationship to
something else nothing exists that doesn't have
doesn't come from something doesn't interact with something so it's known and has a purpose or has some
existence nothing that nothing exists that doesn't have some impact Beyond
itself and whether it's it you know whether what was first was there some kind of fundamental matter first that
became explode in the Big Bang and then there were relationships of everything
or was it was a relationship first and then so that's kind of like a chicken egg question and the Buddha never
answered such a question because he felt that there's beginningless time there was no
beginning but but uh but the emphasis is not on what's
important is not the things of the world like Adams what's important is not the
events of the world how people relate how people are doing what they're doing and all kinds
of things in the world but rather it's the relationship we have with it
the relationship we have with ourselves the relationship we have with the different things happening with
ourselves relationship to our thoughts our feelings our motivations the relationship to the events of Our Lives
the difficulties and challenges our illnesses and our dying and the wars of
our society and our world it's in the relationship that
they're formed that's the fundamental base basis of life from a
Buddhist point of view and so what we're doing in Buddhism is having insight and understanding and
Transformations about the ways in which that relationship happens this is what's
key so if we're focusing on money like the purpose of life is to be
wealthy or have money and it's just about the money then
we lose sight of the that money is a really a relationship money has a certain
relationship it allows us to do things and connect to other people and have an influence and effect on the
world it was It was kind of transformative for me financially or like in terms of money that I live on on
Donna so the money that I live with is the what's given to me at people's
freely given donations that I I don't ask for anything just just like people seem to want to support me as a Dharma
teacher so um that money to me has a in
my mind at least has a spin it comes with a relationship of people who value
something about the Dharma who value something certain value certain way of
living so I feel like I have a responsibility
or a desire or an inspiration to continue that spin and how I spend the
money so I wouldn't use the money I received from Donna to go Outten buy cigarettes or
guns that that would just be seem completely kind of disrespectful or
worse for what has the relationship that money
represents so I would like to use it for good in the world and to think about
that how do I do that and and um and sometimes because of that when I go
someplace and say well this is It's kind of expensive and I'll tell myself
well it'll just support the people who somehow receive it that's good for them
I receed support I'm happy to support them it's okay I don't know if you know that
inspires you or not but inspires me and u so the
relationship what is the relationship we're contributing what's the relationship we're forming what's the
impact we have if it's All About Me Myself and
mine it's too easy for that to sever relationships it's too easy for that to
dismiss how related we are so that we
are more likely than not than causing harm rather and
benefit so how do we live our life in the world of relationships not in the world of
things how do we live in the world of relationships in a way that supports and
helps everyone invol and everyone in this world is kind of the is is is one
of the fundamental principles of the Buddhist teachings
um um
so um I would like to propose that to use a
non- Buddhist word that it is in the relationships we
have with ourselves with others and the world that we discover what is
sacred that's where the sacredness is sacred is not in something out there
but it's in this it's found in the relatedness that we have is that important and for Buddhists the word I'm
using for sacred is the word Dharma Dharma is sacred for
Buddhists and it's um and Dharma is about relationships and the most classic way
of talking about it I talk about depended co-arising that things arise in dependence on other
things things are arise in relationship to other things exist this is a fundamental principles of the
teaching the Dharma is found in relationships that's where it's
found Dharma is not personal or impersonal it's not in oneself or in the
world it is embedded in everything we are in relationship
with it's it's in that relationship so you do in a sense find it within but
it's not really personal we do find it externally it's not really impersonal
it's all about what is the relationship we
have for humans the known universe is sacred because we live in relationship
with it the known universe is sacred I think this idea of known the world that
we know however wide we can know it however far our imagination can
stretch whether it's to the edges of your home to your block to the city to
the country to the world to the cosmos however far you can imagine the
relationship we have to it that's what's sacred and so if the world is sacred is
because our imagination stretches out to include the
world it's in how we relate and are related to that we find the greatest
meaning value healing and Liberation the most important values and
things we want for our lives is found something some quality of relatedness to
something so what's and so the quality of relating and the object of greatest
reverence is not what's on the other side of a
relationship it is how we relate so it's not an object out
there that we rever but rather the reverence in Buddhism of what is that
relatedness how do we relate how we how are we interacting what are we bringing with us what are we seeing what are we
intending what are we supporting what qualities in that bridge in that
relatedness that way we use conventions and language and speech and actions in
relationship to others what are we conveying in it do we think about it do we become
unconscious where we don't care about other people we drive on the freeway
without any concern for others you are still relating to the
others on the freeway but you're not taking responsibility or taking care or
attention ition to what is the relationship being form
there it's sacred it can be sacred how you drive your
car if driving your car you're considering the relationships all the
circles of relationships that are coming into play do you drive on the freeway to make
it a better Driving Experience for the other drivers or are they all obstacles for to
you having a good driving experience and so you know and so you
use your finger to let them know or do you drive such a way that's
easier for other
people so then when we come into this relationships then the heart of the
Dharma that we teach the Buddism the part of Buddhist teachings is
non-harming an ancient teaching is that the primary characteristic of the Dharma
is non-harming if there's any harming involved with Buddhism then it's not the
Dharma the primary characteristic primary reference point for understanding the Dharma is non-harming
and non-harming is a relational issue with ourselves not to harm ourselves
with others not to harm others this means non-harming in all our
relationships including to the animals and to the Natural World the teaching of the Buddha was
actually held this up as a very very high
value the universal the universal emphasis on non-harming the Buddha gave
is a challenge for us living the lives we live for most of us and so it's a is
it a challenge that we're willing to accept to live with to relate to in a way that is healthy and hopeful or do we
just shut down say well it's impossible to live non non-harming life
and then not think about it again and it's possible that uh one of
the most important relationships to rectify to clarify to create move into
this non non-harming way is the relationship we have with ourselves
violence causing harm harms the one who is
violent sometimes more fully than to who violence is
directed so this emphasis on relationships all relationships I'd like
to propose evocatively provocatively and kind of as a catalyst
for you to think about this see how it might be true uh relationships are
stories every relationship is a story can be explained as a narrative and this happened this is how we relate this how
it unfolded so it's been said that the world is not made of atoms it's made of
relationships made of stories what stories do you live
by are your stories one that Empower are your stories one that that uh create
peace bring love bring friendship bring kindness bring support that bring
respect for every everything that you encounter or do you have a story that
you may be unconsciously lived by that does the opposite of that that just disrespect
disregard this things are certain things story is that certain things are not important enough to pay attention to or
to care for a story that some people don't count some people
are we have a world filled with people who are treating each other as subhuman
treating each other as
monsters and this is partly the reason why people can wage war because of the stories that are told
about how terrible other people are so what are the
stories So What story do you bring to everything you
do some people say we need new stories I don't know if we need new
stories because I don't know if there's any new stories there's been a lot of stories
down through history we just need to choose the right stories there's a lot to choose
from the Buddha had a story and I like that story I think you know that's the
new story even though it's 2500 years old and um stories that
heal stories that unite stories of mutual support and care
stories of peace through
nonviolence we can't solve a problem with the problem
itself can't overcome violence with violence greed with greed we can't overcome the problems of
over consumption with more consumption we can't overcome the
problem of depleting a natural resources by taking out more natural
resources in the world of conflict we can't solve conflict with more
conflict we can't end divisions by continuing to be
divisive we can't end Fighting by fighting
more we don't find self-respect by disrespecting
others we don't find happiness by denying happiness to
others we don't s we don't find safety by making others
unsafe we don't overcome selfishness through more
selfishness so with a Dharma the fundamental aspect of Dharma is
non-harming so nonviolence nonviolence is always myopic
with for the powerful violence can be successful
sometimes in the short term but not in the long
term and that happens in small ways in between people between friends between
families and spouses that people use power and kind of violent language
violent assertions to get their way and they do well that was successful I
was angry and yelled at them and they stopped doing what they did great but then something shuts down in
the other person that person no longer trusts that person no longer is willing to present
to themselves and the the relationship now has been severed in some way can it
ever be
healed it might look like like it people pretend people go
along so the old Story the Buddha had this wonderful teaching I think maybe
painful to hear but maybe not pleasant to to hear but this is the old story
that should be the new story The Killer begets a
killer one who conquers begets a a conqueror the abuser begets
abuse the reviler begets one who
reviles I don't know if this is universally true but I kind of believe it's more true than
not that when we cause harm in the world we don't create a conditions in
the world where the world is going to be safe for ourselves and so often Wars
create more Wars they create people with with um you know who are deeply
hurt and traumatized and so they one of the things they respond to is to 20
years later 10 years later is to fight
more um so I don't know how whether this the
data behind this this quote is completely accur accurate but even if
it's half accurate or quarter accurate I think it's a meaningful quote
it's my man named Walter wink he was writing in the you know I think in the
1990s so in the last century in 18 in
1989 13 Nations comprising 1.6 billion
people experienced nonviolent revolutions that succeeded Beyond anyone's wildest
expectations if we add all all the countries touched by Major non-violent
actions in our Century the Philippines South Africa the independence movement
India the figure reaches 3.3 billion people as staggering 65% of humanity
back then all this in the teeth of the
assertion endlessly repeated that nonviolence doesn't work in the real
world we don't remember there's something about We
Remember Violence we don't remember nonviolence very well soon after Sandy Hook there was
a man very similar who had a assault rifle and 500 rounds of
ammunition who was able to force himself around the security at a school of 00
kids he was going to try to shoot as many as he could somehow I ended up being HED up in
an office with two hostages one of the hostages who was
really scared started talking to him her name her name is antonet
t she started talking to him and she started off by telling him the challeng
ches she has in her life that her husband had committed had died and that she wanted to commit
suicide or she had wanted to commit suicide she started talking to him about
their shared grief their shared challenges in
life she started telling him you don't have to die
today life will still bring you about turns but we can learn from
it she said that as she started this conversation she started because she saw that this man who wanted to
kill was a sick person who could be cared
for when he said that when he she kind of finally this starting conversation with him that um before she started it
um he had shot his weapon once anding into the floor of the the room there and
the police had done a barrage of of uh shots through the door that didn't hit
anyone so it was kind of a tense situation she has conversation with
him and when he kind of she decide helped him understand that maybe he was better off turning himself in she
praised him you're a good person I love you I'm proud of
you and he and at some point he put down his gun and they open the door and that
was the end of it we don't remember this event we
remember Sandy Hook shouldn't we remembering this isn't
this Monumental that how many people it saved that this act of nonviolence this
act of love and care had such a huge impact this makes a
difference so one of my uh Heroes is a man named Michael N nagler who was a
professor of Peace studies at UC Berkeley for 40 years and I got this
story from him he a book his most recent book on nonviolence called the third dimension and he says he studied these
kinds of these kinds of situations these kinds of people have done this much more
often than we realize and he says they have four things in
common you see a distraught person as a suffering person not a threat or a
monster you show the person they are not alone in their grief
you share your personal pain with them you offer one way or the other the
teaching this too will pass and then the way he writes it you
Buck up the person you Buck the person up you kind of Praise them or do something positive and because many
times these people have never been have been bullied or never never seen with
respect I find it remarkable that in his study these are the four principles he see that's in common with with um you
know so many of these things that don't make the news enough this is what can change the
world so therefore respect or love of one's Oppo opponents is pragmatically
useful I think this is the kind of a teaching from his book respect or love
for one's opponents is pragmatically useful in being a technique that distinguishes the Deeds from the
doers this increases the possibility of the doers changing their behavior and hopefully their
belief so this talk is kind of kind of centered
around this idea of nonviolence but the reason for that is
that this is in Buddhism is that this is a central principle that guides us into
what is sacred into what has the greatest value which is the guides us
into the story that orients all the relationships
we have to everything to events to things to people to this world
it's a fundamentally a relationship of non-harming that's the bottom
line above that there are a few things like
love generosity and kindness and respect and this is not necessarily
unique to Buddhism but I wanted to read a somewhat famous passage for those who know it um in India I think from the
Mahabharata in this 17th chapter so the the Sanskrit word for
non-violence not harming is Aima many of you probably know
it ahimsa is the highest virtue ahima is the highest
self-control ahima is the greatest gift Aima is the best
suffering isn't that the fascinating a Hima is the best
suffering if you're going to suffer suffer because of that a himsa is the highest
sacrifice in United States we have this idea that the higher sacrifice is what
to die because for your
country in war aimsa is the finest strength aimsa
is the greatest friend Aima is the greatest happiness ahima is the highest truth and
aimsa is the greatest
teaching so as we come to this
momentous transformation that will happen at midnight
or 10:30 or 9 in my house we are voluntarily you didn't
realize that maybe you're reluctantly doing it but participating in a mass
movement of a of a relate way to we relate to each other a bridge a network
a connectivity that we all have and when we celebrate New Year's
Eve maybe we're celebrating those relationships and it's arbitrary that
this is the New Year's Eve that we call it that but it's not arbitrary the way
that we're related to each other and you could just ignore this one
and to go to sleep that's fine but don't ignore all
the different ways that you see don't ignore this fact that we're related to each other don't ignore the fact that
that the fundamental way of taking care of yourself is in taking care of the
relationships you have with everything yourself with your
atoms with other people with the natural world it's in relatedness we discover in
relationship we discover the Dharma it's in the relationships that we
discover where we cling and where we're generous where
we're hostile have animosity and where we have love it's in the relationship to
things that we discover wisdom and our foolishness and our
delusion it's in the world of relatedness we discover how to be
free free of all that harms intentionally harms purposely
Harms and that clears the clears the room
clears the room in our hearts for the best qualities of of the heart to come
forth because if the heart did anything the metaphorical
heart it's the deepest most valuable place
from which we can relate to anything and everything
may it be that as we go into this new year and prepare ourselves for all the challenges that
come that we let our heart that deep place
within be the place where each of our worlds
begins that if we want to create a peaceful world a loving world don't wait for other people to do
it don't wait for your politicians to do it it begins with you with how you
relate to the people close to you how you contribute
to harmonious Harmony and peace and the people you know and how that Community
then relates to the bigger communities and the bigger communities let it flow from
you and let that be the place where you rest let that be the place where you're
ready for whatever comes even though the if the world comes with tremendous
challenges that are overwhelming for all of us as they are right now for others in Gaza and Ukraine and Somalia and the
list goes on and on and on the places where people are living under horrendous
challenges there might be our turn next be
ready in such a way way that you always remember that the
world begins with your heart the your world that you relate to your
relatedness that's where it is and this practice can support you and
help you and help you find how to rest in a from a place that always is
creating a good World from you and who knows what you'll be asked
to do the woman who talked the shooter out of
shooting until that moment till that day she
was the public eye for the news and the books who wrote they wrote and all these
things that she was an ordinary person maybe like
you but something came her way and she responded to it and related to it in a
way so who knows what's coming for all of us let's be
ready let's use 2024 not to have hope for what it's
going to bring but have hope for how we can relate to whatever comes we can use
this practice this practice is
powerful and you give yourself to this prce practice well this practice will
show you the way to relate in a way that's beneficial for
yourself and this world may it be
so thank you