there so hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hours lovely To Be With
You In This Moment In Time wherever you are in the world and
um I'm going to invite us to uh to start
practicing together and I will reveal the theme um as we are sitting together as we as
we practice together so let's just uh let's just begin let's just begin with settling in and arriving
ah arriving This Moment In Time
in this body
turning awareness to greet to greet this moment
it's never been like this before reading this body
reading the touch points the contact points
of the body
with the Earth with the floor
the cushion the chair your hands on your lap
feeling embodied
connecting with the breath
neck thing with the sensations of the breath and the Body In This Moment In Time
letting go of and anything else that comes up
letting go of everything else that comes up taking Refuge
the breath and the body in this moment
it's okay to say no it's okay to say no not now but lovingly kindly
no not now thank you thank you so much
the worries fears distractions thank you for trying to warn me distract me
entertain me thank you and not now
and smilingly wholeheartedly giving your heart
the Peace of this moment the joy of this moment
of just simply being and being breathed
not now thank you not now just this
nourishment
of awareness awareness intertwined with kindness
where's ourselves intertwined with the breath
reading the breath with a smile out breath with a smile the in-breath with a smile
thank you
foreign
like a good friend
with a smile foreign
foreign
if you wish
as you continue to feel embodied feeling your feet on the Earth
your bottom of the cushion or the chair your hands on your lap
and breath in your abdomen your whole body
break to mind someone who has been kind to you
recently or in the past
would be a person could be a pet
it doesn't have to be a huge act of kindness but that is fine too
is simple act of kindness
but also be a benefactor or someone who's been kind to you consistently whatever is easy whatever is easy
never comes to mind your heart makes you feel safe
maybe a smile shows up when you think of this being
bring them bring them to your heart to your mind's eye
as if they were with you
feeling either with your
eyes with feeling into the felt sense of being
with this person what they look like what they feel like
asked if if you're new to this practice choose someone who's alive
so it doesn't get complicated with potential grief and sadness
but if your experience it's okay
bringing this person close this being close to your heart
just sitting with them in appreciation foreign
in your life just relishing this gladness gratitude happiness
for your good fortune the care the love you feel for this
being Let It Be Happy making
foreign
goes into a story your memory come back go back and be with this being with this
dear being time is short
remind yourself this is so lovely and nourishing Dear Heart dear mind
be here with this being
have fun this is not a grim Duty you get to be with one of your favorite
people favorite beings as a part of your practice and nourish
your heart with its goodness with the kindness gratitude happiness
yourself have fun with this practice enjoy it
how delightful I get to sit and do this right now
in my heart in my mind hang out with this being thank you
thank you me for my practice
smiling helps it really helps connect with this practice and spending
time with dear being even if you don't feel like smiling do
it anyway where the half smile of the Buddha
if perchance any challenging perspectives aspects of your relationship come up
okay have kindness towards yourself of kindness towards this dear being
you're doing your best they're doing their best
be kind be kind
and as you're hanging out in your heart in your mind with this dear being
if you like you can add the phrases of meta
or just stay with the feeling the images with the felt scent
and I'll repeat the phrases you might have your own which is fine
these are the more traditional phrases variations are fine
and keep connected to their image of their short sense bringing them close
may you be safe dear one or say their name may you be safe dear
so and so
may you be safe from inner and outer arm knowing that absolute safety is not
guaranteed in the world but we offer this as a wish as a gift of kindness aop may you be
safe I wish you safety wish you safety dear one
second phrase may you be happy I wish you happiness
may you have joy in your heart maybe imagine I'm happy
retrace may you be healthy dear one as much as possible I wish you health
I wish you strength in your body
and maybe see them strong healthy
maybe walking exercising whatever works
in your mind's eye have fun with it
and the fourth raise I mean to do with ease may you have ease dear one hey you take
care of yourself happily may your life unfold with ease
may you be safe connecting with safety
connecting with the person with the being foreign
maybe healthy
may you have ease
let yourself have fun sharing good good wishes
good will for this being your heart bring them close
your meta play time with this being foreign
foreign
if you like including yourself now may both of us may both of us seeing both of
you together sitting walking
dancing whatever it might be you and your dear person your easy
person do or have done May both of us may both
of us be safe
happy see both of you happy perhaps
in a tableau in your mind
smiling fake it till you become it
may we both be happy wish us both happiness
may we both be healthy healthy and strong
see both of you healthy and some activity together
may we both have ease
again we offer these wishes not with attachment to outcome as
a way to Incline our hearts to Goodwill Good Will kindness generosity of spirit
towards ourselves towards others so give these wishes
generously freely to both of you
foreign
and maybe turning to yourself now she
well for yourself may I be safe
self-safety happiness
health and ease
imagining yourself in these
conditions of well-being
have fun with it
maybe drawing a tableau from a time that you're really happy
doing an activity you love feeling strong sense of ease feel it in your body
invite invite the feeling into your heart so if you could breathe it in right now
getting taller with more ease happiness
well-being
spreading spreading this light
of goodness happiness well-being shining it outward
may all beings everywhere be safe
hey all things everywhere be happy
may they be healthy may they have ease
wishing your kindness generously wish of well-being for everyone including
myself may all beings everywhere be truly well
no well-being may all beings everywhere including
myself be free
[Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your practice foreign
I feel happier calmer have a smile that doesn't want to
leave my face after having done meta practice for an easy person dear being and then
turning it to both of us and then turning it to ourselves and then sharing it with all beings everywhere
ah medai is Happy making generosity the simple Act of generosity
of the heart so so we have time actually now we're
going to turn yes we have time for groups that's right we're going to turn with the sense of well-being with a
sense of Good Will the sense of Goodwill for ourselves or one another
we are going to turn to uh
to each other to to small groups we're going to practice in small groups
and uh the invitation always in the small
groups is if he wanted to share something from your own practice something from your practice maybe an
aha moment or a challenge or anything or anything at all or I was distracted the
whole time fell asleep that's okay too you're welcome to share you can also show up and share kindness just say pass
right now um I'm I'm just going to be silent and and if you're gonna say something maybe
limited to a minute or less so that other people have a chance to say
something and they'll come back to you roping groups are about seven minutes or so
so um and be kind to yourself be kind to each other
no questions no interrogation or one another just share whatever you wish and
hold witness to each other really this is a Sandbox to to practice kindness to
practice kindness in small community and be inspired
so so I'm going to create the um breakout rooms
and again confidentiality is always important whatever you say here stays
here please and I've created the rooms let's go alphabetically first name okay the rooms
are created and I'm gonna open them now here we go
okay welcome back everyone welcome back um I see many smiles which is always
nice to see Smiles coming back from the rooms from the breakout groups and and
we have time before any Reflections you like to share for the benefit of yourself and when I say yourself in the
way of being witnessed sometimes actually when we share an aha or a question it's it supports us and also
for the for the benefit of the community because if some question has come up for you or an aha moment actually can can
help others so and you can type it in chat uh either privately to me if you
have an observation reflection or to everyone and and you can raise your Zoom
hand um especially if you haven't shared [Music] um
in the community for a while I would love to invite you to pull forward
love to hear from you
yeah man am I saying your name right it's Yaman Yemen great
um thank you for the practice I felt very present and calm I had a question
for you you mentioned attachment and I was just thinking about how you can
practice uh kindness and compassion and not be too attached
yeah yeah yeah exactly so so so the the practice
um basically I'll start with what I meant in the guided meditation when I
was suggesting you know these wishes that we share may you be well may you be
happy maybe healthy and may I be you know all these wishes so I'm like okay I've been wishing you well are you well
yet like you're calling your friend okay I've been sending you meta are you happy now it's like there's sense of oh I have
the power or or I'm wishing my what myself well I really want to be happy I
really am so unhappy I want to be just like ouch it just it's not really a generous way of offering kindness It's
it's offering kindness with conditions or or sometimes also with other peels
like may you be well if you're gonna be nice to me you're gonna you know you're wishing someone well is conditional
kindness right so so without attachment to outcome it's
just the generosity of art it's the sense of generosity of I wish you well you know you might be suffering right
now I know that and and yet I wish you well I wish you well I it's it's about
my heart it's not so much about the conditions of the world and it's not that I want to control it and you wish
yourself well with it like a really really or clinging around it but it it's again
it's a difference between expectation and aspiration
expectation is when you say you are kind with an expectation of outcome it
expectation for return expect whereas there's an aspiration you're just as there's a sense of uplift that you're
sharing generosity or Spirit does that make sense
yes yes thank you you're welcome thank you for the question Yaman now I'm saying your
name right thanks for that question great one anyone else any other questions or
Reflections what came up for you my practice report is that I was having
a great time I was having a really fun time wishing well for my dear being and
and for both of us and just very joyous it's it's nice to have fun with this practice
can be very happy making hence happy hour do you feel happier now that before you
joined yes can I see it now or no shake or not yes yes I see more than I haven't
seen any shakes yet but then again I always say very few of you
any other reflections like to share before we close
kneel so
sometimes I find it difficult to give method to people who I think are
like really well off I'm like well they don't need this
um right and and it you know I guess it seems silly to me right because of
course they do right and second well it's really more about me than them
um that said you know this has been like a consistent you know sort of feeling
so so I'm yeah what advice do you have for me yeah yeah
I love it I love the question I love the curveball Neil it's awesome because like
the curvy part of it is is your own wisdom like yeah I know they
need it um and it's for the benefit of my heart and yet and yet so so let's explore that
so so let's explore um the you know they don't need it
okay so let's explore that they don't need it and then the wisdom comes back
and says well they really do so so can you share a little more about how that
is you know maybe it's up in the head not in the heart flesh that out for me a little bit if
it's okay to be on the spot for a moment with this exploration
because it's really bad because it's that that's the Crux of it go ahead well you know people you know I have a friend
he seems pretty happy pretty much all the time like wishing I'm happy you know uh right
I I you know I'm friends with him for decades I'm not sure what would be different occasionally he's stressed
right I you know then I understand you know may you not be stressed right but
that's it but that's it but that's it stress is dukkha everybody has dukkha is
the is translated as stress it's not just these huge sufferings and calamities I realized but stress daily
stress but just the daily stress of the body aging and having aches and pains
you have to take care of it and all of this is stress you have to wake up in the morning make sure you go to sleep like these are Thai these are stresses
of life that all of us have so so he had and then but
then you're sharing that he actually has some stressful times and yet really for so for this friend uh he was always
happy um it then it's clearly for your own heart if you if you wish happiness for
someone who's already happy then it becomes mudita practice then it becomes a joy you're happy that they're happy
and your happiness increases hmm
that's an interesting way to look at it basically this is your perfect modita
practice person what you're describing When You Wish happiness for a person
who's already happy it becomes happiness for their happiness and then you're practicing with vicarious joy happiness
for the happiness and of others and guess who gets really happy doing that practice you Neil
okay okay I'll I'll give it a try
perfect words I'll give it a try that's it that's the spirit yeah we're all giving everything a try right we're just
trying it out like oh yeah that works well that's interesting awesome I'm so glad you brought this up Neil this this
was fun to explore together in real time thank you thank you
ah well my heart feels joyous having explore this practice with you and uh
thank you all thank you for your practice thank you for your cultivation thank you for supporting yourself
supporting each other supporting others with your practice may all beings be
well may all beings be free including ourselves foreign
[Music] take care