so welcome good morning uh good afternoon even evening I believe
um
it's nice to see all the names and uh lovely yeah
um you know I talk a big game about uh
letting go and uh that's honest I try to represent my life
and practice with a lot of honesty but the uh Golden State Warriors played
last night for those who don't know it's a local
basketball team sports ball some people call it and um
they're at the end of kind of dynastic run and uh
it was a tight game and I was
as the kids say a hot mess and I had this moment
as I was being told to calm down had this moment of thinking like I am
not a person who anyone should ever listen to or look
to for wisdom
um that I thought of you and um
Wild but here we are
ah something about caring for things that
actually don't really matter that I like
um they won they won by the way Steph
yeah um okay that's the intro for our meditation
and uh let us uh let us contemplate
the depths of human potential okay
so finding a posture feels sustainable
foreign
just taking stock of your heart
the impacts and residues
of the day so far the week this year
whatever's here in this moment just awake to the residues of the moment
and we relax
willing to feel whatever residues are here
maybe we use the the breathing to smooth out the energy
of our body mind
to to unify the field of the body
cooling the hyperintensity is
enlivening the
unconscious or numbed out Zone
there is a kind of effort we make in practicing
that we want to be careful about
not letting our willfulness eclipse
the grace of this moment
the way is the
self-based efforting
obscures something important
and so you're invited to relax that too
the effort we make is partnered
the effort to relax these surges
of willfulness
to actually sense the abrasiveness
of always doing something to the moment to ourselves
and then in a way there is nothing left to do but be awake
and it can be supportive to have of course an anchor for the
attention for the attentional spotlight
but uh
the attention often
as a kind of flavor of meanness
the awareness that emerges out of that attention
doesn't taste like me
whatever doesn't depend on you
rest there
foreign
okay
the uh contemplation of mortality can support
uh samadhi can cut through the noise and
clarify what of value to us
and um and today insight into self self limits
of willfulness the ways in which my
my life does not belong entirely to me
and mortality offers uh us the
contemplation maybe we can say the egos helplessness
the world that is unresponsive to our willfulness
Tuesday I think was futurelessness
samadhi today helplessness because
what of life is left when the ego is all out of moves
and death um
is in one sense a kind of the ultimate humbling
but also the source of a great deal of our
of our grandiosity and
this sense of of self sense of self as a kind of Hub of control so what I was
alluding to with the ways in which you know the direction of attention the
kind of attentional Spotlight can incarnate a congealed sense of self
a sense of like me as the attentional agent
foreign the attention to the breathing or the
body or this or that and then and then something else in the
field that does not depend on us that does not taste like me
the sense of self is the kind of Hub of control this is
um death obliterates control and throws us off
so one Gabriel Vasquez
adulthood um brings with it the pernicious illusion of control perhaps even depends
on it I mean the Mirage of dominion over our
life that allows us to feel like adults where we associate maturity with autonomy
Sovereign right to determine what's going to happen next disillusion comes sooner or later no one
who lives long enough can be surprised to find their biography has been molded
by distant events by other people's Wills with little or no participation
from our own decisions those along processes that end up
running into our life sometimes to give it the shove it needed sometimes
to blow to Smithereens or most Splendid plans tend to be hidden like
Subterranean currents like tiny shifts of tectonic plates
when the earthquake finally comes we invoke the words we've learned to calm
ourselves accident fluke sometimes fate
what is what is our relationship to helplessness
before we die we want to develop a relation
a relationship to helplessness that's Michelle McDonald's language
often would say like develop a relationship with
and sometimes I think a synonym for dukkah usually translated suffering a
synonym for ducas may be helplessness and there's almost always some move to
make but our capacity for for
influence creates the illusion of control
and then we come to a place where there's no move
to make and maybe we've not developed a kind of relationship with helplessness
and part of meditation practice is about willingly
experiencing helplessness
we call it surrender
maybe we call it equanimity
and part of why we do this is that willfulness
obscures certain qualities of the heart mind
the moment is never perfect when I'm in it
it can feel um can feel terrible not to be able to do something
um it's yeah it's like the Cardinal you know an animal it's like helplessness has got to be
the lowest on the list you know you can feel so terrible but then then
of course there's like so much relief sometimes
sometimes when we actually just give up on exerting ourself
like on making change unchanging something someone
and so I part of this contemplation of
mortality is is to help us find a way to keep our heart open even amidst
powerlessness where
we're surrendering our clinging or doing nothing left to engineer
um Tibetan teacher can say ripache said something like I don't remember it exactly but something like at the end of
our life our mind gets very small or very vast
and I for sure have seen both
and sometimes when people are at the end of their life and they have nothing
in a sense nothing left to defend no territory to defend nothing really left
to fear the love gets a very vast
right it's like the hatred and the contraction
the tightness is a is a function of the
territoriality the fear
said that um you know we
we usually think about the self as the cause of things but the Buddha said that
it's it's the effect the self is the effect of things the
effect of what to my mind most centrally I'd say it's
the effect of fear
and part of how we we kind of Ensure our safety
is by by uh in a sense we orchestrate our Survival by by
hallucinating self the self in a certain sense feels like
the kind of headquarters of my clinging you know
longing for more fear of an end
and so in our practice we we can notice like the more
safe it feels in meditation
the more deeply the moment feels like Refuge
the more we can forget ourselves
the more safe we feel the more we forget ourselves
and then some stimulus frightens us
right we hear something we think something with the knee hurts
and we like are chased back into the corner of self
so maybe we say self is is it it may be partially it's the the effect of fear
but it's also part of what makes death seem so terrifying
because um you can feel like we imagine death from the perspective of self or
imagining the destruction of the self
and
where where in a certain way protecting a phantom
you know I I don't think insight into I'm not not self is like a perfect
consolation for death and loss it's not a perfect
consolation and it's imperfection that's the theme for tomorrow not perfect
but it's very meaningful it's pretty good
the philosopher the very famous quote Derek parfaith
it's difficult to believe that there is no such thing as an All or
Nothing self no deep further fact
beyond the multitude of small psychological facts that make you who you are but I believe that my existence was such
a further fact I seemed imprisoned in myself my life seemed like a glass tunnel
through which I was moving faster every year and at the end of which there was
Darkness when I change my view
the walls of my glass tunnel disappeared I now live
in the open air there is still difference between my
life and the lives of other people but the difference is less
other people are closer I'm less concerned about the rest of my
life and more concerned about the lives of others
death and self willfulness surrender
for this for your consideration so uh yeah may we live well today yeah
maybe maybe we live well whatever that means
um yeah touching to uh be with you and uh be uh swimming in
these Waters together so thank you