good morning everyone or hello good afternoon in some places evening
and others happy to be here with you
and we continue uh you know this overall series on
practice working with challenges
one of the important principles of Buddhism is that
our inner life what we how we engage it how we work it
is the nutriment the food for certain
things to grow so we want to be careful what we feed and one way of understanding this is
that our capacity for attention is a kind of food this that feeds whatever it
goes into and so if we give all our
attention to fear to despair to
anger to preoccupation to
our imagination our projections of what's going to happen
if all our attention goes in there we're actually feeding those very things in a certain way or feeding something which
is not actually so beneficial for us and the analogy would be maybe something
like if a person has two Good Feet that they can walk on
and and they've learned to walk and they can be walk stably and well and
and um but if they give no attention zero attention to
their feet as they walk and all their attention goes into the hands swinging making sure they swing
far enough and far enough away from the body close enough to the body the right
whatever just everything goes into there absorbs and just The Swinging of the arms
then the feet might be functioning but the full support the full
um benefits of those feet might not be available to us we might not notice
where we're stepping we might not notice that there's a cliff we're walking into we might walk on difficult gravel and
not really pay attention to where to walk or slippery ground and not pay attention so because we're not paying
attention to our walking and our feet and where they go we are not benefiting
from what's possible how they can support us so the same way if we're most of our
attention is going into our preoccupations our fears our all these things
then we're not available for a broader support as we go through our
life one of those supports the Buddha gave is
our posture and he talks about in mindfulness
instructions clearly knowing that you're sitting when you're sitting the posture of sitting
know that you're standing when you're standing know that you're walking as you walk and
know that you're lying down as you're lying down it's so simplistic this instruction it's easy to dismiss it ignore just kind of
sail right over it then reading it but it's actually pretty fundamental and
it's fundamental in working with challenges if we can have uh really
engage our posture as a place to inhabit or in in body
awareness embodied posture just when we're standing really no clearly know and
embody standing sitting embody and know we're sitting
and so forth and whatever posture you're in then
um it's like then we have enough attention to our feet as we walk to get the support of the feet
then if we're in our in challenges then not all our attention is going into
the challenges we might be thinking about it focusing on it enough
but we're not lost in it we have a grounding we have a place of stability
we have a place that keeps us balanced more and uh and keeps us connected
to the present moment in a vital way in a way that is um
uh wonderfully animated or wonderfully kind of connected
and um and so it's a protection from getting lost in just paying attention to
the hand swinging as if that's all there is it's a protection from getting preoccupied in our challenges in such a
way that um we're not really don't have available to us the full intelligence of our whole
system we can get lost in that world and finally
um it's one thing to try to do this when we're in a challenge
it might be too late but the more we can practice mindfulness all the different aspects of mindfulness
but the more we can cultivate an embodied presence in the posture or whatever we're doing
and that becomes a second nature becomes really a grounding or familiar with it
and and the channels are quite open and clear about why this is beneficial we
feel it then we're prepared for challenges then we bring that with us into the challenge
and we'll find there's a strength there's a grounding there's a a whole
kind of support system present that we wouldn't have if we weren't
mindful so cultivating this mindfulness of posture is one of the important steps
that the Buddha gives for working with challenges so
assuming a meditative posture
each person will find their own posture that's right for them
couple of guidelines around meditation posture is ideally it's a posture
where there's no obstructions nothing is constricted or collapsed
some people you find it useful to loosen their belt if it feels tight then constricting
there
it's also useful to have a posture that does feel aligned and balanced
a lying so that both sides of the body are
as doing the same thing as close as possible given the circumstances of your body
aligned so that the muscles of your body
have the best opportunity to relax deeply
slumping in a couch to meditate might be better than being tense
but it also doesn't allow for the muscles to relax that deeply
some people avoid is upright align posture because then they feel their tensions of their body
that's okay we can still cultivate this embodied
awareness of posture
and also we begin we offer the creating the conditions for
that tension to really relax deeply that they wouldn't do if we mask it
by slumping in the chair or something
gently closing the eyes
and taking you a few long slow deep breaths
and those deep inhales if you really take a full inhale as
you're comfortable with and take maybe even hold the end inhale
a little bit at the top and with that adjust your posture
exhale a long exhale and at the end hold your breath for two
seconds and see if you can relax more of your body
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and for a few more breaths relax in your body
one of the functions of relaxing in the body is to bring your awareness into the body
so you can be more embodied a greater sensitivity
how the body reveals itself through Sensations
and then taking a few moments to feel your body globally
and with a global awareness of your body to whatever degree you can
have kind of a relaxed Global awareness of your posture
the sensations accompanying your posture
what your posture looks like from the outside doesn't matter
with your posture feels like from the inside does matter
and as the posture feeling the sensations
think of it as the support
the gentle holding of a deeper embodied attention to
breathing posture
is a grounding Here and Now
that holds the sensations of breathing
and in some ways if you're aware of the breathing in your torso
the expanding and Contracting of the breathing
touches up against your posture at least there in your torso
in the posture touches your breathing
perhaps giving a little bit more attention to your posture
just a little bit so the posture grounds you more Here and Now
it maybe supports your attention to breathing
through the present moment
and as we get come to the end of this sitting
to again bring some attention to your posture
but imagine
that you're sitting with someone who's a friend or someone you respect and
who you trust feel comfortable with
and the person is sitting in front of you with a posture that shows presence
balance they're fully grounded in themselves
aware and at the same time they seem fully
present for you
not leaning forward not pulling back
eyes are soft the hands and arms are soft the
shoulders are relaxed but the spine seems almost like their torso seems like
embodiment of attention
balance a certain strength
and as they're sitting there in front of you you become more aware of your own posture
hopefully without any Judgment of what what it is
but how would you adjust your posture for a few seconds
to resonate with their posture
how would you adjust your posture to be more grounded
so your torso is more present and
maybe even next curtain certain kind of strength
of presence of being here in the present
maybe your chest a little more open
and then the two of you close your eyes and then you realize that with your eyes
closed you're less self-conscious and allows your heart to open
allows your Good Will and your friendship your kindness to flow
and you sit here quietly with a friendly disposition a kind
disposition not necessarily wishing anything for
anyone but says present with your friend others
the whole world
or their friendliness or uh Generous Heart
with love
with a disposition that
it would be easy for you to have
thoughts words and actions of good will of care
spreading your welfare and well-being to all beings
so that in your small way
you contribute to the welfare and happiness
of everyone may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
hello everyone and welcome to this second talk and the series on
mindfulness of the body using the Buddha's teachings on
mindfulness of the body as a support for how to work with the challenges that life gives us
no matter what the challenges are and the second instruction the Buddha
gives and his teachings are mindfulness to the body is mindfulness of posture
and posture can be a difficult topic for people and challenging sometimes with all kinds of
physical conditions that exist but it's also a part of
the integral part of human life is we always in some posture other physical posture
and the Buddha emphasized the value of bringing attention to it to really know
the posture we're in and um and then begin discovering the different
dimensions that different ways in which mindfulness of posture can support us
support us tremendously and um
and in terms of challenges one of the things that mindfulness of posture can support
is that it um is a preventive
from all our attention to go into our challenges into the our fear our dismay
or preoccupation or imagination or spinning thoughts
um and if all of it goes into the challenges we have it can be a dark hole
we can collapse sometimes it um it strengthens the sense of inner challenge
the fear perhaps or the dismay or the anger it fuels it and keeps it going and
some people will can spill out in fear or panic because of the loop between
their thinking and and causing fear and fear causing more
thinking and or depression the same thing there can be this Loop and that Loop is strengthened by the
degree in which attention is given to those thoughts or attention is given the
solely to the emotions that are there and it's remarkable that when there's
fear or when there's anger when there's confusion when there's greed all kinds of these
strong forces in the mind people have a tremendous capacity for concentration
the very people who stand sit down to meditate and they say I don't have any ability to concentrate
give them a good threat and boy they can be focused on it
everything goes into it and all their thinking and thoughts and feelings
give them a good thing to be angry with and boy some people can be zero in you
know one pointed almost like boom they're right there they're not going to kind of leave it behind they're like
stuck on it so we do have a many people have much
more capacity of our concentration than they realize it's just harder to do it for some
people when there's nothing no threat nothing to blame nothing to
trigger self-preoccupation self-identity self-conceit which is kind of can be a
magnet for preoccupied attention and so to begin bringing attention to
the posture is to break the hegemony of
some of these strong difficult mind states that come into play when we're
with challenges not denying their real challenges but the excessive preoccupation Rhythm
the excessive absorption in them is counterproductive
and it's actually works it's we think that the more attention we can give to
something the better we can take care of it but actually sometimes it can be the opposite when we have the challenges in
our life and so we want to find some way for our attention to to be be more beneficial
for us as we go through these challenges and one of the ways is to have our
attention rooted or grounded in our body
and one of the ways to do that is to be cognizant of the posture we're in
and uh and more so uh in like in meditation for example the meditation posture there's a lot of
value to having that posture be in intentional
so you know you could just kind of lay down in bed and just kind of completely kind of collapse and for some people
laying in bed and just really relaxing is very powerful I don't want to undermine its value
but you might not get the same benefits uh in the long term and in daily life
when there's challenges if you don't somewhere or other begin cultivating
the value of a grounded intentional posture and intentional means that it takes a
little bit of internal effort intention to maintain it
it uh there's in order to maintaining consistently there has to be a consistent attention
so the upright meditation posture eventually becomes second nature eventually there's a kind of meditative
energy that keeps us upright and alert but there's a lot also a kind of a
foreground or background intentionality to stay upright and in
the beginning we're beginners we slump and we sit up straight we slump we say until we find this place intentionality
to stay present um and uh and to take an intentional
posture that allows for presence allows for really being there with something
so maybe turning towards something or sitting upright or standing upright in a
balanced way um not crossing the arms or crossing the legs in such a way that something's
obstructed something is limited something is closed down but just sit in a way that everything becomes kind of
open available present flowing unobstructed within an intentional
posture and to learn how to be embodied in it to be
grounded in the sensations to be inhabiting intentionally and
attentionally this posture not as the beal and end-all for sure
but so that it becomes second nature to be grounded and present in a good way as we
go through our challenges so we learn not to collapse physically in the presence of our challenges so we
learn now to get to tense up unnecessarily in the middle of our
challenges the posture is a mirror for seeing what
our relationship is to our challenges and if you're if you have a kind of balanced
posture as a reference point a line posture that's open unobstructed present
you'll have a very wonderful reference to catch earlier if you collapse
if you slump if you kind of give up or if you give in to some kind of the
pressure of the anger the pressure of the fear and start spinning out
and the posture is uh was an earlier warning sign of what your relationship
is that might not be so beneficial for you it's also a to maintain a strong
balanced posture rather than collapsing or or acting out
it's amazing how that it's not denying how we're feeling but it's almost like
giving a room for how we're feeling so some deeper process of unfolding evolving healing can happen that cannot
happen if we collapse it cannot happen if we engage from a place of hostility
or blame or or something else
um this mindfulness really puts us in our bodies so that there's a deeper process of the bodily wisdom and
intelligence can kind of move and relax and open up what's going on so that we
can think more clearly so that we can see the situation more clearly without our projections and our fears and our
emotions kind of excessively
filtering our perceptions so to um
to cultivate to make a practice of being of of
intentional balanced unobstructed posture in different circumstances you
might try it standing in line in a store I don't know what you usually do
standing there but you might stand there and you know both feet on the ground feet apart just balanced and and just
stand there with a full maybe their eyes cast down because you don't have to see much more than the person in front of
you goes forward and you can take the next step forward to the cashier but just really be there and and
practice this embodied intentional attention of posture
an intentional really to see what you can learn about a posture that allows for a kind of strength and
attention a strength confidence in your ability to be present and here
it might be how you sit in a chair you might experiment with times and
places where you don't slump or relax into the chair but you sit away from the
backrest and really sit there and if where you kind of are offering to the
room to lose there a stronger presence here I am
so standing walking it can be done laying down even when people need to lay down to
meditate there's a way of really being careful with a posture that it's somewhat intentional really laying the
body out carefully and and balanced and maybe the knees are up and that has a
little bit of intentionality some people who meditate laying down will have one hand with the upper arm kind of along
the sides of the chest and the forearm pointing right up to the ceiling so it's
a little bit of intentionality is needed to keep that straight and going upright so it's value of intentionality
and then walking walk with confidence
because chances are that a confident walk begins offering you a beneficial posture
to be in if you give too much effort into the confidence you might over overshoot
but kind of take a confident posture as you walk and and be embodied in that
confidence be embodied in the in the in the walking and and track what goes on in your
posture what goes on in your body as you do so if you're in a kind of varied
place where a lot of different things are going on it's fascinating to watch the Kaleidoscope of little responses and
reactions in the body depending on something as simple as walking in the Sun and then finding
yourself walking in the shade walking down a sidewalk with no one's there and then someone comes opposite
direction um you know all kinds of things begin happening that maybe track and what goes
on in the body with your response reactions and and see if you can maintain this confident upright posture
in walking so there is um
it's a hugely valuable and multifaceted practice to practice mindfulness of the
POS of posture and I just scratch the surface of it now
but if you start practicing it and discovering it and make it second nature
to have a balanced aligned mindful posture then you'll be ready for challenges in
the future if you're in the middle of a challenge and you try to have this
support and refuge of a of your posture you might not have developed it well
enough to really make a difference but building it up over time you'll be
surprised that one day you'll go through a challenge and you'll discover that your posture has provided a tremendous
support so you go through it in a balanced way
so thank you very much and we'll continue this series tomorrow