so good morning everyone and uh or good
day nice to have the idea that I'm saying hello and greetings around the
world and uh was a time when that couldn't be
done so
so I want to begin by saying
that when we give mindfulness instructions or try to practice
mindfulness that often people will try too
much uh it's like you try now to make your mind mind be present or focus on
the breath or do something like that and the mind wanders off and we bring the Mind back and bring my mind back and I'm
and that can be done in a beautiful way harmonious way but often there's uh
there can be a strain or a push or a uh you know an effort to be
mindful and uh there are other exercises that uh might evoke a more harmonious
form of mindfulness a mindfulness that follows along and is there kind of as a
support just comes along um and it isn't that we're emphasizing mindfulness but
mindfulness is there it has to be there in other ways of
being and the one what I want to emphasize today is atunement and there's a practice of
becoming attuned to our life to our experience but for
this morning in meditation I'd like to emphasize Attunement to
U oneself we sit down to be present for
ourselves with ourselves by ourselves uh to become attuned here to
what's going on for us and there are some definitions of
Attunement and
um the uh the ones
that so there are some definitions of Attunement and ones that I like are to
be ready and res aware and receptive to be aware and receptive to
be receptively to be just to be receptive requires awareness and to be in
harmony with what you're receptive to or what you're aware of and um and this idea of Harmony is
what I want to emphasize today because Harmony means we're no longer in
conflict with anything We're In Harmony with it even if we have to say no to
something um there's a harmonious way of doing that that we're not setting up the tension
of oppos tense opposition or uh or
contracted kind of uh um disagreement with something or
criticism of something and um we're we're receptive
so especially when we're sitting here meditating with ourselves is there way of being receptive to all of who we are
and to not be in conflict with anything and to find what does it mean to have
the question what does it mean to be in harmony with this it does not mean giving into
anything there's a wisdom factor that comes into play that oh I'm in harmony with this by not interfering with it
without getting involved in it without pushing it away letting it kind of take
its course to be in harmony to with uh the
natural world to be in harmony with our natural world within ourselves and if we do that then
mindfulness will follow there has to be awareness if we're asking how to be
receptive and in Harmony and uh in this absence of
conflict absence of strain is one of the things that brings joy to meditation
practice and the joy of Attunement the joy of finding harmony with what's here
now and um so we we'll meditate
to find a harmonious posture for
yourself a posture that's harmonious with finding a greater
harmony with ourselves a greater alignment a greater
Attunement a greater non-interference to
the aliveness that can be here
within sometimes if we take too relaxed a posture it might feel
comfortable but it might not allow for the free harmonious flow of
vitality and aliveness and it
gently relax your eyes whether they're closed or open
maybe letting the your eyes rest in their
sockets resting the eyes so there's no effort to to look at
anything if the eyes are open a
focus it's not that's soft and wide
and not trying to see
anything and to take a few long slow deep breaths with the
inhale just getting to know discovering
what reveals itself in the
body feeling the body more fully on the inhale and in the longer
exhale settling in to this body
relaxing
letting your breathing return to normal and a lot of the information we
need to find in Attunement to ourselves is found in our body
to be receptive and [Music] aware of how the body
is maybe not needing it to be any other
way but in the Attunement to how the body
is a gentle but greater sensitivity
receptivity to whatever Sensations exist in the
body not prioritizing any one set of Sensations
or but tuning on ourselves to the global
experience of being in a
body and to to be attuned is to be aware without
strain tightness
contraction even if there is strain or contraction there's an art of Attunement
to that as you would be attuned to a friend
may be in a difficult State being present and open
and maybe you're a calm presence in harmony with your
friend
attuned
and within this body as part of the
body there's the experience of
breathing not focusing on the breath or but rather to be receptive
attuned to how the breathing is breathing
itself or how it's breathing with strain or
effort finding a way of relating of no knowing the
breathing that feels in harmony with it or feels ATT tune to how it
is an Attunement that allows for a
care
for
e
not trying to change anything in meditation but instead
to be attuned to ourselves in the present
moment as we
are a kind of deep
listening deep
sensitivity that is not in conflict with
anything but instead
available to know it to sense it as it is
for
e
to be attuned to oneself as one
meditates so one is not in conflict with
anything but rather aware receptive
attentive
harmoniously appreciating whatever degree of non-conflict you
have sitting here in the middle of your lived
life
for
and notice if there's any Joy
or well-being found within whatever
Attunement you might have with yourself sitting here meditating
here
e
and as we come to the end of this
meditation the more we are ATT tuned to ourselves the more we're not
divided from ourselves with inner conflict the greater can be our
Attention our awareness of others our receptivity and
sensitivity so we could also find a way of being attuned to how they
are tuned
in understanding sensitive to the state of others without
conflict and without
assertion without an overlay of interpretations
and
meaning many people value being listened
to and Attunement is is just a expansion of
listening to our whole being listening or
present may we find ways to be deeply
attuned to others so they feel respect did and
cared for and recognized they don't so they don't feel
judged or criticized or belittled or used for our own
purposes May our meditation
practice be a support for promoting the welfare and happiness
of this world may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be
free
[Music]
thank [Music]
you
so so hello and welcome to this second talk on the joy of
compassion and I think this is a very important concept that can there can be
joy and compassion and to keep this as a reference point for our compassion
is is a protection from The Compassion becoming uh tense or strain full or
oppressive or exhausting um it's can be difficult to
be present for suffering in oneself and suffering for others and part of the
medicine for suffering is compassionate presence care and for that to be healthy for
everyone involved um it has to avoid tension and
strain and assertion and collapse and the kind of way of being that is not
sustainable because there's exhaustion or and um and so there just the very
idea that there's joy or well-being in the experience of compassion puts a
question mark next to any other way that we are any strain full or difficult way that we are when we have compassion
and I'd like to believe that the notion of Joy it get of compassion uh
encourages us to slow down with our compassion to not be in a hurry to act
but rather to take the time to find a healthy way of relating to the suffering
of others suffering of the world and one of those ways is to be
attuned to find a way to certainly be aware aware of
it and but not just to be aware of it to have a certain kind of openness or
receptivity to receive it just as like we would be receptive to rece uh
receptive listener to hear a friend of ours talk about their challenges uh the friend doesn't feel
that we are you know we're reluctantly listening listening or half-heartedly
listening or or somehow listening in a judgmental
way and but we're just listening receptive and aware so in in the same
way uh we we attune ourselves to the suffering of the world before we act
before we rush to to do something and because that
atunement is uh an absence of strain an absence of assertion an absence of
conflict with ourselves or for the others um there can be Joy there can be
a well-being there can be a sense of nourishment there can be a lightness
there can be a sense of rightness even if it's painful to be very painful
sometimes to be with suffering in the world um Attunement that maybe don't
feel necessarily Joy but there's something that feels right to be present
there's an openness a relaxedness ah okay this is how it
is and um and uh and this is also where
it's very important to be attune to oneself sometimes with compassion the idea is that it's all about the other
person that we or other people or the suffering out there and we're not
supposed to count and we lose touch with ourselves in their rush to to act or in their rush to be
somehow focused on this the suffering out there but uh it's important to be present and
attuned to oneself and this is where the kind of guideline of um dividing our
attention 5050 between out there and in ourselves allows for actually a greater
attentiveness to others than if we just give our attention to others and the reason for that is we're tuned to
ourselves or we're here we we tend to uh overcome the conflicts the
distractedness the tightness the ways that we are that lets our attention out
there be incomplete be partial but if we keep enough attention
here for ourselves we can relax and open up and actually have much greater
attention than it to others than a partial attention which straining that seems like we're only
paying attention to the other person and so rather than it being a
loss 50/50 like less compassion less care for others uh there's actually more
when we are attuned to ourselves as well and when we learn the art of not being in conflict with anything that's going
on inside of ourselves even those things which are unfortunate or not so
wonderful about ourselves because we've learned to be attuned without giving into it attuned without being pushed
around by it or acting on it so we can make SP space for how we are and as we
make space for ourselves we develop the capacity to make space for others and to
begin there before we rush to judgment before we rush to fix and to
change and so this lack of conflict this Attunement this
harmony uh is a delight and uh it just feels so good uh
it's kind of refreshing to be in the World attuned um because I mean partly because
Attunement to self and others means that the very Act of Attunement is not a
strain the act of Attunement is a kind of opening a kind of relaxing outward
and being present and receptive and here and it just feels delightful to be alive
in this way and to have this capacity to connect to others this way and and um so
there can be a joy in the Attunement and so if we're going to
really allow our compassion to flow out of atunement then the compassion will share
in that Joy share in that lightness or that sense of well-being or sense of
Freedom or sense of of rightness I want to give many many words not just call it
Joy because suffering is so difficult some sometimes that it's you know to say
that there's joy and compassionate presence for it is um maybe too much or
not quite right but there is something that feels that does feel right a
rightness uh a goodness a sweetness
a gentleness so I'm not you know there's many I don't know different circumstances maybe different positive
states are present uh in the compassionate Attunement to others and the com these
these positive States uh can be a nourishment for
ourselves it can have a positive influence on ourselves and maybe if we
lucky a nourishment or positive influence the world around us um I've rushed to take care of
problems and uh and the in the rush to take care of people or something I don't
really show up with the best the best of how I am and maybe I'm for example I
might feel strain or tension and so that tension comes along and people can feel
it but if I arrive attuned and without that tension then uh my presence I hope
is helpful to other people to relax with their challenges um and then as we become more
and more attuned and uh then at some point we're ready for action
and uh to do something but as we did in this series so far um the emphasis is
whenever there's a chance set in the set that set create the foundation for
compassion uh don't have a rush to compassion and um and uh and then as
you're compassionate as you even act with compassion um stay attuned to yourself
to to recognize is there Joy is there a
well-being uh is there a sense of freedom because it's so easy to lose it
as we get involved in the action and relatedness relating to other
people so the joy of compassion it's m many forms of joy that
can come along yesterday I talked about the joy that comes with being aware and
having an awareness practice today it's the joy that come excuse
me today it's the joy that comes from um be uh being
attuned and having a practice of Attunement so the joy of not doing
something 100% successfully all the time but the joy of engaging in the process
of doing it well so that there's room for our you know for our tentative efforts or
maybe incomplete efforts or you know ways in which we're still practicing and finding our
way so and may um May you find the joy of
Attunement the joy of listening the joy of staying present and being sensitive
to the suffering of others and your own and you might today
uh look around as you go through your day uh it can you find
occasions where there might be some sense of the joy of
Attunement in being present and being ATT tune to
others the joy of being in harmony of not being in Conflict even when there's
disagreements so um
thank you very much and um tomorrow we'll talk about the joy of
appreciation that uh appreciating others which maybe seems like a easier understanding of uh how there can
be Joy but for now Attunement thank
you