okay so welcome welcome folks um
you're happy to be with you so that's uh that's it
what and how we attend
shapes our world of experience
in other words shapes our world
and we practice relaxing
letting some of the attention drain out of our body into the Earth
so we can attend in a relaxed way
so that the way we attend is not a recapitulation of our
agitation vigilance
and to what do we attend
the energy energy will follow the attention
and so without making any experience an enemy
the Buddha suggested that
becoming deeply involved in
objects of of green hatred and aversion
ruminative fantasies or nightmares
this is not uh sustainable path of peace
and so without any brittleness in the attention
without the the how of attention becoming
riddle we welcome our breath
the energizing brightening inhale
the soothing exhale and then
soothes and and Smooths out
the energy of our body
foreign
then at the bottom of the exhale
sense of release
employers
suspended in space
and sometimes the the attention just pulls up in that
rhythm inhale exhale release
the world gets small secluded protected
having put down covetousness and displeasure with respect to the world
and sometimes gets very open and it's like the breath
is just a reminder of the
openness of awareness sea of awareness
thank you
no world of Hope and fear
seems like it's always beckoning us
seems like maybe it's
irresponsible or put something 's at risk and not compulsively tending
to Hope and fear
but uh
to always be embroiled with the Loose Ends of Human Condition
fatigues the heart
and our problems our hopes our fears
actually come to look quite a bit different
when we rested in the seclusion protection
of the breath no simplicity
relaxation and brightness
foreign
okay good to say with you
um [Music]
so uh the the good uh witnessed
aging sickness death and it was this this
changingness and maybe we could say
anticipatory grief that that launched his spiritual search
and anticipatory grief
um is a profound engine for Dharma motivation
uh this this week the the it's been uh
kind of Dharma prominent Dharma themes that that that don't appear in this
and so is uh surrender humor playfulness
and today uh grieving
the the story of uh story of the Buddha is that his mother
died around the time of his birth maybe the most uh Primal
form of grief and generally we see that the the Buddha
wanted to be free from grief Beyond griefs are a lamentation grief
sorrow and lamentation this is a path Beyond grief sorrow and
lamentation but then again when when uh
too very dear Disciples of his died the
Buddha said that this Hall that is full with hundreds of monastics feels empty
with the death of sorry put mogalana
and then the sitter goes on to say but the Buddha didn't suffer
and I I don't don't know about you this
great individual don't know about you but um but I want my Buddha to agree
and it took some time but uh kind of clarify in my own heart but um I
I don't place um grief in the cluster of afflictive
emotions and I I don't live it but I could imagine
a life free of of anger and agitation anxiety could
imagine it but it's very hard to imagine a life free of grief what that would even mean
and it's like how do you even look at the world for one minute and see the
the carnival of greed hatred delusion destruction that brings
and not feel some bit of grief
and so for me I associate grief with some of really our best qualities of
sensitivity of Love of morality
I really don't don't know what our Sila would look like if we never grieved
you know loss is kind of it's part of what makes the sanctity of
life intelligible it's finitude
and um you know children children have
sometimes called growing pains right they say their their legs hurt at night or something
and uh Dharma practice has growing pains too
and The Growing Pains of Dharma often
taste like grief how does it actually
feel to change in the actual trenches of change
not on the other side of letting go the other side of letting go
might feel great feel like release feel like we've been freed up from some
impingement but the process of letting go the movement from the clenched fist of
clinging to the Open Hand of surrender of letting go the movement of that
is often painful and that pain often feels something like
grieving how does it feel to deepen our
compassion to truly awaken to Duke to suffering the
Buddha said comprehends suffering to comprehend suffering what is that
what does that entail
how does it feel to grow up ethically to have ones the circle of empathy
expand the process of coming out of our the depth of our self-absorption into
some awareness of the vastness of suffering
that feels like grieving and
before the the truth of suffering the first Noble Truth of suffering
before the truth of suffering ennobles us
we we grieve it we grieve it for a long time
the the ordinariness of suffering the
endlessness of samsara is uh is startling
there's um research Shelley Shelley Taylor
um and on positive Illusions positive illusions
so these are sort of like Illusions we have that seem to be associated with
health and so she writes self-aggrandizing self-perceptions an illusion of control
and unrealistic optimism or widespread in human thought
these Illusions Foster the criteria normally associated with mental health
self-aggrandizing self-perceptions the illusion of control unrealistic optimism
associated with mental health and uh
it said that that these Illusions bolster and stabilize the sense of self
indeed philosopher metzinger says creating
creating too much awareness of mortality
threatens the Integrity of your and other people's conscious self model
because it implies a deep existential loss of control almost nobody wants to gaze into an
abyss for too long because as Nietzsche famously remarked the admit
the abyss might eventually gaze back into you as well
I do get the
the comfort of of our illusions
and we don't live every moment as death contemplation
but um there's a subtle agitation of
self-deception the Dharma is is the longing longing
deep burning desire long in
or truth and when some part of us one part of us
knows we're fooling Another Part Of Us
we can't settle there's agitation
and so the chickens come home to roost at some point
those Illusions will not sustain themselves
the chickens come home to roost and if we've not grieved the homelessness of ego
the ungovernability of existence we've not grieved
the end of all things we will be shattered
and so that sense that a kind of anticipatory grieving
conditions of our heart not towards hopelessness but towards motivation
to practice with what we can practice with
to to um to grow into compassion right the two
wings of Awakening wisdom compassion to grow to deepen into it
to evolve as moral creatures to really evolve like
to grow up as ethical beings
this will stretch ourselves and uh
and will entail some measure of grief
now the grief I speak of is um it's very fluid rather than stagnant
James Baldwin said that people can cry much easier than they can change
my lines always kind of haunted me you know it's like um
I don't want I don't want those tears to be a kind of
a rationalization of stagnation
but the Dharma the Dharma grieving is uh process by which
something else becomes love
and something else becomes love
Dharma is this alchemical process transmuting
transmuting
this beautiful line saying that Greek grief is completely pregnant with
bodhichitta the the awakened heart
completely pregnant and um
and this inside path the path path of purification is transmuting suffering
into to wisdom and love and even when the
grief hurts the love never feels for
out for this for your your consideration today
and
yeah it's good to appreciate the opportunity to be able to uh to touch and to uh
yeah these themes together is kind of universal human themes together
so uh so thank you all and um we'll uh look forward to uh
gathering tomorrow okay have a good uh good day yeah
thanks