okay so uh so welcome folks um yeah lovely to uh to see your names
I'm hoping that you are hearing me and
uh uh we'll uh do uh do that the the
normal uh normal routine so um I'll uh I'll guide us and uh then
offer some some Reflections so uh thank you for uh the
warm warm welcome uh yeah nice to uh nice to see the
uh yeah a lot of familiar names lovely okay um let's uh let's let's
sit
just uh breathing in a way that Smooths
out the uh energy in your
body we're not trying to make what is painful Pleasant
we're just integrating the felt sense of the
body with our
breathing so that the awareness fills out your whole
body
breathing into
uh the numbed out or flat zones of the body maybe the back of
body certain portions of your body tend to uh be
unnoticed don't have much uh access
to
sensation
then breathing into the intensity is the kind
of hot
spots so that they might be soothed in some
way
and so the the whole constellation of Sensations that
is uh the experience of our body it's kind of lit up from
within by awareness
Dharma practice is about uh
learning
but it's uh not about a kind of
continuation of the autobiography that we've been reiterating to
ourselves it's not the next chapter
in that same
autobiography it's a radical
relinquishment and it doesn't mean you can never have your story
again doesn't mean your past is meaningless or
anything of the
sort but we
practice
surrendering surrendering such that it doesn't feel like uh this
moment is tacked on to the story we've always been
telling
we remind ourselves of our autobiography in so many ways what I
like what I dislike what I want and
need where I my life has been where I want it
to go this
meditation sandwiched painfully between past and a
future the headquarters of Matthew
orchestrating choreographing Dharma
practice we surrender all of
that
we don't try to drag all of that knowing into this
moment
instead we get more
more
precise these thin slices of sensory experience
the body the body
breathing we surrender The Familiar reference
points and fall into to the
present
in any given moment a million things are right and a
million are
wrong but we're so perpetually
startled by the way that this ambivalent
realm part of the the value the practice of equinity is uh
we don't need to sort this out anymore just take for
granted that there's loveliness and
imperfection the sense of of self the kind
of freezing of our
autobiography it's a little bit like a maybe
a a hologram
cast by the
spotlight of clinging
equinity it's the practice of non
clinging
we can only keep track of ourselves who what we
are when we're trying to leverage this
moment trying to make this moment about
another making this moment a Down payment on something
else so we
surrender surrender into a
sense of futur
lessness this is a a different kind of way of
learning
[Music]
okay um good to sit with you uh I hope those instructions made some sense
or something
um and uh you know just as a word I sort of like presume that people have kind of
uh have their own meditation experience I'm not that would not be a good first
meditation instruction so I apologize if that was your first
um anyway I'm happy to be with you and
uh uh it's been a while since I've been here um on on YouTube and uh yeah
excited to uh explore so
um it's hard to uh it's hard to talk about
um about Dharma um because what is wisdom in one moment is
a mistake in another and I'm not saying that to be cute it's like what is wisdom in one
moment is a mistake in another and there is no no single kind
of Dharma drum that we can just march to Independent of
context independent of the Nuance of of
samsara this world and wisdom really creates the path
rather than follows it it's not that there's a pre-ordained path and then wisdom is just following it we're
actually creating a path and the way it strikes me the way
that delusion works is often not that we do kind of like the opposite of the
teachings it's not that the teachings say do X and we do not
X the way delusion works is we pick the wrong
teaching we pick the teaching that allows us to act out our
underlying habit energy or craving and so we
need Fierce Det determination and we pick self-compassion or we need
self-compassion and we pick Fierce determination and part of this skill in
Dharma practice is knowing um which teaching to reach
for and the Dharma is really it's found in kind of these Dynamic tensions right
like determination self-compassion passion these things pairs of
values that we um we dance
between and I a couple years ago on on this
stream I highlighted uh a few Pairs and uh this week more pairs of of these
values we dance between and this week it's really it's a kind of dialectic of
the more assertive quality ities of mind and the more receptive
qualities and so today um confidence and
humility confidence and humility so much
confidence and so much humility and maybe it sounds like those are
in you know deep tension but they're they're
really complimentary heart qualities
so the more the more deeply we taste the Dharma the more devotional we become the
more confident we become uh we don't have to be a devotional person I I don't I don't know
that I would cast myself as a devotional person or a devotional type
um but um when your heart is nourished by the
Dharma in the way that it can nourish us you just bow
down it breathes a kind of devotional
reverence so Gil um wrote uh uh he
said um Awakening is not the end of practice Awakening is the confirmation
that the practice works Awakening solidifies our confidence in Dharma
practice we understand that when done sincerely a beginner's practice is as valuable and meaningful as that of an
experienced practitioner the greater our maturity with practice the more often and more
confidently we can begin aresh always ready to keep
practicing when I think about characterizing uh kind of some of the
the effects of of practice one piece that feels important is there's there's sort of
um there's no more doubt that my my real
life is like just out there
somewhere it's just this it's just this and there's no more more sense of
um dislocation the kind of subtle alienation that who I am my
life is sort of like just beyond my reach that I'm chasing
something down that um uh that in my aspiration um
there's a sense of dislocation and alienation no just this
enough and there's a sense of of um a deep kind
of selfconfidence self-confidence which I would say is is something akin
to like a sense of complete sufficiency right sufficiency not not
greatness not amazing not special complete
sufficiency we come to learn we understand more we
become more confident better and better at predicting what leads us to
happiness and so often in our life we're sort of surprised that when we get what
we want it's different than what we thought we were
getting we become more calibrated in this way we're better predictors of our
own happiness and that breeds a kind of
confidence we become more confident that no matter what happens in our life what
befalls us uh there's some way that Dharma can
sanctify it that that um forges a kind of
is confidence so yeah
confidence and still it is such a humbling path right oh my goodness if
you're not being humbled you're not practicing right
um we all have um you know zones where we're a little bit you know
bewildered by life and it feels like well we're doing
the best we can but we're kind of making it up as we go along we don't we don't know how to do
this you know and all the learning and all the goodness and all the whatever
freedom is ours is sort of just like we feel like children again bewildered what
to do don't know it's humbling it's humbling it's
humbling to see the gap between what we know intellectually and what what we
have actually realized what we've actually realized are
um it's only realization that changes behavior and I'm not saying only
Enlightenment changes Behavior but only only uh that which has been realized
rather than known intellectually changes our Behavior it's humbling to see how easily
we can be uh deceived how easily we can be deceived
you know by seduced by our own mind seduced by the
very deeply camouflaged mechanisms of
clinging the Mind builds a kind of House of Cards and then where we live in that
house and then it collapses and what we thought of was truth was really a kind of
confabulation of greed and aversion a a way that we've concocted
something concocted something we're not lying we're not lying but we've um
we've concocted something out of our
clinging and so to begin to wake up to just to see how easy it is to kind of
pull a fast one on ourselves uh this is humbling this is
humbling and it might just be a a micro mood where it's like we just become convinced of
something and then the energy in Body Mind changes we go outside we look at
the sky we take a breath we see a smile we do something and that house of cards Falls
you know it's humbling to um to
see and so humility is a kind of openness
to uh the data of of this moment but a
an unwillingness to cover over the mystery with self-serving
certainties we learn on this path right but we can never irreversibly rule out
the possibility that wisdom is delusion and that that sounds maybe
haunting or something but it's sort of thrilling to me you know that it's like everything the
structure of science actually everything is awaiting
disconfirmation yeah and that doesn't lead us into a kind of instability or
something like that is just all tentative we have to keep
looking reading something uh
uh when uh when research you know research subjects when they when they
claim to be 98% certain about something they're wrong about 30% of the time when
when they estimate 99.9% certainty they were wrong 19% of
the time and when we subjects them we we
when subjects estimated 99 9999
n% certainty they were wrong 133% of the
time something funny to me about
that so the permanent the permanent possibility of being
wrong demands that we hedge we
hedge don't know we hedge epistemologically about about knowing we
hedge
morally to forget the the kind of permanent possibility of
uh uh of being wrong is is the first step towards
violence and
uh and so the humility um
humility uh of which I speak is is um
actually moves Us in the direction nonviolence so much confidence so much
humility so offer this for your um consideration this morning and uh
um uh I wish you uh wish you all a good day and and uh we'll we'll keep going
tomorrow uh tomorrow morning
okay