good evening welcome welcome so as I was sitting uh kind of
bubbled up like oh yeah maybe this topic here I am I'm I'm going to do more
on fear and I've uh been doing quite a few things on
fear it turns out it's such a rich topic there's like so many elements to it and
so many ways to consider it work with it look at it all these kinds of things
but if you're sick of fear I promise this will be the last
one but maybe I I'll uh to justify it I'll say that um I'll be teaching a
class in July that's called the path of fearlessness it's like a six I don't
remember how many months six or seven month program and we'll be looking at fear and all the different ways it shows
up in our lives and different ways to work with it and so that's partly I've been you know
really poking around in this topic of fear turns out to be very I don't know I
feel uh touched by it like I'm learning about practice in in some ways and just
you know what it means to be a human turns out fear is pretty
common so maybe I'll just say that I'm going to lump together
quite a few different ideas about fear so there's this fear of like imminent danger something's going to happen you
know we have fear about that you know the saber-tooth tiger or the bus that's
uh while we're crossing the street and there's also this maybe like
this less pressing fear fear of public speaking fear
of going to a place where you you don't know anybody know something like this and
then there's also kind of like anxiety there's this way in which this anxiety
is maybe this more generalized discomfort of something that's happening in the future maybe it's not even can't
quite maybe even put our finger on it what it is fear and anxiety of course
they both are concerned about things in the future but there there's a way in which
we might consider them in the same so I'm lumping them together but to be sure
I could give another Dharma talk I'm like why they're all different so there's value in that as well but for
the purpose of this talk I'm going to lump them together and so part of you know
actually this can I make this be just a little bit louder I keep on trying to make this speak closer but I I'm afraid
that I'll lose my voice at the end if I'm okay maybe this is better yeah thank you
Martha you guys don't want to hear me with my running out of my voice at the
end so part of the theme I want to talk about is like why bother why bother
talking about fear looking at fear working with fear like what's this kind
of the theme and I'll say that uh last week
talked about like the way to fearlessness was the topic and it talked about how the path of practice that we
do that's to find Freedom is the same path of practice that can really help
with fear and the week before that I did Fe
a as a way to practice with fear friend it befriend it explore or examine it
allow it and release it I talked about that
but maybe in general we can say about just working with fear is similar to
working with other strong uncomfortable
experiences so whatever we learn about fear it's part of the value is can help
us with anger and sadness and just these other kind of sometimes uh uncomfortable
experiences that humans have but i' like to start with a
poem this a poem by Rosemary traumer she's this wonderful poet I think that
uh she's I don't know I just appreciate how she's able to put in words or
Express things with a little bit of Whimsy and a lot of
wisdom so here's Rosemary traumer with this poem hello
fear and it goes like this there I was making tea in my kitchen
when fear hit me like a school bus I didn't need a scientist or a
therapist to tell me it hurt I screamed ah I shouted no but after smashing into
me fear just opened the folding glass door of the bus yanked me on then popped
me into a green vinyl seat I'm scared I said yeah fear said CU
I'm scary yeah I salled as the bus greened through the couch through the bedroom
the splintering dining room table what if I lose everything I said
to fear yeah said fear what if you do and
who will I be when everything changes yeah said fear who will you
be then he opened the door and shoved me off the bus and I was standing again
beside the familiar green counter teacup in hand not a drop
spilled who will you be he shouted from the half openen window I took a deep breath not knowing
how to answer good fear said as if uncertainty
were a gift and who fear said as the bus peeled
away who are you now who are you
really I don't know I I'm smiling while I read this because it's just kind of this playfulness right of this bus
sometimes we have this expression you know just getting carried away or we have this exer I got hit by a bus is a
way that like just got overwhelmed and rosemary traumer she's kind of like works with
this and so I'd like to use this kind of this poem as a way to unpack and to talk
about some different ways of kind of what Rosemary trummer is pointing to in this poem at least in my interpretation
of her poem So It Begins right where she oh
maybe I'll just read these few lines again just the first view there I was making tea in my kitchen when fear hit
me like a school bus I didn't need a scientist or a therapist to tell me it hurt I screamed
ah I shouted no but after smashing into me fear just opened the folding glass
door of the bus yanked me on then popped me into a green vinyl
seat fear is never invited it just shows up and sometimes
it's just those times here or she's describing just being in the kitchen with a cup of tea in my mind I can
imagine maybe she's looking at the window in the kitchen and and just maybe
there's a moment of relaxation cup of teas a little bit soothing and it's often when we
relax that the things that we've been trying to Tamp down kind of like
arrive might be during meditation in fact it's not uncommon that during
meditation the same type of thing when there's a sense of settledness and ease and fear can show
up and I kind of like this idea of a school bus this poet she chose a school
bus maybe because it's something like when we are have a lot of fear there might be a way in which we kind of feel
like the younger version of ourselves we don't necessarily feel like the adults
that's trying to convince yeah I got everything under control I don't have any fear I'm not afraid of anything or
whatever it might be just way of kind of the school bus is not only there's a
younger version of oursel maybe maybe but also the fact that it's a
bus in my interpretation is highlighting there's a lot of people on
this bus fear turns out to be so common even though we don't often talk about it or
even even notice it we're giving it different language or we're calling it something
else but there's a way that kind of maybe recognizing that it's showing up on a
bus is way that we can connect with other people recognize the common
Humanity of feeling fear humans are vulnerable of course we
are so of course we have fear because there is danger it doesn't mean that all the
things that we consider dangerous are in fact dangerous in the way that we imagine them but we're not invincible so
of course there is fear and part of this practice is to help understand those fears that are
helpful and those fears that are not helpful and so something else this in
the beginning of this poem she uh she has this uh this line I screamed ah I
shouted no this is how it is right when fear
arrives there's this resistance no I don't want this go away there this of
course there is this generalized feeling of this is not what I
wanted and it's fascinating that we can for me it's
fascinating that we can work with this sense of no right there's this uh we have fear
that just arises Uninvited and then there's this sense of no I don't want it and there's a way
that this fear and the resistance to the fear are pushing and supporting each
other there's a way that they're kind of like in this little Loop and sometimes to be with the fear
is overwhelming or you know there might be trauma associated with it maybe it's not even wise to go right into the
fear but this resistance all the ways in which we say
no could be enormously helpful to pay attention to
this it's so there's this way that um resistance can show up as this tightness
in the body or this blaming others or blaming ourselves and just to be with
that let the fear take care of itself but to be with the
resistance because we have not only resistance to fear but I was mentioning earlier so many difficult uncomfortable
situations and so we can just being with the resistance is a way that we can like
help the fear to diminish kind of like allow it to do
this arise and pass away because of course the fear is going to end it's not there
always but something that often that we don't talk about is that fear can be a
support for practice I've been talking about okay here's how to get rid of it here's how
to work with it or something like this but there's a way in which fear has a
role in our life and in our practice and I like this uh expression
that Jack cornfield has he says that fear is the
membrane between the familiar and the
unfamiliar between the familiar and the unfamiliar so recognizing so often the fear is of the unknown or the fear is
about you know what's about to happen it's part of why it's uh unfamiliar but
this idea if you're feeling fear you're out of your comfort zone but this is also how we grow this
is also how we like expand our capacity is to get on the kind of like
maybe push this membrane between the familiar and the unfamiliar
how much does the fear of the unknown kind of like limit us limit Our Lives
limit the ways that we think about what's possible for ourselves or
possible for others or possible for the world or some skills that we think that
oh I'm not I don't want to undertake that but I don't know how yet or something like
this this unknown I don't quite know how that's going to
unfold and also I'll say that the I'm going to have a little drink of water
here also we might recognize that the hero's journey includes
fear right and this journey is where the the protagonist embarks on this
adventure like uh faces and overcomes challenges and then under goes personal
growth and transformation and then comes back with gift bestowing hands now that
they've learned something that they can not only live their life different but they can help others in a way that they
couldn't before but this way of meeting obstacles and over and working with them
and being able to meet those challenges always involves
fear but this hero's journey right this is part of how we grow I'm doing I'm
making a circle with my hun because there's a way in which we come back to where we started but we've changed so
maybe the external environment hasn't changed but we've changed and I think all of us have this
experience having some difficulties that we wouldn't wish on
anybody but then recognizing on the other side of that oh yeah I did learn something
really powerful and meaningful and maybe even transformative so this recognizing that
fear even though it's Uninvited and uncomfortable it can be a support for
our life and for our practice so then I I'll come back to
this poem the uh the person in the poem says
I'm I'm scared I said yeah fear said cuz I'm scary yeah I salled as the bus cined
through the couch through my bedroom through the splintering dining room
table so this bus is going through these different parts of the
house started in the kitchen and then we see was it like the couch the bedroom
and the dining room these are all the different areas of our life right the
ways that we show up in the kitchen the ways that we show up on the couch the way that we show up in the bedroom and the dining room table our relationships
our what we do for leisure what we um how we are with taking care of ourselves
you know there's way in which fear can touch so many of these different areas of our
lives and so in the same way working with
fear can take us to to many areas of Our Lives also for example this idea of just
exploring fear or examining Fear Can reveal a tremendous amount it can reveal
parts of our inner lives like because what we fear is related to what's
precious to us what is important to us so as we're like examining fear we
might discover something of these stories that we've created about who we think ourselves to be as we see here in
this poem we might have this idea of like well I'm afraid they won't like
me then we realize oh yeah and we have this might this underlying belief or
that everybody should like me like us and to be sure that's not a bad thing to
have people like you but there's sometimes ways in which we are compromising or things that are
important to us or not standing up for what we know that is right or something like that just so that people will like
us so to recognize part of what our fear to explore it reveals our inner lives
maybe even what we think the purpose of our life is or what we value what's
important what feels threatened but when we examine the fear
we also reveal the way that kind of like these persistent fears that we have are
often like limiting our lives or limiting our freedom and we might not be aware that
the role that fear has in our lives until we really look at it and examine
it fear might show up kind of maybe just in general as apprehension or hesitation
or dread or worry but also maybe more explicitly as not being able to sleep
well or just feeling moody in a bad mood or
in a dampened mood or heavy mood or just being really light moods all over the
place or can also just show up as the opposite of kind like not expressing our
emotions we don't want anybody to see the fear perhaps or something so there's a way in which we're kind like tightened
up and clammed up and not sharing so it really has a big role on our emotions
whether we're ones we're expressing or even not
expressing and there is a way in which we could say that fear you know is such a big part of conflict this way in that
we our inner life or what's uh limits our freedom this sense
of It kind of like it can sorry that lost my thinking
there that it's at the root of conflict in the sense that we're afraid that
somebody is going to take credit for something that we did at work for example or that they won't um respect us
if we share what's really going on with us or they
will um not appreciate the our vulnerability because it makes them feel
vulnerable so they'll be turned away turns out though that right being
vulnerable in a way that feels comfortable like not sharing too much but not being closed off it's really how
people connect it's really how people form relationships and
friendships and it's if with the it there's been lots of studies about this
that uh if somebody seems like a little bit vulnerable then maybe I shouldn't
even just the opposite maybe a little bit vulnerable or that is not completely
perfect or polished then people are more apt to you
know want to talk to them or have a or include them in what's happening or
you know have them as part of the
conversation and so exploring fear also reveals some of our patterns of reaction
ativity the way that this resistance that I spoke about shows up it can be this procrastination
avoidance anger blaming lashing out so the way that we kind of resist fear so
much is also we could be resisting anger or sadness or anything else that's
uncomfortable and then also looking at fear reveals the role all that desire
and expectations and clinging have in our lives because fear is so often
related to this it's like we're afraid of losing things so we're really holding
on or there's this like this vicious circle of fear leads to
clinging and then this which and then the clinging kind of leads to this
identification then identification leads back to to fear because the things that
we're clinging to feel like um they're often feel under threat whatever often we're clinging to
ideas about ourselves and we want others to see us a particular
way we're expectations we want to feel a certain
way and we're maybe afraid of we don't want to be uncomfortable so I expect that this will happen and this won't
happen it'll be the right temperature and and it won't be too loud or too
quiet or these types of things but so not only does kind of
looking at fear help us to learn about ourself but it helps us to hone some of
our some skills like how to be with difficulty but
also how this recognition that some fear is appropriate and some is not
you know fear sometimes um I had this habit when I was younger maybe it was
like from when I was really young just a grade school age and sometimes I find it
showing up uh when I'm I don't know what the conditions are but sometimes it shows up that I used to have this idea
that when I was walking on the sidewalk I shouldn't step on the crack because we had the saying when I
was a kid like step on the crack break a back or something like this and
sometimes even as an adult I'm like oh wait I you know I'm adjusting my feet so that I don't step on the crack this is
silly right this is but there's a way in which things that really don't make
sense show up and for us to really pay attention like oh yeah fear of harming
others this could be helpful fear of St stepping on the crack and the sidewalk
not so helpful so helps us to kind of like make some distinctions what are our
reactions are they appropriate or maybe they're not so
appropriate and just to have that activity this question of like is this helpful is this not helpful is this
healthy or is this not healthy learning to do this with fear we can also do this with our anger with our
sadness or are blaming or this inner critic like there's so many different ways in which we can do
this and then I also want to say that looking at fear can help us to face death face
death with more equinity there's this way
that part of you know we have this fear of deaths we never look at it I shouldn't say never we are tend to not
look at it or um even think about
it but there's a way in that if we can reflect on death it's even a practice
some of you may know this marati these death contemplation just this recognition I'm going to die you're
going to die everybody's going to die if the fear kind of gets moved away
or even isn't there I'm sure it's probably there but there's a way in which we can work look at death in a way
that can be sacred and we can work with death in a way that can be
liberating and I had a good friend who was a practitioner and as he was
dying he just kind of I felt like he showed all of us like how to die with um
I don't know with some beauty and Grace it was such a gift that he gave us that
he he had can and he was for many many years he knew that he was dying so he
had time to get his Affairs in order and to say goodbye and but just
to I don't know it was a beautiful just kind of like a letting go and the
unknown and he had some fear I'm sure he did but just a way that uh he didn't
hide it it was a it was a beautiful thing to re to recognize oh yeah people to there
the dying process can be a beautiful process it's going to happen anyways for
all of us and then the last part of this
poem what if I lose everything I said to fear yeah said fear what if you do and
who will I be when everything changes yeah said fear who will you be
then he opened the door and shoved me off the bus and I was standing again
beside the familiar green counter teacup in hand not a drop
spilled who will you be he shouted from the half openen window I took a deep
breath not knowing how to answer good fear said as if uncertainty
were a gift and who fear said as the bus peeled
away Who Are You Now who are you
really so much about fear is this fear of the
unknown the truth is we don't know as much as we think we
do fear the unknown is often like well I'm not quite sure how that's going
to happen how that's going to unfold but how many things in your life
have turned out just the way you thought they were this is coming from somebody who
has a PHD in Biochemistry and is now sitting here as a Dharma teacher right how many times in
our lives we think like oh things are going to go this way and then they kind of like turn out going another way
that's like in the big picture but often you know we have these fears about
what's going to happen if we go to this uh holiday
gathering that we get invited to for example and I don't really know anybody I only know that one person and oh it's
going to be awful I'm just going to be standing there nobody's going to talk to me and maybe maybe
not there's this way in which we have this uh this we just want to have some
confidence in things that we don't really know but it turns out that
uncertainty is kind of the way forward because fear like in order to not feel
fear we're trying to like control things and which is limiting we're like
limiting what's possible for ourselves and what's possible for
others having uncertainty the sense of H I don't
know it's so much better like oh my gosh okay I have to make sure this doesn't happen I have to make sure that doesn't
happen therefore I'm going to do this I'm going to take care of that and but there's a way I'm just saying I'm not
sure that might be awful it might not be awful
too but to somehow allow things to unfold in a way instead of always trying
to shev them a particular way and make them be a certain
way so I'm not saying to be completely passive and I am not encouraging like
just terrible horrible things to just keep going but I am encouraging us to
not uh assume that we have to um Corral everything
or um try to make sure it only goes the way
that we think it should go so often things have a like a natural
unfolding that might be better than what we're even thinking
about and sometimes there is a part of us that prefers the difficulties and
that prefers the stress and prefers the
you know this worry because it's familiar so we shouldn't underestimate
like how much we are often trying to get rid of uncertainty and in order to do
that we're holding on to things that just aren't helpful for us and we have these patterns you know
of familiarity these are really powerful and so there can be some wisdom but we
can also bring some questioning like when we see when we recognize some of
our patterns of behavior yeah I'm usually showing up this
way well is part of that is just because it's familiar
what would it be like to invite more uncertainty in our lives you just this little bit of fear like you know I'm not
quite sure how this is going to go and can that be
okay because as I said we really don't know as much as we think we do and we
certainly don't control as much as we think we do even though we try right of
course we do so the truth is that
uncertainty is is can be like this Doorway to freedom and this fear this membrane
between what's familiar and what's not familiar this it can be a door that's
closed but fear can be a doorway but it's often in uncertainty is
the next step but then that can lead to Greater Freedom greater
ease something that maybe we haven't even imagined yet maybe we don't even
know can't even we don't even have an idea what it might
be so in this way working with fear can work with also this sense of uh our
sense of self that so often we feel like has to be protected and bolstered and
made to look good but if we recognize this
uncertainty and say I don't know kind of like softens that this
sense of self is when we have this sense of certainty there's a sense of like I
know and when there's a sense of I don't know then there the there's a
opening there can be a less rigidity less limit so in this way working with fear
can be a support for greater Freedom so the next time that you're
having tea in the kitchen and fear
arises maybe maybe it'll be a school bus maybe it won't be a school bus but is
there a way that you can just a allow yourself to see what it has to show
you allow yourself to feel the experience of
fear maybe I'll say briefly to one way to be with fear and
that's not overwhelming is to be aware of the body what's happening in the body
the mind is gr really fast and making lots of stories especially when there's fear but if you can ground down into
feeling your feet on the ground feeling the lump of throat lump in your throat
or the butterflies in the belly or what whatever it might be that's a great way
to kind of like hold the fear without this sense of like it has
to go away and then maybe you can work with the resistance as I said before this sense of no and the sense of no
often is showing up in the jaw clenching the jaw or tightness in the jaw or
sometimes in the shoulders all of us are different but these are some generalizations of how to work with
this okay so with that I'll end and open it
up for some questions or comments thank
you I'm going to read this poem just one
more time yeah you know there's a way in which may be something that we you know
we hear more than once it uh because you guys might have your own interpretation of this right you might have something
else that sticks out for you there I was making tea in my kitchen
when fear hit me like a school bus I didn't need a scientist or therapist to
tell me it hurt hurt I screamed ah I shouted no but after smashing into me
fear just opened the folding glass door of the bus yanked me on then plopped me
into a green vinyl seat I'm scared I said yeah a fear said
cuz I'm scary yeah I squealed as the bus kened
through the couch through my bedroom through the splintering dining room table
what if I lose everything I said to fear yeah said fear what if you do and who
will I be when everything changes yeah said fear who will you be
then he opened the door and shoved me off the bus and I was standing again beside the familiar green counter teacup
in hand not a drop spilled who will you be he shouted from
the half openen window I took a deep breath not knowing how to answer good
fear said as if uncertainty were a gift and who fear said as the bus peeled
away Who Are You Now who are you
really hello so I'm having some fear right
now um first of all I wanted to just say like how much I appreciate that
reading I get so much more out of a poem when I hear it spoken I think and then the voice of fear seems
to sort of change or at least it seems in the end becomes instructive or an aid at
least that's one way you could look at it is sort of under reming the Identity or
exactly and then on a more personal note I've sort of realizing that there's also
fear of fear yes and I I just recent like in my within the
last year of my life I've realized just like how powerful fear has been in my life like from a very early age and I
think I was always sort of trying to like to deny that was more of a social fear Than Physical fear in terms of
risk-taking or things like that and I don't really know where to go with that except it was just I think
maybe I'll sign up for for the class so path the
fearlessness yeah we're starting at end of January it seems like a very rich uh vein to a mind to look at
yes thank you I appreciate very much that you're saying that that fear has some wisdom at the end kind of like
undermining identity and then you said fear a fear yes I agree right even here
uh the poem says she goes I don't forget what she says oh I'm scared and yeah
fear said cuz I'm scary this fear of fear right how much a big role it has in
our lives I think if in my case it was like trying to deny that I was afraid
and that's like this big thing you don't want to look at and leads to all sorts of undesirable outcomes so yeah
yeah um I uh appreciated what you said about I I think it was something like
Comfort Comfort or familiarity of of fear and and anxiety I think when I'm
feeling anxious about something um every topic that I'm anxious about
puts my mind into a certain a certain course and uh you know I have the same
kind of plans or whatever as I did last time to to deal with whatever I'm
anxious about and I guess there is a certain amount of comfort in that but it's also
frustrating that I'm doing I'm thinking the same thoughts again and of course I'm not getting any more out of them
this second time time or third time or 10th time as I did the first time
so uh it's almost like um you know I think that I'm this time I'm really
going to figure it out whatever
um yeah it does it does tend to put my mind in very familiar patterns
and there I guess there are there are aspects that that feel good and and
aspects of it that feel bad yeah yeah this makes perfect sense I think all of
us do this right we have our usual ways and they work a little bit or they work sometimes or you're like there's a
reason why we do it but then sometimes this recognition having to do something
different and maybe I'll just share for you and for others that I used to uh
when I noticed like fear was coming up or something I would just like do a long exhale this is just like the physiology
of long exhales just kind of help calm us down so I would just do that all the time like oh okay this works but the
fear would just like keep on coming back and it wasn't until I said you know what I'm going to stop doing this long exhale
and actually just kind of be with this fear and it turned out not to be so bad
what I was doing was like kind of soothing but the fear to be there like oh my goodness and then to kind of like
go away and then I don't know if felt like something shifted with that maybe
in the same way that you get into these thought grooves I was doing this and the thought grooves I mean they can be
helpful right and I was doing this physiological sigh or something like this to help it so maybe I'll just share
that too there's so many ways in which we get into these habits thank
you Diana I love the way you read the poem
thank you you're welcome it was it was great um for many years uh this is in
the somewhat distant past I noticed that as soon as I sat down to meditate what
would happen is what I called the three PS which was planning pleasing and
plating oh and of the I the placing and plating I could understand and the
planning was n just normal planning it was like planning the same thing again
and again which I recognized after a while was magical thinking like if I
planned this thing well enough then bad things wouldn't happen in my life and so
when I looked at those those three PS I thought oh okay that's fear yeah that um
and it was really helpful to recognize that thank you thank you for your talk
oh thank you thank you thank you Martha and thank you for saying this about fear is underneath planning absolutely
there's a way in this we're trying to control things or be prepared for whatever is going to happen because
we're afraid that somehow we'll be uncomfortable or something untour will happen yeah thank you Martha I like this
plating pleasing and planning okay the three
PS thank you all and I wish you all a good night and
safe travels way home and Thanksgiving is coming up so I hope that uh in
whatever way you celebrate or if you celebrate I hope you have a wonderful time thank
you