so warm greetings to all of you
and um
his uh as part of this wonderful community of
ours of 7 A.M meditators and the one who does the most speaking
maybe I can represent all of you and and offer that welcome and behalf of all
of you so we're all welcoming each other and have a sense of being included by the
whole community so thank you for being here
and I want to start with analogy say that you're going to go do some
exercise maybe go to the gym and you really enjoy exercising
you need to exercise there's a physical kind of thing you're trying to heal from or something
and so you're determined and motivated and everything's good you go there and as you're going into
the gym you you're thinking about uh yeah it's just you see other people working out this is good to work out and
certain vitality and engagement this is a really healthy thing for people and you think about a friend of yours who
really needs to work out maybe for all for many reasons
and so you're thinking about your friend you care about your friend you have compassion for your friend and you want
to help your friend and um and so you walk by a little Lobby part
of the gym and there's some magazines
and maybe there's a magazine big headlines you know working out in health or something just like with your
concerned for your friend so you pick up the magazine and you go uh sit on a
maybe in a little couch in the back wall of the gym
you hear people working out and for the hour you had to work out you
read this magazine another magazine and all caring for you know to think about your friend
and then your hour is up and then you realize wait a minute I didn't exercise at all I spent the whole time you know
thinking about my friend you know I could have worked out I need to work out
and I could have done the reading and magazine or looked into it later in fact I didn't really learn that much
by looking at these magazines so I gave this analogy for coming to meditate
we're here to meditate to kind of a kind of a mental working out if you may
and if you start thinking have compassionate thoughts for people who are challenged and you start thinking
about it I'll help them and do things for them um and you spend the whole meditation in
this kind of planning mind discursive mind thinking about them in a sense maybe for that meditation
session you're not meditating at all you're not doing it for the practice you're doing thinking about a friend
in the context of meditation of course you might think about a friend
who's suffering and of course you might think about how to help them or do something for them but in the context of meditation
the most significant way to respond to the suffering of the world
that we experience and feel is actually not to use meditation as a time to plan and think about what to do
rather if to really prepare ourselves for doing and acting later
that powerful thing is to act in a certain way
and that is to go back recognize what's happening to you recognize concerns recognize the
feelings that are there recognize the impulse the aspiration to help these are all good
and then go to fold it all back in to your
workout to your practice and these steps we've been doing this week around compassion
are a great series of steps to do to fold it back into your practice
come back and just rest in Awareness being aware of how you're feeling be aware of the
sensations in the body of of the compassion the care the concern
you have for your friend and uh what it feels like in your body to have a desire to do something
just be aware of what's happening for you as you're aware become attuned to
yourself find harmony with yourself and to go ahead long into planning and
thinking about the friend is actually a way of losing touch with oneself meditation is a way of being profoundly
in touch with oneself here and to be attuned to this person and if
you're suffering attuned to your suffering if you're not suffering being attuned to the sensations and feeling
and what's happening appreciate appreciate yourself
appreciate what's happening respect it deeply but don't give in to it don't
fall into it don't spin out with it and and then here have an aspiration
maybe the aspiration is in fact to care for the suffering of oneself and for
others and then in meditation then you can do
it again and again and and so you're actually building
by this repeat repeated Cycles you're actually building the kind of foundation
that allows compassion to grow that allows it sets the ground for
cleaner and greater simpler straightforward compassion to be there
for later if you go head along into I need to fix the problem I need to help the problem I
need to do something and start planning it
um at times that's useful but not when you're working out in the gym
then you want to then you want to sit deeply and come back do the cycle again
and again to purify to clarify to simplify how it is for you
so that we're freeing ourselves from the
you know the distractions of discursive thinking about it
we're freeing ourselves from looking at the magazines rather than doing the exercise
and by doing the exercise something strengthens inside of us then later
will give birth to a greater capacity for compassion and get greater capacity for how to act
so to assume your meditation posture
foreign and gently close your eyes
and to
without anything else
begin your meditation and if the occasion is right for it
go through the first four A's of the five A's of this week
cultivate awareness Attunement
appreciation aspiration
and Debian meditation the aspiration is to be present
be here desperation is to keep cultivating
greater awareness of the present moment greater Attunement to the present moment
greater appreciation of the present moment and letting the aspiration to do so
be simpler clearer more harmonious more supportive
of going through this process again
if you're thinking if you're reading the magazine
begin the cycle of aware attuned appreciative
and aspiring to be here and present not lost in thought
and he if while I'm meditating you have any
suffering stress tension about something
offer yourself these five steps be aware in a deep way
attune yourself in a useful way
appreciate yourself and
in a supportive way
have the wish the aspiration that you be free of the suffering
and then act and the ACT we do in meditation
is to do the first four again go through the cycle
just keep deepening with it expanding it
quieting the mind
and then as we come to the end of this meditation
to appreciate that meditation is a time to
be inward inward Focus to our own experience Here and Now
and to maybe do it so deeply so fully
and that we become we turned we are turned inside out
so that there is a deeper sensitivity
and availability to the world
and to let now the attention go out into the world
aware of the joys and Sorrows that are so extensive in the world
to be attuned to a certain kind of Harmony
of heart with all the joys and sorrows
to never forget to appreciate and respect
all people in the world
and to allow the hearts aspiration to Bubble Up
the hearts of aspiration to care for suffering wherever it's
encountered and when we encounter it in the world
around us to Aspire that that suffering comes to
an end and then action
May each of us aspire to do
at least small actions
to make this day a better day for others May each of us
alleviate lighten the suffering of others
through even the smallest acts Smiles checking in how are you
offering a small gift
being aware attuned and appreciative of others
that itself is a gift that alleviates suffering
it doesn't have to be more complicated
and if you know if nothing else is relevant
your act to support the world is to go back to being aware
attuned and appreciative
the benefits of doing so will spread out into the world
may all beings be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you [Music]
so then today we come to the Fifth Element of compassion action
and it's actually very important that we Act
and there's something empowering something freeing something uh enlivening
in actually acting rather than just have wishful thinking rather than living under the weight and
burden rather than just feeling the challenges and the suffering of the world
and um and even a small Acts
count for our hearts small acts who knows how much they'll benefit others
sometimes small acts of kindness of compassion I have the biggest impact
and but always it's important to act but we have to be very careful what that
means and how we take that in if we live under the obligation that we have to go and help someone else
then it's very easy to add stress attention to that very effort and to
bring along and can imbue it with something which is actually maybe not beneficial for yourself and others
one form of action is in fact to keep purifying oneself to
really clarify and develop oneself and um and so there are times when we feel the
suffering of the world and maybe we can't do anything there's so much suffering if you read the news and we're
not going to reach out to all of it but we can still be moved by it we can
still do the first four of these elements of compassion and as we move into action
it's not necessarily to do things directly for the people who are suffering but sometimes it's just simply to go
through that cycle of of awareness appreciation awareness Attunement appreciation and
aspiration again kind of it's kind of like a cleansing it's kind of like a refining it's a
smoothing out it's a it's a growing of the of the
so the clarity of that compassion the fullness of that compassion and care
so it becomes stronger and it becomes less and less mixed with
tension with suffering many times compassion when we there's a quick impulse to be compassionate we
don't realize how much we bring along our conceit our ideas of self of others
of of pity of um of tension of obligation that kind of messes it up in
some way there is something like a natural compassion that can well up
I feel very fortunate because that my discovery of really The Beauty And The
Wonder of compassion was it found me through this repeated meditation practice I did and just by meditating
day and day and day for years it welled up it's like I made space the the
hindrances for compassion settled and they are lo and behold there was this
beautiful feeling of compassion and care and love that was there it wasn't and it
first was there without the need to do anything or a specific direction that had to be addressed it was just there
and I got to appreciate the beauty of compassion so one of the reasons to be recursive to
go back the action is to go back and go through this cycle of mindfulness again maybe when you're meditating
is so you can start discovering the natural compassion that really is quite beautiful
and sometimes that got the action of compassion and the aspiration for suffering to end for someone
leads us to say well I can do something it's not just wishful thinking it's a
wish that yes I can do something for them I can do something for the world
and um and then but to do but to do it on this foundation of the first four
elements hopefully means that um that there can
be a beauty there can be an Attunement there can be a A
naturalness in the action that we do and um so it isn't a sense of uh heavy
responsibility it is a sense of like bearing down I got to do something and and
um and maybe do something because I'm angry and I have to fix something in the world yes I have compassion but I'm
angry and I'm gonna go do something um the natural compassion that can well
up when we really centered on ourself really have this autonomous awareness
this deep Attunement this this agency that goes into kind of clarifying it all
that um there's a beauty to it and a pleasure to it there's a it's a
kind of source of happiness that is not happiness that is something we're intending to be happy because it's
not about us but it's something because of this the the Purity the clarity the Simplicity
the absence of of
dust the absence of tension the absence that it's doing then the uh then when we
get ready to act there's a Simplicity to it the naturalness to it a beauty to it and a
kind of pleasure something that feels good and I was so surprised when I started discovering how good it felt
just to have these very simple acts of care and attention and compassion for
other people and um and first I thought is this okay is are we allowed to do this because
it's felt so good you know and and um and you know just so just sell am I doing it now for selfish reasons
but I found very quickly that as soon as I tried to do it for myself that that messed it up but there had to be kind of
a kind of an absence of Self in the action in the care that and there was
something deeper than this self-concerned self-preoccupation that was motivating the whole thing
so and then if it comes this natural compassion this natural action then it's
one that's attuned to oneself attuned to the situation and even if what it is is sending a
check to a good cause that um there's a there's a kind of a delight
a joy and to be able to do it to kind of a kind of a steep satisfaction a kind of
pleasure happiness that to just be able to do that it isn't like oh I should do more or
some things just oh yes this is good um if uh a friend is suffering and all
your all what seems right to just go over and sit near them uh you don't have to get more involved
sit near them and see what happens maybe it's near them might be you know 10 feet away and sit there and be available and
see what happens and and there are people sometimes who find it so meaningful as they suffer that they were
accompanied from a distance someone was there with them or maybe exit closer maybe you don't say much
and um and because just sharing the spaces enough with them
maybe it's getting somewhat a glass of water you see they're distressed and can I
bring you some water can I you know we know are you hungry
there's so many small ways in which compassion can take form
um I know there's not necessarily you know so small but I had this wonderful experience when with my son when he was
small and maybe it was five years old or something I was going out to a Mexican restaurant to get a burrito or something
with him and um and there was a homeless person in front of the restaurant asking for money for some food
and um and so uh I said well come come with us
and I'll buy you something and so he came in and he just ordered the simplest thing like a simple burrito
and I said don't you don't want more and he said no this is enough and I thought well I thought maybe this was his chance
to anyway so he and his offered to eat with us but he said no and he left
and um and I didn't think too much about it uh until I left the the restaurant and
he was waiting outside for us and he had no paper but he had found a brown garbage uh you
know a shopping bag and he was a poet and he said I wrote a poem and I want to
read it to you and thanks and he read this beautiful poem to us it didn't give us the poem but he read this
beautiful poem and um and uh and that was his thanks and I said wow
who gave who a gift here it was you know it's pretty simple for me to pay for his burrito but wow what a
beautiful thing to take the time to write something and so nice so um
so to uh what do we what can we do HUD and what how do we do it in a natural
way and and how do we do act so the action
that we do benefits ourselves if it's only about benefiting someone
else that it's too easy for it to get messed up
um and if it's only about ourselves it certainly will be messed up but there's a way of caring for both to
be attuned to both and being attuned to oneself is not be attuned to our at our concept of self
our our Alter Ego or something to be attuned to self is to be attuned to
the motivations and the sensations and our suffering and our Joys and our pleasure attuned to where the beauty is
here selfless Beauty so that when we act that's what flowers
in us not um not our selfishness
so compassion is a profound and wonderfully natural aspect of the human heart
it's a kind of a Birthright it's kind of who in some ways at some point you realize oh this is
it becomes a point where you feel this is who I am
this is what I want to orient my life with because it feels so integral and so right
it's not a duty it's not an obligation it's an expression
of some of the deepest understandings deepest ways of being
centered here in a selfless way and to be able to come into the world
to express this deep deep inspiring part of our hearts
is one of the greatest things to do in this life and until we really discover that then
can live that don't underestimate that one of the
greatest actions you can do is this practice of mindfulness and awareness
really cultivate awareness Attunement appreciation
aspiration these four things are part of the profundity of Who We Are
and to practice them and goes through them and deepen and just clarify and
and then when the time comes for action you'll know when when the time is
sometimes the action occurs when nothing else makes sense
and so may we all
be agents of change to change the world to make it a better place
I teach the Dharma to help individuals to support individuals
and my aspiration is that and my trust is that as we individually
Blossom and the Dharma that we benefit this world I would like
this Dharma to really flower and benefit the whole world and so this process of clarifying our
compassion is you know it's one of the profound ways
that we become agents of Peace agents of joy and
support and compassion so thank you all
very much for this and um and next week I'll be on retreat at the
retreat center an inside Retreat Center in Santa Cruz and very happy that uh
um Nikki murgafori will be coming back one of the Great teachers here at IMC and you'll be in
good hands with her and they'll be back in the following week and I was thinking that probably I
would like to continue this theme of compassion and there's because there's much more
that's invaluable about it so probably I'll do that when I come
back so thank you very much and um look forward to being here and
the week after next