so follow up a little bit on that announcement about the threshold choir it's a beautiful um group of people who
go and sing songs to people who are dying and
so they're kind of a service they provide to different places and and so the songs are quite moving and soaring
and peaceful and kind of appropriate for that time transition in life and it's um
also quite nice when we don't think we're in that
transition so
um I think uh people often come to to meditation to be changed in some way
there's something going on in their life in themselves often in Buddhism called
suffering that um something which is difficult and they somehow see that
meditation can change them change something so that there's not so
much discomfort or difficulty or stress or suffering that they live with some
people come with the idea that there's a cause for suffering and so you have to get the insight to be able to see deeply
in and find that cause and pluck it out and then live happier happly ever
after some people have the idea that um there's some kind of way of touching
into a some wonderful State a wonderful state of calm or peace
wonderful state of not self wonderful state of non-duality nonpar oparation
that's some place to go and and then
sometimes people drop into some wonderful State and they think I have it
made and um yeah maybe for that moment and then life comes comes in and
they leave The Retreat Center or Leave The Meditation Center and they find that they have two flat tires in their car
when they're when they go out and whatever that great state was is like they've even forgot about it does they
try to like what two I mean I have places to go important things to do and and I was dwelling in all this peace and
calm I have an important calm to experience I better you know get this
fixed right away and you know anyway so these states they come and they
go and um so there's another approach to what meditation can do rather than
changing us or changing some aspect ECT of fixing something inside what it does is to expand our
capacity to be uncomfortable now we don't advertise
this come to IMC and learn how to be more uncomfortable than
you but in fact this is actually an important part of it if you want if you want the meditation to be realistic
if you want to be a practice that supports you in all the different facets of your
life and um the um because life will change life will have challenges you
never know what's going to come the um this is one of the wonderful
or very significant teachers in kind of in the 20th century for many people here
in the west America was um man named ramdas
and he went around uh teaching spiritual practices and spirituality and practicing himself for decades and then
nearby here he had a um stroke I think he was in one of the local hospitals
here afterwards for that and uh and he said that when he had a stroke he was
kind of dis discouraged because his practice no longer worked so how what was going to support him then
so so to find something thing which we can rely on and one of the things we can
rely on is increasing our capacity in modern psychology sometimes they call this uh increasing the window of
Tolerance that uh we can tolerate more and so part of what mindfulness is
is increasing that window of tolerance so that we're less troubled or disturbed
or stressed by what happens we not less we're less overwhelmed we're developing our capacity to hold increased degrees
of challenges so that if we get sick if we have an accident if some tragedy happens
in our life not to take away the idea that it's unfortunate not take away the idea it's
a tragedy or loss and things like that but to not be pushed around by it or entangled with
it or limited by it but to be able to have a wide capacity and open heart and
open mind that has space for it that can hold it so we can have a chance for for
wisdom I have a chance to see clearly we have a chance to kind of relate to it in a different
way and um and so part of what we're doing in meditation practice is in fact
learning to be uncomfortable learning to be comfortable with
discomfort now don't go make yourself uncomfortable so you can learn this lesson
when I was a a Zen monk I noticed that if I had pain while I meditated I could
get more concentrated and so I went to the Abbot and said I noticed this now should I sit
in full Lotus so that I could have more pain and he said
no don't don't look for pain don't make pain but when pain visits you when it
comes then sit with it some then practice with it but don't you know rely
on pain for your concentration or for anything so don't go look for to be uncomfortable when you meditate it's
actually wise to kind of make yourself as comfortable as you can when you're going to meditate within reason
comfortable and alert but sooner or later uh you'll be
uncomfortable and for many of us it sooner rather than later the body gets uncomfortable
especially if you're a new meditator um you know you're uncomfortable with how much rumination
your mind is making how much you're caught up in spinning stories and ideas and plans how much you're still caring
resentments and challenges and um and um and so when
those things are there the idea in meditation and mindfulness meditation is not to see them as problems
not to see them as wrong or you're not meditating properly but to see with have
the idea okay this too I have to learn to open up to this
too I have to make space for how can I expand my window of tolerance so that I
can allow this to be here without being caught in it without being reactive to
it and so that's kind of an exploration like what what does it mean to give breathing room to our mind to our hearts
to our feelings what does it mean to make space for it and then stay present
for it stay with it without reacting to it
and the the image that I love for mindfulness practice that what we're
doing is we're cupping our hands together like this so the two hands are making a cup kind of and then uh they
they come underneath and hold whatever is happening for us whatever is
happening whatever challenge we're having we're just holding it and um and it's a little bit like um
uh you know if uh if um I'm troubled by the world and
you know I'm kind of trying to resist it all and the resisting of it all starts to be tiring but I have to resist the
world right I can't stop because the world's going to do something terrible to me and I'm afraid to kind of let go
and then I think I'm supposed to meditate and so I go there with you know go and meditate and try to deal with
these hands these fingers try to relax and all that but nothing really works but what does it mean to come underneath
and hold it what it means is something like discovering what's
deeper and then come and hold that so it can rest and if the elbow can rest then
the hand can rest but as long as the elbow is uncomfortable being like this it's kind of trying with its hand to
find an answer to something so to begin to one way we find
our capacity to hold things is to really be present and find what it is that
needs to be held in the field in the in the lap of awareness hold it just let it
be there and um and then to be able to have
more and more more capacity to be uncomfortable I was uh told something
disturbing this week and um and I heard it and um I thought to myself wow this
is quite something I think Gil this is the time
to just make space for it uh I've been in situation like this
before where I react where I took it person personally where I felt like I had to do something immediately send off
emails or you know whatever and no I don't think so I think this is the time
just to let it be not to ignore it but to make space for it and let it be and
see what happens let's just kind of hold it and I'll address it when the right time comes rather than rush to put out
the fire that was no fire it was just kind of it was just kind of a difficult
statement someone made and that made it so much easier to go through this that I had the capacity the
willingness to just be uncomfortable with it make space for it breathe with it not not not kind of react to it
immediately and fully so to increase our
capacity so I want to give you uh provide a um imag that comes from the
Chinese Buddhist tradition the Chan tradition in China that has all kind of wonderful
implications and um and hopefully use it as an example of what I'm talking about
and um apparently there was uh like a wizard in
town who uh had the ability to read people's minds and so he was kind of you
know kind of impressed people by his ability and and so there was a Zen student who
said well I don't think you can read my zen Master's mind I can read anybody's mind so the
Zen master was out for a walk on in town one day and there was a river running through the middle of the town and uh
and this and may imagine kind of the most idic river through an idic town in
the springtime or something really nice blue sky and just really nice and
there's this nice River and there's a prominade or something along the river and um and in the river there's a few
sailboats that maybe little cargo boats with sails that are gently moving across
back and forth across the river or down the river it's kind of idic and peaceful
setting and so those end Masters walking down this prominade and looking at the river and the boats and just out out for
a little walk and um that he runs into the
wizard and The Wizard uh now stops that stops in front of him and like like
maybe I don't know what Wizards do it pears into his eyes or you know in order to read his
mind and after a short while the wizard got very
disturbed and spun around and R away and left that town never came
back but someone stopped him before he actually left and said what's where you going what
happened well I I looked into the Zen Master's mind and all I saw was the river and
some sailboat sailing in it is that what his Zen mastered mind is
like and um and how I understand this story is that he was reading the Zen
Master's mind in a sense but there was nothing about the Zen master to be
seen it was just the Zen master was just there present for the environment around him seeing the river and the boats and
that's what was in his mind because that what was happening in the moment but there wasn't any like wanting to be on
the boat or you know thinking that you know I should have been a captain boat captain rather than a zen
master I must have chosen the wrong job and or you know you know I have to give
a Dharma talk and I should be thinking about that Dharma talk and worrying about what I'm going to say and you know
he was just kind of walking down and taking in the moment for that and um and uh a similar idea to
this is uh goes back to the ancient Buddhist tradition the ancient text
there there they have not a wizard but they have this idea of Mara Mara is the
personification of everything that'll tempt you to be caught in the world of
the senses so whatever you know sense pleasure whatever ever kind of
absorption in with you know the whole world of sensual pleasure just imagine the ideal world would be a casino with
naked dancers and every drug and alcohol possible and you just kind of would be
wonderful [Laughter]
right so that's Mara's world and so so Mara is trying to and last thing Mara
wants is someone to get enlightened because then they're not going to go to the casino you know they're going to you
not going to get caught in that realm and so um so this ancient world
this this personification of Temptation um U when it when uh when the
mara looks into the mind of someone who's awakened they don't see
anything because what defines someone what for Mara is their attachments is
their clinging so whatever you're caught in that's kind of what you become in
Mara's eyes and then Mara can get you but if you're not defined by your
attachments because you have no attachments then there's nothing that defines you there's nothing to H hold on
to there's nothing to grab a hold of that Mara can kind of convince you to
you know to get caught so both of these examples are
examples of Minds that have great capacity because they're not getting
attached to anything they're not holding on to anything and that's what limits the mind that's what contracts it and
makes it small and some of us can feel that if you have a busy day running around doing
lots and lots of things and even multitasking and and um and just kind of
doing doing doing the you can feel like the mind gets very small and tight and
stressed and and it's kind of like you know claustrophobic in there and by the time you stop sometimes I've SE I've
noticed sometimes after doing a lot even like sometimes cleaning my house a lot just going to do cleaning cleaning
cleaning cleaning that I finish kind of do you ever finish you I finish kind of and I could
see my mind is still reaching out for something to do I don't know what it is I don't know what I'm I'm not supposed
to do anything but but the mind is still looking for something right it's a caught and um so careful be careful
because Mara can read you now can see you knows exactly what you're about you're you're that wanting wanting and
so that's the ideal situation where you want but you don't know what you want Mara will come
with all the Temptations and so um so this pass this
ability to let the mind be a open wide field a open space like this River with
the boats kind of great great sky and everything like makes space for everything make space for something
rather than fix it make space for something rather than changing it and
make space for something rather than defining Yourself by it and that's one of the Temptations
that Mar as a personification of ourselves where we're tempted to Define ourselves by our attachments by our
desires by what we want what we don't want um our opinions about these things becomes Who We Are
and so rather than doing that the the the IM the imagery the kind of
alternative is this idea of make room make room in Awareness make room in
the mind make room in the heart we can hold this and one of the reasons why this is
so useful is that any room and space we can
make to hold ourselves and what goes on within us translates or inter as as also
a capacity to hold the suffering of the world the difficulty around us of our
friends or family our communities the world itself and I think this is a great gift
that we give to not be not be not drowned in the suffering
around us not be distressed by it not be afraid of it or angry by it but have the
capacity to open wide to hold it all so in a sense the suffering of the world is
the sailboats on the river not to diminish the suffering not
to ignore it or make it some kind of polanish kind of thing rivers on the you know boats on the river but rather to be
able to see it clearly so that then we can respond
appropriately in a good way and we see lots of things and that's
things that are very Troublesome in this world and things that hopefully we will respond
to um you know what you know what do you do
if you witness an act of racism do you react to it and close down
do you get angry do you get afraid do you say it's none of my business I saw one right down the street
here by the high school someone yelled out of a car a
racial um kind of terrible thing to someone walking down the
sidewalk what do we do when this Happ these kinds of things happen can we open our
capacity not only to hold it and be aware of it without reacting but also
even more better is to allow the welling up of an appropriate
response that too can arise as space for that and when we have the capacity to be
uncomfortable that also translates to our capacity to act when it's
uncomfortable to act oh this is difficult one of the one
of the things I've learned I feel through this Buddhist practice is to
um I think I think the expression is counterphobic so I've learned to when
I'm a afraid of something to turn towards it okay what what's this what's this and
um I was with someone recently and I told her that I this is something I've learned to do in this practice of mine
is step towards things which are uncomfortable a little bit frightening and so I told her we were
walking we're in a little walk together and I said um scare [Laughter]
me and um and she um she used to be an actor actress so I guess she has some
capacity to so she took it on so she kind of suddenly kind of
roared at me it I was I was slightly surprised how quick she she respond how
quick she did it and and strongly she did it but sure enough because I knew I knew what was
coming kind of sure I just turn towards her and step closer like this like you
know I got within a foot of her or something and boy was she
surprised she was like she like she's the one who got it
sprayed so this you know to be able to to to be willing to be so to be
uncomfortable to be willing to have capacity allows us sometimes to do
things in the world that to help in situations that are difficult or uncomfortable it's not a drag to develop
greater tolerance for discomfort it allows us to take care of the world much
better I can't tell you how much I learned about being uncomfortable being a parent of young
children that's a great training okay this
[Laughter] too and the one of the representatives
representative kind of high points of that kind of learning to be uncomfortable with discomfort
maybe you want to cover your ears or something but was um when I did this thing I cuffed my hands right like just
hold hold everything in your mindfulness like cuffed hands my son my little son when he was a
a toddler or something maybe younger than that even um I kind of quickly put my hands
in front of him like this um to to catch his
vomit and it was just an act of love love you know like of course you
know if ID said this if I'd heard this idea before I had kids I would have thought
yuck I'm sure some of you did hearing it sorry about that but you know oh this
too there this this window of tolerance to hold in big space and to be with
what's here such a powerful skill one of the ways we learn this in
this mindfulness practice is not to do it automatically it's kind of the ideal is
to have the ability to make space and be uncomfortable to have a great capacity for
whatever um it's the ideal but one one of the principles we have in this
practice is don't go directly for the ideal rather study what gets in the way
of the ideal so that means study how you are uncomfortable with discomfort study what
the reactivity you have is the beliefs you have the notice study of what you do with your body rather than stepping
towards something you shut down and you pull away even with your posture study
what you how you are when things are difficult get to know it well it's by
understanding yourself and your reactions and all that that wisdom and capacity
grows because if you go directly to the ideal I'm supposed to just kind of be now counterphobic and open up to
everything uh you might actually be doing yourself a disservice you might not have the
capacity and also the the the Tendencies to be reactive are still there Lodge
deep inside and ready to come out and you can sometimes cause more harm to yourself and others if you kind of in a
naive way make yourself open and available kind of vulnerable in a sense
and you're not ready because the reactivity is there to kind of bite you come up and rear its head or do
something so we're very interested in this practice is how do we
react how do we get caught how do we push away how do we succumb to fear or
succumb to beliefs or judgments or about ourselves or others how do we limit
ourselves and as we study that that's what we hold in the palm of
mindfulness okay this is how it is for me what it's like just to let me with it
for a while let me be with my reactivity rather than thinking I'm not supposed to
be reactive let me be with my fear rather than believing supposed to be
afraid now Gil is counterop phobic I'm supposed to be counterop phobic no
you're supposed to be Pro
phobic in the sense of you know be with be it and hold it until you learn learn
something until something shifts in you something relaxes or something you start
understanding what's further deeper down like the elbow is that what really needs to be relaxed or you still or you simply
develop a capacity wow I am really afraid right now but
this is a new world I'm living in usually when I'm afraid I'm running around like a chicken Rel at its head
but look I'm just sitting here calmly meditating and I have all this fear coursing through my body and I had no
idea it was possible to sit calmly and have so much fear at the same time they
two can coexist maybe now I'm ready next time I'm afraid to not get
caught by the fear but rather make space for
it and I'll end with this story that I've told a few times
now of a of a a person who was in a retreat many Retreats with me and had a
very very difficult time lot of suffering lot of like like you know just
just everything was challenging and I had the thought that I've
um that maybe a Dharma teacher should never have when someone sincerely
practicing and trying and keeps coming back and even though it's challenging I had the thought maybe I should tell this
person to stop practicing so but I did
and then 6 months later the person came to me and said remember that Retreat where I had such a hard time I said yes
I sure did and I didn't tell him what I was
thinking and then I said well that was such an important Retreat for me because
after that I had a lot of challenges in my life and I was
prepared I knew how to be I knew how to be with
challenges so I didn't see that coming I just thought the person was challenged and it wasn't like quit you know hitting
his head against the wall over and over again but in fact he was learning how to be with such difficulty uh in a way that
he could be with it when it really arose for him in his life he had the capacity
to to not have it not be there but make space for it and hold
it so um part of what we're doing here in this
practice is expanding our capacity to hold
discomfort and I would hope that we never think
that there's an end to that process because if we do then it's too
easy to believe I after we act here I have to be angry I have to somehow
attack or blame or do something but okay let's open let's open and then let's see
what wisdom arises in that capacity in that openness the last thing I want is this
kind of great capacity to be open to unvailable and be uncomfortable to mean
that we don't respond to the world that is not what we're looking for here but
the idea is to respond from that place
so that it's more effective it's maybe giving the world the gift
of space for people to be who they are so they can see and they can relax and
they can soften but if we react in response to other people's
reactivity maybe it just becomes more more worse and worse it doesn't help
anyone one of the great gifts we can give the world and others is to be a
safe person for them this is what the Buddha said he said he said make yourself safe for
others isn't that great so those are my thoughts
today and um so we do have this we have 15 minutes before the end maybe if some
of you would like to ask maybe it will take about five minutes for questions if anybody would like to ask anything or
any testimonials you have about developing greater
capacity Gil uh I'm curious about how you handled that situation nearby when
when someone yells a slur you know I didn't do anything which sounds pretty
bad but I was inside the high school and there was a big fence and so I heard
this terrible thing being said and I didn't see who they were talking to I was like wow what was that and um and
the car car drove off and so I kind of kept walking along the high school until
I could see who it was that it was I I wanted to know who it was I because I felt that was important to know what was
this about but so maybe in retrospect I could could have gone found the person
that it was the yelling was done to and done something supportive or something I
don't know what I could have done but because of the distance in the big fence and all that that I didn't do anything but it it it
really have had a big impact on me and like right here in our neighborhood just like there was this uh
I was a little bit stunned last week to read about the police officer in San
Jose who was laid off because of his racist texts you know right here this
like feels like this is right in our neighborhood and so this is something we have to kind of you know care
about
yes uh Gil I have a question somewhat weird question but nonetheless it's a
genuine question so my dad has been diagnosed with uh metastatic prostate
cancer like week and a half ago so it's been difficult so as you know I've taken
Chaplan C Core so I and I've been to two maranasati
Retreats even before that so I had an opportunity um to relate to this part of
life that normally people don't give themselves an opportunity too so my
particular challenge right now is um when I'm talking for instance to my
husband uh about what's happening to my dad is that um in that discourse I also
include you know and his 5 years survival rate is 33% but it's uh being taken by my
husband that I'm being pessimistic I'm not again it's taken by your husband uh as being pessimistic
uhhuh or overly negative but I'm not there is just
certain big data that points that that's the case is and this is one of the
things that um are happening and one of my reactions
so right now I'm stuck in the polarity with my husband that he's like oh yeah let's be optimistic you're too
pessimistic but I'm not and I understand that with a
Buddhist with great amount of respect we weird bunch in how we relate to things like
like I get that so I don't know
um just what to do about that because it adds extra level of
misunderstanding extra what extra level of misunder understanding because it's
not optimistic versus pessimistic like like I'm not being pessimistic but by acknowledging that this is realistic
prognosis I'm really not so my question is how to handle fam
relationships when our Buddhist discourse is being
[Music] misunderstood well I don't know what to
say but uh was you know it's fascinating my my my uh I'm getting poor hearing
right and I don't have my hearing aids in so I heard almost everything you said but I misunderstood one word when there
was some degree of misunderstanding you said the first time you said it I I I thought you were saying um uh uh a
higher degree of me me misunderstanding you know you know no no you didn't say
that but uh but oh there's too much me here yeah and I thought maybe that's a
clue that um and since you did the chapy training maybe your job is to be
everyone's chaplain oh I know that that's
did I know it's not the novel s like totally because I'm like okay my husband
cannot take care of me maybe I can take care of my husband like I totally get that but uh sure I mean because it's my
dad it's not my husband that's that's fine uh but so so you want someone to take care of you no no no no I don't
want a fictional problem to be there because the fictional problem that it's
not really there that it is in my husband mind that he's optimistic and
I'm pessimistic I'm not pessimistic I'm just acknowledging different realities around
my husbands uh around my dad's cancer and like and like
I don't feel the need to recoil at Green
prognosis but that does not mean that I'm being pessimistic so I just like to like so the question is why do you care
so much what your husband believes ah I care so much about my husband's beliefs
well first of all because I love my husband very very dearly he's a phenomenal being but but aside from that
um the times when my dad is diagnosed and he will start treatment soon is a
time of great stress for the entire family for obuse reasons so because
there is this important misunderstanding it creates conflict and
it creates difficulty talking about my dad's cancer that is affecting
everybody in the family yeah so so if your husband is accurate his assessment
of you then you have one issue if he's not accurate which you're saying then one possibility is
to is um is to agree to disagree another
possibility is to say I'm neither pessimistic or optimistic I'm just trying to take it
take into account all the possibilities so we can be ready for whatever happens and if that's if you think that's
pessimistic then let's just agree to disagree I think that's what we end up doing but I was just you know because I
respect your opinion so highly and I know you have so much experience I was just like wondering if there is a
particular angle that we're missing because what we end up doing is a is a great much respect for me then I'll then
then then I'll kind of air on the side of my [Laughter]
preference and that is um you know
uh taking care of yourself and how you are so important for this and be have
have a capacity to relax and accept yourself as you are and all this and by
doing that also maybe your husb hband needs some care as well sometimes when people want to be
too optimistic around like that something like this it means that they're afraid exactly yeah and so you
don't you know him better than most people so it might not be the case but uh but you know no it is the case very
much so then so then as the as the family
chaplain all right okay I got it and in a family you have to be a stealth
chaplain you because you you don't want to kind of show show up and Qui okay sit down I'm going to be your chaplain you
you want to just you know what's his fear what what kind of reassurances he need what kind of presence does he need
and if he gets that then maybe it's easier for him to accept and understand your your position thanks so much I hope
that was okay thank you yeah we're the one way you come and talk to me afterwards because what I'd like to do
because there's a tea time today I would love it if you would all of you you don't have to if you don't want to but
um just turn to someone near you maybe you know one or two people near you look around so no one's left alone and just
say hello and if this idea of kind of increasing your capacity is evocative of
something for you interesting for you what what did devoke and then just doesn't have to be more than a couple of
minutes but also since we have tea and everyone's invited it actually kind of breaks the ice a little bit so you get to meet someone it's kind of nice so so
please