foreign [Music]
happy Friday
oh I'm not sure how it is for you in
San Francisco the morning has a just a beautiful Sparkle to it
I hope wherever you are is full comfortable
and if it's not may you be well
so today to continue this discussion of Social and communal Harmony
we'll first sit together mindfulness of the Body for 10 minutes or so and then
to the fourth Brahma vihara of the equanimity
foreign [Music]
an alert aligned
meditative posture
okay
this perhaps familiar beginning
to stop foreign
to see
maybe a roll of the shoulders to relax the back can align the bones
and a few deep breaths to establish the connection
between the sensations of breathing and attention
foreign
keeping a steady connection but the breathing body
refreshing that connection renewing it
foreign
now a gentle shift
moving toward the fourth Equanimity the fourth Brahma bihara of equanimity
it's first again generate just a touch of loving kindness
matter directed to ourselves
holding yourself in a kind regard
and wishing yourself well
maybe even seeing yourself in your mind's eye
may I be happy
may I be healthy
may I be safe
may I live with ease and peace
repeating as you wish
and letting that register in the body in the mind in the heart
may I be happy
foreign
having invited loving kindness Mata
to arise
now to call to mind someone with whom you have a simple
relationship simple
holding them in mind arousing equanimity
equipoise a balance of mind
with regard to them
along with this this wish foreign
happiness
wishing may you take care of your own happiness
and then noticing the heart's response
may you take care of your own happiness
foreign
clear or quite subtle
may you take care of your own happiness
them
much like the warm sunlight of matter
that reflects coolly off the Moon
this Equanimity can shine Cooling
balanced
arousing Equanimity in this way
we can now radiate to the first quarter in front of us
so all beings in the forward Direction [Music]
may you take care of your own happiness
foreign
to the right
letting the cool light of equanimity shine on all beings
foreign
may you take care of your own happiness
now behind
to all beings in the quarter behind us
may you take good care of your own happiness
now to the left
a cool light of equanimity
may all beings in this direction take care of their own happiness
and below foreign
Direction may you take care of your own happiness
and above foreign
s above us
may you take care of your own happiness
and finally to all beings in the four quarters and above and below
foreign
relaxing any effort in the method
just registering the state of the body and mind now
may all beings everywhere be happy
peaceful safe and truly free
[Music]
foreign
Ty
a group of practitioners it's a rare and wonderful thing
so for today I have a few Reflections to offer and I would also like to hear from you
but to begin let's say this week in the
in in our consideration of the Buddhist teachings on social and communal Harmony
we started with right view of course that are our actions have effects
and that we can discern we can choose then we practice this tool of repeated
reflection which gave us an approach to discern how to move forward skillfully
with both our challenges and um
those joys in our life then we looked at good friendship form
of friendship and the question I would like to ask on this last day
is having looked at all these means or methods or approaches what is our aspiration for a harmonious
community what does it look like and what is it for
in the in the Zen teachings there's this image of a um
is orienting toward the North Star
uh that there's a there's this distant North Star that we direct our in this
case a boat interact your boat and you sail in the direction of the North Star
the the north star of course is our vision it's our aspiration
and we move uh interestingly as folks who say oh no
you don't go straight at the destination you have to tack
left right left right and respond to the particulars
of the the challenges the terrain I guess
all in all making this um uh making this
vow this perseverance a dedication of moving in the direction of this North
Star so in this in this discussion of the
week we've been talking a lot about how to meet the waves how to move amidst the waves
approaches how to row and I'm really interested today in
what's the North Star about I may have more questions about this
than answers and I'm curious about what comes up for you too
but just briefly say a couple of things as someone who um for maybe nine of the
last 10 years I've been living in Dharma communities a fortunate life
um I've noticed a couple of things about these different spaces one is the the first Dharma Community I lived in
I had a very particular strength it was kind of amazing to witness and that
strength was its Singularity of purpose it was so clear to everyone who was
there that the community was set up for the practice and the practice was absolutely first
priority all the time it was amazing it was amazing
um one of the best examples of this that might sound a little drastic in our in
our regular day-to-day life there were three times every day for one
hour that all of the work on the property stopped completely and everyone went to
the meditation Hall everyone
can you imagine it was so still and we got into this
Rhythm this Rhythm as a community in a way we kind of harmonized
now is the time to go to meditation there was no deliberation about it but they had this real strength in this
community of the singularity of purpose the clarity that shine like a bright
light from a distance
and then in another Community I was living in I saw a different strength this community
um had many functions many arms we'll say
um and their strength was responsiveness this community was uh was such that
there were there were many people asking many things of this community and there was there was a way that in
contrast to just having this one thing that we focused on instead it was trying
to meet the needs of a varied a varied and very large group
and this was a function of its location its people even its teachings
I heard a story of one of the well-known
um uh projects for support of the unhoused
that's associated with the Dharma Community the the teacher who initiated this program said oh
I I never intended to start this program but I saw a need and I responded
so responsiveness
purpose responsiveness these were our strengths but what were they for
what were they for I really hold this as a question I wonder what it is for you
in the Buddhist teachings of course he he holds holds forth the the per the whole purpose of the
teaching in the community is for the sake of liberation it's an inspiring possibility
and I think I've seen the way in in our Dharma communities that [Music] um
they perform a function for so many people
they can be a home for rights of Passage important ceremonies they can walk us
through these big transitions of birth and death and change of job and
um so many things so many things under the umbrella of
Buddhist practice so it's interesting to contemplate
what's the purpose what's all this for one way I help myself get grounded is
actually to look smaller and I ask myself the question how would people treat each other
what do the interactions look like you know there's some
says this thing I've heard that the mind is not our own but we are
responsible for it I feel a little bit that way about our
communities and our relationships too they're certainly not our own uh
but we belong to them we give ourselves to them we're responsible for them we're responsive in
them and what does that look like Buddha has this beautiful teaching you
may know about the six principles of cordiality that to me pretty pretty beautifully
encapsulates what a harmonious Community can look like in terms of relationship
he's teaching these monastics these six principles of cordiality and they're meant to produce cohesiveness in the
community they're conducive to non-dispute to Concord
and to Unity and the first three are all variations on one
variations on loving kindness the first three of six principles of cordiality
he says that um a person in this community maintains
bodily verbal and mental body speech in mind
acts of loving kindness toward the others in his community or Community
their community and that this this produces respect and
Concord and affection and unity what's interesting about this is that
the the acts of loving kindness they can be said openly or privately which means
they can be things that others know about and see and they can be things
that they don't see that they don't know about but even still
it's conducive of respect and affection cohesiveness
and Concord so the first three variations on loving kindness the fourth
is that one shares what one has we often reflect in in these talks on
the the power of giving and sharing it's no surprise
the fifth is possessing in common with those in your community
virtuous Behavior that kind of Sila the commitment to the
the precepts in short the commitment
to non-harming and that this shared in common with others in your community is conducive
Concord and then finally we come right back to
the beginning the sixth principle for a Concord or for cordiality is a variation of Right View here we are
with Right View again it says a monastic dwells both openly
and privately possessing in common with fellow monastics of you that is
noble and emancipating which leads out for one who acts upon it to the complete
destruction of suffering this too is a principle of cordiality
that creates affection and respect and conduces to cohesiveness
to non-dispute to Concord and to Unity
so maybe maybe this is what specific
interactions look like can look like in a harmonious community
well my hope is that over the course of this week we've we've covered a fair amount of territory a fair number of
teachings about social and communal Harmony and I hope that it gives rise to some reflection about
what would you like what would what would you aspire to for a harmonious community
for your harmonious Community ours what might that be for us
I hope we hope we feed that reflection and then in our last two minutes and
I'll stay a couple after I'm interested um you know my connection my connection
with you is the YouTube chat but I thought maybe I would ask
what is it what might it be for you from the week
but you feel like you that you're making your own that um
you're turning or considering or applying or seeing or recognizing in your in your own life
in your own relationships wherever you are This Global Sangha
and I won't be able to read them all but if you if you put some in the chat I'm
happy to without the names read out a few so that this can be part of our
um part of our our time together
I'll just wait here
and see one that says I've sown within grown Within in my own within not alone with him
thank you for all our Unity
one says responsibility for our own authentic path
and someone's reply uh someone's making use of the rahula
questions repeated reflection ah yes the clutch of mindfulness
respect and loving kindness very nice
times of Silence to work with the process hmm
supporting great
I'll stay and read some more and I will better YouTube recording farewell thank
you for this week in practice may you be nourished may your practice be nourished may all beings everywhere
be free foreign