good morning Sangha
um so sweet to read the messages each
morning knowing that you're joining from all
over the world
hello again welcome everyone thank you for joining This Global Sangha in all
those days meditating learning together
what a gift to ourselves and to the whole world
hmm and just a feeling that joy and
uplift from this whole week being with you all
and today and in our meditation this week we're being speaking about
this list of words start with R
and today we'll add yet another r word
and so we started a week with relaxing
and then recognizing [Music] the phenomenon
in a relaxed field and then we added
um what did we say we had relaxing recognizing
and we have releasing releasing any extra tension
are seeing in our world we call it tukkah releasing dukka
and um when their extra tension being released
we can rest rest here
peacefully calmly and today I'll add another word
uh which is realizing
and this realizing comes as a flavor of
having some insight into our phenomenon our lived experience
and it can be as small as recognizing oh
I didn't have to believe the story that I've been telling myself in my head
anymore that I'm always quick tempered
that was just a story and so that comes from
this began to see clearly this is just a phenomenon of
thinking grasping
and we can recognize the truth of it and realize that we don't have to get
entangled with this anymore so this realization doesn't have to be
some sort of a big bad realization you know but um can be small
um uh moments of seeing something that's true that's new that wasn't available
before and it may be
realizing that a holding on to certain kind of
um for myself this uh realizing the striving the try trying
holding on to the goal that I have set up for myself at the bar I was holding
for myself that was just a barrier for the practice
and that's a moment of realizing something and the realization realization has a
function in our practice it began to offer something for us to
shift within so there can be an inner shift when this kind of realization
come forth so a realization can come along the way
in this process and doesn't have to be kind of happening in some sort of
and of a certain process and so it takes pain careful attention
to what is happening so what began our meditation
and are inviting everyone to kind of go through this process that we've been
speaking about and practicing with and allow yourself to kind of open to
whatever might be available in this process um wherever you are is a perfect place
to be as a girl often speak about this
so let's begin
arriving Here and Now
entering into the Temple of this body mind and heart
entering into a practice lineage
that has been going on for Generations
or the practitioners before us practiced like this
arriving here and now
mindfulness front and center
heart bonus front and center
as you take the inner outer seat
again to open to the broader sense of
your experience maybe the global sense of the body
sitting buying down
you're standing
and relaxing and easing into the posture you're taking
it's the relaxing invoke a sense of opening in various ways in the body
maybe opening of the chest
softening of the belly
dropping of the shoulders
letting go of the thoughts
letting go of the conceptual overlays
dropping into about sense of your experience
and allow this earthy body resting on Earth
grounded and settled
if you like you can gently turn your attention
to The Familiar object of the meditation
the movements of the breath
and dancing Sensations in the body
are there elements earth water
fire winged
recognizing each arising just as it is
each passing away just as it is
releasing the stories
resting in the field of clear kind
knowing
who's arresting is a kind of not doing doing
so one of my teachers often says
quiet and still knowing
he must come still
field of knowing
every experience that arises
is fresh
the tension stories creeping again
you can always began again
as we invest abide
in a peaceful clear knowing
sometimes you may realize that
there is a different way of being
that does not involve
getting hooked in our stories grasping
maybe New Perspectives open up
we can choose
we can choose calm rather than agitation
you can choose these
rather than an entanglement
and sometimes there's realizations
may be manifested ask exactly how we are
nothing needs to happen
foreign
[Music]
hmm
so uh yesterday um I left you with a cloof hair
it's a cliffhanger as the statement that the app is made in the story that I was
telling yesterday and that it says the Buddhist the path only exists
while one walks it so I'm going to continue
and today's story it's gonna follow this theme
and it's called they Abyss
so we have to end with some dramatic ending so
they Abyss hmm
a monkey told this story I had a reached and in passy after 25
years in the monastery I had it devoted myself diligently to
monastic practice through much effort my powers of a
concentration mindfulness and compassion were among the strongest the apples had
ever seen I was known for my peace and equanimity
I had no obvious attachments however
I had not yet attained the realization other monks and Nuns with less time in
the monastery and the less thorough practice at a reach to various levels of
Awakening everyone thought my circumstances was most estranged
then one day the abyss took me aside for a long talk
we discussed how I was held back by my fear of completely letting go
as much as I trusted the spiritual life at my core was some deep
unarticulated nagging mistrust as long as I could remember
a part of me was on the lookout for impending tragedy
and this is a side comment and I think most of us probably can relate to this
always on the lookout for danger
at the end of the conversation the app is told me she could think of only one
more Catalyst for my enlightenment just the possibility brought me tears of
a joy until she told me it meant entering a basement room called The
Abyss no one in many generations had entered
this room only the abyss was entrusted with the secret knowledge of what was inside
no one else knew while the red door to the room was kept locked it didn't need
to be an atmosphere of Terror in emanated from
within and the monks announced were afraid to walk anywhere near the door
walking down to the basement the app is explained that my one and last
opportunity was inside this room once I entered this room
there would be no turning back standing in front of the door I had to
mix the feelings about entering the app is carefully explained the
instructions that had been transmitted to her I was to step into the room the abbess
would close and lock the door behind me and under no circumstances would she
unlock it again I'll enter in the room I was simply to
walk to the other side of the room and exit through the door there
it sounded easy enough suddenly the app is opened the door and
pushed me inside before I could get my bearings I heard the door locked behind me
the room proved to be huge perhaps a hundred feet wide
on the other side of the room was the door just like the one I had entered
the room had no floor I was standing on a two foot ledge as wide as the door
between me and the other door was a gapping Abyss I could not see the bottom
from the depth came horrible grinding and cracking sounds
occasionally a ball of a flame shot upward
I was scared and perplexed how was I supposed to walk across
I spent the first day standing on the ledge studying the room
certain that I was meant to discover some secret way to get across
I spent the second day banging on the door hoping that someone would let me
out I cried most of the third day until while sitting on the ledge one of my
slippers fell off my foot as it fell the grinding noises seemed to
get worse on the fourth day I desperately and
repeatedly reviewed the instructions they were so simple
walk across the room and out the other door
could I trust the abyss tired and hungry on the fifth day I give
up all hope and thanks I had no other choice but to try the
instructions I decided to walk off walk out of the
ledge I tried not to imagine what awaited me down in the depths
terrified I looked straight ahead and took a step into the room
into the unknown as my foot came down
the ledge stretched forward receiving me with affirm steady base
it took me another day to take the second step but when I finally did the ledge again
extended itself outwards to receive my foot
I continued walking into the emptiness
and with each step the ledge became longer
long in a song enough I had reached the opposite side
from that day on letting go into the freedom of
realization as um easily
the Buddhist a path only exists while one walks it
that's a real daring Endeavor right what we're doing here
showing up each day to practice and learn
to walk the path it's a real
courageous Act even if you don't feel heroic just yet
until we there do we dare to walk the path unfolding
right underneath of our own feet maybe with the fires shooting up
underneath and the Heat
do we dare to choose calm and compassion when someone is needing and angry to us
do we dare to meet our own inner turmoil turmoil even though
the default reactivity would be to blame and Escape
your way there to choose a wholesome even though when it seems to be quite
impossible my husband my husband shared a little
cartoon yesterday with me I had a picture of a old wise man and a
young little girl and the little girl asked the old man a
question and she says tell me sir in which field could I make a great career
and the wise man replied with a smile being a good human being
there are a lot of opportunities in this area and very little competition
yeah the way they are to choose something unpopular
so walking this past um takes a lot of Courage patience
persistence determination sincerity
and commitment and boundless kindness
to ourselves and others
so in many ways there's a whole week of stories and Reflections are pointing at
how the practice path is a whole life path
I think one of you kind of put this in the chat box the other day that's a whole life path
and I would also add it's a whole lifelong path
it's a way of a living a great
Thai monastic feature key in her book
pure and the simple says this the practice isn't something you do from
time to time you know you have to keep doing it continuously
throughout life you have to keep up with the Holy life because you're playing for real
you are playing for real here and this is not dipping our toes in
water and just walk away this is crossing the flood
crossing the flood of a greed hatred delusion
and so may the stories and reflections enrich your practice
and deepen your practice and may our practice and and are
learning together benefit all beings everywhere
and so I deeply bow and appreciate all
of us on doing this together What a Wonder in this world
and I also want to introduce our teacher for next week another wonderful IMC
teacher Meg Galler will be here joining you
teaching from France appalache and another wonderful being to be with
and so may your practice blossom may you thrive in Dharma
thank you everyone