good morning good morning everybody those are just joining I guess everybody on this continent it's
morning but if you're on other continents it's not morning so good day whatever time it is or even if
you're listening to this you know when it's not live sometime later but uh
just greetings
okay so I think we'll get going here
so this morning I'm going to continue on this uh theme of Mara's armies
but before we get there we'll do a guided meditation
click in our meditation posture
and if you're sitting up tuning into this sense of
a brightness in the body the sense of
moving through space upwards in some kind of way
and letting this be the container for experience
in whatever way that makes sense for you
yeah so we have some uprightness
but there's also softness and ease
and connecting with an acknowledgment that to practice is a movement of kindness
to come to this meditation maybe to put hellos in the chat
is a movement of kindness can we connect with that
this well-wishing for others and taking care of ourselves
this giving of care respect
to ourselves and to others this is a beautiful thing we're doing
and then just connecting with the experience of the body more generally
using a light and curious attention
what is the experience of having a body
the experience of the body
whatever is there tuning in
showing up for that experience
as best we can as best we can
touching experience with this kind and delicate attentiveness
and allowing the experience to be what it is
as best we can
not trying to force it to be different
not pushing it away or pulling it in
but allowing the experience to be what it is
it's likely the experience of the body includes the experience of
breathing
feeling this stretching at the end breath
on the release of the stretch with the out breath
again with this kind and delicate attention
noticing the transitions between in-breaths and out breaths
inhales and exhales
letting experiences come and go
arise and disappear
making room for whatever shows up
might be sounds maybe a line Body Sensations
might be thoughts
can we just simply acknowledge the experience
and gently kindly Begin Again
with the sensations of breathing
nothing needs to be a problem
in this spacious awareness
as best we can we acknowledge the experience
and gently begin again with the sensations of breathing
in a relaxed easy manner
foreign
foreign foreign
oh yeah
foreign
foreign foreign
[Music]
good morning good morning again so today I'm continuing on this theme
of these letters a story of letters that
Mara is writing to the leaders of his armies he has 10 armies
and these are set in contemporary times these letters were written from by um
Jean punadamo of the arrow River Forest Hermitage in Northern Ontario Canada
and so they're kind of a Whimsical but they have a little bit of bite also these letters and in particular the
letter I'm going to be talking about today but before I go into that we might just
a reminder who is Mara and Mara is this character that shows up the Buddha to be
when he's sitting underneath the Bodhi Tree and has made this commitment that he's going to become a weakened and
before Awakening he's the Buddha to be is visited by Mara who is accompanied by
10 armies so there's a number of different versions of this story of the
Buddha's Awakening but uh I'm just focusing on this one and this character
Mara and then as I've said before I'd like to emphasize that in this tradition
Mara is not this demon that wants people to go to hell or anything like that
more Mara to encourage complacency
so he doesn't care if we have tons of central Pleasures in fact he would prefer that that we are having such a
fantastic time with our life that we don't even consider practicing to finding a way towards greater freedom
so the story of Mara versus the Buddha is a story of complacency versus
commitment to practice it's not a story of good versus evil
I just want to emphasize that Mara is perfectly happy if we are having a
fantastic life and so we might ask well how can we use
these stories these things that you're sharing Diana what relevance do they have us for our practice there's a
number of them and one is that it can help us recognize our common Humanity
these stories are applicable to all of us and so when we find something that
there's letters and one that I'm about to share is resonates with us we can
recognize oh everybody experiences this it's not just
me and there's a way that there can be this lightning of the load when we realize oh
yeah this is part of the human experience and not only does it maybe lighten our
load it also helps us to have compassion for others recognize or yeah others have
these same difficulties too and they may be showing up in a particular way because they're
experiencing these difficulties okay so with that as an introduction to
these letters today I'd like to talk about this letter that Mara is writing
to one of his armies the armies of cowardice
and this one has a little bit of a um I don't know a little bite to it at
least it did for me when I was reading this and so I'm again I'm excerpting this um
has written the letters are longer but I'm just excerpting there them for this so here's Mara writing to the leader of
the army of cowardice okay my sixth Army you have a special place
in the task of keeping beings in a state of bondage you weaken the beings whom
you attack and render them vulnerable to my terrible aspect
I prefer to charm and Delight but I will tolerate No opposition and those few who
fail to be seduced by my charm must be terrorized into submission
physical cowardice is useful in its place but it is the spiritual and moral
type of characters that is the most suitable for our purposes beans must be
cajoled into clutching at a sense of security
this is the trick we must play of course you and I know there's no
security in this realm and all beings are subject to this awful realities of
birth sickness old age and death but no matter the dream of security is a hopeless one
but it is powerful beans everywhere are afraid to ask to
I'm sorry are afraid to risk what they have and can be seduced to this spiritual impotence by that fear
so encourage beings often not to take risks
because if they risk they may grow and if they grow they may awaken and then
they will be out of their clutches to be sure it takes great courage to
plunge into the emptiness and this we can undermine this is after all the golden age of
cowardice we can make we can encourage them to
make a virtue of their cavities call it Prudence call it responsibility
and with that they will get up every morning put on their hats and take this
Subway to their dull grind of a job and carefully plan for their retirement and
by that time they will be so beaten down that they will slide easily and
thoughtlessly the rest of the way to the Grave while never escaping our clutches
to reading this it kind of feels uh it's very uncomfortable to read this at least it is for me
this idea that golden age of characters and that we have to take risks
and this letter to the army of cowardice is pointing to how this we need some
courage we need some courage in our lives and some courage on our practice
we might say courage is this capacity to face fear because it's true that as long as beings
have something to lose as long as we are exposed to risk and
uncertainty that fear is a part of The Human Experience there's no getting away
from it and even though we long for this security this wish to not have any fear
the truth is that humans are vulnerable and so we will always have a little bit
of fear this is sometimes a really difficult pill to swallow but there's also a way
in which it's helpful to align with the reality of what it means to be a human
and so this stereotypical idea of Courage is this hero who stands up to
this beast and we might even say that we have this in this story of the Buddha
standing up tomorrow who has these 10 armies and some versions of this story
have these armies as 10 different types of bees so the mara didn't want Buddha
to awaken so he brought his army to attack him but that Buddha stayed
and practiced and became awakened despite these threats and despite the
attacks and we can't you so again
I don't want to like wash over this idea that humans you know that don't have any
fear and we shouldn't instead we need a little bit of Courage because no matter how confident or Brave we are or how
many advantages we might have risk is in the essential component of our life as
we know it and we're all aware of this accident disease embarrassment
humiliation loss failure not to mention old age sickness and death
but maybe I'd like to add on to this also that there's this courage that we need to grow
sometimes this courage to expand this courage to change to feel Joy
to experience the beauty to love the world to love ourselves
in spite of all the ways our lives are endangered
spite of all the risks um in this human existence brings to us
some everyday courage is needed not
ation right one of the core teachings is about the truth of suffering and to part the
first Noble Truth right there is suffering and it takes some courage to recognize this suffering
obvious suffering the way that our lives are at risk in our experiences are
ever changing and can't be reliable but also the really subtle suffering
a subtle unreliabilities subtle ways in which we're really want
something to be completely stable where we can finally relax
like oh okay I made it but this subtle suffering and maybe it's
not so subtle sometimes this way question oh we can't have like this spiritual
retirement so it takes courage to do something
other than this habitual way of Turning Away From The Suffering but to acknowledge it and to treat ourselves
with kindness and care and to bring our wisdom to the way that
we work with this suffering and work with the difficulties but in a way that's appropriate for us to turn
towards them and to not turn away
which we so often do I know I do
so this courage to be with the suffering and so how do we develop this courage
well we often come to meditation practice thinking that it will lessen the
difficulties that we have and that will gain some wisdom and gain some new understandings and maybe we'll even have
some cool meditative experiences but for all the reasons that we choose
to meditate practicing with courage is probably not something that was on the
top of our list and yet practicing with courage is a big part of
this practice maybe sometimes it's under the radar but
it is what's happening the courage to face things about ourselves
but maybe we don't want to face very difficult
the courage to face things one more time that we've seen countless times before
but to look again and
and then Buddhist texts don't really have anything specific to help us with courage but there is a connection
between courage and Trust
so is there a way in which we can connect with something bigger than
ourselves taking the refuges doing meta practice
doing any devotional practices that feels comfortable for you
and then maybe I'll end with something that brene brown writes in her book the
gifts of imperfection brene Brown writes courage is a habit
you get it by doing courageous X it's like you learn to swim by swimming
you learn courage couraging
and so with that I leave you with this letter from Mara to his army of
cowardice an encouragement encouragement for us to find the courage
in a way that's appropriate for us honoring and respecting our experience
honoring and respecting where we are in our life trajectory and our life story
we don't have to jump into the most difficult but is there a way that we can meet
some of the difficulties as best we can
you learn Courage by encouraging
thank you