greetings everyone I'm happy to be with you this week
and um I should probably tell you that I'm
speaking to you from a remote part of the south of France and the the
um internet is not perfect I think the sound should be okay but you
might find the video uh choppy at times
and I'd like to thank uh sveta and Julie for taking care of the tech side
so in Gill's teachings last week he put a lot of emphasis on quieting discursive
thinking and my aspiration for this week is to
give you some tools for calming letting go of the
self-preoccupation that often is behind discursive thinking
so we have to begin by befriending ourselves
and take a posture that expresses your aspiration
for your practice
and settling into the body
and offering your body your heartfelt friendliness
this is how it is
we try to assume a posture that is both settled
and relaxed and also energetic
so inviting the energy of the earth we've gone into you
through the base of the spine and moving upwards
through the back and exiting the body through the crown
of the head
so the invitation is that we take in the Earth's energy from Below
and release it above
and now we invite the clear open energy of the sky
we come down through you from the head
down through the Torso in the legs
and out through the feet bringing the energy from the sky
through you and returning it to the Earth
so that the body here in meditation is settled
but also a channel for the flow of energy
now the invitation is to light a little flame of
friendliness meta benevolence in your heart
and let it warm and protect you
so Breathe Into Your Heart and see if you can connect with
a little flame of loving kindness
it protects and comforts you
and now opening the edges of your body
the edges of your heart see if you can radiate
your unconditional friendliness to all beings everywhere
radiating meta to the front
to the right to the back
it's a left above and below
in the context of benevolent awareness
reheating outward the invitation now is to
come inside and connect with the breathing
you may want to imagine an oval
of the breath
so on the inhale a wave of breath coming up the back
and then when it reaches the crown of the head a little pause
and then a wave of breath cascading down on the front
of the Torso
moving up the back on the in-breath
tasting the Stillness for just a moment
and exhaling downwards on the out breath
in the front
see if you can experience the breathing as waves
waves rising up and then falling back down again
with the ball is at the bottom as well
the invitation is to connect with the flow of the breath
breathing in breathing out
is constantly changing
Anita
one continuous flow
then I'll see if you can stay the flow of the breath
reeling out with constantly changing
yielding a flow of the breath see if you can sense
it's in constancy always changing
and then if you can inhabit
the change
going in going out
if you haven't already love the eyes you can do so now
and let the process of breathing convince you
in a peaceful way of the ever-changing nature
of our experience
staying with the phloem of the breath
then when you
when you see your thoughts arise
take a moment to appreciate how unsubstantial they are
they have no substance
and rather than choosing to follow your thoughts you can choose instead A Quiet Mind
a peaceful mind
your mind free of the preoccupations of Me Myself and mine
just present open
receptive and available
or the experience of breathing
or the experience of being you of being alive
your thoughts are not you
that his thoughts should arise instead of going back to the breath
right away recognize
I will insubstantial they are
flimsy fleeting
no substance Just Thoughts
and recognize also a believing in our thoughts
is a path to bondage
whereas the path to Freedom is seeing through
their unsubstantial nature
and then the tendency of the mind can naturally want to come
for peace to being settled
and one's direct experience unencumbered
by thoughts
and in those moments where the mind
is empty of thoughts see if you can feel and appreciate
the peacefulness the wholesomeness
on a quiet mind
I mean
a mind that is not succeeding
on thinking
and abide in the peacefulness
of emptiness
and to end this sitting we open our circle of friendliness
to all beings or care
or benevolence we offer to all beings
may all beings everywhere be safe and protect it
being safe may all beings including ourselves
be contented at ease
may we all abide in peace
and may all beings everywhere be free
and with this bowel I join my hands
and bow to you all to end this meditation
about your practice and your sincerity thank you
greetings everyone I'm delighted to be here with you this
week um and I should say that I I'm not able
to see the chat uh today in the YouTube but I do very much value your feedback
and um I will download it and read it
as soon as the teachings are finished so thank you for that
and I would also like to announce that um we'll have a q a session at the end of
the week on Friday following the talk
so in Gil's meditation meditations and talks this last week he's put a lot of
emphasis on quieting our discursive thinking
as a way of connecting with a deeper Wellspring
within us you may have noticed that this is easier
said than done and my aspiration for this week
is to give you some tools for calming
and letting go of this self-preoccupation that is the motor
of our discursive thinking Me Myself and mine
and the theme for this week is training and emptiness
so normally training and Emptiness is for a very Advanced stages of practice
and deep concentration but what I'm going to try to do is to find
some ways of giving you aspects of emptiness that you
can use uh in your everyday life and in your meditation
whether you're a beginner a middling practitioner or an advanced
practitioner
so it's in our DNA um they want to protect ourselves
they want to exist to survive
and so our natural habitual tendency is
to be very reactive something comes up and and we react
and often um with some clinging to
um either wanting more of it or wanting less of it or
not even knowing what's what's going on and being confused
and it's our clinging that is the source
of all of our mental constructions the word in Pali is Sankara which
literally means constructing together
so what we do without any training is to
fabricate a sort of amalgam of our inner experience and outer experience
we're constructing the way we think things are and
this constructing uh as its most
um I guess uh dangerous aspect in that uh
the the construction of all construction was is
clinging hanging around wanting to be
uh and when we really understand that
everything is constantly changing we see things all things including
ourselves as inconstant
we we understand that the mind uh habitually fabricates
uh this continuous process of constructing and reconstructing our
experience in the form of these mental constructs
thoughts um but we could go Gil gave a lovely
talk on the Chana suta in which uh an elder monk named Chana
who was uh had been very very caught for
a long long time by conceit
uh he had he had been the Buddhist charioteer and I felt that he had a he
knew he had a special connection to the Buddha probably grew up together
and somehow in his mind this this was good enough
and so he plateaued for decades
until finally um he was able to realize
with um rather Stern the encouragement from the Buddha
that he was not on the right track and he was
not able to see the dumb mouth the Dharma
and so uh there wasn't him a
sincere desire for Liberation and
he thought he would go to visit uh Parable Ananda because Anonymous someone
that he could really trust and so he did that and Ananda was
delighted to see that at last he was asking questions he wasn't the
know-it-all that he had always been and so when Shawna asked Ananda to
please give him a talk so that he could see the reality of the demo
uh Ananda was happy to do so and he began by reassuring Channel
that he was able to see the dhamma he had he had what it takes
and with that China was um joyful and delighted and hopeful and
that was that was that the fact that Ananda believed in him was
the real turning point in China being able to open his heart
to the teachings
so um
believing in someone is a great gift that you can give them
and it can be transformative so
um I'll reach you a summary of what Ananda fought Shana
you're helping understand and really penetrate really see the dumb
and he's reciting a discourse that the Buddha had given to another Monk named John
mostly this world is attached flinging fixated and in bondage
but if one does not attach or cling to mental constructions such as
this is myself then one will clearly see dukka
suffering when it arises and when Duca ceases
that person will clearly see it ceasing
and with this one's knowledge is independent of others
this is right for you
so the key to understanding
everything about the dhamma is seeing through the mental Construction
of this is myself
of course you know we we know from the teachings of in constancy Anita
that everything is constantly changing and
we know also in modern physics that what we think of as
solid you know like the table uh here
um okay it's it's solid wood but it is 99.999999 empty
um there's a nucleus in the atoms and electrons whirling
around the nucleus and mostly it's just space
so in the same way uh our minds are
um basically empty
in our original nature
so perhaps the most important Insight that we can have
to benefit our practice is that everything is empty of itself
we're empty of a self everyone in our family our friends our
community all of us are habitually
putting this self forward all the time selfing and being attached to oneself
and yet this idea of itself is just a mental
Construction a Sankara
so um
so Buddhist practice can be seen as emptying ourselves
of all the projections and constructs and attachments
that we overlay onto our experience we do this all the time
this is what the untrained person does
and as I said before is it's in our DNA to be reactive
so it's um and being a very liberating idea to
embrace the idea of the emptiness of yourself
so I'll read to you now um AR Norman's translation from the
delapada 93
those who have extinguished becoming who do not depend on the future
whose range is empty silence and secluded
their path is hard to track like that of birds
in the sky
so when we go camping most of us
write a practice leave no track and we can try the same thing when we
aspire to emptying ourselves of clinging
of attachment or greed hate and delusion
end of selfie
when we see thinking arising during meditation
we can imagine stepping out of a cage of our belief in Me Myself and mine
and then being able to leave more tracks
we can do the same thing uh when we're talking with friends
stepping out of the cage of Me Myself and mine we've become
a much better listener and we're in a great position to
be of benefit to serve our friends and their
development and aspiration for happiness
of the same thing is true at work if we
remember that being caught up in our own ideas of how things should be
we can be a much better team player and work in collaboration instead of in
competition so
knowing um that living beings don't have substance
and permanent selves doesn't mean that we don't exist
and we can imagine the mind as water they're pure water
and all of our references to self as the sediments
that make the water that we're swimming in muddy
so we can train the mind by emptying it of the constraints of our
mental constructs wrapped around the idea of self
and our reactivity and gently slide into the wholesome
clear water from a mind that's temporarily empty
with suffering and farting and enjoyed the flow of the water
thank you very much for your attention
I wish you well in the sky of emptiness