Hello friends hello and welcome to happy hour hi and if the audio is okay I already see
Neil's getting me a thumbs up already love it
audio's good love it so uh my name is Nikki I'm in Mountain View
California unseated oh Looney land and uh as we always do I invite you to warm
up the space by saying hello with your greetings so who wants to take it away
let's just start
hey this is uh don from DC hi Don foreign
Belmont California hi Padma this is Bill in Dallas hi Bill
y Santa Cruz hi Leslie in Santa Cruz and Neil in New Hampshire
and hi Fred in Oakland and Linnea says sends warm hugs from Spokane Washington
on YouTube from Austin Texas hi June
hi I'm Sabrina from Redwood City California hi Sabrina
hello kittycon from Thailand hi greetings what time is it in Thailand if
you would put it in chat hello here from San Diego
I am Stephanie from Los Angeles hi Stephanie
and hi Carrie from Prague oh it's I think two or three a.m there beautiful
we are definitely International this evening this morning this middle of the night whatever your time zone is in
haibu Paul from Sunnyvale no longer in Hyderabad India but from
Sunnyvale again hi everyone okay let's let's begin let's formally begin
thank you Neil for posting information about happy hour groups and 9 A.M in
Thailand beautiful good morning to you kiddacon so so at this time I changed the setting so
that unmuting won't be possible excuse me
and I uh changed the chat settings uh the chat will only come to me instead of
everyone but I request that we keep the channel quiet because they can be quite distracted to receive chats when I'm
teaching and last but not least I'm going to turn on recording
for the sake of Audio Dharma here we go great okay so hello and and welcome a
warm warm welcome dear Sangha
so let's dive into practicing together and I will
introduce the theme for this evening during the meditation
as I sometimes do just to mix it up so so let's begin
let's arrive let's arrive in our bodies
ah arriving in this body maybe start by three deep diaphragmatic breaths we'll
take a deep breath hold it for a few seconds and then let
out with a sigh let's do it together breathing in into the belly
hold and release
your shoulders come down your whole body release one more
releasing deeply let your breath be received in the belly
third one hold
and release you can do more if you want on your own
time oh I return I return to natural breath
as we do in mindfulness practice letting the breath be natural
after you have settled after you found it
and opening up the body the body especially the lower abdomen
the whole body starting from the lower abdomen to receive the breath to receive the
breath all the sensations whatever is present
opening your heart to whatever is present foreign
settling arriving
foreign
the question can I be content right here in this moment just taking Refuge with
the breath in this moment Solitude and silence can there be contentment can I meet it
and I stop running needing more seeking
becoming Just In This Moment can I try it out
and if the answer comes back now can I be content with the resistance can I
embrace that can I hug the resistance with kindness
and warmth if there is any and if not
can I make space for myself to just be
rest
can I put down planning wanting needing becoming foreign
I can always pick it up later right now can I experiment
with releasing into peace into just this
radical acceptance
foreign
has picked up something else I thought I'd plan
and becoming it's okay totally fine can you be kind
with this wanting mind oh dear sweet wanting mind
says your habit isn't it it's okay all right
and we let go sweetie can we let go for just this moment
I was putting it down just being with the breath making Refuge
being enough whatever has happened or not happened
to be enough
Just In This Moment see what it's like
breathing with being enough contentment is kindness
foreign
let go of thinking becoming wanting Just In This Moment
make peace with the contentment of just being here being breathed
this moment in time everything that has led to this
embracing a bounty
the enoughness the plenitude plenty of this moment
are just enough it's more than enough it's abundant
and so many ways
can we turn to that not turn to the lack
What's missing yes we can turn to plenty that's missing
or should or could but can we turn choose to turn to the abundance
are they enough this
thank you foreign
rest this is enough
rest
breathing in breathing out
foreign
foreign you be kind to the mind to the heart
that wants to plan wants to remember all of that and
it's okay and you're reminded that it is enough in this moment to just
be gently kindly lovingly remind
the puppy of the Mind a heart and it's enough In This Moment
there's abundance right here it can rest
and be nourished
nourished with their breath with the entirety of the in-breath
entirety of the out breath just this one breath and then again this one breath
just one breath at a time be nourished by it
not planning for five or ten breaths no just this one and then Begin Again
foreign
as we turn to bring this meditation to her clothes
and we embrace and be content with whatever
this period of practice was like whether there was
contentment or not maybe a whiff of it or maybe not the
mind was wondering wanting this and that can we be content with that as a radical Act of contentment In This
Moment this practice showed up for me exactly
as it needed to In This Moment In Time given all the causes and conditions can I accept that
can I release into peace with contentment yes
and trusting that there is goodness here co-created through our practice our engagement our
effort and sharing this goodness offering it freely
for all beings everywhere including ourselves may all beings everywhere no
the taste of contentment ease goodness not as a way to resign it's not a
resignation but as a stepping stone for growth
may all our Collective practice be of service to all beings everywhere
may all beings be well may all beings be free including
ourselves
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so so a couple of words
one is in societies and cultures where there's always one thing more and more
and more and more and more practicing with exploring contentment is
a radical act it feels quite radical sometimes even unfamiliar feels like
resignation and it's not it's not resignation it's a way of
accepting contentment turning towards what is enough what is good and oh yes
it doesn't mean we don't engage with with growth we don't engage with the
practice we don't engage with cultivate and continue to cultivate wisdom compassion our hearts our minds
it doesn't mean that we say oh it's I'm content with just what is it doesn't mean that but there is a level of of
contentment that's needed with what is so that we don't become a Hungry Ghost and there is this um the story of in
Buddhism there are these creatures on on one of the hell realm levels
they have a very very long neck and it's a very narrow narrow long neck
and also a very narrow small mouth and they have a huge stomach
and they're called the realm of the hungry ghosts they're always hungry they cannot get enough to eat they're never
satiated uh they're they have a huge stomach so they're hungry they want more
and more and more but but their necks are very tight their mouths are very small so the realm of the Hungry Ghost is a
pretty tough one and and whether we believe in the Buddhist cosmology we can actually see it as as
in this world sometimes we become a Hungry Ghost we want more more more more more this more of that thing more that
so we we are in this realm of suffering of more and more more so turning turning
towards contentment to release that hungry ghost-ness
and again just to repeat myself one more time it doesn't mean that we don't engage we don't
we're resigned it doesn't mean that we give up we continue to to cultivate a
practice but if you explored it tonight the sense of exploring contentment it gives rise to a
release it's letting go like ah okay sense of stability and then actually the
mind the heart can be more available more ready more open to uh to engage in
a different way not in a hungry way not in a graspy way want this plan this remember this it's kind of an open it's
a different way of being anywhere so for tonight's um
inquiry together the question that I'd like to invite you
to explore is how do I ex how do I
um experience how do I experience contentment In This Moment how do I
experience it and we'll go around and each person will say just one word or a
phrase maybe I experience it as release I experience it as freedom I express it
as ah my breath feels more free and then the next person offers something the
next person you can also say pass and just hold witness compassionate witness kind
witness to everyone you don't have to speak um but let's explore maybe a couple of
rounds and then you can open it up for exploring reflecting together and
remember you're just sharing for me your own experience you don't ask other people's experience even if what they
say you don't understand it all you don't explore you don't like ask them
just just offer from yourself and and receive whatever is offered in the space
with contentment so not directing the space
so so again the question that uh the inquiry question is how do you
experience contentment in your body in your mind in your heart how do you
experience contentment how is it experienced for you okay
all right I'm creating the rooms the breakout rooms be kind to yourself
be kind to each other here we go
foreign
s are close now and everybody's back welcome
back everyone welcome back so and we have some time for Reflections for
observations aha moments challenges questions and especially if you haven't uh spoken
for a while in the big group would love to invite you to move forward for the
benefit of yourself and others what did you notice with this practice both with
the sharing and the guided meditation Gene
yes it was more of a question Nikki that came up and just it prompted in my small
group of just the idea that is contentment a synonym or involved
with acceptance surrender and love even
just wondered what you might think of that yeah yeah thanks Jane interesting
um it's it has a contentment is definitely
um you know I think of a Venn diagram with circles and and it's not exactly the same as the ones that you named but
there is some overlap there is some overlap with acceptance but it's not exactly that it has more nourishing
quality to it there's more an uplift there's more of a sweetness to it um and and it's not exactly synonymous
with love though there is this aspect of contentment feels no feels loving feels
kind but it it's so so I I think it's
it's fun it's it's it's such a I'm so glad you brought that up because it's it's um
it's a lovely curiosity to explore um what's these different beautiful hard
qualities they're all they're all a little different and similar and and I share this because um in the way that uh
when I was practicing with my Burmese teacher punks I had a um years ago and there were these very
very nuanced uh states of mind that he would have me explore and look at and
just really really feel and uh feel into what they were like and at the
first you know at first you're like oh this is like that but then you really feel into it or you explore it you're
curious like oh yeah this this feels different and qualitatively different so
I so with the question that you raised Gina I invite you to be curious about the similarities and and nuanced
differences between all of that how does that sound thank you Nikki that sounds good yeah I
appreciate this practice yeah thank you thanks for that question Charles Lee please
oh yeah thank you thank you I missed uh meditation practice but I did uh was
here in time for our small groups and uh had a wonderful uh content
experience so very recursive uh and uh
I guess what came up for me is just uh kind of yeah that feeling of warmth
but also an idea that you know contentment is is
always available I think prior to my practice of Buddhism uh I kind of you know maybe accidentally
ran into contentment you know every so often but I had no idea that
there were ways to to [Music]
bring about contentment um you know in in in some ways almost that
almost at will um and uh and and so so it's just been you know
it's just been so wonderful to you know to be able to do that and then uh one of
uh the people in my group had mentioned that contentment was like a
like a home and uh you know I I thought you know is it another or is it is it a type of Brahma vahara
you mentioned you know love and kindness and mind States and so
um it gave me a lot to think about but uh yeah contentment um kind of the Buddhist Joy
um it's not you know fireworks it's not you know this you know
very like you know super sense pleasured place but
but gosh it feels you know it just feels so easy yeah yeah see beautiful thank you so
much for these Reflections Charlie just just a beautiful
um so many important points you raised one of them being that um it's available
it's here it's always available and and
there's something about the Buddhist practice about the beauty of the beauty of this practice that lets us appreciate
that it doesn't doesn't mean that all conditions have to be perfect you know this and that and relationship and
finances at the moment it doesn't have to be per Perfection you know there's
this sense that an ordinary mind has that oh yes I'll be happy I will be
content when X and wines even well be in the perfect relationship yeah that's when I'll be content when I get my
degree or all of that and yet there's obvious contentment it's just this this
beautiful soft easy as you said and and also it real as you were talking also
realize it in addition to what Jane was the beautiful states of mind it also
relates to Equanimity there's a sense of equanimity resting in this oh yeah spaciousness of the heart and mind and
um yeah thank you beautiful wise Reflections charisley and and I smiled
when you when you said in the group it was it was lovely and it was recursive you said Rick Rick are you a computer
scientist that's the recursion I was just delighting I haven't heard recursion in this context
oh sorry dropped my device uh I'm a neuroscientist that was my degree in
college so not as smart as a neural as a computer scientist because recursion is
a particular term I I thought all the Nerds on this call would probably I've seen Neil who I know is also fell and I
was like oh yeah recursion but anyway just uh enter a joke of a particular way
an algorithm is is is is coded it's kind of recursive but anyway thanks for bringing that in Charles Lee that that
that brought a smile to my heart that was fun
great thank you [Music] um bill says this was educational I don't
remember ever seeing the Mind still hungry and to then realize that it is the normal State of Mind Of My Mind 99.9
of the time can we do more of this yes and somebody hearted that request yes we
can do more this was such a fun exploration thank you all and Serena says I don't think any path
owns contentment everyone human can be capable of contentment even with the
people who don't follow a particular path oh of course yeah contentment is
part of the human you know all the range of emotions are part of the range of uh
our human [Music] capacity I think what what I was saying
and and agreeing with Charlie is that many of us don't realize that it's available to us we're all we if we don't
have a training and it could be any kind of training Buddhist training uh Christian any kind of training that
points to to or or stoic training I don't know there's so many philosophies
points to contentment if we don't have a training we're usually stuck in in
negative states of mind and so so for me
also this practice really supported me to to get in touch with contentment so
so thank you all I feel full and delighted and happy and content with
with our practice this evening it's so much joy so much joy as we come together
and practice so thank you all thank you for showing up cultivating your heart
and mind exploring Equanimity exploring
contentment for benefit of yourself and in service of all beings everywhere may
we all know contentment may we all be free
[Music] thanks everyone take good care
and