okay we'll get started here so I'm continuing on this uh theme of
The Poetry and practice and part of the power of poetry is that
it lets us see things in a different way maybe it's like pointing to things
differently Maybe by using some metaphor or maybe just using a different language
something different than the usual way that we consider things and sometimes
this perspective is surprising like oh yeah I hadn't thought of it uh this way
and maybe there's a little bit of humor to it or maybe there's a little surprise
or maybe there's even a little like oh yeah something that doesn't feel so
comfortable that when we recognize some of the maybe the deeper elements that
are getting pointed to and we recognize oh maybe I've just been on the surface but there's something deeper there too
so there's so many different ways in which another perspective might show up
and poetry helps us I would say and that's part of its power
is to see things from a different perspective it helps us not
see things or view things or consider things in the usual way
so today during as I've been doing in the preceding weeks I'll drop in a poem
during the guided meditation and I'll unpack the poem and talk about it and
some of the themes and maybe even share some additional poems after the guided
meditation Okay so with that as an introduction
we'll take a meditation posture
and taking a moment to settle in
taking a moment to tune into this experience
of beginning a meditation session
I like to begin by noticing the experience of
being in this particular configuration
might include one's environment what room you're in what location you're in
noticing the sounds
the temperature
and then noticing the bodily experience of this particular configuration
what is it like at this moment to be here
and now
it's made me feeling the sensations and the feet and legs where you're connected touching feeling
the pressure of whatever it is that you're sitting on
and feeling this support that it provides
the grounding
feeling the sensations on the buttocks as there's this pressure
and support we're grounded connected we're here
if you're leaning against a chair or couch or
whatever it might be feeling the pressure against the back
and if you're sitting upright feeling the uprightness feeling that support of
the spine as it allows the
shoulders and arms just hang
I often at the beginning will just tuck ever so slightly the chin and
maybe push the chin back as a way to have that Be steady and open
up this tiny little space in the back of the neck this is a very subtle slight movement
might not even be noticeable if somebody were watching you
and in the shoulders be far away from the ears
tuning into the Sensations around the face
sometimes there can be some tightness there
some tension can we allow it to relax
and then allowing the attention to rest on the sensations of
breathing
noticing that that body knows how to breathe it's just this natural movement
associated with breathing
noticing the experience of inhales
and exhales
how are they different can you feel into that answer
rather than thinking or figuring it out just notice the feelings of inhales and
exhales
the sensations the experience
and as the mind wanders it doesn't have to be a problem
it's just the next thing that's happening let me very simply gently
begin again with the sensations of breathing
what would it be like to practice with a sense of openness
open to what the experience might be
rather than having any particular expectations
open curious what is this like
foreign
very short there's
absolutely nothing you need to do with this poem
you don't have to figure it out
just allow it to land into your experience
the poem goes like this
another day walking in circles with an empty bowl
leaning on my staff in the middle of the road my whole body shaking with hunger
what little strength I had left left me
as I was falling to the ground I saw
I was the Spoonful of rice and this whole world
the bowl you can't miss even if you try
I'll repeat it
another day walking in circles with an empty bowl
leaning on my staff in the middle of the road
my whole body shaking with hunger
what little strength I had left left me
as I was falling to the ground I saw
I was the Spoonful of rice and this whole world
the bowl you can't miss
even if you try
foreign
[Music]
[Music] welcome to uh this morning's
short little talk
so again I'm continuing with this theme of poetry I've practiced and this poem
includes a surprise I can maybe I'll even just say the
biggest shifts in practice are a surprise it's not like there's a certain like we
can see a big shift uh coming and then we just inch up upon it and then we know
like okay the next moment something big is going to happen or a shift is going to happen it doesn't happen that way
and all of us know this right with those of us who have a meditation practice it's often when there's
um like maybe drop into a little deeper level or gaining an Insight there's
always an element of surprise to that that's just the way the practice is it's
not like we could exactly see like oh okay as soon as I meditate for 12 and a half minutes longer something is going
to happen but there's a way in which we're always like stealing ourselves or embracing
ourselves against surprises so one way that sometimes I think about
practice is that this idea of um going up a
children's slide you know a little playgrounds they have these slides and that it takes some effort they have to
like walk up to the top of the slide and that's some effort but then you get to
the top and you go went off you go like down the slide
and so it's not like there's always a complete letting go and it's not like there's always just effort
and the difference uh between this uh metaphor this analogy that I'm making up an actual practice is of course that we
don't really know when we're at the top of the slide and the sliding down is
about to happen so I'll read this poem the same poem
that I dropped into the guided meditation and uh maybe I'll unpack it a
little bit and we'll see how this is so the poem goes like this
another day walking in circles with an empty bowl
meaning on my staff in the middle of the road my whole body shaking with hunger
what little strength I had left left me
as I was falling to the ground I saw
I was the Spoonful of rice and this whole world the bowl
you can't miss even if you try
so there's lots of different ways we might interpret this poem and I'm offering you some thoughts right this is
just one person's ideas I certainly don't want to sit here and say this is the authoritative way I'm just offering
some food for thought some things to consider but maybe you have your own
interpretation maybe there's a way in which your life experience your practice
would point to a different interpretation and for me this is part of what I love
about poetry is that there doesn't have to be one way
we're not necessarily sure exactly what the poet is pointing to and maybe it
lands differently for all of us and so for me poetry is like an invitation for
us to explore for ourselves okay so this poem The Poet writes
another day walking in circles with an empty bowl
so as I pointed out a few days ago in this poem this idea of like walking in circles is this idea of like I'm not
getting anywhere I just there's maybe some movement happening but there's no sense of
going anywhere so this feeling of stuckness
we might even imagine that this uh the person in the poem is on an Ohm's
round right they uh might be a nun in our monastic who is you know that this is
what they would do they'd have like with their own spools and girlfriend Ohm's rounds to see if somebody would put
something a meal for them to eat in their own spool so I like that this idea another day so
this isn't the first time it has happened so even though it's happened before the
first time it happened she didn't completely give up like okay I'm still gonna do this it's
kind of like still persevering even though there's this feeling of stuckness or not getting what she wanted
so this empty bowl I would say is like pointing to this sense of lack
this sense of insufficiency this sense of needing more
and maybe for those of us who don't go into arms rounds we might uh I have it think it's
pointing to the sense of seeking yeah I I gotta find something
it's something's not quite right I need more I need something in order to feel
full in order to feel complete and I think for many of us we come to a
spiritual practice because there is this sense of lack and there's then spiritual practice
becomes this really strong sense of seeking seeking seeking
so the next lines leaning on my staff in the middle of the road my whole body
shaking with hunger kind of like this idea of like leaning
on a stuff using a cane recognizing that we need support but
that not letting that stop us so maybe we can't walk as easily as we once could
but that doesn't mean that we completely stopped walking person in this poem is just using the
support that's needed it you know sounds like a very skillful wise thing to do
and then the problem is saying in the middle of the road so I haven't arrived at her destination but not quite where
she started and maybe not quite where she's going so maybe she's in the Miss
mix in the midst of crossing over the flood some of you know this expression
that's common in Buddhist teachings of like how to cross over the flood like how to get to the other Shore
so the poet here rather than using this analogy of crossing the river maybe he's
just crossing a road and she is in the midst of Crossing not quite there yet
but maybe it didn't even recognize not quite there yet
shaking with hunger yeah right feeling this sense of lack
thoroughly it's uncomfortable
we do not want to feel this nobody wants to feel this but maybe there's a way in which where
there's no longer possible to stop feeling it it becomes like the most
dominant experience this real sense of I want something different
and maybe there's a sense of possibility that there can be something different
and and a poem that I wrote another day and that earlier day in this series there's a sense of trembling like
feeling it all through the body and it's a physical visceral experience
so it's not so much thoughts and so here that same idea of getting expressed
through shaking with Hunger here's like you know really feeling thoroughly that there's
something here that's not quite right and that and this wish for it to be
right and then a surprise happens
kind of just letting go when letting us feel exactly what we don't want to feel none of us want to feel this
shaking with Hunger or this trembling or this sense of lack and maybe there's a
way that we've been bracing ourselves maybe we've been using this cane this
stuff as a way to support ourselves and bolster ourselves to make sure we never
feel it but then whatever strength she had left
left her so no longer being supported by what
once was supporting and it's true that some of us come to this spiritual practice because what was
supporting us is no longer available I have a terrible diagnosis or a loved one
dies or this like an unexpected change in our life circumstances ending of
relationships children leaving for college whatever it might be
is what we were using to support us and maybe Define us is no longer there
and then the next line in this poem as I was falling to the ground I saw
this radical letting go not the usual way not walking not
upright not sitting falling to the ground so this literal different perspective is
what's being the poet is talking about here literally ladies were falling we see things differently
and it it's certainly disorienting and frightening this is exactly what we don't want and
it's a surprise we don't see it coming but this seeing
that happens with this big different perspective with this big shift
and it's often people report a big shift in their
practice these big shifts that happen with practice some people will say this
is like life-changing is when there's a shift in perspective
so for some people it's literally like going from sitting meditation to a walking meditation I know I've had some
big shifts when just something is simple like that or maybe this shift in like just
drinking a cup of tea this this moment of something different
so it doesn't have to be as radical as falling to the ground but sometimes it feels like that like like what we're
used to just the rug gets pulled out from underneath us
and it's only under those circumstances where we can see this different perspective
so this person says I was the Spoonful of rice
she was what she was looking for
she had been outside of herself looking for something looking in this case right
maybe on Ohm's round literally but figuratively how often are
we looking outside for the world to give us to satisfy this sense of lack
she discovers oh I was the Spoonful of rice
she was looking for her she was what she was looking for and it's the very Act of seeking that
prevents us from seeing because there's so this seeking has this
momentum to it that doesn't allow us to see
and she also sees this whole world the ball the whole world is like supporting
there's a way in which being held by this bull
sometimes we feel like the world is doing anything but supporting us but what would it be like if we considered
that actually that everything that's happening in our life is to help us become free
is to help us find or so that we no longer have to seek
and maybe we have to stop seeking in order to feel this support
because inherent in seeking is that we have this insufficiency that we can't see or that we don't have what we want
and then the poem ends you can't miss
this encouragement what would it be like to not be seeking
what would you do if you knew you would succeed
what would you try if you knew you couldn't miss
so one more time I'll read this poem
another day walking in circles with an empty bowl
leaning on my staff in the middle of the road my whole body is shaking with
hunger what little strength I had left left me
as I was falling to the ground I saw I was the Spoonful of rice
and this whole world a bowl you can't miss
even if you try to this poem
is by Matty winegast the same poet from the first two days of this week
again it's Matty winegast and he's writing in this book the first free
women so I wish you all the wonderful day
thank you