one of the opportunities and often purposes of Buddhist
Meditation is to settle deeply inside of
oneself become calm and settled in order to understand oneself
better and uh and by understanding oneself better uh being able to let go
of that which doesn't serve us that which gets in the way of further understanding further
Clarity so I offer an analogy that if the kitchen sink the
faucet is on and the kitchen sink is blocked and the water fills and Spills
over onto the kitchen floor and you come home and see the floor
wet and then you run around the house looking for buckets and
sponges and and maybe eventually you find them and you start mopping up the floor and mopping up the floor and
emptying the water and mopping up the floor and after a long time of doing
that you're getting tired of all the soaking up and throwing away it occurs to you how about just turning off the
faucet and uh so that it's that way in our lives sometimes that we can go
around with a lot of challenges of kinds we can go around with a lot of conflict of all
kinds and we might be trying to take care of them and and uh sometimes we do
take care of them and it's important to care for a lot of things but the opportunity in
meditation is uh to sit quietly and no longer
objectify our experiences our life our challenges ourselves the world around us
but drop into a deep subjective experience of what's here so we can come to the place and
recognize where the fet is on so we can turn it
off and the more you're preoccupied with something upset about something
concerned about something even thinking about something more you're you're involved in you're
involved in a certain kind of objectification there's the issue there the thing you're thinking
about even if what you're thinking about is something that's present for yourself right now we'll often objectify that
we're thinking about it concerned with it figuring it out analyzing it um and
the opportunity here is sitting quietly is to begin feeling our way into
what's deeper where the faucet in where the energy is coming from where and one of
those things is tension one of the simple ways of where's the tension where's the the stress where's
the uh agitation because that the energy of
agitation the running water of agitation the running water of tension the running water of stress if if that's still
on it'll produce we we keep getting caught up in this objectification objec
objectif objectifying world of concerns and there's often we don't see
we're so caught up in the concerns we don't see that the faucet is
on but there is a faucet that's giving it energy giving it power giving
it the helping us be attached to it and I'd like to propose for this
sitting that uh uh the faucet that's on
the running water that's uh flooding the kitchen floor is
um discovered through T the its tension the agitation the
stress the constriction that we find in our body and mind and if you find that see if you can
relax it see if you can calm
it sof soften it and maybe you can't turn off the faucet but maybe you can um
slow down the flow decrease it AIT little bit so to assume a meditation
posture and being reminded that it's a posture with which we are going to
really show up in our body here and now for our present moment
experience so a posture that is almost
like taking a stand yes this is where I
am this is where my attention will be here and now
not denying anything but here to
see how everything manifests as present moment
experience that the direct experiences Here and
Now gently close your
eyes and just to the extent that's
comfortable for you take some deeper breaths longer
inhales and on the exhale relax the
body maybe stretching out the exhale a bit
so there can be more time to soften let
go
release and then letting your breath breathing return to
normal and continuing on the exhale taking time to relax the muscles of the
face there's a way as we relax the muscles of the face we sense the sensations of the face
more
fully maybe extending the exhale a little
bit to see if there's a little additional relaxing of the
face releasing the muscles of the face
and then doing the same for the shoulders on the exhale softening the
shoulders
and relaxing the
belly softening the
belly and for wherever in your belly B you're relaxing see if you can feel or imagine
your yourself deeper into the belly for a deeper
release and then bringing the attention to the area around the heart
and there too gently maybe lovingly on the exhale
relax around the heart
center
maybe a softening throughout the
chest
and then taking some minutes here also to relax in the thinking
mind the muscles in the face the eyes the
forehead associated with
thinking any tightness and pressure agitation in the
mind on the exhale allow it all to
soften
and
finally on the inhale feel some
your own way a global experience of the body and on the
exhale release relax the whole
body
and then settling yourself into the body's experience of
breathing accompanying the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out and if anything troubles
you feel your way into the body mind
heart to where the tension is the stress or the
pressure and see if you can relax it relax the tension the pressure
soften on the
exhale
for
[Music]
e
rather than thinking your thoughts feel the underlying tension or
pressure to think to be
troubled and as you exhale relax the tension and the
pressure wherever it might be gently
slowly
for
[Music] and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to gently almost like writing
outwards on the inhale expansion of the
chest movements of the lungs as you breathe
in in your way feel as widely in your body as you
[Applause] can and on the exhale let
go on the exhale relax the
body on the exhale release any holding that remains in the
body and then like and then let go of even trying to let
go and sit here for a few moments breathing not even meditating just being
present and as we come to the end to turn our gaze outward into the
world from The Mind's Eye
imagination bring in the people in your lives near and
far the people in the world who are suffering
terribly aware of them from a relaxed
state from which maybe we have access to love compassion respect
care no matter how much how challenging it is what we're
considering and from that place of care
wishing well on Others May all
beings be happy may all
beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be
free and may we contribute to the welfare and happiness of the
world from a place within that there is no stress and
tension no agitation
so that how we contribute to the world is through the
medium of being peaceful ourselves may all beings be
[Music] well
thank
you
for
so hello and uh welcome to the second talk on the Buddhist teachings related
to quarrels quarrels disputes and um
the idea that human beings live in conflict with each other was very well recognized by the
Buddha and not only he have a lot to say about it but it could be understood that
the core teachings of the Buddha even the whole purpose of becoming enlightened um is uh has to do with um
creating a world where people are not driven by unethical
behavior that the core teachings of the Buddha are ethical with an ethical goal
a person who is awakened is defined as someone who will not harm anybody at all
including how the n in the way in which we have disagreements with people
certainly we'll have disagreements uh but uh to disagree in
an argumentative way with hostility and anger and and um assert assertions of
power and and um demeaning other people uh is
not uh the direction in which the Dharma teaching Dharma practice the Buddha
taught um he really wants us to take responsibility for our contribution to
suffering in the world and certainly that that's not enough to diminish the suffering in the world just to look at
ourselves but without that without a deep look at ourselves and what's going on with us uh we could actually
inadvertently continue being models and perpetuators of hostility of hate of uh
assertion of power of of um all kinds of ways that uh are continue the endless
cycles of harm that has existed since the time with the Buddha so his teachings on quarrels is
the topic for this week and um and one of the ways
so the primary strength of the Dharma the
Buddha taught is the capacity of this practice for us to really take a deep dive in ourselves and understand
ourselves not to ignore the world but I like to think of it as we Deep dive
inside of ourselves to really see ourselves and and and free ourselves from the inside out turn ourselves
inside out and return to the world with a heightened sensitivity and capacity to
care to love without any hostility without taking on any stress in that
process without any kind of conceit that gets in the way of caring for others and
the world so in one set of teachings about quarrels disputes the Buddha talks about
six Roots um that um uh six roots of of quarreling and
these are the six kind of uh problematic ways in which uh underneath the quarrel
that give that from which we contribute to the quarrel to the argument to the disagreement in an unhealthy
unbeneficial way and so we want to find a way to go under the under the surface
take a go a layer down um and not kind of constantly be involved at the level of the coral and
who said what and what's going on and what I should do and which is living a little bit in an objectified world of
what you the problem but we also want to take time out to really understand what are we
contributing what gasoline are we putting Into the Fire and so one of the
purposes of things like meditation is the introspection to drop a layer at least a layer into our being into our
psychology to see what is the what are we contributing in terms of pressure in
terms of energetics agitation stress uh onto how we contribute to the
quarrel so the Buddha talked about six uh six roots and in fact each when he
talks about them he pairs up there pair so somehow they're considered Maybe
synonyms or close synonyms or part of a family um these six
pairs and uh each of them we can understand to imply that as they settle
maybe they get replaced by their opposite the first uh uh root and the
and WD uses the word root because uh it the reference point is a plant that if
you cut off the plant at the surface um it uh it sprouts again from the roots
and if you really want to uh take get rid of a weed you have to really get down there and pull out the roots so it
doesn't nothing can re uh re resprout so the first of these roots is
uh anger and resentment and um and anger is in the
Buddhist lexicon is maybe not the same as the English word uh the Koda is the
word in po um in involves uh some people in the west want to justify certain
kinds of anger clean white anger or something uh Justified anger but the
anger that Buddhism is uh say is a problem is a poison is anger that in
that has within it hostility has within it hatred so and resentment is also kind
of a kind of a poison that um that uh certainly har harms the person who's
resenting and so these are two Roots the first first root is is anger and
resentment and if these settle down then uh what's possible is
friendliness care uh we can come from a different place we might still disagree but to
disagree in Friendly ways there and if we can't be friend friendly because that's too high a bar to disagree with
care for the welfare of everyone involved what does it take to really engage in disagreement in a productive
way not easy the second route is contempt and
spite to have this attitude towards others who are in disagreement with and
have contempt and Spite and we know that uh there's whole movements and political movements politicians who are demonizing
the opponent and uh kind of contempt in spite uh that it just uh uh putting
gasoline on the fire on the fire of a lot of social political National um
conflicts that exist in our time and uh there's no hope to resolve a a conflict
if there's contempt spite hatred um demonization of the
other and uh and uh so there the alternative is respect to enter into
disagreements with respect for the other even if they don't respect
us the third route is envy and greed and the word for greed
can also mean selfishness so envy and selfishness and um Envy for some people
is a really deep poison that uh it's not an issue for me but I've talked to people and I'm so surprised when I
started talking to people learning from people from which who how toxic it is for some people to live with envy and it
seems to maybe come along with a certain kind of uh um um undermining of One's
Own Integrity or well-being to just kind of be envious of others and what they
have and their situation uh or to be greedy uh selfish to uh want more want
everything and so some of the uh disputes has to do
with we want what they have and they don't want to give it to us or we can't have it the alternative if that settles
if that level of tension within quiets down the alternative is uh the healthy
alternative is generosity uh to want other people to be well to have things give them some of
our things um wish them well then the next route for uh disputes
quarrels is deceit and deceptiveness to uh uh uh so uh to be
trying to deceive people into getting what we want uh to be deceptive in what we say to lie and uh this also is poison
for our society poison for our interpersonal relationships and uh it means that there's no trust there means
that again there's no respect for others uh we're just trying to uh get our our way um without any cost at all the
alternative to that as we relax the inner tensions forces of Deceit and deception is honesty honesty is medicine
honesty is uh the food for health
psychological spiritual health then that spreads and
inspires uh the next one uh the root of uh quarrels is uh evil and wrong View
and what exactly is meant by evil is not so clear but a wickedness just a pure
and simple maybe um tendency some people have just wanting to cause harm uh
without any other reason but to cause harm in some way and uh and wrong view
is the wrong view that doesn't understand the nature of uh what is harmful and what is not harmful
so both of these evil and wrong View and from the Buddhist point of view involve
some kind of tension some kind of contraction some kind of agitation
within just like all the other Roots so as we drop down in our awareness of self
below the level of the coral and really in the subjective subjective level we start discovering these tensions and we
discover what we can relax and if this this one relax evil and wrong e and
wrong view uh there can be greater wisdom and the core wisdom in Buddhism
is the wisdom that uh penetrating wisdom that applies to almost everything is
what what causes harm and what causes welfare real welfare and the f f last root is
attachment to the world just being attached to this life that we're living and uh it can seem like like of course
we should be that way but uh the alternative is to be generous to the
world and um we don't have to be attached to the world to live a full full life in fact I would suggest that a
a world that would not at being attached to anything but being able to give being
able to be um a u generative from what inside out uh is uh is really what is a
kind of fantastic sense of well-being and and freedom um to be attached to the world
means that we are a consumer only holding on and not giving
away so the primary lesson that I'd like to pass on the Buddhist lesson is that
we want to be able to sit quietly enough in some way or other or find a way to be that we can um step below look below the
level upon which the quarrels are going going on the disputes the fights that we have to see what is our contribution
within what's ATT tension pressure what are the roots within us and this list is
a good checklist to see are any of these present and as we find them to really
feel the physical subjective way in which that tension pressure is present
for us the agitation and then learn to relax and maybe it's easier to relax
physically mentally emotionally even than it is to
pull out the root itself initially to stop being envious but we might have
access to relaxing the tension around it so I would propose to you today if you
have any of these things today anger and envy
greed um deceit lie tendency to lie attachments of any kind contempt for
other people that you read about in the news politicians whatever it might be uh stop look below it subjectively is
there any tension and if there is see if you can relax and see what healthy
alternative is possible when you're relax so thank you very much and um look
forward to seeing being with you with you again tomorrow