okay thanks to everyone for checking in it's always nice to
hear where you are and see you there but now we'll go ahead and get started
so settling in for meditation together
you can see in the chat all the folks that are joining us
and just allow yourself to be in the shape that you're in
closing your eyes if that's comfortable
and just softening the body into the meditation posture that you're using
today perhaps feeling the contact of your
seats with the chair or the cushion
or whatever you're lying on or maybe you're standing
just sensing the support beneath you
foreign
slow deep breaths and on the exhale just allowing the body
to settle in a bit more
we're taking in just the sense of the whole body
in whatever posture it's in
and gently softening softening the expression on the base
softening the eyes and the eyes of its
can even soften all the little muscles on the scalp foreign
allowing the shoulders to be soft
letting the shoulder blades slide down the back
checking in Into the Heart area scenting if there's any tension or
tightness ache
if there is that's fine but just inviting a softening
letting the rib cage relax
all the way down into the belly area
maybe on the in-breath imagining drawing the air down even below the lungs all
the way to fill the belly area into the lower abdomen
letting the hip joints soften
down into the thighs the knee joints
and all the way to the feet
and then returning to the sense of uprightness and with some initial
softening and ease seeing if that allows the spine to
straighten up a bit more softness leads to a deeper kind of
strength
feeling the body supported through the middle
and soft around that
men in the mind
bringing awareness mindfulness to the four
sense of being here present for our experience
and that provides the stability and the strength in the mind and everything around that can be soft
letting the thoughts be soft letting
emotional Energies just flow in the background
letting mindfulness be the spine of the Mind
we can notice that there's a certain feeling of ease
when there is awareness in the present moment even if what's going on in the rest of
experiences something uncomfortable
something in the body or something in the art
the simple fact that there's mindfulness of it that there's presence actually has a slight amount of joy and
ease associated with it
and we can tune into that as kind of a reference point
that feeling of simple ease when the mind is mindful
so the invitation is to use ease as the reference point
some part of the body that's at ease and the ease of presence in the mind
as the reference point something that we Orient around
you know when the mind is entangled in a thought or an emotion or
some reaction to the body we can feel how that's complicated not
useful and return to the reference point of
just useful awareness of the flow of the present moment
foreign
has become complicated and the body has tensed up
because of thinking or entanglement just gently
re-prioritizing ease as the reference point the ease of staying simple
just being aware of what's happening in the present moment
softening the body
and if there are parts of the body that are painful or tight then there's mental
ease around how the body is it's fine right now
foreign
and if you are finding that there is some degree of ease
compared to when you started they sit
just allowing that to continue infusing into the body and mind
noticing what happens if you just open to the possibility of
ease or peace or contentment
whatever word seems to work
sometimes we can be surprised to find resistance
to ease
like it's not quite allowed or not quite right or might harm us
I don't know we can just have ease with our resistance
it is interesting
and as we move toward the end of this sitting
we might just open the mind to some gentle reflection
now would there be some way that carrying a reference point of
ease and presence and peace in some way
could help with letting go of the various
things that come up during the day
what are we willing to give up our peace for
we've finally gotten the puppy quiet a little bit
original let it lunge out and run around
I suppose that's what puppies do maybe that's what our mind will do
but maybe there's some unnecessary running around and lunging after things
that our mind tends to do where we could just say no thank you
it's fine just being present
we might find that this is supportive for other people too
not participating in the often
escalations that happen as each person gets more and more excited and
entrenched in their view or opinion
to seeing if that might be supportive this reference point of
being your ears in some way
foreign
[Music]
so this week we are talking about seven practices
that lead to letting go and recall that letting go is
multi-dimensional you know sometimes we actively engage sometimes we watch
sometimes we have some agency but often we don't really control the actual Act
of Letting Go we just do these practices and then the Letting Go occurs when and
how it does so a very important way of letting go or
factor in the process of letting go is seeing that was the what we talked about
yesterday and we talked about it in the context of noticing whether wholesome states are
increasing or unwholesome states are increasing and then redirecting what we
pay attention to or how we're paying attention if needed in order to support the mind
staying in a more wholesome condition so this method from yesterday actually
weaves through all of the other six methods because we often have to check if we're moving to Warrior away from
suffering so in a sense this seeing that we talked about first is actually the most
fundamental way of letting go and clear scene
provides the discernment needed for all of the other methods
and we actually didn't completely finish talking about seeing so I'll probably say a little bit more about it on Friday
since it's so fundamental but for now we'll move on to some other
ways and the next few that we'll talk about apply in particular domains of
experience so I think yesterday I said you know if it's a glass jar we would open it by
turning the cap and if it's an aluminum can we need a can opener and so forth
so today's method is called restraining
and it comes out of seeing actually if we see that unwholesome states are
repeatedly occurring when we do certain actions then we might wish to restrain
from doing those actions that would help right that would help our mind
so the teachings say that there are cases where we will experience taints
vexation and fever if we don't have restraint
um and I think we're actually all familiar with what it feels like when we
could have had more restraint and sometimes that can be kind of painful right
so what we're actually restraining is the compulsion that leads
the Mind down a path toward Duca I don't know why the mind sometimes wants to go
toward Duca that seems to be one of the problems we inherit as a human being and so there's this compulsion sometimes and
so we want to restrain that part of the mind that is you know running in the
wrong direction for our own care right so
there are three domains maybe to pay attention to um one would be compulsive actions or
you know so like eating that third piece of pie and this isn't sort of an obvious one
you know as we sit there after the third piece feeling bloated and with an
amazing Sugar High we might be experiencing taints vexation and fever
associated with not having quite enough restraint so I think in that case the the
terminology we can get a sort of a visceral feeling with that
um and then of course there's the area of speech so I knew someone once who was working
on refraining from complaining and I was impressed that you know she took this on
and over a several week period She tried not to complain either verbally or
mentally um and what she discovered uh and it
wasn't so much whether she was going to succeed 100 or not because that would be very difficult but it was like a
learning experience you know you put down the the idea okay not gonna not gonna complain and then see what happens
with that like observe how the mind is and she discovered that complaining has
a compulsive side to it and she would um you know come to mindfulness in the
middle of complaining sometimes it was afterwards but as she got better at it she would become mindful in the act of
complaining in the middle of it and she would realize she realized that she couldn't stop and in her words I chose
not to stop because it felt too good in the moment but afterward it did not feel
good at all so it's like this with complaining it feels so good while we're doing it I'm
gonna sock it to that thing that I'm complaining about
um and it feels really good for a moment and then but if there's mindfulness he realized doesn't feel so good to put the
mind in a state like that so there's an interesting practice you
know could we restrain in some way before we put
ourselves into that not good feeling like before we have the third piece of pie
so there's an interesting practice I've heard about and used when practicing
with restraint in the verbal Realm and it's a it's an acronym uh weight
w-a-i-t and it stands for why am I talking
so I recommend this um you know when the mind is thinking about saying something you just
insert weight why am I talking and maybe it's fine maybe what you're saying is
useful or helpful or even compassionate maybe it's even Fierce Compassion or favorite uh you know but
um maybe not and so maybe just putting in that question we might realize
whether or not what we're saying is something that we really want to say would really be useful and helpful and
contribute to the situation foreign
area that we tend to have compulsion there's actions in speech and then
there's also thought you know we do have very much I think if you're a meditator you know you have compulsive thought so
the tendency to just keep chewing over a memory or a fear or an anxiety about
something and if we repeatedly think about some topic and get upset could we
choose to restrain that train of thought or even at the subtle level of remind there can be ways of restraining that I
mean there's lots and lots of them out there so there's another area where we can't talk through all of that but
um you know there there's the possibility of switching the line to something that's and what's called an
antidote so you know if we are complaining a lot could we switch to meta some kind of appreciation or
gratitude uh for what for some other aspect of what's going on instead of part that we're complaining about
another thing we can do is deliberately reflect on the suffering that comes from
such thoughts you know before ruminating on something and if we are stuck in the
topic of the rumination the mind is removed from the present moment actually it's in a concept and if we actually
feel in the body uh how how much suffering there is associated with those thoughts sometimes
that's enough that the mind is like oh I don't wanna I don't want to be doing that
so you know there's a number of ways that we can do this I've I've mentioned some internal ones but it's worth
mentioning that the Buddha does talk about where ways that there can be external restraints uh in our life you
know we don't have to just sort of knuckle under and take it on as I gotta do everything internally
um there was the case of a new monk named magia and
um the Buddha gave him some suggestions to help settle his mind and stop thinking compulsively and some of them
were external so the the story is probably something that we can relate to
um McGill was serving for a while as the Buddhas attended and so he was hanging
out with the Buddha and there came a time when you know it was meditation time in the afternoon and he said can I
go meditate by myself in that mango Grove and the the Buddha kind of
discouraged him and he said nah that might not be such a good idea for you mcia but he he was really determined and
he asked again and again the Buddha said maybe not but he was so determined and he said no
please I'm really devoted I really want to go meditate in the mango Grove and so it would have said all right what can I
do it's about meditation go for it and so he went there and he um sat down for the day's
meditation if you will and the suta says but while McGill was meditating in that
mango Grove he was beset very badly by three kinds of unskillful
thoughts namely sensual malicious and cruel thoughts and then he thought it's
incredible it's amazing I've gone forth from the laylife into homelessness out of Faith but I'm still harassed by these
three kinds of bad unskillful thoughts sensual malicious and cruel thoughts so
you know here it is we've become we're not monastics but we've taken on a spiritual practice of mindfulness and
we're sitting down meditating so well and lo and behold all these terrible thoughts come and what I love is that
Mickey doesn't say oh I'm so bad he says it's incredible it's amazing how could
this happen so it was sort of genuine wonder he went back to the Buddha and he
said this is what happened to me and so then the Buddha took this as an opportunity to teach him and he said
when the hearts release is not ripe there are things that can help it to
ripen and he names a whole bunch of them but I'll just name a few
he says good friends Companions and Associates this is the first thing that
can help your heart to ripen so Sangha friends companions talk sitting with
people being in a group that's also practicing very supportive for a mind
that is harassed what does it say beset so that sounds like taints vexation and
fever be set by difficult thoughts and then second he says um
uh one can be ethical conducting oneself well and associating the suitable people and so
forth and so then there's there's a way of course that is sort of an individual effort but ethics are relational so you
know getting people around us who will also be ethical and will help support us in why speech in Wise actions this can
be very very helpful and then also the Buddha says to Makia
it's very helpful when a person gets to take part in talk about self-effacement
that helps open the heart whenever they want without trouble or difficulty and then he says more
specifically talk about fewness of wishes contentment seclusion arousing
energy ethics concentration wisdom freedom and knowledge and vision
so these are you know lofty Dharma topics but the chance to talk about the
Dharma is also an external support that we can use that restrains the Mind from
running off into difficult thoughts and restrains us from difficult verbal
behavior and and actions so it is it can be useful to have some good support
around us if our mind is in need of restraint in some ways
and then we can see that also how we do the
restraining matters so um for example if there's a text where
someone is supposed to evaluate whether or not a teacher is good for them and
one thing they're supposed to check is whether it looks like the teacher is restrained without fear not restrained
by fear so is a person who's you know leading a
group uh restraining by fear of them you know there's themselves or are they
making others comply out of fear or is it a natural kind of internal restraint
so restraint by fear is not what we're looking for we don't restrain ourselves because
we're terrified of the consequences we restrain ourselves because
there's ease we have a basis of ease we know that it's more useful that way
in the dalapada there's a chapter that opens with a rather remarkable stanza it
says if one knew oneself to be precious one would guard oneself with care a sage
will watch over herself in any part of the night so we restrain ourselves because we know
how valuable we are we watch over ourselves in a protective way because we matter our inner life
matters our heart matters so I've noticed that here in the west it
can take some time for people to begin valuing themselves we may have
internalized a lot of criticism so we don't really like ourselves or we might have learned that it's better to take
care of everyone else and not ourselves but at some point we have to make our own well-being a real part of the path
and that includes restraining the parts of our Behavior speech and thought that are unwholesome because that harms us
so it comes down to our heart our cheetah
our heart lined so we're a little over so I'll just end
with the Buddha says I do not see even one other thing that when tamed guarded
protected and restrained lead to such great good as the cheetah the heart the
cheetah maintained guarded protected and restrained leads to great good
so this is a healthy helpful movement the cheetah is our emotional Center and
it starts out in tangle with all kinds of bad habits it's been kind of beat up
and so then through Dharma practice we disentangle it unfold it and it becomes
free but at the beginning we have to protect it like a Little Seedling and restraining is part of that protecting
process so when we restrain compulsion it
becomes less compulsive you know its energy gets weaker and eventually those habits really don't sway the heart
anymore and so we become happier and lighter so restraint can lead to letting
go in Freedom all right so thank you