okay so here we are the top of the hour
just a warm welcome to everybody I'm Delight it is for me to be here and to
be sharing it in with the goodness of this Sangha it's quite something
and many of you know that Gail is starting a a retreat
so more than happy to help support him I see
take some well-deserved Retreat time
maybe I'll wait a few more seconds before I start with the guided meditation
and wishing everybody a good morning again and here it's a little cloudy too I like
how there's a little bit this weather report there is a little bit cloudy I'm in Redwood City not too far from IMC
actually
okay so we'll start with a set
being in the meditation posture
and can we bring an aliveness of attention
to the experience of sitting
to taking a moment to settle in
what does it feel like to sit to be in this particular posture
be feeling the legs or touching the chair or the
mat says a bench couch bed
whatever it is
feeling the feet
and whatever they're touching
on the back side whatever it's touching
cushion chair couch bed
bench so many different ways so many different ways we can support
her sitting
feeling the pressure against the body feeling connected
feeling grounded
and can we feel the stability of this sitting base
feeling the steadiness of this sitting base our legs and feet and backside
and allowing that to support us
then bringing an aliveness of attention into the body
into the bodily experience more generally
is there a way we can inhabit the body with aliveness
with presence
alive to the body and the way it feels right now
maybe there are some areas of tension or tightness
if so we can rest our attention on those areas
with a spirit or with a intention of allowing
just for this sit can it be okay
those areas of tension tightness are there
maybe your the shoulders
the face
around the eyes or the jaw
allowing any softening any opening relaxing
and if there isn't any softening opening or relaxing
can we allow that to
being okay with it not being quite okay
can we set the direction the attitude of
our sit together this morning can it be a direction of kindness
of warmth
of care
in some ways we might say that
just the ACT is sitting down to meditate is an act of kindness towards ourselves
way of taking care of ourselves
but just intentionally bringing in that orientation that direction of kindness
goodness time together
and if you haven't already is resting the attention on the
sensations of breathing
feeling the body as it breathes
in a relaxed easy way just noticing
the sensations breathing
you know in the mind wanders as it's apt to do
just very simply gently Begin Again
foreign
[Music]
so again oh let's see I need to stop the recording here for a moment
so good morning good morning thank you for that
set together it's lovely to sit together
and so this morning I'd like to talk a little bit about stories
and the role that they play and some of the stories we tell ourselves and certainly some of the stories that are
in our tradition so there's one story that probably many
of you are familiar with and that is the story about the Buddha's Awakening
The Story Goes that after the Buddha to be after renouncing Bulls like this
Central indulgement in all possible Central pleasures and
then going to the opposite extreme and having this extreme asceticism nearly
starving himself to death so after trying both of these extremes
and that didn't work he didn't become awakened then he decided okay well I'm going to meditate and it's going to go
under a tree and sit and not move until he was awakened until
he was enlightened and while I was sitting there under the
tree The Story Goes there's a number of different versions of this story as often as the case when there are stories
is that he was visited by Mara
Amara tried to entice the Buddha to be with these different fantastic things
Central indulgences and when that didn't work he attacked
the Buddha to be with armies and that's a little bit what I'd like to
talk about in that in our week together is about these different armies that uh Mara used to attack the Buddha to be
before his Awakening so that this story here
so we might say that Mara and this story symbolizes that which
gets in the way of our for their freedom our Awakening
this movement towards enlightenment I might say that Mara represents some
people might say the hindrances and certainly you know Mara we could say it's the hindrances but it's also more
than that it's uh that which gets us that captures us and uh makes us think
that we don't need to move along this path towards greater Awakening or distracts us uh from this path towards
greater freedom Tamara as a character I want to
emphasize that he's not like satanic sometimes I've heard uh different teachers or writings that kind of refer
to him more as this demon or demonic but I would say that real important
distinction between Mara and any satanic ideas we might have is that Mara
absolutely has no wish for beans to do evil or to be in hell
it's actually the opposite Mara wants individuals to enjoy all the
sense Pleasures they can imagine Mara would like for us to have the best
food ever that best vacations ever the best sex ever the best anything just so
that we like feel Intoxicated by essential pleasures and or indulging in
them again and again and again and instead of like seeking towards
greater Enlightenment or Awakening we find ourselves endlessly seeking and searching and striving towards freedom
and peace but never finding it because we're like stuck with these
enticements of uh whatever it is that it's in the way of our Awakening gets in
the way of Greater freedom and peace so for Mara you would say there's this
way in which we're never leaving what we might call samsara
there's a few ways to understand samsara one is that there's these different
Realms that beings can exist in some of them we might say are Heavenly Realms some are hell Realms we can understand
it as you know some moments we're in the heaven Realms things are just perfect and ideal
it was nice for me to sit with you guys just a few minutes ago maybe we could say that was a little bit of a heaven
Realm and then the hell Realms where we have real difficulties you know
difficulties and then the human realm or just kind of our everyday life
so we can understand it it's just one moment in the next or we could understand it as you know one lifetime
to the next for the purposes of what we're talking about this week absolutely doesn't
matter however you like to hold this idea of samsara of you know this being
in the next one realm one after the other but getting back to this idea of Mara so
he's not uh satanic doesn't want you know evil or bad so he
emphasizes complacency and contentment in some kind of way but
really like this complacency so the story of Mara is the story of
complacency versus effort
being satisfied not really doing anything versus you know
working or I don't know if that's the right word opening uh towards greater Awakening so it's not
good versus evil it's complacency versus I'll use this word effort but I don't
want to imply that it has to be super hard effort because sometimes it does but sometimes it doesn't
so to this uh story of Mara there's been a
modern day reinterpretation that I just think is delightful and that I've really
um have enjoyed and this story has been written
by ajan punedamo who from the arrow River Forest Hermitage in Northern
Ontario Canada and he's in the ajanta lineage
and he uh wrote this story that's the
story of Mara writing letters
to the generals of these 10 armies so he has these uh letters that he's
written to kind of like encourage those individuals who are leading these armies
that lead in humans we'll say into this complacency so here's the setting in which uh
Jean punadamo wrote as describing Mara sitting down to
write these letters and here's here's a description in a far away realm there's this most
intoxicatingly beautiful Pleasure Park in all the vast swarms of universes
Golden Leaves suede by gentle breezes tinkle with soft and lazy Melodies
gorgeous birds and enormous butterflies flutter through the Shady Groves
and then he goes on to describe how there's this castle and inside this
Castle there is this individual named Mara who is sitting at a desk
um setting down sitting down to dictate a letter to the ten armies to the
generals of these ten armies so you can this really Fantastical realm
and sometimes that's kind of what makes it fun I think is this Fantastical realm that this uh maybe this sense of Whimsy
as opposed to some of the seriousness because this practice is really serious but sometimes we need a little bit of
Whimsy to uplift the heart and for maybe to see ourselves in a way
that isn't so maybe critical or overbearing
so the scene is Mara is sitting at this desk in this beautiful castle in this
beautiful land to write letters to his generals or the leaders of these 10
armies so what are the ten armies sense desires
boredom hunger and thirst craving
sloth and torpor uncertainty malice and obstancy
honor Renown and notoriety and self-praise and denigration of
others so these are the ten armies these are the things that uh
get in the way of our leading to Greater freedom
and so in this um in these ensuing weeks I'll be
talking a little bit about these armies and the letters that ajan punadamo has
written to the leaders of these armies so
um we might talk say well why what about stories like why do we even bother with
these uh stories like this is silly Diana but stories have such an important
part and kind of like The Human Experience like we all share stories we share stories with our family of our
family of work of our experiences and certainly uh in our daily lives we might
refer to myths or folklores or characters from TV shows you know that to explain things to
others or maybe even to explain things to ourselves and I know in Buddhist circles we
sometimes use this expression like the second Arrow referring to a story right
the Buddhist story of the first arrow is what life brings us
but the second arrow is our reaction to difficulties and the second arrow is can
be just as painful or as painful as the first Arrow so that's just a representation of a
story that kind of as practitioners we share and we often use it to represent
something that's meaningful and the use of a story is a way in which
we can maybe do a shorthand but also kind of connects us
stories let us share information that maybe creates a little bit of an emotional connection with others or or
maybe help us understand information and maybe even make that information memorable it's really easier to remember
this idea of the second Arrow rather than a complicated
idea of well then there's what happens and then there's our reactions to what happens
but how can we use these stories to help our practice
maybe even these stories with Mara and his armies these stories can help us recognize our
common Humanity all beings
experience these visits from Mara and his army
we don't have to take it personally it's part of the human experience to be
visited by sense desires boredom malice and obstacy thirst and hunger and you
know all these other armies so we don't have to identify with them when they arise
because when we identify with them we may feel incompetent or inadequate or we
may feel discouraged so there's a way in which sharing these stories
can be a way for us to connect with others and to feel like oh yeah this is what it
means to be human and then I'll add the role of Whimsy
for me I actually really like this Whimsy because there's a way in which it dissolves some of this anger and
frustration or maybe we might say let's light shine in some of the Dark Places
or we might even say that it warms our hearts or softens our hearts and makes
life more interesting to have some of these stories and to have a little bit of Whimsy that eases some tension
there's a way that connects us together so the role of stories in practice
certainly there's stories that we tell ourselves that are not helpful but I'm hoping in these few days
together to share stories that are helpful and them having this Whimsical
Fantastical form helps us remind us that their stories and maybe helps us be able
to look at ourselves and our own experience with uh some of this warmth and kindness
that connects us with others so I hope that you'll join me for the rest of this week as well as I'll share
some of these letters that were written to the leaders of these different armies I'll choose a few of these tomorrow will
be boredom so how does Mara encourage people to be bored and then how can we
as practitioners work with that so thank you and I look forward to
spending these days together and wishing you a wonderful rest of the day thank you