so welcome uh welcome folks nice to uh nice to be with you nice to see all the
uh the well wishes and chats and um
yeah okay we'll do what we do
and uh settle in
so the Jitter heart mind
that which gets liberated this path
not exactly sure what chitta is
but uh
ajin sajita says uh characterized chitta heart mind as a
primarily a receptivity system
so we make ourselves porous
rather than coming to conclusions about life about ourselves
let me sit poised in receptivity
compassion is said to be the quivering of the heart
but in a sense our whole being is always quivering
always being touched by phenomena
the relentlessness samsara
when we sit here deeply embodied
our skin sensitive to
everything
our heart sensitive to everything
our affect emotion feeling
signals various urgencies
the urge to fiddle with samsara
sometimes there's wisdom in it
but for right now we treat everything as a kind of false
alarm
thing poised in receptivity
which is another way of saying
we're not Landing in conclusions
about ourselves about life
or poised in receptivity
is writing the intensity of embodiment intensity
of this human Realm
intensity of time
of Pleasure and Pain
um it's the intensity of The Human Condition your porousness
almost can feel like we we have to brace against the world
and the way one braces so as to minimize the pain in a certain
part of our body
or injured maybe we brace
trying to quarantine the pain
in a deeper way we brace
so as to protect sense of self
the Matthew within Matthew needs protection from all this
receptivity
but it's just sensitivity all the way down
the opening
the skin Quivers the heart Quivers
no more fake urgencies
no more protection
safety in the openness
in our race activity where we're not trying to go
anywhere to get anywhere
become anything
the goodness is already here
we can feel that
when there's just a kind of faith the logic of the Dharma
foreign
okay
okay so um
or Surrender uh humor playfulness grieving
and now five days in the week uh final factor in this uh
made up made up list and um
I needed needed in my mind needed
a factor that acknowledges the the iterative
the iterative nature of the path uh
that that are understanding of of what we're doing of what the Dharma is is
continually updated and
we get comfortable there are phases these kind of alternating phases of
getting comfortable within a certain View of the Dharma and then
some the rug being pulled out and too much comfort for too long
is stagnation and so there's the the iterative nature of Dharma
I wanted to emphasize the way that the way that a Dharma life is a kind of
continuous feedback loop giving seething
growing giving receiving
and I felt like I needed a factor that acknowledges
the permanent possibility of being wrong
a possibility that there will never be dispelled really
and so today beginning again
yeah on this path we're going to have to to begin again
it's not it's not a kind of linear path
of of practice progress practice progress practice progress
and if we can't begin again on the path
uh practice can become uh humiliated and
maybe we stop all together because there are there are plateaus and
descents and times when we're super inspired and the Dharma feels so fresh and alive
and times when we have zero motivation
and so we learn we learn to begin again
at uh the micro level
We Begin Again when we're attending to the breathing or whatever and notice
that we're encased in fantasy let me Begin Again
and at the macro level
um the level of our life sometimes
our past maybe is just
too messy to sort it all out the day was too messy to sort it all out
We Begin Again sometimes
our family history is too messy to sort all out
we Begin Again Redeeming the pain or the prior
generation and in our lives
how easy it is to forget the dumb
to become in one way or another alienated from our wisdom and from our
love so it's it's meaningful to me that that
Sati uh mindful translator renders mindfulness
um has connotations of of memory of memory
we We Begin Again when we remember the Dharma
in my suffering there's a kind of
sense of it being a kind of of forgetting
in the the dream the the you know said life is kind of
dreamlike yeah but um suffering definitely feels dreamlike
something uh about the dharmas Forgotten utterly forgotten in our
sorrow and despair and we remember we begin again
of course we we make uh messes the kind of
the debris of greed hate delusion
and sometimes our messes were embarrassed embarrassed by the messes we
make and uh
it can be humbling but um we just Begin Again
and guilt in a way is just a kind of overestimate of the wisdom we had at the
time course we made a mess
of course how could it have been otherwise
of course they made a mess
and we learn the the kind of lesson of
the the defilements we learn the lessons as deeply as we can
and then we completely forgive ourselves and begin again
We Begin Again within relationships within the various relationships of of
our life that sometimes there's a dense tangle or a Discord or conflict
or a seemingly irreconcilable kind of
pain of one kind or another and there can be
this tendency to want to tie up all the Loose Ends to iron everything out
and sometimes that can be done sometimes that's appropriate sometimes it's it's
utterly vital to talk things through to come to some kind of Dayton some kind of
resolution but sometimes the Loose Ends won't be
tied up and we just let them lie And We Begin Again
Norman Norman Fisher said it's hard being a human being there's a lot to it
it really is so I want to say in conclusion let's all agree to accept the reality
that we're not going to be able to do a very good job at this there's too much to do isn't it a relief
to know it's not gonna work out and you can just forget about that to
start with so you're not going to get it right you're not going to get it perfect well don't worry just remember there's
no hope but the important thing is the important thing is despite this and
recognizing and embracing this reality don't worry about finishing the job or
doing it perfectly but start you see
start and continue this is the thing
you can really trust that if you will start and if you will continue with commitment
that will be enough that will be enough
our our intentions uh for practice
they change over time we have to begin again sometimes we achieve or we outgrow what
brought us to the path we came here to
manage anxiety or came here to and for some circumscribed
kind of it reason and now okay I feel better
what's practiced now let's practice now we have to find new sources of of
motivation We Begin Again with new intentions for practice
and sometimes sometimes we We Leave Behind things as we begin our
practice We Leave Behind pieces of ourselves pieces of our history things
that were meaningful the ways
we used to play or read or pray
we leave these things behind but practice has this weird way of
looping back to Old currents in our life things that were meaningful
that we've put down and then we pick them up but in a new
way we we begin again with Old loves
begin again at the macro level We Begin Again in each moment
so uh offer this for your your consideration and uh
yeah feel um yeah honored to be uh to be with you and
uh appreciative of
a sense of of freedom I have to speak my heart
so uh yeah thank you all thank you and um
yeah I appreciate uh appreciate the scheduling mistake here
uh our session uh thanks for your flexibility
with that and thanks for all your support of uh
of IMC and your practice and grateful
okay folks so uh we'll wrap up and see you see you somewhere on the uh the the
YouTube Zoom circuit and or elsewhere and I wish you all a good week
okay I know