so my my topic for today is spiritual friendship and I have to say I am
brimming overflowing with uh emotion as I kind of
contemplate joy and just move my heart is so moved and just now like just this
these offerings that have just been announced and are being offered are by you know this is the Sangha this is
spiritual friendship this is amazing you know um
I think uh I hope you all know how welcome you are here
that you you know that each of you belong here if you want to be here
that you get to be fully who you are and be here and uh Gil I'd love Gill uh as a teacher
and one of his teachings is um you know you're a member of IMC if
you want to be if you don't like membership no problem you can still come like whatever it is
that works for you that's how spacious it is and I guess I'll um
can you zoom in in on this for the YouTube folks I'll pass this around but
maybe you've noticed this so when you come in the door there's a very a transparent logo on the front door and
this is also posted by the door it's still in draft form but um it says all are welcome here
all are welcome here and there was a group of us that worked on you know collaborating to create this
sign and um wow was it wow was it a project I to think about how do you represent
everyone being welcomed and I'm not suggesting we did it but you
know really not but it was the best that we could do so it was good enough for
now and I love it it's beautiful okay I'm gonna move my arm now and just kind
of um you know just to talk about what this includes is um you know three hands
right three hands of different races colors ethnicities together holding
a young tree a Bodhi Tree which is what the Buddha is said to have enlightened under you know that it takes us all
coming together and that it's it's our heartfulness it's our kindfulness it's our mindfulness that create the soil and
conditions for all of us to thrive all of us to thrive and then of course we have a rainbow here for
you know the lesbian gay bisexual transgender
asexual non-conforming gender non-binary everything
two-spirited plus people in our world and when we were
working on this we like tried to list all the kinds of identities that we could think of how can we represent this
and we tried you should have seen the other models they were a little too much
this this this kind of was like I said the best that we could do
so I'll just pass it around and um you can look at it or not just you know
allow it to flow I just want you all the opportunity to see it
huh and um so it was you know as I was kind of
growing nurturing like you know yeast inside of me this talk and my
Reflections on spiritual friendship I was thinking about a name for it a
title for it and um first I thought well mindfulness is spiritual friendship I thought about
um heartfulness this spiritual friendship and then I remembered
um ajan Brahm wrote a book called kindfulness
and that just it's like oh yeah yeah so mindfulness and heartfulness and there's
this term in Pali chitta which represents heart and mind together
heart and mind together because friendship really especially spiritual friendship does require the
heart and mind to come together because to be kind we have to be we have
to engage the mental capacity to assess a situation to implore and and work from
Wise view wise intention and have wise action we need them bind to be engaged
and that without equality of the heart this the kind sort of the quality of
this you know the Brahma baharas loving kindness compassion Joy
and Equanimity balance we we absolutely need all of these things and so this
term kindfulness for me really was where I
I settled kindfulness is spiritual practice
kindfulness and the you know
spiritual friendship is what this Sangha is made from
completely what the song is made from it's amazing actually
so everything here started in a
I think it was at the um what's it called
Hillary what was the name of the the friend yeah what was it but it was called the
friend what do you remember what it was called there was like a um a small Center that let us
um calm and practice like I wasn't even part of the song it was like maybe six or nine people or 10 or 12 or whatever
and then they brought Gillen to be a teacher and they just rented spaces until this
Sangha grew and they raised money to buy this building
this building was a church and that's probably how we got it because the church you know owners and
Gill met and they appreciated what we were going to be doing here sitting in silence
right so everything here is because of Donna generosity
and people coming together and working together and the image I have for Sangha in this this place is like a spider web
there are so many people doing little bits to keep and create the
space unbelievable number of people and so who here Volunteers in some way just
raise your hand we got one two three four five six seven
like eight nine ten I don't know this is like you know quarter of us sitting here
at least and right now there's 150 people in person and online sitting
gills three-week Retreat which means a lot of people who would normally be here who are volunteers are not here
so probably half of us would be normally volunteers Hillary does that sound about right
as our amazing volunteer coordinator Hillary and so the the spiderweb image for me is
so powerful because it's like every every little intersection of the web is people
holding hands taking one piece from the next person like getting a flyer printed
takes a person to teach a per you know and that person usually creates a draft
and then somebody else prints it and you know like there's just everything here is hand to hand and that I was thinking
organizational charts and you know how they're looking fairly linear you know they have like little
veins that come off and there's this stacking we're we're a spider web our
organizational chart is an absolute spider web and there's often things that you know
people leave and come and go so just like a spider web is imperfect we are imperfect
we are absolutely imperfect and there are places where Things Fall Apart and don't go well and
and and then there's people that come in and connect this strand with a headstrand like this you know or their
toes with their feet too you know it's amazing and and then another thing about this
spiderweb is that it's loving kindness it's the it's the kindness and the compassion and the joy and the
Equanimity that the practitioners these people holding hands creating this
space that is you know tenuous and strong but bringing that heart quality lights
up the web like golden strands absolutely the heart quality just moves
through the whole thing and makes it absolutely beautiful absolutely beautiful
so thank you for being here because also just being here even if you're not a volunteer
you're supporting my practice because if I didn't have somebody to
that I was inspired to share this with all of this goodness that's been coming
up for me would not be here it would not be arising in the same kind of way
it's your practice your attending you're coming that supports my practice deeply
deeply
so I'll give you a little bit of a there's no I have no idea how much I'll
get to but these are the things that I have in mind I like to let you know where I want to go before I go there
so number one how powerful spiritual friendship is for our practice how
supportive it is it's incredibly supportive I've been talking about that already I'll say a little bit more
of uh asuta called good you know good-hearted friends advice for laypeople that comes from the teaching
of the Buddha to share that highlight the importance of
understanding that spiritual friendship is actually a training it is something we train in
it's not haphazard and and then there's this important part
of suffering that is part of spiritual friendship and which is you know in all of us we're
conditioned right this is what the Dharma in a Buddha taught us we get conditioned by life
automatic pilate takes over and we're no longer present
well this is really true in relationships as you know right
as you know so understanding that deeply is incredibly important to to knowing
and being able to be a spiritual friend and then
um maybe I'll say this now but another part of my inspiration for this topic tonight
is that starting in October on Thursday nights I'll start a two-month series on mindful
mindful speaking and mindful listening it's incredibly incredibly important
part of our life and being spiritual friends to each other
and I have a practice some of you may be aware of the raft practice
anybody know about raft not many couple so I'll talk a little
bit about how to use a raft in the context of relationship spiritual friendship
so I have a I have a poem to read to you
and um maybe before I read it um
I'll just ask you to think about bring to mind a spiritual friend somebody
who's been a spiritual friend to you and it could be somebody you know or
just somebody you know of who's done things that have inspired you
and what are their qualities what kind of qualities do these
friends spiritual friends have
and anyone who is willing to speak if you share out loud any of those
qualities I'll say them and repeat them to make sure people and YouTube who are joining us can hear
is anybody willing to share what qualities came up for them yes
presence Brave
and non-judgmental thank you loving
kind kind
again available available nice
curious Trust
what makes someone trustworthy
you can share and it's confidential right and you know maybe that they've got your
back
thank you yeah put it up here is great so I don't forget it gotta put it back on the bulletin board
consistent beautiful insightful
um perceptive
oh receptive yes beautiful honest oh truth yes
accepting and caring good listener
really important I was listening to a talk
um by James baraz on spiritual friendship and he so this is like third hand right and he was talking about
somebody who teaches non-violent communication a lot and that he said that that person said
that when it comes to non-violent communication it was the listening that mattered the most
so I'm there's more right it's okay this was good and so here's this poem
and the title of the poem is aftermath
I'll say more at the end of the poem those seeds you planted in me with your
words all through the night they rooted grew stems sprouted leaves
by morning I'm in full bloom my thoughts are rebellion of petals a mutiny of
beauty or once only Shadow spread all day your words unfold
in layers of purple and unruly gold I like it when people stare Everywhere I
Go I share this the aftermath of your kindness
right this is these are the seeds these are the gifts the qualities that have been given by our spiritual friends and
when they take hold it bloom bloom in US wow what an aftermath
this is by Rosemary traumer
so what did the Buddha say about spiritual friendship he actually said you know some pretty and poignant things
and um one suta he says with regard to external
factors so things of the environment outside of ourselves I don't Envision any other single Factor
like admirable friendship is doing so much for a monk in training
no other not any other Factor like admirable
friendship can do so much for a monk in training
that's that's pretty significant
I'm sure you've heard the this I I chose not to bring this suta into because so
well referenced but you know there's this conversation between Ananda do you know who Ananda is the cousin and the
attendant to the Buddha and and there's this conversation where
the Buddha and Ananda are sitting together and Ananda is probably you know feeling really uplifted by spiritual
friendship and they're sitting there and he's talking and Ananda says Noble one oh Lord you know friendship is
half of the spiritual path and the Buddha responds by saying no Ananda don't say that it's all of the
past it's very very pivotal really really
really really powerful there's um a poly word for Spiritual
friendship and it's kalyana Mita I like this word km for short
kalyanamita you're my kalyanamita my km kaliana can be translated as spiritual
can also be translated as good true virtuous upright or beneficial
and Mita is the same root as meta
loving kindness loving kindness
good friend spiritual friend virtuous friend
and another suta Nakaya 31 the Buddha gave a teaching
about good-hearted friends and it's advice for Lay people that's us right
or lay people and he's talking to um
a young man and he said be aware of these four good-hearted friends
and describes describes them as a helper one who endures one who's a mentor and
one who's compassionate so I'm going to talk a little bit about each of these four qualities
and the Buddha said the helpful friend can be seen to be loyal a loyal friend in four ways
he looks after you when you're inattentive right looks after you when you're
inattentive he looks after you when your possessions are inattentive you're unattended
he is a refuge when you are afraid
that's profano just hit me you know a refuge when you're afraid right how you
know it's not everybody who can hold us with their presence or listen when we're afraid not everybody can do
it's a really big thing to be stable enough to be with somebody when they're afraid
to see them with their potentials still intact right
and um and then the last thing he says is when some business is to be done
he lets you have twice what you ask for twice so this generosity right
in our city
there's um this is an example from tiknot Hans
Sangha of this idea of being helpful and twice
what one is asking for they created something called second body Sangha second body Sangha
we established a second body practice to deepen our relationships and to support our practice
each participant has two bodies a Sangha member they care for and their
own body the care was determined by Mutual consent and might entail a weekly phone
call or a daily sitting practice
pretty cool I read you know there's an article and I think it's lion's roar somebody wrote about it who was there
and described you know waking up or being sick and you know having food show
up for him because his second body brought him food and
I I just really appreciated this idea this notion the way it was framed right
the second body just your second body like somebody who's there just to do these things and
there's something about that too that's like you know you you don't get any gold star
for being a good friend the second body you're just acting like you would for
your own body right you you have this care for another
like you care for yourself it's just beautiful
the second quality um is described as an enduring friend
the friend who is the same and happy and unhappy times
can be seen as a loyal friend in four ways he tells you his secrets she guards her
secrets they do not let you down in misfortune
they would even sacrifice their life for you
so what is this what does enduring through good and bad times
friendship look like what does that mean you know here at IMC it might be you know somebody
hasn't been coming for a long time and we welcome the back no matter what right
I might mean you know being willing to listen to Somebody's fears or difficulties or Joys over and over again
or in really great detail
the third quality is the friend who points out what is good for you
it's also described as a mentoring friendship the friend who points out what is good
for you can be seen to be a loyal friend in four ways they keep you from wrongdoing
they support you in doing good inform you of what you did not know and
they point out the path to Freedom
in our in our scene here we have kind of formal and informal mentors
formal Mentor might be a teacher right somebody who's in a role as a teacher
an informal Mentor might be the way somebody is sitting
during meditation that inspires you the way somebody
behaves and demonstrates through these qualities of love and kindness and you
know compassion and sympathetic Joy
and you know even um Gill likes to prefer he prefers being
thought of as a spiritual friend over a teacher
there's something really you know connected about that isn't there
really connected it's the word that comes to mind for me
I think I'll say here too just that you know this is certainly how he came to be my
teacher was I started you know volunteering
I showed up I supported him he supported me in all kinds of ways
like he did a lovely job with a bell I remember the first time I managed an event and I hit the bell at the end of
the sit everybody jumped out of their seats it was so loud oh my God and you
know he was so kind to me after this he was just so kind like
he taught me brought me over helped me learn how to hit the bell and just said
there's no mistakes here there's no mistakes here wow
techn says what is most important is to find peace and to share it with others
right this is a spiritual friend this is what Gil did for me he has found peace and he
shared it with me in that moment and many others
so spiritual friendship is a training it is actually something it is like
practice it is it is practice it is the embodiment of our practice it's bringing our practice not just from
this inner realm but to everything that we do
and you know um incredibly important part of our our
training in the Eightfold Path right which is said to be the way to Freedom
in the middle of that is Sila or ethical or virtuous action
and it includes wise action wise speech wise livelihood
and wise action is the abstaining of killing living beings
right abstaining from taking what is not given
abstaining from false speech abstaining from [Music]
um harmful sexuality
and abstaining from intoxicants that cloud the mind and cause heedlessness
so by engaging in these five wise actions we you know we're we're abandoning a lot
of greed and a lot of hatred and hopefully a lot of delusion too
so this is a really important part of of how we train these are things that we don't just do
you know when we're casually there are things that we do thoughtfully mindfully
there are these four Brahma viharas which are um kind of essentially
expressions of love spiritual love
and um they're really healthy emotional mental States
that really support us and
they arise without craving aversion and ego
if we have too much craving aversion and ego They Don't Really rise up
and their helpful emotions that are much more likely to arise when
we're not preoccupied and when we're not kind of caught and
craving an aversion so this is core to our practice right
it's kind of like we can notice if we're in a Crowd Oh is there is there kind kindness present is there am I able am I
happy or envious with somebody else's Joy right if we're envious we've got craving
or aversion happening so it's a you know this beautiful mirror for us to find ourselves to find the
qualities that are active in our heart and mind at any one time how we respond to each other
is a a reflection for us of what's happening within ourselves
it helps us find and notice and recognize
and um you know the way Gill put this this is his
sentence contrary to the popular idea of Falling in Love is a mysterious process out of our
control the Buddha emphasized cultivating our capacity for love cultivating our capacity so it's not
something that just you know is this biochemical Rush
it's something that we we grow we train
and it's these kinds of Love is different than sensual desire it's different than affection that's
entangled with attachment and the need for reciprocity
so sometimes you know when we hear the teachings of Letting Go and not clinging
people feel like well but I'm attached to my family and my partner and
does that mean I'm not supposed to be no no no no what we need to abandon is the craving
not the love the clinging not the love
it's the whole grabbing onto the expectations the wanting something back wanting somebody to be different
you know wanting to control what people do the hat is what we need to let go of not the love
not the love so with loving kindness
um it's uh this wish for everyone to be happy and that's Happy in their own way
not my way it's respect
showing respect right to the dignity and uniqueness of each person
and you know to Freedom I like to say
um let you be you and me be me right creating the conditions for us each to
flower fully the way we are for who we are into what we what we like our heart
most wants us to become
Christina Feldman wrote in the cultivation of metha friendship is turned into a verb
learning what it is to actively intentionally and consciously befriend all people including ourselves all
events and all experience
the second Brahm of ahara which you know this first one loving kindness is really foundational it helps us kind of get
things going so it's really the starting place for most of us with the Brahma baharas
and from it we start to grow you know the capacity to have compassion
which I love the Aya kemma's teaching which is you suffer
just like me and just like me you know just like you I suffer so it's
yeah you you suffer too just like me and I suffered just like you you know
there's like we all suffer right so having the capacity to attune to
suffering and see it as this thing that we all share in common
and to have compassion for that and and then the wish to be a support for the
end of that suffering
and how we help or don't help with the suffering is really important to attend to and this
is where we come back to this idea of kindfulness bringing in the mind
there's this um a book I was trying to think of the name of it um happiness hypothesis Maybe
and there's a metaphor in the book about an elephant and a writer anybody know
this book no yeah is it happiness hypothesis is that the
name of it yeah Jonathan hade and um so he talks about the elephant as
you know like our body is the biggest part of us and and the biggest part of
us is also so much is unconscious or semi-conscious
you know this is the beauty of how our mind is is evolved and it's also
potentially the liability of how our mind has evolved because it's like um
there's so much that we need just to uh you know operate on an automatic level for functioning in this world
there's just way too many things that if we had to pay attention to them in detail that there's no way we'd have
awareness left for anything else it's like and when I was in high school I volunteered in the special needs
classroom and the assignment for me was to sit down and write how many steps it takes to tie a shoe I was shocked it was
I think it was 30 something I was absolutely shocked I was floored and so if you think about like that's
just one teeny tiny task and there's so many of these things and
this is where there's this Brilliance of this elephant that just knows how to learn how to do these things right and
can do them so that we can be a writer we can stay aware
but we also have to grow our awareness we have to kind of keep growing it especially as Things become more and
more routine familiar to us because we go to
sleep as the writer we go to sleep if we don't work on staying present and that's
mindfulness staying awake and aware and all the things in our life
all the things in our life that happened to us you know we get born into a body
into a family into a community culture Society
and we are our conditioning starts before we're born
the tone of our parents voices whether or not we're kept or adopted you know
who ends up being there to raise us how we're treated by the people around us what our third grade teacher tells us
about our drawings all of these things go deeply stored
into this elephant and they inform how we experience and like we I like to
think about amygdala this is sort of like the storehouse of memory and there's
something I like to think about as like the librarian and so something is happening and the
librarian without her telling us without her telling us to do it goes and searches all the memories it says what's
like this oh this is like this and this is like this and it just it chooses and it says okay here you go this is what's
happening right and and so we just we're our our present moment is informed by
our pasts and most of that was not anything you chose to put in there
a lot of it you probably really wish wasn't there and a lot of it you don't even know is
there it's like the water you're swimming in Gil talked last week about the training
in deep diversity that we did as a um you know Sangha
there's a book called um deep diversity written by Shakil Chaudhary
and he's a mindfulness practitioner and he wrote about bias and racism and um
oppression and you know how can we bring our practice to this world and get free
from for me how do I get free from what I have internalized and didn't want around my gender about my sexual
identity about my race as a white person how do I get free from that conditioning that I have how do I
free you from the conditioning I have about your gender your identity your race whoever you are how do I free you
and how do I free myself this is incredibly important work
and in the Sangha these these conditions these this bias these experiences that
we have they're gonna all bubble up they're going to all Bubble Up in various ways
so it's incredibly important to be humble and to be listening and to be noticing
and remembering that when things come up for you and you're looking out at somebody else
and you're thinking it that comes from your story
that comes from your story and you know as a white person there's so
much conditioning around like thinking my my experience is the norm like like
that's how it is and so it's really easy to look out into the
world and see others as different I have a practice of when I see that happening
wait wait wait look at me how am I different I'm Different what's happening for me
what's my reference point here not about you me what's me what's going
on in here that's me to help me let go a little bit of that so I can more clearly
see you and tiknot Han has this phrase when he's talking about being a
spiritual friend and and meeting someone with compassion he says
it's important to ask if we understand the other person not to assume we do
he says sweetheart do I know you well enough do I and you're asking do I know you
well enough to assume that I can respond to you in a way that's truly compassionate because if I'm responding
to you from my story my conditioning my past my bias I might just do more harm
so compassion is tricky because we have this elephant the heart gets moved and
the Heart elephant wants to rescue and take care of people and it's so powerful
unless the writer is really present really awake and aware the elephant can
like the bull in the china shop right can really trample over
people and that emotional conditioning there's um emotions I feel like are like a
derived system they're motivating action if you think about it you know if you
look at if you've seen those little Emojis with faces right we use them on
our phones and charts just the facial expression tells you so much about you
know what what somebody is feeling right and you can imagine what is the posture
of somebody who said right there's this whole
intense biophysiological thing that comes with a Feeling
so there's a there's this you know we're not even aware sometimes how far we're feeling and we're expressing it whether
it's anger sadness Joy so this is the elephant energy this
automatic natural beautiful intelligence in the in the system that gets polluted over time
you know but um it needs to be managed we need to be aware so that it doesn't just drive our
behaviors so another the third Brahma Bahar is
mutita which is you know sympathetic Joy or joy
it's like shared Joy it's like when somebody tells you
something like yesterday I had a friend texting me and said I'm really great today and I felt so happy I really was
like Yay that's so great right that's so great
and I think you know Joy there's a lot like if you follow Neuroscience if you
listen to Rick Hansen or a lot of other people that are teaching about happiness
right now and making our brains feel better you know we have this tendency to not
appreciate and settle and receive the joy that comes up in our life even for ourselves
the small little joys like this morning I took a picture of this guy of a friend
who we send photos each morning if we get outside for early morning light
because it's supposed to be very helpful for sleep right to get exposure to the early morning sunlight
within half an hour of waking up so it said I believe it but so we'll
take pictures when we go out when we actually make it so this morning I took this picture of the sky
and it was like confetti like clouds she said she when she first looked at it
looked like stars in the skies you know it was just this beautiful moment just taking this picture taking doing this
practice going out taking this picture sending it was like wow this is this helps me connect with the joy
take it in don't miss it right and this when we don't miss the joy the little joys in our our life
there's a lot more ease and ability to connect with the joy of others
when we're really disconnected from the joy in our life we're gonna miss the joy in others we're going to feel envious
resentful hurt left out so it's really a practice really
important practice for us to take it seriously to sip to take sips of the goodness
so take it all in yeah
what time are we ending what time are we supposed to end at what time
10 45 three minutes ago okay
yeah well I have more to say but hopefully I'll see you again and like I
said I'll be starting the mindful mindful listening and speaking and Thursday nights at 6 30 to 9 6 30 to 8
sorry here in person only and um I just you know thank you thank you for
being here I really appreciate your attention and just everything
yeah thank you