so hello everyone and warm
greetings and warm greetings in a cold world it's a little bit cold I'm wearing
a sweater but uh a world that's full of War
violence hostility in all directions
and no Direction you look probably you don't see it so here we are warm greetings in a
cold world and one of the things that we're called on to
do in this challenging world that we live in is to not be
afraid and this maybe is a tall order a huge
challenge but if we're afraid the the more that we're afraid
the more that we cannot help make this a warm World a Caring
World the more that we cannot be agents of change in our
households in our neighborhoods hoods in our towns work spreading
outwards fear
interferes fear tears
apart so one of the tasks of practice is to learn to sit with fear so that we're
not afraid and that is a maybe needs a little
unpacking I think we can assume that we'll be
afraid or say it differently we can assume that we will
be uh there'll be occasions when fear fear will be present for
us some of the fear is appropriate and healthy and some of it is
not regardless of what it is the practice of
mindfulness is to sit in the middle of it and not be afraid not be
afraid have fear but not be defined by the fear have fear and know how to study the
fear to learn the lessons of fear
without becoming Frozen or becoming indifferent or becoming
removed so as we sit this meditation
here how would you where would you go within how would you be
within if you were in a meditating in a place that has no fear
where you are not afraid where mindfulness Is Not Afraid there might be
fear in you but you're not defined by the fear
what is that place that's free of fear in the midst of your
fear so whether you feel fear now or not what is that place where is that
resting place that ref Refuge that place of strength that place of
non-fear with which you can meet whatever fear comes
your way so that's the question that's the
contemplative suggestion for the contemplative exp exploration for this
sitting so to assume a meditation
posture and gently close your
eyes and as you're sitting here as you are to
relax let the shoulders release
soften let's let the shoulders release to the pull of
gravity relax the
belly relax the
hands
and relax the face soften around the eyes the
cheeks the
mouth
and to see if you can let the relaxation go deeper gently take some long slow deep
breaths and the exhale as long as it's comfortable long
extended exhale in which you relax the
body release tension and
holding
and then letting your breathing return to
normal and continue relaxing softening this
time relaxing the thinking
mind softening the tensions and pressures agitations of the
Mind
as if the mind is a rough sea as you relax let the surface of the
sea quiet down and spread wide and
peacefully letting the waves become
quiet
and then within your body relaxing the
heart relaxing the emotions you you have if if they're fluttering or agitated
or feeling fragile or V
vulnerable or there's any feeling of
distress not to make it go away
make a room for it all to settle to relax almost as if it's
allowed to relax into
itself
for
and then sitting quietly settling on the body's
experience of
breathing as if the experience of breathing provides a gentle
reassurance here [Music] now you are safe things are
okay in the moment sitting
here it's okay to relax further with every
breath
for
and now can you
find or imagine place
within maybe deep in your body or deep in your
mind that is free of
fear if you're anxious or afraid maybe deeper than the fear you
have at the center of all things a place of rest of Peace of
calm of clarity we're knowing being
aware is to be aware with an awareness that has no fear
in it just aware it might be aware of
fear it might know this spar within you but that
knowing is done from a place of
safety that knowing is
courageous courageously without
fear where is that place within
where there is no
fear where you can know all things
fearlessly and it might not be all or nothing it might be a matter of
degree where you get closer and closer to the place where there's less
and less fear in how you're mindful how you're
present
e
for
from where there is no fear allow yourself to know
fear without being identified with it without becoming
it in a place within where there is no hostility
no hostility that's present without becoming
it in the place within without
greed no greed when without becoming identified
with
it from the place where there's no agitation no agitation that's
present without becoming the
agitation
for this peaceful place
within is a place free of
opposition there might be oppositional feelings don't become
those from this peaceful place
within don't oppose anything including your fear your
hostility just let it relax as if it
relaxes in the gentle
warmth of this peaceful Caring Place Within
for
e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to see if you can relax more deeply whatever you're holding on
to or whatever is holding on to you let it
soften relax for you to settle into a deeper
place of
knowing knowing that has no
fear has no identification with
anything but from which from where comes care and
compassion that tenderness of love and
respect an ability to gaze upon all things
kindly as if all things
warrant attention
knowing knowing in a way that lets all tensions begin to
relax and for to whatever degree you can rest in this knowing that has no fear no
hostility no identification with anything
or whatever degree you can imagine such a place of openness and
Clarity let that be the source of wishing this world
well may all
beings be free of
hostility may all beings be free of
violence may all beings be free of
Affliction and harm
may all beings [Music] know that there are people in this world
who care for
them who wish them no
harm may all beings be happy
may all beings and people be peaceful and
free and may we contribute to that
possibility
[Music]
thank
you
e
so I want to start this morning with two quotes from the
Buddha the first is go forth for the welfare and happiness of
the world so this call to benefit the world
that we live in
however he this uh instructions from the Buddha
is meant for people who can go into the world with enough
self personal Liberation enough self under knowing that they can go into the
world without causing any harm and they know and can
recognize what harm is and the impact of harm and and uh they freed themselves from
any tendency to act in ways that are harmful to themselves or
others they can go into the world peacefully as promoters of
Peace the so this is a tall order but I think
that the direction the Buddha is pointing us to is to become people who
can go forth for the welfare and happiness of the world and in doing so there's a second
quote among types of beneficent conduct
beneficial conduct among the best is
promoting settling and establishing an une ethical person in ethical
Behavior so that's quite a statement that uh the best conduct is is
uh not just being ethical yourself and maybe not even going forth
for the welfare of others in a kind of way of you know just helping them out in a
sense but for the Buddha the best conduct best thing you can do is establish an unethical person uh in in
ethics in ethical Behavior so you know I don't fully
understand the statement and implications of it and and how Universal we should understand it but I'm inspired
by this statement and I'm inspired that it's one thing to help another
person uh and another thing to to
have someone learn to be unethical to be ethical so they don't go around then
harming many people it's possible that in a certain kind of way that this is much more uh
beneficial in the long term is to support and develop and encourage
greater ethical behavior in this life in this world of ours and I know that when
I was young teenager that um I I I wasn't
unethical mostly because maybe a lack of imagination it
wasn't I was an ethical person but I just didn't I just wasn't had had no
orientation that way to be unethical and um and but well I thought
that people the idea of Ethics to me was kind of uh superficial kind of being
excessively sweet or or um I kind of um
look down upon people who were referred to as ethical as somehow being sometimes
being hypocritical sometimes being too too artificially sweet or
something and one of the big changes for me in coming to Buddhism was coming to
have a deep appreciation for uh behavior and ways of being and discovering
sources within uh that are the Wellspring of non-harming living in a nonharming
way and that uh part of why I'm a Buddhist teacher is to be able to convey that to people and spread that deep
sense of peace that can come from this inner place that is really has an ethical
quality the the uh Buddhist path of Liberation is an ethical path of
Liberation an ethic enlightened person is an ethical person there's no
no doubt that this is what the Buddha taught but what does it mean to be an ethical
person the Buddha as I said in this statement here talked about establishing an unethical person in ethical
Behavior elsewhere he talks about um uh there's what's
beautiful and then there's what's more beautiful than beautiful and what is beautiful
is being ethical oneself and what is more
beautiful is than then that beauty is uh
encouraging or inciting or maybe that's the wrong word being a
catalyst uh for other people to become ethical so here there's this call to go
forth for the benefit of the world is uh also there's includes in that the the
call to speak up to act up to to try to change the world and change how people
are not to convert them to Buddhism not to
uh believe in in religious truths of any kind but to believe in to understand to
appreciate um the value of non-harming nonhostility non-
greed um and uh and not just to believe in it but to really understand be
motivated from the inside out to live this way now there's a reason why the Buddha
emphasized this uh that's very different he lived in a very different world than we live in uh for in that world there
were no elections to uh try to get the
government that you like to kind of run the show or fix things the way they should be fixed there was no there were
no economic systems wide systems that uh that needed to be changed there was no
capitalism or socialism operating and there was no way to have these huge
impacts on the economic systems we live in so that they could be more Equitable and more uh
supportive there was no um you know there were no nonprofits there were no
there's it was very simple world the one of the main organizations back in time
of the Buddha were the Kings the monarchs who uh ruled with often Iron
Fists um they were quite comfortable with killing people on the spot if there was any
disagreement and so for someone to protest back then someone to go and say
to the king and you should stop the War uh that meant was off with your head there was you can't you couldn't really
do it back then and there was no sense that you could do something but the
Buddha did speak up and he spoke up in ways that were sometimes not direct uh when he uh talked to Kings uh
he would not tell them directly but he would tell stories uh in the form of myths of how things were in the ancient
world and uh and one of them had to do with a king in the ancient world who
wanted to perform a big sacrifice so they could be benefited in some way and
um and uh and so in this myth the minister who hears about this big
sacrifice uh tells the the king your Majesty's country is beset by
thieves and is ravaged villes Villages and towns are destroyed the countryside
is infested with uh robbers if your majesty were to tax this
region he going to tax it to be able to do a big sacrifice that would be the wrong thing
to do suppose your majesty were to think I will get rid of this plague of robbers
by executions and imprisonments and or by confiscation threats and
banishment the plague would not be properly ended those who survived would later
harm your Majesty's Realm so if you go around using violence to
get your way then sooner or later the people who survive will come back and harm
you however with with a following plan you can completely eliminate the plague
to those in the Kingdom who are engaged in cultivating crops and Rising cattle let
your majesty distribute grain and fodder to those in train trade give capital to
those in government service assign proper living wages then those people
being intent on their own occupations will not harm the kingdom your Majesty's
revenues will will be great the land will be tranquil and not beset by thieves and the people with joy in their
hearts will play with their children and will dwell in open houses not locked
up it's so painful to read this ancient admonition when we had have you know
million children or more in Gaza who cannot go outside cannot be play in the
streets now who are hearing constant bombing all around
them children who are dying what are those children going to
grow up to be the ones that survive they're going to be scarred you know and
in the first couple of decades in the 1990s and early 2000s when I was
teaching uh I met people who were elderly who uh as children had gone
through World War II uh in various all kinds of different
capacities um uh some were not just children but also adults and uh horrific
things they'd seen and experienced as uh uh in the bombings of London the
bombings of Dresden the um the holoc cost the concentration caps and um and
what struck me a few different things was um the horror of it and how long it
lasted for people and uh and impacted them even when they were just the toddlers or
couldn't even speak and babies being carried in shelters and bombing around them um uh it seemed to have affected
them for their life and they come on these Retreats having to deal with these deep uh conditions that they were grown
up with so to um to plan for a better future to be
careful and this is the difficult work when the Buddha says establish unethical
people in being ethical I'll read it a little more exactly
um
so what is beautiful abstaining from killing abstaining from taking what is not
giving given abstaining from sexual misconduct abstaining from speaking falsely abstaining from speaking
divisively abstaining from speaking harshly abstaining from speaking
pointlessly abstaining from being avaricious abstaining from hostility Asain abstaining from wrong
View and what is more beautiful than beautiful what is better than
beautiful abstaining from killing and prompting others to abstain from killing
abstaining from taking what is not given and prompting others to abstain from taking what is not given abstain and so
forth all of these this is a very different world that the Buddha wants to live in than a
world where people live in opposition to each other this takes a to do what the Buddha is saying is really difficult in
a sense it's easier to be in opposition it's harder to approach people in such a
way that you prompt them to change how they live is it possible is it realistic
is it uh uh unreasonable to do this given the level of pain and Challenge
and violence that we live certainly the Buddha prefers advocacy like this over
oppositional behaviors he uh when he wants people to
avoid divisive speech the unhealthy unethical device of
speech um he calls this a speech which divides those who are united and stirs
up those who are already divided spoken by a person who loves
factionalism Delights factionalism enjoys factionalism speaks
to create factions um and for people who want to
abstain in order to abstain from uh divisive speech the Buddha emphasizes
creating and perpetuating social Unity
um uniting those who are divided support those who are already United and speak
to create Harmony so this is an explicit call to
make a difference in the world to heal social Discord and
divisiveness it's not shy away from the challenging work of uniting those who
are divided
engaged in three actions are those acting for the welfare of many people
the happiness of many people and the benefit welfare and happiness of many people what three they prompt them in
physical acts of Concord verbal acts of Concord mental acts of
concordion so the Buddha was not trying to change social institutions because there
were none back then in the way that we understand it and uh but what the Buddha lived in
was a world where people had personal connections uh and that's where
information traveled for the most part because there was nothing no writing there was no TV there was no radio It
All Happened orally when people connected to each other and so the world of human connectivity how we connect to
each other was a rich world of where social change could
occur and in a sense we've come closer to that in our modern world where this
phenomenal degree of social media and communication that we have that we've never had before in um spreading so far
this is a world where hostility is being promoted this is a world where perhaps
we can find a way to promote peace I'm very happy happy that for this
that we can use YouTube for these 7 a.m. sittings I don't know all that goes on
on YouTube but uh I've heard that it's not so good a good part of it there's um
some people have suggested we shouldn't be here it's somehow unethical to even be using
YouTube but uh for me this is a platform in which
to try to encourage all of us myself included
to live a more ethical life a life of not harming not just a life of being
peaceful and distressed but a life of being social change agents for the
better so we do the very difficult work work of creating Concord and
unity and and even if we might disagree with others uh we are all committed to
avoiding causing harm and we want to and we encourage people to do that this is
what more beautiful than beautiful so thank
you and um so at least one more talk tomorrow for kind of bringing this this
week to a conclusion and um thank you very
much