good morning good morning IMC Global Sanda nice to see you
I just love looking at all these greetings these warm greetings in the chat
and seeing the weather report from different parts of the country different parts of the world
it got really chilly here in the Bay Area last night and yesterday
so I hope wherever you are you are comfortable dry feeling the warmth and the
friendliness
it's just inspiring to be with all of you
so we are at seven o'clock
Pacific time and um invitation is to
drink in any of the good feelings from the greetings in the chat
and to start to consciously bring those into your heart into your mind and
Savor them Savor them
[Music] enjoy the Refuge of Sangha
and then taking a deep breath or two
allow your gaze to soften
perhaps your eyes to close really intentionally relaxing softening
your eyes
allowing the breathing to return to normal
maybe a slight smile to come to the lips
that softens and relaxes the muscles around the mouth and the face
and softening the tongue
softening the eyes the face the tongue sends a message message to the rest of the body but it's
okay to relax the parasympathetic rest
system
you know tuning to your surroundings
acknowledging whatever is in the space but to occupy In This Moment
perhaps noticing the contact of your feet or your buttocks before we're cushion in her chair
noticing noticing the contact of your skin
against clothing or air
perhaps your hands are touching each other or your lap
allowing allowing yourself to be here immersed in
this moment
and really scanning through your body
noticing any Sensations areas of tension
relaxation [Music] cooler warmth
solidity or spaciousness
turning into the aliveness in the body
the sensations of your body breathing
or perhaps all the little pulsings and tingling and let you know you're alive
[Music]
no scanning through the heart and mind
noticing any contraction or openness there
scatteredness or settlements
and inviting kindness kind awareness of all of it
opening to being generous with
this moment
allowing the heart the mind the attention to settle on
whatever keeps you most easily connected to this moment
breathing sound sensation meta
whatever it is
settling
from time to time relaxing opening further
into the flow into the flow of the moment
inviting the experience of now
foreign
against the mind and hearts that um perhaps knowing noticing knowing
the spaces between be rising the passing and the space
between sound
between and in-breath and in our breath
between thoughts or Sensations
maybe settling softening into the space at the bottom
of the Napa for allowing the next Ingress
to refresh the awareness
foreign
in the final moment so this meditation
the invitation is to soak gather find
any bits of peas kindness patience mindfulness
to intentionally reflect and what has been cultivated here
in these minutes of practice
really drink them into your heart even if it's just a little corner if he's somewhere quiet somewhere
notice it appreciate it so get in
feel it in the heart
and then when you're ready turning your internal gaze
outwards to all of the Myriad people and
creatures your life touches or is even just
can gently in some way in relationship with
and then all of the lives that they are in relationship with outward and outward
gazing upon this vast Matrix of humanity and
kinship of creatures with kindness relishes
dedicating this practice to the benefit of yourself
others in your life and all all beings
foreign [Music]
[Music]
so greetings dear Sangha good morning
and today today we're going to continue on the theme of this week which is
qualities that the Buddha taught that will improve both inner and outer
Harmony over the course of this week in the last two days we've talked about
mindfulness and wisdom of benefiting self
others self and others in the world in our practice through intention and
reflection on how we show up and yesterday we talked about the
individual and relational benefits of kindness loving kindness compassion
good will and today's topic is sharing
just like back in kindergarten when you used to share lunch or shared stickers or treats
it's also known in um through the translations as
non-stinginess generosity
and these are qualities kind of a suite of related qualities that naturally
emerge from mindfulness meta wisdom
sobikuboti renders the poly of this quality in the Sarnia dhamma the
principles of cordiality as to use in common what has been
received to use in common what has been received
and that's perhaps a nice reminder that some of the fundamentals we have in life
we've received without asking without making it happen
life itself we did not will it water air sunshine
nature offers all of this freely
knits the basis on which all else is received right
so to share to share without reservation is
sujatos translation this kind of sharing is a way of
building friendship creating closeness just think about in all cultures all
over the world breaking bread together or sharing a bowl of rice together is a way of building social connection
and often a way of inspiring reciprocity too right this kind of generosity and reciprocity
was woven into the culture of the Buddha and his followers it's a tradition that
lasts to this day and it's been around for millennia can imagine
back in Ancient India the monastics supported laypeople citizens with teaching presence wisdom
advice and the way people would support the monastics with food and requisites
third Psalm that kind of reciprocity and sharing persists now it's really touching to see
it in Asian countries especially but the tier here in California here in the United States
all over the world you can imagine
that in a generosity dependent group like the ancient Sangha of the Buddha's
followers generosity and sharing were really important very dependent upon others for
the meal that ends up in your bowl and maybe your friend doesn't get enough you share with them
there's a story of one young monastic I'm just going to call him puku
who had really learned this well early on so he had never met the Buddha but was
completely inspired by the teachings that he had heard that sort of rippled through India through other followers
and he had received teachings from one of these and ordained as a monk and was practicing with a lot of
sincerity and was inspired to go up to North India traveling by foot to
join the crowds to hear the Buddha teaching so the way that worked the way it still
works if monastic's do this kind of wandering practice is there
um asking or being invited to sleep in people's backyards in a garage and a
shed under an overhang as they move around
and so fuku had received permission from a friendly Merchant in some Village
somewhere to set up for the night in the woodshed and so
he and his few belongings were there and right about the time maybe sundown
another stranger came to the door and politely asked said the merchant said
that if it's okay with you I might stay here too total stranger puku
just bowed smiled and said yes welcome shared his space
and the two of them turns out we're both in this tradition of the Buddha's early
teachings and they set up in opposite corners of the shed and both of them sat up and
practiced most of the night and pooka's practice was on fire he was
sitting and this stranger was quite impressed
with the strength of his practice and the open-hearted generous non-stingy
nature of his sharing of the space but little he had
well the stranger turns out was the Buddha and come morning when they both woke
he began without introducing himself he just asked would you like to receive some teachings and puku said yes of
course and the Buddha began to expound on his teachings and at some point not
very far in puku realized who was talking to him and he was just overcome with gratitude
Joy so in his travels to go see this famed
esteemed teacher amidst the crowds his generosity allowed for
this beautiful meeting one on one sharing of the Dharma
so you just never know what kind of beauty might open up
through an invitation through a generosity
this kind of sharing can take many forms right in the Buddha's case it was the
sharing of physical space time teaching
it can also be an expression of respect to share attention or share credit with
another person it can be the generosity of receiving
feedback honestly and adjusting my behavior or my manner
this is a kind of generosity of spirit generosity of spirit towards our own
experience and towards the experience of others
it's a kind open way of seeing Humanity
the good qualities and the foibles our own and others internal and external
personal and relational
you can even be an act of generosity to be vulnerable enough to share our
vulnerability enough to receive others generosity
modern science Bears this out it might seem counter-intuitive but allowing
other people to be generous builds trust it builds friendship and relationships that doesn't mean
grabbing and asking or demanding but to
be open be real be allowing and be open to the generosity and the beauty of
others it helps build relationships it helps
build trust and from a Dharma perspective allowing others to be generous
is generous because it allows them to build this very beneficial quality of
heart and mind and spirit generosity non-stinginess isn't just
reciprocity as beautiful as reciprocity is it's also an open hand
a letting go and that that is a powerful foundation
for the deeper forms of letting go into Liberation itself
perhaps that's why the Buddha said and this is a quote if beings knew as I
knew the results of giving and sharing they would not eat without having given
nor with the stain of miserliness overcome their minds even if it were their last bite their last mouthful
they wouldn't eat without having shared if there was someone to receive the gift
so there's attitude this inner posture of sharing and generosity
it's so helpful to mindfulness meditation all along the path
it can be helpful to recall our own acts of generosity
That's the basis for a peaceful heart peaceful mind very different than the
memory of a bit of stinginess right generosity also lends itself to openness
which as a trait and it's a learnable trait is a vital importance in spiritual
growth psychological and emotional resilience and just general happiness
greater openness towards whatever arises in the heart in the mind
allows what needs to be seen or heard or healed
to be metabolized to transform to move through
some this generous kind of mindfulness
in a sense it's an openness to seeing all all of what is in the heart
the mind the path and with kindness and with discernment
of what's afflictive or beneficial to ourselves to others to ourselves and others and to
all this kind of open generous attention ultimately Frees
leads to Freedom so for the next 24 hours if you are open
to some homework perhaps just notice how sharing
a spirit of generosity benefits you others
yourself and others or The Wider context in which you find
yourself can talk about it write about it just notice it
and maybe in your own heart and mind link it to how does this relate to
practicing with wisdom and mindfulness how does this relate to
practicing and showing up with kindness
so we've reached the end of our time thank you thank you very much for your
practice so just very quickly
dedicate our practice here together this Global Sangha to the benefit and Welfare of all beings
everywhere may all beings be free
[Laughter]
foreign