hello everyone hello and welcome to Happy here and if you can hear me okay
give me a thumbs up adios okay fantastic great
so I start by saying hello welcome to happy hour lovely to see you to be with
you and uh my name is Nikki I'm in Mountain View California and who would like to
say hi and help warm up the space
visitors from Michigan hi Desiree and hi Neil very good
this is Barbara in the Alameda hi Barbara salaam Ali from L.A hello
Ali from LA and hi Bill in Dallas hello this is Bill and Chad hi
hi it's Kim from tofina British Columbia hello hi good good to be with you from
um speaking for our or showing up as our Canadian contingent
good to be with you Kim hello Corey from Prague hi Kari this is
Prague Prague Czechoslovakia oh wow what time is it right now it is 3 A.M and I happen
to wake up and get a notification that this was occurring [Laughter]
oh it's uh that's sweet that's sweet so well
um it'll be calming enough so that you can hopefully be uh going back to sleep
through the meditation lovely that you're joinings is just lovely
hi this is Vicki from L from Oakland hi Vicky from Oakland good to be with you
and hi and hello here from Wendy San Diego and on YouTube we have friends
joining us and uh and uh e m Tina says
hi from Thailand Bangkok time 9 00 a.m good morning to you on on YouTube Sweet
well feels like the Sangha has assembled so let's let's begin let's begin
thank you Neil for posting information about the happy hour Google groups in
chat if you are new to happier we have a um low traffic Google Groups for you to
join and hi Stuart from Caracas yes we are absolutely International right now
from many places in the world very very sweet so
um I change the settings right now my muting won't become possible and also I
change the the chat settings on Zoom so that the chat will only come to me
but I ask that we keep that channel quiet um because it can be quite distracting
and last but not least I turn on the recording for the sake of Audio Dharma
here we go out okay sweet so hello hello dear Sangha dear
International Sangha so sweet to get all the hellos from all these different time
zones joining each other to practice so
so for our theme for practice for this moment in time
I'd like to um invite us to consider
um the cultivation of appreciating that support support is available support is
available support is available and support available internally
available externally there are many sources of support internally that
sometimes when things are challenging in our lives we may not we may forget the
support the sources of support that are available internally and of course externally many sources of support
and through remembering through remembering this goodness of support we
can tie back into we can connect back into the uh sense of Goodwill kindness
goodness that's available for us internally and externally that we are
held in so that is our way in tonight and of course I will say a lot more
um during the meditation and I think that's enough of a frame so let's just dive in
and practice together so so I'd like to invite us all to settle
to settle and arrive to settle in your seat
in your sit bones however you are sitting or lying down or
maybe standing if that's what's appropriate right now
and turning your gaze inward connecting with the breath the
sensations of the breath the lower abdomen
and letting letting awareness be spacious and receive receive the breath
sensations of the breath relaxing softening letting go of whatever is not needed in
this moment letting yourself be simple
space of the heart the mind to be simple
and if thoughts are rising saying hello
serving as entertainment distraction plans it's
okay it's all right
you see them smilingly thank you thank you for trying to plan or remember
or reminiscent please come back later not now
I'm giving my whole heart in this moment to this practice my whole heart
just the spread in this body in this moment
calming soothing settling with each breath
that this breath in this moment be nourishing all that's needed all that's needed nothing more
just awareness loving awareness and the breath sensations of the breath that's
all
let awareness be your support recognize it as support
kind awareness this breath
knowing the breath of support
like a lifeline
can you lean into rest in the support of this breath in breath out breath in this
moment and knowing of it can you lean into it
feel it's supporting you filling your whole heart body
the breath I support bringing a sense of
stability integrity inner support
thank you
and now can we turn the awareness or knowing to know the body the feet and
the Earth you're sitting on a cushion your legs on the earth their sense of connected to
the Earth sitting this body not moving stability stability of support
ability of the body calming supportive
and while we stay embodied appreciating the support of the breath the body's
stability
let us bring awareness to one strength one Inner Strength source of strength we have
internal which is a source of support and could be anything
maybe you tend to be persistent
or curious
or gentle with yourself kind yourself and others
understanding
or anything else praying to mind this source of inner support
maybe you reach out for support
bringing this strength source of inner strength to mind
and breathe with it feel its goodness your support available internally
and breathe not to think about this source of inner strength it's not a rumination it's not an invitation
you think but to breathe with this strength
you feel it in your bones in your heart
maybe with just one word
now if you will opening the door
of the home of our hearts too those who support us bring them to you to your
hearts home to your mind's eye
maybe some family friends
sources of support people who appreciate you see you see
your strength maybe you're rooting for you maybe it's simply
they wish you well they wish you well they're well-wishers
and it's okay if they're alive or passed away seen or unseen
breathing in the Goodwill the support
again not ruminating thinking planning just feeling breathing with
the sense of Goodwill support that's available
and maybe it helps to just see them looking at you with kind eyes maybe bring each
person each being
front and center see them looking at you with Goodwill with care
receiving the support
letting yourself feel supported receiving the good will the kindness
it's available now and has been available in the past Maybe some people from your past
you're not thinking so much but maybe some people show up
in your mind's eye feeling their Goodwill feeling the continuation of your good will of their Goodwill
there may be people from the future you haven't met yet with whom you are your life is
intertwined Through Time
feeling their Goodwill such a network such a net of support support is
available
and not allowing yourself to feel the support both internal from your inner resources
body breath awareness your strengths your values all resources
of support as well as external people in your life resources maybe if you have aches and
pains yes there are medical professionals perhaps available you can reach out to support
support internal external
there are challenges in life of course everybody's life has challenges
of course and there is support
maybe in the last few minutes also consider the people you
have supported beings you have supported that you are support for others have
been are and will be
and that can bring a sense of strength
know your own goodness and being of support
foreign
as in the movie It's a Wonderful Life where the angel
shows the protagonist what the world would have been like had they not been there
without their support maybe a couple of vignettes come up for you
so he can appreciate the support you have given to others
source of support
that you have been a sense of Goodwill appreciation for this being who is you
now letting go of all these Reflections letting go of all the reflections just coming back
to the body to the breath to awareness awareness is
Premier support the power of knowing knowing the breath knowing Sensations
knowing thoughts knowing Consciousness is amazing
support power of knowing
as we bring this practice period to a close let us
share the goodness of our practice the goodness of our heart
all the support we've received the support we've given the goodness of all of that our cultivation
sharing it with the world may all beings everywhere
including myself be well feel supported
feel the support that's available in the world and May
we all be of support to one another may all beings be well may all beings be
free
thanks everyone thanks for your practice and the support of your practice both
for yourself and for the community
so report so many sources of support
internal external our own goodness
external the beings we're connected to the way we have supported them such a
party there's so much support so much support wow my heart feels more full after this
meditation feeling the support that's available and and this being is a
source of support their sense of uprightness goodness oh yes I play my part in this in
in this interconnected world so So speaking of support being support for
others and allowing others to support you when small groups as we transition into
them as a way of supporting each other's practice showing up and be supported
showing up and be supported and appreciating enjoying that support
and the question the inquiry tonight is
for each person to name one source of support internal or external and then
the next person and then the next person it can be like a celebration celebrating all these sources of support and people
might name some things you haven't even thought about like oh yeah that is the source of support in my life
um can be quite quite inspiring this practice Above and Beyond in the the things that
I've shared and mentioned so so the invitation is in the small groups
again showing up with support showing up with the intention to support each other
yourselves and um and sing and again will go around each
person sharing one then the next person and then the next person then I'll come to you again sharing something else as a
source of support and then going around and round can again be quite inspiring not asking questions not directing but
just showing up you can also show up with silence and say I'm showing up with Silence of offering my awareness and
support and that's perfectly fine you don't have to speak you can show up
um and and offer your your presence um
be kind to each other be kind to yourself propose those are the important
things to remember so I'm going to open the rooms right now if it's possible for you
to turn on your camera in the group that would be wonderful so that you can
actually see each other if it's not possible it's okay let's go alphabetical
order and uh and enjoy enjoy the support here
we go
okay their rooms are closed everybody's back and we have some time for any uh
Reflections aha moments um questions challenges what did you
discover in this practice either the guided meditation as you explored on your own or in the group as you explore
sources of support especially if you haven't spoken recently I'd like to ask you first to uh
to pull forward into the brave space
sharing your insights bill please
uh some of our group mentioned something that I'm not maybe I misunderstood what I
heard or maybe I got it right but the idea occurred to me of supporting Myself by supporting others like my doing
volunteer work and that sort of thing so yeah thank you beautiful yeah thank you I
love that yeah that is a strong support yeah beautiful beautiful when we give we
actually receive so much and the volunteer work is definitely an example yeah red please
I I think I'm uh stating the obvious but I just want to State it anyway that this
exercise just brought forward this extraordinary structure of support uh
that was you know largely human and uh you know if I would have had time to get beyond
all those people for whom I feel such gratitude for their support then there
would have been a whole bunch of other non-human supports too you know like the the road that I can step out on and the
fact that the mail comes or all these things but but also um the fact that I've have the opportunity
I've had the opportunity in in big ways and I hope we'll continue to have the
opportunity to be of support to other people and and it's both of those things that are really important
um and I I feel like I can't quite express it all but just the the depth of support the Love by so many people
um I'm just really grateful for that thank you thank you Fred
you put it so well so well thank you the as you said it wasn't quite the
obvious that you said I think there are many nuances that you added uh and and
you put it eloquently so thank you for speaking so uh Ali please
yeah thank you thank you for the uh exercise I'm beginning to see the uh
the goodness that I have and then the support that I have for me I mean what is right with me versus what's wrong
which has been like deeply conditioned yeah yeah thank you Ellie and that's
that is so common for all of us human beings it's the it's the conditioning we
have to turn towards what's missing what's bad what's negative it's it's it's
for all of us humans we turn to toward do we turn towards that more more than
towards what's good what's what's working what's great so yes welcome to welcome to Being Human Ellie
and it's wonderful to to to try to of course this is part of what we practice
in happy hour try to turn to the goodness Marianne
and yours will be the last reflection okay thank you so being not not being
very used to this uh like you say it's kind of human to look at the other side
of it I found it wonderful and I was excited and I noticed I was excited to
do it I and I noticed I had a hard time keeping it
non-egotistical that I I had to continually like remind
myself oh let's steer it back to just what we're grateful for not what we you
know might be proud of or something like that yeah so anyway that was interesting yeah yeah
okay thank you yeah because I think as it's a new a newer thing yeah yeah and and I do appreciate
um and and so so glad that you spoke up because this is an important discrimination to make it's a it's it's
an it's a uh uh it it's a it's a takes sensitivity
to notice what you noticed to notice that oh yeah okay now we're