great okay all right so uh so let's begin
let's begin by uh
arriving together and uh acknowledging that this this is a Sangha we practice
together not alone fellow human beings who support us
by showing up we support them and by their showing up they support us and
there's this Sweetness in that there's such a Sweetness in that if I was just here alone staring into the camera
talking to imaginary people it would be very different from me just just so that
I share that with you and and as I look and see your faces it just warms my
heart and you guys are welcome actually to to put it on gallery views so that you can see each other it's quite sweet
to get a sense of yeah this Sango that has assembled these uh wonderful beings were coming
together to just practice and support each other support each other just by
your presence so so I'll leave this theme into our
meditation tonight and um yeah without
further Ado let's um let's let's begin let's let's sit together so it's
arriving in your body seeing what your body needs if it needs to shift and move
a little bit if the shoulders need to be rolled back a little bit maybe side to side the whole body to find your
center of gravity ah arriving and settling
arriving and selling in this body
here I am here
foreign
our feet on the Earth sit Bones on
cushion her hands on her lap
ah party alive and breathing
what's happening right now internally letting go of any assumptions
presumptions and meet meet this moment meet this body
with fresh eyes as a beginner
curious interested
if you're meeting your body from the inside internally for the first time
and relaxing relaxing the body and receiving
receiving the sensations
receiving the sensations with interest with openness of heart
as if you're opening your heart to your home making space
welcoming all Sensations
and your awareness is so welcoming
is a good host gracious host that welcomes everything
welcomes every sensation feeling
whether they're Pleasant unpleasant or neither
whether they're familiar sensations of the breath
or notice for the first time perhaps differently
your awareness is kind welcomes welcomes everything
foreign
s between the hands cool and warmth
um there's space for you yes come
hello welcome sensations of the forehead a little tight it's okay we love you
anyway come
hello sensations of sit bones hard resolved expansive heavy
light tired however you are the sit bones
feeling the chair the cushion
Welcome All You Sensations welcome
so nice to meet you In This Moment
so nice to feel you
thank you
foreign
[Music] shoulders
maybe a little tight it's okay welcome welcome
nice to feel you nice to see you foreign
[Music]
attention awareness this host Hostess gracious host hostess
this wholeheartedness welcoming
all Sensations
foreign
particularly calming and soothing nourishing they can be
[Music] hospitality
it's gracious kind wholeheartedness awareness opening its doors
um yes there is room for you awareness so vast so spacious
your heart the home of your heart so spacious there's room for everything all
Sensations
you know all sounds it's okay it can all be just
as they are arising and passing there's room for you
sensation sounds foreign
foreign
attitude of spaciousness welcoming
this gracious host it's your awareness
same attitude towards Sensations
sounds feeling expansive sounds coming and going in our thoughts
don't need to be entangled with them
same spaciousness you had with with sounds
giving them space they come and they go same way with thoughts
nothing wrong with thinking don't make an enemy of it let it come
and go
there is room for everything you don't have to become stuck
become tiny in a thought plenty of space
in your heart and your mind spacious as the sky
love her cloudy a cloud a fluffy cloud of thought can
come and go on this vast sky
it's welcome
oh welcome
not going to fish for them but if they couldn't go
friendliness with everything
even if their thoughts of self-judgment can you be friendly towards them thank
you you're really trying to just be helpful thank you I don't have to be entangled
start believing you you can come and go thank you
spacious welcoming all
without clinging
friendly kind host that's your heart of awareness
foreign
let them come let them go let's go let them go
let them go with kindness
the spaciousness friendliness with hallows friendliness
with goodbyes
elephants fall Sensations in the body
all sounds all thoughts
all states are mind state of heart
friendly friendly there's room for you to welcome there's room for you
foreign
thank you
can there be friendliness and there be friendliness
with different beings in your life in your mind's eye
they're really inviting them as if you're hosting a big party
your awareness your heart your mind heart is hosting this big party
um welcome welcome it's room for you dear friends
family
my Sangha welcome hi
he realized there is so much room so much space in your heart it's Limitless
for people you know and love
people you know a little bit people you don't know at all
but you wish them well with Goodwill
and even people you have challenges with you may be surprised that your heart is
spacious enough your gracious host enough
you're welcome everyone with kindness
actually strengthens your heart and stability
of its own courage
the particular strength that comes from kindness
and maybe in your mind even you welcome you greet
though the challenges or difficulties you have in your life right now you
greet them you welcomed them there is room enough in your heart spacious enough
your stable spacious beyond your imagination there's room enough in this
castle of your heart and so why does spaciousness the sky
welcome challenges hi there's room for you welcome hide
as we turn to bring this meditation together to close
as much as it's available at your heart your mind feel as spacious as the sky
with goodness capacity strength
and your kind awareness to be with everything to be with kindness
kind awareness to welcome everything it's possible
possible for you
May there be every goodness in your heart and your mind spaciousness
stability equanimity
strength spiritual strength to serve you
serve your loved ones and for your goodness to serve all
beings everywhere in ways you cannot imagine
May our cultivation our expansion expanding our hearts
in goodness and wisdom and kindness be of service
goodness to freedom of all beings everywhere including myself
may all beings be well may all things be free
thanks everyone thanks for your spacious practice welcoming everything
with kindness it's so fun to have a party right and
welcome all Sensations all thoughts just their
space their space it's okay then we realize our kept capacity or strength
there's a sense of stability yes yes challenges come there's room for you
I've got this yes it's the sense of resilience that can arise from that kind
openness that doesn't arise from pushing away like I'm afraid of this I don't know what I'm gonna do or this piece
there's room for you there's a room yes yes there's a sense of resilience really
that can arise that can serve us and I can serve others [Music] um so so thank you for practicing in any
way then hopefully it it supported you
so I'd like to invite us to uh to say yes say yes
to say yes with kindness and welcome meeting
couple of fellow practitioners yes hi there's enough room in my zoom Square
for for a couple of you come hi welcome so that's so be a gracious host to each
other let's try that on for side that's when the rubber meets the road so opening up
high the sense of hospitality to each other what if we meet each other
as gracious hosts our awareness meet each other as gracious hosts we're all
welcoming each other into our spaces you know right we're all welcoming each
other into our homes in a way it's you know with our backgrounds and it's it's
a very intimate thing we're not at a meditation center when everybody comes together we're all coming to each
other's homes so in a way it's like oh take a moment when you go into small groups maybe go around first and welcome
just each person will welcome the other person Welcome to My All welcome to Myspace and just go around and just the
sense of welcoming just welcoming each other um and so that would be their first
round meeting meeting each other with welcoming with a sense of kindness and
see what might arise or might be playfulness right the playfulness of meeting the unexpected we never know
what's going to happen the next moment and then go go another round again each person can share something don't don't
direct don't ask questions just show up show up with your kindness with your hospitality
um hello welcome and if you like you can share something about how this practice was for you maybe just a nugget maybe
just 30 seconds and then the next person and the next person that would be the second round or you can say pass so the
first round you welcome each other to your space and have fun with it this is kind of why not I don't know if you've
ever done that before on zoo yeah well welcome to my home I have a virtual background but hey welcome welcome to
Myspace welcome to my virtual Zoom space um so so have fun with it how lovely it
is to be able to practice with others so
excuse me okay so I have created this the the
rooms the zoom rooms and invite you all to uh to take care of each other with
kindness and here we go opening all the ropes
the rooms will close in about 10 seconds we'll wait for everyone to come back
okay your rooms are closed everybody's back welcome back everyone
um we have time for a couple of Reflections especially if you have not spoken recently invite you to pull
forward if you've spoken well back make space for others so what was it like the
meditation you can reflect on that and the AHA moments challenges and also um
how was I was welcoming you to being a gracious host to each other with
kindness meaning and greeting each other with kindness can also put your Reflections in chat if you wish if you
type them to everyone I'll read your name just type them to me and I'll um
it'll be private Jamie says we had a love party oh my God that is so sweet we
had a love party I love it that's that's sweet ah
any other reflections Fernanda and and friend said I thought
it was just us that's great uh rain says he was delightful and I
want to thank you can you unmute me yes I can let's see how uh hold on I need to
ask you wait hold on oh no uh can you raise your hand I uh it's hard to find
you hold up because I see you very okay here I'm gonna look for you there you
are I'm gonna ask you to unmute there um I've been meaning to thank you from
January 23rd it was a Monday night that you had us envisioned going somewhere
and I went to my sister's home on Long Island so not only do I feel like we had a great time tonight where my Gene and
fossil we did great tours but how this extended to my sister and it was like 10
o'clock her time and I really visited her gave her tea and she just felt so
loved the next morning I text her and she's like I go did you notice anything about 10 o'clock your time she goes oh
my God yes I felt so comforted but for me it was so great because I used that
night to visit her I don't get to see her enough and see I imagine seeing her
husband and her son and it was so yummy not just my room but it reminded me of
that night as well tonight's meditation so thank you oh thank you it was so
sweet I was thank you so much for sharing that the Delights in vicarious
Joy I'm feeling lots of mudita vicarious joy for your practice for the sweetness
tonight and that night with your sister so sweet so sweet thank you
um and let's see uh fazel says it was really nice here's one of your your uh
uh co-partiers Denise says was Jamie's love party in his car apparently yes we
have a thumbs up that is great and let's see here oh
Jamie says it was yusels okay and Charlie says awareness is a gracious host unlock the spaciousness I didn't
know was available it's a great way to describe awareness to those I love who
don't practice oh beautiful thank you Charlie that's lovely yay oh that's just
great yeah what a beautiful weight share this your practice with with your loved
ones uh yeah yeah and Greg says it's my first time I want to say so Greg I need to
look for you hold on there you are Greg okay now you can unmute
so I I also wanted to say thank you and it was wonderful to hear your voice I
was at your Marana Sati retreat in December and it was absolutely
transformational for me my life is one thousand percent better
and I don't know why it took me so long to come to your happy hour but here I am and I'm just so happy to be here
ah thank you Greg thank you so much for your practice oh it gosh it makes me so
happy speaking of Marana Sati mindfulness of death um if I die today it would be worthwhile
this life of service would have been worthwhile so thank you so much for for sharing your practice and coming to
happy hour yeah and keep coming that's so great I will I will thanks for
sharing it just makes me so happy to know the retreat was uh was transformational and supportive for you
yay yay and Fernanda says I felt very joyous to meet the inside of my hands
and my arms and welcome them to my party oh that is so great that's I love it
meeting the inside of your hands and arms it's just there's so many ways we can welcome thoughts and Sensations and
tightness in the body and others just beautiful so beautiful yeah appreciation
begets abundance yes exactly author of breeding sweet grass
you are so welcome thank you Fernanda and friends for joining thank you all
for your practice tonight thank you for welcoming
um yourselves all parts of you in welcoming each other welcoming being
welcoming yes awareness as a gracious host thank you all so grateful thank you
for welcoming me to the Sangha I'm and I welcome all of you it's just a mutual
right we welcome each other thank you for your practice what a gift what a gift this Sangha is to me thank you well
may may we all be free may all beings be free
take good care be well see you on Monday