so hello and welcome everyone to this edition of happy hour
so um last time Monday um
we started with the meditation I didn't say too many words to frame it
um and it was relatively Quiet One inviting the nourishment of
settling in of of Peace of quiet as an expression of meta and and many of you
expressed enthusiasm for for having another similar uh happy hour
so so let's see let's see how it goes tonight I'm not gonna say much similar
to Monday let's explore together let's see what arises exploring silence as
nourishment of meta uh and and meta okay so let's begin
let's begin our practice our formal practice of meditation together
ah
you're sitting in a chair
letting your body be afraid
not uptight but upright no tightness needed in the muscles
but the sense of Integrity in your posture
and if you need to lie down that's okay or stand up
to standing meditation that's perfectly fine as well
I'm gonna give the instructions assuming you're you're sitting though so assuming you're sitting
feeling your sit Bones on the chair and the cushion
paying attention [Music]
foreign
attention to the body how are you buddy how are you in this
moment in time greeting greeting your body
the kindness it's worked so hard all day
how are you body pay attention foreign
places in the body that are really tired heavy
maybe tight maybe achy
can you greet them welcome them to be just as they are
maybe there are parts of the body that are feeling good comfortable warm
light
invite them too
to be as they are
and also inviting the body I said wanted to relax a little bit let
go of tightness and tension
listen listen carefully
listen spaciously
listen spaciously with your heart
to the body
and the listening here is metaphor for paying attention spaciously
listen spaciously
through the sensations of the breath in the body in the abdomen
with another sensation in the body is louder it's okay listen to that
listen to that wholeheartedly
listen lovingly body
to the breath
nothing needs to happen
be just to listen
foreign
but
if their thoughts are rising can listen to the Ark of them coming and
going not the content the content isn't needed right now
the fact that thinking might be happening thank you thoughts not now
I'm listening to the body to this
amazing dear body that is the tuning fork really
it resonates
with emotions with mind States
it's a tuning fork I want to take care of
attend to caringly
relaxing relaxing the body
for the next out breath
and lovinglyless
listen to the sensations
they are loud and clear can you hear them
can you sense them
thank you
come interested become curious
become fascinated
by listening the body relax
rest back rest and listen
this is an expression of mitta to care be present for to listen
our body just as it is
and if thoughts arise take you away from the body not a
problem release them smilingly
listening to their Ark coming and going
and not entangled listening to the body
giving your heart
the body can teach you Stillness the body can teach you patience
kindness pay attention all you need to know is already here
already here
foreign
it is an expression of care of matter
be present for the present or pay attention to
spaciously listen
this body right here
with loving kindness
foreign
thank you
meta can show up in so many ways and flavors
spacious deep listening kind presence
is one way it shows up
can we express that for our bodies for this being whose me
In This Moment
listening listening to the sensations
the Lullaby of the breath
foreign
thank you
the body is a great teacher
pay attention relax the tension
the attention to the Stillness
silence between the notes
in this body
foreign
and as we begin to bring this practice session to a close
opening up your sphere of awareness a little wider
not just where your body seemingly ends
border of your skin but as if your body was more extensive
more expensive part of the air the space around it and
Beyond
listening spaciously internally externally
this being who is Me In This Moment In Time interconnected
and vast unfathomable ways
eternally externally
so much more I this being who is me is so much more
and Where'd I take it to be
connected supporting others being supported by
others appreciating perhaps with all this vast
Universe inside and outside and offering our goodness
or care or deep listening to the world as a gift
as we listen to ourselves as we can be more present to ourselves with meta
we can be more present for others with meta
may all beings everywhere including myself be safe
happy healthy heavy may all beings be free
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
so so what we did tonight was
a practice of meta as deep listening
as presence deep listening internally for to this
body listening to the sensations of
sensations of the pharah and really being a good student being a
good student of the body the body is attuning Fork as I mentioned the meditation when there are
State of Mind states of heart emotions etc etc etc the body like a tuning for
resonates so the more we get to pay attention and be present for with meta
without pushing things aside in a way like I don't want to listen to that no let me listen to that let me listen
to it all even if it's quote-unquote bad news I want to know I want to be present for it
all so tonight our expression of meta our practice of meta was deep listening
deep listening to this body Sensations and one then the mind can get quite calm
settled with this deep spacious listening to the
sensations there's a lot of Stillness in the body in between the vibrations
and all that as I was describing it like the silence between the notes as if it
were music so paying attention so
like to open up the space or any Reflections questions
comments anything you might have discovered or noticed
denied with this practice offered for both your own benefit and the benefit of
others bill says when you spoke of seeing
thoughts come and go without becoming entangled in the thoughts themselves I
had a real problem with doubt not sure how I can do that ah okay
um I appreciate the question pal so
so it takes some practice but consider a stance he stands of
um not entanglement into the thought but knowing I mean thoughts can come and go
and and at first maybe you realize it later after you've been entangled into thought it's okay then oh yeah I was
gonna be unentangled oh it's okay but in that last moment become aware of the
thought disappearing going away so start there it starts there
and then little by little while you're in the middle of the thought when you're still
entangled then this awareness comes like oh I'm entangled or can I just see
can I just step back and see thinking is happening like oh no no no no no no no they can be a little bit of space and
then through this practice then you can see yeah thoughts are coming and going
when the mind gets a little more settled without getting entangled from the beginning but it happens step by step by
step you can just do the whole thing um at once start when you just wake up
having been entangled and thinking for a while start noticing the thought going
away so that's the place to start Bill and that that way your confidence will
be built in this practice little by little you are welcome
Richard I see your hand
oh my God yes uh you know there's always different
Sensations in the body but there's also different sort of ways of being in the body or being the body
like a gang gang thing a very passive thing a very active thing
uh it's like every week every state of emotion and
thought you know just sort of shows up differently
yes yeah there are lots of different ways but being in the body and tonight
I was specifically inviting you guiding you to
to relax and to listen spaciously that
was the key word to listen to the body spaciously that spacious way of listening
that it was an unentangled way of listening it's a particular way of
paying attention and also I was bringing the sense of Meta Care with this with
this presence with this spacious presence uh I'll try I'll try yeah great thank
you thanks Richard yeah there are so many ways
any other Reflections or questions before we transition
any aha moments perhaps you hide
being present for this body this deep listening
spacious listening Jesse please
yeah thanks Nikki for this practice um yeah this was great you know this deep
listening practice I've done some day language sheets with you before on
concentration practice and which usually use the breath as a meditation object but this this felt
really different and I'm just wondering if you could maybe compare and contrast
samata or shamata practice with this this mindful deep listening that you presented tonight thank you yeah yeah
thank you so much Jesse yeah um so
practice often translate as concentration where the mind gets still
when we keep coming back to an object and usually in the west we use the
breath for this practice though there are many different objects and by the
way in February 4th and 5th I'm teaching a white Casino which is a different way
of developing concentrations on my skin schedule if you go to my website
nickymergaforia.com but um the body is also another way to
cultivate concentration settling the mind the sensations of the body are
definitely a concentration object and tonight with this invitation for deep
listening and I was talking about listening to the Stillness the silence between the notes that was an invitation
for the mind to settle into some idea actually uh the Stillness yeah exactly
right on Jesse great thank you thank you
Elaine says I really enjoy turning tuning into my body and getting a break
from my thinking mind lovely another practitioner
says thank you this was much needed I felt a sense of ease amidst the physical
pain I've been feeling lately um thank you for sharing that Sandra says
it was nice to quiet my mind and turn into the body at the end of the busy day
yes he asks how can one stay with the practice in a Rowdy environment for
example kids are Rowdy and shouting caregivers are screening Etc do we just
try to extend the meta to all of them as well yes yes exactly so this practice of deep
listening when we practice when it's not so rowdy perhaps around and we get to
listen then we can take this to where it is rowdy and we can still listen to our
our own heart our own mind when there's a lot happening externally as well as
extend our full presence to others and listen to them without
toppling over it all starts internally and then of course it extends to to all
beings everyone whether they're Rowdy or shouting Etc
thank you for the reflections everyone so not like to invite us to engage in
small groups in the Sangha breakout groups and then the question for
tonight's reflection and you can choose to reflect you can choose to just be silent uh offer your
silent presence is um this this tuning this tuning into the
body listening deeply into the body this um
this act of listening um
is there what what supports your deep listening
to the body and what challenge is it what supports it and what challenge is
it what is supportive what's challenging so what's supportive might be oh yeah an environment that's not so loud uh maybe
a guided meditation is supported no it's not supportive is when I maybe when I
try to push and I'm really really tensing up to listen to my body I
realize actually it's counterproductive anyway so your Reflections your mileage might vary but what's supportive maybe
one thing and one thing that's not supportive that you discover and maybe you have one and not the other like the
other one I don't know what's not supportive or what's supportive I'm still exploring this you can just hold
space for others so so with that I'd like to invite us to
to here we go the breakout rooms I'm going
to create them now so as always please just offer it and Reflection from
yourself and make space for others not asking questions not directing and let's go alphabetical order just offer
something maybe you say pass the next person next person he'll come back to you go around and around
take care of yourselves take care of each other here we go
okay the rooms are all closed everybody is back and it's seven o'clock so
um I wonder if there's any very quick Reflections from what you learned maybe something surprising or discover uh
surprising like a 30 second reflection someone who hasn't spoken Ali please
hello thank you for uh on your teachings and and sharing with us uh
what came up with me is just like I mostly in the mind but this thing is more I mean with the body it's more
solid and I can just feel the sensations rather than the you know stuff in the mind is like more ephemeral harder to
catch so thank you for that reflection I just going to practice more staying with the
body beautiful thank you so much Ellie thank you for your practice and sharing that reflection it's so fresh and the
way you shared it for the benefit of everyone beautiful so thank you and thank you all for your practice may all
beings everywhere be free including ourselves foreign
thank you Nikki thank you thanks everyone so I'm going to stop