morning everyone and welcome and both everyone who is might be watching
on YouTube hello and I've been away for a month or so
it's nice to be back here with all of you here
and um I was a way of doing a month-long
Retreat and and I was really on my own new cabin up in
the series but I had one uh discourse with the Buddha that went
through my mind that I reviewed and was kind of inspiration for it and so I'd like to share that with you
today and um there's a Core teaching of the Buddha
that this that's given in this course it's not by the Buddha it's he gave it
but then someone a disciple is repeats it in the context of the story
and the story is interesting I mean the teaching is particularly powerful and it's said to be teachings
from the Buddha that was kind of the Genesis of what of Zan of Mahayana
Buddhism of this famous philosopher nagarjuna so it's a very very very very
significant teaching but the fact that it's in this wider context of the story is nice
and the story has to do with a monk named Chana and China had been a monk for
it could be 45 years and and he was distraught for a number
of reasons for one of them after 45 years of being a monk in the time of the Buddha he still was an enlightened
he still didn't hit his language he knew the teachings but he had not seen the
teachings and uh just learning the teaching is one thing but to see that see it for
yourself and your direct experience that's a whole other thing but not only had he not seen the
teaching discovered and experienced it for himself he apparently was a bit of a troubled
man so many of you have heard of him in without his name if you've heard the
story of the Buddha how he left the palace is a prince and he went with his
charioteer out into the streets he was he was given a kind of a protected life and somehow able to leave the palace
compound and his Chariot here took him out into the streets and there he encountered What's called the four
Heavenly Messengers he saw someone who was sick someone who was old someone who had died and then he
saw a monastic renunciant and he never seen those before so it's
kind of unusual in the world to have people um
Nazi sickness old age and death though many people in the modern world United
States don't see it very brightly especially death and things are put away
coincidentally the first time I ever saw a dead body in my life was when I was 11
years old in Nepal which is where the Buddha went out I was out in the streets
and there was this young child wrapped in blanket being carried to the river to
be burned and so the Buddha who was 29 supposedly
and so the charioteer his name was Chana this is the man who became a monk and
the story is that he was born around the same time as the Buddha born of a servant maybe a servant in the
palace and so probably the Chana and the Buddha grew up together probably they were
friends they'd known each other for and um and then to make it more
kind of powerful this connection from the Buddha and China when the Buddha
then eventually escaped to the palace and went to renounce his royalty and go off into down from the area of Foothills
to the Himalayas down into the plains of where he did a spiritual seeking as a
renunciant um Chana took him on the first leg of
that Journey took him out to the edges of the Kingdom I guess and then uh we would have said okay you
can leave me here and he took off his Royal garments his jewels and he hadn't John I
don't need this anymore they're yours and um and then John I was supposed to go back to with them all
and so that was a momentous role for Chana and it said it was very
meritorious to be the one who supported the Buddha to do his renunciation
so after the Buddha was enlightened he came back to his hometown and uh China
then ordained as a monk and uh and then
but it seemed like he was had some problems maybe he was a troubled person
and it seemed that for one thing he was he kept breaking the root monastic rules
and uh he kind of would deny that he broke them and and then at some point it was bad enough
that the Buddha said okay you have to kind of go live it by yourself for a while you can't live with them together with other monastics for a while so
and so what he did was he just went to found another monastic Community to live in I mean another Buddhist Community
another town and that was kind of like that that wasn't that was breaking the rule so the Buddha called them back and they had a
they work something out and um but he was kind of known to be obstinate
stubborn and um and maybe other ways
also he was an arrogance conceit that he had because of this special connection he had to the Buddha does it need to be
louder is it okay the volume okay so um
so this conceit you know that he has a special connection to the Buddha kind of interfered maybe with his
engaging in the practice so uh apparently his behavior as a
monastic became bad enough that one of the last kind of declarations that Buddha made
before he died like the last note the last thing one of the one of the last things he had to say was something like
and by the way the manchana he is going to have the the Brahma danda
the Brahma punishment which is one is considered to be one of the highest
kind of punishments or something that you can get as a monastic and and that is that no monastic in the
order was supposed to talk to him anymore so he wasn't he wasn't this robe it's
just like you know no one should talk to him and that's pretty bad you know kind of may make you isolated so he must have
done something pretty bad but not bad enough to be disrobed and um so that was one of the last
things that's the significant thing that Buddha to say so so the Buddha died and then Ananda the Buddhist attendant who
was also kind of from the same town and known each other for also for a long time it was his job to go tell Chana
about this order this what happened that seemed to have upset China quite a bit I
seemed to have a wake-up call for him and he decided well I better get serious
here about my practice I better do something here and maybe that's what the Buddha knew the Buddha knew that China needed some
real poking to really get him to get serious after 45 years of being a monk and not really doing the practice
and um and so in fact that's what he did he got serious and so the the Sutra
called the Chana suta begins with China going around to the Elder monks of the
time going I guess early in the morning and maybe waking them up and um and he says to them may the
elders instruct me May the elders teach me
May the elders provide me with a Dharma talk so I can see the dhamma so he
really is ready he wants to see it he doesn't just know it however there's this rule Brahma danda
that he's not supposed to be talked to so the Elder monks kind of dismiss them
but they do give him a little teaching but they give him this the most wrote kind of simplistic or the most wrote
kind of formulaic teaching the Buddha the core Buddhist teaching of the time
that they could they're kind of like like you almost feel like they're like just yelling at him like and they're
saying some of you know the teachings of the five aggregates usually it's called form feeling
perception mental formations and Consciousness I prefer to translate it
as appearances feelings recognition constructs mental constructs and and
cognitions and they tell they tell Chana this Elders say
um appearances are impermanent in constant appearances are feelings are in constant
recognitions are in constant constructs mental constructs are inconstant and cognitions we have are
inconstant and then they close the door sometimes they say and all those things
are not self so appearances are not self feelings are not self recognitions are not self
mental constructs are not self and cognitions are not self and they close the door
and uh and so China then says wait a minute this is going to distraught
because he speaks to himself any uh any thought
I know all this I know all this but my um but my mind
is not leaping in inspiration by this teaching
it doesn't become my mind has become confident settled resolved
about the quieting of all my mental constructs
all my mental kind of Shenanigans in my mind my chatter and all that that doesn't I'm not confident about the
value of doing that of quieting the mind and constructs of giving up all my attachments
of of uh ending my craving of nibana Freedom Liber liberation
so here's a teaching so not only doesn't that he doesn't see it for himself but it doesn't Inspire him he doesn't
understand it well enough to that this is great this is a great thing and it is hard to understand how these
teachings on their five Aggregates is a wonderful teaching but maybe I'll try a little bit to get us to give you a
feeling because it will prepare you for what's going to come so they say that appearances are in
constant and permanent so appearance is what this means is anything that appears
at any of the five cent stores so sites side objects appear
sound objects certainly sounds appear and we hear them smells appear we smell
them tastes appear and we taste them and tactile experiences appear
and these are called appearances and these are inconstant they're constantly shifting and changing and
flowing and and becoming different things you go through the day and
there's a whole series of different physical Sensations you'll experience throughout the day
um it's already you know it's a little after 10 and I'm already hot probably we should turn the air conditioner on and then we'll have a
different Sensations in our body and but this morning it was kind of cool and nice all kinds of things it's all
shifting and changing and so now what's appeared for us for some of us I guess
is it's warm that's what's appeared but we know that it's not going to stay warm it's going to be warm for a few
hours but sooner or later it'll get cool and things will shift and change and we
know this is inconstant and for some things that we hear that they're in constituency okay we'll put up for this
for now we'll work with this now it's not going to make it make a big deal I'm not going to get attached to it being
having to be this way or attached to it needing to be different because it's all shifting and changing and the sense of
Shifting and changing can loosen up the grip we have on how things are at any
given moment this becomes more important when it has to do with our feelings and feelings
here is in the Buddhist context means that the experience of pleasantness and
unpleasantness and that also is Shifting and changing throughout the day and the hour and the
minute depending on what rather the Mind lands on
now unfortunately I brought up the fact that it's warm in here so maybe some of you have been reminded of how unpleasant
that is or maybe some you find it very pleasant and very satisfying but if I hadn't said it you probably would have
been so gripped by my teaching that you wouldn't have noticed it and um and so
and so uh so you can be reminded by things or then you can be I can tell
some tantalizing story more tantalizing that China's story and you'll be the edge of
your seat and you won't notice it anymore your body's uncomfortable it's unpleasant or you won't notice how pleasant certain things are these all
these these these all appear they come and go they change and shift and there's something very significant
about tuning in to how the flow the stream of Sensations come and go and
shift and change all the time that somehow or other is quite freeing if we see it then live in it
we partly don't live in it because we live in our constructs we often live in the stories we tell ourselves and the
interpretations or the recognitions the third of these five aggregates
and recognitions have to do with uh how we identify or see something that is
innocent enough you see a door and you recognize it as a door it seems no problem but we recognize things that are often a
problem you know racism is a recognition right you recognize people in a certain way
and or internalized racism you recognize yourself in a certain way
or all kinds of other ways in which we recognize other people or recognize ourselves and when we see other people
on the street what are we what are we seeing what are we reacting to what are we identifying what are we taking as
being the important thing to notice if someone is uh looks big and
threatening and dangerous that's their recognition Danger if someone is really attractive then the
recognition is ah this is interesting maybe I shouldn't look
or something but we have all these we recognize things but when we can see that the
recognitions that we have are contingent the recognitions are
partly a product of our own mind and they also come and go
and we can see them come oh there's one so you know I've gone down the street and recognized someone at this being
that's a dangerous person and maybe and and then I say oh I could watch my mind have that thought
and because I can see it being born is that really so
I didn't have that thought before that thought came out of my mind it's a mind mind creation construct it might not be
true but if I don't have the mindful to see the birth of the thought
then the person and the danger are not distinct I kind of meld those together
and my projection of Danger on that person is is who the person is in my
eyes so to be able to see the arising and then the disappearing of these
recognitions we have is very freeing and very wise because then you can give
that person of Street a second look is this really the case Oh no just the
person just looks like my third grade bully and that's all actually the person looks
quite sweet and uh and so then kind of the the recognition bubble pops of that
recognition perhaps maybe the person is dangerous I used to live in a dangerous neighborhood all my
roommates got robbed at gunpoint or knife Point except for me and um and uh
there were people and they you know I think I'll cross the street and then they'd follow me
and then I went into a store you know to kind of be safe or something so so there's dangers out there but uh
but you know just to be able to see the recognition and are we really seeing accurately
and then these stories the constructs we make is kind of related to what I just said
to see how they come and go and see see how they're born gives us a sense that they're not solid
they're not fixed oh there's I made a story up and then cognitions are all kind of in
the same regard the difference between cognition and recognition is not that great in their
teachings but cognitions are more basic than recognitions recognition is a recognition of something you already
know from before so this is this is the emphasis but to
say this in a simplistic way over and over again as the Buddhist teachings do
makes the mind numb and uh and probably that's what happened to China you know
so they said to him you know this is all these are impermanent all these are not self these are just things that are
occurring not self that you don't make a self out of them so again the heat that's happening here
is that who you are are you the sensations of heat at the moment are you the heat no
you are you the unpleasantness of the heat if you make yourself like I am that
unpleasantness then who are you when it gets cool do you shift and change your identity
based on what you're feeling all the time you your identity fixated by your what
you recognize or something deeper and submit many of the recognitions we have
um about ourselves our contingent our tentative are not so accurate even
sometimes but we can live kind of glued onto them and have a lot of suffering
so to see these five different areas as being impermanent and not self to see it is one of the things that the
early Buddhist tradition said was freeing so China
had enough of this from these guys and so he was distraught and he said I'm
not inspired by any of this and uh and he said um
instead what arises in me my mind doesn't leap in Inspiration rather what grows is my
anxiety and my clinging so he's just an anxious guy you know
just the more he looks at this and feels the more anxious he gets the more he clings and holds on it's a poor guy
he says my mind is spinning poor guy you know he's he's really
troubled he's spinning he's you know and then his companions in the spiritual
life his fellow monks are not really thick you know talking to him anymore
so what is he going to do and then he says for someone who sees
he's thinking to himself for someone who sees the teachings it does not occur to ask who then is
myself who's the self what is the self someone who sees doesn't that ask that
question which is a common question it's considered one of the great spiritual
questions or existential questions who am I but for the Buddhists there's something about if you really see this life
directly in a clear way you wouldn't ask that question why is that
um so he says so um so that I can see
the teaching who is it who can point the teachings out to me
who can make it clear and then he remembers Ananda the Buddha is one of the primary
attendants and fellow person from the same town they grew up in the same town also
and he says Ananda was praised by the Buddha and
esteemed by his wise companions in the Holy life vanderbil Ananda can point out the
dhamma so I can see the dumb the teaching I have a lot of love
for vanderbil and under why don't I visit him it's very touching this guy's so
troubled and he said I have a lot of love for this man and um and so he's gonna go see
and so he goes to Ananda and um
and he tells him the story of what happened with these Elder monks and and
the whole story that led up to why he came and then he says to say he says may
venerable and under instruct me May venerable Ananda teach me
May venerable Ananda provide me with a dhamma talk so I can see the teaching
and uh in reply Ananda said on this
matter I am certainly delighted with venerable Chana that you have opened up and cut
through your obstacy so you know he apparently it wasn't
available for the teachings for 45 years and he was obstinate right so that's quite something to come to the teaching
policy was around it and around and rounded but it wouldn't really take it in wouldn't open himself up to really listen and take it in and
but now finally after their all this he was willing to and so so Ananda says
I'm delighted that you're opened up and cut through your absentee
listen venerable give ear Janna you can
understand the dhamma you can understand the teachings
and then China thought to himself very excitedly
oh it seems I am capable of understanding the dhamma if Ananda says
so it must be true and so a great Rapture and Delight sprung up in
venerable China so here's something very significant to have someone else believe in you
to have someone else think you can do this you can understand someone and some
people grow up without having anyone who believes in them that way in any way in all kinds of ways and so you know
there's a real barrier to do to learn to open up to God even go out into the world if you haven't been believed in
and supported and and shown that you're capable and loved and cared for and all
kinds of things that go on and maybe China maybe you know he was a son of a servants
and maybe there's something about that life of poverty and servitude that didn't really support him to have that
kind of confidence or maybe it kind of maybe was a difficult life and maybe something shut down or was discouraged
or who knows what happened to him who knows why he was so difficult for all his lives maybe he had a very
difficult time growing up and and so to someone there's like Ananda say you can
that that really went deep he had Rapture and Delight
so um so then Ananda says okay so then he starts giving him the teaching and he
says I heard this in the very presence of the Buddha because he was his attendant he was
there and this is the teachings to a different monk named
gochana gochana gota and um and he asked the Buddha what is
Right View what is the Right View it's the right way of seeing or the
right understanding to have to engage in the dhamma yeah generally more technically right
view in Buddhism is the way we see the world when we have the first glimpse of
enlightenment so it's not just what you learn you know from a book but when you have some kind
of your Dharma eye your enlightened pie opens now you see in a new way so when you ask when this monk asks what is the
Right View he's asking more than just what's the you know some piece of teaching he's asking what is it what is
what's the vision that we have of the world when we when we're enlightened
and um so the and this
and so the uh the Buddha was said that it said Nando's repeating with the buddhistana
this world relies on the on the dyad
of the existence and non-existence that things exist or they don't exist
but when one sees with right wisdom the arising of the world
as it comes to be the thought of non-existence doesn't occur
when one sees with right wisdom the cessation of the world
doesn't occur that something exists so the idea that things exist and a
particular thing that exists that's a big problem is you
of course you know I want to say of course you exist but in the Buddhist worldview you don't exist as a fixed
thing there's no essential fixed solid core thing that you are
and and also you don't not exist and so this is an enigmatic it's
quandary people struggle with kind of teaching how does this mean I don't exist and I don't not exist I mean these
Buddhists are crazy and um and giving these kinds of kind of
statements and um but then the Buddha says that if you can see
that a thought arises maybe it's not paraphrasing a thought arises in your
mind that person is dangerous you see that it was just born in that
moment it didn't have an existence before it's temporary it's just there it doesn't
exist in some permanent solid way it's there as a visitor
and um but it's there you can't say it doesn't exist but because you see that
it's we see it pass away after a while that you no longer have that thought
then you see that it just person just looks like your third grade bully and so immediately you feel okay the person you
see oh the person's sweet actually then you see it go you say well that now
I see it went away and so because it's gone away it it was
it didn't solidly exist as something so it it you don't say it exists you
don't say it doesn't exist what you say is that it's in process
it's it's inconstant it comes and goes it's part of the flow and shifting
changing stream of living experience that we live in and the idea is to in Buddhism is to
learn how to float swim in the Stream of constantly shifting and changing world
that we live in swimming in a stream in a river
as opposed to if I'm allowed to stretch this metaphor
um getting stuck in the river in the winter time when it gets frozen over
and you're Frozen in it and you can't get out and so often we get Frozen around our
ideas Frozen around our Concepts and feelings and emotions about holding on to them and clinging to them and getting
fixated and so to see their comings and going
oh they are just appearing now for a while they just it was born it just came into being
and now it's gone and there's something about seeing that and knowing that we begin to relax our
grip something begins to thaw and melt that has been frozen for a long time or
fixated for a long time and um so so when the Buddha says the
rising of the world he means the world of our experience it's very clear in the teachings it doesn't mean you know the
external world it's the world of our experience it comes and goes
um so um so that's nice maybe I don't know what
you think of that the next teaching is what was very significant for me in my
month-long Retreat that I kind of supported me as I went through
um and I'm going to paraphrase it to make it serious so it's real simple and maybe understandable
there's a lot of synonyms you know you know there's a lot of words extra words maybe to make it really clear but I
think it distracts also um this world mostly this world says mostly
this world for all the people is attached
that's most people are attached um
but in relationship to these attachments
if one does not cling to the attachments
if one does not cling to them with the idea this is who I am
so it's one thing to be attached it's the other the other thing to put on
top of that a second attachment where I'm identifying myself I am that
attachment so I might really like ice cream hot day
it seems nice attached to ice cream that's maybe you know ordinary enough
but then you know I get attached to I am the ice
cream eater I am the ice cream Liker and I better let everyone else know that
this is who I am and I'm going to prove that I'm a really good ice cream Liker
by buying sophisticated ice cream flavors and uh and really show that I'm really
kind of like a special ice cream Eater Not just an ordinary ice cream eater and I'm gonna get a little label on my shirt
that's you know just you know Champion Ice Cream eater or something and and then it becomes important not
just to go to you know I don't know the ordinary ice cream shop but you have to
go to the Artesian ice cream shop to get you know
the most sophisticated ice cream because you know how that says something about who you are as a sophisticated person
so it's one thing to really like ice cream and want it and maybe even crave it but the layer of cell thing that can
go on top of it can be quite strong so so that's a silly example I'm hoping that you can
understand maybe apply it and see that maybe something like this plays itself out in your life also
that how much we identify and one identification to clinging especially
among Buddhists is because in Buddhism we're trying not to cling and we see that we're clinging and now
we say I'm a bad Buddhist and now we've added the second layer of
clinging clinging to a kind of self we've identified I am a bad Buddhist
you know it's bad enough to cling to ice cream but to then be a bad Buddhist because
you do you know it's you know that's adding these layers right so
so that's what the teaching so the teachings are um
so and then it goes oh so the world cling the world gets attached
and to those attachments uh someone has a right view does not cling
to the idea this is who I am um
one and then one will have no doubt that that very Duke got that's very
suffering of the attachment
is just the arising the appearing of suffering
when we'll have no doubt that when it disappears it's just a disappearing of it so there's something about the
attachment of self that we have the clinging to self and then applying it to all other different things
that obscures the nature of the uh the first layer of attachment
There's Something About Me Myself and mind that we overlay on top of it that
freezes it fixates it obscures it but if we don't identify with our
clinging don't identify where their attachments you don't say it I'm attached we say
there is attachment here then there's a better chance to see
that what all it is it's it's suffering
suffering is occurring so if I get really if you know maybe some of you now too I'm sorry if I cause
this for you um you know now you have mostly what
you're thinking about now is ice cream and you're like as soon as this is over guilt wins to stop talking because I
need to get out to this ice cream store quickly you know and you're attached to your ice cream
but then if you um if you pay if you're not kind of distracted by I'm because I
need to go to ice cream I'm the great ice cream eater and I need to prove it to everyone but you're staying close to the primary
attachment then there's an opportunity to see that that's suffering that hurts
ouch there's a clinging a contraction or hurt distress any attachment we have involves stress
anything anytime we clamp down clings
um you know is stressful but to see the stress that what the Buddhists call suffering
dukkah as uh just to see it arrive to see it appear to have the ability to be
mindfulness there it is it just appeared gives you the opportunity to stay in the
Stream and not to freeze oh it's just suffering
that's what it is and there now I've gotten distracted
you know I could probably distract you if you some of you are suffering Now by how long this Dharma talk has been
I can probably distract you for a moment if I talk a little bit about say
something like you know that it's possible that spiders will fall from the ceiling yeah
except for a moment probably you have got everything else but the spiders
and um so the anyway so uh
so then the Buddha goes on and so then he says if you see this clearly
then you will become independent in the teaching
in the in the Buddhist teaching you you won't depend on anybody else or any book or anything because you don't have to
it's not learned the teaching now you see it
which is the goal that China had he wanted to see and so anandas there's pointing saying
you see it by seeing how you get attached to self
around your experiences you have and sometimes there's a negative
attachment sometimes it's a positive attachment sometimes just a confused attachment but we often it is a
solething thing is a big source of suffering and the attachment of self is considered
maybe the primary core suffering of it all because it obscures
all the other clingings we can't see at this part of the stream and the flow and
the shifting and changing so we can kind of float along without freezing around it getting caught in it
so that's all it takes you don't have to get a PhD in Buddhist studies to understand the Dharma you can just
kind of see this is how you see it is to see how things when they appear when you're right there mindful is right
there oh there it is there it is it appears oh and there it went it makes the mind the heart more fluid
more at ease more open more kind of willing to kind of go be carried along
in the Stream of life as it flows and goes through us and the Buddha goes on and says as
quoted by Ananda everything exists is one extreme
everything does not exist is the second extreme
avoiding the two extremes teaches the Dharma
through the middle and the middle is that things arise and they pass
that's the alternative that's the way you find your way into the middle of the stream where it's not frozen where
everything flows so uh
so I sat in my retreat and was reminded of these teachings regularly and right
there awareness arising right there don't don't make this the self
don't make this into Me Myself and mine let it be let it be
let it just flow let it come and go feel the suffering of it come steal the
suffering of a girl there's something very when we see when we feel and see how the arisings and passing are
suffering it makes it a lot easier and simpler to want to let go of it
who are sophisticated people sometimes so if we have sophisticated clingings like the ice cream
and then it's hard to kind of you know give it up but if we just see oh that's clicking to
ice cream that's suffering that's stress to have it it makes it a lot simpler and easier
okay let go let go and um
so let's see
so uh
so then uh China is a story about China at the end so the setup ends with China telling
Ananda Reverend Ananda this is how it is to have care
to be cared for that nice I mean here I do this is what maybe even Behavior among all these
decades maybe he was not open he was not available to feel how the people care
for him this is how it is to have care well wishing
instruction and teaching by The venerables Who were our
companions in the Holy life so they come his companions right that's
you know the people is having heard this dumb mother's teaching
the teaching now has been fully settled very nice standing nice story
so I thought there's a huge there's a Humanity to this story about this man who's troubled and
and what it took to be somehow open to hear the teachings and and then as he
heard these teachings to feel cared for and loved in a certain way perhaps and and uh and then to be and then to
understand now it's settled now he knows so whether you understand that core
teachings that is said to be the origin of much of Mahayana Buddhism then even
um maybe at least you'd uh were struck by the humanity of
care and love and believing in each other and
and maybe that's the way to be opens be available to hear these teachings
then maybe some days do have a teaching settled
so thank you very much and um
may you all be well
sometimes then during these last months we've been meeting out in the parking lot afterwards if people would ask you
know question and discussion it's kind of hot out there probably so I suggest we turn the air conditioner on and and
I'll just stay here for a while some of you want to stay and we can have a little discussion and you're not to do the air conditioner
so any questions anyone wants to ask maybe we can ask what the handheld Mike
so that so that people can hear them
we'll take maybe 10 minutes for this girl just wondering
which uh it doesn't sound like it
testing Gil which suta is that about China it's that you call the Chana
and it's known by its number is that 22.90 in the connected discourses so the
22nd chapter is the 90th suta in that chapter connected connected discourses
2290 yeah yeah you can have it thank you this is it
okay you can have it I also posted it my this is my translation I posted it on imc's website you know there's a
Reflections from Gill under what's new so I put it there in my Reflections for me so you can if you want to read it
again it's there
um
thank you very much for that talk Gail I'm really struck by the transition of
awareness emptiness and then meta
for Chana it's it's it's almost as if he he had the talks but he wasn't aware
and then this sense of not belonging somehow cut through
that sense of maybe ignorance delusion and then with the teachings on emptiness
it allowed the meta and the karuna to just flow freely it's just thank you it
was just told so beautiful and part of the direction their flowed was into him yeah beautiful
okay yeah I just wanted to
State a interesting quote I heard the other or read the other day Alan Arkin
who recently died the actor he said um
acting is not who I am acting is what I do and that's really
stuck it really drove home that point of the self of how we identify with the
things that we you know are professions and beliefs and all that stuff nice very nice
thank you that thing is not who I am it's what I do
including being a Buddhist including being a Buddhist instead of just
following the path yeah maybe no one should be a Buddhist
we just do we used to do Buddhism
yes all the way in the back
thank you so I just wanna say the
The Plea believing in me that piece is really inspiring and a resonating in the
way that uh sometimes for all the circumstances the people you
close with may not believe in you of your pursue
and uh I just want to express the Gratitude of the Sangha in the way that that's aware
I find a belief and a care fantastic and it's fantastic that you resonated with that
that's really meaningful that that you took that in thank you
[Applause] Hey Joe
so I was curious how Buddha missed that he missed that didn't he with Chana or
all those uh for 40 years yeah yeah
yeah you know and then you can't expect everyone to get it right all the time
it's a it's a pretty big order we expect the Buddha to be perfect but
it was he was human too that's why we need a sun god community so that uh we all have different kind of
capacities or connections and so on when he needed Ananda
and on that point maybe Chana wasn't ready when the Buddha was so he wasn't ready so he he wasn't ready he was he
was so closed and so obstinate that he did it and the medicine was that the Buddha finally at
the end of his life said Europe you know you know no one's supposed to talk to
you anymore no one asked you're not part of this community kind of that's powerful medicine and then I hope that
Buddha did that that of all his wisdom he knew what was needed and it seemed to that seemed to have worked that's part
of the flow and that that that moment would have led to
what eventually happened yep sometimes very strong language
strong actions are needed I kill good to have you back
I wonder if you feel like sharing more about how you worked with
that teaching during your retreat more like
specific things you noticed or
oh simple things like if I was doing walking meditation
and I had this thought that uh oh I'm not getting concentrated enough enough
so I said oh that's a stressful thought that just arose it was just a thought that arose I don't
have to believe it I don't have to identify with it or make myself into a bad walking meditator
oh look at that was just that was the rising of that and then it was just like oh then it would it would just kind of
dissolve I
think there are a lot a lot of little things like that through the day and so
I was also struck by the fact that uh Ananda despite the Buddha's instructions
not to speak to China that Ananda not only spoke to China he really
engaged with him fully so I I think that's interesting I mean that's profound right to me and I don't know if
you have any thoughts about that as well I don't know if there's best thoughts or something but Ananda has this reputation
of being a really friendly really friendly Monk and he was much more
friendly than some people thought he should be so for example he was he was a big supporter of the nuns and sometimes
those can some people thought he was like too friendly to nuns and so he was he had a very friendly disposition and
and um and that's what he was known for so the nice guy
and then in terms of this uh this this rule that the Buddha said you know
against China China soon thereafter became poorly enlightened and when you're fully enlightened all your those
rules get dissolved they go away so then he was in good standing
um one thing when I was hearing this story was that if I were to know China I would feel
very frustrated at his kind of uh um closed or closed office and I'm
wondering if there's any anything else around maybe how the rest of the song could maybe if they did feel that
frustration or maybe how they they dealt with with that yeah probably that's why
the elders when they kind of just you know kind of dismissed him with these simple teachings it's all impermanent go
away um it might have been not just the rule that the Buddha established that no one
should talk to him but it might be they've had Decades of you know seeing how difficult he's been and
and how he he wouldn't listen or he wouldn't hear or there was pointless to
try to have maybe people had tried for years to try to get through to him and so their frustration was there and
and it might have been a very difficult person for others and why he was
difficult we don't know and maybe he was I don't know
maybe he was uh maybe we shouldn't even say he was difficult maybe he was just that nowadays we have the expression uh
neurodivergent they're different maybe he was maybe he was uh had some kind of different
brain than other people and so he behaved differently and I've known
people who who I was a little bit cautious around until I found out that that they had
some kind of neurodivergence that was completely normal for some people to have and oh that's why they are the way
they are okay and then I was just completely happy with him so who knows
what story so hard to reconstruct back there but but it's such a common human
phenomena for us to for people to be closed down to each other shut down not
be available and be judgmental and um and uh
and then somehow to for love care respect to somehow dissolve that and
opens things up and I think that that's the kind of one of the powerful lessons I think of practice is an Ananda represents that
someone who understands the value of the power of love and care and friendliness
even for difficult people
I just wanted to get some explanation on this issue of attachment is in terms of
the degree of attachment is strong is is it mild is it uh non-existent and how it
obscures the power of observation as we you described and power of awareness
is there a um is there a way that you could act normally in regards to these
things for example obviously if you come to a totally identify with who you are as a
professional of some sort or whatever doctor engineer whatever or is it just a matter of sometimes a matter of simply
the security that is required to live and he said is it an attachment and is
that if it is does it obscure your power observation
so if I understand what you're saying I can reply this way that I think is important not to think
that attachment is a crime uh you know because just because Buddhism is about the ending of
attachment doesn't mean that it's necessarily wrong to be attached it is stressful it does have a it does
does hurt in some way but uh sometimes attachments better than the alternative
you know sometimes it would be like security and safety um and um you know being being attached
to a job because if you don't have a job how you can take care of your family or all your old age or something and so you
know it's you know you could give up the attachment give up the job attachment keeps you
motivated to take do it well if you don't attach you might be lackadaisical
and get fired or something or just give it up not show up for work and then all these other things where percussions are
worse so if it if the if the alternative attachment is worse maybe it's good to
keep the attachment for the time being but don't reify it don't make it into a
belief or whole religion that you're supposed to be attached recognize oh this is attachment the wisest this is
probably the wisest way I can do right now I don't have to get rid of all my attachments right away just because I'm
attached let me keep practicing and when the time is right the practice is quite
powerful it's almost like the practice has its own wisdom if you creep to keep doing mindfulness practice and seeing
when the time is ready to address an attachment is what you'll know
but and you know the fact that you know that you're attached doesn't mean you have to fix it right away
so when it's the best alternative keep it and I I know Buddhist teachers say even
being attached to Buddhism um is sometimes better than the alternative and and uh you know keep it
as long as it's beneficial at some point it'll benefits will not be there and
then you'll know it's self-correcting or if you become obsessed with it if you
get upset with it obsessed with it obsessed by the way that's the names that's getting a little bit now
edgy because then your family's not going to be happy here thank you your friends
thank you so much for the story girl I you know I've been replaying that story in my head again and again a little bit
louder I is it loud now yeah I really like the story and
I've been noticing in it you know very recently like how unconditional love is
answer to so many questions and I really loved how Ananda was there
and just giving Johanna unconditional love irrespective of all the rules and everything yeah
thank you beautiful thank you nice to hear so we should stop I'd like to stop
and um thank you all very nice nice to sit here with you and be