welcome one of the tasks of mindfulness meditation is to keep our attention
fresh meaning to always be ready
to discover each moment for itself almost
like each moment arrives and it's a new event completely fresh and not to carry along with us our
preconceived ideas our biases or are conclusions we've
made about what's happening and of course it's easy enough
and maybe appropriate to make conclusions about their recognitions of what's happening but then it might keep us from
being fresh for the next moment and so one way of staying fresh
like every every moment is a new moment even even if it's repeating what just happened is
um is to kind of have the attitude
is either what else what else is happening here what's
next or the attitude Maybe not maybe it's not like
this maybe so maybe not we shall see
especially this idea of maybe not and then maybe you come to the same
conclusion the same recognition that's fine but to stay fresh always new what's
this ready to be almost like you're ready to be surprised or ready to
discover and in the process of doing doing this it isn't so much about what
you discover what you're aware of what you know as it is is it the openness the
freshness the relaxed attention that doesn't settle on some
idea or conclusion the sense of being the attention is always
fresh like walking through some beautiful natural setting
You' never been to before and just like the the eyes the mind is just ready new
seeing something new and wow so on this sitting to sit quietly
with maybe it isn't so the conclusions I've
made maybe not let's see let's see what's
next so to assume a meditation
posture and lower your gaze or close your
eyes and even if youve meditated a thousand times 10,000 times
before each moment is fresh each meditation is
new no two meditations are the
same and what is it that's here that's new what is it to be fresh and alert
present as if it's the first
[Music] time
and then taking a few long slow relaxed
breaths and in a relaxed way relax as you
exhale
letting your breathing return to normal and continue in a relaxed
way to relax on the exhale roaming around your body to see
where can you
soften
and then settling down to accompany your
breathing each breath is a new
appearance in inhale just this inhale with no past or
future just the exhale with no past and
future just this to be aware
of with no conclusions not bringing with you past
bias or judgments or concerns about
anything just
this fresh alert ever
ready for this moment to be
itself what appears as this
moment
the now is
inseparable from what arises in the
now the shifting changing experiences of
now with no conclusions not car caring with you
judgments fresh for every moment breathing in and breathing
out
for
[Music]
the direct experience of being alive is always in the present
moment to be here in your direct experience with a center of gravity
center of attention on the
breathing in the present moment experience of breathing with a fresh
attention this is our lived
experience
for
e
as we come to the end of the sitting to consider
one of the gifts we can give to others is to meet them without precons
considerer ideas preconceptions
judgments bias to have a fresh mind to meet
others and to do that gift to our eles to be mindful in such a way that
we're aware of ourselves without preconceptions without
judgments without thoughts that limit
us and to be able to do it for ourselves
strengthens our ability to do it for others and vice
versa and as we come to the end of this sitting may it
be that we can give people the
gift of being known and seen and appreciated free of our bias our
judgments prec conceived ideas to meet even people we know with a
friendly not knowing wanting to know who is
this knowing others with delight and appreciation with no preconceived
ideas so they can relax so they can just be who they
are and with whatever fresh eyes we have to see people may we wish them
well may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all beings everywhere be
[Music]
free
thank [Music]
you
e
so continuing this theme of quarrels and disputes
a topic that Buddha had a lot to say on and he came across situation where or
report that there was a group of religious teachers
philosophers who are arguing philosophically or metaphysically about the nature of the universe nature of
life things like the universe is forever the universe is finite
infinite that um human beings live forever in multiple rebirths there is no
rebirth the nature of what happens after death so all kinds of things that are
not really about the here and now but about these big existential questions that
people Ponder and these people who are
having opinions about this were arguing quarreling about who was right and then the Buddha described them
with an analogy analogy which in some ways is uh
pretty apt for how people can be but also it uses maybe an analogy that is
not really uh maybe it it itself offers a kind of bias or a kind of stereotyping
that we don't want to live in so it's an example of what not to do and um so what he said was
uh uh or what he talked about or what he suggested to a King who was questioning
about this was to have a group of blind people
come and to with their hands to touch different parts of an elephant and then report what they were
touching and those who touched the the
um the legs said it what they were a solid column those who studied the Torso
said it was a big round Barrel those who touched the ears said it was a winnowing
basket those who touched the tail said it was a rope and um and so it went and so each
of them then thought they knew what the elephant was but they only had a partial
View and uh and so in the same way these these people were arguing because they
only had a partial view of reality of life and we're arguing based on that partial
view so it does speak to how human beings are partial uh in their attention their
awareness we come with preconceived ideas we have come with Selective Vision
that we see things selectively according to what we want and in this analogy the Buddha in a
sense does that too unfortunate unfortunate way with blind people assuming that that because they're blind
they can only have a partial understanding of what is going on and that's certainly not
true but uh but still the Buddha put a great emphasis on the ctivity process
the bias the um preconceived ideas the
judgments we make through which we see the world around us and that based on
this limited views that we have when we're seeing through ideas like this
that uh to argue based on that is to uh is uh very unfortunate and that is part
of the the root of many argu is um is the the select selective way the biased
way in which we understand and see the world and he talked about uh many many
examples of this uh he talked about um two in
particular that for some people uh it is essensual desires that make their
attention partial makes it biased or selective and um and then that orients
them in terms of what they want what they don't want what they'll argue about about the conflicts they get into and
other people uh the other big category is people uh selectively choose based on
their views their opinions the stories they're living by insisting that they're right this is how things
are and um and then arguing because of that and um some of the bases for these
select Ive or biased viewpoints is um objectifying the world being being being
the one who sees and creating this kind of objective objective relationship
that's all seeing through the lens of Me Myself and mine so what kind of
selfishness or self-centeredness now how does this relate to me so a sensual desire what is
in it for me what can I get out of this uh what kind of discomfort sensual
discomfort can I avoid and for opinions and stories and
Views is how what supports my view what threatens my view that I have to attack
and criticize and show how wrong it is and um the um we have preconceived
ideas that we bring with us into these things we have something like we see a friend or see a person who some time ago
was one way and we treat them that way and forever more or maybe that's happened to you that you've feel like
someone keeps seeing you in the way that in very selective they recognize you about someone something you did long ago
that doesn't really represent you anymore and um or the conclusions the
judgments we make and one of the big ones is uh comparative thinking we compare ourselves to others We compare
our views our opinions who who has the best wanting to have the best view the most thorough true idea and um we want
to have the best pleasure we want to to have the best experience and uh and this is what the
best is this is what's not so best this is the and I always want to have the best so the um uh the drive for sensual
pleasure in Buddhism is actually broader than what we might think of in English
uh when we say that you know the drive for sensual pleasure um it's the drive for Comfort it's a
drive for pleasantness it's a drive to avoid discomfort to drive to avoid the
unpleasant and we can get into conflict with others if they stand in a way or if
they cause if they're unpleasant or do unpleasant things for us and we think
that that's not what we should be what should what we should experience we push them away we don't like them we uh maybe
get into conflict with them and it's all about you know what we think is pleasant and unpleasant um we're envious and jealous
because they have the pleasure that we want they have the wonderful experience and uh and then we have um
the views and opinions the stories that we live in and part of the reason why
they can be so sticky is sometimes we Define ourselves by those and we want to reinforce who we are we reinforce the
idea of who we are by propping up those stor insisting those views and things are
true so in all these ways we are seeing partially we're not seeing the full
picture of things we're oriented we're selective and in that selectivity not seeing the whole things we run into
things that challenge that selective narrow View and then we're in easily get in conflict with it and can be in
quarrels and disputes wanting wanting my pleasure you need to provide it or um
this you know my way or the highway because I want to have this that's you know the wonderful Pleasant enjoyable
thing and um and uh and that sometimes the there
are kind of real intense fights over people's strong drive for addiction to
what's called Buddhism would called sensual pleasures and the same thing with VI and opinions people get furious and
judgmental and self-righteous and in doing so both these ways we stop seeing the full
picture we stop opening up to the full experience of what's Happening here now
the full Humanity of ourselves the full Humanity of others and part of the goal
of this practice of ours is to be able to drop the bias drop the selective ways
in which we see self and others stop the judgments we have the comparative
thinkings we have the ideas that I'm not good enough I'm a problem or I'm great I'm wonderful and we have to prove it to
everyone to relax all those things to quiet the mind that's involved in all
that chatter it's not just chatter it's also a deep kind of subliminal kind of
attitudes we carry to be able to relax it so that we
can go through the world without being in Conflict without being quarreling and
disputing and bumping into people and and and um self-righteously arguing and
complaining and and criticizing um but
instead to try to kind of keep opening up to the full picture of here what's really happening here what's the
fullness of yourself what if you see yourself as whole so whole
that it can't be taken away by other people's opinions views desires
what if you see other people as whole and worthy and autonomous respect worthy
people so they come they show up we're more fresh and interested curious who is
this person what is this we don't have to agree we don't have to go along with
what they want but that doesn't have to be done with as an argument it doesn't have to go as a dispute it can kind of
Grant people okay that's interesting tell me more most people if you ask more deeply
what's going on for you why you know how do you come to this and what's the background for this view this desire you
have what are you trying to fill or what are you trying to do here as you start
uh getting to know people better we'll find there's depth there's background there's context of who people are that
um changes the whole nature of how we relate to people that's not possible if
we Clash around desires Clash around views and so this meditation practice we
do a practice which helps us to relax the judging mind relax the mind
that makes comparative thinking the mind that wants to be right and wants to hold
on to views and stories and chatter the mind that wants to is driven by desire
and it's wants and its aversions and it's a phenomenal to drop down relax
settle and to be able to be present for the world without those in a responsible
engaged uh wise way that's respects everyone involved that has space for
everyone and maybe in doing so supporting everyone involved in a
conflict in a dispute to begin opening up and seeing each other more wholly
more fully and finding a different way a way that doesn't involve quarrel maybe a
way that supports the welfare and happiness of everyone
involved so thank you for this and um we
have one more talk on this series on quarrels and I'll be doing that today
I'm going to Spirit Rock Meditation Center Retreat Center about an hour north of here and an hour and a half and
I'm going to uh broadcast from there I don't know what the conditions will be like there um and I might be doing it in
office or wherever the Wi-Fi is strongest so letting you know it I'll be in a new new
location thank you