oh great so hello and welcome everyone it's
lovely to see you it's lovely to be with you I was
um away from happy hour last week I was teaching a retreat at the inside Retreat
Center where many many of our happy hour Sana members were present and it was
lovely to meet you in person and those who were not present we held you the
Sangha in our hearts just really nice to have this sense of the Sangha that's online and and Retreats and and various
ways for us to come together which reminds me actually I'll say it now I'll say it later too I'm also teaching in in
person meta De Long at IMC for those of you who
are local uh on Saturday September 30th
so put that on your calendars if you're in the Bay Area so
so with that I'd like to um
to share practice this evening and and bring in the sense of Landing into peace
and quiet and with with this
um with meta with kindness and intertwining of these two practices which can be
quite nourishing to the heart the place of Stillness and and within that also
meeting and holding it with a sense of acceptance
um any emotions or any any thoughts there might be you know today maybe you've felt
um disappointed frustrated sad we've had difficult moments it's okay it's really
okay as human beings we have these moments we have we have emotions
so how do we hold them with skillfulness
feel them not Exile them and
and bring compassion bring care both for ourselves and others so these are the
themes I'd like to to bring in um to our practice in this moment so so
with that I'd like to invite us all to land to transition to Landing in this body
earning awareness inward
and Grading whatever is present in the heart and the mind and the body
as if you are taking a pulse a kind pulse with kindness
what's here maybe there's some achy in his present
maybe agitation [Music] distraction heaviness in the heart whatever is
present allowing it to be present just as it is
with kindness relaxing the body
letting there be spaciousness
can all be here
and letting the breath be just as it is you don't have to breathe in any special way
and tuning into the spaciousness there is around holding
all of present in the body in the mind
as if the breath is expansive it's spacious
making peaceful calm space to be with everything just as it is
letting the body be relaxed and breathing away whatever is present with
patience kindness
letting the breath
be a soothing calming friend
making space if the mind is busy distracted okay
the breath can be present making space around that so we don't have to get agitated or
upset it's okay that's right can there be ease
making space with kindness for whatever there is
breathing with it breathing around it and so
it's plenty of space in the heart and the mind for everything to be here just as it is
nothing else is needed
just to be with the breath
company the breath this friend making space with kindness for whatever
there is the body mind and heart of this moment very simple
spaciousness of presence an acceptance with kindness
it's okay it's okay just plenty of space everything to be here just as it is
here here spaciously here with kindness
but the breath or whatever is present
let us now glad in our hearts our might
let us recollect some act of kindness
take Delight in generosity or just the fact that we have brought
ourselves to this practice period
not judging how the mind or body are but appreciating our intention
not goodness to show up just to show up take a moment to recollect something
good about this being who is you
kind act
generous wise something
let your heart be uplifted take your time
as if you were observing your own life your own actions as a loving good friend
would stepping out of yourself for a moment
maybe it was patience perseverance support you offered
your heart be uplifted by the goodness
don't take these acts these little ordinary kindnesses act a
wisdom patience for granted by turning to them we help them grow
let this recollection of goodness so
as a way to feel to hold yourself with kindness and meta this being who is you
may I be safe
may I be happy may I be healthy
now I have ease may I have the supportive conditions
to help my goodness grow and shine for my own sake and the sake of all
beings
I wish myself well
let's return this practice period so close
appreciating you're showing up and everyone showing up
mayor co-created goodness in this space be of service to our own growth
to our own cultivation of kindness peace goodness ethical Behavior
and made support the weakening of not just ourselves but all beings everywhere
may all beings be happy may all beings be free
including ourselves
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your practice
now before we turn to a small group practice
I wanted to just say a few words about what we did tonight a summary so the invitation tonight was
actually a very simple invitation the invitation was to be with the breath
and letting the breath make space make space in accepting space
around whatever is accepting kind space around whatever is
present in the body and the mind and the Heart without pushing them away by connecting with the breath as a way
of stability as to create collection collectiveness of mind and
kindness and then a sense of spaciousness spaciousness because there's so much
more we usually focus on what's difficult and our mind gets really tight and small but this invitation for
spaciousness and then realize wow yes the challenge with difficulties if there are any
emotions we can have them without being completely overwhelmed by him there's a
lot more that can be present and at the end I invited you to turn to
uh recollecting your own goodness to Glad in the heart it's uh one way of
doing this practice that's called Buddha nusrati they're collections of the qualities of the Buddha in this way
we're we're collecting the qualities of the Buddha within the kindness the generosity the
the wisdom itself that was what we did and whatever showed up for you or didn't
show up for you is all fine it's exactly as it needs to be let there be
acceptance peace non-judgment what needed to arise
this month this this evening this well depending on your time zone Wherever You Are
so now I'd like to invite us to uh turn to practicing in small groups and um
The Prompt is what happens what happens
you know when you have a difficult emotion what happens if you have a difficult emotion
um what what happens if you deny it if you try to push it away deny that you
have it versus if you allow it to be which doesn't mean that you act out of
it but if there's a sense of okay frustration arising sadness arising
and and also if there is a sense of spaciousness around the acceptance so
maybe some words come up and if no words come up you can just bow and say pass
hold uh kind presence um in the container
so so I'm going to create the breakout
rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other be kind
and um hold on one second
let's see creating the rooms here
okay all right I think I am ready to open them my ready actually wait I need
to do one more thing before I open them hold on uh you can have patience you can you can
practice patience as I uh as I do as I move things around okay
let's see what happened I didn't mean to do that hold up all
right having some technical difficulties difficult okay there I think that's it all right great okay here we go I'm
about to open their rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other be kind
um okay and oh yes one last thing I forgot to say um in in practice in in the small groups
yeah a couple of things I forgot to say uh one is let's go in in alphabetical
order and the second is that you only share please you're invited to share just
something from your own practice just maybe share a short nugget maybe a
minute or half a minute and then let another person speak and then another person and then it comes back to you so
you can go around a few times and it's not appropriate to ask questions from
another P from someone else or or God or
lead the group just show up with what you want to share and let people share whatever they want to share or not just
creating a safe space as possible for one another is safe and and uh accepting
space okay all right here we go I'm going to open the rooms now okay welcome
back everyone the rooms are closed and we have some time for Reflections you
can either raise your hand if you haven't spoken for a while in the group
um you can raise your Zoom hand if it's your physical hand I may not see you we can also share your Reflections or
questions in chat and if you send them to me privately I will read your
reflection not your name if you send them to everyone I will also read your
name to attribute it to you so what did you discover in this practice or either to silent
practice or in the sharing why did you discover
but making space with kindness for what is emotions challenges instead of
pushing them away letting their kind space
maybe with Stillness even any reflections
Sabrina
yeah I uh I showed up today with a migraine and I didn't realize how much I
was pushing the pain and frustration away until until I chose to really embrace it how
much like more space there was and how much much more acceptance I was feeling and
and then by the end of the session my migraine was gone so it's just like it felt really practical for me
um as well as like a reminder to keep acknowledging my my emotions rather than pushing pushing them away so practically
it was really great and like emotionally it felt really great so thank you so much yay thank you Sabrina oh my goodness I'm
seeing co-ops and appreciations and and hearts in in Zoom space for your share
thank you so much for sharing that it's so inspiring what you shared beautiful right when we in the moment we turn we
realize and just things shift yay yeah I'm celebrating your practice along with
others this is so beautiful yeah this is so great exactly what Sabrina said that
that's great beautiful and Rain am I saying your name right
yes yes yeah um what I shared was that um
I I had been in a hit-and-run bike accident I had to work through a lot of that was in August and I actually showed
up for this group got through it when um back in anyway back in the end of it was
Diana that night anyway fear and anxiety and having to work
through that came out of that accident that's become easy for me what I've noticed lately is when I'm feeling
really happy I feel guilty around people because there's still a lot of a lot of people I
know are in fear and post covet kind of a malaise here in San Francisco they've
lost jobs just or you know so something you did last Friday we did the
emanating love and being like a son so I noticed lately I just
one ways I've mitigated that and guilt for feeling so happy around people who are sad is like I'm just gonna shine and
share my joy and just yeah because I don't want to give
it up but it was just a great tool that you gave Friday to help me
have that beautiful thank you so much rain such
such wisdom in applying that to what's arising as you said with the sense of
guilt or shame like others happy and it's you know it's bad for me to be in three lives actually I can I can give it
away I can be that and I can give it away I can give my gladness my kindness
my meta my my Stillness my peace I'm gonna give it
away it's not for me to keep it's like a sun that shines I'm giving it away ah
what an act of generosity you've chosen to do rain that's beautiful thank you thanks for for sharing that
inspiring ah so lovely hmm
and nushan yes nusha says thanks for your kind words it was my first Retreat
and it was very impactful yay just uh attended this a seven day silent
retreat at IRC delighted that you were there in USA and it was uh impactful for
you may you shine your light now may you may give away your happiness may you give away your kindness and peace from
the retreat so great yeah any last Reflections comments questions
Yeah question here from sridevi after I noticed that I'm afraid of doing something new then how do I address it
the same way acknowledge that you're afraid don't try to push fear away can you
see it acknowledge it okay breathe with it make space for it
and don't let it take the whole Space don't let it suck the air out of the
room it can be here yeah it's thank you for trying to warn me thank you for trying to protect me dear fear yes I see
you okay okay you be here too and there's also a wholesome intention etc etc let it
have a seat on the table but not the but not the megaphone so that's what I would say three diving and see that in your
own practice how that works so so thank you all thank you so much for your
practice thank you for letting your light shine cultivating your son and letting it shine and making
space for kind space for what there already is in this heart and mind may we
all wake up may we be happy and support all
beings in their happiness and waking up through our practice
[Music] thanks everyone be well