so good morning everyone welcome happy to be here with you
all and um as I prepare to give this talk uh
certainly what's happening in the Middle East is very much on my heart
and um you know the when I teach the Dharma sometimes it's
not explicit why I teach but I all my teaching is as a teacher is directed
towards trying to address the suffering of the world at hopefully at the deepest
level and um but there's so many different ways to get at that that sometimes it seems like I'm maybe not
talking about that directly so I'd like to uh dedicate
today's talk to the people who are suffering in the Middle East and certainly the Palestinians in Gaza were
so so many innocent Palestinians are dying and injured and homeless and it's
an must be U hellish to be there right now very difficult I think of all the
children who are going through how difficult it must be for them and how difficult it probably be for them for a
lifetime to go through this and the hostages that uh are also being held
isra hostages and it must be also hellish to be there and part of that and
so I dedicated to to the welfare and happiness and the peace for all the
people who are suffering Middle East so
um the um so conventionally the topic for today
is effort and uh the poly word that's often
translated as effort is viia and viia has a lot of different translations into
English and sometimes it's effort sometimes it's it's energy sometimes
it's endeavoring some people like the word persistence uh the word in in Sanskrit
has a kind of has association with courage or uh maybe even uh
heroism and we have in um I think in Tibetan Buddhism I believe sometimes this Baria is translated as heroic
effort because of the connotations that IA has and
um the um and the word that I'd like to use
today is vitality and having a embodied sense of
Vitality is a reference point for wisdom in Buddhist
practice and not just the emphasizing the importance of making effort but uh
how we make effort is important and the source of our effort is important within us and uh and by paying
attention to this uh we can develop a lot of wisdom about how we
practice this topic of how we make effort is so important that it could be
the only thing we ever need to talk about like everything you need to discover in Buddhism will be discovered
by how you make effort generally I like to think that when we do Buddhist practice 50% % of
our attention is focused on what we're doing and 50% of attention on how we're
doing it how we're doing it including the effort we're making as we do something is as important as what we're
doing what we're doing is important of course the Buddha said that um if you're trying
to make sesame oil by squeezing
gravel that's going to be unpr productive effort you have to know what to do that is to the point of what's
really what of what your intentions are and not be doing something that's not
right but then also how you do it is important and so as I said some people
like to translate the Veria as persistence because
uh uh the continuity of persistant effort is sometimes much more important
than the strength of the effort in fact the the turtle and the hair um
Fable is very up propo to Buddhist practice that uh sometimes making you
know heroic effort really strong effort um is actually counterproductive Buddhist practice if it stir us up stirs
us up and it's so easy to be stirred up like partly because when we make strong effort there tends to be a lot of self
and or ego involved in it and like I have to do it I have to be successful and I have to kind of fix what's going
on and and we gear up in a way that just kind of agitates the Mind more than
settles it but if we can practice with a settled effort but do it
persistently um and sometimes it doesn't look very hot the effort but the fact that it's being done continuously it
carries the day it carries the the lifetime for for our
practice there was um I wasn't there at the time but I've heard now from a few of my friends who were there um of a
large uh teaching that the Dal Lama gave in Arizona many years ago a big
convention center and thousands of people were there and he was giving some
teaching I don't know what he was teaching but then there was a period of uh questions that he would respond to
and a Gentleman stood up and stood by the mic to ask him a question and asked him um uh something like something like
um what what's the fastest way to Enlightenment and the diama was silent
for a long time and I was as I was told the story as it was told as it was told
to me a tear started to go down his cheek and he finally start spoke and
something to the effect of um it was so sad this idea that going for the fastest
way to Enlightenment that just represented kind of a kind of a wrong way of practicing a selfish way or
caught up way or misunderstanding of what practice is and it just made him
sad um you know for him he he he dedicated his whole lifetime to Buddhist
practice and when you did give yourself to the whole lifetime to it I think it tends to be a bit
humbling I think we we tend to understand how much there is to work with and how much there is to do and how
much there is the the work of of freeing ourselves from all the little and big
ways in which we're selfish and the way which we're uh afraid the ways that we're greedy the ways that we are um you
know have hostility or have ill will or aversion there's so many layers and layers and layers of ways we get stuck
and it takes a lot of patience sometimes to find our way through this practice
and so they're persistent just steadily keeping at it keeping at it and uh it's
remarkable how slowly things begin to shift and change the metaphor or the
analogy that I love for this is I don't know why I settled on this one maybe because I heard it this way or I used to
swim a fair amount and um but people who are like really you know athletic
swimmers uh competitive swimming um uh now I probably don't know
what I'm talking about but so you maybe just theal it go go along with with the analogy not
literally and uh and that is that uh you know they'll do the same stroke over and
over and over again tens of thousands of times and slowly each of you know each
time they do it in a most minuscule little way their body kind of begins to
tune into how to make it more efficient how to make it just just like a little
bit stronger uh stroke and little bit smoother and slowly slowly the this the
stroke becomes more and more efficient and more elegant but it it's not something that they can figure out for
their particular body you know by just reading a book and say this is how you do it you have to keep doing it over and
over and over again something begins shifting same thing with this practice we do it over and over and over again
and something begins shifting and changing you see it in people's meditation posture and when people are
beginner is in meditation posture um you know it's it's difficult it's stiff it's
challenging when I was in the Zen Monastery in Japan like this
real you know tough Zen Monastery in Japan uh they would some of the new monks had just come from college they
would go to Buddhist College some of them you know they they'd go to get a bachelor's or something and then from
there they'd go to the training Mony but some of the member had been athletes there and and for them they hadn't done
a lot of meditation and I remember they were just in excruciating pain and one of them who we
all slept together in the meditation Hall and so before he went to sleep he put a whole bunch of this like I don't
know like I don't know benay or this kind of this this this Menthol cream on
his legs to kind of get it to relax and the whole that meditation Hall was filled with his Menthol
thing and um but you know so but slowly slowly the body stretches and changes
and and all kinds of subtle ways and you can watch over a few years I've watched over a few years people's meditation
posture change until it's kind of like a yogic posture it almost like that now
they can sit there in a way that's stable and upright and without fidgeting but it's not a process that happens
overnight it's a slow slow process that from the continuity the Persistence of
doing it one of the things I'm maybe too fond of of uh
saying is I'll say I won't do it for you I'll save you from it so I'll just tell you what I
do is I'll say um uh Buddhist practice doesn't work I'll shake my head and do
just doesn't work and then I'll pause you know wow Gil says that um uh then
I'll add um uh if you don't do
it with the emphasis on you know you have to do it to make it work and so some people will have this idea it
doesn't work and they won't even try the Buddha said that this practice
that he was teaching or the Dharma that he was teaching is for the energetic not
for the lazy that's a quite a powerful statement for the energetic not for the
lazy and um and some people I know who are really busy people are actually lazy
and the reason why there's not seem as being lazy they're putting a lot of work into being busy but their business is
avoiding really facing what's difficult for them they're get they're being busy to get away because they don't want to
take the time and the effort to really confront and meet what's really going on for them in their lives and whether it's
in themselves or in relationships they're in or something so um so
Vitality as a as a as a possible aspect
of this word Viria energy and the reason I find that it's
such a wonderful word is that Vitality is a is not necessarily coming from um
uh self-conscious applying ourselves pushing
ourselves um there's many ways in which through the day that we gear ourselves up and push ourselves to kind of get
something and get and have something I suspect a fair number of people who drive cars are putting in a little bit
more effort than they need to when they drive their cars they're pushing leaning forward trying to get someplace little
bit more on the gas pedal little bit more clutching the steering wheel like they have to get there before the light turns red you know just like you know in
that kind of effort there and that's certainly energy but uh uh and it's it may be a
kind of um embodied energy of gearing up and getting tight and muscles are working
but uh it's not the same thing in my vocabulary of Vitality Vitality is a natural arising
of being enlivened without there being any stress
associated with that kind of energy so nonstressful
vitality and um the
um the writer the kind of a psychologist religious
writer from the 20th century called Joseph Campbell he wrote this very
interesting statement he said um
um uh something like again I'm not I'm not quite remembering it accurately
um um what people need the mo people people think what they need is a sense of meaning but most people are searching
for Vitality for a sense of I think he used the word aliveness a feeling of
being alive and there's some there can be this wonderful sense of being alive
vital that Vitality of being alive that's satisfying in and of itself that
just oh it's so good like it's easy to be content it's easy to be happy to be alive um and we sometimes we get that
from doing certain things you're going for a nice hike or doing something really fun like a maybe Sports or
playing a musical instrument or something that kind of sets Something Free that then we have when we're
finished we feel a sense of Vitality that is uh very different than
um feeling like we've been pushing and trying and working hard to make something
happen and so um this sense of aliveness and I think that a lot uh to
maybe say the same thing as Joseph Campbell I think a lot of uh the effort
people make is to uh try to solve their suffering try to get away from it to
find something to do that can assuage it to bring Comfort to bring safety
avoidance that's are often driven by suffer but you know to to somehow deal and cope with our
suffering and sometimes in doing that we're making the effort in it kind of in
the wrong direction we're kind of squeezing the gravel rather than uh
turning inward to where the guess sesame oil in Ancient India was pretty
special and uh and so to turn it Inward and to pay attention to how we make
effort how we're doing anything at all and what's the consequences of it so one
for examp one example I've For Me Maybe it's for some of you as well that um my
effort can sometimes go into uh problem solving I'm worried about
something concerned about something trying to figure something out in my head or I'm involved in
fantasy all kinds of different things and um and so um I leave it to your
imagination what a Buddhist teacher fantasizes
about and uh and uh and I can feel that the energy
of that effort has gone up in the top of my head and it's feel to me it feels like it's going in spirals that are
getting Tighter and Tighter that energy it's like working sometimes I feel this
mental energy being caught up in the thought streams that I'm in and it feels really agitated and rather than
spiraling around in faster and faster way or tighter and way it just feels scattered like ping pong balls are going
on in there and uh sometimes I can feel the effort of thinking uh involves pressure
or tension in my forehead and my scalp in my head in my shoulders and all kinds
of different ways the Buddha described uh had this analogy of of the how the
mind works as being a puppeteer and it has all these strings that go down to all the different muscles in our body
and that the mind is kind of pulling on those strings strings of tension and we
get tight in the shoulders and the belly with what's goes on and and the beautiful thing about the freedom that
comes from Buddhist practice is um we no longer have a
puppeteer that we no longer have this activity in the mind which is has this
negative kind of tentacles that go out and affect the rest of our body in all kinds of ways the body starts becoming
relaxed so the energies that can be up in the head the effort of trying to make something happen or figure something out
you know whatever and um but the Vitality is a whole different species of
energy Vitality is not dependent on what we're doing but how at ease we are in
ourselves and how awake we are how much Clarity there is in our being and how we
are now that for in my for me the word Vitality has a feeling of being clean
something very clean about it it just feels good to be alive here I am and once we have this kind of
settled relaxed calm sense of Vitality uh some people might call it
Chi or Kei in Japanese and now chi in Chinese uh
there's something there's an upwelling of a nice sense of aliveness that's here that um that can boy us up that can
support us so when we meditate it's not a matter of applying effort when we
meditate but rather it's riding like a maybe like
a you know a boat rides the waves or rides on the on the surface of the ocean
that's a matter of riding the vi riding the natural Vitality the natur natural
aliveness that's here within us so it's not so much applying effort to pay
attention to the breathing but relaxing and allowing ourselves to float to the
vitality the energy that's in the body that requires us to be
breathing so it's kind of a floating on that sense of movement and energy and
activity that goes on as the body breathes and that's a very different feeling the floating on top of it and
allowing it the natural Vitality as opposed to being the one who has to have
a laser focus the one who has okay now I got to try hard let's try it now let's make me more
effort and um and so to start having a reference point for this clean Vitality
this nice way of being alive and using that as a this is where
the wisdom part comes in using that to see how we start applying a different
kind of energy effort in our lives to be able to have that contrast between how
to be at ease and relaxed in the body in the in the body's
vitality and how we lose that when we start making self-conscious effort oh
I'm late for a meeting I better get there fast and we certainly can have a lot of energy and we get there and we've
you know we've got walked really fast maybe we even ran to the meeting and we sit down there's a lot of energy
coursing through our body from all that effort and energy but some of that will
not feel like the delightful Vitality some of it might but it came
from the stress of trying to not wanting to be late and trying so hard and and it it comes along with um energy that goes
with being tense and so then that tension carries
momentum that tension because it's uncomfortable stress that's uncomfortable that generates more
stress we're stressful we're stressed so we try harder we don't like the stress that
comes from trying harder because and so it's uncomfortable so the solution what
is to try harder and some of that is unconscious but it plays itself out in
what we're thinking about what we're concerned with and how the mind it goes into these habitual Loops of thoughts
and ideas of what we need to do and but if you can start feeling the
energy the energetics of your thinking habits it's thinking
loops and and that's the how you're making the effort all the energy that there the tension that's
there and then you say is this the how by which I want to
live which is kind of the central Buddhist questions how do you want to be not what
do you want to be how do you want to be and uh how do you want to be alive
Here and Now and the what you want to be is certainly relevant and important
sometimes but I think that we have a culture that is a little bit too tied up in that what I need to be the whole idea
of identity and identity politics and asserting yourself and being someone
that and being self-promotions you know is really big in our
society and uh yesterday I saw a website for someone who was a Buddhist teacher
it just seemed like 100% self-promotion in the way that I've seen
for other people who are trying to promote their services and themselves as being you know the leading person in
their field and what they're doing and I said what is a Buddhist teacher doing with this kind of clear and making
claims about himself that no self-respecting
you know for a thousand years 2500 years Buddhist no self-respect ing Buddhist
would ever say such a thing it just doesn't you know at least that that I know of the way I was trained in
Buddhism like where does this come from this comes out of a culture of this kind of self-centered being someone and
proving yourself and you know and this self-promotion and and then those of us
who are following in the wake of that it's so easy to when it's in a culture to kind of little bit
start it becomes NE it becomes normal I'm supposed to do this and then we get
goes go along I'll tell you a story of many years ago when I first moved here to the
peninsula I lived up on Skyline and that's irrelevant to the story but I had
um I had um I had been given a I think it was
a 15-year-old Toyota Celica and um you know and it was red
which was cool but it was you know it was just kind of old car and um so I was I I
lived in San Francisco first and in there I just drove this old car around kind of and there was no no thought
about it I just happy content with it having it and then when I came here to live in
a peninsula and I'd come down to paloalto to teach after a while I noticed you know I
had one of the oldest cars on the streets it wasn't that old right but it was one of the oldest cars being
paloalto even back then and then at being there long enough at
some point I had these thoughts maybe I should get a new
car as long as I was living in San Francisco there wasn't that kind of reference point of all lots of everyone
has new cars but you know but here in PA Alto there was that reference point and
it slowly Creed in innocently so this self-promotional kind
of culture that we have kind of comes along and act you know kind of unconsciously seeps in and and then we
feel like I'm not good enough I'm not doing the great and wonderful thing that I'm not you know don't have a website
yet and um and so so a lot of this unhealthy kind of
Vitality that comes from pushing and trying to be something and proving
ourselves or apologizing for ourselves or do these things we can feel the different how that doesn't feel
good and so the shift in Buddhism is for many people is to now
pay attention to how am I right now not what am I and that's where Joseph goldstein's
little quote I think is quite significant that he um that maybe what
we're looking for is sense of aliveness that's been
misplaced in Buddhism we would say we're looking for a sense of Freedom that has
been misplaced and maybe those two things are not so separate to really feel a healthy
sense of aliveness there has to be no longer the pushing the straining the stressing the
self assertion that involves a very different kind of energy than the energy of Vitality
which uh you know can come from uh really enjoying what you're doing for
its own sake and so that's one of the you know
one of the signposts of meditation beginning to really uh benefit us and
providing a lot of wisdom is when we sit down to meditate and the body has settled into
the the posture and we're at home in the posture the mind has learned to calm down we've
learned to recognize how we strain and push and how we tend to beat ourselves up and be critical and we learned to
recognize these things and we learn to settle them enough that we begin paying
attention to the quality of our inner life how am I and that quality of the inner life one
of the things that kind of become sensitive to what's that sens what's the quality of being alive right now
is there a it's a Vitality that feels good and this can be equally uh valid or
or important way of uh checking in with oneself when one is is sick or injured
as well and sometimes it's actually more important in those situations where conventionally you don't have much
energy you're exhausted because being sick chronically sick or something um and I've been sick and um
it was wonderful to be sick or injured uh when I was in the monastery uh doing
a lot of Buddhist practice and it was I was I learned so much about myself in that environment where the practice was
so you know right in my face it's like always having to be close to the
practice and there were times when I was so sick that um uh that in order to
manage I still had to go do the mon work and um or I did it and in order to
manage with it I had to be very careful to how I was doing what I was doing not
only that I had to pay very careful attention to what I was thinking and and I could see if I
thought certain thoughts I would feel sicker my Vitality would
diminish if I thought other thoughts it would come back not dramatically but the
between those two were enough between managing and not managing I there was times also in the
monastery where my back went out and it was horrendous for me I thought I was I was so much pain and and there too I got
what was so wonderful about it was um uh the you know ordinarily I have a lot
of slack in my body I can get away with a fair amount of things you know without
it you know I have arranged where I can do things but when I had my back went out the range was so so almost no range
at all so much so I couldn't even think certain thoughts without it affecting my
back and and so I learned this reference point of of energy of Vitality of stress
that I carry my body became such an important ref not became important it
became an essential reference point when I was really sick and really um injured
just watching it very carefully and um without thinking I had
to be super vital you know like the embodiment of Vitality for anybody it just like I was just trying to cope but
it was such a valuable way to understand myself I learned so much about how my
mind works when I was sick and the difference had made how to be present so
hopefully you don't have to wait until you're sick for that but uh this is part of what we do in
mindfulness practice is we start uh becoming more and more mindful of how we are not just what we're doing and one of
the areas of how we are is our sense of Vitality and um and the kind of effort
we make when I was a new Buddhist practitioner the big big kind of
exploration was how to make not too much effort and not too little effort and for
a long time I learned that it was I was never going to get it right but I could get the swings be
smaller and smaller just like driving down the freeway I you know I don't know
for some of you maybe now that you some of you have cars are self-driving and they're
straight but I'm constantly almost you know unselfconsciously without any thought making ever so slight
adjustments as I'm going down the straight Lane on the freeway um and um and you know and you
know just just finding my way so same thing with meditation effort there's oh there's too much that's too little so
there was a long years where that was part of the reference point like how to do that and oh that's too much let's try
to back off and oh that I backed off too much now and it was not making enough and let's come back and finding my
way and then over time I learned that there are different kinds of energy in
system and that uh there's the self-conscious energy there's the pushing energy there's the the the me
that's making the effort and then there's the Vitality which is the natural Vitality
the chi of the system that also varies over different
circumstances but to begin having that as a reference point is really helpful
and I'll end with this because it's possible as you go through the today to
pay attention to what is happening to your native
Vitality in the posture with which you sit in a chair with your Vitality by how you sit
in your car seat with your driving the Vitality about how you listen to someone else
talking what's the Vitality in your body posture and how you are when you're
doing something you don't want to do what is the V what's the sense of energy
or aliveness inside of you when uh you're in conflict with someone what
happens there within you what is taking precedence and what what what can you learn from that because when you're in
conflict with someone and the sense of energy now feels stressful and tight
or you're the one who's responsible for that not the person you're in conflict with you're the ones source of the
energy and so oh is this really how I want to be this how I need to be is
there another way is there another way of being alive here how to be where I'm
actually more productive more effective more wiser in being in the
conflict and I've certainly learned that when I'm stressed in Conflict I can make
a lot of mistakes speak out of terms and speak with things I wish I didn't say
afterwards be more unconscious about what's really driving me but if I'm
relaxed and it ease in the conflict I'm actually able to stay involved in a much more useful
way so what's your Vitality what's your sense of
aliveness is it one that brings you satisfaction feels good it feels like oh
yeah it's good to be alive now even it's even if that aliveness is very teeny in
you oh there it is that feels good or is your inner sense of
aliveness one that feels difficult and if it is difficult what is
a need from you what is a need for how you are with
it not what you do to it but how you are to it and then maybe you could meet it with
some of the Vitality the aliveness of your own heart to meet it with your kindness with
your love so those are my thoughts for today
and uh we have about we have a few minutes here if anyone wants to ask any questions or comments or
testimonials about
vitality
push the felt to make it green got
it um thank you Gil this is really lovely and
um I'm curious to have I feel conflicted
because the question in my mind is one of when there's urgent situations where
action is needed and that and I often feel that um the practice of Buddhism is
about taking more time stepping back like you said said and that feels I'm
I'm In conflict with that when there's urgent matters and how to take action in a way
that keeps balance so um I'm sorry that you feel in conflict with that that's a strong word
for me but I'd like to say that that's a very wise
concern that you should have because that's the that's that that's often the
the asso ation people have with Buddhism you're supposed to do things slowly and calmly and some situations that's not
what's called for and what's called for is to do things fast and efficiently and
quickly and um um I remember friend of mine many
years ago ran a ma was involved with a company that sent out I know male mail
their their product out to people who who ordered it and they hired someone
from from the Zen Monastery to work there and the person was you know
putting the things into the box slowly stood there a little while and
observed how that was maybe moved the product around the Box a little bit and then close the lid and you can't run a
business that way so the person lost the job and then when I was um when I left
the monastery I was uh the San the San Francisco Zen Center still has back then
it had um The Greens restaurant in San Francisco which is a little bit a fast
food place to work work and I was a signed when we when when we as monks had to go work there now they pay people but
back then it was I got you know I worked five and a half days a week and got paid $60 a
month for working there and um so but I loved working there but so I came from
the monastery and I worked there and it was obvious being on the the lunch crew making lunch
that you couldn't do things slowly and what I learned was how to do things fast
and mindfully Fast and calmly with inner calm and I loved it there was a dance I
was spinning around and I multitasking you know you had I had all these different dishes I had to kind of prepare at the same time and the pizz
were in the oven you had to do something else while they're in there you don't stand in front of the pizza of and waiting for the pizza to be done and uh and uh
and the idea was how to be fully present and engaged without being
stressed and so that's the art so yes definitely let's not uh we can we can
learn to be calm but uh and sometimes it takes a while to learn how to have a
foundation of being maybe calm and slow in order to learn the basics uh and then once you know it well
then we need to respond appropriately to the situation but hopefully without any
stress it's urgent it's so urgent it's so important
the last thing you want to do is to be stressed let's but let's do it
vigorously I grew up
I grew up in paloalto and so that message of try harder definitely sep in
in many different ways so one of the mantras that I like now is try
softer uh and then maybe we could add try softer but
persistently just keep keep steady keep steady at least at least in terms of Buddhist practice
practice it carries the day and also if you get enlightened
slower it might be a better
Enlightenment so you pass it back
there um so it was a follow-up question too kind of the question that the lady
shared um during the time when you're working um at the restaurant what are
some of the things that helped you to what were some of the things that helped you to stay Mindful and calm in a
fast-paced environment thank you well um the um the the practice that I had
then the kind of in in what I what I learned to do in Zen Monastery which
then I applied to working at that restaurant when I came there was the question for me was not um how should I
be mindful of this situation uh because sometimes when uh that's a little bit removed from what
you're doing to ask how to be mindful at sometimes and rather I asked myself uh
the practi was how do I participate more fully with what I'm doing and um and I learned in the
monastery how much I only participated half-heartedly quarter heartedly you know sometimes I like
especially if I didn't want to do something I like oh I'm not going to really give myself to it and but in the
monastery I learned the joy of giving myself fully to what I was doing and this a full Engagement full
participation so when I was there at The Greens restaurant that that was my task
how do I how do I participate in this fully the consequence of that was that I
had to be mindful I had to be very aware of everything I was going on but the awareness followed in the wake of
participating uh as opposed to the awareness leading what I was doing and so I became very
present in fact by the time I left work uh end of the end of the work day I was
more concentrated than when I came because I was so fully present there for what was going on and I wasn't lost in
any particular detail it was like I was participating in the whole thing and
tracking many different things and um and whatever came and one of the things I loved doing was I was
doing all this you know I was fully in the present moment doing all this different stuff and then all these
dishes and putting them up for the waiters to come and take them to serve to the people eating there and then I
also at some point I tried to have this um to have a conversation a relationship with each of the waiters and try to
remember what we had talked about between dishes when they came in and tried to have a kind of a kind of a
meaningful connection with them on top top of it all so it was a fun time for me and you know and I was much younger
so so I had a lot of energy then so probably what it would look like now if
I worked at greens you know that I'd probably have to have a little bit of
allowance to do things slower and take breaks than wholeheartedly now full
participation now means would mean with the energy and the stamina that have now
in my age that does that answer your question
is good enough because there's a lot of could have said but was a good
question okay well thank you for being here and appreciate it very much and um one
thing I could add as you're leaving is um uh every year we do a yearend letter
for kind of kind of a fundraising letter for IMC and um and we never really ask
for funds here think I don't know if you never we never ask for things and and in fact if you Le the looks like a
fundraising letter it smells like it if you shake it it shakes like one and um
they actually don't ask but there is a remate envelope but this year I Tred to write
the I write I always one who writes the letter and this year I thought I want to write the less boring letter and uh I
want to do something that has some something that's memorable in terms of the Dharma so anyway so if you want to pick
it up and read it it's on the counter as you leave and um but I could well
imagine people don't want that that that's
okay thank you