welcome everyone welcome to the morning meditation I'm really enjoying being
with you and reading the chat greetings from everyone to
everyone this week is dedicated to cultivating wholesome beautiful states
of mind yesterday we discussed meta the Brahma vihara or Divine Abode
of goodwi friendliness loving kindness It's a wholesome inclination of
mind that can meet all of experience as well as a healthy way to
relate to ourselves and others when goodwi meets suffering it
manifests as Compassion or karuna in the ancient poly
language compassion is many things but it's a
sympathetic vibration of the heart or response of the heart that knows looking
at someone else's suffering that if we had the same conditions we would be
struggling in the same ways and compassion wishes for suffering to
end it's a practice that helps us grow beyond the self-concern that can keep us
wrapped up in the problems and suffering struggle stress dissatisfaction in our own
lives and if we're fortunate enough not to be experiencing difficulty compassion
practice helps us prepare for the future pain or suffering that's likely to occur
when we experience loss sickness aging death
this is a time of year that can seem to magnify excuse me magnify the suffering
that we see around us and make clear the need for
compassion the disparities to which The Human Condition subjects people stand
out really strongly to people many people lately in particular
disparity surrounds us there's abundant wealth and there's crushing deprivation
Everywhere You Look Around the Globe and this was true at the time of
the Buddha two about 2500 years ago it's been true ever
since so there are ways that the Brahma vihara practices of loving
kindness compassion sympathetic Joy joy and equinity can support us in growing
our ability to feel compassion for all of what happens to ourselves and our
fellow human beings and fellow beings of all kinds on this
planet it helps us to stop and realize what suffering actually is and how it
affects all of life and as we progress through these
practices will also touch into how to hold it all with a balanced mind and
heart so that we're not crushed with despair looking at all of
this meditation practice and mindfulness in everyday life develop the heart and
mind in the direction of compassion and bit by bit we build this
capacity to be present and not a void or look away or pretend intense suffering
isn't happening as with the other Divine abodes we can also deliberately practice
compassion starting where it's relatively more doable or more uh we
have an ability to do it without succumbing to grief so with that let's
begin our meditation today
settling
in perhaps starting with a few long slow deep
breaths allowing the out breath to release any tension from the
body that can be let
go and letting the breathing return to whatever is normal for you there's no
special kind of Brea breathing needed for this
practice giving yourself time to find a comfortable way of
sitting standing or lying down that is also alert and it's okay during Brahma power
of practice to adjust the posture when you need
to during the course of our sitting being uncomfortable does not
support wholesome states of Mind especially if it causes pain that
lasts so taking time and bringing ease and
care to the body
the heart and the
mind receiving whatever is present whatever arises as it becomes
prominent in awareness
allowing it time and space to be known no need to
rush no need to go out looking for experience just allowing it to arrive in
its own way and no need to push anything away
there's no right or wrong thing occurring in
meditation awareness receives everything
equally and if there are difficult or unpleasant experiences that present
themselves in Awareness meeting them with the kind of care you might offer a good
friend offering compassion to whatever difficulties arise during
meditation during the day perhaps with the silent wish may this difficulty come to an
end not as a demand or an agenda simply as a gentle
wish may it be so may this difficulty come to an
end
receiving the pleasant the unpleasant and experiences that are
neither Pleasant nor unpleasant receiving an all with care
with
kindness during this this meditation if if it fits for you I'll offer a practice of sending
compassion to a living friend you can pick someone with whom
you have an uncomplicated good relationship whom you know to be
struggling a little dissatisfied perhaps
suffering and if this does not suit where you are in meditation simply let
my voice Fade Into the background and continue in whatever way
suits
you for those who wish to engage in this compassion practice bring to mind the friend whom
you know to be having some difficulty perhaps not the worst
suffering or situations uh that tend to pull you into reactive emotions pick
something simpler to start with and when you're
ready letting your mind and heart fill with images and memories of
this person
a felt sense of what it's like to be with
them bringing to mind their
goodness and then seeing them in their current
struggle and noticing how they are in the face of that
difficulty and as you fill the heart and mind with them inclining your mind to
wishes of compassion without any agenda to fix
your friend without any idea that their suffering has to go away as a result of
your meditation not solving their problems accepting them just as they
are right
now and then perhaps taking in the following
phrases seeing which resonate with you for your
friend you can simply receive them hear them or you can silently
repeat them radiating them towards your
friend
I care about you your suffering matters to
me may you open to this difficulty with gentleness and compassion for
yourself
may you meet this suffering with ease and
kindness
may you be free of stress and
suffering perhaps continuing to repeat these
phrases or other phrases that come to your mind as expressions of
compassion for your friend without solving their
problems may you open to this difficulty with gentleness and
compassion may you be free of stress and
suffering and continuing either with phrases or with a felt sense of caring
and compassion as we continue the meditation in
silence
[Music]
and an invitation it's traditional uh to
continue meditating as you hear Reflections like the ones that I'll offer so you're
welcome to continue to receive experience as it arises in the body the
heart and the mind as I offer these
comments and then you can see what sticks from the reflections I I used to
make an effort to take two or three things from each of Gill's talks for many years that I could
practice with during the day or during the week so the whole 45 minutes could
be considered a meditation so uh the poly word karuna is
translated as compassion and it's what good will or
loving kindness feels when it encounters suffering it wants the suffering to
end Gil has written that compassion is sometimes referred to as the jewel in
the Lotus the Lotus symbolizes the heart or mind that with practice blossoms into
freedom and the Jewel represents the compassion appearing in the center of
this blossom so that's how important this is in this
practice we can cultivate this wholehearted caring for anyone who's
suffering for ourselves and for others and compassion is not pity it
doesn't look down on suffering from a position of privilege when we practice compassion
wholeheartedly we put ourselves into someone else's shoes and we know only too well that if we
were living their life with their conditions we would be suffering in the same
ways so in addition to sending compassion to those who are innocent um
and on the receiving end of difficult conditions that just come with human
life we can also cultivate it for people who are are engaging in unskillful
actions that cause harm and this practice does not come automatically or
easily it takes time and plenty of mindfulness to get Beyond anger at those
who harm others and to begin to see the way that greed hatred and delusion are
distorting their minds and their actions it also takes some time to separate the
person from their harmful behavior and to see that even if they seem
perfectly fine content happy as they perpetrate harm we can know that at some
point their behavior rebounds into enormous suffering for them as well at
least in the terms of Liberation from suffering from from
harm so in terms of the full practice of the Dharma full liberation of our hearts
and Minds until we can grow to cultivate the compassionate wish for all people
all beings to come to the end of suffering suffering will not end among
human beings of course we can certainly take
action in the world um to bring harmful behaviors to an end
so true compassion especially if we decide to support or help another person
or group of people has this ability to differentiate we work at differentiating
between what's helpful and what's one's own agenda so it is most helpful to begin
with respect listening to the person or the
people who are suffering and hearing what they might find helpful rather than
deciding that we know the solutions to their problems I there's a simple
example of this that I guess many people on this Zoom or YouTube have
experienced and that is when one member of a couple or family is upset by
something that happened at work or school or in one of their friendships and they tell they come home and they
tell someone else or they tell everyone and when somebody instead of listening
just listening with care when The Listener jumps into advice giving mode often the
person who's sharing either seems to fight back against the advice or grow
frustrated in some way very often when somebody's sharing from their heart like
this they're really just wanting someone else to understand and hear their situation not to try to solve their
problems for them
of course we can also be understandably unhappy about our own past unskillful
actions we've been if we've been around for a few decades there's probably something we've done that we've
regretted and we can cultivate an expansiveness or an inclusivity of heart
and mind that allow us to be open and be present with the resultant discomfort
that's that discomfort is a healthy conscience at work we can move forward
into compassion for the ignorance in our own past that led to our harming
ourselves or harming others and BEC this is because endless
self-punishment won't do the world any good it won't do you any good so
recognizing what was harmful and growing towards what is nonharming will help those around us as
well as ourselves release from the suffering and move towards
Freedom as we start this process we're using words to begin to embody
compassionate wishes uh and sometimes when people hear the word
compassion they believe they have to feel highly emotional or kind of almost
oozing Compassion or or sentimental and that isn't the case so the word
compassion in one dictionary definition means to feel with but that doesn't mean
we jump down into the pit of suffering with someone else the heart and mind can
be moved uh we can care a great deal and
still be equanimous a bit
objective um today some of you may have experimented with this practice of
silently saying compassion phrases as I offered that and that can start any of
these practices of Brahma viharas and saying phrases can start as a feeling
like they're just words but over time the more we bring our hearts and our
heads together in mindfulness and in meditation the more we see the benefit
of wholesome inclinations of mind the more the heart gradually opens to this
and in the process we grow the capacity to be with suffering in a caring way
instead of keeping it at arms length at a distance or instead of pitting anyone
who is suffering or instead of being hard on ourselves because we're
suffering we can start by offering care for the difficulties we're
experiencing if that's relatively accessible uh that can provide a
reference point from which we can genuinely develop a caring compassion
for others um and there's there's a phrase that sort of exemplifies this just as I
wish to be happy and free from suffering so may that being may all being
be happy and free from
suffering excuse me the next person to whom we might
traditionally offer silent wishes of compassion might be someone towards whom
you have a loving respectful relationship could be a mentor a valued
teacher or someone who's been completely supportive in your life
um and th by the way this practice is intended to develop to develop your
Capac capacity to be compassionate towards the
living so when you choose people to whom you'd like to direct these phrases or
this feeling pick someone who's alive after being able to offer
compassion to someone with whom you have this very supportive relationship that helps develop us
towards being able to offer silent compassion for a friend or a family
member someone who we dearly love but maybe we have a relationship that you
know has ups and downs the next step in developing compassion to its fullest is to offer
compassion to a stranger and this is usually someone you see in your life
regularly like a letter carrier or someone whose name you see on this chat
but it's someone you don't really know and then the the final stage in
formal compassion practice is to direct thoughts of compassion towards people
with whom you have difficulty or you dislike them traditionally it's called
the enemy but maybe you don't feel like you have enemies or you might as you become able to do that
you're really developing this state of mind that can really understand and kind
of get on a visceral level that people are not fixed in their nature nor are
you nothing is everything is in constant and
changing sometimes rapidly sometimes very slowly and all conditioned
phenomena including the behavior of others it's all subject to suffering or
Dua in the poly language it's all has this
unsatisfactoriness when we still on some level believe that uh there are things that
can be in this conditioned realm of human existence that can be relied on
all the time for happiness or that things will remain stable and satisfying
or that they have a fixed nature that we can use as a sense of security as long
as we believe on any of that and sometimes we don't even know it but underneath we do believe that we
continue to have stress dissatisfaction and suffering but we can grow um with caring
and compassion in the same way that we can grow Good Will and the other Divine
abodes by paying attention to them in daily life and also by meditating them
with them in this formal way that really gets absorbed in who you're sending the
feelings towards and filling your mind and heart with them and then really
staying with this practice it develops this quality of collected mind fully
gathered mind a Sade that ultimately is
a source of growth and in in insight and in
wisdom and wisdom is one of the keys to becoming free from stress and
suffering so the meditation practice and daily life practice with these Brahma
viharas tends to support they tend to support one another so they come to a
point if we do them frequently enough and keep keep at the mindfulness they
tend to arise more naturally in Us in response to what's happening around us
uh the Mind becomes very stable and flexible able to deal with ups and downs
without reactivity um and we get to a place where we can remain capable and calm in
the face of whatever comes our way so for those of you who want to
continue or start to treat today and this week like a
retreat you might allow yourself to notice what brings up a response of
compassion or caring in you today and silently you could
send this radiate this compassion this care wishes for relief from stress
suffering dissatisfaction towards anyone who you know is having a hard
time of course if you're in a position to actively help taking the time to listen
deeply and carefully to what that person wants in the way of support but this is
a great way to bring the compassion practice into your day I wish you
all freedom from stress and suffering and an enjoyable day exploring this
practice if you choose to do that see you tomorrow morning be
well