so it's nice to be here and see all of you is the sound okay you hear the okay
great so I'll start this morning with a
proposal and it's something that can be verified with mindfulness
and that is that the human mind has a lot of desires
so what I'm calling desire here is quite broad let's say that it refers to any
kind of wanting whether gross or subtle so you know we have a desire for food
when we're hungry we have desire if we're
hoping to get home in time to get to an important Zoom meeting
or I had the desire to drive to Redwood City this morning at some level otherwise I probably
wouldn't have gotten here and sometimes desire comes in the form
of not wanting something right we maybe we want the neighbor's dog to stop
barking or also this morning while I was driving here there was a squirrel crossing the
lane in front of me there were no other cars coming but halfway across the road
it changed his mind and came back and and so I slowed way down it wasn't clear
which way it was going to go and I definitely I felt my mind narrowing which it does through desire but I
didn't want to hurt the squirrel I had a strong desire not to hit the squirrel with my car
and luckily it headed back into the grass so you know there's a lot of desires and
then there can be more subtle desires like while we're while we're sitting
often it's hard to sit in the same position for a long time we actually will subtly shift our weight
even when we're meditating sometimes but also on the computer and that's just because you know there's a desire to
move or shift the body isn't meant to be in the same position for a long time
or we can sit in meditation and subtly be holding on to a state of calm for
example we want that to continue now that we've got it so
there's a lot so let me ask a question then how many
of you would agree if I say that the second Noble
Truth of the cause of suffering says that the cause of suffering is desire
yeah that's often what we hear I see some hands not not not all the hands
so you know there's a lot of wanting in the mind and what's going on with that and so another
proposal that can also be checked is that at some level we tend to think that
fulfilling our desires is going to bring happiness or at least it's going to make things better than it is now so we
fulfill desire after desire to try to get things that we like or get things
that feel Pleasant so that we can sustain a sense of some kind of happiness or ease or safety or
well-being whatever word we use for it so it's actually not such a ridiculous
idea to to want those things in our life
um but it may not be complete have the idea that we need to keep
wanting things and getting them in order to be safe or happy or have well-being
and if we practice mindfulness we will start to see more of the picture
so if we keep looking with mindfulness there's a couple things we might see there's a lot of things we might see but
I'll just highlight a couple of them one of them is that it is not entirely
the case that we can become Happy by fulfilling desires
how many would agree with that yeah so nearly all the hands went up for that one so you know it's it's tiring to
constantly be going from thing to thing to thing and we have to keep at it right because each one lasts for a while but
not forever so there's always and then there's always one more thing coming one more refinement one more next thing that we
want and all of this is not entirely in our control is it you know at some level we
understand that the things that we want we don't have complete ability to get
some things it's easy sort of it's pretty likely you can take your
next breath but not always right but that's pretty
likely that one's pretty likely but other things that we try to get that we have to buy or that we have to go and
acquire or get from somebody else there's a whole other set of conditions
out there that are not in our control about whether we can get that right if we start looking more clearly
so we may not be able to get what we want or get rid of what we don't want
how about that what does the Mind do with that so our quest to find happiness by
fulfilling desires gets more and more suspect as we practice mindfulness
and then maybe the second thing that we would realize is that not all desires are actually harmful for
us not completely I deliberately painted a little bit of a complex picture at the
beginning with all the things that I pointed toward so some desires might be
useful on the spiritual path maybe right and some of the very real happiness that
we get from fulfilling desires because there is a kind of Happiness we get from that some of that might be good for us
you know how about the peace that you get from coming to IMC or watching on
YouTube you know that seems useful doesn't it settle the heart and mind better than doing something else with this hour hour
and a half so we're gonna have to look more carefully at these issues of desire and wanting
so I'll just say clearly so it's so it's stated are all desires bad
no no but we have to have a lot of wisdom about that
so yeah the Buddha was actually quite nuanced in his teachings on desire he
taught in different ways at different times he taught different people differently knowing where they were on the spiritual path
but basically he noticed I think he was brilliant that he noticed that there is in the mind a tendency to move toward
things also a tendency to move away which is related you know we're here and
we want to move toward there let's broadly call that desire and so he
thought well you know people have this tendency of wanting to move toward and away which is to some degree equality of
the unawakened mind but we have it so why not use it why not use it on the
path to move toward things that are actually helpful so I want to talk about this
desire that we have this movement toward I like
to say that there's a broad range of Desire or a diversity of Desire
kind of like a spectrum of Desire but it's not really linear it's not really a linear sequence it's more like a space
so I'm going to frame it today as five aspects of Desire or five classes of
Desire this is not a canonical list from the Buddha but all of them are talked
about in the teachings and I've just kind of gathered them together you can see if it's I hope it's a useful
way of classifying things so as we get in touch with these I'm
going to talk about each one you might just sense for yourself oh okay is that present in me how does that operate in
my life how does that resonate for me so the first kind of Desire clearly in
the unwholesome part of the space is the one that's called a tanha that's
the Pali word tanha and it literally means thirst but it's usually translated
as craving this is a kind of grasping kind of Desire that is obviously painful
obviously harmful you know it it's a gripping essentially it relates to lust
or greed or kind of extreme wanting that we have and you know we've we've
probably we've all experienced this actually uh and when this kind of craving is
about the world of the senses which it often is we call it comma comma tanha
which means it's desire for sensual things sense desire or sense pleasure
like the Kama Sutra you may have heard of very much about sensuality
and so um kamatanha is strong grasping of sensual
objects it's not really about the object itself it's in the mind you know so we
might have strong grasping at ice cream at a certain time and not at another
time right it's not about the ice cream it's about how much we wanted at a given time or we might be caught up in how we
look you know our clothing our hairdo or various sexual fantasies and desires
a particular form of this kind of Desire is addiction to alcohol or drugs
so tanha generally causes trouble for us and it's
a clearly a Troublesome one it can also relate to things that aren't sensual I emphasize that one but there are other
things we can have lust for power or for having a certain identity being a scene
in a certain way that can also be the realm of tanha so it's obvious that these kind of desires
don't support the path to Liberation right they are themselves binding for
the mind and then maybe a second class of desires
basic desires that are related to bodily needs we all have these to need to eat
the need to drink they need to use the bathroom so these desires are not usually seen as
inherently harmful but they are somewhat stressful aren't they
how we relate to the desires and needs of the body influences how happy or
unhappy we are even awaken people still feel physical hunger and they still have the need to
pee that still happens um there's one suta that says that even
arahans who are fully awakened beings feel Sensations that are according to
the suta dependent on the body and conditioned by life so there you go you don't you're not
going to overcome those basic things even the Buddha had back pain you know they're not all Pleasant these things
related to the body but there is some distinction between beings regarding whether or not these
bodily desires bring any dukkha any suffering
then there's a third class of Desire very big one that's related to the
desires that it takes to fulfill a human life you know trying to live a typical
human life among other humans we have desires that go with that the desire to
find a livelihood may be the desire to have a partner the desire to be part of
a community to secure a place to live and have access to food that we like all
of these desires this is the world many of us live in from day to day these
desires take a lot of energy a lot of our attention and effort
and they're Myriad I can't even name them all I just named a few relationships politics family life all
these worldly desires uh Gill sometimes says that we should call ourselves
instead of human beings we should be called human desirlings which I think is that's always struck me
I've heard that from him years and years ago and it stuck with me so these kinds of desires are very
interesting for the spiritual path because they're the ones that we tend to defend as normal and even necessary you
know if I didn't have those desires what would I do I just sit on the couch all day I'd be you know I'd be a couch potato I wouldn't do anything I couldn't
accomplish things I couldn't help people I couldn't serve my family so we tend to
mark these desires off as off limits this is necessary we don't even you know
how can we even question those the Buddha asked us to put a few question marks on those
as to whether or not we have to pursue them with any kind of grasping
so it's a big realm for Dharma practice because this realm of desires occupies
much of our day these are the ones that we go from one to one to one throughout our day right
so many of them are mild forms of what I call comma before the world of sense
desires and sensual Pleasures not all of them are tanha that grasping kind of Desire but their comma this this world
of the senses and we don't have to have deep pathological grasping in order to
be somewhat enslaved to our desires and the Buddha asked us to question that
enslavement and see if we could find other ways to live our life such that it doesn't have
that inherent stress associated with all those things
so then continuing with the five classes of Desire with a fourth one I would call
our more elevated human wishes um
there are various words for this wholesome skillful refined elevated
spiritual choose the word that works for you but these include wishing to be ethical
wishing to be kind wanting a peaceful and happy life where we are able to care more about how we're
living than about money or status wanting to learn to meditate wanting to
learn the spiritual teachings desire for the well-being of others
These are nice desires these are generally very good desires these are
the kind of wishes that can serve our Spiritual Development if we engage with
them right so the these are the ones where the Buddha used are let's call them elevated
desires as part of the path he encouraged us to do these kinds of
skillful wishes in order to uplift us or Draw us along the path
so when we allow these wishes to be felt in our heart they encourage us towards
skillful and wholesome action and the happiness that comes from
fulfilling these kinds of desires this fourth class are nourishing they bring a nourishing
kind of Happiness to us so these are the wishes that can support confidence ease brightness a certain
kind of refined Joy not a bubbly kind of Joy more associated
with the sense world but a tranquil kind of joy and that's the kind of pleasure that the
Buddha approved of this is from this is actually repeated in several sutas
this is called the Bliss of renunciation the Bliss of seclusion the Bliss of
Peace the Bliss of Enlightenment I say this kind of I say of this kind of
pleasure that it should be pursued that it should be developed that it should be cultivated and that it should not be
feared how about that the Buddha says there are kinds of pleasure that should be pursued
so there's also you know the famous story of the Buddha realizing that all
of the efforts he had done up to now this is the bodhisattva before he was the Buddha realizing that everything
he'd done hadn't brought Awakening yet and he was frustrated all of his aesthetic practices all of his practices
of the formless genres uh and then he thought back to a time in
his childhood where he entered meditative absorption as a child sitting
under a tree peacefully and how easeful and joyful that felt and he recognized
that that was the way forward that was the path this kind of meditative pleasure that he had first felt somewhat
spontaneously he then cultivated that under the Bodhi Tree and was able to awaken
so these kinds of pleasures and happinesses are part of the path
it's important to note that even though that quote I read included the Bliss of Enlightenment these are not the goal
actually so this kind of meditative pleasure that we get that comes kind of
as a fruit or a byproduct of calming the mind and calming the body and having
bright awareness that is not actually Freedom yet there can still be some
delusion in there such as a sense of self or Pride but if we keep up with the mindfulness
practice that will be those kind of side points will be seen and addressed at
some point and this uh this happiness this meditative happiness will allow us
to awaken so that's the fifth class of desire which I think is worth separating out is specifically the aspiration to
awaken to be free to be liberated that can take various forms you know
what kind of wanting is that so it's wanting to know to discover to
investigate to see to touch into to realize to release
these kinds of wishes often these desires and aspirations feel
very beautiful very clean very wholesome a little bit distinct from that fourth
class where we want to be ethical we want to be kind Etc
um sometimes at certain points on the path this fifth kind of desire to awaken
can get very strong and then it's called Samuel or some Vega
which is often translated as spiritual urgency and maybe you felt that one also
um for some people there's a resonance with the Western idea of a calling a calling
to practice a deep sense of wishing to be free sometimes it can be a little bit unpleasant even so at least desires feel
beautiful and clean and wholesome and then there can also be get me out and that's part of the process too
sometimes this wishing to be free can come really Straight From the Heart
so we have these five we have tanha grasping kind of Desire we have basic
desires related to fulfilling bodily needs we have the desires that accompany
living a human life among other humans we have our more spiritual wishes for
kindness for ethics for meditative development and then we specifically have the aspiration to be liberated
so they're not quite a linear Spectrum I hope you see they kind of Define a space
but nonetheless there is a clear division between unwholesome and wholesome right between unskillful and
skillful some of them are blatantly painful you know and those are the ones that we can
feel that contraction other ones we tend to make a trade-off you know we say I want this and the
benefits of it are going to be better than the detriments so I'm going for it you know like when we're working a
certain job that has some stress associated with it but we need the income so we make these trade-offs in
the kind of the middle realm and then um you know there's some of them that are really quite
beautiful and we can fulfill those as much as we want clearly helpful and that
will support us on our path
so I want to delve now a little bit into
that realm that I called the skillful desire because it's not talked about as much as
in that way so I hope you're seeing at this point that you know there's a lot of different kinds and we're going to
need to be careful about you know which one which side we're on we'll talk about that so what about these skillful desires
these wishes that can support the path so in that scheme of five they were the fourth and the fifth but actually I'm
going to take a step back into that Third Realm and say that it's important to realize that in order to support our
more elevated spiritual refined kind of desires we have to do some work in the
realm of the Third Kind of Desire the everyday wants and needs of creating a human life
we have to do some Preparatory work in the realm of our life in order to
bolster our ability to fully develop these more refined kinds of Desire
so in other words we have to set ourselves up we have to set up our life everybody in this room and on YouTube
you have set up yourself such that you could be here this morning that's not bad that's already an accomplishment a
lot of people haven't done that so we can work in the very ordinary Realm of the sensual world the stuff of
our life in order to create conditions that will be able to move forward on the
path with the more refined kinds of happiness so there's a couple things I want to say
about that first of all we need to simplify we need to simplify our life in certain
ways in order to support practice so this is aligning with our our lifestyle
with that and I want to read some lines actually from the metasuta
from the Buddha's discourse on on meta on loving kindness or good will
that are they're right at the beginning and they Point toward a way of being that has an air of
Simplicity to it that I find quite touching a way of being that's kind of
straightforward and uncomplicated so this is from the armor avati translation of that suta
some of you may recognize it because it's done in a chant this is what should be done by one who
is skilled in goodness and who knows the path of peace let them be able and operate
straightforward and gentle in speech humble and not conceited contented and
easily satisfied unburdened with duties and Frugal in
their ways peaceful and calm and wise and skillful not proud and demanding in
nature doesn't it feel nice just to hear that
people who are like that are really nice to be around and this has to do with generating the
conditions for loving-kindness in our life but it points toward a simplification
of how we are simplifying our actions simplifying our speech to be
straightforward and gentle probably even simplifying our thought processes so that we're not always caught up in a
million theories and speculations and anxieties about what other people are thinking about us
ah not necessary and not so supportive of our practice
so we want to live in a way that has some spaciousness to it to the degree that we can
that can be I I support creating some outer spaciousness if we can reducing
the amount of running around that we do simplifying our activities bringing in more spiritual friends into our life
um but even if you you know those aren't your life conditions you have busyness you have many people you have
work that's complex there can be an inner spaciousness in relating to that you know this phrase unburdened with
duties there's a lot to be said for not having too many duties
um and if you do there's a way of being unburdened by them right there's a way
of relating to them such that they aren't heavy and difficult and stressful for us if we
create inner spaciousness around those so if we want a life of practice that
includes a life of meta and Good Will and kindness these are these words that
I offered give us some touchstones straightforwardness gentleness humble
contented unburdened frugal
and so then that leads in to finding ways to relate to the sensory
world the material world skillfully so that we can create a sense of Refuge you
know of all the vast realm of skillful and desires and wishes I'm talking about
just one here but the the desires that help us find refuge and some of those
actually come from the sensory World from the material world so the five
physical senses seeing hearing smelling tasting and touching can be used or
related to in ways that nourish our heart and mind these are often Associated of course the
sense realm in Buddhist teachings is often associated with the need for restraint that's the word used and
I would agree with that generally because often we're not restrained in that realm and that only leads to stress
and so forth but not all sense stimuli are to be
avoided how can we and we we have these sense organs
so we don't have to avoid everything we can use the sense World in ways that
evoke faith that evoke Refuge that evoke nourishment for us when we're properly
attuned we can even use the Sixth Sense which is our cognition our mind in ways
that are nourishing sometimes people have the idea about spiritual practice that anything related
to thinking is bad anything related to you know cognizing is very suspect it
should all just be kind of I don't know coming from the heart coming from emotions but it's not the case we can
use our thinking mind we can use the fullness of our of our mind and heart to
nourish us so I want to name a number of ways that
we can use the ordinary stuff of our life our six senses
as to encourage refuge and a sense of faith and ability to
go forward with our practice to align our life with Dharma practice I guess I'll say them somewhat quickly
not with a lot of elaboration with the idea that you might just kind of feel which ones resonate for you and maybe
you'll also get some new ideas if you let me name a lot of them you'll get some new ideas and say oh you know I'm
not really using that realm using that form in a way that could be helpful for
me so for some seeing seeing
certain objects such as you know the Buddha Rupa for example or images
even monastic robes going to see monastics can be deeply nourishing
that's interesting there's a way in which our visual senses
can um resonate with something in us the
posture that the Buddha is in when sitting in these Buddha rupas I don't
know if you can see from where you are but there's kind of a elevation of his chest and this is actually deliberate
it's meant to evoke a sense of confidence that posture has an uprightness to it you remember that word
from what I just read in the metasuta and there's a way in which we can you know we're not going to necessarily
literally imitate what a stone figure is doing but there is a way that if we sit
up straight or feel the mirror between us and this Rupa
um there's a way that we can actually feel some of that confidence in ourself the posture of the body is not
Irrelevant in how we feel so
there's that and then there are there's the beauty of a retreat center it's not
an accident that the aesthetic in this room is simple there's this meant to evoke simplicity
so that we have Simplicity in the mind also that doesn't mean our mind is simple when it comes here but we can be
inspired by that it can be uplifting there's a subtle sense of calm
and it might also be that you can feel if you have a certain sensibility when you walk into a room like this can you
feel the Stillness in this room because a lot of people have meditated in here
it's been a lot lot of hours of meditation in here and so there's a way in which that I
mean that's a sense coming in through our sense doors and yet it can be nourishing for us if we open to it
hearing the Dharma has long served as a gateway to profound insight and at a
more ordinary level it's inspirational so you know being here this morning to
hear the Dharma and there's also you know a vast number of talks and guided meditations available online and in
other forms so listening can be a ready source of support for our practice
is that a sense desire to want to hear the Dharma yeah but it's it's um it also
goes in that elevated Realm reading the Dharma is also good you know
reading using the Mind using the cognition I recommend reading the original texts
if you're drawn to them of course in English translation there are good English translations available now and
there are also some very good modern interpretations by teachers Dharma books of various kinds the Buddha encourages
reflection on the teachings you are allowed to think about what you've read
think about whether it makes sense to you think about how it might apply in your life have questions about whether
it's really the case what that really means you probably wouldn't want to do a lot
of long thinking while you're sitting in meditation just because we want to separate those but you know outside of
sitting on the cushion please do think about the Dharma reflect on it um
for some practitioners the first re-taste of kind of real confidence in
the Dharma comes when we read something that is exactly like what we've experienced you know we've been sitting
for maybe even just a short time but we've experienced something or we've felt something or our mind shifts in a
certain way and then we pick up a suta or a teacher quote something in a talk and we realize ah Buddha said exactly
what I've experienced and that was 2600 years ago maybe this guy did know something about how the mind works so
I'm joking a little bit but there's really can be a profound resonance when we see that some of at least some of
what's in the suit does reflects what we see in our own mind and body right here in the modern world
and we also understand oh the mind can be trained the process works when I'm
even when I meditate it's not an exception I'm not the exception oh it works for everyone else but not going to
work for me but it does when we see that it does so that can be very nourishing
and I think it also helps at a more emotional level it's really nice if we hear stories about people who
overcame their suffering you know in the sutas there's a a wonderful story about
the a woman named Kisa gotami who was very distraught because her her baby died and
she carried the child around she just couldn't grok the death and brought even you know
and everybody was like you know not able to help her really and she came to the Buddha with with her dead child and he
said okay uh you know there's help there's help for you if you
can get a mustard seed from a house where no one has died so she's set off on this Quest brilliantly skillful
teaching on the Buddhist part because house after house after house was willing to give her a mustard seed
tiny little thing but there wasn't any house where nobody had died
so she got it you know she got it over time and we can be inspired by these
more subtle ways that the Buddha taught people he didn't always just talk about the five kinds of Desire
but there were you know he really could touch into people's deepest emotions and
find ways to connect that into the Dharma so you know we can learn from this also
we can resonate with her grief and also with her wisdom in understanding through that practice
Buddhist compassion and then also being in nature
that's a decidedly sensory experience but being in nature can give us a
glimpse of the Dharma in certain ways but sometimes can penetrate more deeply than things that are explicitly
spiritual sometimes you know just seeing the trees the bees the clouds
the streams did you guys see the blooming Dogwood on the way in amazing
so you know these things tell us about him impermanence impersonality
conditionality in a very straightforward way we see the cycle of Life happening
and we understand how we're part of it this too is the Dharma the truth of nature can heal and clarify
things for us and then there are certain devotional
actions this isn't for everyone but if you've never tried it you might certain devotional actions that can
uplift our heart and mind that maybe make it more easy for us to
connect in with these refined forms of happiness so for some people bowing you know maybe
before you start meditation or chanting or ritual these things can
connect us in with the spiritual dimension of life
I guess there's a fortunate resonance in the uh in that this afternoon at IMC
there's going to be a session on chanting and talking about some of the
devotional practices of Asia with a wonderful scholar and that's his
profession is to be a Buddhist scholar but I would say he's really quite a deep practitioner who has studied this so
fear at all interested one to three o'clock this afternoon there will be and I think it's online also I think it's a
hybrid so even for those of you on YouTube it's possible
so that's not everyone's cup of tea but for some Skeptics like me originally
some Skeptics have been stunned at How Deeply these kinds of simple devotional
actions can go they can really touch the heart um
so are there ways that you could express
your spiritual desires through your material life it's a question for all of you just to
consider you know is there some way that you could shift maybe take some of the energy that's going into ordinary desires like
food Comfort various Pleasures I mean we devote a lot of our attention to that
how am I going to get this or that or that get the next one that's going to be good how could we convert that into elevated
desires for simple surroundings that support practice
for trust and confidence in practice for learning the teachings for Spiritual
Community there's a way in which we can Elevate our wishes along the you know
toward the upper end of those five classes of desire and sometimes we're able to literally kind of convert the
ones that are a little bit more worldly focused oh it would be even more nourishing if I could want
these deeper things these things that are part of the path
so we started by talking about how desire first of all is very prominent for us
but also that it has some subtlety to it clearly a lot of the desires that we
Chase don't really help us they're exhausting we don't have control over them they're pretty temporary when we
get them they don't you know they don't last and we have to do the next one and yet some things are good to want
I don't know if you can get awakened without wanting that at some level it's not going to just happen so we have to
do something we have to want something along the way so you know these spiritual wishes for
goodness in meditative development are good ways to direct that movement toward in our mind
movement toward to be movement along the path eventually I think we will move into the
complete release of maybe all kinds of Desire except for those bodily ones but definitely we move
into the release of tanha the grasping part of Desire that is the cause of suffering in the
second Noble Truth it's not desire it's tanha it's the
grasping kind of Desire but then that leads to a natural question how do we know
how do I know if I want something is that a good want or a unhelpful want
it's a little bit of a trial and error there's a need for discernment there we have to keep checking we can check
our wholesome states in the mind increasing and on wholesome States decreasing or the reverse you know if we
want kindness we will tend to not increase our tanha when we do that if we
want to be kind it can still creep in we can want to be kind and then we can say
I'm really a kind person you know we take it on as an identity and that's when it becomes unskillful
slips into that but if we just keep checking you know is there wholesomeness is what I'm wanting helping me to be
calm more wholesome more skillful that's probably a good kind of Desire
and also we can check if we're more you know felt sense meditator we can
check if there's tension associated with a certain desire if we want something that's
you know grasping or you know more in the sensory realm tends to bring some
tension some stress with it whereas other kinds of wants have a more open
feeling to them there's still a little bit of tension maybe but it's more subtle
and we can also check whether what we're wanting will help others or only us
that's a good clue if it would help others then it's more in the realm of skillful
so developing this kind of discernment is part of the path also we are not perfect at first at knowing whether
we're having skillful unskillful desire so we'll have to develop that over time
but one implication of thinking in this way is that the whole world becomes our
realm of practice you know every moment every encounter every
wish that we have in our mind right here in the tangible world
is a doorway to taking a step on the path if we can see it in that way
so there's a completeness there's a fullness to our relationship to life and
especially when we've undertaken a spiritual path then we start to see the ways in which
some of what we do supports that and some of what we do doesn't support that and we can start to prioritize move
toward this movement toward move toward the things that are actually helping us that are then propelling us along the
path part of the subtlety of this knowing about which desires are helpful and not
is that it shifts over time so something that was helpful for a while might become unhelpful later you know we have
to let go of certain desires that we're okay at the beginning but then they become burdensome
so be prepared for those shifts over time
so I hope I hope what this has done is maybe clarified a little bit this
realm of Desire so that we don't have an automatic sense of oh it's all bad I've
got to get rid of all my desires and then the reaction against that but I don't want to get rid of all my desires
and I shouldn't have to and blah blah blah we can sweep all of that aside and
consider Instead This dimension of wholesome unwholesome skillful unskillful which desires are supporting
the path and moving more and more toward having more of those in our life and then letting letting the mindfulness
take care of the rest of it letting the ones Fall Away moving us toward that
aren't helpful moving us toward that final movement into Freedom into Awakening
freedom from all those movements of mind
so thank you
I guess we would have time for one we're pretty much at the end so um
I'll stay a little longer if anybody would like to come up and ask anything but thank you