greetings friends greetings from Mountain View California unseated oloni
land where I am in this moment in time and uh it's lovely to be with you it's
lovely to sense your presence from around the uh the world this blue
planet of Arts joining each other in this moment and practicing together
so so this week we've been exploring the Dharma of Improv
or The Improv of Dharma there's so many relationships and uh and today
we in the meditation we will explore something that is both
very important in in our practice and in our lives as well as its key and improv
absolutely key and that is embodiment
we need to be embodied in our bodies not in our heads
to be present to be present with whatever is arising in the present
moment and the idea of embodiment really feeling the body sensing the body
um not being the head not being not doing mindfulness from the Mind
assuming that it's somewhere up in our heads but actually body fullness body Ness
be present with whatever is arising without judgment without
fighting against it need for embodiment similarly need to be
embodied when you're improvising really be but think about what you're going to do or say but really allow your body to
to sense and lead and meet the moment I'll say more about it
worsen the dormant but but to plant the seed for really bring attention to how
embodiment can support us to meet this moment sort of jumping forward or or
being in a reverie of the past and there's more that I would I would
add to it so so with that set up let's uh let's begin
let's begin and arrive arrive in our bodies
sensing sensing our bodies
greeting our bodies hello body good morning good afternoon whatever the time is
good moment
hello dear buddy how are you
thank you
checking in checking in with your toes
how are you toes this morning it's Moment In Time
how are you feed how are you at the bottom of the feet what are you sensing hmm
one is being sensed are you right now
not from the control tower of the head but
what's being felt sensed
in the feet of cells contact points catch points
in curious with lightness
as if your awareness was the king of this this town was going around and
meeting and greeting
looking after all the residents of the surface Village that is your body
this community that's your body a sense of care
imagine the benevolent King going around hello feet
awareness awareness checking in with the ankles
with the lower legs awareness filling filling out
touching internally
and there's awareness is filling
senses in your lower legs
maybe you notice more Sensations
if you're becoming more filled out
if you wear a pop-up balloon or pop-up doll oh feeling more air more awareness
awareness oh yeah feeling more filled out this leg that was just an idea
so many Sensations moving up to the knees
the upper legs and sit bones
so many Sensations contact here
adding your awareness rest here
for a little while
moving up your awareness your knowing
from your lower abdomen also so many Sensations breath
expansion contraction maybe a release is needed here to make more space
maybe a release at the out breath
letting go with this letting go with a sigh
ah
moving awareness up brushing
the upper abdomen Lord diaphragm
awareness of the sensations your chest this chest
and your back lower back
so many Sensations mid back
upper back
her entire trunk uh confront
to herself
especially your shoulders
kneeling the sensations and if there's any release needed
allow it to happen at the out breath
upper arms let them relax feel the sensations Russian
elbows
lower arms
wrists hands
so much sensation in the front the back of the hands your palm
let yourself enjoy not a grim duty but with lightness
curiosity interests enjoy the sensations
as long as we don't get attached and cause we're suffering there is no
problem with enjoying what is
it feeds the heart to become calmer more settled
it's part of the path of practice
gently moving up neck shoulders
shoulders and neck up to the head
and face
softening relaxing releasing
a tightness and sensing so many Sensations
now allowing awareness to fill the whole body the
entire body this body here sitting breathing
alive pulsating filled with Sensations
heaviness lightness
cold and worms
tingling movement low
let the awareness be content and happy enjoying
resting from the body nowhere to go no need to go into the future or past
right here meeting this moment it's so rich
and we have the Refuge of the body coming home
resting in the body joyfully resting
Sensations all saving sensations of the body
and there be a smile give it a try greeting this body
is living breathing amazing anchor
meeting meeting our bodies with a smile
it's lightness
Let the Body breathe
Simply Be with the breath be with the sensations
there is such contentment and happiness Unleashed
just this breath in breath in the body
in the abdomen is out breath
so much comfort ease Unleashed with just this
the mind is racing towards the future planning
or reaching out into the past can we release smilingly release
let awareness rest know the sensations of the body
breathing meeting this moment
around it embodied
in the last minutes of this practice
can't return into the lightness the joy
or simply the quiet piece the simple joy simple happiness of just being here with
the body in a moment
a light of Peace of just this here for a moment
taking Refuge
resting releasing into the body
and however this practice period was or wasn't without attaching to outcome
but knowing trusting that we have planted seeds of presence embodiment
peace Delight
and appreciating ourselves for having shown up as best as we've been able to
yay
many practices take time to write it's okay
I'll pay attention the rest of the day to the body
resting in the body and for now appreciating the co-created goodness
with moments of embodiment groundedness
peace May these cultivations serve us
the awaken to live without suffering and causing
suffering
both our lives and the lives of all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere
be well happy and free including ourselves
thank you for your practice friends
and as we take a moment to transition with the recording
if you feel mood to put a word or two
what's arising for you in this moment with this practice of cultivating
embodiment and the peace The Joy the Delight of embodiment or whatever might have Arisen for you
readings everyone greetings friends thank you for your practice
and just as we ended are Sid I asked if you wanted to put some
words so I'll bring those into the space just a few of them there's so many
beautiful ones alive rested calm and peaceful healing comfortable except
and sleepy all of a sudden yes when the body gets really comfortable we can get sleepy it's there especially if you're
asleep deprived they can be each other's uh that their neighbors Serenity meta
invigoration container calm softening
yeah not mindful yeah
energy of Life precious body
um connected head to the body
simply here grounded self-compassion thank you all for bringing
or for voicing what's in the space and so many other things in addition to distraction and sleepiness it's all okay
it's whatever is here it's perfectly fine it's whatever is arising In This Moment
so as I mentioned um the beginning of our practice today
the meditation today that the theme that we're continuing to explore with
the theme of Dharma of Life a Dharma of Improv improv of in Dharma
is is groundedness is is embodiment as you might have heard before Gale
speaking other teachers myself speaking about embodiment feeling the body the mindfulness of the body the first Sati
patana really the first establishment of mindfulness is about the body the body
the body most practitioners when they start practice they want to go to the
the mind the third Sati Katana mindfulness of mind
the Buddha taught about mindfulness of the body being Mindful and and resting
in the body first we're really important it's a fun it's foundational practice only later after feeling tone we get to
mind ones of mind so in order to to awaken we really do
need to to um explore and really make friends
understand how important embodiment is for our practice for our daily life
and for me it it took some time when I was a beginner practitioner it took me
some time to really understand to really grock how important mindfulness of the
body was and then it just opened up my practice deep and then opened up more it was it was quite profound actually
um when when that when that unlocked so so since then
mindfulness of the body teachings have been so important both to me and also in
my teachings with others they seem so basic oh yeah embodiment yeah yeah the mind is where it's at no
no believe me it's the body where it's it's all at to be grounded to be
um to to sense the body and also to allow
the there I would also say the wisdom of the body the wisdom of the body to lead
instead of being in our heads and trying to think and figure it all out but let the wisdom of the body lead
similarly in the Dharma of improv it is
important it's a it's a primary rule teaching of improv that you need to be
embodied not in your head not disconnected thinking about what you're
going to say in a scene what you're gonna do and especially as you're interacting with others in this
relational field in this relational field
in fact that the the basic rule the basic teaching is be embodied and let your
body lead let your body lead your choice your your thoughts your your actions
your interactions really use the tuning fork of the body when you're embodied
use the tuning fork of the body Let the Body lead Let the Body lead the in
sensing the emotions the the all the thoughts in the body and again not the
control tower of the head but in the body and and in improv the scenes where
people are really embodied and actually as as a player improv player when you when you're playing relationally and you
are in your body you let your body lead um it's so satisfying it's such a
satisfying co-creation then when you realize oh actually in that scene I was really in my head I was trying to like
figure out what to say or what to do and so like ah just it was it was hard it was tight whereas the body there is this
both the ease of resting in the body stable grounded yes
and and the body um leads really leads and and and gives
you the cue as to what is needed it's it there's so
much more wisdom to the body than just our head thinking in fact I'm gonna be
silly for a moment you know what do we ascribe in the west to be our mind is
yeah this much whereas there's so much wisdom to the rest of us it's and in fact
um our mind there's the seminal book years ago in in um
in uh in Psychology called the embodied mind really an amazing Dharma book
by Francisco Varela the the famous neuroscientist the Dharma dharmic
neuroscientist um and um
Eleanor Raj and Evan Thompson amazing book for those who who are uh inclined
that way but really that wisdom the wisdom of the body embodied mind it's
it's the entire mind is really in the in in our bodies not just not just in our
heads and so much research and actually philosophy to support that so
so so the invitation as we as we practice both on the cushion and as we
improvise Our Lives we're all improvising Our Lives
is to be in our bodies not in our heads to be
in our bodies to keep coming back to the body to keep coming back to the body and I'll give you an example and and for
example when I teach mindful leadership and and um one of the things that I teach
leaders in inba is that when you are for example sitting at your desk when you
are sitting you're about to send an email you're about to do something check back with the body before you're about
to send an email check back with the body ideally you'll be embodied the whole time but you know we know us right
we get distracted check back with the body how is it feeling what's happening check back in with the body feel
grounded feel your feet on the earth feel your hands um on the keyboard feel your
self-present be the step back into the body p and body take a breath embodiment
is um is really the key to awareness is the
key to awareness of what is arising what the appropriate response is at this point is it really Wise It's kind to
send this email you're about to send oh the body will tell you um
and if the body's so agitated that candle could get up go for a walk become embodied really without sense and and
and and land in the body so embodiment is so helpful both on the cushion as
we're practicing and you might have noticed and again I noticed this in my own
practice that when I am embodied seems like there is this big large
um you know if if there's a balloons of thoughts then they're under swinging in the wind this wind that way oh you know
the same way that with helium balloons we attach a weight to them so they don't
go off everywhere body is that weight is that lovely light
they're not heavy and you know Grim duty but this this this
ah the sense of coming into our own in our practice
unmoved unwavering not being pushed over by this thought that thought
that emotion but actually having the resilience having the stability to be
with our with with everything that arises with this sense of Integrity of the body
I love the statues of Buddha all these different
postures but mostly we see the seated posture and there's just such a sense of
Integrity you know his legs again you can be sitting on a chair or or or on
the cushion it doesn't matter and yet this as we look at his statue there's a sense of stability the sense of
stability of the body grounded stable upright the sense of dignity Integrity
of the body so so important in our practice on the
cushion as you're sitting actually as you're listening to me in the in the relational
practice of of relating to others mindful listening and mindful speaking
the primary trick or the primary way of of deep
listening is to be embodied to really be in your body and listen to others so as
I'm listening to you in fact you can't be practicing embodiment you can be
feeling your feet on the earth your your your legs your sit Bones on the cushion
your breath is it tight is it Loose ah so much wisdom in the body and of course
relationally in improv you need to be in your body to to be actually light and
responsive you be in your body not in your head to be responsive and improv
can be pretty fast if you if you watched um if you've done improv yourself or if
you've watched it you know Whose Line Is It Anyway for example there's this can be quite fast and sometimes people are
intimidated wow how are they thinking about all this it's actually it's really
a lot about embodiment it's it's that's the trick it's like The Wizard of Oz
I've pulled back the curtain it's about embodiment it's really there's so much Dharma uh in improv it's about
embodiment meeting the moment meeting the moment not from the cleverness of your head but but bringing bringing your
whole self your body um letting the body lead so
so thank you thank you friends may you be embodied today as you're moving
um cooking or eating or walking going to
the bathroom oh it was sitting at your desk typing emails and body come back to
the body listening especially interacting with others relational field
and again it's not that you just check out and you're in your body but you let the body lead it's both the stability
and also the tuning for the body tells you whatever is needed if there's upset
anger if there's anything that's oh that's not quite right before it develops to full-blown say anger is like
oh yeah something isn't quite right here let me check in anyway so much to the mindfulness of the body so much to
embodiment both relationally and on practice in on the cushion thank you all thank you so
much for for your cultivation for your wholehearted whole body dedication
take good care be well be embodied today observe plant seeds and looking forward
to seeing you tomorrow