yeah so welcome again
it feels so still in the hall and I'm inspired to say
if the if the gravity of
the sitting practice is predominant just keep that going
and let all this just wash right through
so the the topic for tonight I wanted to bring up is practice discussion
it occurred to me that we so rarely talk about practice discussion
so I wanted to offer some reflections and first to start I wanted to recognize
that um there may be a range of maybe degrees of
experience with this I know there are some in the room that have probably been doing practice discussion
for decades and some maybe never done it before
um yeah so to try to to try to discuss the topic
knowing there's this broad range of experience so I thought I would begin with a story
um one that's about maybe good friendship in the form of practice discussion and it it's a story
that comes out of uh Gill's book a monastery with him it's called appropriate instruction
one of the monasteries old monks had become a Hermit living deep in the mountains
a two and a half day hike over difficult Mountain paths
many visitors made the Trek to receive advice and teachings from the old man
he was reputed to have an uncanny ability to know just what each visitor needed
prior to giving instruction The Hermit asked that the visitor promised not to tell anyone what advice
or instruction they received
After the Promise was made the hermit would say simply say what are you not willing to pay
attention to this was the only thing he would ever
say to anyone asking his help many visitors were first perplexed by
this question but by the time they'd walked the two and a
half day track out of the mountains they invariably would praise the hermit
for giving them just the instruction they needed to hear
the story makes me so curious of all the different all the different places and times we can apply the question what are
we not willing to pay attention to
and I think of the the person who must have been so motivated motivated enough
to Trek for two and a half days into the into the difficult mountains to seek advice what must have been going on in
their lives but something something called to them
and they recognized this was a beneficial thing to do
and they sit down they have this discussion or receive this comment
and then and then something for me is like the Trek the two and a half day Trek
back out it's like it worked it worked the lesson or it worked the question or the thought
into the body just over and over on the walkout
so I'm hoping we can look at practice discussion in terms of uh three things
and that is practice discussion as a practice of recognizing
recognizing what's wholesome practice of articulating expressing in
words and then a practice of embodying
embodying spiritual maturity so for anyone anyone who hasn't hasn't
done this before in our Insight tradition practice discussion are these they're one-on-one meetings between a
practitioner and a teacher in the context of Dharma practice
um one of the primary purposes is to
recognize and reflect upon the teaching the Dharma that is
apt for exactly your current experience and we sort of find that together and
Discover it together I think that from the perspective of the teacher practice discussion provides
that opportunity for a really good understanding of what's going on for someone and to apply just
the one right question perhaps and then from the perspective of the practitioner
it could be to receive support or clarification to bolster confidence about the next
step of the path or um even a practice in its own right of
reporting on your experience to try to report on your meditative experience and your inner landscape
in your daily life so
these sorts of these sorts of these aspects these skills and qualities that come to come
to develop in practice discussion of recognizing articulating and embodying
of course we develop them in other ways too I think of our um year-long Dharma programs where we
move through with a cohort and we have Dharma discussion we have small groups or you have friends you get together
with and have coffee and talk Dharma
so all that's here too in the spirit of a good Dharma friendship
so in the context of the the tradition way way back in my textual memory
and it occurred to me looking at the sutas of these these ancient teachings of the Buddha
it seems like the vast majority of them are question and answer
it's almost like we have these really ancient records of people going and doing practice discussion with the Buddha
pretty amazing that that's available and most of them follow a similar format
there or at least they have a similar frame so there is most of the time a sort of respectful
approach and then a formal greeting of some kind then someone will take their seat
and then they'll bring up their topic one of the most well-known collections
of that is uh sujata was just teaching about this the chapter to the way to the Beyond uh the
paryana Vaga basically 16 practice discussions that we get to read read in on
um and then also very well known the questions of King Melinda where um
the king is having this extended interview with the Monk nagasena
outside of the texts and real lived bodies and places in time I think of the terravada and monasteries
also something of a model for us in my in both my hearing and my visits
to places like this something I notice is that the interviews can sometimes be pretty informal
they kind of run the run the spectrum of formal and informal sometimes it's just
like group t with the Abbot in the afternoon it's like it feels um maybe I
can appropriately say low stakes but um the Abbott is just totally
available and If you have Dharma you want to bring up a question you want to ask
so that's there in the background of our tradition also and then I'm also kind of delighted
there's one more image of monastic uh practice discussion where I've heard
about a certain Monastery where during these intensive periods the meditators will line up about one at a
time and they'll just they'll approach the teacher they'll ask ask their question they'll get their answer and then the
next person goes but because they're all lined up like this I would imagine the few people right
here get to hear the Q a right so it's not exactly private but you're you're
gleaning some of this Dharma wisdom from overhearing the Q a
so these ancient texts and these forms in the monasteries they form some of the context for
for our form of practice discussion and the Insight movement the Insight tradition
of course we have practice discussion on Retreat and we have practice discussion off retreat
um yeah yeah
I want to address that that uh for some I have I have heard
um the practice discussion can kind of feel like a high pressure situation because uh I don't know if anyone here
has ever had that experience um and it reminded me of this
anecdote about Blanche Hartman she she was the first abess of San Francisco's
Zen Center and she was describing what is a really formal meal ceremony that happens at Zen
Center called oriyoki um everything is prescribed you know there's a detail for everything takes
about an hour to eat lunch and wash your bulls and put them away and very very common for someone doing
this for the first time or the first 20 times to be really nervous about the details
she set us all or she set everyone at ease by saying all it is
we're gonna we're gonna unwrap our bowls we're going to eat our food and then we're going to wrap them up and no one
is going to die [Laughter] if things if things go according to plan
so something as high stakes as a formal Zen meal was sort of set at ease and
I think looking at the looking at the structure of just how simple a practice discussion can be might also put us at
ease it's like we we get in the room we sit down we discuss our topic we say
thank you and then we go that's it's just that easy
when we look at the old text of course we might see that it's it looks quite formal uh there's a there's this
really great formulaic way that they they talk about it say when um
let's see a certain brahmana approach the Buddha goes like this then a certain brahmana approached the
blessed one having approached the blessed one he exchanged friendly greetings after Pleasant conversation had passed
between them he sat to one side having sat to one side the Brahman spoke to the blessed one thus what does the
venerable gotama assert what does he preach it seems like there's this long wind up
to the question of prescribed activity similar but abbreviated for the
monastics like venerable Ananda went to see the Buddha and it just says he approached
the blessed one the Buddha paid homage to him or paid respects and then sat to one side and then asked his
question these days you just come right in
come on in and have a seat so after you've taken your seat we we
get to discuss or whoever you're there with you get to discuss the thing that comes into my comes to my
mind is um another another notion about sort of setting one at ease and practice
discussion is that the time is totally yours the time totally belongs to
the the person coming to ask the question um whatever feels whatever feels alive
most relevant most helpful for you right now but it's totally totally up to you
um I think of I think of entering the room when I go when I go see my mentors and
teachers I think of entering the room kind of is like entering a field of gifts
like entering a field of Donna like they're they're just they're just there holding this open space where I
can bring up whatever whatever in the context of the Dharma
it's such a special thing and in some of the best meetings there's
this Simplicity and I imagine some of you had recognized this this feeling like actually nothing at all has to
happen there's nothing we have to accomplish through this conversation
even if we just sat there in silence that would be perfectly fine maybe that would be the best
but say you do want to bring something up um
I look again to the ancient texts and there's this there's a sort of formula
for wise reflection and it takes a little bit of translation I think for for most of us to apply it
in our lives and um but when think when going to visit when
going to visit monastics and going to visit the Buddha in these old texts the um the formula was something like uh
what is it what is it that's skillful what is it that's unskillful what's
beneficial what's not beneficial and what uh if I if I do it would lead
to my long-term harm or what if I do it would lead to my long-term benefit and happiness
so it's um at least in the in the text here it's focused around one's conduct questions
about one's conduct one's practices and then the qualities that develop out of
that that seems to be some of the focus of these discussions
you know for a long while I would go to practice discussion and then I would just of course I would leave when the
practice discussion was over but I um I didn't have any regular way of reflecting and thinking about it after
the fact um I think it may have been years it never
really dawned on me oh you know I'm going to write about this I'm going to reflect on it I'm going to see how I can really put this into action I kind of
just put myself into the practice discussion container and then I left
and I trusted that something was going on that was fruitful or something was continuing to work on
me until I remember I remember going to a meeting once and
um asking based on this conversation what do you
what should I do a novel question and the teacher said oh you know I hope
that you remember what we talked about I hope you reflect on it
and then make some decision about how you want to act on it so he he gave me this like very clear
way of integrating I hadn't known that was missing
I think one of the things of immense value that can emerge out of you know such a
simple form is the fact that practice discussion is a place where the the let's say the
Dharma the theory let's say of Dharma meets actual lives
actual lives in the Dharma come together in the in a conversation
the um what's what's revealed if um
let's say if we meet in the spirit of the Dharma or meet in the context of the Dharma is um
yeah our actual life like the the tangible bits of this lived life and how
the Dharma reflects on that
so in order to be available for that something that something that um I found really helpful over time was to
invoke or invite a sort of sensitivity to have a kind of attitude of
sensitivity um
so yeah so I could be receptive to the
Dharma that was coming or sort of open the channel and let the Dharma arise
I think they're a host of really useful attitudes that might might serve Us in practice discussion one is to be open to
possibility of something different to recognize a possibility
um yeah I remember having a number of
conversations where um it almost felt like the teacher was just like tossing out something in the moment
that was like wow how obvious I never thought of that and it um
it landed with a spark of inspiration and opening and all of a sudden it was like they loaned me their confidence for
this new beautiful possibility that um if I could then reflect upon and see if
it opened up in my life
one more important comment I think is that even a brief exchange can be quite powerful
um in the text we have the example of course of venerable saripota Awakening by the end of a four-line stanza
may it be so and uh and I think of these little Snippets
there are these they're these questions and answers that we still
they end up being stories for US 20 30 40 years later there's this one well-known story in our in our circles I
think of had come I think to Spirit Rock and someone asked her what's what is in
your mind and she responded um
loving-kindness concentration and peace
and I still feel a wow in my heart and she didn't even give that response to me
but it it's it's brief it's powerful and it's
still living in uh I guess in this talk
the brevity can also be non-verbal I've heard that upon Dita is known for the
power of the raised eyebrow um the gestures can mean a lot
Suzuki roshi the founder of San Francisco Zen Center is also pretty well known for this and not the eyebrow but
the brief teaching and um
yeah another one of these pithy q and A's that that sticks with me someone
asked him what is nirvana and he said seeing one thing through to
the end
and how that you know how that lands it must be you know
let's say that was 1969 how many years ago was that conversation that was just a guess it
might have been earlier anyway I think through these exchanges
through through these meetings even if they're brief
we come to recognize something about what's skillful
and we get to see it being enacted right there with us you know we're discovering the Dharma
together emptiness emptiness means one thing
when it's um oh how does he how does he put this uh
it's like as a concept or in the abstract but it's quite it's quite another to encounter it in a being
you know the Dharma living right there and I think that teaches us something about how to bring It Forward in our own
lives or what's possible for us
so having talked about receptivity I think it also um Bears talking about the additional
opportunity of checking out teachers well I think it's an interpretation of the
Kalamazoo to the encouragement to like really check out for a long time
teachers in terms of do you notice in their content conduct
greed hatred and delusion I think and like
please please do please do that I think it's for the health of the community
for all of us not just for a one particular teacher-student relationship but that
we're we're sensitive to Greed hatred and delusion and their opposites practicing over and over their
recognition and then there's this other thing that
sensitivity opens us up to and that is whether there's Affinity with a certain teacher
you know
so I think there are many ways to frame practice of practice discussion or to
frame the notion of who you're meeting with I I think for some folks it's thinking
of the visiting a teacher as like a consultant others go seeking a guide others go
explicitly seeking a teacher or supporter um one really fruitful way I've I've had of
reflecting on this or thinking about it is is with the teachers that I've connected with long term it's thinking
of them in a sort of apprenticeship relationship and this the more I dig into this
metaphor the more I really like it um just the way we think about
Carpenters developing skill by watching very skilled Carpenters or working with
them or I think of musicians especially
um when I think of someone someone with just like Talent enthusiasm and interest
and they're given a piece of sheet music okay that that takes you so far that's like our that's our written Dharma okay
now put this put this written Dharma into practice like play this sheet music and and with someone who really knows
the cello let's say they can listen along and hear possibility
even if they're not being like Oh yes great and no no no that was terrible they could be like oh
I heard this in your interpretation have you thought about this have you considered this possibility
and in that way you develop skill develop skill with this instrument and
it uh it feels quite alive when I think about the Dharma in that way
you know um we have the we have the Good Fortune of having in our community people who have
practiced for a very long time and and coming into conversation and
discussing hey this is what I'm thinking about um skillfulness and unskillfulness this
is my situation this is this is how I'm practicing this is what I'm seeing
and um yeah bringing bringing them into that bringing in our good drama friends
one of the other one of the other pieces I really like about the apprenticeship metaphor is that this um this pointer
to have practice discussion with someone from whom you're willing to
receive input seems obvious seems obvious but someone
you're whose feedback you're willing to hear and consider um
for obvious reasons
maybe one more thing thinking about practice discussion
specifically in terms of Kelly animita or kalyanamitata admirable friendship or
good good spiritual friendship good friendship um
the
in learning to recognize good Dharma friendship and look at the texts very interesting
there's an opposite it doesn't it's not really bad spiritual
friendship but it's this word it's this word that um one of its meanings is infertile like
infertile soil I find that evocative like what what
friendships what connections what conversations are nourishing the soil of my practice
and how can I how can I care for those and develop them
in the um in the terrigata kisagotami's poem
she says associating with an admirable friend even a fool becomes wise
later on associating with people of integrity one would be released from all suffering
and stress would no stress the origination of stress
cessation and the Eightfold Path the Four Noble Truths
I'm encouraged by this and how our our good friendship and tonight in terms
of practice discussion um that movement
that supports our growth in our discernment of the Four Noble Truths our realization of the Four Noble
Truths our walking of path to peace and that we don't have to do it alone
so maybe in the last minute or so I'll just say at uh
for those who don't know at IMC a couple of the easiest ways to engage in practice discussion day longs usually on
Saturdays and then Wednesday half days their sign up practice discussions for both of
those at Insight Retreat Center that they're folded into the schedule so that's
that's part of what goes on um and then there are various days a
small group or individual practice discussions that happen on Zoom so you can check all that out on the IMC
website then find an opportunity to
to recognize the Dharma together to articulate the Dharma and to embody
it into yeah take part in this joyful path
so
to close with just a simple wish I think may it be that all of our encounters
nourish our practice and may all beings everywhere grow in
wisdom and compassion and be free from suffering
yeah thank you and I
skipped a fair amount so we could be sure to have some conversation or questions or comments or
stories whatever whatever you'd like
thank you codo yes I'm wondering um thank you first for this
question I've often asked the question about what
I should be discussing during our practice discussions and I've never really gotten it
so going to sleep um
I'm wondering um if you can say you know on the sutas they always talk
about um greeting go to my
with reverence and then sitting to the side yeah it seems that they're always sitting to the side and I'm wondering
is that um I don't know what that means does it seem confrontational to sit
directly across or do you know what the relevance of sitting to the side means yeah it's a
really it's a good question I I'm not I'm not so sure about its meaning within
the context of ancient India yeah I I could I could guess about some
things but they wouldn't be grounded in any any kind of evidence
yeah if anyone here knows
well this is an entirely speculation but in many places
it's considered um disrespectful to show the bottom of your feet to somebody yeah
certainly in some of the Pacific Islands but I've had a a monk at the monastery
point out to me that I was sitting with my the bottom of my feet
pointing towards him and I did I didn't know that that was a
breach of etiquette sure so that's might possibly be part of it sure sure
yeah I'm curious same thing extends uh to uh altars I think Buddha statues
so I wanted to thank you for your talk um
I mean a couple of kalyanamita groups and
so we share people take turns each week or each meeting offering a prompt question you
know some kind of uh maybe a question that's relevant for
them and um
often turns out to be a very relevant to everyone else as well because it's it's
somebody else's question but it might be something that's a little bit of a blind spot
so the sharing of questions in a group like that
um can often deepen inquiry yeah yeah
I appreciate that and it it sparked something for me when you use the word blind spot
that seems to be uh in my in my observation over over the
years one of the most important functions of
keeping up a practice discussion connection with someone who you can really trust in terms of the Dharma to
kindly point out your blind spots because we all have them
so we and we sort of entrust ourselves to our Kelly animita and our teachers
and our Dharma friends to help us see these things
well I want to say thank you and um
yeah just to appreciate our time to sit talk
um maybe it's the dogwoods outside
there's something really soft and lovely in the meditation Hall tonight and I want to appreciate being here with you
so thank you for having me May our practice
certainly benefit us and benefit everyone we know and all
those beings we don't know may all beings benefit