good morning Sangha
good morning everyone
hmm so welcome everyone
see I am not seeing myself here
um are you able to see me on YouTube some reason I'm not able to see myself
hmm okay so I'm going to
um started the meditation I'm hoping this everything is working
okay I'm not able to see the YouTube myself
but I do see the messages okay so let's begin
I'm gonna assume that everything works okay
um so this morning's we're being working
through um this uh words that start with R
and today I will add one more R to this
unfolding meditative process and this
um last a few days we've been using the word
we started with relaxing and
added to it in the relaxed field and we can recognize the things clearly
and with recognition uh we get to release any extra tension
that we notice with these scrap grasping cleaning
and today I will be adding one more word to this
and that is resting and so once any extra tension gets
released we can simply rest
and so that's the process that we'll go through and so let's begin with a meditation
so please take a meditative posture if you're not in one already
now again evoke this image of entering into a temple
maybe that's a conducive because of the
uh metaphors we've been using in our dharmette
so take a few moments to allow yourself to settle into the space you're in
arriving Here and Now
as you forward entering into a temple
in Ancient Temple
the Temple of this body is mind
This Heart
just to this image of entering into the temple may already evoke
some felt sense in the body
are certain feelings in the heart
for me there is immediate quieting down
of my mind
and there is a tenderness respect in the heart
as we enter into the Temple of this body
and take our seat right in the middle
arriving Right Here and Now mistake
um rounding the body
inviting relaxation and ease
as if you're settling in the home
the homecoming
mindfulness is a front and the center
and maybe a heartfulness is front and center
as the sense of arriving arriving depends
and about the relaxation and the ease to deepen
maybe the relaxation can happen throughout the body
and maybe even add to the cellular level
microscopic level easing up
relaxing the thinking muscles
relaxing the heart in some sense of opening
but unburdened heart
in this relaxed field
and can begin to turn our attention [Music] to any familiar meditative object
whether it's recognizing the movements of the breath
your Sensations in the body
waves of emotions
inflating thoughts
simple recognition fear recognition
maybe this recognition arises out of
the felt sense the immediacy of the felt sense
through the body
and we can let go of the conceptual overlays
the stories
staying with the felt sense of your experience
you notice any tension tightness
Construction that's creeping up
see if there is a way to relax
and release the extra tension
this is not a big project to undertake
very light touch
it's like opening the Palms
a simple unentangled awareness
allow our system rest
to deeply settle
your resting word resting
nice is such a flavor of peaceful
being peaceful in the midst of
what is happening in your experience
peaceful abiding
to rest is to stop doing
resting is simply being
and there's a process of relaxing recognizing
releasing and the resting
wherever you are is perfect a place to be
I'm sitting in the relaxed and restful field
our hearts and Minds can open
to receive
experiences of the World At Large
the challenges and the beauty
and from this field we can receive
and challenges and beauty in our own heart and mind
[Music]
thank you everyone and today I will continue from the theme
that um were being speaking about um this is the
multifaceted or multi-dimensional aspects of our practice path
we've spoken about how we practice the words kindness
embodiment you know holding the babies in the premature World
um word or practicing in family Dynamics
and yesterday we spoke about practicing in the relational field
and so today we'll continue with yet another story
from a monastery with ink and this is called
many ways of walking the path
the monastery held a big public event celebrating the birth of the Buddha
as crowds of the visitors came to commemorate the event emotion emotion and the noise rhymed
throughout the monastery in the early afternoon for young monks
decided to slip out the back gate they had decided
that they weren't needed that their absence would not be noticed
they decided to hike a well-trodden path into the mountains
as they hiked one of the monks said I'm so glad we
decided to get away from all the chaos of the monastery I was agitated by all the people and
activity another Monk replied it hadn't occurred
to me that we were trying to get away from anything I thought we left the monastery because we wanted to reach the
Outlook with a beautiful Vista that is along this path
the third monk then spoke up quite forcefully I am not interested in escaping what is
behind us or focusing on distant goals I thought we were simply walking the
path to enjoy the views each step along the way
impatient with what the others had said fourth monk said I thought we headed out
on this path to get exercise the girls you all have
for our walk are all temporary by building up our strengths we will be
better prepared for even longer hikes that we may have to undergo
also it is such a delight to move and feel Vitality Crossing through the body
as each committed to his approach for walking the path they each decided to go
on their own way after all why should they be troubled to walk with someone
who had a different understanding of what the walk was about
the further he walked from the monastery the less the first among felt obsessed
by the festivities he had left behind when he felt quite removed from the
monastery his motivation for the heart could disappeared and he sat down and took a nap leaning
against a tree this might remind you something the
rabbit and the second monk was so eager to
reach the Outlook that he didn't notice the rocks and the
roots that lay across the path he stumbled and fell often after a while
he was scraped and bruised enough that he sat down giving up on the hike
further along the path when the past passed us through a syndic
medal the third monk left at the past to admire the beautiful butterflies flying
among the colorful flowers thoroughly enjoying himself he stayed in
the middle until it was time to return to the monastery
the fourth month became absorbed in the exercise of a walking as the flow of a Vitality increased in
his body his attention was increasingly absorbed into his immediate physical
experience when the path went by the Outlook he
didn't notice and kept hiking further into the mountains
that evening the apis who tended to notice everything that happened at a
monastery met with the four monks and asked why they had left together but
returned separately the monks explained that they had
disagreed about why they were on the path they said because they couldn't agree on
what they were doing they had to separate it each hiking according to his own purpose
for walking the path upon hearing this the abyss laughed and
then said the Buddhist path the capital P had only
exists when someone walks it while people walking on this path for
many different reasons they were equally all walkers
it doesn't matter what motivates them as long as they walk the path mindfully
if you're mindful the shortcomings of any purpose will be
overcome as Abyss my job is to help make sure you
keep walking the path your mindfulness and persistence will
take care of everything else
so well we can't talk about the practice or the path with without saying
something about mindfulness right
no matter why we started walking the path
what forms of the practice that we're engaging in whether it's the meditative a practice
or on Retreats and holding babies or caring for the family
caring for the community making a livelihood
mindfulness mindful presence places such a central role in our path
I loved this analogy that I heard early on in my practice and that is
mindfulness is like turning the light on in the Darkness
so when the light is on it has so many functions the path will begin to unfold
clearly and so in the story the first Monk walk
to the path out of the desire to escape the chaos in the monastery and some of it us may have started the
path out of desire to escape the chaos internally to ourselves or externally
but when we began to pay attention
to our immediate experience we may notice so often I wouldn't say all the time but
so often they chaos is more or less like a
jumbled cluster of thoughts stitched together by
our views beliefs ideas and they become a story that we repeated
to ourselves again and again and they can't be so dark convincing
right I can start with something very simple you know
my neighbor talks really loud well what's wrong with this man
how can that be how can you be so in considerate
you know maybe I should move away from this neighborhood I can't stand to the Sea anymore
well I've been thinking about moving away anyway for the other reasons
maybe this just is yet another reason for me to do this
but wait a minute problem why should I move things should be
moving and you can see right and there's so many times
the chaos that we create in our mind it's just this kind of a jumbled set of
thoughts gets us stitched it together because of our opinions of views ideas
but if you're paying attention were mindful about it we can see through
oh ah this is just a whole jumbo of opinions
thoughts they're quite fleeting they're quite elusive
and so as we become mindful we can relax
and the release release the holding the belief the solidity of the stories
that we may be holding on to
and the second monk who rushed through the path to try to get to the end or get
to the Outlook he ended up with a lot of scripts and the bruises
giving up the walk all together and so without being aware
our goals can become a barrier at some point
I remember from myself the first Retreat the first to teravaga
retreat I had no other agenda but to get enlightened that was it you know I had
no other thing going on that was it and so I tried so hard
I got up early in the morning slept late in the evening
and I got a whole lot of bruises and scripts of my own kind I must Retreat
fortunately I didn't give up like the second Monk I did a persist
and at some point a little bit of a mindfulness lit up
and I realized that all that striving and trying were creating a bigger
barrier rather than being a support
and so that actually cracked open the path for me
and so mindfulness is a key part of the practice
and the third month was all about enjoying the scenery and got caught up by the butterflies and the flowers
and so just like the Monk um sometimes they can get caught by the
goodies along the path you know whether it's a pleasant meditative experience or some high
praises and your friends have been telling you how do we avoid getting caught
mindfulness we can become aware how we might get caught
and when we release that we can keep going the last month of the story kept on
walking by simply present taking one step at a time
this is simple immediate kind of walking a path
broad vitality and sustained him deep into the mountain
and so as the app is says the Buddhist path capital P only exists while one
walks it so this last amongst the story is to be
continued tomorrow and so that's probably enough for today
so thank you for your attention and thank you for your practice
and we will resume in our Global Sangha tomorrow morning
have a wonderful day everyone