so hello everyone welcome
and welcome to this now next half hour of
I hope that it's something delightful
delightful period of meditation and to introduce it
I want to make the point that
we have many physiological systems within us
that are fairly distinct from each other they also work together
so for example we have the capacity to hear sounds I hear the garbage trucks
outside not right now and and
I mean some of us can hear and some of us have the capacity to also
to walk and those can be done independent of
each other and they can support each other
so we have psychological systems within us that can be independent of each other and work together
and one of them is partly at the protective system
that reacts to the threats in the world and responds quickly
but that also becomes reactive to all kinds of challenges all kinds of Imagine
challenges all kinds of things which are not ever present
but maybe imaginary or future threats or
that um and and so then this reactive system
it kind of can go Haywire and sometimes what the reactive system
is reacting to is thoughts and memories and impulses ideas in ourselves and
reactivity is sometimes reacting to reactivity and so the cycles of reactivity kind of live in people
sometimes for decades foreign so there is this protective reactive
system and then there's also the nurturing loving system
and this is where we appreciate people we have good will for them we respect them
that there's love of all the different shapes Shades all different forms of love
and uh and sometimes the reactive system
predominates when we have challenges then in particular the reactive mode gets the
upper hand and the nurturing mode the love mode is forgotten is pushed to the side
they're always there together and they have the opportunity to cooperate and work together
and they can be done independently and meditation is a Time
to relax and quiet the reactive mode it has a role sometimes in our lives but
it also it's really healthy to learn how to quiet it
to let it settle down to have a break a vacation from that
not as being disloyal to it there's a time and place for it
the reactive mode but if we can quiet down settle it in
meditation then we can bring forth the love mode the nurturing mode that
that which is really feeds us and fills us with kind of healing loving
soft dharmic um
qualities it's always there but my thing for it's often the one
that's forgotten the one that's overlooked the one that is somehow
buried so to call upon to tap into
the capacity to have good will well wishing
to view look upon others kindly
and good will your words Good Will kindly doesn't mean doesn't have the high bars
if we use the word love it's possible to have good will and look
kindly on people who we don't like liking and
love not liking and Goodwill liking and kindness are two different things
and one way to distinguish this is that
love liking good will is so good for ourselves
it nourishes ourselves and it's possible to have this good will
and its benefits fill us in a wonderfully inspiring
healing maturing way
so to sit in meditation
and to assume a posture that allows the reactive mode
to relax if you're sitting first thing in the
morning maybe the reactive mode is just a little
bit left over from the day before a little bit of physical tension
maybe there's reactive thoughts and contractions and tensions in the mind or
the heart but to sit in a way that is going to allow that to relax
then that classic posture of sitting upright can allow for the deepest relaxation
gently closing the eyes
and taking some long slow deep breaths and on the exhale
without ambition or trying too hard
relax your whole body and mind let things release let go
to avoid being reactive to your attention
to avoid have any aversion to the tensions of the body and mind
while caringly kindly
letting things relax as you breathe
and if you could intentionally relax act on that intention
and see if you can find how the intention to relax
can arise from a good will a caring
a kindness to yourself into your body
meditation is a time out
from being involved in the challenges of our life the best we can
or at least a time out from being reactive to them
trying to solve them or understand them or
relaxing relaxing as a form of self-care
and then letting your letting go of actively relaxing
and sit quietly with your breathing
as if you're getting ready to gaze upon breathing kindly
with Good Will with love for your body breathing
but first just let breathing reveal itself to you
let the inhale and exhale arise and manifest
as if they want to be known in whatever way you're breathing
breathing is the way that they want to be known
in you just feeling it knowing it
and to gently without any worry if you can't do this
and to allow your breathing
to relax let there be a caring
a good will a kindness for your breathing
to make room for it to relax or to ease up
breathing moves in the direction breathing easily lightly
being content with the very slight
easing up or relaxing of breathing
looking for places where the inhale has a softness to it
looking for places where the exhale has softness as part of it
and then is there a place in your body anywhere at all
that you associate
with good will kindness
love and well-wishing of others
well wishing of yourself maybe in the heart area maybe your belly
maybe in your mind maybe your whole body
and wherever is the
Place associated with love kindness
breathe with that breathe through it
as a Gentle Wind that fans aflame
gently fans a campfire Fanning the flame of love
kindness
centering yourself in the kindness
not in the reactivity
and then turning your attention more fully
to gaze upon yourself kindly
to view yourself with Good Will with care
with friendliness your eyes your inner eyes
gazing upon yourself kindly forgivingly
and then to turn your gaze out upon the world to the people around
you your life and your communities is if you're looking out into the world
whoever comes to mind for you quietly peacefully
maybe without them needing to know gaze upon them kindly
an attitude of friendliness warmth good will
the Buddha likened meta Goodwill
to the sound of a trumpet
you don't see it the sound travel but it travels out from the mouth of the
trumpet out into the world far so let these words of loving kindness
project your kindness good will out into the world
as a loving trumpet call
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
and with our love with our care and friendship
May each of us contribute to that possibility
even in the smallest ways
[Music]
so hello everyone and we're here at the second talk for this
week's series on love in times of challenge
and um so just repeat a little bit what I said for the guided meditation
we have many systems operating within us and um physical psychological
physiological mental systems some of which can work independent
enough from each other and some work together and
but even some of their independent can cooperate so for people who can hear and people
who can walk those two functions can operate
independent from each other and but also
they can support each other if you walk and hearing a car coming from behind you
makes you safer as you walk and um so
we have two primary systems and in Buddhism it focuses on
the most common way they talk about it is the wholesome and the unwholesome but
I don't know if that really represents well what happens for us inside that what I want to emphasize
I'd like to I like to think of them as being the protective and the and the nurturing
the protective and the cultivating so the protective is what reacts
the the reactive mode of something dangerous up and suddenly we have to act
instinctively and quickly and just react you know without thinking about it
but this reactive mode can operate when there's no immediate pressing Danger
and so um and sometimes what we're reacting to is our own thoughts I've sit quietly
sometimes and or just being by myself and and it started to have a little
fantasy imagination of some scene that turned out to be kind of dangerous
and I could feel my system reacting to it I get tense and activated and and a
little bit feel the alarm comes up and it's all a product of my imagination it's not a real thing but my system is
reacting to the imagination and so some people that end up living in
a reactive mode this protective mode way too often in such a way the protective mode is not really protecting
us it's doing the opposite that uh over protection overreacting always being in
this reactive mode is phenomenally stressful for us for the system
so um so it has its role but it can be overdone
the other system is the nurturing one the one allows that cultivates something
to grow and develop from the inside out and nurtures
the wholesome in US and that system as it operates very
differently it doesn't react to anything it it Wells up from within and we create
the conditions for it we create the ease and part of the reason to relax deeply and and live with less less stress is so
this deeper system the nurturing system can operate best and that nurturing system sometimes has
a lot of intelligence that can help us find our way through life's challenges in a very different way than the
protective system does which tends to focus on the immediacy of things and and
um and sees things through the lines of lens of threat and fear doesn't see things through this lens of
the wholeness of it and so this nurturing system is where
love exists the kind of deep abiding um
nurturing love which Wells up from the inside and does not get entangled with the reactive
system sometimes what we call love is mostly in this world of reactivity
transactional love a love that comes from maybe feeling insecure and what we
really are in love with is not a person but we're look searching for security in someone and someone seems to provide
security and that's what we're really wanting and the strong want for security
the strong want for children the strong want for
um praise strong want to be associated with someone who somehow
builds up our sense of self it's it's kind of trying to find our way
in the reactive mode rather than um the love being something that Wells
up from the inside that's not transactional it's not looking for getting something from someone else
some people love others occasionally why they love them in quotation marks is
because they love they're being loved and it's so meaningful to be loved that
they're in love with being loved more they're in love with the other person so the love thing can be complicated
when it's mixed up with the reactive mode but uh what we do when we really can
relax deeply and what Buddhism really Champions is a non-transactional love
a love which is not needing or getting something from another person
but has a number of beautiful qualities it has a tremendous appreciate
appreciation of others for who they are there is valuing others like this isn't
they just have a tremendous sense of value and the importance of this person there's a lot of respect for the other
person um that uh respect that also includes kind of granting them giving them their
autonomy uh letting them make their own choices and have their own independent life in a
certain way and not needing to fold their life into mind so that I feel safe or secure
and um and then there are the primary characteristics of this Buddhist love is
uh Goodwill is well wishing wishing really wishing someone well
and that well-wishing is not you know calculated well-wishing but rather just
a nurturing feeling like you want to nurture this person or maybe that's a little bit suffocating for some people
they feel too nurtured but but uh we just want we want the best in them and we take the light in in the possibility
of them thriving and being well and and this combination of respect
depreciation valuing and wishing people well and wanting to support the Wellness
in people um is kind of this constellation that is meta loving kindness
and that's a nurturing system so these things can operate together or
they can be mutually supportive but what happens when we're challenged uh some challenges uh trigger the
reactive system the protective system so strongly that it's the only one that's operating
and if it's only the reactive system it's fine if the mountain lion is
attacking you but uh it's not fine if it's uh you're going
for a job interview and the job interview is in a month and the whole month you're just living kind of biting
your fingernails and pacing around your room and kind of activated in some kind of tense way
That's not healthy living that kind of reactive mode
to to be hurt deeply and to live in the reactive mode that just keeps Us close to the Earth and
keeps us spinning in the reactive mode is also not healthy for us
so that to live solely in this reactive mode is not healthy so when we're challenged
the important question I'd like to propose is where's the love
can there be love here can there be kindness here where does or where does kindness begin
where do I find it here and some of that we find in wanting it
to be there to want to have love to want to have good will and meta that desire
for it is profound it's the beginning of love even if you can't do it in a
conventional way you're beginning it by just wanting it and just appreciating that wanting and
relaxing as opposed to being in this transactional mode of wanting and then
depending on getting what we want it's wanting and appreciating the Wellspring
within in which it comes from and so when we're challenged
notice if you're forgetting this other whole system the nurturing system within
and what can you do to tap into it what can you do to let the nurturing system
support you to reduce self-care to to find ways in
which to settle the reactivity enough or put it aside enough so that the
nurturing system has a chance to to emerge as well
maybe it's something maybe going for a walk or stepping away from the challenging things spending time with a
friend who makes you kind of feel happy so that you're not always kind of caught
in the realm of your challenge and and then you could come back to the
challenge in this with with this other mode available the nurturing mode the
kind mode the Goodwill mode and maybe your ability to engage in the challenge will be very different
than if you're only living in the reactive mode so this is a this is a suggestion then
that there is kind of a strategic stepping away from our challenges
when possible when it's not the mountain lion there and meditation is one of the ways to
step away from it so we're not thinking about it chronically if we can but find some way to step away enough so
it's not obsessing the mind and it allows something deeper to emerge
from the inside some sense of well-being some sense of Peace some sense of calm some sense of Goodwill of kindness
look for the kindness and sometimes it's enough to just ask the question
what's that kind thing to do here what would be the kind thing right now
and inserting that in the middle of the you know swirl of challenges
can contribute to there being light you know
appearing in a dark room it can it can create space in a place that's been
claustrophobic so um
non-transactional love non-trans transactional meta and Goodwill
what do you know about that what do you know about love how is it that your love
for others is mixed up with transactional love or mixed up with the reactive system
is there a clarification a purification of love that's possible when we quiet the reactive mode down
dramatically and now and then keep asking what would
be the kind thing here what would be the supportive thing here and finally this mode of coming from the
nurturing mode the kind mode is um is one that
um wants the best for everyone involved
not just for oneself not just for the other for everyone involved
and believe it or not even for the people who are our biggest challenge
even for people who you might think of as your enemies the Goodwill mode
has no boundaries for who deserves and doesn't deserve our
basic Goodwill so thank you and I hope that you take
these words and reflect on them and think about them maybe have conversations with people about them and
see if you can really kind of discover for yourself in this nurturing mode the loving mode
and uh and how it can become a greater resource for you
don't let it atrophy thank you