foreign
good afternoon good evening whatever time of day it is that you happen to be here
wherever you are welcome to here here Wherever You Are
my name is Maria strotman and I'm sitting in for Gill this week who is off
uh on a retreat so uh I'm very grateful to be here
I am I've been with IMC for about 25 years and Gail has been my primary teacher to
my great good fortune in my life there have been many changes
in your lives there have been many changes in my life this morning there are issues
there are changes there are things popping up the conditions of this moment are not
the same as the conditions from 25 years ago and I'm not the same person
Nora any of us but this morning this is who we are and
this is where we are so I invite you to join me
in this time in this silence so what we're going to do is we're going
to sit for about a half an hour I will very very lightly guide the meditation
that is you're mostly not going to hear me and then we'll have a little talk after that
and then there'll be a time for questions and answers so
welcome to this time together please put yourself
into an alert but relaxed posture
so that you're here and Eddie's
let's be at ease take a couple of deep breaths and let them out
and enter a brief period of Silence and just see what comes
whatever it is allow it to be here allow whatever happens to happen
uh it's this way now it's this way now
I breathe in I breathe out
and this is true and this is now
and now I am just here I'm just here
thank you
you're not waiting for something to happen we're just being here
foreign
and are you still here just here
thank you
foreign
let's recall that we are here
become aware once again here just here
I'm just here feel your body here
feel your mind here your heart here
just here just now just In This Moment
just here
let out the breath and bring it in
just this breath just this one
[Music]
ah so welcome everyone
my name is Maria strotman and I'm sitting in for Gill this week
um I am just here just me
I have been many things in my life I've done many things in my life I've been a scientist a businesswoman
I've been retired for some time I've been with IMC for 25 years plus
I've done any things with IMC I've been a hospice worker
I've been mentally inclined I've been filled with my heart as of all of us
we've been many many many things
one of the things I'm doing now is I organize the online group practice
discussions and offer them a couple of times a week although that's changing but
that's been wonderful to share with people the Dharma I love the Dharma I
love talking about the Dharma I love living the Dharma
I asked some people what do you think you'd like to hear what would you like to to have as a topic
and I got a couple of a couple of suggestions one of which was something about Ai and you know what I discovered
is that everybody has an opinion about artificial intelligence and I'd be spending all my time talking about what
it was and so I'm not doing that but there was another suggestion that
had to do with how do I deal with self-blame and
self-criticism and since that's been up for a lot of people lately that I've talked to
and is something that we all grapple with I thought maybe that's what we'd talk about we're going to talk about
self-blame self-criticism but I wanted to do it by by calling the whole topic
blamelessness discovering and recovering blamelessness
and the shift is one of energy it's not something I have to fight about but rather something
I want to embody in my life blamelessness it's lighter somehow
if you've ever been plagued by self-criticism you know that it's very tight and heavy and it's a truly
burdensome
what we're going to do over the course of this week is talk about several ways into that
why why do we engage so much in self-criticism what are the elements of it and how can we become less
affected by that criticism that voice in our heads that say you're not good
enough you should be better you should have not done that you shouldn't have been that way how come I can't let go of
that why can't I let go of that I don't really want to be that way
and all of these are arguments taking place in the head so
one of the tools that I use one of the mantras that I use is the opening to the
dhamapata I want you to think about this week that
this weekend have it in your heads all experience is preceded by mind led
by mind made by mind speaker Act
with a corrupted mind and suffering follows like the wheels of
the cart behind the Hooves of the ox all experience is preceded by mind led
by Mind Made In My Mind speaker act with a peaceful mind and
happiness follows like a never departing shadow I like the fact that the happiness thing
comes later because I can kind of take let the breath out you know I said the corrupted mind the mind that says no no
no what about what about what about has tightness and and the energy of
contraction around it and the peaceful mind has the energy of ease and openness
and lightness and it leads to happiness like a never
departing Shadow wonderful I'm there I want to do that
in order to to Grapple with why it is that we get tied up in self-criticism
there are three things that are important to keep in mind one is
we don't know what's actually going to happen because there's an element of
self-criticism that has to do with I'm sure I know what's going to come next it's always going to be this way I know
that this this is what comes from that so so the attitude of not knowing
is kind of an antidote to the I know I know this is the way I am
not knowing not knowing
impermanence it's changing all the time
I was talking to someone the other night and they said given what you just told me why are you
smiling I said because I'm because right now everything's lovely because right now I'm speaking to you and my heart is
light and I'm smiling I don't have to carry everything from my
past into this moment I can just be in this moment the impermanence has to do
with just being here in this moment I don't have to worry about what's
ending and what's arising I can just see this
what's the attitude in my heart right now is it tight oh
I can feel the dis the distancing from that the desire to distance myself from
that and not self
all of the things we believe are true about us are just one thing
we are not the same people we were we're not the same people we were a moment ago
a moment ago we were tied in something else now we're tied or loose here
improvements impermanence
we can be born into every moment every moment is a new moment
but then I think about how much courage it takes to be completely present
to feel safe enough not to hide behind the vigilance of
needing to be different or the vigilance against that condition
or admitting we may not know the outcome of something
we may not know what that person is going to do we may not know how we'll feel about something tomorrow
we may not know it takes courage to be completely present
you know I I was visiting my grandson a few weeks ago he's three okay so you
have a little three-year-old if any of you have three-year-olds in your life or recall three-year-olds in your life you
know that they are not particularly rational although they you get used to talking to
them and you think oh yeah they know exactly what I'm saying so I got engaged in this conversation with them because
we were putting together some snacks to go on a trip and I was going to stick him in my purse and I had this little
dish that had the snacks in and I found a lid that fit on that and he said no no
we can't have that and I said no it's okay and he says I can't drink out of that and pretty soon he was screaming
and shrieking and I have this hearing aid that increases high frequency sounds
because that's where my hearing's loss is and a three-year-old shrieking in that ear is painful and and trying to
explain to them but you don't need to drink out of this lid we're just using it as a lid no no I can't
I can't have that and I thought what am I doing arguing with a three-year-old it must be crazy and so I walked away I
just walked away never underestimate the value of temporarily walking away
and I thought okay he can't reason his way to this what is it that's bothering
him he can't drink out of the lid okay so I went back to him and I said I'm going to
take this seal off the top oh okay
I had to actually hear that he couldn't drink out of a cup the fact that he
wasn't going to drink out of the cup was totally irrelevant when we were trying to argue ourselves
out of something we're just like that we're busy saying but I know that won't
work that won't work and we're not hearing what is it we're not seeing what is it
that I'm actually protesting against is it
my fear of being seen a certain way is it my fear that I'm not worthy is it my
fear that things are going to happen enough of my control am I worried about being taken advantage of what's
underneath that criticism of me what's underneath it what is the place
that is close in to me that I'm experiencing that I am
my mind habit reflecting out as I just can't I just I just can't do this it's
all my fault it must be my fault if it's unsatisfactory it must be my fault
who says it's just unsatisfactory
it's the tendency that we as humans all have to sort of wrap things up and make them work
if if there's something coming at me that's painful I have to I have to take care of that I have to organize it I
have to control it because I don't feel safe
somewhere is the trigger that says I'm not feeling safe
and somehow it gets translated into why can't I be better
and what I'm saying is it's better to just be you whatever you are however you
are in this moment not who you were yesterday or last year and mind habits over the course of a
lifetime become incredibly strong and we believe them just as we believe
our thoughts but just as we don't really know
I want to remind you that life is not a ledger it's not like we line up all the good
things we do against all the bad things we do and if the bad things outweigh the good things then we're good we're bad
or vice versa life is not a ledger
all experience is preceded by mind led by mind made by mind
speaker act with a corrupted mind and suffering follows
be correct with a peaceful mind and happiness follows
like a never departing shadow so when you find yourself tied up
and trying to argue yourself out of something let go of all of the mental activity
around that just walk away temporarily
take the lid off and say what am I really feeling right now
just be you here the you that is here now
and just for that moment you are completely safe
no a moment of being safe
because like all practice it's cumulative it's cumulative
it comes and the more we notice the more often we
notice the more easy it becomes
so I have a little poem to read you in this last moment
I hope
I put on again the vest of many pockets easy to forget which holds the reading
glasses which the small pen which the house keys the compass and whistle the
passport to forget at last for weeks even the pocket holding the day of digging a place for my sister's ashes
the one holding the day where someone will soon enough put my own to misplace the pocket of touching the
walls that Auschwitz would seem impossible it is not
to misplace for a decade the pocket of tears I rummage and rummage transfers
from Munich from Melbourne to Oslo a receipt for a Singapore kepi a device
holding music Bach Garcia Richter Porter part a woman lawn dead now gave me when
I told her I could not sing a kazoo now in a pocket
some wear a pocket build holding a Steinway somewhere a pocket holding a packet of salt
where gazian vest Oxford English Dictionary vest with the magnifying glass tucked inside one stabbed closed
pocket Wikipedia vest Rosetta vest Enigma vest of decoding how is it one
person can carry your weight for a lifetime one person slip into your open arms for a lifetime
who was given the world and hunted for tissues for chapstick
let your life be like that open vest the memories are fine but they're not
who you are the route to blamelessness the root to
blamelessness is through allowing you to be just who
you are now not the person tucked away in a pocket
thank you may you be at ease with who you are
so if anyone has any questions or comments I'm happy to hear them
hey thank you Maria um so if anyone has anything in uh any
questions from Maria you can go ahead and raise your hand and call on you and in YouTube If you have our YouTube
viewers regarding poster questions in chat and
pulls into Mia
so Maria just uh as a initial question like you know I've heard that you know with adults uh taking a break for like
20-25 minutes is usually appropriate um you know when you want to walk away for three-year-olds what would be your
uh estimated well you know three three-year-olds are
great because they give up the moment so easily they haven't got an accumulated history and so they actually I I went
back to him oh I don't know about three minutes later
and said oh I've taken the lid off the top the seal off the top and he said oh great
they really have the ability to come right back oh okay so maybe it's like uh uh
the number of minutes you take the break is like equivalent to the age of the person you're dealing with it can be but
not necessarily okay I I use this actually when I find myself in conflict with my husband
I have this great story where I was I had been on a diet it was a very restrictive diet and I had to eat and it
was really and eat at regular intervals and I was really really hungry and he had this elaborate plan for
dinner and I kept saying no no I'm hungry I'm hungry and I realized I was hypoglycemic and I was
rational and I left the room and I came back
and immediately we were in it again I went out of the room I came back I had to come back three times the third time
he handed me a carrot which was perfect and then it was over so it isn't it it's
just it's a pause it's a it's a break it's a break in the habit actually it's
a break in the intensity that you're looking for sure is that time related or it's but it
is related to being aware of what's going on great well thank you um Marlene has her
hand Reese so uh Marlene you can go ahead and unmute hi Maria hi everyone
um I'm gonna try and get to my question Maria it's pretty convoluted because this is a very
fraught topic for me um as you have some understanding of since I've spoken to you a few times
fear is an overwhelming consuming Motion in my life and um
I find myself trying to focus and be aware of what I feel in the moment
what's happening in the moment since that's all we really have that we can focus on with any reliable sense of
reason um and then I find myself going into
projection about this could happen in the future this could happen and I have no way of knowing what could happen or
what could not happen based on the past though I would say talk about
impermanence being Illustrated and glaring reality
constantly over and over again everything is subject to change at a moment's notice
or no moments notice um so what am I trying to get to
I'm trying to I I'm trying to figure out what do I want
who do I I mean that's a huge question I know we'll see so here maybe maybe this
will help you know one of the one of the one of the things we often find when we're tied up in mental habits is that
there is some fear this may happen this may not happen and arguing ourselves out
of it will not help so I remember one time being in a very fearful situation where I thought it was going to fall off
the side of a mountain and I'm terrified of heights and I said you know you're a good Buddhist
you know that this is temporary you don't have to believe these stories none of that was working
and I said okay I'm afraid and allowing myself to be afraid was
freed me from having to justify being the fear I didn't have to justify why I
was afraid I just said I'm afraid and as soon as I was able to accept fear
is here then I said so what are you afraid of well I'm afraid I'm gonna fall off the mountain
and it was easy from there to say well I will either fall off the mountain
or not fall off the mountain but the one thing I'm sure of is I can't stay here
yes that's a very good point okay so it's it's first you have to say
this is what's here anger is here fear is here uncertainty is here you have to
have the courage to say I don't know how to fix this right now
but this is here this is here this pain this this anger
this whatever it is so what are my choices given that this is
true now what given that this is true now what
and and try to stay in the moment and not in the future but just here given
that I'm scared to death I choose not to Die In This Moment
and move on it's you not only can walk out of the
room but you can stop thinking about stop turning turning it over turning
turning let just okay
and what you discover when you're paying attention to that corrupted mind idea is
that the fear is not as corrupted as the fighting around it is not as tense and as structured as the
fighting it the some of the fighting is creating the very energy that you'd like to let go of
so we train ourselves not to be afraid of what is here
but to say this is Pleasant this is unpleasant I neither have to like it or not like it
I can just say here is this to know the nature of it is to free us
from having to choose or not choose it there's a nature of it
did you say that last sentence one more time please to know the nature of it is to free
oneself from the need to choose it or not choose it
to let go of the struggle against it or for it
allows us to be present for joy and present for pain
I think I'm still crawling but I'm making some progress thank you very much
aren't we all Maria there were a couple questions on
uh from our YouTube viewers as well as on Zoom about the title of the poem and
the poem this is invest by Gene Hirshfield so it's Jane hirschfield the
best it's from her latest book called The Ledger I'm a big fan of Jane hirschfield so and
that was called the vest thank you uh really give more
information than that but I ran out of time sure sure um Kane on YouTube asked uh Maria can
you please talk on societal self-criticism I guess the difference between critique
and criticism as some criticism can lead to better ideas or disbanding old held
assumptions for example women's rights around the world
Okay so so it's important to distinguish between
um let's see how can I put this um
I was going to talk about something that I think is actually Your Role but directly to the question so I'm resorting in my head so so it is the
difference between discernment and blame discernment and blame so
so excuse me to take for example
um women's rights I was a
person in in high tech business for most of my business life
and I ran it and I was often the only woman in the room and to maintain my
place in the room was sometimes very difficult and to not have to be something I was not was
very difficult and I'm very uh aware of the stress that
can arrive arise from women's rights and myself I'm a very
strong proponent of women's rights and at a time in my life I developed a
horde a bag of anger over that that I carried around with me that could be
triggered at any moment and this was not only unhealthy but it was part of the corrupted mind that was
keeping me in the world of suffering I have not given up
standing up for women's rights or supporting organizations that are
defending women I have stopped
feeding my own anger to justify my position
so the difference in criticism and critique is that criticism says it's
your fault which is irrelevant to actually solving the problem I don't
have to place lame I just have to deal with the Injustice
and do something about the injustice I don't have to build up the history of hate that is related to it's your fault
or it's my fault I don't have to replace
discernment with blame in order
to improve conditions in life so I hope that answers the question
yeah I guess it kind of sounds like that Razors Edge between like reflection and rumination or something yeah yeah very
good observation thank you uh Roxanne has um uh just to be who you
are that's the question who am I how do I know who I am so I think that's
something that I think everyone has had to deal with at some point like how I guess
who am I so the the most important part of that question is the question itself
who am I not knowing is really important
so in order to know who you are
one needs to be in touch with what am I experiencing now
and what are the reactions of now and what are the the sensitivities of
now it isn't what you do for a living or how
you spend your time or the causes you believe in
those are consequences of who Who You Are
when I say to just be you what I mean is
that it's not necessary for you to become someone else to be free of suffering
you don't have to achieve the ideal whatever that is
you just need to be here with this with the uh the honesty to be truly present
with what's here so if I am at the moment
resentful I need to be able to see resent
and say oh I'm sorry you're feeling that way Maria because it doesn't feel good and and do
I have to tell myself the story to justify that resentment to keep it there
yes I do and so I can stop the story I don't have to condemn the resentment
I can stop defending it who I am is the person who is in this
moment grappling with whatever is true In This Moment
and it is a result of the conditioning I've had my whole life
thank you all of the events I remember and don't remember
and the conditions of this moment over which I have very little control
the conditions of this moment one might say none
so where is the blame what we have are is our intentions and
what we do next and what I hold in my heart
so know what you're holding in your heart thank you
if I could give voice to just what's true for me now what would the voice sound like
would it be harsh would I shy from it would it be light
just know it
see it clearly
I want to ask myself that question for a month long retreat who am I and I've got
a lot of answers and at one point I there was a conversation going on my
head this person was saying this and this person was saying this and running and it was going back and forth and then
there was another voice that said shut up and I said to myself
who am I all of these voices
we are not the voice in our head
so kind of keep that in mind also I hope that helps I'm sorry if I
would take a longer conversation conversation to actually know if it's
helpful hey thank you Maria and then uh Charles
Lee just had a uh a quote I think is related to the uh uh critique criticism
um this is from Tony Morrison uh the function the very serious function of racism or any systemic bias is
distraction keeps you from doing your work keeps you from explaining over and over again your reason for
being
repeat the first part of that place it's the Tony Morrison quote Yeah
yeah from Charlie uh the function the very serious function of racism or any
systemic bias is distraction uh it keeps you from doing your work it keeps you from
explaining over and over again your reason for being
yeah it
significant that one does not see whatever pause one
has ignoring what is true or walking away from what is true or
walking away from what one sees or the discomfort of the moment
the quality of
seeing what is perhaps
un uncomfortable for us or unpleasant for us
contains a message that says I can get distracted into
arguing about this or I can live my life in a full and open way that sees that
and works within it
to right wrongs to live my life free and openly and not to be
actually constrained by all the things that I believe
it's a very interesting quote Charles Lee thank you
yeah and I think finally uh Marlene has her hand up again so Marlene you can go ahead
oh thank you um I wanted I really loved that quote that
you that you read Maria about um speak with a with a corrupted mind
and suffering follows um speak with a with a peaceful mind peaceful mind and
um basically happiness follows
so um I certainly believe that speaking with
Equanimity and peace in your heart um is
the way to go to to trying to move forward to understanding to getting things done to
to having something to talk about and knowing what to do about it but if
you're if you're dealing do you have any suggestions for how to
um how to how to speak with someone how to get to the point with someone who
lives in the state of anger
um just as you can't talk yourself out of anger you can't talk someone else out of
anger nor do you have a responsibility to talk them out of anger but I recently met
with a friend who was very angry and had indeed turned some of her grief
at losing her husband into anger towards other people who justifiably were
her her anger could be justified by the unfairness that was she was being met
with but as she was speaking I said
she said she said something like uh I guess uh I've just been naive
in trying to be open with them and I said because they
are as they are does not mean that you have to stop being as you are
you don't have to give up being a warm and open person in exchange in
order to fight against them you can still be the warm person that
you are the warm and generous person that you are you can just stop being generous to them
but you don't have to fight them or develop anger in your heart that is not
consistent with your own intentions in life you don't have to criticize your
own generosity because of how it's being met you hold on to just Who You Are
you hold on to just who you are and you act accordingly to who you are so you
need to live your life according to who you are if it's what is the condition of anger so so I
saw the anger at her and I offered her the opportunity to not be angry I didn't
try to talk her out of anger she would she was being attacked by these people no question that she should
react to it she didn't have to be talked out of it she just needed to get back in touch
with her own intentions and not be changed by them
not to give the power over to the opponent and guess what I'm trying to to get to
though is it's not just a one-off case it's a case where this person spend so much time in the in the state
of anger that do I think that I talked her out of being angry no I only gave
her a piece another way to that she could experience the moment right I hope
those moments increase for her right you cannot change someone else's name right and you can't if you are the recipient
of their anger which I also experience you can either say I hear your anger I
hear your objections but I have no quarrel with you or you can engage in
becoming angry in response which is not useful
you can just say I have no quarrel with you it's amazing what that will do
thank you but you have to reside in a place of here I am just as I am
it takes courage to be present it takes a lot of courage to live in the
present moment I don't think I had any clue as to how much
happiness lies in the present moment though thank you everyone
and thank you very much Kevin for taking care of me yeah well thank you everybody and uh we'll see you all tomorrow thank
you Maria for your teachings thank you Maria