Welcome to our YouTube meditation time and uh oh someone just wrote the
links are still wonky um so I used a calendar link today
and that worked for me fine so I don't know uh maybe there are other places that it hasn't been uh uh fixed so um if
maybe if some of you are trying other places to get a link to the to the YouTube maybe you can put in the
chat where you tried and where you found it not working um and uh and I can't really ask
the people who haven't made it here who are maybe kind of uh not finding a good
link so uh but there a little team of people have been working hard try to figure out what's going on and there's
some idea that maybe something has changed that uh at YouTube about settings
or something something went wonky so
um so welcome and
um I I believe there comes a time when it's useful to consider that meditation
budh meditation mindfulness meditation um involves a very different
Paradigm very different orientation or basis than how we ordinarily go about
our lives and not necessarily to um
to dismiss or belittle how we go through our ordinary lives the concerns and
orientations we have but it uh to add to it a a very different way of being at
least for a short time maybe it's as the different as between being awake in our
ordinary life taking care of all kinds of things and then sleeping both are needed but you don't
want to continue doing in all the activities of daily life um in your
sleep and that doesn't belittle what we do in life to sleep it actually enhances
them because it hopefully makes us refreshed for it so the same way with meditation it's uh something that's
different than both the activities and usual ways the mind works and it's also different than sleep and so it's a third
option which is refreshing it's has its own tremendously valuable
value and um so I'd like to offer you a perspective on this alternative way of
being that meditation can offer ordinarily in our life uh we can be
concerned about something sometimes we're concerned about other people sometimes we're concerned about
ourselves sometimes we're concerned about events and things and ideas
and objects and experiences that we can
have the possibility in meditation is not to have the mind
concerned about anything and what I mean by concerned is that uh it's oriented towards something
it's picking something up it's considering something it's um it's uh
organizing its thoughts its emotions its attention around something that's we
want to deal with or respond to or be involved in or not be involved
in and uh and uh and
so to um uh and so and that's kind of often
how the minds you Minds usually work but to have an attention and
awareness which is not concerned with uh
anything but alert and aware and receptive to what
is not con concerned about it not avoiding it not shutting down from it not
distracted from it but a certain activity of the mind has come to rest
and I'd like to offer uh some Expressions that might uh represent
these uh we have a number of Wonderful ful expressions in English that begin with the word
open a person can be open-handed which means that uh they're
not clinging and holding on to anything there's an openness and willingness to share and be available to the
world open-handed with their
generosity openminded open-minded means we're available and open to lots of
perspectives points of view consider to uh you know we're not holding on to any
particular view or opinion and saying it's the best or the only one we're
receptive and and able to take things in and to hear them and and um maybe
maybe even consider their truth or their possibilities so to be open-minded to
things openhearted the heart is open
means it's receptive it's available but I think it also has a
meaning that uh that uh some of the best qualities of the heart have been revealed so love and kindness and
compassion and sensitivity and
connectivity and then we have uh kind of a modern Buddhist uh idea the of open
awareness so uh open awareness that uh that uh we
are that the awareness is not limited or
contracted or fixated on anything the awareness is available to all things and
all these seven common a sense of openness to possibility openness to availability to what
is and in terms of not being about concerns about others being concerned
con ered about oneself being concerned about things and events it's a kind of a prec concerned
State before we become concerned what is awareness like before
we become fixated or worried or start planning or wanting or not
onean thing what is it like to be aware
openly aware openly openminded so that's kind of the the
suggestion for this meditation is to explore this open way of
being that is there
before the mind gets involved in its concerns and you will get involved in
your concerns for this this meditation I'm sure but
um look behind them look underneath them look before
them look between them look let go of them to see what is there in this this
openness vast openness of awareness of
attention so to gently close your
eyes and let there be a gentling
within a gentling that includes relaxing the
shoulders
and [Music]
two soften the belly
maybe softening the hands relaxing the hands they're a little more
open fingers are not tight in any
way and letting the face
relax we talk about something times a face being an open face s of openness in
the face a lot has to do with the muscles
relaxed relaxing the thinking mind softening gentling
the energy of thinking the intensity of
thinking the speed of
thinking and any tension associated with
thinking
and sitting here with a global awareness of your
body whatever Global might mean for you easy
relaxed awareness of the whole
body in whatever way that is is for you maybe just a
torso above the waist or anything and
to and then this way of being aware that's before
concerns before agendas before judgments and needing things to be a certain way
or not be a certain way see if you can let that
be the way in which you now become aware of your body
breathing
being aware of the body breathing wherever it's easiest to be aware of
being
aware in a way that's easy to be
aware aware of the
obvious before you have any concerns or with relaxing the concerned
mind letting the concerns recede to the
background
openminded
openhearted open
ended open awareness
here
now
for
e
open
handed
openhearted
openminded open
not limited by any concerns not focused on any
concerns with awareness wider more
open
Fuller than any concerns for self or others or
anything the unconcerned
awareness
for
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
there's a different way of caring for the
world where the heart is
unconcerned meaning it's unfocused or
un not worried not preoccupied not
tense not fixated on anything
but the heart the Mind knows something about being deeply at
ease and with that ease knowing that ease wishing that for others wishing
others to have a kind of unconcerned happiness unconcerned
peace un fixated
freedom may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all [Music] beings be
peaceful and may all beings be
[Music]
free
thank
you
so
happy to be here with you and to continue here on Wednesday
with the topic of the day which the week which is action compassion compassionate
action and trying to offer some different perspectives on what we can
do motivated by compassion and so Monday was compassion
and action for the sake of others yesterday was compassion and
action for the sake of oneself not distinct or separate from
others but in addition so the compassionate action
where we're both doing it for our own sake and for sake of others for the sake of others and for ourselves so there's a
mutuality a fullness of care in all Direction c s and um the suggestion is that that uh
compassion for others caring for others is richer more valuable when we know how
to do proper care Compassionate Care for ourselves we have more care we are more
love to give others when there's a Kind of Love here for
ourselves so today I want to do uh the third form of AC ction or way of acting
and that is action that's uh for the sake of both self and others and this is
a category that the Buddha often uses um that in addition to kind of intentions
for the welfare of oneself of others he also talks about the intention for the
welfare of both self and others and um and uh and I understand
this both both self and other as being the we that exists between us the kind
of the the nature and quality of the Rel relatedness the relationship that exists between us and
that's something that's distinct enough from the other person from ourselves
it's kind of the the dynamic the chemistry the the interaction the
quality of the interaction between two people and um and uh so when we do
compassionate action for others what what relationship does that
establish between you and um and this mostly focuses now
on uh you know compassion action that you're doing in the presence of another person uh if you send a check to
support um you know uh orphanages in Uganda because you read about in the
newspaper you know there's not that much of a relationship between the Orphans in
Uganda but there is maybe uh you are in a sense establishing some kind of
relatedness that maybe is a little bit one directed but it's still a relatedness with uh suffering in Uganda
and and uh and you know there's a bigger kind of Wei that's operating here as
well and what is that so especially when we're doing to directly for ourselves uh
directly with someone else and it's easy to have easy enough to do what we think
is compassionate action that um uh uh we're kind of very strongly
kind of uh imposing ourselves on the other person or so focused on the other
person that we're completely ignoring ourselves and in ignoring ourselves we
also then ignore what's being established between us because that involves both self and
other a relatedness and I've known people who have done wonderfully compassionate
things for others out of compassion but there was no personal connection even when it was oneon-one It was kind of
perfunctory or it was kind of just like yes I want to help this person and here you can this here something you can have
or do or how how you can be helped but there's a kind of a
distance um and and um and some of that distance sometimes is when we hold ourselves apart sometimes uh with the
idea of pity or superiority or here let me help you who's so poor and you know
miserable and um and is kind of looking down at people and so the relationship
then is not a healthy relationship to be the one who has the power and the
authority to do things and the other person doesn't and so then to be compassionate with our power and our
Authority to fix things for them or do things for them but what it continues is a the relationship of kind of a power
Dynamic uh that's not really that healthy either and it's not the best vehicle through which compassion and
love can flow much still be helping people in beneficial way but their relationship is
not necessarily such a wonderful relationship to have and so is it a relationship of
mutual respect or is a relationship of respect
even if it's not mutual in One Direction which kind of changes the nature of the
dynamic between the two people is there love is there friendly Friendship between them is friendship being
offered um are we contributing to a richer more valuable relatedness between
the two people or are we holding ourselves off at a distance and are we
kind of being one-sided or are we not open to the relationship uh we don't want to
be open to the relationship we don't want a relationship we maybe give uh uh
maybe some money to someone who's homeless but you know we're afraid of the person or we aversive of the person
we don't really want to have any more contact we want to help them but we don't want any more contact because of
all kinds of reasons and so that the relationship is one that is not no relationship in a sense and the the the
importance of this relatedness in relationships is that um the kindness
the friendliness the the M mutuality that can exist in relationships even
with strangers for many people is kind of like food for the heart that uh human
beings um in a big for many people not everyone but many human beings um the
really kind of who we are as a person how we live as a person how we grow as a person how we uh are happy as a person
has a lot to do with how we are in relationship to other people a lot of our unhappiness is also
how we're in relationship with people and there's often a uh over concern with
relatedness over concern what people think and and am I going to be rejected
I'm going to be elik and what can I do to have a good Rel relationship how do I get respect how do I get love from other
people and there's a lot of concerned activity and there is something we learn
through meditation about being unconcerned unworried
unopinionated un without neediness in their
relationship but open to establishing a healthy relationship between self and
other and the simplest healthy way is one of friendliness uh we don't want to have
too high a bar that we're supposed to love everyone that's a that may be nothing then that can be
interfere but just a simple friendliness or maybe even more simple maybe it's
respect to to establish a level of respect in that relationship between you
uh appreciation uh Attunement um and um awareness that
people thrive in being listened to and being seen clearly for who they are and
sometimes if we can see someone and stop and listen uh lo and behold that that
gives them the possibility of doing the same to us and then what happens the magic the
specialness that can happen between people even total strangers even seeing each other for 30
seconds of being kind of open and and to acknowledge to see and to know each
other where we meet with an open mindedness and open-heartedness and
open-handedness and we see each other in that openness we see each other in the
richness and the fullness without needing to Define without having needs without having
fears so compassion and action that where the maybe the part of
the compassion that thing that is most beneficial for everyone concerned is not
giving someone money is not giving them food not driving them to the doctor
that's the vehicle for some deeper movement of care and compassion that
allow creates a richer valuable connection warmth love between people so
what is the relatedness we're creating what are we contributing to it take someone to the emergency and they might
remember that for a long time but take someone to the emergency with a real
love and care and kindness and respect and that uh uh might be what has a
long-term benefit for them that might even be greater than whatever the doctor does for them in the
emergency um so compassionate action for the sake of
self and other is uh something uh to be concerned
about when we do compassionate action so that it becomes a more considered more
richer more there's more facets to what compassionate action is than the simple
thing of doing something for someone else and um and that's this UD of
establishing this good relationship or offering that um is why it's so important the second thing we talked
about yesterday which is um uh compassionate action which is for the
sake of oneself meaning we take care of ourselves we do it so that it nourishes us it supports us it liberates us it
opens us it to love and care and respect for others and then there's more
richness and possible in the relatedness between self and other so compassionate
action for the sake of self and other so if you'd like over the next 24
hours to uh explore this in your life daily life um you might no one needs to
know you're doing this but you might um uh give some attention to notice when
you're with other people what's the quality of that relatedness and what are you
contributing to the quality of relatedness relationship between between between you and and um and again it
doesn't have to be you know dramatic it doesn't have to be
love but is there something what's the chemistry what's the atmosphere what's
the Dynamics that's been established between you and others even strangers
like you know clerks in a store or or U people standing on line
or people you pass on the road is there relationship or do you just walk down
this down the road and ignore whoever's passing you by or are you available to
smile or say hello and and in a way that feels safe and appropriate what is the relationship you
have with the people what kind of relationship established and then if you do this exercise it's very interesting
to see how it shifts that relatedness in the course of a conversation or a time
together how the quality of conversation that what we say and how we feel and
what we convey to others we can feel that the conversation opens the conversation connects us more or the
conversation closes us and creates more distance and we can sometimes see in
other people uh that the effect of what we're talking about that now now they're pulling away a teeny bit they feel more
closed they're turning away a little bit looking out or now they're really opening up they're present they're
delighted and it can be very subtle energetics that shift and change
but what happens if you start noticing the Dynamics of the relatedness and how does that affect how you want to be
compassionate caring um helpful for for other
people so um thank you very much and I
look forward to continuing this tomorrow