I spent a good part of the summer in the wilderness or the edges of the
Wilderness play places and recently I was a one one uh
place where there was some people who are quite skilled and had Wilderness
skills and they were going to help some of the people who didn't have much skills talk about you know how to navigate in
the wilderness and and so one of the skills is what to do when you're lost
and so I want to talk about and then later there's a friend who's studied with a indigenous
person in Canada and Indigenous person herself and she
told the story of her Elder finding someone who was lost a boy who
was lost this story really had a big impact on her and helped and really had a big impact
on her Buddhist Meditation practice so so this idea of lost has come to my mind
so I thought and I think not a few it's not so far not such a stretch to think
about how in this as a metaphor being lost for how people are confused or lost
or not don't know how to find their way in their life in their lives
it can be lost in relationships confused uncertain what do we do now
it could be in a sense of purpose in life or work it could be in in oneself once identity
once what's important for one what's what are we supposed to do it can be lost with our emotional lives emotional
lives are quite difficult and often not obviously rational or
obviously therefore a clear reason that we can address so some people feel lost in their emotional life and so this idea
of being lost I think is a um in some way or other is a common
human phenomenon so these two stories that I've been living with about being
lost I think might be a nice reference point so the Wilderness guides a guide who is
telling people what to do when they're lost is explained that the best thing you can do if you as soon as you're lost
stop stand still in the wilderness the people who get really lost in the
wilderness and they are not found easily are the ones who kind of stumble along trying to find their way and keep going
and they don't know their way and they end up going deeper and deeper into the Wilderness and places where maybe it
doesn't occur to others to find them but if you stop as soon as you're lost
then you're relatively close maybe to a place where other people go or where people think you've gone or something
so the idea of stop and be still and that's counterintuitive because you're lost it's dangerous you have to do
something and so let's keep going let's keep searching or something but this emphasis was really stand still
in weight and um and someone you know if someone will find you especially if they know
you're out in the wilderness we didn't tell anyone that's you know that's not a that's a sign of
not being skilled in Wilderness either so
um so the um and so this idea of standing still when
you're lost I think is quite a wonderful thing in life in general and one of the
things that standing still does and what it's a metaphor for is not to keep going not to keep spinning
and in the wilderness uh if you stop and stand still maybe there's opportunity to
relax to settle to catch your breath begin looking around in the environment
what's going on here and and people who panic when they get lost don't think
very well don't study their environment very well but if you stop and stand still then all
the surface tension all that kind of extra stuff that we add on top of the situation has a chance to settle
and if you have a med if you have a meditation practice maybe even you sit down and meditate for a while to really
let the surface all the extra agitation emotion spinning of the Mind fear subtle
enough so when you open your eyes maybe you can look at the situation more clearly and you notice oh it's kind of it's kind
of quiet and uh now I can hear better and quietly in the distance I hear that
River you know the river that's where I came from I crossed the
river and I know I know the direction of it but you had to be quiet enough to hear it
and um or it's quiet enough to think oh there's a Hilltop just really close by I
wonder if I go to there and look get the kind of the overview of the place maybe I'll have a better sense of where I came
from or what's the direction to go and so just being calm settling down is
powerful in all kinds of places when we're in feel like lost in our lives and
one of the things that does is stopping whatever we do stop and be still meditate maybe is what we're beginning
to shed or allowing to settle away is all the stuff that is extra that's not
needed that gets in the way of our Clarity our wisdom our kind of seeing you know what the valuable
landmarks there might be for us to find our way and um so a big part of what meditation
practice can do Mindless practice do is not what it gives us but what it helps us to let go of what
we shed from it which if if in fact we're agitated afraid caught up in what's going on
spinning then um you know at shed all the stuff that's extra from some kind of clear seeing
and this happened to me I wasn't lost physically but I was in the wilderness
when I had this I was living in a Wilderness Monastery Buddhist Monastery so I spent a lot of time walking in the
mountains and by myself and we had days off in the monastery so
that's when I went walking in the world in the wilderness and and sometimes on Trails sometimes off trails but uh the
first year in the monastery a lot of what I did during these days law days off was be kind of miserable
because uh that's when I was left alone enough to start thinking about what am I going to do with this life of mine
you know and we should what should I do I I'd been accepted to graduate school and I
contact the graduate school and told them that something important it kind of came up had come up and could I please
defer for a year what I didn't tell them that the one important thing that came up was I was
going to a Buddhist monastery and um they said sure So I knew they was
waiting for me this the question should I go to graduate school and and um and
it was it was a graduate program to do some be of service to the world and what I thought was an important way
and so this idea of being a service that seems almost like should I do that they said okay to do that and where my
motivation's accurate is this the right thing to do should I continue in Buddhism and you know what should I do
with my life and so I was in my 20s and it and was wondering what did what to do
and and so because I did couldn't figure it out then I had a lot of doubts about myself and doubts about my ability to
choose I was lost and I was confused and I was miserable and that you know with
all this how I was and um and so this went on for long you
know many many months and at some point I was on some trail the height doing this usual usual kind
of kind of rumination usual kind of kind of questioning myself wondering what to do
and I said Gil I said to myself you're spending a lot of time and more
and more time in your imagination of things other places and other times
what you're going to do in the future and where at some place where that might be where I might go do that
and I said you know this is just your imagination it's not actually what's
happening what would happen or whatever I made it I realized it was I felt I felt kind of
hopeless after all these months of this kind of reflection and thinking and I didn't I
feel like I didn't feel like I couldn't find an answer anymore that way
and so I made a decision to be still I mean I think I still walked on the trail but uh to just start
and to really stop all this movement of the mind and Imagination and doubting and all that
and um and just take the next step just show up for the next thing that was
there so on this Trail The Next Step was literally The Next Step and it was time to get back to the
monastery so that's and you get back to the monastery there it's all choreographed they ring a bell and you
have to go meditate you know ring another Bell and you go eat and all this stuff so so I was really lucky that I
made this decision just start my it was it literally was the decision was to start my life over
and I don't know maybe it's kind of naive to think you can do that but uh but I'm naive sometimes that's okay
and sort of serves me sometimes and so I said I said okay I'm going to start over and but to start over in the
Buddhist Monastery that's kind of unusual I feel so lucky that that's where it was because then you know the next thing
that I had to do you know the next step was the bell rang you have to go meditate what a great thing to do and uh
and and then next thing was to go do the work they have to do and and living that monastic life and so that just kept
opening the doors and in some very real way for me my life did start over again
at that point but because I started in a monastery that really kind of informed how my life
then unfolded as it opened up step by step and now I'm here with you because
of that choice so that's not so bad is it no I think it's great
and um so so this kind of being still stopping
some kind of rumination sometimes a spinning of the mind some kind of spinning and doubts
and emotions learning how to quiet all this so that we can see differently so we can
start fresh so we can you know maybe some different decision will come that cannot come when we're all spinning
around when we're lost and I think this is true in relationships too it's so easy in
relationships to be spinning and agitated and Afraid and and angry and doubtful and all kinds of
things but to really learn to stop and be still is maybe sometimes essential in
relationships maybe not in the moment when it's difficult but maybe if the relationship is going to last for some
time maybe you'll find some way to kind of really come and stop and be still and
let the agitated mind agitated heart quiet enough so that something different
can happen some different seeing and so what's a different thing that can
happen so this is the second story now that uh from this um indigenous
person in Canada so he had spent a lot of time in the
wilderness in the woods working and living and uh and at some point there was
where he where he had been his kind of Homeland or place of it became a
national park in Canada so he continued being there and and at some point there was a young boy
I don't know how old he was maybe I don't know pretty young who got lost and the people in the park the Rangers
and stuff spent two days looking for him and they couldn't find him so they went to this man Jim City and
said can you help and so he said take me to where the boy last place of the boy was seen
so he went there and I took him there and then he stood
in that spot for half an hour without moving he stood still maybe just studying the spot
and then um he said it this way and he started walking into the woods
and he just followed had some sense of where to go and he
went for some time I think he I think he went alone and um and at some point he came to some
place where he stopped and he um he said he hollered and uh and then something hollered back
right there next to him and it was the boy but the boy was petrified
so what he did was he just sat down next to the boy and it took about a half an hour for the
boy to thaw and calm down to be able to somehow carve a conversation and be
ready for something next and then he brought him back to the world
and and then he talked about that experience later and how did you manage with that and he said well every living
being is unique and you have to kind of find what's the unique thing about
whatever whoever it is whatever it is whatever creature and then you can maybe follow them and what he was talking
about was the boy had unique footprints and he knew about the footprints of all
the animals of the woods so he knew how to differentiate and so that's apparently standing there half an hour
one of the things he was doing was looking around seeing what is the footprint of this boy like and then he
started following the traces of the footprints that he could find through the woods
and uh and uh and then he found the boy and this this thing about just again stopping and being still with the boy
accompanying the boy so the boy could kind of begin to in two days in the wilderness you imagine he was terrified
and so that boy could kind of relax and calm down enough to be able to come
along so um so my friend then took this story
that was very impactful for her and and applied it to her meditation
that uh she when she's lost she has to stop and be still and then search for
the trail the traces in herself to find a way forward
and one of the ways to do that that I find very helpful for me in my meditation is to be quiet enough and
then to ask myself the question um what is what what inside of me is
asking for attention what inside of me is calling for
attention or is inviting me or welcoming me my attention
so rather than me having some idea I'm supposed to pay attention to something and and sometimes I've done that in a
very assertive way you know I'm by golly I'm going to get concentrated here I'm just going to zoom in you know or I'm
going to get rid of this pain I'm going to do just the Bazooka approach to the grenade approach to mindfulness it's
going to go in there and just blast it away I mean that's not a very good approach to mindfulness but the idea of being
still and quiet and then asking what wants attention what's inviting me in
and uh and often for me when I begin meditation it's my breathing
but it's a very different relationship to breathing when I'm Still Still and quiet and ask what is this that invites
me and then and then um and then it's like
trade now that I've been invited what is the tracks I'm following
uh and so the idea of them following something is very different than the idea that I'm trying to make something
happen I'm trying to build something I'm trying to attain something it's more like again I I don't I'm not
I'm not the one who is has designs of what's supposed to happen I'm not the one who is
you know trying to get something for myself
but there's there's a track to follow the track of the invitation that the tracks of what's calling or what's
that's inviting me to to follow itself and so then I'll tune in to the breath
and and it's more like okay I'm I'm the tracker or I'm the visitor or I'm the
the person who reads the invitations like this here here
and so so there's a track inside and uh there's you know that we follow
and sometimes it's the breathing sometimes it's Sensations in the body sometimes it's emotions sometimes the
state of the mind sometimes the content of the Mind the thoughts that I might be having but there's a sense that that I'm not so
much in charge I'm more in charge of the tracking of listening for the invitation
so I do have a role but uh but I'm learning learning how to
read the traces inside of myself and just like this uh Elder said that
you know every living creature is unique so each of each moment for us each day
that we show up for ourselves we're kind of unique our inner life is unique and what is it
let's discover what it is each time rather than come with a preconceived idea of what it is
and many people come with preconceived ideas some people come with um like I did when I was walking those
trails in the outside the monastery I showed up with preconceived ideas about
my inability to decide what to do for myself my life big decision in my life that I I'm just a
condemned to being a doubter and that's so I showed up I already showed up with you know
in a challenging way with a preconceived idea that I couldn't do this
and um but is that really listening to the invitation certainly listening to what's asking to what's called for
no you have to kind of figure out how to stop and be still enough so that you can
see in a fresh way not to carry with you your Prejudice your preconceived ideas
your bias your all kinds of things so stop and be still
so the Buddha uh is you know well there's a wonderful analogy that Buddha gives
that has to do with being in the woods and finding something and the analogy is
not a is about a wood a woodworker someone who worked in the woods Forester
who wasn't lost but spend time a lot of time
in the forest but found that the tracks the traces of an ancient
Road the jungle had overgrown and but he found the traces the person's forced to
found the traces and Then followed the traces and very slowly and and uh clear a
little bit and follow traces and it came to some great ancient capital city that
had been fully overgrown like the maybe like the cities they're fine still finding in uh on the Mayan peninsula in
Mexico or something that um that is amazing we're still finding this long-lost cities that have been
overgrown and um and then the Buddha that this
with this Forester then leaves the leaves the the force and goes to the monarchs of
the of the of the realm and tells them you know we I found this ancient Road
traces of it I found the the this ancient capital and so the monarchs are
happy and they arrange for the road to be cleared they range for the capital be declared and they all move back into the
Happy Ever After Capital something like that and um so it's an out it's an allegory
it's a metaphor that and it's meant to be a metaphor for yourself
that the ancient capital is our own freedom our own capacity to find a place where
the heart is free of its distress its troubles its suffering a liberated heart
but to do that we have the the path that exists that's overgrown is the path in
ourselves and um and the path that was overgrown is with attachments with clinging with
fears with anxieties with with uh hatred and condemnations and for his
resentments and all kinds of things that grow and grow over a lifetime and for some people these can grow unabated
without any any limitation just keep growing and
growing so by the time we reach a certain age kind of something like in us has been
overgrown so thoroughly we don't even know that the inside of us is this
wonderful Capital this wonderful place this wonderful home this wonderful kind
of place of being safe being found and so this invitation or this way of
practicing where we're assume I'm going to follow the traces of what is asking
for attention right now it doesn't mean rumination it doesn't mean keep okay thinking about things and
thinking more and more and more it's being still being quiet though
enough to listen to something deeper than thoughts or listen to the what lies
underneath your thoughts and to listen quietly and then then oh
it's my breathing oh there's my heartache oh there's a tightness in my
belly oh there's a lot of energy and agitation and thinking
that kind of wants my attention let me hold that and be with that and then what it what now wants
attention maybe more of the same or look at that it's beginning to calm down
that calming seems to want attention it seems to call me it seems to be you know and then we stay with that and then
slowly we find our way and uh and in the Dharma and the the
what the the way that we found we find is the a big part of it is that we discover
that the path itself is so precious
it's so wonderful to have a path of practice that getting to the Capitol may be a
secondary but just the fact that we and following a path like this is an expression of
freedom is a manifestation of our freedom maybe not initially but as we keep doing it
and keep showing up and being Mindful and being mindful of what's here we start seeing that the act of mindfulness
is an act of freedom meaning an act of mindfulness means
we're no longer caught up in that moment caught in our preoccupations caught in
our emotions caught in our past or caught in the future cotton or whatever it might be
we don't deny all those things but we're not caught in it wow
this is what's happening there's Freedom here and so as we keep doing this movement of
being still and quiet enough to have the mindfulness be full
where mindfulness can be there together with its freedom then we begin appreciating more and more
that simply the being on the path of doing this
is something to celebrate it's a refuge and some people will find
oh this now I've found my home now I find kind of with this I have a
sense of belonging in this universe because with this I belong
in that freedom because the freedom is letting go of all
the non-belonging all the ideas that I shouldn't be here all the ideas that you know other
people's ideas I shouldn't be here or something we let go in that freedom just this
just this and then for people who are Buddhist that movement of Freedom each moment is
represented by the idea of going for Refuge and the Buddha talked about how you
don't find your refuge in temples you don't find refuge in
he even talked about that can exchange in India in sacred grove sacred spots
you find the Refuge in this practice you find refuge in what you see how you see
being caught and how you see being free this is how you you find your freedom
and if you see that then he says you can see a path
and the and the path that you need to clear is he says is the Eightfold Path
so there so but the Eightfold Path is not something outside of you it's really something inside of you
and what it means is that like the part of it part of it is the the ethics the
three three of the Eightfold Path is ethical and you start seeing the invitation here
or is to not cause harm that's what ethics is about
not harm anyone and is is there an invitation does that feel is there a rightness something inside that calls on
that if you're still in quiet enough and can really be mindful and pay attention I
think with I mean all of us there is an imitation a call a request don't call
don't cause harm because when we intentionally cause harm
we're covering over our depths recovering over the capital
with more more debris more weeds and all that we're actually closing something
down when we're hateful or hostile or something and that doesn't feel good if
you really pay attention you're going to feel how we're diminished by that so ethics comes naturally through this
practice because that's what the deepest invitation is
and so each of the steps of the Eightfold Path some of you know what they are um is really an expression of something
that's already in US it's not an imposition from the outside
and so the value of stopping being still
and maybe if you're lost something will find you
and what will and what we find you is maybe the invitation that traces the
tracks the call here here is where to bring your attention
here is where to attend to to feel to be with to
this is where to walk this is what to do and and then we kind of follow the
traces and the tracks and
Something Beautiful begins happening Something Free and that kind of place
now I've been found even if it's not a geographical place
Maybe it's never a geographical place in Buddhism it's always here and now in
yourself and then you bring that with you wherever you go so even when you're lost physically
you're not really lost to yourself isn't that nice
so I hope that made sense for those of you who occasionally get lost
and if you don't get lost great for the potluck anyway
so thank you very much and we have a few minutes before we usually stop here and
so anybody have any questions they want to ask or testimonials about being lost that
relate to what I talked about or anything
oh then I have a poem to read but maybe I'll take some questions first and end with a poem
so
and if you say your name first that would be nice
hi I'm Caitlin um I was thinking of
being lost in sense of trying to find purpose which
I think many of us find on on our journey through life and I was watching a YouTube video and
on such thing and a lot of it was about how
when you are constantly putting your attention to the outside world which is how modern society puts us on like puts
us towards you actually lose sight of what's within what your values are and
what's important to you and so part of finding your purpose is looking within
which is very much in line with right you were wonderful thank you and uh and
then part of that the importance of that is that there's all kinds of messages from culture from society or from family
about what the real purpose of life should be about and some of those don't serve us they're not they're not a match
for who we are but if we're if if we have to think we have to be that way but it's but it's there's a dissonance
between who you are and that thing then it can be a lot of tension
I have to be rich or I have to have a career or have to
you know it's all kinds of shoulds that we struggle under and what happens if we can listen deeply
within and become free of those social messages about what the purpose should
be about and find out what is it what is it that that makes our hearts sing what
makes our hearts feels happy and delighted you wake up in the morning happy to do
what you want to do and the answer for some people and this is kind of one of the things that I
think spirituality often points to is that one of the messages from our society is the answer to what is the
purpose of my life what should I do is a thing a what
you know the career or a relationship or something and what spirituality often
points to rather than a what a how how we're going to be in the world and
some people find tremendous meaning in how they live more than what they
live for what they do and and but that's a hard thing to justify
in by many segments of modern society because you know when people ask what do
you do oh I try to be kind
you know that doesn't so you know it's not what they're hoping for and
thank you
hi I'm Margaret you spoke a little bit about starting
over or starting from scratch when you're in the monastery can you say a little bit more about
how you did that or what that means to start over or be reborn
well it's possible that it was pretty fortunate I did it in that situation
because I'd been there already a year and and it was really you know deep in the
wilderness so we didn't get newspapers we got were like several days old and there was no
internet then there was no TV there so so you know so much of things had fallen
away that normally I'd be caught up with caught up in so that just made it really relatively
easy I think in compared to doing it in the middle middle of a busy life and it made a big difference that I was
meditating a lot so that the meditation was also a very deep
embodied and heartfelt kind of letting go and I could I I'd be doing it for some
time then by that time I'd been meditating probably for about five years by that time so I had some skill
and letting go but uh my mind from earlier in life had
a lot of skills in picking up again after the meditation so you know
this I think was constant kind of this pattern of letting go and then picking up and back into
but uh but because I had to learn to let go in meditation I had a reference point
for what it was like to really just stop and that reference but even having that reference point helped me then find my
way and gave me some confidence in not needing to know not needing to have
every all these plans and ahead um so that that's I don't think my
answer is very adequate for you but that's the best I could do right now it's a good question
I was uh Imagining the path that you were talking about and I believe you
said something about maybe being on the path is more important than getting to the overgrown
capital and then you mentioned the Eightfold Path and that did Havoc with
my imagination and I saw the path splitting into eight different ways and
so I wonder if you could say more about how the Eightfold Path could help in our
path towards finding ourselves so kind of it's giving you a clue the April path
of what you're looking for in the jungle and we're looking for the the uh the
first one is the Right View we're looking at for the perspective in which we look at our lives and uh so what perspective is useful and
you may ask what perspective am I using is this a useful one and what what's the deeper requests
what's what perspective really is being you know the deeper request of the heart or something
and then uh the second of the Eightfold Path is uh kind of uh the right attitude
or the right intention or something and uh so you asked what is what's the attitude by which I'm going about my
life and the and the what we're looking for is more specifically is an attitude of
of uh non-harming and non-cruelty sometimes people say and non-greed or
non-lust and some people say um an attitude of being able to let go when
it's appropriate and attitude of kindness and attitude of compassion so what's the attitude so we're kind of
okay that's what that's what that's the footsteps of the little boy who's lost let's let's can we find that the
attitude and then uh how we speak uh how we act in the world it turns out
that you're not going to find your freedom uh through killing stealing and sexual misconduct
so you know that's a pretty big footstep to notice and then what's called right it's
usually called right livelihood I think that's maybe two two modern of a concept I think it's
more broadly a whole way in which we live the lifestyle that we live
that includes work but it's broader than just work and then so what's the lifestyle of
living is this lifestyle you know in Harmony and and uh is this you know
what's the deeper request and what's the what do I listen to what do I how do I pay attention to Lifestyle and then some
people realize I never thought about it you know I'm just going along with what I was given and but we start questioning
what is the lifestyle I want to live and then um there's the the the sixth of
the Eightfold Path is the uh the what we Endeavor to do and here uh the the hint that Buddha
gives with which step is not the what we do but how we do it and that is the how
is is it healthy or not healthy or wholesome or unwholesome so there is a
differentiation we see between what is healthy and not healthy for ourselves and that's the how
and then uh then there's right mindfulness yeah you know so one of the traces is um
do I have any mindfulness and you know and what and if if I asked if I ask the question how you know what
is awareness asking of me what does awareness want from me rather than being
the one who's mindful what happens because it's so important and then um a subtle Focus concentrated mind
that's another footstep I I now have this view of
the eight paths are in parallel and going in the same direction great
so I'm going to read the poem that I have for long and this is a somewhat famous poem in English poem by David
Wagoner and it's called Lost
so lost stand still
the trees ahead and the bushes beside you are not lost
wherever you are is called here
and you must treat it as a powerful stranger must ask permission to know it and be
known the forest breathes listen
it answers I have made this place around you if you
leave it you may come back again saying here
no tweet no two trees are the same to Raven no two branches are the same to
Ren if what a tree or a bush does is lost on you
you are surely lost stand still the forest knows where you are
you must let it find you
so thank you and maybe because we're having a potluck partly it would be nice if you can take
your one or two minutes to say hello and introduce yourself to the person maybe a
couple of people next to you and and if you're and welcome whoever
you're talking to even if this is your first time at IMC you've been here long enough to welcome
the person [Laughter] so um and then and then you know they
can get the potluck ready and we can do that thank you
yeah