so hello everyone welcome to this meditation session
and the talk that will follow and um
and of some words about meditation before we
start or mindfulness
it can be useful to divide up our experience into two halves
and give each half equal value
and one half is whatever is happening to us whatever our experience is
the other half is how we're aware of it the mindfulness
of it commonly we're concerned with our
experiences our thoughts our ideas the content of our
of our thoughts and and it's appropriate to do so to be
concerned focused be aware of that but sometimes we're so aware of it so
involved in our thoughts so involved with our experience the conversation we're having
that we're not really attuned to this whole other half
and that is how we're aware how we're attending how we're mindful
and by giving it so much value in this little description I wonder if it's real
on seven emphasites it's really important to be aware of how we're aware
and it's actually a kind of key to living a more
happier life a more easeful life peaceful life calmer life if we're not
consumed by or preoccupied by or fully engaged in
the content of our experience the experience itself of the conversation
the what's happening in the moment involved with our thoughts about the
past the future and our ideas and Fantasies
but rather than being absorbed in those or completely caught in them to open up
and really take into account the other whole half and that other half of awareness being
aware of it being mindful of it that's the domain that's the place where
um the huge place where that's where we discover and are tuned in some
meaningful and deep way to ourselves that's where we began discovering
freedom so there's a simple
excuse me there's a simple
um guideline for what I'm talking about today and that is
whenever you're aware of what's happening to you the breathing the body your emotions your thoughts The Sounds
around you whatever it might be ask yourself
is the way that you're aware of it beneficial is the manner in which you're receiving
it registering it is it enjoyable is it satisfying is it
peaceful or is it unsatisfying is it agitating is
it conflictive is it resistant is it assertive and greedy and
all kinds of things what comes along with that way of being aware
and see if you can find a place that no matter how uncomfortable the experience
is how you're aware of it is comfortable no matter how agitated your experience
is maybe you're agitating your body your emotional life how you know how you recognize oh I am
agitated that is not agitated no matter how sad or depressed you might
feel the knowing that you're sad or depressed that is not said or depressed that is
there's a Clarity there's a receptivity it just feels like it's very simple
and it isn't so much that we have to make ourselves that way but rather it's the nature of awareness
to be very very simple and in that Simplicity if we can recognize or find that Simplicity that's
already there that you might find that it's beneficial it's enjoyable it's it's nourishing it's
just a nice place to be and it doesn't deny everything else but
it changes the half the whole ecology changes where we can then now be with
our experience in a way that might actually be much more beneficial much
wiser more caring more non-reactive
so in this sitting today to ask yourself the question
am I aware in a beneficial way and if not
can you relax and find some way to be aware that simple and much more
satisfying so assuming taking on a
entering into a meditation posture
and lowering your gaze or closing your eyes
and to begin right away as you now bring your attention to
yourself in meditation checking in and recognizing what's here
for you and your experience
is how you're aware of your body your mind your heart
are you aware in a beneficial way or a satisfying
way or even an enjoyable way
and then becoming aware of your breathing
the body's experience of breathing and taking a few long slow deep breaths
relax as you exhale
settling in Here and Now
letting your breathing be normal and with every exhale
see if you can let go or loosen up
lighten up around your thinking
letting go of thoughts and settling into your body
and sitting here quietly aware of your breathing
noticing whatever it is that takes you away from the breathing
then returning again to your breathing
let's see if you can adjust your knowing the way that you know
that it feels like it's Pleasant enjoyable
that the knowing in and of itself is beneficial not that what you know is beneficial
but how you know how you're aware
maybe you can be relaxed around it calm receptive
maybe it's a awareness knowing that has no boundaries around it
and so the spaciousness of knowing
feels good
not being in a hurry and knowing but whatever you know
to know it clearly as if you're making a greater room for
the experience
that the awareness has greater room feels good
foreign
how clear is your awareness now
can you be aware of in a way that's clear open receptive
making room for what's happening
so that awareness is not hijacked by our agendas and her desires
our impulses
being aware in a way that you appreciate being aware
feels good feels beneficial
so then as we come to the end of the sitting
to spend a few moments considering
ways in which your awareness your knowing of what's happening in the present
is something you can appreciate there's a value there's
a rightness of peacefulness in how you're aware
maybe awareness is not hijacked by selfish assertion or
self criticism
awareness is receptive open
this has a room to experience whatever is happening in
the present
in whatever sense you have of awareness that has this
goodness to it or rightness to it
consider what it's like now to be aware this way
of other people of others when you're together laughs
maybe nothing's required of you you don't have to speak but is there some way to be aware
of others in this beneficial awareness
what's it like to be aware where you're giving room for other people to be as they are
we're being aware of them is not mixed up with
our desires and our aversions
our self-concerns
almost as if there's lots of room in our mind our hearts
for others to be as they are and in all that room
then there's more space for our kindness our care
our good will for others and as we end this meditation
may the good will we have travel out
into the boundless space
of awareness Beyond awareness
may all beings be happy
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be safe may all beings be free
and may we and how we're aware
support people in being free at least free of ourselves
thank you
so good morning good day so this is the fourth talk on why speech
and today's talk is about beneficial speech the Buddha gave five
criteria to be used as a reference point as a support for
wise speech and to repeat what we've done so far is um
is to is that um and now my mind just went blank
is it um like I
yeah so that's amazing to have a mind that can't recall just a little bit
about coming out of meditation right now that uh the um the words are not quite here yet
but today's talk is is the speech beneficial and the
so uh the question then is when we're about to
speak or when we're speaking it does it have a good impact does it have the intent is it beneficial what
we're doing is it helpful to have a conversation
and the the question is that is one that makes us consider what is it
we want to accomplish is it um
timely that's where the timely is it true is it uh
Pleasant is it something that people the way we speak
it is in a way that people will listen with a feeling that this is coming
across with a kind supportive voice does it touch people's hearts what we're
going to say but is it beneficial and there are certainly times when we
feel that we need to speak what's true times we feel like you know you kind of
we think it's time to do it I mean we've been waiting for a long time or there's can't be any other time
and we might feel that it's uh you know yes we're going to do this in a in a
in a kind way Gentle Way and um but the person we're speaking to
is not capable of hearing this of registering it of taking it in
and uh and no matter how much we think it's true how much we think that yes it
has to be talked about the person is not to be capable the person's shut down the person is not
receptive in any kind of way and and so then to exhaust ourselves
trying to say trying to explain trying to find a way to kind of get in and make
ourselves heard is a waste of our own energy it's kind of harmful for us
sometimes and sometimes it's hard to believe that people are not amenable to a
conversation not available to hear the truth not available to have a serious
conversation and so you know we keep trying and keep
trying and but there are times when it's not
beneficial to have a conversation with someone sometimes it's not beneficial it's it's
because there'll be retribution they'll be angry they'll be upset then we know if we
bring something up there's a they don't have it that's that's what's going to come back maybe because they're in a bad
mood and you kind of feel that there's a you know a Angry Cloud over the person
and if we if you come talk to them about something you feel is really necessary to talk about they're going to just kind
of react in such a strong way that makes the whole thing worse
uh some people are just too guarded and defensive that they're not going to
lower their guard they're not going to allow any kind of valuable any kind of truthful conversation to happen they'll
just shut down they'll avoid they'll deny so at some point it becomes a waste of
time at some point it no longer becomes beneficial at some point it's actually harmful
there's people who use the truth to harm people and so I'm just saying I'm just speaking
the truth sometimes people are receptive and ready to hear
something hear the truth but the way we say it is so harsh so judgmental in it
that because of how we're saying it is not beneficial
and and so if what you're saying is not going to be beneficial the Buddha says
don't bother uh don't exhaust yourself when it's not beneficial
and this goes back to the question of timeliness is that sometimes you have to wait a
long time before someone is ready and receptive and uh there's something that something
has a shift and change in their lives and so sometimes there's the wisdom of waiting
sometimes the truth is true but we
haven't learned how to say it we haven't learned all the details we haven't learned all the aspects of it that we
it's true what the piece of it we know but we don't know the bigger picture
and and so for example one way is that the event what's happened between the
person has done what we can see the action the person has done might seem terribly misguided or wrong
but uh so it's true to point that out to them but what we don't know is
internally the challenges they're living under maybe they feel really afraid maybe they
feel insecure maybe they've had just had a terrible loss that they're grieving a
grieving with and so coming with the truth or the
action it really misses the person and so the truth doesn't work in the circumstance
where someone's inner life is in turmoil they're difficult so is there more truth to open up to do
we have to take time to get to know the person better what's happening and then to
um to uh you know to be gentle and kind even gentleness and kindness this
doesn't come across well to some people so so one of the ways to find our way
with speech is to not come assertively not begin our speech with being very
assertively or aggressive but to begin with simple questions that
tries to understand what's going on in a bigger way what happened what was happening to you what was happening with
you when you did X or I'm you know I was really troubled by what happened before and I you know you
know can you can you what was from your point of view what was that happened there when um you know when
you you said to me you know that x y and z so don't come immediately with
assertions and like as if you know what's going on but uh ask simple kind
of almost innocent questions to find out more discover more what was like for
that was hard yesterday what was going on for you or how was that for you and and um and then as you start unpacking
and learning what's going on then you might learn oh what's beneficial well
that's just that is beneficial to get to know the person better and learn what's going on and then slowly kind of fill in the
picture of all the pieces that you're missing of what was going on for the person and then once you understand a person
better then you can have a better sense of the beneficial way to speak to them
and um and maybe you know more you could offer
an appreciation or some gratitude or or some some empathy for how they are
and only then is it beneficial to speak so so to not go ahead log into a
conversation but find a way to ease into a difficult conversation if possible
so is is what I'm going to say beneficial
and maybe you're unsure about it so in that case maybe you go about in the
roundabout way maybe you find other things to talk about for a while that are beneficial or
are supportive or are connecting that creates a kind of more richer relationship
and after after a while of doing that then you switch over I've been in conflict with people and
um and have asked to meet with them and sat down and have said like before we're
going to talk about this challenge we have can we just check in with each other I'd like to know how you are and what you're up to these days what's
going on for you and that now I've entered the conversation in a more beneficial way beneficial for me maybe
beneficial to the other person that now I'm just trying to establish a human connection and get to know the person
better and what's going on and once that's established then it's okay you know now you know I'm ready to
talk about our challenge that we have if I started to do it immediately
then um it would have been challenging to um
to do it and and finally is it beneficial to
speak it isn't only what's beneficial for the other person but what's beneficial for us and are we in a
situation are we in a state of mind state of heart where having the
conversation is going to be beneficial and uh and do I need to somehow
uh come come in a different mood or come more rested or become more not so
charged from the events that are going on do I need to walk around the block so
I can come back and be available in a beneficial way so even though it's it's timely even
though it's true even though we can speak gently even with that
um it addressing certain challenging topics might not we might not be in a
state where we can benefit from it or where we're not triggered and get exhausted or we are somehow agitated or
over activated by it so this question of benefit is it
beneficial is it useful and finally it's also connected to the purpose that we
have for the conversation is the pr to ask ourselves why what's my
intention in speaking here what am I trying to accomplish am I trying to put the person in their
place am I trying to jab the person with as uh you know with my anger or my
criticism to harm them am I trying to find a way to understand them better and
by trying to establish some kind of richer human connection with the person what's the intention
and to ask ourselves what's the purpose that I want to speak and is that purpose beneficial
and if you have one answer what the purpose ask again and if that's the purpose what purpose do I have that
purpose for to really be clear that the purpose you have is beneficial
and I'd like to propose and this is the way I like to live my life
is it beneficial for everyone concerned can we be have the welfare of everyone
on our minds and so for certainly our own welfare but
what is best for the person even if this person has done something that's been harmful to us
within reason there are times where what's best for this person this person
really needs something and needs to just having the person stop what they're doing
or tell the person the piece of our mind um is that really what's beneficial for
them and so this concern for the welfare of everyone
and that's what the Buddha championed is this anacampa this care where we care
for the welfare and happiness of everyone even the people we're challenged with
so um to to keep in mind this
guideline is it beneficial and it's a multi-dimensional aspect to ask that
question so as you go about your day today you might um consider this
and before and after you speak you might look for times but when you know you're going to say something or you're going
off to have a conversation with someone to spend some time in a request what's beneficial here what's beneficial for
myself what's beneficial for the other what's is the purpose of the conversation beneficial is how I'm going
to have it can be beneficial and then also do that after the conversation after it's all over review
what happened and consider was that beneficial how is that beneficial did I miss an
opportunity there and all that
so um may your conversations be beneficial for
all involved may they be helpful and may it be a way of living your life
to that such a way that brings you greater peace greater well-being
thank you