so hello everyone welcome to the moment
now if you missed it my name is Maria stratman and I am filling in for Gill
this week who is off leading a retreat at one of his favorite places so
we can share a moment of being happy for him
so this week what we have been talking about or we will continue talking about is how to overcome self-criticism or
self-blame and in thinking about it we use the word blamelessness because
that's where we wish to be is in the world of blamelessness and today what I'd like to talk about is
Judgment because it is Judgment through which we finally come to the place where
I did that wrong I shouldn't have done that how did that happen
so I want to talk about a couple of aspects of judgment you know judgment is really about
forming an opinion about something it's not the behavior so much as it is the opinion about the
behavior and we do that very largely through the
act of comparison We compare it to our ideal our ideal self our ideal way that
anyone would behave but there's always an element of both opinion and
comparison right so it moves beyond the realm of just straight
discernment I can tell the difference between a and b i can distinguish between A and B it goes to the place
where I prefer A over B and I compare A and B to one another this act of
comparing things gets us in the realm where we start judging and we seem to have these ideas and
beliefs that we're labeling against all of the experiences we have
so I want to quickly there's so many things to say about this
I want to complete uh first remind you of of the uh the way
that we experience all experience there that we call this the Aggregates and they're called the Aggregates because
they're the five ways of receiving experience that we use to form a self
which is tied to what we believe and what our opinions are so so they are the
the sense Factor itself what I'm hearing or seeing or tasting or
smelling or touching or thinking the sense experience itself whether that
experience is Pleasant or unpleasant not whether we like it or not
that's an important distinction but is it Pleasant or unpleasant
Pleasant or unpleasant we don't actually have to go to like or dislike it can just be pleasant or
unpleasant so under some conditions I might taste a lemon and think
that is so blessedly wonderful after all of that sweetness or I will taste it and feel only the
bitterness of it in that taste those are Pleasant or unpleasant whether I like or dislike them has to do with all other
kinds of conditions the third thing is uh perception it's
it's noticing something it's it's the naming function you know this this this is a glass
but actually is a container but I call it a glass
because it has my water in it so there's a a naming feature and we name our experiences all the time
we name this is this is uh running this is sitting this is standing
so we perceive what it is we name it and that places a little placemark for us
the fourth thing is thinking so I'm a and I've got a few comments yesterday
I'm going to look at this and call it a bowl and I look can look at this and
call it a bowl one is much larger than the other I can
compare them on the basis of that I can compare them on the basis of sound
that's how they sound together
that's large and deep
small now I might have a preference for one or
the other and that's where we're in the realm of thinking now I'm thinking well this one is like this and this one's
like this and I can compare them it's the world of comparing in that experience and usually we compare based
on our experience and the other conditions around us
so maybe I prefer the light Bell if I'm alone in the room and just want to make
small Mark and sound and I might prefer the large Bell because it resonates much
more and I feel like that is going to be a better thing for me
the fifth thing is awareness if we're not aware of something it
actually doesn't even exist for us now behind me I know there are things on
the wall there's this I don't know if you can see it there's a little green heart underneath the picture and the the green
heart is made up of leaves and it was given to me by my husband I have all kinds of associations for it but behind
me when you can't see it and I can't see it it doesn't even exist
but when I look at it I know it it's not just that I see it
but I know that I see it this is an important part of mindfulness
when we're when we're considering what's going on in the moment and we're mindful of the moment
we see something there's an object we see it but the awareness is knowing that we see
it we see lots of things you look around you the environment you end you see all kinds of things but what do you know
I don't mean the knowing of what do you know about it but the registering is the
awareness part of it where you use oh yes I see that I know that so all of these elements are present in
any experience we have so judgment comes in when we start
comparing something some action some feelings some emotion to what we believe
is the right thing believe where did that come from
I failed in this because I really was sure I'd never do that again
how do I know I've failed in this well the outcome wasn't my expected outcome
it's all opinion what do you mean expected outcome oh oh
this is about what I think should happen not what happened
the art of blamelessness of non-judgment lies in being able to see your
experience just as an experience
oh this one this happened
and then I can say oh that wasn't my desired outcome
but I don't have to say that means I'm a failure that goes to another place now I'm comparing myself to something else
and instead I can say well that didn't work I'll try something else next time or I'm not going to do that I catch
myself doing something I have done over and over and over and I thought I wasn't going to do that again
ah I'll try harder next time it doesn't mean that we necessarily
dismiss any responsibility for the outcome but only that we look at it
cleanly without adding it to a whole list of other ways
in which we Define who am I judgment comes down to me
this is what I think this is what I believe this is what I maintain is always the same
when the experience is Just Happening Now a moment is only a moment
the assigning meaning to that moment is where we start creating suffering
when we have an opinion about it
when we can look at something without adding our history to
it sometimes we can see it more clearly
if my history tells me that being kind leads to people taking advantage of me
then I'm going to be worried about always being taken advantage of and I'm going to compare any experience I have
with kindness to whether I feel like I'm being taken advantage of because zero that's me
but if I can just be kind without tying it to what the outcome means
I find it's easier just to be kind
so in any moment when we find ourselves wallowing in self-criticism
might be a moment to say what actually happened what's actually happening now and what
is being wounded in me what is the wound that I'm experiencing
well I am feeling
dismissed I am feeling like I made a fool of myself I'm feeling like that person's
not gonna like me I'm feeling unliked feeling unliked is very different than failing
very very different but if I'm busy having an opinion about the
experience I can miss with the experience actually is
the image is getting in way in the way of seeing clearly
the oh this must meanness ask yourself
when you're thinking about all the ways in which that person is
failing you you are failing that person whatever those judgments are think about how that's tied to the
history of the moment and not just the moment we tend to take these pictures of
ourselves and and drag them through our history on this string here it here it comes this is me following my experience
and I'm right here see it's just the same when the conditions are totally different
totally different the moment is totally different and if I let go of that string
I'm better able to see clearly this is what's happening
and maybe in seeing this is what's happening I can break the habit
of belief that leads to that judgment
now I want to be clear this doesn't mean that we don't have opinions about things
it doesn't mean that we don't have value systems it doesn't mean that we
don't have ethics but it does mean that we can look really cleanly and clearly at what it is
and not decide in advance if it looks like this this is what it means so
yesterday I came home and there was a paramedic truck at the opening of our garage the last time there was a
paramedic truck here someone had just died and so immediately there's a rush of anxiety
now had I been anxious before that I might have
been the conditions would have been different but this time I was mostly curious because there was no one in the
building that I would have expected might need a paramedic and then I noticed three firemen coming
down the outside stairs and one of them got to the two steps down and he leaped
off and clicked his heels together as he before he landed
and I I thought Charlie Chaplin right I laughed and I thought oh that's totally
inappropriate and then and then immediately oh that's inappropriate for him and then I thought no maybe it's
because nothing serious is actually happening and all of these were opinions and judgments about what might be true about
this fireman leaping off the stair and I have no idea why he leaped off the
stair and clicked his heels none whatsoever
but I didn't notice there's no urgency here no urgency and I could lay down
the judgment about why he did and just enjoyed the moment
of him kicking his heels together just enjoy the moment of him clicking
his heels together so today I'm going to read you another poem yesterday I failed to mention that
it was Jane hirschfield's poem the best and so today I want to be sure that I
tell you this is Tony Hoagland and I will find that column here
title of this poem is I have news for you there are people who do not see a broken
playground swing as a symbol of ruined childhood and there are people who don't interpret
the behavior of a fly in a motel room is a mocking representation of their thought process
and that there are people who don't walk past an empty swimming pool and think
about past pleasures unrecoverable and then stand there blocking the sidewalk for other pedestrians I've read
about a town somewhere in California where human beings do not send their
sinuous feeder Roots deep into the potting soil of others emotional lives as if they were greedy six-year-olds
sucking the last inch of milkshake through a noisy straw and other persons in the midwest who can
kiss without debating the imperialist baggage of heterosexuality
do you see that creamy lemon yellow moon there are some people unlike me and you
who do not yearn after fame or love or quantities of money is unattainable as
that Moon thus they do not later have to waste more time defaming the object of
their former arter or consequently run and crucify themselves in some solitary midnight
Starbucks Golgotha I have news for you there are people who get up in the
morning and cross a room and open a window to let in the sweet Breeze and let it touch them all over
their faces and bodies
you read it again there are people who do not see a broken playground swing as a symbol of ruined childhood and there
are people who don't interpret the behavior of a fly in a motel room as a mocking representation of their thought
process there are people who don't walk past an empty swimming pool and think about past
pleasures unrecoverable and then stand there blocking the sidewalk for other pedestrians
I've read about a town somewhere in California where human beings do not send their sinuous feeder Roots deep
into the potting soils of others emotional lives as if they were greedy
six-year-olds sucking the last inch of milkshake through a noisy straw and other persons in the midwest who can
kiss without debating the imperialist baggage of heterosexuality do you see that creamy lemon yellow moon
there are some people unlike me and you who do not yearn after fame or love or
quantities of money as unattainable as that Moon thus they do not later have to waste more time defaming the object of
their former ardor or consequently run and crucify themselves in some solitary midnight
Starbucks Kolkata I have dues for you there are people who
get up in the morning and cross a room and open a window to let the sweet Breeze in and let it touch them all over
their faces and bodies
let yourself not be the person who needs to find the meaning in every step
but simply walk across the room and let the sweet Breeze Rush all over your faces and bodies
thank you
hey thank you very much for that Maria and um I guess at this point we'll
take any questions over Zoom or on YouTube if you want to post them in chat then I can
Maria
and if you want to raise your hand uh in Zoom then we can also call on you
what were the uh just kind of start off what were they Aggregates again and can you kind of just uh kind of repeat like
the I guess the connection to um I guess quickly summarize the connection
to blamelessness or judgment and yeah sure okay so the Aggregates are the
sense input the feeling tone which is Pleasant or
unpleasant or neutral perception the naming function I name
this as thinking about where we form our opinions and what we
believe about them and awareness which is just what do I know what what am I
registering when I look at this or feel this or see this these five things are
the ways that we create self they're they're the ways that we say I like this I don't like this I like it
because of this it's the way in which we form opinions and beliefs about us in
relationship to the experience so the experience has all of these elements in it
and we use them to form a sense of self
I am having this experience it's the place where I am having this experience
and the way that we want to live that leads to less suffering is to
live in a place where I can just see the experience I can know the the
part of the experience that I am aware of I'm aware that I'm thinking
about this I'm aware that I have an opinion about this I'm aware that this is Pleasant or unpleasant and it allows
us to enter the space where we can just experience and say Pleasant unpleasant I
don't have to run away from unpleasant I can just see it as unpleasant
and we can practice being with what is unpleasant without needing to fix it
without needing to change it it allows us to be in the space of
non-judgmental awareness it's a really big topic I
apologize for throwing it in the middle but it needed it's the basis for
how we think about judgment that allows us to step away from self-criticism
through judgment so I hope that helps yeah no that's great and it's good to be exposed to
these things even if just for uh and a little remorseful yeah
so are there other questions
we'll give folks a little while to and for the YouTube folks to catch up as well
so one of the one of the tricks
of non-judgmental awareness is realizing how
our opinions about life our need to have an opinion about life is about feeling
that we're about creating a sense of familiarity and comfort
we are we are much uh we find the familiar more pleasant than the
unfamiliar part of being non-judgmental is being comfortable with what is ambiguous
one of my favorite business books mostly for the title was a book called uh
sacred cows make the best hamburger which offended a lot of people but what
it reminded me of was that if I come into a situation totally believing what the outcome should look like
I miss opportunities I miss the opportunity to see things clearly or to
see something that I wasn't looking for that's one outcome of being able to
be in the space of knowing this is Pleasant or
unpleasant I don't have to change it I don't have to make it something other
than it already is can I be okay with it just as it is
what is the name of that book again Maria oh the book I talked about yeah the hamburger book or hamburgers make
the uh sacred cows make the best hamburgers
I don't think I have it anymore or I'd give you more information about
it and keep in mind that's you know that's probably 20 years old
or more okay we've got Nancy uh Nancy you can go
ahead and uh uh unmute yourself and hi Nancy goodbye
everyone to hi Maria hi everyone on zoom and YouTube
awesome good to see everyone um so
my question is about um the point of the
the process where there's the seeing what's Pleasant and unpleasant and then
there's uh the comparison informing the opinion and then that was my notice my battery's
getting low so hopefully this holds um and then there's this story about how
this reflects something bad or unfavorable about myself
and could you talk about that that point because it seems to me like that's where
the suffering comes in it's like when I've made this story about me or something yes like something
uh unfavorable about myself
talk about a fault I have uh or it's actually not a fault it's a it's a feature
uh but it took me a while to figure it out so at some point in my life I decided that uh I had to be the
strongest person in the room that this is what would make me safe and it happened around the time my
mother died when I was 12. okay so long time mental habit of needing to be the
strongest person in the room I could withstand anything I could be tougher than anybody else
so over time I came to understand that this created a huge amount of suffering both for me and for the people around me
and I decided I would stop needing to be the strongest person in
the room no deciding that doesn't just make it happen I have to tell you so I would practice things like
oh I know the answer to that and they're really on the wrong track but I'm not going to say anything I'm going to sit
here and not say anything I'm not going to exert control over the meeting I'm just going to let it happen
and how watch how unpleasant that was and how difficult it was and the story
running in my head was something like oh I have the answer and it would be better if I just told people and I just let it
happen and I discovered sometimes I was right about that that the outcome was not very
good and sometimes I was wrong about that and somebody stood up with a really great answer and a great solution and oh
I wouldn't have done it that way but you know I think it's going to work and so allowing myself to notice that I don't
have to be the way I was is one way of dealing with it I don't have to be who I
have been I can be someone else and it may not be
comfortable and when I say someone else it doesn't mean I'm trying to be an ideal self but just this person who has
this tendency to be the strongest person in the room and to know that that is actually a
skill I have to be wielded at the right time and under these conditions it can be
criticized and under those conditions when there's chaos for example and
nobody can quite see their way I can establish a vision for people
this is an appropriate use of it I can suggest a vision for people you
see how easy it is how easy it is to fall into that because I was already to execution okay
this is how you this is how you do it because that's the outgrowth of that feature but it's just a feature
and I've also discovered the ease in not
being strong sometimes that the appropriate thing for me
is to just be there and so it allows me to see more clearly
that I don't have to judge What's Happening Now by what's come before or what
I would like to become I can just be in this moment
and see this is what's happening in this moment
I can see The Need to Be Right which is tied to the need to be liked or
the need to be seen in a certain way or so I don't have to get lost in an
analysis of it I can just see oh that's here that's here that's here
so if I'm in a conversation with my husband and uh we are not we're packed
talking across one another I can say okay
I have an intention to be kind to my husband so is our difference a matter of
my needing to be right or does it have some other impact
does it have an impact that affects the future or just this moment
I can let it go if it's just me wanting to be right I can say ah much better to be kind to
my husband than to be right much better
so I can make that judgment based on just seeing just this and not well you
know if I give in now I'm going to be giving whatever story whatever story we're telling we don't have to tell the
story so does that answer the question
thank you thank you very much
okay we've got uh um uh just to share something like I guess when you said about getting it right uh or being right
um I I listen to Sports Talk Radio all the time and there's this uh um uh
uh there's a there's a particular uh co-host I listen to and he often says I
want to get it right not be right so that's
that's good uh let me
go to YouTube there's a question there uh and
um so Sam asks uh Maria how can we make sense
of experience without being insensitive
well there are a few loaded words there so first of all
um the only way to See Clearly what the experience is is a
kind of heightened sensitivity so uh making sense of the experience I'm sorry
ask the first part of again because I'm getting lost in the words sure
um how can we make sense of experience without being insensitive right okay so
so part of the uh drive here is the need to make sense of the experience which
means I'm incorporating it integrating it into something that is uh has been
happening might be happening could be happening in the future the making sense has to do with giving it meaning right
and the point about blamelessness
is that not every experience has to be put into
a pattern it has to be put into uh an ongoing story that says well this
means this because it looks like that so if I talk about my firemen for example
what I the sense I made out of him leaping off the stairs was there's
no urgency here
but it would have been possible for me to incorporate that into a whole
and therefore because there's no urgency here
it it was unnecessary for me to form an opinion about an opinion about that
fireman jumping off the stair had I gotten a sense that everybody else
was rushing around I would have more likely formed an opinion that this
guy did not have the proper concern for the job he was doing
there's all kinds of things that can incorporate which are
additional to the minute to the moment that so the making sense of part
has to do with the in whether you're doing it in the immediate experience or
whether you're later reflecting on what something what has happened and you say well now what were all the elements of
that now you're not trying to make it now you're trying to
reason you're aware of the fact that you are thinking and trying to to resolve
something which doesn't have anything to do with self-judgment as soon as it goes into
the place where I'm judging whether it's good bad or indifferent as opposed to
is this appropriate to the mental process that I'm following I can get
myself in trouble I'm sorry if that gets confusing but I'm trying to make a distinction between
analysis in the moment which is going to be fed by my opinions
and what and me and reflection which incorporates
more wisdom and is not colored by whatever emotional content I have in the
moment or may not be colored by it unless I introduce it
I start saying oh that's my sister she did that she always does that she I
don't know when she's going to stop doing that now I'm applying something from the past to the future and I'm not
allowing her to be any different than she was
because I'm interpreting according to the story that I'm carrying with me so the difference between seeing clearly
and fitting something into a pattern is quite distinct
I hope that helps yeah thank you
uh Elroy uh or Eloy had a question um can you talk about how aspiring fits
in aspiring to write thought for example
okay so uh you may remember that when I
was talking about the firemen or when I was talking about discussing something with my husband where we were talking
past one another I reminded myself of my intention so I would say aspiration has
to do with intention so
you can use your aspiration your intention to
re-center yourself in a moment when you feel uncertain
this is my intention because what we have all we have
responsibility for In This Moment is Our intention and the action that we take
the next step what's already happened has already happened we can't change it we can't
undo it we can look at something with remorse and say uh I'm not going to do that
again and if I can make up for that I'll do that but carrying guilt with us
is trying to make it better in the past in the same way aspiration is
an intention this is this is where I want to place my attitude for the next
Moment The Next Step that I take and those intentions are changing all the time also we have broad intentions
and short-term intentions that the aspiration so I'll to make it less
theoretical I can say that I have an aspiration my My overall large intention
is to be open-hearted to be open-hearted and at one point I
noticed that begins with be open oh it's not about becoming something
else it's about being open so I can apply be open to this moment
and then I heard myself say B just be the way to be open-hearted is to not
have opinions about everything but to simply be as present as I possibly can so if you're doing
something like an aspiration to why speech that you know I can always ask myself
is this is this uh is this true is this useful
is this kind is it Timely and if it passes all of
those things I can say that I don't always have time to go through all of those pieces of my aspirational wise
speech but I can notice when something is unkind or I can notice when it's
not timely or I can notice there's no point in my saying this to this person because it will not change
his mind her mind and only leads to further conflict
so I can back off based on my intention or I can pursue it based on my intention
but it isn't about becoming someone it's about being
how can I apply my intention In This Moment
and when I fail to be kind
I can feel the corruption in my heart and that suffering follows from that
and I increasingly sensitize myself to that so that I will
be less likely to fall into that pit again
so
are there any other questions
I think that's pretty much all the questions that uh that we have in YouTube and
um and uh uh I guess Cindy just kind of commented uh and zoom like we could
probably have a day long on this topic so um and we only had a 15-minute talk so
yeah you know the truth is around judgment every lies everything in
Buddhism why wisdom why is wise view wise speech wise action wise livelihood
meditation all of it is there so uh
we have to choose where we point our attention as always
thank you all thank you thank you may you all be safe and well and thank
you to job for handling the streaming and to Kevin and all of your AV team for
your support thank you