hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour delighted to be with you
delighted to to uh receive your greetings really at the beginning it
always makes me feel connected to uh this International sa from so many
different parts of the [Music] world so for this evening I wanted to
invite us to uh engage with um
compassion practice it seems like it's the right medicine for this week what
with what is happening in the world what is happening geopolitically and also
what is happening very likely for ourselves um and also with people
perhaps we know um so compassion you can never have enough compassion Never
Enough compassion and as the Dalai Lama said compassion is not a luxury it's a
necessity it's a necessity for us humans to survive for us to survive it's
not a luxury so so with that um yeah I
don't think there is not there's much more that I want to say to frame it but to say that um please you're invited to
um compassion practice to practice compassion wherever you are called for
in this session um there might be a lot of
physical pain right now where you're sitting um practicing there might be
heartache um in your heart or or there might be SC and deep deep care for
people um who are in very very painful
difficult situations extremely painful difficult
situations um elsewhere in the world um our sisters our brothers our siblings in
humanity we're not so different and maybe that's where your heart goes to hold them with compassion and good
wishes so so let us engage let us begin
let us Begin by arriving arriving arriving arriving take a moment
to arrive in your
body in this moment in
time in this seated posture take time to arrive the preliminaries are
important how are you safe [Music] sitting if you're sitting in a
chair or your feet the bottom of your feet touching the
Earth are you sitting comfortably is your back
straight are your shoulders rolled back sitting with a sense of Integrity
dignity as well as comfort is your body
relaxed is there extra holding and tightness where there is no need for
it can you relax your body especially if there is pain physical pain
present we often tighten up your around the pain or around emotional pain we
tighten up can you invite your body your dear
precious body to relax in this moment relax relax
relax relax just be
breathed nothing
needed nothing extra
relax and let the body be breathed because it knows how to do this
knows how to
breathe and awareness simply receiving the breath
the sensations of the breath in the belly are being received on their own
you don't have to add much effort on top of what's already
happening
Let each breath especially each out breath be more and more relaxing letting
go of expectations of thoughts and just be present thinkinking
more deeply allowing
preoccupations to be put down to be released for just this moment this
moment of respit deeply needed
and we put it all down in this moment just for a moment we can pick it up
later but first we need to establish the ground the ground the
stability of the
heart intimacy with this
breath
and can we imagine that each out breath is releasing calming
soothing bringing comfort and sucker to this body to this heart and
mind
every out
breath as if the out breath is soothing calming
massaging wrapping a blanket of
care around
yourself
and the in breath is gathering any acknowledgment of discomfort
pain not so much thinking about it but it's automatically happening
as if the pain and the heart and the body is being collected and transformed in the heart the heart
center and breathed out as comfort and
sucker nourishing yourself with each
breath
and if it feels like too much Mo think about the INB
breath electing the challenges and being transformed in the out
breath breathing out sucker Comfort compassion and let go of the in breath
part and just consider the out breath is soothing
comforting bringing calm care to pain and
sorrow
and now if you like you can expand ex extend and
expand the circle of [Music] compassion
to include a few people in areas of the world that are
suffering right now include them in your mind in your
heart as if your out breath is bringing them care sucker while they're
afraid [Music]
grieving
suffering there are human beings just like me just as I wish to be happy I
wish you happiness and freedom from sorrow and
suffering just as I wish it for myself
and include all of
you in your practice include
yourself and others in a
challenged area in our world right
now
just as I wish to [Music] be free from sorrow free from pain
I wish you fellow human beings I wish you freedom from sorrow and pain may you
have ease as much as possible in the midst
of this
difficulty as if with with each out breath you were putting your blanket of
care around people you don't
know but it doesn't matter we're all
related we're all part of the human
family you could have been born as them they could have been born as
you
and now for the last few minutes of this
practice let your heart be drawn to
wherever it's drawn to the most for the compassion practice
maybe someone you know who's grieving someone you don't know yourself your body your heart
wherever you're drawn breathing out compassion and
sucker
care
offering your wishes for well-being without attachment but as a
gift to the world to yourself to [Music]
nonviolence to more love and compassion in the world training our hearts and
Minds to
care
and in the last minute of this practice
period offering compassion to yourself or however this practice period
was whether it was sleepy or distracted doesn't matter offer care and
compassion that you showed up you've done your best and letting go of the
rest May our practice be a cause and [Music]
condition for wisdom for compassion in our world may all beings
be free including
[Music]
ourselves thanks everyone thanks for your
practice so the practice of compassion meeting sorrow and suffering
with with care with kindness and tonight the way I let it is we started
with ourselves and then we rod in others and also another thing to note is
um for those of you who know what tonglin practice is breathing in um
suffering breathing out care I offered that as one
variation um early on but if it became too overwhelming
invited you to just lean into the out breath of bringing comfort and peace
meeting suffering so so just some nuances of tonight
so so as be back everyone and uh we have some time for
any Reflections if you want to share them in chat chat is open or um also you
can raise your hand hi Amy I see your hand please thank you so much um I've had a
lot of aha moments when it comes to um finding PL ways to elicit
compassion for others deeply in hard moments moments of conflict and one is
like somatically like you guys see me rocking here a lot the rocking chair reminds me of holding a young child and
rocking them and meeting them in their emotions and the hand on the heart or or
a hug um and other pieces and then another piece I've been doing is
um putting aside their story and trying to see the emotion under the emotion
that's under that I can relate to and the the part of them that probably started having that emotion when they
were young so defensiveness or that comes out of fear or sadness I can
relate to that and and stopping my own need to be seen or validated in that
moment but instead seeing seeing them and then once I can deeply like see them
for like ouch like they are in pain right now and they're relating it to me or they're relating it to something and
we don't necessarily agree in that aspect but that doesn't matter about that what matters is is that like
they're this human experiencing a pain and if I can see them then usually their
defenses can come down and sometimes there's discernment for me to then share
mine and if there isn't then I can go here or to another friend or someone who
can um I can feel a congruence or an Attunement or a validation or love Feel
Love from um but I I feel like that's been a very big aha moment for me in how
I try to meet conflicts profound thank you Amy thanks
so much for sharing you're a and see so much you shared here beautiful both the
sematic aspect of relating as well as because we have all we all have bodies
so that's doorway of of somatic experiencing
or through the rocking or or hand on the heart you mentioned and also as you you
said so beautifully I was touched when you mentioned um seeing not the P you know what what's
happening on top but but you know what what emotion is underneath and H how that perhaps came to be when they were
younger um the causes the conditions I think that's my words to to bring the
the Buddhist terminology to that but but really getting in touch with that and it
um and not overlaying your own perspective on
it and how I can kind of relate to that pain for them so that I can like that can be the true compassion there like if
it's it's oh I could see how that would hurt then that can elicit that true compassion and yes I see how that would
hurt exactly if I were in their shoes this would hurt of course yeah yeah
thanks Amy thanks so [Music] much
Ron yeah someone in our group mentioned something that really reson ated which
was when we become so aware of of so much
suffering and in so many areas at times it it can almost feel
like it's exponentially growing and can
start to feel almost hopeless in some way
um but when when we sort of turn turn
inside to focus The Compassion on our own
suffering it has a quality to it of you know a it's it's something that's
doable and we have some control over and B it's also a
we're we're better at being compassionate and helpful to
others when we've also turned that compassion onto
ourselves and and done that work indeed well well said I'm so
appreciating you um sharing what came both for your practice and also in the
small group it sounds like yeah had a very very um juicy wonderful conversation about
the benefits of compassion both turned inwards how that can actually support it
turning outwards and and not veering into overwhelm because the mind can get
overwhelmed but the heart when it stays in the present moment can always have hope can always have hope yeah thanks
Ron thank you
CLK um so I was starting out trying to Envision like a family who maybe on side
being persecuted and I was like struggling to connect and trying to anyway and kind of to my surprise a
little ways into it I have this very clear image of somebody on the other side who is
doing doing persecuting and kind of like Amy said seeing the pain of hurting another
person and the Bad Karma of that and then also all the causes and conditions and pain that would have led them up to
that and then I thought about that scene I don't know who seen um everything
everywhere all at once but there's a climactic scene where she puts a googly
eye on her third eye and instead of fighting all the other people she uses
this new power to see what needs they didn't get filled in their past life that are making them act the way they
are now and she creatively starts helping them fulfill these needs that
they don't want to be violent anymore and it just made me think about the courageousness that you need to respond
and and creativity and um yeah to respond in the face of of
really intense suffering like that and I just love that image of her putting the googly eye and this wind blows behind
her and she stands there really strong and then instead of fighting she just Embraces them all with compassion
yeah beautiful thanks for bringing this in claric I've seen the movie and and um
I'm getting chills as you bring that in to this moment because yes in in in the
movie she becomes the expression of of the Buddha of compassion in that moment
and and really seeing the cause and condition and what does this person need they didn't get and gives it to them
it's so sweet actually it's so sweet and and I'm so touched that that you bring
this in from your own practice of oh yeah this is what came up for you this is what came up for you instead of
seeing um someone who's being prosecut prosecuted and and seeing their pain oh
it just flipped naturally which is beautiful what an expansion of our heart
to be able to to go there on its own that yes this person who's causing pain
is really really hurt in I'm I'm deeply Touched By by your practice report as
well as everyone who's shared tonight Ron and Amy too thank you thank you all
beautiful deep practices thank you and one question is coming Nikki how
to overcome Bel that that blocks compassion this happened to me today my
belief about someone events blocked compassion for me towards myself or others
um so I would say that it um in order
for me to answer that I need more details like what because there are different things that block compassion
so so actually this is what I'll say okay this is what I can say I think what
what needs to happen is that when compassion gets blocked you need to see
with awareness what is the belief that has blocked it is it that I don't
deserve it is it that they don't deserve it is it that it's going to make them soft me soft like what is that belief
that's blocking compassion that compassion is too soft I don't know there are just so many beliefs I can't
go through all of but but please Free Yourself see what is the belief that is
causing that block and then put a question mark next to it is that so is
that so is that really so challenging instead of just believing it um because
there there are so many um unhelpful beliefs that we can
carry around unexamined beliefs we can carry around that block compassion so examine them
that's what I'm trying to tell the person who wrote me the private question in chat that you're
welcome so thank you dear ones thank you so much for your practice
for cultivating your hearts I'm deeply deeply touched with the reports tonight and
just holding so many sides of of this aching
Human family where we are in pain and we cause pain and may
we may we grow in love and compassion may all beings
everywhere be free from sorrow may all beings everywhere be free including
[Music] ourselves
thanks everyone be well