right welcome hello everyone lovely to be back with you I've missed
you as I mentioned at the beginning uh various things were happening the past
week including on Monday uh the Persian New Year no ruse which is on the Vernal
equip Equinox it's the first day of spring which was on Monday so happy
spring to you all happy spring yeah so so let's um let's start meditating
together let's begin and More Words
will will the theme will will emerge
let's let's arrive let's arrive together in this body
In This Moment In Time
arriving arriving every moment
each moment a new arrival
every moment like spring
every breath it's like spring every sensation in this
body fresh new never liked this before
and we have a beginner's mind beginner's mind the mind
that is fresh
like the green grass
like blossoms cherry blossoms in springtime
fresh new blossoming meeting this moment anew
let us meet sensations of our body
resting on the earth on the cushion our sit bones
of the cushion on the chair I feet on the Earth bottom of our feet
grading these Sensations
in New
and we meet the sensations of this breath in the abdomen
like the spring Breeze fresh new Sensations
the in-breath the entire in breath and the entire out
breath as well as the past
in between the in-breath and out breath out breath and in-breath
receiving opening the door of your heart
agreed
the breath the sensations of the breath however they arrive
staying with them like an honored guest
before meeting for the first time
and we have a childlike interest curiosity
Delight at this world
this inner world the breaths Sensations
receiving it with ease relaxation softness
thank you
foreign
and we meet this moment can I meet with this moment like a friend
I made this moment with friendliness whatever is arising In This Moment
if you are meeting a friend haven't seen for the first time
for a long time although they're tired
cranky oh it's your friend oh the same Joy Delight
friendliness
that the pains and aches in your own heart
here you won't be upset that your friend is tired or cranky or hurting
you're just happy to be with them oh it's okay however they are
freshness of appreciation
to meet whatever this moment brings even if it's a crowd of Sorrows
in our heart
meeting with friendliness they're fresh
maybe your mind is scattered and you meet your mind
with friendliness made it like a friend
might be tired scattered it's okay
love your mind love your heart
you're doing their best they be present
and if it's quiet inside
meeting the breath
with friendliness kindness appreciation
imbuing the breath with appreciation
breathing in appreciation breathing out appreciation
and whatever Rises if it's judgment I'm not doing this right or
this is terrible or boring and you meet this whatever Rises
with kindness with friendliness made it like a friend a friend who's cranky
right now it's okay it's okay
you still love your friend
I meet this moment with friendliness
generosity of heart
they meet this body with friendliness
now I meet my heart with friendliness
with kindness
and I made my mind with friendliness with kindness
I made I body art and white
whatever Rises with kindness friendliness
with patience with peace
foreign
I made the present moment being fully here not in the past
not in the future but right here right here letting go
letting go of the past future letting go of entanglement in the
present Simply Be simply be here
opening opening with kindness made whatever arises in this fear of
experience Mind Body
up with appreciation kindness
as if spring has sprung
and we also meet whatever arises externally with kindness
sounds that might be arising the environment
the people with whom we're sharing the space
this practice face in our hearts meeting them with kindness
everyone here and zoom YouTube
an audio to our mind Beyond all people everywhere
all beings everywhere whatever their conditions might be
meeting everyone
every being with kindness with friendliness
with good will
of seeing ourselves meeting others with kindness being a source of kindness Good Will in the world
spreading kindness generosity good wealth wherever we can however we can
wishing you well for all beings
may all beings be well
may all beings know peace and causes of peace freedom in their
heart from greed hatred and delusion
foreign
from greed hatred and delusion may we have peace
may all beings everywhere including ourselves be well
and know true happiness the Bliss of
integrity generosity
wisdom
you all thank you for your practice hmm
so tonight we are at this moment in time whatever your
time zone is we uh practiced with um
a couple of themes one was needing the moment meeting whatever arises in the
body in the heart and the mind whatever rises in this fear of
experience with with kindness with friendliness like a friend
also in that theme we brought in a sense of freshness sense of inspired by it
being the first couple days of spring as if we're meeting this moment fresh
whatever is a rising fresh this childlike interest freshness curiosity
because as adults we kind of get um
I don't know um board perhaps or we lose our the
freshness we have to rekindle it we have to remind ourselves at this moment has
never been like this before and will never be if you spend some time with with a young person you'll just see the
sense of delight anything any little game or any little toy just there's a
sense of wonder um so this invitation to meet each moment
with beginner's mind as spring has has arisen fresh can be very helpful as we
go around in our daily life instead of bah humbug yeah it's Wednesday it's oh wow this moment
is fresh it's never been like this it's and it will never be like this again we
just take it for granted we think we're going to be alive for so many more Springs who knows who knows
I thank you for joining through this practice so so I'd like to invite us not to turn as
we meet this moment with internally we have met it with kindness
as much as possible as much as possible can we turn can we befriend whatever
Rises can we meet others like a friend can we meet can we meet this moment can
we meet a couple of other human beings like friends whether or not you know them you've seen
them before or not meet them as if for the first time without the the um the
assumptions presumptions that we have oh this person is like that this is what they're going to talk about no just what
if you try that out for size it's easier for people you don't know so well to meet
them afresh meet them Anew with friendliness and then maybe you can
practice in the sandbox and then take it to your family and friends if there are some buttons that you have buttons that
that are pushed pushed by some friends family and colleague maybe you can just try on for size for a few minutes what
if you you met them fresh without all the expectations presumptions
um with friendliness so that's the invitation
or the small groups that will engage with in a moment and the prompt is what
what was this practice like for you you can share maybe a sentence or two and the next
person will go alphabetical and the next person will share something and the next person or you can just say pass and hold
silent presence but those who are receiving those who are hearing hear the
person as if it's fresh it's new without presumptions without thinking about what
you're gonna say just friendliness friendliness and spring so these two bring them in pla play around
see how you can um play with that make it work for you and I'd be interested in your
reflections so I'm going to create the breakout rooms
and invite you as always to be kind to be kind to yourselves to be kind to each
other and I'm gonna recreate the rooms hold on
a second here we go okay let's try this all right okay be kind to yourselves to
each other and about to open the ropes here we go
the rooms are closed everybody's back welcome back everyone would love to uh
open this base and also the chat if you'd like to share exploring this what
was it like bringing the idea of meeting others with beginner's mind fresh as well as
this friendliness Ali please
hello hello everyone so I just love the beginning of how you started to start
the meditation and saying that though see what comes up kind of like allowing and that's what I
did all the way through the meditation and towards the end I just came up with like a
spring renewal you know in the Persian tradition as you mentioned uh with this spring so what what do I
have to say grateful be grateful for for the Sangha and then it came to me that
made a spring spring every moment you know in our lives so that came to me you
know and then you kind of like you know started in that team and in the group it
came to me that the Hindu tradition uh one of those sages said that every moment you open your eyes you create a
new world and that is very true and so may that be our case for
this lovely space here you have Nikki and the other teachers and then we're the greatest song on the whole world
May the spring is spring every month yeah thank you Ellie thank you so much
sorry about that no that why are you so that was beautiful okay that was that
was absolutely beautiful I so appreciate and and this this is a May the Springs
be springing every moment and actually it is and as you said this Hindu uh
saying is that actually every moment it is it's just that we we don't pay attention to it in that way we're like
uh humdrum humdrum same thing okay I'm gonna open my eyes again like no actually it's it's we're creating worlds
we're creating new worlds every moment so yeah exactly so let's let's have
actually that that perspective of freshness newness this show is not going to go on for that long so we might as
well it's always bringing new every moment we just don't don't appreciate it so thank
you so much for bringing that beautiful thank you and as they say in Persian happy happy New Year happy new rules yes
today new day exactly means new day it's all new day thank you
thank you so much lovely any other reflections you can
also type them in chat either to me uh privately or to everyone if you like
clear thank you I'll be very brief but this
was not what I talked about in our group but the last allies share
um reminded me to just to mention that and I've talked about this before I I
circulated gratitude list with two friends every day uh and uh
I've been doing it for years now it really forces one to look at what is
working well in the day rather than things that might be going wrong or just
to monotony of it it really have to focus and think through the details and
it's beautiful I mean it's worked so beautifully for me in terms of seeing the day every day fresh yeah yeah lovely
and and you know and also what it becomes Zach after you do this practice for a long time which I think you're
alluding to but just to unpack that for everyone is that maybe at first one you only you know one only looks at what is
going well and but then later it's not just that you also actually start to appreciate it so many things are going
well I mean it's just like oh my goodness the preponderance of fresh and new and wonderful things it's just like
wow you start to notice more so so um I think that it it's important how
they this practice actually changes our mind instead of I think some people maybe do this practice like well I've
already been grateful for this and that and like oh what's new like I actually know it shifts and changes the way you
see so so I appreciate you bringing that in thank you yeah what else any any
other last Reflections before we close
and you can also chat uh type them in chat as I was saying they're publicly or privately any insights from this
practice any incites anything different um what was it like to meet others in a
group with beginner's mind even if maybe you had met them before perhaps you
should try that on for size or no it just went out the window after 30 seconds of being in the group that can
happen
okay all right well
Let's uh let's bring our time together to a close so so thank you all thank you
all for your practice thank you for for cultivating your hearts towards kindness
friendliness meeting this moment internally and externally
and new and like a friend may all things be well may all beings
be free including ourselves
thanks everyone happy New Year happy noroo's new day new
moment every moment take good care of yourselves see you on Friday bye
perhaps