good evening and welcome welcome everybody
nice to see you all
so when I first started a meditation practice number of years ago now I I so often had this idea like wow wow
everybody else must be like on the brink of Enlightenment or they're enlightened and I am so awful as a meditator
I remember the I actually learned how to meditate on a Meditation Retreat and it
was incomprehensible I just could not understand how come that person sitting
in front of me was still for 45 minutes I just didn't even like know how that was possible I was like in so much pain
and non-stop squirming and it was quite something
and I had this uh I was saying myself why did I ever think this was a good idea
but as I learned more and more about meditation you know it really touched me kind of like in my heart and some kind
of way that I couldn't even describe or explain something was pooling me
but I still couldn't do it very well and I couldn't sit still and my mind was all over the place
but it wasn't until I had been meditating for quite some time I remember precisely how long but for
quite some time before I ever heard of these things called the hindrances
and that was a game changer for me when I learned about this
some of you may be familiar with this it's a common teaching but for whatever reason maybe I was just absent on those
days when they were being talked about I had never heard about them but it made such a big difference so
what are the hindrances these are something that the you know are um
preserved in the teachings from early Buddhism so it's attributed to the
Buddha so thousands of years ago people were talking about this same thing which
for me I'd love this idea like wow thousands of years ago they were talking about what I'm experiencing today
and that somehow you know makes it less personal right that countless numbers of people have had these same problems that
I'm having these same issues that I'm having so it kind of like normalized my
meditation experience and the difficulties
probably word is Never Enough which often gets translated as hindrances but we must we might also think of these as
obstructions or impediments or obstacles to the mind and bodily mind and body is
settling down things that are getting in the way from
settling down and they typically they have this list
of five these like all the things that ever happened to us while we're trying to
meditate they kind of like you know boiled it down to five there are other lists that um kind of are more fleshed
out than this list of five but I'm going to stick with this five
and I'm not going to talk about the hindrances themselves but I'll just
briefly mention them I'm going to talk more about our relationship to them and kind of
like flesh out what they are as a group and how we might work with them in different settings and our relationship
to them and what does it mean for us as meditators so what are these five hindrances
so the first two are about this sense of kind of like often we use this
expression or I use this expression of pushing or pulling so this pushing I don't want it get it
away from me pulling I want more of this please don't
leave pushing and pulling I guess pushing would be aversion and
pulling a sense desire typically they go in the other direction so it'd be pulling and pushing I guess since desire
and aversion the next two have to do with the amount
of energy that's present I think we all have this
experiment this experience that there's just too much energy and we just feel agitated and we can't fidget so it's
either with the body or with the mind that the mind is racing and trying to solve problems or kind of
like obsessively in a loop or something like this or just feeling like we have
to scratch or itch or shift or something so too much energy
restlessness or not enough energy
this odd expression sloth and torpor which these were never part of my
vocabulary before I started practicing Buddhism but that's the you know when there isn't enough energy kind
of like falling asleep or yeah I'll just falling asleep is a or
is it feeling like you're you know egoing in that direction and then the fifth one is actually one I
think is the most interesting I'm not going to talk a lot about it today I was thinking that maybe I'll do some Dharma
talks on it that it gets called doubt but it's really about vacillation or
hesitation okay well maybe I'm gonna sit and um I'll do some loving kindness practice I
thought that was good may you be happy but we maybe I should do some mindfulness practice because
this thing on my knee is bothering me it came looking at the well maybe I should do some concentration practice because I
heard that's really good no maybe I should do meta practice because that helps with the concentration practice I think I'm just going to go and defrost
the freezer you know is this thing kind of like you're just bouncing around and not really settling but it often has to
do with this what what should I be doing like what's the what's the right practice or does this really work this
practice do those teachers really know what they're talking about
how do we even know what the Buddha said you know these types of things so this is doubt kind of this vacillation or
this hesitation so these hindrances part of what um
makes them so interesting I would say and Powerful to work with
is we notice them in our meditation practice when we're trying to settle
down when we've decided that we're going to meditate but they are there whether we are aware
of them or not they are there in all aspects of Our
Lives work any creative projects we'd like to do
any service projects we'd like to do volunteering and long-term relationships
these hindrances quote unquote don't just hinder the Mind settling into they
just get in the way if our doing what's important to us
they get in the way of our expressing our values in so many different ways
so there is one way that we might consider meditation practice sometimes I
like to lump things together so if you were to do like a big huge lumping together
we could say all of meditation practices of one of two kinds one is a really deep
meditative State very deep the other is you're working with the
entrances that's it like these are you could say these are like the two types of things because the hindrances are
always there unless we're in really deep meditative States
so in some way they are like seeds that uh you know Blossom or bloom or
grow and maybe what they are when they are growing they have like
these hooks that like to hang on to things or they're looking for things to hang on to
and then they then they kind of like fuel whatever it is they get connected to
for example a story that um I have is on this really long retreat
had it been in for months into the mind is really settled and I noticed but in this one sit in
particular there was like some of this uh desire there's like these fantasies you know now I don't remember what it
was but fantasies of something good right that I wanted maybe like a more comfortable uh cushion or you know
whatever it might be but then I noticed uh this you know like
oh okay this is just a hindrance the hindrance of desire there's a number of ways we can work with this and I was
working with it and the desire was kind of going away it was a baiting and the
mind was finally settling down and by the end of the meditation period I felt like oh
finally settle down a few okay feels good the Bell goes off at the end of the
session and uh I thought you know what I finally got settled I'm just gonna stay I don't
have to jump up right when the bell rings so I'm sitting and I'm sitting for you
know some minutes more then I decide okay it's time to get up
and it's uh lunch time so I'll go have lunch
and those of you about meditation Retreats know that's right it's just like a buffet line and I got your plates
and you serve yourself in the line so
I go to the dining hall wash my hands before get my plate and go up to
whatever the first thing is oh my gosh this looks so good okay I'm gonna put some of this on wow oh my gosh this is
fantastic I'm gonna put this or maybe I should get two wow look at this they also have this I'm gonna get this I had
so much food on my plate there's like no way I was gonna be able to eat this
what I had seen is that the desire had just gotten a little bit more subtle and
I found this hook that when I went to lunch it just got expressed to just piling all the food I could onto this
one plate so there's this way that they get expressed and sometimes it's obvious
and sometimes it's really subtle
and that's a little bit what I want to talk about today is about how there's the hindrances it's not like they're
present or absent it's really definitely a spectrum
and there can be really obvious or really subtle and we can work with them
in all these different ways with the subtle and with the obvious end with the subtle
but how ever we work with them there's a way that we might consider and I'm
influenced by Rob burbella another Drama teacher wonderful Dharma teacher
and he describes hindrances as Hidden Treasures
Hidden Treasures and part of the reason why he says this is be this recognition that they are
showing up in our life all over a place wherever and that even if we go on a Meditation
Retreat and we're spending days weeks months on Retreat or if we just come to
a 45-minute sit or we do a day long whatever it is
if nothing happens during that meditation Endeavor except
working with desire working with ill will working with restlessness working with drowsiness like we feel like or we
have doubt like should I even be doing this I'm so awful at this if we if the mind and the body never
settle but we learn something about these
hindrances we learn our habits
the patterns of our minds patterns of our bodies
when we have a something we'd like to do and there's difficulties obstructions
obstacles that get in the way if the only thing we ever do is notice
oh yeah when there is desire I notice how my body leans forward and I'm just I
can't stop all these fantasies and they're colorful and provocative and
there's the mind is just doesn't ever want to come back it's just lost in fantasies and then I kind of forget what
it was I was trying to do if we have nothing but those experiences
but we've learned something about ourselves
those of that might be more transformative than having some settled meditations
that might be what really changes Our Lives because having a settled meditation is
pleasant and it helps us to see some of the more subtle things that are going on in our life but the subtle yeah subtle
Minds that are going to settle things that are going on in our minds but learning about the hindrances and
shifting our relationship to them
instead of like dang it this again shifting it to okay
this is what's here how can I work with it how can I be with it this is what's happening
um I might as well learn something I might as well practice some skills I
might as well see get curious about it
that can change your life
helps us like when we're having difficulties and difficult conversations somebody we love has a difficult
diagnosis and we notice like oh yeah I I don't want to hear that this is like the worst
thing I ever want to know but if we have know that how we
the pattern of our reaction with aversion this helps us be present for
difficult things and this can change our life maybe we don't
shut down or yell back when our boss or a co-worker does something
untoward or whatever it might be so Rob Rebecca calls these hindrances as
Hidden Treasures and some and I actually really love this so is there a way that we can learn to
view them so that they lose their power so that they lose their Authority
they're still there they're still happening but maybe we're not as caught up in them maybe we're not believing
them the stories that they spin or we're not so swayed by the direction
that's that they're pointing to you so they still show up maybe as seeds but
maybe the blooming and the blossoming isn't quite as much maybe they're just plants
instead of seeds so one thing
that can help with this is to get a little bit curious when like I
hit either when hindrance is really evident or maybe just more
objectively to notice or get curious about the hindrances are a spectrum
I say this is a really obvious or really subtle so it's not that they're simply present
or not present so there's a way when they're present we
can sometimes feel a little bit demoralized or dejected or like oh again all this desire I'm always I learned of
when I I noticed sorry when I started my meditation practice I discovered how much desire has such a role in my life
I'm always thinking about things I'm going to buy I'm thinking about things that I want or you know all these things that I
want that I don't have but if we notice that they are a
spectrum then we can start to rather it just being they're there or not we can
notice like oh okay it's there's desire here but maybe
there's also a little bit of settledness it's we're not completely consumed by
the desire or maybe there is a time when we are
pretty settled maybe maybe more than usual and yet we
could start to sense like oh there's this wish for even more settledness
so to notice that oh yeah even though the more obvious type isn't there there might be the more subtle type of Desire
that is there and so maybe we can work with it and I'll talk about how to work with some of
the hindrances here in a moment but I also I want to start by talking about
Spectrum in regards to energy
because one is one of the hindrances is restlessness
and it turns out that the Buddha he actually talked about in some of these not as well-known suit does and not so
well-known lists those of you have been around the Buddhist scene no there's a so many lists
there's different uh levels of intensity of this too much energy so one is what
typically is called the hindrance which may be described as agitation or
excitement or distraction or this like flurry this sense of
agitation you're like this busyness
and so this could be in the in the body it's like this energies pulsing through and there's like this sense to fidget
but there's also like this agitated uh
vulnerability like as if we've had too much caffeine
so it could be in the body but it can also show up in the mind as this scattered or persistent thinking
can't quite settle down or just this inability to focus or the mind just
resists being directed anywhere it's just doing what whatever it wants to do
so that's one type of like too much energy this what we typically call the hindrance
but then the Buddha also talked about like this excessive efforting
that is like a little bit too much exertion in the practice
there's a certain amount of settledness but there's a straining
there is this I definitely have to do more I need more or I want more or I'm
just trying so hard and there's a way that this can make things feel really
tight like I I gotta get this and pulley this is a turreta Viria
and I love that uh there's this very simple simile that's offered that is of
a person that holds a quail you know these cute little birds
we have the California quail I just love them they're just adorable for those of you who know them the way that they walk
with these little things on their heads they're just adorable I just love them I just saw some baby quail the other day
it was just anyway so if you're going to uh hold a quail and if you hold it too
tightly you can crush it so in the same way if we hold our
practice the effort too tightly it crushes it and then it just this
straining so that's another type of maybe too much
energies kind of gets translated into too much effort
but then there's this even more subtle type is this often the Derma teachers
call this drifting so I haven't seen this anywhere in any Buddhist text this is something that
Dharma teachers have come up with but I find it's a good description and can be
helpful and this is when the mind is settled
feathers it's not agitated it's settled but there's a way that it just kind of
like slides from one object to the next
and then goes to the next so it's not that it's sluggish it's just kind of
moving slowly so it doesn't have this quality of agitation but it also doesn't
have the quality of just staying with the object instead maybe it's like
oh the sensation in my knee breath thinking about dinner
breath other knee but there's a way that it's like um sometimes gets described as um
well maybe slow motion like a monkey that swings from One Tree to the next
but slowly so they have one thing but they're already reaching for the next and let go
and then grab the next and then let go and then grab the next so this drifting quality this is really
so the mind is settled but there's a way in which
the mind doesn't quite land so there's this tendency for it to drift off off
the object or the subject that's being it's looking at so they're just a
bit more thoughts and images in the mind than there would be if the Mind were
more settled and then maybe a fourth layer
maybe even more subtle is let's say okay the mind has settled
on this object and there's this it's just right here with the object I'll just say the breath sensation of the
breath just noticing the breath just being with the breath noticing the breath
and they're like wow the mind isn't thinking oh that's actually thinking but
because we didn't notice it it's just doesn't get really seen so there's this way in which there's
this subtle way in which thoughts kind of like intrude and like like whoa It's so still and you know
that happens we're over here as I thought and then coming back that's also a little bit more energy
so then I just want to share a little bit because energy is something it turns out that this is definitely the art of
practice I would say is working with these different levels of energy
too much or too little and to recognize that they're a spectrum and so we have a
those were going from the most energetic to most subtle form a little bit too much
energy and then if you don't have any energy at all the most obvious form is
when you're about to fall asleep is of course is not an uncommon thing with meditators
and this is you know where the body feels heavy and lethargic and weary and
the mind is dull and cloudy and sluggish
and when it's strong we don't even know it's there we're just you know doing this thing or you know this thing nodding off
and this being a hindrance is distinct from physical tiredness or mental
tiredness so it's not that there isn't any energy
available it's that we're not accessing it
so there's a way in which there's a choosing not to access it
choosing maybe is too strong a word but often this is due to a sense of
resistance like like we don't actually want to be present for what's there so
there's a type of shutting down or this discouragement or this hopelessness or
frustration or boredom so when these things are present there's
a way in which they're kind of the whole energy just kind of drains out
so that's like the obvious form that's the most obvious but there's also a more subtle form
which uh the Buddha called atalina Viria and this is when there's not enough
effort it's a certain amount of complacency so
the simile is like the same as with the quail holding the quail instead of too tight
now it's too loose and the quail just flies away so like okay yeah I'm with the object
but not with a lot of energy and so it just kind of goes like this
the mind kind of drifts away and then maybe comes back a little bit and then
drifts away so this kind of deficiency of effort
maybe I'd say this like coming back there isn't a lot of emphasis on coming back to the to the object
there's also another type of way in which this shows up and this is as
inertia so just this way is the just kind of
like letting the momentum of practice unfold but then the momentum Runs Out
and then we just do whatever our habits are whatever our patterns are
just show up when the there's this kind of inertia like and it's not uncommon to like we'll sit
down on the especially long time meditators to sit on the cushion and just do what they've been doing for the
past five or ten years and they not really a sense of freshness or brightness or curiosity
okay look at this energy yeah this is what I do in the morning I sit
without a sense of it going somewhere or wanting it to be a support for one's life
and then even a more subtle version of that is what we call sinking mind
s this again is not anything that you'll find in any Buddhist teachings but something that Dharma teachers talk
about and I was so happy when I learned about this because come to find out I used to spend
a lot of time doing this unknowingly
it's a way in which there's a the mind is settled the body is settled and it's
in this nice cushy comfy cottony
fluffy dull space so it feels like you know the outside
world is a little bit away but this feels like um
like it starts off maybe feeling nice because there's there's aren't
things bothering you but there's a way in which the energy is
always just slowly draining and there's something about by the end
of this sit I feel awful you feel like oh I'm so tired and the world is meaningless and I
kind of hate everything and beautifully resistant there's a just draining out of the area so it starts as being comfy
secluded but then it doesn't it ends up feeling kind of awful
and it takes some real effort to get out of this and this can be a habit for a lot of people they just get into this
comfy cottony fluffy puffy I don't really know how to
describe it place and stay there and stay there and stay there and I think
that this is their practice this is a good practice and some way it is but they don't have a brightness to their
mind there isn't some uplift or some clarity or
Vitality instead that maybe that's a good way to describe it you're in this comfy fluffy place but the Vitality is
draining out and you you end up with no vitality and that's not a good feeling
so there's all these different ways in which the hindrances show up I was just talking about energy levels you know to
the most obvious to the most subtle but then of course we want to work with them
like what do we do with them and here's something that I think is maybe helpful
to consider how we respond to the hindrances
depends what kind of practice we're doing and what we are what Our intention is for that
meditation period more specifically
if you're doing mindfulness practice you'll work with them in one way if you're doing concentration practice
you'll work with them in a different way you might ask well what's the difference
between mindfulness and concentration and I guess I I can describe this in the
as a along with a description like how one would work with them in the mindfulness
practice so mindfulness practice is a practice of noticing what's actually happening here
in the present moment and we often do that by starting with
being mindful of the breath but we're mindful of the sensations of breathing like noticing how does an inhale feel
how does an exhale feel how do the transitions be between inhales and exhales when I'm doing guided
meditations for mindfulness of breathing I'll include like noticing some of the
changing aspects of the breath and then
when the Mind Set a little bit we'll turn to what's compelling discomfort in the body
emotional states lots of thoughts sounds whatever it is so mindfulness of the
breath something's compelling we turn over here and we're doing mindfulness I'll just
make this a pain in the OR discomfort in the knee when that's no longer compelling we come back to the breath
oh there's the sound the dog's barking then we come back to the breath so that's more mindfulness and so when
things are hindrances come up Ouija that's just one more thing here's the breath oh here's the sensation of
too much energy feel into that be with that and so it's no longer an obstacle to
mindfulness it's the object of mindfulness and then you're just being mindful you have to be mindfulness of
too much energy but it mindfulness is mindfulness however with concentration practices
we want to be a little bit more proactive with the hindrances and not just be aware of them
but to apply what we might say are antidotes like waste what are things that we can do to work with the energy
and so one way one thing that we can do is
if we feel like there's too much energy we can shift our practice to start doing
body scans going from the head down to the toes this gives the mind of something a
little bit extra to do and it's a way that rather than trying to keep something you know in one place you can
you know it goes Sensations in the head and shoulders back chest belly Sensations on the seat
Etc so giving something the mind to do is a little bit easier for a Restless mind
something else you might do with concentration but you wouldn't do with mindfulness
is to extend the exhale just a little bit
just the way the human physiology is the extended exhales are calming
it's kind of sometimes where we go ah right this guy is a habit but to just
intentionally just very simply extend the exhales a little bit and that might
be a way in which you can work with too much energy another way is to just find a way of
breathing that feels soothing and this might mean bringing in a little
bit of an imagination something that I've heard a Dharma
teacher say is that maybe as if when the mind is quiet pretty settled
but there's still some restlessness so it's settled enough that you can notice the feeling of breathing in your back
you like the or uh the muscles between our ribs move a
little bit when we breathe and including the ribs in the back when the mind is quiet you can like feel that
and you just might you know imagine like it's maybe like somebody that's like uh it's like stroking your back in a way
like a loved one like when we you know we do this like with kids or people that we love we stroke their back
just might notice or like have the breath of this maybe sensation of like
somebody is like soothing touching your back and that can be a way also with
restlessness bringing in a little bit of imagination that's still connected to the sensations of breathing and so we
would apply these antidotes just as a way to kind of help the restlessness settle and when that restlessness has
stopped or settled more then we can come back to more conventional concentration
practices so that's one way to be with the too
much energy if you're doing concentration practices but what if you're doing
you have too little energy and you want to be doing concentration practices it
turns out doing body scans is another way to do it if you're with the breath to shift to body scans so body scans
work with both too much energy and too little energy and part of what can be
the difference is the rate at which you're kind of like doing the scan can help bring the energy up or bring the
energy down for uh to bring up the energy actually
longer inhales just a little bit you know like just I'm not talking about
super long ones but just a tiny bit longer that kind of like brings up kind of like
energize the system energize the body and the mind
or something else same we might do if there's just not enough energy
if we're doing concentration practices is there's a way in which we can open
our awareness really wide
now this is hard to describe if you don't have experience with this but maybe in the same way that if we're
going to do mindfulness of sounds we kind of like open up and but like we're
listening to sounds that are in different places to open up the awareness to be really
big this is something you'll just have to play with it's hard to describe but
because when we're really tired have you noticed this that there's kind of this collapsing right and we're just kind of
there's or just this dark little experience
often with my body too like I can't help myself I there's this with the body is
leaning forward but if you want to bring in more energy to bring up the posture
and have the awareness be really big just something to play around and
explore with
wow so there's I'm saying well because I'm looking at the time
there's a lot I can say here but maybe I want to point to a few things I talked
about how the hindrances can really be working with them or even being aware of
them can really be a support for our life and part of that is
like shifting our relationship to them one way to shift relationships talk
about how or acknowledge that there it's a wide range obvious and subtle
and we can work with them with mindfulness or with concentration
with mindfulness what we learn about the hindrances as we're making it a
meditation object we can bring into our daily life some of the things I talked about for concentration we wouldn't necessarily
but there's something also to notice
that shows up as a hindrance which sometimes we don't even consider it as a hindrance in our meditation practice
that no matter what degree of settledness or collectedness we have
let's say that we we feel pretty good like okay yeah it feels okay
and then there's this way it says yeah but it was better that other time
so there's this way in which there's this little negativity that uh shows up
and I love the way that Rob Barbay describes this this he calls this this a
micro negativity this habit of the Mind and described it he has this simile it
says as if you were a Potter and you're throwing
I don't actually know what the crate words words for this but there's a potter's wheel the wheel's spinning and
you have a lump of clay in the middle and you want to make something you know like a bell or a vase or cut purple or
something so you're working with your hands and if there's just this little
negativity yeah it was better before this is so this is pretty good but
that's like a little bit of pressure and then the pressure gets put on the on
the this piece of clay and it starts the shape starts to change because there's just this slight pressure
so it's really subtle but it really starts to change the experience the
bear would change what's being made so is there a way that we can notice that
this feeling of yes it was better and then maybe do a little bit of a
course correction and lean into any sense of well-being
any sense of contentment any sense of
pleasure any sense of happiness and just attune to that
attuned to any sense of okayness
because also that will shape but it's less of a pressure and a more of
allowing and so I don't know if this analogy really works so it will but I will say that
tuning into any sense of well-being even if it's not your predominant experience even if it's just a portion of your
experience it turns out that it's always a Way
Forward to tune into a sense of well-being okayness happiness contentment is always
a way forward in meditation practice tuning into what's not okay and kind of
awful turns out to be a dead end we have to discover this for ourselves I
mean I'm telling you this right but it's not until you go down that dead end 100 quadrillion bazillion times that you
start to really believe it but I just want to maybe offer this encouragement
sometimes we feel like meditation practice is this dull dreary thing we're
supposed to do and to be sure sometimes it is hard sometimes we come in contact with a lot
of difficulties difficulties arise and it's decidedly unpleasant and sometimes
awful so meditation practice has that those
experiences but even if we could
have a sense of any sense of okayness like oh yeah this really is awful I wish
it weren't like this but if there's any sense of but it is like this
not so it is like this and if we can attune to any sense of
okayness That's the Way Forward
so then maybe I'll end with this
maybe an encouragement that these hindrances they have this
wide range and there's different ways to work with them and to you know notice the obvious and
the subtle one way is to not take them personally
they've been described for thousands of years this is what human beings do
three human being does this is what it means to be human
is to be pushing and pulling and too much energy not enough energy or be
unsure and have vacillation we tend to make up stories because this
is happening I'm a bad meditator but because it's happening it just means you're human
all it means so is there a way that we can shift our
relationship to the hindrances like oh yep okay here it is but the hindrance
has this flavor at this time but this is just what's happening
and can we attune to that Yep this is just what's happening that sentiment and
that'll be part of the way forward okay so I did a lot of talking there
sometimes I talk less for these Monday nights but appreciate your attention
and I'll end there thank you
so we're at the top of the hour so I won't open it up to questions and answers in general but if you like I'm
more than happy to answer some if you'd like to come up here and talk to me otherwise I wish you a nice evening and
safe travels home thank you