foreign hello everyone welcome back
my name is Maria stratman I'm sitting in for Gil for install this week
and just to note early in this sit I thought
I heard what sounds like the beginning of a failing smoke alarm you all know
that those intermittent very loud noises and so my hope is that
it was a fluke but if you hear something don't panic
otherwise we'll just stay here anyway so
um this week we have been talking about blamelessness blamelessness as the
um the antidote to self-criticism self-blame
piling on of things that we do to ourselves about how how we are not succeeding
and we're we're teaching we're thinking of it as blamelessness because it has a little bit more positive vibe to it you
know it's how do we live in the absence of self-criticism
how do we establish the Equanimity of blamelessness this is here this is not here so we
talked about the beginning of the dhamma Pata and I want to just repeat that as we go into this next topic so all
experience is preceded by mind led by mind made by mind
speaker act with a corrupted mind and suffering follows like the wheels of the
cart behind the hose of the ox all experience is preceded by mind made
by mind led by mine made by mind speaker act with a peaceful mind
and happiness follows like a never departing shadow and I repeat that because it's the it's
that final happiness follows part that I find encouraging
that if I can find the peace in my heart always going to be well there's a
there's an element of trust there but today we're going to talk about
doubt doubt is perhaps one of the most Insidious
hindrances to practice and one of the things that most often leads to self-criticism doubt is that is
the undermining the word doubt comes from the Latin word dubitare meaning to hesitate
so we stumble in our practice but also as we hesitate we give the
chance for all kinds of other stories to come in and tell us how it's not going to work so
unlike my usual habit I'm going to begin with a poem and this is this is a Jane hirschfield
poem and it's called My doubt my doubt
I wake doubt beside you like a curtain half open
I dress doubting like a cup undecided if it's been dropped
I eat doubting work doubting go out to a dubious Cafe with skeptical friends
I go to sleep doubting myself as a herd of goats sleep in a suddenly
gone quiet truck I dream you doubt nightly for what is
the meaning of dreaming if not that all we are while inside it is in transient amorphous in question
left hand and right hand doubt you are in me throwing a basketball guiding my knife
in my fork left knee and right knee we run for a bus for a meeting that surely
will end before we arrive I would like to grow content and you doubt as a double-hung window settles
obedient into its hidden pulleys and ropes I doubt I can do so
your own counterweight governs my nights and my days as the knob of hung lead
holds steady the open mouth of a window you hold me my kneeling before you
resistant stubborn offering these Furious praises I can't help but doubt you'll ever be
able to hear me
I doubt everything I doubt this I doubt that I doubt the other I pull it into myself it's my doubt everything about
this poem epitomizes the nature of doubt and the and the truly
undermining aspects of it once we begin doubting We Begin we hold on to that
doubt and it becomes something that guides it well I can't believe uh why can't I believe that I can't
believe that
it often arises when our desired outcome is not realized hey we have an idea it's like we make a a deal with Universe if I
sit every day then I'm going to have marvelous insights and I'm going to be a kind person and
as if as if just because I want it to be this
way it should be this way and if it's not this way
well it actually happens is we suffer but we're very used to as humans trying
to find out the cause of what is endangering us what is threatening us
what makes me feel not safe and then we have this myth that we
should be able to fix that and then when we can't fix that doubt
arises well okay it's my method so we begin to doubt practice we begin
to doubt that I know how to do it we begin to doubt the teachers we begin to well it must be the the chair I'm
sitting on or the cushion I'm sitting on we we throw up reasons
why we're not realizing the outcome we desire and we're missing we're missing the fact
that what we're suffering from is simply things not being the way we
want them we want things to be other than they are
which always gives rise to suffering but not only do we want things to be
other than they are but we think we have responsibility for that we think that it's our job to make sure
that we're happy hold on just a second here
we're perhaps least happy when we don't know why something is true
I'm gonna have to clear my throat
we think we know why we need to know why something is happening so we can fix it so we can shape it so we can control it
we can make it what we need it to be what we want it to be and if that doesn't happen
doubt Creeps in that that little note that says oh if I
were better if this were different ah but it's not happening
it's not happening and so and so we come to a conclusion
the uncertainty is so uncomfortable for us it must be that we're doing something
wrong it must be that this job is wrong it must be that this person is wrong
because I have to have something to blame I have to blame something I have to
blame myself if I can't find anything else to blame I blame me
where we find ourselves is in a place where we're trying to find out
why am I thinking this why is this here
and it Digs at us and it Digs at us and we begin to dig into it what is
happening here what is happening here and everything seems to shift and nothing I do seems to work out I'm
probably just going to be late anyway if we could say ah
I'm probably going to be late and stop
oh late you know sometimes I find myself in my car and I'm late because I've tried to
put one more thing in and I find myself gripping the steering wheel and leaning forward and I remind
myself I can't get there any faster than the car and I sit back
this is how we deal with doubt it's ah doubt uh-huh
and we come to realize that doubt like everything else arises and passes away
it's just that in the midst of doubt we doubt that we know that
we don't everything
what we need to do is think about what are the thoughts we're investing in
would we investing our energy in so when doubt arises for me
I think okay I'm doubting I'm doubting yeah curiously this morning when I was
thinking about okay what what's going to be the centerpiece of the talk this morning
I began to doubt that I'd be able to come up with anything that was going to be interesting or new to say about it
and I felt that that creeping sense of oh no oh no oh no
and I said oh yes I'm quite familiar with this it's just doubt
and unless I give doubt the rains if I give doubt if I reify
doubt if I make it a thing it's just doubt
it's just down it doesn't have to mean anything
it's just doubt
sometimes we forget that thoughts are empty they're just thoughts
the ability to be in the presence of Doubt is something that we cultivate and
we cultivate it by surviving it for one thing and we say oh well
yesterday I was so full of doubt today I'm not certain but
huh it doesn't feel as strong as it did or in that last moment I felt down I
thought oh no oh no I don't know how to do this
the reason I began with the dhamma Pate again is because I wanted to emphasize that it's really what's going on in the
mind that is creating the condition that leads to doubt
what are the thoughts that we're grabbing onto are we grabbing on to all the times when things didn't work
are we willing to take a risk it really comes down to a sense of safety
can I feel safe even if I am full of doubt
well It's Tricky it's hard to hold those things together
we don't we're not comfortable with the uncertainty of doubt
but we don't have to be comfortable we don't have to be comfortable
we don't even have to be doubt free we just have to
come up with that little piece of faith that says I'll wait and see what happens
I'll wait and see what happens it's like stepping out of the room when you're angry or when you're confused or when
you find yourself out of touch just pause and say doubt
doubt learn what doubt feels like so that you can recognize and not be
surprised by it when it shows up in your life to not get so far into thinking about
doubt that you're down in the pit before you say oh that feels like doubt
it feels like doubt so then you watched out and you say ah doubt looks like this it has this kind of shape this is what
it does with me the interesting thing that I have discovered
is when I am most full of Doubt when I'm most uncertain when I'm certain that the
teacher is wrong and the place is wrong and I'm wrong and I'll never sometimes
in the middle of retreat I'll discover I've forgotten how to meditate totally just can't meditate I don't even
remember what it means I'm so lost and I'm very happy in those moments
because what I realize is something's about to happen when I am most full of doubt
my experiences not what I believe about it my experiences when I am most full of doubt
something is about to happen it's rather like I I think I told this
story to you the other day but I'm not certain maybe it was in the question and answer I was talking about fear and
being on the side of the mountain and and having to call it fear and instead we're trying to talk myself out of it I
said fear I'm afraid what am I afraid of I'm afraid of falling off the mountain
the only thing you can be sure of is you can't stay here
and the realizing that you can't stay here
freeze you it gets to the place where you can say oh I wonder what's going to happen
as soon as you open yourself up to the Curiosity of I wonder you're you break
the bonds of the doubt that says I know I can't rely on
and you have the beginning of confidence which by the way
is one of the first of the five faculties for a spiritual practice is the development of faith and confidence
it is the backside of doubt every time you come out of a moment of
doubt every time that moment rejoice and
realize ah one more tip for confidence one more tick for trust
one more tick for I'm safe just with me
I'm safe it'll be okay
what will be okay is I'm still here not that it's going to be the outcome that I
want not that I'm going to come and give this talk and be amazingly brilliant
but that I will be here the intention will be here
the thoughts will be here the heart will be here this is what I can rely on
in the midst of everything else I am still here
no requirements for how I'm here just here
from this blamelessness Rises
where I stop expecting something I stop expecting something of myself and I'm
simply here still here despite everything still here
we don't have to give up everything we don't have to be brilliant we don't have
to be wise we just have to realize
the is-ness of just being here
I don't have to believe anything I can just experience this
this is enough this is enough
for now all the other expectations can come after that
there was a I read an article the other day by Dan Harris in the New York Times and he is the guy that has uh 10 happier
podcast which is Buddhist related and he talked about visiting with Adam a lot of llama recently and
his struggle with the word uh selfish that all practice seems somewhat selfish
and the the dominata said sorry ah
Dalai Lama said you know it's wise to practice wise selfishness
and I thought about that and said you know this is the point at which the doubt am I doing this right am I doing
it wrong why is selfishness why is the tension to just this
and then from here I reconnect with my intention from here I take just the next
step and see what happens
just see what happens thank you
so hopefully that is useful
and if you have any questions I'd be happy to entertain them
hey thank you very much Maria that's a lot to chew on and I'm sure if anyone
has any questions uh you can go ahead and in YouTube uh post them in chat and
we'll try and get to as many as we can and in Zoom if you want to post them in chat or raise your hand
you can do so as well okay we've got Stuart oh right on the
line so Stuart go ahead and uh um unmute yourself and
hi hi thanks that was very helpful very encouraging talk
but while you were talking about doubt I found myself substituting the word worry for that I'm
just wondering if what you're saying about that applies equally to worry
they're very similar aren't they now worry is doubting the outcome that you desire you know you can you can
substitute the words one for the other you can also look at it as there are
lots of elements to worry but it is the uh it is the fear that
what I wish to be true turns out not to be true and in doubt it is the fear that all of
my best wishes don't come true don't aren't
realized so down and worry are very very similar they have a
they they both have the the quality of
wanting wanting wanting leaning into something I want and
and the fear the fear that I can't have it and it comes down to the fear
in the end for that form of Doubt so I would call worry a form of Doubt so yeah
I think it's very very similar thank you and the the the antidote is
also very similar okay right now this is what's true right now
this thank you
Marie we have a this is not a question but it's more uh a
uh a comment from YouTube uh LG uh says one of my favorite things
from aam assuming that's Alcoholics Anonymous is don't quit five minutes before the
miracle would give me space from doubt and an invitation for patience
um and uh I don't know if anyone's familiar with the the book The Dip this kind of sounds something
similar to that you know don't quit before the payoff comes
uh so
it's doubt is full-blown I realize something is about to happen for me
uh so that is a wonderful quote yeah don't don't quit right before the payoff
um yeah I I I once experienced an entire
month of a Persian in a retreat and I uh
because of that I doubted everything I doubted the teachers I'd doubted the place I was at Spirit Rock I was never
going to go back to Spirit Rock again it was a terrible place the teachers were all horrible I was just in the pit and I
did that for the entire month and the only virtue of the whole thing was that I became very familiar with aversion and
doubt and I know what they feel like and what they the shape of them are and and that experience allows me to see it more
easily when it arises so you know if all else fails just see what
you can learn from that from from being there with that
so uh next and uh Patron
thanks Patrick um thank you this this very timely for
me or maybe always as Timely um I experienced doubt constantly all the
time and I sense when I'm like more Curious that it has a lot to do with recognizing that
I have no control and recognizing that things are subject to change and unsatisfactoriness and and
all these things and that maybe there's some part of me that's fighting that reality or trying to protect me from it
like well if I just like really really question everything I'm doing maybe I'll come up
with like the solution the the thing that is like uh in like
is not affected by change and and you know things falling apart
um and and I think as I get older I've Just Seen Cycles happen so many times I've
seen myself go like yes this is the thing like this is the way and and then
it's like black and then coming back around and so seeing these cycles and
and and so what I sense is that there's somewhere deeper to reach or a sense of
of faith and groundedness um as we say about taking Refuge but I
often find that hard because I feel it very much in my body it's really a like nervous system kind of like fear
um so I don't really I'm trying to get to the question in this it's something about like how to how to work with um
with doubt in the body and like
what is the anchor that um that helps
just sort of let doubt be there but draw from something deeper to find a deeper
source of of um of Faith or or confidence in just
being a human and whatever might come from that yeah so
uh so if you were listening to you if you were listening you might come to the place where you'd
say oh that must be so painful
and if you were listening to you you would you would feel that piece of tenderness in yourself
that place that seems so
Raw and you would recognize it
and you would say oh I'm sorry that you feel that
and you would be cognizant of the compassion that that has generated in you
and doubt is very far from that one of the difficulties we have with
doubt is that we try to work it out in our heads we try to to analyze it and
and shape it and find some reason some other way of explaining so that doubt is
not so prevalent but what doubt actually feels like in the body has to do with what is the
trigger that is giving rise to doubt
what is what is the center fear so it is in fact in going deeper and
deeper and deeper into that place of rawness
that we evoke something else from ourselves we evoke the peaceful heart
that doesn't support doubt and we're able to say as painful and as
tender as this spot is for me I wish myself well here
is it it's a form of giving in and not
fighting the doubt that the struggle against doubt
stimulates doubt it stimulates the corrupted heart it keeps it stirred
up I'm fighting doubt I'm fighting doubt I no doubt is is undermining me
if I can stop fighting and say what is it that's being hurt what is it that's making me feel unsafe
here and look there then doubt doesn't have a home
does it come down to of fear of
existence does it come down to a fear of not being loved
does it come down to a fear of space
what what is what is that point of tenderness in my body you can only find
it in your body in the head you can do all their their arguments
they're just arguments and you know the strongest arguer wins today
but it doesn't doesn't change
it doesn't change the heart and the heart is where the doubt lies
not in the mind the mind just explains it so
so say what else is here until you get to the place that is raw
and then allow that to be true
say I see you I see that that fundamental fear I see that
and I would wish it was not here but it is here and I am still here this person
right now here
okay thank you so much
you've got a question from YouTube from um
I think it's see if I can find it here
um so on YouTube someone is asking uh can you please talk a bit about the
connection between the sense of being safe and being present
and the courage to be vulnerable in presence
okay so uh that's similar to the exercise I just went through the discussion I just
went through but what what uh what I've discovered
so I'm only speaking from my experience is that
when I am doubtful I remind myself that the doubt arises out of actually not
knowing the outcome and that it is uncertainty and ambiguity
and that that means I don't know the outcome
it could be pleasant or unpleasant could be good or bad it could be successful or
not success and in the end it will be
and what am I afraid of and so
it turns out for me that in order to realize my intentions
in life it has become extremely important to become familiar with allowing myself to be vulnerable
doesn't mean I put myself in unsafe situations in the sense that the the their life life-threatening but I show
up in a space that that says here I am
I hope it's enough and it is enough for me so it's a little like
uh what what I've discovered is that the the safest place for me is to be totally
present that's the safest because I'm not trying
to be something other than me which is an extra layer of suffering an extra layer of being
and so the the the essence of that statement I am here is the I am here
this person is here as I am today with all of my strengths
and failings and uncertainties In This Moment under these conditions
this is I'm just here
and open to you feel okay about that or you don't
feel okay about that and I may alter what I say to you based on what the
feedback I get for you it's not as if I'm isolated in that showing up at all
it just means that I am willing to be affected by what happens next
I'm willing to be affected by what happens next there's a willingness in that showing up
and the willingness and and it means that sometimes you get hurt
and sometimes you say oh that wasn't expected
and then you Marvel at how that wasn't expected
but it involves staying at that place of of the peaceful heart try to stay there
try to try to have that and when it feels tense
back away from that let that let that not occupy you
it's the best I can do with that one I hope it helps
so our questions great thank you Marie uh Susan Sanford
you can go ahead and unmute yourself hi
um thank you so much for this week it's wonderful I'm noticing how
my um I would call my superego or my critic
um uses doubt um to
like it's a hook like to limit my practice so I will
it'll say well you may as well not even go to that Retreat because you know you're not gonna get any further anyway you know so
there it's like this kind of and then and then it that leads into
sloth and laziness you know like well I may as well not even practice
I may as well not even meditate because I'm not any good at it anyway
so there's this constant um way that
that I used doubt it's a reactive doubt preemptive doubt
I'm gonna I'm Gonna Save myself from being disappointed by just not going there yeah when I when I was a teenager I
decided that life was so horrible that I was not going to have any expectations
because then if I didn't have expectations I couldn't be disappointed this is very similar to that I adopted
it as yeah this is how I'm going to go through life I'm not going to have any expectations and then what I discovered is I also didn't have any dreams
it was nothing wonderful to anticipate either that it was really self-defeating yeah
which isn't you know I don't want to make light of it I mean I understand preemptive doubt trust me I go through
this uh I have an exercise class that's really beyond my capability and but I go
and I I'm exhausted afterward and sometimes I'm in great pain afterward and and I have so much resistance to
going and but I know I'm I'm stronger and I'm better for doing it but it isn't
until I actually get there and start working out that I feel like I should be there it's I overcome the doubt by
saying well I really don't know and I use the discipline of effort to
get me over the hump it's it's the is this wise effort
part of the Eightfold Path there's a place effort has a place that says you know you just have to not give up
because if you give up you can't do it doubt is the thing that says oh who says
yeah who says and you know
like I said I went on that month-long Retreat and it was horrible and you know who would want to do that again and it
was yeah later in retrospect that I looked back on it and said wow I learned
so much about that at the time I'm not even sure why I stayed the whole month
and subsequent Retreats have been quite different all the retweets are different and you know this also every Retreat is
different and I always have anticipation before I go because I don't know what's
going to show up and that can be frightening not everything I discovered was wonderful
yeah and they're always really difficult they can be
pretty much so far they always are but then that usually at the end they're like oh yeah like they're always open
you know there's always amazing openness always an opening yeah
I'm still here damn it
I'm I'm just gonna do it yeah there's
the inertia of Doubt can be very strong just inertia
you don't have to follow it you don't have to be there with it you don't have to say this is mine right
oh that's a dirty trick just yes name it
oh thank you go to retreat
anything else we're going pretty late I hate to hold up all the uh all our teams so
is uh are people generally okay here yeah I think uh I'm fine so um there's
there's actually another question off of YouTube um and a person asks Maria is it is
doubt to some degree another form of inquiry or is it more of a negation or fear
now is it a result of inquiry is that the question another form of inquiry or
is it more of a negation or fear yeah uh doubt okay so there is a
the doubt of inquiry is the one that says
do I see this clearly and it's in the the inquiry has a
different energy than the doubt that I've been describing which is is more of a hesitation than a stopping so if I
have a doubt that I understand something well then it is wise for me to question
what's that about what's that about what's that about and there is a form of doubt that can be that I can
have for example uh in in the example that we just explored
with Susan when she said well you know I I it may is probably not going to have a
good outcome anyway then establishing a and well I wonder what could happen
is is a form of inquiry it's sort of questioning your own doubt is a form of
inquiry so they're not exactly the same one can say for example here's another
example so uh when I read Buddhism for 25 years before I ever sat on a cushion
I loved the ethical path of Buddhism but I was particularly stopped by the idea
of non-self because I was pretty sure I had a self it was a very strong personality and it made no sense to me
but it was and so I I asked about it and asked about and asked about and and it
wasn't until I was actually sitting on the cushion that I came to understand the meaning of not self which was not to
deny that there's a person here at all but rather that there's an unchanging person here and then I know exactly
what's going to happen and so it was the inquiry that was inherent in actually sitting on the cushion and allowing
curiosity for the answer and not not the form of inquiry that says I'm
going to prove you wrong but the form of inquiry that says I wonder what
so doubt is that I'm going to prove you round or wrong part the spirit of
inquiry is I'm going to see what's true all of Buddhism you should not believe a
word I say you should accept it with a a grain of belief that
says well that sounds like it's working for her let me see if it works for me if
that has value for me it it's the belief that comes out of experience Buddhism is
totally reliant on that I hope that answers that
sounds like a healthy skepticism
so it's it's not non-believing it's an open an openness to what may be true
that we as we strive for
thank you all for the earnestness of your questions of your showing up thank
you for your practice the world is a better place for that we offer that our practice for the
benefit of all see you tomorrow