so good morning everyone and welcome from
imc's Insight Retreat Center and
and welcome also to this week where the topic is compassion
so these guided meditations are related to that or pointing towards that or laying down
the foundation for it so someone says they hear a very loud hiss
and I wonder if other people are you hearing ecstatic or hiss or
that's a problem or is it maybe that person's device
and uh so no his no hiss okay
there someone says yes yes to his no static yes well
some people have a hiss and some don't yes it's loud it's a
so no his interesting um some people might have that volume
turned up louder because they need to hear better and um we could try to try to do something
right we could try to change back to them which one
so we're going to try to turn something back here um if you
we turn the two back to the to the Mac or to the country's
to MacBook so let's see if this works better
and uh so um
okay so now is the hiss there I have to wait
better better better no hiss great okay so we're all using these new
devices here and trying to figure out how to make them all connect nicely
so maybe we'll start over
so then welcome you again to Insight Retreat
Center where I'm teaching this week and um I feel I feel very kind of uh
I don't know what the right word is cozy comforted with the topic for this week it has to do with compassion
and um uh the
and these morning meditations this week that are meant to be kind of a foundation for compassion that supports
it so for this day I want to emphasize calm
and to say that there's always a choice maybe it's not easy to find the choice
but there's always a choice to have a certain kind of calm when we meditate
in the calm I want to emphasize today is calm awareness calm recognition
come feeling what's going on sensing what's happening
calm observing what's happening there's some capacity in the different
forms of awareness that we use in this mindfulness practice to let that become
even if it were being aware of is agitation
so there's there's a moment a place a little location somewhere in the field
of in the place where we're from that that is calmly recognizes agitation
so if there's a recognition then the mind would either verbally or
in some or Silent Way would have a clear but calm recognition agitation
agitation is present they um
the if there is um discomfort anywhere
we would recognize discomfort if the if the place of calm awareness is
a little bit more embodied like it almost feels like this feeling the body
can sense and feel discomfort or agitation then feel that with the calm
that's the place of for them to mindfulness if there's more a sense of being The
Observer a little bit removed from the experience stepping back in a sense and
just observing that's and that's where calm is then take that backward step and observe the experience
if it's most common to be intimate with the experience really close in then really touch the experience softly
maybe likely but really be close if it's more calm to step back and have a bird's
eye view of it then um the
the do that so see if you can experiment with whatever is happening to have a
calm awareness so assuming an upright posture
and gently closing your
your eyes
foreign
to just be aware of how you are calmly
is there some way of just matter-of-factly recognizing how you are
in the most obvious way that is calm
a calm knowing
a calm sensing
and with that calmness be aware of your breathing
and now take a maybe two or three long slow deep breaths
relaxing as you exhale
settling in
then letting your breathing return to normal
and settle into your breathing becoming aware of your breathing
and if your breathing is in any way uncomfortable
be calmly aware of the discomfort the uncomfortable
breathing maybe without having a need for it to be
any different way
if your breathing is comfortable easeful
know that calmly
if if there is discomfort in your body
it's tense or aches in some way hurts
know that calmly
and this calm knowing calm awareness
might be fleeting it might just last a moment or two with
and let yourself be content with that that's enough
and then do it again
if you're if your mind is uncomfortable you're agitated with your thoughts
know that calmly
calm recognition this is how it is
if you have emotions which are challenging you who are uncomfortable
know that calmly a Tranquility of awareness
as you're aware of your breathing finding a way to be calmly aware
maybe even comingly aware aware so something
becomes more peaceful tranquil
if you're agitated be aware of that calmly
being aware in a way in a way that is calming for yourself
as you're aware of breathing Body Mind
whatever you're aware of if you can be aware of it calmly
lightly
can you find in the middle of that or next to it
some care some motivation or imposter care or have compassion
the simplest form of compassion for now it doesn't need to do anything
Who air with calm compassion
where with tranquil love even of what is difficult Here and Now
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to consider for a moment or field for a moment
The Compassion that might be a companion of calm or tranquility
a Compassion or love that has no room when the mind is
agitated in a hurry reactive
the simplest form of care
and if you were going to live this day with care with compassion
that came from being calm calm compassion compassionate calmness
how might you live your day differently
how might you live your day informed
by a calm love calm compassion
compassionate calm
would you live differently if you were informed by Compassion Care
love or kindness
live differently in their small details of your life
who are in the large
areas of your life
and may our care for the world somehow be carried out into the world
on these World these words may all beings
be happy may all beings be saved
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free [Music]
thank you
[Music] thank you
foreign
so the topic of this week is the seven factors of compassion
and how these seven factors follow in the wake of compassion that we live in a
compassionate way and we find that in the wake of that or together with that
there comes a form of awareness mindfulness there comes a
a quality of investigation that we do kind of distinguish
and for compassion we distinguish between suffering and the absence of suffering in all the different ways that
we call you know distress or feeling emotionally challenged or things are
difficult that um compassion is based on the recognition
of suffering whether it's mild or big it's a recognition
and that recognition involves a distinction between the
suffering and the possibility of the absence of suffering and so with this come with Compassionate
Care um there becomes a sense of awareness or
attention to what's happening because compassion is you know is has an
object or has a way of living or a way of attending to the world
and then um and part of that attending is to make of is the compassionate nature of
compassion is to see a distinction between suffering and the absence of it
and this is the fundamental distinction that Buddhism is about it lives and it grows and develops and
flowers out of making this distinction because with this distinction it's possible to move towards greater and
greater Freedom greater absence of suffering freedom from suffering
and so it's there is a deeper and a more more sensitive attention to suffering
when we do this practice and some of the coarser suffering might go
away but it becomes a more acute sensitivity to smaller and smaller or deeper and deeper ways and that's not a
mistake that's the way of doing house cleaning to kind of clean the house and and
clean things up in a sense with that distinction and so all of
Buddhism can be seen as a rising out of the impetus to compassion it's so
Central to the whole Enterprise of Buddhism the whole religion of Buddhism and sometimes that compassion takes the
form of kindness and friendliness or they're they're kind of part of a mixture of care
and so sometimes it's not exactly compassion that's in the Forefront but kindness the friendliness
a sense of care for people for ourselves as this uh unfolds then there's a we see
the distinction between suffering and the absence of it then comes effort
comes the desire to do something to make a change so from this guided meditation we did
um the change there that was emphasized was that becoming calmly aware
so we can suffer and we can just kind of suffer unapologetically just you know just be
living in the suffering really kind of captivated by our
suffering fully inhabiting it or we could in a sense step away from it
and be aware of it calmly it involves a little bit of disidentification with the suffering
like it's my suffering and I'm suffering but to step away and say oh they're suffering here
and to calmly be aware and then that calm awareness
to see it more clearly and one of the things we see we see that
they're suffering and there's something which is not suffering so much the calm awareness
that's an important distinction and with that distinction we then were
able to choose more often that which is not suffering the calm awareness it's not getting rid of the suffering
it's not still there it's not just fixing it it's not
condemning it's not ignoring it but if it's meeting it from a place where we're
not identified with it or we're not kind of glued to it and this is a powerful thing of
compassion this ability to see clearly and calmly if the compassion is not calm it might
not really be compassion it might be distress that we're feeling so the importance of finding that calm
place is not easy to do but it's worthwhile to do and it's possible to do
and maybe the for some of us the easiest place might be in the mindfulness itself
in the awareness itself so the mindfulness factor of compassion
with the mindful inspector factor of compassion we see these distinction better between suffering and the absence
of it we see a kind of a distinction there just a with that as we start seeing this
distinction and the possibility of being without suffering then comes the effort the effort factor
of compassion the the engagement the activity of
moving towards or coming close to or giving yourself giving ourselves over to
that place where there is less suffering to do that which decreases the suffering
and for if we kind of build on what's Happening already a place of less suffering is not getting
rid of the suffering but is a heightened at impact capacity for attention
awareness can kind of Blossom become stronger while the
suffering is there and maybe the suffering doesn't get any better
but mindfulness awareness gets stronger which creates a very different context
as awareness gets stronger then maybe we can identify or live more in the
awareness than we live in this suffering so it's a very significant thing to say
that the suffering doesn't have to go away it's being it's being replaced in a
sense or the Ecology of the Mind heart is being changed but we're bringing in
something that's stronger or larger more significant to be next to it or be part of it or be
around it and that's the capacity to be aware to wake up to the middle of it
and um and uh and to be able to shift the paradigm
from needing to get rid of suffering to becoming bigger than the suffering or
become resting in a place where it's peaceful to look on the suffering that's
a radical thing to do so that's living this this the investigation Factor the distinction
factor of compassion and then the natural effort to engage to
activity to keep practicing to do something about it so yesterday I used the example of a
little girl who's got hurt on the playground with a scraped knee and there's compassion in the adult
who's going to care for her and of course the adult puts effort into care for the child it brings the
Band-Aid brings the the water to clean the wound and does it very carefully and
the engagement is one of care and love but it is engagement it is effort being put in
but that effort doesn't feel like work The Compassion is is a motivating force
for a relaxed easy maybe in a certain kind of way non-self-centered
effort an effort that's here to make things better
and part of the difficulty people have with the concept of effort is some people make effort which has suffering
embedded in it they're straining they're pushing they're expecting their
anxious they're disappointed they're hesitant they're
feel hopeless in the effort what is it so then we come back to this
whole compassion oh there's the suffering be mindful suffering is in the effort
itself part of the reason to make effort is to
discover how the effort is off and then to see that distinction and
then in the seeing of it began in kind of finding a way engaging in a process
the engaging the effort to find effort that is calm find effort that is engaged
but not agitated find effort which is engaged in doing what needs to be done but has
no strain in it that's caring that's loving that's present
so the suggestion is that um this is a natural
in the wake of compassion in the wake of caring and it was feeling
a sense of care for something in the wake of kindness feeling kindness for
something in the wake of love feeling love for something that there is starting to make
distinctions the investigation Factor and from that comes a certain kind of
effort so um
and they're the big efforts would be to go out and save the world to go out and really trying to help someone who's
suffering that's a beautiful thing to do an important thing to do but maybe as an as a way of uh kind of
really discovering the compassion informed effort
that includes compassion for oneself compassion for the very effort we make
maybe today we should not be in a hurry to be compassionate for the world but
have the compassion really be towards yourself uh to to these factors to not even to
yourself but to the particular ways in which your mind hearts are operating
in the way that you're aware are you aware in a way that's stressful
or demanding or expectant uh or can you be aware in a calm way
are you making distinctions are you seeing the challenges you have but building on that challenges or you're
judging yourself and being upset with things or can you find a way to see that
making simple distinctions between suffering and the absence of it really is a path to Freedom
and then as you engage in this practice and practice with all this the effort part
have compassion or care for that can you recognize there where there's strain and suffering
to do this very personal work sets the stage for
bringing a healthy form of compassion into the world and for others so we're laying down the foundation here
so um thank you and um
and I'll be here for the week at the IRC so I'm happy to be here and as I said uh yesterday I think I look
forward to the chance to show you the meditation Hall on maybe the last day here and we can zoom out a little bit
and scan it for you to see let's see what's here so thank you