Welcome to our teacher James Morrison James Morrison was ordained as a
Buddhist monk in the Thai Forest tradition and live with meditation Masters in Thailand for 15 years
for the last 12 years he has also practiced at his property in the Santa Cruz mountains the Redwood Hermitage
James has now retired from his life as a monk but is continuing to teach the
dhamma he has inherited from his teachers currently he is staying at his
peaceful Hermitage surrounded by redwood trees others are welcome to join him
spending time on individual Retreat experiencing the Tranquility Beauty and
simplicity of nature welcome James
good all right
foreign
so this morning I'm coming on the way to give a talk on overcoming worry and as I
say a funny thing happened to me on the way to the meditation center so the car
the vehicle I'm driving in uh suddenly has a rear tire blowout
and uh and made it here just in time so
another good dhamma lesson in being able to be prepared for overcoming worry
about anything that might go wrong in the future and uh fortunately uh Nancy
responded with uh calm collected and she saved the day by
getting me here in time
so today I want to talk a bit about worry as a mental state and how it you
know what it is how it affects our life and more specifically what are some
strategies that we can use to to overcome that I lived in New Zealand for a long time
and the classic saying there is hey no worries mate
you know it's their way of saying everything's fine you know it's no problem no worries mate
but it's a lot easier to say than than actually have a mind that's free of
worry and just understanding what worry is and why it's uh such a stubborn uh unhelpful
mental state yeah it's basically fear basically fear that something is going
to go wrong in the future now the thing about worry is that even if everything's
perfect right now everything could be perfect right now like every need and desire met
still we can ruin it by worrying about the future worrying about now
everything's great I might lose it then we start to worry and so if
worrying becomes a habit then will never really be able to enjoy
our life even if everything is wonderful because
worrying doesn't allow us to to be joyfully present we'll be thinking about the future and all the things that
possibly could go wrong and one of the things about worry is
that because it is concerned with the future
and the future is unknown it's basically infinite you could worry
about anything and it's really only limited by the the
scope of our imagination so if you have a good imagination and a tendency towards sometimes worry
it's just you can imagine kind of any scenario and think yeah you know whether
it's realistic or completely unrealistic you could think yeah yeah that could happen what about that what if that
happens so that's that's a terrible way to live
right and it really does make it very difficult just to enjoy life you know
even when everything is actually pretty good now as we know there are realistic
dangers or things that could go wrong in life absolutely and I always sometimes
going to have things happen in the future that we don't want or that are unpleasant absolutely
but there's no there's no reason why we can't live
in peace and relative contentment in the present knowing that will happen in the
future a wise monk once said
if there's a problem and there's a solution then you just apply the solution and no
need to worry and if there's a problem and there's no solution then
why worry
so you realize yeah why is it that with all of the drawbacks of worrying you
know it's exhausting it can be mentally exhausting it can be physically exhausting it really doesn't allow us to
to be present doesn't certainly doesn't allow us to fully enjoy what we have
then why is it that it's so difficult to let go of
it's because like unlike many other mental States or negative mental States worry is often conflated with wholesome
qualities such as care love or maybe even just being a responsible person
as if we're not worrying about something if we're not worrying about a person if
we're not worrying about our children or our parents or partner then it's as if
we don't care it's like it's it's almost saying you're a bad parent if you're not worrying
about your child uh or if you're not worried about your
future people think something wrong with you you're not being responsible you know
learn how to grow up and be dour and worrying about about the future like
everybody else so to be able to to to separate
the wholesome qualities from the unwholesome qualities you know it's not always easy but it's essential say yes we want to be loving
and caring how do we do that without falling into the the darker side of of
worrying yeah a worrying as an expression we think somehow is
expression of Love Actually no it will be able to love and care much more fully
if we're not worrying right so being able to begin to see how
these are not the same thing and separate them out and the same thing with taking responsibility there are so many ways
that obviously we we do need to take responsibility for many things in our life things that are
maybe conducive to worry Financial worries Health worries they go together
Health Care finances just all manner of of things that we may
need to to look into and take care of in our life
but applying the solution or taking responsibility for something
doesn't mean that we have to worry about it especially uh if wording just becomes a
habit then maybe the same repeating thought can just be cycling around over and over again and it
becomes very counterproductive so then how do you actually
stop worrying it's not like we can just say you know worrying is is
counterproductive I'm just going to stop because if it's an entrenched habit
and if we're not fully aware of what's going on it has a lot of momentum and it will
just keep going and going and going so it's not just a matter of yeah I'm
going to stop worrying but then before we know it you know it starts cycling through our
mind again so I can give you uh some good
strategies to work with that and then that will that will be a start to put it into
practice and then you can apply these I'll call them four very helpful strategies to any situation where we
might be worrying whether it's worrying about a loved one uh worrying about situation at work
worrying about the future of our finances we're you know it's just endless amounts of things that we
possibly could worry about so any subject you can apply these four
basic principles so the first we should be fairly familiar with is
clear awareness right you just have to start by knowing
when worry is present it's so Insidious if it becomes like a like a default
position of our minds that uh there's an underlying uh anxiety about the future
underlying feeling of insecurity you know like something's not right
things could fall apart at any second which is kind of realistic too but
the the fear is the problem right if that becomes
a basic underlying default position of our minds
then we need to see that clearly
right and and not just accept that as a reality or as what's normal
so clearly seeing worry when it's present
right just watching and noticing as soon as it arises
now in order to understand worry you don't have to bring it up
if your mind if you're looking at your mind and you're free of worry
fantastic enjoy that and really pay attention like
close attention to a mind that is free of worry
because it's intrinsically Pleasant it feels peaceful it feels content even if
it's just for a few seconds right just clearly notice the mind that's free of
worry because our minds will naturally incline towards
that which is Pleasant if we just give it the right information
now if we're not paying attention to our mind when it's free of worry we're only paying attention to the thoughts that
are conducive to worry are giving fuel to it then those thoughts
worry fueling thoughts become our entire reality
so if we pay attention to also that when our mind is calm or
quiet or at least free of worry then what we pay attention to will
become stronger and our minds will incline towards that because it's intrinsically Pleasant it's peaceful
so you don't have to bring up worry there's plenty of times that worry will
arise by itself you don't have to bring it up in order to understand it
but when it does arise notice his presence but then also notice
what preceded that if you can without getting caught up in the the story within the thoughts just
notice what preceded that and then notice its presence
and then notice if you're just watching it eventually it will stop so notice the cessation
and then when it ceases pay close attention to that that mind which is is free at least temporarily
not worrying
so the second of these four strategies is developing a
a wisdom in action a reflection trying to understand the nature of what
worry is the nature of fear how it how it arises how it affects our
life and essentially the subjects about which we might be
worrying about if we truly understand the nature of
things we're not going to worry it's only because we have
unreal unrealistic expectations
because we identify with certain things
if we don't understand the the true nature of something then
of course it leads to a certain delusion around it and that is conducive to all
sorts of unwholesome mental States but particularly worry
so if you understand things if you understood reality
very clearly you would not worry and it's not a question of everything going
right in your life to be free of worry right after the Buddha was enlightened
he had so many difficult uh things happen in his life
managing the Sangha his cousin tried to kill them numerous times things that probably most of us
don't even have to deal with and yet as far as we know the Buddha never worried about it he never worried
his mind would not go to worry so it's not a question of getting everything externally perfect
it's not like it's not like you know if you're sitting on a a beach at a at an exotic Resort
surrounded by the perfect family the drink in your hand they think oh that's definition of freedom of worry
but freedom from worry but the reality is
unfortunately a lot of people at places like that are worrying about their
business so worrying about their family they're just unable to fully enjoy even when everything is externally
perfect it's really a matter of internal work
so understanding the nature of whatever it is that we're worrying about
right you can use kind of active reflection if it's uh a personal relationship for example
we're worried about another person or a relationship with another person
understanding that yes every relationship is is uh temporary subject to cessation
constantly changing it's going to end someday most
things in life are out of our control right
if we can be at peace with those things then that alleviates a lot of sources of
worry about understanding things correctly so I mean that's a big subject in and of
itself or how we identify with with people
we can identify with other people's bodies and Minds
as if somehow they belong to us right even just the the phrasing that we use
you know my partner my children my parents my my dog whatever
right if we identify with something then there's a certain amount of possessiveness wish to control it or
almost like we think we have the right to control it if it's ours
and so challenging that that's unrealistic I mean other people and things don't
actually belong to us in the big picture and even this body in this mind is
mainly out of our control to say nothing of other people's bodies and Minds
so using wisdom to be able to reflect and understand the nature of of people
and relationships and and how we relate and essentially how we perceive others
you know the reality we create through perceptions that are projected out
if we understand that more clearly then we realize it's really nothing to worry about right
things may happen in the future that are unpleasant
so so what right things have happened our whole life sometimes that are
unpleasant have we made it through have we survived is it sometimes difficult sure but we make it through
the future will probably be the same this is how you take the the energy or
the strength of any kind of fear and and uh
just look at the fear and challenge it and say if that actually happens
would I still be able to survive continue uh
uh grow sometimes even its most difficult situations which where we grow
the most and if we can be at peace with the the
the subject of what we're worrying about the scenario the realistic or unrealistic
then it takes all of the energy away from that that fear
it's like it doesn't have the power to control us anymore
but it's it's difficult to develop wisdom if our minds are very scattered and
agitated so leads to the next the third recommended strategy which is meditative
calm it is uh
it's so helpful to be able to develop this skill
right even if you're sitting meditation today and it feels like most of the time you
weren't Mindful and most of the time you were thinking still even if you have
a short amount of time during meditation or throughout the day where you feel
mindful present centered grounded even if you can just
take a few deep breaths before your mind starts to spin out
again that's good that's a start that's the it's a skill that we all have the
ability to develop and generally wisdom will go as deep as
our level of meditative calm
and it's also a way just to to overcome worry at any given moment because
a mind of worry connect simultaneously coexist with the mind of
calm contentment so if you just take a few deep breaths
feel a moment of contentment and calm then at least that breaks the cycle it
starts to break the habit and then of course you know the more we do that the better
now the fourth fourth strategy is look at our lifestyle
sometimes there are things we can actually do to uh live a lifestyle which
is going to be less conducive to worry right um
if if we're regularly doing things that are for example illegal we might worry
more or if if there's certain ways that we
relate to other people that is conducive to worry you might think maybe it's not it's not only
changing our attitude towards worry but also maybe we could make some Lifestyle
Changes is there a different way of relating to people or a situation taking
responsibility for things which would then allow create a life which is
less conducive to worry and there are there are usually is you
know certain changes that we could make and even if
even if the changes that we make don't seem to make a difference just
knowing that we've made an effort and we've really tried our best that in and of itself
makes it easier to accept whatever happens in the future and once we have
that acceptance then we just don't tend to worry anymore
so these are for uh things that can be applied to pretty much any situation
whatever you might be worried or feeling insecure about or whatever fears might
arise it may take a while it's not like you
can just you know say oh now I've got the answer and suddenly your mind is calm and free
of worry but they have to be applied again and again and again
and one of the things that that helped me a lot overcome worry I I find I don't worry
that much uh and there's a lot I could worry about
there's there's a lot in my life I could worry about if I was prone to worry
but one of the the things that I had done
previously when I was a monk I would do what's called tudong right
but which comes from the Pali word tudanga which means anesthetic practice
and real tudon means you basically I would just go out
typically I would take say a month and go to a distant location and give
myself a month to get back to the monastery somehow but I would have no money we're not
allowed to have money we're not allowed to store food so I didn't have any food
uh uh didn't know where I didn't have any fixed plans
that's very important no fixed plans it's not like I had a bunch of places
lined up where I was going to go because that that gives the illusion of security and
you have fixed plans in your head makes you gives you a delusion that you think
you know what's going to happen in the future but if you just determine no plans
so no money no food don't know where I'm going to stay no vehicle of course
now if my mind was conducive to worry that going on tudong would not be any
fun at all it would just be like oh my God where am I going to sleep
am I going to have food tomorrow how am I going to get back how am I
going to get anywhere right so if I was prone to worry I realized
pretty quickly this was not going to be any fun so I had I had just to learn how to trust
trust that if my intentions we're good
then I would trust in the results that came from that that's basic law of comma
you can phrase it in different ways you say if if you if you do the right thing the universe will look after you or if
you look after the dhamma the dhamma will look after you
but I realize that almost everything was out of my control in that situation
but one thing I did have at least an illusion of control over was my intentions
I could keep generating wholesome intentions what is my purpose why am I here what am I doing this for clarifying
that purifying that and then and then
and then whatever results came from that just learn how to accept it some would be pleasant some would be unpleasant
but what I found was that I never went hungry I had some strange
combinations of meals sometimes but I never went hungry I always had a
I always had a place to stay somewhere um even if it was outside yeah most of
the time it was outside somewhere and I always
I always got back to the monastery I always survived and I had the greatest experiences that no
amount of trip planning you know prior to going could have imagined
so if I had tried to control everything by planning everything out it would have been much
much less enjoyable it was not doing that I had the most amazing
synchronicities happening because every day I would just wake up
and say okay which direction do I go today I'm going to wait for a sign or
something to happen and and sometimes it would just be meeting someone and say oh
well you know I live over you can come this way if you want and come with me or you can stay at my place or I'll give
you a ride here and then okay and just wait for uh wait for a sign to see which
way I'm going to be going that day and then yeah what I found is that when
I wasn't trying to control the future and I wasn't worrying about it
I was just very very open to whatever would happen that
it was life was the best there was better than it was it was so
much better than than normal and of course once I got back to the monastery I have many
responsibilities and schedules and you know you have to have
a schedule so I couldn't live like that always but
this lesson of how to trust that seemed to carry on
just really trusting that if my intentions are good I'll Trust in the results
right and that carried on and so I would try to to do that for many years
I did that practice every year now
so give it a try sometime but the basic idea that comes from it is
that you know it is possible to overcome worry and and really trust put your trust into
something larger and then good things come from that and then
things work out okay so I offer this for your reflection
this morning
and then if anyone has any questions
feel free to ask if anything you're curious about
yes
thank you for your talk do you have a any books that you've written
or that you would maybe even recommend regarding what you've been talking about this morning
not specifically on the subject um I have written some books and
articles but mostly on samata and vipassana
but not specifically on on overcoming worry if you're
thank you very much
I too I don't believe in worry um I've practiced not worry for many many
years and one of the things you said about intentions I think I have
confidence in my intentions and that really helps me to not worry
um and your month-long trip the question I had was if someone offered you a ride
and I'm in a vehicle were you allowed to take it and I think you said yes oh yeah
I could accept yeah okay okay I didn't have to walk the whole way so it might take longer than a month
okay good yeah well my when I was married and in my 20s my husband and I
just took off to Europe and hitchhiked through Europe and we didn't know where we were going
exactly we just went from day to day and place to place and it was really lovely
I don't know if I could do it today but it was lovely and so yeah I agree with
you worrying is useless not that I don't do it
it's yeah it's counterpredictive
hello it was really relevant to me thank you
so much for the talk but I think in general the women us
tend to worry more than men is that that's what I think
especially I think it's in a nature as a mother to
make sure that the safety or things are taken care of right
so my question is how do you
get that balance it's it's really tough to be
prepared for a certain because it's like we can't always
say okay if I'm in my intentions are okay if the universe is going to take care of me it might happen but it might
not so how do you strike that balance between being prepared
and not worry I think being prepared in some ways is also a little bit because
you're worried and you're being prepared right right well first of all I'll say
um I know my my mother used to say yeah I would I'd be off traveling around Asia
or something and she was like oh I'm really worried I said don't worry she said I'm a mother I have to worry
which is not true but I can't really stop her from worrying because that's tied up
with caring and love right so this is how do you separate
the the destructive aspect of fear and worry which is unhelpful
from act from care and love and being responsible and preparing right
of course we need to make plans and and contingencies to do our best you know to
be responsible so things work out in the future right yes definitely but
if we're always let's say there's a big difference between being responsible and then constantly
worrying about the future and what could go wrong it's a very it's like our minds get in a habit of
seeing the negative all the time the potential problems and
and then that becomes sort of uh just how we see the world it
just feels like there's always a big problem right around the corner there's
always things that could go wrong at any moment there's things that could go wrong because we're always
our minds going to worry all the time as a habit or fear
and then that becomes you know I mean so many people just base their lives and actions and a whole
sometimes their whole life is based on fear fear of what other people think fear of
not you know fear of not pleasing our parents or you know it's just so many
types of fear that may control our life how do we how do we start to separate
that out clearly I mean I don't know what it's like to be a mother but
we you can develop the nurturing caring
loving side of things without the
without the worry is that possible give it a try
thank you
thank you so I'm a mama too and I really hear you on this and what was coming to
me is that art and that dance of mothering
with good in I know I don't like these things with good I feel like I want to sing
um good intentions and
the trust that you spoke of because setting it up the planning I mean I I
agree with you because I think as mamas we manage a lot right we're managing us and then all our little ones sometimes
the spouse so there's a lot of control going out my twins just turned 16. I'm sharing
this with you because I'm still standing and I had the gift of being reminded that
it's putting it my journey has been my journey putting it out there arranging
offering and then releasing and then and in that making the choice
to not fall into worry but to to instead embody
trust and give the energy to my faith right to all that you spoke of
the intention the knowingness the knowing that at every turn the wave is going to be exactly as it
needs to be so I practice that every day and I go tumbling constantly
but it certainly helps to abort the worry
the the laying it out the writing of it and the knowingness that will land where
we need to land I guess I hope that's helpful in some way
can't stop the worry but but can ride a little better right
I guess I try to look at it a little bit more logically one of my one of my biggest fears has
been ending up a bag lady on Market Street so Financial Security especially as I
get closer to retirement has always been a big concern so I break it down into you can't
control the market right so uh you know I break it down into goals
concrete steps that I can take and things that I can do you know like
using certain index funds for my investments steps that I can take having
more Roth Investments you know just logical things that I can do and then after that you just have to
give it up you know you can't control certain things you just can't control them so you take action on the things
that you can control and then you just acknowledge that there's things that you can't control
or politics you know God help us in 2024.
um but you know there are things that you can do you can get involved in campaigns
you can contribute to certain campaign funds you can write Congress people so
there are certain actionable things that you can do you can talk to people about issues
but you know you can't you cannot control what other people do how they
vote things like that and of course the meditation and just learning that you can't control everything in
life so you know there are certain aspects you have to know what you can control
and what you can't control and I think giving up that control is important and it's important to accept
and realize yeah
as a the longer I practice the more I realize the the things that I can't
control get bigger and bigger and bigger I realize well what actually can I
control and even my intention is like it's sort of an illusion of free will
and control rather than actual control
uh thank you so much I just had an observation that
um being older and practicing for a while I worry much less and it's wonderful and
what worry will do we'll just kind of cancel out any sense of adventure
toward life so when I don't worry about a situation I have a sense of adventure
that replaces it it's like well this is going to be interesting to see what happens instead of worrying which doesn't do anything except take the joy
away right for anything you know you're like clinging on to see what's going to happen and then there's
the next thing and it's not even that thing that's so important to me it's just the fact that you know
I have a need to kind of be on the lookout all the time you know
for any potential you know and I have to have them all lined up but definitely for me when I do
have periods of time where I didn't worry first of all it's so relaxing and then there's a sense of adventure
instead of a sense of fear so
yes I mean Life Fitness Adventure that we don't really know what's going to
happen even if we are very responsible and competent we don't know what's going
to happen we could go all sorts of different directions so just treat it like a a big two-done
it just had a quick question on worry of course so uh do you think
you know it's it's kind of human nature to worry um so instead of not worrying is it like
blood pressure you know goes up but then you calm down pretty quickly so the idea
is to really come to that Baseline fairly quickly rather than say don't worry
well worry can be completely eradicated through just through wisdom yeah
it you can say that worry is human nature but you can also say that anger is human nature a delusion is human
nature and all of that is true greed is human nature but we that doesn't mean we have to live by those principles or or
just um be complacent about it no we can overcome those things we can focus on on
the Opposites um self-nesses and and uh and non-anger
and wisdom that's also Human Nature so yes I mean if if we're humans and we
sometimes worry yeah that by definition is human nature but we can see is this a is this
conducive to happiness or not and if it's not conducive to happiness we don't have to follow it and then the
Habit will get weaker and weaker and especially when we start to see the
see some of the positive feedback you know oh and I don't worry I'm actually even more at ease
I can feel I can recognize the blessings in my life I feel more content
all right there's a lot of you know and then it becomes easier and easier to to break
that habit yeah but certainly whenever worry arises
if you can recognize it quickly right that's like first strategy mindfulness clear
awareness as soon as it arises catch it quickly before your blood pressure gets too high
take a few deep breaths or maybe a quick reflection say ah you know it's not
really my it's not mine it's out of my control or it's whatever and then kind of come back to being
centered and balanced the more quickly we can do that the better
I I have one other question so I was at a event with the Dalai Lama and you know
he was talking about this uh monk uh Ani monk women monk in Tibet
that got burned and had a lot of um you know torture and stuff like that
and he just burst out crying and then but so I was very surprised you know
like you would cry at you know like show his emotions but then he kind of calmed
down so how do you explain that I know you're not you can't represent Dalai Lama but
is that kind of normal or he should have not cried
uh Dollywood Dalai llamas can do whatever he wants
well no I mean there's nothing wrong with uh showing emotions but it
you know love is an emotion loving kindness uh compassion these are all
emotions too right and so we're just trying to emphasize the wholesome
emotions that lead to happiness and peace benefit for ourselves and benefit for everybody else
so I mean a situation like that you know that Dalai Lama was a case
where there's somebody who has potentially a lot to worry about right representing his whole country
culture threats against his life uh his uh Sangha members being tortured
yeah it's it's very touching so it's not surprising that it was very you know it was very painful
very very painful to to reflect on that
I have a question um it's about the travel experience and
like you know going without money and I'll they think he said it's the term for it uh too long okay
so do you think like you know when you went for the travel you I'm assuming you
were in Asia and like do you think the amount of worry changes based on the society you are in because like you know
certain societies are more trusting and if you you know the condition that you
gave like it basically defines a homeless person like in in America I
feel like they have more struggle than if you are in Asia right like you know people are I think
have that sense of like you know I want to help my Society move this is my
observation could be wrong that's how I felt so do you think our worry I mean levels of you know worry changes based
on where you are or has it been true for you so what's the difference between the noble practice of tudong and being
homeless well first of all yes I went too long sometimes in Asia
and that has certain benefits and drawbacks but most of my two dong was in
uh New Zealand right uh Western Country
non-budhist and I would go to remote places where they had never seen a real
Buddhist monk before and it's like people think they're not going to feed
you why would they feed you they don't have no idea even what you're doing
and say yeah I'll find out then we had to adjust it a little bit
according to culture but we're not allowed to ask for anything so I would just stand silently in front of the grocery store
yeah yeah I mean it helps if you have a Buddhist
robe okay a shaved head Monk's robe it's like okay
that's an archetype that people can tune into and even if they've never seen a a
live Buddhist monk they've probably seen it on TV somewhere and it's like okay so a spiritual person of some
type and often they would want to give me money right and I was then I can say oh we're
not allowed thank you very much but we're not allowed to accept money we can only accept offerings of food and then
more often than not they would say oh okay well just wait I'll get something inside you know they're going shopping
anyways so on the way out you know they pop a sandwich or or apple or something into my ball
um so there was a slight adjustment for culture which we would not do in
Thailand for example Thailand if you're walking uh in the early morning with
your ball people know what you're doing but they wouldn't know that in New
Zealand so but I think that's a good example of
if you just listen to your fears you're not you wouldn't do it
all right you miss out on some of the best experiences if you just listen to your fears about
the worries about what could go wrong how people won't recognize what you are
people might you're not going to get food you're going to go hungry it will be terrible
people might harass you well none of that happened
right it was just like 99 positive experiences I met
people that would never ever come to Buddhist Meditation Retreats and uh or
or monasteries we had some fantastic conversations and
and feel like I was really retouching people you know so it was very gratifying and it was just wonderful in
every way but so no even in
even in uh any I think any society you know
if you can really put yourself out there with the right intention
it's going to be a learning experience one way or another
uh-huh with the four strategies just to repeat yeah sure so the first is is clear
awareness recognizing when where is present uh second is active wisdom using
our reflection to understand the subject that we're worrying about if we truly
understand the nature of that subject then that will that will the worry will
dissipate and but it's difficult to have clear
reflection if our mind's not at least somewhat calm if it's very scattered
right because otherwise it's just like scratching the surface so if our mind is calm then our reflection has an
opportunity to sink in more deeply and be more transformative and the fourth
one is making actual Lifestyle Changes you know practical changes in our in how
we live that would be less conducive to worrying or Rising
Mr okay I have a really Petty question why was the cousin trying to kill the Buddha
Sangha politics office politics
um his cousin was a talented meditator but
was unenlightened and he he got the idea that he should be the one to be the
leader of the entire monastic Sangha and he had he had a certain following
which kind of bolstered his delusion around that and so he thought
if he just killed the Buddha then he would be able to to be the one to to take his place and Lead this whole
community
so be grateful for your all your cousins who aren't trying to kill you
okay all right maybe we can bring it to a conclusion then all right thank you for
inviting me nice to see you today
go back