so greetings and nice to be here with all of you
and I feel kind of cozy sitting here I've been this is the second time I've sat down here to meditate in this Hall
today six o'clock there was a meditation with the group that's here
it's very nice and now with the with this with all of you thank you for being here
and um
one useful definition for mindfulness
is that it's being undistracted
and why that's useful is that it doesn't imply that we have to do anything except
maybe let go of our distractions and then
we are there aware of whatever is left
so to let go of distracting thoughts let go of thoughts that interfere with
being aware and then be aware in whatever way remains
being aware of whatever arises
and without you could even be without any choice
whatever arises in the present moment in Awareness is allowed to be there
and this kind of way of understanding mindfulness is supported
by the idea that uh that were present for whatever arises
easily we're not looking for something or trying to make something happen or
trying to penetrate deeply into the nature of reality we just very simple lightly calmly
receptively easily with ease whatever comes
and it can be a little bit uh easy to be impatient or feel like it's
not enough because after all meditation mindfulness Buddhism is pointing to
you know all kinds of fantastic great States of meditation and attainments and all kinds
of great things and so I mean that's what's important and just something ordinary like just whatever comes arises
in awareness may seem like it's too ordinary
but it's not the ordinary because most people live their lives distracted
and and uh
and they in the continuity of this ordinary
easeful undestructive state leads to Great freedom
it is a kind of a freedom in itself so
um to begin with a posture
that has a little bit of intentionality in it if you're sitting in a very relaxed way
on an easy chair or some other posture that's very relaxed
see if you can do a small adjustment that adds a little bit of intentionality
to the posture it could be sitting up a little bit straighter
if you're meditating laying in bed you might stick your forearm Point your
foreign forearm up towards the ceiling the upper arm can be flat in the bed and so at a right
angle the forearm points this up and and that's a little bit more virus requires
some intentionality
and then gently close your eyes
and without much more preparation
What In your experience Here and Now arises effortlessly or arises easily
what is easy to be aware of Here and Now
and as you're aware of whatever is easy
is there any momentum movement in the mind
to wander off in thought
they're kind of wandering off where
that eclipses oh where present moment awareness
kind of wandering off in thought where we lose touch with
being easily aware aware of what comes easily to
to us here and now
and if you do find yourself moving into distracted thoughts
you might just use the phrase or the word
undestructed oh maybe like a question
or a reminder to open again
in an easy way to be aware
of what's easy here what's left
when you are undistracted
for now there's nothing else you need to do you don't have to focus on the
breathing you don't have to
have a something that you're focusing on and
trying to stay with
just come back to this simple place
where you can be aware of what appears easily
in awareness
and if there's commentary and judgments about anything
that's also a pull away
from being aware easily
staying close to this undistracted place being aware of what comes into awareness
ease easily you might notice that the mind sometimes
settles on certain experiences other times
there's a shifting Sensations that are coming in
almost like the mind just moves between things and floats
and all kinds of things are appearing shifting
and undistracted
and then you might
let awareness be more centered on the body breathing
becoming aware of whatever sensations of breathing
arise easily into awareness
oh
as you return to undistractedness
and being aware with ease for whatever is easy
easily comes to awareness whatever is easy about the breathing
is there any tranquility calm or peace
in that easeful awareness
undistracted
what remains when you're undistracted
and what is it like to be aware of that
easily with ease
and if whatever is occurring here for you
is uncomfortable or painful physically emotionally mentally
what might it be like to know it
with this easeful awareness whatever is painful
whatever is Duke let it appear let it arise easily into
awareness without becoming distracted by it
without being pulled into commentary and stories
undistracted awareness
of the challenges that arise simply and easily
Here and Now the hereness of them
and in the Simplicity of awareness might there also be a tenderness or
warm-heartedness a compassion
that vibrates or was awakened
in the ease in the calm
is part of easy awareness calm awareness
easy compassion easy tenderness
kind-heartedness
and now as we're coming to the end of the meditation
bringing to mind someone in your life who has challenges of some type or other
and in these last couple of minutes
bring them to mind and see if there can be for a couple of
minutes a simple light useful
sense of care compassion
tender harderness
kind-heartedness
not a doing so much as
what can I Rise
when we're undistracted
and may our ability to be undistracted
as we go about this suffering world
and allow for our capacity for simple compassion
to be present and available
always ready to wish everyone well
may all beings be happy
may all beings be free of their suffering
may all beings have their burdens and oppression lifted
may all beings be free of their afflictions
they they may they get well
may all beings be safe of harm
they all beings experience peace not war
may all beings be free
so they can breathe easily smile easily
care easily may we all care for each other
[Music]
thank you
foreign
so hello and Welcome to our fourth
talk on the seven factors of compassion
and today we talk about the Tranquility factor of compassion and
the samadi factor of compassion
so just to kind of review a little bit a few weeks ago about three weeks ago I
suppose two weeks ago I gave it a series of talks on kind of the foundational elements for compassion
the things that ideally would be in place so that compassion can come forth in a in a healthy and useful way
and so learning how to be aware in a calm non-reactive way just to be
aware and to be aware what's happening with it within us carefully and well so we can
track and monitor monitor our response to compassion and how to be
compassionate so I'm just learning to be aware and then to be attuned
to attune ourselves to the people we're with the compassion that we're being present for
to find the right way to be in harmony with it before we act maybe even before we focus
on Compassion or and then appreciation
to have some deep respect and appreciation for oneself or others so that when we're compassionate it's
not pity it's not kind of uh feeling sorry for someone but uh maybe there's
something there more important than compassion which is a deep honoring and valuing of
of fathers and oneself and then there is an aspiration
aspiration that people not suffer that we don't have suffering that we come to
the end of it that we support the end of it and then there's action
and when all those five things are in place then compassion has a healthier foundation for being supportive and
actually nourishing for our lives rather than being debilitated by The Compassion
because it's so painful and exhausting it's actually enlivening and valuable
for everyone and um and uh this week it's when we do
have compassion to continue practicing with the presence
of compassion not just take it for granted or not just take it as being something we have to now live with as it
is but to begin appreciating some of the different elements that follow in the
wake of the compassion if there's healthy compassion then as we live compassionately
um there will be mindfulness there will be a kind of a natural easeful awareness
if we're coming from that motivation of being present for somebody or someone
ourselves with compassion and we don't have to work on that so
much to be mindful it just kind of comes along in the wake of the compassion but and that awareness that comes along
is useful so that we can really see better what's happening as we're compassionate and see are there ways
that we're operating that are harmful or not harmful and harmful or beneficial
are we a little bit straining are we a little bit under the burden of responsibility and contracted around
that are we a little bit afraid are we feel like we have to jump in or
so how are we with it and to see the difference between a way of operating which is not so
healthy or beneficial and then one that is so rather than being straining to learn
how to be present and engaged with with the kind of ease or relaxation rather
than clinging to something finding a place of non-clinging so that compassion can flow more more effectively
and um the um
and so and as we make these distinctions and seeing where the challenges are with
the compassion and adjusting for it that's the effort factor of of compassion we do make some effort and
follow a path or make the choice to go in the direction of where it's more
useful where it's more free where it's more you know less clinging less attachment
less resistance less burden and so there is a effort factor of
compassion that comes along with the compassion that supports it and then there's the appreciation side
The Joy side of compassion there's something very where there's a there's a kind of sweetness that comes from
healthy compassion and if we don't feel that sweetness we probably should go back and review and
do these other steps and maybe even go back to this the Four A's awareness
Attunement appreciation to really see what's going on here
with us ourselves and then and then comes Tranquility
calmness that healthy compassion has a calmness
to it a Tranquility to it I've sometimes responded with compassion
to try to take care of something in the world and that seemed to be taken care of right away and because I I acted
reactively kind of agitated I have to do something and jumped right in I ended up making a mistake
and once I thought there was a little fire
in the distance from the farm I was living on and without
I wasn't calm I got immediately activated I didn't take the time to take a second look before I called the fire
department and they came and I don't know what it was anymore now it was so long ago over 50 years ago but or so 50
years ago that it was some kind of it wasn't that wasn't a fire and and if I
had actually taken the time to look I would have seen that you know there was not not a problem
so this idea of being calm have enough calmness to see clearly so the calm factor of Awakening
and that is supported a lot by the ability to trust easeful awareness to
trust and awareness that's not straining or not under the burden of the need our
needs or our desires our fears that's not easy to find but it's part of
the gift of this practice as we do this practice is discovering this useful calm
awareness so that the compassion can exist without calmness as well
and then it comes this fascinating wonderful capacity of compassion to support concentration samadhi so the
samadhi factor of compassion that and a lot of somebody is a
unification gathering together I like to think of it of feeling so at home in our
experience that we just kind of settle into the
settle really deeply so that all of who we are settles together and feels at
home with itself and so what that means about samadhi is
that um it's not meant to override
Uka our challenges or override the way we're distracted or varied our suffering
um it's a samadhi should wait until we find a way to be present for what's challenging for
us find our way through it with mindfulness with compassion with care with attention
so that so that we do find that even in the midst of challenging experiences in
life we've found kind of an inner home that we're home in our hearts we're home
in our inner well-being and again that's not an easy thing to come to at all it might take years for
some people practicing to find that but that that's when we begin at that point
we can appreciate how compassion is an ingredient for a samadhi for uh it's
part and parcel of this being collected and settled and contented and and just
really kind of gathered around so that the focus of compassion the focus of
attention can be an effective way just here with what's needing to be done just
here gather together in the moment and uh and so when we have this easeful
relaxed kind of way of being present and this beef at home this in this world even if the external World we're not at
home and we're at home with ourselves we feel like we belong to ourselves we belong here we belong in this universe
in some way even though maybe even the people around us are don't feel that we belong we carry our belonging with us we
carry our subtleness with us that's part of the gift of samadhi
especially if samadhi is not held on to as some kind of only some
kind of deep state of concentration in meditation holding on and attached to it has to be
really kind of something special there are deep states of meditation
that happened they're called somalis and but some the samadhi in daily life
of meeting the world is more the the after effect of being settled and
calm whatever ability we have to settle and calm and be centered and belong and
be feel cozy and at home here um and if it is very deep states of concentration
it's kind of the the after effect of that that teaches us how to be feel at home
or be at home to ourselves that after effect is also a kind of I think of it as samadhi
and so to to allow for that reference point to be there
and and then it's really really a fantastic thing and then with that samadhi without the kind of ability to
gather around and let the concentration just be and the attention really be present for what needs our attention
and that's part of the sweetness that can come from compassion so an example I
gave in earlier a little girl who scraped her knee in the playground that we care for we care we try to be
sensitive to a tune to her and and care for the wound and in her and the kindest
most supportive way for her and so but that's is there's an ease to that we're not to learn because you know is not a
big danger she's in we're present in a kind caring away and we almost become
self-forgetting in caring for something like that and then that's self-forgetting there's
a deeper and if we're at home in ourselves and collected here for ourselves then that Gathering of attention to care
for her knee or care for her comes along with our capacity to gather
in or our unification of being focused just focused and concentrated on the
task at hand that has a sweetness to it it's so sweet to have this ability to be focused in
this kind of way and um so the the the
samadhi factor of compassion so we're going through these and we have
one more tomorrow the Equanimity Factor and what I'm hoping that you'll learn
from this is that not to take compassion as a fixed thing like you like you're
either compassionate or not compassionate and then you're compassionate whatever way you're compassionate and um and you don't want
to hear anything else you know you want you know this is my way of being compassionate or something or or you've
never thought about it you're just compassionate the way you are and think you're supposed to be that way
not aware that compassion has many flavors and many component parts many aspects many things interact with
compassion and so to learn to be mindful of compassion and appreciating the
different factors of it then then we can start playing in the playground of
compassion we can start kind of exploring it and adjusting it and finding how the best of compassion can
come forward and and so it's not just you know the compassion just happens to arise which
might sometimes not be so healthy um what we call Compassion but we find
that which is most healthy for ourselves and for others
so um so if you would like for today
um maybe focus on um tranquility and calmness
if you have occasion for have compassion for the suffering of
others and in the circumstances allows you to take some time with it you don't have to
jump into action um so you can kind of do the experiment to kind of explore
how can you um feel the warm-hearted tender compassion
for somebody and um or for yourself and let there be a Tranquility as part of it that maybe
it floats on Tranquility or it's supported by Tranquility or it just the
compassion is tranquil itself and um and you know try not to feel or
fall into the Trap of the worry that you're betraying compassion by focusing on having it be
or some other person by finding the Tranquility for it actually it supports
um and helps grow healthy compassion in a wonderful way
so thank you all very much and I look forward to our time tomorrow