and Hugh from San Diego so I think the space is warmed up I feel I
feel that all the love from all the different places in the world and different time zones so invite you to
feel into it too and thank you Neil for sharing information about happy hour Google Groups so we have a low traffic
mailing list and if you're not on it you're warmly invited to to join the
mailing list it's what I like to say it's low in traffic but high but big in heart
at this point I change the settings so that unmuting won't be possible so
the space stays quiet and the chat settings chats will only come to me but let's not send any questions during the
guided meditation can be very distracting I'll open up later for the reflections after our meditation
together and last but not least I'm going to turn on the recording for the sake of Audio
Dharma here we go great Okay so hello and welcome everyone
to this rendition of happy hour lovely to be with you and in uh in cyberspace
if not in same space but in time and maybe not in time if you're listening to
to um Audio Dharma but just lovely to feel each other's presence coming together
with Our intention that's it and the dimension of intention we're definitely all coming together to practice together
so I'd like to invite us to just start sitting and aim for tonight will will be
revealed during the guided meditation so so without further Ado let's let's sit
let's practice together ah
arriving arriving in this body
arriving in this moment in time and turning our awareness
inward what's happening
greeting reading the body
sensations of the body
sensations of the breath
how can I be kind to myself in this moment
how can I be a friend to my sis moment
as if each breath we're singing this song
gently kindly
how can I be kind to myself
with this breath in this moment
how can I care for my heart or my body in this moment
and the answer that comes up for me is oh sitting in Stillness
with awareness but the breath is calming soothing it's
nourishing the act of self-care at this moment
notice I'm not saying I'm not inviting us to focus on the breath
that gets the mind too tight please don't do that instead relax relax the body and receive
the breath receive the breath like a lullaby
like a song like you wish for your own well-being
make a blessing a whisper in your heart
expansive in your abdomen how can I be kind to myself
relax and receive
whisper the song of the breath with kindness
foreign
how can I be kind how can I be gentle
for this being who is Me In This Moment his mind and his heart
treat them with care as a practice for treating others with care
and I let go put down preoccupations thoughts plans
entanglements just to take refuge in kindness
with this breath
and if thoughts arise I can release them say thank you dear thank you dear
thoughts not now please come back later
this moment is perfect just as it is thank you very much
nothing more needed
foreign
and I'd like to invite you if you would Just As You Are
sitting or lying down or standing and feeling your body feeling breathed
each breath one breath at a time
see if with your mind with your heart as if it were a radio a receiver you can
tune into tune into the
The Joy The Joy the pleasantness
of just sitting here being breathed nowhere to go nothing to do this moment
of respite he can tune into the Delight the joy of
that and if the judgmental mind comes along
oh you're not doing anything thank you judgmental mind thank you I know you're trying to help but I'm actually tuning
into appreciating the joy of doing of
non-doing there's a joy to it a joy to non-grasping
not becoming there's a freedom a joy
you just feel into this for a moment just a brief moment to taste it
later you can become all you want but right now see if you can tune into
this delight s wholesome goodness
of non-striving just being
thank you
the joy of not doing you see do you feel something release
do you feel lighter or chance notice what does it feel like
this subtle Delight
and you savor it help it grow
again the Puritan judgmental mind can count okay all right
dear judgmental mind can rest take a break
you're working so hard I'm exploring something different
the joy of not becoming
and striving
just being
foreign
it's a deep profound place of rest
it's Joy of not becoming not doing and it's right here so
accessible right here
relax and receive
mind doesn't have to race thing to be to become
to solve it can release
the heart also doesn't have to solve all the problems of yourself or your life
the world
just resting on the tip
of release into Joy
a refuge
Refuge of Deep kindness care
refreshing of refreshing for wisdom
Joy of not doing not becoming not grasping
foreign
whatever Rises you can release every thought I don't have to follow this one
if I released into the joy of non-becoming not becoming this thought
and rest there said that tip
Joy of not becoming of release
thank you
foreign
it's letting go into the joy of non-doing not becoming
be a place of deep rest
The Refuge however this meditation was whether
there were moments of rest Refuge peace Joy
or not it's perfectly fine you showed up
you showed up you did your best given all the costs
and conditions shade yourself yay I showed up thank you
for showing up I trust you've planted seeds please trust your planted seeds
they will come to fruition in their own time not according to our demands or schedule
all we can do is to do our part to show up
With Our wholehearted intention and you've done that whether the mind is distracted
lots of visitors all plans memories sadnesses agonies
arising In This Moment it's we don't have control so much
so appreciating that you showed up practiced
saying your own goodness and together as a community
sharing the Merit of our goodness the Merit of our practice
of our wholeheartedness offering it to ourselves and offering it to all beings
everywhere May our practice be of benefit to not
just ourselves our loved ones our families our own liberation
made support Maybe helpful
to all beings everywhere in ways we cannot imagine trust that it is may all
things be free may all beings be happy including ourselves
thank everyone thanks for your practice
so what we did today just a quick review started with
feeling the breath while coming to breath and relaxing and receiving the breath as
a lullaby yes calming and soothing it's this nourishing of the brethren
tuning we start to tune into the breath as as a blessing as something beautiful
and then I invited you to try something we haven't tried here before
which is the exploring the joy of not
becoming of non-becoming of non-being non-doing non-striving
and the way to explore that Joy was to release was to release into non-being if
a thought came about I plan to do this and that's like oh sweetheart you don't have to it's all right later I can think
about all this stuff and become all I want later but right now what if I just release that and then turn my mind to
the Joy to the Delight of non-being wow that can be such a place of ease rest
release this place of it's just like the tip of uh like I had this image of I
think there's a saying of how many millions or thousands of of angels can
fly on the tip of a uh can dance on the tip of a um uh what is it
blunt my mind is blanking um uh um on a small tip of something or other
anyway so I had this image of oh yeah so much e so much expansiveness so much rest ahead of a pin that's it thank you
all head of a pen support is right there in in uh in chat for me waiting for me on
the head of a pen right there so there's so much ease so much relaxation and
peace and the head on this tip of this pin of not becoming not doing just
releasing into that so um interesting
interesting exploration I hope um I hope you found your way your
relationship into it either through this meditation and maybe some
other time and of course the the mind the uh the judgments can come like oh
you're not doing anything like it's okay sweetie it's all right I'll do I'll do everything like you know the becoming
can all happen later but it's so so freeing to explore [Music]
um to explore even for a moment if it's accessible like wow the mind can just
let go release into non-becoming non-wanting not wanting not becoming not
around this this like this samsara this continuously thinking and becoming and
wanting it remembers like even for a moment through the past 30 minutes if you felt into that wow
that can be such a deep joy release into that so
so with that um
the invitation to uh to now transition few few will
to being with one another in small breakout groups and maybe nothing needs
to be said if you're very quiet if you just had oh wow deep release you don't
want to become you don't want to become this talking head you don't want to that's perfectly fine what let maybe let
that be your guide what if what if we show up with others without this need to
say to be to become to to share maybe
we'll just show up with peace with Silence with non-becoming
that look like I don't know let's explore that maybe there will be a lot
of Silence in the rooms and maybe there will be a movement to perhaps to share
something from the experience or maybe not it's very free-floating or maybe
you'll just sit together with eyes open for the six minutes in silence and that's perfectly fine uh maybe just
wishing each other meta wishing yourselves well wishing each other well so let it be really low-key what is this
and also notice if there is the desire for becoming for wanting to to impress
especially you know if there's a desire to perhaps share and and um or good will
just be be with good will I know this these instructions these invitations for
the small group sound unusual it's not the usual prompt up discuss this no it's
it's actually it's a different way of being with other human beings
does that make sense so the invitation is in the small group of roughly size three or four what if
you showed up without any desire to be anybody in
or show up in any particular way being being with a sense of ease anyway let's let's
try that on for size dear practitioner so I'm going to create the breakout rooms
and be kind take care of yourselves take care of each other no questioning please
this is not a time to ask anybody any questions you want to share from your experience you're welcome too if you
want to hold Silence with meta and non-becoming what does the what does the heart and
mind feel be curious that's it lead with curiosity not becoming be curious all
right the rooms are created I'm going to open them now take care of yourselves
take care of each other here we go come back and let's take a couple of
Reflections you can type them in chat if you like
um it's open now to everyone or to me privately or you can raise your hand if
you haven't spoken recently um how this practice was for you what did you discover in the AHA moments or
any um challenges you want to ask about ditto about
[Music] um ditto about the small groups Bill asks what is becoming what is on becoming ah
non-well non-becoming not on becoming non-becoming but becoming yeah thank you
for that question so so in the uh Buddhist teachings there's this idea
that that um we we calcify around a want a a this
this uh but something that we want to become that for example there's so many
different ways to think about this but let's let's relate it so let's say you have this idea you know you have a
memory and then all of a sudden you're upset and you're angry and you become you become this angry person you become
because of the thought you had or or thing I mentioned a couple of sessions
ago the idea of this Hungry Ghost which is again in Buddhist cosmology is this
creature that has a huge stomach and Tiny neck and Tiny mouth so it can never be satisfied it's always hungry always
greedy so maybe you see something or you're or think about something and you
become you become a Hungry Ghost it's becoming it's this always becoming
you're always becoming becoming this becoming that and so that's the idea bill of of becoming and taking birth
into these unwholesome states of mind which again could be thought of as
different uh hell Realms we take birth into these different hell Realms we keep
becoming these unhelpful versions of ourselves instead of just not taking the bait not
not taking the bait uh Bill asked becoming is related to
Greed and the version then he agreed hey yes yes it is great exactly right yes it is this becoming is
related to the three unwholesome Roots uh um greed hatred and confusion which
actually the confusion the delusion um it it gives rise to the greed and
hatred so that's exactly right through that cycle we keep becoming we'd be taking birth so you can think of it as
multi-life we keep becoming is in the multi-life model if one believed in
rebirth you keep becoming becoming because or in in one life model you keep
becoming the next moment you become something more it's different different instead of just releasing and being
there's a sense of release ease um and releasing into goodness service
so that's the teaching there and I appreciate you asking these questions you're welcome
Bill excellent questions um I hope it was helpful for others too
whenever you sends a direct message that was a beautiful exercise thank you you are so welcome thanks for practicing
this yeah and if you want to raise your hand and say more because I don't remember hearing from you uh you're
welcome not to put you on spot and the spot but you're welcome to raise your hand Amy Says a group sat quietly
without unmuting being with and at random times we just grinned at each
other oh this is sweet I love it there's a sweetness to what you shared Amy
it's very sweet being with and at random times we just grinned at each other it
makes me happy it's very sweet I'm not becoming together yeah
it's exactly right well it feels like a rich exploration
we've done together the rich exploration that I invite you to to practice it
actually not just on the cushion but in daily life when you're about to become
something which may not be ideal you don't want to be oh pause do I want to
become this or do I want to release into non-becoming release that that
tantalizing um thing whatever it is that fish hook into
anger and aversion and greed whatever it might be like can I just let go and not become can I let go into contentment in
this moment and explore that so thank you all thank you for your
practice thank you for your wholeheartedness dear Sangha may we all
be free may we all be happy may we all have joy in our hearts explore the joy
of of non-green non-hatred non-delusion which actually is the joy of generosity
and love and wisdom may all beings be well may
all beings be free [Music]
thanks everyone be well take care I'll see you on Monday