so welcome here in San Francisco it's Tuesday
morning and we are discussing the the 10 Perfections the 10 paramis and my
name is kodo let's take a few minutes to
arrive and then we will gently begin with a
meditation something uh something you'll hear me say quite a lot this week is
um one of the features of the practice of the Perfections the practices
of the paramese is that they apply on the cushion when we're meditating and off the cushion
in what we call the rest of our life though we we know well that that line is arbitrary
um what we do on the cushion follows us off and what we do in the rest of our lives
follows us to the cushion there's no real line there
but these parties are deliberate ways we can reflect on and approach experience and bring the bring the possibility and
the beauty of the Dharma into everything that we do so for now let's let's do that in the
form of meditation
[Music]
so settling yourself in the way that you know best
could be that it's time to take a few deep breaths as you feel and
roll yourself into your body
tuning into sensing
this sensing that's happening all the time
to support our arriving
or sensing our sensing our way to the sitting base
feeling the connection with the seed or whatever is supporting us
and then sensing our way through the spine
feeling upright
feeling relaxed and alert
for this morning we're going to
turn our attention deliberately
to each of our senses one at a time
turn our attention there sense for any attention
and then relax so let's begin with the eyes
directing attention to the eyes
before making any adjustments just feeling
any tension or discomfort and letting that register
and then with our breathing and time with our breathing just gently relax
letting go what can let go
then registering any ease
pleasure relief
keeping our attention here with the eyes
if more tension
coagulates in the area
just repeating
to register that discomfort
we gently release and know the relief
then when the moment feels right turning to the area of the ears
maybe not the ears themselves any tensions in the area
but maybe you have a sense or linked to hearing
gently release
now letting go of the ears turning to the nose
in the area of the nose
sensitive to any tensions
gently release
foreign
the eyes ears now letting go
of attention to the nose turning to the tongue
and not only the tongue maybe there's tension in the
the jaw chin even the guns
for the upper throat if it feels okay for you to sense into
these things
just long enough
and gently relaxing
and registering really registering the relief
relaxing the tongue the mouth
turning our attention to the
attack time sense of the body
with a gentle touch
registering anywhere anywhere that tension
is calling for attention
and first coming to know it I'm not doing anything
bringing the attention into the area that's being called for
and then gently relaxing whatever can be easily relaxed
then another area may call and so on
foreign
and finally the mind
feeling any tension in mind ill sometimes calls the thinking muscle
the head the temples maybe you're on the eyes
sensing relaxing
and registering the relief
foreign
eyes ears
the moments um
body and mind
released
near our practice ring relief and release
to all beings foreign
[Music]
so hello again
after this meditation on releasing relaxing the sense bases I wonder how
you're doing you've just participated I would be interested or open if you have any
comments in the chat so we'll proceed today with our
discussion of the Perfections the parties and part of what we just did was a was an
experiential way of introducing the practice of what we call renunciation
you'll see as we go so these uh these 10 Perfections we're talking about is
10 Noble qualities that can apply in all sorts of areas of
our life and importantly each of these qualities and practices are accompanied by
compassion and skillful means they're accompanied by compassion
something heartful and skillful means which is the wisdom aspect
the 10 as you might remember giving
virtue renunciation
wisdom or discernment energy is fifth
patients sixth truthfulness
resolve Goodwill and equanimity
these are the ten and today we'll focus on renunciation and wisdom or discernment
we've been talking about the Pyrenees in pairs um as both practices that we can do and
the qualities that arise based on those practices so as we said yesterday the practice of giving supports our
quality of generosity and as we'll see the practice of Letting Go supports our quality of wise
renunciation we're talking about these parmes as mutually supportive
and with the potential not only to apply everywhere in our life but also to bring about a thorough going
freedom for the benefit of both ourselves and for others
so we practice these primaries step by step sort of in the way that it's taught
in this text uh we practice we practice them in order so
um we practice giving and then that is followed on and complemented by uh virtue ethical
conduct Selah and it's interesting how these two work together that it said that giving
benefits other people sort of obvious ways and then virtue or ethical Behavior
prevents the Affliction of the other people so we're benefiting them with our giving and then we're preventing harm
with our ethical Behavior so in a way we could say that establishing
ourselves in in a conduct that's compassionate and wise means that we we turn the potential for
harm into the potential for benefit for ourselves and for others through our
words and our Deeds as Gil will sometimes teach
through this practice of mindfulness just sort of sort of by nature of the
practice of mindfulness we start to develop what he calls an ethical sensitivity
um and that is we become sensitive to identifying what our what our actions
that we do that cause an ouch and those actions that we do that cause
an ah sense the difference and we'll see that this naturally sets
the stage for pronunciation so let's pick up the thread there first of the quote from the Google body
the well-known translator and teacher who tends to put things in such a clear way
so bikubody talks about renunciation this way the tool that the Buddha holds out to
free the Mind From Desire is understanding
real renunciation he says is not a matter of compelling ourselves to give
up things still and really cherished I'm going to repeat that
not a matter of compelling ourselves to give up things still inwardly cherished
but he goes on of changing our perspective on them so that they no longer bind us
he concludes when we understand the nature of Desire when we investigate it closely with Keen
attention desire Falls away by itself without need for struggle
isn't that wonderful that the the potential for freedom is right there with the desire
through our clear investigation this is the power of the practice of mindfulness I also want to highlight how uh in in
talking about renunciation sensual desire since objects the the difficulty
is not necessarily in the thing what we're studying in this Buddhist practice is the glue
that we call craving and clinging so I want to share a
personal story to illustrate this which is just before
uh oh wait it's a personal story that really well illustrates how the mind will let go of itself
at the discovery that something will know will no longer be serving me actually something that I'm Desiring is
causing me harm so just before my my 30th birthday
um I received a surprise diagnosis that switched the way that I relate to food
so um yeah I was 29 and a surprise to me I
became a late onset type 1 diabetic and as is obvious that has all sorts of
implications for what what can be eaten so right after the diagnosis I can't eat
um let's just say sugar anymore I'd go to the grocery store and I would
just Pine I would wish for sweets um
the uh at this point though the ice cream aisle let's say it's just a it's just a a location of suffering for me
at the time I remember getting very very interested in sugar-free anything sugar-free Jello or whatever
what I had along with this suffering was some really hard data about cause and effect
eating such and such a food would lead to such and such a consequence and this this sort of tracking that I
was doing throughout the day and the experience of my illness along with a very
clear potential for bodily harm um
it yielded a relatively Swift change in understanding and way of relating and
after a pretty short time sugar no longer registered as a food item for me
it may as well be paper so it was it's with a sensitivity to the
drawbacks um that's what really changed the change
the landscape for me and the the desire for let's say cake
just kind of faded out and really to to emphasize this point it
wasn't it wasn't that I drove out the thing that I loved
but um that the mind was no longer bound by it So within a couple of months I could I
could walk down the ice cream aisle no problem whatsoever
Suites may be a sort of simple low stakes example but the logic applies to many of our compulsive desires
so some of them may seem harmless enough um but yet that process of compulsion
re-conditions a process that's at work during some of our most intense difficulties in life
ice cream is one thing but craving and clinging conditions conditions things like
conflict and quarrel um can think of think of its influence on robbery and
theft or harm and then all the ways that all the ways that craving and clinging
that have that energy of craving and clinging supports Us in indulging our
in the text what we might call misconduct of body speech and mind
or ways that we we our actions support harm for ourselves and others rather
than benefit so this is one really good reason for
seeing the connection between these practices and qualities because you hear right there how renunciation and the
practice of ethical conduct and Sila work together and as we said earlier as we practice as
we practice virtue as we practice ethical conduct our sensitivity to the
harm or benefit we call this others comes more subtle and this is this sort of observation how
we help and how we hurt this is right where where renunciation practice belongs
so it's one thing to say that it's one thing to say oh you know just think about the drawbacks but these these
cravings and clings that we have relative to sensual Pleasures they're often so well ingrained well practiced
uh we we have I can sort of playfully say we have perfected the art of craving
and clinging over many many many years so um
this uh this teaching suggest employing some other means to
help shift the perspective really thinking about the nature of
desire and what we actually get out of it so
um some of the some of the metaphors that acharya damapala uses in this treaties
on the palmies helps us to shift our perspective from thinking and thinking and experience the
way we normally do which is sensual Pleasures are long lasting ultimately satisfying
um they're only Pleasant not at all painful and instead encourages Us in this reflection
using these pretty dramatic metaphors first of all emphasizing their brevity
like a flash of lightning um encourages a reappraisal of the mix
of Pleasure and Pain out of sensual desire maybe maybe like a drop of honey
that smeared over a blade or their promise of satisfaction but
that they can't ultimately deliver um like needing a drink of water but only having that little thin bit of dew
on your fingertips maybe um
maybe even uh thinking that a sensual desire and
embracing it is going to satisfy us but in fact it makes the situation worse it
actually intensifies the craving and the image here is so apt it is addressing
our thirst with by drinking salt water and feeling like that's going to solve
solve the solve the issue diminish the craving but in fact exacerbates
so just one final thought about renunciation and that is in this um in this reappraisal of sensual desire
and our relationship to them uh it doesn't mean we need to stop enjoying life
as big Cabot said at the beginning it's not that we push out the things that that we enjoy
but we learn to shift our relationships to them I think of food as a great example and there was a monastic who
trained trained his monks to really pay attention to how long in fact does food
stay Pleasant in the mouth after starting to chew it compared to how long we obsess over food
how long does that pleasure actually last once a morsel of food is in the mouth
so renunciation has the consequence of being a strong support or settling
unification concentration and this is where renunciation and wisdom come
together as Dawn so beautifully covered last week
um in the in the tradition discernment or wisdom is associated with the ability to
make distinctions and particularly the ability to make distinctions that are supportive of
freedom and liberation the image here is of uh of an Archer who
shoots an arrow at the Target and penetrates and I like how in that image the target is um
split in two we made a distinction
and there are sort of three modes of developing these distinctions developing this sort of discernment and wisdom one
is simple hearing and learning the second is reflection what we call reflective acquiescence it's a fun
phrase where you sort of chew on turn over and start to have these aha moments
about how the practice lives in your life and then the third is through meditation
and whether we deliberately bring our study or reflection into our meditation or not it's it's in there working on us
it's the manifestation of wisdom is non-confusion and its proximate cause is the
concentration associated with renunciation so to close I want to I want to suggest
uh as we did yesterday for bringing this into your day of practice the the um that same mode of practice of
observing and reflecting on um how does renunciation show up in my day
and how does its opposite show up in my day no just to know and then how does wisdom how does
discernment show up in my day and how does its opposite show up delusion and again we're not we're not trying to
just do it right 100 of the time but we really want to know this whole range the quality
and it's opposite so we'll pick up here tomorrow with energy and patience
thanks so much have a beautiful day of practice may all beings be happy peaceful and
well