so good morning everyone and or good day
and happy to be here with you and and I'm also happy to be here
with myself at the appreciation of our ability to
be present for ourselves is a wonderful appreciation
and to about value that and to
um
feel like we are worthy we are valuable we are
we are worthy of attention
and for people interested in being compassionate we have a lot more compassion or the
compassion is Fuller or maybe even cleaner if the agent of compassion namely each
of us holds ourselves or sees ourselves
with a certain value and worthiness and dignity
if we kind of inhabit ourselves fully or
appreciate ourselves as a Simplicity of being a human being
maybe not necessarily for our accomplishments or all kinds of worldly
values but just a deep appreciation of our value as a human being
if we have that kind of respect for ourselves then when we are bring compassion to
someone else we bring that along and it conveys more
value The Compassion conveys more value there's like a fuller compassion the
person who's offering compassion then is more present more the person is there
a person's not apologizing for themselves or not hiding themselves not
uh doing things kind of half-hearted because they don't think that they're important enough to do something
it's easier to be a wholehearted fullness of presence which brings more
presence into the compassion brings a lot of different wonderful things into the compassion so
this idea of respecting ourselves
respecting this human being that
we have the role of inhabiting living with for this lifetime
so to begin our meditation
with the care respect for this human being that you are
being careful with
the posture you take so that the posture you kind of spend
some time moving around a little bit wiggling swaying
looking until you find the posture that seems aligned and
balanced and feels right for you to inhabit
to live in the embodied posture
gently closing your eyes
and perhaps with care respect for yourself to take a few long slow deep breaths
we feel our body more fully when we breathe in deeply
and as we feel our body feel it with respect
exhale with care and respect
and letting your breathing return to normal
and as a form of respect and care as a way of
becoming more whole
as you exhale continue to relax the face the eyes
relax the shoulders
relax the belly
letting the breathing return to normal
and one of the meanings I like for respect
is to look again we if we respect something
it's worthy of a second look further connection
and as you're present for yourself breathing
each moment of awareness
each thing that you're aware of is worthy of a second look a deeper look
to respect each breath
is not just be aware of an inhale once but each and nail almost as if you're
giving yourself a second look a deeper connection
a second look a deeper connection to exhaling
if the Mind begins thinking to have respect for oneself
is to not only know that you're thinking
but to give it a second look
I haven't even further mindfulness of the phenomena of thinking
almost as if you respect it without
participating in it just seeing it more deeply the phenomena of thinking
and then respectfully allowing the thinking to fade away like
a thought bubble floating away
and begin again with your breathing
might your mindfulness become a little Fuller or
it'll ignore available in a stronger way
if the mindfulness is supported by respect
for yourself
even if you don't feel you deserve respect
offer the respect anyway as you might for any other person
if there was a occasion to support them and
in times of great need
and then to bring this meditation to an end
to consider how a certain
self-respect might translate or make possible greater
respect for others
and in with resp with our respect for others respecting others
to care for them for their welfare and happiness to care for their dignity and autonomy
to care for their success in life for their
deep spiritual fulfillment
and to wish them well May others be happy
May others be safe May others
be peaceful May others
be free
and with our with respecting then in with respect to them respecting them
may we in our own way small or large contribute to that possibility
[Music]
thank you
so for this week discussing the different
aspects of appreciation
I think appreciation can be a food for people I think people benefit tremendously from
being appreciated and I would say that a lot of people are not appreciated enough
and something Smiles inside something lifts and delights when there's appreciation
and if there goes a long time without appreciation especially if we're doing something for
others something begins to sink something feels a little bit off and not
quite right we live in a world where there's a mutual give and take a mutual
kind of a reference point we use for being with each other
and we might have tremendous generosity and offer things to others but if if not
even appreciation or gratitude comes back then at some point the feeling of generosity begins to become less and
less um but if it's a simple appreciation people understand what we're doing and
value it then it could be a smile and happy to do it and maybe easy to do it
so appreciation is a really important ingredient and
appreciation has these different elements to it and today I'd like to suggest that uh
important element is respect and respect is I just let you many of
you know I love the Latin root of the word which means to look again and when we respect something we're
willing to take a a respectful look again where we value
something enough we're not afraid of it enough to look again where that can happen but we
respect it we value it enough that yeah this is something we want to be connected to or to see or to understand
and so but the respect carries much more respect carries the idea that um
the person we're with has value has worth is um
is granting some someone a certain degree of dignity and um
and many people in our society don't feel valued they feel marginalized they feel relegated to the edges and maybe
overlooked and so but they have no one overlooked to have everyone worthy of
being seen again being seen clearly and appreciated and valued
it may be even more than valued to be delighted in and to be grateful for even
if people don't do anything for us the Gratitude can simply be we're
grateful to be delighted in another human being we're grateful to the chance
to be connected or to see and all these ideas might seem like we
don't have time for it it might seem a little bit superficial or or you know there's important things to do so we
can't stop and look again and Grant people's dignity and value Maybe
but the source I'd like to propose the source of respecting others is to
respect oneself and to respect oneself is to Value oneself
and value yourself not because what we're going to accomplish and so we have to do a lot but value something here
that's present value ourselves in this present moment manifestation
and this is very important because the Future Self
may not exist at all we don't know how long are we going to be alive the future self might be very different
than who you are today any future self ideas you have is just a
prediction a fantasy an imagination it might be a reasonable prediction but we
don't know the past is receded into memory receded into maybe
the residue of past experience in us but the past itself is just a kind of a
virtual reality of sorts and uh and memory of the past is not
always accurate the uh maybe maybe frequently is inaccurate and sometimes it gets more
accurate over time when a certain selection process and a certain kind of Storytelling begins to shift and change
and um and so the present moment is something very different than the past
and the future very different than fantasy it's the only place where our lived
experience can be the only place that our lived Humanity can manifest and be
this is a very important time and place um to really experience life because
everything else in life is not quite life it's uh kind of virtual or
something to pass in the future but here and so to respect what's here to Value
this these moments of Consciousness the value of this the heart beating and his
chance to experience and be in this life and to value
our well-being and to respect their autonomy and our dignity and
our efforts to try to make make our way through this difficult life
so to respect ourselves is uh maybe not always easy but the more
we have the self-respect then the more respecting others carries
value and it carries strength in it if we diminish our value and kind of
half-heartedly or on the sly or on the side or offer respect to others offer generosity
to others it could be wonderful but it's not received maybe as fully as it would
be if a person shows up completely there and there's a fullness because we
respect ourselves there's a fullness of embodiment here I am and this person here all of this person here is present
for you for a few moments with respect with care with appreciation so and that that carries a lot more
strength maybe power more more value for the person
and uh that we offer respect to we offer appreciation
and so offering having respect for oneself is not um you know it doesn't have to be an
overly self-focused phenomenon it's a it's uh it it's a important phenomenon
important way of being that allows us to convey and care and respect and love for
others in a greater way and it's almost as if you want to love
others if you want to care for others Begin by respecting yourself and with
that comes a tremendous amount of healthy care for others
a lack of respect for others can simply also be not because we disrespect ourselves but because we don't think
we're have time to take care of ourselves we don't have time to eat and sleep and
exercise and maybe meditate so that the best of us has a chance to come and meet
the other people so respect is an important element of
appreciation and and this is certainly the minimum
that is to really see that it's appropriate to bring our attention to really see and understand who's there
but it also involves seeing people as valuable as important some people might say precious that some
people might say that others are Treasures um but so not not just a lover not just
a family member do we kind of offer our wonderful love and appreciation and Delight but we can do it in an
appropriate way even for strangers and for people who are difficult in our
lives sometimes offering respect to people who are difficult
appreciation to people finding ways to appreciate them finding ways to respect
them is the ingredient for how to overcome some of the conflicts we can be in
so uh respect as a foundation
one of the foundational elements for being able to offer compassion in a full
and effective way if we offer compassion without respect
then we're in trouble I think people can feel that and uh and maybe then the
compassion sometimes might not even be accepted because the people don't feel somehow
that they're recognized in in any important way
so for some of us maybe the concept of respect as an ongoing
orientation might not be familiar might not be something we do but at least for this day
maybe you can do a meet again maybe you can carry with you the the notion of
respect and to see how you how that lives in you do you have respect for
yourself do you have respect for others if you were going to respect the people you're with what what form would it take
if that's appropriate for you how do you
embody respect how does that that the movement of respect to move through you
in your own way because for different people maybe different things would be considered
respect um and uh so for you what's a clean healthy form of respect for self for
others and what happens when you begin embodying that in your relationship to other people
and I use the word embodiment intentionally as a kind of wholeheartedness a whole bodiness a
whole wholeness you know really bringing ourselves into it in a more
full way than maybe usual so it's the intentional and purposeful and and
really really has this kind of a center stage uh for what we how we go about
so thank you and uh I value very much that you're listening to
this and maybe practicing with these things and I have a chance to teach them and thank you and I look forward to
continuing tomorrow