hello and good morning for those of you here
on who living in places where it's Dawn and uh or
morning and good day for everyone
else and there is a dangerous teaching in
Buddhism so dangerous that um I've been told that in one Buddhist country in
South Asia that um the government forbade Buddhist monks from teaching it
it's so dangerous and uh and that's the danger that I'll be offering you today so I
want to contextualize a little bit but first I'll tell you what the danger is
and that is practicing contentment and the reason why
governments don't like it business corporations capitalism doesn't like it
is that then people if they're too content they won't consume more if they're too content content um they
won't uh push themselves to work harder and and um build more make more make
more money and uh in a certain way maybe many economies are based on
discontent so they can keep going imagine the
headlines the world became content and economies failed
everywhere so it's a dangerous teaching and maybe is not always appropriate so
one of the ways of beginning a meditation practice is to settle down a
little bit and then check in with oneself and discern how you
are some sometimes what's needed is just simple basic
mindfulness sometimes what's needed is a little bit of more focus on concentration to overcome a distracted
mind sometimes what's needed is uh truth-telling to really admit to oneself
what's happening and then we can settle sometimes what's needed is a lot
of compassion a lot of care and kindness
forgiveness sometimes what's needed is
um what's useful at least is
gratitude sometimes what's needed is um
patience and sometimes what's helpful is contentment and primarily when there's a
lot of discontent sometimes there can be a contentment that just comes along where
we're not really driven by desires driven by an aversion to how things
are and we're just very content just to sit and meditate to have a certain contentment
to meditate it helps to distinguish between the actions we take in our
life some things need to change in life and and we're not supposed to simply be
content with how things are and not change things but when we're sitting to meditate we don't have to act
and now we're trying to orient ourselves in a very different way and if there's a lot of difficulties
a lot of emotional difficulties challenges that we have then maybe contentment is not the
right way of honoring and respecting that or it might be the contentment to
just be with it to be content this is what's true now and so I'll be present
I'll practice my mindfulness with this difficulty
so to check in at the beginning and deciding what is appropriate so for this today's
meditation on contentment if this is not appropriate for you you're welcome
to take what is useful or ignore what I
say so to assume a meditation
posture lower the Gaze
maybe with the eyes slightly open something different way of
connecting to oneself if one now takes some long slow deep
breaths breathing in breathing
out relaxing as we
exhale and if if as you exhale it feels good to close your
eyes feel the goodness of that clo of closing
them and letting your breathing return to normal on the
exhale gently relaxing the
face on the inhale feeling the any tension in the
shoulders and when you exhale relax the
shoulders
on the inhale feeling the belly as you exhale relax
soften
and the inhale feeling whatever emotions or state of heart you
have on the exhale a softening around
it
on the inhale feeling the state of your thinking
mind and on the exhale relaxing the thinking
mind
for
and then is there any place in your
body where you feel contentment either now or
at other times when you feel content where is it living
you when you have had contentment in your life feeling deeply content in the
moment what has it felt like in your body
what has it felt like in your
heart and in your
mind
and here we are meditating a remarkable
event for some of you it's a daily event it's still an amazing thing that
we have the ability time and circumstances to be able to sit down
to make meditate a Time free of our
responsibilities tasks of Life busyness of
Life maybe even free of some of the challenges of our
mind and to sit quietly to find something some way to
feel
content it's easy to be discontented which is always kind of
particular and overlooks the vast number of things right
now that we can be content
about
when people practice a mindfulness there's something very
important very an opportunity that's really
phenomenal the opportunity to be content with being
mindful content with a power of being aware without fixing
acting having it different just aware just
mindful for whatever is happening contend to breathe
mindfully breathing surrounded by an
attitude of content with this moment
here
e
for
if you're wondering often thought does that represent some
discontentment can you find a contentment where you're not focusing on
your thoughts contentment that comes from being present
here to this moment in this body this
breath
e
for
what might contented breathing feel
like what might relax in the
body
for
is
for and as we come to the end of this
sitting to appreciate that contentment is one of the great states
of being it's a healthy
state that represents many things but it represents or as an
expression of a mind which is not
discontented not struggling or fighting or resisting or afraid or caught in
desires and
conceits contentment allows this psychophysical system of ours to operate
without agitation without
something activated contentment allows us to feel
the
whole and to whatever degree that we appreciate contentment is a valuable
healthy state may we wish it for
Others May our contentment be a nourishment for
Others May our contentment help bring calm and
peace May our contentment help us to be more generous
and loving for Others May our contentment protect us
from being caught up in
ourselves May the benefit of practicing meditation be for the benefits of all
all people everywhere may all
people be happy
contented may all people everywhere be safe and
protected may all people everywhere be
peaceful able to rest at ease may all people
everywhere be free free of Oppression and
violence free of hostility and
fear and maybe this these possibilities for others be something that our practice
supports
implicitly unintentionally and intentionally may we contribute to the
welfare and happiness of this
[Music]
world thank
you
I'll be back in a
moment
so hello everyone and welcome to this series on the 10
protectors and so today's uh protection is as to do with
contentment uh and it's a particular form of contentment but before I talk
about the particularity of it I'll say a few things repeating myself from the guided
meditation that uh there are people who consider contentment to be a dangerous
State because it undermines uh the
motivation that people get from being discontented that uh uh if we want to if
we're discontented with the State of Affairs as we they are then uh we won't
fight we don't work to change them and uh and certainly there are
things we should not be content with and there are things that maybe are
not healthy to be discontented with the there are people who have
plenty of money who are discontented with uh what they have and want to be
richer than that there are people who have uh plenty of Pleasures but always
want more there are people who uh have plenty
of stuff but they always want more
better um and so to be driven by discontent is what supports you know
many e eies in the world and so there's there's a vested interest in people
who many people to keep us discontented so we keep buying or so we keep working
long hours to try to get ahead and uh and to kind of uh be
feeding or encouraging discontent is I think part of what advertisements do and and um
so to in some ways to be content in in
uh in certain ways is a radical act it's a disrupting
act um from the Buddhist point of view the benefit of
contentment is that then it's easier to focus on the practice to focus on what's
Happening Here and Now and uh if uh
there and then are is a two-dimensional reality and if fantasy is a
one-dimensional reality then uh being really rooted and grounded here in
ourselves um is uh entering into a three-dimensional reality it's more Rich
it's more multicolors like going from black and white to multicolor and um and this being this
three-dimensional reality of Now does not mean that we don't think about the past and the future or that we don't in
some ways let the creative mind fantasize but we do it rooted here we
don't lose touch with this place here and contentment is one of the great uh
states that helps us to be rooted and and able to stay here and the teachings on these 10
protectors the Buddha was giving the teachings to monastics and for them he
said that they should be content with the basic necessities of life and what
is not often recognized is the monastic lifestyle designed by the Buddha might
look like a deprived life from the point of view of how many people in the modern West might be living um but uh it was
meant in Ancient India to be the middle way where just enough uh basic
necessities are provided to live well but not more than that but not was not
not ancient India understood to be a life of deprivation it wasn't considered to be an aesthetic life because there
were people who uh were more extreme in that direction uh for the Buddha we were not
supposed to harm ourselves so there was no aesthetic uh you know flagellations
that was going on but rather uh this uh enter into this meditation that was
understood to be a pleasant abiding an enjoyable place to be provided that we
had the basic necessity ities and so what monks and nuns are you know content
with is um the food the food that comes in their arms bow the clothes they have
the shelters that are given to them and the basic medicine uh to uh for their
for their health so those are the four uh basic
necessities and to be content with that and how many of us maybe are not so
content with just having the having the basic necessities uh we have more the clothes
than we need and we are not buying clothes for the sake of just staying
warm and and protected from you know uh insects and such things dirt um but
we're getting clothes and paying a lot of money sometimes for um for other reasons and then to how many of us are
not content with having a simple roof over our house but we want a bigger house nicer house uh home or something
how many of us uh are not content with the basic necessity of food that we have
but we're you know buying food that's expensive and um we don't really need it
but it's so nice it's so pleasant it's so enjoyable and so for a monastic uh to be content with
the basic necessities then gives them it's easier to live ER radically simp simple lifestyle a lifestyle that allows
them to stay connected to the Dharma the Dharma that they love uh the the Dharma practice which they like to engage in
without having a lot of other things to take care of that um can make it harder
for this uh you know U Love Affair that monastics will have with the Dharma they
want to stay close to their lover uh it's so important to stay close and attend to it and let that relationship
grow and develop and flower um all day all moments of the life of of the
day so to be content with the basic necessities is the core thing here and
um for those of us living a l life it might be a little bit uh different what do we consider the basic
necessities uh the ancient Buddha didn't consider uh the emotional needs or the
interpersonal needs as as much as maybe is needed for people in modern cultures
and so we have a we have a richer kind of domain of basic necessities that we have to take care of um but
still uh can we find how much we need so we can be content and um and what is the nature of
our discontentment um if you feel discontented what is that why what's
driving the discontent uh is there some feeling of lack is there some feeling of insecurity
is there a strong sense of Desire what's that feeling of not enough like what's really happening here and is
there another way to address not having enough another way of addressing that
something has to happen have to do something I have to be busy and really to settle something here to relax the
belly to relax the shoulders relax the mind and the heart to really sit sit sit
down and learn how to be content even if that contentment is just for the period of the meditation
practice um the uh there are things we should be discontented about there's
healthy contentment and unhealthy discontentment uh there's
unhealthy there's healthy discontent and there's unhealthy discontent so both
both have their place and both can be unhealthy and so uh to be
discontented with our suffering to be discontented with a suff uffing of the world that might that's not necessarily
a bad thing that can be motivating for sure but uh and so we should act on that
one of the ways to act on that is to really sit and meditate and settle our
discontent um so that we don't add our suffering on top of suffering and be
contented enough to sit and be present for what's happening with us us and find the way through our Suffering From the
Inside Out out than trying to change the world around us so we don't
suffer and um and if we need to change the world around us because it is suffering then um to distinguish acting
in the world from the activity of meditating meditating meditating is not
the time to act this is a time for some other process to deepen and unfold and
to learn how to be content with a moment we're meditating so that we're not kind of still spinning and driven by the
desires to change the world or to get what we want or avoid what we don't want
uh to be content with our lives at at least for the period of meditation maybe
we have a time my Necessities are taken care of I have enough food for those of
us who do uh we have enough us we've had enough shelter for those of us who do we
we have enough clothing for those of us who do and we have enough medicine for now at
least for this moment for those of us who do and um and so to feel that
contentment that uh least for these minutes uh it's okay this is special
this is unusual for human beings to have the time the ability the wherewithal the
understanding the dedication to sit down and meditate meditation is a phenomenally useful and
important act and um it's a phenomenal gift to the world that the inner
transformation that can happen through meditation um where we don't continue life with business as usual with greed
hate and delusion but we settle all that's all that's unresolved un
unsettled in us so that in that settle State some of the most beautiful
qualities of our being can come forth and represented by things like
generosity love and wisdom and then coming out of
meditation we have maybe a better way of knowing how to act and if there we are
discontented with the State of Affairs then um we know how to act and what to
do if we are discontented with all the dirty dishes in our kitchen then we go
and wash the dishes in a meditative way in a contemplative way in a respectful
present moment engaged way that feels like we're bringing meditation with us into our life and it's an enjoyable
thing we're not rushing off and multitasking if what we feel is uh the suffering of the world
elsewhere uh whether it's you know anywhere right now Israel is huge the
suffering there the whole nation is traumatized or deep pain
uh Ukraine deep pain and um this goes on
if this really troubles us when we come out of meditation and we're discontented with those States then maybe we have the
generosity of the wherewithal to do something about them and even the smallest little act um may be offering u
a donation to Charities or to uh someone who's uh helping the sick and the
wounded or doing something we don't want to uh meditation
is not how how to be calm and uninterested in the world it's to be deeply
contented with ourselves with the moment in a certain way so that the what
motivates us to act in the World to Change the World comes from a place of
tremendous well-being comes from a place of generosity comes from the Wellsprings
within of our goodness not from the agitation of our fear and distress and
our anger this is the possibility that contentment can bring so I would encourage you today to
explore this the your contentment and your discontentment do you would you care as
you go through the day maybe once an hour check in with yourself and would you characterize how you are as more on
the discontented side of the spectrum or more on the contented side if you're
discontented what's happening what is that about can you settle it can you be present for it can you investigate it if
you're more on the contented side of the spectrum feel that enjoy that take that in be nourished by it and if it's just a
little bit on that Spectrum uh by recognizing the small amount of cont contentment you have is there some way
that's appropriate way to settle into it more fully so it becomes a resource that
supports and guides your day so thank you very much and
um we have two more of these 10 protectors thank
you