good morning everyone and welcome my name is Dawn Neil
is the volume okay so we will break with tradition and do
some lightly guided meditation most of it will be in silence but I'm just going
to offer a little bit of guidance to help us settle in and for the benefit
of our friends online
so the invitation is that wherever you are
wherever you've come from
to settle in and acknowledge where you are right now
scanning through noticing any energy that it took
to get here to sit down in meditation
and acknowledging too
the generosity or aspiration or intention
in your heart and mind that you're bringing to this meditation
feeling into that feeling it into your heart your body your heart mind
and taking in the goodness of whatever that is
and if you haven't already perhaps taking two or three slower maybe a
slightly deeper breaths
letting go on the exhale allowing
releasing releasing any excess energy your tension
and inviting in a sense of being nourished
nourished by your life's breath on the in-breath
and releasing any special way of breathing any controlled
kind of breath and allowing
allowing the breath to be natural
writing your belly hang Softly
and inviting the rhythm of breathing
to soften everywhere the sensations touch
sweeping through your body inviting a softening there to
balance of relaxation and alertness
and inviting an openness a kind internal gaze
to whatever arises in these moments of meditation
non-contention okay
settling settling in on whatever object of attention
feels most soothing prominent steadying
for you
thank you
if something else arises in consciousness
flurry of thought to sound it's okay
acknowledging it noticing
this too is a moment of awareness mindfulness
and then return Ed to this moment now
the anchor of present moment awareness
thank you
foreign
all right
[Music]
foreign
taking a moment again to feel into
what this was like maybe with a tiny kind internal gaze
noticing whatever nourishment goodness benefit
even little tiny glimmers may have come in our time of practice together
and the invitation then is to turn that internal gaze outwards
advocating this time of practice to an intention
of goodness kindness towards the others in your life
may all beings benefit from our practice together
so welcome again those of you who came in mid meditation welcome to IMC Welcome
to our friends online also part of IMC before the talk our manager bill has
some announcements thank you Don is this audible okay yes
uh two announcements one mindful parents is meeting in the
conference room today that's that room over there from 11 A.M to 12 15.
so parents of children of all ages are welcome
second we're having the first potluck since before the pandemic
next Sunday here May 20th May 28th at 11 A.M
so you're invited to bring a vegetarian dish to share with several others if you are unable to bring food
please bring yourself and enjoy the Sangha informally after the Dharma talk
thank you were there any other announcements thank you
thank you Bill and thank you Mark and Joe and everyone else who all the other wonderful
volunteers here who help make IMC happen and some quite a beautiful thing
so um this morning I want to talk about
some beneficial ways of moving through the world that both support and express maturity
of Buddhist practice or spiritual practice more broadly
and I'll do that through a series of of stories or vignettes we'll kind of tease
it out as we go along so knowing that's where we're going
Once Upon a Time imagine yourself back in Ancient India
North India the time of the Buddha more than 2600
years ago it's the Bronze Age
the snow-tipped peaks of the Himalayan Mountains jut up against a pristine vast
sky planes and Rolling Hills it's an agrarian society and it's
heavily influenced by caste and as we zoom in on these little nation-states proto-nation states that
were evolving at this time the winds takes us to a country called
kosala it's a good country led by a benevolent
monarch king possanity and
his rule is proficient
skillful kind
Sula is among many many different protonation states at that time that are kind of jockeying for power or a place
in ancient North India and at the time of which I speak a
neighboring king the king of a country called magada decides to unprovoked attack
the good Kingdom of kosova so suddenly kosova finds itself at War
and so far in this story we're more or less in the realm of historical fact
all of this happened commentaries on the ancient Buddhist
teachings commentaries I relate to more as ancient myths with all the embellishments and
the wisdom that myths have they have stories about this time
and one of these stories is of a peasant girl young woman
the daughter of two flower Growers and her name in English is Jasmine or
Jasmine bud and she like pretty much all kids back then in
agrarian societies helped her parents out with the flower growing business
in one day she's walking to the field for a day of work Gathering flowers and she has her
whole days worth of meals with her all three meals in her basket and as it happens on that particular day
she encounters a group of wandering mendicant monks on her way to her work
and the leader of these monks is so Sublime so radiant has so much presence
and kindness that she spontaneously
kneels down bows and offers all of her own food for the day into his bowl
and the Buddha but that's who it was Smiles at her and she goes on her way and he goes on
his way when she arrives and starts Gathering the flowers for the day she just has
this joy in her from her generosity from the encounter with this radiant Sage and
she's filled with this sense of confidence and joy and it kind of just bubbles out of her and she sings as she
works and she gathers the flowers
well later that morning later that day the good King posanity was returning to
the Capitol from a battle that did not go well tough day
and he's riding his horse along the road and he hears Jasmine her poly name is
Malika singing and intrigued perhaps pleasantly distracted he rides
his horse over to where she is in the fields well filled with that confidence that
joy that happiness Malika doesn't do what a normal
low-caste peasant would do when a king approaches she doesn't hide she doesn't bow down she doesn't have her eyes Down
cast but instead as he approaches she smiles and as his horse comes to a stop right
next to her she looks up into his eyes gently grabs the horse's reins and smiles at him
and he is transfixed absolutely stunned
first words out of his mouth when their eyes matters are you married
no sir no Lord I'm not and at that he Dismounts
and as The Story Goes he started to confide in her all of the tribulations
all of the troubles his concerned for his troops his country his people
confiding in her eventually they sit beneath a tree in her heads and his head is in her lap and she's stroking his
hair and consoling him well after some time the king is
consoled it's a touching scene right and he rises
up and he asks her would you please accompany me on my horse and she agrees so he lifts her up on the
horse gets up and together they ride to her parents house where he asks for her hand in marriage
isn't that a sweet Cinderella Story right
so that is how Malika Jasmine became
possanity's first and most beloved Queen she wasn't perfect but she was valued by
her King and her country for her compassion her strength her wisdom
and above all her concern for all people of all casts
her care and compassion for her common the common people
and her lack of any pretentiousness snobbery
so let's pause for a minute and I want to just tease out some of the themes of this story so far
so Malika's actions the spontaneous generosity she let herself really feel the joy of
that the joy of that giving right and that in turn led to a confidence as
she reflected on absorbed her good actions joy and confidence and self-respect
went a long way towards the interaction with this King
all of these all of these traits Joy generosity which is the laypersons
letting go right some release a giving up
the confidence the trust all of these are really beautiful mental
qualities internal attitudes to turn back around and bring
to our own meditation practice
it's helpful to learn to celebrate or at least acknowledge our own good qualities
our own good actions in particular this feeds nourishes the relationship we
have with ourselves and with our practice
this doesn't have to be anything complicated if you're like well no I haven't done anything good it can be as
simple as the aspiration to suffer less to sit down to practice to develop the
mind and the Heart through meditation
it can also be as simple as a single act of generosity
through your day or your week an act of kindness or a stranger
sort of a modern modern anecdote from science about this there's a scientific
researcher that has done a couple of studies on the effect of kindness and
generosity on The Giver and one of these I think it was his first
the study participants were recruited at an ice skating rink so it's cold right
I'm not sure if it was indoor or outdoor but they keep those places cold and their task if you can call it that
was to give away free hot chocolate to total strangers
and they followed up both with the study participants and with the total strangers receiving the hot chocolate
and some interesting things were learned first
the study participants had no idea how good it would make them feel
to do this not just in the moment but through their whole day
and they also underestimated how good it made the recipients feel
not just the Boost in the moment of receiving the sweet treat but the warmth
and the kindness of being thought of at all being offered anything at all rippled through their day too
and it turns out it made them more likely to be kind and generous
so everyone underestimated the power
of the kindness and the generosity
so that kind of uplifting warm effect on
ourselves and others can be nourishing nourishing to relationships nourishing
to practice all right now I'm at act two of the
story of Queen Malika and King posanity and in this scene
the king and his young fairly new beautiful queen are up on the castle between two parapets they're on some
kind of porch or duck type thing and they're looking out it's a glorious
Sunset and they're looking out at the Horizon the mountains etched against the sky the Dusky Indigo Villages and Fields
and it's kind of a touching scene
the king turns to his wife and asks in all the world Malacca
and all the world wife Who Do You Love most
who do you hold most dear and
commentaries some of them say that pasanati pasanity expected his
wife to answer that it was him and the ancient commentaries opined that
it was because he would have thought that because he lifted her out of poverty to the most powerful position a
woman could possibly have in that day and I think of it as more of a maybe a
tender vulnerable moment Between Two Lovers husband and wife spouses
one feeling may be a little shaky and insecure and turning to the other
and asking about their affections in any case the moment stretches on and
the silence thickens and Malika finally answers holding both of
her hands and his his hands and hers sorry their hands are clasped and she
looked straight into his eyes again with all that love and wisdom and says my Lord
it is myself I hold most dear
oh wait a minute that's not how a love story usually goes is it so much
well he was taken aback too in that moment maybe a little hurt
surprised but they hang in there and they stay in the conversation together
and with her luminous eyes her hands still
on his she looks up and says my Lord truly
Who Do You Love most in this world
as happens often between them and these ancient stories her words really give him pause and
after some moments of Silent reflection pasaynadi turns back
his eyes to hers and still holding hands he admits I do hold myself
most dear
so I suppose there are people listening who might think of this as a somewhat selfish exchange a cautious admission
between two of the most wealthy and powerful people of their day but I don't see it that way
instead though it's impossible to know with ancient India Millennia between now and
then what all the cultural resonance was what the cultural context was we can't know
that but from where I sit in Northern California
two plus Millennia later there's a modern psychological perspective to bring that her love for
herself her regard for herself could be the Wellspring from which the
love for her partner flows and for that matter for anyone else
and she has the Integrity to say that and encourage and be able to hear her
partner and his perspective too
that kind of mutual honesty reads this courage and integrity to
and that kind of honesty that positive self-regard those are also very powerful
bases for any relationship to others to ourselves and to our practice
King vicinity though like this really was on his mind he journeyed a little ways to go see the Buddha
consult the wisest Sage he knows the teacher to which his wife has entrusted
her spiritual life and he relates the conversation and asks the Buddha about it
and the Buddhist Age We nods and affirms that what Malika has said is indeed wise
and true and then the Buddha
unpacks the significance of what Malacca has said and he talks about how
searching all directions with your awareness
you won't find anyone anyone dearer or more Central to your
life than yourself and it's the same way for others too
each person holds themselves as the reference point holds themselves
as most dear and the Buddha is teaching about this whether or not we agree with this
presumption in our contemporary Society is that anyone who loves themselves
anyone who cares for their own life shouldn't hurt others should practice non-harming
so self-love is assumed in early Buddhist teachings and it's taught
as the initial basis from which to cultivate love kindness non-harming
towards all and
for some of us this is challenging this is a challenging assumption
for many people raised in contemporary culture so
another way of understanding it I touched on as I'm named his teachings which is to notice that for most of us
most of the time ourselves our perspective is the most Central and
primary even if we absolutely love and sacrifice
for our kids or our partner or the people we care for there is that Central reference point of
self and seeing this being honest about it helps develop
perspectival empathy Compassion Care a true understanding and respect for
other people based on the notion that they too have this Center Point from which
they're living their lives all sentient beings do
this is a basis for non-harming
at its most mature it's an alternate way of understanding this notion of Buddhist
conceit many of you have heard of this idea of being better than or greater than less
than or worse than or even equal to this is um
one of the last Fetters one of the last kind of Bindings that hold people back
from waking up and instead of that greater than less than or equal to
this teaching encourages a sense of wow
we're incomparable we're unique each person each life is precious to
itself and
common to commonly bound together by the wish for happiness
so when the self is no longer at the center of things
wisdom arises and when wisdom arises especially in relation to others
kindness and compassion naturally flow
in a field of responsive equanimity
and this brings us to the third and final vignette in the story of posneri
and his wife Malika there's one night maybe this was some
time later where the king had a series of many disturbing dreams 16 disturbing
dreams in all there were these visceral kind of nightmares that sound totally real and in them he heard the moans and
cries of suffering people but they're they were in kohaid he
couldn't make out what they were saying just a syllable here and a syllable there
he woke up in the morning perturbed really shaken and began to reach out and
consult some brahmana priests who happened to be nearby
these Brahmin priests interpreted his dream for him and they interpreted it as
a Calamity a massive catastrophe was coming to the realm
wow hassanity was shaken by that too and the brahmanas assured him that a large-scale
sacrifice would prevent this horrible event or series of events
from happening so somewhat reluctantly but wanting to do the best
for his people he agreed and it was a large sale sacrifice not just of animals but for efficacy they
were supposed to involve four human beings too innocent human beings
so Malika I'm not sure if she'd been away or whatnot but she hadn't been involved or around
and she returned to the castle to see all this activity with all these brahmanas preparing for this thing
Gathering of animals and people and digging of pits and all this and she goes to her husband and says
Dear what's going on what's happening and he explains and moved by compassion
as well as perhaps some wisdom she tries to persuade him to call off
the sacrifice and he's reluctant he doesn't want to kill and he also doesn't want to harm
his realm but she does persuade him to go see the Buddha at some distance so he
Journeys to go see the Buddha and ask for his interpretation of the dream
and the Buddha's interpretation is ethically based
ethically based it um includes
the Buddhist acknowledgment of the king's sensitivity of his concern for his realm but puts an ethical lens on
the whole dream and pasta Nady is so moved by this that he becomes a
follower of the Buddha on the spot and when he comes home he agrees to
Malik as a wish for non-harming and calls off the sacrifice
many lives saved even after they both became followers of
the Buddha the king and queen supported many different religious sects many
different kinds of Faith followers and in a
gesture of generosity I it was not long after this they dedicated a park
in their realm to the Buddha and his followers and in that Park Queen Malika
had a Hall built and this Hall was for the purpose of interfaith and
inter-religious dialogue peace building tolerance
so they were big supporters
so themes here the concern for well-being of others
but when that is dominated by reactivity it can lead to interpretations that
aren't necessarily so helpful or leaning outwards for knowledge in ways that aren't helpful
Malika's compassion and wish for non-harming broadly
non-harming and then not arising from reactivity the
wise person perhaps in this story the Buddha with concern
what's best for oneself others self and others and all concerned
everyone and this is the definition of wisdom one of the definitions of wisdom in the
ancient teachings
so to summarize so far the traits behaviors exhibited evoked in these
stories could be described of as practices belonging to the Buddhist sort
of Developmental basket if you will of Sila ethical ways of moving through the world
concern for other people these include the joy of generosity
laypersons letting go confidence and self-respect
that come from appreciating our own good actions
Trust kindness positive self-regard or self-love
honesty and compassionate regard for others
non-harming
so all of these all of these are also deeply beneficial ways to relate
to one's own mind and heart and practice some of them will be more accessible at
times than others and even just the wish for them is a helpful
energy to start to bring to the practice
so here I'll transition because
we're moving now into talking a little bit about meditation the samadhi basket
in the Buddhist developmental schema meditation basket of produce
and there's a famous discourse many of you have heard of this
the acrobat discourse a master acrobat and his Apprentice
whose poly name translate to as frying pan of all things so it's a little bit of a playful story
and it's got a lot of Truth in it so in Ancient India acrobats these
acrobats in a way used bamboo poles to do their tricks and the deal was that
one acrobat would be on the ground standing or walking around doing their thing and they would balance the pole
either on their forehead or on their sternum and the other acrobat
their job was to be on top of the pole doing their trick
so it's quite a precarious Act of balancing right so the master being the more experienced
was in charge of sort of holding the polls steady and right before their trick he says to
his Apprentice my dear frying pan
here's how we're going to do this I'll look after you and you look after
me and that way will perform our tricks safely get finish up and collect our fee
and The Apprentice considers this for a moment and despite being younger less
experienced and a woman in that Society she says I don't think that's the best
way to go I need to look after my own balance and
you need to look after your own balance and that way we will both be safe
perform our trick and collect our money well
they did they were safe they collected their money and at some point the Buddha heard about the story
and the first thing he said was that you know The Apprentice is right
mindfulness is a way of looking to our own balance looking to our own heart and
mind and life and body that not only helps us move through the
world in a way that is more harmonious for ourselves but it also protects others
protects others from us and
the master was right too the concern the loving concerned regard
for others that expresses as ethical comportment Selah
that is a way that we take care of each other so they're both right
and together these are powerful ways to move through the world that support a deepening of meditation
and they can blend together blend together
so one last short anecdote the Buddha is often depicted in these
ancient teachings as traveling from place to place often from one group of monks to another
and a group that turns up particularly often is a group with a famous monk
named anaruda and this particular group is a joy to
visit talks that suit us talk about how pleasant they are to be around they're
described as being like milk and water Blended harmonious viewing each other
with kindly eyes wow
the group of people living that way they were enacting it becomes clear I'm not
going to read this retort recite it but that they are holding themselves in mindfulness and looking out after each
other and this enables the harmony to happen they're supporting each other with and
I'm quoting here mental verbal and bodily Acts of kindness
when these conditions are in place it's possible to go with the flow pretty easily right
and this kind of restraint consideration
non-contention lends itself to cohesive Community whether home or work or
neighborhood and turning inwards
it lends itself to deepening of the meditation practice
now getting there isn't always seamless I would say it's not seamless for any of
us it's helpful sometimes to consult a teacher in the Buddha when he was traveling was indeed the Consulting
teacher that this group talked to it's also helpful to consult the teacher
Within your own heart take time metabolize
turn inward to meet everything that's unfolding The Good the Bad the Ugly
patients kindness a kindly gaze of curiosity
interest with that kind of internal gaze
internal weather our systems naturally move towards most often wholeness
integration healing and Awakening
discernment will develop and eventually this inner congruent
discernment and letting go ripen into deeper levels of spiritual
maturity wisdom and unfold towards Awakening itself
so those are my thoughts thank you very much for your kind attention
we have about 10 minutes for questions comments if anyone would like
to offer them I think it's easiest for all concerned if you use the microphone if you have any
Floors open and if you're comfortable saying your
name that would be great sure hi first name yeah my name is salsa
uh I just wanted to point out Malika does not mean Jasmine it means Queen so
her name already meant Queen and she got the title okay thank you and the poly English
dictionary gives Jasmine Bud as one of the definitions of Malika or Malika of
Malika m-a-l-l-i-k-a yeah yeah so it's in the
poly English dictionary I'm from Nepal like that's my name is
not Nepali yeah yeah it evolved right so I'm sure Malika came to me and queen
probably because of her or maybe not but these myths conflate and blend names
like that so but it is um thank you for that I had not seen Queen in the dictionary but in
the poly dictionary p-a-l-i not Nepali one of the meanings this flower jasmine
but appreciate it any other comments
hi I'm Soul um I'm kind of new to Buddhism and I really loved all your story it was very
touching so I'm just wondering like if there is a good introductory book that I
could find and read more about it to find out more of our stories like the
ones that you told um so most of the introductory books don't have those stories in them but
they have more of the principles and the ways of practice in them are you more
interested in the stories or learning about sort of the principles and the practice maybe both both okay fair enough
so um a great place to start with the practice is a dhamma Donna book a freely
offered book that's here which is called the issue at hand it's a series of short essays that kind of unpack the practice
in a really relatable way um they're by Gil franstall and then
another good practice book of which there are many is mindfulness and plain English
by Bonte gunaratna and that is in the library on the other side of this wall here you're welcome to check it out if
you want to and then as far as the stories go the
stories that I conveyed in in this talk are all in an anthology that was
translated by a man named bikubody a very famous and revered translator Monk and it's called
something like great Disciples of the Buddha maybe some places to start thank you
thank you any other thoughts quibbles questions
comments
okay in that case I have an invitation for you those of you who are interested
um we have about seven minutes left of uh formal morning program and I'll stay
around for a little while we'll gather some chairs in the parking lot maybe for 20 minutes after around 10 45. but
meanwhile the invitation is to turn to two people near you and welcome them here even if it's your
first time here give them a warm welcome and maybe mention something anything
that stuck out for you in this talk that was um helpful or resonated or reminded
you of something so um please don't overthink it just turn to a couple of the nearest people
ideally someone you don't know super well but if that's who happens to be here that's fine