greetings everyone good to be back with you
I'd like to offer my apologies for the technical glitches yesterday
before we started um and to thank you for your kindness
in that respect so we're going to pursue our
training in emptiness with the aspiration of cutting through
the illusion of self
and so to begin we recognize the wholesomeness
of mental seclusion
so knowing the tendency of the mind to proliferate
we carefully place all our concerns worries
stresses outside the meditation space
we can come back to them later no need for now
so begin by assuming your meditation posture
settling in whatever is supporting you
whether it's the cushion the floor bed chair
and feeling the contact this body
and this is contacting with the Earth
and closing the eyes if that's comfortable for you
and letting the attention
um to the breathing the long slow deep
inhale and exhale
as a way of connecting
and we'll do a brief but hopefully loving body scan
bringing warmth and kindness and meta
to all the parts of our body and as we do so
relaxing them to the best we can
so starting with the head
the eyes are closed
and see if you can feel the muscles in your face
see if there's any tensions anywhere in the forehead or behind the eyes
around the mouth any sort of folding
and it's a lovely thing to soften that
and bringing our loving attention down through the neck
and then letting go of the shoulders the arms and the hands
and down through the Torso the heart
your belly developments
loving awareness through the legs and down through the feet
and now making the connection with the Earth
and drawing up the Earth's energy through the feet
up through the legs the pelvis
the belly the Torso
the shoulders arms and hands
the neck the face
and the crown of the head scalp and that little opening
a remnant the fontanelle
we can let that loving awareness shine out
into the sky
so being grateful for this body however it is
and now solutioning our mental state our mind
state with a taste of meta
lighting a little candle in the heart
and letting it farm and encourage
this body
and then little by little that he had spread out
far and wide to the front
the right that's it back to the left
above and below
gently radiating that down doesn't matter how far it goes
the intention is benevolence towards All Creatures
everywhere in this universe
I'm now keeping that flavor of meta
as a sort of background theme to our meditation
inviting the mind to rest in the body
resting in the body is a home
it's a safe and wise space for placing our awareness
if you like you can imagine the myriad biological processes going on in your
body and they
experiencing the body as flow in constancy
constantly changing and fundamentally empty
of a self
and we can move from the Ecology of the body to the Ecology of
the Earth and since our interdependence
with all the various creatures on the Earth
each breath
taking in oxygen and and giving away CO2
sharing these molecules with who knows what beings
and when and where
We're All in This Together I like to say and um
I find thinking of my life in ecological terms
should be very very beneficial
it's really physically the case that there is nothing substantial that
we can really reified as a self that's in control of
everything
it simply doesn't exist
and these molecules that we share and receive
this process is so ephemeral who knows
who's participating sometimes we breathe in
molecules that somebody else perhaps like
[Music] they're Buddha perhaps may have breathed in
some of the molecules that we're breathing
and then getting down to Basics seeing the body in the body
and this means that we see the Dharma in the body
knowing our own and others bodies are just impermanent phenomenon
and now opening up our awareness to whatever is arising Moment by moment
through any of the sense doors and very carefully
attending to our lived experience
this is crucial because in each moment
we create the causes and conditions for the next moment
and so the crucial importance of seeing clearly
of keeping our mindfulness fully in gear
so that we can see when something arises whether it's wholesome
or unwholesome and then we can decide which way to go
and instead of choosing the path of bondage
being stuck we can choose the path to Freedom
may my practice be a cause for awakening
so whatever you do choose mindfulness
keep practicing like this
foreign
weeping our awareness on our lived experience
in this body in this place
In This Moment attending to whatever Horizons
and seeing that clearly
seeing the inconstancy of all that we experience
the flow of our experience
and being friends with whatever arises
and choosing which path to take
if something less wholesome arises
as we come to the end of this sitting we reflect on the goodness
of this path of practice and we each open
our Circle of Care to offer whatever wholesome conditions
we created in this meditation [Music]
to benefit all living beings on this planet
mayola beings everywhere be safe
and protect it being safe
may we be contented at ease
may we all abide in peace
and may all of us and all beings everywhere be free
about you all about your breakfast and I invite you
to join me as we bow to each other with gratitude
for this circle of Sangha
greetings everyone welcome back to uh this series on
training and emptiness
as you may know the pillar uh the pillars the three pillars of the
Buddhist path are ethics and samadhi
and wisdom in Bali it's uh Sila Samari Banya
um and it's really important that we keep
in mind that we have to bring all that
into practice in order for our meditation to be at all
beneficial so we begin by
doing our best to be ethical
in body speech and mind and I also take generosity
to be to be a part of being ethical
in addition to the five precepts
generosity because we're not just doing this for ourselves and it's it's a great thing to keep in
mind um the importance
of other people again an opportunity for
letting go of our obsession with Me Myself and mine
so samadhi or deep meditative composure
is not an end in itself it when it gets deep it is very
pleasurable and it can even be a trap if we get attached
to it but the purpose of deep meditation
is that it's allows us to collect the mind
sufficiently and to be sufficiently empty
in order to have the insights that lead to Freedom
to Awakening
so um yesterday I began reading to you from
uh the Buddha's shorter discourse on
emptiness and this is the um
and um if you were there yesterday we began with
uh Ananda going to the Buddha in this beautiful
um building and the forest um with where the monks were all practicing
meditation and he went and paid his respects and sat
down and and something was on his mind and he said and he really wanted to make sure
he had heard things right and he asked the Buddha to please um
let him know if he indeed heard correctly that the Buddha said previously
that he often abides in emptiness
and the Buddha was delighted by this question and confirmed yes indeed
I abided in emptiness then and I often abide in emptiness now
and then he begins to explain uh to Ananda
um what it means to provide an emptiness and how you might
actually approach deeper and deeper uh States
of meditation that become more and more um
empty so
um
what the um Buddha affirmed to Ananda is that
it is really important in order to dwell on emptiness to
um be clearly aware of our experience in
every moment and we should know as practitioners what
is present in our experience and in addition to that we should know
what is absent so
um
it's uh the teaching is that whatever is present is empty of itself
it's it's not it doesn't have thingness uh it is essentially uh a process
um the uh
our body and whatever we experience is empty if anything that's
uh substantial uh or eternal
so after this introduction that I read yesterday the Buddha goes on to say
thus one regards what is not there as empty
however as to what remains there one clearly knows this is present
thus Ananda this is the genuine undistorted
completely pure descent and to emptiness
and then he goes on to give some instructions and
here I'll be the the Buddha Buddhist text uses the word biku which means Monk
and uh Scholars now agree that um Biko can refer not only to monks but
to all monastics including nuns and to lay disciples as well
so I'll be using the word practitioner as a translation of Bitcoin
a practitioner attends to the Oneness dependent on the perception of Earth
through the perception of Earth the Mind gains confidence
becomes settled remains still
and is inclined towards release
so the advice is in this phase of the
gradual entry into emptiness this phase is
being aware of the Earth as a way of
not being so attached uh through oneself and to details
so then the Buddha goes on to say um
not attending to any of the rivers and ravines
the tracks of stumps and thorns the mountains the uneven places
what attends to the Oneness dependent on the perception of the Earth
so perceiving the Earth in its globality without
getting bogged down and uh specifics
in details and then he says
through the perception of Earth the Mind gains confidence becomes settled
remains still and is inclined for its release
so this is this is a refrain one clearly knows thus
whatever stress there might be dependent on the perception of people
that is not present here there is only this measure of stress
the Oneness dependent on the perception of Earth
one clearly knows this field of perception is empty
of the perception of people there is only this that is not emptiness
the Oneness dependent on the perception of Earth
thus one regards what is not there as empty
however as to what remains there one clearly knows this is present
this Ananda is the genuine undistorted completely pure descent
into emptiness
so we experimented with this a bit in in the meditation [Music]
and the idea is that
um we begin with mental seclusion with physical seclusion as we do when we sit
down to meditate and then we cultivate mental seclusion
um seclusion from the hindrances seclusion from the chattering mind
and uh
and then there was a step in between which was
the forest um but the text is repeated in each one
and today I wanted to begin with um
this phase of the gradual approach to emptiness which is
awareness of the Earth and we don't have to know everything about the Earth we don't have to know as
the Buddha says all the mountains and Ravines and rivers and so forth and
Fields so
this is um a very interesting instruction to not
get bogged down in details because as soon as we start doing that
the mind starts roaming around and um
and it's very easy to indulge in some sort of reification
so helping he's trying to help us out of the very human
tendency to reify our experience
um and I find that particularly helpful because I tend to be way too much of a
of a detailed person and um there's an expression in English
the uh the devil is in the details and
that's uh I've certainly seen in for me that that's the case I I can get
um by details and you know I wanted to make sure everything's in the right place
and uh that's the way it should be and this is not skillful uh on the path to
practice so if you would like some homework for
um the week or I mean not that we for for the next
24 hours um see if you can in your experience uh
really pay attention to where your mind is going and not just in meditation but in daily
life as well and if the and see what you're focusing
on are you focusing on people uh or what and then if you want to
simplify a bit the invitation is to focus on the earth as a unified
perception it's grounding it's settling
and uh it can help us to stay centered
and then as the Buddhist says
the there is only this that is not emptiness
the Oneness dependent on the perception of Earth and thus one regards
what is not there as empty
however as to what remains one clearly knows this is present
thus this is the genuine undistorted completely pure
descent into emptiness
thank you for your attention thank you for your practice