hello everyone and happy to have this time
together with you and to offer you teachings that are
close to my heart and and to share this meditation
time one of the ways of
translating the very important word of debana or
Nirvana is it translated as release one translator translates it as
unbinding and so often Buddhism is associated with letting go but it's sometimes for the English
speaking audience that doesn't really capture the richness the depth the
essence of what this is about and sometimes I think the word
release works really well so if we our our hand is in a tight grip we can
release our grip we might still hold on to what we're holding but we release the
grip or if we are tied up in
knots the Buddha talked about the uh untying the knots the releasing of the
knots that bind us or we're covered over something inside
is covered over and so there's an
uncovering there's a lifting of the weight the burden that we
carry and then there's a lightning so all these things imply something really nice that happens the release of a grip
there's there's a kind of an ease or relaxation lightning of a burden we feel
light lighter untying the knots of the mind and the mind feels released or free or
open so the emphasis here is on how we benefit from releasing whatever we're
holding on to clinging to so maybe this meditation that can be
the emphasis release release whatever you're preoccupied with release
whatever you're fixated on or caught in release the preoccupation release the
way in which you're relating to what's happening when the relating
is not free or light or open
allowing step back into that space where there can be release releasing the grip on your
thoughts releasing the resistance to what's uncomfortable releasing the hesitation
to be honest with what's happening release the attempt to get
away release the drive to acquire
and attain make something happen just release release
so assuming a meditation
posture and lowering the
Gaze and maybe closing your
eyes and begin with an effort to
Gentle the gentling of yourself within a gentle
calming a calm gentling of the
heart relaxing as you
exhale
letting your attention roam around your body relaxing the body as you
on the exhale relaxing the thinking mind softening the
Mind softening the edges of the
Mind
e
and then centering yourself on the
breathing letting the physical sensations of breathing be an
invitation to feel your body more fully to feel how your body experiences
breathing
for
tuning into the rhythm of the body breathing in
and out the rhythm of the Torso expanding
and
Contracting
for
and then gently without a lot of effort a gentle
effort as you inhale let there be a
release release of your thoughts your
tensions the grip in the mind in the
heart not a full release but just a gentle
opening maybe as the Torso expands with the
inhale things are allowed to release
outwards float away open
up
and then a gentle release on the exhale as
well release of the DI from the
Torso a releasing of things the mind thoughts feelings the grip the holding
the resistance any ways that you can let things on the
exhale just wash off slide off
relax
and letting there be a rhythm of release on the
inhale release on the
exhale maybe slightly different movements of release with each
one not being ambitious just loosening the edge es
softening incremental movements of releasing where there's tension or
contraction holding
preoccupation congestion in the
mind
for
e
for in these few minutes we have
release even what you don't want to let go of for the at least for these few
minutes release with every
breath
for
e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting there is a
release that allows a more open
Attunement receptivity presence for other
people release of being guarded or holding on to
resentments or fears
and at least for these couple of minutes during this meditation in the quiet and
peace sitting here to release whatever blocks your
heart so you can gaze upon the world with Good
Will so that you can make a connection between your
meditation and wishing others
well between the ways in which you let go relax open up in
meditation and how it makes you a better person to relate to
others and in that better way
to give expression to your good will with the following
words may all people be
happy may all people be
safe may all people be be
peaceful may all people be
free and may we stay close to a
heart that wishes this for others and contributes it contribute
contributes to the
[Music]
possibility thank [Music]
you
so hello and welcome to this Monday day when we begin
another 5 days of talks and uh I thought I would finish my
life story around in relationship to Buddhism last
week I kind of thought that was plenty of time but um there's still some more
to talk about so we ended up on Friday with um
my decision to go to Burma to follow up with my first
experiences with vipasana in Thailand and that it took a while to get the visa Burma had been they didn't know
this but was closed to any foreign or at least Western
travel and um until about maybe June or so and I was able to get
there in September I was there for eight months at a meditation Monastery and in those
eight months uh was the headquarters of what's called The mahasi Meditation movement it was probably the biggest
uh you know terad Buddhist Meditation movement of the last
century monk named mahasi saow kind of formulated a way of teach of practicing
vipasana that was very effective for many people and it spread very quickly
there's when I was there there were maybe 300 centers of this practice in in in
Myanmar and had spread to first to Sri Lanka and then to Thailand and then uh
uh it came to United States and one of the kind of initial people who really
got it established here was Joseph Goldstein and Jack cornfield and Sharon sburg and Jacqueline Schwarz they came
and had come out of that scene and in Asia and came and started teaching it
here so I went to the headquarters the source of it all and there was was a very large Monastery kind of like a
community college campus with some 5,000 people meditating there at a given time
spread around the complex and um and it was to do
intensive meditation we were supposed to get something like 4 hours a night of sleep at night and uh otherwise uh
practicing throughout the day two meals a day breakfast and lunch and then um
most days there was a meeting with the Abbott for about 10 minutes and most days he gave a Dharma talk around 4:00
in the afternoon and um in otherwise uh I
practiced mostly during the E months in a my small smallish room it was small
enough it was big enough to have two beds in it and I had one that I slept in and meditate on on and um often did The
Walking meditation in the room sometimes outside in the hallway and um and it was uh some I
would say one of of the most wonderful times of my life uh I had a lot of joy
and happiness and just Delight to be doing the practice um and I came there out of my
zen practice having you know I was still a Zen priest and I um had this idea that I was
going to continue with my zen practice which I defined to myself as an unconditional acceptance of the present
moment and um and but I was going to learn to do it better and that I was
going to follow the instructions of meditation teacher upand say and in
order to do that unconditional acceptance because what I had learned from doing Vasa practice is that my
unconditional acceptance of the present moment that I learned to do in Zen had
was very U meaningful for me very helpful for me and and I'd learned to be pretty settled
and calm and peaceful and um and and resilient in my
life but uh it was only kind of in the macro moments in the larger picture of
scale of things and what I learned through vasna is in the micro moments the small you know in between everything
or underneath in a deeper layer there was a lot of non-acceptance going on a lot of wanting resisting not wanting
judging critic criticalness it was very much more deeper and so the kind of the surface kind of issues of my life had
kind of been settled in a very important way but there were still deeper Roots
deeper um activation there that um I wasn't often aware of but in the aposta
practice and they more careful momentto moment attention um and the deeper concentration I could see was still
operating and so I was going to follow the instructions very carefully and uh in order to do this
unconditional acceptance this was extremely important for for me because
uh the teacher who uh upand he was very uh he was like a little bit of a general
he's kind of like a uh you know if uh um
you know he was going like um he wanted us to strive he wanted us to try hard
try harder try harder stay up all night it was always kind of pushing us to
strive and um it was some westerners under his tutelage they crashed it was
uh really difficult for some people who somehow their Western psychology didn't
match very well the striving effort that he he was often pushing for but I didn't
buy into it I had this resiliency and this acceptance that I had from Zen that
I did together with uh the careful attention that he wanted us to have and so um and so it worked for me
fairly well uh in the beginning first two months I was there I did kind of uh
try you know put in more effort than I usually would in Zen it was a little bit maybe in order to kind of because of
upand was so demanding you kind of okay I'm going to really try to practice here and we had
to uh run an account every day we saw him of how much sitting meditation and
walking meditation we had done in the last 24 hours we had to kind of sum it all up and um and he would hear we had
to be honest right so we had to hear how much we were practicing alone in our rooms and if it wasn't enough his
eyebrow would go up and here having this kind of fierce General's eyebrow goes up was enough to like we don't want to do
that again and so I would sit and walk much of the day much as I could and um I
would never do laundry uh on the um uh on the days I was going to see him uh
once a week we had a day off from seeing him and that was the day that I would would do my laundry and do a few other
kind of cleaning things so that because I didn't want to report less time for
meditation so I practiced along and I was happy to practice but then this amazing wonderful thing happened is that
he left for Australia for two months to teach a retreat there and as soon as he left I was poised in a nice way I think
it wasn't it wasn't conscious of this that something in me relaxed and when uh and that I had the
momentum and then I relax and let go and settle into a much deeper place of
well-being of peace that you know that was really wonderful and that became
then the entry point for me to go deeper into Vasan and I had uh experiences of
release and freedom that i' never had before in my life that were life-changing for me and uh teaching me
how deeply release can be I had a sense of peace I a sense of the value of
Letting Go I had a sense of clarity and a lot of things before from practice but
um uh it felt like I reached kind of the the deepest possibility of that in my
experiences there under that those eight months of practicing there and um and it
was uh I didn't realize it at the time um but that uh over time I came to
realize that this was life-changing um at some point I decided
to continue doing the practice by uh going to um uh I wanted to now tell
really teach uh practiced with Western teachers who I could really make sure that I had good um communication with
rather than through a translator and also I found that uh we didn't eat anything afternoon and I found that um
it didn't quite work for me that I would better if I could have just a little bit of a snack in the late afternoon or
early evening to sustain me you I was very thin I was I think I weighed 140
lbs and so I had no reserves to manage to get through the the evening so I came
back to America and um and I was going to go to IMS Insight Meditation
Society but um uh something um told me so at some point I felt too
weary uh to go I have was signed up to go but I felt to something inside of me some deep weariness that was not I
didn't identify what it was but I said no I'm not ready to go and so by then I
was back at the San Francisco Zen Center and I was asked to uh take a kind of leadership position there in the
meditation Hall got the meditation hall manager um for the year so since I
wasn't going to IMS and I had nothing else to do I was actually you know I was a Zen priest and you know I had no other
life plans so I was I felt very lucky to be able to spend another year back at Zen
Center practicing there and that was a nice integration practice for me from this intensity of being so full on in
Burma to uh then being a community and in a monastery
and and then during that time uh there was a man who had been at Burma with me
he was a monk had been a monk and um and he came to see me at
Green Gulch and uh in the conversation with with him I reviewed and talked
about what had happened to me in Burma I realized that um uh the way I practiced
I had overemphasized concentration and that I didn't realize that and uhand tried to tell me that but
I the way he told me I couldn't understand couldn't understand what to do with it and so the amazing thing
happened when my friend when I realized this and talking to my friend uh immediately that weariness evaporated
and immedi immediately I said okay now I'm ready to go to to continue at IMs
and so then I went um in the fall
of 1987 I went to do a three-month retweeted IMS with uh studying with
Sharon salsburg and Joseph Goldstein and um and to continue their
practice and um and that was also quite wonderful for me to do it had different
challenges than I had before but it was really wonderful and um and in the process of
doing that um I had a similar kind of deep releases I had in Burma that
clarified for me uh kind of an understanding of this possibility of of
uh what the work was about oh now I felt like now I understand that um that oh
this is the practice at the essence of it is this deep release uh of uh all holding all
clinging but what I learned at IMs which I um which I hadn't learned before in
theas was I learned about Goodwill I learned about meta when the teachers there they didn't
do this in Asia but the teachers in America included guided meta meditation as part of their the three-month Retreat
and um as a Zen student it was that was too art official or too sweet or too not
authentic to do this kind of phrases and stuff about meta so I I tuned out the
teachers when they did the guided meditation until in this deep deeper
releases that I was having in practice meta arose and then I said oh that's
what they're talking about and then I had something as a foundation for
practice of meta and living from that meta full place well I did Zen practice
I was compassion doing Vasa I was metad I was good
willed I don't know if these two different movements were inherent with the practice that I was doing or whether
it was really the phases of my life because Z I really was contending with a
lot of my suffering um a lot of the conventional suffering of my life and in um in in
doing bipasa um there was not much suffering uh there was a lot of physical
pain at times when I was at IMs but not a lot of suffering and then I
um I um um and but there was a lot of
Joy a lot of happiness and it was was kind of being softened and softened and
softened in a very different way that I had been in Zen or during that Zen time
and in that there awoke in me this meta and kindness and
friendliness and then became the kind of the orientation around my practice
leaving IMS was very much had to do with um um this release this deep
freedom and this meta this warmth that came out of it and uh that seems like a
good place to leave off um and because then I came back to uh California to Zen
Center and uh wondering what to do next I'd spend that time I'd spent almost 10
years in monastic almost monastic life and uh wondering what to do next
and that will be where I pick up tomorrow thank
you