readings greetings friends readings from Mountain View California
and see that Olney land where I'm joining you in this moment in time whether it's morning or whatever
time it is in your time zone wonderful to be joining you and practicing to get together today so
so we've been exploring um why speech this week and we'll continue
um let's practice together I'll give us
some invitations for exploring our inner speech
and um and yeah I'm excited about sharing more
um about this topic this very important topic uh during the dharment so
so let's uh let's begin let's begin to sit together
ah choosing a posture an intentional
posture that is supportive for you
In This Moment In Time
if you are sitting you could be lying down or standing as
well but if you are sitting allow your back to have an upright sense
a sense of integrity
as if you're sitting tall like a mountain
the Integrity of your body mirroring your inner integrity
your inner intentions for integrity
let there be a brightness
a form that feels wholesome in your posture
but not effortful not effortful
might be able to imagine An Invisible Thread connected to the top
of your head pulling your head gently up supporting you up invisibly
ah spine straightening vertebrae by
vertebrae and yet the rest of your body the soft tissue the muscles can
relax and relax give their weight to the Earth
bringing down down the center of gravity that's often
in our head somewhere around her head with thoughts I bring the center of gravity of your
being down through redirecting your attention down
down down [Music] and your face
down your neck and your chest and your heart center
proverbial hard Center of the chest
place of wholeheartedness emotions and then continuing to move
your awareness center of gravity
of your beingness down through your diaphragm foreign
[Music]
your lower abdomen your sit bones
and let the center of gravity be in the lower abdomen said bones maybe touching into the lower
the upper legs lower legs and feet as well
but receiving receiving the breath and the lower abdomen
as if the body itself is an organ of perception
perceiving receiving the breath knowing the breath knowing Sensations
not from the control tower of the head
letting the body the heart be soft relaxed
upright and relax
In This Moment tonight
and if any thoughts arise any inner speech
gently kindly no it's important to know
oh what is the tone what is the quality of this inner speech of this thought
we started with inquiry is it true is it factual
is it different true for self-judgment you're a terrible meditator or some such
opinion is it even true yes it do and true said even factual
a sense of humor challenging the facts of this opinion
the thought is about others is it divisive
said harmonious
no today especially noticing let's say gentle or is it
sinner speech tone especially when it's directed towards
ourselves oh sweetheart no need for any harsh tone
no need
kindness kindness and after knowing after the knowing the
landscape of the Mind releasing releasing
and letting the breath in the lower part of the body the sensations of the breath
aches and restraint Center Stage Center Stage
in our awareness that's all
is the way you're receiving the breath you're listening to the breath the sensations of the
breath does it have gentleness or harshness in your listening
in your receiving of the sensations
what's the posture of the mind of the heart
foreign
our bodies are attuning Fork
paying attention by knowing
it's happening in the body
we know it's what's present in the mind the quality the quality of Earth
intention speech inner speech
by calming the body
kindness we can realign and soothe a mind
and as we bring set to a close together
appreciating if there was just say one moment of awareness and aligning
with our values yay celebrating that you showed up you've
done your best letting go of outcome non-attachment
to how things should be or should have been but appreciating yourself
for your your engagement recognizing the goodness for showing up
being part of the Sangha
and together with generosity offering our goodness suffering our best
to all beings everywhere to the world our good intentions are
our integrity our kindness may all beings everywhere especially
those who are suffering with natural disasters right now
parts of the world are siblings
may they have ease may they be free from offering may they be safe
may all beings everywhere be free from suffering male pinks everywhere
be safe happy healthy have ease may all beings everywhere be free
including ourselves
[Music]
greetings greetings everyone
so today our third day of of exploring together the topic of why speech
and um on Monday we started with the first
um question to ask ourselves and by the way all of these go together all these six
that I will be sharing so so if one of the conditions is not met and the last one I want to give you a heads up the
last one I'll be sharing on Friday is is it timely is it the right time so even if it's if it's not divisive and it's
true and it's today we'll talk about gentleness it's not harsh um uh if it's kind all is everything is
is uh satisfied still if it's not the right time then we don't say it so so
all of these go together um so I wanted to add a little bit of nuance actually to the teachings from
yesterday and and the day before before we um going to the new question today to ask
ourselves if our speech is Harsh abusive or is it gentle so that's the new
question and and on Monday we talked about is it true and factual and um and
yesterday the question was is it um is it divisive is is this speech
divisive what are we about to say divisive or does it create Harmony
so a couple of nuances to add to the teachings one as I already mentioned
that they all go together um all the questions and the other
Nuance um is regarding um truthfulness
um is what we're about to say true but it doesn't mean that we just blurt out
everything that is true all the time because of course there is wisdom in
what is appropriate to say when how all of those other considerations come
together come come in um and also again together with the
other considerations with truthfulness often um folks bring up this this hypothetical
situation oh if I were say if I were alive during the World War II and I was
um uh giving safe keeping to to people who were
persecuted at the time and they were hiding them in my basement and and and say soldiers Nazis knocked on the door
would I have to tell him the truth well I appreciate the the um people who think
this way and and really try to engage with what what does truthfulness actually mean there was a bigger
question of what is of benefit what is kind of 360 degrees what if what is of
benefit what is of least harm so in this case telling a lie that saves a life in
this case of someone who's Prosecuting the bigger picture of all things of course it makes sense so it's it's not
about um sticking to a particular rule without
context without um non-harming this this this
um wish for greater goodness and non-harming in a bigger way so
it's so important always to to um bring in the context which again maybe this this inquiry or this question
in a uh uh more um how should I put it in a uh more
casual or or disinquiring a more casual way when somebody you know puts on
address and tells you do I look fat you don't blurt out yes you you know you just have to be a little Kinder you know
the other other aspects of kindness come in but how can you be but um
and nevertheless the the this this precept uh of of not lying not shading
the truth really has to do with the intentions really it goes back to the intentions and that's something I've
been trying to stress how does it feel in the body why are we lying is it for
uh our gain is it because of hatred like what is what is the underlying intention
motivation so really let that be the guide um is are we deceiving in order to get
some gain similarly similarly
the what I mentioned yesterday with the question of is it harmonious or divisive
also there's wisdom there you know you don't want again not divide people up
because you want your friends to just be your friends and break people up you take joy in in Discord
um again it comes back to the intention however Buddha also has teachings about if say something has happened
say something has happened and another person is invited to say did you
see something you know that person is supposed to say what what has happened you know what did they see if
um in in a way say um uh if your friend is about to let's say
hire someone um who you know is going to be a really
bad match um and and it's not going to work out
for a variety of reasons of course it's not wise to hold back oh I don't want to be divisive like what is the intention
here the intention you need to out of kindness for everyone with the heart of
loving kindness for everyone involved oh this this is given these facts in the past maybe you
share but this is what this is what you need to know again out
of kindness out of kindness or always goes back to the intention and and what is happening in the the body
um uh and and in the mind in terms of intentionality so
so now with with those nuances it was very important nuances adding more and
more layers as we continue this week the third question to ask is is it harsh
is it abusive speech what the way I'm about to speak or is it gentle
so so the Buddha instructors of course to abandon speech that is spoken in
anger or with a mean sarcasm intended to
demean to insult to cause pain to make someone feel bad it just it's it's it
has it has shards in its speech that has shards in it
laughs this kind of abusive said in an angry
tone is often is um the root of it is aversion the root of it is hatred one of
the three poisonous roots um a very agreed hatred and and the
illusion so aversion is its root and it's often impulsive it doesn't
involve forethought the same way that Slanders and divisive speech that we talked about yesterday did so slander's
speech has doubly heavy Karma because it's both has its as its root has has um
hatred and it it involves forethought but but just a slightly lighter Karma
this has lighter Karma because it's impulsive just we're just angrily and in a mean way we just say something and
maybe later we feel bad and yet ouch we both heard our Karma we've heard the other person the ripples in the world
the Ripples and the way it's affected us ouch ouch ouch um
still on skillful even if it has a lighter negative Karma of course
um the antidote the antidote to to this type of unskillful speech is patience is
the parames the beautiful quality of patience patience patience
so if you find yourself to be someone who just blurts something out and
regrets it later in in a angry tone in a
in a sarcastic rebuking demeaning insulting it's like ouch out and you feel about patience in that moment
it could pause come back to the body just not speaking is the best thing causing
the least harm causing the least harm is the best method and later when you
have your calm the right time then you can address it so patience
patience patience beautiful quality of the heart and of course when speaking wisely is is
just impossible in a particular situation our secondary goal becomes causing the least harm the least harm
to ourselves to our own karma really causing ourselves harm with with unwise
speech and of course to others and to the relationships that we have to others
and then the Buddha instructs us instructs us to um not just abandon
harsh speech but speak gently and and I love these words the Buddha directs us
to speak words that are soothing to the ear affectionate go to the heart
or light likable and agreeable to the people I'll read
them one more time it's like poetry so pleasure like poetry speak words one speaks speak speaks
words that are soothing to the ear affectionate go to the heart
polite likeable and agreeable to the people
this reading that is goes to my heart and feels affectionate the Buddha really I
it's almost as I hear his his affection and kindness through the Through the
Ages yes yes dear Yes dear this is so thus this is how you should speak
okay so so as we go throughout the day today
um my invitation is to notice um is it harsh is it is it gentle or is it
harsh and oh yes another thing I want to add especially is with this one in particular not just
external speech our external speech might actually be gentler and gentler than our internal speech sometimes we
speak to ourselves in tones that we would never ever bear or or want to use
with others or so that the tone can be so harsh so are so ouch
ouch notice the ouch of that um and not needed can we bring bring
kindness can we bring compassion can we bring gentleness um can we say the same thing but in a
very gentle way um so so as we go through the day
um I'd like to invite you to to notice notice the tone of your speech the inner
speech and the outer speech is it um is it soothing to the ear
affectionate go to Ghost of the heart polite likeable and agreeable to the people or is it harsh and abusive so
okay thank you so much for your practice for your cultivation dear Sangha and
um and I look forward to our continuing this Exploration with why speech
tomorrow take care be well