good evening
many of you are already meditating
just to say that we'll sit for 45 minutes
a little Derma talk
so I'll see you in 45 minutes
good evening hello can the volume be just a tiny bit louder
because I feel I'm stressed or I feel like I'm making
my volume a little bit better and I'm just saying words so the volume okay
there we go thank you thank you otherwise I feel like at the end I'm
really straining so thank you sveta
so welcome welcome so tonight I'd like to talk about
this phenomenon that happens sometimes around the end of January or February or
March somewhere in there where we have maybe these ideas that
we're going to begin a meditation practice with uh we have a lot of enthusiasm
we're gonna sit more or sit longer those of you who are here right
I already have a practice but sometimes we might have this idea that
we have this great resolve and we're going to meditate every day or we're going to have compassion for all beings
all the time we're we're going to follow the precepts exactly and never tell a
white lie again or all these types of things it's not uncommon at the beginning of the year the end of the
holiday season to have these ideas I think it's pretty common in fact
but then something happens and we lose Steam
we lose kind of the momentum or the motivation
and then what we earlier had been so committed to and yes this is what we're going to do then it just turns into a
chore and something that we don't really want to do and we find ourselves feeling like
I'm too tired I'm not going to do that I'm not going to get up early I'm not going to drive to IMC I'm not going to
stay up late or it's too hard everybody else seems
like they can do it but I don't know I need to find something easier for me or I don't know there's like this Untold
number of little Expressions that we can have for ourselves or
can be telling ourselves if why we're not getting to the cushion
and maybe we completely abandoned this whole idea and kind of gets put on the
in the pile of other things that we thought we would do but hadn't quite got around to or
or maybe we spend some time kind of beating ourselves up
there's this quiet little voice saying well you said you were gonna sit longer or sit every day and you're not and it's
just like that other thing you were going to eat will exercise more you know all these things that we say we often do
so I'd like to kind of describe this using this word of resistance like there's
some resistance uh maybe I'll say specifically like getting to the cushion
cushion being some meditation practice so this resistance or maybe there's a
way in which we sometimes I like this word I feel like I'm in a tussle with myself this little you know little
wrestling match kind of there's a part that's come on Diana now they're probably like no I don't want to
I think it's not so unique to me but I think this is part of the human
experience but there's a way in which there's can
be resistance to even just getting to the cushion or if that is not something that's a problem maybe it's already a
habit to sit regularly this idea of resistance can come up or
even this idea of a tussle or a struggle can come up even if we are on the cushion and we don't want what's
happening to be happening and we're struggling or pushing it away or
resisting it so if resistance shows up in all kinds of different ways even for us to not get
to the cushion but if we are there to not be with what's happening
and so I'd like to talk a little bit about resistance is just a natural part of
practice and how to just work with it in a way that doesn't ask
us to no longer be resistant it's not asking us to be somebody that
we're not or to completely maybe I'll word it this way the practice
meets us where we are and if we're filled with resistance then that's how
it is but it's a natural that the mind I'll say this Rebels when we're trying to
train it when we're trying to you know try to keep on coming back to the present
moment or the sensations of breathing it's natural that sometimes when we're
meditating and we notice that um are lost in thought and there might be this
sense of oh yeah I'm supposed to get back to the sensations of breathing or whatever the anchor is
but then there's this other idea of like no I want to keep on thinking this this
is interesting or I'm going to solve this problem finally or this is entertaining or something like this
right our minds are used to kind of wanting to be destructed and entertained
and it's going to there's going to be some resistance to training
I think this is true not only for humans but for all creatures
when we want to train them to do something
but part of the function of this practice of
coming back to the present moment or if you're doing loving kindness practice to
keep with the loving kindness or if you have a chanting practice or we don't do a lot
of chanting here but if or if that is part of your practice part of all of
these practices is to help us learn something about
ourselves because how else would we notice the
resistance things don't show up only in meditation
right they're a part of our experience so this resistance is showing up in our
daily life but maybe we're just not noticing it because we're distracting ourselves or going on and doing the next
thing or um providing a justification or rationale why we need to stop doing that
and start doing something else or something like this but part of the function of this practice of like okay
just keep on coming back whether it's the breath or whatever practice it is loving kindness or chanting whatever it
might be is to notice resistance
and to notice how it feels to get familiar with it
and as best we can to stay with it to stay with the practice
and if we didn't have this and I'll talk a little bit more about that but also if
we weren't trying to like bring our breath back to the sensations of breathing
then have what's might we realize that we have these attitudes
and they mind these maybe These Quiet attitudes that aren't so obvious that
are our resistance is causing harm to ourselves or maybe causing harm to others
in a subtle way maybe we wouldn't even notice
I'll say for me that um I mean if you look at me right I'm kind of like conservatively dressed and I
like appear as a conservative person and for the most part I am like if you think of my life story right it's pretty
conservative for the most part but I didn't realize Alice and I started
to realize oh I have this rebellious streak I don't like it when somebody tells me what to do and I just really
hadn't noticed that so much until I started to sit and I realized you know
okay now bring the Mind back and there was always this no I don't want to kind of attitude that would flare up
and then I started to notice oh yeah that's um I can see how the profession that I
chose was one where I could have a lot of autonomy where people don't tell me what to do you know I was trained as a
Scientists scientist is all about questioning Authority right you don't just go with the received wisdom but you
would discover things that are new so there might be something to learn
to discover about yourself just to recognize what role resistance has for
you not only in your practice but in your life
so what do we do when resistance arises
I'm gonna offer a few things that we can do and one is
maybe without you know let's say we have this resistance we don't want to go meditate
okay so we're not going to meditate what if we just investigate right there
what is it why don't I want to go sit which is probably exactly what you don't
want to do but I want to offer this as a a reflection because if there's some
resistance that means that there's really just one
thing usually I would say and this one thing is that there's
something in our experience that we aren't accepting or there's something that we don't want to look at are there
something that we're trying to push away or ignore or not to be with and whatever
way we can do that because if we were kind of like just letting
accepting things or being with how things were then we would just go sit and that would just be the next thing
that was arising but there's a way in which not
being with not accepting what's happening is fueling the resistance is showing up as
resistance so instead of resisting this resistance or struggling
with the struggle or getting all tangled up there's a way that we can just ask the
question just ask the question it's the activity of asking
that is the step forward not finding the answer
but asking the question and so what question is this
what is happening right now that I'm not open to
what is what is happening right now that or what do I imagine will be happening
that I don't want to open to
and maybe just feel into that without the idea that you have to find an answer
and that right there is such a big part of practice just to have that activity of investigating
investigation is the second factor of Awakening it's a real it's an integral part of practice
so of course mindfulness meditation has a role but so does investigation
but we have to be careful when I'm using this word investigation this is not
an exploration of why
why am I resisting it's because it reminds me of that thing that happened I was eight years old and then my brother
did this and I really should have done that you know that's not what we're doing here it's just having this
question of what would happen that I don't want to open to or what is happening right now
that I don't want to open to
and maybe something bubbles up maybe something doesn't but asking the question is a way of
being here and now in the present moment and that's the practice
so in some kind of way you tricked yourself into practicing you're not on the cushion necessarily but you know so
much of practice is not on the cushion so it can be a trap if we think that it's you know older or not that we have
to be on the cushion or not so once we become
maybe aware of like oh yeah there's this difficult emotion or I feel
embarrassed or ashamed that I didn't do that thing I was supposed to do I was late with that I didn't send that email
to that person or I keep on rehashing this painful conversation I had or
rehearsing in a difficult conversation I need to have but as soon as we become aware of that
then our relationship to it shifts and so much about this practice is about
just becoming aware of and shifting our relationship to what's happening
because all of us know we don't get to control what's happening even though we would like of course
but instead just to maybe get in shift our relationship to kind of uh
not looking at it to like oh yeah that's what I don't want
and maybe maybe it ends there but maybe also there can be some
kind hearted adjustments
some kind-hearted adjustments
so what's a kind-hearted adjustment
maybe is to recognize the difficulty
and recognize the humanity of that experience
like learning to do something new
never easy never straightforward if this is a beginning of a meditation practice
takes time but isn't a linear experience that you know just get better better non-stop of course not
in the same way if you ever learned to play a musical instrument learn to swim learn to play tennis learn to knit all
these things right it's oh it takes time and not every and there's mistakes that get made and put
it down and maybe pick it up again so
same as a whole other experiences but also recognizing that being present
for uncomfortableness is not easy
and if we're anticipating that there's going to be some uncomfortableness or even right now in the moment when we
think like oh it's time for me to go meditate but I I feel lousy
it's hard it's hard to be with uncomfortableness
so maybe this one of these kind-hearted adjustments is to recognize the humanity
all humans have this experience it's not easy to learn something new to change a habit
and it's difficult to be with uncomfortableness
and there's a way in which that might soften a little bit some of the inner
critic that might be that's associated when we're not have when we're not getting to the cushion when we have this
resistance I'll talk a little bit more about the
inner critic in a moment but if all of this were easy
then just think there wouldn't be so many self-help books there wouldn't be New Year's resolutions how many podcasts
are about you know getting better or doing something like this right there's this whole kind of like societal push
right okay we need to do something better so just recognize that this is part of
the human experience and maybe that's a way in which we can
have a little bit of compassion for ourselves
for others everybody else who's trying to make a change do something different
when there's a sense of like oh I I really should be meditating or if you
are meditating there's this resistance like um I like I don't want to do that like if the mind is like keeps on
bouncing off of the object of the breath and chew is off and uh
fantasies or planning or whatever it is
another kind of inquiry to can be a real support for this is
just to notice the sense of self
that's present and what I mean by that is
usually when we have this sense of like I should be doing something that sense
of I should that's often accompanied with a strong sense of
me here and the whole rest of the world there it's a little bit of Me versus the
world is this kind of a subtle feeling but it's really has this sense of me versus
the world or if it's not quite like that it's the feeling of it's up to me I have
to make it happen if I don't do it it's not going to happen
and so there's I don't want to there's a way in which that's true and
not true and if we get really stuck in the sense of it's all up to me and it's me against
the world then that's a place that's really tight and constricting and
there's not a there's not a lot of freedom there there's not a lot of ease there instead
it's a real sense of tightness and
sometimes it can just feel despair comes from this kind of place
and this isolation and shame and all these kinds of things are
associated when we start to get this really constricted I should do this
so to kind of like make this point I'd like to contrast this when we have this feeling
like I should be meditating more to contrast it when you're doing
something that you really enjoy one of your favorite hobbies
cooking at the kitchen sometimes I kind of like to cook this is kind of a
I don't know if other people have this as well maybe I'll use the example at first some
of you know that at IRC The Retreat Center the teachers make the breakfast
and I do not have experience cooking for 50 people right so
so for me when it's my turn to make the breakfast you know there's very clear uh instructions
but you know there's just a lot of stuff to do and and while I'm doing it there's this kind
of like a focus like okay this but oh wait okay that has to be done so that this gets done on time but then take
care of this and you know the coffee you have to make sure the coffee is the butter has to be a little bit melted and the peanut butter don't forget the
peanut butter you know like all this kind of stuff but um there's a way in which I kind of love it there's this uh
you know just making things happen in a sense that it's also it's like an
act of generosity it makes me happy to think that I'll be uh serving others you know that what I'm doing will benefit
and support others and so there's a kind of like a delight
in it so maybe there's something like this for you if it's not cooking maybe hiking
being out with nature and being amongst the trees the redwood trees
for me I would say especially the redwood trees or knitting drawing whatever it is
notice or remember bring to mind how you feel when you're doing those things
versus how you feel when you have the sense of I should meditate more
when we're doing these pleasurable things these uh these Hobbies the reason why they're
pleasurable is because there isn't such a strong sense of I and we have access to both of this this
really constricted I must do it it's all up to me and then just this flow of
making things happen or getting lost and just the knitting
whatever it might be and we can watch during the day how we
kind of like go from this really tight sense of I should to some um they call
it a flow we might say this like Flow State dancing singing knitting whatever
it might be and throughout the day we were going back and forth so when you have this sense of like I
should go meditate is there a way that you can maybe like
shift over to like open up and realize oh yeah
yes I'm here but I'm also connected to all kinds of things it's not completely
up to me I need to have heard about these teachings or even knew about this idea
of meditation to begin with there is that former self that had the
idea it was gonna try to sit regularly or maybe there's a app that you listen
to or a dermatuck you listen to or a book so there's these other people that are supporting you and maybe there's the
you sit on a cushion or you have a favorite chair and maybe there's the manufacturer of that cushion or that
chair or that also helped make that cushion come to being and can start to
think about like all the different conditions that are coming together to
support sitting and this can be a little bit of a mental list and this is one way that can help this
shift from I should it's all up to me to something that's a little bit more
relaxed and open and kind of like going with the flow of the process and sitting
is just the next thing that happens so that's something else that can be a
support for practice when there's this resistance and if it happens that you still don't
get to that cushion but just going through that exercise enormously valuable
enormously valuable just to be remember that we're connected
everything in the sense maybe I'll say it this way we are not as isolated as we
often feel it's not all up to us in the way that we are imagining
and instead we can feel into all the other conditions that need to come together
so simply notes that might be part of the resistance of not finding way to the
cushion is there might be the sense of well I'm not sure like what practice to
do is this really the best practice and maybe if I just found the better teacher
it would be easier what if they were just a better practice
or you know seems like the those people are doing the Tibetan practice they look like they're having fun they have a more
colorful things and or maybe I should do that right you know so there's these ideas that well maybe if I just had the
perfect teacher or the perfect practice then it'll be easier and I'll wait until they find that
I like this story that Jack cornfield tells
I think it's uh yeah it's very I think it's very helpful he talks about this very thing about this idea that we have
about our teachers and practices and he said uh some of you may know Jack
cornfield is that Elder in this whole tradition and he is one of the primary
people who brought it from Asia to America and so he was a monk in Thailand in the
1970s and he practiced with ajan cha who
recognized as one of the greatest Buddhist living Masters I don't know at
the time right I've never met ajanta of course but he's highly esteemed so Jack was a student of ajanta and Jack
tells this story how he was one of the very few westerners who were
in Thailand in the 70s in these monasteries he might Jack might have been the only one
and he and Jack tells a story about where kind of this you know American hubris
says to arjon try this esteemed meditation master he says you don't seem very enlightened
I guess because ajanta would I like I don't know what he would do but and so ajanta responded
it was good that he didn't seemed enlightened because then you'd still be looking for
enlightenment outside of yourself was pointing to you're looking for
something outside but it's inside you're thinking that if you just look at
your teacher that somehow you'll get everything that you need and Jack tells
how this was a really important teaching for him because he realized how he had been
doing that right he had moved to Thailand formerly he was in the Peace Corps if I remember correctly and
that's how he found himself there but this idea that enlightenment's not out
there it's not really for the perfect teacher or the perfect practice right so
much of it is us what we are doing and that it's helpful for us to see and
to recognize that we can take the beautiful teachings that make sense to
us that make our hearts sing that are really important for us and moving for us
and we are welcome to leave everything else behind we're not saying this isn't All or
Nothing proposition we're saying take what is helpful and useful
and you can leave what everything else behind
it's also helpful to see and Jack tells this that you know some teachers
are he's when you write in the history of Buddhism in the west there's
certainly been lots of scandals you know some inappropriate behavior
and jacket says you know there are definitely some teachers who get really
compartmentalized so they might have some freedom in one area of their life and they're
maybe able to help people support them with their practice but maybe they're also harming people in
some other areas so he's saying because people have teachers have harmed it doesn't mean
that they haven't also helped some people and this was helpful for me to hear
because Jack went on to say he said this happens in all areas of our of humanity
that Nobel prize-winning physicists might be completely disconnected from
their bodies may you neglect their bodies so they have some real skill and one area of
what it's like to be a human but not so much skill in another area in the same way some Olympic gold medal winning
athletes might not have in touch with their horm or emotions and be able to express their
emotions so this idea that
teachers that we are welcome to take what's helpful and to leave behind
what's not helpful and maybe to put aside this idea that we have to wait until we find the perfect
practice for the perfect teacher until we really kind of like commit to
practice commit to showing up for ourselves on the cushion
and maybe something else that can be a help for resistance if we have resistance
is notice if there are any beliefs
sometimes we have these hidden beliefs that have this idea that there shouldn't
be any discomfort in practice like so often we come to practice
because we want some ease we want to relax we might have this idea that we
could Bliss out or something like this and so it feels like if there's any discomfort whether it's physical
discomfort sitting or emotional discomfort emotions are arising that are difficult
or just to see how our mind is sometimes is a little bit astounding and
uncomfortable to see what our minds do
so just notice if we think that we should only be experiencing peace and
ease all the time it wouldn't be surprising if we had that idea because certainly
Society leads us to think that anything that is uncomfortable is a mistake
and something has gone horribly wrong and we have to blame somebody this is kind of like the message that we get but
have you noticed pain is part of human life
pleasure is part of human life too inescapable and so there's this way in
which this kind of message it should all just be happiness and rainbows and unicorns kind of idea that I mean I'm
saying that it's kind of silly and exaggerated but there might be these underlying beliefs that it we can't
do anything except really Pleasant experiences on meditation and there's no
value in being with some of the difficulties when I say that out loud I think all of
us recognize that there are difficulties but there might be these like I keep on using this word hidden beliefs
so notice maybe I'll say one more thing about this
that because the if having this idea that there
shouldn't be any discomfort puts us in contention with reality
because there is discomfort being a human being
maybe there's a little bit of discomfort in the way you're sitting right now but part of the resistance that we might
have to get into the cushion is because we're anticipating it's going to be uncomfortable
and it may be but is there a way that we can say well
okay that's just the way it's going to be today maybe increase our capacity to tolerate
some discomfort
and then maybe the last thing that I'll say I have a
I'm trying to decide here which what what's the last thing that I'll say here
's what I'll say if you have resistance of going to the cushion or meditating
or even if you are meditating in your in a meditation posture but your mind is
doing anything except meditating
do another type of meditation practice
do walking meditation walking meditation be fantastic
you can even do this in the whole way in your house I do this sometimes I go from the kitchen to the bedroom to the
kitchen to the bedroom I don't know it's you know it's kind of nice actually
do some love and kindness practice while driving
through some loving kindness practice while you go for a hike for all the beings that you're saying
there because remember the purpose of meditation is to
transform our minds help us see clearly in these other practices support that
too but what can happen is if we are resisting going to the cushion and then
we don't go to the cushion then this whole story gets created like oh I haven't done it for four days and what's
the use I shouldn't do it again or something like this but that's not helpful but just do what you
can okay I'm gonna be mindful while I'm washing the dishes after dinner
okay I'm gonna be mindful while I'm brushing my teeth whatever it might be so just to do
another practice and maybe you do that other practice for a while
days weeks whatever it is and but it might be a bridge to get back
to the cushion because if we have this All or Nothing idea then it just starts to get harder
and harder to get back to the cushion but instead if we have this idea that well there's lots of different ways of
practicing and I'll say a little bit about
loving-kindness practice because I did a whole series some of you
may know that it I was teaching what we call happy hour twice a week for years I did this and I
just ended this week actually but I did um for a couple months this I'm working
with the inner critic on how to do this and it turned out to be really impactful and helpful for a
lot of people or so they tell me right so you know I
only hear the nice things there might be things out there there are people like that's terrible I wish Diana would stop but you know they don't tell me that so
I don't want to make it seem like everybody loved it but
there's a way in which we can do some
practice specific to work with the inner critic and maybe I'll talk some more about this in a
later talk but I'll just introduce the idea
is first it's kind of like just soften the heart in mind
and to do some loving kindness practice where it's the absolute easiest this is
critical easy easy easy for some people this is imaginary
kittens puppies and babies because right we don't have there's you
know it's imaginary right so it's easy to these cute things whatever it might
be for all of you meditation mustard some very esteemed
meditation Masters Jean Brahm he describes uses a kitten imaginary kitten
for this so to spend some time with this
softening the heart this could be 10 15 minutes just imagining The Lovable being
and doing some loving kindness practice with them and then after you've done that sometime and you
feel like there's a a little bit of softening or opening
then to bring to mind a minor difficulty that's happening in your life
a minor difficulty on a scale of one to ten two or a three
just some little minor irritation because we don't want to yeah I'll just
say we're going to start where it's easy and if we start where it's hard then it's just too hard and we doesn't we
don't do it start where it's easy bring to uh
a minor difficulty and that's often where the inner critic
starts to arise this what I talked about this idea that we feel like we should never have any pain or difficulties when
things are a little bit difficult there's often this little voice like um you should have done this or
yeah you're not so good at this and when are you going to get it together or you
know something like this so in the same way that we would do loving kindness practice where we would
repeat phrases here's if some phrases we can use
may this difficulty be held with kindness and ease
Shifting the relationship again may this difficulty be held with
kindness and ease I'm doing the best I can right now
I'm doing the best I can right now just to like say this like to oneself we
are at that moment we're doing what we can or I'm in the process of learning new ways
and this takes time
I'm in the process of learning new ways and this takes time
can you feel like there's a little bit more space there and the kind of like the inner critic gets quiet and you can
feel like there was a shift in relationship and sometimes it might be helpful to kind of like speak directly to this
inner critic this voice inside of ourselves it's putting us down
speak directly to it and say I know you're trying to help but that's not helpful
I know you're trying to help but that's not helpful
so these are some different ways we can work with resistance to get into the cushion we can just turn it into
practice can investigate well like what it is there something I'm trying to avoid or
that I don't want to see right now form of practice
we can notice if there are any beliefs that we have that there shouldn't be any
discomfort that's part of practice to help us understand ourselves better
we can make some kind-hearted adjustments maybe doing a little bit of this practice for the inner critic maybe
that's your practice it's no you're not going to do mindfulness then you're just going to do some of these kind-hearted
adjustments work with the this inner critic practice or maybe have some compassion recognizing the humanity
that it's not so easy to do new habits or to be with difficulties
and then also to notice this sense of I we have this sense of like it's up to me
I need to do it it's really tight is there a way that we can soften and
move to where it's a little more looser and softer and part of the way to do that is to recognize that so many
conditions have to come together and are coming together
I offer this as a way of what there's resistance to practice of how to work
with it or just to turn the resistance itself into practice without actually having to get to the cushion
and I didn't leave a lot of time for questions but maybe there's time for one
or so I'm sorry about this but I wanted
to hi thank you
um I'm trying to remember exactly what my question was I know I remember the first
half which is um when you spoke about the voice of I should it was kind of you described that
it's kind of like this me versus everything could I hear you re-articulate that a bit it really
resonated with me but I'd like to just sort of hear it again yeah it shows up
often as me against the world this idea or kind of like being isolated
there's also the it creates the conditions for so many things get glumped on top of that
I don't know if this is what you're talking about I was talking it's um yes so what what that's where what are
my notes do I have oh it's not only me against the world but also everything is up to me like I have
to make it happen [Music] um and and so and so then I understand this
idea of being able to practice with this voice identifying where there's resistance and perhaps
our relationship to this voice being a form of practice um
how do we how do we evaluate the part of the voice that's that's that's
holds some truth or some value or some realness like I should do my taxes when
they're due you know but maybe there's resistance to that but I actually should do my taxes
you know how do we how do we balance um this like
opening to it but also listening to what it has to say yeah I guess yeah so this
is the part of the art of practice is can we do our taxes with ease right so
and this is part of the practice is to really find okay can we find ease when things are uncomfortable
because if we're always finding wanting them to be useful right we're going to have some resistance and not want to do them maybe we don't want to do our taxes
but is there a way that we can open up to them so instead of there's I have to
do the taxes it was just it's kind of a subtle thing in language but to kind of say
um taxes are being done sure okay I like that thank you
thank you okay so we're at the top of the hour so
thank you all for your attention and if you'd like you're welcome to come up and talk to me otherwise I wish you a
wonderful evening and I'm leaving this weekend for a month-long Retreat so I won't be here
for the next few weeks I'll be happily I don't know if I'll be happy right we never know what happens on
Retreats right there's no guarantees but um I'll look forward to coming back
in uh March so thank you