welcome everyone I'm Nikki in mountain New California happy to uh welcome you
to happy hour today and as always we have this tradition of saying hello
warming up the space with our greetings so uh take it away sa who's here who
wants to warm up the
space Hi Mima from yaka Valley Hi Mima Padma from Belmont hi
Padma hi Deb from New England good evening to
you from Cabo Mexico hi drma from Cabo
Mexico welcome I'm Ruth from Vancouver Washington hi Ruth from Vancouver
Washington welcome hi I'm Valerie from
hi Valerie and I thought I heard Neil Neil in New Hampshire hi
Neil Sarah Sarah from Toronto hi Sarah from Toronto
welcome Noel from P Alto hi Noel welcome
Kim from teina BC hi Kim our Canadian
contingent hi n in Oakland hi Fred and who was that Sandy
Sandy hi Nikki thank you hi Sandy welcome both to both of you and hello
says fosil from Illinois and Roger from Sacramento and Hugh from San Diego and
Paul from Prince uh pent Penington British Columbia and Carrie were joining
us on YouTube and Jesse from s Rafel Megan from pal lots of
Hells yeah yeah very sweet anybody else wants to join in before we transition down from
Kito hi Don from Kito nice great it's so
fun that you join from Ecuador while you're you're there very sweet so what
time is it there by the way sorry uh nine o'clock 900 p.m 900
p.m yeah over East Coast time welcome yeah good evening to you great okay so
let's transition to uh now that I feel the
space has been warmed up I just find myself getting Smiler and Smiler as I hear all the hellos coming from
different places of the world um and hi Doran from Montreal Canada sweet okay so
let's transition if you're unmuted please mute yourself I will change the setting so
that the chats will only come to me but uh we'll keep that channel quiet uh
because it can be distracting for me to receive chats and um thank you Neil for posting
information about happy hour Google groups in the chat um if you're new to
happy hour we have a low trffic U mailing list where quotes poems
information is shared you're welcome to join that and also there is a guide for
um breakout room etiquette the way to offer ourselves and each other um safety
and care so with that I'm going to turn on recording for the sake of Audio
Dharma friends who will listen later here we go great
okay so hello and welcome everyone to this this edition of happy hour
so I wanted to um offer a uh poem
today and uh for us to to sit with peace
to practice peace with every breath uh wishing peace both for ourselves our own
minds our own hearts these Minds that get entangled get
entangled and also for the world and also for the world so I got this this poem actually I
was teaching a retreat last week at Spirit Rock um with uh with Sylvia borin
who's a dear friend and has been a teacher for many years lovely Sylvia and
she shared this poem with me um and the name of the poem is taking sides and and
it's by Irwin Keller in fact I'm going to put a pointer
to this poem in chat so that if some of you are visual and would like to
follow um the uh the poem you are able to do that there we go
and I will read it out loud so here we go okay taking sides today I am taking s oh
also to say the the person who uh wrote the poem irin Keller is a um what what
he says on his website is that he's a rabbi teacher writer and hope manager I
love that hope manager may we all be hope managers piing sides today I am taking
Sid I am taking the side of peace peace which I will not abandon even when
its voice is drowned out by hurt and hatred bitterness of loss cries of right
and wrong I am taking the side of Peace whose name has barely been spoken in
this winnerless War I will hold peace in my arms and
share my body's breath lest peace be added to the body
count I will call for deescalation even when I want nothing
more than to get even I will do it in the service of
peace I will make a clearing in the overgrown Thicket of cause and effect so
peace can breathe for a m for a minute and reach for the
sky I will do what I must to save the life of peace I will breathe through
tears I will swallow Pride I will bite my
tongue I will I will offer love without testing for
deservingness so don't ask me to wave a flag today unless it is the flag of
peace don't ask me to sing an Anthem unless it is a Song of Peace don't ask
me to take sides unless it is the side of
Peace So I did say hope man oh hope Monger oh
gosh I yes I said not I didn't mean mang hope Monger not hope manager I'm tired
hope Mong thank you that's funny hope Monger I love that great so what a
beautiful what a beautiful poem what a beautiful hope hopeful poem I love hope
Monger hope Monger so let's sit with this I especially like the lines of
um I will hold peace in my arms and share my body's
breath and that's what we'll do we'll hold peace in our arms and share our
body's breath as we practice with awareness with mindfulness of the body
mindfulness of the breath one breath at a time let's hold peace in our
arms yeah so so with that as the
Preamble Let's uh let's begin our formal
practice of sitting together sitting in a posture that is comfortable
for you ideally your back is upright if you're lying down let your
spine be straight no problem feeling your body and this
Earth feeling this body [Music]
sitting offering its weight to the Earth not tight
[Music] and holding tightness but if there is
tightness offering it to the
Earth let the body be relaxed and soft as if you were holding a little
baby a little newborn tender full of
Hope if Fe holding peace in your arms cradling
peace supporting peace for yourself for your own sake and the sake of
everyone with each
breath
sharing
sharing your body's breath with
peace
letting the practice be very simple tonight with a lot
of Silence just the breath the breath ever so
simply being breathed through the body and if there are thoughts
preoccupations [Music] plans releasing them for the sake of
Peace in this heart and mind releasing them for the sake of
peace in your own heart in your own mind not disturbing the
peace was said Years Ago by famous teacher that it's so quiet in here I
think a famous Swami that it's quiet inside it's always quiet and peaceful inside we just stare
it up we stare it up so if you notice steering up has
happened can you release into peace holding peace in your
arms like a little newborn sharing your breath whatever metaphor image works for
you
practicing peace taking the side of
peace with each
breath
connecting with each in breath and each out breath in
the body just here just
now not past or future and with each breath letting
their PE letting there be peace connecting with with release releasing into
peace in your heart and your
mind that metaphor works for you or holding peace cratering peace like a
newborn in your arms and sharing each breath with
peace with benevolence whichever works for
you
e
breathing in peace and breathing out peace with every
breath
in the last couple of minutes of this sitp is there any area of our hearts or
Minds any area of our thinking or habit patterns that would be helpful to
bring bring the blessing of peace
to breathing a couple of peaceful breaths that way if something has come
up letting go releasing and trusting
that no matter how we deem or practice to be how we gr it to be how we rate it to be
trusting that we are planting seeds of presence seeds of
Peace as we keep turning our hearts and our attention towards
it may all beings everywhere
be peaceful wishing
goodness
gladness peace
safety for all beings
everywhere may all beings beings be happy may all beings be
free everyone thanks for your practice may we all serve as as peace
mongers as hope mongers not fear mongers but peace mongers
[Music] and and hope mongers what what a beautiful play on The Words the author
of the poem uses Ain Keller so practicing peace being peace
with each breath again not judging or practice I was distracted
I was thinking even if there was just a couple of breaths where you con connected with a sense of
Peace that's enough we're planting seeds we're planting seeds just trusting the
power of this practice in ways we can quite understand
so so I'd like to invite us for an exploration the question for
the small groups today is this question we'll do it as a
question that a repeating question the question is what supports peace in your
heart what supports peace in your mind what supports peace in your life
what supports peace cultivating peace what supports
it [Music] and hello everyone welcome back the
rooms are closed and we have a few minutes for any
Reflections questions and I'm going to also change the um chat setting so that
you can um send your Reflections if you like through chat if you send them to me
privately I won't read your name if you send them to everyone I will read your name and your Reflections so so what did
you discover in this practice either the meditation as we meditated together or
in small groups as you explored what supports peace for you what did you
discover we'll take a couple of Reflections
um couple of Reflections one private part of me is feeling so much grief
tonight and I'm trying to allow peace and grief to be present at the same time yes
exactly of course not trying to get rid of one or the other another reflection
hearing from others what brings them peace brings me peace yes isn't that
lovely that's really lovely I feel kindness which leads to
peace oh beautiful such beautiful Reflections thank you all and SAR I see
your hand thank you so much
um there were many words of wisdom in our group U but also lots of
silence and then I realized silence can bring peace and we know we did that teaching
also a few weeks ago when you um asked us to practice that and
many of us were actually surprised that we expressed that wow there's something in this
silence um and I also reflected on the teaching in a way that this teaching brings peace
also for me but you also added a sentence today
that in a way that I can't quite explain and I find that A very wise
added piece because sometimes I feel like I I really want to know what's
happening and I can't tell um I want to know the nitty-gritty
of all this and you know s scientifically dissect everything and
figure it out and I can't figure it out and and just that's like I can't quite
explain it's it's giving me fruits but I can't quite explain so that was also very peaceful for me thank
you thank you thank you so much thara John beautiful to hear your your
Reflections and your practice yeah wow nice nice and and this last piece that
you said I'll pick that up especially about we can't quite explain we just
know that we start to feel different or be different in the world or re or react
differently or not be as reative there's just something starts to shift slowly ever so slowly it's like by osmosis it's
it's like the Zen s story actually I just told this on the retreat it's like
you know you you walk in the fog you know if it's really foggy there's moisture in the air you keep walking and
walking and before you know it your clothes will become wet with the Dharma they will
become drenched by the Dharma you don't can't quite tell when it happened and how it happened but just slowly as you
keep walking and you keep putting one step ahead of another in these practices it shifts it happens which is beautiful
and uh yeah yeah so beautiful thank you
yeah so so may we practice peace may we
be peace mongers hope mongers yeah love
that yeah Jerry says just being here now allows me to be at peace Ah that's sweet
yes me too Jerry being with all of you brings brings more
PE yes Community really Community a likeminded
community um that's dedicated to cultivating peace and and taking the
side of peace that brings peace for me and in the world so so thank you all
thank you for being this beautiful um community that keeps coming
together and and cultivating peace may all of us be
happy peaceful and may we spread peace in the
world thanks everyone be