ah welcome uh of
discussion practice on the theme of the 10 Perfections the
parties so nice
um again sorry to be just a couple of minutes late I will um I'll try opening the room
a little earlier tomorrow um yeah that way if there's any technical
bubbles we don't lose any time together
so yesterday we talked about the the Perfections of energy
and patience and I'm wondering if um as before we get into the
the meditation itself for the day if there's anyone who you know reflected on these
two during the day looked for how they showed up if you want to put any comments in the chat I offer that invitation
so yesterday we had a look at some of the ways particularly that
energy and patients work together and today we're turning our attention to
truthfulness and resolve or determination
so let's um let's move into the meditation
this is a this is a guided meditation on the theme
of our our noting practice
and I want to call this honest noting
let's first settle ourselves here
um just forgiving our way back into intimacy with the body
all of our efforts and activities
and this body this breathing body is right here
and we have a an ally in the silence
between the sounds between the thoughts
letting us in the direction of Stillness
the Simplicity of here
and I would suggest using a small
note light whisper in the mind
to it identify recognize
what's being noticed now
often we begin with the breathing
putting in another inhale out and the exhale
the note is not meant to lead the attention
but confirms what's been recognized
with the intention to clearly know
particulars of this experience
seeing it honestly
breathing in a little label little note in the mind
it's in her naming aligning with our experience
tuning our energy
so that the attention stays clear this is what's happening now
this now this
and that's last minute
to continue with the noting practice
sensing the way in which
this simple naming of experience
turns the mind in to honesty truthfulness
[Music]
foreign
so hello again
summarize a bit of our our last session we we talked about how the parames the
Perfections of energy and patience work together how they support each other and
we looked at this skill of tuning Our energy such that it's appropriate for
um both the situation and the activity that we're engaged in and they looked at how
um the wisdom that we're involved in this complex set of processes we call life
supports our patients and then Donald Paula picks up the
thread here and he says it's entirely through the spiritual power of energy
that the practice of all of the qualities of Enlightenment succeed it's long list long list long list and
then he includes in that list of what's achieved through energy the determination upon truth
so this is where we'll continue our exploration of the Perfections with truthfulness and determination
resolve so let's get specific about what we mean
in this context so um the Perfection of truthfulness
we're talking about non-deceptiveness non-deceptiveness in speech accompanied
as all the Perfections are by compassion and skillful means we're honest with an eye Torah the
skillfulness of the moment and an eye toward um the effect on each other
with our with our open heart or their affect so this is the Perfection of truthfulness non-deceptiveness
and then the Perfection of determination or resolve um is unshakable determination
to undertake all of the good qualities for the good of others
accompanied by compassion and skillful means so to move in just a layer closer
we break these down into practices of truthfulness
practices of restraint things that uh maybe get in the way of truthfulness
and then how compassionate and skillful things play a role um the the obvious thing to avoid when
practicing truthfulness is deceptiveness in our speech and then the volition is to speak what's
true it's skillful it's beneficial and for determination of course we
undertake all of this beneficial activity and we refrain
from straying off and putting our effort somewhere else actually
so let's look a bit more closely at truthfulness we'll look at some of the encouraged
practices before we talk about refinements so
truthfulness is said to make patients long lasting
and staying in alignment with truth makes our patients long lasting
and this manifests as something we call Devotion to truth then they ring Adele for some of us
so buoyed by this patient endurance that we've been cultivating when someone uh hurts us
when someone maybe does wrong are resolve to truthfulness is meant to not waver
and this is a practice this is a practice uh Suzuki roshi said I can't find quite
where the where the story happened but he's he's known to have said you don't know how hard it is to love some people
and this is a person who is devoted to caring for others
but despite it being hard I trust he remained honest
so the sutas the Buddha speaks of safeguarding the truth maybe you've seen this in majima 95 and we do this by by
being explicit and clear about what the bases are for our views I have such and
such opinion based on this according to this without the accompanying demand
that is only this is true anything else is wrong I've got the one right View and
everything else is uh false invalid or whatever reason
there's no um there's no receptivity there is no uh there's no openness there's no
connection so in turn we Safeguard the truth and in
turn the truth safeguards us uh as the Buddha tata's own son when one
is willing to tell a deliberate lie there's no he said there's no wrong one
would not do and the word wrong here is related to soil that is now infertile
to look down from the other direction to grow the wholesome qualities truthfulness is
like a fertile soil
the sorts of practices we refrain from when cultivating truthfulness speaking deceptively internally and
externally we practiced this a little bit in the guided meditation uh
speaking simple honest truth about our experience
some of us some of us have heard ill use this expression of them uh
honesty truthfulness is like mindfulness out loud it's also mindfulness Insight we're
sub-vocalizing another thing to to abstain from to take
care take care watch for in our practice is this clinging to views it's
um as we mentioned before only this is true everything else is wrong this is discussed kind of poetically and
nicely in uh the atikavaga is a subsection of the Sutton ipata and
something called the passura suta the the Buddha is having this discussion
with with someone who's really uh let's say involved in the debate culture of ancient India
um anyone could come challenge uh an aesthetic to a debate and then the loss
the loss of that debate meant I think you um you lose your following which means you lose your livelihood and
um your disgraced more or less so debate was kind of high stakes um
and there was this there was this uh um powerful way of speaking that
included uh only what I say is true anything else is false and the Buddha has a specific
instruction a specific encouragement he says if grasping to a view
and disputing someone says this alone is true you can
just tell them in this dispute you have no opponent here
I love this you're not uh you're not getting entangled you're not um
staking out your claim your happiness and unhappiness is not dependent on having the right opinion or uh reasoning
or reasoning your way to have them admit oh you're right and they are wrong
um there's another way to be together and another way to express the truth
in this dispute you have no opponent here I relate this to the skill of of uh when
you know when you need to be you need to have some honest communication with something but you know the other person at this moment in
this current state is not receptive it's not the time it's not the time we're not going into dispute we're
trying to have honest communication so I'm reminded of the one of the
standards of Rights speech that's timeliness
so then of course this um this relates to truthfulness as it's
accompanied by compassion and skillful means we're not using the truth to harm someone
um you might think of this um might think of you know pretty maybe a well-meaning commitment to to
um to share something but maybe without a maybe without analysis of whether that
that harms another person oh well it's true well I have to tell I have to tell them it's an imperative
but there's a sensitivity here to what's skillful what's the right time what's beneficial
in my own practice [Music] um to this some years ago as I was start as
I was starting out I had a real tendency um to not not say truths that were a
little edgy in my life or um if I if I thought it was gonna cause a wave in the
relationship at all I wouldn't I wouldn't say anything and so I kind of went I kind of went
really far in the other direction not sharing everything I ever thought with everyone but in a safe space with
my mentors and teachers and people I could be really safe with I developed
a willingness to speak truths that felt scary to me
and then once that once that matured a bit then I could bring these two into alignment where there was discretion
about speech there was both a willingness to speak and wise reflection
so this truthfulness living in truthfulness I think can give us confidence in the past
and can be a sort of lodestar a direction for us and then we turn to determination
determination as like an unshakable Commitment if wise truthfulness orients our ship
then we can say determination sets out upon the course truthfulness orients determination sets
out Ruth identifies the path where whereas determination resolved resolves to
follow it and short we might say that determination is to set our sights on
something and when they start to see a theme if you're you're listening through the
series Dharma Paula teaches without this part of me none of the others are possible and with this part of me all of
them are possible and all of them mature all of them are perfected and purified we're starting to hear this
a lot and I think that points that points to the fact that uh
the parties work as a group I was reflecting on it yesterday and sharing that
I'm starting to see these 10 qualities of the Perfections as kind of an ecosystem of beautiful qualities
we support each other so we might reflect that in the absence
of determination we might hear about something like the paramese or hear about um practices that sound good to us
um are interesting to us but we without determination we don't undertake them so they remain words
I was reflecting on aditan determination resolve I'm reminded of some of the some of the
practitioners I practice with myself included in my early vipassana training we would do these sittings of strong
determination and uh one of us I won't say who um said I don't I don't care if I'm going
to die during the sitting I will not move which kind of it reflects the the Buddha's determination before before his
Awakening um and there was a way that that generated a lot of energy and commitment
to stay with the practice and then there's this complementary
quality which is uh we'll see that determination is followed upon by loving
kindness that a determination a determination
to follow the path sometimes even a great effort uh is is greatly supported by the
tenderness of loving kindness be honest with um what's possible for us
I think it's important to talk about um when we consider the practice in the
long term what about when we set our sights we set our determination
and then um what happens if we fall short
or vacillate or we're human so we're shakeable we determined to not move and
we move um and this is a case I think where we Orient we can Orient toward our ideals
but we live in our actual life this is both compassion and skillful means
and I think when we're walking a long path we need a wise and compassionate way to relate to our
Humanity our fallibility and our foibles I think a little bit of humor maybe uh
may be necessary I'm reminded of Suzuki roshi again
who I consider someone who took his practice very seriously without taking himself too seriously
he's very committed to the well-being of of all beings so in the first few years of tasahara
um there's a story told by Blanche Hartman there was a there's a wedding after a
wedding at tasahara there's this big celebration there's a band one of the priests is playing a keyboard another
student is playing the guitar and singing and someone else is on the drums and are very serious determined zen
teacher Suzuki roshi is sitting on the corner of the stage playing it because it
thinks his practice seriously doesn't take himself too seriously it's a long path
so we take care our foil our foibles our fallibility our shakeableness
it's neither an indication that there's an error in the system and it's also also not a reason that we
shouldn't Orient toward our ideals but how do we do this wisely
and to make it personal for ourselves how do we how do we encourage our faith how do we encourage ourselves
how do we Foster confidence especially when we're shaken
and do we do we have a trust that we cultivate in awareness regardless of the content of experience
even when it's out in patience
when we step off the path how do we step back on it's a great help to have Dharma friends
um so truthfulness and determination
to set the course and then determine to proceed
with compassion and skillful needs as I'm fond of quoting di kubody said you only need two things in Buddhist
practice one is to start second to continue
so for today as we've been doing I'd encourage you to look for truthfulness in your uh in your daily
life and then your impulses to the opposite and then look then look for your determination resolve and then impulses
to the opposite and tomorrow we'll pick up with the last two of the ten Perfections tomorrow
tomorrow I'll try to have a shorter talk and we can have some time for questions so uh please bring them and we can type
them into the type them into the chat and I'll try to address as best I can uh for a few minutes tomorrow
thank you so much best wishes for your practice may all beings benefit