so uh so welcome welcome folks um
yeah nice to see the names over there thank you to whoever said yesterday that uh it appeared that uh we were double
booked you were correct and um
and so this was the uh the arrangement we got since both were publicized in different ways
um so Meg took the the 7 A.M I'm taking the 8 A.M and uh that's how we're uh
we're proceeding I know normally we reserve the 8 A.M for unconsciousness seven for
mindfulness eight a.m Consciousness but we're switching it up today and uh
anyway it's sweet to be with you so um
yeah I knew something was different yesterday because the the there were some familiar names that I didn't see
inside around other stream anyway welcome to you all happy to uh
happy to be with you so um
yeah that's um that's it that's uh yeah we enter enter enter into
the Dharma enter into the Dharma
in this uh this ritual we we create and in practicing together
maybe uh beginning each of our days with a kind of reminder
uh and the reminder the reminder of the Dharma
becomes very tactile even just to say those words to enter
into the Dharma has a kind of its own effect
and this very dense web of meanings and connotations of memory of feeling
is evoked for me in that phrase for you you find your own
to enter into the Dharma
and so not to get burdened with the sense of a technique and doing and busyness and
fixing myself and doing a kind of psycho spiritual surgery
on my own heart no no no just entering entering into the Dharma
and so finding finding a posture
just letting the the nectar settle to the bottom of the glass of juice as uh
technology says
we recollect Buddha Tama Sangha
the measure this blessing of the lineage
so many ways to suffer
in so few ways to be free
but this is one of them
so we wrap ourselves up in that Dharma blanket of sorts
sense of sense of coziness
being held by something
then the breath begins to remind us of the Dharma
remind us of devotion
remind us of change and poignancy
the preciousness of having been born
you just let all that suffuse body and mind
letting life come to awareness
rather than reaching out to hold experience
the heart and a kind of posture of surrender
surrendering to samsara
surrender to imperfection
and trusting that this gesture of surrender
strengthens weakens heart
in other words we we abide in receptivity
uh our minds must always doing double duty trying to
Shore up our lives
incredibly uh when it actually
to see the movements and machinations of our mind
and testifies to the bigness of the world
and the fragility of our condition
but sometimes
we seek our safety
from somewhere else we seek our safety
from within the surrender
foreign
our heart can be nourished even by imperfection
we develop a kind of faith in openness receptivity
foreign
so we are welcome to our
um so
at the the and towards the end of his life
reflecting on his kind of happiness and suffering
uh Leonard Cohen was asked by by an interviewer about his kind of his art
and um asked if he suffered in the ways that he uh that he used to
and he says no and then adds um
it's not so much that I got what I was looking for
but the search itself dissolved
so yesterday the theme was was a wonder and awe and
today it's a surrender surrender
and surrender is is not so much a word from our
tradition Associated more with mono monotheistic traditions
and um it was a couple of beautiful lines from
Augustine's um confessions
we are but a particle of that creation thou awakest us to Delight in the praise
for Thou made us for thyself and our heart is restless until it
Repose in the hide not the face from me let me die
lest I die only let me see thy face my soul is like a house
small for you to enter but I pray you to enlarge it
it is in Ruins but I ask you to remake it it contains much that you will not be
pleased to see this I know and do not hide
but who is to rid it of these things there is no one but you
let's have kind of curious that I find that um so um
beautiful given kind of my my own turn away from
theistic tradition and yet the the potency of that
seems very clear so what is the role what's the role of
surrender and Buddhist practice on the one hand
we are encouraged to be independent to
be in the phrase Guild loves independent in the Dharma
to verify the teachings for ourselves that famous you know uh
language from the Kalama suta when you yourselves know
when you your you know for yourself that these these
practices these teachings are skillful when you know for yourselves
there is a kind of theme of it of um the in the resourcefulness of the
individual heart you know in this fathom long body we find
suffering and its end and uh and so there is this self-sufficiency
something like this uh maybe that's not right self-sufficiency
but there is a kind of encouragement certain kind of self-reliance
and surrender of course is it's a dangerous thing and word and many of us
at some point have surrendered to to bad ideas or bad
people bad habits and so I'm cautious with that word but
so much of the the goodness of the path requires
surrender our our maybe we say in the Dharma comes
from a kind of surrender and we're not surrendering in this
tradition to someone exactly but surrendering
to the moment and trusting that it will shape our heart well
no Will To Power um the urge to possess or dominate control
possess dominate control ourself
this can't take us deep into the Dharma it's like all of that willfulness is
such a tangle of so much intense feeling affect
so we practice relaxing it
for for me um the the kind of willfulness seems to
draw my own willfulness in practice seems to draw its energy from something
like a tangle deep in my own heart
it feels almost like this very primitive
anger or control and
that willfulness kind of masquerades as dhamachanda a longing for the Dharma or
masquerades as varia a kind of energetic vigor
but um we must all kind of ask like what
what does practice look like on the other side
of your willfulness
the most transformative practice really unfolds
when our ego is all out of moves you know
and that that beautiful passage from the confessions is like oh yeah The ego's
All Out of moves there and so the path in a sense it begins
with surrender to acknowledge at the beginning that um
um I don't know exactly how to live I know that this can't work out the way
I've been doing it but I don't know exactly how to live let me open
to the wisdom of a of a lineage
to uh to be present just to be present it is
um is really another way of saying we're we're we're
ceasing our attempts to govern the future
to make this moment about some future moment of security to make this the
present a down payment on some future happiness
and we have this sense of of always deploying mindfulness to
to solve this problem or that problem but mindfulness itself is a kind of
surrender and the receptivity
an openness to the moment this is a kind of surrender
our mind wants to do something to the moment rather than be
Changed by it to do something to the breath rather
than be changed by it to be suffused by it
and so rather than fidgeting with samsara we're opening
radically to non-control
and that's that is surrender
in order to to forgive samsara
we we have to surrender to it at least in moments
just to yeah pause
deeply in a sense of like okay I'm not going to be able to
work out the the imperfections in in this realm
surrender involved in that and in order to
to relinquish uh stories that no longer serve us we have to surrender to not
knowing you know like repairing a ship at Sea a
little bit um
how we don't the nature of insight is is not knowing
Insight arises out of the mind that doesn't know
we can't know what we'll find it's always insight as always a little surprising
sometimes as people deepen in the practice they they describe getting more
settled the self getting kind of thinner thinned out
and and sometimes they feel like uh the precipice of some some some really deep
silence Stillness kind of get jerked back into
sometimes into our the worst thought we could have the worst habit we have
jerked back into a kind of very congealed sense of self Mara the force of suffering kind of
playing his trump card in the moment
and so we actually are learning to surrender to groundlessness a trust that
um that Stillness is a refuge even if we
lack our ordinary reference points Stillness is a refuge
this is how we settle into samadhi to the kind of unification of the Mind
there's effort involved but often much less than we imagined or a different kind of effort
and at some point in the kind of journey into Stillness effort itself is just
another species of agitation
and so we settle into silence and Stillness through a kind of falling
kind of falling into something and a trusting that the silence won't
harm you the groundlessness won't harm you
and so we're not so much focusing more closely we're surrendering to to silence
so surrender surrender surrender but here's the thing
from from surrender we find our power
from surrender we find our security
so for this fear consideration this morning
and uh it's good to be with you
be back tomorrow eight o'clock Pacific and uh
hope to see you see you then I wish you all a good uh good
Valentine's Day and um
yeah I'll see you see you tomorrow