uh so the topic for the The Talk today is generosity
and ethics as a prerequisites for meditation
and I found very interesting that in Reading one of the discourses of the
Buddha in the the one about the gradual training that he talks about these two qualities
as two qualities we want to begin with in our practice first to lay the foundation
before we begin to meditate
so we can say that these two qualities are the most basic ways to prepare
ourselves
generosity I see as a way to
it's like as if you were to take the Earth and start to loosen it up and then
the ethics is like pulling out the weeds all the things we don't need for then be able to plant something that will be
wholesome for us
so the Buddha made sure that his followers
had really had these two qualities well established before he taught them to
meditate but here in the west we we rush to begin
with meditation and many people have great difficulties with
it because we haven't done the Preparatory work and nowhere did I see it more clearly
than some years ago when I was working with sexual offenders that had just come
out of prison and I was to teach them meditation
it was really an eye-opening experience for me to see how tremendously difficult
it was for them it was painful for them and for me to
see what it took for them to sit quietly and have to face
themselves I remember a particular one one man who who just sit and after just a minute he
would just start sweating he could only sit for a couple of minutes it was just too difficult
now of course this is an extreme situation but I think that for us too
sometimes we have a hard time settling in because
we notice perhaps we were not kind with somebody or in some ways
we didn't follow what we know is an ethical way of living
so as we train ourselves with with ethics
is as if we are preparing ourselves to give the gift to others
of being harmless that's a very beautiful thing for other
people to feel safe with us and I want to although the training
begins with generosity in this talk I want to begin with uh with ethics
just because I want to leave the generosity at the end it's it's such a
sunny topic that I wanted to leave you with that at the end
so one one thing that I have noticed here in in the west is that
um with with a popularization of mindfulness often we have lost sight of
the connection of Mind mindfulness with the rest of the Dharma and specifically
of ethics and this is a real problem and a real loss
because then what the meditation and mindfulness ends up uh
being is just like a way to relax ourselves it's kind of like what I like
to call the Spy effect and yeah I mean it's nice and it's very positive to to have this relaxing effect
of the meditation but if we don't use it as a means to really
learn how to more and more free ourselves from suffering than the effect
of the relaxation is just going to last only as long as you know like a massage it's just you
know a little bit afterwards we fall into something that's unskillful and we we tense our whole self again
so as we train ourselves with ethics
we are training ourselves it's very important to make ourselves aware from
where it begins which is in our minds which is with with our thoughts
that's very important a lot of times these thoughts is where
this unwholesomeness begins and we notice that when they are already very well established
but if we catch them at the beginning we have much more of a chance that we'll be
able to pull them out stop them change
so we want to be able to train ourselves to watch our thoughts and then of course
our speaking and our actions
so the most succinct way that we can express ethics for us in in the context
of of the Dharma is um via an equation we can say ethics
equals happiness it's just as a simple you know to look at it that we are not
required to be ethical but that if we want to live uh a life that is
happy that we're Carefree that we need to work on our ethics
and so this is looked you know following these uh
General guidelines of an ethical life um
is seen as a logical and natural way to
um to have a happy life and they're just as natural as the laws of gravity you
know just like everything in our planet is subject to the law of gravity the same is true for us
when our thoughts and words and actions arise from a skillful place
then we will be happy and when they arise from greed hatred
and ignorance they will lead us to suffering
so the guiding principles that we have in the Dharma and that maybe some of you
already know the precepts you know this is just kind of like the most rudimentary way of
presenting some Guides of how to live our lives
but what we want to keep in mind is just because they are rudimentary it doesn't mean that we are Beyond it
you know sometimes we feel oh I know the precepts memorize them and Beyond them
but I think we all have to stop and rethink how is it that each one of these
precepts encompasses a whole range from something
very obvious and terrible to something quite subtle that
we can actually fall into easily
[Music] um and so we can look for example with the
first one you know refrain from from taking life I think when we hear this we all say oh
yeah yeah of course I don't I don't take anybody's life but how do we deal when we have a
problem of ants in our house you know that that's that's something
that happens to all of us or or mice or how do we deal with a situation of a
pet that is already very old do we consider euthani euthanasia for the pet
so there are these other issues that we really need to consider and the
wonderful thing about the way we work with the with the precept is that
they invite us they're an invitation for us to stop and be Discerning to really
look carefully the unique situation what are the components of this situation and
what is the wisest thing given the situation
and so the second one refrain from taking what has not been given
you know there's of course the obvious you know stealing something but then there's something that is very common
that people do that they are in the office and there there's there's a lot
of paper and you just take some paper home or some folders or um
often we don't think in those terms or sometimes with taxes you know people
are always kind of looking at ways of go around it and and perhaps not pay what
it is fair or one that the first time I heard it I
thought hmm I would have never thought about this as as taking something that is not given and that is arriving late
but it actually is one of those subtle ways that we're actually taking the time
of somebody else that maybe is waiting for us that was not given to us
so you see how it gets really interesting if if we take the time to really look at this and the more we
practice the more we become more sensitive to pick out these uh things
that make you want to be more precise more careful more subtle in your
decisions the third one refrain from causing harm with our sexuality
first of all I think that's a wonderful way of putting it the first time I heard it I thought wow what a what a
simple and Wise Way of being of talking about sexuality don't harm with your
energy with your Sexual Energy and so here of course
we know that one one obvious and and egregious one would be to impose
ourselves actually to somebody else but you know on the Other Extreme could be something like flirting you might
think that is very innocent but sometimes it actually can cause harm
another one would be the consuming of pornography you know
how does it make you feel to consume pornography
and then the fourth one refraining from speaking falsehoods there's of course the obvious you know
lying on purpose but uh then there's the other one that I
actually noticed in myself some years ago and that is that often we're telling a
story to friends we tend to exaggerate just a little bit and notice just to
make it a little more interesting and I said that's a good one to just kind of catch ourselves and say no I don't have
to do this you know just this really notice notice that
and then the last one of refraining from consuming alcohol or or drugs you know
which which we know you can really harm yourself and others if you do it unskillfully
um but then you know there's the the other more subtle that you drink a little and you get kind of goofy and and
uh maybe very entertaining but how easy it is to let some something come out
because your tongue is kind of loose and you let something come out that that can that can hurt somebody
so this is just in in general some of the things that we can think of
but I actually wanted to share with you uh one particular example that
um of a question that that was posed to me when when I was teaching a retreat
and I would say some years ago when George Floyd was murdered
I was teaching a retreat online and there was a latino man living in New
York who who told me look I'm somebody who have committed
to following the precepts but I have to tell you that
I don't feel safe in the streets anymore in New York you know he was somebody who who participated a lot in in racial uh
you know demonstrations and so he said
um I just don't feel safe and I want to buy a gun
what do you think so this is a very interesting question he said he had already made he hadn't
bought it but he already made all the the necessary paperwork that was needed
to to buy the gun and so
the interest what I find it's interesting that when when one is in the teaching position is that you cannot
take at the decision for somebody else somebody has everybody has to carry their own responsibility of their
decisions and so what I did was to say well why don't we just think together I'm going
to ask you some questions because the way I can help you is to help you
consider carefully and so some of the questions that I ask is what is your motivation
for having a gun and what attitude is behind that
motivation and then try to really imagine how would
you feel if you possess a gun
you had a gun at home or carried one with you also try to imagine how would you feel
if you actually had to use the gun
and how would it be to live with yourself the rest of your life if you
had to use the gun and you harmed somebody
or how would you feel if you were attacked and you didn't have the gun
and I also asked can can you think of another option where you don't cause harm
and you do manage to protect yourself because one of the things that I've
noticed when you really stop to think about it clarity
happens and somehow a creativity also arises
and you think of options in it that you hadn't even thought about it so you reframe it so maybe the
question is not going to be should I buy a gun but maybe the question is going to be
how could I protect myself in a way that is not non-harming
that's quite different isn't it and so so these questions we compose
ourselves these questions and then come up with
a more refined way of asking ourselves
the first time I heard this I was I was very intrigued and that is that when you
follow rules rigidly or ethical principles rigidly you don't mature
but yeah that makes total sense right because if you follow them rigidly you're not stopping to really consider
how do I stand how do I stand with this how how do I
really what what is what is my attitude towards this
because sometimes we're going to find in situations where breaking the precepts is the right thing to do
but when that when that situation happens then there are two things we have to keep in mind
one is to be very aware what is the attitude that you have as
you break the precept is it benevolent have you come to the
conclusion in this particular situation this is the most benevolent thing I can do
and you also realize that you are going to carry some Karma
With It because there will be some consequences but if you took that decision
based on this is the wisest and the most benevolent option
then consequences won't be that bad for you
and the last thing I want to say about about ethics is something that I heard from from
Kamala Masters this wonderful teacher that has a center in Maui she puts it in
such a positive way when she talks about ethics she says we're dealing either
with purification or purifying
and so what she means is that when you
are being Mindful and you check in with yourself and you notice right now there
are no unskillful mind States so
I haven't broken any precepts so that means right now there is purification there is purification in me
but what about if you stop and notice and you are assailed
with some of the obstacles you know with greed or you're or sloth
and torp or whatever it's present then you begin to work with them
and there are many ways that many tools that we can use to know how to work with
them and then what's happening then then purification is happening
and so we can see that that this keeps us engaged we are
looking at the reality of what's going on but it's in a very positive way it there's either purification present or
we're in the process of purifying
so that's as far as that's all I want to say as far as ethics
and now going on to generosity or Donna
is a topic that I like very much to talk about
so generosity implies giving myself of myself to others whether material or
immaterial Goods such as my time or my attention
and we can say that generosity is not just an isolated event of giving something to someone but is a quality
that we want to cultivate and embody
and so generosity of spirit can be expressed in many wonderful ways it can be expressed in a smile
it can be expressed it's really listening to somebody it can be expressed in just saying thank you to
somebody or it can also be expressed as not judging ourselves mercilessly when we
notice that we've done something wrong
when we give wisely we're told in the Dharma that we
experience Joy before during and after
and if you've paid attention when you've given in a wise way it is so much the
case practicing generosity is a wonderful way of having access to Joy
at any time and
in Asian countries generosity is something that is practiced
and taught to little children while still in arms are taught how to
offer even if it's just a handful of rise to the monks who come and ask
for food I also found interesting that in Burma when it's your birthday
you don't give birth you you you don't receive presence but you give presents
which is such a wonderful thing I actually just had the experience a couple of years ago of a dear friend of
mine who turned 90 and she asked us all don't bring presents in what she did
was to give each one of us in her party
a book of her best poems that she had written in the last 30 years
it was such a beautiful gesture of sharing something so meaningful it's kind of of the Harvest of her life
and so we all practice generosity in in different ways some
for some of us it comes more natural and for others not so natural
um but what is really wonderful in the way that
the Buddha taught is that he was such a fantastic teacher and he always
knew who he had in front of him and how he was going to teach them
and there is one way that he he taught generosity generosity I think it's
wonderful it assures that you will succeed and the teaching is very simple
the teaching is that you take one stone with your right hand
and you put it on your left hand okay I think this we can we can all do and it basically is getting the feel of
this idea of how renunciation is related to generosity in
order for this hand to receive the stone this one has to let go of it so it's
just a very simple thing it's imagine that we can teach that to a child
you know something very simple where a child can feel very very good about himself or herself
and then go on later to share something that's much harder like to share a toy
when um we feel the impetus to
to be generous we're told in the Dharma follow that impetus
and so the last thing I wanted to to share with you is an experience that I had not that
long ago um where I was able to see a series of
very beautiful generous gestures that made a big big difference for for
somebody um so last November I had the Good Fortune
to visit an indigenous community of the guambianos in the Colombian Andes
and our last day as we were leaving the town closest to the reservation
I got to talking to an indigenous woman it was like she was a grandmother and
she was there with her little granddaughter and she was wearing you know her
traditional gambiano clothing which is this long Woolen black skirt and this royal blue kind of a shawl in this
fedora hat and
she told me she needed help to carry a rather big and heavy sack of potatoes
that she herself had planted and harvested she needed to get this enormous act onto the bus
so a dear friend that was traveling with us was strong enough to lift it for her
and she was very very happy and once in the bus we just sat together
and and we continued talking so it turns out that this woman was
traveling like us all the way to the city of Kali
but her reason for traveling was rather sad because she was
traveling to the city to visit her daughter or the little girl's mother in the
hospital who was very ill now there's
lovely grandmother had arranged for somebody to buy her potatoes in the next
town where we were going to stop and she was doing that in order to have
enough money for the trip so as we arrived to the next town the
person who was supposed to buy the potatoes from her was not there
and she explained to the bus driver
that what what happened and asked him would you please wait for me to see if I
can get somebody else to buy the potatoes now try to imagine this situation
in this country or in any City I should say
but where I was in the area of this guambianos they have a very very strong
community and they really they have a sense of belonging and they really help
each other so the bus driver somehow recognized The
Plight that this poor woman was in and waited and much to my amazement not there was
not one person in the bus that complained so we were about 30 people we all just
quietly sat in the bus and waited and somehow miraculously the woman was
able to sell her potatoes and not you know didn't take that long I don't remember how long but it wasn't that
long so then let next leg of the of the trip
because it was a pretty long trip I sat next to the five-year-old and
and decided to share with her some of the the things I
remember from sharing with my son when he was little so
when I ran out and some of the the songs that I knew in in Spanish I I actually
even translated a rather or improvised a rather questionable version of The Wiggles and the bus but she loved it and
she the the grandmother sang along and did the hand movements and so there we
are in the bus doing our our singing and so in the next in the next stop she
goes off with a grandmother to get to get some food and the bus happened to to
stop right in front of a of a stationary store a very little humble looking
stationary store and I somehow
had the subtle sudden impulse to get off
and and I thought it would be very nice to get this little girl a present
so I walked into the the stationary store and was able to find a very nice box of colored pencils and a little
notebook with blank pages for her to draw on so made it back to the boss and and once
once they also returned I presented it to to the little girl and her eyes just
got so big and she just was actually I love to draw
and she was just caressing the box of pencils and it was just so it was just so happy
so it got dark and it got very quiet and as
far as I knew she had gone to sleep and suddenly I see this little hand that
went up she was sitting in front now in front of me and this is the backrest and I see this little hand that goes up and
she was doing like this with her fingers as if it was like a little bug that was looking for something
and so with my hand I went like this and started to go on the other in the other
direction when she felt my hand she just took my hand I could I couldn't see her
face and she just held it and so most of the trip to gali
we just sat there in silence and she held my hand it was such a beautiful simple way of
her to say thank you and so as soon as we got into the city
of Kali they they got off we said goodbye as
as if we were old friends and there was a real sense in my heart
that what the woman and the little girl had received from several people during the
day was going to help them or carry them
through the difficulty of encountering the Heavenly messenger of illness once
they were in the hospital so just this remembering you know just
this little gestures that we can do for each other of kindness of
generosity that can make such big difference
and so to finish I wanted to share a poem with you
by Rosemary watola trummer is called what it might con how it might continue
and for me this poem kind of captures this idea of us being able to do
something for somebody else that might seem like it's minor that it doesn't not
that doesn't really change much but that inside something important happens
wherever we go the chance for joy whole Orchards of amazement
one more reason to always travel with our pockets full of exclamation marks
so we might scatter them for others like apple seeds some will dry out
some will blow away but some will take root and grow exuberant Groves filled with
long thin fruits that resemble one hand clapping so much enthusiasm as they
flutter back and forth that although nothing's heard and though nothing's
really changed people everywhere for years to come will swear that the world
is ripe with Applause will fill their own Pockets with new seeds to scatter
so let us close our eyes for a moment
and just allowing the words that you've heard
on generosity and ethics
allow them to come in to your heart
to your mind
and may the words that you've heard today benefit yourselves
and every person that you come in contact with
thank you for your attention and we have a couple minutes if anybody has
a question or a comment
good we feel complete so I thank you all
be well and a good evening to all