so when I was young
I grew up in four different countries and there was a period of time where we
would actually move between them every year you know twice a year kind of between
different ones and so it was a lot of moving and a lot of living in different countries and I was born in Norway so
when the one of those four places was United States so I was a foreigner in this country
and I had this strong wish at the time that I didn't tell anyone it's just it was a something I thought about in my
mind I really wished I could get a United Nations pass passport
I had heard there was such a thing and uh and um
and excited I didn't want to I wanted to belong to the whole world I wanted to it
didn't feel like I wanted to belong to any particular country but just be Global if they belong everywhere
and uh and some of that was born from seeing the divisiveness that happened
between countries and growing up in uh with parents and grandparents who
went through World War II and she said you know I was young I'm you know I was young young enough in the 60s
to really still experience the the after effect of World War II and the
divisions between countries and so this idea of you know kind of choosing your country against other countries was kind
of very painful these living in these divisions so uh that was you know that was kind of
my wish and now I've been here in the peninsula living here for 30
years about I guess 28 years I think living here but 33 years of being here because I started going to school at
Stanford in 1990. and and one of the great Delights for me
in living here in the peninsula is how over these years has gotten increasingly cosmopolitan
so maybe I don't have to have an international passport you know I just live here and I
appreciate more and more diversity of people from all over the world who come here and diversity within this country and I I feel like it's much richer and I
also feel like it's for me personally much safer to live in a diverse community
um and the the representation of that was in all these kind of jumping around and
all this I did when I was 20 I lived for uh four months in the biggest hippie
coming in the United States it was 700 people who lived in a place called The Farm in Tennessee
and how a bunch of hate the Ashbury hippies end up in Tennessee as a whole
you know story and um and and when they were in hey Dash Berry or this locally in the 60s LSD was
kind of like the sacrament for this group of people they had kind of a spiritual bent
and uh of sorts and but they went to Tennessee it didn't really work well to take a lot of LSD in
Tennessee back then so when I came there to visit for a few
days actually the the leadership of the community was in jail for a year because of
such things and um but it was it was a year and they came out while I was still there
um and um and so they had to find another way of
you know there we can't do LSD anymore here we have to find something equivalent we can do that's legal
and the amazing thing they They Came Upon was honesty isn't that pretty cool that honesty is
you know equivalent to LSD and now that now there's a Resurgence of psychedelic interests in their in society but um I
haven't seen the same Resurgence of honesty but if honesty and psychedelics are equivalent
you know let's let's get high on honesty so I was so impressed by this
this really blew me away and that's seeing how this community had developed capacities to have these honest
communicate conversations um was the reason I stayed more than two
or three days and um and I stayed for four months
and uh learned a lot from them was inspired was actually my introduction to spirituality I had no background in
religion or spirituality before that but that was a doorway into the spiritual kind of world was that people who were
exploring honesty but the reason I left was that it was a
homogeneous culture for the most part there are all these people like me white
middle class hippies and I and I've been I I had grown up so
so many different cultures that I didn't feel safe to be around people who were too much like me
and so I left because because of that reason and uh some people would have stayed because they feel comforted by
that and feel like now I belong and and you know now we're all right together
but uh but I actually felt a little that's not quite right to do that
so uh because it's very easy to end up with um you know a very strong US versus
them and recently in this training I'll tell you about they gave an example of this
of of um Sports
and apparently there's a phenomena kind of a double standard that if the referee
or the Umpire uh kind of is a little bit ambiguous whether the
call was right but it's for your team that's that they got the call was right
then you know well that must be right but if it is your team and the call is
ambiguous but it's they you know maybe for the Empire the referee says it's wrong then people get really upset
the same opposite for the other team if the other team is ambiguous but their
team is the referee says it's right it was legal the game then
um if we get upset because it's the other team they have it wrong referees I have it all wrong they need to get new referees but if their referee says
they're wrong there's a penalty then yeah of course you know so there's a there's a double bind there
that's more likely there's a there's a bias towards forgiving or seeing the rightness of
your own group and the wrongness of another group and so you see that because I've seen people get it's
dramatic watching people do sports watch sports and how strongly their opinions
can be and how outraged they can be about these referees when they're voting
when they're against their own team so that's kind of a representative
representative of a kind of deep deep kind of bias that can operate in people
when we have us versus them so um I kind of feel uncomfortable for a
little bit watching even I am kind of weird I guess maybe for a societal standards
um the competitive Sports is kind of strange to me and I I kind of mostly root for the person who's losing
[Laughter] you know because then I want that you know and I like it in soccer where you
can come out even you know zero zero or one one and you know that I like that and um
and uh when I was in college in the 70s there was a little movement of
Theodore was called um alternative games that people played there were no books written about it at
least fun games you could play that were not competitive so maybe that kind of is wonderful and
also we lose something in the process but so um
so I want to read um so I want to tell you a little bit
about this training we did for about 30 of us here at IMC called the trading
called Deep diversity and here at IMC we've spent a lot of time looking at diversity issue
diversity Equity inclusion issues and um and uh have read some of us have read a
lot about this some some here at MC much more than me and we've kind of settled on a
particular approach to this Dei work that really we feel works for who we are and that's uh we found it through a book
called Deep diversity and deep diversity uh created the people the author was
co-founded an organization called the anima uh leadership just called out of
my leadership organization something Institute or something doesn't have a third word
and um and they offer trainings and so 30 of us did the training and it was
quite wonderful I thought two weeks ago and uh and at various times we've been
we've had book groups here at IMC reading this book deep diversity and and
um with some of our Sangha leaders kind of leading the discussions and um and so we're going to begin to
bring more of this deep diversity to IMC and so I wanted to talk a little bit about this if I wanted to do it the best
I can and in the context of our practice and what we do here dharmically
so I want to begin with a suta and begin or continue with the sutta this course of the
teachings of the Buddha where someone came to the Buddha
and um said there are these four castes
the king oh so so um are these forecasts the Nobles the brahmanas the merchants
and the workers two of them that is the Nobles and the
brahmanas are held to be superior since people pay homage to them rise up
for them and Accord them reverential salutation and polite services
so are there people like that in this country this people who for whom are
held to be superior and people pay homage give them more respect than other
people rise up for them when they come you know kind of listen to them more their voices
are more important than other voices are there people in this country who are reverentially saluted and people who are
not and polite Services people get preferential services
uh periodically I hear from people who say yeah I went to a store and the person
there just ignored me I was there'd be Earth first I was in line first and and I just looked felt
like I was invisible sometimes people get older they say I feel invisible in society people just
overlooked me for that reason people racially are ignored and I remember going to Costco to get it
new tires for my car and there was a black woman sitting there and I came in later
and uh and the clerk came to me so I turned to the woman and said were
you here first and she said yes but then she explained she seemed okay with it and then we became friends it was very
nice but uh but to you know to see this kind of thing over and over again it's quite something in our society that can happen
so they might not be brahmanas and Merchants noble people but still we have
enough of this and and in our society that I think we can recognize some of this
so maybe the question is almost like you know are these distinctions existing here in our society in some way similar
um and um [Music]
so um so there's a recognition of these different castes and then the question is is there a
distinction or difference among them so the caste system is just taken for
granted what's the distinction and difference between them so this is the Buddha's answers he
answers indirectly first he says there are five
abilities for efforting five efforts we can engage in
we have the ability to awaken faith
confidence trust deep trust in something and then he gives the example that
trusts the capacity for human beings to become enlightened they become free to
become liberated of their suffering so it's possible to have deep faith in that that's the first he says
the second is um it's it's possible to work for and make the efforts for
becoming healthy and that's problematic just the way it's worded here but uh sometimes people
don't get healthy physically but you can get spiritually healthy even if if
you're chronically ill but there can be effort towards some kind of health health
there's efforts to be honest and sincere that's something we have the ability to
do that um one is honest and sincere one shows
oneself as one actually is to one's teacher and one's companions in the
spiritual life the other the next one the fourth one is
one can be energetic we can really put effort into
abandoning the unhelpful things that we do so there's plenty of people who do
unhelpful things even harmful things unskillful things and sometimes it's
called in Buddhism unwholesome things I like to call it unhealthy because it's
easier to identify with it but sometimes what we do is unhealthy for other people not just for ourselves
but to make an effort to stop doing that stop doing things which are unhealthy
we have that ability and we have the ability to undertake the
helpful things The Helpful wholesome skillful things to do and to be steadfast
and firm and persevering in cultivating these healthy things to
do so we have that capacity the ability and then the fourth fifth one uh one has
that we have the ability to be wise and we in particular we have the ability to be wise about how radically
changeable this reality we live in is our experience human life is how much change there is
and whether it's change Moment by moment or change year by year societies change all kinds of things change and it's
recognizing that change for Buddhists that is the Catalyst for Spiritual
liberation for the here which leads to the complete destruction complete complete end of our
own psychological suffering so we have these abilities
so ability to work for to develop Faith to develop some kind of Health to
develop honesty to develop uh to to let go of unskillful developed skillful and
have this wisdom about the changing nature of our experience so that's what the Buddha this Buddha's
first answer about the distinction between people he doesn't answer to answer the question yet but he's setting the stage for it
um and um now uh uh then the Buddha says so there
certainly are these forecasts Nobles the brahmanas the merchants and the workers
um uh now if they possess these five factors would there be any difference among them
in in this respect so first he established these five things people can do abilities then he
says what's the difference with between them what distinctions can we make between them in these five degrees
and then he makes the analogy there are elephants and horses and oxen
that can be well tamed they have the ability to Be Tamed the capacity to Be
Tamed um and if there are two oxens two horses
and and elephants have been well tamed um
would they if they had the ability to Be Tamed and then are tamed would you call
them tamed oh yeah then we call them Tamed and what about two that have the ability
to Be Tamed but don't get Tamed would you call them tamed and well
disciplined no and and then he goes on to say
um uh
so it's not possible so it applies the same thing to these
these five factors these five factors are things you can develop so there are those who develop them and
those who don't and that's the distinction that Buddha wants to make everyone has this ability
but he wants to make actually a distinction here between people those who develop this capacity all the way to
freedom and those who don't those who develop the capacity to be honest and those who don't those who develop the
capacity to avoid doing harmful things and those who don't and then he goes on to say that well
if you make a fire from the name lists five different kinds of
trees because back then they rubbed sticks together to make fire so if you take you know Oakwood and rub
it together or if you take Manzanita wood or if you take fur or all these different kinds of three and you make a
fire is the fire difference with each time no it's the same thing the fire is the same
same thing anybody in the forecasts if they actually develop these five
capacities they make the same fire same spiritual fire the same qualities inside
of themselves there and if they develop those things then there's no distinctions between
them that the Buddha thinks is relevant elsewhere he goes on a different suit
does the same kind of idea appears and then he says um can uh people in any of the casts
uh kill oh yes but can they not kill oh yes equally
how about taking what's give not given if it's stealing and not stealing how about sexual misconduct and lack of it
how about lying and not lying how about intoxicating themselves and not the time they can all do that equally
he says well then there's no distinction that's relevant between them they're all equal can they can everyone develop a heart of
loving kindness that's boundless that includes everyone and the Buddha says and they say yeah
everyone can do that it doesn't matter what cast you're in well then there's no real relevant distinction between them
so the Buddha is kind of is making distinctions for me people but not recognizing any distinction that makes
one person Superior to another in terms of their cast in terms of their
race in terms of their ethnicity in terms of their gender in terms of their sexual orientation
but how they live and behave ethically in what qualities
they develop inside of them those distinctions have some value to for the Buddha but those don't distinction those
distinctions don't separate people into Superior and inferior
so that's interesting Maybe more interesting I think is the Buddha
actually just as they told gay people instructions in meditation practice
gave people instructions to living an ethical life he also gave instructions that we should
speak up if people are harming others
if people are killing stealing lying involving sexual misconduct sexual harm
or causing harm through their intoxication that
not only you know not only should we not do that but we should also speak up
and encourage people not to do it he never said that we should speak up to
uh to be oppositional to anyone about it but we should speak up to point out that
this doesn't work this is not healthy and the opposite is so much better
so here our Buddha does make distinctions but not about who is superior inferior
but about how people behave and the behavior of people is the real
emphasis the Buddha has the actions how we live our life makes a difference
and and we want to speak up so in our society we have plenty of
people who are killing killing people who literally are killing
their Spirit we have lots of situations with lots of situations where in our
society in the United States there's taking what is not given there was announcements about the
climate change stuff and the amount of taking not given in terms of our consumptions and use of resources I mean
the resources haven't been given freely there's often kind of a kind of they use
the word rape often for pillaging how strongly the The Taking of what's not
given goes on in our society and uh in our world
so it doesn't take much to see that there's a reason to speak up
but how do we speak up I think one of the things that uh
Buddhism emphasized don't speak up until you've looked at yourself deeply
understand what's skillful and unskillful understand what's healthy and unhealthy
in your own heart first don't act from your greed don't act it
from your hate don't act from delusion monitor yourself learn about yourself
about how these horses work learn to recognize how you get caught in
attachments in your social relationships and your situation in life learn how to
recognize how you get tense and reactive and judgmental learn how to recognize when you're watching a sports game
that you've got caught by what the referee has done and you're not really
you know you're really attached and I didn't recognize that so that
maybe you're not so attached and you can maybe be more I don't know if impartial is the right word but more fair and
don't have these double standards so in this training we did they
emphasized this quite a bit to the diversity and and one representative kind of study they told us about which
had a big impact on me and there's lots of these kinds of studies it's just one representative of
a whole class of studies that come to the same conclusion it's called that Thomas Meyer study
and they took a bunch of lawyers and offered them a some kind of law
brief to analyze and consider and to rate from one to five
and this brief had a lot of mistakes in it 22 mistakes
some are grammatical some are legal and but they didn't tell that to the lawyers and said just read this and then
and then judge it you know just rate it from one to five but then they as part of all this they
would say to some lawyers that this was written by a black person
and the others it was written by a white person but the exactly the same document just
different the the the racial identity of the author was said to be different
the difference was that uh for as a white author they assumed it was white
author the score would be 4.1 out of 5. when they assumed there was a black
author if the score would be that was 3.2 out of 5. what a dramatic difference
this is called implicit bias I mean the lawyers weren't thinking about them wasn't you know they probably
weren't aware they were even doing this but there's so many ways in which we have this kind of bias that operates
that's a little bit like the sports team or a little bit like you know self and other
part of the training we did was that they emphasized over and over again is that stereotype stereotyping others
having bias is just part and parcel of human life it just comes with being a
human being the way they wanted to explain it was that this life we live in is so complicated
the mind is a pattern recognizing recognizing
mind that's going to jump to patterns and make conclusions about how things are without really seeing accurately if
we didn't do that to some degree we wouldn't find our way in the world but so so everyone has this
but it's possible to become more and more Mindful and aware of how this operates within us
and that's the training and so then with this deep diversity
folks talked about the skills that were needed to kind of live wisely in this
diverse Society it was like right out of the book for the Dharma practice I loved it
so compassion accept the existence of bias except that
it exists have a vision of the possibility of being free of being caught by bias free
of attachments and have the intention to do so
catch yourself in the act which means notice be mindful to notice
how it's operating and name bias and analyze it so name it
when you see it it may be your own and analyze it consider what goes on
be involved in self-learning learn about bias and not only your own
but how this works in our society the social context for it because a lot of
it is learned also some of the biases so to think to assume that you don't have
bias probably means you have more than you realize
um then it was fascinating when it's they're not quite so common in Buddhist circles this one this is like where we
have the most to learn the first one seemed fine for us Buddhists I thought but the next one is step into courageous
conversations to start on the on a whole not many of
you maybe but on the whole are tend to be conflict avoidant tend to err on the side of being polite
and you know accepting and peaceful and but the courageous conversations
and then the last one is develop relationships if you really want to work to create a
society that is less caught by bias have relationship with people especially people who are on the other sports team
when I met my son was in Little League here I sometimes would intentionally go because the baseball games where the
bleachers were like there was like the two sides like I said the parents would sit behind this Dugout of their team so
there was parents on one side and parents said oh I would often go sit on the team for my my posing team for my
son was on it was really weird to sit there
but you know I didn't want to you know I wanted to kind of break the you know the Divide
and um so uh
so this uh exploration of this topic and to do it in a way that is maybe
meaningful fun and not divisive is one of the reasons why we
we've now now exploring this deep diversity approach because there's a lot
of divisiveness in the world of diversity inclusion and equity
there's a lot of politics political stances that people take in it that are
not really recognized as being political stances they're just like this is true and you're wrong
and get on with it you know or but uh what this deep diversity does is
to remove the divisiveness and recognize everyone's involved in this
and and so let's take a deep look at it together and uh and so you know there's
limitations to that as well but this has been a wonderful thing so that we feel like welcome to step into this in a
accepting environment to really look and have these conversations and consider it and how do we go forward from here
and so the Deep diversity work involved four different areas
it was looking at bias itself recognizing it understanding the role
that emotions have in in the the influence they have on bias so that's a rich area to be mindful
of emotions and to understand it that also goes along really well with this practice that we do here
and then to take a good look at identity identities people have and how we relate
to Identity and the fluidity of identity and and how we react to Identity and
and the respect from it is part of all this and then a power
and they had a wonderful there's a few wonderful sayings to this but one was about power
because it's the animal leadership is the name of the organization so they're focus a lot about leadership and
Buddhism we like to consider everyone leaders so it's it's relevant for everyone to step into this kind of role
but it's uh they talked about developing leadership power uh based on caring so leadership based
on caring not on power so Authority that comes from caring not
from the invested power or social power that people are given and I love that that we come from caring
and caring for each other and from that comes leadership or comes working
the other thing that I really quote from that organization that I really liked was
um if you take sides
who's going to see the whole if you if you take side who's going to
see the whole and in the teachings of the Buddha I he
he's concerned about the whole as he said the highest order of kind of
how to care for everyone is to care for the welfare and happiness of both self and others and for our whole community
he was very explicit about this and not to be only care about certain
people and not other people and this gets particularly difficult when there's uh hurt harm being done
and I was on the I was the chair of a Ethics Committee for many years for 15
years I think 17 years a long time and had to kind of uh mediate conflicts
that people had and um and the approach that I took which I carefully tried to explain to
everyone in Conflict was that I was concerned what was the best for everyone involved
and sometimes people are a little shocked by that because what about the perpetrator I mean like yes I'm really concerned about the best
for you what's best for you at the same time what's best for the other person let's look for that let's find that
together and eventually everyone seemed to appreciate that there was value in that
but it really it took a lot of work to figure out how that satisfied everybody's needs
but it was it was an approach that wasn't trying to set up keep things adversarial but everyone needs to benefit everyone needs
to grow so um who looks at the hole who looks that
cares for everybody involved in a situation and so this uh animos anima
um organization now there's deep diversity seems to do that I seems to have that
approach in a very nice way some people are not going to like it
because it's um it's not political enough and there's these uh systemic issues in
our society that appear to be more political than personal and they acknowledge that very clearly
in the organization but um still there's a I think there's a
their approach to addressing it is something that seems Akin or to what we like here the leadership here at IMC at
least likes so um so we finished this it was a four day
training we did it was really really cool to go through it and and uh
and have these issues raised and to look at it in an intentional way
and so we're hoping as the months next over the next year to introduce this
more to the community I don't think we're going to do this like I'm doing today a captive audience who has to sit
here and listen to me talk about it but hopefully it wasn't too bad today I was because I'm kind of inspired by it
but there will be opportunities to um to sign up for different programs different kind of simple things we're doing to
offer offer this training and exploration in our community and the leadership some of the some of the
teachers and some of the teacher trainees and other leaders board members and different people are excited by this
and are investing their time and efforts to be able to bring this into our
community so so some of you will have the option if you you have the all of you have the option
to be part of this if you'd like one of the odd things about IMC is that
we are a very poorly defined community that's about the strength and a weakness
and I like the strength part of it it means that it's open to anyone who comes and if you want to be if you want
to be a member of IMC just by wanting it you are and if you're a kind of person doesn't
like membership in organizations or we don't have membership that's fine you can come anyway
so you know it's kind of like very hopefully fluid you know so so you know
participate as it works for you and what's nice for you but we'll be doing this
and some of you if you find this interesting what I've said today you might think about looking at reading the
book The Deep diversity it's been a very wonderful book for us and and it's a one
of the values of choosing it is that it gives us as a community an opportunity to have shared vocabulary shared
Concepts to find their way with and to have that shared is really helpful because if if it just makes things
easier to have conversations and to understand so
there's tea today so everyone's welcome to stay and set up out there and many of
us go outside in the parking lot afterwards and it's what I like to do when there's tea day is if you don't
mind staying an extra couple of minutes just shortly and introduce yourself to the a couple of people next to you with
some sense that if sometimes when someone's left there alone everyone turns you up the other direction look around and make sure everyone's included
because inclusion is important then and say hello and even if it's your first
time here at IMC um a year now someone who can welcome that person you're with welcome welcome
each other here and say hello and if there's something invaluable or an interesting or problem that are
interesting that came out of this talk I gave you want to share with your friend that'd be fine but it's enough to say
hello introduce yourself and I look forward to seeing you at the T thank you