so good morning everyone
the title of the talk today is
impermanence
and our relation to time
so I want to begin with a chant in Pali
that maybe some of you know it's a
beautiful short chant
that
with just a few words captures
what impermanence is for us in the
Dharma
and as you listen perhaps you want to
keep in mind how this chant has been
chanted for centuries and countless
Generations that have been born and died
have been chanting it and as we hear it
or chanted we're connected to all these
people that go all the way back to the
Buddha that have practiced
and
try to face this reality of impermanence
so if you happen to know the chant feel
free to chant with me
foreign
Domino
tea
testamental so cold
possible translation would be all
conditioned things are impermanent
they arise and they pass away
understanding this deeply brings the
greatest happiness which is peace
so with this talk we want to
explore from one particular perspective
and permanence impermanence is such a
big big topic it's one of the three
Universal characteristics
and it's so big that we have to come
back
over and over again and from different
perspectives
this makes the our journey to get closer
to this concept much more interesting
and then also understand that it's not
just the concept it's something that we
have to embody that we really have to
intuitively know
the first time that
um I came in touch with impermanence in
a long retreat a three-month retreat
the way that I would describe it the
sense that I got was desolation
and
that's why we have to come back many
many times because
it takes a lot of practice to be able to
be with impermanence and not fall into
desolation so that was kind of like the
beginning to just touch this enormity
but as we go along and that has also
shown in my practice as we go along and
touch again into impermanence in it in a
deep way not just not just in a rational
way
then we begin to be in touch with that
luminosity in immensity that comes with
the understanding of impermanence
so you're talking about impermanence
through our relation to time for me is
like breaking this immensity into
manageable bits
and to me as I was thinking about it
this topic is uh particularly Rich
because it is as much a spiritual
question as an existential one and also
a practical one right I mean it's so
important how is it that we relate our
time from day to day
in a group of teachings that maybe some
of you have heard called the abhidhamma
found it interesting that time is
described as a mental phenomenon whose
purpose is to separate and Order events
so this is interesting this is separate
and Order events you know it's very
useful for us to be able to choreograph
our lives in community
but this definition also points by
saying it's a mental phenomenon that
we're dealing with something abstract
so in no way we're going to
Define what time is we're just going to
probe it a little bit here a little bit
there
because just thinking of time in terms
of seconds minutes hours I see it as our
feeble attempt to bring order
and control on something that we have no
control at all
Jorge Luis Borges the Argentinian poet
writes time is the substance of which I
am made of
time is a river that sweeps me away
but I am the river
so we can say that we are time we are
change
time you can also say is the span
allotted to us
from the time of our birth
to the time of our death
time is also understood in terms of
space
that is we visualize time
as a space that can be filled with
activities we plan how many things we're
going to fit in in a particular amount
or span of time
we look at time also as a commodity and
and something we own you know we speak
of I have time
but the Dharma teaches us otherwise the
Dharma teaches us
we only have the present moment we
really don't know if we have one year or
two years whatever time in our lives
so one way that I want to look at how is
it that we relate to time is how is it
that we have been conditioned it's
really quite an interesting question to
ask
ourselves how was I conditioned by my
family my culture
and as I asked myself the question the
memory came back
when I was a kid growing up in Mexico
City my mother was a ballet teacher and
every afternoon before she would go off
to teach her ballet classes she would be
running down the hall
right in front of our bedrooms and she
would call out one last
Direction use your time well because you
will have to give an account to God
I heard that every afternoon
so what did that say about me
I've had to realize that when we have
that relation to time
what she really meant is don't spend
your afternoon playing daydreaming which
is what I love to do
and so some of us grow up and have to
relearn how to play
and by play I mean just you know this
this frolicking just for the joy
of doing whatever it is
not every moment has to be filled with
striving
with producing or self-improvement
do we know how to rest just for the sake
of resting do we give ourselves
permission to just rest
in Retreats I have found that it is very
common to Find Yogis who have a hard
time giving themselves permission
to just be in the retreat and not to be
producing something
is as if we've been taught you have the
right to exist only if you're producing
does that sound familiar
so this is something many of us have
internalized in Western culture
but not all cultures have this attitude
for example in indigenous cultures in
Latin America they have a very different
relation to time
and a friend of mine was telling me of
this anecdote of um the he went to an
indigenous Market
and he saw this woman who was selling
beautiful hands woven baskets and so he
asked her would you would you sell me
all your baskets
and much to his surprise she said oh I
won't sell them all because what would I
do the rest of the day
so for us it's kind of a little bit like
well
but for her she enjoyed this this sense
of smelling seeing talking to people
being in her community
being the whole day in the market that
was an experience for her
and to me that conveys a certain kind of
contentment
that some of us
don't have because we're so busy rushing
from one activity to the other
the writer Oliver Berkman describes
that many of us are productivity Geeks
and I certainly was one with endless
to-do lists
so
most of us have the belief consciously
or unconsciously that if we only had
enough discipline
an organizational skills
that we would be able to do all we want
to do
therefore it is not surprising that
there are thousands of self-help books
to help you manage your time better
and all these books promise
us that if we manage our time well we
will once and for all get done all we
want and that we will have some control
over our lives
but
I think
you're here because in some ways you've
noticed that this keeps escaping us and
that that's not the way
there is one book that has been
published recently
that offers A New Perspective
this book was written by Oliver Berkman
and the title is 4
000 weeks time management for Mortals
so this is not a Dharma book this is a
book for a general public some of you
might maybe already know about the book
but what I really like is that from the
get-go he lets you know
we have only fourth in average four
thousand weeks to live
and we are Mortals
for the general public that's quite an
affront
to remind people that we have limits and
that we're Mortals
but I think this is precisely why this
book is so important for us
foreign
it was always already the case
that you would never experience a life
of perfect accomplishment or security
and that your 4 000 weeks have always
been running out
so this is the kind of honesty that we
are accustomed to in the Dharma but not
necessarily the General Public
the German philosopher heidega
describes succinctly with three words he
says
being towards death
sign Toda
and for me this expression with three
words is saying if you live your life
aware of your mortality
you will live a life that is much more
conscious
much more wholehearted
and you would let go of all kinds of
petty things that we get trapped
over and over again
so now I want to talk a little bit about
this very mysterious
aspect of
how subjective it is of the of how we
perceive time
I think we've all had a very intense uh
experience of that during covet lockdown
where many reported that they were
feeling like time had disintegrated for
them
and to me it felt that way because all
of our routines came to a halt and so
our relation to time really shifted
it's also interesting to notice in more
extreme cases like when we get
the news
of somebody close to us that has died
something very interesting happens with
our perception of time
I don't know if you've noticed but the
way that I tried to explain it was that
perhaps we can imagine that our life is
like a film strip that is just flowing
and the events that organize our life
are are like the frames of the film
strip and when we get like shocking news
it is as if it falls
in between those frames it falls into
another dimension
and we feel as if we're floating in a
different space
I found it fascinating that the Greeks
actually had a term for this
they called it cairos
they also had the term for Chronos and
Kronos is what we are familiar with
that's measuring time according to
minutes and hours and weeks and a
calendar schedules that's Kronos
but Kairos is when we have this
experiences that are like Watershed
experiences that have a before and after
and I read you the way that Krista
Tippett describes cairo's time she says
it is a moment
that disrupts everything that came
before everything you thought you knew
cairo's moments are these pivot Points
when the questions you are asking
holding living actually change life is
suddenly unalterably defined separated
into a before and after
I think it's wonderful to have a word
for that
it's powerful to be able to name our
experience in our practice we know that
in meditation when we are observing the
mind
if we are able to come up with precisely
what's happening in the mind in the
moment there's a shift
it's like
we wake up
so there are many ways that in many
perspectives that we can talk about
of why is it that we perceive time
differently but I'll share one that I
think is important that Workman mentions
in his book
and that has a lot to do with our age
and he says our brains encode the
passage of time based on how much
information we process in a given time
interval
so for example in childhood when we have
endless new experiences
a year if you remember when you were a
child seems like an eternity
but as we get older life becomes more
habitual if we are not careful
we live in the same place we have the
same job we have the same relationships
and the sense of novelty diminishes
so then we have this sense that the
years are just kind of running like
water through our fingers
it is as if the texture of our live
loses its relief
and the days and the weeks and the
months filled with
unfortunately stale routines blur like
in a shapeless mask
the psychologist William James writes
and then it seems that the years grow
Hollow and they collapse
I found this when I read it it's like
the images it's shocking and sad
we don't want that
and and this practice gives us a
fantastic tool which is Sati mindfulness
which allows us to stay awake for every
moment
and if we practice now before we get
really ill
and are unable to have exciting
experiences
then we will be prepared and we will be
able to Delight in little details like
how the Sun is suddenly shimmering on a
little piece of foil paper
but we have to we have to really take it
seriously now
so if I sum up just to a couple of ideas
of what Berkman presents in his book I
would say
that he says accept that you can't do
everything
very important
and then
once you clarified what are the things
that are important important to you I
mean really take the time and clarify
this is what is important to me then you
go and do them wholeheartedly
and all the other things that you cannot
do because you'll recognize your limits
you put aside
and you're free of guilt
so you can see that when you look at
this this way it has a lot to do with
renunciation that we talk about a lot in
the Dharma
renunciation because you are accepting
from the get-go that you can't do it all
and you let go of the things that
you know you can't get to it
and Berkman says it is about
transforming
what he calls the fear of missing out on
something
to the joy of missing out on something
not interesting the joy of missing out
on something
and this to me connects very nicely with
the way that we Define renunciation in
the Dharma
you give up
a lesser joy for a Greater Joy
so how would this letting go
give us
this greater happiness in this context
we can see that when we clarify what's
important for us
it's an expression it's it's an
expression of our values
this in turn
gives you is a result of clarity which
will give you confidence and joy
will also experience a sense of
lightness of lightness of not always
carrying this big load of you know we
think we have to get all these things
down and it weighs us down
so the last
um idea that I want to bring up with you
is is something that Berkman calls deep
time
but for us the equivalent would be
mindful time
so
it's really the ability of just be to be
as present as possible
but what I found interesting is that as
he writes about deep time
he describes in a very candid way how
for himself somebody who's done a lot of
study and also meditation around this
topic of the of time
how it is difficult to be to remain
present
and he writes
the more you try to be here now to point
at what's happening in this moment and
really see it the more it seems like you
aren't here now or alternatively that
you are but that the experience has been
drained of all its flavor
so then he goes on to describe how he
went on this Arctic trip
and he prepared
um a lot to what was going to be a peak
experience and that was to witness the
Northern Lights
and he comments I was determined to
relish the exhibition which the next
morning the locals would describe as
particularly impressive
but the more I tried the less I seemed
to be able to do so
much to his dismay you found himself
thinking oh the northern lights look a
little bit like one of those
screensavers
foreign
that's kind of that's kind of sad isn't
it
to go to almost at the end of the world
and then think about your screen saver
so just briefly
where wherein lies this why is it that
in moments like this in Peak experiences
we're not able to be there fully and we
feel as if we have a glass in between
the experience and ourselves there's
much that we could say but we don't have
much time left
so
of course for us in the Dharma the
ethics part is essential to to be able
to be calm and to be present
but I think in this situation what's
going on in the the and what Berkman
describes it's more like right effort
from the noble hateful path
now this ability to be able to monitor
our mind constantly to recognize this is
an unskillful mind State I want to let
go of it I want to weaken it or ah this
is this is a a wholesome one I want to
cultivate it
it takes years to fine-tune what we call
this effortless effort
and this is something that little by
little will allow us
to remain more and more fully present
so I want to finish
with um
a haiku
by the 18th century Japanese poet Issa
it says on a branch
floating down river
a cricket singing
on a branch
floating down river
a cricket singing
this image
for me summarizes all what we have been
talking about
the sense of impermanence
the river moving changing
that we are the river that we are the
change
it also captures the
vulnerability of our human fate the
precariousness of our life of the
Crooked balancing on top of the branch
and yet
if we are able
to embrace this reality
wisely
we too will be able to sing like the
cricket
thank you very much
and so let me just close our eyes for a
moment and let the word sink in
thank you
so I understand that
at this point you go out and uh
we can sit outside and
talk a little bit but if any of you
maybe has to go and like to ask a short
question or has a comment please go
ahead and do it now before we move
You Feel Complete
good okay thank you so much