good evening everyone welcome it's nice to be here with you
my name is May Elliott and I'm coming today from San Francisco
Zen Center where I live and work and I serve as director there
um and I spent a lot of time sitting vipassana despite living at a Zen Center
so I love this tradition and I'm very glad to be here if at any point in the talk you can't
hear me just do this and I'll raise my voice a bit so I wanted to start with a very short
poem about two very large beings by the great Sufi poet Rumi
and his title for the poem is two giant fat people
and it goes like this God and I have become like two giant fat
people living in a tiny boat we keep bumping into each other and
laughing I'll read it again God and I have become like two giant fat
laughing so some of you may be familiar with hote
sometimes known as The Laughing Buddha you might have seen sculptures of him sometimes in gardens and he's typically
depicted as having this big belly and a huge smile sometimes his hands are up
like this above his head sometimes kind of rest in a resting posture
um and as it turns out hote is actually the depiction of a an old Chinese monk
um and as Legend has it hote was known for
being so large because he would eat the suffering of others
so he had this big belly because he consumed other people's problems all the
while being full of joy so when I hear Rumi's poem what I see
are two Hotes sitting in a tiny boat floating on the
ocean of suffering bumping into each other and having a great time
and what I love about hote is he is that he shows us that that Joy
helps us metabolize suffering right if we want to be resilient enough to
face our own suffering we need some joy and if we want to be in service to
others if we want to meet the crises of gun violence or of racism or of deadly
earthquakes then we need to be pretty well resourced and joy helps us be well resourced
so that's what I'd like to talk about tonight Joy the practice of joy and specifically
I'm calling this talk the buffet of joy cultivating wholesome States
so uh considering so much of human life is spent trying to obtain joy and avoid
unpleasant experiences it's kind of surprising that we don't talk about it more directly and more frequently so I
became really interested in what does Buddhism have to say about Joy and what
are reliable means of cultivating it and can Joy be available when circumstances
are unfavorable and this is a relevant topic for me
because I've spent much of the past 15 years being really serious about
practice and there have been many parts of that time where
the practice was not about Joy it was about suffering and renunciation and
getting rid of my hobbies so I could meditate and sacrificing time with loved
ones for Retreats and all of that has been a really powerful training
and I've learned over time that it's severely underemphasized Joy
um and it's taken me a long time to realize that cultivating Joy is a tremendously important part of the
spiritual path um yeah Joy is not an add-on some people
feel like suffering the meat of practice enjoys an accessory but that's actually not the case like there's there's a
reason that the Buddha was known as the happy one
and joy is found all over the place in the Buddhist teachings so you know if you're a list person you might know that
you can find it in the seven factors of Awakening and in the 16 steps upon upon asati it's
in Transcendent dependent arising sympathetic joys of Brahma vihara so
it's all over the place you don't have to go far to find it um James bear is the Insight teacher
who's probably best known for his teachings on Joy he actually wrote a
book called Awakening Joy so if you want a little more joy in your life that's a good one
um he says gladness and Delight do not merely
balance out negative Tendencies they actually heal the aversive mind
I love that gladness and Delight don't merely balance out negative Tendencies
they actually heal the aversive mind so one of the ways that I've learned to
attune to Joy is by getting to know the different flavors of Joy kind of in the
same way that one might be a connoisseur of fine cheeses
one can also be a connoisseur of Joy so here's here's a quote from the dhamapata
tasting the flavor of solitude and peace one becomes free of distress and Evil
drinking the flavor of Dharma Joy ah so happily we live we who have no
attachments we shall Feast on joy as the radiant gods
sounds pretty good right so I'm using joy as a more general term
tonight just to Encompass all of these wholesome States kind of a catch-all term
but they're actually like very precise distinctions in the sutas about the
different flavors of joy and there's a set of teachings that's locally known as the gladness pentad
that actually goes through some of these flavors so I'm going to share them with
you in the way that you're sometimes getting to to hear distinctions helps
wake us up to see those distinctions in our own life and to be more more attuned to them so
um the five parts of the gladness pentad there's gladness pamoja is the first
then PT Joy Tranquility pasadi
happiness or sukkah and concentration or samadhi so gladness Joy Tranquility
happiness and concentration so in the sutus this is presented as
something that can naturally arise in the heart and can they unfold from one to the next to the next so it's kind of
sequential um and so let's zoom in now on a couple of
these because it seems a lot like gladness joy and happiness like those
seem like they'd be synonymous but they're actually not Tranquility I'd say most people are familiar Tranquility has
a slightly different flavor you know calm or concentration or the stealing of the Mind the collecting of the mind but
those three that I just named they seem pretty similar so those are the ones that I'll unpack for you so
the first gladness or pomoja [Music]
this state is more actually more evaluative in nature so that's to say
there's often it's often evoked by a mental catalyst um like I'm glad about something so
gladness arises when we evaluate a situation it might happen in a split second and we go oh this is pretty great
you know and often gratitude has this Quality quality of gladness because it
comes from reflection like oh I'm so glad that that meeting at work went well today or oh I'm so glad that I have this
cozy blanket for my my bed so it's it has a mental Catalyst for it
Joy PT on the other hand the next factor in the gladness pentad does not rely on
a mental catalyst so it doesn't need any sort of mental stimulus for it to happen
instead it's more physical very energized uplifting and often it
comes forth from wholehearted engagement in activity So like
um so meditative Joy or PT sometimes it's even translated as Rapture because as
the mind really begins to collect a lot of energy and joy can come forth
physically in the body so um then we have tranquility and then
happiness so happiness is considered the most subtle of the three
um it's more subdued relaxed calm satiated
um so uh contented and it happens as we continue to become
more collected more immersed in in wholehearted engagement with the task at
hand and then concentration so those are the five
um but to share maybe an analogy for those three the three really similar ones
there's an analogy in the commentaries to the abidama that does a nice job of just describing
how joy and happiness are different and I think it actually I'll add in a
way that it also explains gladness too so imagine for a moment that you are out in
a desert and you are parched it's been a long time since you've had anything to drink
um and uh you happen to hear from someone that there's an oasis nearby
so you can imagine that upon hearing this news the Mind becomes very glad
it's really glad about the fact that there's an oasis there like there's that gladdening in the heart
when actually starting to travel to the Oasis you can imagine there's a lot of
energy and excitement and joy so that's that's how it is going to the Oasis
once you get to the Oasis and you drink water to your heart's content and you
bathe in the waters and there's birds and lotuses and you rest back in the
shade and you're satiated and content that is sukkah
so PT is the excitement of going to the Oasis and sukkah is that satiation
thirst quenched so these are the three flavors of Dharma
Joy so hopefully you can just start to feel into those in your own life and
practice so you can develop a palette for them
and uh what's so wonderful about them and I mentioned this briefly before is that they they happen naturally they
don't come into being because they are uh they're not they're not willed into being
um by the practitioner but rather the practitioner just puts in place the conditions
for the gladness pentad to occur um so we can think about it a little bit
like growing a garden like we're not in charge of when the seed actually Sprouts
right we can we can provide good soil and make sure it's in a place where it
has plenty of sunlight and we can water it regularly but we don't control when the seed sprouts and similarly we can
put conditions in place for the gladness pentad but we can't we can't force it to
happen right so um and what's great about what I like about this analogy of the of a seed
growing is when a seed Sprouts you know little seedlings they have the leaves that unfold one and then the other and
that's how the gladness pentad can unfold too it can be gladness one leaf then the next leaf on unfurls which a
joy then Tranquility Etc um and so our job just create favorable
conditions so uh the next question might be well
what are the favorable conditions um and that's what I'd like to spend the rest of the talk discussing is
um what are favorable conditions for the arising of the gladness pentad
and specifically I want to focus on some lesser known ones I think
all of you probably have some wonderful ways of cultivating joy in your own life
people love spending time in nature and with people they care about and they
have wonderful hobbies and that is all fabulous and sometimes it can be helpful
to have some lesser-known modes of bringing joy into one's life so the three that I'm going
to share with you are all noted in the sutas as causes as as conditions for the
arising of the gladness pentad so one is ethical conduct
Sila virtue so ethical Behavior uh the next is generosity or Donna
and the third is Faith or Sada so ethical conduct generosity and Faith
so I'll spend a little time sharing about each of those um
so to start uh virtue ethical conduct this
some of you may have may be familiar with the term the Bliss of blamelessness
so this refers to the lightness of being when we're not guilty of causing harm
and when we're not we're not weighed down with the burden of unskillful
actions we're not killing or stealing or engaging in sexual misconduct or lying
Etc [Music] um and you might be able to feel into this in your own life and just connecting
with the experience of the difference between feeling guilty
and non-guilt like like there's uh feeling sneaky is no fun
so those uh states of um yeah of non-guilt
um are are lighter um and it's actually it's very hard for
the mind to settle uh when you've done something unethical like I know people
whose meditation has been really haunted by the um unwholesome actions of their
past and so it's actually it's a really supportive condition not just for gladness but for the settling of the
mind to um to have wholesome uh engage in wholesome
activity to um be upright in one's actions
um so at Zen Center some time ago there was
a very Charming new student there who is just starting to take up precept
practice and she was engaging it in her life to try to get a sense of like how
um how the precepts were helpful and did they bring forth joy and what's this all
about so she told a story about a time that she went to the grocery store
she went to the clerk purchased her items and as she was about to leave she
realized that the the clerk gave her too much change so she practicing her precepts not
taking what's not freely given she went back to oh excuse me you know you I think you gave me more change than you
intended handed it back and as she was about to leave
she noticed the person that was next to her in line that was about to to check
out themselves um they just looked astonished
and they said whoa that that just restored my faith in
humanity so this new student they're like wow not
so bad huh restored somebody's faith in humanity like how's that for cultivating
Joy so we never know how our upright actions
how our sea level impact others and the ways that it'll brighten the heart
and there's such a joy in being able to do what what's honest I can think of a few times myself when I was kind of torn
between a decision and one just didn't feel quite as ethically upright and in
choosing the one that felt cleaner it was like oh just a little Sparkle of
gladness arose in the heart so that's that fruiting of the gladness pentat
there's a there's a joy of Freedom an inner relaxation uh when we're not in
Conflict about the right thing to do so that's number one Silo the second
generosity or Donna so generosity comes from I mean it can
occur in so many ways material gifts giving time giving attention giving an
apology giving the gift of fearlessness that's talked about in the Buddhist
tradition that actually when we live ethically we're not um
a source of danger for others so so many ways that we can be generous
and for me for years I I kept a gratitude list every night and uh
in addition to writing down what I was grateful for that day I would also include any gifts that I had given that
day and it might not necessarily be a material gift but you know maybe the gift of my listening or any any gifts
that I gave that day um and I noticed how much it gladdened
the mind to recall those at the end of the day and actually to to feel them again
um and what I noticed was that if if I was able to give on any given day that was a
good day and it became much less important whether that day was pleasant or unpleasant
and so you know what if we based our happiness on what we give rather than
what we get a different way of of relating in the world
and if you do give a gift don't miss it
so if you give a gift and you feel that little bit of joy in the heart really be
present for that don't miss that moment you know um almost like you're a sponge soaking
it up really let your mindfulness register what that feels like in the body
there's a Native American ceremony where parents give their children an
abundance of food and gifts and then they step away and they cry out
I'm hungry I'm thirsty and then the children
get to give to them from a place of abundance
so that's a training in Donna it's a training in generosity
I was reading the news some time ago and I came across a story of generosity
about a four-year-old boy named Nolan and Nolan had a rare form of lymphoma
and he was in the hospital and Nolan
more than anything wanted to be a firefighter
and so the local fire department got word of this
and they decided to go visit Nolan um as it happens it was during the height
of the covid pandemic so they couldn't actually go into his hospital room to
visit him but they did something better they actually
drove the fire truck to the hospital and they extended the ladder all the way
up to the fifth floor where they greeted Nolan
so you can just imagine what it was like to be that first firefighter up that
ladder to meet that little boy like you might even feel it in your heart now just imagining that so you
might even go inside and just connect if you feel any gladness in the heart
imagining that and if you do
that's the arising of the gladness pentad so that's Joy or that's that's
generosity as a condition for gladness so that's the fruiting of this teaching
in your own heart
okay so the next faith how does faith lead to
gladness so I want to note that faith is not a word
that works for everyone
for some people the word confidence or trust feels more resonant
um and faith in what of course in the Dharma
so faith faith in the Buddha the Dharma and the Sangha you know in our faith in
our own capacity for awakening in these teachings in the the Sangha and the
community of spiritual practitioners so so that's the sort of faith that
we're talking about sort of that's the sort of confidence that I'm referencing
um and it might be hard to to understand how faith can lead to gladness so one
way that we can think about this is to realize that there's um
is that when we yeah when we realize that there's an alternative to suffering
that is very good news so to realize that I can actually be
free regardless of whether circumstances are favorable like
that's very good news you know like who wouldn't be happy when they learned that there's an alternative to suffering
so that's that's the thread that takes us um from Faith to gladness like oh there
is another way what Joy there's so much joy in that so in order to grow faith it requires
you to expose yourself to the teachings so by coming to this talk tonight you
are putting the conditions in place for gladness so your your
providing the Sun the soil the water just in doing this
so listening to the Dharma cultivates Faith spending time with Dharma friends
cultivates faith studying cultivates faith
so here's an analogy about about faith from James Barris
so he says that learning to have faith in the Dharma is a little bit like learning to swim
so you know at first we get in the pool and we're kind of thrashing around and doggy paddling and
um don't feel so supported um we're a little out of control we don't
trust the water to hold us yet um but as we spend some more time in the
pool we might learn to tread water a bit we start to trust that the waters
starting to hold us a little bit more so this is like when we we start to practice and we start to gain a little
trust in the teachings we see okay this is working a bit I'm starting to have a little bit of confidence here
and then over time as we continue to practice our faith
becomes verified our faith can become radiant we really trust the Dharma
and that's that's like when we learn that we can just lay back on the water
and float and that the Dharma can support us and that it was there to hold us all along
so it's a joyful experience to go from frantically doggy paddling to resting on
the surface of the water fully supported so that's the joy that's the gladness
that can become possible when we have faith when we have confidence in the teachings
so just like two people in a boat floating on the ocean of suffering
bumping into each other and laughing right
so when we put the appropriate conditions in place
uh when we provide conditions like virtue
generosity faith we create those conditions for
gladness that's our soil our sunlight our water so
so try these out in your life you probably already are and you might
just see the relationship between those activities and gladness between those
activities and joy so in doing so may you taste all of the
flavors of Dharma Joy experiencing the full Buffet
so I'll close with a poem and this is by
Mary's standing otter it's very joyful poem
right now there are Tibetan Buddhist monks in a
temple in the Himalayas endlessly reciting mantras for the cessation of your suffering and for the
flourishing of your happiness someone you haven't met yet is already
dreaming of adoring you someone is writing a book that you will
read in the next two years that will change how you look at life nuns in the Alps are an endless vigil
praying for the Holy Spirit to alight the heart of all of God's children
a farmer is looking at his organic crops and Whispering nourish them
someone wants to kiss you to hold you to make tea for you
someone is willing to lend you money wants to know what your favorite food is and treat you to a movie
someone in your orbit has something immensely valuable to give you for free
something is being invented this year that will change how your generation lives communicates heals and passes on
the next great song is being rehearsed
thousands of people are in yoga classes right now intentionally sending light
out from their heart chakras and wrapping it around the Earth millions of children are assuming that
everything is amazing and will always be that way
someone is in profound pain and a few months from now they'll be thriving like
never before from where they are they just can't see it
someone has recently cracked open their joyous genuine nature because they did the hard
work of hauling years of Oppression off of their psyche this luminous Juju is floating in The
Ether and is accessible to you someone just this second wished for
world peace in earnest someone is dedicating their days to
protecting your civil liberties and clean drinking water someone is regaining their sanity
someone is coming back from the dead someone is genuinely forgiving the
seemingly Unforgivable someone is curing the incurable
you me someone
now thank you very much let's sit for a moment
thank you all for your kind attention
so we have a little time now for any questions or comments
any reflections
maybe anything about your own practice of joy or your own reflection on these topics
that's welcome also and your comments don't have to be genius
sometimes I think that's when in a group there's this sense that like if we say something it has to be genius
it's not true and just say your name before you speak
if you don't mind Mike so you distinguishes three things in the
pentad how would you distinguish Tranquility from concentration sure yeah
so um they both feed each other so often
they're occurring at the same time that's a really good question because often
concentration brings forth tranquility and tranquility
feeds concentration right so um I would describe so Tranquility or
passati is really that state of calm and it can be both physical there can be
physical tranquility and there can also be mental tranquility but they don't necessarily need to
happen at the same time so there's been times where I've had a lot of physical Tranquility but the mind
was not all that tranquil like you may have had the experience of having a really good day of exercise and the body
is so calm in the evening but the mind it's not concentrated so that might be a
difference and there's times where the mind has had the mind has felt somewhat tranquil
um but it's not that it's not particularly concentrated or focused like it's not it's not very collected
necessarily like it has like a subdued quality but it's it's
[Music] um yeah it's not necessarily collected like it might have some kind of like frayed
strayed thoughts whereas concentration it has concentration is the collecting of the
mind you know it's when the Mind collects into the present moment and it's willing to rest on whatever object
we put it on right so it's it's very well behaved
um and so often there's a reason that concentration meditations they're often
called the shamata or samata which means calm abiding because they're so
interlinked that those meditations bring forth calm so concentration quite
naturally brings that forth yeah great question
um one of the things that you said May about
floating floating on your back in the water it's triggered a memory that I had when
I was a kid I was actually very very skinny and my swimming teachers would
tell me all you have to do is float on your back move your head back
and you'll float and I didn't I I could never float on my
back and it was hard not to take that personally like there was some
you know like I should be able to float on the water and it wasn't until I was much older and
somewhat more rotund that floating came naturally but at that point it just so
it made me think sometimes do you have any thoughts about how does
one develop that trust to float when it just doesn't seem possible right
right well when you're a kid maybe you just needed to eat more suffering like hote
hot belly so um yeah
one of the five hindrances is doubt doubt is like one of the most common
things that plagues the mind and the antidote to doubt is faith so it's really really helpful to to
find a way to answer the question that you're asking like how do we develop faith when it just doesn't seem
possible or like when like we want to float but that's not what's happening
um so um for many people it's finding the Dharma
that works for them and exposing oneself to it so if if for whatever reason if um
Tibetan Buddhism is really the type of Dharma that really does it for you
um go for that or if there's a particular teacher that really inspires you
listen to that teacher's teaching so whatever helps um kind of like stoke the fire
like expose yourself to that and then also spending time with Dharma friends so you might not have any Dharma friends
and that's fine but that's why you can come to places like this and strike up a conversation with someone
so these are different things that can help cultivate faith and then there's also
this idea of leaning on the faith of a teacher so
maybe you don't have faith but you see that there's a teacher somebody who's a
more experienced armor practitioner than yourself and it seems like the Dharma is working for them
so you may not have felt it in your own life yet which I know isn't the case for you but for some people you know they
may not have felt it in their own life yet but they can see it's working for this other person so um sometimes that's
talked about is you can lean on the faith of another you can lean on the faith of somebody
that you're like okay I haven't felt it for myself but I I'm going to trust this because I see it's working for someone
else those are a few different access points
thank you so dude
um I guess as far as uh Joy um
that I've been feeling is just coming here and practicing and then seeing it
translate little by little in um you know life life outside of here
so I'm definitely feeling you know grateful for that and um
so you know thank thank you to to Insight Meditation Center for that
thanks for sharing the um you know I appreciate what you said about you
know you come practice here and then you see it changing your life outside of here so I that can be a continuation of
our garden analogy where you know we plant a seed we give it good conditions
but then we don't control when it it sends up a shoot and so I often think
of that in terms of meditation practice you know every time we bring the Mind back it's like planting a seed every
time we cultivate loving kindness It's like planting a seed and you go out in your life
and lo and behold you know maybe you're having an interaction a difficult
interaction with a friend and one of those seeds Sprouts at that moment and you say the kind thing rather
than the harmful thing or there's a moment of frustration and
one of those seed sprouts and you're able to be mindful of the frustration rather than just acting on it mindlessly
so there's a really sweet way that yeah doing this practice it sprouts in our life when we leave here and it's so um
it's very faith building to get to see in one's own life how the Dharma is
working so that can be another source of faith is reflecting on times that the Dharma
has been helpful in reminding ourselves of those times thanks for sharing
um I think I also wanted to add if I made um I noticed uh
I get if we don't feel like I don't know if this is true but like if
I don't feel very hopeful in the moment it seems like that um
just simply by participating with a teacher or with the Sangha
we can we can access kind of kind of by leaning
um so I think that maybe that kind of takes some of the pressure
off of uh oh like why why don't I feel you know are you like is there something
wrong with me because I'm worrying so much about tomorrow or you know I'm thinking
um you know certain pessimistic thoughts
but I feel that with with an ongoing practice we
can we can kind of access this this uh hope and kind of a more simplistic way
is that kind of go off of what what you're sharing I
think totally yeah if um yeah if you come in here and your
mind's going a mile a minute and you're feeling hopeless or uh
you know there's tons of discursive thought and will this ever work for me or you know all these different things
that the mind can say just exposing yourself to this environment um
uh you're yeah the mind is um uh
absorbing some really helpful conditions and that can take somebody really far
so yeah you don't have to worry too much about what the mind's doing in any given moment you know that's just the fruiting
of past Karma and just meet that with mindfulness thanks for sharing all right we should
oh we should probably wrap it up because it's nine but you're welcome to come say hi after if you'd like
um okay great um for anybody who's interested I have a
mailing list of different Dharma activities that I or Dharma talks and
classes that I offer and so I put that sheet I put a sign up sheet on the table in the lobby if you're interested it's a
shared Google group between me and my partner codo conlon and so we we send out
one email a month so it's very small and we just yeah share what we're up to
that month if you'd like to join us so it's on the lobby in the lobby if you're interested
all right thanks so much everyone really good to see you tonight take care