okay so welcome back welcome back seems
that there was a technical glitch and uh
zoom and
YouTube stopped
youtubing I guess and um but here we are
finding our way back so I didn't drop in
the poem so I'll share the poem with you
now and um we can talk about a little
bit the good news is it's that it's a
short
poem and the poem goes like
this I stopped her in the grocery store
her crown of snowy braids held in place
by a great silver clip her erect bearing
radiating
tenderness the way she placed yogurt and
avocados in her basket beaming peace
like the North
Star I wanted to ask what aisle did you
find your Serenity in do you know how to
be married for 50 years or how to live
alone excuse me for interrupting but you
seem to possess some knowledge that
makes the Earth burn and turn on its
axis but we don't request such things
from strangers
nowadays so I
said I love your
hair and I'm sorry if you can hear all
this uh noise it's
outside so I I'll uh read this poem one
more
time I stalked her in the grocery
store her crown of snowy braids held in
place by a great silver
clip her erect bearing radiating
tenderness the way she placed yogurt and
avocados in her
basket be mean peace like the North
Star I wanted to ask what aisle did you
find your Serenity in do you know how to
be married for 50 years or how to live
alone excuse me for interrupting but you
seem to possess some knowledge that
makes the Earth burn and turn on its
AIS but we don't request such things
from strangers nowadays so I
said I love your
hair this poem is uh just great in so
many ways the poem is called I
confess and the poet is Allison
lman I confess by Alison
luterman so there's a a number of ways
that we might think about this poem but
one is that our practice doesn't impact
only
ourselves whether we intent to or not it
impacts
others so we this poem is about one
person seeing another person and being
struck about how the other person they
erect bearing radiating
tenderness the way that they're doing
these simple of putting grocery items in
their
cart and the speaker notices oh there's
something special about this person with
the white hair the braids that put up
with a silver
clip so when we show up in the world
with some steadiness some balance some
ease some presence it has an
impact whether we know it or not whether
it's a
immediately obvious to
ourselves we make an impact we showing
up with some ease and
presence and some
peacefulness spreads out from us whether
we are speaking to others or whether we
are just doing our ordinary things so we
don't practice only for ourselves
we also practice for others recognizing
this impact that humans have on each
other one way that I like to think about
this sometimes is to go to the opposite
extreme we also would notice somebody
who is frantic and throwing things into
their grocery cart and maybe yelling
into the phone at the same time you know
kind of like distracted and just
agitated and maybe unkempt in a way that
looks like they don't care about
anything or you know or clearly having a
difficult time right we notice those
things as well and they have a different
impact on us than somebody who has some
ease and Poise and seems to be radiating
something so maybe that's one thing that
we could take away from this poem this
poem has a lot of different elements and
some depth to
it and for those of you that are just
joining now because we had a little bit
of problem I'll read this poem one more
time before I talk about something else
kind of like a different perspective we
might take on this poem and so this poem
is called I confess by Allison Lerman
and it goes like
this I stocked her in the grocery store
her crown of snowy braids held in place
by a great silver clip
her erect bearing radiating tenderness
the way she placed yogurt in avocados in
her
basket beaming peace like the North
Star I wanted to ask what aisle did you
find your Serenity
in do you know how to be married for 50
years or how to be
alone excuse me for interrupting but you
seem to possess some knowledge that
makes the Earth burn and turn on its
AIS but we don't request such things
from strangers nowadays so I
said I love your
hair I don't know I always kind of like
Chuck a little bit at the end but I also
want to point out one other way in which
we might think about this poem and that
is the speaker here in this
poem the way that she's
seeking like she's
looking and importantly she's looking
outside of herself like nowhere do we
hear about her own experience what's
happening for her but
instead she's looking
outside and for me I'm struck by the
person that she's looking as a person
with white hair somebody who's an elder
I'm imagining somebody who has
wisdom and so she's trying to think like
oh that person has wisdom and she says
that you seem to possess some knowledge
so this seeking for wisdom but not only
wisdom she describes this person as
having some
tenderness and beaming peace like the
North
Star North stars are something that like
show the way or something that we
follow so this way of the speaker saying
she wants peace as well so this seeking
of wisdom and peace so much can be a big
part of our
practice and we might think that it's
all about
seeking and uh for those of you who have
any of you who have done grocery
shopping you know that the let's see the
yogurt and the avocados are never near
one another right they're in different
parts of the grocery store maybe I'm
reading too much into this poem but
there's this way that their speaker is
just like following this other person
stalking her as the way that the uh the
poet uses this word stalking so is there
a way in which we are
stalking wisdom tenderness peace
thinking that it's out
there but not looking
here into our own EXP
experience we have wisdom we have
tenderness times we have
peace The Way Forward is
found with our experience and our
reactions to that
experience we spend so much time looking
outside of ourselves but this practice
so much is about looking in
Inward and then maybe a third aspect
I'll bring about to this about this poem
there's so many things I could say about
this one is of course I just to
appreciate the Whimsy and the
everydayness of
it this recognition that everything can
be a teacher all of our experiences can
be a teacher even this random experience
I'm going to the grocery store I'm
saying random but you know it's often we
tend to think like go my spiritual
practice is only on the meditation
cushion when I'm in a meditation
posture but is there a way that all of
our experiences can be a support for our
practice is there a way that everything
that we do in our life can be this way
that enriches
us doesn't mean it's Pleasant doesn't
mean that we want but is there a way
that we can learn from whatever life
brings
us and maybe lastly I'll say this the
title of this poem I
confess right this this confessing
doesn't actually happen in the poem it's
maybe the poet is talking about the the
character in the poem is maybe doing
something that uh they feel like they
shouldn't be doing so they have to
confess it and you know confess
sometimes is associated with some
religious practices as
well but it there's a way in which it
also sense that we're doing something
wrong right we only confess things that
we do
wrong and how much this is also a part
of The Human Experience especially I
would say in modern times in the west we
often are feeling like we're doing
things
wrong
can we be present for that experience
too even though we may not be doing
anything wrong there way in such we have
this feeling of
inadequacy but
instead can we maybe connect with our
experience in whatever way is
available this poem The Reader wants to
ask this whired woman this beautiful
white haired woman uh about you know how
to be married or wisdom or things like
things but instead she
said I love your
hair she started where she
could this is the connection she could
make and I love that we don't know what
happen happens
next maybe there was this conversation
that was really touching and meaningful
for this
speaker maybe
not but at least she made this
connection I love your
hair I keep on smiling and giggling a
little bit with this poem and for me
that uh is part of the power of it too
is that it brings this kind of uplift
the ordinariness of it
so thank you thank you for joining me on
this journey these five days on the
Poetry of
practice it's been a delight to share
this with you
all and may you find your own poetry
maybe you feel inspired to even pen some
lines on your own or dig out the old
book of poetry that at one time touched
you and may you find your own wisdom
your own tenderness your own mindfulness
while you're grocery
shopping thank
you