in the Buddhist teachings there's a phrase that has
caught my attention over the years
it's practicing in accordance with the Dharma practicing in accordance with the Dharma
it's used quite a bit by the Buddha in the teachings actually it's not just a kind of a one-time thing
that he says in one little place he uses it fairly frequently and something that he brings out in his talks
one way that the Buddha talked about it is that practicing in
accordance with the Dharma is one of the key factors that supports us to wake up
so it's a kind of a key one and a bit more poetically the Buddha
said that people who practice in accordance with the Dharma
beautify the Sangha how about that they beautify the Sangha
so today I wanted to explore this a bit this phrase the poly for it is
[Music] practicing in accordance with the Dharma
so I think there are several different dimensions to what this can mean and some of that variation has to do
with the range of meaning of the word Dharma itself which is a vast term that
can cover a lot of territory the word itself covers different domains
and in addition they're said to be about a half dozen qualities of the Dharma
which is not the focus but they'll sort of come in as we're talking about it
so the Dharma can be the teachings of the Buddha you know
this is a Dharma talk and we're we're focusing on the Buddha's teachings
and so here maybe being in accordance could mean something like following the instructions
so we're not just getting information in a Dharma talk from a teacher that
might be part of it there are explanations there are descriptions but there are also instructions among
other things things that we can do or perspectives that we can take that will help us move
toward freedom from suffering
you know you may have gotten instructions at some point on mindfulness of breathing or on
mindfulness of emotions or mind States
I know mindfulness of aversion for example so maybe you were told to feel
the aversion in the body or to name it you know name recognize
that aversion has come into the mind and name it in order to create a little gap before we you know we just act on the
aversion so these are examples of you know instructions that we get for how to how
to live with our body and mind and World in a way that's relatively free
you know and if we're doing those instructions when a strong emotion like aversion comes up then we could say that
we're practicing in accordance with the Dharma within what the Buddha taught
I wanted to offer this story that's found in Gill's book a monastery Within
identical twin sisters found their way to the monastery
at first it was very difficult to distinguish one from the other and the monks and nuns often confused them not
only did they look the same but they also had the same mannerisms identical ways of talking and as nuns they wore
the same robes in addition they both had extremely aversive personalities they were astute
observers who seemed always to see what was wrong after some months Market differences
began to appear between them they remained as aversive as ever however one sister became more and more
dour and discouraged the other became increasingly happy
soon enough the first sister left the monastic life though this did nothing to
improve her dark state the second sister went on to become the guest master in many of the monastery
guests remarked how her happiness was contagious the first sister directed her aversion
outwardly when she suffered all she could see was what was wrong with the world
the second sister looked inward when she suffered she focused on being averse to
her aversion and toward whatever clinging created it the first sister was crushed by her
version the second was liberated by hers
so we get these instructions and it's consequential whether we follow them or not
so it's interesting to observe in ourselves
you know whether that we maybe don't always follow the instructions do we
I mean sometimes we just forget of course or you know it happens too quickly and we didn't have a chance but
there are other things you know we can start to see with the mindfulness practice that things get in the way of
our actually doing these instructions it's normal that there's some challenge
for us because not all of us is on board with this process of waking up right our
doubt is not on board our ignorance is not on board so when we run into those
things they can sometimes get in the way maybe there's fear maybe there's ego I
want to do it my way why should I listen to the teacher
the mind is very tricky you know what it's putting up doubt or resistance we literally might not hear the
instructions accurately
some people worry a lot about whether they're doing it right in practice so I
want to address that directly I want to name that at least is that this phrase in accordance with the Dharma I hope
that the word accordance maybe feels a little bit more accommodating than the idea of doing it
right there's a little aversion in whether I'm doing it right or not
so maybe we could ask something like are we in harmony with what the Buddha
offered so if you're someone who is frequently concerned about whether or not you're
doing it right maybe you could ask instead am I in harmony with what I understand of the
teachings I might soften it a little bit so thinking about these two sisters you
know who were both aversive but one learned how to work within that and find
Freedom and the other did not maybe one Criterion for knowing if our
practice is in accordance is our unwholesome states decreasing and
wholesome States increasing or the reverse you know are we are we actually becoming
happier or Freer in some way and we don't have to check moment to moment to moment because there are times where we
have a period of some dukkha or some dryness in the practice but in a
long-term sequence are we generally decreasing our unwholesome states and
increasing the wholesome ones and remember that mindfulness is wholesome so that helps
but of course there's there's more to the teachings of the Buddha than just meditation instructions
so we should look beyond that also more broadly
being in accordance with the teachings maybe would be being on the path are we
doing the steps of the Eightfold Path in our life
so if we're for example if we're only doing meditation that's our thing we
meditate but we're not paying any attention to ethics or wisdom in our
life it might be hard to get fully in tune that would be like tuning one string of
our guitar to a tuning fork we've got that one string in tune but we didn't check any of the other strings you know
how is that going to be when we tried to play the guitar
so when we're bringing all the qualities of the path into a
chord together then we could say that the path is unfolding you know sometimes we're
working more on one than another and there can be periods of focus but
generally we would want to be working on all of the aspects of our life broadly together so that they can all harmonize
and unfold together one of the qualities of the Dharma I
said I would sometimes bring in the classical qualities of the Dharma of one of them is that it is onward leading
open naiko so it means that we don't get stuck forever we can't be stuck forever if
we're in accord with the Dharma maybe I should name the steps of the path just in case someone is not
familiar um their I use this word right but it's not
really right It's let's say appropriate or complete or wise so
appropriate view appropriate intention appropriate speech appropriate action
appropriate livelihood and appropriate effort appropriate mindfulness and
appropriate concentration so all of those factors you can see that
they Encompass our view of the world how we see things how we see ourselves how we act speech action livelihood and also
how we train our mind through making some effort through mindfulness through
collectiveness of mind
so there's another teaching where the Buddha talks about how a person understands the path
when they are practicing in accordance with the Dharma how do they frame it in their mind if they're practicing in
accordance and in general what this teaching says is that people like that understand two
things overall first of all they understand that thoughts of greed hatred and delusion
those are the main problems in the mind so thoughts of greed hatred and delusion are ended by practicing well that's how
they're ended they're ended by doing practice and not because of things like material gains or other material
circumstances so the result is this is that they're they're very careful about not extolling themselves and disparaging
others you know let's say you practice for a while and I don't know you become a teacher you become a
mindfulness teacher then but you don't you don't say oh this is this makes me so great you know
instead there's an understanding no what what is helping my mind to purify or improve or get more in alignment is
because I'm practicing and so one focuses on just continuing the
practice and then second which is kind of a more specialized part of the first is that
when even when a person experiences water considered attainments or important things on the path like
I don't know cultivating deep concentration or going on a long retreat or having an Insight of some kind even
then they understand that identifying with those things is not part of the path
so once again it's always just continuing to focus on the practice is
the sign of being in accordance with the Dharma so this is how we think about our
path think about our practice if we're practicing in accordance with the Dharma
we're not measuring our success or comparing ourselves with others
so another meaning of Dharma it's related to the teachings of the Buddha but another meaning of Dharma is
simply nature or how things work you know how do things work so as we
practice with our own particular experience who else's experience are going to practice with so we sit down we
feel our body and its various aches and pains and challenges we have our mind
and we have our memories that come up and the emotions and what it is that
we're trying to figure out in our life right now all of those things are part of our what
we can be mindful of in our experience that's what we do and yet as we watch
just these specific things about us we start to see patterns and we start to
eventually see into more Universal characteristics as we would say so we
watch our own mind but we're learning about how the mind works for everyone you know everyone has dukkha and
everyone has clinging unless we're totally free so we start to see these more foundational or fundamental things
that are going on and in our particular experience are just examples of those
so we come to have our own experience with foundational Dharma principles like
the four noble truths or like dependent co-arising things occur because of conditions we start to
actually see that in our experience or just generally you know how it is for
humans and a big aspect of that is seeing
impermanence for example that's one thing that we often emphasize here is noticing that things change and they
come and they go arise and pass it's very hard to find something that's been constant for our whole life
so there's a famous phrase that people say when they have deep insight into impermanence
all that is of the nature to arise is of the nature to pass away
this is kind of an Insight that we can have and I name it because in that phrase nature all that's of a nature to
arise the word is Dharma everything that is is of the Dharma to arise is of the Dharma to pass away
that's how it is so then we start to get into you know
when we start to see how these teachings of the Buddha are actually applying in
our own experience they're true for us we start to have maybe what a kind of a
felt sense of the Dharma a felt sense of accordance
does this make sense like kind of a feeling of alignment or Attunement in
the body this relates to some of the other qualities of the Dharma it's said to be visible here and now sanditiko so
the Dharma is something that we can see right here you know I I walked into the room and I was in a lousy mood and I
noticed the tear in the carpet there isn't a tear in the carpet here but you know suppose and then we see in our mind
oh when I'm in a bad mood I tend to see what's wrong with the police we see it operating right there in our mind
whereas you know if I'd been feeling happy about the spring flowers I just
saw maybe what I notice is the happy faces of the people coming in so we
start to see how the conditions are flowing along they're changing they're impacting my experience
the Dharma is also said to be timeless akalico or immediate another translation
in the way that natural laws you know always work they're kind of there all the time in
the background so we start to see that aspect of the Dharma the word Accord is related to words like
Concord or Discord it's something like being in tune musically consonant we could also say
not dissonant so there's a way that this is really true viscerally sometimes we touch into
it first in meditation you know we're sitting and yeah there's challenging things happening in the mind but we
start to kind of Orient ourselves toward oh could I could I align with this somehow could my body be physically
aligned could my mind be aligned so we start to feel into the Dharma and
that takes us deeper than just knowing it cognitively or thinking about it
if we really understand that things are impermanent we'll have a different relationship to things in our life
doesn't make so much sense to cling when we see how all of experience is changing
so to be in accordance with the Dharma when we see into these foundational principles helps us get lighter and
lighter in our life nonetheless it's still possible to be a
little bit off so I want to name ways that we can also you know feel a bit if we're getting out
of accordance number one is that we can get conceptual you know
we think about whether or not there's a rule or a principle something I heard in
a talk that I should be applying right now and often it's skillful to start with that you know for example we learn
the five precepts as the kind of ethical basis for Life as a layperson and so we
might think about those and consider whether or not we're applying that principle correctly
but eventually connecting with the Dharma is not meant to be so conceptual it's not meant to be
something that we think about quite so consciously just as an example
if we are applying the precepts really as rules that we may have learned and are trying
to apply we will eventually start to run into a lot of uncertainty we can start
to run into uncertainty you know for example we might know that one of the precepts says that we should not lie we
should not yeah we should not say what knowingly what we know is to be false
clear enough it's a rule so then what about a trivial lie in order to make someone feel happy or
comfortable if we have a rule of always stating the exact factual truth but we also have a
value of caring for our friends what about that moment that classic
moment when they say do you like my sweater and you don't
you know you know it can be a real moment of uncertainty for if we have a
rule system in conflict with our care for this
person so practice in accordance cannot only mean following conceptual principles
it's more flexible than that it's not so rigid if you're wondering what the answer is
there isn't there isn't one clear answer for how to move through that moment
but if we are attuned in accordance with the Dharma we can find something to say
somehow that navigates that another way that we can get a little bit
off is actually um you know the felt sins which I pointed
to Second it's closer you know it's more flexible but even the felt sense can be
a little bit off and what that can happen when we get focused on one particular feeling
so again an example suppose we have an experience where we're feeling tightness
in our chest you know you've gotten attuned to the body you're going You're Going Through the world with mindfulness
and you feel that you've gotten a little bit tight in the heart area and as
you're mindful of that the tightness melts away and you feel your heart open
it's a beautiful experience when something like like that happens you know we we come into Attunement and
somehow we open but then the mind can fix onto that and say oh that exact
feeling is what it means to be in accordance with the Dharma that's the feeling of it it's when my heart melts
and feels open so then after that we go through the world we are continually monitoring the feeling in our chest for
tightness and if there's any tightness we try to make it relax right this so I'm Hamming it up a little
bit but I've done patterns like this you know where I had a certain experience and I then I felt like oh that's it
that's it now I've got it and so then there can be a subtle trying to make
that happen again or believing that that's what the Dharma feels like
so it kind of makes sense but Freedom or Dharma is not any one
particular feeling it's not any one particular kind of felt sense it's not always the same way and we don't want to
get into manufacturing feelings so we have to be a little bit careful
so we can get off by bringing in too many theories and too many ideas or by getting attached to a certain kind of
feeling or a certain kind of emotion so maybe a good image then you know how
do we we're painting a bigger picture now how do we consider this idea then of accordance
with the Dharma maybe a good image is to see in terms of a process of Attunement kind of a
dynamic balance like the way riding a bicycle is a dynamic balance if you're riding a
bike you're almost always falling over in some Direction but you're always pulling
yourself back toward being in alignment always moving toward balance so you know
we have a gradual practice we're finding our way toward more and more accordance with the Dharma but we don't always get
it right we definitely don't always get it right and even if we do get it right for a little while then the conditions change
and things are off balance slightly and so maybe we think more about moving toward balance instead of getting to
balance and staying there there's very little where we're just you know set it and forget it in the
Dharma so
I feel like as we discover what practicing in accordance with the Dharma means and what it means for us it will
take us toward the maturing of both our thought and our emotion so when our
thought maybe originally was very conceptual and a little bit rigid we sort of move toward being more flexible
in how we think and having more intuition you know the sort of the mature form of the cognitive mind
and similarly our emotional heart I don't know that they're so separate but let's pretend for a moment you know
maybe we start out with a lot of reactivity and difficult experiences and
then over time that Smooths out a little bit and we move toward qualities like
Compassion or Goodwill or you know things that ways of understanding relationship that are part of some
larger whole kind of a maturing of the emotional side also we might still be aversive like that one
of the sisters you know have a a critical mind that can see the challenges with things but you know we
move toward using that will and we have more and more happiness like she did or we might always have kind of a sensual
orientation you know maybe you're uh that that type but that can move into
meta for example you know love instead of Love of sensual things we move toward
Universal love that connects beings together
it looks different for different people so this maturing process
can take some turns also often when we often we can reach a new level of
accordance when we give up or Surrender have any of you seen this in your
practice um things can't change and they they're
sort of stuck or dry and we we're putting in effort and we have to we do have to put in effort in order to engage
but at some point what's most fruitful is to give up to let go sometimes sometimes it's about
us doing something in order to practice if we don't do anything I would guess that
we will continue to keep suffering if you just sit on your couch waiting to
awaken probably will end up just continuing to suffer but there are also times when
we're getting in our own way in a sense or our our view our way of seeing things
is itself limiting and they're asked to we sort of grapple with that and at some
point it's the stepping back that helps for the Dharma to lead us onward
so then a question for us is can we you know can we learn to trust in the
unfolding of Our Own specific experience you know can we learn to trust the the
flow of the Dharma and it might not look how we think this accordance I want to tell a story now of a it's a
it's a true story of an Irish Trappist Monk so a Catholic monk who his story of in
his experience was Zen meditation so he was early in his monk life he was
given a book about Zen and he wasn't very interested in it somebody gave it
to him and said you might find this interesting and he thought I don't think so and the person further qualified the
book by saying this is a Spanish translation of a German trans of an
English translation of the German original and it's a bad translation
so he really wasn't very excited about reading this book but he did agree to read it and he did and he got two things
from this book one was he got instructions in for how to sit on a
cushion and you know which he had never done right and he decided to try it because
he was often falling asleep in the when he was sitting in the Pew in the church or wherever he was sitting in the church
he was often falling asleep so he got got a pile of blankets he didn't have a meditation cushion so he got a big pile
of blankets and he sat on it and he figured if I'm sitting in a position like this with my legs crossed I'm not going to fall asleep as easily
and then the second thing he got out of the book was it had a koan in it he
didn't know the word koan he didn't really know what that meant but it had this question and the question was what
was your face before you were born which is a classic koan from the Zen tradition
and so he had no idea what a koan was or how to work with it he didn't have any
instructions for sitting meditation he didn't have a teacher but for some reason in his heart he was drawn to
engaging with this practice and so he just did his best to follow the instructions
so his fellow Catholic monastics were teasing him gently about whether he was really Catholic or was he Buddhist they
also asked him to sit somewhere else because it was a distracting for them when he sat on his pile of blankets in
the church so he found a little room to sit by himself and he contemplated this
koan about his face before he was born and
after a long time of doing that making adjustments along the way that felt
intuitively right you know he really did his best and he tried he did make some
changes but eventually he decided that he hadn't seen anything and there was really nothing coming from this practice
and so he was a little bit sorry that he hadn't ever really found a teacher to learn more about it
and he decided to give up so he stood up and in his words
that's when I saw my face before I was born
later he met some Zen teachers and he actually eventually became a roshi an authorized
and teacher in addition to still remaining a Trappist Monk and he said that all of this drew that Drew him much
closer to the deepest teachings of Jesus he really understood how those Point toward emptiness that was his
understanding so this too I would say is practice in
accordance with the Dharma um really bringing himself to it really
living the sincerity of his engagement with this and maybe maybe you'll agree with me
that there's some beauty to this Monk's path and how he just kept engaging
so how about us so engaging when we engage with Dharma practice which all of us are in some way even if this is the
very first time you came here or the very first time you're tuning in on YouTube
you're here so in some way you're engaging with the Dharma right now
and so we we often will find that we'll run into unfamiliar terms like
practicing in accordance with the Dharma as I said this has caught my attention over the years I didn't know at all what
it meant when I first read it the very first time and I found it to be fruitful to engage over over the years and
consider in my own practice you know what is this how does it unfold what does it mean for me now
how do we explore and familiarize ourselves with terms like this
if it feels important or relevant or interesting I encourage you to engage with terms even if they seem like
they're like you're not sure what they mean so one you know we've been doing a
little bit of that during this talk I've been kind of exploring different dimensions
trying to create a larger picture you're welcome to take the ones that make sense to you and leave the ones that don't
so we can also step back a little bit and kind of consider that process itself you know what is it that we're doing
so we might engage with a Dharma term by posing a question that monk had a koan as a question some
Buddhist Traditions have made this into an art form we don't do that so explicitly but even less formally
questions are a very good way to engage with the Dharma so we can pose the
question what does it mean to practice in accordance with the Dharma
but the question might be then to whom or to what are we posing that question are we posing it to our intellect
our linguistic mind I decided to pose this question to uh
chat GPT so I thought it was interesting I
thought I would read you the answer so I typed in what does practice in
accordance with the dhamma mean I think I'll read it in the voice that
kind of goes with it the term dhamma typically refers to the
teachings of the Buddha which emphasized the development of ethical Behavior mindfulness and wisdom therefore
practice in accordance with Adama means to practice in accordance with the ethical principles mindfulness and
wisdom taught by the Buddha in Practical terms this means striving to cultivate
wholesome thoughts speech and actions while avoiding unwholesome ones it also
means developing mindfulness or a clear and non-judgmental awareness of one's thoughts feelings and surroundings
lastly it means cultivating wisdom or an understanding of the nature of reality
and the causes of suffering as taught in the Buddhist tradition overall
practicing in accordance with the dhamma means making a conscious effort to live
in a way that aligns with the teachings of the Buddha with the goal of reducing suffering and cultivating inner peace
and happiness q-e-d
so in terms of basic information content I have to admit that this might be a lot of what I've said during this talk I
don't know do you guys need Dharma teachers anymore um I would probably change a little bit of
the language I saw a few holes in in the doctrine there but you know it's good
information actually it's pretty good information but do you think it gets you all the way
there no what about that Trappist Monk who
didn't have any of this information he had no books he had no teacher
he had no chat GPT but he did sit on a pile of blankets and sincerely
apply his mind until his heart opened
so in exploring a Dharma term we are not just posing a question to our language
oriented mind you know the answer to our question is not a bunch of information it's not
about the language we're posing the question to our cheetah to our heart mind or even more broadly
to our whole body heart mind system that means that we can use the whole
body hard mind system to resonate with that question
a friend of mine I think said it nicely she said accordance is multi-dimensional
mind heart and body are all used to connect to wisdom and knowing In This
Moment knowing right now such that practice is in accord
another of the qualities of the Dharma is that it is inviting us to come and
see in particular note that the body is
involved you know we can we can consider the Dharma or drop in a
question and then feel the energetic ripples in our body that's it no need to cognize what's going on create a story
figure it out so to do this kind of full engagement
with the Dharma term or question is kind of kind of like living it
to live the question I'm borrowing that phrase there's another phrase that we could ask you know what is live the
question it's from uh actually comes from the Western tradition it's from a
work called letters to a young Poet by Reiner Maria rilka this is a fairly oft
quoted segment have patience with everything that
remains unsolved in your heart try to love the questions themselves like locked rooms and like books written
in a foreign language do not now look for the answers they
cannot now be given to you because you could not live them it is a it is a question of experiencing
everything at present you need to live the question and perhaps you will gradually without
even noticing it find yourself experiencing the answer
so to live the question of what it means to practice in accordance with the Dharma
is to take that question into daily life into relationship into work into
community life into deep into your heart while sitting on the cushion all of those
it takes some trust and confidence to listen carefully to that question
that you've posed with your whole mind body heart and then actually go into it
to actually go with it to actually change things in your life in order to
live by that question this is your life
it matters it matters what you do
so maybe you have some sense now of what it means to say that somebody
who is practicing in accordance with the Dharma beautifies the Sangha
the Buddha loved to see people engaging with the teachings and really seeing how
they play out in their own life and he created an environment where
people could do that they could give themselves fully to the
teachings so I've been here with the IMC Community
for a long time and I can say that it's quite a good place for practicing in accordance with
the Dharma it's a place where people can try out different ways of being
where they can feel some Harmony and yet
enough security to be daring with how they
are and their support all along the path for engaging with our ethics our
mental training our wisdom all of that is here and I think we see that beauty among us
today and we can even extend it out into the folks on YouTube who are joining us
can see how far across the world the beauty is spreading
so thank you all for your beauty and your engagement with the Dharma
it'd be yeah so I'm there's a few more minutes we can
if anybody would like to ask questions or comments
yes here why don't you wait for the microphone thank you
this is I was just wondering what that song is
the Sangha what is it wow there's a whole other explanation that we could do yeah I did use that term without
defining it thank you probably other people want to know too so Sangha is the
poly word for the community generally it refers to the community in
the west we use it as the community of practitioners so like this is the IMC Sangha and the IMC Community more
traditionally it refers either to the monastic Sangha of people who were ordained or actually the most generally
it refers to people who have some understanding of the Buddhist teachings
so people who have reached some deep insight into it and can serve as guides
for others um and maybe one more Dimension I'll mention is that the Sangha is one of the
refuges for us so Buddha Dharma and Sangha are the places where we can
Orient toward in order to support our practice as we're going along the path but does that help yeah
thank you for asking the question
here's another one
do you could you share the name of the Trappist monk did he write anything
oh it's a good question I didn't have um I didn't write his name down I found a
video where he spoke about this in a Buddhist Christian Conference like a
um and I didn't catch his name so I'm sorry for that but it was a recent video
and he was right there speaking it so I'm sure he is alive well I'm not sure but as of when he made
the video
anything else one more yeah
you talked about the twin nuns and how they were both aversive and then one was
no longer as aversive or actually followed the Dharma how do you handle or
approach friendships and relationships in your life with people who are aversive
or become more aversive over time how do you work with that that's a good question so is it is such a person a
practitioner or not most likely not most likely not yeah we
can't always know for sure huh so then um what we're working with is how it
feels for us in relationship with that person and it can be
that we need to be in relationship with this person we don't have a choice is that the case I have the feeling you're
referring to a specific example but we don't need more details but is that true okay yeah yeah so then we do still have
some choice right we have our own sense of what's coming up in Us in response to
observing or experiencing that aversion of course if there's any danger you know
the aversion is directed toward you in a harmful way then you know there would
need to be some caretaking for yourself I just want to state that right up front but if it's a
little bit more of an observational thing um then there are things that we can
cultivate to protect ourselves essentially so certainly mindfulness you know being aware okay I'm observing that
we are allowed to observe things externally externally internally and both
but in yourself probably the first cultivation is equanimity accepting
the reality okay this is what's going on for that person I don't know
what's happening inside of them but accepting it and then there can be also
some Connection in that people who are behaving aversively and not apparently
aware of it are probably suffering so an appropriate response for you might
also be compassion for them and for you for the experience
that you're having so there are ways that we can begin to change ourselves in relationship to this energy
such that it is less harmful it's not coming into us and getting stuck you may
need techniques also to allow energy to move through or you may need to you know
physically moved to a different place when things are happening you know you can leave the
room or or even giving a wide range set a boundary things like that
but generally we have more options than we think we do is this helping
yes thank you okay yeah and of course if you need to if you
want to speak sometime with a teacher about more specifics of that there might be also things that I could say more
specifically than in a general setting yeah
oh looks like we're at the time so thank you everyone it's been a delight
foreign