so good morning good day everyone I was appreciating so much the chats
that um I was almost forgetting to start speaking
so thank you all for being here and I appreciate very much that
we have this Wide International Community that comes together to practice to meditate to engage in
these teachings and I feel very fortunate to be able to offer these teachings
still to such a receptive audience
so thank you so there is a
kind of current of teaching in Buddhism that uh one of the meetings
of karma when we do something that has a karmic consequences
is that it leaves traces and that when we are doing something
without any karmic residue there's no traces that this possible to do things that
somehow leave no traces leave no residue
therefore leaving us fresh leaving us kind of new or able to meet the next
moment without bringing with us the baggage and the
influence of the past so when we sit to meditate
we can start recognizing that there are traces left so for example if the mind wanders often
thought and then you bring your mind back but you're not really successful able to do
that the the pull of the thinking is strong that pull is the traces of momentum that
was set in place that somehow there was a force operating in the
in the way we're thinking the way we're maybe attached that
remains even once we've kind of let go of the thoughts or we let go of them for a moment but
very quickly were pulled back into that world and that the force that keeps pulling us
into it into our preoccupations our thoughts the past the future
our fantasies the force of that is um part of this residue that's left
over from a momentum that's set in place of what we've been doing in the past and
what we've been thinking in the past and what we've been feeding so if we're feeding in the past just
living our daily life where unrestrained
in our preoccupations you know only thinking about what we want they're only thinking about how we've been wronged
then um there's uh there's sometimes because of the involvement the identification
the attachment the resistance the strength of that involvement with that
preoccupation it leaves a residue and that residue
has a function of like ready to reappear in some way or
other becomes a habit almost so one of the functions of meditation
is to try to be in the present moment the best we can be with the breath is to notice how much residue there is
the traces that are left over where we're you know automatically pulled away or preoccupied and caught
and things some of that residue we feel and the tension in our body
all tension is a residue of our some way in which we've been preoccupied
and that's a marvelous thing to have that the body relax enough that the residue
at least a surface residue begins to dissipate certain emotions are left over they're
they're not just you know fresh and new but there's residue that sometimes
reappears sometimes years later the residue the traces has been left behind unresolved and then there comes
there comes a residue there's the traces again there's no need to feel bad about it or
feel bad about yourself that there are traces of karmic traces like this but it is invaluable to see it
to know that's what's happening and it can be a lot easier if we just see it that way oh that's what's
happening these are traces these are this is the residue this is the residue still
having momentum it's maybe it's easily easier to disidentify with it not be so tricked by
it to think that it's so important to do it might be easier just to recognize it in a simple way oh residue traces
and then dig it again and that Clarity of residue traces might
make it easier just then to come back into the present moment so
so assuming a meditation posture
and I put a lot of value on a on the posture we assume in meditation
and intentional posture that establishes us here in a clear
definitive way here in this place and this time partly because on one hand it's easier
to then release the residue and
and also because it's easier to see it if we have a posture that's
karmically neutral where
the habits of attitudes dispositions don't
dictate the posture we have
and and so this you know upright posture that of the Buddha statue
represents a posture free
of Karma free of the momentum of the past dispositions and attitudes
taking it long steep inhale
releasing a long exhale
breathing in breathing out
letting their breathing return to normal
and the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out from the body
maybe it can be like a waves washing up and down against the shore
if there's been a disturbance on the beach
the waves just come and they go and they smooth out the sand bringing it back to
the way it's been maybe for millennium flat
or we have a coarse piece of wood and we gently repeat over and over again
the sanding of it back and forth slowly something gets smoother
so that gentle staying with the rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out we might feel the karmic traces in our body and mind
but staying with the Rhythm like a waves washing across everything
slowly letting the karmic traces and tensions
be smooth out
without being tricked into thinking
reacting to anything
staying with the rhythm of breathing
waves smoothing out the beach
what residue or traces are found in you now
and instead of being involved in them or thinking about them
let breathing be the massage or the waves
that softens the strength of the residue
and then coming to the end of the sitting taking a few long deep breaths
relaxing as you exhale maybe relaxing some of the residue of
tension traces
and considering for a few moments how there can be love
or care or kindness without any residue
without leaving any traces behind in our hearts or Minds
simple straightforward clean love
and to gaze upon the world
with such a care
wishing well for everyone without any attachment
any fear any hesitation
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be free
[Music]
thank you
foreign
so continuing the topic of how mindfulness
of the body can support us in challenges the third exercise the Buddha gives in
his famous teachings on mindfulness third teachings about the body
is to be mindful to be aware to know
the activities we're doing with the body as we're doing them
so as we're moving certainly as we're walking as
we're talking as we are putting on our clothes as we're going to the bathroom as we're
showering or bathing each of these everyday activities is a meditation center in itself is a
monastery in itself is a sacred Dimension sacred place
for practice of mindfulness and to see it as a you know as a as a
meditation center as a sacred location as is to put a lot of value on the
presence the attention the care that we give in being in being with each
everyday activity that we do eating the Buddha mentions drinking
stretching out your hand to grab something to open a door turn your doorknob
to close the door to put on your shoes to be cooking in the kitchen or cleaning
there's you know innumerable ones of these everyday daily activities and the third exercise in developing
mindfulness is to bring mindfulness attention into these activities as we do
them and this has a lot of benefits in kind of the ordinary
way of thinking about mindfulness it's a way of being mindful in the present
moment and it's a way of building up the muscle of mindfulness muscle of attention to the present so that we can
begin abiding living in the present more and more and thereby receiving the benefits
from doing so and but also doing this reveals
what's going on otherwise that if we stop and pay attention
to that stop but if we do our activities while we're attending to them and really present for them
there's you might notice how the mind has other ideas it's drifting off and
thinking about tomorrow or yesterday or a fantasy of some kind and the emotional lives can follow the
thoughts or the emotions can be very much about something that's not present here and now and are being
reinforced by the thoughts the stories about this other time or their place
and so there are traces this residue left over from other things where
there's preoccupation concerns attachments resistances fears that are operating that have a kind of sometimes
a life of their own momentum of Their Own and it isn't necessarily wrong to have
that but it's really helpful to see it and when we're present
for our daily activities standing over the stove you know stirring a pot of
soup to really be there for that stirring we notice well I'm not really there
I'm still thinking about the traffic ticket I got and how it's unfair and this and that and and so there's so
something happened to us early in the day that's sticky and we're kind of stuck with it or glued to it or
preoccupied with it and so seeing that as we are stirring the soup we say oh
look at that now I can see the power this has over me if we just go about our life it just
unconsciously let us know the Mind think about its preoccupations and thoughts it might seem like business as usual and we
might not even notice that it's uh how much the mind is caught how much the mind is preoccupied and the influence
that preoccupation has in our body our emotions our hearts but if you're stirring the soup and you
see that you're thinking about the traffic ticket then um wow that's really strong
oh is this really the right thing to be thinking about or do I need to attend to
this in some way do I need to settle something deeper maybe I should turn the stove off and go sit down for five
minutes and just really let the the leftover um
the agitation of the traffic ticket to wash through me and kind of drain out by
just sitting breathing with it that's what's needed otherwise the residue of that tension agitation is going to be
driving my thoughts so the simple way of maybe saying this is that as we bring our attention to the
present moment and try to be with what's happening as we're doing it we start noticing how
much we're not there and that reveals something really important about ourselves important information
and then what you do next is up to you but at least you know something that you didn't know before
in terms of uh some of the challenges we have in our life the some challenges we get stuck in the
stronger the challenge sometimes there's a stuckness and some people freeze go numb some people
hunker down and some people collapse and some people do the opposite and get agitated and are really
spinning out to go about our daily activities the simple brushing our teeth
washing our face to really be there in a simple relaxed
way is uh the middle way between collapsing or being numb or frozen or
being agitated it's using the movements the activities of the body to channel
the energy to give space for the energy to get movement to get fluidity to lubricate our system without it being
too much or too little um going about the daily activities as a
way of loosening up as a way of settling as a way of grounding as a way of not being
glued to our challenges we have our concerns for them is very freeing very helpful it
lubricates it massages it kind of can be grounding so that we can be more wise about how we
consider our challenges how we address them but if the and so the more engaged we
are with our more caught up we are in the challenges the more it really has grabbed us sometimes the more useful it is to do
something some activity that kind of
frees us a little bit loosens up us a little bit or settles us a little bit sometimes like it could be going for a
walk and uh and and the walk is what allows the energy of the emotional energy of
the challenge to start becoming a little more fluid and not so stuck or if we're collapsing into it or going
numb it can kind of wake us up a little bit if we go the opposite direction and get too agitated the walk can actually
be settling the walking around these daily activities I like to think of them
as the middle way that brings things into balance so you might try that that next time you
have some kind of real challenge that's hard for you to be with maybe not the most challenging but
something that you know moderately challenging that's difficult don't just sit and do nothing don't just
fret but and don't don't go kind of numb and do things on automatic pilot uh enter
into the activity of what you're doing in the moment with mindfulness and presence
maybe even an embodied presence so you're really there almost like imagine that you're
a dancer or an actor who is embodying the part of the whole being
stirring the soup brushing the teeth and and see if that creates a little bit
more space and lubrication for the challenges we have more more
balanced by the time we finish that maybe we're a little bit more centered a little bit more able to think more
clearly it's not that easy they're just brushing your teeth is called all it's going to
take but we have lots of different everyday activities through daily life
and to be mindful really mindful of them we have lots of little opportunities to
reset to ground and to discover what is really going on what are their residue
what's left over what's the strength of that residue what's the strength of the our kind of the way we're glued
or to the preoccupation the challenge we have and to not necessarily the
challenge doesn't go away but one of the things practice can do is it can maybe dissolve the glue that keeps us glued to
it or the stickiness that can be washed away so that
unstuck we can you know address the challenge or be with it or figure out what's best to
do so we have many opportunities throughout the day daily life practice into the to
be mindful of the activities of the daily life and maybe it's useful to think of it as
the ordinary regular repeated activities that you do
as as your Meditation Center your Monastery your sacred grove sacred spot not the
place but the activity is where it is so significant
and if you take you know a dozen two dozen of the regular activities you do through the day
and really make it a place to lubricate to massage to ground to be present to
discover more clearly how there's so much residue so much ways
in which they're spinning out um I think it could be invaluable
for helping us work with a challenge which have happened every day of life to not do that for some of us that might
mean that we're actually feeding the preoccupation repeating the cutness the
the emotional reactivity to the challenge if we you know that's so easy to give
into it or live in that all the time but to have some kind of way to cut through the reactivity cut through the
the stuckness that we have around challenges is invaluable
in our ability to address them more wisely and if you have no challenges
then it's a delight to give ourselves over fully to the physical activity of
these daily activities that we do to really enter into it and embodied
absorbed way just this just washing the dishes just stirring the soup just
brushing the teeth and and maybe that just is a source of rejuvenation
May the activities of your daily life become a sacred dimension of your life
thank you