Hello friends hello and good morning from Mountain View California and seated
olani land wherever you are in the world lovely to join you in this moment in
time for our practice today so we have been exploring together the five
Aggregates the five heaps these constituents of experience the
five condos and today being Friday we're going to
explore the fifth one consciousness vinyana Consciousness which is the most
subtle one and yet fear not we're going to practice with it and and turn towards
awareness awareness Consciousness and sometimes we can use these words interchangeably so
sometimes we make distinctions but today I'll use an interchangeably with with an
asterisk so uh yeah I'll say more later about
this so let's let's uh let's practice together let's begin let's
let's land let's land in our
ah I see there's a problem with Wi-Fi is this the case oh there is a problem with
my Wi-Fi hold on I'm going to fix that
let's try it again okay
all right I hope that got okay let's try this again video is freezing yes I see
that I hope the audio came through though um okay let me know if there is a
problem again
and let me know in chat and I will
um switch all together let's see it's working now tell you what I'm going
to better now good there okay thank you for your feedback everyone in real time
I will um and try something here the joys of
Technology okay much better now okay if it's fine okay I'm glad sound has been
good okay if it's final continue otherwise I'm going to switch from Wi-Fi
to the left to um Ethernet cable so I'll wait for a second
all is good here is Frozen okay all right I'm going to see if I can the
sound is fine but the video is slow okay I'm going to switch to ethernet here we
go I hope I don't lose the whole thing here we go okay all right
switching to ethernet
buy Now find now fine
good here okay seems like
very good okay all right
still streaming okay I've switched to ethernet now I'm crossing fingers that
see the part of practicing with conditions
as they are great okay hopefully it's all okay now all right we're on either
it so okay looks good all right so let's um
yeah Gotta Love Tech yeah me too exactly all right I think this is as good as
it's gonna get because I'm on ethernet so let's um yeah I see I also have an iPad setup it
seems like the Frozen this has gone away I do have quality assurance q a in real
time all right good okay so okay so let's let's practice together everyone let's
meditate together so okay
um letting the flurry of activity
letting it go it's okay releasing with delight
it's like this to be human it's like this to be human we plan for
things and they happen in a different way sometimes
causes and conditions they arise due to causes and conditions
not necessarily our intentions are our control so letting it go
and arriving in the body arriving the sensations of the body
feeling the sensations of our feet connected to the Earth
feeling our sit bones the cushion or the chair
feeling our hands letting there be a sense of ease
relaxation
the Mind relaxing into the body and the body relaxing into the chair of the
cushion
can the body be relaxed and soft
receiving each and breath each out breath
nowhere to go nothing to do and to just be with this
the gift that has been given to us this opportunity
not taking it for granted not wasting but being fully present in this moment
with this the sensations the stream of experience just as it
presents itself a training training our minds and hearts
letting pain breath and out breath be calming soothing collecting the light
electing
allowing the body to be relaxed and for the mind to know
the objects that come through the sphere of knowing
it's turned towards of all these objects what I mean is whatever you are knowing In This Moment
know it very clearly and very clearly is it the breath the
sensations of the breath Sensations in the body
sounds
like Pleasant unpleasant to neither whatever it is being known now it clears
it
there be more clarity more enjoyment in your saying in your
clear saying as they fear your mind
just turned on the lights or put on its glasses there is this sharpness this
Clarity of seeing not effortful
but bright relaxed and bright
relaxed and bright
clearly clearly rocking seeing knowing
sensations of the breath for example
what are the sensations where do you feel them where in your abdom tongue the
signs in your back
and now knowing
that you are knowing sensations of the breath
know that you know we're shifting
turning The Stance of our knowing just a little bit from the object of knowing to
knowing itself knowing that you are knowing
the fact that you're knowing
knowing that you know
that you are sensing
the sensations of the breath
and now turning the knowing
further to the knowing itself to awareness itself
that awareness of awareness feel expensive
objects are being known
and this faculty of knowing cognizing
is operating is operating Non-Stop
cognizing the flow of experience
either were you directed maybe with the breath Sensations
or through the different doors of perception recognition sounds Sensations
thoughts smells Etc as they arise
organizing knowing is happening turning awareness towards awareness
organizing is happening continuously [Music]
in a relaxing this investigation
letting the body the Mind relax sense of awareness expensive
knowing the stream of experience and notice the changing
nature you know this flow of experience
breath keeps shifting and changing sensations of it
maybe feeling tone Pleasant unpleasant neither keep flashing through
keep popping up shifting changing
volitional formations mental formations thoughts coming
perceptions recognitions it keeps changing
the heart the mind has ease in the midst of the Sea of change to see the sea of
change relax with the Sea of change
arrival a departure every moment
and as we turn close this meditation period
who said together let us
appreciate no appreciation in our heart
and mind for this beautiful gift
cultivate our hearts and Minds together
trusting there is co-created goodness
letting go of any judgments if there are any
leaning into the goodness and sharing his goodness together
sharing it generously with all beings everywhere our good
wealth our good wealth we don't do this practice this will work
just for our own sake we do this we cultivate our hearts for
everyone's sake may all beings everywhere in ways they
can understand Our Father benefit
from the fruits of my cultivation may all beings be happy may all beings
be free including myself
thank you for your practice everyone I'll take a moment to switch over the
recordings
saying hello hello hello everyone hello again
delighted to Be With You In This Moment In Time
so as we've been exploring the five
Aggregates and today we have come to the last one vignana or consciousness
so God meditation for
um I I invited us first as a way and this is one way that we can practice
with tuning into this aspect of the five aggregates
first we tuned we turned towards the body the sensations of the body Rupa the
first aggregate and of course I invited you if you wanted to open up to some other
Aggregates if the mind is stable enough it is possible to also open up to the same time this flow of experience not
just sensations of the body but but also weight in a feeling tone evolutional
formations thoughts maybe even perceptions how things are being perceived and known
foreign video again oh my what is going on I
think that's my internet um yeah I'm on ethernet so there is
nothing more I can do as long as the audio is okay if the audio goes let me
know but uh the video there's not nothing more I can do about it dear once
yeah it's probably my provider um
bummer hmm so I will continue hoping that it will
adjust it so let's see if there's anything else I can do here hold on uh
uh let's see I'm going to um audio is okay my voice is clear okay
let's let's hope and trust that that is fine
um everything else I can do hold on I'm
gonna take a moment and see if there's anything else that
could be done here there
okay let's try that
see if that's better okay
all right it's still a little choppy but maybe better okay all right okay we're
just going to go with this now exactly more opportunities for practice
as Cynthia yeah okay all right
so where were we yes yes I was recounting what um one way that we can
practice with perhaps tuning more into awareness renyana Consciousness as we
start we can start by looking at an object that we're aware of so the mind
can become stable knowing an object that we are aware of in this case I invited
you today to to tune into um the breath the other uh uh and maybe
sounds and then and then after the mind is stable and really become turning on
the light remember this analogy that um the analogy of turning on the light
you know this grocking really brightening this really really brightening this sense of knowing
knowing an object connecting with an object connecting with the sensations of the breath really brightened
so so and then so if this is knowing if my right hand is knowing
my light making the outfit brighter making
the object brighter so that or the knowing of the object and kind of happening together no no getting this
brighter and then we turn towards oh knowing that we know knowing that we
know we kind of turn awareness onto itself knowing that we know and then for
some it's it's uh if the mind is stable enough then you can rest in the sense of
awareness and then knowing that this stream of experience is being known and
then in the guided meditation we turn towards seeing impermanence impermanence of all these Aggregates arising and
passing again this is [Music] um five Aggregates are so rich so many
aspects and and this week primarily um we have spent time to tune to tune
into them um and of course and um they so so we have tried to kind of
tune into them to recognize them as these constituents of experience and to
say that that's usually the first step we want to tune into them and then we want to see that they are impermanent
that's really what's um so important about oh I just got a
note that my uh internet connection is unstable so it is my internet oh boy
yeah I see the videos topping I hope the audio is okay dear
once anyway I'll just continue to teach trusting that at least this will be
recorded and it will be available in Audio Dharma this part so here we go
um so it's it's also a very important part of this teaching after we have
tuned to these constituents of our experience to see their arising and passing to see
uh their impermanence and also to see how they dependently
arise how they're dependently arising how for example a perhaps evolutional
formation a thought arises from a perception from a particular perception which has given rise to say a pleasant
or unpleasant feeling tone and that brings a whole bunch of thoughts and
volitional formations so so so the um so seeing the dependent arising in our
experience these are all conditioned it's all conditioned none of this is fixed uh and and and to see the empty
nature of a phenomena and an empty now this word sunyata emptiness
um I I preferred relational as a better translation of emptiness empty seems
kind of hollow and kind of dangerous and scary but sunyatta we get to see everything is relative everything is
relative is relational everything arises related to everything else so we see the
relationality and the relativity the relativity in in the sphere of our
experience in in in the way we experience the whole world through the five Aggregates this is such an
important teaching a couple of other things I want to say um one is that these five Aggregates
um are not things unto themselves they are processes they are processes that so
it's for example it's not just a vignan not as as a cognition or as
Consciousness but it's cognizing it's cognizing or it's perceiving it's this
process of perceiving that keeps happening that keeps um uh it's it's it's a flow of
experience it's it's a flow so so appreciating um tuning into that sense of flow
um a couple of other things one is that
um regarding this Consciousness or or cognizing and knowing
it tends to show up in different and different uh what's called in Buddhism
the The Sixth Sense stores the uh seeing
and and hearing and tasting and touching and and all the other aspects and
cognizing the the sixth uh door the sixth door uh being the Mind door so so
vignana or cognizing can show up in all of these and it's it's uh it uh it's
there's a one Consciousness there's one Consciousness keeps moving shifting to
to these different aspects of of of perceiving our world
and and it is it in again as we practice as as I invited you to tune into
um both first object and then this this knowing this cognizing itself
um it can be quite interesting not that not to be so fixed on a particular object for example not to be fixed on
our thoughts but to the sense of openness of oh yes knowing just knowing
is happening knowing is happening it can bring a sense of uh freedom
and uh and especially um yes the one last thing I want to say
before give you I want to give a couple of references too um uh last thing I want to say is that
these five Aggregates again they're not separate they all happen together they're dependently Arisen so for
example cognizing and mental formations and and perception and feeling tone they
all happen together it feels like a cluster they're just yet you can see
them so they arise and and they're in a process of flow together but you can't tune to them to see them differently and
to see their impermanence and and their impersonal nature uh so a couple of
references I wanted to share with you one reference is um is for those of you who are
psychologists there is an interesting paper the five aggregate model of the
Mind so you might uh you might oops I hope this comes through here we go so
it's it's uh five let's see if I can type this in real time they're five
aggregate yeah model
okay so here is the paper for you um it's an interesting paper that talks
about yeah the five accurate model of the mind and relating it to psychology and and
um might be of benefit to the non-psychologists as well and another
reference I also want to share and provide is to uh majima nikaya 28 to the
um uh in in the in um the this
Buddha talks about um it's a beautiful Satan the Buddha talks about the five Aggregates and
and um the you know how practicing with it really seeing the the conditionality
um of all of them arising in the impermanence leads to Freedom oh yes one last thing one last important thing I
wanted to say ah one last thing I just remembered um so so I want to be sent the question
to me about the clinging aggregate so I wanted to to say that so the clean so
clinging Aggregates so so these five Aggregates are often also referred to as
clinging Aggregates and it's um so so it's because we cling to them
we cling to them we we take them to be me and mine um so all these five Aggregates they can
they are they can be clinging Aggregates but we don't have to cling to them so
when there is freedom when for the for the awakened mind and in the moments of
of Awakening and freedom there is no clinging to them there is no clinging to these Aggregates so so you might have
heard the clinging Aggregates that's what it is that can all be clinged we can be clinging to them or not clinging
to them so clinging Aggregates or non-clinging Aggregates okay uh how do you spell that and majima nikaya it's
the middle length of discourses of the Buddha it's the it's that that book in
the corner that brown one it's the middle link discourses of the Buddha um so if you if you do a Google search for
mn28 it'll you know pull it up it's also it's a greater discourse on the simile
of the elephant's footprint so okay so it's been rich and there's so
much more I hope um your your interests in the five Aggregates and and practicing with them
has been kindled or rekindled this week and it's been such a delight be able to share and explore this with
you um for those of you who are local tomorrow Saturday I'm teaching a day
long at IMC a med time day long loving kindness day long
um come drop by say hello if you can even if you can just come for part of the day that's perfectly fine no
registration needed just come to IMC would be lovely to meet you in person dear online Sangha so thank you so much
for joining me and the community this this week and exploring exploring the
five Aggregates May the fruit of our practice together be of benefit to all
beings everywhere thank you so much be well take care