hello welcome welcome to
our meditation together as a community and hopefully uh you appreciate that
there are so many people meditating at the same time and with the same
orientation is here towards IMC and teachings and
meditation and so welcome
so as an analogy if there are two people standing on a
Hilltop and one person is standing quite skillfully on one foot maybe even
they have strong that one foot is quite strong and the first game is then under
Tippy Toe and to stand for a long time and the other person has both feet
firmly rooted in the ground and uh and a strong stance like spread
apart a little bit and then if a strong wind comes on the hill strong gusts
they'll both experience the wind the intensity of the wind the wind itself in
the same way they're just as sensitive to it just susceptible to it
but the ones standing on their tippy toes one Tippy Toe is not going to have the stability
to be able to withstand upright in the wind will be pushed over
the one who has both feet kind of wide stance strong stance rooted rooted
stance maybe even their knees bent maybe even leaning against the wind will experience the wind just as much as
the person standing on one foot but the person rooted on the hillside
won't be pushed over so in the same way we can be sensitive
to all kinds of things and we can be sensitive in such a way
that our own experience our emotions our thoughts our feelings the world around
us what's happening with other people two people can be experience it to be
sensitive equally sensitive to what's coming their way but one of them is doing the equivalent
of standing on their one foot or standing on their tippy toes and the other one is doing an equivalent
of being rooted firm because the ballast has a grounding
is kind of very very stable on their feet on their metaphoric
feet and both of them will experience life
events the same way the same way the sensitivity to it but the impact it'll have very different
one people will feel like the life events the inner life is just too much is overwhelming
and they might blame the event the other person will find it maybe Intense or challenging in some ways but
they're able to keep their balance and they're able to stay stable and so
they're not thrown off balance by it and uh and they feel content and
confident that they can have a stance that supports them and is less inclined
to say the events are overwhelming because they have the stability to
handle it so awareness can be on Tippy Toes or awareness can be
well grounded rooted stable and and depend someone can be equally
sensitive equally kind of a sense of awareness to what's happening but have
this very different stance very different rootedness to the experience
so when we set to meditate we want to kind of tune into this as well
do we feel stable do we feel grounded and that can be partly physical
a posture a stance a way of feeling the way to the body so that we're rooted here
it could also be with the awareness where the awareness doesn't it's not like a
you know cotton ball that just gets pushed around in the wind awareness has a kind of stability a kind of kind of
rootedness a kind of both an openness but but uh you know as
a kind of a presence of being rooted and here yes I'm aware
and this is where and it kind of I kind of this image of the weight of awareness
awareness has no weight but the weight of presence the weight of being present
the awareness is kind of settled into the Torso especially
settled into the belly here a place where things are
unstable is when we're aware but the awareness is rooted in our thoughts and
ideas and our stories and Imagination then we get tossed around
but if awareness is connected identified with the body
can be a lot easier so to assume a
stable posture for meditation
close the eyes and to feel the weight of your body
especially feel where the weight of your body rests on a chair on a cushion on the floor
whatever is supporting that weight
and taking some long slow deep breaths and on the exhale
letting go into that support let the weight of your body be received
by what holds the body the weight of the body
and taking a few more deep breaths gentle not too much but doing so in a way that as you
inhale your belly goes out relax your belly
the diaphragm will as you breathe in is pushed down and that pushes everything in the belly
down and out so to relax the belly and if the belly gets
pushed out there's a broader base at the bottom of your torso
providing support for the upper torso
then letting the breathing return to normal and still allow the belly to expand
expand and relax as you breathe in
the belly doesn't have to do any work to move it's being moved by the diaphragm
it's letting the belly kind of be pushed and then pulled in
and then on the exhale relax in your body scan through your
body see you with poetry but parts of your body can relax
and as you do so relax and let the weight of your body settle a bit
and then letting yourself settle into your breathing
and feeling the breathing the body breathing
in a rooted way and as if
the breathing in the Torso the movements of the body in the Torso
is a ballast is a kind of strength and stability
and to be centered more in your body your torso
then in your thinking mind here
and as you're mindful as you're aware
whatever you're aware of be aware while rooted in the body
be aware so that the body
provides a ballast for your awareness
so awareness doesn't get pulled into our thoughts or feelings
or doesn't get pushed around by them
so awareness can do its work of just knowing and recognizing
from a place of stability
unmoved by The Winds of the world
thank you
can you relax your belly your torso
and let the weight of your body settle a bit
in order to provide more stability
for mindfulness in the present moment
and then as we come to the end of the sitting to take a few moments to
really let yourself be stable here in your body in your heart
your mind is if there is strong ballast
heavy ballast that keeps you rooted grounded
so you're not pushed around by The Waves by the wind
by circumstances in life you just hear in the middle of this
tall firm strong
and from the stability to gaze upon the world kindly
to gaze upon the suffering of the world the people you know
people in your area people far away
to gaze Upon This World suffering from a place of stability
careful to watch if you lose a stability
by being swept up into the mines alarm
the mind's distress the minds
worries in the stability of the body
gaze upon the world kindly compassionately
as if that is a phenomenal gift to give the world
just that
gazing upon the world with compassion the eyes of kindness the eyes of
compassion wishing may all beings
be free of their suffering
may all beings be free of all forms of affliction
may all beings be free of war and oppression
may all beings be free
of hostility from others and to others
may all beings live in peace profound peace
free from all
that troubles the heart may all beings be happy
[Music]
laughs
thank you
so hello and welcome to this second talk on
elements of compassion and by having all the elements of
compassion together then compassion can be effective compassion can be uh
treasure can be nourishing for ourselves and hopefully beneficial for others
and so these five are awareness Attunement
appreciation aspiration and action
so today talk about this Attunement but the Attunement is built on the
capacity for awareness and one of the things I tried to convey
in yesterday's talk about awareness it's not just simply a matter of being aware
but it's also possible to be aware in a way that is stable
rooted aware in a way that awareness is autonomous
independent from what it is aware of so that if you someone says something
you clearly hear it and know it but the awareness is kind of like you oh you
know this is happening but the awareness doesn't get ruffled where an assistant gets pushed around
doesn't get agitated parts of you might get agitated but you know that oh there's agitation
parts of you might be afraid you know there is fear and that the awareness itself is not
afraid awareness doesn't get pulled into anything we don't and part of it if we do that by
managing not to identify with the thing like oh this is me or lean into it or
get glued to whatever thoughts feelings emotions events are happening
awareness is like this Still Point in the middle of the storm or the Still
Point in the middle of everything it's not becoming aloof it's not
becoming indifferent it's not becoming um
uncaring it's the opposite that when awareness can be free
autonomous independent so we know whatever is happening then we're able to
meet everything with wisdom also we can meet it with stability when
awareness is stable and free then when we encounter the world we can
figure out how to attune ourselves in the right way for the circumstance
so the analogy I gave in meditation like to do again that if two people are standing on a
Hilltop one is standing on one foot on their tippy toes and the other is standing
both feet both flats from the ground so his feet spread apart it's very stable kind of a strong stable position
if a strong wind comes along they're both impacted by the way to equally
and however the one in the tippy toes the one foot is going to be blown over
the one who has sustable footings feeds widespread apart can withstand the the
impact of the Wind what can happen in that kind of situation if he uses a metaphor for
Human Experience in life is that both two people can experience
life events equally but the person is doing the equivalent or standing on one foot will say I'm a
really sensitive person I'm so sensitive I pick up everything
and in a sense it's true but both people might be sensitive but what equally
sensitive but one has a strong grounding and rooted and the other doesn't and the
one who doesn't is the one who kind of will attribute the issue to Too Much
sensitivity too much stimulus coming which is definitely sometimes can happen but it's a whole different way of living
if you find that stability of awareness here because then you can
figure out now given if you know that and have that then you can figure out what direction to face Against the Wind
you can figure out how to stand and how to lean and how to attune yourself to
the wind so the wind doesn't blow you over so once we have ability to be balanced
rooted in awareness then that's a fantastic foundation for
what leads up to compassion and the next thing is to be attuned
to the suffering of others and and I like the word attune quite a
bit because there's a when we use the word empathy
many people will interpret it as being feeling what others are feeling
and uh and some people who feel like that's really what you're supposed to do when you have compassion you have to really feel the other person suffering
and some people do that they do feel that other people are suffering but I don't know if that's that's not
Attunement Attunement is to be very sensitive to
the inner feelings of oneself the residence the the tune into the other
person taking in all the information and what's there and because we're rooted in awareness
the Attunement is how do we dial in so we have just the right
Attunement just the right way of being present for someone people don't necessarily need you to
feel their suffering fully what mostly what they need is someone to
be accompanied them to be present and to understand them in fact to feel people suffering so much
that it becomes your own you're not really available to help someone else well
some people might appreciate it because they feel that's not alone but there's other ways of accompanying people then
kind of experiencing the same thing they're experiencing through them through some kind of empathy
and so Attunement and I like it because in the old days when I was growing up we had radios that
you would tune into a radio station and you had to turn the knob you know just
and um and to get just the right wavelength and if you had just a little
bit uh either side of of the wavelength that the radio station was coming in you
get a lot of static so the same thing as we attune ourselves to other people we're finding that place
where there's not a lot of static there's not a lot of leaning in or pulling away a lot of spitting out and
thoughts a lot of reactivity but finding the place to be and this is why the stable awareness is so important because
it's with that awareness that we can kind of find like how do I really
understand this other person how do I really sense them or be with them in an
effective way that's useful for them and for me so Attunement is not just simply
experiencing people's emotions Attunement is the question how do I be present for this person's emotions this
person's life this person's suffering in a way that's supportive for them and supportive for me
so there's a kind of uh choice there's a kind of agency there in how we experience the suffering of
others if we don't feel like we have an agency we're supposed to just experience the suffering of others or we just that's
what we kind of do automatically then then we're not finding that place
of agency of choice and this is why the stable awareness
gives a possibility to start finding what could how can we be here in a wise way
and start feeling confident in this Attunement process this having the
question what's the wise way of being here what should I be aware of here with this person and we get a lot of
information from other people who are suffering and it's clear that some people want you to sit next to them some
of them wants to have a listener who listens to them as they talk some people just want someone to bring them a cup of
tea some people want to be left alone and there's you know so you want to be
attuned what's the need here what's and then as you feel that need or feel what's maybe appropriate
to like okay now how how do I communicate with this person how do I
share my presence with them do I Sit Close do I sit far away do I
um do I just uh do I do I really listen do I ask simple questions
um and if you're not doing that you don't have that kind of closeness with the suffering of the world and say it's
through the news or something you've heard about far away um there's very little direct maybe
information to be attuned with but still that a question can still be there how
given what I know how to obey how do I be attuned how do I be present and
attentive so it'd be helpful in this situation help over them and helpful to
myself and if we get overwhelmed or anxious or upset or we allow it kind of to to feel
it in such a way they were on our tippy toes standing on one foot then it can be overwhelming and
confusing and and upsetting distressing
but to be attuned also means attuned to oneself and the question for oneself is how do I
be present for this person that I know who's going through some really hard time who's not sitting in front of me is
maybe in someplace else how do I be attuned and a big part of it
when you're alone away from the person might be how do you attune yourself
so you can be present and aware with that place of stability balance strength
find the awareness that's calm and available
steady and
able to make choices able to if the time comes to be attuned and ask
the question what is useful here how do I help this person what what does this
person need what kind of attention presence does this person need and so there is an acute or strong sense
of kind of knowing recognizing maybe even feeling in some resonance way what the
other person's feeling but it's not feeling their suffering
if we're suffering because someone else is suffering it's probably not empathy
it's probably that's our own suffering and that needs our compassion
to find our ability to be present for that in a stable way and ask the same questions for ourselves
how do I effectively attune myself to the suffering that I'm having
so I don't sink in it so I'm not pushed around by it so I'm not standing on one foot with it
how do I find the stability how do I find the how do I answer the
question what's a useful way for me to be with a suffering
because as soon as you ask that kind of question the question of how to be attuned how to be usefully present
you're beginning to separate yourself from being glued to
the suffering being kind of immersed in it it's a it's a expression or a growth of
our kind of autonomy or Independence or freedom
to ask how do I attune and if we ask how do I attune to my
suffering and someone else it's deeply respectful it's a way of caring very deeply
because without respect for oneself without respect for others I don't know
if it's going to be compassion and so that'll be the topic for tomorrow
appreciation so awareness Attunement and with the Attunement having appreciation
and respect for the person we're with or for themselves and uh and that's a really critical uh
element for it to be for a compassion to be healthy clean and nourishing
for everyone so thank you
um and um if you want to do some
exercise today based on what I'm said experiment through the day about uh your
best understanding what I mean by Attunement be with people and see if you can be
attuned to them not identified with them what does it mean and uh and attune this
one of the things it means is to what kind of presence was useful for them
what kind of presence allows me to be in the circumstance without any static
with some balance and stability so experiment with that maybe in small
ways in the place and times that are not so challenging so you get a feel for it
thank you