hello and welcome everyone lovely to be with you so many hellos we
hide from around the world hmm feeling our our connection our coming together
on this Earth practicing practicing together
so so the themes I want to bring in maybe
I'll just say a very quick word and we'll transition to meditating
one is this this appreciation appreciation for this being who is me being
a character in this play called life in a particular time in a particular
zeitgeist I've been teaching at 7 A.M about the
Improv of the Dharma the Dharma of improv and the taking on characters and
seeing ourselves as a character yeah this kind of a character was showing up because of all these cause
and conditions so little lightness to the way we see ourselves the way we
relate to this being who is me it's one idea I want to bring in and um
and the other one is sense that oh this this dear character meta for this dear
character who's me there's a particular time and Zeitgeist that we're living in
this character is is living in it's listening to a podcast and it's an
artist who was in New York at the particular time it was very creative time and I was just you know here we are
we we're lived through the you know the famous
a covet time and you know this is the Zeitgeist just looking at us through
that that lens of oh yeah these are the characters when we hear from different people different Generations different
things that have happened in time um here we are living when the spread of
the Dharma in the west is expanding so rapidly wow be Generations who would
look back and say wow those people who lived at that time and the drama is really spreading in the west and they
were just starting to have these online communities so just appreciating
ourselves our our efforts our practice from this other perspective from ways
into the future perhaps anyway so letting go of all that and let's just
come to this moment in time to what we know right here right now it's
let's arrive together and if it feels ah appropriate to close your eyes
after to drive to settle in this body in this moment
and having meta connecting with meta with good will
for this being who is me this character and this play called life on this Earth in the
shape in this form laying my part
being impacted by others impacting others
doing the best I'm able to it was meta for this character who's me
who has become me because of all the causes and conditions
genetic historical
evolutionary biological so many causes and conditions
wow with tenderness with care for this being
who is me
living their life living this life they know they know best
with each breath appreciating
foreign
relaxing softening the body the hurt
taking your seat on this Earth
I am here as Earth be my witness I'm here
doing my best
cultivate kindness wisdom non-suffering not causing suffering
as best as I'm able
letting this breath
your reality waking up to this breath the reality of this breath
because present in this moment to this life
to this moment experienced only in the way we experience it
we sense that we know it wake up
write awareness
not sleepwalking through our lives
there be a sense of delight appreciation
or awareness or Consciousness In This Moment being aware knowing to be alive
and this moment in time
as it is perceived through our perception through our senses
thank you
and as if we were watching ourselves from be outside as if we're watching the
movie of Our Lives the way we watch historical movies world
wars or or other historical drama and here we are this period of time watching the
movie of Our Lives
we are the protagonists doing our best we know
our hopes and aspirations we know our challenges we know the way we suffer
this protagonist suffers we know can we watch this movie with compassion
not with grief but with compassion with care
with appreciation
rooting for the character cheering them on
feeling tenderness
maybe this movie slows down some particular moments maybe
we witness some of the challenges this protagonist protagonist of her story has had we feel
but uh feel compassion oh sweetheart this was hard
it even send them compassion and meta
maybe we see some moments in the story where they're truly happy
intent joyous happy moments of their lives we feel gratitude
take your own time
practicing meta loving kindness compassion
compassion for the challenging passages Joy maybe equanimity
for the whole Arc of the movie peace and ease yes it's like this
like this and it's okay
see what your heart needs the most right now
which practice
foreign
needs In This Moment it needs soothing
led the practice of compassion
lead it needs uplifting let mudita
happiness for your own happiness as if you're watching at this moments of your
life your life on this reel of this movie real feeling happy
or your own happiness
with gratitude or maybe the tone needs to be just love
just appreciation
or equanimity it is like this yes the ups and downs
sense of Peace appreciating simple days
simple days the persistence putting one step
after another every day see what your heart needs
I lean into those aspects of the movie of your life
using ibrahimovihara
foreign
s like to arise
as you're watching the movie of your life and the appropriate response
is love loving this character is doing their best meeting
joys happiness in their life yay celebrating
scenes of happiness letting yourself be happy
reliving perhaps or being happy for those moments of happiness
not so much reliving but deteriorizing gratitude arising
if scenes of challenge difficulty arise I think
therapy sucker compassion Etc
another few minutes until we close the set
let your heart your body lead not your mind not your thoughts
appreciating the whole Arc of
the life of this protagonist who's you of course the story isn't finished
yet we're alive and yet with the perspective of the Arc of the movie until now
the ups and downs they keep trying they're doing their best
to learn be kind
sometimes failing and it's okay for giving this character
forgiving the story continues you still have time
to learn cultivate kindness compassion forgiveness
service yay
may we all know appreciate the Ark of Our Lives
and know that we still have the chance as long as we're alive to learn to
contribute to cultivate the wake up
may all beings everywhere wake up to their goodness appreciate and love themselves
may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your practice thanks for exploring this practice and
in in a novel different way we had never quite practiced in this way so many ways
to practice so many ways to to practice with the Brahma vihar is the Heavenly abodes the the four beautiful
practices so so the invitation tonight was to this
sense of perspective of ourselves the protagonists this plane
called our life and watching with with the Brahma vihar is watching scenes from
our lives with and whatever those scenes arise maybe they realize Compassion maybe their eyes would detach all of yay
maybe the whole Arc of the movie gives rise to a Calamity yes ups and
downs ups and downs yes this is human life this is what it's like and always always sense of matter I
always sense of Good Will good will for this character it's trying their best
so many many things that might have come up and uh
and it's all good it's all okay as long as there was a moment of kindness
more compassion or more data or any of the Brahma viharas if just one moment of
it it's all good it's all good it's all planting seeds so
so with that I'd like to invite us to to engage with each other
in um in small group practice
and the invitation if you wish the invited to participate in this way and
of course you can participate in the groups but hold silence hold compassionate caring silence just show
up with silence that's perfectly fine um and and the invitation is maybe sharing
a nugget if you wish what was this like for you and it's okay to say I was
sleepy I I didn't hear anything any instructions from the since the beginning it's okay it's all right just
show up it's perfectly fine having kindness for yourself um or anything else
um and you offer one brief nugget then the next person the next person that'll come back to you so you go around and
around make sure everybody has time so keep your your sharing short and it will
come back to you so you can go around a few times
um and be kind be kind yourself be kind to each other no asking questions no
directing not no giving advice just share what you want to share or share
silence that's perfectly fine and so we really want to create safe
spaces for each other so take care of yourselves take care of each other I'm
going to create the rooms now and um
and here we go oh let's go alphabetically
according to first name okay I'm opening the ropes here we go
all right welcome back everyone the rooms are closed everybody's back and we
have a few minutes for four Reflections um especially if you haven't spoken in a
while in the large group I'd like to invite you to step forward and if you
have spoken recently step back so that we can hear from and folks who haven't shared in a while
um or ever so Amy please
hey so this I love this perspective on looking at life as if we're like
watching ourselves in a movie it's great I think I'm gonna carry that with me
and uh it reminded me a few things one is Defending Your Life um not all this is an old movie where
they're watching their lives after at the end um and try to decide if they're gonna go back to Earth and do it again
differently and better or go on to something else and it's a little bit of a cringy movie but it's like similar in
that way um and then the other thing it had me thinking about was with internal family systems and this which is like Arts work
where you have like these different parts of yourself but as I was watching the movie I was like oh there's this part of me wanting to do that and then
trying to be compassionate and equitous about that and then this other part of me the one's the opposite oh that's cute
that's fun and then you know just kind of like noticing all of it um but trying to come from that yeah
that like Buddha Dharma land um if I'm watching it off it's very
sweet thank you thank you Amy thank you so much it was just so lovely getting Goosebumps as as
you're sharing um this this compassionate perspective on on your life and and all the person I'm familiar
with ifs internal family systems I love the framework so to have that like oh
yeah that's that poor sweetheart yes yes oh sweet oh you won the complete opposite oh you too sweetheart it's just
oh such a rich thanks so much for bringing that in love it and this movie you mentioned defending our like cringy
movie I have never heard of it so great good to know there's some you know some other frame that uses this I love it
that's great this is awesome thank you Amy
um bill please Elisa says thank you so much it means a
lot uh it's probably for both of us Amy Thank you Lisa the timing of it bill please yeah uh
what came up for me was was gratitude um because I have a a relatively
Newfound equanimity that has developed over the past year or so
um and Doc went through some stuff today that would have bothered me much more a couple years ago and now it doesn't
phase me that much and I felt a great deal of Joy over that and it's because
of the practice here of course thank you yay oh thank you so much Bill that just
makes my heart so happy to know it and I'll see hearts showing up in the zoom space for you oh my goodness this is so
lovely yay and clapping hands to oh this is we are we're all celebrating your
practice belly we're celebrating your practice how wonderful to have the sense
of oh yes more equanimities something happened today that would have been really hard some time ago but but look
there's wow progress on the path this is so awesome Bill yay yay so happy making
see so happy making thank you Bill this is so great may your deepening your
Equanimity continue made continue it will continue you're practicing so
there's no doubt I have full trust this is awesome people are asking what's the name of the
movie the name of the movie was yes thank you Amy Defending Your Life Defending Your Life
um PT um are you saying that PT arose when you were practicing PT meaning Joy arose
when you're practicing you're not quite sure about that but you can comment there SRI Devi
Meineke really enjoyed the the you know the topic um so I have a you know I asked a lot of
questions so my question is uh I want to you know I'm most of okay I
like to be honest so it seems that white lies are required by adults
um so I don't want to do White Lies so how do we say things
say the truth but at the Saint not heard I don't know like
don't hurt the other person but at the same time it should be the truth
yeah well truthfulness is is no I actually recently wrote a piece on right
speech on why speech that just showed up that just came out in lines or magazines so you can look at that but but
um since it's a little off topic for today but but I uh what you're asking
but I will say that there are different guidelines for for why speech and
truthfulness is very important and it's important um not only truthfulness is important
but but but even more so there is this idea of not causing harm not causing
harm so with the white lie consider how are you causing harm
Force to yourself to others is there a way um to not cause harm
and um so it's really becomes a an inquiry
um so the Buddha of course talked you know being truthful and factual is one of the the
it's part of the right speech and yet you know people often ask you know if if
they you're living during you know World War II and the Nazis knocked on your
door and you were hiding people who are being prosecuted you have to you know do you have to be truthful I can think well
that's where's the harm who's going to be harmed in what way which is a really big frame and maybe in the cases that
you're talking about maybe actually you're hurting your own Integrity more by telling the white lie than actually
just being honest and making yourself uncomfortable and making the other person uncomfortable so through just a
lot of considerations I can give just a one size fits all answers but just an
inquiry for all the the different questions that you need to ask all the different considerations for why speech
you can look up the various considerations for why speech you're welcome
yeah thanks sure and oh look there is
I think there Neil just shared a uh an article oh look at that it's already
showed up it's online okay thanks Neil you are fast good heavens
oh that's so great Ruth please
um I realized that I can't change my past but I can change my reaction to it the
way I look at it and I can be compassionate about the past
wow Ruth wise words thank you thank you powerful powerful wise words
wow beautiful ly said
yes thank you so much for saying that so concisely powerfully beautifully wow
we cannot change our past but we can change our our reaction to it with more
compassion forgiveness just the way yeah beautiful beautiful
thank you thank you Ruth and fazel you get the last word
well thank you for reminding me of that route
that's beautiful in anything else I was in appreciation for Ruth fossil
oh wait I lost you either you're muted there no that's all I had to say Ah that's
sweet that's very sweet I love it Ruth we deeply appreciate you thank you and
we appreciate everyone here thank you thank you so much thank you so much for
all of you for coming here practicing or supporting yourself supporting each
other oh thank you so much what a beautiful Community to be a part of to
to gosh to call home what a beautiful International Community so thank you all
thank you so much for your practice may you be well may you be happy may you
um see your past with compassion
the parts that need to be seen with compassion the parts that arise Joy may you take delight and joy and Equanimity
as well may all beings be well may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music] thank you all for a profound
session of practice thank you take good care