good morning everyone and good day for those who are in
different time zones and so this week I'm going to be here
with you for this is 7 A.M um practice and
sharing Dharma so I feel just really happy to be here with you all
and so we'll begin with um about half an hour of a meditation
so for this week um I feel like I'm still writing along with
um the waves of the two-week Retreat that the guild taught in May
and so I'm going to channel some of the teachings from that retreat
and so this morning meditation will
um will be guided by a set of awards and that starts with R
and today I will start with relaxing
and so that's where we're gonna begin our guided meditation today
so if you like to join me um please allow yourself to settle into
a sitting posture that's a supportive of a sitting for about half an hour 45
minutes
to begin maybe take a few long deep breaths
as you breathe out and now the whole body
to settle towards the ground
may be allow the whole body to ever so slightly
began to relax
offer a guided body scan to relax the whole body
maybe feeling and sensing into the lower half of the body
feeling the feet touching the ground
maybe the sit bones making contact with
floor chairs bed
wherever you may be meditating from
relaxing the feet
relaxing the pelvic floor relax
whatever relaxing might mean to you
for me it's a sense of settling down
allow the weight of a body to settle downwards
maybe a sense of letting go of any extra attention
unnecessary tension that may be a holding
holding the the legs the feet
so relaxation is not a demand
it's a gentle invitation
if the body doesn't want to relax
maybe relaxed about that
relaxing the lower half of the abdominal area
and relaxing the whole belly
just as if the breathing and freely flow
Valley can freely rise in the fall
there isn't any extra Construction
a gentle invitation to relax the construction
softening and a relaxing the lower back
however it might manifest itself
it could be just feeling the back
softening and easing up
relaxing the waist area and the upper back
allow the weight of the Torso
and settle simply by trusting the gravity
nothing to do here
softening and relaxing the chest
there may be a slight opening
softening the shoulders arms and hands
allow the shoulders to naturally drop
the body is naturally supported by the Earth underneath of us
there's no need for extra effort to hold up
relaxing the muscles around the arms
and
softening any tension that could be softened
relaxing the muscles around the neck
in the front of the neck sides and the back
relaxing the face muscles on the face
a jaw
they even soften the tongue inside the mouth
if it's a helpful you can't open the mouth slightly
and gently close release any tension
Construction tightness
soften around the eyes
and forehead
and sculpt
soften whatever may be softened right here
relaxing the mind
wherever the Mind might be located in your body
and relaxing the thinking muscles
as we relax the body and mind
you may notice that your experience become
clear
the whole body is at ease
the mind is at ease heart is open
soft
the movements of the Bride Sensations in the body
become fear
visible felt
if you find your energy
energetic field feels a little dull
and you dial up a little clarity
without adding tension to the experience
the relaxed the mind and heart hello clear singing
their reclammation
if you find mention picking up again
or striving is present
you simply in a relaxed way
invite using relaxing
and softening
just a gentle invitation they don't have to go away
and now your awareness to be relaxed
as if whatever arises and passes away
is a health by the field of
relaxed awareness
relaxed awareness already in it
as the flavors of kindness the flavor of tenderness
but
foreign
[Music]
for this next part of the Garment if you wish to continue to be
kind of in the meditative mode um please continue to
sit in your meditative posture sometimes I feel that
um the Dharma talks when being received in a meditative way it has a different
effect on Ami and so I offer that as a possibility
so this week's on darmeds that I'd like to Channel girls with them by reading a
set of stories a Tales from yo fransto's book called a monastery
Within and the
stories that I selected from this book form a theme
which was to do was the Dharma practice all right the Dharma path
in particular this is stories hopefully will offer some aspect of
um the sense of a multi-faceted or multi-dimensional nature of the Dharma
practice I think for most of us if not all of us
sooner or later as our practice unfolds will come to realize that the practice
or the path that Dharma path we walk
is not what we think it may be like [Music]
so to me this is the case for me when I first started the practice
and I thought if I just read and understood
studied enough in my head then that'll do it
and so you know I did a ton of readings and studies and sutas the books and and
disgusted them with groups in groups until when I feel like my head was about
to explode if there's more information but to be stuffed in my head
and so I realized that in the Dharma path is more than
sort of this information accumulation in my head
and so that opened me to extend or expand
my practice of field with meditative for
practice and the books also said it's important right it's um so I sat and meditated at
home on retreats until at some point I realized
well there is a more to the practice than this form also
and so the practice began to expand even further
included family life and particularly after my
son was born maybe that whole journey
included in my family caring for my family relationships
relationships with uh closed circles and then expanded to
relationship of other people I don't know well or I don't know at all
and so this practice began to expand in many different dimensions
I realized at some point I began to reflect how I choose to live my life
how I behave or speak and the attitudes I hold are living this
life and at some point I began to ask myself
what do I exclude so this is a long way to say that the
practice is a multi-dimensional or multifaceted and so the art of our practice is to
begin to open ourselves to this multi-dimensional nature of our
practice our path because all of those different dimensions
support each other and inform each other
and so each of the stories that I'll be reading this week points to some
dimensions of the practice that one may or may not have considered
and they're not exactly what you must do or have to do like what the stories are
pointing to but rather they serve as metaphors to point to how one might open oneself
up to the multitudes of the practice
and so as I read to the stories sometimes I'll be offering some
Reflections and commentaries and um you might this might be an invitation
for you as well and to incorporate some of your own reflections
so that's enough said I'm going to read the first story of this week
[Music] so this is called
inside out an engineer had been a regular and
devouted visitor to the monastery for many years the meditation practice taught at the
monastery was the only thing that made sense to him in fact
the pragmatical logic of the meditation teachings give him hope that he would
overcome his chronic unhappiness and deeply felt pain
he tried all the meditation practices that the abbess taught him
he began each practice technique with enthusiasm only to have each end with
the same frustration he would encounter a wall he could not
pass the closer he came to the wall the more he would recoil back into trying to
think his way out of his pain offering him much support
the apis encouraged him to relax trust the practice
and to Simply feel his inner pain without reacting to it
after many years the Abbas decided a different approach was needed
during his next visit to the monastery that Abbas told him that if he wanted to
continue being her student and to be able to return to the monastery he would
have to take on a special practice once he had completed the assignment he
could then return for deeper teachings once more feeling hope
the engineer quickly agreed the app is said
for two years I want you to volunteer 10 hours a week at the maternity world at
the local hospital the hospital needs people to hold babies who are born prematurely
if they don't receive enough physical contact the babies will not grow healthy
when you have finished this two years please come back to see me
the man was quite perplexed by this instruction but because of his trust in the abyss
and his failure to find any relief elsewhere he plunged into volunteering
in the maternity world he was surprised at how small and
fragile the babies were that he helped he would hold them ever so carefully
he would watch their every breath because they all seemed in danger of a
stopping breathing spent a lot of time thinking about how
he would how he could more effectively care for the babies he held
but there was nothing more effective than simply holding them against his
chest after about six months
he started a feeling something quite new he started to feel a little spot of
warmth and the softness in the very center of his being
since this was a foreign experience that didn't fit any of the ways he
thought about himself he ignored it
ignoring it was the best thing he could have done
because it prevented him from interfering with the warmth by thinking
about it too much over the following months
the tender spot grew until it pervaded his body
as it did the cold dark wall around his heart
slowly relaxed thought and dissolved
when he had completed his two years of a volunteering in the maternity world
the engineer returned to the monastery the office saw immediately
he was a changed man he was no longer desperate
and he was no longer trying to fit everything he experienced into a
conceptual framework now he wanted to learn what else the app
is had to teach giving him a new instruction
the app is said to him when you meditate don't think about what is happening
father let your awareness be seated in the
tender warmth you feel in your body if you do this
any meditation practice you do will be fruitful
the man found this to be true
so what might be the walls that blocks the deepening and the richness
of your Dharma path in this story The Abyss is the one who
offered the new instructions to the engineer but for each of us
the abyss maybe ourselves we may have to discover
the wall and new possibilities for ourselves
and like myself at some point of my journey I realized
more study more reading
it's only going to build a thick wall
and so I had to open two new dimensions of the practice
and similarly just like this engineer often we may practice using a lot of
conceptual framework that we learned about we don't quite
know to how to practice in an embodied way and so for this engineer holding the
premature baby and a softened and opened him up
to get in touch with his own direct embodied experience
and so for each of us we may have to discover
because you know the pointer of a holding baby in some different ways
so for many of us we know that the
drama path often is described as a three-fold
practice of asila samadhi and panyas and so sometimes
maybe the ethical Dimension is challenging
and this can be a wall for ourselves and maybe sometimes we have to cultivate
ethical conducts in order for other dimensions of a
practice to come along so it's quite rich and there's a whole territory and my invitation today is
um to discover and open your practice in
multitude of ways and I will continue tomorrow
in this way so thank you everyone for your
presence and your practice and may the spring benefit to yourself
and to all beings everywhere thank you everyone
have a wonderful day