foreign welcome it's lovely to be here with you
and I I really do appreciate your being here with me
so here we are today
in a community where we're creating together uh opening the Dharma heart
cultivating wholesome qualities in our arts and Minds
Monday it was focusing on receptivity
yesterday cultivating a softness of mind
and today is perhaps uh an ambitious one of cultivating a mind that is
unobstructed so I'm sure many of you are familiar with the five hindrances
those unwholesome states of mind sensual desire
wanting not wanting aversion ill will
Loth and torpor or feeling rigid and stuck
the agitation of restlessness and worry and the hindrance of doubt
so to make this a doable project for a 30-minute meditation
we'll try to create the conditions where we can notice if one of these unskillful
tendencies starts to arise and see how we might let go of it
so let's begin by vowing to be gentle with ourselves
kind with that mind that may be spinning off in thoughts
and if we see that the mind has been spinning for a while it's no problem
we can Rejoice that we've seen it and we come back to being present
here in this body breathing
and then comes the important part appreciating what it's like
when that negative tendency subsides even if only temporarily
so as we have been doing and will continue to do this week we begin
with each of us setting Our intention or this period of meditation
what motivates us to practice
and now taking your meditation posture sitting or lying down
connecting with the Earth
and aligning the spine
so feeling your seat or
your body on the bed and the Earth supporting you
and feeling your spine as in a live space where the energy can flow through
you up from the earth and out to the heavens
and you could also appreciate the energy that comes down
from the sky through you and into the Earth
it's important to try to Center the head a little bit on the spine so that it's not
logging forward or looking out for being off to the one side or the other
so with our alignment as balanced as comfortable as we can
make it you do a scan from the head down to the
toes relaxing the shoulders
foreign s and hands
the heart area the belly the hips
the legs and the feet
and if you can settle down into the stability of being here
it's really invaluable if you can refrain from moving while you meditate
just be here in this body the way it is without trying to change
what your circumstances are
and now we'll continue with some short meta meditation
the last two days we did it with a inviting a benefactor to come and
join us sitting in front of us and looking into their eyes and sharing okay
the well-wishing
I just heard somebody maybe there's a participant who's not muted
so if today you um are comfortable being your own benefactor you can try it that way or if
it's helpful for you to do that in the company of someone that
you yearly love and always feel good with that's that's fine as well
and what we're doing with this little bit of meta is warming up our
mindfulness meditation by lighting a little flame
in our hearts of kind friendliness towards ourselves
and towards whatever arises moment after moment
we're creating a safe space where we're protected by this feeling of warm
-hearted well-wishing towards ourselves and all beings
may I be safe and protected
may I be happy
may I be peaceful
may I be free
may all beings be safe may all beings be happy
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
and with this well-wishing we light a little candle in our hearts
bringing warmth receptivity softness
and openness to our mindfulness
and now we bring in the wisdom
The Vow that for this period of meditation
we'll do our best to help the body and the mind
to settle down it's the wisdom to know that we and our
community here are better off if each of us can leave our preoccupations
responsibilities worries concerns
outside of our meditation space no need for them now
so connecting with the breath and letting that little flame of wishing
ourselves well in view our mindfulness
with a feeling of benevolence
enacting with the cycle of the breath
breathing in well-wishing
breathing out well wishing
breathing in safety breathing out happiness
breathing in peace breathing out of freedom
and just staying with a quiet
of the mind that is happy to be here just breathing
together with our like my dear friends from all over the world
breathing in [Music]
I'm sorry [Music]
sorry about that I must have forgotten to turn something off
so let's go back to the breathing
breathing in with a warm heart
and breathing out with a peaceful heart
feeling the beginning the middle and the end of the in-breath
the beginning the middle and the pause after the out breath
the quality of friendliness towards whatever arises
and letting ourselves be nourished by the quality of warm-heartedness
as we breathe in as we breathe out
and happy to open the windows and the doors
of the Mind
not shutting anything out
and not spinning off in useless thoughts foreign
heart radiate inwards as we breathe in
and letting it radiate outwards as far as it wants to go
as we breathe out
and if you should find yourself on a thought train
you could say I see you Mara so if you don't know who Mara is he was
the tempter who was Furious that the Buddha had so
many devoted followers and was so highly respected and Mara's job in life as far as he was
concerned was to knock the Buddha off of his
pedestal of Enlightenment and to knock all of his followers off as well
so uh I find this a very helpful image if
I I just give her oops you know that thought green for a while
and I just say I see you Mara and tomorrow when he's seen he's
defeated and he slunks away
so if we find ourselves thinking again
just coming back gently no judgments at all
and just with his simplicity of being here in this body
in this breath and tasting
the goodness of even a second of just uh
if another thought starts to arise ah I see you
no thank you and with a smile you come back
being here in this body with the ebb on the flow of the breath
and gently daring to open the windows and doors
breathing in enjoying the spaciousness
of a moment of freedom letting in the warm sunlight
and the fresh air enjoying
these moments when the mind is unobstructed
breathing in radiating warm openness
breathing out radiating spaciousness
for all beings
breathing in openness breathing out spaciousness
and as we come to the end of this sitting with a mind that has benefited from
fresh air by opening some windows and doors
through the goodness of our practice may we from our Center of openness
now radiate our heartfelt wish
that all beings everywhere be safe
may all beings be happy may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
foreign
I do uh appreciate your presence
I appreciate your practice and I'm happy to be here with you
today's the third talk on opening the Dharma heart
and we're looking at five qualities of mind that the Buddha used himself to
see if someone was ready to become awakened
in Bali the word for mind is chitan and the qualities we're looking at this
week are
[Music] and someone yesterday asked
where this came from in Nepali Canon and um
although they're not one of the many Dharma lists that you often see in the early texts I looked it up and they do
occur as a group together uh nine times in the early teachings and
the text that I'm referring to is near the end of the Ramaya sutta which is
Maji manikaya 91. on Monday we talked about being
receptive available and ready to change
yesterday we evoked the quality of having a soft and malleable mind
and Gil talked about this process of suffering the mind with the idea that
we're each a work of art and in working to progressively become
more and more beneficial to ourselves and others having a mind that's stuck or rigid or
hard makes it difficult to change ourselves in a beneficial way
we need a mind that's receptive and also soft
so that we can shape the mind to become more and more beautiful
and today we come to the third quality which is
and probably V is a prefix meaning away from or not
and nevarana are the five hindrances
those powerful forces that we as humans all experience
the root word in poly for these hindrances is which is to block
so the hindrances are obstacles obstructions and barriers to Awakening
and it's important that we look at freeing ourselves from the hindrances as
a progressive task these five hindrances exist in each of
us on a spectrum from being completely caught to being completely free
as you may know the first hindrance is sensual desire wanting greed
the second is not wanting a version hatred ill will
the third usually call it sloth and torper refers to resistance stiffness
shutting down the fourth includes restlessness
agitation worry regrets and the faith is doubt
doubt about the value of the Buddha's teachings or God about our own ability to walk
this path of freedom so one of our first jobs as a
practitioner is to get to know these forces in ourselves
to study what causes them to arise and to see the unskillfulness when we're
caught and reactive and then finding ways
to see them start to arise and having the wisdom to know this is not how I want to be
so in the process of getting to know our own unskillful qualities it's important
as a voice to remember to be kind to ourselves because we're Human After All
you might think of training the mind the way you would brain a sweet little puppy
but if you yell at the puppy and kick it every time it makes a mistake I'm going to end up with an angry
aggressive dog and if you want your puppy to grow up to be a happy relaxed loving dog
then you drain it with caresses and with treats
giving the puppy positive feedback every time it does something right
so in the same way without setting expectations too high
we can give ourselves positive feedback by noticing the moments when the hindrances are in
advance and appreciating what it's like to be free of him these
obstructions if it if it's just for a second ah it's like we've opened the windows
and doors of the Mind and we can enjoy the healthy pleasure of
the sunlight and the fresh air what a relief
not to be spinning around in preoccupations
and the more often we notice the goodness of these moments of freedom
however short-lived they are the more we build the neural Pathways so
that letting these obstructive forces in the mind subside can happen more easily and more often
so take these moments of freedom in and Savor them
without of course clinging or getting attached
it's enough just to say ah right now the mind is unobstructed
and I mind that instead of being caught up in Me Myself and mine
is open to the sunlight fresh air and spaciousness of the Dharma
that's beautiful so let yourself consciously receive and enjoy these
moments when the mind is unobstructed open
beautiful you can enjoy the taste of well-being
and gladness they come with letting in the light and the fresh air
of open awareness my first Buddhist teacher was the Zen
master Suzuki roshi and I began studying with him at what
was for me the tender age of 21 only two years after I had gotten out of
the mental hospital and I still had a lot of work to do with myself
and that struck me so deeply right away was
that the end of every period of meditation he would bow to each of us
as we came out of the meditation Hall and when he bowed to me he communicated
that there was something worth bowing to in the same way he would bow to a Buddha
no matter how screwed up we were he saw the beautiful potential
that each of us had and he treated everyone like a Buddha
and I had the Good Fortune to become his disciple and to be
on the receiving end of his unconditional love
and it wasn't uh because I was someone special
but it was it was amazing to just be with someone where
was convinced that there was nothing unworthy about me
I didn't have to worry about being worthy or unworthy it was enough
just to want to practice sincerely
and this is something we can do for ourselves we may have been taught that we were
inadequate unworthy or unlovable
but being inadequate or worse is a harmful Mirage that we can let go of
and the beauty of this path is that even those of us who struggle with scars from
having been deeply traumatized are perfectly welcomed
this seed of the Buddha the beautiful Buddha is Alive and Well in each one of us
I hope you believe me it's alive and well in your own
so this path is about little by little learning not to cling to the unskillful
coverings that we thought were necessary to survive
and in to enjoy the aliveness and taste the freedom we can experience
in moments when the doors and windows are unobstructed
so if you're for a little homework for the next 24 hours
see if you can slow down enough so that whenever possible
the mind can take a break from its reactivity from spinning off in thoughts
notice how beautiful it is to Simply abide even temporarily
in the moments when you're unobstructed in the absence of the hindrances
this moment of touching the doorknob the aliveness of being right there with
the doorknob or mindfully cleaning the sink
and it's lovely to just be cleaning the sink or though
out all the commentary of the Mind
listening attentively to a loved one
without jumping ahead on how we want to reply
just being receptive soft and and without barriers for them
so the homework is to really touch into the joy and gladness
of those moments when you are fully present with your experience
so thank you for being here and know that I appreciate
and am very much encouraged by your practice thank you