oh so in some parts of the Insight Meditation communities
there was a decision 10 years ago to celebrate the
first week of October as their Earth care week and so when it comes for of October so
when it comes to the beginning of October when I come and give talks I like to give a talk on that topic today
is October 1st and so uh I just love this word this
combination putting together in the same phrase Earth care
on the surface at least or you know in kind of first thoughts
associations to the word Earth it's the planet out there
and but care is something that's in here in our hearts or in our in our life it's
something that arises from us and so to put these two together is such
a beautiful thing that we have this capacity for care and we have this Earth that we live in
and so we couldn't care for it and then you could say Well it cares for
us Earth care could mean not that we care for the Earth but Earth care is recognizing that we're cared for by the
Earth and but that's not maybe so popular to think that way both of them cannot be
so popular that we should care for the Earth or that we are being cared for it I suppose
to have the idea that it's caring for us then we feel like well you better do something in return
and um but you know if we don't you know the Earth is just a hunk of rock
floating into the face and we don't deserve we don't need to do anything for it it's just for us too
live our life for our love say to bring him together Earth care
and uh it also for me raises some of the points
to some of the great spiritual questions I think people religious people spiritual people are grappling with in
one way or the other explicitly or implicitly questions like who are we
who are we in relationship to the world who are we relationship to the other people
what is this world we're in it and what relationship does the world have to me who are all these people who are sharing
this planet with and what's their relationship to me and you know how do we fit into all this
and um and in our particular inside meditation tradition if people just you
know the anthropologists from Mars came to see us you know study what what are these people doing they go back to Mars
and say they just close their eyes and they tune out the world and they
just sit there look inside you know and uh they seem to be oblivious of the world around them it's a very very
peculiar species and or subspecies
and um but uh um but as we do this investigation into who
we are and what it means to be living here there's all kinds of interesting things
that become clear one is that um we divide up our world in all kinds of
ways that are not natural to the world out there but their constructs of the
human mind and today is October 1st
the construct it could be some other month that you know in Ancient India they had to they
used the lunar calendar so I don't know if it's we just had the full moon so what two days ago so this
wouldn't be the first it would be the second of this particular cycle of the moon
and um and then there are you know probably other calendars people use and uh and uh for us at Sunday and that's also
kind of a you know arbitrary it was really fun when I lived in the Zen monasteries that they don't follow the
seven day week there they have a five day week and so this Monday to Sunday that just
wasn't relevant and we wouldn't you know no one would would you say it's you know tomorrow's
Monday the days were named by their the number so days off we're not Sunday days
off where the days that the number of the day the month day that was had a four or a nine in it so they say four
and nine days the next four and nine day will have it some time off to do your laundry they would say
or something and then three and eight days there was a special
ritual they did in the monastery so so you know no one you know we kind of
forgot about days of the week when we were there and but I think for those of us living in a seven day week Society we
kind of know you know what the weekday it is but it's a division that we make up and to make it even more clear this
whole crazy way in which we divide up our reality um I don't know how many of you know
that um if we were if we knew Latin that we
would understand that October 1st is the first day of the eighth month because October in Latin means eight
and then that you know like we have it wrong right we're confused the Anthropologist for Mars I'll say what's
going on and then uh November is the is the ninth
month right no it comes from the Latin word for nine December is a Latin word for ten it's
our 12th month so you know these names that we put on things not
only is it arbitrary to divide up the Year this particular way but also it's a you know we kind of arbitrarily there
were the names we put on it and um and so we keep making this Latin
mistake every year so you know it's a little bit amusing
maybe but uh oh what happens is that we do the same thing to ourselves
and to the world we live in we have concepts by which we divide it up and just a very idea that there's me
here and you there is kind of self-evident and of course we have to operate in a world like that but
it's not completely so straightforward what that division is
um some people will Define themselves as a radical individuals completely separate from who
are you and they'll say well I'm this person who's you know this age the size this color
here this kind of interests It's All About Me Myself and mine it doesn't tell any any you don't say anything about who
you are in relationship to your family or your community or something and um and whereas some cultures if you
ask who's who they are then maybe immediately first and foremost say well I'm I'm the child of such and such
parents or I'm I'm part of this Village or this tribe or something and that's
their identity first comes forward in terms of who they are as part of some other group
and it was fascinating for me to to live for a year in the monastery in Japan and
which is uh one of those cultures where they tend to think of themselves as part of a group more than individuals that
are separate from all the other individuals who might make up a group and it was fascinating to see how I
understood the social dynamics differently than all these you know there were about 30 monks young monks
that I was living with and it took a while to see it but by the time I kind of learned enough Japanese to understand
I was kind of it was really fascinating to see how my my way of organizing the world was
different and their way of organizing the world and I didn't think that one was better than the other
but I did think that there's a very important to see that what we're doing is uh we're constructing this thing all
the time so this is a central teachings for the Buddha that we are constructing
ideas about ourselves ideas about ourselves in relationship to the world we're in
and and some of those constructs are what when we attach to self to who we
are that we're attaching to constructs that we make up and we might think that you know we're
innocent we're just kind of living our life and we are what we are and you know and all the concepts we're using are
completely self-evident and normal and everything and just uh and they are just
as much as October 1st is and um so an example I like to give
is in these days is um is a maybe you're deep in the woods
there's a tree that no one's ever seen before and no one's gone through that part of the woods but some some people
go adventurous go go explore and the first person that goes into the wood is a botanist
and the botanist sees this kind of tree and the botanist zeros in on the leaves
and the shape of the leaves because uh recognizes what genius is but doesn't
know what species it is the tree and that's how you identify the trees by the shape this particular genus is the shape
of the of the leaves so once the once the the tree has been
identified like this goes home it's happy uh someone who's a sensualist who loves
sensual qualities goes and they're like going around looking where is it really
Pleasant in the woods and look at that tree and it's these beautiful flowers and it smells so nice and the color
green is and they just oh this is like you know
better than perfume and this is you know just and this is I'm going to come back here just to kind of get a whiff of this
beauty this is like looking at art you know wow so they're looking at it for particular
qualities that they're selecting out uh someone who is a woodworker
will go and I'll be looking for the wood that could make good furniture or tables
or whatever they make and so they're going around and trying to identify the kind of wood trees have
and he sees this tree and goes over and knocks on it and pushes on it and is this hard enough for what I want to do
and it's trying to identify now recognize in the woods something that
the woodworker wants to you know whether it's usable cut down the tree and build something
uh hey someone who's a uh you know a
Born Again Born Again devoted romantic
you know it comes in trees look at the tree and looks around and looks a nice grass under it and how it's nice and
shady and a warm day oh this is where I should come with my lover you know with picnic and you know and
little figs and chocolate and and we'll just lay here under the tree and just kind of looking deep into each other's
eyes and it's just like this is like you know love incarnate place and um and uh and that's the orientation
about how it's going to fit the story their fantasy of this wonderful outing with our lover
uh the tree doesn't matter too much it's what this how it builds up the story and then finally I don't know if this
works so well but a painter comes along and decides to paint the tree
and uh and the painter doesn't need to know a lot of it we except for all its physical characteristics with light and
shadows and shapes and needs a lot of little details to pick up a lot of little details of all the little
features visible features and it turns out the the painter loves
that study loves the activity the energy the interest of the eyes and studying
and taking it in and translating it to you know to Canvas and and it's like
kind of something comes alive for the artist to kind of you know tracking and absorbed and all
those details the artist just loves not the details but loves the Consciousness
which is engaged in the play that's needed for the art
so five different people five different ways of experiencing a tree
the tree is is whole the tree does not divide itself up this
way the tree does not divide itself up between its branches and its leaves tree
doesn't you look at my trunk it's not it's a little bit too fat
I put on some weight in my you know in my in my middle ages
the tree doesn't he doesn't think about that it's shape of its leaves means that
it's you know now you're this kind of tree the tree is an organic hole
that doesn't divide up in its mind or anywhere it's Parts the whole thing as a whole
operates as kind of an ecology or as a whole as a process and um and but humans have this ability
to select out of the environment and make really hard divisions between what's what
so it's you know it's maybe a little bit interesting about a tree it's tragic sometimes about ourselves
we do the same thing to ourselves we are an organic coal or so but how often do we allow
ourselves to just be an organic coal without living in the divisions in which we live by
and so some of us are obsessed about our physical appearance
and our society our culture supports this and in all kinds of ways and uh if
how we look is is actually significant in how people treat us so it's very
painful at times and um and distressing and worse that uh
that how people relate to us if it's all about appearance and all that and um and so that's one way that we
make this division for ourselves some people live their life based on
comfort avoiding discomfort and it's really Paramount for some people everything's
navigating and negotiating being comfortable learning comfortable you
know they don't call themselves sensualists but that's the base of their life the Buddha in his ancient world when he
thought when he considered human beings he considered that what defines human
beings is uh their concern for pleasure
and avoiding pain that's such a Central Drive for human beings a preoccupation for them
and then we have thing we have concepts by which we recognize the world and the
our Concepts we recognize the world with sometimes are inaccurate
like when you see a a stick on the trail in the woods so you think it's a snake
or something a rope and you think of the snake but some uh sometimes it's inaccurate and sometimes it's tragic
because what we re how we recognize the concepts Concepts we use to see other
people um demeans people and worse
sometimes we take advantage of people or somebody see someone as a you know primarily we recognize them as objects
for our sexual interest and that's pretty uncomfortable for people who are on the receiving end
more than uncomfortable and um so so we have these Concepts we
carry around with us and some of them are inherited from our family our society our experiences in life and we
don't see that we're seeing through the lens of these Concepts we have
and we do that to ourselves when I was in seventh grade a teacher came over and watched me make
a drawing on my little desk and just said in the most matter-of-fact word where a matter of fact away said again
you have no artistic talent you know just like you know and I didn't
care you know I didn't have any concept of myself it didn't actually affect me in terms of my mood or I didn't feel bad
about myself but she was the authority so I went for the next years thinking
you know Mom I have no artistic ability and I'm just one of those people you know it didn't bother me but I
carried that idea with me and that's how I understood myself until I had uh my
first college roommate was an artist and he kind of kind of tricked me into doing
art and and then I took art classes and it was nice
and um so uh so these so we we lit we
live under the burden of a lot of Concepts uh you know that I'm guilty that I'm I have shame I did something
terrible and a lot of people live with shame a lot of people live with uh with the
conceit of different types I'm special or or in Buddhism saying you're special
or saying you're terrible is kind of the same game and both of them have the same Source within us that is it partly is by
this division that we're dividing up things that were that are organic whole
and so we want to kind of you know free ourselves from these Concepts we're stuck in
and so maybe that's enough to kind of describe this the way the Buddha sees that we construct and there we have
stories right that we live in too and the stories tend to also separate out and divide up and and construct during
that sometimes stories are complete fantasies and sometimes we have fantasies and then
we expect other people to share in our fantasies and sometimes they do and then it gets you know kind of out of
control sometimes and so uh what this meditation practice
that we do is meant to relax quiet down
all these constructions we live by and um and so that when we're here on a
sunny day with a blue sky we're not you know sitting quietly
minding our own business and meditation and thinking October 1st October 1st October 1st
this is October 1st you know I mean that's you know I hope I don't think
anyone you did that did you maybe now you're doing it in a minute but you probably had other things you were
thinking about and uh and so the idea is to to quiet this down
and um and as we quieted down and these the divisions the constructs we live by
the the conceits we live by that the ways we get caught by desires and
aversions fears these quiet down and one of the things that we begin
experiencing is ourselves as an organic whole and which kind of doesn't it's not so
easy just to Define it like this is what it is because uh it's so easy then to
choose some part of us over the others part and um and so in meditation we learn to
leave ourselves alone so that we can just be let this organic whole just operate
without a construct it's not let it operate whatever way it wants with the constructs
with hate with fear but there is a quieting down partly it quiets down
because we start seeing we're doing this so it's not a it's not ignoring or or
Blinder to what we do with all this but these quiet down
and then we start seeing the difference between living and constructs
projecting our constructs onto the world and not doing it living living with all
kinds of thoughts of self-criticism self you know we can be pretty hard on ourselves and not doing that
and we start seeing there's a difference between that we have some choice about whether we create inside of ourselves
constructs that lead to harm harming others harming ourselves and there's it comes a time where you
start being able to choose between them not that I don't need to I don't need to think
about that anymore I don't need to get involved with that I don't need to to divide up the world
this way I can just sit here and breathe breathe nicely and easily
one of the things that can happen eventually an amazing moment will arise in
meditation practice I hope it's soap sooner than later but sometimes it takes a long time
that you're sitting there kind of minding your own business in the present moment being present for yourself
and you discover your breathing in an easy way wow it's so useful the breath is just
coming and going it's it's an embodiment of ease I didn't realize how much I controlled
my breath how much it's held in check wow just there's ease and now I breathe
and um and you know what is that ease doesn't you
don't need to know what it is you don't have to put a label on it it's just it just it just kind of knees there
and then with that easeful breath that becomes a reference point to begin
understanding how you lose it and and you can see if you get involved
in certain thoughts the breaths tightens up and it's not so easy
and you can see it all kinds of ways internally certain emotions arise and affects the breathing
so then you start seeing kind of a little bit how it works and maybe you have some ability to adjust things accordingly do not go along with those
thoughts maybe that way of thinking but also what happens
we start seeing that what happened in the outer World affects our breathing
too and
the way that that eat our inner ease is not only dependent on what's going on
inside of us it also depends on the world around us
uh you know last week there was smoke here in the Bay Area from fires
and that affected our breathing to some degree and I know my breathing was
slightly more labored at times with the smoke here especially if I try to go for a walk outside
and sometimes it's been a few years ago it was really bad and uh and I could feel the extra work it took to be
breathing it didn't feel like it was that useful to breathe that that represents the how you know
there's something so profound and important for us as our sense of inner ease has some effect is affected by what goes
on around us in the environment and uh and we are not independent of the
environment we we wanted many of us want to be independent people
but maybe we can be somewhat independent in certain kinds of ways but that's just one of the divisions we make one of the
constructs we make constructs of Independence some people really want to be independent with the kind of conceit
their kind of specialness or or to be not or so we don't have to be responsible for anybody else
but uh you know we live I think so I think we're all only about our
independence overlooks the fact that we are amazingly dependent on other people
and on the natural world not many of us grow our own food 100 in
our society here not most of us in the society here don't
make our own clothes from our own sheep that we share and you know we you know
the things that support our life come through the the vehicle of other people's efforts and labor and work and
and it just you know it's an amazing network of people and things and
processes that make it possible for us to live and and to live our life we kind
of in some ways depend on it probably not many of you remember how to knit if you had to
and and so the um but also the natural world here we
completely depended on it and you know most of us know that we have to breathe regularly otherwise we wouldn't be here
so our life depends on having oxygen to breathe in
um but uh so we you know we have every few seconds we live in this dependent
relationship to the air and um does that make us separate from the air
are we like an independent thing or is the air out there and independent of us
or is there some way that who we are is inseparable from the air Inseparable
from the Sun Inseparable from the ground that we walk on how do we want it how do we do this
divisions how do we where do we see where we begin and where we end
is that arbitrary or is it really clear lines between where I End and You Begin where I and
and the air is and lately I gotten fascinated by the
air that we're breathing all the time and it was pointed out to me this Summer that trees plants but trees are solid
air isn't that amazing mostly what trees are made from is the
carbon that they get from the carbon dioxide in the air and so imagine you know how much carbon
does it from the air carbon dioxide does a tree have to take in to get enough carbon
molecules to be a redwood tree and you look at these big redwood trees
you know I think in my mind I used to without I never thought about this but I think it was just kind of I kind
of assumed that plants and trees most of what we have the solidity there came out of the
ground but actually most of the solidity comes most of what we see there the carbon
comes out of the atmosphere and and because they take the carbon out
of the carbon dioxide in the atmosphere they release
uh oxygen and guess who needs the oxygen
we do and so uh and so there's this wonderful process so now the question is
this tree in the forest in the woods right that I talked about earlier
you know is it that tree over there and I'm here
or are we part of an organic whole is the organic coal more than just the
tree more than just me all these processes that are working together
and is it a little bit arbitrary how we make these divisions but some of these divisions that are
constructed of the human mind cause a lot of suffering
there's a lot of selfishness a lot of self-focus
or there can be care there can be opening the heart and the mind to look
around and see that we not Just Me Myself and mine
but maybe what's more realistic it's we ours and ourselves we're all in it
together and that we we us ourselves is much bigger
than uh our human Community it's how we how we're in a certain kind of community
with the natural world with this Earth is there an organic hole of the whole
Earth and does that organic coal
have some bearing on how easy it is for us to breathe
our inner sense of peace and well-being where is that found and where does that
come from and and and uh when there's you know when there's forest fires
nearby how easy do you breathe when there's you know the air is full of
smog how easy how easy how much ease do you have do you have more ease when this air
is clean and you can see across the bay or is there something maybe almost subconsciously where it's a little bit
oppressive a little bit you know tight and constricted
to live in the smog to hear about people around the world
who are living under environmental challenges and
does that have anything to do with you are we independent from that do we share this planet with others and everything
or not and that's a division that we we can make we can construct
but when our consumption of goods is gathered from all over the planet how
independent are we I don't know if it goes on on anymore because China stopped but China used to
take a lot of our garbage until they decided we our garbage was too dirty
our recycling was too dirty we don't clean our recycling so it's much harder to recycle if we don't clean it
so um so this Earth care idea
is in our practice we first what we're
learning is to care for the Earth in Us in ourselves
to care for the natural world that we are and in the deepest way we are not the
the mental constructs that we create we manufacture all kinds of ideas that
separate us and divide us and can cause a lot of suffering but that's not Who We Are
and but if we can drop down and quiet those constructs then we start becoming aware of organic
processes within that are not constructs that are not mental creations and this
is part of the Buddha's emphasis over and over and over again he used similes from nature
to describe how it's possible to live a life where our breathing is easy an
easeful breath that easeful inner life a peaceful inner life and um and uh and it's Awakening this
natural process inside but that natural process inside
is not apart from the natural process of this Earth outside of us
they're intimately connected they're kind of part of the same whole same kind of evolutionary things or all these
processes are coming together and moving back and forth and so to care for ourselves
you can't really do it unless you fully unless you care for the world around you if you care for only yourself
then you're living in a divided World more constructs if you care only for the world outside
same thing you're living in a divided world and it constructs it
but I would like to propose that when we can settle enough the constructs the
preoccupations of the Mind that then the opportunities here that
the care that we have is part of the natural working of life the organic
functioning of human life has within it the capacity to care to be concerned to
love to be generous to to be attuned to the welfare of self and
others into the interested in in supporting others and caring for others or being kind and being supportive and
sharing this planet together not because we should not because
there's an obligation but because that's what lives in us if we fight if we drop into this place
where the natural world has a chance to flow through us and why it works that way why this
natural world has created us in this kind of way that it's natural for us to want to care for our babies
you know some of you have had kids it's you know it's pretty
deeply ingrained to have this kind of Parental Instinct that of course we care and that that care doesn't have to stop
with our babies or our children or our parents or neighbors it can that
movement of care is completely natural phenomena part of the natural world
we have and to allow that to be
used to grow and expand and spread so that the care is in all directions and
whatever we touch whatever we see we see it with care we see it with
kindness we see it with appreciation we see it
as part of the organic home as opposed to seeing it through our
greed or hate or or conceit and so
for there to be Earth care is I think a profound thing
I think it's a profound natural thing that human beings given a chance to
tap into their depth inside
will care for themselves will care for the people around them
will care for this world at the same time as we feel know that we
are being cared for maybe not to the degree to which we would like
you know the stock market was incorporating today and caring for me
you know I don't know if that's a good way of thinking that's more
divisions but this world is caring for us in profound ways otherwise we wouldn't be
alive and to drop the concern with the stock market or whatever
and to appreciate that we can breathe and that there's water to drink and there are people around us who smile
and this and it may be people who appreciate that we smiled back
that's a beautiful thing so Earth care
this is not something you have to do but it is something which I hope will
come from your inner Freedom as you discover Your Capacity to really drop below all
the divisions and constructs that the Mind tends to make and feel like you're part of an organic
goal of this planet and I hope we can take care of this planet well
because it's a way of taking care of our family our communities
what we love and it's a way of taking care of ourselves
so thank you Earth care this week so maybe this week can be a week that you consider this
topic maybe just keep this phrase in your mind Earth care maybe ask your friends what do you think
that means Earth care in my as you can say in my where I go and meditate this is the earth care week
what do you think of this think about it and let's see what uh what uh what direction your heart goes
if you keep this close by for the week so thank you very much
and um as I said uh I'll go if we go outside in
the parking lot and if those of you who would like to talk about this some more or say hello in other ways to form a little
circle there with the chairs and then for maybe I don't know maybe 20 25 minutes and then um we'll allow the
Dharma Sprouts to come in here get set up thank you