so hello and welcome to happy hour everyone lovely to be with you wherever
you are in the world practicing together so um
yeah a couple of words and then we'll
practice together and we'll meditate together the same for tonight I'd like to invite us to engage with
um bring to our hearts and Minds a beautiful practice of gratitude
and it's really important not to approach this practice of gratitude as
it should like I should be grateful oh God I should be grateful no no no please
please don't actually it's it's not a practice to have any issues about it's
it's an invitation can I be grateful for this can I be grateful for this and if
the answer comes back no I I don't feel great then don't don't push it don't
push it but it's a gentle invitation and yet it's such an important practice in
this very gentle way of of not shooting uh that someone said not shooting all
over ourselves um is is because we usually look for
problems in our lives or it's just the
way human beings work it's it's our um evolutionary
um basically Heritage because those those uh who survived those who passed on
their genes they were looking for threats in their environment those
ancestor human beings they were looking for threats in the environments they were not looking for those who were
looking for berries did not survive the uh they out survived those who were
looking for threats and and um so so we are looking for threats
we're looking for what's not going right what's problematic that's it's so we
need to balance we need to balance the tendency that we all have as human
beings for what's difficult um it's it's said I've heard this before
that I might have heard it also that our minds uh are like uh velcro for what's
challenging and difficult and they're like Teflon uh the old days when there was a lot of Teflon for for for good
things for for uh for things that are good in our lives they just don't stick
to our minds like oh yeah yeah we get a compliment oh yeah thank you maybe it doesn't quite stake the goodness but oh
yes what's challenging what's wrong what's problematic are we just go
through it again and again and again so velcro Teflon
so so in order to balance in order to balance our hearts and mindsets it's
helpful to turn to what is good and when we intentionally just ever so gently
turn towards good and what's good could be outside what's good could be inside oh
the goodness of my intention I'm showing up yeah maybe I find
meditation challenging maybe I'm a beginner maybe I fall asleep and and and
yet I keep showing up this is good this is good so so sense of oh yeah can I be
can I appreciate maybe not even use the word gratitude maybe that's too heavy for some people can I appreciate can I
appreciate that I'm showing up and maybe yes yeah I guess I can if I step out of myself I can appreciate that
this person who's me is showing up uh even though they fall asleep all the time or judge themselves we're not doing
it right yet oh yeah there is goodness here so so internally externally as a
way to turn our minds to so much good to so much good not to take it for granted
so much good really and and when we notice good the good in our lives
then it feels like more good shows up because we're noticing the good we're open we're open for more goodness to
appreciate to befriend uh to support to give to be generous it's it's it's we
we try we joined we become part of a virtual cycle
all right I've said plenty let's um let's practice together
so arriving arriving
arriving each moment a new arrival
arriving in this body moment
moving our attention connect
our awareness no know that we are sitting and
breathing
foreign
letting our awareness connect with the breath the sensations of the breath
in the abdomen lower part of the body receiving
receiving each breath Letting Go Letting Go letting go of
plans thoughts entanglements for a moment the connect
with this being who is Me In This Moment the goodness of just sitting and being
breathed goodness of being here
and and you invite a sense of appreciation
to imbue this breath as you're breathing it as it's breathing you
if the answer is no it's okay just stay with the breath
noticing the sensations of the breath of your sit bones
on the chair your hands touching your lap your feet or your legs on the Earth
feeling grounded and Bodied here
just here wonderful to just be here even for a moment not scared scattered
here and there [Music]
with each breath reaffirming
rejoining
the goodness the goodness of being being alive just here
just here a sentient being
sensing the breath
Sensations
foreign
an opening opening door opening our hearts
what is nourishing in this moment in this body maybe the breath
maybe the breath feels smooth calming like a lullaby
and we enjoy it with appreciation let yourself enjoy
can we open up to something else that's nourishing
supportive In This Moment
maybe it's this chair or seat that's supporting us
opening opening to it to its existence in our lives with with appreciation
maybe where we're sitting there is
clean air to breathe so I'm appreciating there's air there's air that we breathe
supported by the air
the air element supported by what we're sitting on
the Earth element supported by worms
it's not too warm not too cold us humans
out of the limited range of Comfort we can survive in so yeah
supported by worm nice
thank you
supported by this body so many organs functioning internally
the blood flowing
the water we drank earlier
the food we ate at supporting us now
and stay you stay with appreciation stay with the good stay with
appreciating goodness you can open it up more and if your mind starts going to
to lack those in the world who do not have these resources right now
yes it is true and yet this is not the time for that practice
that is compassion practice another time
bringing your mind erecting kindly directing to stay with
this practice so that you can have enough stability
enough Joy then to open up to the suffering in the world
not to turn away forever but to have the space to create the space
the stability the joy to contain more
of the challenges so staying staying with the gratitude
feeling embodied opening up the goodness in your life
the relationships you're grateful for
friendships
using perhaps one relationship
being this particular person to mind with appreciation sharing your Goodwill your meta for them
your good will your appreciation
wishing them well appreciating them
as if they were sitting right in front of you bring them close your mind's eye
and maybe opening up to other friends relationships family
colleagues or their appreciation
feeling the abundance of your interconnectedness
with so many amazing beings alive complex
as complex As You Are
foreign
and whoever comes to your mind you have some appreciation for them
whoever shows up
even those you have challenges with
they are your teachers they help you grow they help us grow in ways we may not
want to or find challenging
appreciating you know whoever shows up
and feel free if you'd like to open up too and appreciating other aspects of your
life
maybe opportunities
and also challenges what stretches you maybe
consider something that has stretched you challenged you recently
can you be grateful for this yeah and don't push it
but drop in the question can I be grateful for this too and let yourself be surprised see what
comes up
can we open our hearts maybe experiment now if
you like
imagining your heart so fast so spacious
so spacious your body's so relaxed your heart's so spacious
so vast and you can include everything
to be grateful for everything
Generous Heart that receives with gratitude goodness challenges opportunities being alive
and this human Realm all its ups and downs
ten thousand Joys ten thousand sorrows
of its impermanence deeply woven into the fabric
being alive in this impermanent moment can this hard
to be wide open just for a moment experiment to receive it all
passing through appreciating the whole catastrophe
receiving giving gratitude with generosity
giving thanks
practicing opening it up you can always close it in a minute
if it feels too big too much but just for a moment see what it feels like if
you open your heart wide beard dared to open it wide
spacious spacious as the sky species as the universe
The Grateful heart as spacious as the universe itself
to include everything
that has been is will be
the mystery of it all beyond our understanding
that I am a part of this whole mystery I'm a player in
sentient conscious playing my part
growing learning serving giving
hurting being hurt gratitude for all of it
or the ways I've grown in the ways I have yet to grow I have yet to grow and stretch myself
and if you find if you meet limits of your heart it's okay bow to it be grateful for that
too be grateful for this too
is being authentic and true
foreign
as we bring this meditation to a close can we
be grateful appreciate or whatever showed up or didn't show up
it's okay
appreciating that we showed up we did our best not attaching to our outcome
appreciating ourselves appreciating the Sangha for showing up and supporting us these amazing human beings
who keep showing up and practicing cultivating their hearts
thank you thank you universe
thank you my inner goodness to have led me here thank you
I love the universe thank you Karma thank you Sangha the community
May our goodness May our practice serve all beings everywhere may all beings be
happy may all things be free including ourselves
thanks everyone I'm grateful for your practice or you're showing up
showing up so I'd like to uh invite us to transition now
to uh to practice to express our
gratitude appreciation um in small groups in small groups and
the prompt is the prompt and this can be quite powerful actually this practice The Prompt is what are you grateful for
so you say one thing you are grateful for one thing and then the next person will say
something then the next person and then you again and it goes around and round and round and it can be so uplifting
with with feeling your own Joy letting it be witnessed as well as witnessing
other people the sense of mudita vicarious Joy arises if especially if you're feeling a little heavy
at this moment in time this is a joyous practice it's it's a wonderful uplifting
practice um to fill our hearts with joy so yeah
so I will I invite you and then yes going in um let's go and
alphabetical order and um yeah what brings you Joy is the uh is
the prompt so I'm creating the the rooms take care of yourselves take care of
each other again you can also pass when you turn comes just offering something
and then letting other people have their turn okay so I've created the rooms be
kind be gentle um and here we go opening the rooms now
okay everybody's back welcome back everyone I
see some Smiles so uh yeah this is great this would love
to hear um maybe from a couple of people and you're also welcome to write your
Reflections and chat if you just write it to me it will be private I'll won't
read your name just your reflection if it's to everyone then I'll read your name as well and you can also raise your
Zoom hand and somebody's giving a thumbs up I think they're trying to raise their Zoom hand is this Jamie
are you trying to no that was my comment oh that was your
comment thumbs up you liked it okay that's great I love it
they're very concise now I want to invite you actually especially if you haven't spoken recently Susan says so
much to be grateful for if you haven't spoken recently I'd like to invite you to challenge yourself and be grateful
for the opportunity and and step forward um I see you Claire I'm just gonna get pause for a moment and and see if and
get someone who's um oh maybe it hasn't spoken for a while
or maybe he's new to happy hour what did you discover in the small groups or in
this practice any aha moments okay all right Christine and then Claire
please thank you Nikki I really enjoyed this uh meditation tonight
you've talked about that before making a soup like we made a suit tonight and one
of the gentlemen that was on my call this is the first time here and it was just we all went around and like I said
we just added a little bit to each other tonight and it was just uh a lot of
gratitude in my in my uh breakout room so I'm grateful for both my uh
people that were with me tonight and my Stanga first thing I said was I was grateful for showing up tonight and
being part of all this just exactly what was needed so thank you so much Nikki
and everyone beautiful thank you so much for sharing Christine and for your practice and
showing up yay it's so beautiful makes me happy yay Claire please
and actually I know I've said this before first of all I want to say thank you for this uh and I've said this
before but I just like to sell it again through another spiritual program that
I'm in I started circulating a gratitude list with two friends on email about six
or seven years ago we do it every day and it made such a difference in my life and I think even just one night like
this it can make a huge difference yeah I mean because I tend to look at everything that's wrong with my life
we all tend to yeah exactly where's this me to look at what's right there's a lot
so there's just so much that's going right it's it's just it's overwhelming
actually it's quite quite lovely thank you Claire thank you for that and Diana you're next and before that I want to
read a message if I came to me directly and one of you said I realized that a lot of my meditation practice was to
observe things neutrally it was very refreshing to observe things grateful yay beautiful yes so so lots of
different practices and with the practice of with vipassana with with
with uh Insight practice we often try to well it's in some ways it's neutral but
in some ways we're looking at a rising and passing we're looking at things but but with the practices of the heart with
meta and with with all the Brahma vihars with loving kindness with compassion
with vicarious joy and with Equanimity there's a particular way of looking and
especially with mudita and and by the way gratitude fits under vicarious joy
in the in the in the for Brahma vijayas that's where it fits because when you when you feel great
happy for someone else's happiness it's joy for them when you're happy for you
feel happy for your own blessings yeah guess what that's gratitude anyway so um
so yes there's a particular there's there's a beauty there's a goodness to this practice of modita vicarious Joy
turned inward that becomes gratitude so I'm delighted person who uh sent this
this reflection yes it's such so refreshing it's so beautiful to and
um maybe I'll just say one more thing the path towards Awakening doesn't go through just the gray zone of the things
or as they are there's a lot of Joy the Buddha was was known as the happy one
and the path actually in this instruction step by step by step by step um as well as you study the suttas you
see there is joy and there's contentment then there's Bliss this and there is gladness all of these parmesan and Piti
and and sukkah you know all of them they're just laid out they're just uh so so the path and then at the end is oh
yes nibana Awakening but it just goes through these the mind the heart need to go need to contain Joy need to contain
all these uplifting qualities in order to be liberated it's not a grim duty to
be liberated so anyway thank you for that reflection Diana
oh this is just really quick um we were thinking uh and saying that
we could actually if we had time do this all night the this gratitude just go
around and around because what happens is you keep thinking if at least for me to keep thinking of things and and it
builds and it makes and and Oddball things too could come to mind an oak
it's just like an endless array so it's a it's a really joyful practice thank
you for offering this to us thank you thank you so much it's that's lovely and
one of you reflects I had a lot of rage come up during the session it was not about Joy at all for me tonight no
problem and that's what needed to come up um rage anger so so there are conditions
in the mind and the heart and that's when you when you quieted your mind when
you know we quiet our mind and there's just a lot of something else that needs to be a 10 ended too maybe that comes up
or maybe or maybe the rage comes has come up perhaps because of a sense of lack or or
um or you know various things but it's worthwhile not to push it away and and
say okay this is you know it didn't work out it's the disaster but actually stay curious stay curious can you I know this
is going to sound like a high bar but can we even be curious or or have
gratitude about the rage can we have gratitude that we can actually have
emotions instead of just being a complete blank and and not just
completely blank uh or that we have the mental facility faculties to fear age and then when when
you welcome Rage with gratitude not necessarily acting out of it I'm not
saying act out but well yeah it's here okay can I be grateful for this too yeah
I can have emotions I can feel upset can that be a way to then turn towards
um working with it and and actually cultivating uh gratitude anyway
thank you all thank you so much for your practice thank you for being here for your cultivation may all beings be well
may all beings be free including ourselves