good morning everyone good day hello greetings from uh Insight Meditation
Center I'm very glad to be back here it's been
how long it's been maybe uh six weeks that I've been away and um or so five weeks
and um
from traveling and teaching and different things and um now I am
coming back from inside to retreat center where I just finished teaching a week-long retreat
so um a little bit I feel like a beginner
sitting here being away and now use that as a theme
for today the um also maybe it's appropriate to feel like
a beginner and that I Mark today as maybe the
approximately the beginning of the maybe it's next week the beginning of the or
finishing this week is finishing three years of these 7 A.M YouTube teachings
and next week I guess we begin the fourth year so thank you all for being here
and in the theme of being a beginner I think it's useful to consider maybe
realize that when we are when we meditate
we mostly meditate as a beginner
that it mostly was like we're starting over or and then sometimes as we get settled and
mature and the practice there are times when we have we course along with some kind of more experienced deeper
meditation but often in the bakeries of life we sit
down to meditate and it's kind of like starting over so we're all beginners
but the difference between someone who's a beginner or real you know really beginning someone who's an experienced
beginner has done a lot of beginning is that the attitude with which they
meditate how they meditate the how they're aware how they
concentrate and as people become more experienced
experienced they're more relaxed about how and also more dedicated and this
combination of being that it calmly dedicated without striving
without judging without bringing all the baggage of Me Myself and mine along when
I meditate my experience what's happening I'm doing it wrong I'm doing it right what should
it be as people come home or experience they just settle in and are more at ease
with being a beginner and uh and just going through the basic
instructions so I'll offer you some of those today
so to assume a meditation posture
and uh what's nice with a
in being caring and careful about the posture you take that it's a posture that feels
unobstructed somehow we're sitting in such a way that
there's no obstructions and that's part of the advantage of the
classic posture of the Buddha sitting upright and
cross-legged posture is that there's no obstructions in this body no places that
are contracted or limited or collapsed
sometimes if we sit too comfortably in a couch it might be comfortable
but maybe there's a way in which the shoulders and the upper body is kind of
curled and curved in such a way that it doesn't
really allow kind of obstructs a kind of compresses a little bit the chest and
unobstructed posture
and then to gently close your eyes
and without much more ado to take a few moments
to recognize to know how you are in your body
how you are in your mind and heart and how you know it is important
to know it's simply matter-of-factly
to know it without being for or against
and in recognizing how you are now
going into your body feel
what that feels like the somatic experience
of how you are in your body and your mind and your heart
and again how you feel is important to feel it with a radical simplicity
not having an agenda or a need imposed on what it feels like
not trying to change anything
offering a respectful attention in feeling sensing
how you are somatically
and then to
relax the body
relax the body on the exhale
and how you relax is important to relax without trying too hard
trying hard at all just relaxing simply matter-of-factly
content in doing so
in whatever way is easy
and now maybe taking a few longer deeper inhales
gently on the exhale relaxing deeper
relaxation that follows it longer in exhale longer exhale
all the way to the end of the exhale
and now letting the breathing return to normal
recognizing knowing what it's like for your body to be breathing now
and how you know is important being content to know it in whatever way
is most obvious no need to
analyze or bore down just the simplest way knowing
what you like for your body to be breathing
and then to feel what it's like for the body to be breathing
feeling the somatic experience of breathing
and then without much any without any ambition of
how well you can do this gently
soften and relax the breathing
soften the muscles that engage around breathing
maybe softening the muscles of the belly
and then to be with your breathing in a simple
way resting and breathing
and whichever is easiest to help you stay with your breaths helping you quiet your mind
stay with the knowing recognizing inhales and exhales
or stay resting in the feeling the somatic sensations of breath
riding those Sensations
and with every exhale quieting the thinking mind
thank you
and as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps we're always a beginner in our relationships to other people
are always changing we're changing contexts changes
foreign and to be a beginner is to
be willing to not bring with us
the old beliefs associations ideas of who people are
but to see them freshly
but more important as we become experienced in meditation we learned
that the how we're aware is important we learn to be aware without
our judgments and preferences and agendas and needs
we learn to see others simply and openly
with our feelings about them
still feeling the way we do but see them to know them
without the filter of the feelings feelings are one thing and
seeing is another
and to see freshly
without philosophy without cynicism and skepticism
just see
and perhaps to see then with kindness
with good will with the friendliness
with care to gaze Upon This World kindly
as a beginner
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings
no deep contentment
may all beings know that they are respected
may all beings be free
and may we contribute to that possibility
[Music]
so hello everyone I'm happy to be back after I've been
gone for a while and um
I trust that you were well cared for by Our Guest teachers
they're all they're all wonderful teachers and very happy that you're able to that
they're able to come and teach and that you were able to hear their teachings
and experience their presence and how they are and um
and I think that this coming year the it'll be I think starting next week the
fourth year that we'd start doing these 7 A.M teachings that they'll be gone more than I have
been and um so that we'll have more these guest
teachers coming through and some of the same will return and some probably all of them will return at some point and
and um and others as well will come along and you could experience a range
so um
so at the beginning of the year I started teaching about challenges how to
practice with challenges the plan is to continue doing that and thinking about it today I thought
well that's what all of Buddhism is Buddhism is how to practice with challenges and overcome cat challenges
into Buddhism doesn't use that word at the center of it all but I think that in focusing on it here
now and these these this year that um
I'm highlighting how practice is certainly useful in everyday life
but how it's useful when there's stress when there's anxiety when there's
confusion and difficulty and that kind of heightens the level of uh
of a sense of there's a challenge there's a difficulty here and that can be a range it can be the
simplest little thing and but it could also be some of the
major life challenges that people have that um
sickness old age and death people go through tremendous horrific experiences
in their life and how to deal with those is calling him challenges maybe is to make
him too too small and but uh but in this this teachings on
how to work with challenges is difficulties is you know what to do when
things get kind of life gets concentrated
so that there's a lot of intensity all at once
so what I'd like to do this week is go back to the four foundations of mindfulness the beginning of this series
I did this week we did a week on each Foundation of mindfulness and today I'd like to this week I'd like
to focus on mindfulness of the body that the body in Buddhism mindfulness to
the body has been emphasized tremendously since the time of the Buddha it's such an important part of
practice the Buddha even said emphatically in a variety of different ways that there is no maturation in this
Dharma practice without mindfulness of the body and in recent decades this will become a
tremendous appreciation of the value of the body for
healing the psychological healing that um
maybe starting in the probably the 50s 1950s
and then onwards there were psychologists who were discovering how important it is to really drop into the
body feel the body feel the psychology as it's manifested in the body and then more recently it's recognition
of how important that is somatic work is for trauma
so in Buddhism we have this emphasis on mindfulness of the body and and have it
using the body connecting to the body in times of challenges is invaluable
then in the four foundations of mindfulness there are
um six exercises on mindfulness of the body and uh and so we'll go through five of
them this week and the first one is breathing and in times of challenge remember to
breathe remember to breathe mindfully in a warily because when we get challenged
the breathing tends to get tight or constricted which tends to reinforce attention
before a force agitation shutting down even and it might be valuable to kind of for
the breathing to stop or slow down to be constricted if in fact we have to get
into a fight or have to fight have to run or do something but in many challenges that's not what's
needed to happen and what needs to happen many times is to calm down and
take a deep look at what's going on so that wisdom can operate the clarity can operate
and um and then especially if there's a if there's uh we feel challenged when there's not an immediate challenge
present it's uh the challenge is someplace else in the future or has been
or dealing with the repercussions of it and then we can then maybe we can take
that time to catch our breath we say come back and breathe
and um and so you know take deep breaths exhale
it's invaluable simply to do the three breath Journey and that is
just maybe close your eyes but just uh uh for three breaths follow be with
those three breaths and in everyday life if you go around and if you stop for take those three
breath Journey that's enough sometimes to just shift and change a significant
amount of how we are how we feel how we see the situation and if you do a three breath Journey
once every hour I bet that your whole day will start having a very different flavor
so I come back and and check in with my breathing you know regularly kind of a
constantly it's it's all these years of practice has become second nature to feel my breath to connect my breath see
where the where the constrictions where I'm tight where slapping in the belly what's happening in the chest uh how am
I breathing and um and to use the breath as a relaxation
so when the Buddha began the Spore foundations of mindfulness he talked about he put breathing at the center of
it because it's first so to connect to your breathing
and and recognize the breath and then as we begin recognizing
breathing then begin feeling he said the whole body I'd like to begin by just feeling
the experience of breathing throughout the body wherever breath breathing whatever is influenced or touched by the
experience of breathing and to take time to feel the somatic experience of breathing in the body how
is it and then um and then they would have went on to say if after you felt the whole body
relax the tension in the body relax the body and this is kind of the beginner
practice however so many of you have been practicing for some time and as I said
in the guided meditation I think most of us most of the time are
practicing as beginners and we sit down and the mind is busy and agitated or spinning around concerned
there's maybe we've had a busy day and there's tension in the body and the mind is not settled and calm and immediately
gets concentrated so we're kind of like a beginner and and to just appreciate them maybe
you know just as a almost like a assumption that mostly we're practicing as beginners and sometimes we are
practicing like you know like really getting made deep in meditation but the as being beginners people who
are experienced in practice are quite willing to begin again and again be beginners in meditation but what shifted
is their attitude one is there's a willingness to be there for that experience not to be fighting
it or agitating it or judging I think I'm I'm not doing it right I'm supposed to do it right what's supposed to happen
here um there isn't there's a more spaciousness a graciousness with oh
um I'm just here practicing beginning exercises it's okay and and not to be
I'm not gonna and there's a feeling that the how we're mindful is more important than how deep we go
and rather than kind of jumping ahead like leapfrogging ahead into what we
want to have happen in some depth of practice it's um is where we take a backward step
into recognizing how am I right now how am I feeling and how am I being aware
am I being aware with with strain am I being aware with need and wanting
and trying to fix something am I judging you am I for or against my experience am
I complacent am I you know I'm here but I'm not really you know that interested in meditating
and I'm just gonna I meditate every day and I'm just here so I'll just kind of like Daydream or something because I'm
not really into it so how how is the mindfulness how are we practicing
becomes important for beginners they know that that's an important thing to look at and be with
and then as we become aware of how we are in any situation how are we how are
we with challenges how are we paying attention to our difficulties and what's
going on for us then to breathe in the middle of it you feel and allow yourself to breathe
and the rhythm of breathing the massage of breathing maybe taking some deep breaths and exhaling long and deep
and then with the breath at the center uh start feeling the whole somatic
experience of body as much as it's easily available and relax the body
so these are the three steps that the Buddha offers is kind of beginning practice uh is to recognize what's happening with
oneself to feel it to sense it to experience it somatically
and then to relax and those three are wonderful little
three-step process and as practice unfolds it might seem
that first one of those is not really relevant and then no longer necessary you don't
need to relax anymore and then it's just recognizing and feeling at some point feeling the experience
might feel too much or recognizing the experience might be too much and then the practice gets simpler and simpler
so um so when we when you have challenges
you might do a few things you might do the threes breath Journey
when you recognize oh I'm challenged now take time and and unless it's less the
you know the threat is immediate uh if you know there's some time and
space then um take at least a three you know the time
for three breaths close your eyes and just kind of be really intimate then follow and connect it to three breaths
just three and see what happens the other is to practice these three steps the Buddha talked about
really recognize how you are feel how you are somatically
and then relax and that can be done together with breathing and and this is beginner practice
and if you are an experienced beginner then you know that how you're practicing
is as important is there and you can feel you can recognize how you're
practicing you can feel it somatically how you're practicing if there's strain or tension
and you can relax how you're practicing so there's no extra attention involved
in the practice that you do so if you should have some challenges
today and unless it's immediate threat that needs to be addressed I'd encourage
you to uh engage with practice practice in the middle of it it's invaluable to practice
and challenges it really strengthes and inspires and and really that's where the
kind of a muscle of practice and maturation of practice really starts
taking hold so thank you and um
and then we will continue tomorrow