oh good morning everyone here in person good morning those of you hello for
those of you online maybe for some of you it's not morning
so happy to be here with you all nice to be together in person I think one of the I guess I guess is well
recognized now that that lack of Community has been a very big
negative impact of the pandemic and so they come back come together is
pretty important for many people and uh even if you're we're still
wearing masks here can you hear me okay is it loud enough for everyone
so um and we are discussing uh ending the mask requirement here at IMC we're like one
of the last big places right with with this some people show up at the door with
your surprise how could this be but we still are and at least for this
month May and it's a work in progress but we're considering ending that masks
in June so um or ending them being required
they're optional and recommended
after that so um
so the talk today could be titled
um suffering as a door to go through
and I think many of you know that one of the core aspects of
Buddhism or kind of Buddhism is addressing suffering and
the general idea or the kind of the ultimate idea they decides possible to end suffering bring suffering to an end
and um and that's you know it's fully fully enlightened is to bring suffering to an end
and that's perplexing for some people like like how could that be really like am I still going to be human if I don't
suffer at all and um and so some of this has to do with how
we Define suffering and I think that people Dharma teachers like me uh
seldom defined enough we just assume everyone knows what it is
you know we use the word suffering suffering suffering suffering until you suffer
what does he mean what's going on here and um the
and um it's a good I think it's really reasonable to question what this what we
mean by suffering and to have what do you mean what do you mean because for
example it doesn't mean all forms of sadness sadness feels uncomfortable therefore
because it's uncomfortable as I mean we're not enlightened you're not supposed to be sad anymore and if you're
going to be Buddhist good Buddhist you have to stop being sad please or no grief
does it mean that you never get annoyed or irritated is that that also is uncomfortable
so is that kind of you know crossing the line into suffering you know that's not supposed to be
um never be heartbroken you know see some of the things going on in the world and you're supposed to just kind of
continuing you know singing happy songs and smiling and you know well Rome Burns
or whatever it is so what about you know uncomfortable emotions is all of them supposed to go
or what so uh I think what's important to say
is don't look to Buddhism to answer those questions I just raised
that makes you more then now you're suffering more if we're frustrated more because wait a
minute that good isn't supposed to have answers it's supposed to describe things I think what Buddhism is trying to do at
least the kind of Buddhism that I'd like to espouse or that I see is is encouraging us to take a deep good
look at life and really and discover for ourselves what's going on in a sense answer those
questions for ourselves the questions that are really good what is suffering and is some suffering inherent and part of
even an enlightened life or are some forms of suffering um
you know are all suffering are going to go in but what is suffering what does that mean what are we talking about here
so to for you to answer that question for yourself and that requires stepping in and taking a good look
at whatever you might generally consider to be suffering so as some of you know the bumper
sticker I think Buddha should have for their cars is I stop for suffering
because to really take a good look to enter into suffering not to suffer better or more
but to do the opposite of running away from it the opposite of avoiding it
and the opposite of collapsing with it or the opposite of kind of just like just just living under the burden or the
struggle of some of this child emotional distress dismay pain that so many it's so common
the human life so to stop and take a good look at it so I call it a door
and so calling a door that you go through is maybe a paradigm shift
for how many people address their own suffering their own distress and stress and pain and challenges
because often we want to avoid it and we want to make it go away but we want to
like push it away or just cut it off or take a drug so we don't have to feel it
or something or be distracted and um but to stop and take a really good look and think of it
as a door that you have we develop a lot of faith or a lot of confidence this is a good
thing to do and that's a paradigm shift I've known people who've taught that
this kind of idea that you know you should turn around and be present for your pain and your suffering physical
pain even and really look at it and I've known that some people maybe some of you are here today already get angry
no this is terrible I'm here to get rid of it not to have it not to look at it
not that you would have to look at it and feel it even more my gosh you know this is like you know it
doesn't promise the end of it they now have to you know yes but
[Laughter] but this paradigm shift this kind of
almost almost a radically different way of looking at suffering where we don't see it as a burden we don't see it as an
oppression but we see it as a door that we go through to get to the other
side and um and and as we go through that door as we turn towards it then we can
start looking more and more deeply to understand the nature of that suffering
and we can answer the question which suffering is appropriate to live with
and maybe accept and maybe even appreciate as part of the richness of
being a human being and what part of the suffering do we have is just a really optional and
unnecessary and a product of the odd mechanations of my mind and
heart that don't really have to operate that way and so I see how that works the
operating system of certain kinds of suffering that comes from what's you know the unfortunate unnecessary functioning
of my mind and that I'm happy to let go of maybe it's not easy to let go of it but
I see now so we start seeing a distinction between their own
so in this regard I want to suggest that this investigation of suffering is
supported by taking a good look at three different aspects of things that could
be called suffering just inherently some people might say it or are
sometimes are the kind of thing that Buddhists call suffering
the cut of suffering that's what we want to bring to an end and some of it maybe is not something
you can reasonably bring to an end and you have to learn how to live with
that and how do you live with it wisely how do you live with the suffering
that's you can't get rid of ever in human life how do you live with it so you don't add
suffering on top of it that is optional that is not necessary to have
so then so so this is this that's the investigation and each of you will have a different answer today and tomorrow in
a month in a year and your answer will change over time because the answer will change a lot by the the by number of
things by how well you understand yourself
and the state of your mind the mindset that you live under
and the quality of Consciousness the quality of the Mind provides a very different vantage point
for understanding our life understanding ourselves understanding what's important
so it's not just simply answering the question from the state of mind you happen to have today which maybe is a perfectly good State of
Mind to have when you're in that state of mind but to have uh but you know the way we
see the world changes when we're more concentrated for example when we're peaceful
when we see aspects of the ma of this world that are invisible to us to this
to this state so so I keep asking these questions and seeing in new and new ways
so in three areas in these areas I want to talk about are
um plain and simple discomfort
emotional pain and the complex of ideations
that Belong To Me Myself and mine the kind of the whole ideations around
identity and self and all that so to to dip into these in a deep way
that those are the that's these are doors to really address and maybe go through so we start with discomfort
I'm sitting here right now and I'm uncomfortable in my right leg somehow
something shifted in my old age I used to sit comfortably like this for years and now there's a degree of discomfort
and pain that I didn't used to have and um and uh so I'm just kind of I
don't know writing it off is the right language I'm just kind of like okay you know maybe that things change and I was
very comfortable for many decades and that was nice and now I'm not so comfortable and maybe that'll last for a
couple of decades and then it's all shifting all the time and actually I've had all kinds of
discomforts in my meditation career that's about 50 years old now that um
that uh they've come and gone at different times and you know so it's
part and parcel of meditation for me is being with discomfort
I have I would say that I have no suffering or barely any suffering
by this pain that I feel going down my leg here right now it's just okay you
know it just okay I don't give it much attention I
give it enough attention to make sure that I'm not injuring myself or not wrong to have but it's just there in the
background and you know it's you know it's cloudy today and I can meditate with the Cloudy Sky I have no pain in my
pain in my leg and I can just meditate with it without any issue so so discomfort and physical pain of
all kinds comes with human life so to degree to which some of it is
unavoidable for human beings to look at it then
deeply and one of the things we start seeing is not the discomfort itself
but the relationship we have to it so I just described to you kind of
hopefully to be a little bit encouraging that I have pain in my leg and I'm completely at ease with that then fine
that's just not an issue and and that that that that relate kind of relationship is possible is very
different that I'm sitting up here and I can have all kinds of reactivity to this here
I could get angry I've been meditating 50 years and by now I should not be uncomfortable
which is to be completely and Bliss that should be floating I thought Buddhism was the kind of Flows In The Clouds and
you know just kind of just everything is kind of blissed out and and what am I doing you know this Buddhism is a
failure that finally realize this Buddhism doesn't help me at all you know because I'm not in that Bliss state that
I thought the promise was so that's one relationship and some of you are laughing at me
for having that ideas and um so that's you know that's a relationship I have to
the pain that uh I would and because you're laughing you realize it's maybe a
little bit ridiculous and silly to have that it could be that um I feel really discouraged
you know wow you know I should and then it also a big idea I shouldn't be feeling pain
could be you know uh you know I'm embarrassed you know this is like
I shouldn't admit it I'm a meditation teacher you know and you know they're going to
think bad of me now I should be able to you know sit here and just kind of again just be you know blissed out or
something so uh uh I can be angry at the pain
you know that leg of mind or you know and I'm gonna get back at it I had a friend who had knee pain in in
meditation and he said that he would um whenever he heard he'd heard it back
yeah push at it
so you know there's all kinds of odd relationships to pain right to discomfort
so we are embarrassed we feel it shouldn't be there we're angry at it we're trying to escape it some people
are incapable of being with certain kind of emotional discomfort and they'll run
away they'll go for alcohol for example or sometimes sex or sometimes
Netflix or whatever you know something you know just to get away from it food
you know and so they don't have to feel their discomfort and um and um
so it in when we do the mindfulness practice one of the things we're learning how to
do is to take a good look at the relationship we have with discomfort and
see that the relationships the attitudes that we have are different than the discomfort itself whether it's physical
or emotional discomfort it's without a judgment about the discomfort without the idea that you
have to end all discomfort once and for all through Buddhism but rather you're trying to understand
that relationship we have so the relationship itself becomes one of ease and peaceful
so we're not adding unnecessary distress pain stress on top of our life by the
reactivity we have with the discomfort so the slogan I like for this is learn
we're learning to be comfortable with discomfort that's a radical thing to do compared to
what most people in our society know what to do some people have the idea that when
they're uncomfortable they failed at something you know somehow to be a successful person you have to kind of
just never be in pain or never be uncomfortable with something and you have to fix your discomfort at all costs
his life is a lot easier to go through if we're comfortable with discomfort if we're not a slave to discomfort
pushed around by it and having to react and do with it as we become Freer in that way around
discomfort then we're in the much better position to look at the discomfort
in a kind of objective clear way and decide is this healthy for me is this
appropriate for me so like the pain I feel in my legs or sitting here
I pay I give it some careful attention and decide okay this is okay
for now I don't think I'm injuring myself I don't know exactly what's going on and and probably I should do more
stretching you know or something or maybe I should find a different posture to sit in but some because I'm
studying it and looking at it I can begin kind of coming to terms with it and to understand well maybe I shouldn't
be this I'm comfortable enough with having it but maybe there's ways of fixing it that are appropriate
but now I'm going to fix it because of wisdom because it just seems like a sensible thing to do as opposed to fixing it
because I'm angry or want to escape it or I have aversion towards it or I'm
just really attached to comfort you know so it's I need to get to myself as comfortable as possible that's what's
cozy and I would love that then so what's the attitude and so as the
attitude becomes simpler and simpler and non-reactive then we're in a better position to
answer questions about the discomfort okay this discomfort I can live with this one I shouldn't live with this
involves it this requires a change now let's see a healthy way to do it I don't
think that's just because I have leg pain I should go now to the bar after this being here with you all and just
kind of you know you know crank away my pain you know that I don't
recommend that but uh but you know so what's healthy
what's the health so so discomfort one of the things that's powerful for
this investigation and I think phenomenal is to begin appreciating the
difference between an event here discomfort but it could be any
event we have and our relationship to it and we're beginning now to question and
look at that relationship and clarify it some people it's called purify it
simplify it free it so that we're not caught
in the grip of that relationship and I caught in the grip of aversion and desire and all kinds of other things
that they're kind of driving us kind of they're they're controlling us rather than we controlling our inner life
make some sense so that's just that it's been fantastic so then we go to a deeper layer in this
study and we start looking at what can be called emotional pain
is all emotional pain suffering the Buddhist idea of dukkha or as emotional pain some of it is the
Suffering The Buddhists end and some emotional pain just comes with human life you have to answer that question for
yourself how do you answer that question one of the ways is to look at your
relationship to emotional pain that's a kind of discomfort too right and so the what you learn to do with
like physical discomfort or ordinary discomfort now is addressed in this emotional pain
and you start seeing well I hate it I really want to feel some other kind of
Happy Feeling in them chasing that I feel shame you know I somehow I'm in
Buddhist for a while now and I thought Buddhists were supposed to be always equanimous and peaceful and cooled and
chilled and and here I am kind of you know feeling a lot of agitation and and
I guess I'm an embarrassment to the Buddhist world and uh so so that's that's a
relationship an attitude that we have to what's happening and we start seeing all
these layers of unnecessary judgments unnecessary interpretations that are causing us distress or
undermining us or discouraging us or something and so at the same study we did with
discomfort it can be done in relationship to emotional pain and they're also the same lesson we can
learn to be comfortable with emotional pain we can just be peaceful with it and then
we can study it more deeply and lo and behold one of the things
you'll probably discover is that some of your emotional pain
comes from some deep react deeper reactivity some of the emotional pain you have
becomes because you're really attached to something clinging to something
and so for example if I mean I can be so simple thing for me
of wanting to get someplace on time because I wanted to go show up at IMC
and teach people how to be non-attached and just be relaxed with what is and not get caught up and but
there's a lot of traffic to get here and I'm going to be late and I got to get there right away and
it's important to get there right away and people get to sleep they'll all go away and no one will be here and I'll be
giving a talk about myself I have to get there you know teach them to be relaxed
and uh and so uh so there's frustration there's anger
at the traffic but I'm clinging to something I'm clinging to all kinds of things what it
means to be here and the clinging I'm just kind of clinging to the fear you're all go home if I don't show up in time
and so I if I'm mindful enough of what's happening for me they're in the traffic
feeling all hot and sweaty in a hurry so wait a minute Gil you're really attached to layers and
layers of things here do you have to stay attached yes the
lawyers of the Mind come up and say yes [Laughter]
but if I kind of can you know offer the counter arguments then I said no I don't have to be it
doesn't do me any good the traffic's not going to change and um and it's not going to help me to
be stressed and hold on to this attachment to be there on time and so then I begin letting go and relaxing and
I feel so much better so the anger with the traffic the distress around the traffic you start
seeing yes I'm relaxed enough about it but it might look more deeply at it there's a lot of attachments connected
to it and so to look and we find there's a lot
of things we hold on to a tight or we resist furiously no I'm not going to do that
things we hate things we want and if we do an honest look at it
we'll discover that sometimes in it in these emotions that we have these painful emotions
that we're attached to something inkling to something if you don't see the clinging if you
don't see the attachment then there's no attachment to let go of
maybe there are some emotional pains that are not supposed to be to end
you know when someone dies and we feel grief are we supposed to like now feel like we're a Buddhist failure
you know I read the news and I feel pain I feel heartbroken at some of the things
I read am I not supposed to feel that I kind of think I don't have one to live
in a universe where I don't feel sad or feel grief or feel heartbroken
over some of the things that I see happens in the world it feels completely appropriate to feel
that but I don't think it's born from attachment for me I don't think it's some clinging
to something or resisting something it just kind of comes through me but it doesn't get stuck there
it just kind of I feel it fully and clearly and sometimes I've read news in the
paper and started crying that you know I I don't I have no idea I know I have no
thought that I'm not supposed to feel that and feel that pain but if I stop and take a deeper look
I might see yeah in the corners of that there's something I'm attached to and
clinging to but in the heart of it no it just seems very very simple and clear
there's no one nope nothing and so I just let it be there
and I don't add layers of suffering on top of it like I'm not supposed to be this way or as opposed to like get rid
of it quickly grief is supposed to be you know after all it's been 30 minutes now
and so I should be finished with my grief you know
so we have all these attitudes that we add on top and so we're learning more and more at
these attitudes and simplifying and simplifying and that we discovered well some things
I don't see any attachments in this emotional pain and I've learned how to be at ease with
that I've learned not to add anything on top of it this we're comfortable with discomfort
comfortable with feeling emotional pain this is a phenomenal gift we can give to
the world because it means that you can be a friend to someone who is in pain emotional pain you can share in that
pain even but your your own distress you're not distressed you're not upset
you're not attached you're not getting Afraid on top of the Heartbreak
you're able to be there in a full honest clear way to offer accompaniment and
companionship and and a safe kind of listening ear a safe kind of
companionship with someone which is a phenomenal gift to give
people who are in pain let's go for a walk together you know I'm you know and I'm willing to
feel uncomfortable it's okay I know how to do this and I'm just here with it then we'll just breathe and be with it
together and I'm not trying to fix anything I'm not trying to fix you I'm not trying to fix myself
some people who are compassionate caregivers supposedly they think they
are are really trying to avoid being uncomfortable themselves
they're so uncomfortable with the discomfort in the world that they're trying to get everyone fixed and good so
they don't have to feel they don't have discomfort and I think that leads to often kind of unhealthy Behavior
and so this ability to feel our emotional pain separate out what is an extra the layers
of reactivity the layers of attachment and clinging attitudes and beliefs and
so it's simple simple simple and then be able to go through the world and be with ourselves I think as a gift
so the third layer I want to talk about is the layer of Me Myself and mine
so as we're looking at suffering as we turn towards a door of suffering and start going through it
some of that suffering is happening to me thank you
it's my suffering and uh and the attachment itself the
ideations around self of course it's a you know certain pain
like this pain in my knee I'm it's happening to me there's no question about it
but it's also I'm the ideation that this is my suffering I'm suffering I feel so
sorry for myself 50 years of meditation pains and you know enough is enough and
you know I feel so sorry for myself and I deserve a break I deserve going to Hawaii
having a vacation and I deserve something better and and now we're now we're entering this
this world of Me Myself and mine how I think about this and how I think the
impact is on me and what I need and stuff and some of it some of that's innocent I mean earlier on I said I'll
consider this pain and consider whether I need to change my posture that's use of the word I is kind of
innocent and simple but oh poor Gill
and I hope I can really let you know how horrible and terrible it is that I'm suffering so much with my legs so that
you'll feel sorry for me and that'll be great will have a gill feeling sorry Fest
as if that's going to help anyone right so this eye thing gets can get really activated
so I want to suggest a little exercise and you're all sitting here I think and
you're all sitting either in chairs or zafu's on the cushions on the floor
and uh if you're not one person is leaning against a wall so the wall is there
and uh so um
say you have to go maybe to the bathroom so you get up happily go to the bathroom and come back five minutes later
and someone is sitting in your place
that was my chair that was my cushion that you took from
you know one of our cushions here you didn't bring with you so what are they doing sitting on my cushion
if you hadn't gone to the bathroom and just stayed here to the end and went home and came back next week you would
have no memory which Christian which chair was yours it wouldn't you wouldn't have that kind of idea as soon as you
leave it's not yours anymore the idea that it's your chair your
cushion your spot that does not exist in the natural world by itself out there
that belongs to what I call the ecosphere
or the eye sphere the me swear the that that is it kind of invisible
like that chair that's empty now sitting next to Lydia right so someone sat there
once upon a time I don't have any clue who sat there
any clue who saw it that's my chair they didn't engrave their name and
decide you know so we know it's their chair it belongs to the world of mentality and
thoughts and ideas what what are what are the what is that world what is the ego sphere of thoughts
and ideas and ideations that creates this Me Myself and mine
you know it doesn't it doesn't have a weight does it have color does it have shape
is it the shape of the chair it's um you know it's a it's an unusual world
that's kind of invisible to everyone else if all of us went home today
with different because we took all our shoes off right for everyone who took their shoes off went home with different
shoes than they came with your shoes won't care
this uh the shoes you know unless you wrote your name on
it but even then you know the shoes don't have any idea that they belong to you
or you belong to them who belongs to who right and so these
shoes don't have that idea that idea but boy if you leave here now and your
shoes not on the rack when you leave someone took my shoes
yeah or you could say yeah oh the shoes I came with they're not here now
oh well I got to figure out what to do now oh some other other ones there it happened to me once many years ago I had
Birkenstocks my birth stocks were not the burger stars I came with were not there
oh but there's another pair and it's the same size
and it's newer
and so the next week I became back to IMC and and discovered there was a actually a three-way exchange for
Birkenstocks that happened and um
so um so again this things that things belong to us
is somewhat arbitrary it's somewhat an ideation an idea that's imposed on
things but that imposition of ownership
does not belong in the natural world out there it belongs to this ego sphere this
thought sphere ideation sphere that we kind of are swimming in
and we're swimming in it as a society and we support it we we you know and there's even laws
that support the ownership of property and ownership of things and so it has a kind of very strong
pressure and and kind of a orientation that's intense
designate does that make it true the fact that it's legally true
I mean these lands that we live on they said you know we're now we're appreciating more and more that many of us here in the United States are living
on land they were stolen from people and the fact that it was stolen from them uh in horrible ways sometimes
genocide and and uh
the fact that I bought the property that I'm living on does that mean that really it's mine
given that it's stolen property to begin with to descendants of the indigenous people
still have a claim could they have a claim what happens if an indigenous family came to the property that I own
say you know my proper my family lived here for Generations
and so we have a relationship to this land would I say well this is my property I'm
going to pop it I'm going to put up a bigger fence now to keep you out is that the right thing to do if for
someone like that what's their relationship to the land we bought this house actually a little
sad story up here many years ago and in the basement they they left this huge
ancient desk which was kind of like you know wooden desk it was big wide with big drawers
and it was kind of a classic from the 1920s or something and um I kind of liked it but the top of
it was completely warped so I put a new top on it took a long time to figure out how to do
it and then some years ago someone came to our house and said you
know my grandparents lived here before you you know some you know in the 50s and 60s and 70s and we used to come
visit all the time and we just wanted to see it it's a great come and look and looked
around and showed them basements oh that's the desk it's really big so no one ever the
different owners over the years never took it out because it's kind of hard to get out I said would you like it
say oh yes you know belong to their family at one point had emotional connections so so
the ownership and what belongs to who and did it belong to me it was just left
there I guess legally it would be but does it really so ownership
and then we have identity and identity is a Hot Topic it's so hot topic these days I feel like I shouldn't even use
the word as soon as I say the word identity I'm gonna upset someone
um but it's a difficult topic right and uh but it's a very important one to
address and to look at in our society these days but the issue of identity is also complicated
and and you know for example my identity as a teacher
is that complicated or should I be complicated or easy for me if I go home with the identity of a
teacher it's a problem
it seems to work okay here [Laughter]
and until the identity of being a teacher becomes my my value as a human being is
dependent on that identity and what everybody else thinks about me in that identity and now we're getting into
dangerous territory and now I'm gonna have to give a talk that's brilliant
you know how the pressure is on and all kinds of things right so so we're talking about an invisible
world that belongs to this world of the
thought sphere that you most people can't see exactly from for yourself
what we identify some of the things we identify with some of the things we take as mine some of the ways we Define
ourselves ideas of ownership
and I I do this sometimes I find it meaningful I don't know if it will be meaningful for you
but just look around the room the ceiling the walls the lights and just
look around and where do you find me in it
where's I and all that where's mine and all that
probably it's not there has any of you had this I thought that
this the chandeliers are mine or I'm the chandeliers
just it's just lights it's just walls it's just you know free of that sense of self
and to turn that kind of attention inward to what degree can you turn it Inward
and have the same kind of experience where you're looking at parts of yourself inside experiences and you see
no that's not me that's just phenomenon that's those things happening
you know a exercise I've done many times is maybe it doesn't work so much now
anymore so long ago this song but maybe you know I'm going to have a thought
arise in your in your mind that you didn't put there you didn't
want to have you're going to try to resist me don't have this thought and as this thought arises is this
thought you is this Define who you are or is that me
making this thought or is it what is it that's it's your brain but is this make
sense to call this Me Myself and mine it just conditions come together
the hills are alive with the sound of
at least some of you a certain age probably couldn't help for your mind to
to finish that sentence and um and so to have that thought is
that you you know does it quite make sense to claim that that's you it's just you know
it's just a response the brain has to me saying something
so you have the wind brushes against your cheek
is that experience of sensation to his cheek is the sensations itself Me Myself
and mine it's happening to you do you want to clean up claim ownership of it do you
want to Define Yourself by that sensation do you cause the sensation did you orchestrate it and design it
it just it kind of no that's not me and what we learn in Buddhist Meditation
is to begin questioning and looking deeper and deeper around these ideation
this this eye sphere the ideation sphere that we swim in and begin seeing how
much of it we don't have to do and we can quiet that the thinking mind
that creates Me Myself and mine is a little bit of a wind drag or very
much a wind drag for the mind and as we slow down and quiet We Begin
letting go of the wind drag and and it can be Blissful and beautiful
peaceful to because so much of this Me Myself and mine comes with attachment
comes with resistance comes with tightening up comes it's also the me
myself and my thoughts that we have are one of some of the primary kind of
inner idiations we have that's a source of our reactivity when we react automatically habitually
for or against things it has a lot to do with this identification with self
that exists within us and we start seeing how much is not part of the natural world but part of our ideations
and thoughts and ideas and we see that really clearly in meditation because
it requires processing activity in the brain
to have these thoughts and as the mind gets calmer and calmer and calmer we start we do less and less
this thinking this way and we get calm enough we see that if I start thinking
that those Birkenstocks out in the Shelf are my Birkenstocks just that thought itself
he's like that's agitate my nails gotten agitated it's true enough
with my thoughts my why would I want to agitate my mind when I'm so peaceful let's not have any more Birkenstock
thoughts in meditation you know I can do that later
and so but with that example is in so many different ways we start seeing
clearly I don't have to think this way maybe it's okay a way to think for later
and then it becomes a really kind of a revolutionary thing to experience ourselves
without this eye sphere this ideation sphere operating
so the topic of today is how to study your suffering the vantage point of studying or
suffering without the ideation of self is a radical revolutionary change
because there's a whole layers of reactivity of emotional pain
that belonged to that ideation Around Me Myself and mine
and if you can really see that that changes the whole understanding of what
emotional pain this is the ordinary part of human life and what is unnecessary
and a lot of people will want to justify their emotional pain because it's just
natural this is part of life but it's not really that natural because you see it's part of the
reactivity around this created construct of Me Myself and mine
that's been constructed with the help of our society our family our life experiences how we've been treated by
people by our our desires and wants and
advertisements all kinds of things that build together and it feels so natural to be yourself
that it's very hard to see how much your I your whole sense of self is a construct
that's been built up over a lifetime and there's very few things that can help you kind of break through that
meditation is one of them and I think meditation is another one is
psychedelics you know which we're not supposed to encourage here
and I think meditation is more powerful in the long term
so I said I made that the p word the
I lived for in the biggest psychedelic hippie commune in the country back in
the early 70s but they they decided because of legal issues to stop using psychedelics and so
they wanted to find the next best thing and the next best thing was honesty
and that's why I stayed with them I'd never been around people who were so honest I was so inspired by it
so anyway so honesty meditation other things to really see clearly what's
going on here so suffering in the end of suffering
it's for you to discover what suffering you can end but suffering is always a door to go
through and to have confidence and skill and to build up the capacity
to be willing to stop and look at sufferings stop and take it go through
that door it's really worthwhile to go through that door because one way or the other you can get
to the other side and what that other side should look like no one can tell you
it's not supposed to be floating in the clouds it's going to be your own your own way
and so really no one can answer these questions
except yourself through your that's why mindfulness and deeper looking is really so important
and I hope you do answer those questions for yourself and now you probably answer the questions differently
over time and if you really kind of get a handle
in this whole eye sphere ideation sphere that we live under you probably answer the questions
differently than you do before you really address this part of your life
so I hope that you are inspired to do this work I hope you
come to a time where you enjoy doing it you're delighted it it inspires you it's like such a wonderful thing to
have the Good Fortune to have a practice and a means to really step into this I
think of his way of stepping into being fully human if we're running away from our disc pain
and discomfort or suffering we're actually
shutting off or shutting down part of our full Humanity step in through that door of suffering
and you'll be much happier
thank you