Hello friends hello and welcome to happy hour high and if the audio is
okay please give me a thumbs up quick thumbs up fantastic great
so let's begin as we always do with um saying hello welcoming ourselves each
other with with a sense of meta in the space and I begin by saying hi welcome
I'm Nikki I'm in Mountain View California on seated Ohlone Island who
is here foreign
Santa Cruz healing Santa Cruz that just surprises me when you say that so used to Nearly
New Hampshire I'm sure Welcome to California
down in DC and I'm envious of Santa Cruz and you're what
envious of California hello Don and DC
who's working on having mudita for people who are in Santa Cruz how's that
reframing Don foreign
from Thailand who says hello it's 360 Degrees meta lovely
and high carry as well anybody else wants to say hi
hi I'm Jill I'm in Redwood City and it's my first time joining your happy hour uh
Nikki and I want to say thank you so much for your teaching this week at the 7 A.M it's been absolutely
refreshing and delightful and thought provoking all the right cocktail items
so thank you so much oh thank you so much Jill thank you for your kind words thank you for your practice and thanks
for joining happy hour welcome warm welcome to you thank you yay beautiful
delighted you're here and Lich says hi from Oakland highlish
long time no see hope you've been well hi Sarah from Flagstaff and yeah and more more folks also
joining us on YouTube this is sweet very sweet well my heart feels warm to see
old and new friends um and uh let's let's begin let's
practice together thank you Neil for posting information about happy our Google groups in chat
and at this point I changed some settings I uh change um muting so that
accidental unmuting will be possible and I change the chat settings so that
they only come to me but I ask that we keep the chat quiet because it can be
quite distracting for me to receive chats while I'm teaching but I will open that afterwards
and last but not least I'm going to turn on recording for the sake of Audio
Dharma here we go great so hello hello and
welcome to happy hour everyone lovely to be with you
so for today's practice I wanted to invite us to explore
um expansion the the practice of of Good Will and
compassion for all beings um I
uh was uh teaching the 7 A.M as jail earlier mentioned uh I was subbing for
Gail this morning and for the 7 A.M and and um the topic was compassion and this
morning I taught uh compassion 360 degrees for all beings everywhere including ourselves and others and I've
been practicing it the rest of the day as I've been walking around seeing people just and uh this the the sense of
spreading my my meta my compassion to others to to random people and beings
that I see and it's been so uplifting so happy making uh so expansive in my heart
to be practicing that during the day but I wanted to bring that into happy hour
as well for us to practice together that uplift that Joy of this expansion of the
heart now just in our formal practice on the question but also in our daily life
I did find myself I was walking and I was thinking about what I had to do and
and in my own world this and that I'm like wait wait wait a minute sweetie let's let's practice let's practice
compassion for this passerby and I just found myself smiling at them and they smiled back it
was just so uplifting so what what a great way to um
to cultivate to cultivate our hearts our minds to have more space more space
instead of being in our own little world of concerns and and uh and challenges so
so with that as the preview Let's uh let's practice together let's practice
so so Landing in this body Landing
in whatever posture is most supportive In This Moment In Time
and inviting the breath inviting the breath to be like the
spring Breeze to fill our lungs
be received
by our body by the lower part of the body if possible
it's a way to settle into the body and connect
perhaps even feeling the breath move through our legs our feet
foreign
inspired imagination but you know the breath is moving through all our limbs
the oxygen is through our blood so it's not so far
this breath is moving through our lips
keeping us alive oxygenated foreign
yourself to put down to put down any worries concerns
stories in this moment and inviting ourselves to give our hearts to this practice in this moment
all the thoughts will still be there later right now just giving our hearts to this
releasing any tightness holding in the body any tightness or holding in the heart
and the limbs
with each breath feeling more present more fully here
fully connected to this breath
in the body
you're now inviting ourselves as we continue to feel our bodies and body
feel as if we are sitting
in a circle in a network of care a network of interconnection of care
that we are a part of we may not see it we may not acknowledge
at every moment and it's like the air we breathe
and let the breathing of this air let breathing not be effortful
it's not so much that you're breathing it's automatically happening
I mean you just Witness that this body is partaking
in the nourishment that is available on this planet on this Earth
is oxygen
and as if we feel we invite ourselves to sense
this sense of support seen and unseen
from people we know we don't know past present future
feeling ourselves supported cared for
by the air we breathe
by the food we eat right the shelter we have
and all the beings all the beings whose lives
we are interconnected with and support
our well-being
and as we breathe in as we feel the sense of care
foreign let us join our own care
for this being who is me
may I be safe
from inner and outer heart knowing that complete safety is not possible but it's a wish it's a blessing
we offer ourselves an act of Goodwill may I be safe
may I be happy I have joy in my heart
may I be healthy and strong as much as possible
and may my life flow with ease
and if there are any challenges right now in our body in our life
foreign these difficulties challenges
to be met with kindness now that we're judgment or pushed away
but with kindness may I have ease as I meet the challenges of my life
may I have peace in my heart
so I work through difficulty what is difficult for me
may I have all the resources I need
all the support with this challenge may I have ease
and may I be free from sorrow I'm suffering
foreign
and if you like you can experiment with opening your
heart to other beings who share this planet
with you
all of us together on this Earth together
just as I want to be happy not suffer
these other beings the humans
animals four-legged fish
Birds insects Etc they too just want to live happily
with ease
as if you're letting your your heart your Good Will Shine
not effortfully but it's already there it's already being received
through this network of support it's being shared this Goodwill
pouring in pouring out we are part of this network we're not separate
we are supported and we offer support
ing all beings everywhere foreign
as much as possible knowing that absolute safety is not
possible in this world but it's a wish it's a blessings it's kind
[Music] wish that we offer
to cultivate our own hearts
may all beings have safety foreign
s be happy
may all beings be healthy
they are being savings take care of themselves happily
and acknowledging that for all beings life is not easy there are challenges
Being Human is as its own challenges with our
incessant thinking and demands and also being an animal being living on
this Earth We're All impacted the changes
to our planet
so as we acknowledge challenges of living on this planet
as a sentient being letting our hearts meet
the challenges the suffering with Goodwill with kindness
with compassion
may all of us all beings on this planet
may we have peace and ease may we have the resources and support we need
foreign to live happily to meet our challenges
may we all be free from sorrow and suffering
may all beings including myself be well
compassion 360 degrees foreign
no part left out
all around and through this being owes me
foreign
radiating from your heart in your heart center middle of your
chest is this goodness kindness good well friendliness flows
out Shines on its own not effortful
every being it touches it brings care sucker kindness
good will foreign
it touches you first shining out of your own heart
perhaps imagining yourself walking around
walking by people you don't know Neighbors passerbys
sharing your good will
them just like me they want to be happy just like me they suffer
they they have ease may they be happy
maybe you walk by a bird it's not easy having a body
constantly looking for food safety shelter
may you have ease dear bird
etc etc
you can hear the sound of the ambulance it's driving by
it signifies that somebody is having a difficult time
may they have ease may this being who right now
is having a difficult time
may they have peace ease as they made this challenge
may they be free from suffering foreign
hurting they may be afraid or in danger
wishing them well
foreign
to bring the
meditation to a close
acknowledging that all of us share this planet
and there are challenges in living in this planet foreign
and acknowledging that living our lives with a heart that has good will and kindness
spreads radiates kindness Goodwill compassion 360 degrees
it's a much more spacious uplifting happier way to live
to serve to be on this planet
so appreciating ourselves for having showed up in this practice as best as we're able
to
and without any judgment or attachment to what could have been or
wasn't letting go of attachment to outcome
trusting that we are planting seeds of kindness Goodwill
and they will flourish in their own time
and sharing our goodness our co-created goodness with all beings everywhere
may all beings everywhere be well
may all beings everywhere be free including ourselves
foreign [Music]
thank you for your practice
such a rich practice such a rich practice to
cultivate our hearts and expansion and kindness in Goodwill
for all beings everywhere not just for ourselves but for others it's so expensive
so uplifting so spacious happy making
and however much it was available to you however much it was available to you let
that be enough let that be oh yes ah what a relief
how lovely so as we do and happier at this time we
turn to practicing with our eyes closed on the cushioned
practicing together in community and the invitation for the small groups
roughly of size three the breakout rooms
is of course showing up with um with kindness with kindness humility for
ourselves for others kindness and compassion and just sharing from our own
experience of course we can just say pass when our turn comes in which case
we'll just be sharing silent um presence kind presence but it's a
really wonderful opportunity to take our practice from the cushion to daily life
this is a Sandbox It's a Wonderful sandbox to be able to experiment with so
the prompt is what arises for you what what do you note when you when you have
compassion when you have good will matter and compassion with it both tonight
for all beings for other beings what would arises maybe share one nugget from
your practice if you wish and and it's perfectly fine to say actually I uh just
I was completely distracted or fell asleep it's okay there's no wrong answer it's not a quiz it's just to show up
with kindness and support each other and please only share from your own practice
no asking questions no giving advice to others and if you notice somebody's
doing that it's okay to say hey we're not supposed to ask questions or give advice just
keep the container light and as safe as possible for one another
so be kind enjoy um interacting with one another being
inspired with one another and again remember that you're sharing for your own benefit to be held witness you're
not sharing to impress anyone or educate anyone it's just
sharing in community this is what came up for me or maybe nothing came up and it's perfectly fine
so I'm making the breakout rooms take care of yourselves take care of each
other be kind be kind be kind here we go
welcome back everyone the rooms are closed and we have time for Reflections
for questions um and chat is open you're welcome to
type in chat it could be either to everyone or it could be privately to me in which case I'll only read the
reflection that your um name and if you haven't shared for a
while you're welcome to raise your hand and and share your reflection question
challenge why did you notice with this practice
oh Neil says lovely practice for Earth days Eve oh thanks Neil yeah
I was thinking that tomorrow's Earth Day exactly
yes all of us all of us together living on this Earth
our home our home
any any other Reflections how was it did it feel uplifting to be practicing
kindness or compassion for other beings all beings I see some nods
anyone care to comment or was it challenging that's fine too it's all
okay okay now I'm gonna open it up to those
who have spoken recently as well as those who haven't
read these
well thanks Nikki um so it's always better to do this than
not and it it doesn't have to be terribly powerful for me in in the
instant of the experience the experience is recognizable as being
positive and it may sweep out the
[Music] debris of of thoughts that aren't very very useful
but I feel with increasing confidence that it's
uh it's it's worth it's always worth doing and uh the
the impact maybe later uh or it may be accumulative
it just doesn't need to be fireworks all the time
thanks Fred well said all the points you made doesn't have to be fireworks it
feels always feels better than not and it is accumulative and it is ripens
later all the wonderful points you made very wisely absolutely
um yes yes and yes thank you for making them thank thank you
he who says love for all is a two-way street the more we love the world the
more love the world pours into US yes that's how it feels doesn't it it feels
like when we meet the moment with kindness um then it's it's basically our
perception that the world becomes kind to us that we see more kindness in the
world we see more compassion in the world and if we see fear and danger and
threat always that's what we'll perceive as what our mind will pick up
foreign an anonymous sharer thank you Nikki I
made a mistake today where I mixed up two people I spent a lot of the day trying to recover from shame thanks for
the reminder that sending compassion towards outwards means the compassion is
touching me too I appreciate it thank you for that reflection beautiful and
yeah things we make mistakes and and our compassion always it's 360 Degrees
touches us first beautiful thank you for their reflection Ellie I
see your hand please yeah on the Gratitude and Nikki thank
you that's the same thing kind of like happened with the chat that you read to me today actually around lunchtime I was
making lunch I was hurrying up and then you know I had two things in there and then suddenly your voice came to me oh
oh something like that oh I can see you're having a hard time sweetheart it's okay it's okay something like that
that I mean I was calling myself and then uh oh I hear you or something like so that you were talking about before
and then I just like calmed down and and then the things flew okay I don't know Wednesday uh
actually something that you had mentioned I had question about the wisdom and then you said without it
it'll be a bumpy road uh without incorporating the loving kindness aspect of the bird into wisdom
aspect only and that is that it that that I was just kind of like reflecting on that so I just wanted to thank you
for those two reminders for me but on Wednesday and just today that it's just
like uh your voice uh you know in happy hour arose in me I saw that I mean the
moment of uh rushing panic hmm oh sweet thank you Ellie thank you
so much for sharing that yeah it's it's not the first time that practitioners tell me that my voice jumps up and they
call themselves sweetheart or dear you know whatever I bring in into the guided meditation like well sweetheart you're
having a hard time you're stressed ah it's okay it's it's the mind
um bringing in reminders wholesome reminders so yeah I I celebrate I'm I'm glad that really this to your own
practice really it's your own practice it's your own mind it's your own heart that's supporting you and and it's it's
taking this way and yes without kindness wisdom alone is pretty bumpy it's um
Joseph Goldstein likes to say that um writing um it's like riding a bicycle without
air in the tires wisdom without kindness It's a pretty bumpy ride you want to put
air in your tires definitely and so kindness meta compassion all of these
practices put air in our tires so so thank you all may you have air in
your tires as you as you travel this this Earth as we all travel this Earth
may all beings everywhere on this planet and Beyond may we all be well may we all
have all the resources we need to face the challenges we have on this Earth male may we all be well
foreign [Music]
take good care be well I won't be here next week I'm teaching a
retreat at IRC I'll see some of you there so take good care be well
the recording I'll stop the live stream and now it's just us on Youtube yay
calorie review I get to see you and I get to thank you and ask you if you wish
to unmute yourself for Our Kind spreading compassion kindness to one
another and saying goodbye blessing each other with our goodbyes take care
goodbye everyone bye-bye thank you bye-bye have a good weekend thank you thank you thank you everyone good night
thank you good night
in the night take care bye