good morning and so thank you Martha and thank you
Jill for all your help with these potlucks path I feel are important part of our community life those of you like
to share in the community life of IMC staying and being hanging out for those are wonderful
way so as I think some of you know
that uh ever since the Hamas invasion of uh Israel I think my public talks
have been a response to that in some way or other and um and I'll continue that
today but I'd like to do maybe a preface to it all that maybe is important to
understand that I do so as a Buddhist teacher grounded in Buddhist values as I
understand them and as someone who doesn't live with the
urgency of uh violence that's happening in the
present lethal violence that's happening in the present if I was living with that
urgency I would probably if I was teaching at all I
would teach maybe differently and um
and coming here to speak about this today I become certainly alarmed by
what's happening in the Middle East but I'm also alarmed by how divisiveness is
spreading around the globe and that people who were friends
or just kind of neutral with each other now are seen as enemies because of the strong divide
between opinions and who's right and who's wrong and
who's from my side and who's if you're not from my side then clearly you're against my
side and so it's uh to not take sides is often seen as by one both
parties as taking sides for the other side and it can be um difficult to speak
up and uh and offer an opinion of you which is not
what people would like to hear but then uh maybe gives birth to more
divisiveness more anger so I I'll start with a clear kind
of Buddhist grounding in this kind of topic of violence and quarrels and disputes and then uh say a few things
that are directly concerns what's happening in the Middle East and then we'll see what happens
then so uh I'll begin with what for me is
uh one of the very valued most important top five maybe teachings from the
Buddha and maybe I don't want to put those top five in the hierarchy what's one's the highest the most important but
this is like for me one some one of the most important teachings that that I inspired by and live my life by
it concerns who is a wise person a wise person of great
wisdom does not intend for one's own Affliction or for the Affliction of
others or for the Affliction of both self and
others rather a wise person thinks only for one's own
welfare the welfare of others the welfare of both and the welfare of the
whole world in this way it is in this way that a wise person is of great
wisdom so there's wisdom and there's great wisdom and um and uh this week in my
morning teaching I I talked about the Buddhist teaching about what's beautiful and what's more
beautiful than beautiful and what beautiful is living an ethical life what's more beautiful is
encouraging prompting others to live an ethical life of not killing not
stealing and um and so here's a call that we want to live in a world actively
we want to live in the world responding to it but from a Buddhist point of view
it's not one that is going to set up more divisiveness but but it is one that
wants to address the unethical issues of our of our world not be silent but and
not not demonize anyone but figure out this very difficult task seemingly
impossible task to promote to help others um
uh live an ethical life which from a Buddhist point of view is how we can
live the best life the greatest good comes from all for
ourselves when we live an ethical life that from the Buddhist point of view is actually
impeccable the standard of the Buddha is very high of how much we're going to
live a life that doesn't cause harm whether we think that that's unreasonable and that's the question we
all have to face but this one here that one lives concerned for the welfare of
everyone we ourselves are not excluded sometimes with the teachings of
Altru altruism you're supposed to kind of sacrifice yourself for the benefit of others there's no such idea in
Buddhism we're we're as important as anybody else our welfare in fact our
welfare sometimes emphasized in Buddha in Buddhism as a Paramount thing that we
should be concerned with because when we're really well then we're in the best position to
support other people to be well if we're if we're spiritually ill sick or
underdeveloped or something we have so much less to be able to support and help and recognize and encourage for
others but it's not limited to self then it's maybe selfish and uh but also be concerned for
the welfare of others and then this wonderful uh concept concern for the
welf of both and for me that concern for the welfare of the both has to do with
um uh who we are as a community the US and then for the welfare for the
whole world and it's a a life that thinks thinks it's possible to look for
the greatest good for everyone involved and that is not an easy thing to
do and uh and one of the places that I've been involved where that was a challenge was uh I was a i chaired an e
Ethics Committee for about 15 years where I had to I was the primary
responder to all kinds of ethical complaints where you know there was a
whole range of things that that was were came but there was usually a conflict
between two people and now there was one that someone the complainer and then there
was a person who they were complaining about the victim and the perpetrator
occasionally we might be appropriate in some people's
vocabulary and uh and the approach that I took was how do I how do we find given
what happened not denying if something bad happened une ethical happened not denying it not not kind of papering over
it but how do we address all the issues here that need to be addressed
and consider what's the greatest good for everybody involved and for people who are the
victim that was a hard thing to hear sometimes and so part of the discussions
was to help the the person who was the victim to understand that this was
possible that that we were concerned about the victim's greatest good really want to take care of that person but
there was no need to ignore the well-being of the the person who had the problem in fact taking care of them took
care of the whole situation better and um and sometimes for the the
person who was complained with against the um uh we had to sometimes
convince them that they had to they had to it was very important for them to
live with a uh with that there was consequences they had to live by so they had to be changed they had to go through
some kind of process of something uh and and that sometimes they
protested well this is ridiculous you know I don't need to do this or this is not right but we we convince them that
yes maybe that's true but the whole needs you to do
that and so the greater good comes from this and it's not really very harmful
for you it just takes time and um and uh and so then and so
usually what happened um with this process when it went well and somehow
didn't get interrupted in the middle or something um everyone came out
happy and uh and even more important was that the wider community that I was
supporting began to trust the Ethics Committee that when the Ethics Committee
called them up and said you know I'm calling from the Ethics Committee
that rather than having their heart sink My Hope was that they would smile
oh great someone has the greater good for
me concerned and okay this is not maybe won't be all all easy but like this is going to be a good process to go through
conflict doesn't have to be a lost loss for everyone win loss kind of situation
it can be a win-win for everyone involved but it takes a lot more time to do
that so this this teaching here that the wise person someone considers the good
for everyone involved this to me is uh I think speaks to a heart that is not
going to live divisively a heart that's not going to see anyone as enemy but it's going to
see everyone with the goodness of our of our the best place in our heart in which we gave upon the
world and um and so I'll come back to that and then related to this is
um I don't know if it's a top five teachings of the Buddha but it's up
there pretty high for me and it's particularly valuable this time and I think I've read it this last couple of
weeks even hatred never ends through hatred
by non-hate alone does it end this is an ancient
[Music] truth sometimes this quote is read hatred never ends through hatred by Love
Alone does it end to me that's more inspiring non-h hatred to for me is more
attainable and um and so I'll settle for non-h
hatred the ancient language this word when you have this negative word non
non-h hatred it's it's often said it implies the positive and what's nice
about this is that the positive is a wider range than just love and so maybe love is not exactly
what's called for maybe generosity is called for something
else and then and then the same
discussion he AB oh this way they abused me attacked me defeated me robbed me for
those carrying on like this hatred does not end they abused me attacked me defeated
me robbed me for those not carrying on like this hatred
ends the people who have been abused attacked defeated
robbed can feel like they're Justified to hate in fact hate might seem as a
necessary means by which we're going to defend ourselves care for ourselves have
Justice in the world and I don't feel like I want to capable of when someone has been
harmed to want to argue that's not the case
that's that's too uncomfortable it feels almost disrespectful or putting salt in a wound which is quite
deep and he abused me you know hatred does
not end this way we have by criticizing others by
yelling at them and saying you know the idea here is not to say in some simple way I was abused I was attacked but it's
the blaming the attacking that this this quote is
criticizing and the final there's a four four verses here and the final one here
that's kind of I see as a set maybe it's supposed to get our
attention to change how we live Our Lives Many Many do not
realize we here Must
Die For Those Who realize this quarrels
end so I don't know how that strikes you and uh sometimes uh quarrels have
ended when realize that the blood of those who die is more
valuable than oil more valuable than a lot of things we're trying to
preserve so the bud addressed the issue of quarrels of disputes and for years I
read these teachings where he addresses it some of them um in
detail as I didn't quite they were kind of flat for me didn't kind of inspire me
in some way until recently and uh there's teachings where he uh talks about the conditions the
conditions that lead to quarrels and it's a layers of conditions where uh the
first layer sets the conditions in place for the next layer kind of a more activated layer and that sets the
conditions for more active activated layer kind of goes like until finally it were so activated we're fighting with
each other and um so the first one the gives
a five-part kind of conditions that or four parts that lead to corals and um uh the first first the to
those corals and the immediate pre condition for quarrels is a a word which
challenges a lot of people when they hear it so if you're challenged you're in good
company cherishing cherishing is a
condition now is cherishing a necessary condition for conflict is cherishing
wrong or bad we don't have to see it as wrong or bad but cherishing the the way
cherishing is done sometimes leads to all kinds of problems the uh the kind of
powerful representative example some of you might know is uh in The Lord of the
Rings Gollum cherishing the
ring his precious I mean if that's what cherishing is we're all in
trouble of course that's not how we all cherish maybe there's innocent harmless
cherishing of things but there's a way of Leaning into what we cherish we want to hold on to it we want to keep it to
ourselves we don't want to share it with anyone we want to there's attachment that comes and so when there's
attachment with cherishing then we're defensive then we're acquisit we have
avaricious all kinds of things happening but before corals There's Something That We're cherishing an
opinion a idea idea a thing a place possession
something um before cherishing the precondition for that is having some kind of Desire
here we go these Buddhists always making desire into a
problem it isn't that all desires are a problem but there has to be some desire
for us to want to cherish and some desires occasionally
some of us will accidentally have a problematic desire none of you of
course the precon precondition for desire is pleasantness and
unpleasantness to or liking and not liking is another way of translating it to have something we like and not like
um then we have desire for more of it or desire to have it or push it away or not
have it and is it wrong to do that no of course not but it's kind of has to be
there first in order for us to want to desire have a desire desire for something we like or desire for something we don't like to go away and
then for the Buddha the the of in this particular teaching the fourth the last thing
condition the bottom layer the first layer is simple sense contact just simply being in the world
going about your own business and having the wind against your skin seeing the clouds in the sky not today
you know and just tasting your food the most basic sense contact is there any
problem with that not necessarily but if you if it produces a
liking that we are attached to and the liking that we're attached to
produces desire for more of what we're attached to that that produces a a
cherishing which has attachment built into it and then what happen what's happening is that we're getting
increasingly activated there's more we more agitation there's more higher order thinking
processing wanting motivation operating in the mind all of which is kind of
increasingly stressful even though it might seem Pleasant all along and um and it's as we go along
also the focus of attention becomes narrower if you're just sitting quietly in
meditation for example and just allowing all the sense experiences to come and go
and move through you it can be deeply relaxing but as soon as you have
something that you like the liking of it the attention is a little bit more kind of now tightened up and focused on the
liking and if you and then if then you if you want more of it the attention
gets more focused around the desire and if you cherish it now you're even
more focused and tight around this thing and then if you get into a
dispute you know you can some of us are capable of getting into arguments and disputes and conflicts minding our own
business sitting meditating no one has to be around you
know and suddenly she said he said they said you know like oh you know how could it be that
way and I'm a little bit you know embarrassed to say that I've s sat in meditation and and made up conflict it
didn't exist you know that you know so someone said something they shouldn't have said
it and then I went and checked and they didn't say it and I was you know had just got all worked up right so this
this process is process of getting worked up and when I understood this about this list these lists of the
conditional Genesis of conflict then I got excited this is interesting because
if you can go backwards from a most activated State and relax and
progressively relax and go through these layers and come to the place where we're no longer activated no longer agitated
no longer contracted with our awareness come back to this place you
know here in this list sense contact that's not to disengage from the
world not to then you know away and just the Simplicity of sense contact but
something much more important can happen and that as once we
get maybe I maybe it's okay I hope it's okay to use this word once we get
diffused once we become disarmed totally disarmed in the mind from all the
conflict all the things that lead up to conflict then we have then it's possible
if we know how to access um a profound
place of knowing a profound place of understanding of thinking of contemplation a profound place of deep
feelings that can arise well up from within that are not feelings that are
reactive to what the world is coming at us with when we when we react to things
that's when we have anger and that's when we have hostility and that's when
our conceit gets afraid all kinds of things can happen there but there's a
the premise in Buddhism is that we have tremendous sources within of wisdom of
Love of care of har Harmony making
instincts to live in cooperation with others in the world not to
divide the world and that this comes from a profound place within that is not
in the reactive mode so when we go through this these lists of the Genesis of conflict and as a practitioners and
we're deactivating ourselves and come to in you like in meditation to a very simple place we're just here in the
present moment with our experience that's the place where we can
now ask ourselves from here how do I want to live how do I want to respond to
my friend who uh you know got angry with but I'm not angry now I'm settled the
issue hasn't gone away how do how can I address this so it involves the greater
good for both of us I'm hurt I'm afraid maybe my friend
is as well let's not make it worse is there some way we can talk something we
can do maybe we have to talk but before we talk maybe I'll send my friend a
gift and um I'll you know I'll bake some cookies or something and you know just
just do something that Bridges The Divide and then and you know that sometimes we can do
but so um so then we get to the difficult
topic of that I probably is not suited probably not
going to address the emotional needs of some of the people involved in this deep
deep issue in the Middle East and
um but what I've been how I've been orienting myself in reading this studying about
this is not to get fixated on Military
strategies and to read up about you know and consider all the kind of
military strategies of what needs to happen and why it needs to happen and what is a just war and all these kinds
of very painful things that um people are involved in but rather I've been focused on those
groups of people who are trying to look for the greatest good for everyone involved the
ones who are trying to not create more division but create cooperation create a
sense of unification of people who are normally divided and for this some people say
that it's very important to consider in the Middle East that
Hamas doesn't represent the all the Palestinians that the Israeli government
doesn't represent all Israelis all Jewish Israelis without if we make if we don't
make that distinction the level of divisiveness the level of blame that gets spread is
really difficult and so there are people who who are not doing this but are
actually coming together cooperatively from both sides and this is what excites
me so the one that I kind of got the most excited by is organization called
Sisterhood um it called uh Sisterhood of Shalom
Salam those are those the two words for peace in Arabic and in in uh Jew in
Hebrew um and they write in their website as a Sisterhood of Jewish and
Muslim women we hold multiple truths at any given moment it is possible for us to
acknowledge that murdering civilians is a war crime and firing missiles at
civilians is also a war crime it is possible for us to pray for the safe
release of the 150 Israeli captives when this was written and pray for the safety
of the besieged people of Gaza it is possible for us to recognize that
Palestinians are not Hamas and Israeli citizens are not their government it is
possible for us to grieve for our own dead and grieve for all those lost in
this horrible cycle of violence and be reminded that violence will always be
met with more violence
at the same time we have to choose compassion which literally means
suffering together and wishing to alleviate suffering we must have compassion for all those who lost their
family members all those those who are in
captivity and those seeking shelter from Heavy Artillery equally important it is the
feeling of compassion for each other and for our own tears shock pain and
fears we truly are all suffering together at this moment this is what it means to be human
this is what it means to possess moral Clarity it's a beautiful statement the
very uh there was a co-founder was a woman named Cheryl
olitzky I think she's a polish jew from what she writes but she in writing about
what inspired her to help start this organization that
talmud the the Hebrew Bible the talmood
asks or oral law who is a hero the an and
answers one who makes one's enemy into a friend isn't that something that's a
hero the rabbis communicated that it's possible to change people's attitudes and that it is desirable to
strive to do so then Cheryl wrote I knew I had to change
attitudes so this is what also Buddhism is doing so this Buddhist attitude that I'm trying to or teaching I'm trying to
offer here at IMC is not isolated to BU Buddhism this what what she's calling
from talmud is very similar and um one
who makes one's enemies into a friend what a great
thing and um the mission of this organization is
based on our shared values the mission of The Sisterhood of Salam Shalom is to
build relationships between Muslim and Jewish women of all ages to promote and
advocate for human rights and to end acts of hate for all human beings we
envision a world a world where Muslims and Jewish people live without hate and
where Freedom equality and social justice are within reach for all of
us there's two more organizations that I want to read about and another is a
organization in Israel called standing together is a Grassroots movement
mobilizing Jewish and Palestinian citizens of Israel in Pursuit Of Peace
equality and social and climate Justice while the minority who Ben this
is important while the minority who benefit from the status quo of occupation and economic inequality seek
to keep us divided we know that we the majority have far more in
common than that which sets us apart when we stand together we are strong
enough to fundamentally alter the existing sociopolitical reality the future that we want peace
and Independence for Israelis and Palestinians full equality for for all citizens and true social economic and
environmental justice is possible because where there is struggle
there is hope so I love that recognition that this takes work this is not an easy
thing to do and um but one of the things I I view I point of view point point out is
that as difficult as creating peace this way is I it's probably a lot cheaper than
all the money spent on arms does it take more time I think it
takes a lot more time than any given War much more
difficult but then it creates the conditions for a lasting peace War creates the condition for more
war and that takes a lot of time sometimes I've seen just in human
interactions over and over again that if we don't take time to sit down to work
out our differences our conflicts or all that that uh um it it festers and lasts
a long time but it's so inefficient people people are
inefficient and you know to sit down and talk and work it out and work out our differences it's such an inefficient
process I mean who has time for that we have a long to-do list but I've seen over and over again
that unless you take that time there's so much more processing that happens later and on and on and on so it turns
out to being inefficient sometimes is it the most efficient so the
struggle the last one I want to read is a interesting group in Israel called
combatants for peace founded in 2006 it is a nonprofit
volunteer organization of EX combatant israels and Palestinians men and women who have laid
down their weapons and rejected all means of violence we are working together to end
the occupation of Palestine bring Justice to the land and demonstrate that Israelis and Palestinians can work and
live together we are a group of Palestinians and Israelis who have taken an active
part in the cycle of violence in our region Israeli soldiers serving in the
Israeli Defense Force and Palestinians as combatants fighting to free their
country Palestine from the Israeli occupation we serving our people raised
weapons which we aimed at each other and saw each other only through gun s
sites we have established combatants for peace on the basis of
nonviolence nonviolence principles isn't that remarkable
at uh Mahatma Gandhi was uh uh most enthusiastic about former soldiers who
be joined his non-violent uh e efforts in India because he said being
nonviolent it takes a lot of strength a lot of Courage yet and the soldiers have
it sometimes and so I'm impressed by these so these are three organizations there's
other organizations who doing this kind of work I think for the most part these
kinds of efforts don't make the front page but I think they should I think
this should be championed and supported and and um and brought
forth so to be concerned for the greater good of everybody
involved to be able to find a way to process our own fear or own trauma our
own hurt our own anger in healthy appropriate ways to really bring out the
best in each of us and then to be able to be in a place to want to be in a place where we live
this life uh where we trying not to cause
harm to live non-violently trying to promote the welfare and happiness the well-being of
everyone that's the kind of world I'd like to live in and is it naive to do
so I don't [Laughter]
care if uh this is the way this is the way I want to live this is the world I
want to live in and I don't want to contribute to the opposite I want to contribute to this and uh
and I don't see for me there's any other choice so that was my effort to say a few
things and I both am a little bit reluctant but also feel maybe it's wise
to see if there's any comments or questions anybody has yes
please can you wait for the mic because otherwise I won't hear hold it like a rockar hold it like a rockstar okay then
um no I just was wondering if you could repeat the name of that second group so I could remember it oh yes the
the
um standing together thank you standing together there's an organization called Stand
Together that's in United States and then standing together is in
Israel yes yeah it happened to be yesterday I heard a mediator say something along these lines that you
reminded me of that uh when responding to someone who's angry she said um it
sounds like you really care about something yeah I want to know what you care about yeah for that's wonderful
yeah and then you kind of drop below and eventually maybe you find some really great values that you share with
them but the application of it maybe has gone
differently so thank you for listening thank you for being here I hope this was
close enough I mean I talking to a Buddhist audience or not Buddhist audience but an audience who came to a
Buddhist center to hear a Buddhist teacher so I feel like I have some permission to to do something unpopular
if that's the case so um so there is a potluck today everyone's welcome to stay
whether you're Brad Sumer think or not it's a wonderful way of being a community if you're willing to take a
couple of minut five minutes before the official ending if you would be willing to turn to you don't you can don't have
to if you don't want to but if you turn to um maybe a couple of people next to you so that everyone kind of look around
and see who's there around you so that no one's left alone and say hello and any thoughts about this talk or
something