Hello friends hello and welcome to happy hour and if you can hear me okay give me
a thumbs up audio is good fantastic great so uh I welcome you I'm Nikki in
Mountain View California unseated olone land and uh let's start with our ritual
of saying hello where we're zooming in from as a way of bringing our meta into
the space with our friend and just greetings hi take it
away PMA from Belmont hi PMA from Belmont Maryanne in Burling game hi
maranne Leslie in San Diego hi Leslie Jesse Cel hi
Jesse hi Susan and Claudia Susan from s
yes hi Susan and Claudia too and hi fosil from Illinois
Bill and Dallas hi Bill and Sarah from Toronto hi I see the hells in chat
they're coming in so sweet Neil in New Hampshire hi Neil Kim from Tofino hi
Kim our Canadian contingent and hi Joseph from Washington
State welcome anybody else wants to say hi hi
Ellie Ellie or Eli remind me from Vancouver unseated Coast Salish
lands uh such a thoughtful question it's it's Eli Eli thank you thank you Fred
and Barbara here in Oakland tonight hi Fred and
Barbara and hi Petro from Minneapolis and Karen from pettan Washington who say
hello in chat and hi Rosa who sends a warm Autumn greetings from New England who says hello joining
us from YouTube so we have YouTube and zoom friends at the same time and hi
Sandy from Western Washington ah the S sa has assembled I feel the warmth of Us
coming together so so let's uh let's formally begin so and this is a queue
for Neil to share information about happy our Google group groups in chat if
you're new to happy hour we have a um low trffic mailing list you're welcome
to join and there's also a document about how to um offer each other and um
your self- safety later when you we engage in small group breakout groups and at this T time I change some of the
settings or chat and more hellos are coming in on YouTube from uh Scotland
yay Night Owl greetings yes it's kind of late thank you for joining us may may it
be supportive to you the the meditation we'll do together in Pacific Northwest
and as well as Malaysia thanks for joining us John from Malaysia so we're definitely very International tonight so
many different time zones so take that in everyone for a moment how sweet that is a sense of yeah lots of practitioners
coming together from different places in the world so with that I will um start the
recording for the sake of Audio Dharma
and here we go great so hello and welcome everyone
welcome to happy hour this rendition of it in this moment in
time so so for tonight
um I'd like to invite us to to
uh yeah practice starting with starting from ourselves and
then um going outside internal external internal external
care um kindness compassion so this internal external movement of the
heart and [Music] um yeah maybe that's all I want to say
not and let's just lead into it get into it and practice so whatever you need
will be shared with you during the the uh this period so so let us begin let
us turn our awareness
into our posture our sitting posture assuming posture of integrity
and stability and if your body needs to move first if your limbs need to
move shoulders maybe need to be rolled back maybe shifting left and right to
find your seat the center of gravity so that you
really arve with a sense of presence not feeling
automatically not the automaticity of habit but you really
take stock of this moment of being
alive it's like this being
alive feeling your your feet the bottom of your feet on the earth if you're
sitting in a chair the bottom of your legs if you're sitting on the
cushion on the bottom of your sit bones your sit bones connecting to the chair
or the cushion taking your
seat taking time to land let's take our time to land
here
and connecting with the movement of the breath in the
abdomen INB breath the out breath entirety of the in
breath entirety of the out breath
allowing the body to relax can this body relax
soften
not feel so separate from the environment in which
it is [Music]
held letting this body This Heart In This
Moment be both grounded stable well
rooted connected to the
Earth and let it also feel expansive
appreciating the grace of this opportunity in this
moment to sit and breathe be breathed
the grace of this gift to be able to practice
together in community in this
moment the gift to be simple the gift to
be present
there are so many distractions so many things we could be doing there is
always fomo fear of missing out and
yet and we take Delight this gift and this grace
of being
simple the grace the joy of Simply being here exactly where
we are the moment expands feels
infinite breath feels
intimate
if thoughts are arising it's okay it's not a
sin our minds think it's okay so not Bering ourselves beating
ourselves up noticing what the thought is in this moment s thank
you and I release you smilingly without any guil or
[Music] shame smilingly I release this bird of
thought taking Refuge the Simplicity of this
moment with the breath with the body the Sens of care tending tending to this heart to
this body being
simple the nourishment of
stability
and now consider
same way that we can touch we can
feel a surface say a desk a chair the hardness
of it same way that we can
feel water can touch we can feel
so any way we can feel the air by its warmth its
coolness by the pressure atmosphere the
atmosphere put in our
bodies imagine what it feels like to feel to touch a
sense of
presence let it be a c not to be f out but as you ask this
question as you tune into it can I feel into can I touch my sense
of presence in this moment not tightening around it but with
curiosity dropping in the question with curiosity and relaxing notice if the sense of presence
becomes more palpable in an unexplainable way
don't
struggle tching into the sense of each breath and might take some time
after a few breaths being with a few breaths with the sense of presence
too become more into
Focus be more palpable presence in this
moment right now right
here my might be a feeling of uprightness sitting
more dignified inhabiting your body see what it feels like for
you to feel to touch sense of presence right here right
now embodied presence
and now however the sense of presence is showing up for you in this moment
however much it can be sensed in this body with this
breath now tuning into dropping in the question
can I become aware a sense of kind presence embodying a caring
presence and it might help if you perhaps conjure up someone you care about could be a child a
pet and feel into your sense of kind mind presence
for them maybe you're just sitting at their
bedside maybe they're not feeling well you're just holding silent kind
presence no words
needed
just sitting keeping watch
caringly or maybe you have a memory of having
held caring presence for
someone at their bedside if they were
hurt without words just holding
presence caring presence compassionate loving
presence
and now whatever you're Conjuring up whoever you're Conjuring up holding
presence for put a younger version of
yourself and perhaps this younger version of yourself not feeling so well
maybe sick or sad or
injured just holding patient caring loving presence for
yourself really feeling this
palpability of the stability groundedness of caring
presence
and now in this last step expanding expanding the holding of
this kind caring compassionate presence for the
world as if you're keeping vigil for the
world just as you and people you care about
out are deserving of your care your compassion so are all
beings so not turning away but holding
witness holding compassionate presence especially for beings who are suffering
right now
in areas of the world where there is
war famine hatred so many
challenges our fellow
humans
as if you're sitting by the bedside of humanity Humanity
hurting the bedside of
humanity pcking Humanity in
under a blanket of
care oh dear sisters brothers siblings on this Earth I wish you ease I
wish you
well I hold embodied caring
presence for all of
us
as we turn to bring this meditation to a close offering caring presence for
yourself kindness acceptance for whatever this
period was like without judgment
without wishing it to have been any different than it
was with gratitude with appreciation or having showed up as well as you were
able to and
offering goodness of our practice TR trusting there is goodness trusting there is co-created goodness here that
we've planted seeds of care kindness stability
presence embodied caring presence offering the goodness to all
beings everywhere may all beings be free from sorrow from suffering may all
beings be well including [Music]
ourselves [Music]
everyone so much for your practice so
we began with a sense of stability groundedness with the breath with the
body and then I invited you to tune into the idea of presence as if it were
palpable this palpable like water or or touching a
surface or touching the air palpability and I was hoping that by dropping this
in that there would be a sense of presence perhaps becoming more palpable
this embodied presence and I invited us to feel into caring embodied
presence the way you might have experienced it for a say a child or a
parent or a friend sitting at their bad side with care this of presence and then
substituting yourself on that bed so a way of
invoking kindness and compassion for ourselves and then bringing humanity and all of
humanity and tucking them in on the bed with care with with embodied presence
for Humanity not turning away crumbling away but a sense of embodied care so
that was the invitation and some of it might have worked for you some of it may not have it's all okay these are
experimentations for us to find our way into what works for us what works for us
so don't judge yourself what that didn't work for me I didn't get that not a problem it's all part of
exploration so so um I'd like to invite us to engage in
small groups and the invitation for the groups is this tonight for you to
um really show up with a sense of embodied presence what does it feel like
to to show up in a small group with really the sense of embodied presence
not hiding not really with a sense of embodied care embodied presence for
yourself and for others there may not be many words that need to be said that's
perfectly fine but see if you can feel it into that palpability ofay presence
with others sort of thinking about what you're going to say or what they're going to say just sense of embodied
presence this is this is supreme practice that you can take into your daily life
just not being overwhelmed by thoughts and emotions so showing up in small
groups and when your turn comes you're welcome to explore for your own good for
your own sake how this practice was for you um and again this is for your own sake it's not not to educate it's not to
impress you're just exploring for yourself and other people are holding you with witness they're not asking
questions they're not giving advice uh they're just two human mirrors reflecting holding with embodied
presence embodied care what you are exploring and if you want to say past
that's perfectly fine and the next person will offer a nugget the next person will come back to you if you want
to offer something again or not you go around and round a few times until the time the six seven
minutes is over so so take your time and silence is perfectly time maybe you want
to say actually I'm losing my sense of presence I'm getting in my head so I'm going to be silent take 30 seconds feel
my presence feel your presence ah sense of care I care for this being who's me I
care for these beings who are showing up with me in this small group you're human
beings just like I am I like to be present with you in this brief moment in
time so feel free to explore out loud the process not just the content of
what's happening but the process oh yeah this is how I'm relating to this right now you can do mindfulness out loud
speaking from that state of trying to tune into embod caring presence as you
are with talking with other people it's like writing a icle and I don't know tapping your head and you're rubbing
your belly at the same time can take a little bit of uh oh yeah how do I do this so so enjoy exploring don't just go
into your your habit pattern of just starting to talk blah blah blah please don't do that just take some time to to
yeah how can I be present embodied present and being silent is perfectly
fine so stretch yourself so wonderful to stretch
ourselves so I'm going to create the breakout rooms and um take care of
yourselves take care of each other and um let let the order be
of maybe uh first name first name reverse alphabetical order yes and know
that you can always say pass here here we go opening the rooms take good okay
everybody is back the rooms are closed welcome back
everyone um and we have some time for um
questions comments Reflections so um yeah if you like to raise your hand
if you haven't spoken for a while and you can also I'm going to change the chat settings you can put the
your notes in chat your your questions your Reflections in chat if it's to me alone privately I won't read your name
if it's to everyone I'll read your name and Megan I see your
hand um my room was such a beautiful uh embodied presence um and
that's such an incredible gift um truly truly truly grateful for that and the
the holding oh thank you oh I'm so touched to hear
how how this felt sense of the embodied presence was so palpable in your
breakout room wow I am so touched thank you for sharing that I'm getting chills
actually is with the way that you're sharing in these beautiful spaces of
holding we can have on zoom on right from different places we're not even the
same phys physical Place For Heaven's Sake right we're on zoom and yet we can
have this palpable sense of of presence with oh how beautiful thank you thank
you Megan for sharing that Maran yeah I just felt very full and
emotional and I was afraid I was going to start crying or something embarrassing but it was I felt very warm
towards the people in the room and uh the idea thinking about um tucking in a child
that was sick really really helped become more embodied me to feel it
rather than you know intellectually like conjure that up but that you just would sit there and and just be caring and
concerned and there's nothing to say just loving presence so that that really helped thank you thank you Maran thank
you so much beautiful appre appreciate how the
practice lit up for you in your heart Beautiful on YouTube Victor says loved
the message of sitting at the bedside of humanity yeah thank you and Jennifer
says um thank you Nikki for all your beautiful meditations and being here
with us oh thank you Jennifer thank you so much yeah and I see your reflection
Richard glad you like the the book any other Reflections having to do with this
particular practice tonight this palpable sense actually I have a question um when I invited you to
feel into this palpable sense of of presence as if it's palpable did that
shift something for you did that I'm going to look down and see if anybody's nodding did that bring it more oh yeah
presence caring presence can be this palpable sense um if was the case for
any of you can just put yes in chat or offer um because that can be a way in to
not just let our thoughts Willy neilly go here and there it's like oh yeah present it's oh yeah I see a thumbs up
great thank you for the thumbs up um let's see who whoever gave the thumbs up
yes and Eli says yes as well great thank you um so yeah oh it's Sarah who's gave the
thumbs up thanks Sarah um yeah I'm glad I'm so glad because that is it feels you
know there are these different ways in for us to to access our sense of
presence they're here they're not so far away so um yeah oh and thanks Bill I
appreciate your reflection um presence didn't register for me but kind presence
did great lovely oh and I see Megan's reflection too yes I felt a larger
container of Love lovely and one more reflection to me here um it was very
helpful to imagine the felt sense my mind was wandering but it kept coming back and feeling the presence it was
very soothing beautiful thank you all I'm so grateful to you all for the way you have engaged with with the practice
and with each other tonight I'm just so grateful to hear the reports from the
the um small groups the palpable sense of kind presence that you shared that
you showered each other with and yourselves how I'm so grateful for this community so thank you all thank you so
much for your practice for showing up for cultivating your heart um your whole
being for the sake of all beings everywhere our practice makes a difference in the world I know you know
it makes a difference for us for others may all beings be free may all beings be
happy including ourselves
thanks everyone thank you so much I am going to