welcome welcome everyone can I have the volume just a little bit higher it sounds like a I
don't want to have to be yelling and then this is the awkward part where I have to talk nonstop while you sounds
like I can maybe that's okay how does that sound does that sound okay
okay so welcome welcome it's nice to see you all
yeah I'm sitting here with a little bit of a heavy heart about uh what's happening in the
world yeah just to acknowledge
that and the emotions right that emotions arise
it's part of being
human and this practice offers how can we find
Freedom in the midst of emotions with
emotions I know there was a time in my life when I thought oh Freedom meant I wouldn't have any emotions they were too
messy and just got in the way and
and that had no small part in my decided to become a research scientist early in
my life because I thought oh you know scientists that they clearly they don't have emotions
and turns out to be ridiculous but uh that's C you know kind what I figured or
what I thought but how can we find Freedom
with emotions right we don't get to choose when emotions arise we don't get to choose when they leave we don't get
to choose their intensity their duration which ones we don't get to choose any of
that as much as we would like to as much as we would like to
control and you know only have certain emotions and not other ones and only in
convenient settings not in other settings
but what does it mean to have like Freedom with emotions what whichever
emotions we're having there's a few things we can point
to about this like what would it mean I'm using this word Freedom as a way to point to what would it mean to not be
pushed around by our emotional life not being like compelled to run away cuz we don't
want to feel certain things or to avoid certain situations in order that we don't feel things or to always feel like
we're chasing after certain emotions what would it be like to have
freedom ease steadiness with the emotions that life
brings us so one
thing is to recognize that em ions are part of the richness the
depth the beauty of life and so part of freedom is to have a
whole range of emotions not just the ones that we like and that are maybe
socially sanctioned but to all of them because let's be honest we do have the capacity
for all of them and we don't want to disown parts of our
El or try to pretend it doesn't exist excise it get rid of it these types of
things but to have the whole range the whole range of emotions because what we can feel emotionally is
enormous if you Tak in all the different flavors and intensities and kind of the
different aspects of it from this mild irritation to murderous rage from this
mild fondness to deep unconditional
love maybe some even like you just some contentment to intense
Joy so part of Freedom with the emotions would to be able to have this whole range to whatever is arising and there's
this part of the variety of emotions that are available that humans have
does provide for a life that I use this word depth to it it feels like that so
rather than just being on the surface maybe it has some color or
Vitality or richness to life so that's one way we might think
about Freedom with emotions another way is to actually be able to be with our
emotions which whichever ones are arising and not feel overwhelmed by
them not feel out of control in this sense that uh we tip
over into where we kind of like lose sense of our faculties in some kind
of way or not feel like we have to get rid of them but allow them to be
there and to be able to be present for them that we can learn the the lessons
that they have to teach us one way to consider emotions is as
Messengers like a way to communicate from ourself to
ourself there's something that's being communicated with emotions sometimes
it's clear sometimes it's not clear but one way to be consider about Freedom with emotions is to be able to
be with our emotions when they arise
and then also to be able to unot things when it when it gets Tangled and
messy and we feel tight and constricted either because we're trying to avoid
something or have more of something or maybe we just feel a wave of emotions and we don't even know what it
is but we want to be able to feel like we can unot things when that's
appropriate when things feel all jumbled up and confusing and we found ourselves
flashing out or closing down or something like
this so another part of having Freedom with emotions is also to learn to have have some of the skill the
capacity to unot them untangle
them another thing we might think about having Freedom with emotions is to have
confidence that whatever emotion arises that we can be with
it that we're not going to get so overwhelmed or that it's not going to send us into a spiral that we can't work
with or be with sometimes we have fear of emotions so maybe we're not consoling somebody
who for example terrible diagnosis or a
loved one has died maybe we're not offering support to them because we're afraid of our own sadness that might
arise or maybe we're not having some difficult
conversations because we're afraid of our our own anger or their anger or what
might happen so part of Freedom with emotions is to have confidence
that whatever emotion arises that we can be with it as best we
can we can stay in it not like detach in some kind of way in which we are a bit
cold and detached and a little bit removed but to be
there with the experience and to have the confidence
that it's okay it's okay even though it might be exactly what we don't
want that it's
okay so H how do we have this Freedom with
emotions notice that what I've been talking about is like it's all about like our relationship to
emotions our way that we respond to them the way that we react to them the way
that we hold them pushing them away or trying to
shove them [Music] down or maybe just holding on or maybe
even trying to like fabricate a little bit thinking that oh this is what I should feel
but so how can we have some Freedom with emotions how can we understand our
relationship to our emotional life because all of us have an emotional
life it's true for some people maybe they have this really rich
emotional life that they're in touch with that they can express and they have the vocabulary to even
describe and for some people maybe it's not so
clear our emotional life might be kind of like the
three main ones are mad sad glad that's okay we start where we
are part of being know relationship to emotions is maybe to like increase our
emotional vocabulary awareness
just not an easy process it's not something like you just decide okay I'm going to be more in touch with my
emotions it can start by just occasionally saying well how am I
feeling right now and I was touched that uh Jack
cornfield he writes in one of his books I don't remember which book I read this in that
he was a a monk in Thailand and then when he came back to
America he uh kind of back in the American culture and all the
expectations and things he realized that he really didn't have a rich emotional life and
partly you know being a monastic he was very simp much simpler for him to kind of like be a steady and
quiet but he realized that he had just completely detached himself from his
emotional life and he had it to he found a list of emotions a long list and he
discovered that he had to familiarize himself what is this I don't even really know what awe feels
like I don't really know what disappointment feels like how is that different than just sadness or frust
ation or thrill you know these types of
things so I want to normalize that some people have a really rich vocabulary
experience and other people have uh maybe have
less but one thing that I think is important to also say that whatever idea
whatever Notions we have about which emotions are appropriate which ones are
are inappropriate how they should be expressed how they should not be expressed all these ideas
about one's relationship to emotions they are always historically and
culturally situated there is no one right way to be
with it even somebody who sits up here and talks about emotions right you know
I'm coming from my culture and my time
why we can understand that in the Buddhist time we we don't even really have a word that we translated his
emotion it's fascinating right they just had a different way that they kind of like sliced up the pie of emotion I'm
sorry of The Human Experience and they didn't label one just
emotions fascinating right that for us it seems like well that's so obvious why wouldn't
they as a little aside I'll say they more had like mental States and bodily
States and emotions are a
mixture and some for some of us that's was a little bit of a wakeup call what do you me what do you mean it's both the
body and the mind if we pay attention to our inner
Life we'll discover that every emotion has both a physical somatic bodily
aspect to as well as a mental aspect to it and part of the way that we can work
with emotions is to kind like tease apart those two
aspects and to be with the bodily one to be with the physical
one the tightness in the throat the fluttering in the belly
the I'm like feeling into my heart because that my heart feels a little broken or I have a little bit of
heartbreak these days I don't know what is I use the word
heart
tobreak so often also just to recognize that you know all these cultures and
times in history and have uh relationships to emotions some cultures you know tend to
be a little more appear to be more stoic and some appear to be you know of like
exuberant just also to say including even like the Dharma subculture right of course there's something here we have a
something that we talk about emotions
too but one of our relationships to emotions might be that uh we have some
resistance to them and it turns out that often it's
not the emotions themselves but our resistance to the
emotions that it turns out to be where the difficulty
lies I heard this in a Dharma talk years ago and I thought oh that's cute I wonder if it's true and uh I've since uh
heard a neuroscientist say this like okay so here's like independently validated this idea that uh emotions
only last for 90 seconds they arise we feel them and they pass
away and you may say but wait you know I've been angry
for hours days
years sad for decades like what do you mean 90
seconds yeah it's fascinating how there's often it's this
story it's the mental part it's the I shouldn't be having this or who do they
think they are or I can't believe this is happening again it's these type of uh
narrations these commentaries that are fueling the emotions and kind of like keeping them
there and I think if all of us if we look closely at all those emotions that tend to stick around we aren't having an
open is of like wow sadness feels like
this I have this pressure behind my eyes I have this heaviness in my
shoulders I feel like I kind of want to collapse wow this is what sadness feels
like and just to be with it and not to just keep on going with the
stories it's human nature of course we have a narrative and why we're sad and
what we're got to do to get to stop it and all these kinds of things of course we
do but it turns out that that's extra and there's a way that we can
maybe take away some of the authority and the power of this
narration and then it just starts to
atrophy so one of our relationships to emotions is that we might have
resistance and we might know or might be indicate that we have some resistance if
we just in general feel uncomfortable talking about emotions or we notice
ourselves doing frequent things just to distract ourselves so that we don't feel emotions
right so many of us have these electronic devices that now are designed
to do precisely that want to distract yourself here pay attention to this
right they been capitalized on this kind of wish to distract ourselves or maybe
we do a lot of procrastination because we don't want to be with our emotional life in some
way so where that's kind of a way of avoiding or not quite being with uh
what's arising or maybe we have this idea that
this spiritual practice means that we should become a little bit like a
emotional somehow and may as well start now and I shouldn't have any emotions or
turns out not to be true spiritual people of course they have
emotions what's different is maybe the duration and intensity I don't know
about the intensity when maybe the duration but they're not a problem they just arise like maybe anger
is there and then it's gone okay sadness is there and then it's
gone I'm not a completely awakened person so I can't tell you but it's not like we stop becoming
human stop caring about things with this spiritual practice
so we might have some resistance to emotions and there might be a way in which there's a part of us that kind of
likes these emotions that can get us into trouble the greed or the
hatred there's a part of us that kind of likes these ones that the anger we might
feel like this power and exhilaration and you know this real sense of self-righteousness this real strong
sense of self is that me against the world I'm right they're wrong don't they
know who I am how dare
they there's this way in we can feel like Justified to do whatever we want
when we're filled with hatred we feel like this that's part of this exhilaration this sense of Vitality
that can arise or maybe anger I'll put in there anger or hatred both of them kind of
have that or maybe there's a way in which we
like this kind of the greed because um this just the whole ideal idea of being
attracted so we're so attracted to the object but there's also a way in which
we're kind of like attracted of just being attracted it also can bring some juiciness to our lives and and then
we're always let Maybe be looking for the next thing to want we has also a huge industry that
supports this too Medicine Avenue write all these advertising wow we is that powerful
partly because you know we we like there's this way in which the the greed
I'm using greed right the strong words here anger hatred and greed but to make a point that this uh there's
this this I don't know this want I'm doing this with my body I'm leaning forward probably because for me it kind
of feels like that this yeah oh I want this thing over there and there's this way in which okay I don't have it but
the next moment you know I don't have to be with this moment the next moment is going to have it'll be
better or maybe we have this certain attraction in some way with anxiety
because maybe there's a way we have this belief if we worry enough about potential problems then
they won't happen or if we worry a lot that's how
we indicate that we care and so we're attracted to feeling
this worry or anxiety even though it might be draining
us or taking away some of our Vitality or
our ability to be with what's
happening so of course the downside to the anger or the hatred or the greed or
the lust or the anxiety is it doesn't allow the best forms of ourselves the
best aspects of ourselves to come out our greatest
wisdom we all have wisdom of course we do but it takes a lot of energy too at
the time at might feel like oh it gets to bring a lot of energy but wow does it take a lot of energy we feel empty we
feel depleted and then we feel like we have to chase after the next thing maybe to
replenish the energy and maybe that chasing itself turns into an
issue yeah so our relationship to emotions is a place where we can practice where
we can notice our relationship and is is there a way in which we can have more
freedom have more ease have more stability not making things go away but
be able to stand on our own two feet in the midst of
them so here's a story this also is from Jack corner field that I appreciate very much I like
this story it's about a poison tree so a tree
that has poisonous fruit and then we might say that uh in
our lives we might discover like oh there's a tree and it has this poisonous fruit and maybe it's this greed or this
hatred or this anger or whatever it might be whatever ever it might be this
poisonous fruit and we might say well let's cut this down let's cut down this tree before anyone is hurt because we
don't want anybody else to eat the fruit this poisonous fruit and we don't want to eat this poisonous fruit so we
clearly we just have to get rid of this tree then when we are faced with stress
or loss or conflict or depression or sorrow in ourselves we may think like
okay I just got to get rid of this you know where is the saw got to chop this down
and this poison afflicts us let's uproot it get rid of it got to chop it
down of course we do I've done my fair share of this of
course I have all of us have and then maybe with a little bit
more maturity more life experience
we discover that uh whe there's this poison tree that has this fruit it's uh
poisonous and maybe with our life we've realized that to open to life to open to
what life brings us requires a this deep heartfelt
compassion for everything that's around
us and so encountering the poison tree it's like let's let's not cut it
down let's not cut it down instead we can put a fence around
it and the fence will protect ourselves we won't go near the tree and it'll
protect others and let everybody know like okay here in lies a poison Don't Go
Near it and so out of kindness and care they
build a France around the tree and and the tree also gets to have its own life
so it's compassion for everybody everything is to build this fence but of
course takes energy and lot of effort to maintain
fences so maybe a third type of person or maybe in the same person in a different uh situation encounters a
poison tree and they see this tree and they see the
poison and they have a different response they say oh perfect just what I
was looking for and they examine the fruit they take it apart maybe learn
some of the ingredients maybe isolate a little bit of it combine it with some something else and make
medicine out of the poison they transform
it they transmute it into something that is
helpful that can be healing for themselves and for
others so they're not trying to get rid of it or make it go away but maybe they
you know have learned something about these poisons they're not afraid of
them and have the confidence and the wherewithal to not only to be with them
but to kind of feel into and discover what's helpful
here and to leave what's not helpful behind and combine it with you know a
dash of compassion and some loving kindness and wisdom all these other things to make some
medicine so what are some ways in which we can make medicine about out of some
of these emotions
one is if we have this idea that our emotions are messengers from ourselves
to ourselves so that there's something that's need to be learned or
communicated or something that maybe isn't
seen about the emotions then we can
briefly reflect on why is this emotion arising in terms of like what why is it
useful how can it be helpful as opposed to just automatically
thinking good or bad or something like this to ask another question like how can this be
helpful what can I glean from this or what uh where's the the the medicine
maybe inside so what is skillful what is
valuable and here are some ideas Daniel
Ingram had this um has this list and this was helpful
for me quite a number of years ago when I was having a lot of emotions and I I
just I felt a little bit of wash and I found that this really helpful so I'll
share it with just in case it's helpful for you guys too so Daniel Ingram says well maybe in
this whatever emotion is having is there something in there is there a wish for
me or others to be happy and can we tune into that and be
sensitive to that this wish for others to be happy the wish for ourselves to be happy or maybe there's a wish for the
world to be a better place for
everybody it's part of this emotion has this this part of this wish as part of
it or maybe there's a wish for someone to understand something that could help them make
their life easier part of this emotion is born in
this wish for someone to understand something or maybe there's just a wish
for things to be better so can we tune into that this
wish this idea this notion that things can be better this possibility this
aspiration for things to be better maybe part of the emotion is due to this wish
for things to be better or maybe there's a wish for
tranquility or the end of suffering
for ourselves for others and this wish for the end of suffering this is a
wholesome wish all of these are wholesome skillful wishes maybe that's what's kind of like
fueling these emotions or wrapped up in them disguised inside these emotions or
something like this and is there a way that we can have this gentle
inquiry is there something in this emotion
that has a aspect that's related to
compassion that's related for the wish for the world to be better ourselves to
feel better for others to feel better for the world to be better and compassion has this feeling
in the heart but it's a softness and this softness can undo some
of the brittleness that we find in some of these other emotions the ones that have a strong
sense of me against you or us against
them which is exhausting and turns out not to be so
helpful there's this uh verse in the dapada I don't have it
in front of me but it goes something like this
hatred never ends with hatred by non-h hatred alone does it
end this is an ancient truth hatred never ends with hatred by
nonh hatred alone does it end this is an ancient
truth of course I like this translation nonh hatred
that's we could say is literally what the paully says some translators will
translate it as love but I think that's asking too much it's like nonh hatred makes the room for
all kinds of things doesn't have to be love maybe it
can be a sincere wish for the suffering to
end maybe it can just be some amount of respect for their
Humanity so when we find ourselves in some of these emotions that aren't so helpful or skillful for ourselves maybe
we can find the compassion in them or maybe we can also find some of
the skillful underpinnings some of the ways is that maybe it's uh not so
directly compassion but something else that's skillful for example
fear can have as part of it this wish to protect this wish to take care of
ourselves others so maybe to feel into
that or maybe anger just wants the word the world to work
well wants there to be a way in which
there is not so much
misery so not so much
suffering or maybe frustration comes from this caring sensation of anger being
thwarted that frustration is I'm not expressing my
anger because I care but the frust there is some anger there a little bit of
anger and to tune into the care not expressing my anger I'm not expressing
it I'm not letting it get as big as it wants and feel into that care not a way
that we're repressing or trying to shove down things but like to recognize yeah it's not best for me it's not best for
others in this situation to just feel the frustration as a part of
care or maybe desire is rooted just in this wish to be
happy and certainly a part of Desire can help us be
happy not all of it some desires right they're skillful and unskillful helpful
and unhelpful but to tune into that helpful part of Desire this wish to be
happy of course we want to be happy everybody
does so maybe to tune into the that wish
and to recognize that that desire has maybe that is the
root or maybe if we find judgement we find ourselves judging that's not good
that's not good that's bad and you know all these types of things maybe we can
tune into this Wish for Things to have this uh have a certain maybe we can even
say high standards we don't want things to just atrophy and lots of entropy you know
just get worse and worse and worse and fall apart we want things to be as good as they can
be maybe there's something in this that recognizes the Beauty and the power and
strength and others and in ourselves and there's judgment maybe is a little bit
of we can as an expression of our wish for that to be expressed maybe we can
tune into
that so in this way we can do a little bit of this
transformation taking this poisoned fruit and turning it into
medicine I'm not saying this is easy sometimes right we have patterns of
how we express emotions and what's appropriate what's not appropriate and how to express them and you know all
these kinds of ways and these patterns get reinforced by our communities our
families of course they do I keep on saying this word of course because it's so natural right that we have this I
don't want to say any of this is wrong but also it's natural for us
to maybe wish to express the beautiful parts of
ourselves to express the strength that we have the wisdom that we
have and maybe to Aspire for that to be for the benefit of all
beings for ourselves for the people that we come into contact with but in a way
that we can be a support for whatever we
encounter whomever we
encounter so our relationship to
emotions might sometimes get in the way of our ability maybe to transmute them into
medicine there might be a way in which we bat a bat away certain emotions or
something that we really hold on to that's okay we start where we are we
start where we are and where we are might be just to examine some of our
beliefs right maybe we have some ideas I shouldn't feel this or maybe we have
some ideas right and often these ideas are not so clearly articulated they're
just a general sense but we also might have ideas that every emotion we
experience should be expressed freely and everyone should know about them and and whatever emotion I have it's the
right one to have and whatever intensity I have it is the right one to have and there's a way in which we might feel the
opposite of kind of repressing that we feel like we have to express it all the
time so we could just have like what are my beliefs about maybe this emotion that
I'm feeling now or maybe we could ask ourselves what scares me about this
emotion which whichever emotion it happens to be or we could ask if I were to to fully
feel this emotion what would happen What would happen if I were to
fully feel it feel it in the
body not try to Temp it down
or yeah our emotions are such a rich part of our human
experience and I don't think that humans maybe as as species or as
individuals we ever get to the end where we have them all figured out and
understand them all or like in some ways like we will never be
robots there was always be a kaleidoscope a richness a depth a
beauty ugliness there will always
be for humans and so part of our relationship
to emotions and it's where we can find the freedom for this wide wide uh
Spectrum or this what's available in this our
inner life
and when way we might consider there's so many opportunities for us
to make
medicine I want to it reiterate it's not it's not easy it's not
fast there was a time when I was a chap uh up in San Francisco General
Hospital and um I felt like wow there's like there's
a lot of suffering that's you in all hospitals right by definition right
then and um I discovered this
book I the the author escapes my mind it's a well-known
book but I think the title was like the wounded healer and the notion was the idea that
from our own wounds our own difficulties our own you know emotions our maybe
unfinished business in our hearts it was that that would allow us
to connect with others it was that our own difficulties what we've learned and
our own vulnerability our own emotional life that allowed us to to show up for
others and at the best chaplain were the ones that had a
history of you know being wounded in some kind of way they they knew what it was like
to be
wounded and that was quite helpful because otherwise we might feel like we
have to have all the answers or you might need
to be appear to be invulnerable or something like that and
that just is a big way of denying
ourselves so turning Med poison into
medicine with our emotions finding Freedom with emotions
I wish for all of you is that you can find
Freedom with whatever emotions come your
way doesn't mean it's not messy doesn't mean it's pretty or easy
but can you find Freedom whatever life brings
you thank
you sometimes I open for questions but tonight I'm um I'd rather do this
without a microphone so if people want to come up and talk to me you're welcome too but uh I I'll do it with the mic off
so thank you and I wish you a wonderful rest of the evening
for