Hello friends hello and welcome to happier and if you can hear me okay give
me thumbs up audio's good fantastic great welcome welcome to happier I'm
Nikki in Mountain View California unseated oloni land and as we always do
we start happy hour by saying hello warming up the space with meta our
greetings so who wants to help warm up the space take it away
hi Jesse you in New Hampshire hi Neil good
evening my friend Oakland hi Fred
I'm George from Texas hi George welcome Susan and San Mateo hi Susan
Vicky from Oakland hi Vicky and hello Bill from Dallas who says hello in chat
anybody else Stephen Houston hi Steve
and hi KJ from Karen from Santa Clara hello foreign
before we transition
okay all right well we're going to declare the the space
warmed up with our meta and hellos to each other and uh thank you for posting
information about uh happy hour Google Groups to chat new
um we have a low traffic mailing list and if you are new to happy hour you're
warmly invited to click on that link and become a member of the Google Groups
where information and and links and poems and things like that are shared
it's a pretty low traffic and also you can be keep in contact with the Sangha
so at this time I change the settings so that accidental unmuting won't be
possible and also chat is now changed so that
um chats will only come to me as the host but I ask you to keep that channel quiet during the guided meditation and
the little darmet because it can be very distracting to receive chats while I'm teaching but I'll open it up afterwards
and last but not least I will turn on the recording for the sake of Audio
Dharma here we go great so hello hello and welcome everyone to
happy hours lovely to see you hi wonderful to see you makes me happy to
see you um and for us to to come together to
practice what a beautiful um a way to to spend our time to cultivate
kindness cultivate Goodwill and presence for this very life or this life that
seems to keep passing very very quickly impermanence impermanence
um in in full in full force full regalia impermanence arising and passing every
moment of our life so so I wanted to to bring a couple of
quotes for us to to play with um tonight and
and they um they have to do with the passage of time and really how we show up how we show up
for our lives how the way we we intend to show up
um for ourselves and for others so couple of [Music] um
quotes one is one is by Alan Saunders you have
probably heard this one life is what happens to us while we are making other plans life is what happens to us while
we are busy making other plans and
um another one from Vivian Green which is life isn't about waiting for the
storm to pass it's about learning to dance in the rain
and here is the third one um by Anonymous life is what happens
when you're busy worrying about the future or worrying about the future so so these are the things I want to bring
in with the invitation not for us to worry about the future and let life pass Us by but actually notice if we do have
that tendency if we happen to have that tendency to to be worrying about the future or we're
not really be present with our lives so that's one invitation to really ah to land to land in our seats and be
present for this beautiful amazing mysterious challenging
um thing called our lives can we be present for it and not waiting for the
storm to pass not waiting bracing ourselves for it to pass but can we learn to dance in the rain with kindness
with patience with generosity with with gratitude with spaciousness for
ourselves and for others it's changing shifting our relationship to the way we show up for our lives for
the sake of ourselves and others and this is of course a a theme that we explore at happy hour cultivating
kindness and compassion and gratitude in these practices of the heart regularly
and this is another way bringing more leaning into the presence being present
with kindness with spaciousness for what is sort of bracing for it to be over can
we celebrate the the fullness the busyness the the
being as being as they are even if they are not exactly what we would want them
to be but they're here already can we be present for them with with spaciousness and and the sense of Celebration even so
so okay I think I've said enough to set the stage so I would bring these uh
themes in as we meditate together so let's let's arrive let's land
in our bodies and start meditating so
so arriving arriving in this body In This Moment In Time
and we invite our feet our legs to rest on this Earth
sitting on the chair letting the bottom of both feet to rest
onto yours
on a cushion items of our legs underside of our legs
and our bottom on the cushion on the chair
relaxing releasing arriving fully
taking your seat
both figuratively and literally
on this Earth in this moment taking our seat
aching our seat
making our seat on the earth in this present moment
as if experience comes and goes
as if there was a revolving door comings and goings and yet as if we were
just resting standing by this revolving door of experience planting ourselves in
the present moment watching the flow of the comics and
goings we don't have to accompany them and travel with them but just resting
right here this open revolving door comings and
goings like this
can we be a kind patient wise Witness
pretendant at this revolving door of the present moment
letting the breath the movement of the breath
sensations of the breath in the body be support
to hang in to hang by
this revolving door of the present moment
the breath can be like a friend who supports us
we can lean on the breath be more present
for the risings and passings
leaning into the breath spaciousness
um anyway yeah release Thoughts From the Past plans for the
future worries In This Moment
can be released and trust that the past is already gone
if we can be present fully present cultivating
wisdom kindness in the present moment the future will take care of itself when it becomes the present moment
can we be here right here right now supported by this friend our breath
in breath out breath spacious
present
sitting by the revolving door of now-ness
the revolving door and surprising and passing
the door at the door is the revolving door it's always now
it's always now can we just release
open our hands for a moment
and appreciate take Delight
it's moments
presence sense of full presence
perhaps you can imagine yourself if you like as an attendant
standing by a revolving door if friendly
kind attendant who has good will Smiles that
whatever passes through the revolving door arise arriving passing moving
through greeting all phenomena
with an open heart an open friendly heart of Goodwill
not attaching getting clingy
jamming up the door
not joining any Travelers moving to the Future
or the past but just staying right here at the revolving door of the present
if you find the mind is wandering not a problem no worries it's okay it happens this is what Minds
do gently inviting
awareness to come and rest with the breath
resting with the present moment
where it's most restful right here
resting in the presence with a smile greeting
all visitors that come and go In This Moment all phenomena passing
through
and if it gets overwhelming at any point it's so much passing through just stay
with the breath just resting with the breath
being present for our life In This Moment and this passing moment
resting with the breath with kindness and good will
for ourselves or whatever is arising
and if there is currently a storm in your life challenges
is that possible imagine yourself just a moment
you imagine yourself dancing in the rain
learning to dance in the ring sort of bracing yourself for the storm
to pass is that possible if not it's okay don't push it
maybe the heart opens it just a second in some way
to see yourself embracing what's difficult what's challenging being remained on being soaked
being undaunted
by the dilute
there be a connection even for just one second a sense of uplift
or join the midst of this rain
the star the deluge
getting soaked
here here
In This Moment this passing moment spacious moment
then as we turn to bring this
practice to a close feeling into this metaphor
or one more time if there are challenges
rain storms can we connect with the freedom of
getting soaked dancing singing in this ring even for a moment
if it's available if not it's okay
letting that go connecting with the metaphor
of sitting resting with the breath and breath and not breath
at the revolving door of experience spaciously present
here not leaving our post
going after experience into the future or the past
spaciously just here
with kindness Goodwill ourselves
and everything and everyone that passes through
these Gates these doors of awareness
and as we cultivate plant seeds of presence and kindness
may we meet ourselves with good will
may we meet whatever Rises with Goodwill
even if they're challenges with the spaciousness
as much as possible may all beings
be happy may all beings be free including ourselves
[Music]
to everyone thanks for your practice
so as I mentioned at the end we're working with a couple of themes one was this
this metaphor of sitting by the revolving door of the present moment
now-ness can be very helpful um metaphor some time
and greeting greeting everything that passes through with a
smile all all events instead of having a a sense of
aversion or clinging one or the other with phenomena that arises that was one
and then the other was this can we for a moment have the sense of dancing in the rain
and again a few quotes that they shared at the beginning connected to the
practice today one is by Alan Saunders life is what happens to us while we're making other plans so the invitation was
to be right here with with the revolving door of experience instead of
connecting and accompanying some experience into the past or future as a training as a training of course might
have happened 100 times during this practice that you did that but we do it as a planting of seeds as a training
and this other quote by Vivian Green life isn't about waiting for the storm to pass but about learning to dance in
the rain um and it's funny because a few days ago I was listening to this
[Music] uh AI generated playlist of of songs and
something that came up in this song which I hadn't listened to for for a long time and her for a long time was
the song dancing in the rain oh yeah oh yeah what an interesting Happy song and what the concept of this idea of
Singing in the Rain I guess that's what it's called Singing in the Rain like oh um I think the lyrics were something
like Singing in the Rain oh I'm happy again how happy I am I'm Singing in the Rain I was like oh how interesting right
imagining us embracing The Rains of our lives and just dancing and singing in
the rain so so so it can really our practice and and that the Buddha taught
with so many similes so many metaphors my goodness the the sutas are filled
with very helpful similes and these metaphors they're really open us up to
possibility instead of be within breath be with the out breath you know yes those instructions are very helpful and
prescriptive but and metaphors can be so helpful to open our hearts and Minds to
to the possibilities that we know but um I I don't don't relate to perhaps as red
leaf if there were prescriptive same with poems anyway so
so with that I'd like to invite us now to to take advantage of practicing with
the community with the happy air community in small groups and the invitation The Prompt for small group
practice tonight is this um was there something about working with either of these metaphors that you
found supportive you found opening um or was there something particularly
challenging and you're welcome to again share from your own experience what arose or you can say past just be part
of the group and hold silent kind presence for yourself and others
perfectly fine you don't have to speak if you do choose to participate in the
small groups let it be a sense of kindness to yourself kindness to others
just like me we're just like each other we're just practicing cultivating our
hearts and Minds as as well as possible in this limited time called human life
and and share from your own experience no questioning no not directing the
group but just sharing your own experience and let let Let's uh
do reverse alphabetical order it's first name first name reverse alphabetical
order is the order of the groups and be kind to yourselves be kind to one
another just the breakout groups are also called breakthrough groups because
we often discover so much about ourselves about each other they can be
supportive so I'm creating the rooms now and take care of yourselves take care of
each other here we go the rooms will close in about 10 seconds
we'll wait until everyone gets back
okay the rooms are closed everybody's back
welcome back everyone and uh we have some time now for Reflections questions
comments how was that practice for you what did you discover
um and also what you discovered in the in discussing it perhaps in the small
groups with one another and if you haven't spoken in the large group ever or for a while I would love to invite
you to pull forward and if you've spoken recently um or often pull back and make space for
for those uh who haven't spoken receipt would love to hear your reflections
Lisa hi Nikki thank you so much
um I found myself kind of teetering between being it was kind of really obvious what
was coming up for me and the it was not a lot of in the revolving door like it was
okay this kind of emotional tangle of things that I was being with but it's like I was teetering between
like noticing a little resistance to it and then like
going into it like being in it and then versus like having okay A
little this the like friendly kind space around it and so it was like well
and then when it was passing at the end I was like is it really going like I don't know am I sure are like okay is
this you know so it was like that Nuance but yeah I don't know is that just something that like happens or do you
have any instruction or guidance around like the being in the Thing versus kind of
like coming out into kind of a space around it and I guess I associate that with like the singing or dancing part
and then the rain maybe is like my direct emotional thing that's happening
to me that I could yeah yeah yeah yeah it's beautiful I so appreciate the way
you described it actually this is lovely that that you observed that at some point you know you're you're um you're
in the midst of you're entangled it was like you're in the revolving door you're hanging out with all the people all the
things are coming and going and like okay and and and then there were some spaciousness that happened like oh yeah
it's coming and going it's happening but there's some spaciousness of presence uh and and you associate that with the ease
of dancing in the rain being with the difficulties or whatever it is arising and passing so so actually you describe
that beautifully Lisa that that transition yourself um and and in terms of any guidance or
support um I think leaning into the breath a little bit kind of leaning into
the present moment can allow that spaciousness but also an and and observing what you just observed about
oh yeah I can be in the myth there's there's a difference between the mode of being entangled with it and there and
and slightly different when yeah it's still a rising the uh but there's just a little bit of space of observing it uh
arising and passing so so um I think you already have it so I'm just basically uh affirming the wisdom
you already have and the way you engaged with it wisely yourself it's quite lovely yeah thanks Lisa that
is so great um and I actually changed I forgot to to open up the chat so it's all the chat is
open either to me individual privately or to the whole group uh Pietro
hi Nikki hi hello everyone so thank you for the well for the meditation and the
theme time passage of time and uh yeah I was just reflecting the group how
much time I spend in planning and worrying so that's very humbling
but yet I also I also have sometimes this experience I think oh yeah we all
have that of just boredom it happened today a lot at work there was just
boredom coming up and um and it's kind of like you want
time to go faster in those case and it's really sad because as you were
reminding us time is so limited our time is so limited and yet they're at this time those times those days when you
actually want to go faster so and and and it's not pleasant to be in boredom so I was just wondering if you had any
any suggestions ideas how to how to be with boredom especially when you're at work and maybe it's not as easy to just
engage in a different activity yeah yeah beautiful thank you so much for bringing
this up this is so important kind of the other side of the coin you know there's
a range of Human Experience right it was we realize we're spending so much time and thinking and we're losing out in the
moment and then we're losing out at the moment because we want it to end right it's a different way of wanting it and
either we're in some difficulty we're bracing for this challenge to I know it's or if it's boring and so so the
mind is really eating basically in relating to it to the present moment the way of pushing it away wishing for a
future moment and then when the future moment comes like oh wait wait I just missed out on that wonderful so you're
bringing out another aspect of it great so so boredom
um boredom is is such an interesting experience it's it's
um not so much about what it is that's happening uh but it's the relationship
of our minds to what is happening so I will venture to say there is nothing
that is inherently boring including sitting with your eyes closed doing
nothing right that's not because there's so much that it's that is happening that we can become curious about so if if we
already know as meditators that we can sit with our eyes quiet and nothing is happening and yet it's interesting like
so wow we can become curious the mind can become more Curious and subtle about
the subtle risings and passings and in the mind and the body and just really
studying turning the awareness to itself to be curious even even if this can be
interesting as we know so how can whatever thing it is that you're doing how can that be boring can we bring more
can we bring more curiosity not just to the to the act itself to whatever it is
to the function that you're doing to can can we so two things I'm going to recommend
one is to bring curiosity and interest to the ACT to do whatever it is deemed
being boring to the task can I learn more can I do this with I don't know
Panache can I do this with alacrity can I do this with interest can I do this with Joe can I do this with a spirit of
service like you the task itself you can can I do this Singing in the Rain you
know can I you know can there be a lot of different attitudes that you can bring in to just explore to keep
learning to keep learning about yourself about the task um Etc and yet another whole area is
become curious about the boredom itself be really curious what is happening what
are the words what is the message right now that this is boring I don't want to be doing this oh really okay well tell
me why what's boring about it let's explore this together boredom explore how boredom feels in the body in the
mind the moment you learn to become curious about boredom
you are never bored it's and it's fascinating it's it's such
a transition it rarely does come up for me that I'm bored and yet yet there's
some moments like I've noticed that the mind's like oh bored like oh really oh it's six foot what is this mind state
that says boring like what is this mind State I wanna I'm curious about this
mind State and it just uh anyway it's it's it can any moment in life becomes
fascinating does that make sense Pietro what I'm inviting you to explore yes yes yes be
curious with boredom be curious with boredom and then you're not bored anymore yes yeah yeah and also challenge
yourself with whatever task there is with the attitude and with different ways to learn and serve and be with I
mean this task is it to serve use it to serve others are there other human beings that are impacted like how can
you relate to this to this task to to find more meaning more interest in it
thank you thank you thank you so much such a great question really great
question so so thank you all this has been such
an interesting period of practice in one of your texts a chat to me singing in
the rain is an energizing song it sure is so may you may you bring that in as
an inspiration as an inspiration um yeah so thank you all and how to
think about serving when doing chores and cooking especially when I'm bored but that's exactly you're serving your
family when you're cooking when you're doing towards you're serving your family it's it's an act of service and and then
again have curiosity about boredom itself person who asked that question so the
mind is so interesting it just labels the most interesting things as boredom so and we just believe it oh yeah this
thing is boring um it's just a label don't believe all labels have a beginner's mind have a
beginner's mind and um and dance in the rain so thank you all thank you for your
practice thank you for your call for your cultivation may all beings be well
may all beings be free including ourselves
thanks everyone