so hello and welcome to our meditation session
and I met in India many years ago
Indian Insight teacher vipassana teacher named munindra menendrachi
and one of his sayings that he was well known for is that he said if it's not simple it's
not to be possum so this idea of simplicity
is challenging because we have our challenges that are
we think are complicated that we can't figure out we're confused about or lost in or
so many different factors involved but if it's not simple it's not to be
passing on if it's not simple it's not love
if it's not simple we it's not going to be uh
let's leave it at that and um so what I'd like to offer this morning
is something very simple a little technique that is can be used in so many different
situations a little technique that it's going to be hard to say there is no time for it
unless there's something really pressing happening really at the moment
and it's a variation of What's called the three breath Journey
and uh so let's do it together and taking your meditation posture
and just very simple and they don't have to do anything really just close your eyes
and with your eyes closed take three simple ordinary breaths but
really be present for those breaths really feel the breathing in the body
okay so then
is there a difference between how you felt before the three breath journey and afterwards
sometimes in daily life just taking three breaths to stop and close your eyes
can interrupt the Mind stream can we can step off the trains of
thoughts that are spinning along and uh
always in danger of derailing but to step off the trains
and uh and take a moment to just let go
be present can relax things we can let go things can give us a different perspective it can take the edge off the
challenges we have The Edge that comes with our alarm our
tension that we carry with us and I don't know how well it worked in
the morning the first thing to do this but I'd recommend that in your daily life you try
and now I'd like to suggest a different variation of the three jet breath Journey
and I'll go through a little bit slowly and I don't know if my speed is going to match
how how quickly or are you speed in which you breathe but if I go too fast
then just remember and just you know just do it you follow afterwards afterwards if it's too slow
then maybe you can do do it over again or do two breaths in a row doing the same thing or something
so with the eyes closed
take a breath and feel the breathing
then take a breath and on the exhale soften in your body
and then take your breath and on the exhale ask the question
where is the love
so we can do it again it prefers just to feel the breath one breath
second soften in the body and third
where's the love and let's do this two or three more
times on your own
and the softening also means letting go of any criticism or resistance to doing this
and to do this without any expectations or measuring or
or judgments about how you are just an open allowing
exercise breathe
soften something within and ask where is the love
and just dropping that question in allow whatever happens to happen
so having introduced this to you now that kind of starting over again in
the meditation maybe taking a few long slow deep
breaths to re-familiarize yourself with your body and your
meditation posture long exhales to settle
letting the breathing return to normal and still take a few moments to relax
let go the body
and also to relax and soften the thinking mind
and then if you'd like to continue with the three breath
Journey
first breath is to breathe just breathe and be present for it
second breath is to breathe and soften relax something
and the third is to ask where is the love
not expecting an answer but maybe just opens
a sense of curiosity presence
or maybe you discover that the love can be found in asking the question
the care the tenderness from which that comes that question
and you can do this through the whole sitting just to go through the three over and over again or
periodically as you wish or just sit here silently
you could simplify the third breath
do not have a question but just say the word love quietly to
yourself in your mind maybe saying
breathing for the first breath soft
for the second love for the Third
saying the words is quietly
as the mind is capable
if you find yourself thinking a lot during the meditation
then the three breath Journey might be a better alternative
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
perhaps a three-breath journey three breaths
can be done in preparation for ending the sitting and being ready
to enter the world again one breath to breathe
one breath to soften and one breath for love
where is the love
and then taking some deep breaths
and on the exhales sending out into the world your good
will you're well wishing Your Love
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank you
so
hello and welcome to the last talk on
working it including love as part of the practice of being in with challenges
love in times of challenge
and um I think that it's fair to say that
when we have challenges almost definition of a challenge is that
it preoccupies us it concerns us it affects us in some sometimes Deep Way
and it's easy then to in that preoccupation to lose track of some of
the important values important the capacities we have
and one of them is love that sometimes some challenges we get
caught up in anger and blame and that can be a loop of
anger kind of triggers more anger blame triggers more reasons to blame
we could be caught up in fear and that also can be a loop where fear
evokes more fear fear gives rise to more fear thoughts that produces more fear
there could be um greed or ambition or there could be Pro
the problem-solving mind comes into mind and the problem-solving mind is so absorbed in itself that it leaves out a
lot of the background of who we are that actually is there to support us and help us find a way
find a solution and so uh
to take to pause long enough so that more of who we are more of our resources
and our capacities and can be present as
we're there with a challenge so we're not uh the attention and the concerns haven't
been narrowed or haven't been hijacked or haven't been caught in Loops that are not so helpful
so one of the classic techniques for the wise life is to pause
and I'm a mindful pause can make all the difference in the world
so we're not kind of on automatic pilot but do we pause long enough to see where
we have some choice and one of the simple choices we can have is to pause a little bit longer
and this technique of doing using three breaths to ground ourselves to interrupt
the Mind streams to remind ourselves of what's important
is a valuable thing to do and three breaths hopefully you almost
always have time for three breaths and if you don't feel like you have time
for it then really take a good look at the situation is
you know the truck barreling down at you is the mountain lion
growling is uh so really some threat and danger that's immediate
or is it uh Nah if it not then question whether you can't just pause for three
breaths and one way of supporting that maybe is that to realize that love
does take time if love is important for you it takes time for it to make time
for it and make room for it and even if it's not readily available
pause and maybe recognize that and pause and recognize is not present
but find out is it how important is it for you is it important enough for you that you
wish it was there to wishing love was there is in fact the
beginning of love provided the wish is soft is without the
expectation without demands without comparisons and judgments just a very
simple wish so if you can take the time to pause for
three breaths three breath Journey and the simplest version of the three
breath journey is just simply stop and take three breaths mindfully presently
and sometimes in a busy life running around doing many things that's where
that's so powerful to take the three breath Journey maybe you drive someplace and then maybe
you're even late a little bit or you're a little bit tense around it before you get out of your car after it's parked
sit there quietly and take the three breath Journey and this busyness they're racing of the
Mind might be then quieted you might be reconnected to yourself just three
breaths sometimes can in a busy life can just kind of reset things maybe not dramatically but enough to make a
difference if you're standing in a line in a store a three-breath journey
if you turn on your computer to look at something
um before you look before you open the monitor take a three breath Journey so
that the the momentum of stress the momentum of tension or desires of doing
doesn't have the upper hand when you sit down to look at the computer so you
ground yourself in something else besides the momentum of the mind that's maybe been busy all day long
so um so then
another variation of the three breath journey is to to have the first first
breath just be a grounding in the breathing the second one is to use the breath
maybe the exhale to relax and soften and the third breath to ask the question
where is the love where is love or just say love
and sometimes in these three best Journeys it can be helpful if their breaths are a little bit deeper than
usual longer than usual and maybe it's a little bit hard to keep that up you might come out of breath but
for three breaths maybe you can do that so the longer breath maybe is grounding and connecting
but to ask the question where is the love and see what arises
it might that might be enough to reconnect you to it it might be uh
enough for you to realize that you think something is more important than love
right now and if that's the case it's good to really know that see that in yourself
wow am I pissed off at someone and yes certainly that's more important than
love and if I give in to love now or take the time to love during one breath
then I don't know it's uh I'm not following
my responsibility the need the requirements of the situation to
be angry to pause and see that's what the mind is
thinking and how it is might give pause give occasion to pause even more really
is that true is that really how I want to live my life um where is the love
can I be angry and have love at the same time maybe we can but maybe then the anger
takes it changes its nature to a very different form maybe it takes the hostility out of the
anger maybe there's still fear when there's love
but with love fear doesn't take the center stage it's not the only game in
town maybe what the love needs is love what the fear needs is some love
and that's often a good principle that when there's fear there's a need for love unless it's you know an imminent
threat um with the you know if there's not an imminent threat probably a chronic
anxiety underlying fear that's going on for some time uh maybe has more to do with reassuring
the heart in some deep way and uh and reassuring The Fear With Love
With Care with kindness with um acceptance with generosity
so exactly what happens when you ask the question where is the love
will depend on the circumstance depend on you at different times but it's a a powerful question to ask
and to keep it in the Forefront where's the love here where's the love in this
challenge oh I forgot that I care about this person
and or oh I forgot that there's love here for
myself that I'm so lost in the challenge that I'm not caring for myself
I'm actually harming myself with attention that I'm that I have
so taking time to pause the three breath
Journey It's a Wonderful technique it's
something that can be applied in daily life in many circumstances no one needs
to know you're doing it um it could be done in the bathroom when no one's around
it can be done as I said the cars when you park your car before you start your
car or when you're on your device and and in many circumstances and it allows
us to reconnect to some deeper value some deeper sense of of of being alive
which might change the orientation or the perspective for how you want to continue
because it's all too easy to be caught up in a perspective caught up in concerns which are not so healthy caught
up in self-preoccupation cut up and giving our beliefs
too much Authority and and so to have a way to cut through
that we have a way to interrupt that have a way to question that to reconnect to something deeper
and something as simple as the three breath Journey might do that and it might do it sometimes better than
simply pausing to be mindful of the situation that can still come that can come after
the three breath journey to really tune in but then the quality of the
mindfulness quality the attention might be a little bit different or softer or caring
um if you've gone through the three breath Journey first
where is the love where is the care where is the kindness
where's the friendliness where is the generosity where's their
respect where's the reverence where is
valuing yourself valuing your own well-being
valuing yourself respecting yourself caring for yourself
so that you don't perpetuate unnecessary stress tension hostility
criticism anxiety that
kind of enter into kind of automatic pilot that we're just kind of living that way and not questioning it not
dropping down not offering love to ourselves
in all the challenges that we Face life is challenging
sooner or later it's challenging for everyone it doesn't mean we can't stop briefly
to love and appreciate and respect ourselves
so thank you and um I hope that this week on
bringing love to bear or to inform how we go through challenges
is useful for you and um I appreciated the chance to talk about
it so um
I appreciate it thank you oh and
um I'll be here Monday through another week and then the following week
Nikki murgafori is going to come back and do the the
7 A.M teaching and you know slowly we're warming up or
picking up the activities we have here in person at IMC
so if you're at all living in you know within uh
close enough to come to IMC you might want to check out the calendar or check out the what's new
and uh and see what's here tonight we have a beginning of the parents group
meeting again that we used to have and we have things on Saturday and all kinds
of things and it's a it's been wonderful to see people coming
back here and um it's been now three years it hasn't been
that much activity here so thank you and
may you be well