okay welcome welcome folks uh appreciate seeing seeing your names
over there um yeah welcome to the uh the 8 A.M session
here and uh I thought
Gil and I made a mistake but actually eight o'clock is a more dignified time
for me to speak and so um yeah you all are benefiting from uh
the pharmacodynamics of caffeine better profile uh
and uh I am awake so uh let's uh let's sit together
stay tuning attuning to the present
tuning to the present in the way we might attune to another human being in front of us
to attend to another human being is to uh to cultivate
empathy
to clarify the the landscape the inner landscape of the other it's
Attunement
to be responsive to the inner landscape of the other
and of course meditation is a kind of self-directed
empathy Attunement
this pool of affect of feeling energies sloshing around
of emotion that calls out for its objects
and so a surge of of feeling in the body effect
and then a kind of interpretation of what it means for this moment what it means for my life
for what I must have what I must rid myself of
so much of our thinking proliferation
is like a smoke Rising off of the engine of affect
where always reading the the Tea Leaves of our
body
coming to conclusions about what we
want and don't want
so natural adaptive to be able to do this
some of the time
but fatiguing for our heart to do it all the time
and so here in our practice
as the energies of our body surge
and swell and Bloom and collapse
where
practicing not over interpreting any event not making it mean too much
treating all of the urgency that are feeling life creates
as a kind of false alarm
for so long we've made our our feelings affect me in so much so
many things so many objects
born of that feeling so many plans and strategies
of acquisition of removal
but now our our feeling or affect means one thing
so often
suffer
foreign
early Pleasant means good
unpleasant means bad
but uh
in our practice we
Revere all experience for its capacity
to soften our heart
in the pleasantness we we abide
rejuvenating our heart
truly resting
letting the the Dharma saturate
in our their unpleasantness
we let the imperfection
soften the somethingness of ego
we call it purification
staying empathically connected to yourself
to experience to the the richness of our
feeling life
foreign
okay
um that's good to say with you so I I saw some some chats about the
cyclone and Gill and ajin sachito and I have not been in touch with Arjun sujito
Nancy's been in touch with with Gil and I reached out to uh the retreat center
and they're safe and sound they're still posting to uh to Dharma seed actually so
yeah so excuse me
so I I was um was talking talking with a uh a yogi
after a retreat and they said um said something like
uh you know I'm suspicious of spiritual teachers who who lack a sense of humor
the lack of a of a sense of humor usually means they haven't reached deep
into the mystery that's what they said and for a long time
I thought the Dharma with serious business
and Dharma teaching is even more serious
so I'll uh I'll tell you how I got my nickname Captain buzzkill
I I have a lot of joy in my life
but little excitement even things that I wind up enjoying a
lot I'm not I'm not excited about in advance and that's not because I'm like
trying to be all Buddhist present or whatever that's just probably more
temperamental or something and um
and my brother is kind of the reverse younger brother more on the excitement
side and uh he was this is years ago he's telling me
something that he was excited about and I kind of was like what on the first
Noble Truth is still true whatever and
he's just like you know who you are you're Captain buzz kill that nickname is kind of kind of stuck
with me um and so
um so today today uh theme of uh playfulness
and humor that's uh that's next on my fake list uh
Monday surrender yesterday humor playfulness today
so there there is this sense that um that the intensity and the poignancy of
life is somehow In Contention with the humor of it
that it is incompatible in some way but one of the gifts of Buddhist practice is how
quickly even strong forces
can move through US leaving sort of no Trace
and opening us to a very different next moment
poignancy and then Delight grief and then
humor and the seriousness the seriousness is
is often driven by ego which is I think by Nature serious
the the kind of Hallmark of ego is a subtle kind of defensiveness and
territoriality and the ego definitely doesn't think it's funny but but it is
it is it can get tight it can get tight in there and certainly in retreat
my meditation my Insight my samadhi my Enlightenment it
gets serious and yet this is a long path a deep path and
playfulness humor is needed at various points along the path
so what are the what are the characteristics of of playing
what are the characteristics of playing to play in the way a child plays
there's non-vigilance we we cannot be playing when we're
patrolling everything there's uh
an absence of self-consciousness we play we play
in the absence of of that congealed sense of self
you kind of can't can't play you can't play If you're trying to look cool
right or smart or whatever you cannot play right it's a performance and play
is not a performance play is the kind of inclusion of our
of our whole being at ease with ourselves in a kind of flow
yeah it's a beautiful thing to see a child at play it's a beautiful thing for
us to play and we're not it's intrinsically
rewarding we're not we're not getting anywhere we're not we're not building towards something
we're playing uh
winnicott uh psycho psychoanalyst pediatrician said um psychotherapy
takes place at the overlap of two areas of playing
that of the patient and that of the therapist Psychotherapy has to do with two people
playing together where playing is not possible the work
done by the therapist is directed towards beginning the patient towards bringing the patient
from a state of not being able to play into a state of being able to play
a state of not being able to play into a state of being able to play
and a lot of the that can be said for the Dharma too
where can you play where can we play
where can we not can we
play with our foibles
play in the zones of clinging
way even maybe with our shame
as um as the egoic framework becomes less and
less of a kind of organizing factor in our lives we open
to to humor and play because a lot of what is painful in the presence of ego
is playful in its absence
as we we come to to take ourselves less seriously we can we can play with the
conventions of self with who we think we are we play with it
in other words we become the joke and it feels good
feels good I
I've always loved when people make fun of me somehow well I mean not when I was
like in middle school or something but if they're making fun of me with with
love it's a it's a delight and um
and just and making fun of myself there's Delight there too
actually and it's not like a casual making fun I'm
like really actually making fun of myself but from Love From Love
the Buddha says something like you know don't deprecate yourself when you're teaching and I I get that but I I am
making fun of myself from Love
and part of how we can relate to our
defilements is actually through some sense of humor
and there's a kind of in our playfulness there's a kind of
relief we release some of that that affect you
know sometimes affect can re it can really I was pointing to it in the the set like it can go more than one way
it can become shame or pain or something or can become humor
viteness
where can we play where can't we and where we can't it is a signal it is
a kind of signal a little warning light of egoic
seriousness but our path is both serious and playful
I went to this uh a kind of Workshop a
sort of more breathing kind of more more kind of pranayama-ish sort of practice
with a couple friends just years ago and uh a couple other Buddhist Buddhist
people and it was not a Buddhist practice but um
um I got into to a very kind of interesting mind state that I
had known I think it was a 90-minute session and we were made we're in the dark and we're breathing and maybe an
hour in I think we were lying down an hour and I start to hear
um this woman next to me start crying and uh it's just the the kind of
um poignancy of it brought tears to me I didn't didn't you know we had met very
briefly I didn't know who she was but but okay I'm hearing crying oh yeah I'm
gonna be crying too and I start crying and uh
coexisting perfectly in perfect harmony with that with those tears
that kind of empathic connection of whatever she was feeling
was humor not laughing at her for sure not
laughing at myself but humor and laughing deeply deeply
and coexisting with the the tears and with the humor
was this abiding peace
as if I were miles beneath the surface of the sea
so still and yet convulsing with laughter with
tears
and this is our life
so way may we um yeah maybe
find the coexistence of um of grief of seriousness
of earnestness of play of humor lightness
and keep going
okay it's good to be with you so uh
will gather back again tomorrow I wish you uh wish you all a good day
and uh appreciate being being with you in this
way together