Hello friends hello greetings from Mountain View California
unseated olonilan where I am where it's been a little rainy overnight and bold
chilly hope you're well wherever in the world you are joining from lovely to join you this week and explore
um practices of compassion together so
so um the cultivation of compassion is done
in this practice systematically in this tradition systematically in concentric
circles we start with ourselves then we go to a category that's called
benefactor then after that dear friend and today we'll explore the category of
benefactor and dear friend will will join them together it also we will will
still practice with ourselves as well because you can never have enough self-compassion you cannot have enough
self-compassion ever for yourself especially in the west when we tend to have a lot more judgment than than
kindness compassion understanding for this person um who is uh who's us anyway so
Let's uh continue let's practice together
so arriving
arriving arriving in this body
arriving in this moment in time
and allowing our body to release any tightness any holding
and connecting with the breath allowing the breath
to be breathed in the entirety of the in-breath and the
entirety of the out breath connecting with three deep diaphragmatic
breaths in order to arrive and settle let the breath be breathed in holding
for a few seconds and breathing out let's do it together
one more
breathing out third one your own time
letting the breath be natural
comforting soothing
connecting to this moment Here and Now to this party
however is showing up in this moment
let your body soften release if their thoughts are rising
they're not needed right now giving our heart completely to this
practice in this moment so the ruminating thinking planning
connecting to
stories let them go not needed right now are all Concepts
not needed
stay with the Simplicity of breathing right now
and turning turning your attention to the breath within the body
anything that might be arising in the body that's
challenging In This Moment In Time
and can we meet it with kindness can we meet it with compassion
not wanting or forcing it to be any other way but
softening around it breathing around it
or if something is heavy in our heart
similarly breathing with it with kindness with compassion
letting go of the stories but staying with the feeling the sensations
and soothing with the breath here here now
filling our own cup with kindness if there's any
challenges in this moment in time kindness becomes compassion when it's
when it meets pain and suffering
and then go of stories and thoughts and just staying with them
Simplicity of breathing in and breathing out kindness
and now let's invite to our heart space
someone who's been a benefactor it's been really kind to us in our life
it's helpful if that person is still alive for this part of the practice
if you're not very experienced with cultivating compassion practice karuna
someone who's been really kind Maybe a teacher
coach a parent a relative or a friend or a very good friend
it's been there for us
let's if it's hard to come up with someone it could also be a person who's easy for us to have
kindness or compassion could be a child is there a teenager now maybe when they
were a child or even a pet s are often better factors in some way
bringing this being close to your heart
and one aspect of their life one thing that might be challenging or
has been challenging doesn't have to be everything but just
one aspect it could simply be that oh yeah they too have a body
which ages and aches and
and needs care
some other aspect that has been challenging for them
connecting with this being in your heart your mind's eye
connecting with this difficulty and meeting it with good wealth
wishing them ease
income peace as they meet this challenge
as they face this difficulty this pain
as if in your heart you're there for them you are there for them
your heart can feel expensive
with its care not turning away from difficulty but
meeting difficulty pain with gentle
kindness
it helps to really connect with the felt sense or the image of this being
to really bring this practice alive
I feel like you can say some phrases silently
may you have ease may you have peace
with this difficulty with this challenge pain sorrow disappointment
whatever it might be you have peace and ease
as you meet this challenge
may you be free from sorrow
you have all the goodness all the resources you need
to meet this difficulty
they wish you well
keeping this dear being in mind in your heart their felt sense right
they're connecting with it connecting with them
and connecting with their Challenge and holding the challenge with Good Will
with kindness with wishes for its alleviation for
for their strength wishing them well
and making sure you feel stable you're not falling into grief
or overwhelm
but in your heart inviting them to a place of stability with love and care
I wish you ease and peers
I wish you well I wish you strength as you meet
this challenge
new be free from sorrow
may you have ease
and for the last minutes of our practice
holding both ourselves and this dear being together in our heart space
any both of us
have eased and peace in the midst of our challenges
may we meet our difficulties with kindness
may we be free from sorrow I wish us well
my oldest with Good Will with kindness with compassion as we
meet our difficulties
and appreciating ourselves having showed up and cultivated planted seeds of kindness
compassion ourselves for another being
and trusting that these seeds will germinate
in their own time without Detachment to outcome in this
moment and releasing this goodness offering this goodness of Art
cultivation together to all beings everywhere
may my practice May the Turning of my heart towards
goodness kindness compassion serve be of service not just to myself
in my own life and those I know whose lives I touch but
everyone everywhere may I live a life of compassion
and a wisdom may I be of service
to all beings everywhere may all beings
be well may all beings be free
new for your practice friends
and as we transition to
the darmed take a moment to transition the recordings if you feel like putting
your word in the chat about what's arising for you
a word or short phrase bringing into the space if you like
greetings everyone um thank you for your practice
and uh just invited you if you wanted to put a word in
in chat about what's coming up after having done this practice of compassion cultivating compassion for
for ourselves and then training to uh a benefactor or a friend and really
appreciating your your offerings
grateful for mind settling gratitude love I love surprises I love that
compassion love intimacy and a bit for more compassion towards my
mother once a benefactor now in a lot of pain and need Ah that's I'll bring that
in thank you for that I'll bring that into the teaching how these categories of
friend and challenging being and neutral they're all so shifting and changing all
the time and in fact we can be at a given time we can be
ourself we can be our benefactor we can be our own challenging person the person
we're having challenges with so these categories they're they're not fixed so
I appreciate that um coming in and without attachment to
outcome yes present awareness of the breath of the
breath of interaction noticing the distraction yes reassurance
etc etc so many beautiful um
offerings yeah timeliness
so so as we continue our exploration as we go from
cultivating compassion cultivating compassion and
just briefly to review that compassion is the love child of of kindness of meta
Plus suffering so when when meta kindness loving
kindness love Good Will so many nuances of of meta meets challenges meets pain
it becomes compassion that's what compassion is meeting suffering with kindness not meeting suffering with
ignoring it or oh I wish it was otherwise or pushing it away or or anger
like why is it happening now why is this person suffering why am I no with kindness oh sweetheart yeah this is hard
yeah this is hard acknowledging that it's hard and yesterday we also talked about this this cognitive aspect because
we need to appreciate we need to understand we need to really gruck
um that yes this is hard this is hard this is hard anyone in this situation
myself or others they would be having a hard time this is hard this is hard and
that ouch that this is hard acknowledgment is is um really the first and most important
step and then of course it is important to um how to be moved by the emotional
suffering and have a desire and intention to see the relief of it to see
it ease so that kindness really coming and holding it so a few more Reflections today as we
brought in we we first brought in ourselves
um and then moved to to bring in a dear
friend or or benefactor someone who's been kind to us
um or or this category sometimes are put together as we did putting together in traditional teachings they're separate
benefactor and dear friend are separate but here we have five days and we usually bring them
um together so so this category actually a lot of
times for people of practicing with the deer being with these categories
um we can fall into what's called empathetic distress and compassion can
become it what's called its near enemy in the teachings so
um in the classical language there is a near enemy and there is a far enemy of all these practices the near enemy is
something that feels like compassion it masquerades it as compassion but is not
compassion it's actually it's enemy but it's such a near enemy it's like uh
so in one near enemy of compassion or one masquerader if you want to use
um the not the classical language but the masquerader is is empathic distress
empathetic distress and empathic distress is um
is when you meet when you when you acknowledge the suffering of of someone
who's dear to you and this could happen for yourself as well of course it's not just for others but um but for example
I'm going to use the example of others you you you meet their suffering but but you become
so engaged so engaged with the suffering and the kindness the Goodwill is not
strong enough to hold it so it falls into just suffering so you're just suffering you're you're not holding it
with enough Good Will it's out of balance compassion when the good will when the kindness
is out of balance with meeting suffering it's hip tips tips into to empathic
distress and empathic distress could feel like grief can feel like oh this is
so hard I can't do this I come um I just oh the compassioned burnout
um in fact there is no compassion burnout because compassion is always balanced with with kindness this
empathic burnout when we're just empathizing when we're just feeling someone's pain and if you keep feeling
someone's pain without the kindness to that Salve to support the feeling
um then of course it's just too painful so empathic distress empathic distress
also it feels like if somebody is in the waves and they're suffering you jump
into the waves with them and now you're both drowning that and it's not helpful to anyone empathic distress or as
compassion there's a sense of stability and you're inviting them you're extending a loving hand and
you're holding their hand you're extending a branch to to in in your heart to wish them well you're feeling
you're observing your you are with their suffering but there's so much kindness and Goodwill that and stability of
equanimity that you're not falling into the suffering with them this is a very
important distinction I'm trying to make because many people think that uh say oh
I can't do compassion it's too hard it's too painful actually it's empathic distress that's
painful so you might they might be you might have been I we might have been
practicing empathic distress not compassion practicing compassion actually feels
good it feels lovely it's uplifting it it uplifts your heart to your body your
mind it's it has a nurse it feels good the the excuse me
ringing bringing in some um some practice some
research results so so when people are practicing
empathic distress when they're just feeling the suffering not full compassion but just empathizing
areas of the brain networks of the brain light up in fmri and this has been
studied by Tanya singer and others uh clemeki and others or lots of papers
where the area of the brain the networks that light up are just the networks of pain and and
um if you watch someone be for example uh if you watch a video of of someone
being poked the same area of your brain that has to do with with these uh with pain for this hand it will light up so
similarly um that only the empathy part if you're feeling someone else's pain if you're
just empathizing areas of your brain that only have to do with pain they light up so of course they'll just be
painful pain pain you don't want to do that however studies if someone in the fmri actually
is instructed and they know and this has been actually studied with Matthew Rickard the the
um uh long-term Monk and really person who
knows compassion practice of compassion and others too with the practice of compassion both
there is the feeling of the the excuse me the areas of the brain
that that light up when you feel someone else's pain light up but also another
all these other networks light up that have to do with with kindness with with
filial attachment with warmth with love with with all of those so these two
together make up compassion it's not just feeling someone else's Pain ooh that's just
pain and it's not sustainable but it compassion holds this so both of these
networks when they all light up oh yeah it's actually a beautiful practice we're cultivating our heart to meet pain with
love with kindness and it feels good it feels good there's bitter sweetness
there's a tenderness so explore that for yourself please um
and the last quick thing I want to bring up is non-attachment to outcomes and
we do this practice we do this cultivation both not attached
to outcome you know we're not going to call the person okay so I've been doing compassion for you is all your pain gone now it's okay attachment to outcome
externally and also attachment to outcome internally and this could be a
little a little confusing because yes we are doing this practice to cultivate compassion but not attachment to results
right now okay I didn't feel anything in this practice you know I didn't feel this Universal compassion that I've
heard about I didn't feel it right now what what why not why not you're planting seeds trust that they
will they will actually um they will flower these seeds will
flower in their own time so have patience you are doing your part you are doing your own cultivation you're doing
your peace and let go of the rest do your best let go of the rest
so much more to say about the practice of compassion there are more near enemies maybe I'll I'll discuss them
tomorrow PT being one of them I'll discuss that and um May you practice compassion today
and NP and two to both feeling the the suffering but but holding it with with
love with care both for yourself and for others and tune into how differently that feels than just feeling the pain
and you can explore that for yourself and see that yeah it's very different one is nourishing the other is not the
other one is just pain wishing you well the rest of the day
with your practice opportunities for practice there are plenty of them life on Earth is
challenging for all of us being being human is hard work and actually being on
Earth is difficult so thank you