so welcome welcome it's uh nice to see you all it's nice to practice together
and tonight I want to talk a little bit about this phrase
that I heard a number of years ago and then recently I heard it again
and it's a tribute to John Wellwood who is a psychologist as well as a Buddhist
practitioner and this phrase is that but the practice is about waking up and
growing up kind of this interesting idea like that waking up right enlightenment
Awakening you know this Peace and Freedom I like going in that direction
but growing up like maybe working with all those issues or things in our life that maybe
are well I like this expression that Jack kornfield uses this unfinished business
of the heart these things that maybe still need a little bit of metabolism or I don't know
what they need exactly but this idea that practice is both we can't
just do one without the other even though of course many of us come to spiritual practice
maybe kind of secretly hoping we won't have to work with that kind of that
stuff some of the difficulties some of the really difficult stuff
and to be sure we don't have to the beginning but as our practice unfolds you know our capacity to be with
whatever is difficult really grows and so then we're able to
be with or understand or hold
the difficulties in a different way
so if there's a a poem that talks about this
well I'm interpreting it to talk about this I don't know what the the poet's intention I'm not sure what her
intention was but this is how I'm interpreting it and this poem is called
autobiography in five short chapters maybe some of you have heard this
like this one walk down the street
there's a deep hole in the sidewalk I Fall in
I am lost I am helpless it isn't my fault
it takes me forever to find a way out
too I walk down the same street there's a
deep hole in the sidewalk I pretend I don't see it I fall in again
I can't believe I'm in the same place but it isn't my fault it still takes a long time to get out
three I walk down the same street there's a deep hole in the sidewalk
I see it is there I still fall in it's a habit
My Eyes Are Open I know where I am it is my fault I get out immediately
four I walk down the same street there's a deep hole in the sidewalk
I walk around it five
I walk down another Street
I kind of like this right so I walk down another street but I like this
progression like At first we don't see it but then we're like I don't want to
see it but then we see it but we have this momentum of the habits the patterns of our life that even though we see what
we're doing may not be so helpful we can't do it anyways this is part of the human experience
and then we might say you know then walk around it it's really gaining some wisdom on some
understanding but we might say that chapter 5 is walking down another Street this is maybe where some real spiritual
awakening is happening where things are seen and understood in a really different way
and one of these ways that this way came up is described as a number of different
ways people point to it or talk about it but one way is that there's a radical
shift in the sense of self where the self-concept is different it's
a or self-concept goes away we could say so there's no longer this idea that
there's a self that there's a core that there's an essence
to which one appends experiences like having this core then just all these
experiences happen to this core instead it's just this recognition
that's all there is are experiences right there isn't a essence or a core
like so often we might think of course we think that
this isn't something you have to believe this isn't something that you have to
try to make sense logically necessarily this is something that more makes sense with some meditative experiences or
experientially so and I know certainly when I first heard this I thought it was very peculiar and bewildering and
puzzling and odd so you might be having that experience too when I mentioned this idea of not
self but I want to talk about it just a little bit here
because Jack cornfield who's you know a senior teacher in this tradition
if not one of the most senior teachers in this tradition he talks about how this a similar kind
of an idea of a progression of towards this understanding of not
self maybe in the same way there's this growing up and waking up and maybe in
the same way the poem but the poem maybe is a little bit misleading because it's
very you know it's a poem and it just goes one two three four five making
things like this is a perfectly linear experience but of course it isn't
waking up and growing up it's maturing in our life maturing in our spiritual practice
isn't neat and tidy in a straight line it's we could think of it more like a spiral
we have a little bit more insight into
understanding what our habits and patterns are and then maybe that allows our meditation to deepen a little bit
we're not so caught or triggered and then as our meditation deepens
and we can see some O's some even deeper patterns maybe we can soften those and realize oh
yeah that's not so helpful and then as those get let go of we can settle even
more and so this spiral just continues on and on
so it's a little bit misleading like this poem that I read and just this
idea of what Jack cornfield has but I'd like to share it nonetheless
so Jack and maybe I'll back up I'll add this before I talk about it that in the
Buddhist teachings there's really this emphasis on waking up you know I have to become awakened there isn't so much
about this growing up like how to heal those parts of us that need healing
how to work with the real difficulties in our lives trauma or
you know there's so many things that just being in the modern world these
days that we need to work with so the Buddhist teachings don't address
that not at least directly but there's a different modalities of
course that do so this recognition that you know we might need more than one way
to approach this weekend up and growing up process
so Jack cornfield describes that first is like reclaiming and healing
our sense of self I appreciate this very much
so maybe with meditation that we we might start to understand oh some of the
painful conditions that created perhaps this part of our sense of our self that
feels like we're inadequate or deficient or somehow not enough lacking in some
way this shows up differently for different people and for some people it's a really dominant part of their experience and
for some people it's just a minor part but to recognize some of these old
patterns of where we got them from our young life all of us gain patterns from
when we are young then these patterns get reinforced with our family our culture our education or Society
whatever it might be and then gradually ceasing to identify
as much with these old patterns just as we saw with that poem and this is a process
this is not something that happens overnight but this allows for this a healthier
sense of self to just naturally arise to be created
so there's a way in which we can like have this sense of wholeness and
reclaiming our feelings our perspectives maybe our voice our sense of yeah I'm
here and I matter it's not it's not uncommon that we need
like a skilled person to help us with this with this process of reclaiming and
healing our sense of self the next would be like in this protos in
this practice like developing our character and developing wisdom
and certainly this is where Buddhist practice can be a big support for this I
think this is like this patient training and repeated cultivation
so much about meditation practice spiritual practice is about this
training and cultivation hateful path as well as like the seven factors of
Awakening the ten parties right all these lists I'm not going to go through all these lists but maybe I'll just say
like in the 10 parties or things like patience and resolve or seven factors of
Awakening or things like joy and tranquility and Equanimity and Eightfold
Path or things like ethical Behavior and livelihood
so maybe we could just put big umbrella terms and say this idea of restraining
from acting on impulses that cause harm to ourselves harm to others
as part of this training and also this training is like to
systematically and intentionally direct our attention
to different things for example with meditation practice we bring that attention again and again right to the
breath or whatever our object is let me do this to kind of help settle
the mind and quiet the mind but also just mindfulness to just be
aware of what's happening so having the intention to have our attention be with
what's happening rather than remaining agitated and lost just to be aware with what's happening
as well as placing our attention or intentionally cultivating placing Our
intention on loving kindness warm-heartedness towards others towards our self
compassion towards our self and towards others so these are some of the ways in which
we can like develop our character and develop some wisdom
this and Jack cornfield's got like this second step of this cultivation
and then the third step would be discovering this positive qualities that are
within us already and recognizing that what I'm talking
about cultivating and developing but part of that is to allow what's kind of
like obscuring or getting in the way of or covering over
these beautiful qualities that all of us have of course we do
of course we do but sometimes we don't have access to them or sometimes we're feeling disconnected from them
but just to make them be more of an integral part of our life and readily accessible
so this idea that maybe we don't have to like improve ourselves
but just letting go of what blocks our heart or our wisdom
because when our heart is free of fear or anger or this grasping or confusion
then these qualities that we've been trying to cultivate or have been cultivating
just manifest naturally of course they do
it's a big part of practice is recognizing this and allowing it to
happen which turns out not to be so easy all the time
but maybe a part of this also is this of this process is honoring our personal
identity that recognize that there are deep patterns and archetypes that make
up our individuality we're not all exactly the same of course not we don't want to be
but can we allow some of these patterns and these archetypes we might use that
language within us to be transformed from this something that we are really
holding on tightly to something that allows to have this way that really
serves our life and serves others some examples that Jack cornfield gives
is that maybe we have this critical intellect but then can help support us with
discriminating wisdom or we have this desire for beauty and
this can support the force that brings Harmony or maybe we have this capacity for
intuition and maybe this could be a gift for healing ourselves and others
so then okay going along this path of uh development is the fourth step that Jack
kornfield talks about is combining this development and discovery of this self
with the realization of The Emptiness of the self
so this recognition that we need both need a strong sense of self in order to recognize or understand the
lack of an inherent self this you know we're using this word self kind of loosely in these different ways
and I'd like to talk a little bit more about that but this
one thing I like to say is this realization that there isn't this core or this Essence that has to be protected
and bolstered and make sure everybody else sees it the same way that we see it
and all these ways that um
often bring a lot of difficulties in suffering in our life when people don't see us the way that we want them to or
or we don't want people to see us if we have this idea about ourselves is
somehow unflattering we don't want other people to see then we don't allow intimacy with others
so this realization this recognition that there isn't a core this stable
permanent core at the center is associated with a lot of joy and
freedom and it's a sense of relief but when we think about it it might
sound kind of frightening and odd as perfectly fine that's our thoughts about
it but the experience is one of like oh my goodness what a relief this thing that
was so heavy and I've been carrying around I can put it down I don't need it
it's extra so in this practice we do need a strong
and healthy sense of self we it's we needed to withstand the
going through these processes and part of meditation is meditation deepens then
there's a sense of the the sense the sense of itself starts to get really
thin and soft and sense of the body changes the sense of the Mind changes in
some of these deep States sometimes we don't experience that until we have some Retreat practice and those
type of settings but the point I'd like to say here is
that the that the development of the self and the realization of not self they kind of
evolved together and some of you might recognize or know
that this um the teaching if not self is one of three
characteristics we could have this so we often use this language three characteristics of
experience one is that there isn't an inherent permanent core
anata and Paulie not self another one is that things are
impermanent we know this we know that things change
and the second one that there isn't anything that's a lasting source of
Happiness there's not a single thing that will forever and always make us happy
in fact it's often uncomfortable and stressful
and painful duka Anita impermanence
duka it's transmitted so many different ways I'll say suffering
anata not self turns out everything has these three
qualities everything and part of practice is we start to see
that and then we stop kind of insisting that they be otherwise trying to make
things stay be permanent and stable or make us happy and in a way that they can
they just inherently can't so
I talked about these Anita duka anata as three characteristics but Gil
bronstad appreciates that sometimes he teaches them as less as a characteristic
of objects so less says nouns or
but more as adjectives or perceptions and I really
like this because it points to more our experience so not so much about
what are some teachings that we've heard and maybe some philosophy but what's actually our experience at this moment
independent of what you know somebody has said like what's actually going on
and so we could say that nature we could translate as in constant
rather than in permanent when the mind is quiet we start to see
oh yeah there's like a fluttering or a flickering of our experience like we're not having just one single experience
all the time maybe the mind is resting on the breath
for a moment but then there's a sound and the mind goes to the sound and comes back to the breath
that's not just one constant experience or maybe there's um being with the body and then realize
oh yeah the body's breathing and then just being with the movement of the body in a different place
so more easily understood maybe like experience is just recognizing
it's really changing all the time and sometimes when we think it's not changing
is when it's the most difficult when we feel like oh it's going to be like this it's never going to be different
so instead to notice yeah it's changing so Anita as inconstant
all our experiences are inconstant we are not having just one experience
forever of course not and then we can look at dukkha as being
painful rather than translating as suffering maybe being painful
and so this we do have mental experiences we have physical
experiences that are uncomfortable and it might be that part of the reason
they're uncomfortable is because they're always changing we want that to be stable we want a
place to land it's going to make us happy we want a place to just like relax like
oh okay I got it figured out finally but those places turns out doesn't exist
doesn't stop us from keeping on looking for it of course but and it doesn't matter what somebody says
we keep on looking this is something that we also have to experience but this idea of Duca is painful
just to recognize that there were it's not everything isn't like Bliss and
happiness maybe we know this but even to even notice those moments
when we do feel fantastic there's often this flickering of like oh
I hope this doesn't end oh what was I doing right before so I can make sure I get this experience
again there's this kind of flickering of that's happening just to notice that
and then to translate as I was doing earlier on a
time as not self some people translate it as no self
and then that gets a little bit more complicated as what does this mean
there's no self of course I have a self I'm here but not self is more like nope that's
not myself that's not myself that's not myself this not myself this isn't myself
it's kind of like pointing to how when we investigate nothing has this core
this permanent core this Essence at the center
so I appreciate that how like all these uh three perceptions we might say these
different ways of understanding Anita anata is really pointing to our direct
experience not a philosophy not a metaphysical belief
not something that we have to adopt it's more just encouragement to look into it
and to examine it or you know what's really going on in our experience
maybe like shifting our experience from we often are when we have an
experience we bring in all kinds of Concepts or personal history or
philosophy of something that we add on top of our experience
and to shift away from that towards just noticing the stream of moment to moment
in personal experience that for the most part we aren't controlling
so part of putting the conditions in place to allow this shift in perception
from things being permanent and or satisfying
or having a stable core is we don't we can't like make that
happen but part of putting the conditions in place in which that becomes more evident in our experience
is to be cultivating the opposite so just like with Jack cornfield it was
and this waking up and growing up like we cultivate the sense of self to help
us to see not self in the same way we cultivate stability
to help us see in constancy and so what does that mean to cultivate
stability part of it is our meditation practice
is we maybe sitting quietly like literally
physically being stable it turns out that this really does have
an impact on us to pay a little bit attention like to our posture to have some uprightness and some settleness to
feel connected to the ground sometimes when I lead guided meditations I talk
about feeling the sitting base like the foundation what you're sitting on the
pressure against the buttocks or the back if you're sitting in a chair with the feet are on
so feeling connected and grounded literally physically
is one way that can support a sense of stability sometimes we're often just don't pay
attention to that but we can bring our attention to that also we can use some imagery
sometimes the idea of mountains or rocks or
sort of like redwood trees you know here and uh certainly here in Redwood City
right but this that there are
things in our experience that have a sense of stability and we can use that
imagery to support us either in our meditation or in the way that we are thinking about
things or considering we have this expression I know sometimes
we will refer to somebody well this person was my rock when I was going through difficulties well what does that
mean that person of course moved but they were set
applied some stability so what does that mean and can we do that for ourselves or can
we do that for others so that one of the Opposites of
inconstancy of stability if you think about physical stability but also mental stability
and a part of mental stability is concentration so allowing the mind to really get
settled not to be jumping around or but instead
to rest on the sensations of breathing for example or
maybe doing meta practice and just allowing the mind to quiet
and of course this doesn't happen the first time we try it this is something that gets uh cultivated and with
practice really does happen though that there's a sense of stability can happen as the Mind quiets down
and we might use this word also like composure like being collected or this
sense of wholeness or being in harmony with ourselves and with others and our
environment so not fighting against or not pushing against her running away
from but having this sense of composure as well as you know composure we think
about keeping it together as best we can right
and all of these of course are supported by you know learning to soften the
judging of our experiences I like this I don't like that I want
this I don't want that this better go away I need more of that you know our whole life can be nothing but this
but is there a way that we can soften that like yeah this doesn't match my
preferences but it's okay yeah this isn't exactly what I wanted but I'm going to open to it and see
what's going to happen next you know instead of always always seeking seeking seeking trying to make
everything be just like our preferences in some ways that's the opposite of stability that's just forever seeking
is there a way that we can soften our experiences
in the same way that muddy water right you know the the dirt kind of settles
but there's a way in which if we're allowing our preferences our aversions
or things that we want to be agitating the mind there's a way in which we're like
always stirring the pot and the mud never really Settles
so is there a way that you can learn to do that and of course meditation practice and all these other practices
support that
so in order to help with this insight into inconstancy or to notice the in
constancy in our experience we can cultivate the opposite
ability and then to notice or to be with the
opposite to be with duka I could say painful is to cultivate a sense of well-being
and well-being is this has this really wide spectrum of terms
that we can think of joy happiness
gladness contentment these ways in which there can be a sense
of maybe uplift in the heart it's important to cultivate this it's an
integral part of our life and our practice sometimes we might think like oh that seems frivolous I have work to
do it's so important it's really important I know I certainly felt like what
Joy yeah okay that's for everybody else I really have to work hard here that's for the people that have everything all
together you know I don't have it together I have to work hard it turns out that it doesn't work that way
we need Joy of course we do happiness well-being contentment even like these
really subtle things like yeah things are okay things are okay even if that's not our dominant
experience even if there's just this little part like yeah it's okay let's posture I'm in right now feels all
right just to notice those we often we like to be dismissive of them
to notice them and then we can also like intentionally cultivate appreciation
why don't we grateful for the simple things like
for me coffee in the mornings I love having coffee in the mornings it just
makes me happy I'm not even too particular about the coffee
so you know simple things like this or maybe there's big giant things maybe you've received some real benefits in
your life and to have some appreciation cultivate some generosity
help somebody out give your time to somebody give some money to something that
you feel moved to do to be generous is a way in which kind of
always makes us feel good if it doesn't make you feel good then maybe you're doing generosity in the wrong way we
don't want it to feel like something that you have to do just do it as a way that supports a sense of well-being
and then of course the opposite of not-self I was talking about earlier but we might be able to summarize what I was
talking about with this word confidence maybe the to help seeing the insight
into not self is to cultivate confidence as I talked about earlier
and you might say well why do we need to cultivate these perceptions of Anita
duka anata in constant painful not self
deep inside into these are doorways to Awakening
our doorways to greater and greater freedom our doorways to peace and ease
so there's a way in which having some perceiving them having some insight into
them in a way that's not just thinking but that is actually like experiencing
them can be transformative it allows this deep Letting Go allows us
deep softening and opening that allows for greater and greater
freedom so growing up and waking up they happen
together and we can cultivate part of the growing
up part to help the waking up but maybe that's too simple of a way to say it they definitely have been together more
in a spiral so with that I'll end
and I'll open it up if there are some questions or comments thank you
there you go um question I feel like in my meditation
practice I get a lot of glimpses of where suffering comes from and there's
hints and it's very obvious to me I was like oh I'm uncomfortable in this suffering or I get a lot of hints around
impermanence right like breath comes goes away so I get a lot of hints
do you have easy pointers of what the hints are for not self they seem harder
for me at least to detect or get hints off like ah not self not self not self
yeah yeah it's a good question so one I could say that often in permanent scene
in permanence leads to oh well things are always changing they can't be a lasting source of happiness and why was
I identified with that anyway so it kind of the say I had a better way to I had
this better language to say that but often it's described as it starts with impermanence and leads to not sub so I
could say that but something else is uh are you familiar with this idea of vadina the like feeling tone
I'll just say briefly that every experience we have comes in three we
might say flavors Pleasant unpleasant neutral
we notice the pleasant because we want more of it we notice the unpleasant because we want less of it we often am
not noticing the neutral things like maybe the feeling of your feet on
the floor right it's maybe it's just neutral so we don't notice it it can be helpful to pay attention to
like set an intention okay I'm going to pay attention to the neutral things because often the mind just thinks oh
this is boring I want to go find something that I can want or not want
because it turns out that wanting and not wanting bolsters our sense of self
a self when we have this permanent idea or this concept of itself it's always
wanting or not wanting but if we create the conditions in which the wanting and the not wanting go away
then maybe there can be this glimpse of oh there's there isn't anything here so
I offer that this one thank you you're welcome
anybody else have a comment or a question
yeah sort of along the same line it's just a
comment but I heard somebody ask what would be left if there's no nothing left to
to solve to fix what's left and that really struck me when I
heard that it's I don't know simple but it was
thank you yeah
um in thinking about duka what I've been noticing is that there's
there's different levels there's the Duca that's obviously uncomfortable whether it's
physical pain or difficult emotions or
but then there's like a quieter level of Duca that's just like
the unescapable mundanity like
that you have to brush your teeth every day you don't have to no you don't have
to but if you don't that will lead to Greater no there's consequences and that
you have to eat and just these you have to get dressed but now just the the modernity that will
never stop as long as you're alive and is in some way
burdensome simply because it's and we pretend it's not we're like
celebrate eating right to avoid that feeling and we celebrate clothing
to avoid that feeling and but once all that sort of settles and
clears away there's a recognition that actually it's just a subtle level of
duka it's just an inescapable reality of Being Human and alive and
having bodies right we have to take care of them the burden of having a body and
just needing to fulfill these tasks and go to the bathroom and you know just
it's not you can't get away from it you know um
so just recognizing that that is actually
a fundamental dukkha yes to existence yeah
duka shows up in so many different ways right we could say everywhere if we then settle levels we find it everywhere
and it's uh like in one way I can say it's an
unresolvable dukkha because you can't make it go away so the only resolution to it is really
anata is really it's seeing through this uh
the identification and that that resolution of our separation and sense
of Burden
thank you thank you um last week you spoke of impermanence
and for some reason I took issue with that and I was driving home and I was like no everything can be informed us trying to grasp onto something solid and
I thought well you know if you know impermanence is guaranteed then that's kind of like a you know a permanent
solid thing that'll always be there if today's a crap day you know tomorrow and every other day can't possibly be crap
days you might just get lucky and have a good day or something but for some reason I don't know why last week I I
kind of clung onto that impermanence and whatnot and how do you feel about impermanence
today well I think I just came to my own conclusion that uh that it's a constant
so that's kind of a something solid to respond to yeah and Concepts ideas we can hold on
to those are the only things that our study are Concepts well experiences spreads they're not
steady or they are inconstant but yeah great thank you
okay so here we are at the top of the hour so thank you very much
sure okay can space be used to cultivate neutral
feelings can space be used to cultivate neutral
feelings so I'm assuming that this is talking about cultivating space as one of the elements
do you think you I'm not sure to cultivate neutral feelings I would
say we don't have to cultivate well if we're using feelings as vadana
then um we don't have to cultivate them just neutral vedana happens all the time
neutral experiences but neutral feelings maybe they're meaning not being for or
against and I would say that's equanimity and maybe I'll just say really quickly
maybe a part of equanimity is seeing the big picture of things rather than
getting lost in it so maybe space can help with that so there we go
there is this my uh answer hope that was helpful okay thank you