what's up hello and welcome to happy hour everyone
so um as I've been experimenting together with you the past few sessions
um we just start with practicing together we start with without a little dharmette at the beginning and and maybe
I say a few words at the end but I introduced the theme uh during our
meditation so let's let's just practice together be surprised by this being human so
so let us arrive let us arrive in our bodies
together both individually
in this seat in this body that is
that is felt by me and and also together as a community arriving coming together
perhaps turning our awareness for a moment with this
or the beauty of the togetherness
on this little blue planet we call home from different places
and coming together with Our intention cultivate goodness kindness
for the sake of ourselves and others and turning and turning our way our awareness now
this body to this
to this feeling a connection to the Earth through our feet
the bottom of our feet
touching the Earth kissing the Earth
I am here connection of our sit bones
with the chair of the cushion in lieu of the earth I am here I am here
is it first be my witness I'm here
and relaxing relaxing the body
so much has happened already before getting here in this moment
letting it go we can always pick it up later but for
now prioritizing to give our heart fully completely
to itself through itself in this practice here
wholeheartedly here just here
but this breath this sensation
adding this breath the sensations
the song of this breath be the only song
that is nourishing healing calming
no thoughts needed right now the song of thoughts not needed
the mellifluous song of the breath
listening listening sensations of just this breath this
miracle of this breath in this body
aliens of years of evolution this Breath Right Here
spread right here connecting us
to the planet
the air around us the trees
All Humans all beings
that's the miracle of this breath alone
listen deeply
and the thoughts arise static of thoughts
let them go with a smile not now thank you please come back later
embracing celebrating the nourishment of this breath
as good well as meta as kindness to ourselves
what's done is done future isn't here yet just this moment
just here
settling with each breath
and now I'd like to invite you you would bring someone to mind
or home your mental good well care
love whatever Nuance of it is
a lie for you for this being flows with ease maybe you feel safe
when you think of this being maybe your body relaxes
choose someone with whom you have an uncomplicated relationship ideally
pets her simple children and if they're teenagers now you can
imagine when they were young
simple someone you appreciate could also be a
benefactor
a teacher a coach
maybe even someone who's touched you through their work
their writing their talks Etc wherever it's easy
to feel good will for this being for this person or being
still connected to your body to your sit bones to your feet
your breath invite them invite them close as if opening the door
of your heart mind and inviting them close
and see what arises in your body and your heart
maybe on your face maybe a smile shows up
and in this practice today
as we evoke as we invoke the phrases of Goodwill and matter we're
going to imagine them
feeling that way so may you be safe
bringing an image of this being where they are cozy maybe it's raining
outside and they're safe from the elements
of the rain from the cold and the image that
there's some safety may you be safe
from inner and outer arm for the inner harm imagining that
dread peace their thoughts are not bothering them you're safe from inner and
outer arm
may you be happy and have joy in your heart
imagine this being happy imagine them
joyful
you're doing some imagined activity they like
maybe with people they appreciate
may you be happy and see them happy see this being happy
in your mind's eye
connecting with your good will for them you wish them well you want them to be
happy yay
may you be healthy the Third metaphrase
seeing them healthy foreign maybe see them strong healthy
maybe they're hiking exercising [Music]
something Active swimming skiing whatever they love to do or imagine them doing if you don't know
you're strong in their body healthy right with energy may you be healthy
and the fourth myth of a wish may you have ease
may you take care of yourself happily and imagine that with a sense of ease
and the Tableau for this one could be anything you like maybe they're
lying in a hammock on a beach there's a sense of ease
or they're sitting in meditation and there's ease there's peace or whatever
you want to imagine
may you be safe
the image of them safety may you be happy
be there with friends celebrating an occasion
may you be healthy see them strong
healthy body
and may you and these on the image of them with ease
these images we connect with our good will strengthening our good wish our meta
our kindness for this person it's not wishful thinking
or or imagining something so that it
definitely becomes true with attachment no it's just so our hearts
and connect with this wish of meta really feel into
it
you might notice that it makes you feel happy and well imagine this being
happy and well
if the four tableaus are complicated simply
may you be well may you be happy those two are sufficient
may you have well-being your body mind and heart
may you have well-being in every way you'd be happy
and nothing
imagining them well happy and healthy
connecting with this image
though your good will can flourish
now Bowing in your mind to this being
I'm bringing an image of yourself up as as a beloved other
and making the same wishes for yourself and imagining yourself happy and well seeing yourself happy and well
and connecting with mental good will for yourself
as this beloved other the same way you did for your dear being a moment ago
may you be safe foreign
seeing yourself safe an image of yourself seeing connecting
with the good wishes for yourself may you be happy
of joy in your heart
imagine yourself laughing joyful
love energy of joy gladness
may you be healthy and strong
seeing yourself connecting with an image of yourself
was healthy strong
well-being in your body
again not attaching to any of these images
not clinging just offering
offering Good Will through these Pablo's to yourself as a way to open
your own heart to yourself the last minute to wish
may you have ease seeing yourself with ease in your life
ah seeing yourself with ease
your mind your heart your body at ease
the four phrases are too much just simply may you be well
may you be happy or may you have well-being in every way
it's okay to bring a memory of a time when you are happy if it's hard to connect
with an image it's easy to connect great if not you can
bring up an image of you happy healthy from experience you've had
a dwelling on the memory but feeling into the good wish the good will for yourself
don't get caught up in reminiscing stay in the present
may you be happy healthy
in every way
we find ourselves searching too hard for memories Let It Go just imagine something completely bold
you're walking in a Green Meadow in the full sunshine feeling
happy healthy joyful safe
with ease wishing this being well
with all your heart is being who is you
this person who is you carries the sun inside them inside their heart
with Good Will with kindness with happiness health wish them well
may they have ease
connect with this image of Goodwill
and as we close and as we bring this guided meditation it's time to practice together to a
close for the next breath
perhaps bringing the image of yourself as happy healthy with ease save
carrying the sun in your heart bring this image close just breathe it in for
a moment
sense of well-being contentment through and through every cell of your
body just for a moment if we can connect with it
wishing ourselves well as being who is me
and Shining our light sharing our light our good will
our goodness with the whole world cultivating our kindness for ourselves
as a basis filling our own cup so we don't go around and tell and ask
beg everyone to fill our cups with approval
filling our own cup with our own kindness appreciation
so that we can fill other people's cup s may all beings everywhere
safe happy healthy enough ease may all beings including myself
be great [Music]
thanks everyone so
we started by settling in the body with the breath as we always do
and then we um brought someone a dear person to our
mindset I and wish them well with tableaus with images trying to connect
with seeing them happy healthy with ease safe and then
Buddha debate and switch after we had warmed up our our imagination our
imagery than we brought in an image of ourselves as this third person that we've been kind of playing around over
the past week last week as a beloved other imagining ourselves well and
connecting with that wish for wellness and at the very end I wish I invited you to to breathe it in say oh wow the sense
of goodness can I actually bring it close as one way to access Mentha
there's so many different ways so so I'm going to invite us to
transition now into small groups and there will be time for reflection so remember how this practice was for you
um if you have questions comments complaints confusions aha moments please
save all of them and the invitation for small group
practice is the following that we that you're invited if you like
it's in groups of roughly three I hope you'll stay three um two to say a couple of words
um not a couple of words but a couple sentences just a short brief and make
sure you're not dominating the time just saying something about how this practice was what did it open up what was
challenging there's no right or wrong you'd say I fell asleep I was distracted
the whole time it's perfectly fine you can also hold silence perfectly fine and
then next person will go alphabetically the next person will say a few words the next person will say a few words and
then you'll have the chance again so going round and round for about six minutes
seven minutes so um
yeah take care of yourselves take care of each other be kind
um and I'm going to create the breakout rooms now and
um as always here we go all right it's taking a moment here okay
there all right um again you can offer your silence
um and just hold witness with kindness the idea of these groups is again for
the practice to uh um well for it's it's it's really our Good
Will it's the our Good Will meets the world it's the Rubber meets the road as
the Goodwill meets the world so can we actually show up with Goodwill for ourselves and others that's the question
it's not about blah blah blah look at me it's about can we show up with Goodwill
for ourselves and others it's Supreme practice it's really Supreme practice okay
all right so I'm going to open the rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other
hey we'll wait until everybody's back that was a longer it was actually eight
minutes I think the breakout groups within seven minutes um and then an extra minutes an extra
minute to close so um
and if you have Reflections you can raise your hand especially if you haven't spoken recently uh I'd like to
if you have spoken recently I'm going to ask you to please step back um and uh you can also type your uh
Reflections in chat if you type them to me privately I will
only read your reflection not your um name and if it's to everyone then I'll
read uh your reflection too so anything you noticed any aha moments
or any questions or challenges from this practice or something you noticed in the small groups
and again if you haven't spoken in a while I'm going to invite you to move forward and if you have spoken recently
at happy hour I'm going to ask you to move back
Stephanie says my relationships with dogs are uncomplicated that's great
oh that's sweet the other others are agreeing with you
it's sweet okay yeah the reflections maybe we'll take a pause for one word
again if you haven't spoken in a while you're welcome to share reflection I was
I was a small group how was the meditation for you
Amy I haven't heard from you in a long time
um I felt like my group was full of meta so I felt I was really it was really sweet it just increased the energy of it
and we were talking about baby elephants and puppies and you know all those things that uh yeah can really warm up
the meta Vibes so yeah it was lovely oh so sweet oh that makes me happy and
you're smiling you're beaming meta actually as you're talking right now just hearing you and seeing you it just
makes me happy it's very sweet thanks for reporting back from from from your group that's lovely beautiful thank you
Amy and uh thank you all thank you for your practice so I'm experimenting both with
a slightly different form and trying to see if 15 minutes might actually make it
a little lighter happy hour so I'm gonna end now and [Music]
um um thank you all for your practice for your cultivation for supporting yourselves and each other may all beings
be well may all beings including ourselves be free [Music]
thanks everyone now