well hello everyone welcome back my name is May Elliott and this is day two of
our five day series on the hindrances getting to know the five hindrances in
our meditation practice is really essential for learning how to settle the mind
um and as a reminder the five hindrances include sense desire
will will also known as aversion for restlessness sloth and torpor and doubt so today
we'll be exploring the second hindrance ill will the traditional antidote to the
hindrance of ill will is meta or loving kindness so I'll offer some instructions
for meta during the sitting today um and while ideally we might send meta to
the person we're angry at if we're you know if we're feeling ill will this is a tall order for most of us so instead
we'll start where it's easiest we'll start by sending Metta to someone that's easy to love and then this helps grow
the capacity for kindness in a way that's not quite as challenging so it's a little bit more like starting with the
five pound weights or the one pound weights at the gym rather than the 50 pound weights
um so so during our meditation we'll Begin by Landing in the body and then
we'll shift our Focus to doing meta for someone who is easy to love and then for ourselves
um and we'll just sprinkle in The Meta a bit you don't have to do it for the whole period if it doesn't resonate with you
um but I'll try it on if it feels like something that you're interested in and
know that there are many many ways to do meta and this is uh one of many approaches
so go ahead and take your meditation posture whether that's sitting standing
or lying down the Buddha taught meditation in all postures so whatever
works for your body
and connect with a um a landing point for your meditation
um some aspect of your present moment experience that anchors you here
that might be the breath it might be the soundscape or it might be a global sense
of the body sitting whatever works for you
thank you
so connecting with your anchor
setting the intention to land here together this morning releasing thoughts of past and future
inviting the mind and the body to relax
even if it's helpful maybe taking a few deep breaths
resetting reconnecting
and taking some time now to be devoted to your primary anchor
maybe the breath the soundscape global sense of the body
Landing here with a felt sense of the now
all right we'll start by bringing to mind someone that's easy to love
that might be a parent a grandparent maybe an aunt or an uncle
Kwan Yin the Dalai Lama a cat
a dog your fit your favorite pet
or any of these beings are suitable for meta practice
and what we'll do is we'll take a moment to reflect on their goodness so this is
an opportunity to consider the goodness of this being
um you might bring to mind a memory or just a general sense of this being's goodness
maybe reflecting on a time they were particularly generous or compassionate
or patient
something that you love about them
so reflecting on one's goodness is the proximate cause for meta to arise
so we're warming up the heart
and you might picture them sitting in front of you it doesn't have to be a photographic
image
and connect with the heart that wishes them well
so having touched in on the goodness of this being will now offer The Meta
phrases so I'll say a phrase and you can repeat it back in your own mind
when we do this it's almost like dropping a drip of water into a pond and
just letting it Ripple out so we're letting the phrase drop into our mind and body and then
just seeing what happens letting it Ripple through we're not demanding that the heart
respond in a certain way we're just seeing what happens so this is a mindfulness practice
may you be joyful and happy
may you be strong and healthy
may you be safe and free from harm
and may you be peaceful and at ease
and if the phrases feel a little too cumbersome you might try it like this
just saying a single word and directing it towards this person
happy
healthy
safe pre
may you be joyful and happy
may you be strong and healthy
may you be safe and faithful however
and may you be peaceful and at ease
during this practice it's okay if there's not a sense of Love or kindness
it's enough just have the wish to send loving kindness
love can be an action instead of a Feeling
and in saying the phrases we're just planting a seed that seed will Bloom on its own time
it'll Sprout on its own time so we don't demand that the heart feel
warm or light or open however it feels is how it feels
so we'll turn the tables now and reflect on our own goodness
taking a few moments to reflect on ways that you've been
generous or kind forgiving patient
this reminds the heart that you too are worthy of love
and even if it's just very small amounts of kindness not sufficient
so rather than sending the phrases to ourselves we'll keep that person with us the one
that's easy to love we keep that being with us then we'll imagine them sending us the
phrases such that our grandmother or the Dalai
Lama or our our pet dog whatever being it is is actually
directing the loving kindness at us so we're leaning on their compassion on
their kindness
you might imagine them looking at you with a sense of warmth or love
sending you these phrases
may you be joyful and happy
may you be strong and healthy
may you be safe and free from harm
and may you be peaceful and at ease
allowing yourself to receive the meta from this being
may you be happy
may you be healthy
may you be safe
may you be free
we can take you in next few minutes just to see how that feels in the body
in the mind continuing with the phrases if you'd like or resting back with your primary anchor
doing whatever is most nourishing for you
may all beings know happiness and the causes of happiness
right welcome back hello to those of you who are just
arriving my name is May Elliott and today we'll be focusing on the second hindrance ill
will sometimes referred to as a version
uh ill will in poly is vyapada
and this hindrance of of ill will can manifest as anger
not liking judgment resentment discontent
denial fear boredom Etc so yesterday I spoke about the first
hindrance of sense desire so these these first two hindrances are um come as a
pair they're two sides of the same coin they're the forces of wanting and not
wanting and with each there's a wish to change our experience in some way to create a
better moment at the base of both of these mind States is this sentiment that
the moment isn't sufficient as it is I need more of something or I need less of
something to be okay and something that both desire and
aversion share is that they tend to be spellbinding not the narratives we tell
ourselves about what we want and what we don't want they really transfix us
um but at the heart Beneath The Narrative there's simply dissatisfaction
so so where does it come from where does ill will come from so aversion or ill
will are born from unwise attention to unpleasant experience
so aversions born from fixating on that which is unpleasant and when we meet
something that's unpleasant that's exactly what the Mind does it tends to fixate so ticknot Han used to talk about
uh the phenomenon of the one chipped tooth so if you've ever shipped a tooth
you may notice the way that the tongue goes to that chipped spot over and over
and over again there's almost an obsessive quality to it and in the same
way the mind fixates on what's unpleasant and from that fixation aversion is often born
so then how do we meet it so yesterday I introduced a very simple two-step process process or practice
that you can use for all of the hindrances so we'll play with that with a version right now so we start by doing
step one which is recognizing the aversion you know rather than just being fixated on the Noisy Neighbor or on the
bad traffic we recognize well this is aversion
then we drop the fixation on the object we let go of thinking about the Noisy
Neighbor for the bad traffic and instead we turn 180 degrees to feel the inner
experience so step two is that feeling the inner experience
there's a quote by Ralph Waldo Emerson that goes like this
if a dog is chasing you hear and whistle for it
if a dog is chasing you turn and whistle for it when there's something unpleasant we're
in contact with that's causing aversion all we typically want to do is get rid of it or make it stop but more often
than not we really can't change it the other version is already there
so when a dog is chasing you rather than running from it can you turn
180 degrees and whistle for it can you choose the experience rather than
fighting it it's like great I successfully recognized a version what a
victory this is a great thing um so so can we meet the moment in that
way can we meet our aversion with that mind [Music] um
I do want to acknowledge it can be hard to do the first step of recognizing a version because it's so easily hidden by
our Narrative of judgment rejection or disliking so in your meditation practice if you
notice yourself lost in thought yeah or maybe having repeated thought patterns
occurring you might just ask the question what's underneath this
what's underneath this and that might illuminate if aversion or maybe one of the other hindrances is
present actually fueling that thought pattern and it's not uncommon that we'll find
ourselves ruminating about something if we're feeling aversion towards it
the zen teacher Leanne shut talks about the hindrance this hindrance as
the parable twos as in t-o-o-s so if you're thinking a lot and you notice
yourself wanting to change or fix experience you might notice the mind that the mind is saying uh something
like too messy or too cold or too many bugs too itchy too loud
so when we're at this first step of recognizing the hindrance if you notice that sort of story playing in the mind
to this to that it's a likely sign that aversion is at work
so once we recognize you do that 180 degree turn and we feel
the aversion in the body we bring some curiosity to it so um as we discussed yesterday we might
be noticing if there's a temperature or pressure or contraction or tightness and
often aversion has an intense tightening in the body sometimes heat but see how
it is for you you might notice the energy in the body sometimes a version
has a lot of energy to it like anger is a very activating energetically because
there's often great motivation to fight or attack or to push away or expel
something so we can notice this energy in the body and sometimes noticing what's happening
in the body with some um it's kind of like a wide angle lens some sense of spaciousness I'm kind of
noticing what's happening happening in an expansive relaxed way sometimes I can just create a little bit more space
around the aversion we can as we do this step of feeling we
can also feel the hindrance in the mind what's the emotional tone the mind and
the Heart the cheetah what's the emotional tone what does it make you want to do are there repeating thought
patterns so that's our practice of recognizing and feeling
there's a story about vajan cha the great Thai Forest master who is one of
the lineage holders in our Western Insight tradition and in it ajan chav who is known for his
tremendous strength of practice I've been his peacefulness and good-heartedness he was sitting and
teaching as often happened under his little cootie and during one of these times a palm
reader an astrologer came to visit him many people came to visit Adan Chan so
he was one of many sitting around listening to tell stories and teach the Dharma
yeah so this Palm Reader was just activated by ajan Shah's humor and his
warmth and he knew that it would you know ajan cha might look down on him if he asked to read ajan Shah's Palm but he
couldn't resist so he finally summoned the courage to ask atancha if he could
look at the lines on his heart and of course teased him and said oh am I going to win
am I going to win the lottery but ajan Chao was willing and he offered his hand
to the reader and the palm reader 's hand
and after a little while with a good bit of confusion and some surprise he said
um excuse me the lines on your hands you've got a lot of anger
and ajan Cha smiled and said yes but I don't use it
so when we've learned to meet a hindrance over and over again and we can
do so with with clear recognition and a willingness to feel the hindrance in the
body without resistance we actually learn to divest from that hindrance and
we no longer need to be hijacked by it as ajan Shah said we don't need to use
it so as we do this practice of recognizing and feeling the hindrance of ill will
we end up undercutting the compulsion to use our anger in unskillful ways so the
more we're able to train in meeting this hindrance with mindfulness with patience
with non-judgment the less power it has over us we don't need to use it in
unskillful ways
so everything I've shared so far recognize and feel this should be the
typical approach to working with this hindrance however if the mind is overwhelmed if you really just can't
practice mindfulness with it that's when you might shift gears and apply the antidote and as mentioned earlier during
our meditation the traditional antidote to to anger to ill will is loving
kindness is the meta practice so the friendly mind of kindness can
actually obstruct aversion the sense of anger or disliking actually can't arise
when that's present so so this is something that we can engage if it's supportive to us
and we can lean on on the well-wishing of others you know we can bring to mind
and have somebody um that's been loving to us send us the loving kindness
so that actually still that grows the heart muscle that grows the strength of our of our capacity for kindness
I also want to mention um another antidote for aversion in daily life and that's the practice of
restraint all right so if the the um you know we we often really want to do
what the ill will tells us to do um but to practice restraint is to not
do that thing as in don't say the snarky thing to your partner uh or drive
aggressively or hurt someone um and and this this allows us to keep
our ill will from causing harm so practice restraining okay so those are a
few possible antidotes and then lastly as with all hindrances
notice moments when the mind is free of aversion so notice when it passes away
you know you might be totally consumed by anger and then at some point that that anger Fades away and the mind heart
is free so really let that absence register enjoy it when the mind is kind and at
ease really let that take that in
so today um if you'd like to take to pick this up as
a practice you might just notice any moment small or large where you
experience ill will or aversion so you might notice any moments where you feel frustrated maybe maybe it's while
watching the news um or maybe you don't get something that you had hoped for
or you might notice if you're internally judging yourself or another person so
just uh taking a moment to see if aversion is present throughout the day
and if you do recognize it recognize it as a version rather than just being fixated on the on
the storyline of what's Happening that's a great Victory right so this moment of recognition can
actually be a catalyst for gladness so in the midst of aversion you can
actually have a feeling of gladness like wow look at this I'm clearly seeing a
hindrance that's a great thing so so today
if the dog is chasing you I hope that you are able to turn and whistle for it
I hope you have a wonderful day thanks so much everyone take care