warm welcome to everybody wherever you
are all these different places before I turned on the recording I think it's beautiful that we all come
together in this way and maybe not surprisingly today I'm
going to continue on this series The Poetry of practice and so many things that we could say
about poetry but one thing that we could say is part of it power part of the way it makes an impact
on us is that allows us to see things in a different way maybe from a different
perspective a fresh perspective and sometimes it's even like a surprising
perspective which can bring you a sense of delight or maybe even a sense of like
wait what like with a twinge of uncertainty or you know shake things up
a little bit and I love this about poetry to be sure I'm not like a scholar in poetry or
literature or anything like that so I like poetry that has some imagery and
sometimes imagery allows us to consider things or experience things in a different way so today I'll share
another poem that uh has some imagery that I really appreciate this
poem and I'll drop in this poem after a short kind like guided meditation we
have a chance to settle and get quiet and then we can just allow this
poem to enter or touch Us in some kind of way
without having to analyze it or anything like that during the
meditation okay so with that as a introduction we can take a meditation
posture a figuration of the body configuration
maybe of the body that expresses Our intention to
meditate but also has some
ease traditionally this is in a sitting posture with a uprightness with a
steadiness usually focused around the spine the
spine being upright the vertebrae stacked on one another and letting the limbs just
hang the arms just hang from that
uprightness letting the spine be
upright and the muscles to be
relaxed feeling into that experience the experience that is being
had
now
and this is part of the art of practice is finding this
balance between alertness and
relaxation you can begin with feeling grounded
supported but whatever it is we're sitting
on or standing on or lying on or walking on whichever posture you're
[Music]
in feeling the pressure against the body feeling the
contact of the body with the
ground foundation and feeling the
stability that this contact
provides
and from this stableness can arise the spine or this sense of
uprightness
tuning into the bodily experience including the experience of
breathing feeling the movement of the body as it
breathes the obvious large movements as well as the more
subtle smaller movements without having to dig for
them but more receive them allow
them welcome them into
awareness noticing the real rym of the
breathing there's a way the Rhythm itself can be
supportive inhales and
exhales transitions between inhales and
exhales very simply just this pattern of [Music]
breathing being
repeated
it wouldn't be surprising if the Mind wandered and entered into imaginations
and stories and thoughts what if we don't make that a
problem instead we recognize that this is what Minds
do and we very simply gently Begin
Again tuning into becoming sensitive to the experience of breathing
nothing in particular needs to be
happening we're just noticing what's
happening and resting our attention on the sensations of
breathing
and can we bring an attitude of warmth and
care this experience to this moment and the next moment and the
next softening any
harshness
bringing a sense of presence to the
moments being present for the experience of
breathing
I'm going to drop in a
poem nothing you have to do with this palem just allow it to be
received at the end of this meditation after I ring the bell I'll give the name of the poem and the
poet but now just allow the poem to be we
experienced the poem goes like
this and the secret Temple of my heart was an altar with nothing on it I love
nothing the pure potential of it sometimes when others journeyed here
I sense they were surprised perhaps even sorry for me as if it would be better with a Lotus
or a cross or a star or figurine or a photo of someone or a stone always
something I tried in fact to put things on the altar but no thing let itself
stay there was a day when in a single moment the altar had everything on it
and by everything I mean everything every bee every stick every plastic bag
and Beetle every crushed empty can every crumpled shirt every door handle Compass
broken thermometer Apple trash can tree
everything and it was so beautiful I wept for
hours oh the pure potential of it and then that altar was no longer in
some secret temple in my heart but everywhere everywhere A Place To
Worship everything a prayer waiting to be heard to be
touched and inside the most beautiful
nothing not even an altar which is oddly everything I I
can't say how sometimes when I'm quiet enough I
notice it sometimes when I get out of the way I
fall all the way
in
I'll read the poem again
and the secret Temple of my heart was an altar with nothing on it I love nothing
the pure potential of it sometimes when others journeyed here
I sense they were surprised perhaps even sorry for me as if it would be better with a Lotus
or a cross or a star or figurine or a photo of someone or stone always
something I tried in fact to put things on the altar but no thing let itself
stay there was a day when in a single moment the altar had everything on it
and by everything I mean everything every bee every stick every
plastic bag and beetle every crushed empty can every crumpled shirt every
door handle Compass broken thermometer Apple trash can tree
everything and it was so beautiful I wept for
hours oh the pure potential of
it and then that altar was no longer in some secret temple in my heart but
everywhere everywhere A Place To
Worship everything a prayer waiting to be heard to be
touched and inside the most beautiful
nothing not even an altar which is oddly everything I can't say
how sometimes when I'm quiet enough I notice it
sometimes when I get out of the way I fall all the way
in
[Music]
so this poem has a curious title it's a very long
title I I'll say the poet is Rosemary traumer she spells her first name like
like Merry Christmas Rosemary traumer beautiful wonderful
poet and the title of this poem is after reading what's in the temple by Tom
Barrett I considered his question so Tom Barrett is another poet
who wrote a poem called what's in the temple so again the title of what I just
read is after reading what's in the temple by Tom Barrett I considered his
question by Rosemary
trummer so to continue our exploration of uh
poetry and practice or the Poetry of practice maybe I'll share something that
um John Brum who's a created a collection of mindfulness
poems none of the poems that I have been sharing are in this collection but he
um mindfulness teacher I believe and he writes that poetry presents a powerful
way to disrupt the habitual momentum of the Mind its automatic reactions and
obsessive self-c concerns and uh he continues saying to
fully enter a poem we must first stop and step away from the more immediate
demands of life and engage in an imaginative activity that has no obvious
practical value I appreciate is bringing in this way in that to enter a poem is where we
have to stop or interrupt the normal way of thinking or the usual way of doing
whatever it is we do and to engage in imaginative activity so that if right
the poems do require a certain imagination especially ones that have a lot of
imagery and then I like that uh John brem includes it has no obvious practical value yeah right so often
we're concerned with what's practical but and lastly this is the
last thing I'll say from John Prem he writes more importantly we must shift
out of our everyday Consciousness the Speedy mind wrapped in its self centered
stories and projections right usually our minds are you know trying to make us
happy and avoid difficulties and Stave off pain and difficult
emotions but if I were to stretch John brm's uh discussion about poetry I would
say that um maybe to fully enterr a poem he's talking about it is to interrupt
the momentum of what the Mind usually does but what if we say to fully enter a poem is to enter the Temple of the heart
rather than being in the thinking of the mind and maybe in this
way the form of today's offering also kind of um is related to the content the
fact that it's a poem so I'll read this poem again one
that I just dropped into the guided meditation the title
is after reading what's in the temple by Tom Barrett I considered his question
and I'll unpack that a little bit uh after I read the poem The poet is
Rosemary traumer I I just love Rosemary trummer's
poems I she has a a lot of Whimsy and uh
and she's a Buddhist practitioner as well and it kind of shines through in her
poetry so here's the poem in the secret Temple of my heart
was an altar with nothing on it I love nothing
the pure potential of it sometimes when others journeyed here
I sense they were surprised perhaps even sorry for me as if it would be better
with a Lotus or a cross or a star or a figurine or a photo of something someone
or stone always something I tried in fact to put things
on the altar but no thing let itself stay
there was a day when in a single moment the altar had everything on it and by
everything I mean everything every bee every stick every plastic bag and Beetle
every crushed empty can every crumpled shirt every door handle Compass broken
thermometer Apple trash can tree everything and it was so beautiful I
wept for hours oh the pure potential of
it and then that altar was no longer in some secret temple in my heart but
everywhere everywhere A Place To Worship everything a prayer waiting to be heard
to be touched and inside the most beautiful
nothing not even an altar which is oddly
everything I can't say how sometimes when I am quiet enough I
notice it sometimes when I get out of the way I
fall all the way
in so this poem that's called what's in the temple by Tom Barrett because we've kind of
like entered into a conversation between two poets Rosemary trummer's respon to what
Tom Barrett have wrote and Tom Barrett's poem includes this these lines if you
had a temple and the secret spaces of your heart what would you worship there
what would you bring to sacrifice and in this poem Tom Barrett's
poem he also includes this lines we don't build many temples anymore maybe
we learned that the sacred can't be contained
so this question what what do you worship what do you
sacrifice and rosemary tra her response is to say that she's not making these
distinctions that as soon as we designate something as sacred then everything else by definition becomes
profane and of course you know our minds make these
distinctions but if we are saying something sacred then saying it's like spiritually significant and treated with
reverence and respect and there's certain rules or Norms about how we
interact with them so if something is sacred kind of
like implicit in this also is this idea that this will help me find more freedom this will help me find more peace this
will help me find more ease but of course implicit in that is
everything else that isn't sacred the the the profane those things or activities that don't have any spiritual
significance they're the ordinary the everyday the secular and implicit in that is like oh
this won't help me find more freedom oh this is you know an
obstacle and rosemary traumer in this poem she's pointing to what if we stop making those St
distinctions then everything becomes sacred even the ugly The
Unwanted everything becomes connected to beauty and
truth even the very ordinary these things that we tend to dismiss or disregard or just not even
notice Rosemary traumer in includes in her poem like every crumpled shirt every
door handle Compass broken thermometer Apple trash can tree like in my mind I'm just imagining
that the poet is just sitting there and just kind of like looking around and just naming you know what's there and
that visual experience but there's a way in which we
label things conflict you know limits
them because it's makes it this and not that which of
course is true but it also maybe undermines that sense that
meditation of practice is about being present for whatever is
arising and just by our folding it into our practice whatever the experience is
is a way that we find more freedom so what happens if we we stop
labeling things and I know this is um contrary to
what um practice instructions are and to be sure it's very helpful to label but
to make note of things but what if there's a way that we
can be within experience without reifying it without limiting it without
somehow like making it permanent and I first discovered this
the very first time I ever entered some or heard some Buddhist teachings the teacher this was in a yoga
studio uh gave this expression they were holding up an object for them it was a a
a pen but in the same way I'm holding up a striker Striker for the Bell I'm calling it a striker so you
know it is a striker that's how it can be used but maybe it's also a back
scratch or something that can help you reach a place in your back or what if it's a somebody you
wanted to like scare an intruder or something and you can throw this object
or and it would be I don't know something a weapon or something or maybe
if um this got taped to my hand and it would become like a splint you know I'm just making up these things right but
that this one object as soon as we call it a striker it's
limited it's just this it's not all those other
things so to be sure labels are helpful and important and we need them and we
use them and this is what naturally happens the Mind does but what if we softened all these
labels sacred poane Bell strier back
scratcher and if we are stopping making these distinctions between sacred and
profane then there is no longer a maker of the
distinctions there's no longer an entity that's at the center that's assigning
things sacred or profane there's no longer something that's here like oh yes
this is good this is bad this will help me in my spiritual life this [Music]
won't so this idea of making something sacred or profane revolves around a
center the center that's a me or mine this will help me or this won't help
me what if there's no Center what if there's just experiences
without a center and I think this is what the poet
is pointing to when she writes sometimes when I get out of the
way I fall all the way
in and this is real Freedom this is a real deep
freedom and I know this is a paradox about
making labels or distinctions and not making them but this is part of the Paradox of practice and maybe the art of
practice so this idea of softening lessening this making the
distinction between what goes in the temple and what's outside of the Temple
what if everything is ordinary what if everything is
extraordinary thank you thank you for your practice and maybe what would it be like
today to notice everything in a way that isn't
dismissive not in a way that we have to furtively you know always be mindful of everything but just um to be
with whatever the moment brings us whatever the m whatever is arising in
the moment thank you and we see you
tomorrow
I