so uh so good morning folks happy birthday Mary uh 75th birthday one of
our uh sa friends here
um so uh yeah please uh settle in and
uh um let's see what
happens
just
uh settling into posture you can uh say
yes to making whatever ever adjustments you
need
be some uh
gratitude just for for being alive here together
conscious
incredible number of things have to go
right for us to be aware
of course it won't always be like this and
so we kind of uh
rejoice in Awareness as we begin here
together
there's effort in uh
practice kind of subtle effort of of uh directing
attention preferentially to
uh the breath the body feeling the
mind the of
uh letting things be amidst
imperfection choosing not to fiddle with uh some
s
but we also want to attune to uh what is effortless what requires
nothing of uh of us doesn't create a sense of uh burden
on the meditating
self
so there's uh an aspect of awareness that
uh doesn't depend on
you
can't be initiated by an act of
will nor can it be
stopped but when we are in fact
aware can appreciate the uh effortlessness of it that this doesn't
actually burn any attentional
calories
just
awake because it doesn't uh depend on you
whatever you think you
is you can
uh completely take your hands off all the levers and
knobs
because this uh dimension of awareness doesn't depend on you you whatever you
is can uh completely
relax
it's a little like the the awareness blooms and
collapses collapses into an object into a
thought and then uh come to appreciate mindfulness as a certain kind of
Grace
we come to witness a a process that
uh does not involve our
willfulness sense the limitations of our willfulness is a way of
practicing
and of course there's a time for
effort and this uh dimension of effortlessness
whatever you can't
stop rest
there the awareness that you can't
stop it's
rest
so excuse me um the theme um has been uh the more assertive
the more and more receptive qualities of mind and uh today wanted to um say
something about uh action and being passive activity and
passivity the um is a common question maybe the most most common
misunderstanding of uh of equinity is that it's tantamount
to um uh to
passivity um but uh shinzen young uh nice language around this that
e equinity is a relationship with sensory experience not
apathy uh about the objective conditions of the world a relationship to sensory
experience not apathy about the world so
equinity now does not equal passivity in the next moment or tomorrow or
whenever we are uh soft animals and who
are compulsively trying to optimize experience
and consequently d teachers emphasize the the the passive receptive dimensions
of practice often but a lot of that passivity is actually
in service of action and a Dharma life requires a lot of
action we practice being passive uh so that we can discern what
action buys us and what it costs
us Retreat Retreat practice which many of you have done Retreat practice is a
kind of experiment in passivity we relinquish almost all
choices there's a schedule almost every minute we're told where to be what to
do and so we relinquish almost all decision making we we sort of take our
hands off all all the knobs right and we we practice a kind of
radical form of of passivity experimenting a kind of
experiment that exactly what this moment
offers is enough or maybe we say is right
and we're no longer kind of in in Retreat for example we're no longer
using this moment to predict the trajectory of our day our
week our life this moment this moment has really no meaning outside of this
moment I don't know whether it's right but but it me is like maybe we're practicing a kind of
momentary nihilism we're momentary nihilist just
right now but in doing
that uh we begin to understand where our
habitual actions come from what they accomplish the agitation
they cost the relief that they buy us the relief that actions buy us and the
relief that never never
comes and so uh this is a kind of this is a cultivation of our own heart and it
um makes life whatever it brings richer more poignant Freer
we could just say better makes life better to cultivate
this and uh these kind of experiments in passivity also help
us become more effective in our
action is maybe not emphasize so much but practice it it shapes our mind
but then our mind shapes our life and it's a kind of virtuous um
cycle so part of Dharma practice is about making our actions
more effective and
efficient yeah is it not just the the receptivity it's about making our actions more effective and efficient and
part of how we excuse
me part of how we uh we do this is uh through developing our
understanding like if we do not understand this foundational Noble Truth
that there is Dua there is uh incompletion the moment
is incomplete um if we do not understand that if we do not understand a nich that
that the world trembles in all directions as the Buddha said if we do
not understand these things our actions are actually less effective if they're
made on the Assumption of permanence and utopian
fantasy they're less effective if we do not understand the kind of
um un quench ability of the craving
mind we waste so much energy and time and
money if our actions emerge out of the kind
of fever dream of craving rather than the sobriety balance bance of
Desire we're less effective because desire desire doesn't
forget the first Noble Truth craving always
does so many of our calculations in our in our life go something like well if I
do this I get that and if I get that I will feel like this whatever this is
uh but the basis of of wise action is really understanding that action only
changes some karmic streams and not
others so we have to know ourselves really well we have to understand pleasure really well in order to be well
calibrated we talk um all about the present moment but we're
actually getting better at the future at prediction at forecasting our
own reactions and predicting the chances of success
and predicting forecasting the kind of responses of others
too understanding others was reading um uh Allison gnik a
developmental psychologist researcher um she's studied how how
children's Minds develop you know and uh she writes um love love
itself depends on knowledge and Imagination from the time they're very small babies are figuring out theories
of love based on what they see the caregivers around them do and say for
babies who are so utterly helpless and dependent no theory is as important as a
theory of love that's so so beautiful somehow you
know it's like no theory is as important as a theory of Love helpless dependent baby yeah
and maybe as um adults we we of course keep refining
our theory of love and those refinements those
calibrations of our theory of love this helps us live and make
choices and so we we develop uh we
develop a theory of love we develop a theory of of our self self
knowledge and uh come to be very aware of our of our strengths and goodness and
also our our limitations you know we come to
appreciate our limitations in a in an utterly non-m moralistic
way uh no there's no ground whatsoever for shame it's just
H these are the limits of my equinity and to know the limits of our
equinity and respect those limits is important in
actually uh acting wisely right we talk
about like believing in ourselves and trust and all this yeah that's right but we also got to know what our nightmares
are and the places where we just have to honor the kind of depth of our own
clinging I you know I I don't mean that in pejorative way it's just like oh yeah
I can't I know I can't let go when conditions are like this I can't
let go and so then we need to choose a kind of another strategy for dealing
that with that in some way and maybe like I I need to do what I can not to
put myself in that condition and so we we cultivate a kind of respect
for the power of our own habit energies right and yeah we want to work with them
we want to expand the capacity of our heart but in determining a kind of we do it subconsciously but in determining a
wise course of action the limitations of our equinity has to be a premise in that
argument our actions are uh uh made more effective by understanding others
empathy a theory of love we know their goodness are moved by it inspired by it
reminded of our own goodness by others uh we bow down to
it and we also understand the egoic fragility of
others the the kind of uh pressure points in their egoic structure if you
do not understand the egoic fragility of others you wind up uh uh often
trespassing on sacred terrain and this is not good
for relations right we have to kind of in a sense
respect the zones of clinging of each other and treat those with a certain
kind of uh uh
care and so uh we we develop uh in the kind of
receptivity passivity we develop certain heart qualities goodness uh
and goodwi and Goodwill dissipates a lot of
problems um I'm not I'm not uh I don't even
really know what the secret is or the law of attraction but everything I do know I
don't like it just always struck me as kind of like uh the self- congratulatory
grandiosity of the privileged right did you Manifest this
misogyny all this racism
no and when love begins
to uh seep from your pores uh generally people would become
less afraid of you and less defensive
and with that a lot of good things start
happening so we shape our mind our mind shapes our
life we practice Dharma shapes shapes our inner life and
our inner life shapes our our world and uh this is the
virtual a cycle so passivity
action close here and
um yeah wish you all a good day yeah moments of
receptivity moments of action and uh we'll gather back for a
last day together tomorrow okay thank you uh thank you all