all right so hello and welcome to happy hour
so for today's theme of practice
um I'd like to invite us to consider a uh starting starting with meta with
kindness loving kindness for ourselves for this body and then spreading it outward spreading
it outward but we start from ourselves and if you've been coming to happier for
a while you know that we uh we always start um we tend to start by filling our own
cup um and then we share then we spread we
shift we take on the perspective of kindness care not just for this being for that is me but for all beings
everywhere so that's going to be the progression and um
and whatever arises as long as you are kind as long as you
make space for whatever Rises you're doing this practice right whatever Rises
as long as you're kind if it's pain in the body
ah if you're kind to it if you make space for it
if you receive it with Good Will instead of aversion pushing it away
just be kind be kind be kind that's all his practice is about cultivating
kindness towards whatever Rises so with that as
the Prelude let's begin let's settle
in our bodies in this moment arriving
as well as we are able to
relaxing in this moment
and inviting the awareness the attention
to receive the sensations
of sitting of our feet our legs on the Earth
sensations of our bottom on the cushion
our hands on our lap sense of a brightness
integrity
sitting with dignity
and letting there be a relaxation awareness
relaxed receiving the breath
in the abdomen
thank you
if you notice that thoughts or moving here and there
it's okay can we be kind can there be kindness
not aversion not self-reproment oh I've been thinking
again no no need really no need
can there be a celebration of oh this moment
I'm alert I'm awake
celebrating this moment
instead of reprimanding yourself you have a choice 50 50. what do you choose
train the mind and kindness and Delight not in reprimand
Let There Be enjoyment Delight
of this breath this nourishing life-giving breath
in breath and not breath
entirety of the in-breath
the entirety of the out breath
and help us stay connected
staying connected to the entirety of the inbra and the out breath
deceiving with gratitude lightness is
at this moment saving the breath in the abdomen In This
Moment be a refuge dealing acquiring
in nourishment in the heart
whatever is arising In This Moment can the response of the heart
be one of ease one of kindness it's okay it's okay dear it's okay
one of comfort one of care
and if that's not possible can there be care and acceptance of
the resistance pushing away the aversion
can we make space for that with kindness
is there any challenges pain difficulty in the body
or in the mind or in the heart
and we make space for it to be here just as it is
and as if we were holding the tender newborn rocking the newborn
with care with patience can we try on the same
stance the same caring embrace
whatever might be challenging
and if there is nothing challenging In This Moment there is ease
holding making space
for the ease
Goodwill and kindness
with which we hold the goodness with it
see what is appropriate In This Moment for this mind body and heart
if you like to add the phrases of meta compassion you're welcome to
or not it's a simple version of the phrases
I wish myself well may I be well
may I be happy
may I Meet myself with kindness
thank you
other Alternatives may I love and accept myself just as I am
or may my heart open to the possibility of loving myself
as I am no pushing
forcing wherever it's easy accessible
may I be well
may I Meet myself with Goodwill I Meet myself with kindness
thank you and there be an infusion of kindness with each breath
so if each breath in breath that is received
brings in infuses our body or harder mind with Good Will with kindness every
cell of the body
released into kindness
care with the out breath
and breath and the out breath kindness in
kindness out Goodwill in Goodwill out
but dwell in Good Will out with each breath
witnessing goodness out breathing and care
breathing out care
breathing in care to this body heart mind this being who is me
In This Moment In Time and breathing out Goodwill
sharing your kindness with all beings everywhere
just as I wish to be happy
others wish to be happy I wish them well I wish them happiness with each breath
I wish myself goodness
friendliness well-being I wish others
the same friends
relatives loved ones
may they be well those I don't know
neutral beings so many beings on this planet may they be well
those I am entangled with have challenges with they want to be
happy just like me I wish both of us well
in this entanglement may we be well may they be well
foreign
[Music]
[Music] Goodwill 360 Degrees internally
externally all around
may I be kind
may I Meet myself may I meet others with generosity of spirit with good
wealth with care
and as we bring this practice period to close
if there are any judgments or criticisms arising for what happened or
did not happen can we be kind
thank you self-judgment thank you
you're trying to help and no need it's okay
thank you for trying to help and support me it's all okay
letting there be kindness Goodwill towards yourself
appreciation that you showed up you did your best
as best as you were able to show up you did
you get responsibility for intentions
and letting go of the outcome the outcome is not within
our control and sharing your goodness sharing the
Merit goodness of our practice with all beings everywhere
may all beings be well may all beings be free
including ourselves
thanks everyone thanks for your practice
breathing out breathing in Good Will goodness breathing out goodness
breathing in Good Will for this body or this heart or this mind meeting May I
meet this moment with kindness may I Meet myself with good wealth whatever is
arising and meeting others meeting whatever is arising other beings
with Good Will and kinds so meeting others with Good Will and
kindness and meeting ourselves with kindness we have the opportunity at happy hour in
small groups practice meeting ourselves in relationship meeting others in
relationship with kindness it's a sad box it's a sandbox
you don't have to say much you can have you can say past Soul silence kind
silence you can also share a few words if you
wanted to for your own benefit not to educate not to edify but just to share
from your own experience what arose in your practice and anything
is fine oh I was kind to myself there was a judgment or there was pain in the
body and oh and I was kind or I fell asleep I missed the whole
thing that's perfectly fine there are no right or wrong answers as long as you're kind you show up with
kindness towards yourself and you show up with kindness towards others it's a Sandbox and when you notice you get
heady just stop it's okay breathe we're all walking each other home as ramdas
said we're just practicing together in this swimming how how is it like what is
it like to let go of the ego a little bit just be kind and if the ego shows up
it's okay you can be kind to it too so so I'm going to create the breakout
rooms now and the invitation is again speak from
your own experience um not asking questions not directing anyone else's experience
and um start we'll start with reverse
alphabetical order first name say what a nugget what do you noticed if
you want or you can say pass um say something brief maybe 30 seconds
maybe a minute or not and then the next person the next person I'll come back to
you so you'll go around a few times make sure everybody has time to speak don't make your monologue too long let it be a
brief offering from your heart you're showing up with other practitioners who
are here to cultivate kindness can you show up in fact when you when the group
opens when you go to the groups to spend just spend maybe a few seconds in
silence just sharing Goodwill for one another oh dear beings on this Zoom room may you
be well just in silence just wish each other well before you start to uh speak
so so with that I'm going to open the
breakout rooms be kind to yourself be kind to others that's all that matters
okay okay welcome back everyone welcome back
your rooms are closed and we have a few minutes for Reflections so uh I'm also
going to change the chart settings so you can type them to me directly in which case they'll be private uh I'll
only read the reflection not your name or you can type them to everyone if you want in which case I'll read your
reflection and your name as well and you can also raise your hand just like Claire hi Claire
hmm I know I spoke recently so I'll be brief but we were talking about the
physical aspects of the meditation tonight and I was just trying to tell the rest of my team that I actually sort
of started meditating as a cyclist when you're on the bike you can't think
you just have to deal with your body and your environment and and focus on that
there's no thinking going on and it's a form of meditation
yeah it's a different way of being very present in the moment yeah it's very interesting climbing too also rock
climbing as well it's very easy to be so present in the discursive yeah so many
different types of meditations like sports right there's so many different types thanks that's why I like to do it
because it gets me out of here yeah yeah I think he might yeah thank you
thanks Claire I see Fred and Barbara's hand up please
yeah it's me who raised my virtual hand hi Fred I am and Nikki good to see you
you too as as uh we were signing off in the small group one of the people in our
group was saying um meeting in this group in a regular
way you know for you know more than a couple of years now uh at least for me uh had had changed her life and I
thought yes that's that's true uh I feel that too it's not it's not uh
it's not an exaggeration yeah and I I just feel you know sitting with this
Sangha but also sitting in the morning too you know being with people whose faces I don't say for the
most well I guess I don't see them um that has another feeling too but it's
there's an intimacy that I've never felt sitting with people in person and
um building a frame of the day with with the two sittings I just feel so
so grateful to um you know first of all Nikki I feel so grateful to you for for
hanging in with us for a long time and I know you have plenty of other things to do too but to everybody who who keeps
showing up and um I thank you all it's it's just really been important and just tremendously
helpful sorry Fred thank you so much for
the awards of of kindness and and and
wisdom of appreciating and also sharing another person in your group that oh yes things have shifted your life the way
you the way you respond the the the
things have shifted and wow to actually pause and acknowledge that is profound
is the fact that it has happened and you notice that it has happened and also the sense of appreciation and and gratitude
all of that it it it brings so my joy to my heart so my joy to my
heart yes this is possible this is possible this is the path this is the
practice and and there is a lot of support online the
thanks to covid and also I turn it back to you Fred as you would know as you
would expect I would in this moment to point out that you're the one who's hanging in with the practice you've hung
in there for a couple of years showing up uh to happier and also to the morning
the 7 A.M West Coast time and so it's really you it's the beauty of your
practice your continuity your continuity that yes this this this goodness this
co-created goodness arises from from your goodness from your
contribution so thank you so much thank you for for all your practice and
everything that that you've been hanging in here for as long as you have with your practice and everyone and everyone
else yeah thank you Fred that I see that their
Reflections their bunch of Reflections um in uh yes I agree with Fred thank you
says or uh Hugh says ditto yeah and
um oh and Mary says I've been away from happy hour for a week so grateful and
happy to be back with Nikki and everyone welcome back Mary lovely to have you back
and Jerry says I loved the Simplicity of love loving kindness but love kindness
in and love kindness out my heart seemed also very at peace lovely beautiful
thank you Sherry thanks for that reflection yeah yeah and
um and Kane also on YouTube is sharing their their appreciation then their
thanks for many of the teachers their naming um from inside meditation center and
cheers from Perth Australia thank you Kane the smallness of kind
of nice in a way too yeah the smallest is kind of nice in the way too yeah
thank you thank you Kane for for your Reflections any other Reflections before
we close bring the session to a close
I see your hand I swear yeah I might say your name right
yes you're singing perfectly right thank you as I said I'm pretty new to this but
I've always been meditating in some form or the other I just realized today as I was
meditating what a luxury it is and you know it's one of the best things
I can do for myself it's just sitting there being loving to myself
valuing my energy that if I send it out into this world it's going to matter
uh it's just such a luxury thank you thank you for I'm just so
grateful that this is here and I found it so thank you thank you for everyone
who's here and especially and thank you thank you so much
beautiful yeah what a you know it's both a luxury and it's a
necessity it's a necessity that we spend our time this way we we incline
our minds towards kindness towards ourselves towards the world it's
um it's both a necessity and luxury and it's a radical act in in these times
because it's so easy to give into to give into hatred and disillusionment and
and not enoughness I'm not enough I'm not good enough I'm not good others are
not whoa ouch ouch ouch so it's actually a necessity it's
getting in touch it's it's inclining our hearts towards goodness to reconnect our hearts
with its own goodness to see our own goodness it grows it grows when we see
our own goodness it it shines it grows both for our own benefit and also for
the benefit of the world we do this so that we can serve it's this is not you
know when I use the word luxury it's not this luxurious thing that we do for self you know uh self preoccupy we're just
gonna know there's a reason for it and the reason for it is so that we become Kinder gentler not just to ourselves but
to everybody else so that we serve so it's
it is it is out of service it out it's out of love it's out of the the
bodhisattva wow it's the body cheetah intention to serve all beings including
this being who is myself with love and care so so meditation is a necessity
thank you all thank you for your Reflections for your practice it's such
a joy such a joy and Delight to to be serving to be supporting this wonderful
Sangha just makes me so so happy and no matter how I'm feeling how tired and
pain when I I when I come and and sit with you and and uh practice I feel
better always so it's uh it's a privilege definitely a privilege thank
you for allowing me to support you thank you all thank you for your practice and may all beings be well may
all beings be happy including ourselves
thanks everyone take care