welcome everyone to this
edition of happy hour so for today's practice I want to invite
us to to befriend our mind befriend our mind
befriend our might befriend our mind sometimes
it seems like our we're not so friendly with our minds our
minds run around thinking about past and future and
causing trouble and and then we are not so friendly with our mind we're in
in a little battle with our mind so what if we were actually befriended our mind
and I went offer a couple of metaphors one is one that I've used before is idea
of a puppy a little puppy that Runners runs around and just
being a puppy it's being being a puppy being a puppy is is you know the nature
of mine to think about the past future Etc another metaphor actually is uh the two
are similar and uh like little little kittens you know little kittens are cute
and they get into trouble you know they can make a mess they can make noise it's
not that you know it's their nature and also there's so many causes and conditions about being a kitten being
curious being interested being uh playful and and
um the cause and conditions of of kitten nests the suction is the being a a kitty
or being a a little puppy dog and our minds we take
them so personally we take them we take everything we take every thought
we take every yeah every thought every emotion everything so personally what if the
same way that we had the sense of kindness friendliness it's just we laugh
maybe you know the little kittens are making a mess you know in the kitchen but we kind of laugh like they're cute
and and it's just this is the this is the way to be a kitten and we don't take
it so personally right this what if we had the same
perspective we took the same perspective with our minds befriended our minds a
sense of meta a sense of kindness with our minds maybe our minds are grumpy
okay grumpy mind okay grumpy mind instead of okay I'm grumpy
or whatever else is all right can we have just a little bit of ease can we
let there be a little bit of ease of not taking it so seriously so so personally
not taking it so per not taking our minds so personally and those of you who
are familiar with the teachings of in personality or not self or I might have
heard of them in Buddhism that it's not everything isn't so personal there's so many causes and conditions to this being
to the thoughts that are arising to the emotions that are rising not everything is is
um and in fact not a lot of it is is controlled or governed by us we think
like we have control over our thoughts and our mind but actually if you spend
just a little bit of time in meditation paying attention to your mind you
realize that yeah it's you know we have some of course we have responsibility and we have we can
condition our minds to be settled and and condition them to be kind Etc but
they're not as governable as we like them to be so and the best way actually
to have to have a relationship with our minds is to befriend them that's the start because if we are don't befriend
them if we if we beat them up if we take them personally if we
Badger ourselves with blame um it's a non-starter it's a non-starter
we can't quite cultivate um our minds and hearts so let's start
by befriending our minds so that's the uh invitation for today's practice so
with that let's sit let's sit if you need to move and shift to be comfortable
in your sitting posture that there be ease
and let ease guide you let there be ease in your body and your mind
there are no shoulds no hafters
let there be ease
guarding with this dance of friendliness towards our mind
or it's our body
there might be challenging thoughts arising challenging
Sensations in the body can we soften not take everything personally or
believe everything that comes up and be friendly
friendly kind as we would be with a puppy or kittens making a mess in the kitchen
letting awareness connect with the breath the entirety of being breath the entirety of the out breath
help the puppy the kitten settled a little bit
when you notice that they're running around not a problem don't make
it into a problem it's their nature it's all right
simply notice with kindness
with their settling on what they're doing and then ever so
gently invite them to come rest on your lap
with the breath celebrate that they're resting on your lap with the breath for
a moment celebrate that celebrate this
moment of being present as if you celebrate it you take Delight
more and more of them will happen
and we befriend our mind
be a good friend
it is said that in order to have a good friend you need to have a lot of forgiveness
and we have a lot of forgiveness for this mind a lot of friendliness
befriending the mind befriending the heart
when we befriend the puppy of the Mind heart
kittens that run around not take them so personally but have kindness compassion
[Music]
patience forgiveness presence
how can I be a good friend to myself in this month
how can I befriend this mind This Heart
befriending the mind
knowing with friendliness befriending this mind
and as we bring this create a practice to close together
can we befriend befriend this mind befriend this heart
for whatever arose or did not arise
during this practice period
just as forgiving as we would be to a good friend
understanding that they're doing their best
they've done their best interesting that
by showing up by showing up and even planting
one seed of friendliness towards our mind towards our heart
trusting that it will come to fruition in its own time not our
time not our demands our our impatience but its own time
air practice be of benefit not just to ourselves but to all those
whose lives We Touch directly and indirectly may all beings be happy may all beings
be free including ourselves
thanks everyone
oh the topic but we
practice with or invited us to to consider today was befriending
befriending our minds befriending the mind one is back welcome back and we have
some time for reflections questions observations especially if you
haven't spoken in community for a while I'd like you to pull forward and if
you've spoken recently to please pull back and you can raise your Zoom hand because I will not be able to see your
physical hand and um you can also type your Reflections or
questions in chat either to everyone or to me privately and if it's sent to me
privately I will only read your reflection not your name so that it will remain private so what did you notice in
this practice befriending your mind what was there a moment that something
shifted a little bit or just maybe shifted throughout became just a little calmer a little Kinder
maybe you've noticed something in the group when you talked with one another
God I see your hand
yeah um for me it was uh suspending judgment was a kind act I can be very
critical and um and the meditation was
um yeah it's a very nice and you know I appreciated the prompt of being kind and
yeah for me for this sort of letting the the Judgment go was a kind act over
nice thank you for sharing that Don and that is so significant and so profound
when we can just suspend the judgment and be more kind it can be the seed for so much transformation to happen thank
you thanks for sharing that um bill says thank you Nikki my mind
wondered but I didn't seem to care too much I enjoyed it not sure if that's good or not yeah yeah so that's a good
question bill so so it's um
you know it's not helpful to to be judgmental when the mind wanders
that's we know that's not helpful because we're just seeding more judgment And yet when the mind wanders and we
enjoy the wandering then we're also seeding we're also
encouraging the Mind especially during meditation if you've decided that this is a time to sit if you were enjoying
the minute the the wandering then we are encouraging or encouraging the puppy to
have bad habits so we want to actually you know we want to have a a wise we
want to be friendly but we want to give encouraging and
helpful instructions to the puppy so if you notice that your mind is wandering
like okay puppy it's okay you can be kind and yet instead of just letting it
wander around give it helpful instructions bringing it back to the breath or bringing it back
to the body or or um or to the practice of meta so so not
helpful to just let it roam around and enjoy the wandering bill as I'll give
you that note to pay attention to you are welcome
Jamie says my puppy was very cute and comforting at a difficult time I just
hope I can resist calling it in insistently when my mind is less settled in future sets yeah
um yeah that's sweet thanks for sharing that Jamie May mayor puppy may you be
kind to your puppy may your puppy learn to be kind and and gentle and learn from
the gentle instructions any other observations before we
clothes Marianne
I I just noticed that since I went on Retreat a couple of weeks ago that
um I'm not sure I'm getting less distracted I don't think that's really
really changed too much in terms of like quantity or percentage of the time but when I am not distracted it has a
different quality to it it seems like I'm going back to how it was after a few days at in Retreat kind of fast like
connect to the Mothership or some kind of feeling yeah what to make of that yeah so so
wait so so let me make sure I understand what you're saying so so uh seems like
your mind maybe has quieted down a little bit or there's more distraction say that again Marion I don't think I I
grasp it it hasn't really quieted down that much maybe a little but when it
does quiet down it goes deeper faster ah got it okay yeah right interesting
it's interesting yeah you're great yeah you know that is the impact of going on
Retreat it changes our minds it changes our minds so yes because we come back to
the world under a lot of things to to um uh to to attend to uh and yet as you're
noticing when the mind when it settles it it has learned something the puppy
has learned something some new tricks and it's or if we talk about in terms of uh psychological or Neuroscience terms
there's some Pathways that now have have become more accessible and and more
learned so when the Mind settles like oh yes it goes back into what you cultivated on Retreat yay hooray it's
lovely Miriam delighted for you yeah um so one question is coming about uh
would you say a little about how to practice loving kindness um there's so many different ways to
practice loving kindness and meta so many different ways and the way we were doing it tonight is a different way it's
just cultivating kindness towards your mind it's not without with phrases it's not with other beings there's a lot of
different ways to do it and and the more traditional ways is with the phrases with an image of someone or image of
yourself and with the phrases and the sense of Goodwill um a lot of different ways and the way
we're doing it tonight I'm so very very subtle way um of befriending the mind because
basically a meta loving kindness the practice of kindness as long as you cultivate kindness due to
so many different ways to do it you can radiate it Etc and if you want the person who's asked this question if you
want more specific instructions about the the directions the the specifics of
that there are recordings on audio dharma.org and if you do a search for if
you go to audiodarma.org and this might be actually helpful to people who have joined more recently if
you go to audiodarma.org and do a search for happy hour series happy hour series
there's a long series that I think has 40 40 or so uh instructions in it
and and that actually covers all the nuts and bolts and
nitty-gritty details of it well so many ways to practice meta and compassion and
and vicarious joy and Equanimity it's a complete series that goes through all
the categories and all the Brahma viharas so so that is what I recommend you check out
yeah dances had not thought of it that way a way to practice meta is of course it's meta yeah meta by any name Rose by
Any name it's just not um not with the phrases and not with beings but as long
we are cultivating kindness befriending our mind there you go thank you Neil you
put the series number and it's series number one eight one eight seven on Audio Dharma so so thank you all for
your practice for your cultivation to benefit your yourself all beings every
way thank you so much may you be well may you be happy may all beings be well
and happy and free thank you
[Music] thanks everyone