okay welcome welcome folks
yeah good to see names streaming over there
um okay so we'll do what we do
um
so please uh settle into a posture that balances
relaxation alertness
and sometimes we try to establish mindfulness through
attention to an object a breath or sound or something
and sometimes it can be useful even before
identifying an object to establish mindfulness first what does
that mean for you
what needs to unwind in you to establish mindfulness
what do you need to make peace with to establish mindfulness
what images or words Inspire your heart
support the establishment of mindfulness
what ruminations do you have to have one more time
before you sense their dead end nature
what inspires your impulse to to know to understand
to be awake
and then as we establish some sense of presence
maybe the attention naturally can
embrace the object it doesn't feel like
squeezing the mind into some narrow slot
doesn't feel like putting toothpaste back in the
the tube
this natural
perhaps to sense the
sensations of your breathing
natural to notice the beginning [Music]
ending of the inhale
in the beginning ending of the exhale
and the release at the bottom of the exhale
kind of suspension in time okay
open
receptive
there's the way we direct our attention but then there's so much happening in
the meditating mind
ideas and Frameworks in the background
and sometimes we need gentleness gentle
thee in this forgiveness
that is mindfulness
we're giving samsara forgiving ourselves
and sometimes we need firmness
a reminder this thing I keep trying to do that I've tried to do
forever doesn't work foreign
ER into the breath
maybe it feels uh natural to
stay with the breathing or some uh
very defined object of attention
or maybe feel skillful to
open up to the entirety of the field of your experience
everything belonging
but nothing ownable
Maybe we
hallucinate the sense of the self
in order to govern Anita uncertainty
but it feels so good to let go
it feels so good to stop trying to make what
is uncertain certain
ungovernable in my control
to appreciate the centerlessness
of all phenomena foreign
what gets called me
my life my
foreign
okay
I see uh maybe uh Bell volume no volume
up my bell game is off um okay folks good to sit with you
um so
the the uh the the relaxation of Faith the
willingness of of Viria mindfulness this um
quiet uh impulse to know
certain kind of quiet hunger to know
faith effort mindfulness samadhi
the gathered mind unified mind
what's the the relationship between mindfulness and and samadhi
so it's often um distinguish by referencing the the uh
that kind of aperture of attention concentration is narrow just the tip of
the nose or something mindfulness is Broad but samadhi doesn't refer to
aperture it can be narrow or Broad tennis aerobic who says many people tell
us the Buddha taught two different types of meditation mindfulness meditation and concentration
meditation mindfulness meditation they say is the direct path concentration is the scenic route you take
at your own risk because it's easy to get caught there and you may never get out but when you actually look at what
the Buddha taught he never separates these two practices
mindfulness we could say
requires some measure of of concentration
mindfulness itself requires some measure of concentration otherwise we're getting
pinged around from memory to imaged you know to Future Body
Sensations we're glancing off the objects of
attention rather than the sustained soaking aiming and soaking aiming
penetrating in the the mahasi lineage
ajin sajito puts it uh differently of um
rather than than aiming and penetrating the object with attention
uh as pointing and then opening the hand
and the opening of the hand is a kind of samadhi this sort of poised
receptivity even when we're doing quote unquote
mindfulness practice
shinzhen young defines mindfulness um as a three-fold skill set
working together sensory Clarity the sense of of uh
making discriminating a high level uh resolution on sensory phenomena
Equanimity this this non-contention with phenomena and concentration
somebody uh
attention attention is um is this spotlighting function
bringing something to mind Mata sikara and then we kind of brighten the object
with attentional light use that metaphor
and generally concentration samadhi deepens when the spotlight becomes
brighter and brighter steadier and steadier
there's less and less light escaping in other words the rest of phenomena are
unlit and we come to live in a much
smaller world a very pleasant world
much smaller and it's a
it's a capacity that supports the other Realms of of practice so
maybe we say samadhi is the the object of attention is fully satiating for the
mind there's no residual hunger for other stimulation
ordinarily we we think about samadhi as involving attention and it does
but a curious note that uh agencyto makes is uh that
in samadhi all the intentions are aligned
all the energies of the heart mind are moving in a single
direction that captures Something Beautiful about it
there's not a different impulses
banging into each other it's a state of non
ambivalence maybe we say and all the impulses to grasp and push
away all the ways we cope we just don't need to cope anymore we're not in
samadhi we're not coping with samsara in the same way
we're not Enchanted by samsara by phenomena in the same way
in so many of our efforts to so much of our thinking the kind of stories
narrativizing our life are these kind of thin attempts to cope
to Grapple the intensity of The Human Condition with the ungoverned ability of samsara
and uh this this settles out as the mind
gets very comfortable and so the hunger for sensory pleasure has faded away and
there's sort of like nothing to do but offer or attention
and this is uh revitalizing gives
yeah it gives us it's revitalizing in the sense that that it uh
we're secluded the heart can actually rest and Revitalize to meet the
intensity of life samadhi it has many functions in our
practice but one of them to my mind is Faith the first of the of the the five faculties it builds our faith
and it's this sense of as we start to maybe for the first time in our practice
get really settled it's like okay something's happening here
before it's like I don't know yeah I'm mindful yeah I'm trying to be careful
with my Sila my ethics yeah I'm maybe have learned some things but
Somalia like okay wow there's something this is not usual this is not ordinary
and that is um uh in invites us into a deeper kind
of Faith like the Buddha was talking about you you are not the exception to the
Buddha's rule and uh that's important because some part of us
pretty I think maybe deep into the past sometimes thinks that maybe this whole
Buddhist thing is another con of some kind
or it is promising way too much
and then as the Mind settles in it's like wow I don't know what this is but this is different and this path is
definitely something and I can do it I can do it
this is the the fruit really of of letting go of Letting Go not of
engineering um
and so we we can't really cling our way into Stillness
and if we try to cling our way back to Stillness it doesn't work
and there are stories Tales of people suffering enormously trying to uh
get concentrated or these things but um uh
this is a pleasure born of letting go
and so samadhi is kind of protected in the
sense that we cannot cling our way into it
so it's um reinforces and letting go
when we really gather when there's strong sense of of samadhi there's there's not a lot of learning happening
there are many other wholesome things happening but there's not a lot of learning happening
in the same way you you wouldn't learn about architecture by staring
unwaveringly at a small patch of concrete
yeah the image just came the Getty you know
the Getty and Los Angeles or something uh
the Grandeur of that but uh if we were just looking at a
patch of the foundation we wouldn't learn so much
and insight unfolds when the stability of samadhi is directed to
to understanding to understanding how experience is put together the
architecture of experience the architecture of self
savadi is um is the the quivering quality of mind I
associate it with a kind of yeah usually we use the word quivering for compassion but this is a different species of
quivering but very very receptive very porous very
impressionable very in other words fertile for learning
and so in the penumbra of samadhi where maybe there's very little
learning we start to become more attentive to a Nietzsche to
the architecture of experience and in that stability
the the learning the the the kind of mind is very fertile for learning and
the Dharma lessons that we uh we experience they make deeper
Impressions on the mind they make deeper Impressions on the mind
and so sometimes we have some some kind of insight or
excuse me understanding but what kind of legs does that Insight have
what kind of legs does it have how long does it last how long does it stay in our bones how long does the retreat we
sat stay in our bones how long does our understanding about
self love stay in our bones how long does our understanding about letting go
stay in our bones there's some evidence that exercise for
example enhances neuroplasticity the kind of the learning that happens in the
wake of cardiovascular exercise
may be the altered the kind of deeper learning more learning that happens
and if I had to guess I would say the same for samadhi samadhi
um makes our mind brain more malleable what we've learned leaves
a deeper Mark has more legs when we learn it on somebody
so um offer this for your consideration and
pick up what CS Fall leave the rest behind and please know if this causes more
suffering for you uh
that's not what I meant to do yeah people have their own predilections
around samadhi some people they're just Glide path for them
and uh and most people have to uh grapple yeah self-included
um and so uh we keep going you know let me see what
the path offers us okay see you uh see you tomorrow wish you a
good day