so exciting here we're in a storm here
in the walking meditation Hall at IRC and the Acoustics here that is
sound bounces quite a bit and I think maybe tomorrow we could go back into the regular meditation Hall
there were people there who were meditating earlier we were setting up
and um small Echo gives a cathedral feel that's
very nice so welcome uh to our Monday morning to this
uh you know to IRC instead of an IMC for
these two days and uh tomorrow I think we'll set it up differently so maybe it could be a nicer
than this color we have here in this room and um
so the uh I want to start uh briefly the
meditation with a a story it's probably a Mythic story about the Buddha and that is that um
he was uh the night of his Awakening uh he was challenged quite a bit and uh
and maybe one of the biggest challenges he's had in his practice
and he found that he didn't he couldn't rely on himself anymore he done all the
work all the efforts that any individual could do risk practice but it wasn't enough to
just do his own effort and so the story goes that he
reached a hand down and touched the Earth and called upon the Earth or the
goddess of the earth to support him to uh
affirm that it was possible for him to become awakened
and the Earth responded with an earthquake that probably a gentle
earthquake but a message yes and that all these challenges that the
Buddha had kind of vanished with that so it's a little bit more elaborate than Mythic story that goes but the important
point is here is that sometimes in doing this practice we rely on something outside of
ourselves which I'm beyond our usual sense of self and that's expressed in the Buddhist
language going we go to something for support and the going for Refuge
and so when we do this meditation practice it's possible to do it a kind of
it's kind of certain kind of degree of just I'm the one who's doing it and I'm going to
happen puff or focus and manage and it's also possible to do it in
relationship to uh something that is more than your own efforts maybe it's
something within yourself even but something more than you're an effort that you rely on for support
and a day will come when you are only relying on your own efforts and
it's not enough and there's a kind of humility or kind of openness or willingness and to go
or something something else for support and the simple way for our Buddhists is
to go to the Dharma we'll go to the Buddha darma Sangha so for this meditation
I would like to uh if it works for you to for you to consider that as you do
your meditation that um you have a support for being present for being really here
in the moment that there is lots of support that the few hundred people who are here
on YouTube watching here and meditating along our support for all of us to be present
that those of us who are you know and we're supported by the
Earth by the natural world in many many ways our life depends on it and uh in a sense life is here
supporting us to be present so to sit and meditate with a sense of
support to call on that support that is not just your own efforts
but there are supports for you to be present
so to take a meditation posture
and to gently close your eyes
the first to feel the support of
whatever it is that supports your weight gentle pool of gravity against your
cushion your chair all of us are supported
I could say by the Earth and we never fall through
foreign
take a few long slow deep breaths
certainly our life is supported by the life processes of this planet
the plants that make oxygen to make food
are supported here just in the breathing
without breathing there's no life for us and to check they take a few long slow
deeper threats
and as you exhale to relax relax into a sense of support
you're supported by the Dharma you know all the meetings I've done
supported by 2500 years of people who meditated
you are meditating you're not alone
the dedication to show up can be present
for our experience
breathing normally
going to support in your own care for yourself
simple care of relaxing your body
the care of relaxing your minds
the practice of being present here and now is a supportive practice you're not
alone to rely on the sense of support
that reality wants you to be present for it here no
foreign
[Music]
this Dharma practice there's a mutuality or reciprocity
of going for a refuge account for support and protection in the Dharma
that we are supported and then there's the other side which is
that we become a refuge for others may become someone is safe supportive
for others as well we don't just receive support
we also offer it and in that reciprocity
we end up receiving more support we don't lose support by supporting
others in the Dharma the two go hand in hand to support each
other and that's why at the end of a meditation session
it's often Builds on the meditation kind of
expands the value of it to spend a moment of time
dedicating the Merit the benefits to to transform turn around the way
we've been supported and to intend and wish support for
others may it be that our practice together
it's maybe maybe some over 400 of us meditating with a lot of people
collectively that as we go through our day
that we offer support to others who care our love
may it be that we make other people's life a little bit easier today
may all beings be happy evil beings
be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all be free so thank you all
doesn't really work to ring a bell on Zoom so they bow in the city
thank you for it
so so most of these warnings that come down
to IMC for the last three years technology is mostly worked nicely
sometimes there's been those challenges and uh
and it's mostly working today the standard of what works and doesn't work is you know is uh you know
optional what we consider the standard but you know I'm sorry they're a little bit late and here we are at IRC
and now there's also there's some wonderful coincidence that uh we were a little more I was
challenged we were challenging we see some help here at IRC and other places with Kevin setting up the zoom room
thank you um because what I want to talk about are
challenges and uh our lives are full of challenges
and I think I'd like to do that for a while now in this uh these uh teachings morning teachings
here um last year I went through
um last year I did and then the year before that I
it's Sati patana and there's a way in which those uh often the teachings of the Dharma
can easily kind of just give the presentation that it's just an easy thing to do
some of the classic models of the path the practice that the Buddha gives doesn't really say anything about
difficulties sit down and just go through concentration States and things just unfold very nicely
but in fact for most people maybe a lot of people this practice that we do and
the life we live has challenges lots of challenges the Buddha has this wonderful
kind of metaphor for the human suffering
he said that um um all the tears that you have shed
in all your many lifetimes is greater than all the water in all the oceans
so that's a powerful statement about uh the nature of this life of ours the
challenges the suffering that this that the losses the griefs so so much
goes on this life this difficult and the Dharma practice has been
designed in order to meet that to work with it to heal it to move
through it to be discover freedom in the midst of this difficult world and so I would like for a while now to
talk about the Dharma practice
um in addressing the challenges we have and if I can do this well I think I'd
like to do this a little bit like a progression that the building a foundation for really looking at what is
most difficult in our lives and what's challenging in our hearts because uh in the assume that most
people are carrying their hearts deep challenges that sometimes are buried for
a long time sometimes are very well known and uh and to become really free in the
stomach practice is not to override those or to push those aside but that he
has to discover our freedom in all free everything within us
against a lifetime Journey but it's a wonderful journey to be on
so last week I talked about uh five different meanings of Dharma
Dharma as relatedness dharma's action dharma's truth dharma's
teachings and Karma as transformation and I'd like to use those same categories of the Dharma to talk more
generally inductory fashion this week about working with challenges
and uh and uh so for today the it's the topic of Dharma has
relatedness that uh Dharma points to not so much to
um things not too much to the suffering as a suffering but rather always asking a
question where is the relationship here how are we relating to it how is it related to us
uh the first Dharma talk I I gave on an Insight Retreat when I was still in
training to be a teacher was a Dharma talk about
the uh the importance of looking at our relationship that we have to our
experience rather than fixing experience rather than focusing on the experiences from the issue to really take into account
how we relate to it sometimes I've said that um there's only
ever two things there's what's happening and how we relate to what's happening
but for today I want to say there are three things there's what's happening there's how we relate to it and then
what is it that supports us to relate to it what do we go to for support so that we can relate to things
in an effective uh way in that in a
useful way to healing weight beneficial way
this idea of relatedness what is how am I related to this so if you have
um some challenge in your life it's easy to get pulled into the Dynamics of the challenge and the
relationships and the issues and what has to happen and what the concerns but
we can also step back and see how am I relating to this challenge and if we do that we find out that we
might be relating to it with fear and the fear is different in that challenge
but if we don't see that then the fear kind of gets entangled with the
challenge and it's separable from it that it makes it very much more difficult to deal with because there are
these two things going on there's whatever the challenge is and then there's the fear and then where do you
put your attention you deal with the the issue of you to deal with your fear
so for example maybe you know a great example of something very silly not silly but
simple is um if you're out driving you have a flat tire and you're able to
pull over safely inside of the road and so the challenge is how to get the tire repaired
but if there's fear that you can't do it you'll be stuck here and it'll help you then
um the the Practical question what to do about the tire has not become entangled
with the fear we have towards it and the fear might be reasonable to have but there are two different things and
so to ask yourself the question what's the relationship I have to the flat tire oh the relationship is fear is that the
most useful relationship to have it it's another relationship that's more useful to have maybe the better relationship is
um pulling off your phone and calling for help or something but but uh when you
ask when you answer the question answer the question what is my relationship to it then you have a chance to question is
this the relationship I want to be acting on is this what takes predominance or is
there another relationship that might be more useful If instead of being afraid maybe I
should be mindful maybe this is a time in my mindfulness practice really comes to prepare to
really be mindful and present for the fear so that as they balance in the fear
rather than reducing my balance with it so the question is what is the relationship to the challenge
can reveal a lot and can begin to tease apart
The Challenge from how we're experiencing what we're doing with it and not a few times
a large life challenges are made much more difficult because of
how we're relating to it and sometimes we relate to things wonderfully sometimes there's a sense of
being counterphobic we step towards the difficulties we have so we're curious we
say let's find out what's Happening Here um let me look at let me let me use this challenge as a place to understand
myself better to learn how to be more patient to learn how to be more compassionate to learn how to be more
wise or Discerning or less caught and so then we're bringing the
relationship of practice to it so how am I relating to this and uh you can point a figure to point
ourselves back to how I want to relate to it is I want to take it on its practice
and then the practice I trust so then in the government practice we
talk about then going for Refuge so um there's some so there's a third thing
there's what's happening how relating to it and then what is it that we want uh to support us what's
relating to us and the DAR Milo sense is available as a
support in order the clearest ways of that is the practice
to practice supports us where the practice has a relationship to us
which maybe is a little bit counter-intuitive because I can feel like I'm the one who's practicing I'm
the one who's applying myself and um and that could you know that's true but when you apply yourself in
practice um the practice and response something inside responds to honesty to truth to
presence to care to compassion that we bring as we practice something response
and that responsibility is something that's coming that's going to support us
and uh there are times in life when we can't figure out what we can do
for ourselves everything seems so difficult so hard and that's a time when Buddhists
sometimes will go go for Refuge we'll go and show the support of the
Dharma and it kind of can take the shape of this is hard I'm not sure I can manage this but I
trust the practice I trust the Dharma and so I'm going to go for a refuge to
it I'm going to rely on it and it doesn't mean that we become passive
it means that we still are for our practice to it but we don't we're not
caught in the in the OR Frozen by I don't know how to
do it or I don't know what's supposed to happen or this seems impossible we trust there's an enlargers holiness
and it's not always obvious what that larger Dharma
support will be and sometimes there's many many different things depending on the
circumstances but uh it's phenomenal that uh for me in my life how often I've been challenged
where I didn't know what to do didn't know what to say and I I took refuge in the practice I
took refuge and mindfulness to show up and be present so much so
that one of the greatest gifts time for me of doing this mindfulness practice
inside practice is the phenomenal trust that I have in my close practice itself
I trust the practice more than my own mind's ability to understand something or to figure things out or to uh
solve all the problems but uh I'm certainly do my best but mindfulness
means I'll show up and stay present I'll stay with it and try to be honest and
try to feel and be present and recognize what's happening stay in the present moment with this
really uh take it in what's happening don't turn
away from what's happening but also don't attack what's happening don't shut down don't despair don't collapse the
darknesses show up and uh trusting it trusting the
mindfulness and so to say you know related with the relatedness as
part of the Dharma practice we're in a relationship we're in relationship to ourselves
relationship to our challenges we relationship to The Brighter world and it's in relationship to us
in something like the Dharma the Buddha Masada or that's language you don't care for the mindfulness practices itself
um there's a reciprocity there where we offer ourselves to the practice and then
the practice supports us and uh it's a very fortunate thing here
because uh it was all up to our own abilities our own intelligence or it'd probably be
impossible for most of us to really work work with some of the huge challenges of life and
death that this will this uh human life brings us
a degree of loss betrayal
that we go through in this life it can be huge so how to practice with it
so how do I so what's our relationship to it and what do we go for for support so we
can relate to lesson supports so that's this word of the world of relativeness and it's a protection
against getting against getting kind of solidified or frozen in the notion it's
all up to me it's all happening to me it's all about me it's all about them and what they're
doing there's something bigger going on here that belongs to the world of
relativeness in interrelatedness that we all live in
so um if you have challenged today
yeah whether it's small or large even if it's small don't overlook it even it's so small that you can just kind of
bypass it and not think about it but if you have some challenges today ask yourself the question
how are you relating to it that's not really part of the challenge
but what's the relationship to it and even if the challenge is internal to
yourself how are you relating to it what are their beliefs what are the attitudes what are that desires that are
coming to play in relationship to it the emotions and then is there something that you can
that will support you it's relating to you maybe the practice
and mindfulness may be the Dharma it is Earth something else that supports you
that makes it easier for you to go through it because you're not doing it alone you have the support of Buddha Dharma
Sangha so um I call upon all of this for myself today
and a little bit because uh I felt a little bit uh
confused sitting down here making all this work but uh trusted that the Dharma here and
we'd find her way so here we are so um thank you
we'll see if we can make it a little bit nicer to easier tomorrow and if not
we'll just do it this way again and uh then Wednesday I'll be should be back at IMC
thank you all