so uh so welcome folks good morning to most of you again
afternoon to uh to some maybe uh so Thailand in there too so uh welcome to
you wherever you are um
yeah there's always a little bit of a dilemma for me about how uh precise or
impressionistic to be in giving instructions and I
feel like I almost always err on the side of uh the impressionistic
kind of element of of just dropping Dharma thoughts
into the mind that catalyze a certain kind of view but um there is a place for
um yeah for precision and uh attentional Direction
and we can do that I feel without uh
incarnating a meditator self that is it's cramped
tricky but we can do it so anyway I thought today it would be a
little um more technique-y and um share something that's been
meaningful for me from my teacher I sat with her a long time since then Young
I don't his technique is always evolving and so I don't even know if I'm representing it appropriately as he kind
of tweaks and develops it but um uh yeah the the kind of core of
it is discriminating between three core sensory
events namely visual thinking so my eyes are closed but I've got the computer
screen got the room outline of my body
no simpler no no more complex than that there's words in our own mind auditory
thinking we can actually sense a kind of spatial location to thinking
and so if I told you to say your name silently in your own head you would actually hear it somewhere
it wouldn't actually be happening there but there would be like
I don't know if it's echolocation or or something but it's almost like this sense of it happens in a place the way
that almost like holographically arises in a place usually in the head between
the ears somewhere like that and then there is affect in the body
emotionally charged Sensations and
different from kind of physicality of okay I'm tapping on my chest that
sensation is quite different from the sensation I would feel at the same place if I suddenly heard a loud noise the
startled I feel a jolt of sensation but it would be emotional in nature
responsive in nature kind of
essentially wordless surveying of threat and opportunity Moment by moment
very kind of foundational to animal body
so they're seeing there's hearing there's feeling and we begin to discriminate between
those three sensory events paying attention to their arising and passing
and there's really no distress if we're we have like a mindful relationship with
those three sensory Gates um there's not really much place for
distress to arise outside of them so the Panic the dissatisfaction the
longing the the suffering suffering
has to have its fingerprint here and we bring our open heart to it
and
this is uh this is Zia's phone so let's uh let's sit together
relaxing everything that can be relaxed
the spine extending
to the heavens the rest of the body just hanging loosely
from that Central column
and we practice surrendering
surrendering to imperfection surrendering our willfulness
surrendering the subtle violence of self-improvement
Vinnie Ferrara says foreign
there's not much time left
time to let go
and so for a minute just sensitizing to the visual aspect of thinking behind the
closed eyes against the kind of blank mental screen
images memory
maybe an image of my face even if your eyes are closed
an image of the outline of your body or the room
sometimes the images are photographic but often melting and morphing
and when we direct attention for example to our breathing or our body generally
it's often aided by a subtle visual thinking
it's bound up with proprioception
Imaging our body World Moment by moment
the mental notes it's very simple
seeing
and if upon noticing noting
visual thinking it melts away we notice the
blankness for the Tranquility that replaces it
now putting that down and bringing attention to auditory
thinking
normally we just call that thinking with the words the senses the phrases
the voice over the narrator
this constellates in the this auditory thinking world
and our default is to
endow our auditory thinking with Incredible Trust
every thought pinging or being
every thought and subtly or dramatically adjusting the parameters of our body
mind
but now rather than obeying the voice in our head as if it were God
we just listen to it as The Voice
in our head
and so we we're very vividly
examine the drama and melodrama of identification
the ways we incarnate in a thought and you know becoming identified
take birth as a protagonist
from within a thought we lose all sense of attentional
autonomy
then we wake up the sentence ends the paragraph and
we're reborn as a meditator
the mental note is simple hearing
and if at the end of
in making the note or a sentence coming to an end
there's just silence we listen to The Silence
and then lastly feeling just the tuning to
emotional circuits in your body the building blocks of motivation
urgency affirming and objecting
sometimes we know what's arising or it's easy to give a
name to the feeling to the affect arising sometimes it's just a vague something state of arousal state of
pleasant or unpleasant
sometimes it's happening in one part of our body sometimes more broadly
sometimes intense but sometimes subtle and subtle is significant Shenzhen would always say
the note is feeling
and so now we we can practice opening to all
three sensory experiences not necessarily at the same time
but uh the attention may be drawn to a visual
thinking to auditory thinking to feeling in the body Body Sensations
charged with emotion and of course more than one may be
arising at the same time but we just choose one to focus on doesn't matter
which maybe we stay with that arising
for a few seconds maybe it vanishes before that we just
notice it's gone
maybe you use the mental notes could just be as simple as see
here or feel
sometimes I'll simply cycle through these three sensory spheres
is checking in with the CNN
for a few moments
hearing
healing
and then around again
and pouring mindfulness equanimity
into each moment
the tango of I am-ness
begins to untangle
foreign
okay it's good to uh good to sit with you
um foreign
so uh uh roomy
if you bake bread with the wheat that grows on My Grave you'll become drunk
with joy and even the oven will recite ecstatic poems
if you come to pay your respects even my gravestone will invite you to dance
so don't come without your drum
I want to uh want to die that way
if um Anita
doesn't soften us it it'll break our heart
when when we don't meet Anita with with wisdom
the kind of default tendency will be to cling more tightly to double down on
fulfilling this craving or that craving and it might work a tiny bit but it
doesn't really work and so so what does it mean
what does it mean to meet uh to meet Anita with wisdom
I think it can look a lot of ways it can look a lot of ways sometimes it's a very
cooled out State very equanimous
there is this sense of death being huge and it also being not a big deal not
such a big deal let us not be grandiose
right it's like a certain times when I especially when I see animal suffering you know
I know we're different from ants or something but just
um I don't know it's like uh this huge quality of death feels like
um largely a testament to my grandiosity and my enormous ego you know like I do
sometimes think of myself as a kind of overgrown intelligent
insect with an enormous ego basically
okay I may not be grandiose the just utter
naturalness of birth and death drain some of the melodrama
and sometimes wisdom meeting and each looks like uh looks like gratitude
this is a Amy cross Rosenthal writer after very
serious diagnosis she says when I'm feeling dreary annoyed
generally unimpressed by life I imagine what it would be like to come back to
this world for just a day after having been dead
I imagine how sentimental I would feel about the very things I once found
stupid hateful or mundane oh there's a light switch
I haven't seen a light switch in so long I didn't realize how much I missed light
switches oh oh and look the stairs up to our front porch are
still completely cracked hello cracks let me get a good look at you
and there's my neighbor standing there fantastically alive just the stain
still punctuating her sentences with you know what I'm saying
why did that bother me it's so endearing
it's easy to acclimatize to goodness
and uh we want to wake up to it
sometimes wisdom um meeting a Nietzsche looks like
grieving it's like grieving and
classically grieving is is sort of in the clustered with the afflictive
emotions same category is anger something like this
but um I I
Elevate grieving in a way doesn't feel at least certain species of
it does not feel in any way afflictive and it's very hard for me to imagine
ourselves as moral creatures capable of causing harm capable of
Rippling love very hard for me to conceive of how we
can look at the carnival of greed hidden delusion and not feel some grief
and we all um have our
our archetypes and our our visions of Freedom or what we aspire to
and it's not shared by all by any stretch but for me I do want my Buddha
to uh to grieve that um
that uh kind of elevated response to the poignancy
The Human Condition
so on this last day considering the uh the Council of mortality it's about
grief and love the real Redemption
of mortality is uh is more love
More Love deeper wider
and um how is how is how is grief redeemed you
know in this realm of loss how is grief redeemed and uh I don't know I'm sure we all have
our own answers but to my mind it's art and love this these are the redemptions
of grief Norman Fisher says when you love uh when
someone you love is gone that person can't do anything anymore
this means you have to do something or you have to do something differently somehow you were connected to that
person have to do what they can no longer do you have to ask yourself now that this
has happened what will I do what will I do in place of my friend
there is always something to be done when we stop creating the unnecessary
suffering we can notice all the real suffering around us
are the fake unnecessary suffering is actually distracting us protecting us in a way
from the real suffering around us the real suffering is much more
intractable it's horribly painful but it connects us to everyone else in
the world and so in that sense the real suffering is okay
we become numb an isolated because we want to avoid the suffering
but it's the numbness and isolation that feel the worst
when we break through the necessary suffering and connect with others it's
hard it's painful but it's also better
when we open to the real pain of caring for others we do feel better
um what will I do in place of my friend
that is a a very worthy question it's a very
worthy question
and uh
so much of um of anxiety
uh anxiety sometimes described as the the
uh the intolerance of uncertainty so much of the anxiety is about
our anxiety is about not knowing the agitation that arises out of
not knowing out of uncertainty and um
but we already actually do know how the story ends
Everything Changes
and so the kind of anxiety and frenzy and
numbness that can be drained out
and it's just kind of heartfelt connection
The Human Condition and for sure it's hard it's painful we
call that grief but it's also better
so much better
a lot lot of room for uh for love
so I offer this for your consideration and uh
please pick up what is useful or what um
feels uh native to your own heart and leave the rest behind
uh we all have to find our way
so uh thank you
um yeah
yeah thank you thank you all thanks for your practice and um
thank you to the uh the the audio Audio Dharma YouTube editing
crew and Kevin and Julie and Dan and job and
uh much appreciation so I'll sign off here and uh wish you
wish you all uh well yeah okay