hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour hi and if the audio is okay
give me a thumbs up so I know you can hear me fantastic hey sweet
so hello and welcome everyone to happy hour I'm Nikki margafori in Mountain View California
and see that all lonely land and let's begin as we always do by warming up the
space with our hellos with our meta take it away who's here
I'm Wayne in Richmond California hi Wayne Jesse Hammond San Rafael Northern
California hi Jesse Susan San Mateo Northern California hi
Susan Neal in New Hampshire hi Neil
Los Angeles hello Ali Salam assalam
hello Bill from Dallas hello Dina from Hendersonville North North Carolina
welcome and good evening hi Barbara from Santa Cruz gurus is Mari Christine from
hot and humid Sydney oh yes it's it's your summer good uh good morning good
wait morning or afternoon I always mix it up Mario Christine you're gonna type it for me set me straight who else wants
to say hi it's afternoon good afternoon to you anybody else wants to say hi
hi Diane from Soquel California anybody else
okay all right the uh space feels warmed up to me so let's
begin thank you Neil for posting information about the happy hour Google Groups
um if you're new to happy hour we have a Google Groups that is pretty low on
traffic and where information is shared quotes Etc references
and low traffic high in heart I like to say so you are welcome to join that
um and at this time I change the settings uh so accidental unmuting won't be
possible the space will stay quiet I change the chat settings to host and co-host only but I ask you to to hold
your questions and Reflections until afterwards because it can be quite
distracting and hello Nina from Berkeley on YouTube and other folks other uh
Sangha members joining there and one more thing I do now is to turn on the
recording for the sake of Audio Dharma here we go okay
all right great so hello again formal hello and welcome
warm warm welcome to IPR everyone lovely to see you
warms my heart so so for the past few happy hours I feel
I've been on this um uh role of of guiding
um subtle what I what I there's so many ways to call it but perhaps
characterized as sort of a subtle meta it's a silence quiet nourishing
glistening turning into into a sense of Stillness as a nourishment of of loving
kindness care Stillness which is a way of kind of stealing it's not very busy with which which is wonderful the
busyness is wonderful too with the phrases and may I be happy may you be happy all the phrase that's wonderful
and fantastic as well and this is a different way this is a
slightly different maybe a little subtle nourishing calming quieting just a sense
of fear and love imbuing just imbuing our
experience it's it's as if yeah the words loving awareness whatever
awareness turns to and is aware of the there's a sense of warmth and care that
in that intertwines that that that [Music] um really imbues that that knowing and it
just becomes a very kind knowing and that if the knowing is turning towards suffering and pain becomes just a very
gentle knowing of that it's still quiet and still it's not very active uh which
again is wonderfully different work just more still so so having said that I'd like to invite
us to explore that again and always slightly different flavors of this
exploration come through so it's not so much that we explore it again but in that category of Explorations we're
going to take a different path oh this evening so so let's um
let's explore together Intrepid Travelers explorers of the
heart and mind let's let's settle together let's practice so
I'd like to invite us all right
to arrive to settle
in this body
softening softening whatever needs
softening
softening the body
that start with the body
imagine your care for this body is a
tiny little massage therapist
that's traveling around your body
giving a little internal massage it's actually your breath
your internal little kind massage therapist to breathe into
the corners ever so gently and lovingly
that need the little care let's start with that tonight
take your time
do your feet need a little love
your neck and shoulders need the
massage therapist of the breath
give it some love
maybe your back sit bones
another whole body wherever in the body
maybe the mind the heart
Imagining the breath internally is caring therapist
giving an internal massage starting with
the bus opening relaxing if the ma if the body relaxes and
softens the heart and mind do the same
so notice notice the tightness
soften soften
and if they're terrorizing taking your way into
memory plans
can we know them with kindness thank you
noticing the Habit patterns of the mind to regurgitate plans
it's okay can we know it all lovingly of course of course this is what Minds do
this is what the puppy of the Mind does maybe even give the
be a little hug thank you
appreciate the puppy nature of the mind running around
and maybe put the puppy in your lap and stroke it with kindness It's okay
stay right here sweetheart right here at the body with the breath
and when it runs away it's okay runs around give it another hug put it
on your lap stroke it lovingly with the breath let
the breath give the body the mind happy a little massage
calming soothing settling
that the whole practice be about loving your body heart and mind with the
breath
stroking loving the puppy
affectionately
with each breath foreign
just here so sweet later or nourishing to just be here
present Temple loving
appreciating
appreciating this body it's alive it's breathing what a miracle
you can be here this moment sit and practice
with others what a miracle
thank you
and we have benevolence kindness towards whatever that arises in the body
be it pain discomfort agitation the mind or heart
being boredom sadness happiness whatever it is fear
with the spacious heart of the put up benevolence
making space so much space is available
or whatever is here agitation or Stillness
nourishing nourishing Stillness
silence between the words and the body and the mind
thank you
this is my chance today sit
in my heart to silence and loving itself
and I collect myself lovingly silence
nourishing quiet of this moment
inviting the puppy to rest a pea of the might
be content here so much goodness
peace and be available
here
foreign
lovingly here
resting in the heart receiving the breath
relaxing the body here
foreign
and as we begin to bring this period of sitting practice to close
together and may rest in our hearts
with appreciation for ourselves for having showed up as
best as we were able to
thank you me for showing up
for my intentions cultivating goodness wholesomeness
freedom reduce suffering to awaken
recognizing the goodness and the beauty
within and any moments of awareness
kind awareness that might have arisen for the body
for this heart for this mind
and sharing that goodness far and wide
with all beings
may all beings know their own goodness
may they awaken to their Buddha nature within as I wish
to awaken and see and always be in touch with it
see the beauty see the goodness the kindness generosity that's available
male beings everywhere be safe happy healthy at ease may all
beings be free including myself
you all thank you for your practice ah
wonderful there'd be more goodness in the world
and through our practice trusting that there is there has been
so a day we did very light simple very light touch of
meta kindness Goodwill starting with this body
having the sense that the um inviting the sense that the breath is
this gentle kind massage therapist
releasing relieving the body in order to really settle settle settle into the
body release relax I can't emphasize enough how important
mindfulness of the body settling in the body awareness of the body relaxing the
body is it is the First Foundation of mindfulness the first establishment of
mindfulness the first Sati patana in the Sati patanasuta it's so important so
fundamental and always we start there with the breath with the body
and then the invitation tonight was very sparse very simple very simple and
sparse just noticing if the puppy of the Mind as it tends to run
around run away just gently gently bring it back hugging it not chastising it as we
usually do with our minds but just a sense of kindness towards ourselves towards our mind
this imagery of a puppy it's and calming soothing and then we opened
up to whatever arises whether there's sadness
grief pain joy and then also Stillness to recognize
that there is silence in between the words here and so with kindness acceptance
spaciousness for everything that there is so so um
I'll share with you the feeling that came up for me through this meditation it felt like
in some ways towards the end especially as my heart and mind we're getting more
and more subtle and stable and settling into samadhi concentration States
um it felt like I was sitting in my own meditation and you were all joining me
it didn't feel like I was leading you or guiding you or was effort it was just
like oh yeah we're all sitting together you're joining me in my practice of the resistance of spaciousness for me the
sense of gratitude for all of you to be joining me as I practice like oh this is
so sweet like hey this is so great so it's um it's a it's really such a gift for me
um and and guiding leading doesn't feel effortful
does really feel like there's a give and take of generosity in this space so I'm I'm really grateful for this so
grateful for you thank you
so I'd like to invite you if there are any Reflections so any questions comments
bill please hi Nikki hi hi I wanted to thank you for
the the imagery of the the puppy of the Mind um what I noticed was I guess it seems
obvious now but it's so much easier to have space and to include things when
your attitude is one of kindness and it seems like the default attitude
for Me Maybe for most people is is to push away
things that are unwanted this seemed to include everything I mean what you were doing was seeing from seemed to just
incorporate everything and um I really enjoyed it and thank you very
much beautiful Bill thank you so much for your reflections
yes exactly that your Insight is so profound
that we do tend to get rid of things push them away and it's
um and we usually don't see it we usually don't see it it's kind of the default
mode that we operate in it's just started to fall it's like fish in the water we don't see it
and um and what you were saying was oh yeah what this different mode of including
everything with kindness wow that's actually it's easier it's more spacious
it's wow this this works this works better wow there's something I'm often
hears yeah I'm noticing something here so yes bill that's exactly it and keep
keep nourishing keep watering uh this Insight is so profound include
everything push away nothing with kindness yeah beautiful thank you
yeah I see a question asks what can we do with negative
thoughts and energy arising all the time yeah yeah well I think
bill just answered the question so that is exactly it so if we do try to keep to
push it away to try to get rid of it try if we have an adversarial relationship
with it these negative thoughts again ah instead okay okay
all right I see you thank you you have some good you have good intentions and
yet you're kind of misguided it's okay it's okay it's all right
um so again with that kindness turning towards negative thoughts energy
Etc with kindness because by if you turn towards them with with negativity if you
try to push them away you're just giving them more power you're giving them more energy
and I trust there is enough creativity you have enough creative to figure out
how can I bring some more kindness and acceptance and acceptance doesn't mean that you act out of the negative
thoughts and energy doesn't mean that doesn't mean condoning it doesn't mean
acting it out at all it just means you are accepting the truth of this moment
that in this moment here this negative thought is arising because of past
conditioning whatever it is mind external societal education genes family
whatever it is it's coming up all right dear negative thought I see you
ah it's okay I see you I don't believe you when I see you but this is this
turning this this acknowledgment with kindness and just that it takes the power away it
changes our habit pattern with with negativity I hope that helps get a cut
the other question oh actually you know the time has come to turn to small groups I see
so let's do that let's turn so here's the invitation so the small groups this
evening here's an inquiry I'm going to suggest a a question that you can inquire with sit
with if you want with silence in the community
that is um maybe one creative way that you have
maybe one imagery you have where you is is as uh following up on what Bill
shared and kindergarten asked with when challenging when negative thoughts come
up Etc or negative challenges maybe comma Now how do you what what way in
you have worked with them with kindness turn for them with kindness and if you haven't yet successfully how can you um
an idea of oh yeah maybe I'll try this maybe I I can see myself trying this
maybe imagine it like a sock puppet uh which intense well but it's just a
little misguided you don't know anything you're you're you're no good you're a failure like okay well thank you thanks
for your opinion like maybe I can imagine that or or maybe you just hold silence maybe you just hold silence okay
I'm just holding silence so so an invitation is we'll go in alphabetical order I actually let's do reverse
alphabetical origins or the fun of it and maybe share one one bot one
reflection or say pass you can share your silence the next person will say
something and then the next person and then your turn comes you go around and round a few rounds and you can always
say past share from your own experience no questions no no directing others just
share from your own heart okay so I'm going to create the breakout rooms
always remember meta taking care of yourself taking care of others and I am
going to open the rooms now here we go foreign
foreign
okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed everybody's back and it is seven
o'clock so um to honor the whoops I collect asked
someone to unmute that was not intentional um so to honor the time uh let's close
let's close tonight and what I'll do is that I'll stay a minute extra and
um if uh anybody has Reflections or questions I'd like to share from the
small groups then you can share them otherwise otherwise we'll we'll close so
thank you all thank you for your practice thank you and um yeah just appreciating your own
goodness and sharing it with all beings everywhere may all beings be free may all things be happy
thanks everyone take good care