so good morning good day welcome to this
new day even if even if some of you who are
on evening and time zone the idea that every day is new we wake
up to discover what's new overnight it's a
kind of ancient tradition that we wake up Anew to something
a new world and uh
today the topic is aspiration and it belongs to a family of
mental activities that can go on one end can be planning or expecting
to ins what we're inspired for inspired to work for
somewhere in the middle of that may be intention is the midpoint of that family if it's if it's a kind of a range
Spectrum and but intention can lend itself to
expectation to trying hard to trying to get something to intend to do something
doesn't have to there can be intention for how we want to be right now in this
moment we would like to be kind that's the intention and then it's
immediate as opposed to a plan for the future but I like the word aspiration because
it's closely connected to the word inspiration intention can be dry
aspiration comes from some deeper place within as something that's maybe inspiring for
us or something which is in the inspiration in the aspiration something that feels nurturing or nourishing for
us there's a goodness to aspiration for me aspiration I don't know it works
for other people who speak English but for me aspiration always has an ethical quality wholesome quality
what do we Aspire for and um and here I want to offer you an analogy
for having an S nourishing aspiration for meditation
and that is the idea the image the sense that um
the way in which sunlight
enables a forest to grow in the springtime maybe a deciduous
forest and um and the the way the speed the
calm the patience the gentleness the maybe even for many many times
imperceptible changes of the way sunlight in the sunlight the forest grows
so in our aspiration
the Dharma can grow in US and it's not a Dharma that we
see Moment by moment is not a Dharma that we force or
our measuring Moment by moment am I there yet but rather we're allowing ourselves to
be take in the goodness of our aspiration desperation to be present
in a way that is free present in a way that is kind
appreciative present in a way that deeply attuned
to ourselves present in a way where there's a heightened awareness
that is like the sunlight growing a forest
so assuming a meditation posture
and becoming aware of yourself Here and Now
sitting in a particular place at this time
become aware of sitting here in this sort of meditating here in this body
in all its Dimensions all its Sensations
you if it's uh comfortable for you you can close your eyes
and maybe with a sense of invitation to invite your body to
breathe a bit deeper Fuller
to Exhale a bit longer relaxing as you exhale
and to let your breathing return to normal
but on the exhale letting your attention roam around your
body finding places to relax to soften in your body
and then letting your breathing return to normal
and consider an aspiration
for being here present in meditation mindful
that has an inspiration for you one that is not
doesn't excite you but when that enlivens you
it's inspires you with kind of calm
presence of sunlight on a forest
an aspiration for
an appreciative awareness
a forgiving awareness
maybe a kind or loving caring awareness
and aspiration to be present with freedom
that leaves everything alone whatever we're aware of we give it its
freedom freedom from our own clingings and aversions and judgments
aspiring to bring freedom to all things
and if you can find an aspiration for being present that's inspiring
let that be a light
that shines upon your practice of mindfulness let it inform how you're present each
time you're here and now with your experience let it be informed
inspired by your aspiration
foreign
the word aspiration and inspiration
come from the Latin words for breathing like respiration
May every breath have in it come with an aspiration
that helps you to grow your practice
the way sunlight helps a forest to grow
and then as we come to the end of this meditation
to change your aspiration
to Aspire for the welfare and happiness of the world of others
to somehow turn yourself inside out so your care and your mindfulness
takes in the people the beings around you
and may there be a peaceful aspiration
that's like sunlight an early morning light
sunlight at dawn
that awakens and spreads
goodness and Care into the world
aspiring for the welfare and happiness of all may all beings
be happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free
maybe we may we find ways today
to live this aspiration
may we benefit the world today even in the smallest ways
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone and welcome to this fourth talk on the joy
of compassion and uh today's
aspect of compassion that can bring joy and is aspiration
so we've had awareness Attunement appreciation and today
aspiration and this is often closely tied to compassion
in that compassion includes a wish it's for the welfare and happiness of others
for people to to not suffer to have their suffering be lifted
and so there is a wish but to call that wish and aspiration has
a different connotations I wish it could be wishful thinking there can be a wish without anything
behind it or any depth it could be a wish because we're we're upset then we want things to be
different because we don't want to be upset the an aspiration comes from a deep
place within and um and it's more holistic part of who we
are and it it comes from some kind of depth Within
at least I associate the aspirationalism profound holistic organic sense of of
goodness that we something we want that's inspiring for us and maybe for
others and so in the inspiration of it there's a kind of pleasure there's a joy there's
a delight because it's something that we really feel good about we're delighted and
we're happy with it so to Aspire to meet suffering of the world
aspire to feel it and sense it not to be overwhelmed by it but to be a a
witness a supporting Witness not just a supporting witness but even
more so to be a a contributor to the welfare and happiness
to make a difference in this world of suffering to make a difference for the person we're with who's suffering
and and uh and that aspiration can take many forms it's contextual
they're rushed to be compassionate rush to compassionate action we often miss what's mostly needed for people
that sometimes if someone is starving you might think rush to get them food
but maybe deeper what they're starving for is human contact human respect
care and to stop and to be with a person and
offer friendship and understanding and companionship before providing the food or together
with fighting the food then we're really offering what the person needs and something that's deeper for them and in
so being this deeper Source from within ourselves that nurses ourselves at the same time
so that compassion is not all about taking care of the other
it's also in a certain kind of way caring for ourselves and the deeper our
aspiration can come in nourishing for ourselves the more we have to give others the more we can connect with them
and have a kind of presence that is its own food its own benefits for others where we offer
appreciation Attunement respect and so to take the time
to clarify what is our wish here what's Our intention what is our aspiration
in offering others uh Compassionate Care and is there an aspiration which
inspires us simply they wish to give people food might be good it might be a little bit
inspiring but it's kind of I think of it a little bit more closer to something like the surface of the situation and to
offer some deep human connection where we feel safe where we feel inspired by
the connection that we can establish then we are nourished we are supported
by that connection as much as the person we're caring for and so it's a kind of mutuality
aspiration kind of from his deep Place brings an a mutuality of benefit
mutuality of of love or care or respect of benefit to
to everyone and so it's not so transactional it's not so I'm doing it
for you but maybe more we're doing it I'm doing it for all of us for both of us we're doing it together in a sense
and that's where the Attunement the deep attum and appreciation can support the
idea that we're not only doing compassion for others we're doing it also at the same time simultaneously
we're doing something that's really nourishing for ourselves beneficial for ourselves
that's the potential of compassion wholesome compassion that we benefit from it as well and one
of those benefits is a kind of Joy the kind of sweetness that kind of delight
the kind of sense of well-being or a sense of deeper intimacy or
connectivity the sense of being at home here in this
feeling of compassion at home and this feeling of being alive with someone else
so that what we're sharing is also by Maybe by osmosis a transmission that
that there is a way of being in this world that we're feel deeply at home we feel like here I am here I belong here
here I'm at ease here's my peace here I
meet you with with a kind of profound sense of
of [Music] belonging of freedom of Peace here and
now without any anxiety or without any needing things to be
needing it to be different of course with compassion we are trying to make things different the suffering
different but there's something different that happens if we don't need to make a difference but it right the desire to do
so arises not from need but from aspiration not from requirements and requirements
what we have to do but rather from our something that's more closer to generosity
closer to the heart's wish of course we do this
and so aspiration is a very important part of compassion
and and it's much more than just a desire and giving some care some attention to
our aspiration to Our intention so that we get the most benefit out of
it so for example if we simply want to
um I'll say it this way that an aspiration
is a check-in balance for how we behave in the world
that it's so easy to behave with for through our selfishness through our
desire our kind of clingings and cravings and attachments our aversions
and our fears it's so easy to have bias and stereotypes of the situation and
jump to assumptions about things and but if the aspiration is a beautiful
aspiration something that's Universal something we would offer equally to everyone
and then then we might notice more likely to notice that we're holding ourselves back or we're tight or we're
resisting or we're pushing away or we have judgments or we have negative views
of what's going on that that get in the way of a kind of in
uh unbiased flow of generosity in our compassion
where our compassion is not
unduly influenced by anything within us that
um interferes with its universality or cleanliness or or CL or you know
cleanliness in that it's free of Free of prejudice free of bias free of conceit
free of and the kind of tensions involved if
there's status involved or if there's control involved or if there's dominance
involved or if there's fear involved or there's a kind of
diminishing ourselves as we do it or a sense of excessive responsibility we get
kind of tight and forceful that if the an aspiration that's
Universal that inspires that allows something deep within us to relax
then that becomes a reference point for seeing how we're off with our compassion
and it certainly is easy to be slightly off or very much often so that the
compassion is kind of influenced by all kinds of
unfortunate ways in which we might relate to the world and may sometimes unconscious ways we might relate to the
world and so to stay in touch and this is where feeling
our body being embodied that's why I love the word aspiration because coming from
breathing it's kind of an embodied profundity within us that if we're in
touch with this body of ours the body will provide us with the clues that
we're tensing that we're resisting that we're closing down that we're being partial that we're being too assertive
to dominating the body is expressed in all these little micro muscles we have and to feel
and sense these operating becomes a check and balance becomes a protection of our compassion so it can remain
coming from aspiration as soon as it comes from Duty or
obligation as soon as it overrides the ways in which we're getting exhausted tired resistant the ways in which we
feel oppressed or troubled or stressed by it if we override that then compassion
becomes it's not sustainable it becomes
exhausting it becomes stressful it becomes kind of it can even become unhealthy for us
so some people have compassion fatigue some people who are wonderfully compassionate people
but they're going about their compassion in very difficult circumstances in life
that it has a long lasting Legacy of
stress or of anxiety fear of
of grief that kind of builds slowly
imperceptibly over time because of the tremendous challenge
to which the human challenges to which we're bringing are compassion people
suffer dramatically horrible things happen to people and to be a caretaker for that I could have a big toll on the
caretaker if we don't find that place of aspiration where there's a joy or a lightness a
nourishment from which we can do the compassion and if the aspiration if is not
nourishing if the Joy or the lightness or the sweetness is not there that's an indication
that probably what we should do is to rest probably what you do is get a break to be renewed be refreshed
and the middle way is the way of Buddhism not too much and not too little not
forcing ourselves um so we end up being over over stressed and over activated
over kind of energized over and not uh so that we become slothful or
resistant or or sink back in ourselves we want to kind of maintain that middle
way and for that we aspiration
and rest aspiration and renewal aspiration and action in the world that
that we find the place that's sustainable over time
if the compassion is a little bit off or very much off it's not sustainable
so the suggestion is aspiration it can be the depth and the profundity of what
aspiration can be can be a source of joy and a source of protection of our
compassion so please spend time looking deeply at
your intention with the motivation the aspiration that
his part and parcel of compassion and to do so on the foundation of
awareness Attunement and appreciation helps that aspiration
um fulfill its potential so thank you
very much and um and I have one more talk tomorrow and
the action part the joy of compassionate action thank you