so hello everyone and welcome to this Friday and um
Pride Friday morning meditation in California and
I appreciate all the time zones that people are in it's a kind of different way of feeling
connected around the globe thinking about it and I appreciate seeing the names with the greetings so here on
the YouTube chat and it's nice to see all the names and it's and nice to see the names that you know
become familiar with now over time so welcome
there's a I think in I don't know maybe ancient maybe not so
ancient saying that um when meditating
watch your mind when in the world watch your speech
and the two these two watchings these two
ways of being mindful are closely connected because what we say is closely connected
to what's happening in our minds and hearts in our life
often it's a manifestation of it and one way to get a sense of your
quality the characteristics the mood of your inner life is to notice how
you're speaking and when we're watching our mind in
meditation it's also possible to watch how we're speaking to ourselves
they kind of thoughts we have and the quality their tone of the thoughts and the and the
attitude that's in their thoughts and sometimes those can be quite
um they can be quite um
friendly and sometimes the way we think inside can be harsh
sometimes they can be confident and sometimes to get me anxious sometimes they can be critical and other
times they can be appreciative sometimes they are consumed with in a
painful way around thoughts about me myself and mine but I and sometimes they're thoughts which are
free of I or a lightness and ease around the
the eye that they might the thoughts might be about so watching the mind
and this uh watching the mind becomes a
appreciation of
uh observation of how good it is just to be
aware just to be mindful but maybe to do so with a friendly
attitude that sometimes it's possible to see that
the alternative to a friendly attitudes towards oneself and
meditation his painful it's not really it's stressful
so if that's the case why not be friendly why not be kind
why not have kind thoughts friendly thoughts so
to begin by you know
excuse me so to begin and um
intentional way to do so mindfully thoughtfully
to enter into a meditation posture and even if you're already in such a
posture maybe there's some small ways to adjust
the way your head is on your shoulders
the openness in the chest
maybe there's a way that the spine can be a little bit more alert
by elongating it a teeny bit
and seeing if the hands fingers can be in a relaxed way soft
and lowering the Gaze and
closing your eyes
taking you a few long slow deep breaths in a slow gentle way as if it's a
friendly greeting that you give yourself hi
and then that deeper breath than usual to greet and to meet
a greater range of your embodied experience
and then to exhale a little bit Fuller than usual
in a friendly way almost as if or as if
you're saying appreciatively ah
as you exhale
breathing normally in with a normal breath
in a friendly way to relax parts of your body
is if you're offering kindness or Good Will to each part of your body that relaxes
even if it feels strange to be friendly to parts of your body
it's good for the heart for us to be friendly to all things
and then to settle into your breathing
as if you're meeting each inhale and each exhale
with friendliness with good will
that you're not trying to you you use the breath for your purposes
or manipulate the breath or be aggressive with your breath
they're not even holding on to the breath
put a continual Act of friendly warm-hearted
attention
allowing the breath to be as it is and in your friendly gaze
maybe the breathing can just settle relax
maybe the breathing can breathe more easily because it doesn't have to satisfy
any of your desires or wishes for anything
breathing just breathes in you a friendly Observer
accompanying breathing a friendly companion
right there alongside each breath
foreign
perhaps for the purposes of this meditation to assume that all the different ways
you can be fit into two categories
either there's a General Goodwill
or the absence of Goodwill
and in whatever way you recognize the absence of Goodwill or the opposite of Goodwill
meet that with kindness meet that with a kind of friendly Goodwill
perhaps a kind of Goodwill
that allows a thinking mind to relax become quiet
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
to imagine that your awareness
is like Midas Touch that whatever you touch with awareness
whatever you're aware of whatever you know that your awareness is touching it
with whatever deeper attitude you have
it has an influence on the world with what touch
you're aware of it with what way you know it
and perhaps as the end of this meditation turn your attention outward now into the
world around you in your immediate neighborhood
The Wider Community you're in
The Wider Circles of neighbors and friends and Families
A Wider Circle of people out across the lands
and to have that attention to the wider World spreading outward
for it to be an expression of Good Will well wishing
for everyone as if you're you are touching everyone
lightly Softly maybe with a small
touch on the back upper back I'm here with you I care for you I wish
you well
to live dedicated to finding ways to have good will
for all beings may all beings
be the beneficiaries of our good will
may all beings become happier
knowing there are those who have good will to them
may all beings feel safer
in the circles of our good will
may all beings be more at peace
knowing through with people who have good will care and love
and may all beings be free of sorrow and suffering and stress and
despair knowing
that they are supported by those who have good will for them wish them well
may we live this day offering our good will
to all that we meet may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so
we come to the fifth of these five talks on a wise speech and these are five
Reflections that we can do before we speak or after we speak
and not because others should they were obligated to be this way but because these are five ways that
we can flourish our hearts can flourish them are the Dharma path can flourish in
US and their ways of supporting the flourishing of others
so to speak when it's timely the right time
do not rush to speak or avoid speaking but to consider what's the right time is
it now is it some other time and to speak honestly speak the truth
where we're not in no way trying to deceive anyone or manipulate anyone with our speech
to speak in a way that is um
touches the heart the pleasant way but deeper than just pleasure something that
pleases the heart our heart and that of others
to speak what's beneficial what's helpful if it's not helpful if it's
if it's the opposite of beneficial maybe don't say it and then today to speak with Goodwill
with Mehta with loving kindness or kindness with friendliness like all
words that Translate and uh one of the remarkable things that
for me personally that I discovered as I went through this Buddhist practice is that um
when I do not have a good will when I'm not
open-hearted to be with people that uh to use that metaphor then I'm
close-hearted there's a way in which I'm not that way that I'm not really fully
myself or in the coming from a place where I feel most at home or comfortable or free
and it isn't that I'm supposed to always be have good will necessarily there's challenging situations to be and
but that for any extended period of time to not have good will means I'm somehow
caught in something or stuck in something and not that I have to have supposed to
have good will for others I just don't want to be limited by the opposite that
I want to be the suffering or the strain or the stress it doesn't feel good to perpetuate that
and to live that way and so I learned that um that uh and I
came to have a profound trust in that it's in theory possible to have good will for everyone
and I'm motivated to live that way or to find that way or to practice to attain that not as an attainment
exactly but more as as a way of arriving or being fully here in myself with the
world free and so the reference point for that is is there Goodwill or not if there's not
then there's work to be done there's practice to be done and uh internally not to force myself to
have good will and um and and so
but that but to speak with Goodwill has benefits for oneself
I said earlier that there's this Axiom that in meditation watch your mind in
speech in the world watch your speech and when there's a reciprocal
relationship between the mind and our speech that the the how our mind is is
often how we speak influences are speaking but how we speak will have an influence
on the mind so if we speak angrily if we're angry and speak Angry Words that will usually
kind of often reinforce the mind's tendency The Habit to be angry
if we speak if we if we feel friendly and we speak in a friendly way that
reinforces the tendency the the disposition of the mind to be friendly
so and sometimes it's okay to speak with
friendly ways in Goodwill if it feels sincere enough so that it benefits ourselves
and that's one of the reasons to do it is a self-benefit that comes and I keep emphasizing this so that we
don't take it as a moral obligation to be ethical or live from Good Will
and by having a moral obligation kind of to to to
um kind of fake it or kind of uh force it or kind of pretend or it becomes kind of
a Sacrament surfacey kind of Goodwill but I say that that so that
we benefit from it it's really in Buddhist practice we want to always check in with ourselves and how are we
right now and is this really serving me is this beneficial for me
and um and does this touch my heart in a deep way
and um and if we kind of use that as a reference point then it's a lot easier
to want to find the way to live with an open heart with freedom with good will
and as we then Express that good will then that is more likely to support it
than if we don't continue that benefit for ourselves and we get the added bonus that's very
important and maybe it's a primary motivation for sometimes is we're actually wishing well for others we want
others to be well and good but we're not overriding ourselves and just trying to sacrifice ourselves for
others well-being at all costs we are caring for ourselves as much as we're
caring for others we're using the reference point of our own Freedom or our own lack of Freedom as a guide for
how to be in the world in a useful way for others because how we are
is as important as what we say and so that's why when we ask ourselves
is it the right time one of the things we check in with uh how is how I am the
way that the best for me to be able to speak right now maybe I need to go walk around the block and meditate a little
bit because so I can be in a better place to speak how I am uh you know is uh is where the
truth comes from you have much more clearer sense of what's true if how you are settled and calm and and attentive
sensitive and how we are if we are in a in a
friendly place a kind place a compassionate Place loving place then it's easier for us to speak words that
touch the heart of others that are gentle and then is it beneficial
and I would like to propose that sometimes the content of the words what we actually the words we're actually
saying and what they mean has less to do about what's beneficial than how we say it
and I think it's been said that in many settings people who can speak with
respect for others with kindness for others with support with a certain level of confidence and presence can have a
much bigger impact than those people who say the same thing but don't have a
sense of confidence or care or respect for who they're speaking to so how we are might actually be more
important uh if a part of the communication than what we're actually saying
and then is there good will this again has to do with how we are is are we is is are we
expressing or manifesting Good Will in our speech for friendliness in our speech
and um and if we do it's good for us it's healing for us
so these five criteria of speech
and um and I'd like to end the series by uh a teaching by tiknar Han about our
right speech but I think his context has to do with the precept of not having not
not lying and it's a lovely kind of thing
oh where of the suffering caused by unmindful speech
and the inability to listen to others I vow to cultivate loving speech
and deep listening in order to bring joy and happiness to others
and to relieve others of their suffering knowing that words can create happiness
or suffering I vow to learn to speak truthfully
with words that Inspire self-confidence joy and Hope
I am determined not to spread news that I do not know to be certain
and not to criticize or condemn things of which I am not sure I will refrain from uttering words that
can cause division or Discord or that can cause the family or the
community to break I will make all efforts to reconcile and resolve all conflicts however small
and I took this from a book a particular Hans called for a future to be possible
I just love the title um so we want to live and speak in a way
that makes a good future possible for all of us and um
so uh I hope that um this week on why speech has given you
something to think about and for today and maybe through the weekend maybe you
can use the concept nothing else the concept and you're
history of good history any kind of good history you've had of Goodwill friendliness kindness
and use that as a reference point to Simply Be Like a mirror to see yourself
better and if you just use that as the mirror to understand yourself better I wonder
whether you'll actually move towards having more good will even without
intentionally wanting at her potentially making it happen I have a tremendous trust in the power
of looking at ourselves deeply that if we do so we'll naturally want to move to
a way of being which is better for ourselves and others so uh
thank you and I look forward to being here with you again on Monday