ah
good evening so a warm welcome to everyone
so as you know sit in silence for 45 minutes
and then I'll offer a brief talk so we'll ring the bell at 8 15.
thanks
good evening welcome welcome nice to see you all
so I um you know these days there's this talk about artificial intelligence AI
and this some maybe not directly but maybe it is
directly I don't know I haven't I'm not so up to date on whatever he's talking about but there's this question of like
what is real what is real
and if we were anything that we feel like it must be real
it must be like you or me right this like I'm real you're real you're
real right so this idea like okay well you know I'm real
but there's a you know the the Buddhist uh the Buddhist teachings
include this idea of not-self and so what does that mean really
with that whole idea of not self so I'd like to explore this a little bit
and I'm influenced by a contemporary philosopher Julian bikini
not a Buddhist or maybe is I don't know but he writes
as a philosopher and
he he gave a talk a Ted talked every 10 years ago
that I heard and I thought oh okay so there's pointing to this same idea of
not self but from a really different angle that I found interesting and
interesting to think about but
before I go into that I want to talk a little bit about some of these initial reactions we might have to not
self-teachings or even hearing about this maybe for the first time or over and over again
we might have this ideas of what I don't get it
not self like that's just what of course there's a self this is ridiculous
and so we might have this idea of like we want to be a little bit dismissive of it because it's so different than our
actual experience of course there's a self there's a real
self what are they talking about so there's a way in that this teaching runs counter
to our experience and our ideas and certainly the way that like society and
our culture suggests that there's a self I'll talk a little bit more about that but so our initial reactions and
certainly this was mine a little bit of puzzlement or disbelief
and I remember hearing some teachings that they really touched me and I felt
like wow this is like so great so Buddhist thing I felt like oh okay I
found a home here it makes sense to me except for that not self stuff so I kind
of thought that idea okay well I'll be a Buddhist whatever that means I didn't even know at that time but I'm just gonna be a self I'll let them kind of
keep all that not self stuff and I'm gonna keep myself here and it's not uncommon right to have
these ideas you was like oh okay well Maybe
if it true I don't know but to feel a little bit uncomfortable with it and have maybe this
attempted to dismiss it just as um I did and that's perfectly fine you can do
that you don't have to believe anything that I'm saying there's the last thing we want to do it's like
here's a collection of beliefs that you have to adopt or some views you have to adopt that's not the direction we're
going it's this tradition we're really pointing to experiences then I'll be pointing to that in a
moment but maybe one last thing that I'll say about some of our initial reactions when
we hear about this even the concept or the idea of not self after maybe some puzzlement or some disbelief or wanting
to dismiss it is this recognition that this path of practice part of what I think makes it
so powerful and attractive is that it requires or
I don't know if I like this word requires but maybe that it asks for some
open-mindedness and some humility oh this path is about right we hear
about beginner's mind this idea of like okay what is there to learn what is
there to see how can I learn and how can I see
right if we thought that we already knew everything or had everything we
would have no need for meditation practice we would have no need for a spiritual practice we'd have no need for
coming to IMC on Monday nights right if we already had everything
so this path asks us for to engage with our experience
to be present for our experience with a certain amount of open-mindedness and
humility and maybe I'll even add on that that this isn't just a nice thing to say
but investigation this quality of open-mindedness and humility and asking
like what's really here what's really here what are my ideas about what's here what
are the experiences I'm having like what's happening what's my relationship
to happening this whole idea of Investigation this whole practice of Investigation
is one of the factors of Awakening this is part of what leads to Awakening is a
support for awakening so it's more than just saying oh it's nice to have this open-mindedness and
this humility I would say it's an integral part of this path of practice
so let's getting back to this idea of a non-self
so there's this sense of self it just kind of like makes common sense if you
were to ask people maybe if I were to ask some of you or prove to ask somebody walking down the street like what is
what does it mean to have a self and then kind of look at you a little bit oddly perhaps we don't think about
this so much but there's this idea often that we have a a
core or an essence and some people rather than self might
even use this word ego which maybe feels like part of itself or some people might use the word soul
so this like inner entity
that stays with us like through our life as we grow and
go through our lives and there's lots of things in our culture that really reinforce this idea
and uh kind of a funny what I mean not funny but in one that I hadn't thought
of before was this even this whole idea of horoscopes if you're born on this month or this
time frame you have this uh or astrological sign and therefore it
means something about you and often you know I still hear you know people talking about even Buddhist practitioners well I'm a Gemini and that
means that blah blah blah or in true Aries fashion I did blah blah blah you
know there's this idea that even that a person could have a horoscope that says something about how they this integral
to their essence or something like this and maybe if you don't believe in the
horoscopes or astrological signs we still have like in a professional world
and in career development all these types of things we have these personality tests
Myers-Briggs type indicator mbti maybe some of you have done this taken
these tests and you get these four letter designations that like the type that you are
and then they suggest you know what the best way that you work or the best way that you learn or how to be a good
manager a good employee or something like that right so here's another way in society's kind of suggesting that you have this
Core Essence and not only that that it can be uh
assigned a type and that this type is going to be with you as you progress through life
of course it's it's we have these official uh type indicators but you know there's
plenty of websites and magazines there's a lot of stuff take these answer these five questions
and we'll tell you what can I have a learner you are what type of a what type of exercise is best for you the best
diet you know everything right anything you can imagine so this idea that we even have like one
distinct style or type or something is part of what kind of society in our
culture believes and many of us kind of accept this makes sense
and so if we believe that there's this core or this essence
then we have this idea that this core this Essence as experiences
but then just get like tacked on like here to the to the outside of this core
or this Essence there's this thing in the middle and now it has these other things hanging on to it
experiences memories things that we learn Sensations all
these types of things sense of there's something here and everything else is somehow attached to
it but there's this thing here or type our style or
ego Soul self all these types of things
to be sure I mean we certainly we have desires we have beliefs we have knowledge we have Sensations we have
experiences all these things that maybe we believe are been
distinct from this core but somehow attached to it
and then what the Buddha is pointing to and even modern day neuroscience and
some schools of philosophy that there actually isn't this
core there isn't a you uh I me
at the center of all experiences
well then you might ask well what is fair then
so clearly we have these memories and desires and beliefs and knowledge and Sensations
so these things exist and and they're all integrate it in some way and they overlap in some way
or in our beliefs are related to the experiences we have
Sensations that we've had and our memories the things that we think are important are also associated with our
beliefs and maybe the knowledge that we have Sensations are associated with what we
do in the world or how we're experiencing the world and that's also associated with
thoughts that we might have or so there's a way in which all these things are interrelated they're not completely
distinct so that there's an overlap and related
but maybe the emphasis here is on the way that these things are connected
so components are of our lives are connected because certainly they all belong to one
body and brain right they're not happening my Sensations aren't happening to any of you I'm not having any of your
sensations of course so they're connected in that way
but they're also connected because there's a narrative that's
getting created this sensation means X
and whatever the x is is based on our beliefs based on our values based on
knowledge we have based on other experiences we have
so there's experiences Sensations thoughts beliefs
and then there is a narrative that's like knitting them together and making a
story we're adding meaning to them the story that we tell about ourselves
the story that highlights that oh yeah that memory
was me and I'm different now
even though the memories actually happening in the present moment
and the fact that we're remembering it is a indicator of something that maybe a
experience or a sensation we had right now
and so there's this way there's this maybe invisible or unseen story that's knitting all our
experiences together to make sense nobody else nobody likes things to not
make sense we all kind of want to have our life make sense our experiences make sense so there's this narrative that
we're layering on top so what does this mean exactly
we might say that the these connected things I can use this word things
beliefs values knowledge Sensations experiences
are what you is a me is collection
of connected things I'm using this word things
beliefs Sensations values thoughts
in some ways we're like the the sum of the parts
so maybe to I like this example
and this is from Julian bikini the philosopher part of it I like it because uh some of
you may know I'm trained as a scientist and this is a little bit of science tiny little bit of science
makes me happy so there's we could take something like
water H2O we all know this H2O
two hydrogen atoms one oxygen atom put them together you get water
it's real kind of like know this there's I think too complicated about it
but what you guys probably didn't think is that there's this essence of water and
then we stick a hydrogen on it over here another hydrogen ion over here and an oxygen over here
no you understand that it's two hydrogens and an oxygen together and that's the water
there isn't this core that we call water that then we stick things on
or maybe we might even say that microphones
there's a I don't know how microphones work exactly I think there's sound waves
that come in there's a diaphragm that vibrates and it is connected to a doohickey which is
connected to a thingamajig which is connected you know I don't know what exactly how microphones work
there's a wire it's the same thing right there isn't
this core that's called microphone that we stick the diaphragm the coil I think there's a coil I think I'm a jig on and
the doohickey on right no it's a collection of things microphone is you know all
these things in a particular configuration
and they're working together they're doing something they're amplifying my voice in this case
Mickey Mouse in cartoons the same type of thing right it's a character
it's on TV or on the computer which was drawn by somebody
has and there's stories about it but
is it real is Mickey Mouse real
it's a collection of things that were created and I don't actually know how
they make cartoons but Mickey Mouse right it's important for some children as a rule that it
teaches and stories but so it's not not real because it has
an impact on people water is real microphones are real
they don't have a core though they're just a collection of things and
we are assigning a label to this collection
or rainbows right these are just when the conditions
are present Etc right water in the atmosphere and sunlight and
I guess there needs to be like a human being or some entity that has can
visualize a rainbow see in that color spectrum but Rainbows are real
but they're not substantial like we love rainbows we can take photos
of them but they're just a collection of certain conditions came together and made a
rainbow about you they're not I mean they're real but right there have
this insubstantiality to them also
so there's a few ideas that I'm pointing to you here that all of these things Mickey Mouse
rainbows microphones water everything actually
everything doesn't have like a core that we then
stick attached to that has other things attached to it
so why should the self be different why should this idea of a self be
different than everything else in our experience
why do we think that uh that we're not just a collection of all our parts we'll
use that word parts but instead we have this idea that there's a core and other things get
attached to it but there's nothing like that that exists that we can point to
that scientists can point to at all
so I want to highlight that I'm not saying anything like this doesn't exist that selves don't exist or
that's silly of course I exist and of course you exist
we're just saying that often when we say that there's a self we're assuming that
it has certain qualities that has this core and that everything else happens to it
and I'm saying no it's just a collection of parts in the same way that a waterfall
is you know water falling the waterfall is always changing
it's different droplets of water that are going over Landing in different places and the
water has a history before it gets to the waterfalls and it goes over the waterfall so a self is kind of like that
too all these parts are changing they're
interrelated they're changing but it's they're moving in some kind of way we
might imagine that doesn't mean waterfalls don't exist Niagara Falls if you ever take pictures
of them they're beautiful they even make rainbows but there isn't like a solid core
substance to them so the self is like this
and there's actually something quite fantastic about this because
the fact that for a collection of parts
or processes instead of like this
stable core that's in the middle not changing
it means that we can develop and cultivate
grow change otherwise if there was this stable thing that just gets us experiences attached
to we'd be trapped so this is kind of like the freedom
that's available to humans and there's even more freedom when we
really start to understand this deeply because as long as we think that we have
this core then we have to protect it
we have to Shield it we have to pretend it looks a particular way to everybody else
there's a reason why we often aren't sharing our inner thoughts with other people because we often there's a feeling like
oh this inner cores somehow not quite right
this is a pervasive feeling that humans have not everybody but a lot of people have
so we're trying to hide it so we're creating these narratives these stories
that trying to convince everybody yeah I'm fine everything's under control
I got it no problem when we might actually be desperately confused or
feeling not like their life is going the way we want it to or something like this Meanwhile
we're trying to convince yeah no problem I got it
so we're trying to protect it we're trying to bolster it make sure that it looks good we feel vulnerable if we have
this core like we don't want people to maybe even know about it or
to injure it in some kind of way we build walls around it so we don't get
close to other people this idea of this Center a central core
or Essence source of a lot of duka
a lot of Duke a lot of dukkha
and as this starts to maybe loosen up and that's maybe we don't feel like we
have a core but we only do at certain times and then maybe we can loosen up and feel like there's
just a flow of experiences and the more ease we have in our life
chances are if you were to think about the best moments of your life it doesn't involve being like
contracted and feeling separate from everybody else and feeling like you have to protect yourself or something like
that instead probably the best moments of your life or when there's a sense of flow and connection
with others with nature or whatever it might be
so the Buddha is pointing to this that there's the self is just a collection
I'm not going to go into the details of what this collection is maybe maybe I will in a subsequent talk but
I wanted to talk about a little bit how can we go about
loosening up or even seeing how it's part of a collection
maybe one thing I'll say is that it's often meditative experiences that can
really cause a giant shift but there's lots of
small shifts along the way that we can be doing and practicing with
and this is um from Joseph Goldstein who shares some practices to do in daily
life to kind of like support this idea if they're not being a solid core or
Essence and one is and uh I appreciate that Joseph is
saying okay this is for daily life so he says for three minutes so somebody only had to do for three minutes
is just to listen to The Sounds
in this building sometimes we hear traffic it's from the year my voice we hear
people shuffling a little bit maybe your breath it absolutely doesn't matter if you want
to do this exercise I'm not going to point to whether it's in a quiet place noisy place it doesn't matter
just listen can I open up the awareness
hear a sound and then drop in the question
what's knowing these sounds
knowing is happening there's sounds and we know that there's sounds but what's what's knowing that sounds
let me just do a little investigation is there something inside that knows
is there a nowhere this feels like an odd
expression or odd question but we can just look
maybe we'll just do this now what is there a nowhere
inside that can like hear these sounds or even know the meaning of these words
like what wouldn't how would we even know when nowhere
like what is a nowhere so
when we investigate we see that there's actually really nothing to find
and the trick is to look again and again and again
and again and again to do this exercise when you hear sounds
just a turn what's the knower do it when the mind is quiet when the
mind's agitated and just to investigate
it's not it won't be sufficient to do it you know 10 times and say okay there's nothing there I get it now what's next
there's something about the looking and not finding repeatedly that has an
impact so that's one thing we can do it's so
this recognition that all that's going on is hearing
and the knowing of the sounds there isn't uh this nowhere it's just
sounds be known there's no self
there's no core there's no essence a second
practice that Joseph talks about and he also says you could just do this
for three minutes to do this like in daily life and Joseph gives a story
about doing some walking meditation while on retreat
and he recognized that when he was walking there's a whole collection of
Sensations pressure on the bottom of the feet maybe the feeling of air going
across the body or maybe the sense of motion or maybe there's a sense of
lightness like we're not stuck and heavy but we're kind of like have this
lightness mobility of it can move so there's a collection of Sensations
and then to notice that that they're simply experiencing
Sensations in space
the sensations are down there on the bottom of the feet
but there's also maybe Sensations feeling the breeze on the face for the hands
there's also maybe a sensation in the leg as or the legs as the material of
the clues moves against the body so it's a collection of Sensations
there's the mind that creates a narrative and creates the self oh there's a body that's doing this motion
that's walking that's true but that actual
experience different than the narrative the actual experience like really the
actual Sensations maybe I should use that word it's at the bottom of the feet
maybe on the upper legs maybe on the face
but that's not a body that's a collection of Sensations
so Joseph Joseph recommends for three minutes do some walking and feel how
there's oh yeah there's just this collection of Sensations as we move
it's a little bit extra it's not a little bit it's a lot it's a lot extra but we're so used to doing it we don't
notice but it's extra to impute the whole body
that's walking so Joseph highlights to see that
actually the body is he has this expression he was um
he was called like this fluid energy field I don't know if that resonates for you
it might a fluid energy field but that's different than this
anatomical body that you could see on an X-ray for example or CAT scan or
something like that this just this collection of Sensations
so we might have this idea of the solidity of the body and maybe in some way we might think
that oh this is core or the essence because this feels pretty solid
but when we move we can start to see it's a collection of Sensations
and I maybe want to emphasize that this not self-teaching is really about
Sensations phenomena it's so much not about the mind it's
pointing to actually how the mind creates Concepts like the idea of water like we think water but it's not a core
which we attach things water is concept a word that gets assigned to a
collection and the body is the same way the body's the same way and the self is the same way
and maybe for the and Joseph gives this last uh recommendation for something that we can
do to help us see through this idea that we might have that there's a solid core
or Essence is that too this often Works a little
bit better when the mind is a little bit quiet but it's not uncommon for us to identify
with the thoughts okay maybe I'm not my body okay well maybe I'm not um
I'm I'm not uh the nowhere I'm not even sure where that
is but my thoughts clearly what this inner narrative is that's must be me
but when you look the actual experiences again I'm talking
really subtle but that what actually is happening
is a lot of thoughts thoughts that come and go come and go
come and go come go come and go all day long it's just a collection of thoughts
some thoughts we believe some other thoughts we don't believe some are wispy some get repeated a bazillion times they
are all thoughts and so Joseph talks about just for a
while if you can just notice wow wow how many thoughts
we have in a three-minute period can you notice this is so easy often we just get
lost in them but to notice how thoughts are arising and passing thoughts even the thoughts
like this is silly why am I doing this you know they're all just thoughts
and they're coming and going so if we think that we are like our internal World well
which thought would we be
like we're like only these thoughts but not those thoughts the ones that we like or maybe we're only the thoughts that we
don't like and there isn't a core there isn't an Essence there
so this idea of not self is just pointing to
how it's completely appropriate that we use Concepts and labels that we assign
to collections of things
and this idea of scent the self is a label we use to assign to a collection
of things there isn't this core
always will be with us forever and who knows like next life past life these
types of things and I know somebody's going to ask well wait if there isn't itself what gets
reborn this is right right I'm not going to answer that right now it's the you know that it's a perfectly
legitimate question it's a good question right I'm just going to say for here
that uh there isn't a self and the way that we think there is
there isn't like the ego with the way we think there's there isn't a soul the way we think there is
of course there's a self right I'm a self you guys are a self I don't want us to get too tripped up on language so it
would be better if we had another word than self ego or Soul maybe it's a better word
even though that doesn't quite match but uh maybe points to the same thing
so this idea of not self when we think about it
like I said might be a little bit puzzlement or we might want to dismiss it or it might even bring up some fear
or a lot of uncomfortableness I often don't like to teach about this
topic because it causes a lot of uncomfortableness I'll just say this
but it's one of those teachings that the idea of it seems really weird or
uncomfortable the experience of it which usually happens in a meditative State some deep
this deep recognition is beautiful
and it turns out to be like one of the biggest relief
oh I didn't even know that I was like carrying this burden this idea of a self
that I have to protect and make everybody like and you know all
this stuff so the experience is different than our
ideas about it maybe that's a fundamental teaching here
so with that I'll uh open it up for some questions or comments are there some
questions
all right nobody has a self we don't have questions
that's fine with nobody has you don't have to ask questions assistant provide an opportunity
there's a way of been thinking about this um can you hold this a little bit closer so we can and to go like this yeah there
you go thank you I am uh I'm a craniosacral practitioner which is
a very subtle gentle type of Bodywork and I notice
when practitioners talk about what happens in the physiology and the
it comes out of osteopathy so it's got its whole has a particular Paradigm in languaging
around it but I notice when practitioners are
talking about what happens in the physiology and what we're doing and the issue of self as a practitioner
really becomes a problem because it's really it's a type of work that's like a
non-doing it's being very present with somebody and you're not you're not doing
something you're attending to um you're tracking you have awareness
but it's very important that it's a non-m manipulative intent it's not an intent to alter somebody
and so I have been noticing how practitioners have a real challenge around how to
language that and I really feel like it's that self no I always think oh this
is so very Buddhist and it's I mean it's real it's how it is it's just the truth that
they're trying to get at and they often end up going towards a spiritual language and then it becomes like a God
thing right so um it's just something I've been rolling around in my mind about this in terms of
actually the experience that they're pointing to is not self that there is physiology there is
phenomena there is awareness there is a tending to
there is not manipulating there is not controlling there's not fixing there is not
remediating you know so um
just for myself as a practitioner has been sort of playing with you know like oh I wonder how that could be
you know it could be articulated it really to me it really comes to what we talk about in Buddhism as not self
but that's outside of the paradigm that it's operating in right you know they're
trying to they're trying to quantify that experience which is real you know
um they're getting into that essential experience but they lack the language because it's not Buddhist actually you
know so this is so they also have the idea that there isn't this core or that's what that's what I feel is trying
to be articulated because that's a real and true experience when you get into
that that actually there's nothing there's not a self there's just being present with there's attending there's
experience there's phenomenal um and I think you're pointing to something that's when we when there is
like a Core Essence then we often feel like we have to fix it or we have to
manipulate it or to people I don't know it gets yeah there's definitely this sense comes in yes thank you thank you
yes but then when you relinquish all that to just attend to in fact how do you describe it right
what are you doing yeah you know so
um yeah it's something I've been rolling around like huh how could this be articulated and in Buddhism we know how
to articulate that we recognize that as not self but that's outside of the
Paradigm of this thank you thank you
okay Okay so thank you all for your attention
and I wish you all a wonderful rest of the evening thank you
and if you'd like you can come up and talk to me afterwards otherwise I wish you a safe travels home