okay so we'll begin with our sitting
allowing yourself to find a comfortable posture
settle in for our time of practice together
and if you're comfortable please close your eyes and allow the attention to come inward
and just taking a moment to kind of survey the body the mind the heart
how are you right now
with the awareness that we are looking at how things are
perhaps with a sense of appreciation for the opportunity to practice
to good use of time
and just softening the body softening the muscles of the face and the eyes and the
eye sockets
allowing the shoulders to release and sink down
softening the any holding in the belly
knee bracing in the legs or arms
and then sensing into the straightness of the spine
sometimes it's even useful to pass the attention through the spine from the
bottom to the top just relaxing and aligning each vertebra
and then bringing mindfulness into the mind
just the simple awareness of the present moment
and allowing the attention to settle onto the sensations of the breath
to us the simple in and out Movement Like a rhythm
and putting the attention there as a a resting place for the mind
allowing it to gather its Energies
there's nothing magic about the breath but we can use it use this natural
phenomenon as a support for
mindfulness so maybe just noticing whether the
breath is generally long or short
and it might be that the in-breath is long and the out breath short or vice
versa they don't have to be the same
and if we just watch the natural breath there will be a tendency for it to get
softer and shorter
there's no control of the breath in our practice
foreign the attention still maintaining some awareness of the
breath but broadening the attention to the whole body
perhaps sensing the breath in the body or as an aspect of the body
using the natural recurrence of having a body
as a way to support the mind
and it's okay if the body is somewhat uncomfortable or
otherwise not up to our ideal
it is as it is and we accept that and just
intend to release any tension that might be in the body
especially tension that's due to the mind due to the way we are
relating to the body just softening that letting the body be as useful as it can
while breathing in and out
and if we find that thoughts are coming in that's quite normal
but we can just gently reopen to the body and the breath
as if we're releasing the thought like releasing a balloon whose string we have
accidentally been holding just let it float away
just gently tranquilizing the sense of the body
and now opening to the possibility
of some kind of joy in the mind perhaps arising simply because the body
is more at ease than it was before
this wouldn't be Joy like leaping in the air and
celebrating what a simple inner Joy
that comes from ease and bodily tranquility
it may be very mild or it may be stronger but we can open
to that possibility
if we allow that to infuse the body perhaps spreading it with the breath
we also feel a kind of softer feeling behind it more like
happiness or contentment
again it could be subtle
and even if the mind is fairly active and still
not wanting to stay in the present moment there can be a contentment that we're practicing with that
we're here doing this meditation in a sense
contentment is always available to be content with
being here for this letting yourself feel that
if you would like to just continue with the breath and the ease and the body
and a sense of inner happiness and mind
that's fine to just rest with that
and it's also possible to use the the breath and the
sense of Happiness as a support to open to the process of thinking
to actually use and allow the presence of thinking as part of meditation
okay but we would stay in the present moment not do the thinking
but watch the thinking watch it like an activity
like a parent watch as a child playing just the playing of the line with its
thoughts
or maybe there aren't any thoughts that's fine also
foreign completely
sometimes that doesn't happen until we allow the activity of the thought and
then just let it settle out the way we settled out the body earlier
so trying that and remembering that you have the support of the breath in the
present moment and the support of the inner happiness from meditation
allowing mental activity without becoming active
foreign
thank you
gently allowing mental activity to just settle out
breath the body the inner happiness of meditation
there can start to be a feeling of wholeness fullness in the mind and body system
we need to become gathered around just the present moment experience
nothing is disavowed but there is no distraction either
foreign
as we approach the end of this meditation okay perhaps just reflecting a on
the experience of opening slowly to the path and the body
the support of our inner life and then allowing
the mind to be as it is there a way that this is also valuable
in our daily life the balance of having an inner
anchor or orientation or reference point that we stay with
and you know allowing things to come and go as they do
allowing the line to be as it is
can there be both a clear sense of inner orientation and a
complete openness to how things unfold
and wouldn't this be a support or not only for ourselves living peacefully
among the ways of the world but also a support for others in that we
would be available to them open responsive flexible without losing their
own balance and hence providing the support for them they're not balanced
we don't always have the capacity for all of that but we can understand the
potential of cultivating the mind so if it's
grounded and also open and flexible
it's a real gift
[Music]
this week we've been looking at seven ways of letting go
often maybe in our practice we would pose a question like
how do I let go of impatience something like that and
in such a case then these different methods are useful actions to start
practicing with and we let go by doing a certain practice without expectation maybe
without impatience and then the Letting Go can come about we don't really do the
letting go but there's there are things we have to do in order for it to come about
and sometimes it's enough just to see you know just to notice if our mind is
headed into duka or not and sometimes what we see is that we
need to actively restrain something we're going too far or we're getting
compulsive in some way and then over time we'll feel less and less compulsion
around that if we make the effort to restrain a little bit it it just becomes
weaker and then someday it lets go so that's what we talked about so far
and then today we have a pair we have
Letting Go by using and letting go by avoiding
so those might sound like they contrast quite significantly they're even
opposites and that's part of the art you know this week this series is called
The Art of Letting Go and part of the artists knowing which
thing is going to be the best so let's talk through each of these
so what does it mean to let go by using so in the texts this refers mostly to
the requisites so those are the things that we need like food clothing shelter
and Medicine this late people we may also need some kind of Transportation some kind of
communication these basics of life and these are the aspects of life that are
not going away you know and so here we see clearly that Letting Go does not
mean getting rid of Letting Go does not mean getting rid of we're not going to stop eating but we do
need to develop for example a relationship with food that doesn't
include craving and clinging that doesn't include Duca so the Buddha recommends that we
explicitly practice with the aspects of life that we can avoid using
so as you might imagine a lot of the energy in this one goes around food the
the requisite that we often have the most attachment to and there are a lot of practices we can
do to work with our relationship to meeting and it's it's not always just
that you know we're doing too much or we need to you know restrain like the
previous one there can be all kinds of subtle things tied in with our relationship to who we may have some
aversion to having certain kinds of food or that we should be having more of who
knows so don't go in with expectations but here are some sort of popular ones
um there is a practice uh of doing what's called the eight precepts for Lay
people and one of them is to not eat after the midday meal so we
would just have two meals that day and in Asia at least often the people will
do this on the full moon day and half moon day and sometimes even the quarter
moon so kind of once a week but at least once a month they would have a day or
they just have the morning meal and then something in midday and then wait until the next Dawn
and there's a a way of letting go of of our you know busyness with food when we
do that just to see what that's like we may feel hunger of course and we can
learn that that's okay you know we can be with that for a few hours and when we
can do that with relative mental ease which might take a little practice
then we find over time that we're less controlled by our appetite and we're
less LED around and you know our appetite is not as compulsive for us
so that's one possibility is to kind of play around with whether or not we're
being controlled by her belly and then there's also deliberately
eating foods that we think that we like or that we think that we dislike and you
know that we all have foods like that where you know there's one where we just think oh yeah I love that one and then
there's the other ones like I haven't liked that one for 25 years maybe my whole life you know
um and it's not a matter of having an allergy or anything it's just you know we don't care for it and so it can be
interesting to deliberately eat um each of those foods and really watch
instead of just going with the like or the dislike the kind of major feeling tone that comes with it actually watch
what's going on in the mind like notice where does that feeling arise from how
long does it last you know if I take a bite of something I don't like is it just instantly and uniformly unpleasant
for the entire time and it you know or is there like variations in that when
does it come on can I redirect my attention such that it's not really as
problematic and again this is about developing a healthy relationship with
different kinds of food such that we're not as controlled and led around by the
Duke and you know and craving that arise with it it's an interesting exercise it
won't hurt you really um it's also interesting to get just in
general very intimate with the process of eating so you know normally eating is
completely focused on loading the fork getting it into the mouth and and you uh
you get that first hit of what it tastes like and you chew on it for a while and
then as soon as that gets a little bit less interesting you know because the taste does fade we're busy loading the
fork again before we've even swallowed and it's interesting to watch that process like how is the Mind choosing
where to put the attention you know when the when the flavor Fades out very
quickly the line gets bored and moves on to something else and um you know we can notice that the
texture changes it's not as good once it gets all mushy it's kind of not as
appealing and so then we're back to loading Fork if we get very intimate with that process then we start to see
it just doesn't process it's necessary process we have to feed the spine but um
you know can we change our relationship to the different aspects of it such that it's not so there's not so much pushing
and pulling in little instances of the mind grabbing on and pushing away because that's Duca actually at a subtle
level so try it out there are also things we can do around clothing another area because clothing
is related to our image and that's an area where we have a lot
of attachment so we see that these requisites tie in to aspects of mine
where we have a lot of cleaning and craving and identification so it can be interesting to deliberately
wear unusual clothes there's a class I teach about renunciation and on the day that I talk
about being aware of our identity I often wear a dress to teach that class and this is
unusual clothing for me I do own a couple but they're not my
regular wardrobe and so it's kind of fun for me to put that on and see how it feels and see people's responses or
non-responses try it out I remember one time
suggesting that someone who dresses rather fashionably as part of their
practice to go out to wearing old mismatched clothes and just see how it
was to save up the grocery store wearing something that they felt very uncomfortable in yeah yeah I don't know
if they did it or not but um can be fun so in general we would you know they're
also kind of wise Reflections that monastics do around using things we can do that too just being aware of why and
how we're using the requisites of Life are they just supports for us to be practicing or are we bringing in extra
craving and cleaning and we can also use various non-material
aspects of life we would have recommended using conceit to overcome conceit for example which is something
like skillful imitation you know we we compare ourselves that's what conceit is
it's a comparison it's either better or even worse or even equal and so we but
if you want to use this quality of Mind in your practice instead of just saying okay I'm going to try to not do anything
see that's very difficult so instead We compare ourselves to someone that we admire compare yourself
to someone who's more skilled in humility or unselfishness or generosity and then aim to become more like that so
we can use the self to overcome attachment to self in a sense so there's a lot of good ways to use the
parts of life that we're not going to be able to change immediately at least and then there's also
um avoiding you know the opposite so this comes with a quote in the in one
of the texts that says what taints should be abandoned by avoiding here a
practitioner wisely reflecting a voids this is ancient India a wild elephant a
wild horse a wild bull a wild dog a snake a stump a bramble patch a Chasm a
cesspit a sewer so these are things that are actual physical dangers and that's
sort of Common Sense we can avoid getting ourselves into dangerous or unhealthy situations that might get us
agitated um but it also goes on to say that we should avoid associating with bad
friends or behaving in ways that might harm our good standing in our community because others might think ill of us
then in a sense and maybe you think that doesn't sound very Dharma dharmic you know thinking about how we appear
socially um but it does matter in that if we don't think about it we can end up being
kind of enslaved to our relational life goodness knows people really go
overboard on social media uh into avoiding looking bad and trying to look
good and there's a lot of duka around that so we we can be a little bit more wise about that and understand okay I
don't need to impress everybody on Facebook but it would be nice to
um associate with good friends and be in good standing in a community that I care about for the simple reason that we're
nourished by that and we Thrive when we're at ease with people who share our interests and values
so someone about avoiding goes kind of deeply into things that are dangerous
for us physically dangerous relationally dangerous and it can even allow us to care for
others if we do that carefully but if we look we see that we don't always avoid what we could we run into
things that we could have avoided and sometimes we avoid for a while and
then we can use so remember that our pair for today is using and avoiding
until we have enough capacity of attention we might need to stay away
from things or limit them and then when we're stronger we can go into them and learn to be free with them and even
learn from them so [Music] um I remember a friend of mine went on a
long meditation at IMs and for a while for the beginning part of the retreat
she would come right at the end of the meal and you know get her food right at
the end so she didn't have to see anybody in line and then she would take it to her room to eat um which you're allowed to do there
don't do that at IRC but after a while she you know first she
was just avoiding she was just avoiding contact and she found that supportive but at some point she didn't find it
supportive anymore and she felt like it would be more supportive to go and be with the group and see the reactivity
that came up in her mind and so she started being able to use the conditions
of the retreat in order to further her practice so it can change I also have heard a story from ajan
Amaro who said that he used to be very upset um he's a Thai Forest monk at a
monastery here or I guess now he's in England but this was when he was here is that he used to get very upset if people
misinterpreted him at meetings at his Monastery and so you know he would find
that somebody misrepresented what he had said or had misunderstood it and interpreted it wrong and he would get
angry about that and he'll go to great effort to be sure that everybody understood his views and he'd have to
talk with everybody to make sure that they really got it and then he realized that he was just making a huge self out
of being seen perfectly in everyone's eyes so he stopped trying he let people State his ideas incorrectly he let
people take credit for things he had suggested he felt what it was like to be seen as stupid or harsh when others
interpreted his words that way and he said it was a great lesson in emptiness but he did that from a position within
his Monastery of having a good social standing and from an internal space of having enough mindfulness and attention
that he didn't get triggered by having these insults to his identity so um
there are basically no taints vexation or fever if you don't feel attached to yourself
so using and avoiding um there's a role for discernment in
discovering when to do each one of those they're different and what is the
Criterion the one that we talked about on Monday are wholesome States increasing and unwholesome States
decreasing or are on wholesome States increasing in wholesome States decreasing
so check it out maybe we're starting to get a sense now of the heart that's involved in letting
go so that's it for today and we'll continue on thanks