a good day good morning if you're here on the West Coast
hoping you're well
so again my name is kodo and
we'll continue today with this theme of the Buddha's teachings on social and communal Harmony
the first day in the meditation we just grounded ourselves sort of stealing inviting a sense of ease and samadhi and
settledness yesterday in the meditation we moved to
meta loving-kindness practice and today we'll turn to compassion
so we'll start in much the same way
settling collecting and then a few minutes into the meditation there will
be a shift and we'll move to arousing compassion
so let's find our postures
whether you're seated or reclining
or standing
or walking
how can you invite some alignment into the bones
balance on the muscles
and letting the breath reveal where there may be places of tension or
holding
foreign letting the breath help us relax
bringing Just a Touch of energy into the physical body
maybe that means lengthening the spine just a little
balancing ease and energy
breathing breathing through this whole body
for now centering the attention
on the sensations of breathing
foreign
now within the meditation
without too much inner movement the shift
the shift to arousing compassion
which we'll try this way
as in the sitting yesterday we'll first arouse
meta good well loving kindness for ourselves
in whatever way feels natural for you
intending our own well-being
that feeling and the whole body and mind
feeling the wish may I be happy
may I be happy
with just the beginnings of meta
when meta meets suffering the response is compassion
we can turn this wish for well-being
towards someone who's suffering
could be us someone we know
do you mean draw this person up in mind
sense what it's like to be with them
in the same movement of the heart offering the wish
may you be happy
may you be free from suffering
may you be freed from harm and affliction
as we offer this wish our center of gravity
stays in the wish for well-being may you be happy
may you be free from suffering
may be safe from harm and affliction
foreign
foreign gently
this compassion
inviting it to well up in the heart
with the wish may you be free from suffering
foreign
and welling up
compassion can be like that amber light at Sunset
shining from within us
now we can offer this compassion to all beings
to all beings experience suffering
first in the direction in front of us
as if there were a curtain in front of us shielding the light of
compassion from shining forth
gently but swiftly draw back the curtain
and let this light of compassion shine on all beings to the forward Direction
may all of you be free of suffering
now all beings in the quarter to the right
throwing back the curtain swiftly
and letting the amber light of compassion shine all beings may you be free
from harm and affliction
now in the third Direction behind
uncovering the light of compassion swiftly drawing back the curtain
may all beings behind be free from suffering
foreign
quarter to the left
drawing back the curtain and letting the light of compassion shine
may you be safe from harm
foreign
Direction
and above
foreign
[Music] to the right behind to the left
above and below
all beings in all directions
may you be free from suffering
foreign [Music]
relaxing back into ease
relaxing any effort in the method
to register any goodness that's come
maybe and all beings
be equally nourished by this goodness
foreign [Music]
um hello again
just having a moment to transition
it may be in the transition to say thank you so much for your practice
it's no small thing
so social and communal Harmony my brother's teachings to recap a bit where we've been
what we're talking about is that the practice of Social and communal Harmony and the Buddhist teachings begins with
Right View it's this understanding of the efficacy
of our action and then yesterday we discussed how the
Right View is Made Real by our effort by our Endeavor in personal training
we talked about rahula's repeated reflection and then for many of us sooner or later
will encounter a state that challenges Us in some important ways
and I think is especially relevant when we're we're considering social and communal Harmony
how to live and act in a harmonious way with others and that state that emotion is anger
let's start with this short story from the suttas it features um features someone named
sakka uh the the texts say that sakka was the
the ruler of the heavens of the 33 and it's uh likened kind of more to um
Regional ruler than a monarch interestingly characterized as imperfect
but someone of great faith and devotion so suck uh
uh approached the Buddha and the usual usual approach paid his
respects stood to one side and then he said this having slain what
does one sleep soundly having slain what does one not sorrow
what is the one thing ogotama who's killing you approve
the Buddha responds having slain anger one sleeps soundly
having slain anger one does not sorrow the killing of anger Osaka
with its poisoned root and honey tip this is the killing the noble ones
praise for having slain that one does not sorrow
it's a rather provocative turn of conversation I never hear the Buddha talking of
killing I think this was for rhetorical effect and we'll add some qualifications first
about [Music] um uh anger and the first thing is that um in the
way Guild translates or distinguishes this makes them makes a clear line between
anger and hostility in Anger we can take that's just good
information that's good information from our system something that may be saying oh this is
important to me or I have a boundary here that that needs respecting
so anger can be good information for us it's useful not to be slain
and so the guild will translate the word here that the Kubota was translating as anger as hostility
which has something of the edge of the impulse to arm or cruelty
the opposite of this compassion practice we were just doing for all sorts of Anger of course stay
for longer or shorter times one that's particularly sticky
I think for many of us a form of anger a form of hostility that can linger is resentment
and there's a there's an interesting suit on the angutura nikaya where the
Buddha talks the Buddha talks about nine variations on how resentment is conditioned by our thinking
and in that teaching more or less it's uh it's ways that we rehearse and
re-rehearse and re-rehearse this other person did harm to me or my
loved ones or they're supporting my uh foes
there's this really great expression in English nursing a grudge but we're
feeding a hostility
I think there's a clue to how hostilities harmful to us in the in the teachings that said that hostility is
what an enemy would wish for us and I have to wonder after our first
couple of days of teaching is rahula's repeated reflection even possible
when we're heavily under this way of hostility do we have the presence of mind to be
able to reflect is the action I'm about to take um harmful
is it helpful is it cause for affliction for myself
for others or for both or is it for our well-being it's challenging to do this when we're
under this way of hostility the poison root and honey tip has such a
an influence we're encouraged to be circumspect of
course in the interest of our own welfare and social and communal Harmony
so a story I'm about to tell I think I think without mentioning it is pointing to what I think of as the missing piece
when it comes to play to uh practicing with hostility and that is our practice of mindfulness of emotions
now I when I was quite young I learned how to I learned how to drive on an old
Volkswagen Bug just like tan Volkswagen from the 1970s
and young me I was sort of amazed at the power of the clutch
and up until then I had I thought there was this direct relationship you press the gas and the car goes
so just one to one anytime there's gas the car is going to move if the engine is running
so it was it was fascinating for me to realize that if I press the clutch down
while the engine is moving I could rev rev rev rev rev the engine and no matter how much gas it got however loud it got
the wheels didn't turn it didn't move the car didn't move
I think in just the same way our mindfulness practice when it comes to strong emotions like hostility anger
our mindfulness practice can act as the clutch it actually uh the emotion the
information of anger can rev up through the body and with with this practice of
mindfulness we can allow that we can allow that revving let's say
to come through as loud as it wants to get and pass right through
and we don't in we don't move we don't go into Movement we don't engage if we
let go of the clutch something else might happen but to feel our emotions through the body
I think this might have been what was happening during this other story with the Buddha there's
a time that he's at the squirrel sanctuary and someone someone comes to him named bharadwaja the rude
and it's said that Bharat vaja had found out that someone in his cast had gone
forth into um he'd become a monk a student of the Buddha
so the Bharat vaja comes to the buddhanis it says angry and displeased he went to the Buddha and abused and
insulted him with rude harsh words and when he'd spoke in the Buddha said
to him rather this is amazing to me rather than the Buddha uh more or less taking the
bait returning insult with insult he does this
he says to bhardwaja what do you think do friends and colleagues and relatives
and family members do they come and visit you and Barbara responds yes sometimes they
do do you then serve them fresh and cooked
foods and savories they would ask sometimes I do
but if they don't accept it who does that food belong to in that case it belongs to me says
the Buddha says in the same way when you abuse harass and attack us who
do not abuse harass and attack we don't accept it it still belongs to you
it still belongs to you someone who he says when abused harassed and attacked
abuses harasses and attacks in return is said to eat to the food and have a
reaction to it but we neither eat your food nor do we
have a reaction to it it still belongs to you it still belongs to you I don't know if you can imagine this but
someone someone coming forward with with um an insult with hostility
and having the presence of mind that uh that reflection that moment of pause
that push of the clutch that allows allows their strong energy to come to
you and then we have the moment of pause and reflection and choice
to decide how to engage it's not automatic that we meet insult with insult and in this case the Buddha
is kindly kindly explaining that those insults
can keep them they're not his
so in the Buddha's sort of keen analysis in other places he talks about various causes of anger hostility and resentment
some of them are things like Envy stinginess some of them are linked to
craving and seeking and attachment and some of them are are linked to views
or strongholdings of opinions but there are these wise ways that I
think we start to encounter um how to live
with the very human impulse to anger how to
respond to it in others and I think we can base what will become
a full rich functioning practice in rahula's
repeated reflection knowing before during and after is this action I'm about to take helpful
is it harmful
so in another teaching again says when I'm angry I don't speak harshly
and I don't praise my virtues I keep myself well restrained out of
regard for my own good I keep myself well restrained
many other teachings on anger and I want to mention something about some other practices so we have rahula's repeated
reflection we have our practice of mindfulness of emotions of course
and then the maybe a third set that I want to I want to mention is something
we did earlier actually the inspiration for the meditations this week inasuta on ways of removing resentment
three of them are three of the Brahma viharas we can take up the practice of loving
kindness the practice of compassion The Compassion the the practice of
equanimity and in a sort of way condition our affective responses
so that we can live in a harmonious way as best we can I like to think of this this inner inner
cultivation this training of our affect is kind of like giving our giving our
um giving our heart and mind a number of options well-practiced options so that when
we're under pressure these um things like kindness and compassion
present themselves so to close for today I'll just say
in exploring and dealing with anger we can make an effort to get close to it
through repeated reflection and there are distinctions to be made that show us that anger isn't the lump
it too is made of conditions it's varied and our vision of it is such
that it undermines anger's enchantment
as with the other aspects of the personal training
we interrogate anger's causes and effects through repeated reflection
hmm so even with anger hostility
very human aspects of our experience we practice with these diligently and we
find ways to be with them we discover them for ourselves how to live with these
in a way that's of benefit to ourselves a benefit to others and a benefit to everyone
this is this is what practice is asking of us tomorrow we'll move on to good
friendship and mutual benefit May our practice together this morning
nourish us and may it be that our Reflections our
meditation our faith in the Buddhist path [Music]
um May that may that be for the support of Social and communal
Harmony in small ways and large please take very good care of yourselves