hello everyone and welcome you to IMC
into our meditation together and
as we begin uh I want to mention that the attitude with
which we meditate might be more important than how we
meditate than practice meditation practice we do if we do a practice that is
striving we are just developing more striving if we do a meditation practice that has
a lot of focus on myself as a good meditator
capable capable meditator we might just be developing more preoccupation with
self if we do meditation half-heartedly
we might be cultivating more half-heartedness in our lives
but if we do a meditation practice wholeheartedly
as if each moment is arriving each moment is
fulfilling the the purpose of meditation
so we're not ahead of ourselves not trying to make something happen but
cultivating more a deep groundedness a deep settleness here in this experience
then we're developing that for ourselves
a way of being at home in this moment and if we meditate with the attitude
of deep listening that we're here to listen to ourselves
in a deep way then we cultivate number of things we cultivate listening we also cultivate
respect and we cultivate a openness
that allows something inside of us to reveal itself
if we're with a friend who's quite shook up about something and not really ready to speak we used to sit with them we
walk with them we bring them tea and we're we attend to them we're present for them but we don't push them to speak
if someone has something very important to say but they can't find the words they're
challenged they're it's difficult emotionally to start speaking then again we don't push them and
we sit with them and we're available and we're attentive waiting ready for when they want to
speak and then eventually since our friend began speaking
so the same something similar with ourselves that what's deeper in US
the deeper truths about who we are what's going on
they might need they might be shy they might be quiet they might need us to be quiet so we can
hear they also what's deeper in us might
not might not be ready to reveal itself to us until we have the right attitude of
acceptance or openness or non-assertiveness but wholehearted but may be available in
a wholehearted listening we're not coming with our judgments and expectations and desires even perhaps
even with our fears all those are allowed to settle for an attitude of availability
so to assume a meditation posture
and perhaps are some way of elongating your spine a little bit
or maybe elongating little bit in the neck and letting that
chin tucked down a little bit towards the chest
and then to either lower your gaze
or to close your eyes
and letting the eyes be relaxed there's no need to be looking at
anything with the eyes searching for anything and the eyes can rest in their sockets
and without taking some deep breaths listen feel your way
to the beginning of the inhale where in the body
is the first indication that you're going to breathe in
first movement
where's the first indication you're going to Exhale
the beginning of that movement
and where does the exhale end it's a last sensation
that characterizes exhaling
and now from the beginning of the inhale
to the end of the inhale breathing in deeply
connecting to your body from the inside
feeling the expansion of the Torso
and let there be a lengthy exhale all the way to the end of the exhale
breathing in deeply and fully and relaxing on the exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal
and for the next three or four breaths continue settling in on the exhale
relaxing
on the exhale relaxing the thinking mind
soften in the mind
and then settling into breathing
without any concern for anything that's before or after
one inhale
the exhale as of each breath no matter how
comfortable or uncomfortable it is is arriving here
is the destination
to be with each in-breath and out breath it's not the beginning of a process of
meditation it's the completion of it for that moment in that breath
with each inhale you arrive in the present moment
with each exhale you arrive here and now
to be content with that as if that's the fullness of it all
and then to the degree to which you're here with each breath
here in the moment see if you can have an attitude
of being available to whatever wants to reveal itself
deep inside what is your depths
want to say and how can you listen
foreign
nothing more to do but to be here available to hear sense feel
what is here
and then coming to the end of the meditation taking a short period here
to maybe let go of whatever meditation you've been doing
and instead just to listen deeply to yourself
if you're available quietly not searching not trying looking for something
just available for yourself
what shows itself to you
and might it feel good
for how you are to be received and known
in the simplest possible way hello to be as you are
and may it be that what we learn about listening to ourselves being available
to hear feel discover how we are in some deep
way may it be that we can apply this to
others we could learn to do it in our relationships
to be listeners to be present to be available
for them so what's in in them in their depths
you can have space can be accepted can be known
even if they don't tell us
maybe it's good for them to have this respect and care
and may it be
that the benefits of our mindfulness our ability to be present
serves for the welfare and happiness of the world may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings everywhere be free
thank you
so good morning everyone and welcome to the second talk
on wise listening and uh
it's a really a fantastic thing to become a
listener to listen well to listen well to ourselves to listen
well to others and so I want to read a
a poem by a Japanese poet named
Shin kichi Takahashi
it's a short poem I don't take your words merrily as words
far from it I listen to what makes you talk
whatever that is and me listen
so it's not just listening to what people have to say certainly that's important especially if they want us to
understand but it's also listening to what makes them speak what's the motivation what's
the underlying kind of um inspiration or movement to speak
because there is the message of the words and also there's the message of what's making a person say what they're
going to say is it the movement to feel more connected to you
or is it a movement to pull away to avoid you Martin is it a movement to
appraise themselves and get affirmation or is it a movement to apologize for
themselves and to somehow make themselves smaller in relationship to you
is it because they want to get something from you or is it because they want to support
you and see what they can offer you uh is it uh are they saying what they're
saying so that in fact they do feel maybe safer with
you or feel more like a sense of friendliness or connection
or what are they saying what they want to say because they want to be safe and they're trying to create some safety
so that goes on the list can go on and on and um but if we are only taking the
literal meaning of the words into account we
might actually be missing a huge part of what's really happening in the conversation
and and so to go along with the teaching last week on a right speech where the
the second criteria for right speeches is it true
so for a wise listening what's most true here what's really true
because sometimes the literal meanings of the words of what people speak
it might be true enough but not really the truth that needs to be expressed really the truth that is what's
happening here for the person and um you know if a person is praising
you which might feel nice and you might get distracted by the niceness of the praise but if you listen what's behind
the praise and um and maybe people feel insecure and they're looking for some way to make
themselves safe in uh in your presence because if they praise you you'll relax
and not threaten them so if that's what's true under the words that's a powerful and important truth to
recognize and if we care for them and offer them general you know genuine care then we
take that into account and maybe the praise is not that important what's
important is that we show that them that we're that they have nothing to fear with us
if if what they want is they're trying to manipulate us to get with something that's actually important to see that's
actually more true than the words the words might actually be deceptive and so if what's true is they're trying
to trick us into getting something from us then um then if we know that then how do we
care for them then do we simply cut them out and say no or avoid them
but you can also keep asking more deeply what what drives them to want to try to
get something for me are they afraid are they insecure are they poor and
desperate what's happening for people and um and this idea of listening for
what's most true uh in others is a powerful gift we give to people
what is most true for this person here now is it uh and you know so this then going
under the words going deeper what is most true and my suggestion and I thought that the
kind of the Assumption the theory that I operate under is that if you could find what is most
true in yourself most true in others you discover Beauty you discover something
precious just whatever is mean tender something that uh it's uh easy to love
or care for or be generous towards and even people have the the you know the
worst behavior and horrible words of hate and and um
um if we can listen if we can be present enough and behind the hate behind those
words behind the attitude of hate that's there and good what is most true at the depths
of who they are and I'm not saying this is Universal at all but what comes to mind right now is
that there we might find that even though the person is a grown-up we find a scared three-year-old
that somehow never no one ever cared for that fear and and it never got resolved
and and the hate is just an expression of trying to be safe trying to have a
temper temper tantrum to get attention or something and so again I'm not assuming that all
hate is this way but this Theory this assumption that I
like to operate under these yet if you go deep enough you find what's most true you find something beautiful
um I'm not going to claim it's always that that's always the case but
um it's uh very often if that's the Assumption and we listen for it that's
what gets then it has a chance to come forward then it has a chance to be discovered and but if we don't have that
theory then never be discovered and then um
so um so to listen what is most true what's what's the most important thing
here what's the the root of all this behavior that we hear and see
and um so to listen to be available to sense and I love the idea of this kind of
listening being being an availability because we're no we're not
rushing people we're not probing necessarily to get to the bottom unless
they're asking us let's to can you help me explore something but if um but just this deep sense of
availability and the lesson of that kind of listening and availability is that we can be
complete we can be at ease we can be at home in this world in that availability
which is available for what's here we're not uh
anxious about Sierra or greedy of what's here or expecting something or
you know wanting it to be different there's something very powerful about just feeling and sensing oh this is good
and I saw this with um when I was Raising young children
that how significant it was about the attitude the adults around them had
and if the adults who were anxious Were Somehow teaching the kids that the world
doesn't a dangerous place and you should be anxious but the parents who even when things
were difficult and challenging had a sense of being at ease and at home here
and that the the children were learning this lesson that oh this world is a
place where I can feel at home I can feel at ease even when there are challenges
so this idea of listening available as if there's nothing else we need to do and
we're just content and happy to be present and available in here and and be a listener I think it's
medicine for many people to do this so to listen for what is most true
and I believe that to do that well we have
to also have done that for ourselves to listen to hear to sense what is most
true here but not to do it searching into the future
but more as arriving here and being available so what's that deep inside of
us stops being shy or feels it's okay to come forth and
reveal itself so the attitude it's creating in ourselves an attitude of Welcome
availability to ourselves and to others
so um so if these uh
words about listening today or
seem interesting for you to experiment with during the day you might say in the right time
um be a little bit wise about the time to do it not automatically do it everywhere you go with all conversations
you go but you might see if you can what happens to you if in your mind you ask
yourself the question what is most true here under these words behind these words that this person's speaking uh
what is what is most true what's making them say what they're saying and um but don't be probing and don't be
a microscope staring at them but rather be available
to sense and feel be available most as if uh if you're really asking that
question and available maybe something will be revealed you don't have to
figure it out so thank you very much
and um and uh I will look forward to tomorrow
and thank you