so good morning everyone and good day for those who are on YouTube uh as I
just know this is Live on YouTube as well uh my name's Ying uh in Chen I'll
be here um this morning with you um meditating together and we'll offer a
Dharma talk um after about half an hour or so sit I want to see if any of you are uh
brand new to meditation anyone is new I can't I won't know on the YouTube but okay so we do
have um a couple of them who are new so I'm going to offer a guided meditation
then for today and those who's been practicing for a long
while kind of listen to your own inner guide and um so for those who are new um
if it's a helpful you can follow some kind of gentle guidance maybe um to uh
invite us to kind of practice along uh with me in some capacity how does that
sound yeah
okay and so my invitation is to just gently settle into the space you're in I
forgot to check the sound is it okay for uh people in the back okay
great maybe just take a few long deep breath as you settle into the
space
oh begin with this word
pause just pausing
momentarily it's kind of a process to pause right here
we just no to seeing this body
sitting this a passing has an
effect it allows ourselves to become
present maybe [Music] momentarily becoming mindful of what's
Here and
Now maybe pausing
deliberately with an intention to become more and more
present and may notice that our mind
tumbles along with the momentum to think
plan to remember the
past right this being patient and
persistent
to pause and stay
connected with what's here and
now maybe a few long deep breaths
mindfulness is
present noticing the sound
and the silence in
between
when this pausing come to an
end one may become more Mindful and
present a felt sense of the body naturally
arise you may notice the body making contact with the
floor sitting
here the weight of the body settling
down can rest your
attention right where the contact of the
body and the floor is
at may feel the heartness
firmness pressure of the
body against the
floor
let the body rest on
Earth we don't have to do
anything let the
gravity do its own
thing sitting like a
mountain
grounded
settled
open to receive the felt sense of the
breath maybe the flow of the a
breath a
movements the energizing quality of the
breath
we notice the breath in a particular part of the body or the whole body
for
and let the breath massage the body
the movements of the breath naturally energizes the body or soothe the
body
a Chinese word
t a energetic
feel and expand to
receive the dancing
Sensations in the
body and some movements of the
breath or tinkling in some part of the
body pulsations
vibrations a gentle Sway in the
Torso and feel a kind of aliveness
right here with all its dancing
Sensations
for
letting go of ideas and
stories dropping into the felt sense by feeling and
sensing this body and this a heart and mind
e
let the breath flow
freely breathing in from the space all
around and breathing out into the
space all around and
within
allow your awareness to become
spacious
expansive the sound can travel
through the breath can
flow feeling and sensing what's
here with a spacious
awareness so thought bubbles can float
away
and emotions can
move
for
may feel the heart opens with the spacious
awareness
maybe the body can relax even
further
softening and
relaxing into the spacious [Music]
awareness
for
e
know that if the Mind wandered away into
thinking planning
storytelling whenever we notice that we have a
choice we can choose to pause
again can choose to step out of the unconscious
flow of our thinking
mind and step [Music] into being
present here and
now
for
e
[Music]
for
good morning and welcome to IMC and thank you for that guided
meditation and good morning y
Chan yeah good morning everyone and um if you need to move about and shift a
post uh shift the postures or um do some things to help the body don't hesitate
to do that this is a good time to transition
um happy to be with you all feel just very delighted to be able
to spend this morning with you all and um
the topic I brought with me one part of it is
fear I feel a little something me to just name
that and there is also a second part and that is uh how to establish Fearless
relationships with fear and so don't Panic
so so there are there is this two sides uh with um today's
topic and so and the word fear itself may bring a wide range of um emotions
and reactivities or responses inside of us but we can't deny that uh fear is a
very potent emotion in our human
lives and and it arises in all kinds of um maybe arises from all kinds of uh
aspect of Our Lives or all kinds of dimensions of Our Lives can arise out of
uh physical challenges illness aging death and can arise out of emotional
responses of something the loss of loss of loved ones loss of uh Financial
stability and you know all kinds of loss can evoke uh the emotional response and
can be a a psychological um kind of of uh fear uh
maybe a sense of self self-image um a sense of who we are gets
challenged and there can arise a fear of some different kinds
and even in the uh spiritual Dimension um there can be uh fear arise
and so for uh many people who practice in the Buddhist tradition and maybe many
other spiritual Traditions religious Traditions that will come to a point uh
where there is a recognition that all kinds of things that we thought
uh we have Reliance on actually we can't really rely on them
because they're ever changing it feels like the rug gets pulled from under and
that can be a terrifying kind of sense and so there
can be a spiritual fear um arise even in the uh in the in this domain so it's
quite pervasive um and yet uh and how do we
understand fear and how do we relate fear relate with this
emotion um is a big part of our U Buddhist um practice and and then I want
want to say is there is a way that we can relate to
this um strong uh Force within each of us uh wisely compassionately and so that
this can be a force that is rather transformative rather than we feel like
we're narrowed down or limited and getting stuck by
this and so um so I kind of decided
we'll talk about this uh in two Dimensions so the first part of this
talk will be we uh learn a little bit about a fear and then we understand it a
little bit and so I thought and I looked it up and the definition the dictionary
definition of a fear actually is a pretty good one and so I thought I'm
just going to start right there and the dictionary definition of a fear is an
unpleasant emotion caused by here is a whole list of keywords to pay attention
to so it's a a unpleasant uh emo uh emotion caused by belief
perception imagination uh recognition
expectation of some kind of danger or thread which leads to
pain that's there's a lot in this definition right here I was amazed when
I read this and so uh let's tease this apart a little bit
the first one is fear is an unpleasant emotion I think we all know this right I
think all of us experienced some kind of fear worry and it's
unpleasant it's unpleasant kind of emotion and it rises out of causes and
conditions so it's not just something randomly pop up but the cause is a
condition is this long list of keywords here perception belief expectations
imaginations and recognitions of some kind of danger that's
there and this is a fascinating and when I when I saw this
word imagination I realized wow how many times we're afraid because we have
certain imagination about a kind of a thread
me this is on earthquake Zoom you know we're actually on a fault IMC is on
earthquake fault and and now if we can if we start
imagining what this might happen we could be panicking right
now and so many of our fear kind of arise out of
that and um I'd like to differentiate a little bit here and which is quite
important in this definition uh the difference between
danger and fear so danger we can't avoid um by
being human we have a human body mind heart uh there is danger in this world
um like the potential danger of earthquake right here and the danger we
can't deny it's uh um it exists and you
know we have a danger that I didn't walk properly and break my leg might getting
off this platform and that's a possibility but the danger doesn't
necessarily mean fear a lot of times we mix these two
things up I think danger me it's fear you know you're going to immediately
worry and immediately panicking but that's not not necessarily
so um there is a kind of Primal response
that's a survival response that built into this system in response to a danger
like you know um um a car comes in front of you you you jump out that's Primal
Instinct it doesn't necessarily mean immediately we're going to panic and we
actually just know that we get out of of the way to be safe but it's is true that
often uh fear can happen but I'll teach that apart a little bit I want to stay
with this point of danger doesn't necessarily mean fear you all probably
have heard a lot of um stories of great exam Master tikna
Hong uh who spoke about um um people sitting on the refugee boat
to go across ocean um it's dangerous no
doubt but if one person is calm and peaceful the whole boat can be saved a
whole boat of people might survive this but if everybody
panicked nobody might survive and it's possible in this
situation that that someone is Cal and that is possible or you can say
oh wow you know that's Zam master I'm not really sure and that's possible so I
want to give a personal uh example and that uh I think all of you
probably have experienced something like this but for me this personal example
was uh quite powerful in my own um in my own experience in my own kind of path of
a practice so this was uh some years ago I was uh driving and I was emerging on
an expressway uh on the kind of from the right hand uh right hand side and I um I
saw a Jeep coming towards on this Lane that I was merging on it was a very fast
uh driving but it was very far away so I thought okay you know they will see me I
will be able to merge they can change a lan so and I had just this few thoughts
and I said okay I'm going to go so I merged onto this express lane and as soon as I got onto the lane
I looked back from the uh rear mirror this Jeep wasn't going to slow slow down
or change lane and the people in this Jeep were waving and shouting and I just
thought wow this is not stable I'm not really sure what this Jeep is going to
do so I felt the danger right there and um so my instinct was to pull off uh the
Lan completely got to the sidewalk and I guess this uh shoulder and I pulled off
and I just stopped right there and then the Jeep Zoom you know just zipped
through me and the people were still shouting and yelling and and and right at that that
moment what came to me was may you be
safe may you know peace may you know the deepest deepest
well-being I kind of surprised myself I was like wow okay I didn't panic and and
um I didn't curse them that that just came spontaneously
um and I recognized that was a powerful moment learning moment for me that it's
not automatic that we would just become panicky or we become um angry or even
have rage and um that doesn't have to be the
case and so that was a really powerful moment for me to recognize and that was
was a possibility and that was a moment of uh the fruit of a practice showing up
it's not so much about me and you know I did something it wasn't it wasn't it was just spontaneously came that um but but
by recognizing that um I came to have so much trust and the
confidence in the practice I know yeah next time something
like I might trip again because that's just you know habit forces I have that
but it doesn't have to be the only way so through the practice some other
possibility can become available to us I think maybe each of you have those
moments that you can recognize wow okay you know it's not automatic that we
should we all just going to be panicking in situation X Y YZ is so there is a
different a different possibility
um but it is true sometimes you all
probably have noticed that that um it often happens that even when
we got out of the an uh got out of the danger like you jump out of um the
racing car coming at you fear can come immediately after that and why and this
definition give a pretty good uh explanation or you we could notice this
ourselves we can begin to imagine what could have
happened well that is scary even though we're out of the danger we're kind of
safe now but that imagination can happen that belief can happen wow this could
happen really bad and building upon that imagination
we now can start panicking we can begin to have a
fear so this is very interesting this is very interesting and
so many times our fear and worry can happen like that even though we're not
physically or even emotionally in the danger zone we can have this Downstream
sequence in of reactivity and so the deep root in this
process is that uh fear is a reactive movements emotional move movements based
on this set of imaginations and beliefs and perceptions of something dangerous that
may be there um but it's a a form the deep root of this is in the present moment we're
not clearly seeing and knowing what is really happening here we did not see
that we're actually in a SE safe zone right now we didn't not see oh this is
my imagination at work or this is a kind of a perception that's at work and we
also do not see often times that the fear is
present it's just a form of an emotion that's present and so what can happen is
often fear doesn't stop at just this momentary movement of the emotion we can
become Frozen and we can become frustrated and we can
become angry we can become depressed and you know it can get very contracted and
you know we may even do something harmful to ourselves and
others and so there is this whole sequence of reactivity that can happen
that become in fact rather dangerous to ourselves and to others
and so
um some kind of some understanding about this the this AAR maybe just kind of
from our logical mind and conceptual conceptual mind but I also don't want to
diminish this um we're not alone in this department it's not like we get you know
we're specialized staying this department and and this is a strong forth
um now and strong forth sou thousands of years ago I was looking into the sutas
and poly Canon sutas and I was interesting in our U Buddhist tradition
most people know the uh three unham roots of great hatred
delusion uh but in fact if you look at the sutas there is a whole set of a
sutas that talks about the list of four with fear in it so so you know it's a
strong force and so that's one of those uh in the list of three that we often
known and and so it's it's a strong force but I'm going to shift to talk
about and there is a possibility to uh through our practice
to begin to establish uh some more wholesome relationship or skillful
relationships with um this form of emotion called
fear uh this is what I called Fearless relationships and so I unpack a little
bit about
that and the first thing uh maybe is to write along what we been speaking about
out so far uh the first kind of relationship that's helpful to establish
with fear is this word befriending fear befriending
fear kind of this is part of us being human and
um befriending when we befriend something we can know we can learn about
them and we can begin to understand them uh when we have kind of aversive and
push away and get rid of a Runway kind of relationship we can't know them we
just can't know them and so the first uh uh step in this whole process of
establishing skillful relationships is to be friend be friend our fear it's like um
if you have a terrified child um if you're meeting a terrified
child you don't want to just beat them up or you know trying to make them happy
it doesn't happen like that you give them a very kind safe open space for
them to to be to feel that they can be themselves and then they can soften they
can Tha in that field and the same thing uh is that's
maybe analogy for being with our own uh fear our own emotion is to make
space so that the fear can feel safe to be here and so they don't feel like are
we going to you know fix them up right away and so befriending
fear and there is a process to befriend fear um it takes you know I'm going to
just say a few steps it doesn't work you know mechanically like that but I have to say
something that feels a little logical but the first thing is um uh to be bef
friend fear uh is to come to a conscious relationship with it if we're flowing in
this unconscious stream of reactivities we not even know that ex ex
existed in us we just keep on doing something to try to fix it up and getting ready of or uh we never really
pay attention that it's here so the first one is just to become aware oh
this is present in me and so that's the practice of mindful awareness oh yeah
okay I can pause for this now once I know that the Second Step um is to begin
to feel and sense the texture of the fear and kind
of um the form of the fear and to get to
know it now I use this word deliberately uh
feeling and sensing it because the fear is a form of emotion it doesn't speak
necessarily English emotions are movements their
motions they move it's a energy form in us that moves
through so often we use our logical mind the conceptual mind to try to deal with
emotions often times we'll find out you know I got this you know I I
want to get rid of it and you know I I got a lot of strategies to deal with it
we know it doesn't quite work um emotions you can think of it as
if you're going to a different country country that speaks different language from your your language you don't just
keep talking with them using your own language you know no one going to understand you but you can you can be in
that environment at least for a while to observe them to feel them to kind of
feel their body posture and and you body language facial language and how they
move in the space and you kind of you can get a sense how they they are you know you're with your animals kind of
like that also you know um being with animals are kind of like that in a way
it's kind of like our animal nature being shown so um can we feel and sense
into our emotions and can we really
listen not using necessarily all of our Logics analysis to try to map it
out and that's very important and I was looking up um at the Chinese characters
there's a whole ton of you know fear is not just one thing so there are so many words that even in English uh that kind
of are in this domain of um of uh fear in Chinese characters and
almost all of them have the character of a heart in it
um it's quite somatic you feel like heart Quivers or um heart feels
constricted or heart feels tight it's kind of very somatic and so we can get
to know fear through our somatic experience through a embodied sense get
to know that and so those are the two steps into
kind of a be begin to understand and know to feel our emotions is to become
aware and begin to really feel them and sense them and at some point and our
logical mind uh may have some recognition of what is happening but we
don't wanted to have our logical conceptual mind to always dictate
everything has to happen based on what I read in the book you know okay and let yourself really feel into this
and once we bef friend fear and we keep practicing this way then um we can begin
to open ourselves to new kind of relationships with this kind of
emotion um and one of those really important
relationships is to not be afraid of our
fears oh yeah you know
um fear tend to have really bad rep and so we almost automatically have a sense
that it needs to go away you know
um it doesn't work that way and so for me the turning point of my relationship
with fear was this point and that I recognized oh
I don't have to be afraid of my own fear wow that's liberating okay you know
you're allowed to have them but they don't have to just immediately go away or don't have to
beat them up and then yeah I can just be not afraid of it and so
um and so that's the one possibility and uh when we're not
afraid emotions are our movements they actually have a chance to move through
us we kind of have this more open space for it to move through
us and um befriending fear and becoming Fearless of a fear creates possibilities
for us to then uh establish a wide range of wise relationships with
fear I think a sooner are or later we all know there is no one siiz fitall
kind of way to be with this strong potent um domain of our lives and so we
um we needed to learn a wide range of skills and maybe cultivated capacities
to be able to relate to fear um and I use a couple of examples
and you know because I said there's no one way so part of this is to discover
for ourselves what might be needed at different times uh sometimes uh those emotions can
be like tornado they're very overpowering you know it's in the middle
of it's like wow you know it's just not steady and it's really strong we get
swept away and and how to be with that when it's very overpowering over
overwhelming uh one thing to know is that um that is a strong form of energy
so we have a choice to redirect the energy strong energy in some other way
and so you can get physical meaning not
to punch it away um but you can get moving get going
um go for a hike maybe a rigorous hike and um go do some exercise or
movements and um being in nature sometimes allows us to have to to shift
that energy in some way it's not helpful when that kind of strong form of um uh
reactive energies are doing are doing its thing that we just going to um get
stuck with it we kind of feel feel like there's absolutely no other option but know that there are other options
um in Chinese martial art and there are forms of chiong that when you're moving
with certain movements it releases uh certain emotions uh through the
movements and maybe in other um kind of a movements that has a certain kind of
effect on that and this is a skill it's not kind of some kind of Escape
it's something that we come to know oh this is the one way that I can be in
this territory when it becomes overpowering and um doing this it's also
kind of like um a Chinese medicine and that is I know I'm using a lot of
Chinese things because that's my background uh in this domain so it's
like Chinese medicine that often it's not targeted and so you work around it you
work around the system rather than kind of a being with it being with it we T
get looped in and overpowered by it and so uh redirecting your energy
into other uh forms can be very uh useful uh in uh other cultural
backgrounds sometimes uh in really strong
powerful uh emotional reactivity forces uh there uh they know they and they
don't have resources to be with that uh they chant they come to a temple they chant
they chant out loud you know that kind of that that way of being with it some
people take refuges and just come and bow to the Buddha and bow to to a Buddha
statue uh it can be a way to kind of shift our orientation and we don't not everyone
have that culture um background or kind of that way of a being with a really
strong forth and but that can be useful for um people and for
myself and uh in a strong ways I don't know what else I would do to be with
this I'll just come and really bow I bow a lot and when I finish I feel wow
something opens up in me or or something that was really bothering me and it's not there anymore okay I don't have to
solve them and
um maybe the last part uh that I'll talk
about oh no there is another aspect is so there is this overpowering uh time
and then there are other times when uh you feel you're resourced enough you
have the inner capacity uh to be with the fear just as they are then you have a choice to oh
yeah I'm just going to be here and feel it and see how it comes and how it goes
and and just be with it and there is um um suta in Ma nikaya and called
fear and dread and this is uh talking about and the Buddha meeting his own
fear and so uh before he's uh awakened so he lives in the
wilderness you know there are fears come the tricks making sound and something
you know makes sounds and fear comes but um uh and he said you know
I've developed a lot of capacities inner capacities to be with fear so so I'm
going to be with this and he used very specific language here and he
said when I'm walking if the fear
arises I'm not going to change my posture I'm just going to walk and be
with the fear until it goes away and if the fear comes when I was sitting
I'm not going to change my posture I'm just going to sit and be with a fear
until it goes away and and so on so forth with the different postures it was
um quite interesting what is a pointing to is it
did not say that um I'm going to um I'm going to do something different
to get rid of this or do something to fix it up but Buddha has a deep
understanding of the fear is a movement that comes and goes and he has the
capacity to just be with it without doing anything
different so not even changing the posture and so this is the uh the notion
of a being that with that terrified child that you don't do anything the
system has its own way to dissolve to fade
away and as long as we are uh waiting to be with this that's
good enough that's good enough not only that we can then really know fear in its
raw way not with what we believe leave needs to be you happening something
needs to be happening so we can always go Tinker with it there always there a
force you know I got to do something you I got go interfere with this no it was
the instruction was so simple you know fear comes when I'm walking I'm just going to keep walking with
it so and that's a possibility doesn't mean doesn't mean any of this is the
only way um but it's an example of there may be a wide range of ways to be with
fear and the last piece that I'll talk about today is and as we uh cultivate wise
relationships with fear will come to know that this is a gradual training you
know it's not like you know we kind of there will be a lot of times that uh we
get caught up or get stuck um but there is a way to cultiv cultivate a whole set
of inner capacities and resources and skills to become wiser and more
compassionate with uh fear and I'll um maybe name a few this
might worth yet another talk of its own but I want the name of few and so some
of you are already cultivating this and you know yeah that's part of working
with a fear and so first one is to develop
Sila ethical conducts that can feel like it's so far away you know what it doesn't have
anything to do with fear well so many of our own worries and
concerns and fears has to do with I did something not quite uh you
know that can cause cause a sense of a concern for ourselves and concern that
we get blamed or I just kind of cause a lot of uh emotions that doesn't sit in
ourselves very well and so when we know that we live in
this world are not harming in the way of killing or taking something
lying our heart and mind are at ease and the whole host of kind of kind
uh fear and worry would just not
come and the Buddha himself uh in this discourse uh spoke about yeah I'm kind
of really skilled in Sila I'm Skilling other um capacities the second one is
develop somebody collected mind settled mind
unified composed uh capacity
somebody is a very beautiful uh inner resource and sometimes when we rest in
this peaceful quiet abiding we allow things to move through
us without being shaken by it and some people will say oh you know it feels
like a spiritual bypass not necessarily if this is the only way you deal with fear I would say
yeah yeah may want to look into it but this can be a skillful resource if this
is one of the ways that that you can use to um to meet with the strong emotions
or different kinds of ways yeah uh meet with emotions and somebody is also a
very healing place a lot of physical uh things can heal a lot of emotional
things can can heal in this uh samadi space and and we don't have to do
anything and third one is develop um paa and some some of you know this is Sila
Samar and paa uh three parts of the practice paa is
wisdom and we spoke a little bit about de developing wise
relationships and some of the deeper insight into the nature of our own uh
being and nature of uh our our lives uh when we have um when they
become available to us in our own livid experience
um it allows us to become become wise with many things not just the fear but
many uh things and so for example uh one of the three key uh insights that arise
through the cultivation of AIA is the uh
um anicha impermanence and so when we know fear is
impermanent emotions are impermanent and we know that deeply within
ourselves then we can begin to have um a different relationship with it it's when
we only feel like we're so stuck this is never going away you know then we kind
of like we start having you know just kind of a different relation kind of you
know feisty relationship with but when we know deeply this is moving this is
flow this is impermanent something else can open
up um developing Brahma viharas loving
kindness compassion uh equinity joy and so for me me that example I use
for merging onto Express langing is some of this um Brahma bhara practice has a
momentary uh fruit a bearing fruit in that moment in fact the story about The
Meta practice came about the monks got haunted by the tree Spirit like like oh I can't practice
here and then the Buddha said uh you know I'm going to teach you a loving kindness practice and so they become
Fearless with a tree Spirit the last one but not the least
one and is Kalia namita it's so good we don't have to do this
alone um we can practice this together and this room full and all the people
who are on YouTube if we're in a dangerous situation right now here together and
there's one person in this situation can express peace wow that gives everybody a
possibility it doesn't mean that we have to be like that all the time but if one
us one of us in one situation have a capacity to show up
with calm and ease and love that's good
enough and so we don't have to do this alone and we're always being affected by
each other and so allow that to uplift us and
to allow all of our own practice maybe to affect people all
around so I'm going to end that uh with this note um by just appreciating us
practicing together and um explore dhma together and may this benefit all beings
everywhere yeah