so hello
we're back our fifth day excuse me
if they considering the armies the Perfections what a what a wonderful week
of practice
yeah this um this path of the Perfections it's it's um it's remarkable and in a
very specific way um
and that is that there are an array of trajectories
you can develop any one of these 10 qualities and sort of move it move your practice or be moved by your practice in
a certain direction and this um this writing by them Apollo
that we're studying this week is is um pretty fascinating in its period of Buddhist history and the way that it
brings together actually um different currents of understanding
so it feels like it feels like a um a privilege and a real Joy to get to
spend a week in this territory
so let's um begin with gratitude and let's um move
into sitting
in the spirit of our theme for the day which is meta and OPEC
loving-kindness and equanimity
we'll do a simple practice that I'm going to call mindful meta
or mostly do our our familiar mindfulness practice for
the first long while and then at a certain point in the sitting switch to
loving kindness practice
so let's begin
beginning with a pause
is pausing our activities and involvements
inside and outside
finding ourselves here
seated reclining standing however it is for meditating
and finding ourselves here with this body in this body with this body
maybe a few deep breaths to strengthen the connection
between attention and embodiment
foreign ergy
to stay present to clearly know
this moment of experience now this
alert clearly knowing
as we breathe in
alert and clearly knowing
breathing out
against to know this moment
for now is enough
now making a gentle transition
with as little inner movement as possible [Music]
a transition to loving kindness practice
it can be as simple as
wishing well-being
for yourself or someone who is
dear to you
little shift in inner posture healing the wish for their well-being
foreign
Ty sitting comes to a close
that wish for well-being
conditioned by mindfulness
May that wish extend in all directions
may all beings be happy
may all beings be healthy
may all beings be safe
and may all beings everywhere know the ease of liberation
[Music]
foreign
welcome to our
fifth day on the parties the Perfections
as I mentioned we I'll I'll attempt to have a shorter
um talk about meta and opeca so that we have time for your
comments and questions I think as a Sangha we learn so much
about uh about this practice by hearing about the ex or reading in this case
um about the experience of others doing similar practices so we'll get to that at the end along
with a couple of announcements
uh I have heard I have heard that the Buddha's physician
jifaka uh was asked what the Buddha was like
and jifaka this is a person who who knew the Buddha closely you know how well
does your doctor know you um and when asked what what is the
Buddha what is the Buddha like dear physician he described the buddhismetta
the Buddha's loving kindness and isn't that something it wasn't uh
jivica wasn't saying oh you know he is the wisest he gives the best advice
he's so calm or um he frowns a lot but no it was it was his meta
it was the Buddha's heartfulness that came through
and I I like to think of meta as an expression of everything that the Buddha had cultivated for years
so these last two paramis meta loving kindness and OPEC equanimity
here we're talking about loving kindness as a wish and it's a wish to provide for the
welfare and happiness of beings in the world
it can show up as benevolence peaceful action beneficial action
and Equanimity we're talking about the attitude of impartiality
toward what's desirable and undesirable both beings and thoughts
impartiality okay so let's start with meta and meta is a
wish it's an attitude uh doesn't it take some practice
and we have these inclinations toward the opposite and aren't those so ready
so regular practice the the causal basis the the the condition we can put in
place for the arising of meta traditionally is reflecting on the goodness of others
so we can do this deliberately we can um we can incline the mind to reflect on
the goodness oh wow this person did something so kind oh wow this person
said something that uh had such and such an effect inclining the mind to reflect
on goodness and then there are options for for regular practice of course at IMC here
we have happy hour um this wonderful Sangha with Nikki megafori
and then uh I know I know a couple of teachers who do meta at night before going to
sleep they lay down in their bed and rather than having the mind wander they direct it they direct it to may
this being be happy may this being be happy I meant to can really develop as a as a
concentration practice uh it can deeply unify the mind and how wholesome that is to unify the
mind around the wish for well-being for others
loving kindness is also it's one of these practices that I guess I guess most or all of our
practices are this way but they it's an internal practice that becomes external
we cultivate these inclinations and then they start showing up in our menu of actions where the the options we
have for response the things we get to select from start to have this little touch
this little touch of meta the mind inclines to benefit others
in this kind of way meta is known as an abiding
and abode a place where we can live a place we can live inside when we're
concentrated on the on the well-being of others in a place a place we can live
in this world of matter when we offer it said to soften and to moisten the heart
so in in very brief meta nourishes the heart it brightens and steadies the mind
and as such it supports the development of equanimity because when we're so fed we're so fed
by goodness that were less susceptible to the vicissitudes the ups and downs the
pleasures and pains the Praises and blames
if meta softens our heart to the world I'll say Equanimity stays intimate
without losing balance so a few words on equanimity
sometimes called equipoise it's this attitude of impartiality towards what's desirable and undesirable
again both people or other beings and our thoughts
I think it's the last of the Pyrenees for a good good reason sometimes it's called The Crown Jewel of
the emotions in Buddhist practice it was certainly Mastered by the Buddha who was so full of heart
um but it's infused with everything that we've practiced before
in my own thinking uh I I sometimes consider one who is
equanimous as someone who is self-possessed that um rather than being pulled and
pushed around by either circumstances on the outside or the impulses toward greed
and hatred and delusion on the inside instead of being pulled and pushed
around by those conditions were self-possessed we have this abiding
of loving kindness and Equanimity and balance
and an important note is this often comes up Equanimity does not mean heartlessness
it doesn't mean um cutting oneself off from connection with
the world right there can there can be this um understanding of equanimity
where we think we think it's like I'm I'm impartial to the world because I don't care
and I don't I don't experience it that way
um rather it's it's a sort of it's a sort of Freedom amidst
conditions that arises from Clear seeing one of the alternate words for
Equanimity in poly translates to standing in the middle of all this
peace in the midst of all this
and again I think I think Equanimity is last on the list um
in part in part maybe because we've already established
this number of Wholesome ways of being connected with beings and with thoughts
and with this world we've generated the connection of virtue and generosity and renunciation and
wisdom we're closer to other beings through our energy and patience our truthfulness and
resolve and then the intimacy of meta all of this goes into our Equanimity
it's not becoming a zero so
um this is also expressed in the fact that that the the condition that we cultivate
to to support the growth of equanimity it's not ignoring its wisdom
it's clear seeing
so in very brief meta and upeka
I'd like to say as we as we close maybe we have the sense that these uh
this part of me practice is a lot to remember the 10 qualities a lot of do's and don'ts I hope I took some good notes
um but really it can be quite simple
it can be three three things
this wish for the benefit the welfare and the liberation of ourselves and others
just a wish along with our Compassion or care for
others and then our commitment to skillfulness
skillful means in this situation right now what's the most skillful response
so our our aspiration our care and our skillfulness
just that simple all of the parmes
such beautiful qualities um
yeah I think maybe
we take up the practice of the parmies it could be it could be that all of our work is not evident to other people no
one no one we know out there is walking around with a checklist like oh yes their generosity and their patience and
their energy um maybe all that other people will register is oh that person is kind
that person cares maybe they'll maybe they will just feel our meta
like jivakan and maybe that's enough
so the Perfections a path from right where we are
to right where we are with full freedom hmm
wondrous so for the welfare and the benefit of all beings may we endeavor
patiently persistently generously wholeheartedly
and with a heart full of love and a mind of clear wisdom
maybe so
so I'd love to transition to some questions or comments you have we have a we have just a few minutes and I'm I
have a few minutes to stay after but during this little bit of YouTube lag I'll make these announcements
um first on Sunday May 21st it'll be something
the mindful parents class for parents and children of children of all ages
parents of children with children of all ages it's at IMC in Redwood City from 11 to 12 15 and it's a new program
and then the second thing Sunday potluck at IMC uh first one since before the
pandemic that's pretty amazing May 28th at 11 A.M after Gill's Diamond talk
so please if you're available and interested Avail yourselves
so let's see oh a question
uh how to the quantum Economist with duka arising
thank you very much that's right when Equanimity matters
doesn't it how to be equanimous with duka Rising
two doorways occur to me one is to trust awareness
our simple mindfulness practice one of the manifestations of equanimity can be just that when the duka arises we
don't grab on we don't grab on and um get pulled along
and then the other other manifestation is wisdom
and that is also through our mindfulness through our mindfulness practice to clearly
clearly know the duka itself it's a rising its conditions its effect
on us in terms of body attitude
um and then pay careful attention to when the duka let's go
it won't last forever so keeping an eye on this process that's
one doorway that's a wisdom doorway thank you for the question
we'll see if anything else comes up
oh this is great looks like ISC is celebrating Asian American Pacific Islander Buddhist
practice Sunday May 28th wonderful wonderful
some appreciations coming through uh I hope this time has been nourishing
may it be of benefit
and maybe for now we are complete
well Derma friends thank you for this week of practice
I hope to do do this again with you sometime soon um please take very good care of yourselves
thank you