good evening welcome welcome
yeah oh thank you good evening
so tonight I'd like to share with you a little bit um although I like to start off a little
bit from a suta the Maha goslinger and uh it's very uh I don't know I think
it's kind of interesting and a little bit fun that the Buddha he's staying in this
maybe I should say most suitors Begin by saying like where is the Buddha they give like a location I shouldn't say
most certain genre of suit does too and he's staying in the gosinga which is
a Saul Forest Park with salt trees and my understanding is soul trees are
these really Majestic giant beautiful trees maybe like how we might think of
redwood trees you know they have the certain Majesty when you're in when you're amongst them
and so the Buddha is staying there and there's a number of his uh senior monastics who are also staying there and
they're during the day they go off and meditate which is you know not so uncommon so they go off to their own
different places in this Saul forest or these salt Woods
and then um at the end of the day or kind of like late afternoon early evening one of his
monastics mahamagalana he goes to somebody else mahakasapa
and says this is Diana's rendition hey let's go hear sorry puta give a talk so they're
going to go to one of their friends another one of those senior monastics to go give a Derma talk
so are going to here so I pretty give a tug and then
Ruda and says oh okay invites him too so now there's three people that are going
to see sorry put to give a talk and then Ananda sees these three in the distance
it says oh what are you guys doing oh I want to go and he fights revita so now there's all
these people for me this is kind of fun I like this idea that you know they're practicing they're in silence all during
the day but at the end of the day they're connecting and they're friends they want to spend time together and
they want to go hear a Derma talk from sorry puta who is probably the most
senior monastic at the time of the Buddha so all five of them go to see sorry puta
and sorry puta sees them approaching and welcomes them and he says
by this time actually by the time I get there it's now early evening or nighttime
or maybe it's dusk something like this says inside purchases the soul Forest is
lovely and the night is bright this word we could also even say day but
he's just commenting on how it's just lovely here and how the light is and he says the salt trees are in full
blossom so these magnificent trees with lots of flowers it says and there's
these Divine scent that seems to float on the air so it's this really magical
lovely place and sorry puta asks Ananda
Ananda what kind of practitioner could illuminate or beautify this park this
place where we're practicing even more so is there somebody or that by by the
way that they talk or the way that they show up that could just make this even better
and Ananda says and remember Ananda is the Buddha's attendant and he's the one
who the tradition holds was there when the Buddha gave all these talks and
remembered them and so after the Buddha died it was Ananda who taught all these discourses
to everybody else and this is how they got preserved Through the Ages before so
Ananda is known for his memory and known for knowing all the Buddha's talks being
familiar with them so sorry puta asks Ananda what kind of practitioner would make this or maybe we
might even say what kind of practice would make this even more beautiful
and Ananda says a person who has learned much who
remembers what he has learned and consolidates what he has learned and then gives teachings that are beautiful
in the beginning beautiful in the middle and beautiful in the end that is
somebody who would make it more beautiful so you know it's probably not a coincidence that Ananda who's known for
having learned everything and remembered it saying oh yeah somebody who has learned it and remembered it that's that
would be the best and then sorry puta says well Ananda has responded according to his
own ideal right recognizing that this is something maybe unique to Ananda
but then sorry puta says well what about you revita what kind of practitioner
could beautify or illuminate this park even more where we're practicing and
revita was this preeminent meditator he was he was known as somebody that would like to go off on a retreat and he would
just go off and practice on his own and he'd like to just spend time in meditation
so revita he says well a person who Delights in Retreat and takes Delight in
Retreat and who is devoted to internal Serenity of mind and does not neglect meditation a person
who possesses insight and dwells in empty huts dwell in an empty Hut some of
you may know the Buddha is often given instructions like oh go into an empty huts and meditate or go to a footed tree
and meditate so not surprisingly Sarah puta says well
Ravena has responded according to his own ideal what about you Anna Ruda who do you
think would be the most beautiful and Anna Ruda says well a person who
surveys the entire galaxy with a Clairvoyance that is purified and surpasses the human so you know Anna
Ruda is something that's saying something fantastic and
then sorry puto replies well according to his own ideal and then he goes and he asks
and he goes asked sorry puta and so all of them are giving these ideas about
what they are known for so there's six different people they
give six different ideas I think they may be all delighting in this and then they go well let's go talk
to the Buddha let's see what he has to say
so they go to the Buddha and sorry puta recounts everything that happens
and then the Buddha replies good good after Ananda answered in the way that's
right for him revita uncertain the way that's right for him aniruda answered in the way that's right
for him right he says this for each person and then sorry put to us well venerable
sir who has spoken well like he kind of maybe wants to know
and the Buddha replies you have all spoken well
there's a little bit more to this but for me I would love this actually right the Buddha isn't saying no this one's
best or that's you know the worst or anything like this he's saying you've all spoken well
these are all the seniors these are all the Buddha's senior disciples and they all have different expertise or they all
have different Specialties or you know proclivities or things that ways in which they practice
six different people six different ways in the Buddha and you've all spoken well
which I feel touched by because it's not like there's only one way and it has to look a particular way
the Buddha is recognizing that different people bring different things to practice and the practice matures in
them differently and shows up in them differently whether it's exactly the same way is gets described here
is not the point I'd like to say is more that it doesn't have to look one particular way
so I put to us the Buddha who has spoken well and he says you have all spoken
well each in his own way but let me also as to what kind of person would beautify
this Saul Forest echosinka so now the Buddha is going to give his answer
is a person who returns from alms round and after the mill sits down
cross-legged sets their body straight and establishes mindfulness
practices mindfulness and then and resolves I shall not break
this city in position until through not clinging my mind is liberated from the taints
so those of you who know the story of the Buddha this is Verbatim what the Buddha says himself before he becomes
awakened this resolve this determination to after so many years of practice that
he's going to sit and tell and not move until he's awakened
so for me here's a seventh person who has a seventh way to show up but I
appreciate that the Buddha he's not talking about these great fantastic Having learned lots of things having
clairvoyances concealed galaxies or going off and meditating a lot he's just
talking about bringing mindfulness sitting down and bringing mindfulness with some resolve
this is something all of us can do this is something that you know the
Buddha is holding up it's just something ordinary is this this mindfulness practice yes
when the Buddha did it he had this resolve that he wasn't going to move until he became awakened but
I would like to think just this idea of resolve so I would like to say that each of us
have our own way of maybe like Illuminating or beautifying this kind of like a practice area with our own
practice this way of kind of embodying this path
of practice but resolve is something that we can
bring to whatever flavor or way in which we practice
so mindfulness as it matures may show up in all kinds of different ways
but with some resolve allows this mindfulness to Blossom and to unfold and
to bloom in a way in which can bring greater and greater freedom and peace
so what what does this mean to be have resolved with practice
so number of ways we can think about it but some of it is like just certain amount of tenacity or
determination or stick-to-itiveness or maybe overcoming resistance to
meditation all of us everybody has said I don't
feel like meditating I don't want to oh I'm not going to go
to the dharmatology oh I'm not going to sit yeah okay I see my cushion there and I usually meditate it this time but I
don't feel like it I mean all of us do this
it's part of the human's experience but maybe this resolve is maybe just like
putting aside alternatives instead of sleeping in or whatever it
may be or maybe it resolve means having enough trust or faith or confidence in
ourselves or in the practice that even though we might not feel like it that we still are willing to meditate practice
mindfulness and here's something that I think is really important
it's about this resolve I I wish I had a better uh word that I could translate
the poly word aritana with because sometimes when we hear about resolve we feel it can be like this
really like straining and striving and pushing
and it turns out that works for a little bit and then it doesn't
can take I don't think it'll ever work just to hear somebody say that I think we all have to have that experience
but there's a way in which there can be some real striving and straining and
this driving and straining itself is what is getting in the way of
practice because there's a way in which which
often fueling this training or this driving of this I gotta get it which of
course this works in our professional life it works in our educational life but it doesn't work in our meditation
life because what's fueling that is there's a big sense of
I have to make something happen
and as I said it works for a little bit and we need a little something amount of
that but so much about practice is having this trust that you don't have to
make everything happen at that moment and then negotiating or navigating like
and figuring out well what does that mean exactly because to be sure it certainly takes effort to get to the
cushion it takes resolve determination to keep on meditating even though you
don't feel like it or even to begin but there's a way in which it can kind
of like collapse and just turn into a
um there's a word that where you're just gonna I forget what the word is exactly but
you're just like you're slogging through snow and you're like going to just uh
bearing it out so resolve is letting go of the idea that
personal growth can just come quickly with minimal effort but also recognizing
that it needs some amount of effort and this is part of what the
art of practices is getting the sense of well what is the right amount of effort
and so resolve is also about recognizing that you know it's not always fun or
easy and that to recognize that difficulties are part of the path
that it's not necessarily always Pleasant or comfortable
and then when those times when we do give up just to begin again
as best we can like if even if we haven't meditated for a long time or we haven't done any of
these practices that we like to do and we just kind of gosh it's been
months just to begin again it doesn't have to be complicated we
don't have to add all these stories about what it means about us as a person or as a
meditator we just simply Begin Again and to be sure for some people this idea
of perseverance or resolve is a quality that they already have an abundance of
that they are those type of people they make a plan they do it and they just don't stop until it's done
maybe for those people working with resolve aditana
is a way that maybe the the edge of their practice is how to
have this resolve without getting too tight or too constricted or how to do it
that how to continue practice without it turning into drudgery is there a way
that there can be some lightness to it I know sometimes for me I sometimes can
fall into drudgery like oh my gosh I have to do this and I sometimes just uh
like will do it even though it's uh I could like make it more light or not
quite so heavy but I'm like oh my gosh I have to do this it doesn't have to be that way right but sometimes we
can slip into this sense of this drudgery or maybe for some people that's
not so hard to continue their practice or to stay with it but there can be a way maybe in which they disconnect from
people or Brusque with people like go away I'm meditating or no I can't do that I have to meditate or something
like this that their relationships get affected because they're going to
finish this project whatever it is so for some people resolve or aritana is
not so much about keep on coming back but it's about to have this
stick-to-itiveness with some spaciousness and some openness and some
ease and this is so much about the art of practice is having this ease and
openness and stick-to-itiveness we so often kind of want to collapse
around the things that we're doing or need to do but is there a way that we
can do it with some Joy or some happiness
so I would say this what are these things that we resolve on
I've been giving the examples of meditation practice but you know as part
of Buddhist practice we have this resolve to not harm not harm others not harm ourselves
this to be mindful of what's happening if whether it's on the formally on the cushion or whatever is happening in our
life and maybe this resolved to let go was
best we can this recognition that clinging is and holding on really tightly is
lever The Way Forward never the best way forward but it's more kind of like opening
letting go is the way forward
so what are some of the things that get in the way of resolve well it turns out
that that hindrances to meditation are also the same hindrances to resolve as same
hindrances to so many things in our life [Applause] so this idea that um
these five energies these five occupations of the mind that show up
in our formal meditation practice are also what's getting in the way so Central desire
ill will sloth and torpor restlessness and doubt
these are five obstacles to practice or five obstacles
to doing anything that we really want to do and so they can distract us from our
intentions our aspirations and they actually have a pretty powerful in our
life if we're not aware of them they can push us around in such an incredible way
and I I'd like to talk about one of them in particular and that is doubt
because this we might have this um might be way this might happen there's
so many different ways that doubt shows up but maybe there's uh we're meditating and everything's going along swimmingly
and then it becomes uncomfortable either because we have some emotions
memories or something or thoughts oh my gosh I forgot to do that thing and
and now this terrible thing is gonna happen and I gotta jump up and send that email or do this or do that
or maybe it's just pain in the knee or in the back or whatever it might be
so maybe the meditation's going along well then maybe there's a flash of uncomfortableness
with this flash of uncomfortableness maybe there's this inner critic that arises like
do this everybody else seems to be able to do it but I can't do it or maybe there's something about uh
I shouldn't have even started why who do I think that I am or I don't know there's so many ways that we can
undermine our capability start to doubt ourselves
or maybe we even start thinking why am I doing this meditation thing anyway I'm not even sure that it helps or it used
to help but it doesn't seem to be helping now or you know there's so many ways in which
the thinking we can cook up and dream up all these ways that practice seems to
not be helpful or we think this maybe isn't worthwhile anything except all the
opposite except resolve you might notice that you don't have
these types of thoughts when meditation is going well when we're feeling settled
when we feel like we have a certain amount of ease so it's only when there's a certain when
it's uncomfortable or there's a certain
feeling like well maybe I'd rather do something else and who knows maybe it's
because we want to avoid something or maybe it is the discomfort
but a consequence something that happens when this type of thinking starts like well maybe
I shouldn't do this I should be doing something else and I'm not even sure this is helpful anyway
as soon as we get lost or caught up in that type of thinking then we're no
longer actually with our experience said we're lost in our thoughts
and I love what Carolina Buddha was saying you know this person who sits
down in his mindfulness he was kind of like holding this up as a ideal practice
so not so much that we have to do it perfectly
but as soon as we're lost in thoughts then you know thoughts can go anywhere
and everywhere and they do so is there a way that we can just
bring awareness back to oh this is a lot of we could even use this
word doubt this is doubt about myself this is doubt about the practice or
doubt about the teachings or doubt about the teacher
so this sense of hesitation or vacillation or might getting lost in
papancha this like proliferation of thoughts and one way to think about conflict
doubt is that when I when I think about the experience right
this is a hindrance that shows up for everybody there's a certain amount of swirling like oh I'm not sure I'll do
this maybe I'll do that sort of has that kind of a little bit of an energetic feel
and so when we recognize either these thoughts I'm not sure I should do this or I want to do this or there's that
feeling this vacillation this hesitation we can just tune into that that
experience and maybe name it oh this is doubt
because doubt rarely shows up and announces itself oh this is doubt instead it's
trying to you know say like be wisdom you oh it'd be better if you should do self-care take care of
yourself and go do something else just sleep in or take a nap instead and to be
sure sometimes you should sleep in and take a nap but you know sometimes you know just
meditation practice is what's needed
so we could one way to practice with doubt is just to recognize it and name it it's really helpful
to bring it back to the body it's a really good way to feel like this sense of uncertainty I don't really know what
to do it can be helpful to like maybe like feel the foundation like what you're
sitting on feel the connectedness the settledness oh I'm here right now
when I'm doing this I'm doing this meditation practice so to get out of this abstract thinking
and the philosophizing sometimes we can just get lost and
abstract thinking of course we can there might be this restlessness or this
heaviness or the sense of unease so to tune into the bodily experience
mindfulness First Foundation of mindfulness you can also remind yourself that
thoughts are just thoughts they're just thoughts thoughts feel like
right they're ephemeral they a whole other set of thoughts are
going to show up in another moment so you don't have to like grab these thoughts and hold them to be authoritative and have them be the like
this is the truth of the moment they're just thoughts this could say is mindfulness too is the
third Foundation mindfulness of the Mind and so somewhere to kind of like
undermine this idea that oh this is not a good thing to do or I'm not
even sure what I should do and then investigate get a little bit
curious as if you were a naturalist I like this
idea of being a naturalist so okay so I'm having all this doubt
and it feels like this and you might do a gentle inquiry was there something
that planted the seed for it it could be a particular question
could be a particular uncomfortable experience and with this uncomfortable experience then their inner critic shows
up and like you know likes to take over and maybe like undermine what you're doing
think like ah it's not gonna work so you can investigate
and then you something that might be helpful is like to if you
just have it inquiry is there a particular question that I have
is there something that I really do have doubt about
the teachings particular things that you're not so sure about
or maybe you're not so sure about the teacher or maybe you're not so sure about yourself but it can be helpful to
get a little bit more specific is there a specific question sometimes it could be helpful even to write this
down and that can really help clarify instead of this vacillation then once you have a
question you can maybe go find an answer listen to Dharma books talk to other
people talk to teachers do more practice either so Google it right these days
right there's a way in which you can like do something to maybe answer your
question or maybe you can just recognize okay it feels like this to have a question
that's different than doubt that type of a question that's welcome like that's
definitely part of the practice to have a question and maybe not know the answer
that's really part of the practice there's so much that we don't have the answers to and I'm going like this with
my hands because not knowing is a way that we're letting go of
knowing exactly what the next moment is going to bring always having the answer is a way in
which we're kind of like suddenly trying to control things and so that we feel more comfortable
but not knowing is uncomfortable but there's a way in which also not knowing
has that's where that freedom is if we always knew what's going to happen
next there's no Freedom there it's so it this having the question is a
big part of the way forward so when there's a doubt can you identify specific question and
maybe find the answer but maybe there isn't an answer and can you be okay with that practice with that
and that turns again away kind of the away from this vesselation and hesitation to oh yeah I have this
question and and not knowing that answer feels like this
that's mindfulness again and then maybe one less way to work with
doubt that I'll mention there's a number of ways but for tonight I'll end on this one to bring to mind well what do you have
confidence in what do you know about the practice or
about yourself sometimes it can be helpful to reflect like oh yeah before I had a meditation
practice I didn't realize how busy my mind was I didn't realize for example
what a planner I was or since I've been mindful I've not only
have I gained this greater understanding but I have a little bit more patience with other people because I see how
they're trying to just figure things out in the same way that I'm trying to figure things out or
maybe there's this way that we can bring to mind you know there have been times that my practice
have been really uplifting and meaningful or maybe transformative
and it wasn't always that way has been moments like that but maybe it
will be that way again so instead of like abandoning things when things get
difficult just remember that there have been times there have been some real fruits of
practice and then also to remind ourselves that when we sit down
chance to meditate chances are at the beginning however it is that feels the
meditation is is not how it is at the end right there's if the meditation shifts
and changes through the meditation period sometimes at the end it's worse and sometimes it's better but it's never
exactly the way that it is at the beginning so sometimes we might feel like oh this would be terrible there's
no way I can sit here for all this time but just this memory just that you know
there have been times when the mind has really settled and opened and there's been some ease
so the Buddha talked about you know so many different ways of practice I mean it
shows up in many different ways emphasize mindfulness and resolve
and then we can ask ourselves what is it that gets in the way of resolve and very
often it's doubt not exclusively but very often it's doubt and so we can
practice with doubt by being mindful of it by investigating it getting a little bit
curious about it and maybe tuning into or see if we can simplify it
into a particular question or we can also bring to mind what we have confidence in or what some of our
experience has been with meditation that has been uplifting
so with that this is kind of like I like this I started with the gosinga
mahakosuta in which you know there's these people that come together and they practice
together and they appreciate each other and they also recognize that you know the practice doesn't look exactly the
same for everybody and sometimes something that can undermine our practice is the doubt that
takes the form of oh they look like they have it and I don't or clearly they're
doing something better than I am or something like that but just this recognition that practice looks
different for different people I think I'll end there so thank you
and I'll open it up if there are any questions or comments
hi I think when you're talking about the the doubt or the five hindrances it kind
of reminded me of how a lot of times we sort of separate ourselves or we we have a trouble finding common ground and I
was thinking we all have a lot of you know um share a lot of our own sort of doubt and and share that in common with
everyone else but I think we uh spend more time the things that probably separate us
instead of unite us but it was interesting to think about sharing some negative qualities
yeah it's true right it's uh surprising well I've talked about this number of
times how much I love like you know the Buddha talked about these thousands of years ago so there's countless people
that have been having doubts about practice you know through all these years and I think it's something that's
kind of it is definitely part of practice absolutely and not only about practice but
everything in our life right yeah thank you
the common humanity is what it means to be a human is to part of a staffed out
thank you anybody else have a comment or a
question
well I'll make a comment just the last couple weeks I watched a
documentary called the endurance about Sir Ernest Shackleton
and how dedicated he was once his ship once it
was clear that he wasn't going to be able to get to Antarctica to save all of his men and you know there was just a sense of
never giving up never exactly knowing what
was the right thing to do whether they were going to be able to get the land or to certain Islands
um but it was a very inspiring documentary
about that sense of um
just keeping investigating what you know what's what
are the possibilities now I mean as the ship got carried by the ice you know
what was going to be closest than what could they save and what couldn't they
So yeah thank you thank you Jim because that brings to mind something else that could help with doubt is if there's
something for us that's particularly inspiring or motivating like you're a type of North Star that's really
important to us just like Shackleton wanting to save all those men is there something maybe it's not the same as
saving our other people but maybe there's something that really you know drives us or motivates us or inspires us
so actually thank you thank you Jim
thank you
this is the half-page thought so maybe it'll finish as it comes out so I read that suit a couple years ago and I
really liked it and it seemed to me that Maybe
this was written down long after the Buddha because um all these characters in it
have got superpowers that are larger than life and it's almost like the X-Men or the
Legion of Superheroes um and they're very well defined as if they've got they're all wearing their
their different colored costumes um
is this game better and better and also it just seems
unlikely that they would all be in the same place at the same time and the Buddha would be there near there
too um and I'd also remember
really loving about the story that I thought sure they were going to come to blows
because they also vigorously disagreed and you know the the guys with the elephant came to blows yes yes uh but
they were blind yes and these were all arahants yes and
this is a healthy way to have differences of opinion um and then I was really sure that the
Buddha was going to sculpt them and say why are you worried about which of you was even more right than the other one
that's not a wise thing to have your minds on so no you all you all spoke well and here's
what I have to say um think there was something really really gentle
about that so my thoughts on that thank you thank you
yeah I was in my mind I had kind of this idea that uh
sorry puto who's the one who's doing this speaking he just wants to hear from everybody and it doesn't matter so much what they
have to say or something like that uh I don't know and then going to see the
Buddha yeah it is curious like why did they go see the Buddha was it to resolve something or just to share like hey look
look what we did we just sat around and talked about this or something I don't know it's it's kind of there's I guess
there's a number of ways we can read between the lines but I think only uh one of them has these superpowers I
think it's only superpowers
yeah is wearing the costume if one of these I don't really know the
X-Men but I know the the premise so but I was thinking of you know the finger
quotes superpower yeah of asking the right question or being able to sit for
long long times that maybe not superpowers but characteristics yeah they're very finely
distinguished yeah yeah you know I uh there's some other hints in here too
about um why actually it might be a leader suta just to have but you know I don't
know but I I pulled this together because I thought that I don't know it's kind of nice like how there's practice shows up
in different ways we don't all have to look the same
okay okay thank you all