Good Morning Song good morning warm greetings from Redwood City
California nice to be with you all great to see all of the greetings
rolling in from all over Scotland and Santa Cruz Petaluma Moss
Beach Sacramento so many different areas up above in the
chat that I didn't see as well so welcome all of you
happy to be here with you and
as a reminder our topic this week is um
factors of mine that support wisdom stability unification
and they support it in both meditation and
in daily life so to um just take in your Global Sangha
as you're sitting in here settling in here and
I don't know any feelings of warmth happiness connection [Music]
to really soak in to savor them
maybe smile at your Santa mates even though they can't see you
feel how that feels in your body and your heart
and as you're ready please settle back
find your meditation posture and go inward
starting out just by feeling into whatever Sensations emotions are present
[Music] maybe allowing any excess energy or tension
to be softened released on the Opera
feeling into the goodness of the the breath itself the body itself
and the feeling of being connected
to others and to your own breath your own body your own inner life
feeling welcomed to be here in this moment
right now
noticing the entirety of this body from the tips of your toes to
the top of your head
noticing the vibrancy the aliveness
be tingling or pulsing movement
Stillness wait notes
noticing the movements of the chest ribs belly
and tuning into your body breathing
I'll offer instructions on breathing this morning but feel free to use other objects of
attention if they work better for you overall sensations of the body sound
meta many of those are fine
tuning into the motion with the ribs and the belly Sensations
of the life's graph connecting us to the outside world
noticing all the sensations on the in-breath
that's the ribs expand the lungs expand
noticing how it feels at the top of the in-breath
fullness perhaps slightly Pleasant or neutral
then on the out breath producing all of the details
the little micro Sensations within each Opera
turning into every every detail of when the out breath ends
perhaps there's a tiny ponds to Still Point the end of the Opera
allowing the breathing to be natural
and attending connecting
with the breathing in the foreground
acknowledging everything else
I'm smiling at any thoughts or distractions that come up
and returning connecting and sustaining your attention
in the gentle waves riding the waves of the breath
laughs
removing the gentle motion the breathing
to massage the muscles in your core from the inside
out softening relaxing
perhaps noticing the feelings sensations of the breathing
in the throat back of the mouth nose
yeah all the way down through to the Heart Center chest now you're feeling umbrella
following the whole body of the breath
Rising falling belly
sensations of in breathing Sensations about breathing
noticing
acknowledging any feelings of ease
right feelings of pleasure or comfort interest
in this close contact with embodied experience
and if there are any feelings of contentment and ease
pleasure happiness
allowing them to be there
giving them space to grow if they want to subside if they do
and graciously being with all of experience
of each and Raven Opera no wrong experience
from time to time reconnecting
and connecting with the texture of this moment
all of the little details especially the details of the breath
perhaps a sense of relief from relief at the end of the Opera
the goodness of nourishment from the inbra
reconnecting
staying close staying close to the experience
thank you
remember any sense of relaxation and
contentment enjoyment
is the fears to grow through the body
inviting compassion kindness kindness of being with everything else
while inviting it to fade to the background
foreign
there were seen the effects of each breath in the body
the expansion of the whole torso perhaps are Rippling through
energetic resonance through the rest of the body transpiring
massaging breath through all of the body
massaging allowing good feelings
to Ripple through [Music] and say well
interesting resting and contentment in the moment
in the final moment of this meditation
the invitation is to gather up
and he got intentions little glimmers of contentment or ease
calm or joy and Savor them in this body in this
heart
if it was difficult savoring the compassion
the willingness to be with
and then turning your internal gaze outwards towards your life
all of the others you may come in contact with directly or
indirectly [Music]
and offering new sense of goodness kindness
compassion care for them
making the determination that this practice be a benefit
to yourself and to all those Your Life Touch
Ed me all beings everywhere be happy safe
peaceful and free
[Laughter]
thank you [Music]
thank you for your practice
foreign
good morning Sangha welcome to those of you who tiptoed into the YouTube stream
a little bit late and everyone else
so today is day three of the five day series on factors of mine
that support stability wisdom
deepening in meditation practice and in daily life
we started with fundamentals on Monday of mindfulness and practice intelligence
and yesterday I introduced the first two of biogenic factors factors for
stability and samadi concentration and those two were connecting with the
meditation object and sustaining that connection also known as vitaka and vichara
so when connecting and sustaining vitaka and vichara begin to build
the rhythm of continuity than often good feelings will naturally
result from them the poly terms for these pleasurable experiences are PT the ITI and sukha
s-u-k-h-a and they are roughly translate as
meditative happiness and contentment for sukha and meditative
joy for PT AR
the third and fourth of the five Janik factors excuse me
sometimes in contemporary culture people have been raised to feel like it's not okay
to feel to really enjoy joy and happiness
so if this happens to be you please consider this talk
enthusiastic permission to savor these forms of meditative
goodness Savor them enjoy them
it's important to savor and enjoy them when they arise because that encourages
them to arise more often the Buddha talked about these forms of goodness being healthy onward leading
and to be cultivated not to be feared it's also helpful to note that cultivate
your means cultivating the underlying conditions
for joy and happiness to arise we can kind of have a little control
over reconnecting with our experience the meditation object and we can kind of
have a little bit of control over sustaining that connection over time these feelings emerge naturally from
that they don't come on demand and you can't just make them appear necessarily
so Savor but not demand
so the polybird PT has a broad word cloud of translations or meanings I'll
read some of them here please tap into your body
and feel how they feel as you hear them
Joy satisfaction of mind
positive interest
rat interest Delight zest
deal exuberance
Mirth merryman
exultation thrilled
and rapture so you'll notice there's a broad range
and one is not necessarily better or deeper than another
itchy has this large cloud of meanings because of this wide range of ways that
can be experienced it's energetic embodied and it can
manifest as anything from a sense of positive interest to a little pulse of
momentary Delight uplifting Joy all the way through to
wrapped interest in the kind of bubbly Joy or tingles rain like feeling
many practitioners find that as their practice deepens these
feelings actually become more subtle not stronger but they can be quite strong
and some people never experience them at all other than the mild interest or the pulse of joy every now
it's all good stronger is not necessarily better
at its simplest level this meditative Joy is the joy of being
present closely in contact with the moment in a way that helps an energetic
resonance to our eyes and that's available to all of us
like Suka Piti is an embodied mental quality so to explain both of them a
little I'm going to draw on one of yesterday's similes so if connecting is placing your hand on
a friendly furry cat and sustaining is stroking the fur
stroking the cat then PT is the purring that results
results from this natural pleasure of connection and sustaining
it can also arise from another kind of Joy called pamoja in the poly p-a-m-o-j-j-a
and that kind of Joy it's a condition for PT but it also arises itself
when the heart and mind have let go of hindering mental qualities unskeletal qualities
and PT and pamoja can also emerge with the joy of generosity
the joy of Letting Go in a wholesome or skillful way
so there are more than one pathway in to meditative joy and there's more
than one progression that can go on and this series this week is one of those progressions
Gill has talked about another one which is um a gladness pentat I think he calls
it so you'll notice that this is an important um quality in Buddhism because of that
wrapped interest that Zeal enthusiasm it appears in several lists
so that Joy of generosity that can give rise to PT reminds me of a story this is
a from a scientific study wonderful researcher who I'm completely blanking on the name of right now
invited research participants the giveaway cupcakes to total strangers
they were provided the cupcakes as part of the study and what they found was that the giver
received this pulse of Joy from the giving especially when the giving was done with
kindness warmth not only that that
Giver underestimated underestimated how good it would feel to
give right so
there's this giving over to the practice either generosity with others or
giving over to the practice and kind of letting go that opens the door to joy and happiness
Suka a happiness or contentment piece is subtler and it also has a word problem
meanings you can feel into need
agreeable pleasure
ease well-being
the feeling of being blessed
contentment being pleased
and blessed
so CA is present along with PT the more
energetic resonance purring of joy and
it's softer it's subtler so it's kind of invisible sometimes when
PT is present because it's overshadowed by the more Broad and energy
of pity pity Suka is more like a calm happiness a
pervasive pleasure it can be a little like that happy contented glow after a good laugh
a really good laugh and like PT Suka can emerge in other
ways one of the most powerful is from what the Buddha calls the Bliss of blamelessness ethical conduct
recognizing that we haven't done anything to harm others
so to finish the cupcake story it turns out that people receiving the cupcakes
they valued the warmth and friendliness of the person giving them more than they valued the cupcake itself
and not only that the sense of happiness that calm our happiness pervaded the day
of these people from long after the receiving happened
and made them more likely to give to others through that day pay it forward so to speak
that lingering happiness that's the sukkah
the pulse of joy and the giving that's more like
an ancient commentary of the Buddhist teachings called the atasalina
pose a story of a person finding an oasis or Forest after crossing a desert
and then pot you know frustrated exhausted that pulse
of Joy at stepping into the shade and finding a beautiful Cool Spring to take
a bath in that the atasalini describes spt an
analogy for PT then sukha is the ease and contentment
of resting after emerging from that Cool Spring on a hot day
so perhaps one of the greatest teachings takeaways from tasting or learning about this kind
of meditative joy happiness is that we have the capacity to
experience joy and happiness with very very little from the outside world
almost nothing that's required not buying anything not Beauty possessions or fame
but rather attending with kindness and devotion
to every unfolding experience Within that's a gift
and that's how these experiences are most fruitfully regarded as as gifts
emergent quality pursuing them grasping them
scares them away because they can be really shy
so the Buddha said that these are Pleasures to be cultivated
and it's important not to attach too much
the grasp too much this is where the mindfulness and the practice intelligence come in
well it's not the same thing another way of cultivating these can be to open ourselves to simple Joys
Pleasures contentment out in the world it's a good way of teaching our systems
how to recognize the meditative Joy is within
so your homework your assignment if you would like to accept it is to notice today over the next 24 hours
moments of pleasure Joy contentment happiness
and really feel them Savor them
as they come to full fruition and meditation they support unification and that is our
topic for tomorrow thank you for your kind attention