good morning everyone and can you hear all right volume is good
hello everyone online who is watching welcome as well and um
so I want to bring up
a fascinating topic I for me at least
but a challenging topic for some of you
in fact some of you might come up afterwards to me it's a gill
you don't understand let me tell you how it really is
you're not taking something into account
so I do this talk with great risk
so the topic is the state of the world oh God
that was a perfect comment given
the state of the world and um
the elicit that just that phrase elicits a lot of responses to people
some people get have despair around the state of the world some people have a lot of anxiety about
the state of the world some people have
a lot of opinions about the state of the world the topic of state of the world for some
people elicits a lot of predictions a lot of imagination
where we don't see the difference between predictions and actuality
don't see the difference between predictions and what has to and will happen and even to say that is challenging
because of how strong the the views are about this is actually what's going to happen
and um and the this topic of the state of the world
isn't something I've been reflecting on the last few days because earlier this week someone presented this
topic in a very open way as a topic for reflection
when you think of the state of the world what arises for you and it was obvious when somebody some of
you gasped or something that something arises just the topic of it
but for me when this was brought up the context in which I this topic of
state of the world was brought up was kind of unique by that time I'd spent maybe five days
or so four days living Outdoors really Outdoors sleeping
on the ground with the Open sky above me kind of There Were Trees canopy a little bit over me I could see the stars though
and I'd spend much of the day sitting in this meditation posture on the ground
surrounded by a community of nine large trees
and being at this level the ground was really close it was kind of special and the way I was
sitting the ground was uneven so it had to kind of always take it into account
and there was a gentle slope on the ground it was kind of grassy ground dried California grass
gentle slope going uphill so when I looked out clearly the ground was right there
to look at and because I was sitting so low mostly what I was aware of with the trees
besides the shade they provided was their trunks
big trunks that were stable and strong and had been there for many years
and I've done this been there before the same kind of situation for a week
there are some wild and difficult things that happened in that Grove of trees but the truth the stability and the
strength of these trees is there and the solidity of the ground that we're sitting on was phenomenal
so in that context someone brought up for reflection the state of the world
and my first thought was which world is she talking about
there are so many worlds that we live in as the word but the word the interesting English word world
um just like the in the Buddhist language Pali uh they have the word loka
which doesn't it kind of mean like crazy in Spanish
well that's just a coincidence but the um but the um the word Loca has
the different reference points just like the English word world has it can some people just means the Earth
but it's not the physical Earth usually it's it's everything that's in this
earth not just the physical Earth is it is it the human world some people limited to the human world
is it the animal world we used to maybe use that expression the animal world and we'd be referring to a certain
subsection of this Earth that we live in is it the political world some people
when they hear the state of the world they think politics is like the state of American politics
and um people have been going ah this is how much people
ever since I was aware of American politics I think the really the first big thing
that I was aware of in my lifetime that I was a little bit aware of the Nixon Kennedy election
and as a little kid it was mostly prefer the person who had the nicer name
and that's all I knew but then a few years later it was a big
impact to be in school elementary school that is probably third grade or something
and had the teacher send tell us and then send us home because President Kennedy had been assassinated
so the state of politics and um
as elicited you know maybe forever as long as there's been
politics or as a world
the environmental world than what's happening that very difficult things happening the
destruction of the environment the climate is that what we refer to as the world what is the world we live in so I
was sitting there I think wondering about this and because maybe because I was sitting on the ground I thought well what's the
state of the world from the point of view of the mountains
they're kind of solid I mean they come and go to but uh but you know the mountains have
been there stable and strong for so long and the weather comes and goes the
seasons come and go the dinosaurs come and go
all kinds of things the mouth the point of the mountains what is that like the world what is the state of the world to the
point of view of the oceans I love oceans and I spend a lot of time on the surface or the edge of the surface of
waters and I Marvel at when I go to the Pacific coast here and then and watch
the waves come in and wash across the you know this temporary wave washes up
on the on the sand and then it washes out over and over and over again I say wow
it's been doing this for a long long time I'm seeing some a scene here that I
could have seen a hundred thousand years ago someplace on this planet or a million years ago or 100 million years
ago you could have seen this and the oceans you're not point of view
of the oceans have seen so much coming and going and ups and downs and in my hometown in Norway there's a mark
on the I don't know exactly where it is but there's a marker
that says that in the year 1200 the water level of the towns it sounds a
Bergen it's a bay and the water level from the ocean was
here far above where it is now and 100 you
know less than a thousand years ago it was really the ocean go up and down that much was it tied what was it it was kind
of Marvel that this where is the ocean and how does it change over these years centuries and Millennia and millions of
years and the state of you the ocean that comes and this there and sees so much change
what's the and um is it reasonable to ask these
questions from those perspectives the reasonable is that for me at least is that it kind of heightens highlights the
perspective I might use when I have this word state of the world and it kind of puts it contextualizes it
oh it's particular State a particular Viewpoint that I'm using is it the only viewpoint
is it the best Viewpoint view point of view to say this is the state of the world at any given moment
I Marvel at the redwood trees we have here in California there was some of some of these nine trees that surrounded
us but redwood trees and um apparently redwood trees are the
among among the very oldest species of Life on this planet of ours
you know things come and go right but apparently the species of redwood trees that we have here are 100 million years
old that's a species that's phenomenal 100 million years
humans haven't been around that long and and the
uh and what have the redwood trees seen in 100 million years of coming and going
and the here and there it's phenomenal that what's happened and
if you ever want to study tectonic movement of tectonic plates on this planet it's fascinating
I just took I I grew up thinking I took the Earth for granted this is how it is
seven continents and you know this is what but the continents have come and
gone gone over billions of years there's continents that have funny names
that no longer existed and didn't have names then
and um so it's you know and so the Redwood sees the trees have seen so much
it's phenomenal so what is the state of the world and more importantly perhaps what is our
relationship to the state of the world to the world and there are people who their
relationship to the state of the world is that they are victims and that's the primary orientation they
have some people the state of the relation to state of the world is they are
responsible for it and um and so it's like a big deal like
and I get a sense that some people feel personally responsible except to them too
solve the world someone last week talked about some of that might come from the myths
the West kind of the myths that somehow somehow have been spread into embedded in kind of many cultural views
or subcultural views of the hero's journey which is a very individual
Journey like you have to be the hero and it's up to you alone to do it and so I'm
responsible you know to do something
um is the perspective in which we relate to the state of the world are we
consumers of it just for me to consume to have more experiences to have more things to have
more Comfort to more you know just that's that's the orientation
is the perspective we have towards a state of the world to have power and dominion over it
to to be have authority and be in control and you know it's all mine and
I'm gonna you know and there are people individuals who have that kind of view maybe even
cultures have add that to you and maybe even World Views they've been passed down to their Generations that
you know we have some kind of it's us to have power and authority over this world
and um so are we consumers kind of the opposite of consumers could
be are we producers of this world what does it mean if we're the producer
of the world is that like a crazy concept producers of the world
are we stewards of the world are we participants of the world are are we are
we the state of the world to me there's all these very important questions to ask
from the point of view of the Buddha I'd like to suggest that he sought us as
the producers of the world in a funny way in a unique way
that there's a way that the world like the order there are a lot of origin
stories of the world where different cultures religions down through time all these wonderful interesting fascinating
creation stories of the world many of them would embed in them a lot of wisdom
and that's you know people are making of myths were you know ever since they could
make language or something and those myths are fascinating some of them are
really wise interesting but creation myths and Buddhism has one too but that's we
don't need that right now but the Buddha is more his point of view
it's more like the creation myth is that the world begins in each of us
it's born in each of us maybe Moment by moment now why is that important why would the
Buddha say this and of course it's kind of crazy right I mean certainly
this planet Once Upon a Time was just I don't know just molten lava that just
it wasn't even water on it and you know and so we have this growth
and development of this planet and so how could it just be born right now but remember the word world is this creative
world word it's kind of it's not you know it's not the Earth what is the world
so if it's a flexible word fluid world word then what does a Buddha mean when he
said that's where the pre he didn't literally use this word but implied that
we're the producers of the world so um
there was a man who came to the Buddha and um he said you know in this town
here there's people who are your followers but they would have a lot more faith in
you and your teachings if you would send some Monk into town
to perform miracles you know that impresses people some people like Miracles are what gets them
into some religions back so the more miracles you do the more followers you get so you know so
so the Buddha said no he wasn't going to do that the command among the language in Paulie's command
command among the go do miracles no so the man asked again
and the Buddha said no and there's something in India or ancient India at least that about if you
ask something three times it's pretty significant and you really have to take person
seriously now and sometimes you can't say no if someone asks three times or something like that
so the man asked the Buddha a third time and so the Buddha and either acquiesced
they didn't say yes you do that and he didn't refuse the third time instead he said there are three kinds of
Miracles there's the Miracles that arise from meditation practice the miraculous kind
of Wonders that the mind can see there's the miracle of
um of um what was it second
uh
I forget you know because those those things are
not important part of the story but he and then he goes on to say there's a miracle of instruction
Miracle of instruction imagine that the instructions a teacher might give that how's that a miracle
and then he goes on to explain the miracle of instruction it's the miracle of instructing people
um how to focus their thinking what to think about
the miracle of instructing people how to not just think
but to really have some deeper contemplation creative complic contemplation a generative kind of
thinking and then there's the miracle of uh of
teaching instructing people to what to let go of that's a nice thing right not not to let
go but what to let go of and then there's the miracle of uh
teaching people instructing people what states of mind to states of heart to enter into and
rest in there are certain states of being that are really useful and valuable to be and
and so meditation practice Buddhist practice is it points to this and and it's not just simply doing practices but
to do the practices that open the door to different interstates
how to be in this world and to and to enter those doors and to rest in those to abide in it this language
those are Miracles so isn't that great that's the miracle so so send a monk into town and perform Miracles well
that's send them into town to teach so anyway so he says Buddha says this response to this person and as he often
does when he when he kind of dismisses these kind of Miracles ideas
but then he accommodates the person by coming up with what I call a myth that he tells
and um and to somehow maybe kind of go along with a person with a person's
mindset how they see things what they want kind of go along with them and then turn the table on them
kind of you know so so he starts off by saying well once upon a time
long long ago there was a
I think it was a monk who wanted to know where Earth
fire wind and and um
earth oh earth water fire and wind where they end
where do they end and that's supposed to be that refers to the whole physical world that we live in where is that
physical world we experience where does it end and part of the reason they would ask this in Ancient India is that there was
people back in Ancient India who were deeply dismayed
upset scared aversive to how difficult
this world was this world is a difficult painful place to be and the only way out is to transcend it
is to somehow when you especially when you die to go to some good place
and to go to some place where this world ceases to exist that we live in so exactly what that place is is it a
place some people believed in a place kind of the Heavenly realm in Ancient India or
it's kind of not quite like our Heavenly realm in in the west often we have but you know there's this idea of
transcendence like you want to leave this world because it's just too difficult you know there's no hope here
so um so those people that probably you said I'm going to bring up talk about the state of the world probably yeah
that's going to be heavy talk difficult talk you know because we're going to talk terrible it is and the point is to
kind of get it get off this so that's one of the way learn the languages of transcending is to go to where the earth
water fire and wind cease so the monk goes to find someone who can
answer this this question where do you where does this cease and um
and uh he um he wants to find so find some some some
some great sage and says well you have to go ask some some of the Gods
and so he goes travels up to the God Realm and asks one God and now you have to go to a higher realm God
and no no you have to go that's the higher realm of God and he keeps going to the higher higher
around gods and he comes to the highest God in the Indian Pantheon at the time which was Brahma
and and goes to Brahma and says Brahma where does
earth water fire and air wind cease and Brahma says I am the great Brahma
the all-knowing the all-powerful the wise luminous Brahma
so the guy asks the question again and Brahma says the same thing you know
I'm the greatest well you remember it three times right so the guy asked Brahma again
and Brahma gets down from his throne because it takes him by the yellow come over with
me and he kind of goes over to talks privately and says you know
the other gods here think that I'm all knowing [Laughter]
you know and I can't really you know I you know but I don't really know the answer to your question
and I can't admit it so it's kind of Buddhist humor
and so they go um he um and somebody said there's a who
you should ask the Buddha so the guy goes back to the Earth
to the Buddha I guess there's maybe even his teacher and asked the Buddha where does this cease
and the Buddha said oh long ago in my previous lifetime I was a sage who looked for the end of the world the
spirit word sees I traveled every direction forever and ever in all directions and no matter how far I
traveled I could travel like as fast as an arrow for 100 100 years at a time and
and I never came to the end of the world and now you won't find a place
where the Earth where the world ceases
and um the Earth the world ceases
this world of ours in your own body this is the world where you find the
cessation of but you don't find the cessation of earth water fire and Air
it's the place where Earth Fire Water and Air no longer have a footing no
longer we no longer hold on to them where Earth the world that we live in no
longer has rooted itself in our Consciousness in our mind in our in
theirs there's not we're not caught in it still there but it doesn't stick to us
so that's a just a fascinating idea itself and it's a place where knowing
knowing is no longer visible
knowing has no limits no boundaries no edges
where knowing is luminous all around
or clear all around it's fascinating kind of idea knowing
so we're knowing cannot be seen
and uh and for the from the Buddhist point of view knowing they can't be seen is knowing
that is not attached to anything as soon as the knowing has an attachment then it kind of creates a kind of
resonance or contraction or tightness or something that others can kind of tell
sometimes you can see that when someone is concerned about something like state of the world
it's got them you know they they're knowing something in their mind and you can see now that their mind is caught by
something and um and so you know if someone is full of desire for something you see
them searching and wanting you can feel you can see that they're wanting something or they're angry or they're so
there's a way in which the state of our mind gets conveyed and you can kind of pick it up in some subtle way
and the more sensitive the viewer is the more sensitive we can pick up the subtlety of how people have gotten
caught by an idea or involved in an idea but when someone knows something and the
knowing has no attachment in it then there you there's no way of you don't
read the person's mind you don't read how they are there's a knowing which can't be seen
knowing it's free that's so this knowing that can't be seen
and knowing that it has no boundaries no limit there's a way the Buddha also felt that as soon as you're attached to something
or you're stuck in some idea of things you've created a limit to the world you live in now you define the world that
world is defined for you in a particular way and there's a way of knowing that has no
definition there's no limit and that kind of knowing has a kind of clarity openness that's maybe that he
calls luminous or like light all around to the mind the Mind The Knowing feels
luminous and wonderful so um so what kind of knowing is that
but you know that's where earth water fire and air it doesn't cease that's not
the point it's not the point to transcend it the point is to find a place where it's rooted where it's not rooted not we're
not mine's not caught in it that's an interesting idea so that so so here this guy wants the
miracle wants Supernatural powers he wants a demonstration of it and the
Buddha says no no that's not important instructions what's important and then he tells a Mr Smith about
supernatural power is this guy going to the heavens and someone traveling to the edges of the world
and think no that's not the way and then he turns the table on the guy
turns it upside down and says you know yes this you don't find it oh what he
literally says to the guy you're asking the wrong question you don't ask the question where does
the world cease where does the world have no footing where does it not grab us where do we
not get attached to it and then he says we do that happens where knowing is not seeable knowing is
no limit no knowing is Luminous because there's no attachment
somewhere else someone also is asking the Buddha for miracles
and um and similar kind of story and there the Buddha talks about uh the
person wants to ask their asks literally where does the world the Loca where does it end
where does it come to an end and um and the Buddha reply there is that
the world is this fathom long body
so here is here and now he's defining the world this fathom long body
and um and one of the uh one of the things we see in the teachings of the
Buddha he is keeps appointing the attention of
a practitioner it's very important to say a practitioner someone who's really engaging in Buddhist practice
not all about how we're in the world out there but Buddhist practice to the world
of direct experience so here and now not because Here and Now is supposed is the god of Buddhism
but the Here and Now is a place that we're in touch with literally our direct experience the senses the five senses
and knowing here and he saw this fathom long body
is this world of how we experience the world in the senses Here and Now
and he said it's here that we see
the world the arising of the world the origination of the world the ceasing of
the world and the practices that lead to the cessation of the world
and in this case he kind of kind of slides back and forth now between calling the world suffering look Loca
and dukkha duka is suffering the world of we know suffering we know the arising
of it the origination of it we know the seizing of it and the practice it leads to it this world that we that is our Phantom
long body that's where we produce the world that's where the world begins for each
of us and in a radical way indirect experience not the imagination
not the memory both of which have some uncertainty to them both of them would have some
inaccuracy through them some other they're all kind of
predictive or imaginary they belong to the world of the imagination often anything that's beyond our direct
experience but the word our direct experience always begins fresh and new every moment
the world is born here and why why I feel it's very important
to say this is that um the world you want to live in the world
you'd like to live in if you're just waiting for everyone else to make that happen
you're going to wait a long time and if you have the imagination of how
horrible the state of the world is chances are you also have an imagination of what's possible
what could be wonderful and if there is a possibility of a
wonderful world to live in don't wait for other people to make it
be the maker of it your world the world your world begins
with you and you can be the producer of it
be the person who is what you want the world to be
if the world is a place where people are kind to each other friendly to each other support each other cooperate with
each other a world where people resolve their
conflicts be that way be kind be friendly
be generous work on solving conflicts engage in that
don't pass it on to others expecting others to do it because that's a world if you do that that that's the world you
create other people will do it and I'm the consumer I'm the victim I'm
this you know it's kind of a self-fulfilling prophecy
and that's why it seems so real because you're kind of producing the very thing that you're afraid of
but to be the producer of the world that's here starts here and then we can do it together with
others we find other people who are producing that kind of world and there's a lot of people producing a
good world out there and phenomenal many people there was a wonderful book some years
ago that I saw maybe from and gave it to me maybe that um
was celebrating how many small non-profits there are in the world right
now people small efforts in small little town that little towns here and there
and the cities here and there are trying to address the climate change and the environmental issues of our times
and if you cook some total of all these little small efforts is phenomenal what it is New York Times today has an
article about the exponential growth of alternative energy sources and how there are also so many different small places
that are doing it the small governments and so
all that you want to live in a world where we do Collective efforts not hero
worship hero worshiping but to worshiping our Collective let it
begin with you and find people to share with and work with
and then something beautiful is happening here and
who knows the San Andreas fault might Shake
any minute now yeah some of you don't know but a mile from here so maybe a
little bit more two miles from here is a level of tension of two tectonic
plates rubbing against each other and and pressing against each other and
kind of by because of the friction not giving it giving in yet but at some point that pressure will be just enough
it'll together and last time it happened in 1906 you
can see up in some places where the ground shifted you can still see or jumped and shifted
away and it's dramatic
so now you'll go home afraid I'm not scared because that's one way to have address
the state of the world is to is to be right frightened by it
to be a victim of it to be under its way but to be the producer of the world
to cultivate the best qualities of a human being
so that when the San Andreas equivalent of the San Andreas for fall shakes
we're ready for that we're ready
for the beginning of a new world of a new town of a new state of a new
something we're ready to bring forth the best qualities we have
to contribute to what's new in a good way and we see that happens many times in
many places that sometimes the level of tragedy that happens that human caused is caused by
very few people but but how many people come together
to to address the issue and so I'll end with one of the Great American
Heroes who I don't think believed in that hero's journey
Mr Rogers who said that who attributed a lot of
who he became to his mother because when he saw the terrible things happening in the world
he asked her about it and she said oh look look around and look for the
helpers the people are helping and that lots of people are helping
don't forget that don't be so overwhelmed by what's happening in the world you don't see the helpers
don't be so overwhelmed in the world that you don't become one of the helpers that's what's important that's the world
we want to live in to so much uncertainty
but let's not be uncertain about the goodness of our own hearts let's be the producers of the world
let's make it together into a place that's good and I think that's the message of the Buddha
here you can be free here you can Free Yourself are your
attachments here your heart and mind can become luminous and here's where your kindness and
compassion and care and generosity and
wisdom and patience and equanimity can come and meet this world
here maybe even as soon as you get in your car to drive home those of you who
are driving drive as if you're creating a new world
so it's my thoughts today so thank you