Hello friends hello and welcome to happy hour hi and if you can hear me okay give
me a thumbs up audio is good fantastic hi I'm Nikki in Mountain View California
on seated Oland welcoming you to this rendition of happy hour and as always we uh start by
uh saying hello where we're zooming in from and just bringing our um voice are
are uh meta our Goodwill to the space so take it away sa who's here who wants to
say hi Jessie Cento hi Jesse Susan and
Sano hi Susan Jerry and trado hi
Jerry Golden Colorado I heard Ali and I heard was it somebody else from Colorado
who was it that was me that was Jake hi Jake welcome and I see Roger says hello
from Sacramento welcome Diana in New York hi Diana good evening hi it's
Lynette from San Pablo hi Lynette welcome lesie and San Diego hi
Leslie Claire in New York City hi Claire our East Coast
contingent PMA from hi Padma Noella from
talta hi Noella our West Coast contingent this
from I heard Don and I also heard Helen from Connecticut hi Don and Helen Don
where are you zooming in from today Kito still Kito
cool very cool and Hi Megan from paloalto and Suzanne from San Francisco
any any other hell Neil newshire rainy New Hampshire hi Neil from rainy New
Hampshire and somebody else I heard too huh yeah Fred in rainy Oakland oh Fred
and Barbara from rainy Oakland hi and Hugh in San Diego hi Hugh and hi Michael
from Oakland and hi Barry also from the East Coast from DC very cool oh how nice
the song has assembled my heart is already warm I find myself smiling with
all the hello from these different places in the world or different time zones and also we are Live on YouTube um
and Calvin says hi from Minnesota on YouTube folks are joining us from YouTube as well so so I think the space
is warmed up I feel warmed up so I ask you to mute yourself if you are unmuted
and I thank um Neil for posting information about the happy hour Google
groups in chat uh if you're new to happy hour we have a low trffic uh mailing list you're
welcome to join it and uh also there is a little document about um how to offer
care and and kindness and safety to yourself and others if you uh engage in
the breakout rooms that we're going to have which is a lovely part of happy hour so you can take a look at that at
this time I change the settings so that unmuting oneself won't be possible so the space stays quiet I change the chat
settings so chats only come to uh the host myself but I ask you to keep uh the
chat Channel quiet otherwise it can be rather distracting for me to receive chats while I'm teaching I'll open it up
later for Reflections and last but not least is
what I do at this this point we just turn on audio recording for the sake of
uh Audio Dharma here we go great okay well hello everyone hello
and welcome again to happy hours lovely to be with
you so so um yeah maybe a couple of themes I want
to bring in today one is uh one is the theme that uh it's the theme about uh
spiritual friends spiritual friendships and uh about good friends
actually about good friends and this passage in the sua was shared with me
earlier today by my good friend uh Diana Clark you know Diana when Diana and I
used to hold happy hour together for a long time so um so this is the what she
shared with me and we're both delighting in in this um teaching from the sutas
that neither of us um knew uh in in its significance so so um and you'll see why
in a moment it can it's relevant and significant so so this is from angut
nikaya uh 1113 and and
as you might have noticed um if you've been practicing meditation and the Dharma for
a while often the teachings you know taking refuge for example taking trust
it's in the triple gem it's the Buddha Dharma and Sanaa so Buddha both Buddha and also the the um
external Buddha internal Buddha which is our own called uh um ability having
trust in our own ability to work wake up so thinking of that as the internal Buddha and the Dharma as the teachings
the both the the um d uh the Dharma with capital D the teachings of the Buddha
and the Dharma with small D which is the unfolding the lawful way things
unfold and usually the third one is the sa the community of practitioners the community of of uh spiritual friends and
and people who have supported who support us and we can think of the S not
just as the S of practitioners through the 2700 years passing on the teachings
but also people who are practicing together right now for example on Zoom as our
community um Etc and PE people who support us so so what's what's lovely
about this this suta um is is that the
Buddha um talks about Reflections their beautiful Reflections
that that he talks about and then and then uh he gets to the uh recollecting
the realized one recollecting the teachings and then with the third one we kind of expect the usual we expect the
Sanaa right the community but he actually says furthermore you should
recollect your good friends isn't that sweet you should recollect your good
friends and the SI continues recollecting in quotes I'm fortunate so
very fortunate to have good friends who advise and instruct me out of kindness
and compassion in this way you should establish mindfulness internally based
on good friends it just makes me happy isn't that just such a sweet teaching about
good friends and friendships at this time of the year so I'm going to read that one more time I'm going to also put
it in chat so that you have this so again after he's gone on firstly you
should recollect the realized one furthermore you should recollect the teachings dot dot dot and then lastly
further and more you should recollect your good friends I'm fortunate so very
fortunate to have good friends who advise and instruct me out of kindness
and compassion in this way you should establish mindfulness in
based on good friends um such a beautiful beautiful s
this I'm going to put this quote in in the chat in Zoom uh so that you see that and and the
reference is a an and Gaya 1113 if you wanted to look at it later
so um and also another thing I want to to highlight for those who also are
familiar with the four foundations of mindfulness suta where the Buddha talks about
establishing mindfulness in externally and internally in the body with vad a
feeling tone mind States as well as the Damas this is another way this is you
know um Diana and I had never seen oh you should establish mindfulness
internally based on good friends you know we're used to the body we're used to the Mind States but good friends it's
such ATI lovely teaching um so that that's one of the bases for the teaching tonight um
for us to reflect I'm fortunate so very fortunate to have friends who advise and
instruct me out of kindness and compassion so reflecting on on good friends so and and given that you are
joining happy hour you have good friends who are cultivating their hearts towards
kindness and compassion and we support each other in this way so yay it just
gladdens my heart to be in this community in this way so so with that I think that's plenty of
uh teachings and actually tell you maybe I'll put one last quote in I'll One Last
Link in here for later and this is reference to the uh this is the
translation of this so all right look at it later all
right so with without further Ado let us practice together let's
land let's arrive let's arrive in our
bodies aring arriving in this
body
feeling feeling our sit Bones on the cushion of the
chair offering our weight the weight of our upper body to
the cushion relaxing as if we're with each out breath we're sinking
in a centimeter deeper into the chair
feeling the bottom of our feet on the earth with each out breath ah letting
our feet sink a little more deeply into the
Earth and while we feel groundedness the sinking also let
us feel the uprightness the uplift the heart the Mind feeling
uplifted towards the skies both rooted and
uplifted with every in breath with every aspiration feeling inspired feeling our
aspiration the other meaning of aspiration lifting
up letting ourselves settle
with this in breath and this out breath relaxing and
receiving
e
letting awareness receive this INB breath this
out breath spaciously letting the heart be
spacious
expansive
letting the breath be interesting fulfilling
nourishing calming and soothing to the heart and mind In This
Moment collecting
Gathering
I'd like to invite you if you would bring to Mind One Good
Friend one good friend especially if you appreciate their kindness their
compassion
and establishing mindfulness internally with the reflection of this
good
friend the kindness and compassion doesn't have to be in every aspect of their
life some ways as you know
them Let Your Heart Light Up This goodness of this sense of feeling
fortunate to have this good
friend and not so much thinking about it this is not a thinking practice but when you
connect with this good friend in your heart internally let's breathe in and out with
the goodness of it be their felt sense their image the
goodness of their goodness their
kindness goodness of your
friendship of your Kalita kalana this when this word that means beautiful or
wholesome M friendship wholesome friendship beautiful
friendship and if you find your mind going towards all the UNH wholesome or un beautiful friendships bring your mind
back to just one wholesome kalana
MIT also to know that in Buddhism all teachers are considered to be kalana
spiritual wholesome friends not gurus
so so you are my Kalita and I'm
Yours
the butter recommends recollect your good friends I'm fortunate so very
fortunate to have good friends who advise and instruct me out of kindness
and compassion and this way should establish mindfulness
internal based on good friends
Kal
let your heart be uplifted brightness
internally
and as we turn to bring this sitting practice to a [Music]
close one last time bringing the sense of this good friend good friends to your
heart internally let your heart be uplifted how fortunate how fortunate in this
lifetime let the reflection right in your heart and mind internally establishing awareness
mindfulness now can you consider yourself a a good friend to yourself in
this moment may I be a good friend May I a good good Trend to
myself may I treat myself with kindness and compassion advise
myself
kindly compassionately the said as the Buddha
said advise and instruct myself with kindness and
compassion may I be a good friend to
myself may all beings everywhere be a good friend to themselves than to
others may all beings be free may all beings be happy including
[Music] ourselves
thank you all thank you so
much I feel happier after this meditation I don't know by you I my
heart feels up uplifted so
um yeah yeah thank you all thank you for your
practice so for uh our group practice
small group practice today here is the invitation in small groups that we each
um as we go around each person offers one thing that you appreciate about your
good friend one thing and it could be so um you know one person would say I
appreciate that my good friend I'm think thinking about right now they also practice they also love the Dharma and
then everyone appreciates that and the next person offers one thing what I
appreciate by my good friend is that oh they're very kind when I'm sick they call on me and check in to see if I need
anything we honor and appreciate that that goodness of the good friend and the next person offers something and then
comes back to you maybe you offer something again what do you appreciate about the same good friend or another a
good friend doesn't you don't have to name them and tell a long story but just what you appreciate yet your heart be
uplifted and other people's hearts uplifted there's so much goodness in the world
so so this is the invitation for uh cultivating our um Goodwill kindness
appreciating goodness so I'm going to create the breakout rooms and be kind to
yourselves be kind to one another and as you already know please um not a good
not not appropriate to ask questions each person is offering basically for
their own reflection and if you didn't understand what somebody said it's okay Let It Go not offering advice or or
asking questions just let it be it's an offering it's a stone soup we're creating together in this Wholesome Way
but just honoring everything everyone says so um yeah let let your heart be uplifted
from what people bring in so I'm creating the rooms be kind to yourselves be kind to others and let's go in
reverse alphabetical order and if you please if you can turn on your uh camera
in the small groups can really help support the breakout groups um that
would be that would be really appreciated by everyone okay thank you
so much and and I'm about to open the rooms here so
we have some time for Reflections about the practice how this
was for you and um either the practice itself if you noticed um anything you
want to share with the Sanaa both for uh their benefit and yours to be
held witness you can also type in chat if you like if you type your Reflections
to me privately I'll only uh read your Reflections not your name and if it's to
everyone I'll read your name I see three hands up okay lots of Reflections all right let's let's uh hear from Leo
first I was wondering if you could provide more insight into that
wording what was it develop mindfulness internally yeah what's the other kind of
mindfulness I mean was that externally so what does that look like
you you give me two examples how many hundreds do you want
Oh My Goodness I'll settle for one of each so so um in the Sati
PTA where a really a lot of teachings on mindfulness are pulled from are taught
from um and satian is the the establishment of the four foundations of
mindfulness as I mentioned at the beginning I'll say it again there are the four parts there's
the body mindfulness of the body mindfulness of um Vena feeling tone
mindfulness of Mind States and mindfulness of the Damas which is
there's um kind of processes and and and and um um let's just leave it at that
and for each of these four the Buddha talks about say mindfulness of body
internally and externally so every single one of them there's mindfulness to be established internally mindfulness
to be established externally and then internally and externally so that's
taught in the reframe of the satian you might you're actually reading the Sati patan I was going to say right that
didn't help much but it gave me a pointer so I will go look at them yeah but maybe one thing that I can say is um
you know in the west we especially think of mindfulness or awareness let's use the word awareness always internal
always internal but it's not just internal it's both internal and external
and internal and external so so for example if you're um interacting with someone you you want to be aware you
want to be mindful in your speech in your conduct and you don't want it to be entirely internal you want to be aware
of their body language what they're feeling their responses so your
awareness is also external and it's also internal and external so you get that
you know that so does that help it does
great you're welcome Megan
please thank you um I was just reflecting the gift of
friendship um I and I hope I'm able to explain this uh well um for
me what has been wonderful is this friend not just
um accepting me as I am but also allowing me to show up for her and the
gift that it is when she lets me be there
um and and that it's that it's both and and I was trying to tell her this today
um because she was feeling overwhelmed by by my how
much I've shown up and and trying to tell her but it's it's a gift for me as
well thank you Megan thank you so much for br this into the space it is a gift
when others allow us to be generous with our presence with our kindness um
accepting that gift is is another Act of generosity on their part so yeah thank
you in absolutely yeah Helen
please hi um I um shared in my little
group about uh uh a a very special
friendship or love in my life um which is you know I have a
dog and uh I I'm thinking of two aspects
why I would say so because uh first of all the dog my dog sets an example for
me because she's always in the present moment you know and uh the second thing
is uh uh my dog I'm sure everybody else dog the same thing uh has the
unconditioned love for me and for everybody she is in contact with and any
little thing I do for her she shows great appreciation I just feel like uh you
know she's the love of my life and um
she does a lot of things for me and she's my comfort my love and I really
appreciate having her thank you Helen oh my heart is so
happy hearing your love and care for your dog and and uh hers for you
oh yeah and yeah the unconditionality of the love to and from
pets yeah such a lovely feeling to um
inspiring meta and the cultivation of loving kindness and gratitude thanks for bringing our furry friends
in um friended oops wait FR you disappeared
before I could click on you to ask you to unmute where did you go you read there here
thank you Nikki uh I was thinking of um you know a close friend who's really involved in um
you know in practice and Dharma study and how wonderful that is to to have somebody to do that with but then I was
also thinking of friends who would utterly reject this idea and who would um have
no no sympathy and interest at all in anything that would be called spiritual or certainly Buddhist or any of that and
yet they they are great friends for for who provide all the um the love and the
consistency and the and the sort of prodding towards uh trying harder
directing towards me the there's just so many ways in which friendship can
be can be laed to in our lives and it's wonderful to have a lot of
variety um and to to not have any kind of external
requirements beyond what the experience of friendship early is and that it's you know as long as
it's is there at a at a deep level and a mutually sustaining uh Arrangement then
it's all great so thank you thank you Fred thanks for sharing your your words
of wisdom about friendship then and what you shared is really the uncondition
acceptance of of the Care um and the friendship that's there yeah lovely
couple of Reflections coming through mimo I'll get to you in a moment
um see uh one person privately says
appreciate relationships from the past that have given that have Arisen and passed away
yeah we making us who we are and supporting us Jerry says being silent
with kind thoughts while looking at someone can communicate a great deal of loving
kindness yeah and uh so reflection
about um small groups which um yeah I I
want to bring this in um we we really do appreciate we do we do ask you not to
cross talk and especially if you know small group someone says I know we're not supposed to cross talk and yet goes
ahead and comments on something someone has said you know let's let's not do that let's let's offer a um safe and
protected space to everyone so really appreciate you um not doing that it's
and then that uh restraint actually that pulling back that um restraint is very
helpful for everyone to feel safe in in the small groups and we really ask you
to respect that even though it's so tempting to comment on what somebody else has said just
don't yeah so thank you uh one of you says my cat radiates
meta that's very sweet thanks for that reflection yeah somebody's commenting on how cute Jake's dog is Dog I think
you're you're you're yeah here yeah oh my goodness Thea hi hi doggy that's
great Mima we you we come to you please thank you
Nikki um I really appreciate this topic because it helped me
um helped me see how my life is peppered with so many different types of personalities and how I love these
people and how they love me how we show up for each other um it took my focus
off of other things and I think rightfully put it where it belonged to kind of light up my heart and be able to
see um how much I really value the friends I have in my life right now they're so
valuable to me thank you oh thank you for that that pure word
of appreciation joyous appreciation which gives rise to Joy in my heart for
you Mima it's vicarious Joy muita yay yay
um yeah beautiful yeah when we have joy and appreciation for for the friends and
goodness fortune in my life in our life it supports others to do the
same um yeah so so dear ones thank you
so much for your participation your practice your support for one another in
happy hour and um yeah may you be well may you uh
may we all appreciate the good fortune in our lives our our
friendships and uh may we may we spread
may we spread and share our own goodness with friends and um all beings everywhere may all
beings be be well may all being be happy including ourselves
[Music] thanks everyone