so good day everyone welcome back
it's our first our fourth meeting on the topic of Social and communal Harmony
hmm let's start with the sitting
today we'll con we will continue along with this pattern that we've been uh using the last couple of days
we will um first settle in mindfulness of the body mindfulness of breathing
and then about 10 minutes into the setting we'll switch to practicing one of the Rama viharas today sympathetic
Joy so let's find our seat
foreign
into that world of sensation
letting our body physically settle on
our support foreign
s of the body as we sit or recline
the breath flowing in the breath flowing out
the heartbeat and quiver of the body after the heartbeat
foreign
movements of the body and sensitive to any Stillness that's
already present
foreign
in a steady gentle but deliberate way
with the arising of each new breath connecting again
with this moment of physical experience
thank you
foreign
experience a shift
to the arousing of sympathetic Joy
joy and the happiness of another
will Begin Again by generating a touch of loving kindness
for ourselves
perhaps taking the mental posture of kindness kind regard
and wishing ourselves well
may I be happy
may I be healthy
who may I be safe
may I live with ease
may I be happy
foreign
loving kindness
perhaps trying to mind someone who is experiencing a wholesome form of
happiness
maybe you can even see their face in the Mind's Eye
something in there eyes or their smile that communicates contentment
or joy
connecting connecting with this other person
who arouse the wish may your good fortune continue
may your good fortune continue
and registering your body your body's response your mind's response
to the wish
foreign
as often as is appropriate for you
may your good fortune continue
foreign
Ty showing joy in the goodness the well-being of
another
like a bright moon sunlight
shining beautiful
This Joy welling up in the heart
now we can shine upon all beings
in the first quarter to the front
gently radiating may all beings in this direction
May their Good Fortune continue
and in the second quarter to our right
to all beings in this direction experiencing [Music] wholesome happiness
may your good fortune continue
foreign
to the third quarter behind
to any being experiencing wholesome Joy
May or Good Fortune continue
foreign to the fourth quarter to our left
may your good fortune continue
and below all beings
large and small
experiencing wholesomeness may your good fortune continue
and above
may your good fortune continue
the brightening light some sympathetic Joy
shining in the four directions [Music] above and below
foreign
[Music] to a close
celebrating machine well
to all beings everywhere
[Music]
foreign
hello again I don't know if this was happening for
you but I I noticed as we were doing sympathetic Joy meditation without my intending it I had this tiny
smile growing over one side of my face uh
wow such a such a way that giving Joy comes back
so this week we've been talking about social and communal Harmony the practice of it which um
begins with Right View which is then made real
through our effort we've been talking about this in terms of rahula's repeated
reflection and then as a sort of application
we yesterday we We examined uh working with anger
reflecting on its causes its effects um
and the encouragement to make the most wholesome contribution possible
whatever is available we've been we've been talking largely in
personal terms about the Buddhist teachings on social and communal Harmony and then
today I think we're going to move in a in a more communal social Direction
so again I'd like to begin with a story one you may have heard before the um
the details are a little fuzzy so we're just going to have to imagine and the the way that I the way that I
recall this story it's something like there's a there's a circle
of I don't know maybe I don't know the number let's say 10. it's a Dharma
practitioners people who've been practicing on the path together for 30 40 50 years
and they're having a they're having um a time to share
and the topic comes up what are what are the difficulties that you're facing in
your practice and I hear this set up I get interested
um I wonder how a practitioner of 30 40 50 years relates to the difficulties in
their lives and then the first person the first person shares these things are going
well and you know I've got this thing going on I have um I'm still noticing
that this form of attachment is arising in me and isn't that something
and then the second the second person I'm gonna share and they talk about a
conflict that they're involved in you know someone they care about but there's a disharmony in the relationship
for now and one by one sort of discussing discussing some of their difficulties
what I remember the impression of this story was so interesting to me
was that the the the
SE practitioners that have matured over decades what we're seeing it's not
perfection it's not that there's no difficulty in their social lives
but what stands out is the the earnestness with which they engage and a
sort of levity a sort of like lightness oh look at this you know isn't that something I've still
got this I've still got this issue going on after all these years it's not a it's not a hurtful self-criticism
but a sort of lightness there's that sort of humor in a there's a there's a Zen story of uh the the
teacher saying something like oh even after all these years I still put on my robe with a flare
um so I have this wish for all of us that um
that we have a circle of support like this a circle of good Dharma friends that grows over the years that maybe we
find ourselves 30 40 50 years down the path that um we can sit in a circle and
share our our Treasures of practice that includes our
difficulties with this touch of levity
so in the teachings it's also there that something we all know pretty well the choice of our friends has a profound
influence on our lives so maybe it may be useful to contrast
these two terms and the teachings one is kalyanamita good friendship admirable friendship
beautiful friendship and it's contrasted with this other word Papa Mita
Papa has a sort of dramatic translation in English usually it's translated as
evil looking into it it looks like the the word is associated with qualities like
unruliness stubbornness whereas kalyanamita good friendship is
associated with gentleness and being easy to correct I think of someone who's someone who's
open to good advice
in the in the way that the Buddha does he celebrates this this uh factor of the
path good friendship by saying there's not a single thing that gives rise to skillful qualities
or makes unskillful qualities decline like good friends when you have good friends skillful
qualities Arise at unskillful qualities decline
so our choice of friends can have a profound influence on us in the spirit of Social and communal
Harmony one of the things that bikubody says this brings forth is a sense of discretion
that's of Interest a sense of discretion
so looking into the qualities of beautiful friendship there are some very beautiful lists in the in the teachings
and I'll just mention one the Buddha was talking to a young person and he says that there there are these
four kinds of kind-hearted friends there's the one who is helpful
there's the friend who shares one's happiness and suffering third there's the friend who points out
what is good in terms of action and there's the friend who is
sympathetic and he explains the the friend who's helpful is someone who's um
someone who's willing to look after you when you're heedless and gives more than is required
and is a refuge for you when you're frightened when I think to
when I think to the circle of support the circle of Dharma friends that
can grow for us over years and years one of the qualities I feel in that
Circle whether it's explicit or not is that these people can be a refuge when it's difficult
a friend who shares and happiness and suffering this is a friend who
is willing to practice modita for us sympathetic Joy is willing to practice
compassion for us when we're suffering oh may you be free of suffering it's someone who cares
this third type of kind-hearted friend the friend who points out what is good
um it's here that we see that in the texts there's an emphasis on uh
kalyanamita a good friend is someone who is a teacher or a mentor for us
I like to reflect on good friendship in this broader sense it's like all of our relationships
and um there is this way that trusted mentors can help point us away from what's
harmful and toward what's helpful and then there's the friends who are
sympathetic so important to Social and communal Harmony I think this is someone who will
actually commend other people who are speaking well of you speaking well of your virtues Maybe
and will uh it said stop people who are speaking dispraise of you
they undermine divisive speech
then in contrast to the beautiful friend the wise friend the wise person in the
text we have this person uh that we call the fool um maybe not what it sounds like at
first glance but a fool a fool is to Define in terms of uh actions
it's someone partaking of unskillful actions of body speech and mind and that ends up having the effect
socially of a sort of Calamity that brings harm
um in the dhamapada it says that as long as evil has not borne fruit the fool thinks
it is like honey isn't that so
but a really important principle here is that uh it seems and it seems in the teaching fool status is not permanent
that um maybe fool is someone someone who's acting in a misguided way
and that they can always become a wise person
and a story that's really well known the um
the Buddha's attendant Ananda declares
uh half of the Holy life is good friendship good companionship good comradeship and
the Buddha and his well-known response no another don't say that don't say that the entire
holy life is good friendship good companionship good comradeship and when he says the
holy life here it's the training the life of training when a monastic has good friends when a
practitioner has good friends it can be expected that they develop and cultivate the noble Eightfold Path
this has always been an interesting point for me that one of the ways that we can
recognize good friendship in this sense in a dharmic sense is are we growing in
skillful qualities is it supporting what's wholesome what's
helpful or is it uh is it um leading us into its
opposite then the Buddha carries on he goes on
so a and he's asked this rhetorical question how is it that a person with good
friends uh cultivates the the Eightfold Path
and the first thing he says based on good friendship is that they develop Right View we're right back at the beginning of the
week there's this very interesting thing happening here where Right View
we've made our way from Right View through practice to good friendship the
right view points us to good friendship and allows us to recognize good friendship
and then good friendship points us right back into Right View it's this positive
feedback loop good for us good for others
so good friendship is something worth celebrating and also worth noting
I think it applies for most of us maybe I'll just speak for myself we're not perfect people
sometimes we Act in a way that we are the fool and sometimes we act in the way of a
wise person um but there's a there's a way that
there's this great way that Norman Fisher uh mentioned in a talk
these um these actions we take that we're talking about is maybe foolish he calls them our little buddha foibles
I love the levity of this phrase you know it doesn't dismiss the fact that something might be amiss
but there's something compassionate and accepting that gets communicated in the phrase little dutifoigels
whatever those might be in the spirit of rahula's repeated
reflection if we if we act in a in a way with our little buddha foibles
We Lay It open we share it with a good Dharma friend and we resolve
on something else in the future
so maybe at times we're both fool maybe sometimes we're the wise
person hmm
I hope that I hope that allows us to include everything in our practice all
of ourselves there's nothing that has to be outside sometimes we're the good friend
sometimes we need the good friend sometimes someone comes to us and says
oh I notice I'm having this difficulty uh it seems like you kind of have some
skill in this area what do you what do you suggest maybe we're the good friend they come to
maybe sometimes we go to them I'm having this difficulty what do you think
there's some way that the the relationships are nourished by Mutual Trust
and by our practice of mindfulness our practice of mindfulness
supports this this movement to a bond that's deeper than Pleasant and
unpleasant when we practice mindfulness we learn how to not respond immediately
to Pleasant and unpleasant and I think that opens up a field where we can connect on a deeper level
so so good friendship
I hope uh I hope good friends in this sense can be inspiring
encouraging helpful and that we cultivate and make our way
toward relationships that are conducive to the path conducive to our growth to the well-being of ourselves and to others
may that be for the benefit of all beings maybe so
and tomorrow we will continue the Buddhist teachings on social and
communal Harmony please take care
foreign