good morning everyone good morning good morning to folks here and good afternoon and
evening and whatever time zone is or the folks who are joining us online hello hi
hello Internet hello Sangha here at IMC hi
ah it's kind of fun to feel that we're being joined right you were sitting here
and he had rejoined from various places in the world quite sweet quite sweet
so let's um
let's begin meditating together I'll offer some light guidance to help us settle
to help us settle and arrive and um
yeah so arriving arriving in this body In This Moment In Time
arriving in this moment of our journey
arriving with a receptive stance ah it's like this right now hello body
hello mind hello heart
and allowing awareness or knowing to greet to greet the body
embodiment so important the first establishment of mindfulness
the body oh
my God
are letting the breath sensations of the breath within the body
wherever they are experienced however they are experienced
to be received to be received to be received
a receptive stance see how that might feel different
from an achievement stance a receptive stance
irreceptive stance that receives the breath receives
the body
and letting the heart the body and the mind soften soften into a receptive stance
receptive awareness
receptive
receiving this moment not reaching out for the next one
not reaching out for the past but receiving this just this
receiving this fully
wholeheartedly
notice what happens when you shift when your mind shift it's
dance
from doing getting going out
to get to think problem solve or even within the body
from the control tower going to the breath and the body no what
if ah you have this
sense of exhalation in the body relaxing softening receiving
experience knowing experience with a receptive stance
experiment for yourself how might this be different
how might this shift
open something up for you in this practice
foreign
receptively engaged and aware of this
that is arising In This Moment
foreign
good evening
awareness open
spacious receptive
to whatever is arising In This Moment wholeheartedly
wholehearted receptive knowing
deceptive knowing
receptive but not entangled
unentangled knowing
can your heart receptively open to
tune into the goodness In This Moment
right here just the challenges and difficulties
goodness
sitting here in this moment
such Grace
is the heart is the heart is the mind
tightening clinching around something and the body and the mind
thought and emotion can we soften if that is the case
can we soften or stance
soften our bodies there is tightness tension
soften our perspective it's okay it's okay
soften our heart
let there be Grace of knowing simply knowing
being aware without judgment without entanglement
without wanting to fix it or push it away
a receptive wholehearted
embodied stance of knowing
what does it feel for you this stance
and as we turn to bring this sit to a close
appreciating ourselves for having
showed up and letting go of any judgment or
regret it didn't work out this way or
self-judgment or distractions or sleepiness or whatever might have arisen
let go of all of that if there is any
no attachment to outcome you've done your best
showed up as best as you were able to given all the causes and conditions
that came before
so appreciating appreciating yourself
your engagement your effort cultivate calm awareness
wisdom kindness and this can be a moment of kindness
towards yourself an appreciation for yourself and
the community and trusting there is co-created
goodness here in our practice together Trust
there is goodness so much goodness and practicing generosity sharing this
goodness with Good Will with all beings everywhere
may my practice may my wholeheartedness without
attachment to outcome may my practice our practice
support be a cause and condition for my own freedom
for all of our Awakenings and The Awakening freedom of all beings everywhere
may all beings be free may all beings be happy
[Music]
[Music] thank you all for your practice
thank you Nikki and welcome again and good morning good afternoon good
evening IMC are there any announcements
good morning is this working sorry it's number four yep there we go hi I'm
Hillary welcome uh first announcement is there's a t after the Dharma talk and so everyone's
welcome to stay feel free to get some tea inside and then take it outside there's food and you can take chairs out
there and a table if you like or just sit on the benches so welcome everyone to that
um there's also a next uh Saturday April 15th Redwood City annual spring cleanup
and so I have a sign up sheet if anybody's interested in uh joining me
and uh ROM who will be there as well it starts at 8 30 and it goes at until 12
they provide tools and everything and there's actually a breakfast and a lunch that they provide as well so if you are
interested I have a flyer about that and a sign up sheet also the following Saturday off on April
22nd there's a half day retreat in hutterit park
so meditating and outside and Don Neal and I will be leading that so there are
flyers for that also on the literature counter and I wanted just to mention the Family
Programs there's a mindful parents series that started that's on the third
Sundays of the month there's one coming up April 16th next Sunday
and yes we have Melodies here he's actually one of the teachers so if you
have any questions you can see her about that um let's see make sure I don't have
anything else um we also have Dharma sprouts for K
through second graders on the first Sundays Dharma rocks for third through fifth graders on on the third Sundays
and the Teen program so if you have any questions about that see me I'm also the volunteer director
here so we um we're always looking for volunteers for anybody who's interested in being a manager for an event a
recorder helping with a cheese Circle or potlucks or anything like that just um come say hi to me after after the talk
during the tea thank you
specifically one of the volunteer groups that we're trying to form is the
gardening group so just confirm maintenance and also people we need people who know something
about gardening so maybe once a month we would get together and do something outside so
please see me about that thank you foreign
thank you Hillary thank you so much and thanks for all that you do
so so hello greetings everyone here
and online hello so for today's
Reflections I wanted to to offer some
some thoughts for your consideration on the theme of
the journey is the destination the journey is the destination it's the
saying that you might have heard before in different contexts and in the context of our practice
actually in Buddhism in our spiritual practice it takes particularly special meaning so I wanted
to explore that a little bit and not just from a cognitive stance but also
offering some some tools of okay so what what if we how how would our stance how
would our daily perhaps practice shift if we
brought if we worked with this practical tools so so news you can use so that's my
intention today and also some engagement I'd love to have some engagement on the topic because we all have had some
experience with with both the opposite and also wisdom with the journey being
the destination so let's explore this together how does that sound
for it okay so
so let's start by actually exploring in an embodied sense because embodiment is
first and foremost is the exploring everything in the body is is is the
foundation of the practice is the foundation of practice and
in the Sati patana sutta in the four establishments of found four
establishments of mindfulness um where the Buddha talks about the four
establishments of mindfulness the first one is the body the first and primary
one is the body it's really exploring mindfulness of the body and and many of
you might be familiar with body scans which are drawn from the mindfulness of the person so basically embodiment
really having this basis of the body is the very first Foundation whereas in the
west we like to think of mindfulness as oh thoughts and mind I want to do the
third Sati patana mindfulness of Mind first whereas mindfulness of the body is
first second is mindfulness of feeling tone vedana Pleasant unpleasant or neutral
just this constant push and pull we have towards everything right that's the
second establishment the second Foundation the third one
is the Mind mindfulness of Mind mind States
Etc exploring that and then the fourth one the fourth satipatana establishment of mindfulness
is mindfulness of dhammas or um basically various conditions for
example the four noble truths is part of that the hindrance is basically knowing the algorithms the an awareness of how
it happens how it goes after you've got the basics down it's kind of knowing the pros the processes dhamma is kind of the
fourth one mindfulness of the processes processes of Liberation the Eightfold
Path isn't there so but coming back I just wanted to mention the four as a review the first one is mindfulness of
the body the body is so important embodiment awareness of the body
um exploring the body the body as a as a tuning fork also we get to know so much
about our state of Minds about our state of emotions based on what happens in our bodies and
in the west we're often cut off from our bodies we're like walking heads with the bodies kind of disconnected
whereas the body really both supports embodies us grounds us in our
practice ah have you noticed if you're stressed if you take a breath
body right breath in the body ah and if you've been in your mind blah
blah what I do about this ah there's a sense of grounding there's a sense of awareness okay maybe I know
how to do it by this I don't have to spin out in your mind you can become embodied so basically talking about how
important embodiment is not the focus of this talk
yet we're going to talk about the journey as a destination but but we need to start with the body otherwise we'll
get all too heady right okay so now that I've espoused I've sung
the Praises of of really becoming aware of your body and embody him into
practice in fact as you're sitting right now can you become aware of your body posture more aware what's happening in
your body how are you sitting where are your feet
if you feel embodied is there a sense of Integrity in your body would it help the shift to feel more of a sense of oh yeah
really sitting and and engaging with the Dharma right now
does your body feel that way so now as I invited you to feel into your body in
this moment ah as I feel into my body yeah I'm sitting sitting upright there's a sense
of uprightness in the body which also magnifies
sense of wholeheartedness of wanting to share the Dharma with you so there is a connection between the embodiment and
and the mind so now if you drop in
this reflection that the journey is the destination
what if you drop that into your body right now and see what happens my journey let's make it personal my
journey my journey In This Moment In This Moment
of being alive is the destination
drop that in and breathe with it a few breaths my journey
in this very moment
my journey in this very moment of being aware being alive
is the destination they're not separate
dropping it in feeling into what what arises in your heart what
arises in your body what realizations what reflections what does it feel when you really
connect with this let's drop it in one more time a third time
my journey in this moment in time however it's showing up right now my
engagement the way I'm showing up
on the Arc of my journey the way I'm aware the way I'm responding
the way I'm receiving perceiving this moment of my journey
on this path
is the destination they're not separate they're not different
and notice what arises how your body feels how your heart feels
dropping it into your body not your mind let it reverberate
this is it this is it this is it
the journey is the destination
so
you want to open your eyes if it feels okay now
there's a lot I want to share with you but I would also like to
maybe at this point as we're kind of exploring this what comes up for you what came up for you as you explore this
what reflections um if anyone is willing to share any
thoughts that came up any shifts any realizations wow
yes please if we can change the mic yes yes definitely
I was assuming we're going to use the mic for the benefit of people online thank you so much for being the
micrunner well it just showed me the presence is it
brought me to the present real gift
thank you thank you so much exactly their sense of presence like wow it yeah
beautiful
you're gonna get your work out today actually maybe the next person can pass it so you can rest if you wish hi um
so when I was embodied I really felt it settling in and I felt myself
grounding and then it almost felt like my mind was like no no don't do that we still have
to figure out the future and you have to plan on it instantly I noticed that
shift going back and forth like my mind almost thought it's unsafe too
said Lynn let myself fully believe that yeah that's what I noticed yeah
wonderful Insight that is so powerful what you just noticed in this small
little experiment wow that is powerful so powerful that there's some belief in
your mind that it's not safe that it's not safe to settle even for a brief
moment because here we're going to take it all back like this is just a moment right oh sweetheart it's okay you can
rest yes so that's it that's a big Insight that you've just had right now
about your own psyche and the way and and might have come up for others as
well so so one way to to then work with that
because yes of course there is planning and doing in the world and yet we do
need that respite we do need that and if we're always carrying that heavy weight
we never we never have the time to have a perspective we're always in the middle of it I know you know that we know that
and yet there's something there's some belief right which is often unseen so
it's fantastic that it just became seen right now yeah you're showing yourself thank you right
um to say okay you know thank you Billy thank you you're trying to support you're trying to
warn me protect me I I really appreciate the the kindness there and yeah don't
worry it's so it's really you I've got this there's a moment of
peace and I'll come back and just right now I'm gonna take 30 seconds five minutes 30 minutes a day a week to just
be and and I'll have a fresher perspective for a as Einstein says um on
my childhood Heroes um we can't solve our problems with the same mind
that created them
and this is the same mind right it just wants to problem solve and problem solving problem like okay
it's a different mind we want to cultivate a different mind thank you thank you thank you so much for sharing
that any other Reflections or insights this is so great
as I was sitting with the thought um a lot of I mean memories came for me
like um like my school days and like some you know pivotal moment in my life that led
me here and I'm happy today you know that I'm here and some key people that
like you know uh kind of um change in my life during this period and I'm like wow
it's all coming through and like you know and it brings me joy that I'm here so you know those are the thoughts for
me you know sitting with us yeah thank you thanks for sharing that it's so for you there was a sense of oh yes these
points of the journey these really these various points of the journey and this moment is part of this these are these
destinations the people who have been significant being here so all of it it's not just I'm going somewhere but it's it
just it's all part of of the the joy of
my life The Grace Of My Life all of this thank you
beautiful so appreciate your reflections any last burning ones before we transition
last burning
for me uh what came up was like when he was given those instructions
when you mentioned like in this very moment that's when I noticed that in this very
moment I'm free and then just for few seconds I felt
that freedom and after that worries about life outside this room came up but just in those few seconds I felt free
ah thanks so much for sharing that that's so beautiful lovely it's just moment of Freedom there's a
there is a door opening there's light shining in oh yeah right here wow it's possible it's
possible the sense of Peace sense of ease it is accessible it is accessible
here yay beautiful that's it that these are
mini nibbanas these are many moments of Awakening and freedom right here it's
possible and then they keep expanding and expanding expanding becoming more beautiful thank you thanks so much
thank you all for sharing your Reflections how how enlivening to actually have this kind of a interaction
from from us and you will have more maybe later in the talk I'll ask you more but
and also something else I wanted to say um after Genie shared about you know
feeling present with dropping this reflection as I've been actually working with this
reflection for a few days and every time I drop it in in my daily life I'm going
about doing this and that and I drop in the reflection the journey is the
destination ah wow this moment of the way I'm showing up the way I'm being the
way I'm about to send this email this this is it this is all these modes it's not just
not in fact the sense of um
going somewhere right in if we think of a destination you know sometimes we have
this this sense that um or are we holding back on our lives oh
when I grow up once I grow up once I graduate once I get married once I meet
my soul mate once I get the job the dream job once I retire once I you know
there's all sometimes there's one side that once this thing happens then I'm going to start living I'm I'm going to
be that's that's where I'm going that's my destination it's kind of unconscious
and you know or or when I'm awakened oh yeah I'm going to do all this practice I'm
practicing so whenever I'm liberated I'm I'm enlightened once I'm enlightened oh
yeah then I'll I'll have you know I'll have it all figured out and I'll just be living in
my happy retirement of Awakening um it doesn't work that way of course it
doesn't work that way right so I'll say more about the The Awakening bit but but a couple things to say one is I I
realize this this um mindset especially when I was in grad school when I was in grad school at
Berkeley um I remember there were some of my school excuse me said maybe that was not the
case when I was an undergrad but in grad school there was something but the intensity of it that people completely
gave themselves to the grad school curriculum so many of my uh classmates
had this sense of oh once I graduate I'll explore my hobbies or I'll do this
which I love and I haven't done it for years and whatever it might be one side so so there's this sense of oh putting
off our lives putting off like there is this destination which is graduation right or whatever it might be and
and for me was so interesting and in some ways there uh maybe it's more
subtle for us in different ways it's not so so big you know if I I had seen it in
myself at some point oh when I moved then you know maybe I'll give away the stuff and I'll clean up this corner like
wait I don't have to wait until that happens like I can do it now like there's so there could be these subtle
these destinations we set up in our lives instead of it being right here this is it this is it
these moments that were alive we have the grace of Being Alive and Kicking
being alive breathing sentient have agency
this is it there is this title of this book by one
of my favorite authors Milan kundera the Czech author and the title of the book was
um life is elsewhere it's a great book life is elsewhere such an interesting title of it right
the sense of oh life is elsewhere it's not here it's whatever you're doing this is not this is not it other people or
other places or you know it's like fomo I think it is translated to fomo I think nowadays like oh this is something life
is elsewhere as life is not elsewhere it's here it's right here in this moment it's right here in this room
this is it the way we're showing up the way we're engaging in this very moment
is the destination it is the destination also as it relates
to the teachings of the Buddha and the Eightfold Path so I'll get a little more specific in a moment but in the general
way for each of us to feel into that for ourselves
there's no redo there's no recital there's no rehearsing this is it this is
our lives this is our life the way we're showing up and and fashioning our lives
in every moment fashioning our Karma fashioning our our Legacy or our
awareness ourselves it's right here it's right here the journey is the
destination right here it's not so separate it's not so heady thinking about in the past or
future it's right here Liberation is not elsewhere Liberation
is also right here so so this invitation
to consider this to drop this in actually drop this in reflection maybe every day for hopefully the rest of the
day you'll drop it in and you'll you'll experiment with it as you leave it's one of my invitations
it will invite us to stop sleepwalking because we're sleepwalking usually we're
always pulling towards the next moment pulling towards the next moment the next
thing the next thing either we're pulling towards the back you know we're regretting what we did or said or you
know we're pulling back or we're pulling forward usually we're pulling forward the next thing the next thing okay
when is it lunch when is this when's that plan okay that to-do list okay I finished that okay the next thing is
still left to do next next next it's like you know going on on um if you
think of a journey eh a literal Journey if you've gone on a
trip either yourself you've seen that tendency in yourself or you're seeing that tendency in in your other Travelers
you've traveled with a travel Partners there's sometimes a sense of okay all right the next the next place we're
going to go see that Temple we're going to see that site next next like it's okay you go there two seconds you go to
the Eiffel Tower okay two seconds okay next the next place next right it's like wait a minute actually taking the Buster
or walking there is part of this journey it's the whole thing it's not just okay getting there two seconds next next so
so we sometimes have this tendency in our lives next thing next thing next
thing next thing like this is it the way we are actually the way it's not just
taking off the to-do list the to-do list
we're all going to die with the to-do list unfinished
I've just accepted that I'm never going to finish everything I want to finish it's just not going to happen
So speaking of that I um love teaching mindfulness of death which
some of you know mindfulness of mortalities it's one of the topics and themes that I love to teach on and
when I teach um courses one thing that I've done is to invite folks to explore
writing poetry writing death poems which are very common in in Zen Buddhism writing
death poems before they die also the the equivalent of it in in the west is the
Epitaph Epitaph being this the short saying that goes on the tombstone of
people and given that the tombstone is small epitaphs tend to be pretty short
I've invited people over time to write many and this is one that somebody wrote
once I get the job once I meet my soul mate once I'm free below me
quite profound yeah so that tendency that that we have like yes always
reaching for the next Once I do this once I do that once I'm free once I'm
free once I'm awake and liberated ah below me so we never know how much time
we have this is it this is it
so say some more specific things now as it as the path and the journey relates
to the way we live within the Buddhist context so making it a little more
specific now so the Buddha taught by suffering and the end of suffering
but the end of suffering is not a destination so much you know we think of
nibana as the end of suffering like that's it end up suffering
but it's again it's not so much of the place you go and it what place you reach
and then that's it did you ever consider that the Buddha continued to meditate
and practice after he was enlightened
yeah just think about that for a moment
so it's not so much a destination the practice that we do the the engagement and the way we live and also in in in
um Zen Buddhism there is this beautiful saying before Enlightenment chop would
carry water after enlightenment chop wood carry water
so Enlightenment again is This Not That is not a happy retirement of it's the
continuation of engaging with life continuing to engage and and I love that
that you share this moment of many nibbana I mean many pieces oh yeah many Freedom many and and the moments
so so Freedom becomes a part of the path not separate from the path it's not that
we're doing all this practice to to become free as you have whether you're new to practice you've
been practicing for a while if you've been practicing for a little bit at least you can tell that oh yeah
there are things that used to perhaps bother you or get on your nerves or you
lose your cool and now wow there's a little more freedom there's a little more freedom about those
topics in those areas maybe there's some areas that are still really challenging for you but don't either
a few areas there just a little easier now so and you're continuing to practice
you're here you're continuing to practice and engage so so are the the
freedom becomes part of our practice becomes it's just there's more and more
and more it's not like it's there's nothing and all of a sudden who rise like there's more and more freedom
becomes part of the path and in fact um
the path itself the path of practice itself is the path of freedom is the
path of happiness in and of itself there's a beautiful I want to read this quote um
for you this is from Sister true dedication who is um
one of the Disciples of tiknot Han and let me read the quote first so
um she says in his later years of teaching
tiknot Han revised his translation of the Eightfold Path
to be not merely the path leading to happiness
but the path of happiness he taught that in the true Spirit of the inside of
inter-being every step along the path leading to happiness must be happiness
itself if we suffer along the way
we've lost the game already I think that's quite profound
that every step along the path leading to happiness must be happiness itself so
if you translate Liberation freedom is happiness right that's another way to relate to it
it's not the path just leading to happiness it is it is happiness itself right here right now the journey is the
destination so I want to talk a little bit about the
Eightfold Path um and what I just read by the way this paragraph from sister to dedication is
from the recent uh lines or there's there there are articles on the
Eightfold Passage each author has written one one article on the Eightfold
Path from one person from each tradition of Buddhism it's quite sweet
actually to see that so so the Buddha taught
suffering and the end of suffering of course sometimes people are on the
outside they focus on the suffering oh Buddhism is all about suffering no it's about endless suffering
and and happiness really happiness and and the path of Happiness just a sister
true dedication I was talking about the path of happiness
so in the four noble truths so the Buddha talks about yes there is suffering there
is stress in life that's the first Noble Truth of course there is stress it's there's stress in life period all of us
have it all of us have challenges it's just a part of being human and they're big stresses and small stresses they're
they're the losses they're the challenges the tragedies the the
um the the griefs and then they're just the everyday stresses you know
you have to feed yourself and take care of yourself and bathe yours it's just all of us like oh yeah that too that too
there's limited time and there's just little stresses or tiny little stresses it's just part of Being Human
and and the second um Noble Truth is that that grasping
clinging is the cause of the the dukkah the sufferings like wanting things to be
a particular way and clinging to it and and or getting rope burned rope burn is
is when impermanence happens things are shifting and changing so so if you think
of you're grabbing a rope that keeps running through your hands right you're holding onto the rope and it keeps
shifting each and he's stop up don't change
you're getting rope burn that is that's another way that we heard
when we try to stop things from changing and changes the nature of life
and the third Noble Truth but yes it is possible to be free it is
possible to have freedom it's it's possible to be happy it is possible in the midst of all this in the midst of
this craziness that is life human life it is possible to be happy and free and
engaged not that you're going to go sit on top of a mountain okay I'm liberated finally uh no it's it's being engaged in
the middle of it and and okay and then people are on the edge of their seats okay but all right
tell us how uh the hateful path here it is this is
how you do it this is how it's done the Buddha tells you how it's done that's the recipe April path okay
all right okay eight full path but then Eightfold Path this this path
right it's like okay I'm gonna do the first and that second and I'm gonna do all these steps like okay and then I'm
gonna get to Nevada no I actually ate full path if you've noticed it's it's it's drawn as a as a wheel it's not a
path right have you haven't you thought about well it's talk it's taught as a path and a path usually is
like right when you go on a hiking path right it's one step after another right
whereas this path is drawn like it's is a wheel it's an eight spoke wheel oh
that's an interesting path there was a sign right that it's it's
this it's right here it's your why speech and it's wise it's
perspective and it's wise livelihood and it's wise mindfulness and cause it just
it's all here it's all here it's all here and it's not that and you
can you know it's all together it's all intertwined it's all here the journey is the destination
the way you engage is it
this is it so
the right so the different aspects of of the Eightfold Path with
um wise View and by the way the the translation often from Sama the word
samma summer which can be translated in the
Eightfold Path as right view or wise view or appropriate and the word right
remember at the beginning of my practice I had a little bit of like what right like right wrong seemed very Puritan but
actually the translation of the word really is appropriate what's the appropriate what's the useful view
what's the useful speech what's the appropriate speech in the right time
what's so think of the word right as the right tool so you're not going to use
the wrong tool like if I wanted to use the striker you know the cup a glass full of water would not be the right
tool the striker would be the right appropriate tool right so think of right as appropriate so or
also wise Right View right intention right speech right action write
livelihood right effort I actually prefer the word engagement because effort sometimes in
the west brings a sense of effort whereas engagement really what is appropriate engagement in the moment
with whatever we're engaging and um and wise mindfulness right
mindfulness paying attention and samadhi concentration collectedness of
the Mind the sense of stability wise stability
so so
the goal is the path the goal is the path
the way we live our lives every moment the way we pay attention
the way we meet suffering
our own suffering and the suffering of the world the way in each moment we are engaging
internally and externally this is the destination
it's not elsewhere this is it
so in some ways it might seem like a paradox because we
are practicing and we're going to have more and more ease and freedom and yet this is it
if we have The Stance of oh somewhere to go somewhere to get there's always this
this this this Restless mind this this wanting mind it's actually the second
Noble Truth clinging wanting like ah somewhere to go next thing
we're causing more suffering through our practice whereas this is it
so so I want to invite you all to
to drop in the phrase into your body the rest of the day and if it works for
you maybe the rest of the week this week try the journey is the destination
or make it more personal my journey in this moment is my destination this
this how am I showing up how am I meeting the suffering how am I meeting others see with kindness with generosity
this is it this is it we don't know how much time we have this is it
so thank you all for your kind attention
I hope some of these Reflections have been supportive and helpful than whatever
isn't helpful Let It Go it's all good
and maybe given that we have just a couple of minutes left I will ask if
there are any final Reflections since I promised I would open the floor again through any final Reflections or
questions maybe people make space for what
if anything is arising
yes Genie yes it's coming your way
in the beginning I think I heard you say that there were four things
and this was one of them the um the first one but I don't know is
that am I miss hearing oh yes I think at the beginning when I was setting the stage I was talking about
um when I introduced the topic the journey is the destination then I talked about how embodiment is important so the
four Sati patanas the four establishments of mindfulness body
vedana feeling tone the third one being the mind and the fourth one being the dominas the processes those are the four
that I mentioned okay yes thank you for repeating no problem and then I invited us to really engage with the first one
because that's the foundation of the body and drop it into the body not just
the head not just thinking about it but dropping it in that was the entryway into our meditation
there's one more company
I had an image of my son when he was little and anyone who's a parent would probably relate to this
is we're going to the library or we're going to the park but for him it was the going that you
have that you're going to yeah and so I that that was the journey yeah not being
at the park it's going to the party yeah beautiful thanks so much for adding oh
my goodness yeah I feel such tender children are like that right they're like on the way it's like oh they're
just enjoying everything on the way they're going it's the going it's the go
that's it it's the going love it I love it Nancy please
thank you I was just gonna say the idea of dropping that in in sort of the
middle of the day in the middle of what you're doing uh actually seems like a good
sort of diffuser and that if you're reminding yourself
that the journey is the destination when you reach those difficult moments
either with other people or in yourself it is that at that moment that the
practice is really the most important yeah and so um
yeah thank you thank you so much yeah
I appreciate what you said exactly it's just a reminder because we tend to forget or become so focused on the thing
and the next like yeah this is it actually this is these are the important
moments it's all important but especially those moments yeah yeah challenging moments thank you
thank you all thank you so much for your engagement with this topic may you be well may you be happy may we serve well
thanks everyone