good evening welcome welcome nice to see you all
to practice together
so today I'd like to start with this uh little quote that's uh in the suit does
this uh where somebody asks the Buddha question
it seems like a for me when I hear this it seems like a relevant question that we could just ask
today absolutely so the question is
when beings all wish to live in peace this recognition that all of us want
peace of course all of us do not only humans do you write old beings this is part of
I don't know I just imagine what it's part of what it means to be alive so the question is when beings all wish
to live in peace why are they perpetually embroiled in conflict
that's a good question like we all want peace but why is there so much conflict
all over the place and really obvious ways and even in really uh subtle quiet
ways of course we have like nation states but we also have you know just being
irritated with the neighbor because they're a dog barks all the time or something like this right there's
this maybe the conflict isn't um obvious or you know manifest in some
terrible throwing things or saying things or harming but there's this like
conflict like not getting along with being in contention with so why is that that even though we want
peace we find ourselves in conflict sometimes we're even in conflict with
the moment like I don't want this to be happening make it go away
this way in which we're kind of like trying to push things away or change them or manipulate them engineer them in
any way we can just to make them feel more comfortable so that we don't
feel like we have to be in conflict with them
so then as you might imagine and these suit does after that question the Buddha gives a talk
I'm not going to go into exactly that particular suit uh but he gives this discourse where he's tracing all the
causes of conflicts and hostility and he talks about settler and settler
more and more subtle elements of our experience
so I finally kind of like landing on it's our views
beliefs of course it is like how could it be
anything else these ideas that we have about how things should be or how we
should be but it's something it's not quite that
simple either because otherwise we could just say okay well we'll just change our beliefs or
don't have any beliefs or anything like that and then you wouldn't be in Conflict but
somehow that doesn't quite work there's this way in which we have these
views that we're not even aware of we're holding on to them in a way that we don't even know
and we don't want to have this uh approach like oh nothing matters or
everything's okay and we don't need any boundaries and we don't need to say this
is okay and that's not okay like we don't want to do that so how do we find our way with this
this idea of conflict and Views and beliefs
well first I'll start by here's a story that the Buddha gives about himself it's
a little autobiographical and it's a little bit different than what we usually hear about the Buddha it's
before he's awakened and what it was like to be a young man at that time in ancient India
it's very interesting because I can imagine that what he's saying actually I would say that a lot of what he talks
about is we could be talking about the same thing today I mean at the last verse but where he
kind of talks about is the way forward that he found but
starts like this just look at people and their quarrels
and I will speak of my dismay in the way that I was shaken seeing people thrash about like fish and
little water right there is this way that we people that thrashing about and fish a little
water there's this agitation whether it's obvious with their body
movements but there's a agitation that's wanting to lash out or to harm or blame or you know
something like this there's this quality of you know efficient little water has this little desperation to it or it's
feeling like it's not going to survive in some ways people feel like this often
too it's not so much that they're not going to survive but something in them feels threatened
and so they're thrashing about like fish and little water
I will speak of my dismay in the way that I was shaken seeing people thrash
about like fish in little water and seen them feuding with each other
I became afraid quite something somebody who's becomes
the Buddha says I became afraid
maybe I'll just say that I had some neighbors that reliably at 9 00 PM the yelling
would start and it was quite something it was like in the summer especially when we all have our windows open and
they were close enough to me wow I couldn't you know understand the words but I didn't need to
it was made me so anxious that night just to like hear all the yelling and
the yelling and the I felt like oh I don't know what's happening over there but it's pretty reliably almost every
night for years so it's just so heartbreaking
and it's sad too so when the Buddha to be he's talking
about seeing them feuding with each other I became afraid yeah maybe you've had that same
experience too or something about when we see
even like we see like on social media like people are thrashing around and
yelling at each other and you know there's some real ugly stuff that happens there there's this kind of
feeling too of I don't know is it fear but it's something like that
contraction and dismay maybe like this word of dismay
so the Buddha says seeing them feuding with each other I became afraid
I felt discontent at seeing only conflict to the very end
so he felt like everywhere he could see maybe I don't know what it means exactly to the end but in my mind Imagining the
end like of time like he couldn't see that it was about to finish like it was just gonna happen all the time and maybe
the end in terms of space like doesn't matter where he had been and with whom he was with there was plenty of conflict
same as it is now I felt discontented seeing only conflict
to the very end then but now here's where they'll shift
I saw an arrow here hard to see
embedded in the heart quite something
hard to see right didn't notice it but notice that there was this Arrow like a dart something like stabbing in
the heart pierced by this Arrow people Dash about
in all directions when the arrow is pulled out
they don't run and they don't sink
when the arrow is pulled out they don't run and they don't sink
they don't run and they don't sink is a reference to later or in another discourse
somebody asks the Buddha how did you cross the flood like how did you get through all this morass of difficulties
of life and with this metaphor of the flood like maybe a raging River
somebody asks them how did you get across like to the other side where things are safe and
um spacious and free he says I got Across The Other Side by
not halting and by not struggling so he's saying here when the arrow is
pulled out it's the same thing but they don't run and they don't sink
so it's a way to get to the other side where there's freedom and peace and
safety I appreciate this very much because the
Buddha is pointing to something that he discovered in himself he's not saying well okay you know all
you guys you have this problem and you gotta fix it he's saying you know I was distressed
and with that I've discovered that actually there was something I was contributing to this
this Arrow and not only is he saying that he is saying that other people can pull it out
too it's not just something that he did and of course we might even say that his
lifetime of teaching was about pulling out this Arrow
so we might ask well what is this Arrow how do we pull it out
how can we put an end to this conflict
so maybe before I answer that I'll tell One More Story this uh one little more uh discourse that also comes out of this
suit does this is a well-known one I think uh probably all of you who have heard this
it's there's a version of this story and a number of different religious traditions
so not just Buddhism I think from India it's in a number of
different Traditions I kind of like this idea that there's just this wisdom that was just being shared
and you know different Traditions kind of Incorporated it into their scriptures
and there's something about the version I haven't read it in any other religious tradition but the details of
this version I'll point out at the end kind of like makes a difference than the more sanitized version that I've heard
in Derma talks when I went to actually read I thought oh this is an important difference here
so there's this uh King when we might think
of a king as just somebody who has Authority there's this king who asks his servant
and we might even think just serve into somebody who obeys the authority of somebody else
could be a worker or whomever it is the king as the servant to round up
persons who are blind from birth so people had never seen
and when the servant had done so the king asked the servant to show the blind
people an elephant elephants huge these are just huge so
big and powerful so to some so of these blind people he
showed the elephant's head to some of the elephant's ear to some of the
elephant's Tusk to some the elephant's trunk you can just imagine where this is going right if you feel if you're a
blind person and you feel a Tusk you're going to have one idea you have a trunk you're going to have a different idea
so the body the foot the hindquarters the tail and even the tuft at the end of
the tail so you can imagine where this is going right that everybody just gets feels one
little portion of this giant elephant and then
the king asked the blind people what is an elephant like
of course somebody says it's like a water jar it's like a basket it's like
an arrow it's like a pull it's like a store room it's like a post it's like a mortar it's like a pestle it's like a
broom these are all different things
but then here's what comes next so they're saying an elephant is like this
it's not like that but it's not like that it's like this so they get to fighting all these different the blind
people are fighting amongst each other and then this they uh fought each other
with Fists so they couldn't see one another but they were flailing around and like it's
punching each other and the King was delighted with the spectacle technical so this was like
just for the amusement of this person so maybe unlike the Buddha who's like when
he's seen the conflict is feeling afraid and upset here's somebody who's like
just doing it for sport but you know if we do some of that right
maybe there's a part of us we do this too maybe there's some uh athletic events
that are a little bit like this or maybe there's a politics that are like this
right there's this way in which we kind of like set up this conflict and it's entertainment
this is even like part of uh about like so many like reality TV right
this kind of stuff this is so the people became quarrelsome
disputatious and wrangling wounding each other with verbal daggers so they're
calling each other names and and then at the end of this then there's
a little bit of a discourse in the Buddha says in the same way
some religious practitioners so-called are deeply attached to their own views
people who only see one side of thing engage in quarrels and disputes
the people who only gauge in one side of things of course we have views
but it's something different to have views and to be holding on to them so tightly that you have to quarrel and get
in fights with others and try to convince others that it's you know we're right and they're wrong
so this last story kind of with the elephant points to this tendency that we often think that we know the truth or we
know what's really happening when Only We Know a piece of the story
often we don't know what's going on inside somebody else
maybe sometimes when we're in the middle of a conflict we aren't thinking about like the bigger picture like
can you imagine if how the these blind people would have
how they would have reacted if the person who was showing them the elephant said okay so
now I'm doing this so we can do this entertainment for the king and I'm gonna tell everybody else something different
and then we're going to ask you to say what it is so if they had like the bigger picture
they would probably say I'm not going to do that I'm going to go talk to these other people and maybe we will just talk
together what is it like or something so this idea that we often think we have
the bigger picture but we don't or maybe we even have a really big
picture but we're still just holding on but maybe we're just missing one integral
piece of information that maybe we wouldn't even recognize like from our
background our social location our history like we might be biased to think
about things one way and not even recognize that different people think different ways of course they do
how can they not people from different family stories
cultures whatever it is
so maybe we I'll point out that we all have
distorted views not only do we not have the big picture but some of the views that we have are
distorted about the world and about ourselves
that's what we might think that we want to hold on to them but how accurate are they
that's where you might think that we're the ones who see clearly and these other people they're just obviously confused
or just don't know or we might have this idea is that we are the ones that are upstanding and
they are not you know us and Them me and everybody else
or we might have the sense that we are the aggrieved and they are the transgressors
we so often have these views but is this the whole picture and what are we not seeing
what are we not seeing and here's one thing that death this
little exercise that I this was offered as um
maybe I won't give all the Gory details but here's something that an exercise that I did that was a little bit of an
eye-opener for me a realization about oh some of these
views that I didn't even know I was holding that's kind of holding on to them tightly
unknowingly so here's it just starts with this
and just an exercise that we can do together so what are the groups that we belong to
of course we belong to groups so you might say that are you an
employee of a certain company and are you in a particular division within that company
to that group or maybe you're interested in a particular Hobby
belong to that group maybe those hobbyists or you have a profession or maybe you belong to that group and
are you maybe you're involved or interested in the Arts and maybe you identify with a particular style or
school or genre of the Arts you know the violin is better than the
piano horsey or something like this maybe you have this certain
philosophical ideas and there's these different schools of philosophy certain Buddhist philosophy and Buddhist
tradition as well maybe this idea well you know this tradition is distinct and different than the other
traditions and I belong to this one or maybe you know sports teams or maybe
even brand names people or PC
Android or iPhone and maybe there's like this uh affiliation with wanting to be
with uh one of these or maybe citizen of him Nation
City Community neighborhood we all kind of like belong to these
groups a number of them maybe some of them we
don't identify with very strongly but we can ask ourselves
in what way is the identity of this group related to another group in some way
is there a rival team is there a competitor
and I remember like wow when I was in Corporate America this the department I
was in we had to partner with this other department in my department we were always complaining
about that other department and then as a company we were always like the arrival was this other company so
there's this little bit of conflict right that's kind of just got set up as
part of like being part of this group or do we have this like this common
enemies for lack of a better word that's you know kind of that we're all
that provides some of the cohesiveness in this group so there's a way in which there's this
um underlying beliefs just shows up in so many ways that like sow the seeds for
conflict sow the seeds for US versus them
me versus you me against the world
and so there's this um quote from Michelle de montania
it's a French philosopher I think in the 16th century he says
I consider myself an average person except for the fact except for the fact
that I consider myself an average person right we all kind of think that somehow
we're a little bit better than average I think there's kind of this recognition right you know even these hundreds of
years ago so of course there is nothing inherent
in any person nothing that makes them fundamentally
our enemy or competitor or something we need to be opposed
and yet we are so you know easily kind of kind of fall into that fall into that
kind of thinking and so this these are just cognitive biases that we have I
think probably all humans have them and one person a person could even say that
there's some evolutionary advantage to having some cohesiveness within a group
so we can take care of each other but clinging to our views contributes to
conflict clinging to anything
leads to suffering of course it does we know this clinging is not the weight of freedom
but sometimes we have these views that we don't even recognize that we have
we aren't even aware of and so
what can we do what are some ways in which we might be able to work with this
maybe I'll judge art with something this that uh Gill said
a number of years ago I think he might have said it more recently also and this idea of
be still and look upon everything kindly
there's something kind of like very simple be still and look upon everything kindly
so be still is pointing to is there a way that we can stop the thrush in about like fish out of water
which is you know exaggerated but there is sometimes this agitation the same
sense of agitation so can we quiet the mind
soothe the heart so that we can see a bigger picture
otherwise you know we're our view is limited definitely
can we quiet the mind so that we can check in with our experience
and notice how agitated we are sometimes when we're disagitated we're lost in the
agitation and don't really have any awareness of that I know this
happens for me sometimes like when those I had those neighbors that were yelling like sometimes I would just not even be
aware that I was agitated but I would just be agitated
trying to escape from the sound
and then this idea to look upon everything kindly
maybe we need to have to be still in order that we can look upon things kindly
and there's so many different ways we might interpret this idea of look upon things kindly but one of them is can we
soften our heart and soften our mind can we open up
whatever is kind of like feeling constricted
of course there's a few ways that we can do that
one is to just check in with the body and to relax the body of course the body and the mind are
connected sometimes it's easiest to start with the body
stretch be do something comfortable do some long deep breaths or long
exhales these are ways to kind of soften the body these kind of like soothe the nervous system also
then when the nervous system starts to calm down a little bit then we can see a bigger picture and maybe soften and open
the heart a little bit what would it be like
if in a conflict even if it's something that's subtle like this idea of identifying with a one group
that's opposed to another group what would it be like to give this other
group or the other individual a victory yeah you're right you know that's
actually a good point uh you're sorry yeah you know what I
changed my mind I can see what you're saying now oh I didn't realize that okay I didn't
know that other information so now that what you're saying makes more sense
we're saying you know I'm not entirely convinced but I can see that you're convinced so help me understand
these different ways you might maybe like give them a victory so that then that kind of like just brings the
tension down and everybody can maybe with some relaxation there can be
some seeing the bigger picture
I think many of us know this first from the dhamapada
hatred never ends through hatred by non-hate alone does it end
this is an ancient truth course hatred never ends through hatred
hatred is maybe is a strong word but it's pointing to right conflict isn't
going to end with conflict
where is it going to end why not with us
so sometimes we have these cognitive have these biases of like me against the
world US versus them that way don't even aren't even aware of they just seem so
familiar that we don't even question them so much about this practice is starting
to see some of these underlying beliefs that we have about ourselves about others about the
world and and just start to hold them lightly
hold them like that okay this is what makes sense to me now
this is my provisional understanding something like this rather than you're just holding on tightly
and then here's an excerpt from a poem a short poem by Rosemary traumer
the title of this poem gives it away it says Dear moment that wasn't what I
thought it was so here's a little excerpt
thank you for blessing me with reality for showing me when I'm guilty of what my friend calls cognitive slippage
it's like stuffing a big scoop of Wasabi into my mouth thinking it's guacamole
the Mind believes what it wants to believe until it's shown otherwise
so this idea right big spoonful of Wasabi is really uncomfortable horse radish
that's you know just clears the scientist said it's very uncomfortable to have a mouthful of this especially if
you think it's guacamole something smooth and delicious and
so it's uh uncomfortable mission that it's uncomfortable
but it doesn't mean that we can't do it and it doesn't mean that that's it's not a way to greater and greater freedom and
ease not only for ourselves but for others for those people that we are in conflict
with so one way to work with conflict is to
be still and look upon everything kindly
of course to look upon things kindly means that we you know have this warm-heartedness
and sometimes we feel disconnected from our warm-heartedness
mindfulness practice supports this loving kindness practice supports our feeling connected both to ourselves and
to a sense of warm-heartedness
but also to be still I point to are there ways that we can be
more aware of our beliefs some of these underlying beliefs that we
might have can we be curious and maybe inquire about when we find ourselves in
Conflict just even ask ourselves what beliefs am I holding here that puts
me in so much conflict why why can't I kind of like hold this with open hands
still setting boundaries between appropriate and inappropriate behavior we're not being passive we're not
letting people walk all over us but we're not forcing our beliefs on
others we're holding them like this as opposed to like this
so maybe we could be curious about the beliefs and the opinions that
we have why why does that make sense to us
what's underneath them what's underlying them
because our beliefs are resistant to change and if we don't have this sense of curiosity or this willingness to
inquire they'll just stay embedded and they'll just be conflict after
conflict
so be still and look upon things kindly as a way to work with conflicts
to help become aware of some of these views that we have to help create the conditions for
conflicts with others and I'm using this word conflict of course right in a really General way just
mild irritation to really just you know giant as big as
you can imagine so maybe I'll stop there and then open
it up to see if there's some questions or comments
foreign by the verse from the dhamapada
about only by non-hate the other religion says you have to love
thy neighbor and that's a lot to ask can you talk about the difference and
why not hating my neighbor is enough yeah yeah and sometimes translators will say
call say do this love they will but the Paulie is not hate and I like this very
much for the same reason can you imagine why it is why it's uh just not hating is uh
good enough okay well
that I don't have to come up with the love that somehow by non-hating
by putting aside hey setting that aside there's space inside me and the love emerges naturally
rather than me having to do it very nice
very nice very nice I heard I appreciate this very much and
I would say that's definitely or what it's there but but you know love is uh
is a tall order right this I think often when we hear Like Love Thy Neighbor
especially like when there's these when we're having difficulties it feels uh
like we can't relate to that it feels like a disconnect like how am I going to get there when I'm over here with this
real anger or hatred or something it's harder than that because it's not just love thy neighbor it's love thy neighbor
as myself I see yeah so yeah yeah right
so so non-hate is ends with this conflict here right
so it's not that it's yeah it's just the ending of conflict it's more like
honoring and respecting which isn't the same thing as loving it's kind of like okay this is what I just I'm Not In
conflict with them as opposed to loving them like myself or thyself yeah
yeah thank you yes back here
thank you I think for me the concept of not hating someone
what it means to me very deeply and it took me a long time to figure out is hating someone the amount of energy it
takes and the amount it takes away from me and my essence
it just is not worth the conflict or the hatred whatever you might call it yeah I'm not even thinking
about having a positive love or for that person I just don't want to be depleted
anymore yeah and not to be tangled up right when there's a hater then you're tangled up
with them in some kind of way and yeah yeah thank you thank you
foreign about your neighbors and
said that they that that went on for years
something in me just like I'd have sadness yeah
did it ever turn out okay and they moved away
and in the winter we couldn't hear so well because our windows were closed but in the summer right we have our widows
open and we could hear so I don't know maybe they got along better in the winter but I don't know I didn't can
hear um I used to drive a cab in San Francisco
and once I was driving along and looked out the window
if it helps to set the scene it was on Sutter Street around Hyde
and going westbound north side of the street and there was two people a man
and a woman walking along side by side and yelling at each other
bitterly okay and you can see this was a very sustained thing
and I looked at my passenger in the back seat and said
that just so completely unnecessary yeah and he he com he agreed right off the
bat it's quite something that you remember this right all these years later because
they touched something it's kind of like what the Buddha was pointing to you also it touches something when we see this
yeah yeah they could just if they're not happy with each other
just part and go different ways but for some reason people don't do that
he's having to follow on on that summer 1973 I was going on with the
woman that lived in an apartment and the apartment above her there was a couple that fought all the time
and it turns out the story was they fought all the time so they got divorced
and then they missed each other so they got married again and moved in and still
fought so it made me think you know there's something
you know it's kind of like sometimes people like their patterns
so much that it isn't like not having it is worse
than having the conflict for some so it's I I think there's
certainly a place for compassion yeah yeah and also
seeing that it's not just them that certainly there's there's ways in which I seek conflict
not quite not like going to a boxing match but you know there is a I can see myself a
tendency leaning towards that occasionally there's a little Zing of energy and it
comes with that yeah yeah I could see you know why we do this right yeah
thank you Jim 1973 so you remember all these years
later also read this yeah well it's just I mean it was so
amazing to me that they actually got divorced went
apart and then got married again so they could be back together in that same
Dynamic and it was like yeah there's there's some valence there there's some yeah
something maybe psychologists have something to say about that but
thank you thank you it's like movie stars right attire during this yeah
hmm any last comments
I think cater here has a
what you're saying makes me think of my family my birth family my mother my
sisters an aggressive communication is kind of
the norm so I've tended to not spend time with them because I don't like it
um but I've I've learned that
I've learned to not take it personally it took a lot I've learned that I learned that it's just it really has
absolutely nothing to do with me it's how they need to they it's all them and how they need to communicate
and sometimes I don't like to speak aggressively but sometimes it's like
they don't feel matte or hurt or seen unless you raise your voice yeah yeah
you know so sometimes it's like it's just meeting the energy sometimes you know it's like
it's like a dance you know it's like an involvement it's like now I know that you see me yeah which is not how I like
to be um but I can also see that it's
just meeting them right it's just like that's what they need to know
oh okay you hear me and you see me and you know and so then there becomes this
challenge to be able to communicate in that without actually then it's really easy to to without actually becoming
angry right there's no there doesn't have to be any angry right it's just meeting the expression the mode of
expression um submitting the energy and not having it
to be angry yeah or ill because it's really easy when you get back in that mode for that old habit energy to arise
right yeah so it's a it's very interesting dance to just notice how people communicate
and then not take it personally and then kind of what is this situation need
so I don't avoid it as much I I would really was you know because they're my family they're my birth family and I
don't want to um yeah I've learned well sometimes we need to get together
but it's not my personal preference right yeah it's interesting the
compelling nature of habit energy thank you thank you
wishing you all a wonderful rest of the evening can I