so good morning welcome welcome and wherever you are on this planet
maybe it's not morning but uh sending warm wishes your direction
so today I will continue on this theme of these letters from Mara
these uh you know completely made up letters but
I appreciate them they have some Whimsy in them as well as you know some truth maybe a little bit of uncomfortable
truth into them but as you know that will begin with a
guided meditation so
we establishing yourself in a posture that feels comfortable
for some of you that will be sitting whether it's on a cushion or in a chair
from the couch
and establishing yourself in a posture that feels comfortable and feels grounded
and if you are sitting feeling that uprightness of the posture
without stiffness but an uprightness so ease
and trying to think of a synonym for uprightness but if you have one you
could insert it into your mind
and then letting the awareness sense into the body the bodily experience
right now
letting the awareness inhabit the body
and what would it be like to let this awareness fill and
encompass the whole body
the quality of spaciousness
spaciousness and ease
right tuning into being sensitive to
the experience of the body
however the body is right now
might be restless might be tired
might be a little bit achy maybe a lot achy
maybe even some numbness not quite sure how the body is
however it is can we notice
letting the sense of the body reveal itself to you
we don't have to go out and capture it it's allowing it to be seen noticed
felt
because
and then however the mind is right now the emotions the thoughts the images
whatever it is can we also
allow that to reveal itself
to be known to be noticed
to be known noticed with the quality of gentleness and that
spaciousness
maybe even some warmth
without putting pressure
on what's being known allowing this
gentle holding quality of spaciousness and ease
allowing experiences to show themselves reveal themselves
and can we wish ourselves well extending some kind-heartedness towards
ourselves this body is heart this mind
wishing it well wishing yourself well
with some warm-heartedness
and then if you haven't already resting the attention on the sensations
of breathing bringing this ease this spaciousness this warm-heartedness
to noticing the experience of inhales and exhales
and when the mind wanders as its apt to do
no need to make a story judge ourselves
we just very simply gently Begin Again
foreign
to do this practice with an attitude of warmth and care
sometimes there can be a little bit of harshness that Creeps in
when we notice the mind is wandered or lost in thought
or story can we even have one-heartedness towards
the harshness
foreign
foreign foreign
[Music]
hello it's lovely to practice together so nice to sit in community even if it's right
this kind of modern version of community remember and chat boxes on YouTube and these
kinds of things so thank you for are sitting together
and I'd like to continue on this theme that I've been doing this week about letters from Mara
to leaders of his armies so he has 10 armies I'm not going to go through all
10. and he sends letters to each of them encouraging them to continue in their
efforts in obstructing or getting in the way of or preventing people from finding
freedom so I'm not also going to worry myself about what exactly is Mara I'm I'm
holding it right now as a rhetorical device a literary device that's getting
used to convey something and what's getting conveyed is
that we might consider these I don't know maybe these experiences
things that prevent us from finding freedom and this way of uh including this
character Mara is a way in that can um depersonalize it make it feel less
like oh this is a problem that we have or some failing that we have or something along those lines
and so lineage up in Arrow River Hermitage
Monastery in Northern Ontario and of course in Canada wrote these letters kind of written more
in modern times where Mara is sending letters to the leaders of his armies
trying to um encourage these armies to continue
preventing people from finding freedom and maybe I'll just say this a small
little aside is that I heard I don't know if it's true but I heard that there's an effective way to stop smoking
in teenagers was to uh rather than show them the causes of smoking show them
their lungs or something like that that they portrayed these an image of these
middle-aged white men sitting around a table cackling with how much money they
were making how they were getting filthy rich off of getting other people addicted to
tobacco products and somehow it was that that activated this inner Rebel in
people and said I don't want to be part of that here I'm going to show them I'm not
going to get addicted or I'm going to kick my addiction and I admit to something a little bit like that for me
too and these letters tomorrow or letters from Mara that makes me like
it's such a different way like it's such a shift in this orientation away from oh
there's something wrong with me I don't have it quite right to this oh no wait I
don't want to be part of this I don't have to be part of this so without taking things too literally
what I'm pointing to right here is this completely shift in orientation away
from I'm doing something wrong to this depersonalized idea of like oh
no I can do things different Okay so
um today I'd like to talk about this letter from Mara to the leaders of the
army of malice and upstancy there's maybe different ways we could
translate that but I'm gonna go with what ajampurnadamo has done from uh Mara to the leaders of malice
and upstancy and I'm excerpting this letter and it goes like this
it's your duty to see to it that beings fall into the
habits of aversion it will anger hatred in spite it's your job
to develop mental proliferation around any unhappy feeling tones
if they're being being in question is not mindfully aware of their own mental processes and few of them are even
marginally aware then we can turn this simple unpleasant feeling tone into a
whole complex of aversion and resentment
the raw unpleasant feeling tone is a momentary thing of little significance in and of itself but
what fun we can have with it because being engrossed in unhappiness
or anger beings are unable to see things clearly
they cannot see their true situation and they cannot work out and Escape
so we have a whole wide spectrum of emotions to work with there's the very
mild and temporary flicker of aversion towards the driver ahead of you on the
freeway there's that smoldering resentment towards the inconsiderate boss at work
and there's that bitter lifelong ethnic hatred that can inflame entire nations all of
these are Christopher rml and all of these are manifestations of the same
thing but we must be vigilant
against that one credible antidote
that is Universal loving-kindness this is the one force which we cannot
stand so stop it before it is cultivated discredit as a weakness
but little do they know that it requires real courage
to practice Universal Goodwill
so this whole idea of loving kindness sometimes we might think like oh loving
kindness that's a that's what you do when you can't do the real practice like somehow it's this lesser practice or a
booby Prize or something like this or maybe sometimes when we talk about meta loving kindness we get the sense of
oh we're just pretending to be really nice and like everyone or let's just paint the whole world pink
or we'll act like Pollyanna or something like that that's these are some of the ideas that people might have when they
hear this word of loving kindness or meta but loving kindness Mehta is not
that it has a real strength to it
it's not a false and flimsy thing it does have the strength
but the strength has a softness to it so in some ways Manta loving kindness has
this Infinite Strength and this infinite softness which is such a beautiful combination
so menta loving kindness is different than what we might think of as love love
is this beautiful thing and we need it in our lives and it's part of the human experience but mentosis well
wishing it's this deep friendliness but it has this quality of boundlessness
and unconditionality and it's these two qualities boundlessness and unconditionality that
distinguish it from what we usually think of when we say the word love so boundlessness when we look at our
life when we look at our relationships and we look at the movement of care in our life
we will see that our care our well-wishing is actually bounded
that we tend to care for those that are immediately around us our partners our family our friends hopefully ourselves
too and that's perfectly natural this is what humans do
so boundlessness not having any limitations is a really lofty ideal
but that's the direction that it moves that meta moves is this
direction to No Limits to boundlessness
and in the same way unconditionality is a quality of loving
kindness because if we're honest sometimes we might say to a partner or
whomever I love you but sometimes there's this quiet little I love you
when dot dot dot you know like fill in the blank or I'll love you if you change
a little bit I love you except when you do that thing that drives me crazy here or even I
can't love me the way that I am I love me myself as soon as you know something
else happens this is a normal part of the human experience as well you don't have to
beat ourselves up about it but meta loving kindness as this quality
of unconditionality no exceptions like no conditions
whatsoever and again this is a movement of menta
and we're going to this direction that there's this question of deserving or
not deserving just stops making sense it's just well wishing Goodwill
so this direction that we're going with meta is one of boundlessness and unconditionality and that distinguishes
it from this maybe this different uh way we might experience love
and it's also these qualities that help provide that antidote to ill will this
antidote to malice and also kind of put in these from Mara this upstancy this
um getting stuck in one way and like nope things are this way and they're not that way
because if we think about it both ill and obstacy and all these different flavors of it they are very tight
and contracted and they have this story often associated with them I can't believe
they did this or they don't deserve Goodwill because of that
so this movement towards boundlessness and unconditionality
is the opposite movement of this contraction and separation and this dug
in the heels kind of a Feeling so loving kindness is in some ways it's
this um non-abandonment or non-rejection
this means not abandoning or rejecting ourselves
sometimes it's not so easy and there's a way that when we're lost
and ill will or obstacy that we're like cutting ourselves off cutting ourselves off from our hearts
and rejecting others or building a wall around our hearts
and so there's a way in which when we're practicing loving kindness we are reclaiming
reclaiming maybe that of which we have cast aside or which we have cut ourselves off from maybe all those
unexpectable aspects of ourselves which of course show up as unexpected
unacceptable aspects of others too
so maybe I'll end with this idea that the practice of loving kindness is not
an effort to convince ourselves of anything it's not an effort to pretend or demand or plead or
about some you know the loving kindness show up instead it's this practice of
tapping into something that's already inside of us
that already knows about warmth and care and respect
it's not a form of positive thinking it's it's a way of focusing on Goodwill
instead of ill will it's a way of inclining the mind and
heart towards something inside of us that already cares
that already is has warmth and this is where the strength and the
softness of ill will I'm sorry of Goodwill shows up of loving kindness of
manta I'm not going to talk about love and kindness practice per se there's a number of different ways we can practice
it and maybe you already have your own favorite way of practicing
but I just want to emphasize the strength and the softness and this movement towards boundlessness
and unconditionality that loving kindness and mental practice have and in this way it's a real
antidote to me this ill will or aversion that always comes along with these stories
and I don't want to say that you know there isn't Injustice and there isn't
oppression and there isn't lots of terrible things happening in the world I am not saying that
I am saying as a practice can we tune into
this that inside of us that already knows this beautiful quality
of warmth and Care respect
so with that I wish you all a wonderful rest of the day thank you