so good morning Gail good morning good morning everyone hello and hello for those of you who are with
us online and um
thank you for coming I think I'm still in this um maybe under the influence of the
pandemic of appreciating when we come together more than I did before it's nice to be sitting here and be together
in community and so thank you for coming and um
so the topic I want to talk about is one that was inspired by the recent Retreat
I sat I did a self Retreat for a month uh and uh by myself and
and um and one of the things that I found fascinating was among other things was a
kind of an investigation or attention to thinking itself and rather
than thinking thinking that thinking is wrong or bad to investigate it to see what was going on
we're thinking and in some deeper way and uh and you know one of the things that I've
known up some time at least in my mind is that there are different
um what I call levels of thinking different kinds of kinds of thinking
it's not like all thinking are the same and um and so to slow down and stop and
take a look at the thinking we do whether it's thinking in images or thinking in words and start
distinguishing the different uh categories of thinking the different
modes of thinking that we have because some of the modes are not so good for us
and sometimes because sometimes those predominate for some people thinking
itself gets a negative reputation in some circles you know it's almost as if
all thinking is bad but thinking is an important part of meditation and thinking can be
generative it can be useful it can be supportive of meditation and supportive
of life and the thinking can be deadening thinking can be the opposite of
supporting life it's kind of deadening it undermines us and and the unfortunate thing is that maybe
for not a few people in this modern world that we live in maybe the ancient world too
um the something's going to skew with the way that we think in the way that we get preoccupied in thoughts which are uh
debilitating undermining and so to be able to see and recognize that there are different modes of
thinking is for some people it's a new idea and uh and it kind of opens the door
to beginning to live a little different and maybe exercise some degree of choice
about how we think what we think about and just as important some choice about
how we relate to our thinking the attitude we have about thinking when we're thinking
so it's an important topic of mindfulness and it can be explored in meditation
certainly and it could be explored in daily life and you know and all kinds of
situations I've had a fair amount of interesting kind of discoveries around
thinking while driving uh because if I had the radio off or not
doing other things talking to people that um I find that if I can drive safely while actually maybe more safely
if I'm kind of a little bit tracking my thinking rather than being lost in
thoughts which um twice in in this time living in 30 years I've lived in the peninsula I was
driving on 280. at that big Highway nearby here and and missed my exit
because I was thinking a lot about something I was kind of absorbed and I think I think
I was driving safe enough it was I was tracking you know what was going on around me but not well enough
to know where I was and where I was supposed to get off so that was a little bit of a wake-up call you know wow you
could that's something so um but I find that you know driving
is interesting place when I go for walks I like to hike a lot or go for walks and when I walk alone that's an awesome
interesting interesting time to explore this world of thinking and what's going on and if we don't do that for some of us
thinking takes over they could have a design work on automatic pilot and they're thinking just kind of she gets
churns away without any question and and without any um
Choice involved it's like thinking has a mind of its own and we better just kind of
follow along or some people are so strongly wedded to their thinking that
it's almost like who they are as a person is their thinking self is their thoughts
and for some people it's actually frightening to stop thinking because
then they're not they're not anybody they're not telling themselves a story about who they are tailings having
fantasies or conversations where they are a player in it reassuring themselves or some not reassuring themselves but
still kind of making a self out of it and that's one of the reasons why some people think a lot because it's a way of
Shoring up some self-concept that is has become important for feeling safe in the
world or feeling successful in the world or feeling somehow compensating for how difficult this
world is so in the teachings of the Buddha
there are two modes of thinking I mean there's many modes of thinking but in
the in the the in the in the kind of the what I would call the top level of
thinking the more active thinking there is two modes
and one mode in the ancient language is called papancha and papancha sometimes is translated
into English as proliferating thinking so thinking that just proliferates and has a life of its own just spreads and
Spins and you know creates universes of of ideas and things
and sometimes I like to call that discursive thinking and discursive
thinking would I would you know you're giving yourself a discourse or you're having a conversation with someone or
with yourself or you're involved in commentary or making living some kind of
Storytelling mind a fantasy mind planning the future
um you know the future is completely unknown so kind of involved in planning and it's very active active and it's
what what some people might call um mental constructs we're constructing things and ideas
and some people spend an inordinate amount of time in this world of papancha of discursive thinking of of the world
of constructs and the other is the Buddha doesn't call
it this I'll tell you what he says that would be in a few minutes sometimes I like to think of it as deep thinking
so the first discussion I would I kind of like to think of is shallow thinking and the other is deep
sometimes I like calling it contemplative thinking I don't know what associations you have the word
contemplative but I have very warm feelings for it it's a kind of you know deep kind of spiritual connection that
we feel might feel and that from that comes a kind of deeper kind of reflection about things that
and the important distinction between these two and this is one of the really important points I want to make today
is when we're looking and paying attention to how we're thinking
is to discover what's the source of our thinking from where does thinking come
so the papancha thinking that we do this discursive thinking the Buddha Likens to
a puppeteer so a puppeteer is above the puppet show
and um and you know in kind of up above high above and has these long strings
and it's pulling over all the little puppets to get them to do things so this is the thinking mind that's kind
of up in the head the control tower in the head and um and it has all these tentacles
all these strings that go into our muscles into our nerves everywhere all
over the body and if we're caught up in that World um uh all kinds of big and small muscles
are being pulled the shoulders go up the forehead goes gets maybe crunched up
the jaw gets tight the belly gets pulled in sometimes and it's fascinating if
some of you maybe have done this in meditation of being relatively calm and settled and content and minding your own
business and meditation and then your mind the Puppeteer maybe
just has this like really
Big Bang thought and then the energy is there you know
and you've been now you've been ignited with anger and fury or fear and all
these things have happened in your body oh you know how could that person have said that then it was 50 years ago but
how could they how could they have said it and uh and the Puppeteer has you know
come back from vacation you know and suddenly it's you know then then you know the puppeteers pulling all these
strings and emotional strings and muscular strings and postural strings all kinds of things go
on into play and and some people live in that world
and to call it the padura call it the puppeteer means that it's not really Who You Are
even though it's the only you that you might know that you've been living your whole
lifetime but no that's not who you are there's something different the deep thinking
the contemplative thinking the Buddha Associates with something he calls the
Yoni and the Yoni in Pali I think in Sanskrit as well means Womb
and I think it's meant to be a metaphor as opposed to literally the womb but it's a wonderful kind of a metaphor of a
place that's gen it's generative something in which something grows and develops and emerges
uh just States and so rather than being a puppeteer is pulling strings it's something that is
uh flowing something that is evolving something generative within that spreads
out and it can feel very different sometimes Some Kind of Wonderful creative thinking
or thinking that if you're kind of sometimes in love or something with some
place or person or thing and you're kind of in a revery kind of thinking about it nicely it has a very different Source
than this puppeteer unless the love has a lot of desire in it
and uh you know and then maybe it's back into the Puppeteer mode you know we're
all you know fear and worry and desires and ambition and all kinds of things
and um but this deeper Wellspring within and that's a Wellspring and you can feel
how differently it's going to emerging and flowing upward and outward filling
us and sometimes it's delicious uh thinking can be if we're in this other
mode of being and um and uh and that's where kind of wisdom
can occur the this uh this papancha
is the world of two things it's world world of often of clinging grasping
attachment of some kind where we're driven there's a drivenness there's a a push and that might be connected to fear
it might be connected to desires it might be connected to anger it might be
connected to insecurity all kinds of things that it might be what would we call the attachment that kind of kind of
is fueling it or it's fueled with what in Buddhism is
called selfing that where we're kind of the part of who
we are that's not necessarily kind of who we are naturally in a sense but who
we are as a construct how we've learned to kind of create an image an idea a
role presentation Persona that we want to present to the
world and um and I remember when I first came to Buddhism when I was about 20 or so 21
and Buddha Center went to the Zen Center in San Francisco to visit a number of times
and um and it was a bit of a shock to be talking to some of the most senior
practitioners there have been practicing for a long time because it turned out
that I was kind of constantly playing the social game of presenting myself
as I wanted people to see me so I was con you know it wasn't just a construct in my thinking mind it was a
construct in my behavior that I was trying to reinforce and my friends
they kind of participated and probably were all doing it for each other and you know cooperating
but uh at the Zen Center these people had meditated a lot they didn't react I
didn't get any response they weren't going to play that game and so they were this mirror
and I loved it it's one of the reasons I went back to live at Sun Center I felt
so much uh that's where I wanted to live I wanted to live in a place where I could see myself do these funny things
odd things because I didn't feel there was much Integrity in them it wasn't coming from a deep place that I wanted
to come from so um so there's often a lot of selfings self
ideas and if you spend some time looking at your papancha your discursive thought
where your mind is mostly spinning stories and ideas and conversations and what it's doing
chances are relatively high that you're one of the main players in it that
you're not very far away and and it's probably fairly fair to say
that for most of us if anybody was walking next to us repeating themselves
as much as we're repeating ourselves in our thinking we'd be begging them to stop
it might even be worse you know like you know you yell at them like please
but uh but one of the you know we can have the same thoughts repeat the same thing you know over and over again it's
amazing at least I don't know I shouldn't speak for all of you maybe some of you are always brand new creative thought thinkers for every
thought you have but but the but why don't we get bored with it
and uh and one of the reasons is we're the main character or important character in it and who we are is
important and I don't want to take away the sense of importance but sometimes that sense
of importance for maybe for good historical reasons or current reasons it's a part of the
finding out how to be safe in the world or how to be successful in the world or how to belong in this world and this
discursive thinking is kind of become the mode for doing it
however it can come along with a lot of emotions and moods and attitudes which
um like like fear anxiety with anger and
hatred and with despair with with discouragement without with uh it can
come with uh strong ambition and come with a lot of conceit of all kinds
and um and so the in what it means is that if you're having this those same thoughts over and over again
you're actually reinforcing that mood on yourself the influence not necessarily of the
thinking but the influence of the attitude the mood the emotions that come
along with it are constantly kind of uh being registered from influencing
shaping Who We Are and that's one of the big dangers of this discursive thinking is its
emotional impact on us and as I think some psychologists have pointed out something like a high
percentage of people who are depressed are depressed because of the rumination
their them the same kind of thoughts over and over again and so there's a whole form of therapy called cognitive
behavioral therapy where they they actually look at the nature of the thoughts and what you're thinking and
and helping people to think in better ways that don't undermine their psychological Health maybe even their
physical health and so this discursive thinking is not more many times is really not good for
us and it doesn't often do a lot of good if it's repetitive you know driven over and
over again um and um and so as I've said sometimes here I used to do a lot of planning
thoughts I was anxious about what was going to happen so I thought if I planned and thought about it I just you
know I didn't think I think I just did it automatically it wasn't deciding to do it
and then very very slowly took a long time it began to dawn on me that my ability
to predict the future was dismal and and I would do all this planning and
thinking with an image of what it was going to be like in the future and be ready or something
and it was seldom that way and after all slow their Donna McGill
you're wasting a lot of time thinking and planning about things that
don't never never occur they're always different than what you've ever how you thought and after a while I kind of slowly began
to give up this you know this just you know neurotic drive to plan and
think out and make myself safe for something in the future um because I was not being successful
and um and so I'm happier now this is nicer not to always I do still think ahead I plan ahead I do I think
it's an important part of life but but uh not in the that driven way that I had before
and um and so this uh um and so in the Buddhist teachings the
discursive thinking gives birth to What's called the five hindrances
and these are the thoughts having to do with sensual desire or acquiring things
thoughts that have to do with hatred and ill will thoughts that have to do with
resistance and lethargy and giving up thoughts that have to do with that
anxiety regrets restlessness agitation and thoughts that have to do with doubt
or uncertainty indecisiveness what should I do I don't know what to do
and um in contrast this deep thinking this thinking from
the womb come gives birth to a whole different way of
being in the world and in terms of thinking the one of the characteristics that Buddha gives for
someone who has the ability to think from that source is uh they think
about the welfare and well-being of themselves
of others of both self and others and of the whole world
so this the way of thinking kind of what's beneficial here how do people thrive how do people what's good for
people but it's not just for oneself because of its self-focused the chances
are it belongs to the world of the puppeteer but to have it be an integrative
integrative whole whole where the thinking is inclusive of so
much that's what I kind of associate with the womb the womb the womb is the
whole world for us the whole world everything becomes the the place that
something can be can be connected to and be this what allows something generative
to grow and develop and flow from within and as we have kind of opened up in this
wide way then we're not making sharp lines between me and you me and others
that belongs to the Puppeteer that belongs to the constructing mind that's
making a story and making an idea of who I am when all the constructs become
quieter and we have a chance to think from this deeper source that deeper
source is not driven by division it's not not driven by dividing the
world between the good and the bad and the acceptable the unacceptable and the right and the wrong and the right people
and the wrong people that's not the way it's orientation because it's it's
growing into this wholeness like like an embryo grows into wholeness in the womb
so we're still in this wonderful uh you know womb of our planet that's a whole
and we're still growing as adults and uh and that's a place where we don't
divide this kind of way we still have a sense of others so we're concern for them but the concern is not
divided the the the way with the way we desire the welfare of the world the way
we think about people and so we're equally caring for ourselves as we are
for others and I love it that the Buddha says also for self and others
because it's not just the individuals it's also for the the um the communities we're in
the the you know a paired relationship with friends and family are larger connection to family to community and
neighborhoods and colleagues that that that we self and others in the whole
world is included so that's very different way of thinking than thinking from the you know the
hindrances these other ways thinking from attachment
also this deep generative place of that we're thinking can come is associated
with um with mindfulness with awareness it's
generative of certain kind of attention here in the present moment
partly because it feels so uh nourishing that it feels like the feeling of
nourishment that it tends to bring or contentment or well-being tends to kind
of awaken a kind of feeling of being connected to oneself where we're aware we're connected
discursive thinking we tend to be disconnected from the wholeness of who we are we're in this world of thoughts
and constructs and fantasy and and things and it's not we're divided from
ourselves we're sometimes alienated from ourselves because of that discursive world of
thinking and now so there's awareness that comes from it there is
Clarity we start seeing more clearly what's here there is a kind of a wonderful
generative energy that Vitality that can come rather than the thinking being draining
us and tiring us it's actually there's kind of feels like it's kind of self-generating and perpetually you know
can go on for a long time and there's joy it's kind of sense of well-being
the Buddha Associates it with tranquility being calm he associated with being
focused to be able to be really here and focused and you know present for what's going on
and um and he's and he Associates it with a source for equanimity
being and not being reactive to what's going on the discursive mind
is the reactive mind so I don't know you know how much you know I'm just making this up but
um I associate this this Pancha discursive mind as uh well say I think it's very
important not to I'll get back to what I was going to look the sentence but it's very important not to treat the
discursive mind as any kind of enemy you know it has it can cause a lot of
problems it could cause a lot of difficulty and maybe it sounds a little bit negative you know it's attachment
and self-conceit and all that I think it's very important not to treat it as an enemy because in this womb-like
approach everything gets included everything has a place everything we're concerned about the welfare of
everything and so I I associate the discursive thought this being surface thinking and
what I mean by that is kind of like it's associated with the muscles of our body
and that's where we have to operate when it's when it's fight or flight
if there's danger we have to we you know that that we're set up to fight or flight or some people
to freeze but that's kind of kind of in the muscles of our body kind of that that they could activate it quickly and
engaged and the muscles are I what's you know in my kind of
taught way of talking here more the surface compared to this womb-like place which is deep into the organs deep into
our deeper nervous system in our hearts maybe we would say in in the west rather
than the the womb Maybe and um and it comes from a different Source that's deeper inside
but the fact that the discursive thought is associated with survival
it has an important role and maybe sometimes it has that world of
discursive thinking maybe and what comes from it and the emotions connected to it has in fact helped some people actually
to survive and sometimes fantasy even and discourse you know and being lost some people
that's the only way they get gotten some relief and some escape from horrendous kind of life that they're living
so we want to be very careful not to treat disrespectfully this world of discursive
thinking and this is where this ability to have some Equanimity and
some open awareness some kindness in order to envelop or hold or look at the
discursive thought is so important and because then it has a chance to
relax it's almost like that part of us who need what it needs is to be seen by
something that cares for it that sees it with respect and so when there's a lot of discursive
thinking um and you can maybe feel look at where's the source of this where's this
coming from and maybe get a sense of this deeper Source maybe in some certain emotions or
feelings or attitudes and or maybe places in your body where it's coming from
um and then ask yourself the question what would help settle this part of you
what would help this part of who you are feel reassured or to relax or to kind of
feel safer to make room for a more integrative
way of being in the world that includes this deeper possibility
when we get underneath the musculature maybe some people call even called the armor that's on the
surface we get we get from SD per place that's softer more sensitive quieter
um maybe even Shire there's not going to show itself so
easily unless we get quiet and calm but but allowed that to give time for
that to emerge and to meet the discursive part
and kind of be in conversation with each other and kind of maybe go go for a walk hand
in hand or something so that there's a kind of a different relationship to discursive thought than how we usually
do it which is just maybe just giving into it and just letting it run
so it's important not to let your mind have a mind of its own where it's where it's in charge and it just kind of
running you there is a steeper source that maybe we don't call the mind we
call the heart or we call the womb or something that that is very generative and and
really brings forth some of the most beautiful qualities of a human being
and so um so how to relate to all this how to look at
it and realize that there may be a different way than how his business has been going as usual for you
and um and maybe you can hang a sign someday saying Under New Management
and um so I hope that this talk has been um
offered you something that you kind of some new approach new idea that perspires you to take a good deep look
at yourself and to kind of question and how business as usual is in your mind
and say was this really the way to go is this really how it has to be even though it's been this way for 50 years does
this really have to be this way and and so there was actually more to what I
want to say based on my retreat so I'll just say a little snippet maybe when I come back in a few weeks maybe if I
remember I can say talk about this other half and that is that it was wonderful at The
Retreat one of the wonderful things on this retreat was that at some point it
became fairly easy for me I I had the discursive thought operating at times
thinking mind and going and um this and I could just uh shut it
off I I wasn't I I wasn't in control how long it stayed off
but I could shut it off for a bit and um and that was fascinating
to then see what forms of knowing and what forms of thinking emerge kind
of spontaneously kind of almost like they weren't me it was just like they were just arising
um without the discursive thought kind of um filling this filling the room filling
the space you know you've probably all been in a group of people where one person dominates
and so no one else can speak and maybe you can speak well that's what's going on for you the
discursive one the Puppeteer has been filling the room and um and if you're
your your mental space you know your awareness space is re is actually a very
expensive real estate and you don't want to waste it on the discursive
filling it with the discursive mind there's other ways of knowing other ways of thinking that are have that you know
give them a chance and the discursive thoughts well that's nowhere that far away so it'll get its
turn but it might be time for just deeper voices other voices other ways of
knowing to surface so that was the other half of the talk but maybe that's another time to say more about that
maybe so I'm going to stop early 10 minutes
before the usual stopping and uh and what I'd like to so you're
welcome to leave if you'd like when a few minutes when a tough spot when I talked to talking I thank you for being here
some people come here just to be quiet and not to be in community and so I respect that a lot
or just sit here quietly but I would like to suggest since we have tea today is that you turn to uh
towards one or two people near you and just say hello and maybe offer your
name if you will or just something simple you want to say and maybe that's it and then you can go
or or you have a teeny conversation about uh what your thoughts are what
what happened to you listening to these ideas and these thoughts and is there anything useful here for you
in it and it might but but when you have this conversation with each other I mean
don't don't be careful how much you talk it's very easy Once people start talking
to not stop uh or feel like they have to say everything make your comments relatively
short don't tell long stories and so if you can go back and forth ping pong kind of thing I think that's really
nice and as you form your little groups of two or three just have a little bit of
mindfulness around you in case for someone near you it hasn't been easy to find someone because the way people turn
and they're sitting there kind of like alone so you look around and invite them into your your little group and
and um and then I'll ring the bell and now and maybe about six seven minutes and
so some of you can sit silent some people can go and then afterwards we'll have tea and then you've already broken the ice and met some people maybe you
want to stay say hello to each other