hello everyone and thank you for being here
there's a kind of pleasure in sitting down here
weekday mornings and
being together with all of you to meditate for me to be able to do some sharing some of the what I know or
but practice and maybe some of you there's also a
pleasure some of you uh clearly find some pleasure in all this
and the chats that you're warmly greetings and the chats you're giving
and there might be lots of things that are uncomfortable in your life there might be lots of things which are
quite difficult and challenging and things that will lead the mind to
ruminate about them and and have difficult thoughts and
predictions and ideas about it all
and at any given time there is both what is pleasant and what is unpleasant
and one of the revolutionary ideas that the Buddha had for his time
and maybe for some of us it's a revolutionary idea is to allow ourselves to feel more
pleasure to
and especially that's useful when we discover that a lot of the
uncomfortable feelings we have the unpleasantness we experience
has this Genesis or has its support in The Chronic ways in which we're
thinking or The Chronic kind of negativity bias where we kind of through fear or through
whatever reason we tend to orient ourselves around what is unpleasant
and of course Buddhism is about an honest assessment of what's difficult and challenging our suffering
not we're not denying that but if we really want to be able to
manage in a healthy dharmic way with the sufferings and challenges of our life
the Buddha said it's helpful or it to paraphrase him he's it's helpful to feel
pleasure you're allowed to feel pleasure
there's a role for pleasure in this practice
I just went to heat up my water
and I noticed that as I was getting ready to heat up the water the way I was handling the
the cup and the filling of water and I put it in the microwave here
that I was concerned with the talk I was going to give and teach and the
activities of getting everything ready on time and it was fine but if I really noticed that
carefully I noticed there was some unpleasantness and it wasn't particularly
Pleasant it was and as soon as I recognized that
I became attuned to the pleasure that was there and the PLA and the in
filling up the cup of water carrying it stretching my arm putting it into the microwave
as small maybe insignificant pleasure for in some scale of things
and some of that once I felt a pleasure then I could move my arm and be with the
whole phenomena heating up the water I could do it in an even more graceful way more pleasant way
was that a denial of the unpleasantness that I was feeling
I don't think so I think that my mind was just focused on one part of reality
and there was a different part of reality that was more nourishing more supportive
rather than thinking about what I was going to teach you all of you probably better to show up in a good
state show up
you know who are settled the more happy more contented
so as we sit today Orient yourselves towards what is
Pleasant Here and Now not what's Pleasant in your life more generally
but here in your body
and not having pleasant thoughts you know things that they're you know
Wonderful fantasies but if you are going to think about your meditation
can you think in a pleasant way can you focus your attention in a
pleasant way can you be aware in a way that's not
tense or unpleasant
can the breathing be pleasant
so to begin the meditation just
sitting up straight
gently closing the eyes
and to so be sure to acknowledge and not deny that there are things which
are uncomfortable take a few moments to acknowledge here
and now in your body your heart your mind
yes there is a something which is unpleasant uncomfortable
and some of that might be unnecessary some of it is a healthy part of life
but for practice either way we don't have to push it away or deny it
try to fix it and having acknowledged it now
if you can acknowledge what is Pleasant for you here and now starting with your
body maybe in your hands
wherever it might be the pleasantness
maybe there's pleasure in relaxing more softening the tight muscles
and then becoming aware of your breathing
and can you be aware of your breathing in a pleasant way
or at least not to be aware of it unpleasantly with strain or pushing contraction
with beliefs I can't this is difficult
is there something in the most simple way in which your body breathes
simple way your body breathes that you can find some pleasure in it
feeling the body's experience of breathing
is there any point in the cycle of breathing in and breathing out
that has the most pleasure most nice feeling
however fleeting it is
be sure to feel that part of the cycle well whenever you get to it feel the
pleasure or the niceness
don't don't have to look for dramatic pleasure
maybe it's a very light pleasantness
ease
and as you're experiencing your breathing
maybe in a ease full of relaxed way
are there small ways you can adjust your breathing so it becomes more pleasant
maybe there's a relaxing in the belly in the chest
maybe a teeny bit more breathing in
a teeny bit longer letting go as you exhale
maybe a teeny pause before you inhale
and if you can feel some pleasure
let that support the mind to be present here now
in some ways the mind is attracted to what is Pleasant
allow it to feel the pleasantness of the moment as a way of supporting you to be here
and now
to help you settle down and relax to help the Mind Trust
being present here and now
to no Pleasant present moment pleasure
we have to be aware
allowing awareness to be receptive to receive
the pleasure that it knows the simplest pleasure of the moment here
and now in breathing and sitting here maybe the pleasure
that comes with meditation
if there is unpleasant Sensations experiences
is there a way of holding them or relating to them
from the places of pleasure pleasantness
maybe taking them both in as you breathe
so that there's not a fixation on what is uncomfortable
and then as we come to the end of the sitting
are there people for whom if you think about
you feel pleasure that's Pleasant it's enjoyable it's
evokes good feelings to think about certain people
let yourself feel the pleasure of
recalling people in your life you enjoy your who you love for who you
care for nicely the love the Friendship the good will
you feel might be the source of that Pleasant pleasure
the Delight
and to relax into that pleasure of knowing them thinking of them
feeling the pleasantness if it's there
and then imagine that from that Pleasant pleasure you can gaze out upon all people
the people you love care for the people you are neutral to
even the people you're troubled by you can look upon them
with kind Pleasant gaze
and wish them well is there a way that coming out of
meditation that you have access to a different kind of well-wishing
than you usually have one that's more spacious open
less reactive
may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so good morning or today hello and
here to give the second talk on the mindfulness check-in
and how to uh use mindfulness the classic mindfulness
teaching on the three foundations as a way of freeing ourselves from
unhealthy unuseful preoccupations with the challenges difficulties we have in
our life it's not a denial that we have challenges
but it's possible all too easy for us to become fixated on them in a unuseful way
we can get preoccupied we can ruminate we can repeat the same kind of
uh [Music] fear-based thoughts about what will
happen what it all means what's going to happen to us we can possible to steam in in anger and
just kind of be cut up in the endless story of blame and who did what and just angry and about someone
of course there might be reasons to be afraid reasons to be angry
but to ruminate with it to persist in it and spin in it is uh
is one way an unhealthy way of placing Our Life Energy placing our
attention and it limits it Narrows the scope of a way how we can be present for
what is here and so and even just spending a lot of time thinking about things
it limits Our Lives thinking has a role but to be lost in
thought so when the Buddha taught the four foundations of mindfulness
there is no obvious place in there to be mindful of thinking we often will teach
mindfulness of thinking this is how there is a place but in that teachings of the Buddha there's no
obvious way and I think he knew very well that people think a lot in fact he gives
instructions elsewhere of how to work with destructive thoughts but I think in the in the classic
teachings of mindfulness um he offers a different way of being
present for our direct experience that's not mediated so much through our
thinking and that is rather than see things
through the lens of what we're thinking and how we're thinking and is to drop into these four different
areas through kind of tease apart these four areas of the totality of our experience
and that is to be aware of how things are experienced physically
in the body how things are either Pleasant or unpleasant
the pleasure and or the discomfort of things
the Mind States and then the mental processes today the topic is the second
they What's called the feeling tone of experience and when we go through the checklist and
say I'm having some difficulty and um and it didn't happen today but it almost
happened uh coming down here at the IMC to teach a little bit late later than
usual and so I could be could have been preoccupied about no I need to get here
I'll be late what will happen and uh how am I going to be efficient when I get there to set everything up and and I
could be spinning that way so that would be the challenge the challenge of being late in my preoccupation and
and and worry around that once I notice that's happening then I
give myself a checklist no it's happening in the body I'm agitated what's happening to feeling tones it's
unpleasant what's happening in mind State it's gotten narrow
and tight and what's happened in the mental processes
I'm caught up in a certain degree of worry a certain degree of of
um of a little bit aversion to feeling the way I'm feeling
and then if I look at that checklist I say well the most interesting place maybe the
strongest place is actually it feels uncomfortable the whole thing let me look at the discomfort let me
that that's the important place to bring attention to and sometimes that's enough
because that's enough to me to recognize that I'm tense and so then I can relax
I can soften around this how I'm feeling and that kind of opens the field and
relaxes the whole thing without having to figure it all out in
my thoughts and ideas and be stuck there so that's a simple way that mindfulness
can work but for the Buddha the attention to the feeling tone can be
revolutionary and it was for the Buddha because when he discovered some of the pleasures and
joy of meditation he asked himself do I need to be afraid of this
and he said no it's okay to experience this pleasure and this kind of in a very you know
distant way is a little bit a little bit mimics my experience of meditation over these years I've meditated
that in the first 10 years of meditation or so I had no idea
exactly it was discouraged from feeling any pleasure if you talk went to the meditation teacher and talked about
you're feeling Pleasant or pleasure you were told let go of that just kind of stay present be with the emptiness of
things be with just the just sit and not focus on anything just let go of it let go
and there was no way of acknowledging and even though I would sit in meditation in that tradition and have
sometimes really good feelings of being present they were never validated or given a place
and when I started studying vipassana I eventually discovered there's actually
a very important place and it's okay to experience pleasure it's part of what it means to be human
being is to have pleasure but in fact don't be attached to it don't strive and struggle to have it
don't expect it but do allow yourself to feel it
and it can be revolutionary when the mind is
preoccupied with what's uncomfortable if the Mind spins out in fear or in
anger or distress or grief or sadness all those emotions are part of human
life and certainly don't want to deny them or or cut them off directly
but but the preoccupation rhythm and the preoccupation with these kinds
of difficulties and challenges becomes the fuel for the challenge to be bigger and persists longer
and so we have to somehow be able to moderate or monitor how we're what we're
fueling and what we're feeding and growing and in person and
maintaining and so uh it isn't that we're not
supposed to feel some discomfort but maybe it's not necessary to feed it
and there's something powerful that happens if we start tuning into the pleasure the pleasantness of the moment
that isn't doesn't not meant to be a denial of what's unpleasant but it's a way of of uh moderating or finding our
way with what's unpleasant there's a different reference point there's a different way in which our
attention is being fed or attentions being conditioned it's been conditioned by what's Pleasant
rather than persisting with what's unpleasant so some people might protest around this
kind of idea and that's you know maybe reasonable to some degree but if you're pay careful attention
to our mind's reactivity and what we what we're feeding what we're influence
the ruminations the spinning of the mind is having and you find out that a persistent way
of thinking a persists in the way of kind of being caught and is fueling your
feelings fueling the distress fueling the sense of emotional challenge that's going on
that also is not very useful it can actually spin out and you know if you really spin out in a
panic attack or really spiral downward it's really good to uh to go do
something different that's enjoyable go find a kitten to play with
many years ago I used to take long showers when I was really spinning out with with fear and that was somehow
settle anything the pleasure of the shower go for a walk where you can enjoy trees
and skies or something and
finding something pleasant to do when we're in danger of spinning out with our
preoccupation is a very good intervention and to settle the nervous system to
quiet things down and and then we'll be in a better place
to come back and address the issue not a few people have found that taking a hey a pleasure break
to going off and doing something enjoyable playing with a kitten
and then coming back later to address the challenges we have they're in such a better place to reflect on and think
about it wisely or do what needs to be done so that's a common kind of everyday kind
of thing that people can do but we also learned to do that in meditation and through mindfulness
we learn to not prioritize the unpleasant not prioritize the negativity
bias that we might have in all kinds of ways it plays out and when but for many people starting to
feel more pleasure and the pleasantness of life and here now is is just bringing things into balance
when we're in balance in the direction of what's uncomfortable and as we start feeling the pleasant the
pleasure of what's comfortable and give ourselves more time for that that
begins having a different conditioning on our emotional life our mental state
it tends to um change the energy level of what's being
energized and being you know spinning out and it tends to energize healing
States Pleasant States per year it's a lot easier to be with our challenges emotional challenges mental
challenges worldly challenges if we can hold it in a place of being
calm open Pleasant kind of at ease in the world and enjoying it
so to to go through the mindfulness checklist and when you get to the you know is this
Pleasant or unpleasant The Experience there's two things you that are important you can say you
notice that that's where the pleasant Enterprise that's where the Salient aspect that's the big that seems to be
the significant thing I want to bring my attention to so of those four things in the checklist
you might spend sometimes more time with the second
and sometimes all that's necessary is to know it well and be present for how it is
present for the unpleasant that just that can change things but sometimes you want to bring a
balance into the whole system by intentionally focusing more on what's Pleasant
not manufacturing it not going out and getting alcohol to make it Pleasant not
doing something that's too artificial or too contrived or something which doesn't have a good influence on you
but healthy forms of pleasure may be forms of pleasure that don't require
doing anything but rather you know different than what you're doing but rather availing
yourself of the pleasure that's already here and that's what we can do in meditation
what's already here and can that be a support for being with even the difficulties
can I let that meditation pleasure can I take it in fully and don't be and if in the course of
meditation pleasure arises even the pleasure of being a bit calmer than you were before
let that register receive that let that be don't be in this old school uh dismissing you know
can't be attached to that yeah don't be attached if you can but you're allowed to feel it and take it in
be nourished there's a way healthy wholesome
pleasures of meditation of mindfulness of being and learning how to be with ourselves
have a healing force on us so in this way hopefully I've conveyed
that the Buddha's emphasis on feelings feeling tones and the pleasure is a
revolutionary thing for some people to focus on and it's a game changer
so maybe at least for this next 24 hours it can be the game that you play explore
the certainly explore the world of how you've experienced Pleasant and unpleasant
how do you react how do you what's your reactivity way of
being with things that feel unpleasant and what's your belief in reaction and
comfort level with what is Pleasant and can you allow yourself to notice
more of the pleasures that are already here
can you switch the maybe the negativity bias that some people have
to what's unpleasant to begin to give a richer Fuller
experience of what is Pleasant and may that be really beneficial and
support this Dharma practice we're on and support your ability to have a
realistic and useful way of being with challenges so thank you