good morning good day everyone uh Could you type in the chat if you can hear me
okay I'm wondering if the sound is coming through all
right yes thank you very much um I'm so
delighted that I can be with this wonderful Sana every morning this week
um and I have to say it is so delightful to read the messages coming through chat
thank you so much for those um I'm especially happy to be doing this since
this week Falls between the holidays it is such a great time of year
year uh for reflection and for witnessing uh acts of generosity and
kindness um as well as the overwhelming need of all of humanity for
compassion so for these reasons and following Gil's beautiful talks last week about thinking I thought this week
we could focus on qualities of heart and mind um that are trans are called the
Brahma viharas which are often translated as Divine abodes or Heavenly
abodes uh and an abode of course is a place to dwell I I think of the Brahma
viharas as very wholesome places for the mind to dwell to hang out to live in
away uh the Brahma viharas are good will compassion
appreciative joy and equinity of course a wholesome states of
Mind are not limited to the list that I just gave um and there are so many
others which is wonderful um another wholesome state that I want to
particularly focus on today is generosity uh the virtue of giving and
it seems to underly each of the other Divine abodes and our practice in so
many different ways uh so that in fact sitting here and
reading the chats is like opening gifts and in a great form of
generosity um these beautiful states of Mind these Divine abodes and the state
of generosity excuse me don't happen by accident of course
they come come through taking care of one's mental state through the
meditations we do through mindfulness and we have this opportunity to
cultivate and reinforce helpful qualities of mind I think meditating in
a supportive group like this one that's uh so friendly uh to one another is a
generous Act of mutual support so with that as an
introduction let's settle into our
meditation beginning with giving yourself the time you
need to settle
in taking your time for settling into the posture
finding the state of alertness and relaxation that can be
supportive offering care for this body this heart and this
mind and how they are right in this moment
starting with knowing just exactly how we are right here and right
now feeling the gift of
breath breathing in and breathing out of all parts of yourself as you're
here the nourishment of kind
attention to soothe and feed all parts of the body
heart and
mind perhaps gradually scanning the body from head to
toe give some ease to each part of the
body that would benefit from
ease perhaps spending more time in any any area that seems to need your
attention or benefit from some extra breath in and breath
out releasing any extra tension that can be
released anything extra that you're carrying
around allowing the out breath to carry
that away and respecting any part of the
body that cannot be eased respecting and
giving it the attention of accepting it just as it
is the body heart and mind offer us
this record of conditions and how they've
been they show up in this moment perhaps
reflecting some of the things that have gone before and as we give kind
acknowledgment to that often those areas can then
feel the ease of settling into what's happening
now
perhaps feeling the aliveness of the entire
body as it sits here and now or lies down or
stands and recognizing with kindness any moods or emotions that are
present allowing each thing that comes to awareness it's time to be known to be
felt to be seen and
heard
and offering all emotions and moods that are here your good
will receiving messages from the heart in the same way that you would receive a
dear friend whether the friend is
in a great mood or the friend is facing
challenges in the same way gently
attending to the activity of the Mind as you would listen to the thoughts
of a friend accepting every
experience without joining them in those thoughts
but respecting what they have to say having some generos I
it for how they are for how this mind
is
offering the gift of mindful attention to to each thing that comes to
awareness as phenomena come and go throughout the
meditation everything included nothing left out there is
no right or wrong meditation there's only kind awareness
for what is present in each moment that
arises
right
for
it's so delightful to be with you all and there is so much
generosity that is INRI inextricably part of Buddhist practice
as you give your time and attention to the body the heart the
mind this awareness this gift of mindfulness allows what is arising some
time and mental space to be known that gift of attention is one of
the keys to discovering and uprooting what causes
dissatisfaction stress suffer uing and by giving ourselves the time to get to
know the Mind deeply we learn we gradually learn how to find sustainable
happiness and this all started with an act of generosity and that was the
Buddhist conscious decision to teach so according to one suta that I uh
was reading when the Buddha was newly self-awakened he was said to have been
thinking something like this this Dharma that I have attained is deep hard to see hard to
realize peaceful refined beyond the scope of conjecture subtle to be
experienced by the wise but this generation Delights an attachment is
excited by attachment enjoys attachment for a gener delighting in attachment
excited by attachment enjoying attachment then he goes on to name these
things that are going to be really hard for people to understand when they're so into attachment such as conditionality
this if this then that dependent co-arising the resolution of all
Fabrications the relinquishment of all acquisitions the end of crazy cing
dispassion cessation unbinding and apparently you know the
the thought was if I were to teach the Dharma and others would not understand
me that would be tiresome and Troublesome for me so as he entertained
these thoughts The Story Goes that his mind was inclined instead to just dwelling at ease and not to teaching the
Dharma but this particular suta recounts that a
Brahma implored and persuaded him to teach by telling him that there were the
there were people there are people who would be able to understand and after that the Buddha
apparently decided that he would teach those who could hear the Dharma and had
conviction but then he went on to dedicate the REM the remaining decades
of his life to teaching so it's one thing to teach a few classes but imagine the generosity it
takes to spend every day every decade of one's adult life one's you know teaching
what is hard to convey and hard for others to understand so that's that's a
pretty amazing Act of generosity he didn't just discover this for himself he then passed it on and
then the next enormous active gener generosity um to which we owe the
practices we learn was that the generations of monastics who first
memorized and recited the teachings of the Buddha um and to anyone wanting to
hear the Dharma and then later recorded them in writing and then we're fortunate enough um In Our Lifetime that they've
been translated into languages that we speak and these weren't people who were
setting out to make a a fortune from what they knew knew it was freely offered passed from one warm hand to the
next for the past 2,500 years so when we take in that fact 2500
years of people generously offering this um it really registers with a sense of
amazement and gratitude um and if we dedicate ourselves regularly to this practice we
start to feel the ways in which generosity grows um inside so for me
realizing that I'm coming up on the 20th year uh since I sat at Insight
Meditation Center um with Gil 20 years ago and have been doing so ever since
and now online the generosity of the people who developed these tools that enable us to come from all over the
world to gather and meditate together one way it manifests is is in an
attitude of goodwi towards others and I can see that going on in the chat um for
someone who's going through things and the care that people are sending that's pretty
wonderful so we can feel Goodwill towards each other and also towards experience
itself this practice makes us increasingly able to meet every kind of
experience and every kind of relationship with some Goodwill some
fundamental friendliness or kindness and willingness to open to what's happening
instead of being in conflict with it when that good will encounters
suffering we respond with another form of generosity and that is
compassion good willll wants to see suffering come to an end and it's an inclination of mind that
knows that given exactly the same conditions we would suffer in exactly
the same way and not only that when generosity
encounters someone who's experiencing Good Fortune instead of being envious or competitive the heart responds with
appreciative Joy feeling good for the other person um so devoted practice develops
this capacity not only to feel compassion to come from a quality of goodwi but also
to radiate good wishes towards someone for whom things are going
well and there are so many forms of generosity that surround
us um it it lightens the heart and it develops Good Will further Goodwill to
begin to look around you and discover generosity everywhere um Donna is the ancient poly
word for generosity and it's named as in the Buddhist text as the first of the 10
parmes or Perfections of virtue so the first Perfection of virtue is
generosity aan suito uh wrote a book about parmes that I'm sure many of you know and he in that
book he points out something pretty interesting that in order for our minds to be ready to take in the teachings of
the Buddha to really be ready for Liberation um the Mind needs preparation
and the specific preparation that aan suito sites is to
access and take in the validity the the real value of
generosity and also virtue and renunciation so these three together are
practiced as a beginning of being able to come to freedom from suffering
they're practiced not only for on but for the welfare of others and they're said to lead to
Peace So virtue and renunciation that are named in this Trio with
generosity to me actually come from generosity as well if you think about
practicing virtue which you could also say is ethical conduct or morality
that's another gift that we give each other that's the way we create safety
honesty trust and reliability in our
relationships and those things are so fun fundamental to Harmony and
ultimately happiness it brings peace to your own mind and BEC because the
conscience knows that it's behaving unethically and it will never come to peace when that's running under
conscious awareness it will continue to cause someone to act
out cause entire groups of people to act out in some form of discomfort
suffering although it it wears a lot of different
guises renunciation is a another Act of generosity when you think of letting go
of an UNH wholesome Habit in favor of a more wholesome way of being we are not
only benefiting ourselves but we're benefiting other people giving up on
wholesome Behavior UNH wholesome speech UNH wholesome thoughts we get a lot
easier to live around and we become less harmful to others so when we're
practicing renunciation often we're giving up up our Greed for something that we previously craved as if it were
going to be the source of sustainable happiness and when we give up on that greed again we're doing something that
benefits others our cravings and
by using only what we need so as as you've been listening to
the various ways generosity presents itself in these foundations for the
practice of generosity virtue and um
renunciation as well as in the practice of mindfulness itself maybe some of the ways you experience generosity are
coming to mind um what are some of the simple ways that generosity shows up in
your practice in your life if you'd like I'd love it if you want to type some of them into the chat examples of
generosity that you value the generosity um of sharing it with each
other in the chat um will inspire others to see more forms of generosity in their
life so some of the things that are coming to mind for me are the uh really
kind way that when you're riding a bicycle uh cars will give you a wide birth as they pass or the
generosity of actually talking to someone who's a clerk at a store that
you're shopping in instead of just treating them anonymously so presence is one that I
see I see warm hugs being sent that's generosity what else inspires you
as generosity that you see in daily
life the kindness of strangers letting go of taking
credit a meal prepared with
love these are beautiful spending time listening to
others cooking for others smiling at strangers
forgiveness it's huge form of generosity
Smiles even to people you don't know encouraging people to go ahead of me in
line the generosity of willingness to receiving help warmth sharing food with
friends my son-in-law getting sober yes people being
kind thank you melody this talk right now Distributing food yeah acknowledging
generous behaviors from others it's so helpful when people are
thanked for what they're doing they do more of the same cooking for Friends in
Need definitely reaching out to our elderly neighbors and listening to their
stories empathy bringing my nine dogs inside
when it's 20 degrees outside yes it's currently 11 where I live and there's snow on the ground uh the friendliness
of others this is beautiful sitting still with a child just sitting and listening
to anyone saying hello to others when you're hiking help uh this is powerful
helping someone die yes people giving each other space in
lines in listening with an open heart listening and sharing Christmas Day sa
radical acceptance and someone offering Sarah
her presence community service um so thank you all for these
beautiful beautiful examples of generosity and I want to invite you for those of you who
would like to make this week a retreat of sorts I'd like to invite you to
continue to notice throughout your day this is a really fun practice practice all of the beautiful examples of
generosity that you see around you it really lifts and warms the heart thank
you so much sending meta to all of you sending very fond wishes for a happy day