foreign people trickle in why don't we just sit for a few minutes let's just let
ourselves ground and breathe and come on in please join us yeah and um
yeah just taking a moment till that your senses connect with Where You Are
you know feeling the feet feeling your bottom
we can move the chairs you can move the chairs anywhere okay we just randomly
put wherever you put them not knowing who's neutralized
yeah maybe do what Richard just did is take a couple longer slower deeper
breaths you can go ahead and just it's all right
we're just taking a few minutes here to ground and breathe and
invite ourselves to rest I like the word to finish arriving yeah
it's like a car has momentum you know and it needs to slowly stop and sort of we have
the same thing going with our energy our momentum getting here and through
the day just allowing things to come to
Stillness or closer to that
foreign
[Music]
welcome everyone welcome welcome
so I have a couple of questions um who's watched The Wizard of Oz
has anybody seen the movie one two no three four oh okay so Brian only you
have not so far so far but there's probably people out there that haven't watched it too
okay um when was the last time you watched watched it
okay a while ago Susan don't even remember so many years so many years ago Jay a
long time that's great
yeah so were you interested in coming to the class because of the Wizard of Oz or
just because the hindrances or both I'm just curious and like just here yeah
you don't like the movie okay thanks yeah it's pretty weird when
I re-watched it it's pretty weird yeah but um but let me tell you why I was I'm spot
inspired by it I actually went on a long retreat many years ago and
for some reason The Wizard of Oz and a lot of what was happening it came
up in my meditation and I've spent a lot of years trying to unpack and understand
why the symbols and the memories why did they come up in my deep I was in a deep
practice it was actually a very profound Meditation Retreat and the more I reflected on it the more
I was like wow something in there knows something I don't you know like there's just tremendous wisdom
um and in in kind of the insights that I found when I started to think more and more about what was represented
in the movie so I'll say more about some of those things um after Diana gives an overview of the
five hindrances because that's really you know that's the the primary teaching
is about sort of these five hindrances and um and then we wanted to use the Wizard
of Oz as a more of a playful um kind of reference a visual reference
less heavy we often get pretty kind of feel a sense of heaviness about the
hindrances so there's an effort to bring some lightness Joy
um and and actual when you watch the movie some visual Clarity to how the hindrances can manifest so
it's a welcome we look forward to playing with you and exploring and I actually will say
just one more thing and then I'll ask Diana to talk about the five hindrances but
there's actually quite a few books and essays written on the interpretation of
The Wizard of Oz um and like there are some essays like
that oh one guy did an analysis of five different interpretations
and it's like atheists and Christians use the same
examples to demonstrate their points so I think there's a lot of room to
interpret the Wizard of Oz from a Buddhist perspective so why not
all right thank you Tanya for those of you who don't know me I'm Diana Clark and I'm
very happy to be here and Tanya and I are great friends we've been friends for a long time we practice together we
teach together and cook dinner together sometimes and go for hikes and all this
kind of stuff so thank you Tanya for inviting me it's such a delight to be teaching together
and it was tonya's idea about the Wizard of Oz it's like oh okay but I like this idea of a little bit of some Whimsy you
know to bring this in and some fun and maybe what you said about the atheists and the Christians showing that these
are the experiences there's some like archetypes there that's not something
that's just unique to certain individuals and maybe that's part of what we'll be highlighting during this
course but I'm going to begin by bringing in
another analogy another kind of like story or a metaphor
or something that we might use and many of us come to meditation practice
because we want to have more ease more freedom more spaciousness in our life we
want to have a more relaxation whatever it is whatever brings us less suffering
and part of our way of finding more ease more freedom more peace more relaxation
is to pay attention to what gets in the way of that
so often we're just trying to we think that we just have to find whatever it is we're looking for but it might even be
more important to look at what's getting in the way to have what we're looking for
and so this analogy this metaphor or something that's in the Buddhist teachings
we have no interest in people becoming Buddhists if you're here just for that right to we have a Buddha here this is a
Buddha Center but we're and you know we hold this lightly but you will hear me
on occasion maybe Tanya to referring to the Buddhist teachings but there's this um analogy that the
Buddha uses when he's describing the path of practice like how kind of like
practice unfolds either over a lifetime or over one single meditation session
collect the same story can work and that is this idea of a river so
water starting on a Mountaintop and then going from little streamlits
and turning into a river and then going to the ocean
it's natural right Rivers only go One Direction downhill towards the ocean
the ocean is can be understood as Freedom this really immense beautiful
deep body of water and then our practice can be like this
movement towards the ocean but one thing that's in rivers part of
what makes them Rivers are boulders big boulders or Banks or Fallen trees or
you know something like this right of course they're not streamlined we only see those in amusement parks right it's
perfectly smooth and straight down so there's a way in which we might think
like oh if only those Boulders weren't there then the water could go more
smoothly but there's something there's a that we can learn from this and that the
water it meets The Boulders it's touching the boulders and then going around or going
over or something like this has this intimate connection with it
and it's the water then um maybe slowed down or maybe it's sped
up because of some other Boulders but it keeps on going not by avoiding the
boulders by contacting them and so this is part of what we're going
to be exploring what are these Boulders and how can we like work with them and
such that we are contacting them that's the secret here instead of wishing that they would just
go away and that this would be so much easier if they weren't there
so in The Wizard of Oz we might say Boulders or the Tin Man you know there's
like so many different ways that we might um think about this things that maybe hinder or get into the
hinder or maybe impede what we might think of as
progress but here is something that is for me is really fascinating and interesting and
uplifting is that it turns out
that these Boulders are integral to the path of practice they are a necessary
part and we don't think that right we think like oh I'm the only one that has this
or if only these things weren't here but they are an integral part of practice
and we'll talk about this as these weeks unfold like how is that
how is it that they are inherent to this way of finding more freedom part
of the answer to that of course is what I said the beginning is for us to get to
know to understand like how these entrances show up in our life
because what shows up in the meditation cushion of course shows up in our daily life of
course it does we only have one mind one body right so it's not like something on the cushion
is completely different than we see elsewhere but it's a way meditation allows the
opportunity for us to maybe examine it in a way that we wouldn't normally
it provides the opportunity for us to even see the habits that we have of body
and mind that might otherwise not be so clear to us we might just think oh this
is just the way it is everybody does it this way something like this so it's not until we start to maybe like look at the
hindrances become more sensitive to them that we start to gain some more self-understanding
and then of course we might even consider that these boulders
are in fact I think we can say something I forgot that it's
exact expression we put it on the back of Gill's book on the hindrances something like instead of rather being
blocking they are Stepping Stones so they are something that that we use
to help us get to the next stage to help us get further in our practice
so not only because it provides greater self-understanding but also it helps us to it's a little
bit of a mind training too and Tony and I in these ensuing weeks
we'll be talking about this but into a notice what are our reactions when we
come up against something that seems to be getting in our way what's our habitual way of responding do we get
angry or do we start blaming or do we collapse and kind of run out of energy
and give up or do we just avoid it or you know there's so many different ways
that we can respond to things that are some difficulties so working with the hindrances is a meditation
naturally affects the rest of our life and the all the goals and the things that we'd like to do
so that's one way in which their Stepping Stones having us gaining some greater self-understanding
second way is that part of I keep on talking about this what Tanya and I will
be doing is the way that we work with them is by
turning towards them and this sometimes is
um exactly what we don't want to do we sometimes have this idea of okay well
just that thing has to go away and then I'm going to just practice here that thing has to go away but of course that
kind of pushing is aversion which is one of the hindrances so that's the second way is just to have
this idea that we turn towards difficulties in a way that which is not
overwhelming or that doesn't um cause us to collapse or
um give up or something like this but that is just gets folded into practice
I think Gill says this pretty often like you know this too we just we just bring this into practice
so we'll be talking about this also Okay so
what are these hindrances for using this word uh hindrances
I appreciate um that these are captured in the Buddhist teachings which of course are
thousands of years ago for me that's like I love to think about
this like how many generations of people like maybe a hundred Generations before
us like we have our parents grandparents great grandparents and then just think they go back a hundred
all those people all that time ago they recognized the exact same thing that we
experienced today this is not unique to us
maybe the particulars are of you know yeah of course right modern times are
different but there's something about this universality of it that for me I
don't know I feel encouraged by connects me to so many other people this is The
Human Experience we have these hindrances that's just the way it is
and part of the way is we learn to work with them and be with them and the exact
same experience can stop being a hindrance without it having to go away
and that's part of the how we work with them is how do we can make this transition from them being a hindrance
to them just being one more thing that we're aware of and then I'll say it again Tanya and I
will talk about like some of the tools we can use and how we can work with that in a way that really supports our
practice so another analogy or a metaphor that we
might use is sometimes they're called like veiling factors
so this idea of a hindrance is something that's like impedes progress but we can
also think about them as a way that are covering up or obscuring or things so
that we can't quite See Clearly we don't see ourselves clearly we don't see other people clearly we don't see
the situation clearly when we're filled and we all know this when you're filled
with aversion when you're just woke up on the that side of the bed in which you
feel kind of cranky you know things just seem different and you're more up to uh
you know say a Curt word to somebody or yell or get in a fight or whatever it
might be we all knew this that kind of the Mind states that we're in affect how we
interpret or understand other things so these entrances are also we can
consider them veiling factors and as we learn to work with them
then we can find that our life just starts to unfold with more ease
and more clarity you can start to see how things really are
or maybe with less obscurations or
okay so these hindrances there many of you might know this already they're put into five categories
kind of like simplified and classified into these five I don't know maybe today we might come
up with a different list of five but these ones from thousands of years ago work as well
they're given in a traditional order it's not the order that Tanya and I are going to teach them it is actually it is
now okay okay I was just on Retreat for quite some time so I just told Tanya do
whatever you want and I'll follow your lead so here we are so they're given in a traditional order
the first one is sensual desire this uh
this wanting just the next pleasurable thing you know this kind of like leaning
forward and okay this is I need to have you know the most comfy chair and the
best food and the right temperature and you know everything has to be just right and this because wishing for everything
to be comfortable and even Pleasant more than comfortable Pleasant and enjoyable
so that's the first one is this thinking that's you know this is the highest priorities to find the most Pleasant
thing I want to be clear we are not saying that pleasantness is bad of course not
joy happiness Pleasant Sensations are a vital part of this path of practice we
get into trouble if we think that our whole life is about chasing them is nothing about is if our whole life is
about just having that next pleasurable experience and my guess is you would not be here at
a meditation center if you if that worked for you right to just be chasing the pleasant experiences it turns out
not to work so well maybe I'll tell a little story that um
once I was on a Meditation Retreat and this was coming up a lot I was like having all these ideas like whenever I
get out of this dang Retreat I'm gonna go do this and I can't wait to have that and you know I'm gonna buy this eat this
you know like I had all these like long ideas and um but I was kind of like working with them working with the hindrances
like oh no no okay that's desire Diana and you don't have to follow that and I
knew how to work with them so it would kind of fade away but then it would come up again and then I'd work with it and fade away
and I thought like okay okay I managed to get through that meditation session you know all right
as it happened the um next thing that was happening after that meditation was
um the lunch time so you know we go to the dining hall
and I'm in the dining hall I got my plate like oh this looks really good I'm gonna have some of this oh I probably
need to get a little bit more like some of this and then oh wow wow they have this okay I need two scoops of that and
this I had this huge amount of food on my plate way more than I could eat and
realize oh yeah so this desire is still here this thinking that I need to have more and
more and more it's just showing up in this way so sometimes it's obvious and sometimes
it's not so obvious the way that they show up so that's the first one
the second one is the opposite I call it aversion like I don't want
this like make it go away it's this um like pushing it away
sometimes uh a little bit of perhaps this flavor of ill will like dang it get
out of here you know that's kind of a Feeling whether it's a sore knee or this
persistent thought of that terrible thing that our boss said that one time that keeps haunting us that keeps on
coming up whatever it might be that kind of like wanting to push it away so that's the second one
the third one is restlessness and remorse or worry
so it's this um having a lot of energy like this I'm sure if
anybody has a meditation practice you have this experience like you're sitting down and just this real
urge I want to get up and do anything except be here
defrost the refrigerator or organize the sock drawer you know anything
so that's the restlessness it's often called restlessness and worry restlessness and remorse it's not quite
clear how to translate these into English but it's pointing to the bodily experience of restlessness as well as
the mental experience of restlessness of wanting to do something different
fourth one is the opposite of that one we call it sloth and torpor it's kind of this language is maybe a little bit
dated but it's you know just completely run out of energy
it's not uncommon for people to meditate to feel sleepy we would say that's kind of sloth and
torpor but there's also a way in which we can feel sleepy just because we're
physically tired but it also can be a way in which the mind and the body are
reacting to experience we can notice this if at the end of The
Meditation period if we feel like oh okay great I'm gonna go do the next thing but while we were meditating you
know the energy was completely drained out so we can notice whether it's a physical
thing or something with the meditation and then the last one it's often
translated as doubt but I I want to maybe flesh that out a little bit
I would maybe um the way it gets more experienced is more like hesitation like should I do
this practice or maybe I should do this or I don't know that Insight seems nice
but this seems too hard okay I'm going to do some loving kindness practice but oh wait I can't remember the phrases
well okay maybe I'll just do some walking meditation I don't know maybe those teachers don't even know what
they're talking about you know so just this never really getting settled because you have this idea that maybe
I'm not doing the practice right maybe the teachers don't really know what
they're talking about or can't explain it in the right way or maybe the teachings that we've inherited from all
these generations of these practitioners maybe they we might think like oh those are
two archaic they don't have any relevance so it's this doubt so maybe
it's like the lack of confidence in the practice or lack of confidence in oneself or lack of confidence in the
teachers and I'm just going to say quickly one thing about doubt because I think
um often we think oh the opposite of doubt well let me just say this
the how we often how the antidote we might say to doubt
is investigation check it out for yourself ask somebody
read a Dharma book listen to podcasts explore things in your own meditation
practice so we're not saying that you have to have faith you know that's going
to take you all the way instead this is a real encouragement to have some experiential your own experience
as a way to support your practice and to work with doubt there and then I'll just end with this last
thing that I already mentioned it but I think that
um it's worthwhile saying again everybody has contact with these
hindrances it's not until you're completely awakened person that you don't have them
until you're like a Buddha or an or Hut or something like this very easy when we run into these
Boulders these hindrances to start The Narrative of the inner critic like oh everybody else looks like they can do
this and I can't do it or I can't meditate or you know some narrative like
that to start up everybody has these we might idealize
teachers or we might idealize things that we've seen in books or podcasts or
something like this but everybody has this so it's there's no need for us to
personalize it and feel like it's a failing on our part but instead just to recognize this is
part of the human experience having these and maybe with that I'll turn it back
over to Tonya I guess I'll just check in and see if
you have any questions about those five hindrances central desire aversion
restlessness and worry sloth and torpor and doubt just to make sure you have a
chance to yeah Stephen do you mind using the mic there's one right here
hello hello there you go uh what does torpor mean
good question the way that we understand it is like I think that that whole phrase sloth and
torper it's like the energy has run out both of the body and the mind so torpor
we can think of like when there isn't this energy there's like this dullness and the mind is just feels
foggy and maybe cloudy or something like this as well as not having
um or not having energy in the body so that's what I would I think that makes sense but like you know in my
interpretation like sloth is is is something um
that you can contribute to like if you decide to be lazy
or eat too much so I'm relating to that but torpers it sounds like it's just
more of a an effect I would say that and we'll talk about these in more detail uh soon but uh
turns out that uh sloth and this idea of the body it can
be both from the environment what we've eaten or how much we've had to sleep or something as well as it's not an
uncommon way for people to kind of like disconnect from their experiences they
just kind of run out of energy they don't and so nowadays often what
somebody might do is just pick up their phone and kind of just mindlessly scroll or do some Doom scrolling or something
like that is how it might show up so something like that
[Applause]
does Fear fall under one of these categories doing it yeah you know that's an
interesting one because um I just read a different teachers interpretation about fear so
I'll say a few things one is they connected fear to aversion and or to
doubt and the way they did was they said with aversion you know it's about what
we don't want being afraid of what we don't want so it's kind of grounded in
aversion and the doubt was connected because when we don't know what's coming we're afraid
we're like we're trying to protect ourselves in some way I've also connected it with a sense of
anxiety right worry so but it's you know more rooted I think in in the the
aversion and or the doubt yeah yeah thank you for the question
any other dining anything you want to add to that maybe I'll just say that when I had
mentioned well you know maybe today we would divide them up a little bit differently ahead in my mind that maybe
we would highlight fear as its own because it is such a common experience but uh yeah we kind of put it in there
with aversion yeah most often great any other thoughts questions
sound familiar recognize the states yeah great
so um let me talk a little bit about you know this crazy movie Wizard of Oz and
um what some of the connections are and and um how some of the these hindrances
might be you might be able to see them if you watch the movie remember the
movie or just imagine the movie um so first of all just you know these
characters are exaggerations extreme exaggerations so just know it's there
you know that's what makes them kind of stand out and easy to recognize so it can be just kind of fun to think
about well what hindrance would I match with what character you know just sort of like oh yeah and another thing to
think about is that there are there's this idea that and Buddhism they say there's like these
different personality types and often that's referencing people who
are greed type I want I like people who are aversive I don't like you know stop
and then people who are deluded who are just kind of out of it and in their own world
but actually I I would like to expand that to include the other hindrances that there are personality types we if
we stay stuck in a pattern of the hindrances we can develop a pattern of a lot of soft and torpers you know you
might know somebody who you know just doesn't ever get off the couch right or just can't engage mentally and and you
also might know somebody who can't ever sit down that they're restless and they're you know kind of just have too
much energy so this is not enough energy sloth and torper and too much energy
restlessness and worry in the body and the mind and um
I just forgot where I was going but oh yeah this exaggeration right so it's
very easy and these personality Styles it's sort of like the Tin Man and the
Scarecrow and the lion super kind of embody some of these hindrances
um of course the wicked witch
could you just write them down when you have a chance yeah that'd be great um so
um then so I'm going to come back to the characters in a minute but I just sort of wanted to say that about the
exaggeration another thing I wanted to say is that there's often multiple hindrances
present at one time so very often there's a combination of things going on and
um so you can you'll see that when we talk about the characters a little bit and then
um another thing is to notice this idea of a veil or a covering the hindrance is
something that covers the way something is seen you know so for example the Scarecrow he
thinks he needs a brain right if you watch the movie from the perspective of thinking about okay he he
is you know very he embodies a lot of restlessness he moves all over he's very
sloppy in his movement he falls and his expressions are very erratic his moods
kind of Swing all over the place so sort of this too much energy guy
and he doesn't think he's smart but as you watch this show what you see
is he ends up being the person who comes with all the strategies for how to get places do things
he actually is the person who is the most kind of you know like thoughtful minded in terms of he has this in
himself he has a brain but he has this doubt and this restlessness and worry
but Cloud his ability to recognize his own inherent wisdom his own brain
so the lion well actually let me talk about the um the Tin Man next so he thinks he needs a
heart and he is Rusted shut so he embodies
sloth and torper right he can't move and that's kind of what happens there's no energy he's rested shut he can barely
talk you know they have to grease him up help him move and get going
and and but what he has he thinks he you know he needs a heart he thinks he's empty chested you he said knock on my
chest and you have this empty tin can sound but actually he's a romantic you know he
talks about romantic love and he tears up right which makes him rest again so
he goes you know they all end up on on the search with Dorothy to try and get
these things they think they don't have which are all within them but the hindrance is sort of what kind
of prevents them from connecting with it and it's um and it hides it from view even though
it's there it's already there so
um another thing that um you might think about when you think about you know the
Wizard of Oz himself and the City of Oz it's all green
and it's got these painted horses it's just like crazy
fancy wild City and The Wizard himself is is a fake he's a fraud right so he he
himself is from Kansas it turns out which is where Dorothy's from and um he's like hiding behind this curtain
and using the speaker and this like scary visualization with little fire
Puffs and you know to intimidate people and to make this assumption or this
impression of power but the way that I have come more and more to see The Wizard of Oz is like a
magic show it's like the magic show that the mind
is creating all the time the many movies that were you know have going on in our
heads we're creating these stories we're believing the thoughts that are happening and everything gets
exaggerated blown up on Technicolor right when we buy into the thinking and
the stories that we're patchworking together in our own mind
um the mind can really fool us and that's bring up so much fear that's like generates these senses of something
terrible is going to happen so there's this combination of like this
delusion but it's it's a magic show he's all about magic in fact in the beginning
of the movie um so Dorothy is an adopt you know adopted
by her aunt and lives on the farm in Kansas and out in the middle of nowhere and you notice in the beginning of the
film it's all black and white it's just black and white there's no color and to me this is a representation of
where her mind state is at the time which is everything is kind of
All or nothing and terrible they're going to take Toto her dog and she doesn't she tries to get her aunt and
uncle to respond to her and they're busy taking care of these baby chicks because the the lights for the Hatchery have
burnt out or aren't working so they're not really listening to her when she's saying this woman who becomes the wicked
witch is going to take her dog away and so she runs away and she packs her bag because she wants
to you know carry off her Toto and protect him she runs away and she runs
into this guy who's kind of one of those traveling magicians he's got a crystal ball
and he you know she asks him to you know for you know advice and he brings her in
he tells her close your eyes and oh let me hold your purse keep your
eyes closed and then he goes through her purse and pulls out this picture of her Auntie M and the farm with the little
like Weather Vein on the top and he says to her things like oh I see this Farm
and and there's this Weather Vein you know and then there's this woman out there and she's crying you know and and
so he's making all of this up based on you know what he's looked at you know
and she thinks he's you know looking at his crystal ball so this is a magic show
he's pretending to know and what he's doing is you know he doesn't want her to
travel with him in his little Caravan so he's motivating her to go back home out
of worry for her Auntie M and so she's she runs off but at the
same time you see right after she goes there's this storm coming right this twister is coming
and she's off and and he walks out of his little thing and says oh I hope she
makes it Oak home okay you know this is a very bad storm and he knows it and he
sent her out into it too right so this this trickster he's really a trickster
right and um acting to be this nice guy right
so these characters from The Wizard of Oz
come from you know her Kansas place but you'll see if you watch the movie or
think about it you can reflect in seeing you know kind of the origins of a lot of what happens when the Twister comes she
gets knocked in the head the house gets picked up carried up into the sky and dropped into
the Land of Oz this other world and the house lands on the Wicked Witch of the
East right is it the east or the West I don't remember one of the wicked witches and kills the wicked witch
so um Dorothy then is on this search to get
back home because she's worried about her Aunt Em so she has all this drive and desire to
get back home and she she's looking and seeking how to get home and she's
looking to others and then she's putting her trust in this Wizard of Oz to help him help her get home but he's a
trickster right he puts on the magic show and on her journey to the Wizard of Oz
she meets all these characters and they all come with her all seeking from this
wizard the things that they feel that they lack that they all have within themselves
so there's the wicked witch as you know greed she wants the shoes she wants the
power right and she's also the wicked witch of hatred of aversion I'll get you
my pretty she says you know she's gonna threatens and to kill Dorothy the straw
man I mentioned sort of seeing him as the energy of restlessness and worry too
much energy unsteady kind of constantly in motion
um the Tin Man as the sloth and the torpor the not enough energy
um and also like if you think about the Tin
Man is a representation of that that hindrance you notice he speaks slowly
that torpor the slowness of the minds right the mind is slowed down and he
doesn't process things very quickly and his emotions are sort of
dampened sort of depressed in a way and then they come to the lion
and the interesting thing about the lion is you know he's very worried
he worries a lot but you don't see it when you first meet him he actually his own doubt his own
hindrance he covers by trying to instead of you know the opposite of
Investigation he actually pretends he's a brave bully
he he comes out with the opposite of what he feels so he's covering up his own doubt his
own worry his own sort of restlessness you know his own worry and anxiety by
pretending to be the exact opposite right which is quickly uncovered if you
remember and that's he comes out he jumps out at them bullying them trying to get him to fight
and then what happens is Toto comes up and Barks and so he decides to chase
Toto and then Dorothy comes to his protection Dorothy comes to toda's protection and confronts the line and
slaps his nose and then he cries the line just breaks down he's like whoa why
did you hit me you know all of his fears come out immediately he goes from fully and trying to get people to fight to
just sobbing right and so let's see what else do I need to say
just a little bit more um I see Dorothy you know as a character
she has this strong pull the strong desire to protect Toto to get back to
her aunt to find her way home and I see this as what we call
um as Chand a healthy desire it's misplaced but there's this healthy
desire to get home to reconnect you know to sort of get back to sort of
what feels right to her home and I'll call home you know mindfulness presence
being aware being awake and Toto to me is the complete
embodiment of mindfulness when you remember at when they're at the
scene where they go back to see the wizard after the wicked witch has been killed on accident
um Toto goes over to where the wizard is behind the curtain
Toto pulls the curtain back and exposes the wizard behind the curtain
it's his simple awareness his ability to just sort of not get caught up in the
magic show did not get caught up in all the worry and all the things that I want and all
the doubts and you know what I need he's just like look there's somebody over
here pulls the curtain back disposes the whole magic show right
so that's that's how I connect with the Wizard of Oz and how I see all of these
you know the hindrances and a little bit more as embodiments of the the Dharma
so any comments any anything you want to add to that or questions and Richard did
you write down some questions you could hand them to me um before we'll break up into small groups
and we have a question for you guys to um to discuss with each other
but any you want to add anything any other insights questions clarifications
yeah Stephen
have kind of a funny uh
uh like it um so like
basically all these different uh characterizations are kind of something that you can kind of visualize and
they're all they're all happening yeah when we're meditating yes some more than some you know sometimes
you have that multiple hindrance attack and they're all happening sometimes there's a dominant hindrance
that's present so um you know
it's almost like something that you associate with like different colors emotions yeah there's like these things
that come up yeah but um I remember I was on a retreat and we we did a little
sketch where we um personifying these different um
but I just wanted to add that the Insight it was
kind of goofy Canadian guy yeah he had um he just happened to have with him on the
retreat he wore like a uh with the bicycle or when you're in a
cave like those lights that oh yeah yeah so like when we did the little sketch we
in addition to the different um hindrances we also had headlamps a guy who was in
sight oh Insight could see Shine the Light yes
um I I think that that's also you know that's like Toto right shining the light
bringing the awareness on to what's real beautiful yeah and the head the headlamp
is great I love it are you know like bringing insight to like
you know even even an individual like uh an example like like if you feeling
um ill will towards someone you could have like the insight that that that's happening when you're
meditating yes beautiful thank you
anything else
can you hear me yeah okay so how about the monkeys yeah how about the monkeys
what do you think of the monkey's Gus well I I just think that they come up in meditation more often in a much less
structured way than the primary characters yes much less structured monkeys right monkey mind and and
they're they're doing the bidding of the wicked witch they're under the spell of the wicked witch right so
um and as soon as the wicked witch dies they're happy they're jumping around they're happy to be free not be under
her spell you know under her control so I guess you know like it's good to
think about in what way do we you know get under the spell of these
different hindrances and and put into emotion or actions certain things that
you know are like the little monkeys just getting sent off to do things right beautiful
thank you would you add anything to what I just said
uh not really I think in my practice what I do is I just
I noticed that there and I just wait them out and I rate them essentially it you know yeah
great I can't tell them to go yeah
and you know so there's a question that came in from YouTube and you know you're
kind of pointing to what you do with these hindrances or manifestations of the hindrances and
tonight we really and I think it's important to invite you to get familiar
we're not going to talk a lot about how to work with each of these hindrances tonight tonight
so Diana mentioned something that is so important that you know when doubt
arises or when a hindrance arise it's very useful to investigate to get
to know it to like she said the water comes in contact with The Rock so instead of giving answers to how to
work with these things this week we're going to help name them help you kind of
start to identify them and invite you to not take them so personally
and see what you can learn about these qualities these mind States these veils
these hindrances as they come up in your life don't take them so seriously
right don't get too wrapped up in trying to block them or prevent them
you don't want to be acting from them but if you can turn toward them and
learn a little bit about them so
yeah
oh nice
do you wanna
the question was I was curious about how emotions surrounding guilt come into
this with the hindrances yeah guilt this is a very uh interesting
topic and maybe I'll just say um briefly in the kind of like in the
Buddhist um teachings we don't Focus so much on guilt
we're more about remorse and then what's the difference guilt as the sense of
like Oh I'm a bad person I did this thing that harmed somebody or harmed
myself I shouldn't do that and I should stop doing that and next time I'm not
going to do this or something like that so there's a focus on the individual feeling bad and kind of like yeah
feeling bad I'll say remorse has a focus on oh there's this
harm that caused that got cause this person is suffering and this is nobody
wants to suffer and how can we alleviate or diminish the suffering in other people so it's not so much about me as a
bad person it's more about oh there's harm that got caused and let's not cause
harm so it has a different shift a different emphasis and remorse goes in
with restlessness I would add that um
I think guilt like some it's good to again investigate so when you feel
guilty about something what's kind of underneath the like listen to some of the thoughts listen to
the associations that are happening in the mind it could so easily be
you know maybe you had hatred come up maybe you expressed hatred you know and
you or you didn't express it but you felt it so you feel guilty about it you feel you're a bad person so it's sort of
like having aversion to aversion and then it creates a sense of I feel
bad you know this had I'm bad it also for me is like sometimes I will get tripped up in this
doubt that's a doubt guilt dance it's like something about like oh I probably said
that wrong you know and it's like this awful horrible space of feeling this
doubt that comes out in a way like I'm guilty I'm bad I'm not good enough so you've gotta kind of there's so many
ways these things get masked masked you know covered and
and manifested so investigate try and see for yourself so I hope that was a a
good answer out there thank you for asking so let's let's give you a little bit of
a chance to break up into you know we've got one's four seven so two groups
right and um my why don't you go ahead and just make
a small circle here in a small circle here and then we'll give you the next set of instructions
it's an opportunity for you guys to talk to each other instead of just listening to us all the time and once you get there just start by sharing your names
and maybe you know how much you've been to IMC or where you live or something
silly Pleasant like that
so you can see
it
okay so our thinking is that maybe I'll just
first briefly remind us of the hindrances there's kind of like this desire the
Leaning forward and aversion leaning back kind of push pull too we can think about
and then there's a too much energy resistance or not enough energy sloth and torpor and then there's this
fifth one doubt or hesitation or uncertainty or not knowing
so those are the five and as Tanya was saying it's not
uncommon for people to have one that tends to show up a lot for them if you
might know that if you're somebody that's always looking for the next exciting new thing or maybe you're
somebody who finds it difficult to sit still or whatever it might be so just to
share a little bit is there one of these entrances that for you feels
um I don't know particularly interesting or juicy or something you'd like to work with you do not have to share any of
your deep dark secrets or anything like this but is there one of these five that
right now kind of has caught your attention and you'd like to pay more attention it's either because it shows
up a lot in your life or maybe because you doesn't show up at all or you don't see it or you don't
understand it or something like this and so just I have an opportunity for each one of you to kind of like share
which a hindrance and then after each one of you has had a chance then you can just maybe open it
up for a more General discussion but maybe just some general guidelines
is I'm not giving advice to each other there's a no reason to do that and
maybe that's it we don't have to tell long complicated stories we're not going to be here for the whole evening so you
know just enough to kind of give the flavor of what you're talking about or what you'd like to share and then Tanya
and I will ring the bell in a little bit but just an opportunity for you guys to talk to each other and have a chance to talk instead of just listening to us all
the time and maybe just generally speaking each person can talk for one to
two minutes because we'll probably have about 10 minutes in the small group Total so if
you just kind of keep a little bit of a loose eye so everyone gets a chance to share and then a little bit of time for
reflection together time to joining
thank you Jay if you but if you at any point if you want to grab one or both of
us we're happy to come over and gauge if you're feeling like you're just need a
little bit more of our help or support or anything we're right here for you
I I kind of wish I could listen in foreign
we'll have to see are you guys in a good space to kind of wrap up or do you need
more time because if you need more time we'll just take something else off that we were going to do if you feel like
a couple more minutes great so how about I'll ring the bell in two minutes okay
so if I was a fly on the wall and I got to here in what what my I have learned
what would you share with me about how that was is there anything you feel comfortable sharing about your
conversations there's the microphones
thank you Brian
yeah it's uh we all have our own ways of in which the hindrances are represent
themselves like for example I hardly ever am in silence either
something some music playing or a video playing um
you like videos and looking for comments right Netflix
there's different things that we do you know and we try to classify them in
our in our conversations right and for me a lot I think a lot of it is like avoidance like yeah some of the things I
do it's avoiding dealing with something um and you know for some of the other
people in the room what was the fourth one the sloth interpreter where it was just low energy
you just kind of you know disconnecting from things for a while
thank you so much cool that you were kind of describing
what you do and seeing and kind of mapping and seeing that we it shows up differently for everyone right that's
that's so beautiful and that's the thing they're gonna it's not always you know
it's not cut and paste right it's going to manifest differently
so I didn't even realize it before we were talking about it but um like we
were just talking so like nine o'clock at night I turned on Netflix and I tune
out and I never thought of it as corporate before
but I I like it I mean I don't see it as a negative I see it as a positive it
kind of oh refreshes my mind in a way and um
to me I always thought those two sloth and torpor were like
really negative and um
I'm Gonna Keep Going nice you know I I think Diana wants to say something too
but I think our when we get out of whack with our Energies you know one of the things that can
happen is like if we're doing too much concentrating too much making and doing
the opposite is you know happens it comes up and that's the sloth and torpor
right there's a certain way in which there's a an effort to kind of rebalance but we're going from the repentulation
it's too too big the swings are too big right so what were you going to say Diana oh I was going to say right we're
calling these hindrances because they're getting in the way of something so trying on Netflix itself and tuning out
may not be a bad thing it might be just the right thing to kind of help the body and mind relax and like disconnect from
the day or something like that so maybe in that way it's not a hindrance so it works for me yeah so there's
you see it as a oh I see it as a positive not I think yeah yeah so we're talking about
things you know that are getting in the way of things that we want in our lives or in our meditation practice
great anything else anyone wants to share
maybe I'll uh just address this so a question how do the hindrances relate to
the noble Eightfold Path are they manifestations of wrong View I wouldn't say that there are
manifestations a wrong view these are just natural things that happen instead the hindrances are an integral part of
concentration practice and mindfulness practice in fact we're going to talk more about mindfulness in this class but
one way if we were to teach concentration one way to think about concentration practice is hindrance
practice absolutely because hindrances are what get in the way of kind of like getting settled so some ways we might
even say mindfulness practice is hindrance practice too like noticing what gets in the way of
of being present for what's happening so that's where they show up in the April
path yeah and I would say I think the wrong view comes in if we have the wrong view of the hindrances oh yeah you know
if we're if we're relating to them from a perspective of aversion right like
there's a um and not recognizing the suffering that they can cause you know that's
where maybe we might want to look at how they get tangled up with the wrong view yeah I would say like maybe if we do
take them personally and it's like Oh I'm a bad meditator or I'm a bad person
if we kind of like take that on that's definitely would I would say be wrong but you're kind of like personalizing
them and if you don't know what the Eightfold Path is that's perfectly fine too
I'm trying to read uh so are there some aversions
killing Etc that may be actually good can you comment
yes of course I don't want to talk about uh specific
ones but of course we need to uh turn
away from some things we need to set boundaries we need to say this is not
good I'm not going to do that or something like this or it's so it's not just trying to be a doormat and allow
everything to flow through we're talking more specifically things that get in the way of our life get in the way of our
meditation practice seeing clearly getting in the way of seeing clearly thank you getting in the way of seeing
clearly yep yep yep so um let's just see what you guys like
there's going to be a one of the things we're going to teach to help work with the hindrance is a practice called raft
so we could do a very short very short five-minute guided raft practice if you
want that experience yes I see one head yes two it's a practice of mindfulness
practice the acronym is raft so it's a guided practice Yeah so we've
got a yes I think enough of a yes Diana in five minutes in five minutes
okay maybe six Let's uh let's take a a posture that's
um has some alertness but also some relaxation
just tune in in general to how the body
is right now is it have too much energy not enough
energy or is there some wishing that you could go home
wishing that uh get away from something or maybe that's showing up in the body and
the physical experience
just a relaxed easy way tuning in
nothing in particular needs to be happening we don't need to do anything
in particular just bringing our attention to the bodily experience in general
and then can you recognize oh yeah
there is a little bit of restlessness or a little bit of tiredness or a little
bit of push or pull can you recognize can you tune into that
and can you allow it to be there it is there already
can you just allow it to be there
without having aversion towards aversion or aversion towards restlessness or any
of that right aversion is one of the hindrances
can we allow this experience during the meditation to be there
one of the supports for allowing it to be there
is to tune into the physical experience that's how you discovered it initially
but often we get go into a story but can you go back to the physical
experience for example restlessness might feel like
there's a lot of buzziness or energy
bouncing through the body or maybe the legs where the arms feel a little
energized or maybe sloth and twerpa maybe there's
some tiredness around the eyes or heaviness in the shoulders
there's some desire there might be a slight leaning forward or up with the chin
whatever version maybe there's a little slight you know pulling back
can you feel in the body
that experience letting the thoughts take care of
themselves we're focusing on the bodily experience
and something else that can help you allow the experience to be there
is to tease apart to separate what is the actual experience
that restlessness in the body example Separate Peace apart from our reaction
to that we don't want it to be there for example these are two different things
restlessness and not wanting them to be there for example
might be the restlessness is in the body and maybe not wanting to be theirs in
the mind or maybe that's just diversion but can you tease apart
The Experience from our reaction to the experience
foreign
recognize our allow a f feel in the body
T tease apart and then you add a second T yeah so what did what happened in your
meditation that you feel was useful that you can
trust what did you see what did you feel what did you notice
it was something that you you could rely on so the T the second T is trust like oh
it was helpful to try and Pull Apart these two pieces when I pulled them apart oh I felt a sense of like ease in
my body it didn't feel so heavy for example so were you able it was a short practice
but was there anything that became more clear to you this seemed helpful about
recognizing naming maybe it was just oh just recognizing that this is going on
is helpful right there oh can I trust that if I recognize this it's helpful
so this idea of trusting what you can rely on in the practice
is a nice place to end the practice kind of helps you let go a little bit
you feel that that sense of okay it is good it's useful to recognize for
example yeah makes sense this is kind of a little resting stopping point
for the raft so we'll be spending much more time with us our aft raft recognize
allow feel in the body tease apart trust yeah
so eight o'clock okay if I just do a very brief summary before we end
so the five hindrances arise in meditation and our daily life right they're natural
they happen to all of us they're just a normal part of Being
Human we want to encourage you to approach working with them recognizing them with
curiosity with a lightness not a heaviness
and um just part of that is that we tend to
actually reinforce them when we have a like oh no reaction or we try and get
rid of them or we kind of tend to grow them they get stronger
so a light a light approach a normalizing approach and not taking it personal
and then you know one interesting way for me of noticing hindrance is present
is actually to notice what do I share with others or what do they share with
me like somebody comes home and all they do is complain complain complain right so that's somebody manifesting the
hindrance of aversion or there I can't know why should I do just that simple thing what's their what
are they talking about what am I talking about that can help us see the hindrances when they're present
and so this week just the invitation is to
just be curious and to see if you can notice when these different states come up and then notice what happens when you
recognize them and can you if you're thinking about raft if you recognize it notice can I
allow this hindrance to be here or am I having aversion to it or trying
to get rid of it just just that simple so thank you so much
look forward to seeing you hopefully next week thank you thank you I feel like you're welcome to come up and talk
to us if you have some comments or otherwise we'd look forward to seeing you next week