so I'll Echo what Hillary said it's such a practice such a joy to practice
together maybe it's a practice to be together too right as some of you know I'm Diana Clark and
I teach here on Monday nights and uh it's a pleasure to be here on a Sunday morning
well I think Gill is teaching a retreat I think that that's uh where he is
so today I thought I'd talk a little bit about this idea sometimes we use this
word Dharma what is Dharma like what is it what is a Dharma talk
and what is like to follow the Dharma or be with the Dharma or like what what is that really
and we have so many different ideas about it maybe each of us have our own
idea there's lots of room for maybe interpretation
and part of the reason why there's room for interpretation is because this word in poly means so many different things
and it gets used in so many different ways
and one way that isn't so common but it's kind of meaningful for me this
idea that Dharma and Paulie this word comes from the root der which means to hold
to support so the Dharma is something that can hold
us and support us and prevent us from falling
and what does that mean to fall well maybe for each of us we have our own
idea what that means to fall fall into despair fall into hopelessness
or just fall into not caring or maybe for whatever it might mean for us
so the Dharma is something that is support and can hold
and also of course the Dharma is so often understood as the Buddha's teachings
so something that he shared with everybody this was his life's work is to
share the teachings and people who sit in this seat right we kind of like are wanting to share the Dharma also
but also there's also a meaning of the Dharma is kind of like the nature of
reality that's the way things are
and part of Dharma teachings under my practice is to help us become sensitive
to or tuned into this way things are instead of the way that we often think
they are or the concepts or the ideas that we might have or the wishes we might have or but how they actually are
might say is the Dharma and there's this uh quote from the suit
does that includes this word tatakata I like even to say this word
it's a word that how the Buddha refers to himself it's a name that he calls
himself it won't go into exactly what it means but to talkata
so this is the Buddha speaking about the Dharma and he says
whether there is an arising of a titogata or no arising if it's a dog so
whether there's a Buddha or not that law of nature still persists
the stableness of the Dharma the fixed course of the Dharma
a tatakata awakens to this and breaks through to it
and having done so he explains it teaches it proclaims it establishes it
discloses it analyzes it and elucidates it
that's why there's like 40 years of the Buddha talking right he has a lot of other things to do here
but this idea this uh concept that the Dharma is something
that's already there and the Buddha just notices it so it's not something like he
made up it's like part of this law of nature that he discovered and then shares
so in my mind it's kind of like that something like a gravity like gravity is
there but maybe it took somebody like Sir Isaac Newton to get a little bit curious
or to discover you know we have the story of the Apple falling and Sir Isaac Newton getting curious like wait why
does it do that and his understanding in his teaching so gravity was always there
maybe in the same way that Dharma is already there but it takes a Buddha to first break through to it is kind of
the language and then to share it maybe to highlight something that we
already know that we've already noticed
and yet maybe to to Spring our attention to it or to analyze elucidate you know
all these different words to point it out in a way that we can go oh yeah
right right yeah and I'll say for me
the first time I heard the Dharma was entirely by accident that I was trained as a research
scientist I spent years in a laboratory with a white lab coat test tubes the
whole thing right so that was thought what I was going to do and I got interested in yoga which alone was
seemed to be like I didn't dare tell my friends I was doing yoga my science friends would not have thought that was
okay you know this was back you know a few decades ago and I was a yoga Workshop that was over
a weekend and I remember it was called oh so now that it just slips my mind the exact uh
language but it was something about uh oh Tibetan heart yoga and I thought wow
to bed that's like seems pretty exotic and harsh okay this is gonna be great I'm gonna sign up for this
my life was a little bit of a mess then and I was just looking for something that would be hopeful
and so this uh this Workshop we did a lot of you know
the postures Asana practiced what we typically think of when we think of yoga
and in the description there said there'd be some philosophy and I thought oh okay philosophy is kind of interesting
so after we had done all these uh postures then uh we were right a little
break and then we're supposed to come back for the philosophy part so we're all sitting in you know on our
yoga mats and our cute little yoga outfits you know right
and in walks this person which I now know was a in tibetan monastic robes you
know red and gold and this kind of shiny stuff I'm like oh my goodness
no no thank you I did not sign up for this I don't want
any religion thank you no no no no but I was sitting as far as possible
from the door and it would have been really awkward for me to get up and walk out otherwise honestly I probably would
have that was just where I was in my life I wasn't looking for answers and
religion and by some dude wearing these odd clothes
but my stage
and he started to talk about the Four Noble Truths
and this was the first time I'd ever heard anything like this the truth of suffering
the truth of a cause of suffering truth of obsessation the ending of
suffering and a way to the ending of suffering
something in me don't know resonated and I found myself
sitting there with tears going down my face this recognition oh yeah there's
something here something here
you know never did I imagine that uh a few decades later I'd be sitting here
right to giving a Derma talk but that was how it started for me so maybe this
recognition oh yeah there's something there maybe some of you have had some of this
similar experience maybe some of you haven't and that's okay right we all find our own way here
but today I'd like to share a story that comes from a poly Canon about somebody
who also heard the Dharma and felt really touched by it
and does something really unprecedented maybe or unheard of or
radical and everybody gets curious about it and asks wow why did you do that
and then he gives his reasons so this is the story of ratapala
and this Story begins with as most stories do with that are in the poly
Canon with a description of where the Buddha is so the Buddha is in this town Tula kotita with a whole bunch of
monastics this usually what happened like that Buddha would travel around and give talks
so he arrives in this town to Lakota and many people were excited or wanted to
hear he had his reputation was a good reputation and so people like oh okay this
go to ma is here let's go listen to him talk
see what all the above is about and so retipolla went to go hear the
Buddha talk so retipolla was the son of a very
wealthy and influential family in this town chulakotita
his family was maybe one of the most well-known and influential and they had
a relationship with the King you know this kind of a family
so the Sun goes to hear the Buddha speak and he was so inspired by what he heard
the Buddha say he decides this is going to be my life
calling this is what I'm going to do so after the end of the speaking he goes
up to the Buddha and says I want to ordain I want to become a monastic and devote my life to this I was so touched
by your teachings there's something inside me that knows this is what I want to do
and the Buddha said well do you have your parents permission
and he says no but don't worry I'll go by get their permission I'll come back
and then all ordain and the Buddha says okay so retipolla goes back to his family
and says I just heard this talk and I'd like to ordain
and his parents are like nope no no
and they gave him a number of reasons for this and the first one is
you have been raised in Comfort brought up in comfort you know nothing
of suffering in my mind maybe red De Paula had told
them about the four noble truths and how it really spoke to him you know we don't actually know what the teaching was that
the Buddha gave but we can imagine his parents saying you can't handle it you don't even know
what suffering is you've been sequestered in this simple life with a family so wealthy
and then they also said to him you can be happy pursuing sensual Pleasures just
stay here anything you want we can give to you
maybe retipolla probably had been growing up with nothing but sensual pleasures and
didn't think that that was going to be the answer so they give him a third reason and say
you are our only child dear and beloved
when you die we will lose you against our wishes so how can we allow you to go
forth while you're still alive to go forth is an expression to ordain
so to ordain it means that he would go and follow the Buddha or be with the Buddhist he would leave his family
he would have like a completely different relationship with his family once you become a monastic and they're like you're our own only son
how can you do that no something inside of him felt like nope
this is what I want to do that's what I want to do with my life it's it's meaningful for me
his parents said no but he really wanted to
so he just said he went on a hunger strike I'm not going to eat until you let me ordain
and in my mind the Buddhism the parents are going like okay we'll just wait them out where he's so used to having
fantastic food and anything he wants he's not gonna like we'll see give him a little taste of this suffering
but of course it doesn't work and he's getting weaker and weaker
so rhetor Paula's parents go to retipolla's friends say can you talk some sense into him
so the right to Paula's friends go to talk to him I'd say well you don't need
to ordain why just stay with your family with this life that you have
right deposit nope this is what I want to do this is what's meaningful for my life
this just makes sense for me so I write to Paula's friends go back to
his parents and say well maybe you can let him ordain
and he can come back and he can still see you it's not like you'll lose him completely
but if he continues not eating he's going to die and you will lose him completely
and maybe he won't enjoy being a monastic maybe he'll ordain and discover
how difficult it is does Robin come back and just get it out of his system
or maybe he won't maybe those are the two main
reasons you can see him afterwards and he might not enjoy it so just let him ordain
so retapala ordains and he follows the Buddha and he does the Buddha's
teachings and not long after he becomes awakened
believe Ever After right but that's not the end of the story
because at one time the Buddha and his monasticity come back to this town Tula
kotita and there's a number of things have happened but I'm going to focus on one portion of
this so the king hears that the Buddha is back in town
and that retapula is there is now is one of the monastics and the King had heard
this story that the Sun the only son of one of the most prominent people in town had chosen to ordain and the King was
kind of curious why why would this young man who had
everything ordained the king wants to know
so the the king gets notified that retapula is
out meditating in a park and this was common at that time like you know under a tree or something like this in a
protected area so the king
goes up to him and uh the king offers Tourette here's a
sitting mat would you like to sit on this I went to Paul says no I'm actually comfortable would you like to join me
you can sit with me this is pretty unheard of like the king is like is teaching or
showing respect retipolla this young man but this King had such respect for the
monastics and really wanted to talk to retipolla so he teaches
he teaches he speaks to him with such respect and ratapola also offers him
respect and so why don't you sit with me so here's these two people sitting
and the king says to him
to write to public what did you know or see or hear that made you ordain just
thought out asks him I read to Paula replies
great king the blessed one blessed one is how monastic addresses the Buddha how they
refer to the Buddha so the blessed one great king the blessed one who knows and
sees the perfected one the fully awakened Buddha has taught four
summaries of the Dharma and it was after a knowing and seeing
and hearing these that I went forth from the laylife to homelessness
that expression from lay life to homelessness means to ordain
so retypile is saying he heard four summaries of the Dharma
and that's what touched him so much and inspired him to go forth that to forsake
his family abandon everything and go ordain
so if you can naturally imagine what the King asks well what are these four
summaries of the Dharma
was a really skilled teacher and so he spoke to the king in a way
that the king could understand and the way that the king could relate to so he doesn't give the king a lecture
he speaks to the king in ways that the king could understand like using examples that are relevant to the King's
life and he asks questions sir the king so it's more like a dialogue that they're
having rather than here let me preach to you or something like that we can imagine that this is something
that a king would appreciate and I'll say in the Buddhist teachings
in Nepali Canon that practitioners People Like Us
are often referred to as royalty also like there's something some dignity or
some royalty within us I I appreciate this this recognition that
we all of us have our own dignity whomever we are whatever our life is
there's some part of us that's royalty as well
so I like to imagine that Ezra Paul is talking to this King maybe he's talking to us
so the retipolla gives the first summary of
the Dharma the world is unstable and swept away
the king asked for clarification what does that mean the world is
unstable and swept away so here's ratapala's response what do
you think a great king when you were 20 or 25 years of age were you proficient
at writing elephants horses and chariots and at archery were you strong and
capable I was Master at DePaula it's sometimes
it seems as if I had super powers then I don't see anyone who could have equaled me in strength
well what do you think great king these days are you just as strong and
capable no master atapola for now I am old
elderly and Senior sometimes I intend to step in
one place but my foot goes somewhere else this is what the Buddha was referring to
when he said the world is unstable and swept away
so retapala is pointing out what the king already knows that aging happens
and some proficiencies and capabilities and strengths that we had when we were younger
you know that goes away we all know this
and I'm sure the king recognized that but maybe he hadn't thought about it before
things are unstable and I like how the king gives this example that's explicitly about being
unstable right so that he tends his foot to step one way but it goes another
maybe even trips or slips or something
second summary but retipolla says the world has no shelter and no savior
and the King asked for clarification what does that mean heret Apollo says as an example asks a
question in this Royal Court oh I'm sorry the king is saying this to
retipolla in this Royal Court you can find divisions of elephants Calvary chariots and infantry so that for them
was their military their entire military and they will serve to defend us from
any threats yet you said there is no shelter and no savior how should I
understand the meaning of this I read to Paula response
what do you think great king do you have any chronic ailments
yes sometimes my friends and colleagues relatives and family members surround me
thinking the king's going to die when rental Paula says well what do you
think great king can you get your friends and colleagues relatives and family members
to help can you say to them please my dear friends and colleagues relatives and
family members all of you can you like share my pain can you take some of it so
that I don't feel it these chronic ailments no I can't get my friends to share my
pain rather I alone must feel it the Paul says well this is what the
Buddha is referring to when he said the world has no shelter and no savior
so often we have this idea that something out there is going to make us feel better other people other things
but it's pointing to like no there are difficulties that we cannot run away from there are difficulties that nobody
can take away from us that that we far alone have to be with
that nobody else even though we want them to and we so much there's uh
industries that are trying to think oh as long as you just do this or buy that or do this other thing then somehow all
your difficulties will go away so the King has surrounded himself with
these tools of warfare thinking that that will protect him but you know in modern day we might have
what do we surround ourselves with that we think is going to protect us from experiencing difficulties
feeling difficulties some of these things have actually can't go away
I know like there's this cool industry like oh no you can feel younger just
take this you can look younger just do this right you know that's some of the
what we hear but there's nobody that can protect us from sicknesses
completely aging completely chronic ailments completely right
they just they happen that was the second summer of the Dharma the third summary of the Dharma is
retypes the world has no owner you must leave it all behind and pass on
and the King asked for clarification what do you mean in this Royal Court you can find abundant gold coin and bullion
stored in Dungeons and towers and yet you said the world has no owner you must
leave it all behind and pass on how should I understand that
I read to Paula says well what do you think great king these days you amuse
yourself supplied and provided with the five kinds of sensual stimulation
five kinds seeing hearing tasting touching smelling
but is there any way to ensure that in the next life so after death
that you will continue to use yourself in the same way can you guarantee that after death you
will still be able to have this whatever makes you feel good
or will others make use of everything
all this gold and bullion all these things that you think are going to make you feel good after you die you're not
necessarily going to feel good others are going to have that they're going to have whatever the
objects were or whatever the equivalent of gold bullion is for us today
so he'll have to leave behind all his possessions everything men not only possessions but
in the next life will we be able to amuse ourselves with sight Syrian sea
scene smelling tasting touching smelling
we don't know nobody knows
so the king maybe was doing all this hoarding right he talked about how much gold he had and the Dungeons and Towers
there's a way in which we kind of like accumulate things thinking that this is going to protect us or make us happy
but there's a part of us that knows that's not the case
so then the fourth summary of the Dharma
the world is wanting insatiable the slave of craving
when the king asked for clarification how should I understand the meaning of this
retipolla response well what do you think great king do you dwell in the
prosperous land of Kuru that was the country in which they were
I do so what do you think suppose a trustworthy and reliable person were to
come from the East they would approach you and say Dear Sir you should know this I come
from the East and there is this large country that is successful and prosperous and full of people and they
have many elephants Calvary chariots and infantry and there's lots of money and
Grain and you could easily conquer it
and you should conquer it and then right to Paul asked what would you do if somebody said that to you and
the King replies I would go and Conquer it and get all the all the you know their Warfare and their people and their
grain and wealth and and then retipolla continues well
suppose a trustworthy and reliable person were to come from the West
and we're to say to you there's this large country that is successful and has
all this Army and people and wealth and you could easily conquer it what would you do
the king says well I would go to the west and Conquer that twin and you know where this story is going right and then
somebody comes from the north and says this oh I would conquer that too somebody comes from the south and says
this oh I'd conquer that too so it's pointing to like the king just it wants anything and everything
that he feels like he can get
and then write to Paula says well this is what the Buddha was referring to when he said the world is insatiable the
slave of craving insatiable
and it was after knowing and seeing and hearing this that I went forth from the
lay life to homelessness it was after understanding these four things that I ordained
and the King says wow it's incredible musteretta
it's amazing how well said this was by the Buddha
for the indeed the world is wanting insatiable the slave of craving
and then the king simply got up and left
they didn't show that respect to read to Paulie didn't show his appreciation but in my mind we can see that he's a little
bit troubled and like oh this is not what I expected
and just goes off to think about this and other versions of this story that
are preserved in the agamas if that means anything to anybody that the king
pays a lot of respect to retipolla and recognizes oh maybe they're the king
himself had recognized that there was some truth to what was being said
he's pointing out that none of the things that the king believes are going to be sources of lasting happiness
actually aren't sources of lasting happiness and I would say for us there's a way in
which we know this that we recognize this
these things that we keep on chasing and thinking they're going to keep us safe keep us happy
youth Beauty wealth
objects experiences they aren't a protection
from what life brings they certainly enhance life and by no means should we
like deny ourselves and say they're awful and never pursue them but it's a
trap if we think that that's what's going to make us happy if that's what's going to make our life worthwhile if
that's what's going to bring meaning to our lives
and maybe that's something when we hear like there is suffering
there's a cause for suffering there's going to be an ending of suffering and there's a path to sending
the suffering maybe that's what's being pointed to these four summaries of the Dharma
maybe the changing nature of the world sense of any real shelter
from what life brings us the fact that all has to be left behind at death
and then this insatiability of craving is one way we might understand the
Dharma what spinning pointed to with the Dharma
so thank you for your practice and for your attention and I'll stay up here if anybody has any
questions thank you