so hello and welcome I'm Nikki in Mountain View California on seated olon
land and welcoming you to happy hour who is here who wants to say hi so feel free
to unmute yourself and say hello hey this is Don from DC hello s hi
Don Fred in Oakland hi
Fred schola in Oakland hi who this is schola hi scha
nice to see you hi and I see uh bill says hello from Dallas in chat and hi
Hugh from San from Sunny San Diego it's cloudy M there's Leslie in Sunny San
Diego too hi Leslie and hi Peggy from Redwood City just up the
road neing nashille hi nean
Nashua Noel in P Alto also unseated aloney land hi Noel good to see
you great and Claire from New York City good evening to you nice nice are we
International today any any of our International contingent want to say
hello hello from Canada hi Sarah good to see
you great and hi Katrine and Lindsay and I
see Mari Christine from Down Under we're definitely International good afternoon no good morning I forget what time it is
in in Australia but good morning to you good day good good Tuesday to you
afternoon in Sydney thanks thanks Mary Christine great I the
space has been warmed up it feels uh the space is warmed up so let's uh let's get started let's get started and um thank
you for posting information about uh happier Google Groups um it's a low
traffic mailing list that we have uh which Neil just shared information about
in chat and also we have uh uh breakout
room etiquet if you choose to participate later uh ways to support yourself and support
each other so at this time I changed the settings so that uh chats only come to
me but I ask you to keep that uh Channel quiet the chat quiet because it can be
quite distracting for me to to get um chats
and uh let's see what else uh changing settings so the unmuting won't be
possible turn tur on recording for the sake of Audio Dharma here we go
great so hello and welcome everyone to this to this Gathering of happy
hour so um I wanted to uh share
Reflections about equinity which is the fourth Brahma vihara there are these um
four practic of the heart in Buddhism the first one being meta loving kindness
and we spend a lot of time at happy hour practicing loving kindness the second one being Compassion or karuna the third
one being mudita or vicarious joy joy for the joy of others and the fourth one
and and we do practice all of them and and the fourth one being equinity which um sometimes seems
perhaps the most subtle of of them and and folks might even wonder well why is
equinity part of these practices of the heart because um they all the rest of
them the other three seem warm and caring and Equanimity some people misund
understand as as all aloofness or or kind of not caring or like oh I'm
equanimous it's okay whatever happen so yeah what's how how is this one how does
it fit with the other ones and we'll practice it tonight um
and there's so much to say about equinity by the way um and in fact I'm I'm teaching a a dayong on equinity on
Saturday maybe I'll share information later so there's so much to discover but just to to to say here that equinity is
really the the um the birthplace of
warmth kindness compassion because it's really the stability of the heart that
is nonreactive that neither falls into doesn't get so overly involved in
attached or I want you to be well because I want you to be well and I'm so attached to it and I'm going to you know
grieve if you're not well so that sense of uh overwhelm and also it doesn't push
away it doesn't turn away to say oh oh talk to the hand I'm not listening or I
um or push something away with aversion so equinity is the sense of
equipoise or balance of the heart that allows us to Care to love um freely
openly spaciously unmoved um and and also there is warmth
and Care in equinity because if if there was no care in equinity it would become
complete resignation and turning away but it's not that those are the near enemies or the
masqueraders so so tonight what I'd like to invite us to to practice with again
there's so many nuances of equinity but this feeling of um uh this feeling of
um um equipoise this sense of balance I
want to invite us to relate to equin tonight as warmhearted balance
warmhearted balance on and what would that look like if we're cultivating
warmhearted balance in our heart so warmhearted balance and and to feel into it
physically so I've said enough so let's uh let's practice together and see what
it feels like to cultivate feel into um this warmhearted balance
okay so so arriving
arriving arriving in our
bodies arriving in this moment in time however it is and can we sit
with can we sit with a sense of balance in our
body where our feet are not cross our arms are in Cross but the sense of
balance and integrity sitting upright so that the body is
relaxed and yet sense of alertness
balance sitting dignified what does that mean to you
sitting with dignity and yet relaxed take a moment to
feel into your body what does that feel like for you do your hands need to move does your
torso need to move in order to achieve the sense
of relaxed
relaxed relaxed dignified
uprightness feel into your body what does it take for you to be sitting with
relaxed dignified
uprightness pay attention to your neck pay attention to your
face is it relaxed is it soft pay attention to your
spine is it upright attention to your shoulders and
neck are they relaxed how about your
abdomen is it soft your feet are
there are they spread and touching the
Earth your
toes relaxed and
alert
e
bringing awareness to your abdomen as the breath moves in and
out and we invite are tuning into the
calming nature of the breath in breath and out breath there is so much we can tune into
in this moment we can tune into distractedness that's available we can tune into sleepiness
agitation we can tune into so many things they're all
available can also tune into
home balance and this frequency is more
available through the breath if we followed the thread of the
breath and if you lose the thread if you drop it pick it
up following it
breed of calm of balance through INB breath and
out
breath dropping the other threads not needed can pick them up
later Choose Wisely
e
receiving the breath in the abdomen in breath and out
breath letting go of the thread of thoughts plans past future just
here the sense of
spaciousness with relaxed relaxed warm-heartedness
caring we care so much that we are present we're not
turning away from the breath we're not turning away from this moment we're fully present for this
moment not leaning back not pushing it away not leaning into
grasping neither over overwhelmed pushing
away nor entangled we're simply present calm and
present with this present moment as if you are present fully
present with a young
child willly present not
rushed impatient not wanting the child to be any other way with warm-heartedness
simply
present and this precious child is the experience of this
moment simply present for it with warm heart
goodness letting it be just as it is breathing with
it even if it's challenging in this moment with pain physically or in the
heart breathing with it being present with it giving it a lot of
space if it's gladness or joy and Delight [Music]
ease to letting the ease the gladness be just as it is the
spaciousness breathing with
it keeping its presence keeping its
company with equipoise
equinity neither Turning Away nor falling
into
e
in breath out breath keeping This Moment's company and if you lost a thread it's
okay just pick it
up calm
spacious warmhearted
presence present fully for This Moment's experience
unfolding whatever it
is
e
each in breath and out
breath receiving fully receiving spaciously receiving the
relaxed body and heart the experience of this moment letting it unfold just as it
is as if which were the movie of your life In This
Moment you're watching the movie of your life with
interest with [Music]
kindness with equipoise relaxed relaxing every muscle
of the body
and warm-heartedly with interest and curiosity but not with
entanglement being present fully
present for This Moment's experience
unfolding experience exping equipoise equinity one moment at a
time spacious present unentangled
caring it's like this right now how
interesting watching it arise and pass pass
away knowing it feeling it arise and pass
away it's okay it's
okay
e
and as we bring this period of practice to close
together appreciating yourself for having showed up as best as you're able
to no judgments we're planting seeds planting seeds
planting seeds of goodness and trusting trusting that they will germinate in in
their own time not our [Music] timetable and together offering the
goodness we have co-created seeds we have planted to all
beings everywhere may my practice be the Turning of my heart and
mind towards goodness be a support for
awakening for goodness for all beings everywhere may all beings everywhere be
happy may all beings everywhere be free including
[Music]
myself thanks everyone thanks for your practice ah it's so nice to sit and it's
so nice to sit with Community it's definitely different and more profound
to sit with with community so we have a little bit of
time to turn and practice with community in the way of showing up now
for one another with Ain remedy with this warmhearted presence that is
spacious and we'll spend about 7 Minutes in small groups groups of roughly size
three and the invitation is to show up for yourself
and others embodied with a sense of embodiment and the question the inquiry
is what does what what supports equinity for you cultivating equinity what
supports equinity for you and each person will offer one nugget and the
next person then the next person will come back to you will go round and round and so maybe one nugget will be ah when
my I feel my body um that supports equipoise equinity
for me then the next person might say ah um if I'm not in a
rush that might that supports having equ po me the next person might say if I'm
aware of my breath or whatever it might be just feel into your body what what supports what supports eonity for you
and you could also bring in and actually let's just do that what supports also what gets in the way that's kind of the
opposite the other side of the coin so you can maybe tell you what the first round uh the first two round do what
gets in the way of equinity and then the next next rounds do what supports and
then keep going with that okay so first two rounds what gets in the way of
cultivating equinity and then then third fourth fifth Etc rounds then what
supports what supports eonity okay and let's go alphabetical order according to
first name so um be kind take care of yourself
take care of each other um again you're speaking you're exploring for your own
sake not to educate not to instruct not to um yeah and and please don't comment
or as as it's in the etiquette you can click on it the the happy hour etiquette
um document not commenting on each other's practices and and really staying
with the practice not just what happened earlier yesterday
so and the rooms are created I'm going to open them take
care here we go okay welcome back everyone welcome back
so um would love to hear what you discovered any discoveries what gets in
the way what's supportive what is a coity hope it was a rich experience so
um um you can raise your Zoom hand you can also I'm going to turn Chat to be
everyone you can also share your Reflections in chat what did you discover for this for
the sake of everyone what did you discover
[Music] Mima thank you Nikki um it was I think
it was funny because even the the point the things that don't support us was still like in my case it it's
impermanence it's like that doesn't support because I shared that I have I had a real tiny little crockpot and last
night it broke I was washing it and broke I was like no there goes my equinity right and then I was like
that's the way it is it's okay it's okay but it was amazing to see that and then I love the building one another with the
things that that do support us um it was humorous we had fun so thank you for
that tonight oh that's great that just makes me so happy so light-hearted what you're sharing and also I love the the
story of the crockpot and and it's and and you're right impermanence challenges equinity it doesn't get in the way but
it challenges it things are impermanent and that's just the way it is and I loved how how you came back with this
challenge of oh I broke like that's just the way it is things break and and that
wisdom of yeah yeah sweetie Things Are imp permanent that's great be that's a
great example thanks for sharing that mimo thank you a yeah it's beautiful thank you
um Katrin please hi thank you for the practice I
got very relaxed it was very nice um I was recognizing that when like the main
obstacle for me to equinity is my mind of course but the particular
the self-critical sort of like scanning for what am I doing wrong or what is
wrong in the environment and um that what supports me
is to turn towards that part of my mind with loving
kindness and compassion and just be like oh sweetheart you're really you're
really trying to keep me safe by beating me up or by
you know or by pointing out how all the possible things that could go wrong and
that doesn't feel very equanimous but I I love you and I'm I really appreciate your care and then that seems to be the
way so the way like letting the heart be the the bridge into beautiful beautiful
yeah thank you letting the heart be the bridge that that kindness that compassion of of care especially when
the mind is is over Vigilant um yeah balancing it's a way of balancing
because it's it is in some ways the the mind in that case is pushing experience
away it's it's bad it's wrong it's an enemy so befriending by befriending yourself and experience bringing that
balance back instead of lopsided of like ah this is terrible it's okay yeah yeah
and and also um one thought that arose is is maybe another way also to to bring
balances oh what's what's going right what's well what's what's working well right now and it's what what's
nourishing in this moment so um great thank you Katherine thanks for sharing that and I see your Zoom hand
please thank you um something that uh
came up is uh so it's about to be a year since my oldest brother killed
himself and thank you um I I noticed like I'm just
more anxious than usual and um I'm like well it makes
sense anniversaries always get to me yeah so even when I'm not directly
thinking about him um but something that that has helped has been going to a
group that is specifically people that have lost siblings to suicide um so I
think finding people that have been in a very similar boat CU I can understand
people not being able to connect uh about it if they haven't been through it
so of course of course so finding Community it's like specific people yeah through
Community finding your balance and and equinity equipoise through the shared
Humanity the common Humanity of the those who are experiencing this this
grief this loss this this all the various aspects of of grief which which
are more complicated of course and and more piercing in the case of the case of
suicide I'm so sorry to hear about your loss um and and please and remember
remember self-compassion remember self-compassion cuz it's hard it's hard
for you it's so hard with everything that arises all the
aspects of grief so remember self-compassion then equinity may be
appropriate sometimes and it may not be it's so see what's appropriate at a
given time yeah thank you so much for speaking
up so so dear ones oh Sor I see your hand whoops wait I asked the wrong
person to unmute there Sara there you go thank you so much um thank you I
really appreciate your teachings uh Nikki it always um helps me to find a
way to make sense of a lot of things um something that we talked about in the
group was about U how to find equinity in the face of um uh suffering in the
world uh not just the suffering that you face in your life but great sufferings
that they are sometimes very difficult to make sense of um and then as you were
uh offering the teaching something came to mind that today I was listening to
Sharon salsburg um one of her books and um she
used the term she was not specifically talking about equinity but she used the term uh
tolerance and and she used this term as a way that um like we would increase our
tolerance to be able to let in anything the realities of the world
includ including the dark realities and and she used the example
of a the river of the self expanding the capacity of the river
of the self so it doesn't overflow in the face of new wav or whatever is going
and coming and going through it um so that expansion that tolerance it doesn't
mean that you don't react in the world or uh or anything like that but it's
just like you are actually more capable of letting things in without
collapsing so that as you were talking it just like clicked that maybe
tolerance in that context would also be a good way of looking at equinity yes I
I would just share this and ask for your thoughts yeah beautiful thank you so much sir thanks for bringing this
teaching and this beautiful metaphor from Sharon I love it yeah the idea of
this expanding our capacity like this River expanding this tolerance to be
able to be with that's exactly it you can see equinity so it's not being alof
it's you're you're you're being you're yes exactly you're expanding Your Capacity your tolerance to be with all
things with care I think I add that aspect of it with care so that there's
no overwhelm you can be with the river as it flows through you and your banks
are being expanded beautiful thank you so much for bringing this this Insight
of yours and I'm so delighted that it clicked from what you're listening to this morning and the meditation and yeah
that's just beautiful yeah it's just beautiful thank you ah ah beautiful I'll
bring that in also in my teaching this Saturday so so I wanted to to share with
you the link for the Equanimity dayong that I'm uh teaching it's both
online uh and it is in person so so if you have uh time and space and interest
uh it's it's um 10 a.m. to 3:30 p.m.
Pacific time will it be recorded says asks um uh Bill yes it will be recorded
So if you register um yeah you will have access to the recording
so yeah you're welcome thank you so dear ones thank you so much for your practice
your participation your wholehearted participation um and sharing of yourself
with one another um let's dedicate the the goodness of our
practice trusting there is there is goodness seeds of goodness planted here may our practice be of benefit to all
beings everywhere in ways we cannot fathom and imagine may all beings be
well may all beings be happy including [Music]
ourselves thanks everyone thank you so much