good morning
everyone have a good
day I appreciate very much the chats and I know that the people who
chat are a small percentage of the people who are attending right now and who
listen and watch this these teachings and I take those of you who uh chat uh
with wonderful good mornings and greetings as kind of representative of the good willll that uh exists in this
wider group of people who are part of this YouTube community so thank you and
also I Delight in seeing names that I recognize either because you
you you regularly do a greeting on to chat or because I know you from
earlier other places other Retreats and things and uh it's really really nice
thank you it makes it kind of come alive a little bit more for me to be doing this teaching um there was a time years ago
where I would have thought this was really strange and may be impossible to teach this way in a in an empty room um
but I feel I feel very connected and appreciative of all of you and this
chance to be able to communicate this way so thank you and and the chats make a big difference for
that so um so the topic is mindfulness of
thinking and today I want to uh connect thinking to our
emotions for some people there's almost no difference between the two and for
some people they are quite distinct but there's also a strong
Bridge a strong connection between the two and to find a way
of not identifying so strongly with our thoughts or our emotions so we can see
them more clearly gives a uh possibility for new things to arise new ways of processing
new discoveries of deep within ourselves and
so and one of those is uh we can discover that when
thinking is closely wedded to the emotions closely
connected um then if the emotions themselves are difficult emotions then the thinking themselves
are influenced by the that mood and if thinking them thinking is difficult and
challenging uh that undermines us or in some way or other then the
emotions that come from those thoughts can be difficult to be with and can continue to to undermine us or have a
kind of negative influence on us so I can go both directions and
sometimes thoughts influence thinking sometimes thinking influence thoughts and now sometimes they just seem to be
one big ball of things together what we're looking for in the Dharma is
not necessarily to stop thinking but to think from a deeper
place to think from a place where a lot of the difficult emotions um are not influencing how we
think or where thinking is not the place that are we're challenged
and angry or afraid or something there are so there's a source
of thinking that is deep within us and we've been talking this week about the
source from where we think are we thinking mostly from the head or some location in the
body as we relax more and more deeply and the thinking the source of
the thinking can be in a new place if it stays in the old place you
can't solve a problem with the problem sometimes but if we think from a new
place a place that's more free or less identified or feels like it has more of
a calm intimacy from deep within then it's a lot easier to track
and see the connection between thoughts and emotions so we're not necessarily
getting rid of thoughts and thinking but we are learning to think in a different way a simpler way
a deeper way so we'll see in this guided meditation I'll try to keep it simple
but to do this so assuming an upright alert not
necessarily upright that's I use that as a metaphor doesn't have to be literally upright but a
aligned posture a posture that
maybe it's adjusted so there's a little bit of dignity in the
posture and
to gently close the
eyes and as you are right now before doing anything else
become aware of your
thinking how would you characterize your thinking at this
point is there a source from where your thinking is coming from
where it
appears is there any mood or emotion or state of mind that comes with the way
you're thinking how you're thinking what you're
thinking
and then gently as you exhale
relax in your
body almost as
if gravity is letting
water flow or melting butter flow downward let it almost as if gravity
lets your place from where you're aware your awareness
itself flow downwards into your torso make maybe into your
belly certainly out of the
head and so then being aware becomes closely associated
with the sensations in your
torso
and continue now with awareness of breathing the rhythm
of breathing the expanding and contraction contraction of breathing
the alternating sensations of inhale and
exhale ride those Sensations
especially on the exhale relax and settle
in a homecoming to deep
inside
and if you're thinking rather than letting go of your
thoughts don't don't give them any
attention instead to tune into the breathing in
your body almost as maybe as if breathing is
music that's a as if music as if it's a music which is attractive to listen to
attractive to feel that there's very little
competition to stay with your thinking
for
a deep place of sensing of knowing feeling being
aware that doesn't require a lot of
thinking it's more of a quiet silent
receptivity to Sensations and movements and
relaxing on the exhale without ambition just not trying
too
hard
e
for
and then finding deep inside is there some place that's
soft or calm or quiet somewhere within anywhere at
all and from that quiet or soft
place be aware of
thinking maybe almost as if you're happily peacefully
underwater snorkeling looking up at the surface seeing the moving waves
above but below it's peaceful
and if there are thoughts about what you're thinking see if those secondary thoughts
about the thinking can come from that soft quiet
place deep within very simple
thoughts not trying to Fig figure anything out or judge
anything mostly simple thoughts of
recognition maybe bordering on appreciation for what is
happening knowing that you're
thinking
e discursive thinking telling
stories analyzing commentary
planning is kind of like clothes we put
on that we can take off and put on new clothes we think one thing and then
another and those thoughts discursive thoughts
if they are occurring now are they connected to any
emotion and if so the emotion or mood it's like clothes that you wear
they come and they go we put them on and they take them off no need to identify them identify
with them know them from some place deep
inside watching what's happening on the
surface
knowing thinking that's just
thinking knowing emotions or moods just as emotions or moods
maybe seeing how they influence each
other
e
for
and now after these minutes of meditating
we'll go back to how we began become aware of your
thinking how you're thinking the source from where you're
thinking what you're thinking you're allowed to think just
see it clearly
and how might you be different now than at the
beginning how is thinking
different and how is awareness of thinking different now than the beginning
is the connection between thinking in emotions has it changed at
all
and might there be a place deep inside where thinking is characterized by
Peace Quiet
calm maybe an
intimacy that's below the surface of the usual thoughts and
emotions that come and go
and what is it like to be aware of thoughts thinking and
emotions from this deep peaceful
place
e
for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting is there a way of now turning your attention outward into the
world where you don't get caught in the world or reactive to
it because being caught and being reactive that comes and goes
that's part of the surface experience of life even though it might feel deep but
is there a deeper place a quieter place a place of safety
within or Refuge within from which you can gaze upon the
world
kindly be still and gaze upon the world
kindly so in that gaze in that orientation to the world around
you there is conveyed Good Will
kindness love maybe peace
may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
a freedom that begins in their own
Hearts may we care for everyone's
[Music]
heart [Music]
thank
you
so hello and we come to the third talk on mindfulness of
thinking and um kind of stepping back and overview of
this mindfulness practice one of the things that I have
important I've learned many important things by teaching this practice and one of them I Learned was
was that when I started teaching the only reference point I had for the practice was really my own
experience so I thought that was what everyone was experiencing and then as I started to
teach and talk to more and more people about their practice I realized how what a wide
range of ways people practice what a wide range of ways in which people's
kind of minds work or processing work or how they organize and understand their inner processes and
and what they call emotions what they call thoughts what they call awareness itself and so now as a teacher it isn't
that I am hopefully I mean it's maybe this is more aspirational
than what I actually do but it isn't that I have a clear idea this is what you're supposed to do but
rather I'm trying to offer you you different elements different pieces
um uh different different ways of practicing um in different circumstances
to see um if some of it then you can adapt for yourself some of it fits into
how your mind and body work how your experience of Life Works and your inner
landscape because I think uh eventually all of us become our own teachers all of us have to become familiar enough to our
own mind and heart and body to know what what supports us to find peace what
supports us to find Freedom and wisdom and um and uh
so you know a lot of this practice that I'm teaching is to get you present enough attented to know so you can learn
how it works for you and this is true for the world of thinking uh many people
think a lot they might know what they think about and but very few people step
back and really are aware and familiar and and investigate what is thinking
what's going on while we think and I like to think of thinking as
a ecosystem of many factors that come
together and the simple word thinking uh implies a known and unknown ecosystem
that contributes to whatever it is you think that thinking is and it's possible
that many of us have slightly or very different ideas of what thinking is for example thinking in words or thinking in
image images some people the primary processing way is through their emotions
or somatically and uh and somehow that is where the deep understanding and and uh
and recognition of what this world is about and uh less so than in words or
less so in images so um to to really kind of stop
and see and this is how it is for me now given this is how my processing is can I
settle can I find some way to not be reacted to that not be judgmental to
that not be caught in it um not be pushed around by it but find some
balance some grounding some stability with how it is and um so one of the
things we uh some people will learn I can't say everyone that that's how it it should be this way but we'll see that
there's a strong connection between thinking and emotions and uh if uh if you and
sometimes it's the emotion which is the factory for the
thoughts and uh and I think of it sometimes as if the thinking is just a
messenger and we might be thinking a lot and caught in our thoughts but it's I think of it more as a messenger for that
factory for that deeper source of emotions that are really uh uh uh
producing these these thoughts and if we don't understand the factory then um the factory will keep
working over time just keep producing producing producing these thoughts you can let go of the thoughts forever but
new thoughts similar thoughts will just keep being produc produc because the factory is working you know
non-stop but if thinking is kind of like the messenger for something deeper going on sometimes that deeper is the emotions
so for example thinking about the future a lot um for it's a high percentage of
time I think for people there's some kind of apprehension some kind of worry or fear
operating that is what needs the attention that's that's the me that's what the messenger is pointing to
and uh so then learn how to practice mindfulness of emotions like we talked about last week and then we don't have
to think so much we're not caught in the grip as much because we're now attending to what's really going on and what's
driving the thinking and giving it power even so if there's anger uh uh a angry
thoughts if there's then uh feel the anger underneath it the emotion the
factory that it's coming out of and as we feel the anger maybe then we can drop
even deeper maybe the anger comes from fear or from hurt or from feeling
somehow um threatened so to to notice the emotion
that comes along with thinking uh and is very useful because maybe that's what needs our attention
and sometimes it's good emotions there might be the future thinking might be U uh Happy anticipation for something and
why why not continue doing it it makes me happy it's a good thing so that's okay um and sometimes in meditation we
have a deeper purpose something more valuable to do which is to drop in more and more deeply into some deeper Source
within and there is a source within us of Peace where things that come out of
that peace or out of that groundedness or out out of that calm or out of that
uh deep intimacy within that uh something emerges from there and here we have a distinction
that uh I think comes from more or less from the Buddha is there are thoughts which
are constructing things making things up a lot of thinking is making things
up and um and then there are thoughts that arise from deeper place inside
that's not constructing and making stories making plans making judgments
but rather something deeper inside has a feeling of emerging uh there's an emergence of
certain thoughts that do not seem like they're creating something they're
expressing something wisdom care love
kindness um wisdom something deeper so this this ability to notice we're
thinking being mindful of it enough that we can start asking questions what is this how is this how is this being
experienced is a way of stepping away from being in the grip of thoughts and to use a capacity we have
for observation reflection to to not be in the grip of the thoughts they lost in
them and then to ask ourselves what is the emotion that's connected to it um
and uh and then do mindfulness of emotion or as we did yesterday to ask um
how's this thinking uh expressed physically what's am I tight or tense or
activated someplace in my body and is that possible to relax that so these are
kind of ways of reflection of think of kind of like thinking but maybe from a
deeper place or from a place that's more independent thinking that's not caught in the
discursive thinking in the story making mind and the scared mind or the angry
mind or the discouraged mind but steps back and in a kind way in
a relaxed way in a independent way uh is able now to engage what's happening here
what's going on here where that engagement and those questions are done
very calmly peacefully with very little at stake not trying to fix anything not trying to be
in a hurry to make something go away it's almost like as we step back and reflect and aware from a Freer
place um it isn't we're trying to solve the thinking we're trying to
almost um uh grow this place
of of of liberated awareness free awareness deep into deep awareness of
our life so it doesn't matter so much what the consequences of that practice is as
it is as much as it is how that grows that practice that ability to see clearly and openly but we do it by
looking at thoughts and um I think it's very very powerful a lot of the problems that we
run into for ourselves chances are they have thinking has some role to them and thinking might
not be the deepest Source maybe there's an emotion that's deeper than that's feeding the thoughts an attitude that's
feeding them but um the way we think can have a very deleterious effect on our
mood our emotional life our experience of ourselves a lot of people they're thinking is it's undermining their own
well-being we believe the stories we believe the judgments that there's something wrong with us
that we're somehow not quite right or something that there's shame or blame or
or um that uh lack of fame or you know all kinds of things that go
on and um and uh so to start not being
influenced by those thoughts not being caught by them not perpetuating them is part of the power of mindfulness so just
step back and see and uh H how are you thinking from where are you
thinking what is the emotional Source what's the factory for it what happens
if you bring loving attention to anger or fear
that's producing those thoughts or fueling them what happens if you relax the body
that's activated that's prod that's connected to those thoughts and what
with over time what happens if you can observe or recognize or know or even
with very calm thoughts uh recognize what's happening
from this deeper emerging place this deeper place of Refuge that can exist
deep within so what happens so uh maybe that was a lot of
ideas for 15 minutes um and Hope hopefully some of it
uh supports you and for if you'd like to continue this exploration uh for today
next until we meet tomorrow you might um uh become more cognizant of the
relationship between thinking and emotions emotions and thinking do they
come together are they completely wetted are they slightly two different things and as you consider that both by simple
thoughts asking what is this how is this but as you sit back and relax and just observe this can you feel some freedom
from that that uh complex of emotions and
thoughts so thank you very much and I'll continue
tomorrow