so hello everyone and the
um I came today and the been away for a week and that technology here at IMC was
uh somehow a bit off and the final challenge was that uh the way that
I participate with all of you is through my laptop and um my laptop wasn't
connecting to the Wi-Fi here and so I don't know what uh but then I
didn't initially it was that uh it wasn't working at the recording station
but that seemed to have started to work so um now we're connected and I have a
different laptop so hopefully um it's all good sorry to be a little
late so
um so this is the fifth week of this introduction to meditation series that
I've been doing I'll me record so this is the fifth week of this
introduction to meditation series and I want to uh build on what
we've done so far uh this week or apply it in
different ways but one of the things I'd like to talk about today is the role of
concentration as a partner to mindfulness and I'll start with an
analogy and then we'll sit that um many years ago I went to Yus
with my family and small kids when they were
small and we stayed in tent cabins in the Yus Valley and then uh during the
day we did some uh beautiful hikes but some of them were quite Steep
and uh had to keep these little kids kind of entertained as we went along and
we had brought with us uh you know luggage of different types that we could carry from the car to the
tents if I had decided to uh bring all my luggage with us on our hikes into the
mountains carrying the suitcases and the backpacks and sleeping bags and everything that we
had um we wouldn't have gotten very far it would have been quite
exhausting so the same thing with meditation sometimes we carry with us into
meditation um so much of the baggage so much of the memories
expectations projections into the future fantasies we carry it along and um we
can't go very far if we're carrying a lot of baggage with us
the role of concentration is to put down some of that baggage and uh and
um uh even if it's just briefly so um uh we can be
mindful and the mindfulness can be continuous part of the function of
concentration is for the mindfulness to stay put for a while so that can hike
along in our life without carrying a lot of baggage picking up a lot of things along the
way the role of what's called concentration is not just to be
continuous but to be immersed in what we're being mindful of a certain kind of
immersion into so we can be present in a fuller maybe embodied way so with that
as a introduction we'll meditate
and so to assume a meditation posture and part of the idea of an
intentional meditation posture is to a posture which
allows some of the luggage We Carry in Our Lives to slide
off and maybe what slides off is what first is what is least needed for
meditation so take an intentional medit meditative posture where your whole
body recognizes oh here we go with meditation the longer you meditate the
more there's an embodied recognition this is time for
meditation and then close your eyes and
gently uh take the three breath Journey count each breath to three
staying present for the
breath and then let's do that again this time if you to really stay connected to
the breathing continuously or
immersively if you count to three count one for the inhale and one for the
exhale then two two 3 three but do it so
that the count somehow gently quietly almost like a whisper in the mind kind
of is really feels the inhale feels the exhale or maybe you gently repeat it
couple of times through the inhale and exhale so the
count really helps you to be immersed in the experience of each inhale and each
exhale so do a three breath
Journey
of course you many of you all have
different speed by which those three breaths are done you can always do more
so now taking a few long slow breaths
relaxing on the exhale kind of staying with a whole
exhale as you
exhale the relaxing with the exhale is an immersion into your bily experience
an immersion in
exhaling
for and then letting your breathing return
to
normal and
now take a five breath Journey count up to
five to each count this twice once for the inhale one for the
exhale and you can see if you can count as soft as you need to so that it's not
agitating to count or seems like too much work even if you imagine your
counting is enough and count up to five with the
idea that the count is encouraging the mindfulness to stay immersed in the
discovery of what the breath is like the experience or
breathing not straining but relaxing into the full experience of
breathing in and out so there's a continuity for five
breaths without carrying luggage with
you and then continue through the sitting if you loose count just start
over again at one if five is too much go back to
three or if you make it want to make it really simple count up to one and then start
over
again
e
for
as you count your breaths you might think of the count
each count as a invitation to
relax open and feel
[Music] receive the experience of
breathing maybe almost as
if you're receiving
A Gentle Wind that surrounds you fills
you staying with a
breath carrying no luggage nothing with
you open-handed open-minded openhearted to just this experience of
breathing
for
e
and then for a few more breaths see if you can give yourself
over to a to an attention an immersive
attention with no baggage to just
breathing with an equal immersion in the inhale as
the exhale with no
strain maybe as if immersing yourself in the body's
experience of breathing it's like lowering yourself into a refreshing
or warm pool of
water safely immersed in the pool or the
bathtub and as you would feel the water against your skin feel the sensations the waves of
breathing in the inside of your skin inside your
body
and then [Music]
to in this
meditation relax let go of breathing just be here
for a few seconds nothing to do nothing to be nowhere to
go just sit here open and present and simplest way
possible and then without picking up baggage and histories
and fears open your attention your
concern to the people around you in your
communities households work wherever you might be
today and imagine meeting people without any
baggage without any predetermination ideas or judgments
or history that for a few moments you meet them
fresh and in that
freshness with Good Will wishing them
well may the people in my life today May my good
will spread to them may my care for their
well-being be directed towards them may whatever ability I have to be a
safe person person for them may that come forward as
I put down
Luggage in whatever way that I accept them so they can be
themselves free to make their own choices may I accept
them may the meditation practice we do serve
us in one way or the other to
benefit the world around
us
for
so good morning on this Monday morning or good day for those of you it's
already the morning's already gone by and
um so this is the fifth week of this introduction to mindfulness
meditation and um the general idea of mindfulness is
very simple and I think maybe the very beginning of this series I try to offer
the Simplicity of it and the instructions that I've given since then might seem like it makes it
complicated but it's more like uh describing the territory of what we could experience if
we're available and open to the present moment and the idea is to be present
simply for that don't have to make it complicated don't have to do a lot of things except
to be present but we know what to be present for so we began with breathing being
present for breathing that's stabilizing it's connecting it's Wonder for many
people a wonderful beginning for some people it's not and then there are other
uh home bases for attention but uh generally the way we teach in a generic
way is to um have breathing be the home base
and then as we go along the body speaks up and the body becomes more you know
speaks up and wants to be heard and uh and so then we can let go
of breathing and then we the very simple attention to recognize and feel what's
happening is uh with the experience of the body and uh as we go along there might
be emotion that arise and those emotions we can feel in the body are expressed in
the body and emotions can be listened to can be heard can be attended to again
with a very simple attention it's very caring profoundly
meaningful for our emotional life for the emotions to have room to be without
us involving ourselves with them for or against them but they to keep it really
simple and then we some point we become aware of thinking and the idea is to keep that
simple simple recognition as we're recognizing these things simplic very simply then we since
we know the territory we might kind of see different aspects of each one we
might see the particular sensations of the body we might see the way the
sensations in the body where the emotions are most active and most Express themselves we might
see that the emotions are made up of different parts and so to be aware of
these different component parts because we kind of have a sense of the map so it's not like we have to go searching or
figuring it out but we just over time we know more and more of the territory and
we can just bring simple awareness oh this is how it is this is how it is and some people find it very helpful to have
some phrase like uh something like uh this is how it is
now or this is X now this is this is how it is at the
moment uh just leave it that simple so the general way we teach is to
have the breathing at the center something else becomes more
predominant attend to it be present for it receive it allow for
it to be enter into awareness when it no longer feels like it needs to be attended to then go back to the
breathing go to the next thing that comes up back to the breathing and so that's kind of the breathing is the
place to come back to and one of the reasons for that is for some people many people not
everyone um breathing uh having one place that's the place for stability the
place for the default to come back back to helps to develop continuity there and
the rhythm of breathing is a place that's continuous it's always there gently rocking us massaging us being
present here for us and so what we're what we're doing then is we're also
bringing along um uh ability to stay with something
continuously uh sometimes that's called concentration though some people associate concentration with straining
or narrowing down and a laser focus or something it's more an experience of
immersion with the experience and uh or uh uh uh composing
ourselves on the experience just really being here for this and um and the value
of this is that if we don't have a home base like this if we're not cult cultivating concentration with the
mindfulness that um uh our
mind has its own interests and if we're just simply being a available to notice
what's happening in the mind what's happening what's sometimes what we're doing is not necessar is the mind not
might not have the be your best interest in mind and you might not see how
subconsciously there's bias towards certain directions certain concerns certain emphasises like some people are
really almost addicted to their thinking and so just to constantly be mindful of
thinking thinking thinking actually strengthens the thinking reinforces it some
people prioritize their emotions and uh and there's a way in which uh uh uh we
we're predisposed to experience the emotion more than is necessary and so uh our attention is
often not unbiased but represents some of the deep deeper um attachments deeper
fears deeper concerns that uh we bring with us and so uh the idea of staying
with something like breathing as continuously we can is the equivalent to
um not uh going hiking uh in the mountains with all your luggage that's
really hard if and you can't go very far and you might get to understand how the weight of your luggage and the and the
and what it feels like in your hand to grip the handles of the luggage you might get to know those things really
well but you're still not going to go into the mountains very far and so the idea is to be able to put down the
baggage that we carry with us the the bias we carry with us the the uh the the
orientations that we have that don't really serve Us in order to kind of be
become fresher and be able to go deeper and look more without bias without
pre-existing orientation and baggage and so uh something like the
breathing to develop some modum of concentration don't have a high
standard um and so uh even being able to stay with three breaths
continuously um or even sometimes even just one breath continuously is enough to begin to um um
interrupt the way in which we feed thinking or feed our emotional life or
feed some concern that we have and beginning to take this think of
attention as food and whatever Direction attention is going we're feeding that
thing and if attention is going towards being mindful being aware of
thinking then the attention goes to the mindfulness but if attention goes into
thinking then we're feeding the thinking if attention goes into emotions there's a
way in which we feed them but if attention goes into being aware being
mindful of emotions it's kind of like we step back and really see it oh the not
to condemn it not to push it away but not so we're with the experience but
we're not we're not we're not identified with the experience we're not being the exper
experience and um every experience is allowed to be what it is but we don't have to be identified with it we defined
by it be in it so this uh continuity just one breath
is enough to step away and from the uh put down the baggage two breaths three
breaths and to have not try too much because the idea is to let that slowly
grow continuity immersion concentration is something
that's um it's like a muscle that develops it or it's like a um uh like a
muscle that we're relaxing but just gently massaging it over and over again and slowly something develops or it's
like butter if you take butter out of the freezer um it's really hard and you
can't uh you know you have to break it in order to to U Break It in half you
have to kind of you know take a hammer to it or something but if you let the butter sit out in in the
warmth of the room slowly it will uh it'll get softer until you just take can
take a butter knife and just almost even just put it on top and it just sinks right through easily so the same way
with concentration it's it's a slow warming up process we come back and stay
with a few breaths and and then if we're not upset that we get distracted but
lovingly Begin Again Begin Again and something begins to come into the groove
and maybe we get five breaths maybe 10 breaths as an act of will we could stay
for 10 breaths maybe but concentration is not meant to be an act of
will um uh it's meant to be a a Act of
love an act of care an act of of um of uh offering our presence to
something and that's with a combination the coming together of mindfulness and
concentration of mindfulness with a continuity of mindfulness we're mindful
of something and then we stay with it for a while feel it be with it and if
it's not something other than breathing like if it's some sensation in the body or some emotion or thinking
um this idea of a you spend at least three breaths with each one oh maybe
three breaths is enough to fully acknowledge something and the acknowledging and being and feeling it
for a little bit for three breaths I'd be enough to be able to put it aside and come back to the
breathing and um and so this rhythm of three breaths with whatever we recognize
in be with sometimes we want to be longer with something that's fine but uh
it's great sometimes to just stay for a long time with one thing but the three
breaths putting down the baggage just being with that uh can begin
to overcome and relax
the the bias automatic Pilots the automatic
prioritization that the Mind makes for what's where attention goes what we're
concerned with for for example with our thinking so I hope that that makes sense
and um and so I want to leave you with the the principle that uh the way
that I teach mindfulness is with a um partnership
with concentration and the two don't have to be uh done separately but one
supports the other so thank you and um continue this
introductory series
tomorrow