so good morning everyone or good day Welcome to
our morning or meditation on this 24th of
December and what I'd like to evoke for this day
is the the general attitude of friendliness
friendliness in the most ordinary ways the ways you'd be friendly to someone
and a stranger maybe in a public space maybe the person in front of you in the grocery store who in line and maybe they
drop their one of their purchases on the floor you pick it
up for them and hand it to them and they say thank you and the exchange is all
ordinary simple friendliness nothing really required more than just the
ACT maybe opening a door for someone again maybe a stranger maybe opening the door for a
stranger and wishing them well have a good day or
please and so uh the idea of friendliness and maybe there's a simpler
word that you might like to use I don't know if kindness is simpler
uh maybe a simple Goodwill a general sense of well-wishing
an attitude of well-wishing rather than attitude of ill will or suspicion or
fear and so to have that as the basis for
meditation there are some people who will do meta meditation the meditation on good will for the first few minutes
of meditation to set the stage set the foundation for meditation itself to be a
very simple Act of friend of goodwi of friendliness to oneself or to one's
experience as one is meditating a friendly attitude towards
breathing friendly attitude to discomfort in the body a friendly
attitude to calm that might set in a friendly attitude
to a mind that's out of control not punitive to the mind not
aversive to it but in a friendly way opening the door and welcoming it in
Back to the present moment please please enter come
here begin again so to assume a meditation posture
maybe there's a way in which the posture itself can be an expression of the
simplest form of well-wishing or
friendliness to place oneself in a posture which is
aligned a posture in which different parts of
the body can be aligned or in harmony
or be in a kind of Cooperative
balance lowering your gaze
and if it's comfortable to close your
eyes and feeling the weight of your body down through your
torso through your back through your sitting bones if
you're on a chair couch or cushion
maybe the weight of your feet wherever whatever they're
touching and that in that weight in that this substantial feeling of being in a
body may it contain within it a simple friendly less an attitude of
care or
kindness some people connect to kindness more through [Music]
words saying very simple kind
words classically it's may I be happy
for some people it's more having an image of something that's easy someone
or some animal or something that's easy to be delighted in and to have a
Simple Kindness good will for some people it's somatic
a Radiance of tenderness or
warmth some people it's a light that shines
outward that maybe also shines inward maybe the light of awareness
so that everything awareness touches and everything that comes into
awareness is touched by
kindness is received in a friendly way
and then centering yourself on your body
breathing and maybe if it's comfortable for you that
breathing becomes the subject for your kindness
breathing becomes the place where you remember to be
friendly to be kind to be warmhearted
breathing as the training ground for MEA
friendly to breathing in Friendly to the one who's
breathing friendly to breathing
out caring for the one who exhales
maybe appreciating the breathing keeps you
alive so why
not Center your Good Will on
breathing here and
now
for
e
for e
one way to support a friendly attitude
is to have a half Smile as you
meditate turning up your corners of your lips just
enough to feel some
pleasure and another way is to gently quietly sit say the word
yes the friendly
yes both a smile and a
yes that reassures the thinking mind that it's okay to be
quiet to be
still
e
for
e e
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to remember to re remember put back
together yourself with Good
Will wishing yourself well all As aspects of yourself nothing
excluded you might repeat these words silently to
yourself may I be
happy feeling the last words of these
sentences is dropping in to the pond of your inner
life at gentle Pebble Rippling
out may I be
happy may I be [Music]
safe may I be
peaceful may I be
free and then to spread this Good Will out into
this community of meditators participating here on
YouTube may all all of us be
happy may all of us be
safe may all of us be
peaceful may all of us be
free and then to extend your good will your gaze your
Radiance out across the lands across the
world may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may it be that with our simple basic
friendliness may we cont contribute to a world at
[Music]
peace thank
you e
so hello everyone and welcome to this December 24th
2024 and and um this week the themes is care all the
different forms of Love or the five primary forms of love
in Buddhism in the kind of terad Buddhism and so yesterday was care which
I see as the foundation for the other four and when we care for something we
value it we tend to it we nourish it nurture it
that um one of the ways one of the ways that's expressed is in
friendliness and the word meta is a cognate to the word uh M so it's closely
connected friendliness and friendship and friend sometimes it's translated as
kindness Good Will loving kindness well wishing and um sometimes you know it
said that maybe the common English trans ation loving kindness puts a high bar on
it because the word love for some people is challenging when we have people who are quite difficult in our
lives and um but uh the idea of friendliness or good willll maybe kind
of makes it easier more accessible that even uh to someone we
have trouble with that it might be some very basic friendliness or Goodwill that
uh that might work and um but it's a one wonderful
things to be friendly it's a lower bar than loving someone maybe it's an easier
than being um compassionate for people at times and also it's more universally
applicable to go through the day being friendly is more appropriate than going
through the world with compassion certainly the world is full of suffering but uh not everyone wants to
receive our compassion not everyone it's the time and place to be compassionate but it's every place is a
time and place for simple friendliness I have been involved in
I've been uh seen and that uh sometimes when there's uh a
lot of animosity and directed towards me or seen directed to other people a lot of anger I've seen uh um people who were
able to receive it without fear and Without Anger to turn it all around by
being friendly and idea of being able to step towards and look with Care on the World
to not turn away uh but to uh look towards what's
happening and see it with the friendly eyes at least there's a caring
eyes and um and you can ask why or when
is it appropriate to be friendly and the most profound answer that I
could offer is um the the time to be
friendly is when the alternative is worse if you know a better alternative
than being friendly then by all means please do it but if the alternative you
have is not as good as being friendly choose friendliness above all else this
is what the Buddha said uh the uh the concept or the
attitude of meta is really in the ancient teachings of the Buddha the
primary social emotion next to anukampa care that is emphasized and many of the
ways in later Buddhism and in the modern Buddhism compassion is often seen as the primary
Buddhist uh motivation and attitude uh the place of that for many of the same
purposes and reasons and motivations in the ancient text was meta Good Will to
meet others with Good Will to meet them with friendliness and the Buddha
emphasized to be very careful and not sacrifice not give it up no matter what's happening stay close to me
and then he's talking to his monastic disciples he said the way that you stay
true to the Dharma is no matter what's happening you keep uh meta for the
people that are um you know even the people who are abusing
you this is a very difficult teaching but with what I want to emphasize is how
foundational the idea of friendliness and kindness is in this tradition
um the um I have uh kind of a warm place
in my heart for a neighbor here who's an old man who's having quite a bit of
difficulty uh and um uh he went to the hospital recently and I tried to best I
could to figure out how to support him and help him it was a bit hard but when
I went to talk to the neighbors next to him um they had only animal for him he
said he's just a bad person he's always mean and he's never been here for you know I've been here for 27 years and
together with him and he's always been difficult and I replied that um oh uh
yes half the time he's been a difficult neighbor but the other half of the time he's not and I emphasized the half a
time that he's not and um and uh I have a soft spot my for him and would like to
support him wanted to try to be there when he went to the hospital and offer the support I could and um and so not to hold against
him the fact that he has this mean streak um because it doesn't really you
know affect me that he's mean um but it does affect me if I
am it doesn't really matter to to me whether he's mean to me it matters that
uh to me that I keep my heart open and one of the profound things that I've
learned from Buddhist practice a surprise to me not something I tried to talk myself into or kind of snuck up on
me was the realization that in theory or
in in some real way not not easy but in a real way um I was capable of having
good will friendliness to everyone and no matter what and uh and
so the practice was and the commitment was to find a way to make that possible
to do it in a way that was safe for me safe for others that was appropriate but
always at least in my heart to keep my heart open never close my heart even
there are times where I've had to leave a situation because of the danger I had to protect myself because of the danger
that was there from other people um but I the idea was always even so with my
heart keep it friendly have good will there uh as I care for
myself so in our Buddhist tradition there are uh four primary kind of
practices or attitudes or approaches to life that is the uh I understand is the
foundation of it all one has to do with awareness practices like
mindfulness the second has to do with um U ethics being
ethical the third has to do with generosity and the fourth has to do with
Good Will with kindness those are the those are the four kind of
primary uh attitudes approaches teachings that terad Buddhism that I
like to think of swims in that that that's the world which we are centering
ourselves are guiding Us in how we live and it's a world that brings a lot of
Joy a lot of love a lot of sense of being being
like we belong in this world we belong in this in this Society we belong in
such a way that we can include others in that belonging and even though if we feel
like we don't belong because of how others treat us it's possible through these four
practices of awareness ethics generosity and Good
Will to feel centered and at home with oneself enough that now you become the
belonger that your friendliness is one that welcomes everyone uh uh to
um into your field of friendliness it doesn't have to be naive
it doesn't have to put you in danger it can be at whatever distance that's appropriate for you and but that's
that's the nature of your heart it's possible to have a heart of Good
Will and finally to end as you go forth today
into your life if you to be based to base your life on Good Will towards all
friendliness to all uh don't have it as don't have it to be this Grand thing that you're going to
do so many you know do great acts of friendliness think of it as in the small
acts through the day small Acts of Kindness Small acts of friendliness the
opening of the door the saying hello to stranger as you pass them if you fill your day with small
acts of friendliness the accumulation the sum
total of those become pretty wonderful may your day be Wonder of
friendliness may you offer your care your kindness in simple ways to those people
that you will be with today in including please I I ask you please including
yourself may you be generous kind and friendly to yourself
and all that is difficult in you may your heart be open to
all including yourself thank you