so hello everyone and Welcome to our meditation
session and for today I'm sitting
here a little bit um appreciating marveling all the causes and conditions
that bring me here and but one of them that stands out
as I begin this meditation is that it's some point
through this Buddhist practice and I trace it to doing meditation
practice um the practice started to change
me in a sense I was practiced I
was because there's two things happening there's what we offer the
meditation and there is what
um The Meditation does to us and both are important we we create
certain conditions by how we offer ourselves to the meditation and the meditation changes us
dependent on if we allow it to be if we make ourselves available to that
change if it's only about us doing something we're going to miss one of the most
important parts of meditation but if it's only about we're
passive and the meditation is going to we supposed to somehow magically do something for us then it
won't there has to be this reciprocal relationship between us and the
meditation and one of the things that we offer as we sit down to
meditate is we offer our attention we
offer not so much as something that we do but something we show up with we show
up to be present so in a sense we show up with presence with a clarity about inhabiting
here being here and now and this thing of being here and now
puts us in the field of awareness of
attention a prominent part about really here and now is
awareness if you spend a lot of time in your head thinking then you might think
that you have to think your way or work your way into the present
moment and it's work to be done to focus
but we have to offer ourselves to the present moment we have to offer ourselves here with our
presence with present moment present moment awareness and then the meditation has a
chance to unfold to do
something and both these what we offer and what we
receive can be infused with love love there's something about if you're
going to love someone that's a present moment phenomena that's a present moment thing
that we do the stronger the love the more it's really something
that's strong here and
now and if we're going to allow someone to love us in return there has to be an
allowing a receiving of that it's not just one
way so there's a love we offer as we
attend it's a kind of a could be seen as a love for ourselves a love for
awareness a love of meditation a love of the
Dharma a love of this world even that's not a
assertive and then in a certain way we'll be loved in
return in a certain way what's within us deep
inside our capacity for kindness and friendliness love care
compassion will appear if there is the need for it if
there's the conditions for it so as we sit today and
meditate certainly see if you can offer your presence offer
awareness but can you do that together with offering your love your care your
kindness your tenderness your gentleness and then see if you open
yourself up if you available to
receive without expectation slowly like walking in the
Mist will meditation reciprocate so that it offers you
presence it offers you something in the family of
love so to sit in a meditation a or assume a meditation posture that's right
for
you and in some very general way think of it as a posture of
care posture of Love even for yourself
posture which creates the conditions for attentiveness loving
attention to gently close your
eyes and if the beginning of meditation was to be
receptive like you would be receptive to the standing in the warm rays of the sun
on a cold day or
receptive to inspiring
music to let your whole body assume a receptive
mode as if your whole body is going to listen
deeply and then to receive the next
inhale to receive the movements of the body as you breathe
in the expansion of the chest and the belly movement of the diaph
PR and then as you exhale offer your
attention to the release of the air the release of the muscles
the release of the diaphragm contraction falling back of
the chest
as you exhale offer your attention to the
places in your body that can relax
where relaxing your body is a form of
care maybe even a form of love
and we're breathing in is your body caring for
yourself perhaps we can even imagine or feel that the inhale is a form
of love we receive receiving the lifegiving air
oxygen receiving the body's working of caring for
us and the care the body [Music] gives is silent as no words to
it and so to receive that care with ATT tension that is without
thoughts
and as you exhale offer
attention to the whole length of the exhale
offer care and love the whole length of the
exhale a care that does not require words or
thoughts but is a tenderness a gentleness a warmth Within
and so the process of breathing in and out is a process of receiving and
giving receiving love giving
love
e
for
for for
and if breathing in love breathing is too
much let go of all things that get in the
way of receiving love
if breathing out exhaling with
love is too
much let go of all things that are in the way
and when you have let go be receptive to what is as you
breathe
in offer your kind gentle presence attention
as you
exhale
e
for
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to
gently let there be a sense of
care compassion a sense
of wanting to tend to the suffering of the
world and part of care compassion
love is the way wish that is not necessarily a feeling
but it can be the wish for others not to
suffer the wish that oneself does not suffer that
wish is a form of care and love
and may we as we come out of meditation
consider that wish consider a
[Music] world that we could
touch with our kindness our
friendliness so that everything that our eyes land on
everything our hands touch everything our ears
hear is known with love with
care with kindness with
tenderness the tenderness
of wanting to be friends with everything that we
encounter may this
practice expand our range of friendship so we meet
everything as a friend may all beings be happy
may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so so hello and welcome to this Monday uh we begin a new
series and maybe a series that might be appropriate to for this first day of
turning towards the light the day after the solstice and
um and may we light the world with our attention maybe light the
world with our care so what's on my mind my heart these
last days is love the the practice the expression
the idea of love and I'm very aware that the word word love in English is a very
vague word can be I mean it's it has such a wide range of meanings that when
someone uses it it's uh I imagine that anyone uses
it uh anybody who hears it being used might interpret it differently than
intended as far as I know there's no good word in poly in the Buddhist language that covers the range of
meanings that we have for this English word love but for uh there are five words
that uh uh represent or can hold this broad English word love that maybe
give it some uh some clarity or some by
some specificity that's helpful to kind of understand or to understand some
potential we have uh of what can arise out of um Dharma
practice and these five are um in P
anuka meta karuna mudita
UPA and um the uh in English there would be
care kindness compassion appreciative joy
and uh equinity equanimous love and
um and uh care is the one that is the kind of found I see that is the
foundation for all the other five that the other other four the other four that
we'll talking over the next days um come arise out of a sense of
care uh and or expression different different flavors of care depending on the context in which care is
offered and that um and that the the bottom line is something very
simple uh and that is what whatever it is that motivates uh the basic simplest
forms of care that we would offer uh if a neighbor is injured and we
go do their shopping for them for food that there is care we might not love the neighbor but we have a kind of care and
maybe it maybe we call it compassion but it doesn't have to uh be compassion it
could be just a simple desire to be helpful and and um it doesn't have to
come with a lot of feeling it doesn't have to come with a lot of um you know uh it just a basic kind
of instinct to care for someone who needs help needs support and um it could be that uh we
care for ourselves because maybe we've cut our finger and so uh we know that uh
if we don't clean it and put a bandage on it it might get worse and so we care for ourselves knowing that not doing it
might have bad consequences and again there might not be a strong feeling of Love of warmth of
tenderness but still it is offering care it is taking care of something and
um one of the big surprises for me uh in my life kind a turning point in a
certain kind of way was um I was going on a an organized hike in a kind of
desert-like area uh and there were people strangers on that door organized hike and there
was one uh woman who was not so U capable of hiking so well uh but it was
kind of Rocky and we had to sometimes climb over these rocks and these little short I don't know 5 foot Ledges and
stuff to make our way uh through this desert environment and so I saw that she was
this was all hard for her and so I hung back and stayed with
her and um and uh I didn't assert myself but I was just there ready to offer a
hand as she needed it and she uh gracefully graciously just received my
hand took the support I give I don't even remember if there we did any talking about it um I was just there to
offer what was needed and it was very matter of fact and she was very matter of fact of receiving it and but what
what happened as I was walking I started having things there's a really nice feeling inside I started
to have something tender and warm started to occur or something gentle or
a kind of a joy a kind of a feeling of well-being or some kind of feeling of
being a little bit more open or a feeling of being kind of appreciative of just this attentiveness of being here
and present for this person there was like kind of this this uh a kind of a
attention kind of a Som of being uh my my awareness my attention was now
encompasses the uh the present moment in a clear way because I wanted to be ready for her so I wasn't distracted I was
just right there but I was also enjoying the scenery and just walking peacefully and not trying to assert myself for
being too writing her too closely uh just gently kind of being
available and uh and this great wonderful feeling this very felt very nice there was a kind of a peacefulness
to it and this goodness that uh that arose after a while I couldn't tell
whether I was hanging back walking with her in order to support her if I was walking in order to enjoy or appreciate
this wonderful feeling that was arising in me and uh and this taught me
something important it taught me that uh there's a way of caring for the world
that uh we're we're caring for our eles at the same time there's a way of being
open and receptive engaged in support in care that uh feels really good for
oneself and this was a surprise uh I think before that sometimes I would be lost in the
caregiving I thought I had was had a responsibility I better do it um I was
obligated to I had to kind of ride the person be responsible for the person and ride very closely to the person right be
right there ready to take care of of things and it was a little bit fear driven it was a little bit Duty bound it
was a little bit um um a sense of uh I should I must and I must not fail in
doing this and this other way of doing it showed me a whole different way of
caring of uh that uh it was possible to care for
someone uh in a way that cared for myself at the same time that felt good
that was support for me and so began to kind of break the uh
Authority in me of uh shoulds and Duty and fear around this notion of being
support for the world and um and so uh and so that was a turning
point for me and very very valuable uh another Turning Point number
I had a lot of turning points but uh around this generally what we might call love in English this very vague word uh
one of them was another one was the the growth of compassion I had a lot of suffering when I first started doing
Buddhist practice and um and only thing I KN knew what to do was to be present
for it to be present for it in a non-reactive way to be present for it without trying to fix it or do anything
about it and um and somehow I had a lot of faith in Zen practice
and so I kept showing up for my own suffering but I didn't I was not given any tools for how to work with it or how
to fix it just to be present for it and there was something about that being
present for suffering that was tenderizing that softened again some
kind of reactivity some kind of defensiveness some kind of assertiveness some kind of anger some kind of fear
that I had that came along with my suffering and so I slow got
tenderized and slowly like walking in the mist and getting slowly wet uh
unbeknown to me I was becoming compassion a similar thing happened to
me in doing Vasa practice that um I did not care or understand what the Vasa
teacher were were saying when they were teaching meta loving kindness and did guided loving kindness meditation and so
I tuned them out when they in meditation when they did that but to some point uh
as I kept doing this vasna practice the um uh the barriers the again things like
fear and assertiveness and conceit and and uh the shoulds and what I should do
and trying to make something happen all this quieted down for me and uh and
something began space inside for something different to arise and I started to feel a sense of of
well-being a sense of uh peace a sense of goodness
that uh was very was friendly had a very friendly feeling to it and uh and then
one day when the teachers were doing a guided loving kindness practice I had that feeling and I said um um and said
to and said oh that's what they're talking about and so both this
compassion and this love and this care that have become important parts of my life were not something that I searched
for or not something that I tried to make happen but they started to happen
to me and uh and so I learned how important it is to be available to allow these
things to happen towards me to allow myself to uh to be present for
experience and um and then in that allowing at different times when the
conditions are ripe then maybe you'll feel um
friendliness compassion appreciative joy and the joy of others and a certain kind
of equanimous love loving
equinity all of which are a manifestation that we care about
ourselves we care about others we care enough to try
to want to bring an end to suffering we care enough to want to care and the
desire to care the wish to be caring the wish to love the wish to be
compassionate is in fact the beginning of care love and
compassion that the the wish the hope the aspiration is one of the beautiful
qualities of human being qualities of human
nature and I think it's invaluable not to diminish its role in
our lives and make room for it and uh life
unfolds so much better for everyone for ourselves and others if we can
relax or accept and relax and make room for
the wish the aspiration to make a better world for
everyone for ourselves and everyone else that aspiration is an
expression ultimately of Awakening itself this was the Buddha's
wish that's what he lived for after his Awakening and whether and to whatever
degree we awaken to what is in our own heart Hearts we aaken to what's in our
own minds awaken to the wish the
aspiration let's live with it let's care for it let's care for ourselves and
let's care for others so thank you very much and um I'm
looking forward to sharing this part of my life over these next days uh with you
thank you