morning welcome welcome greetings good afternoon good day good
evening
hello whether you are watching us live or in the
future welcome it's makes it differ friends to practice
together and whether you are here live and on the comments or
not welcome happy you're
here Craig writes love and peace from North Carolina love and peace
nice love and peace from Northern California maybe I'll say
welcome Stephen and and Kathy and John Craig burus
Burgas Stuart Mona Sherry Maggie Rebecca good
morning there Susan is in Redwood City hi Susan I'm in Redwood City
also hello Diane and Julie Leila Jenny
and all of you that are sitting out there not on the comments or not you know posting anything in there hello to
you wish everybody good start of the day if this is the
start of your day or if this is a break
in the midst of your day or the way that you're ending your day welcome
maybe I'll wait just a little bit here a little bit longer here before
we kick off our time together this morning
everybody good morning it's uh nice to be with you all to practice
together I'm continuing the series on what I'm calling the Poetry of practice
this is the third week I've done this I've done it uh two other times and I
think it was in 2023 when I've done it so it's been a while since I've done poetry of practice and just bringing
poetry into practice into our meditation practice and I'd like to start this
morning I'm just going to read this uh quote from uh David White who's a
well-known poet and um before I guide us into some
meditation so David White he's writing on the poetic
imagination this expression he's using this poetic imagination and writing
poetry and for me it feels like oh he's pointing to a meditation practice and
David White he has said that he has a Zen practice hasn't he doesn't necessarily identify as a Zen Buddhist
but that he has been practicing Zen for uh quite a few years maybe even
decades so this is a quote from David white one of the great First Steps in
writing poetry is to stop the surface conversation you're having
now the peripheral conversation you're having the conversation where you are in
competition or you feel besieged where you feel
fragmented and drop down into a central image or tonality in the body or in your
understanding that can hold a whole constellation of individual qualities
together qualities that circulate around you at the edge of your ordinary
everyday life this is called the poetic imagination
I love that he's talking about stopping the conversation that you're having some of the we could think about this as like
the chatter the thinking all this stuff that happens in the mind conversations with ourselves
imaginary conversations with other people but maybe just the way that the mind is speaking quote
unquote so he's putting down like to put down the story making and this chatter
and maybe the everyday way in which our likes to do things and instead to be
embodied to be present here so I'll lead us in some guided
meditation and then I'm going to drop in a poem from David White and we'll unpack
it and explore this poem a little bit uh after the guided meditation so if you haven't
already take an upright posture a posture that expresses
your intention to
meditate it be nice to have some
[Music] exhales help the arriving process
help us to get collected
around this bodily experience this
moment so that we can inhabit this moment inhabit Our Lives
feeling the pressure against the body pressure from the sitting
surface feeling connected grounded where here having this
experience ordinary everyday experience and can
that be okay and you be in a body that's just
having an ordinary mundane experience uh being in a meditation
posture
of a b body scan starting at the top
feeling into any area that feels like it wants to be felt
into areas that have tightness or tension often around the eyes or jaw
shoulders letting them be away from the
ears maybe there's a way in which the shoulders move back just a tiny bit that
allows the chest to open allows the chest to be a little bit
less shielded guarded more
spacious very small
movement feeling the other side of the chest the upper
back there be ease softness
there and the lower back
can we send some love and care to our lower back as
humans sometimes have issues
there the belly allowing it to be
soft and it be unguarded relaxed just for this meditation period
and again feeling the pressure of this sitting surface against the body the
buttock back of the legs
repeat and we be embodied with an attitude of kindness
and
warmth resisting any feeling of wanting to complain
or fix the
body can we inhabit our physical forms with
appreciation
as we inhabit the body we notice the body breathes
can we rest attention on the sensations of
breathing feeling whatever there is to be f with
inhales
and exhales what do an exhale feel what's
the experience of
exhaling e
resting knowing that the body knows how to breathe
we don't have to do
anything to breathe or just noticing the experience
of
breathing
e
e e
going to drop in a [Music]
pem you don't need to do anything with this
poem you don't have to understand it you don't have to figure it
out you don't have to remember it and you certainly don't don't need to Google
it and you just experience
it this poem is called sometimes by David
White sometimes by David
White and it goes like
this sometimes if you move carefully through the forest breathing like the ones in the
old stories who could cross a shimmering bed of leaves without a sound
you come to a place whose only task is to trouble you
with tiny but frightening
requests conceived out of nowhere but in this place beginning to lead
everywhere request to stop what you are doing right now and to stop what you are becoming
while you do it questions that can make or unmake a
life questions that have patiently waited for you questions that have no right to go
away
e e
read this poem again the poem is sometimes by David
White sometimes if you move carefully through the forest breathing
like the ones in the old stories who could cross a shimmering bed of leaves
without a [Music] sound you come to a place whose only
task is to trouble you with tiny but frightening
requests conceived out of nowhere but in this place beginning to lead everywhere
requests to stop what you are doing right now and to stop what you are becoming
while you do it questions that can make or unmake a
life questions that have patiently waited for
you questions that have no right to go
away
e
e e
[Music] for [Music]
[Music]
welcome good morning greetings hello those of us those of you who are
joining at this time after the guided meditation the guide meditation I
dropped in this poem called sometimes by David White and uh David White he has
spoken about this poem in a number of uh different settings and like you know some poets who never talk about their
poems and they just kind of like offer them out to the world and let the world
interpret them however they'd like and and David White in this poem
he's spoken about in some rather large forums I would say that is uh with Sam
Harris on a podcast and with Oprah so these are like two big uh forums so
where he's uh discussed this maybe um I'll say this poem a
little bit and then I want to share some things that uh David White has uh shared
about this poem it's called sometimes by David
White sometimes if you move carefully through the forest breathing like the
ones in the old stories who could cross a shimmering bed of leaves without a sound you come to a
place whose only task is to trouble you
with tiny but frightening requests conceived out of nowhere but in
this place beginning to lead everywhere request to stop what you are
doing right now and to stop what you are becoming while you do
it questions that can make or unmake a
life questions that have patiently waited for you you questions that have
no right to go away so David White talks about this
very last expression questions that have no right to go
away and uh he expresses them saying that these are um questions that have to
do with the person we are about to become and he's uh writes that they are
conversations that will happen with or without our conscious participation but
they have something to do with how we might be more generous more courageous more present
more dedicated so he's talking about these questions that um maybe and I like that
that he's using this word conversations there's this way in which you we're often having conversations with
ourselves conversations with our environment with our experiences without maybe necessarily
talk using that expression conversations but there's a way in which the thinking mind is like you know engaging with and
interacting with uh itself our experiences and uh the environment out
there and I kind of like this uh word uh conversations as a as a way to express
that and so he's talking about this um
potential that these questions that have to do with the person we are about to
become so he's talking about like being embodied and being present for our lives
and being present for what's happening and taking note of maybe about
to become in Buddhist language we might say like what are we uh identified
with or it could also be you know what is uh can we be present for what's
simply unfolding here I'm opening my hands we're identified often as like grabbing onto something or uh what
what's uh what's unfolding what's naturally
happening so in response to this uh expression like what questions that have
no right to go away David White he offers a number of questions specifically and I'd like to um
offer just a tiny tiny subset I think he gave a list of 10 I think I'll do two this
morning one question he offers is that we can have with ourselves and that might arise uh as a result of maybe
being embodied my interpretation of what he's pointing to in his poem one
question is what can I be wholehearted about what can I be whole wholehearted
about have this expression wholehearted like you know like bringing in the fragments bringing in the different
pieces and instead just to what is something that feels like all of myself
can be present for all of myself can be collected around or something like
this and David White writes what do I care most about in my location in my
family life in my heart and mind he continues this is a conversation
we all must have with ourselves at every stage of Our Lives a conversation we so
often don't want to have we'll get to it we say when the
kids are grown when there is enough money in the bank when we are retired perhaps when we are dead it'll be easier
then but we need to ask it now what can I be wholehearted about
now I love this like so often we find ourselves spending our time our energy
doing things that we think that we're supposed to be doing showing up in a way that we think we're supposed to but like
what is it that um like all aspects of ourselves can get collected
behind instead of like a way in which we are often uh
um pushing them to a side or ignoring them or thinking like okay I'll get to
that later I'll be completely myself uh be with all different aspects of myself
sometime later I appreciate that he's writing
this is a conversation that we all must have with ourselves at every stage of Our Lives a conversation that we so
often don't want to have and I know that uh when I was a scientist all those
years training to be a scientist and then all those years actually being a scientist in some ways there um I now
you know retrospectively I can look back and say there was this place which I love science I still love science so
much and biochemistry some of you might know I'm a PhD biochemist I love
biochemistry I still do but there was a way in which also I
was ignoring kind of like you know my inner life and ignoring what was or trying to at least ignore certain
aspects of myself just as I was pursuing um science
biochemistry so is this a conversation that what can I be wholehearted
about and then um another question that David White offers he WR here's the question can I
be the Blessed saint that my future happiness will always
remember can I be the Blessed saint that my future happiness will always remember
and then this is David White writing here's the explanation for what sounds like a strange question and this is
David White I have a poem called Coleman's bed about a place in the west of Ireland where the Irish Saint Coleman
lived the last line of that poem calls on the reader to remember quote the
quiet robust and blessed saint that your future happiness will always remember so
I love that day by po right he's kind of like tying together like one poem with another poem and you know he's like
having conversations with himself and the poems are having conversation conversations with each
other so David White he continues we go to places of pilgrimage where Saints
have lived or even to Graceland where Elvis lived
I love to kind of throwing in Elvis there because these people have given to the rest of us music or good works that
has carried on down the years and that was a generous gift to the
future but that blessed Saint could also be
yourself the person who In This Moment makes a decision that can make a bold
path into the years that come and whom your future happiness would
always remember what could you do now for yourself or others that your future self
would look back on and congratulate you for something that could view with real thankfulness because the decision you
made opened up the life for which it is now eternally
grateful so David White is pointing to what can we do now that helps creates
the condition s that there can in the unfolding of our life there can be more and more peace
and happiness and greater ease and I'll use this word
Freedom what can we do now that in the future we will think oh yeah that was
that was helpful I'd like to offer of course that having a meditation practice is a part
of that having a meditation practice in which we give ourselves the opportunity and the space to ask these questions and
to um become sensitive to our lives to embody our lives and to be able to feel
into what is it that we can be wholehearted about what is it that will
help create the conditions we can have a future that is a future that
um has the great uh spaciousness and ease and peace and love and kindness or
whatever it is for you that's meaningful wisdom compassion
Freedom this is part of the beauty of this practice we get to choose which words we get to choose which uh what's
the most meaningful for us but what can you get wholehearted
around what can you do today that supports a
future that's filled with happiness we don't know what the future
holds of course not but can we this is what I'd like to offer can we create the
sensibility the skills of that whatever the future holds
we can hold it with love kindness compassion
wisdom no matter what the future brings us
so I'll end with saying one more time this
poem sometimes by David way sometimes if you move carefully
through the forest breathing like the ones in the old stories who could cross a shimmering bed
of leaves without a sound you come to a place whose only t
ask is to trouble you with tiny but
frightening requests conceived out of nowhere but in
this place beginning to lead
everywhere requests to stop what you are doing right now and to stop what you are
becoming while you do it questions that can make or unmake a life questions that
have patient ly waited for you questions that have no right to go
away thank you thank you for your practice it's
lovely to practice together and maybe join me in this exploration of the
Poetry of practice wishing you all a wonderful rest of your day or rest of your evening
or whenever it is that you're listening to this thank you