welcome welcome good morning good afternoon good evening wherever you are and for those
of you who are listening in the future welcome welcome those of you who are here online welcome welcome what a what
a delight it is to practice together it's a such a beautiful
thing so I'm going to continue on this series on the inner critic today's the fourth day
Thursday talking about this and there's I'm going to guide us in a
meditation that's um going to build on some of the meditations we've been doing
earlier in the week but if you haven't been there earlier in the week that's perfectly fine
also I'm going to point to something inside of us that um it's hard to
describe but it's has a certain amount of maybe
settledness or okayness even though there might be a lot of chaos and
difficulty and discomfort sometimes we can touch into something inside of us that
uh feels a certain amount of steadiness
or wholesomeness even if it's just you know a fleeting recognition of it or
a sense of of it rather than a clear description or clear ability to
land on it like yes this is it now in the Dad I'll be pointing to
this as an alternative to this inner critic which can be so
harsh and so um have such a big impact on our lives in a way that causes us to
disconnect from our experience or
in some kind of way okay so well that as an
introduction i' like um to begin in this way where just bringing to
mind somebody who or some creature some
doesn't have to be a person somebody who just kind of makes you smile a little bit in a very simple way notal
complicated we're not overthinking this just what feels a little bit delightful
when you bring them to
mind we're using our imagination they're not chances are
they're not right here in front of us that we can visually see them but and
maybe they are maybe it's your cat or dog but if they're not just bringing
them to mind and is there a way that we can feel
the warm feel the connection feel the openness or warm-heartedness towards
this lovable being again this is very
simple we don't have to try to find the perfect lovable being if one isn't
obvious just bring to mind mind maybe the spring
flowers here in the Bay Area spring has sprung lot of flowers it's really
beautiful just tuning into the the
light might be this sense
of and then with that sense of delight
or warmth or openness appreciation use whatever word feels
appropriate for you and Orient towards the bodily
experience what is it like at this moment to be having this somatic
embodied experience what is it like to be in this meditation
posture and to feel like we are in this meditation
posture at this
moment
maybe there's a sense of aliveness a sense of
embodiment I'm using these vague words so you can find your own
way
and to support a sense of
ease and extend the exhale just for a few breaths
and extend it just a tiny
bit just tapping into the body's natural
physiology using that as a support as an
ally
allowing the breath to return to normal trusting that the body knows how
to breathe and bringing this orientation of delight
warmth and ease bringing that with us as we rest
the attention on the sensations of
breathing
feeling the body
breathing feeling the
movements might be a stretch in the chest and a
subsequent release of the
stretch maybe a sense of the belly moving in and
out maybe
feeling the air moving in and out of the
nose whichever area whichever movements whichever
[Music] Sensations feel the most [Music]
accessible and the easiest the most
Pleasant
e
and feeling connected and
grounded we're
here
e
when the mind wanders as it's apt to do this is what
Minds do we just very simply
gently begin again with the sensations of
breathing
e
nothing in per needs to be
happening we're just noticing hanging out with the sensations of breathing and a
relaxed easy way without
insisting that something different happen than what is
happening as best we can as best we
can maybe the mind is agitated maybe the mind is
tired can that be
okay maybe the mind is settled [Music] and relaxed and
open and that be okay
e
and can we tune into any sense of
okayness wellbeing contentment
doesn't have to be our dominant experience maybe it's just a corner of
our experience but can we tune into
that any sense of settledness groundedness
okayness
and allowing it to get as big as it would
like we're not making anything happen we're just allowing
inviting any sense of okayness to get as big as it would
like
and can any sense of okay pain
or well-being certain amount of contentment whatever amount is
there can we allow this to be the
source of the mindfulness fueling supporting the mindfulness the
awareness the attention in a simple easy
way as if it were a paint paint and we're like painting our
experience painting our experience with this whatever amount of ease we
have
e
resting attention on the sensations of
breathing and having this intention attention imbued
with any sense of well-being or ease
relaxation contentment that's [Music]
available in a relaxed way and when the mind wanders when
thinking happens we don't have to make it a problem we're okay with that too
and we just return to the
breath
e
[Music]
and with that guided
meditation just tapping in a little bit to this sometimes it's uh obvious and
sometimes it's very subtle this sense of I'm using these vague words like okayness or well-being or contentment
but something maybe that's just not agitated something that's um has
a sense of settledness or uh being present in a nice kind of
way so as you know I'm continuing on this uh series of the inner critic and as I have
been doing the other days just to define the inner critic as maybe it's a um like
a dynamic that's inside of us that is putting us down and belittling us and
judging us in a way that says okay somehow you are inadequate my with the G
you're inadequate I'm exaggerating but I'm exaggerating in terms of like um how
obvious it might be but it might you know feel the same might have this same
way this kind of like blaming ourselves and nagging ourselves with this real
harshness and this kind of be this sense of shame that accompanies accompanies it
and there so much uh pain that can be caught up in this structure and these days I've been
talking about this uh inner critic and for us to not like pone negativity onto
the onto the negativity of course that's how we can break the cycle because if we have that feeling like oh I have to get
rid of the critic that's just more of the same type of energy so we're trying
to meet it with a different type of uh energy that one of warmth and awareness
and spaciousness but we might have noticed
that there's a certain amount of resistance to stop this inner critic
there might be a certain like yeah yeah yeah that sounds nice Diana but I need it I need this inner
critic it serves me it's helpful there might be a part of us that feels a certain amount of loyalty to it
because we might have this idea this notion and it's just an idea it's just a
notion that without this inner critic we would never get out of bed in the
morning we would just lay around eat Bon bonss and um not do any work whatsoever
whether it's work to take care of our living space to take care of our responsibilities or our professional
life that we have this feeling that it's only with this inner critic that's having
this this kind of a whip that's whipping us into shape and
so we have this belief that if the inner critic weren't having this admonitions that okay you have to do better that we
would just end up being lazy slobs they might be a part of us that
thinks that we need this inner critic so there's a way in which um the
effectiveness of having uh this CR iCal
mean disparaging uh movement or experience in
our life is helpful there's been a lot of research is that what motivates people or is it to be more encouraging
or positive and focused on what is possible versus uh what's wrong you
might imagine there's been a lot of research on this because Corporate America wants to know the answer to this
and Corporate America has money to to spend on these types of things so this is not just something in the kind of
like the self-help uh community that we say but there's been some serious research and it shows numerous Studies
have shows that people are far more motivated and
engaged when there's a sense of encouragement and positivity and focused
on what is possible like a Direction they can go like where some movement
that's possible into something that's even better as opposed to just putting us
down and shaming and and anybody who's had a boss or indeed who has this inner
critic that's really loud but if you've had a boss who's really um kind of
mean then you notice how it kind of is deflating not kind of it is
Def I um haven't had a boss like that but I did see when I was in Corporate America in a department that was similar
to mine that we had to partner with that uh the boss of this other department o
this person was mean I couldn't believe some of the things that came out of the mouth of this person and I saw how oh
the people that were uh in that department were kind of like demoralized
and and frankly they were mean to other people too was quite something so in
order to have the best versions of our self it's uh we need to stay connected
to what uh is valuable what we see is valuable within us stay connected to a
sense of meaning and purpose and stay oriented towards what's possible stay
oriented towards here's the direction we're going staying oriented towards
aspirations and what we find valuable so it turns out that we don't actually need
this inner critic especially not in the way that we think we do we don't need it to guide us in these choices because the
inner critic is just this pretty crude mechanism and has a very simplistic
view of ourselves and of the world is this very uh sophisticated view of what
is right and wrong it's as sophisticated as an we might say the
eight-year-old brain that developed it but and we have more sophisticated
ways more helpful ways more mature ways to guide
us we have a conscience we have a moral compass we have some of the Buddhist
teachings the precepts and this movement towards wholesome qualities generosity
compassion wisdom these beautiful things loving kindness we can use these to guide
us rather than the inner critic and it to be sure it does take a
certain amount of trust to kind of like put aside the inner critic and to say okay I'm going
to trust that these beautiful qualities are inside me we all know they're inside
me inside us I don't know if you know what inside me but you know what I mean that all of
us have it inside and it does take a certain amount
of trust to put aside the inner critic and instead to tune into some of these
beautiful wholesome qualities that we all have we all have them and this practice is so much about
cultivating and developing those wholesome qualities we're not creating them out of thin air we're just uh
helping them to grow and become more and more a part of our life so this inner
critic part of its job is to tell you no you need me and you need me to navigate
difficult Realms because you can't do it on yourself this is or you can't do it by
yourself this is the critic speaking this is its job is to tell you that it
needs that you need it but the truth is and if we look at it we'll see that this inner critic just makes us feel
worse and this feeling worse it stops this kind of like engagement or this inquiry
into like what's really happening or some curiosity that can increase our
understanding instead it kind of like just shuts everything down no this is
bad this is good you're bad so you have to do that something like this so part
of this practice with the inner critic is learning to distinguish learning to
differentiate what we might say discernment from
judgment they're both similar and that they're distinguishing and uh discriminating between things but here's
a few ways how we can tell the difference between discernment and judgment I'll start with kind of
judgment this inner critic this inner critic there's a certain type of like power differential there's a s like I
know better this inner critic is trying to tell you know I know better and that not only do I know
better but I have the power and the right to determine what is good or
bad I and this inner critic is telling this uh like this is you know it's a
little bit odd to talk about this uh kind like in the Buddhist context but um
maybe you can uh give me the benefit of the doubt here and um just go with um
maybe part of your experiences so the experience of the inner critic is trying to tell or just assert itself that
there's this pathetic part of you that does a know right or wrong and that the
inner critic is needed to uh whip it into shape in some kind of way and so
this inner critic it has a sense of finality it's like this it's simply like
this and you know like okay done I don't have to think about it anym more and that's part of why it's uh evolved is
because it does makes things simple and a little bit less effort good bad you
know don't have to think about it anymore but this inner critic and this
uh passing of these judgments it's born out of a sense of wanting to control it's it's born out of a sense of
feeling uncomfortable with a sense of you know not with a sense of things
maybe not being as clear as we would like or maybe we don't understand things as well as we would like maybe we feel a
little bit uncomfortable with the ambiguity so the inner critic arises as a sense of control like no I know what's
right I know what's wrong and this is good and that's bad and end of story and of course this inner critic
has this kind of like this reactive quality this knee-jerk response to what is happening without
consideration and because it has this knee-jerk quality and it's trying to give us a sense of control it might just
be flying Under The Rad Radar trying to convince us that no this is the
truth but as I said before it takes one little piece of data one little
experience and then creates a huge generalization you
didn't reply to that email in a timely manner therefore you are a mean
inconsiderate person it's amazing how the inner critic just likes to make up stuff based on one
little thing okay so that's the inner critic what about like discernment what is
discernment this is a more personal conscious than than being critical or
judging it comes from this inner wisdom this inner knowing it comes from this
place that has more of a sense of settledness and well-being and contentment
and it might involve a more intuitive understanding of what is
best it might have this heart quality more than a head quality that's like I
know that the heart quality might be like this feels
right so there's this way in which there's this the um with discernment we
can distinguish what's helpful and not helpful or what's appropriate or what's
not appropriate whereas the inner critic often has words like good and bad
there's a discernment is more like okay yeah what's what's helpful here and so
helpful kind of like takes into the bigger context of the impact it has on oneself the impact it has on others so
it s has some more sophistication so rather than this just a habitual nature reaction it's involves
both our hearts and our minds and it seeks
alignment rather than control like the inner critic this it seeks alignment
with reality it seeks alignment with what's
actually happening it seeks alignment with um our heart's wish to be
free the mind's wish to be free
so it's not so much like pushing and shoving sometimes like how the inner
critic do does but it's uh yeah wanting to align
with truth reality Beauty these kind of
vague words that often our hearts get involved
to help us know those words I'm not saying that the mind is offline but maybe that the heart gets brought in
so in part of this I was pointing to this distinction between um judgment and
Discerning yesterday when I was talking about noticing what kind of thoughts are helpful and not helpful maybe we can use
this language of judging versus Discerning and recognize that
Discerning is a better way to like lead our life which can be a support for us
so maybe we can just check in with a simple uh expression what does
the heart say what does the heart
say so we can add this on to Monday we talked about dropping in I'm doing the
best I can right now Tuesday tuning into to how am I
right now Wednesday we talked about judgment is like
this and today i' like to offer what does the heart
say what does the heart say as a way to help us make this uh distinguishment
between judging from the inner critic and this more we might say
discernment this more mature wise discernment judging versus
Discerning what does the heart say thank you thank you for your
practice together and I look forward to coming back and practicing tomorrow with
you Mom thank
you
thank you thank you thank you
all
maybe I'll do a shout out to all of of you who are not commenting you know I'm commenting and saying hello and reacting
to those individuals that are posting but uh I also want to give a shout out to those people who are not posting I
know there's a lot of you out there and in the the quiet and of your wherever you
are just uh warm welcome and a thank you to you too practicing with
us
I'm looking at the title that I wrote for today detrimental dedication to the
critic I kind of uh chose that as the bunch of the alliterations and it has
that sound kind of like that harsh sound I don't know I kind of
Tracy wrote I love that what does the heart say what would love have me know right now very nice what would love have
me know right
now
what does the heart
say
e
thank you thank you all it's lovely lovely to practice together see you
tomorrow