good evening welcome welcome hope everybody's doing okay with
the heat that uh we're having hopefully we're on the tail end
of that so today I wanted to talk a little
bit about this whole notion or this idea of seeing
seeing you know this usual and complicated thing that uh humans do
but first I wanted to talk about how we like just in English how we sometimes
use this verb to see there's the obvious one this like literal perception with
the eyes like I can see the mountains from here or maybe there's this way we use
the word seeing to talk about you know dating or being in relationship yeah
they've been seeing one another for a few months or you know something like that or maybe we use this uh we're
seeing to talk about imagination or can't can't you just see
yourself going down the slopes in the skiing when it's so hot or something
like this you know just this invitation to uh imagine something in
particular or maybe we even use this expression C to talk about like I'll
accompany you I'll see you to the door or maybe there's this way we also
say that seeing is related to understanding oh I
see this kind of way I kind of like it when there's these
simple words that get used in so many different ways and we can look at them differently and understand things
differently in some ways we might say that that's so much about meditation practice Buddhist practice is about
taking something that seems ordinary and looking at it in a little bit different
way and it has a have a different understanding it has a different
impact so I'm going to look at this uh word seeing and maybe what it points to
and some of the way the experience of it from a number of different
ways and in particularly like how this this part of a path of practice to
Greater freedom and ease and peace and well-being not only just some little
intellectual curiosity fun thing to do but uh it's something that will help to bring some more ease in our lives to
understand maybe a little bit the way that uh we see and maybe some of the ways we don't
see as a support for practice so first I'll start with maybe
the obvious thing the you know using the senses the the eyes we
see and in uh the classical Buddhist teachings they talk a certain amount
about this how there has to be a contact with eyeballs I'll say or the eye
apparatus and there has to be something out there to see in order for seeing to
happen when we say it this way it sounds pretty obvious but uh there's a way in
which um we could unpack that and look at that from a number of different angles but
I'm not going to here I'm just now I'm just going to highlight that there are a
number of elements to this thing that we just do all day long and if yeah that we
do all day long and one is to have a visual apparatus that
works not everybody does and sometimes it doesn't work so well and maybe as
we're aging we're noticing oh yeah it doesn't work the way that it did or when
I have my glasses on it certainly works much better than when it doesn't or something like
that and then also the second element that there needs to be something to be
seen I mean maybe that's like so obvious we don't think about it but uh there's a
way in which we could um unpack that that there's it's that there
requires something that's belongs to the human body body and then something that doesn't belong to the human body in
order for this whole seeing thing uh to
happen I think I'll leave it there that's pretty uh pretty obvious not so
complicated but I wanted to spend a little more time talking about this idea
that like seeing like the role that the mind has in seeing it's not just a a
labs and nerves the optic nerve and all that kind of
stuff because probably we know this but maybe I'll say it explicitly you know
our eyes or maybe I should say our experience of seeing are not like
cameras we all have this experience where you see a picture of yourself you're like oh I look like that because
when we see ourselves in the mirror we see ourselves in some particular way and then when you see a photo you're like oh
okay there's it looks a little bit different so it's not like we get a a
perfectly accurate uh view of what's out
there and I just recently heard this story which also highlighted that
sometimes we just don't notice stuff that maybe that would show up on a
camera maybe even like a zoom camera maybe we uh have this
experience of noticing sometimes uh during the pandemic I did a lot I spent
a lot of time on zoom and I did a lot of teaching on zoom and sometimes having like a curious like I wonder if this
person recognizes that in their background is this you know curious thing that uh maybe they wouldn't want
all of us to look at and uh I heard this story recently of um a zen teacher who
um was in her Zen robes very official shaved head you know very serious giving
a talk and not realizing that her panties were for set out to dry on a
line behind her so I'm sure righta this probably wasn't what she was imagining
when she was uh giving this talk I'm sure people were kind of looking or something I don't
know so there's this way in which sometimes we don't notice things
and in fact this is like a wellestablished phenomenon that uh advertisers and
marketers are uh working with and trying to influence with and that is maybe
you've had this experience too that um I'll I'll share I had
experienced not too long ago where I was um at the shore down there the water and
um saw oh look at these these uh this type of uh seashell wow look at this
I've never seen anything like this this is amazing wow this is so
great and then when I looked again I thought oh they're everywhere I just
hadn't noticed just that when You' really look at something and now your the mind kind of recognizes it then you
start to see it everywhere people talk about this like well I think I'm going to buy this particular car and then when
you're driving you start to see oh wow okay this car is everywhere but you hadn't really noticed it
before this is actually called the B Mina phenomena so I didn't know it actually
has a name but there's something interesting that happens here there's
this way that there's this cognitive processes that kick in and that are
affecting what we see so there's this one in which we have
this itive attention for me when I didn't notice i' had been walking along
the water for quite some time before I noticed oh wow look at this and then I
started to see there's so much everywhere that when we there's like maybe a a subconsciously maybe decide
that something is important noteworthy worthwhile to see before we
hadn't made that decision consciously or unconsciously but once we see something
and often then it's unconscious we start to see it more and more and more so there's this cognitive process that has
decided oh this is important I'm going to notice it
more so then what wasn't seen before all a sudden starts to become
seen and then there's this second thing that's happening is this um confirmation
bias that we start to believe that something is important so then it must also be prevalent or if it's prevalent
it must be important this kind of like link between prevalence and importance
gets made and then because we're seeing it more often we start to think like oh this is everywhere everybody thinks this
or this must be true just because we tend to be seeing it more often but it's
just this confirmation bias this idea that we want because we've decided
something is important we want to see it more often so I'm pointing this out just to
highlight how the mind has a role and what is like actually what's
seen it's not so innocent just this seeing
things not as innocent as we might like to think so we don't see the visual
field with as much Fidelity as a camera does for
example so there's this way so we might say that just the sense organ meeting the sense
object it's kind of like that with the Buddhist language use which would be sensing and maybe we might say seeing is
something that the Mind does when the scene is when the mind is
in interpreting or analyzing or manipulating or somehow you know working
with this data that's coming in through the visual field but we might also notice that
there's seeing versus looking it's kind like this subtle
difference and so seeing is like this natural effortless sensory
experience when the sense or meets the sense object so there's no intentional
effort whether it's conscious or unconscious it's just a what just a experience of seeing is
happening but looking is a very subtle but it's more
of an intentional like oh I'm what what is going on there and wanting to look so
there's more of a focusing in sometimes going for a walk we're just uh
we're seeing that there's green plants all around but then like oh wow look at
this look at uh how there's this plant that's growing out of this sidewalk
right here next to this other thing and we stop and kind of look at like wow how did that
happen wish I could give you a great example off the top of my head but I don't have one but I think we all have
this experience of was that a mouse that was just going by what was said you know looking or
something not here not a mouse here I'm see I was thinking about that did happen to me not long ago I was out for a walk
I was like a little mouse went by like oh
okay so looking is this more intentional directed action whereas seeing is not so
much intentional but there's something that can happen if we become sensitive to
this shift between seeing and looking there's this way that we can
learn something about ourselves what are the types of objects
that encourage this shift to really look at for me it was those plants the one
that was growing up out of the sidewalk and trying to see it did it come out of this crack or is it related to this
other plant over here that you know just trying to understand how it grew like for me it was I kind of
like this idea that there's Greenery that can find its way in difficult
circumstances you know something beautiful and life I like this notion so
there's this idea that I notice these things it uh really it confirms this
this preference that I have it's also of course seeing moving
things but when we become aware of the shift
between seeing and looking we start to understand ourselves better what is it
that causes this looking what do we pause and pay attention
to and what don't we what don't we pause and pay attention
to so what are the like maybe the thought patterns that we have that uh
direct our visual attention oh here's a short little poem
that talks about this by Rosemary
traumer and this was H written in February I think February of this year
2024 but I'm not exactly sure and it's this poem goes like
this I'm not sure I could say they are beautiful these brittle Brown sink foil
stems trembling in the wind though part of me longs to find
beauty everywhere ah the longing to see beauty
shapes the way I meet the world there seeing this truth beautiful
as a Golden Flower so just this recognition oh yeah
she's always wanting to see beauty and is oriented towards seeing
Beauty and that understanding about herself she finds
beautiful and why might it be helpful or beautiful to
recognize one's preferences for seeing or what uh one's orientation
is because if we have an orientation towards Beauty for example we'll see
beauty but we will also see a lot of ugliness because it becomes like this
Frame is this beautiful no is this beautiful yes and there becomes a little
bit of no there's a little bit of pulling back and yes oh want more
of and then our life maybe becomes a little bit smaller because there's a lot of like oh that's not beautiful get out
of here and this kind of dismissive not wanting it to be there have this
aversion this uh subtle way and like you know we want to bat it away and go find
something beautiful for this talk I'm talking about uh visual experiences but you know
this could be with everything but just to have this Insight
what is it that causes us to look maybe it's like something Cur ious
and maybe we like to see problems or and we like to solve them or maybe it's
something that doesn't make sense and we have this bias that we want things to make sense in order for us to feel safe
in the world we want to understand it and it should be uh I don't know clear
to us so then we spend a lot of our maybe
Life Energy and trying to understand things and make sense of things that may maybe it's not worth all our life energy
maybe it's uh something that uh it's not understandable like why did uh something
or rather happen presumably there's a
reason but do we have to spend so much energy trying to figure this
out or maybe we tend to really look at things or maybe maybe I'll back up on
this or I'll continue on this here I am in the middle I'm noticing how I'm
seeing how I I I got stuck there for a little bit having two thoughts in my mind at the same
time this idea that maybe we are just noticing as problems because a we like to fix things
or we're noticing things that aren't clear because B we feel like we want to understand
things where nothing wrong in this but then we might understand like okay how
are these patterns affecting our life same problems maybe we want to fix
things because we want to be seen as one like okay I can take care of it and perfectly
capable and then we kind of get stuck in this identity then we always have to fix
things because we're defining ourselves as the one who can fix things or should
fix things or maybe we have this idea that I want to understand things because
really we're not feeling safe in some kind of way and we're feeling like okay if I understand it better then I I'd
feel a little bit more safe i' feel a little bit more comfortable so there's this way in which
just seeing this recognition from recognizing the seeing to looking
shift can really be a doorway to Greater understanding this something that we do
all the time and when we notice it we can also do the shift the opposite way we can go
from looking to seeing just like relax the
focusing and maybe there's a way there's a little bit of a softing
softening and just allow the scene to happen and the because what happens when
we just allow the scene then there's less judging and
comparing and evaluating and when there's less
comparing judging and evaluating there's more freedom there's more freedom there's more
ease I'm not saying that we have to like stop using our intellect and not discern between what's uh harmful and not
harmful or what is appropriate and inappropriate or you know what's helpful and not helpful I'm not saying that of
course we still need to be doing that I'm just talking about noticing just
like this judging and like oh that's not good enough or how can they do that or who do they
think they are or this comparing wow that person is
uh taller and that I am or something like
this said from somebody who's not very tall
it's for me it's remarkable how we can just notice like this uh the path of
practice this movement towards greater Freedom often we can have the sense that okay you have to meditate you have to
sit in a meditation posture and has to be a particular way and then you'll gain some
insights but what this is pointing to is just your everyday
experience we're seeing if we have have Vision whenever the Eyes Are Open well
we can see when the eyes are closed too right we can see the back of the eyelids well I don't know what we see but it's
there's something there when I'm closing my eyes I see something so there's this way of that we
can have this understanding about actually how our minds create
suffering with all this comparing and judging and evaluating which I'm saying is distinct
from I'm Discerning what is helpful and not helpful what's wholesome and not wholesome what's helpful what's skillful
and what's unskillful we can start to see the role that our mind does because not only is
it doing all this judging and comparing it's also making stories like based on
what we see there might be a way in which this uh visual
cue has uh kind of like Trigg triggers a reaction and then this the reaction
could just lead us down this whole thought train into more and more
suffrin there's this way in
which this can be really helpful that the visual field can start a thought train a reaction for example if I have
to remember to bring something with me when I'm going to go somewhere maybe you guys do this too I put something near
the door okay I have to remember I will see this as I'm going to the door and um I'll remember to take it is really
helpful but there's also a way in which we can see things and we'll just make
this up oh yeah there's that paperwor on my desk I have to take care of it but I
can't take care of that because oh that's that terrible thing that's happened it reminds me of that and I
don't want to be reminded of that so I'm not going to take care of this paperwork and then it just keeps on
getting later and later and more and more overdue or whatever it might be but
and then we start to feel bad like oh I haven't take I haven't taken care of that but I don't want to because then
people will know that I didn't X Y or Z and then there's this lowgrade suffering
that kind of shows up in our life so these stories that are getting
connected to just paper on the desk or something like
this I find myself at a loss tonight to like come up with any interesting
anecdotes I'm sure all of you have more interesting examples than the ones that I'm giving where seeing something kind
like just starts a whole thought train that uh leads to a sense of unease a
sense of dis Qui a sense of like ah
this G something like
that so not only do like the stories that often come up after uh we see
something are they kind of lead to suffering because they maybe are filled with some of this judging
and comparing but it also these stories take
us away from the present moment like we're no longer like experiencing our
life instead we're off thinking about whatever it is we're thinking well we're
just walking past the desk and walking past the desk feels
like just a mundane thing why would we pay attention to that but our life is
filled with just these mundane activities if we are dismissive just for
these ordinary experiences then there's this way in which our life just passes Us by as we
more and more are waiting for something titillating or to you know catch our attention Meanwhile we're just lost
in stories which you know what are stories they're a dime a dozen they have no you
know substance they have uh often they're completely fabricated they have
they start with an experience and off they go
and that's not really living life that's being lost in stories and so often we
don't even recognize how being lost in stories is harming us often we like to do it because it
distracts us or diverts US from some uncomfortable experience but then we
start to become disconnected from our lives and there's this way we kind of
start to feel a little bit alienated from our lives and disconnected from it and then we it can grow into being
disconnected from others because we're disconnected from ourselves and there's this way in which the stories just
really turn out not to be helpful so this shift from looking to
seeing is also a way like seeing is something that's happening right now in
this present moment I'm seeing something that's black there on I don't even quite sure what it
is there on the floor now I know what it is but right just seeing instead of like
a big story about it keeping things simple so that's one another way of
seeing it's like recognizing how the mind is really influencing seeing as
opposed to sensing sensing I'm trying to be cute that use these letter s sense and C but uh
sensing is maybe we we we could say seeing with the senses and seeing with
the mind and then I'd like to talk about one other type of seeing and this is
what we might call Insight and that is we might say like seeing through
something so not seeing the surface of what something
is not even looking at the surface of something is but seeing the quality that
it has for in particular qualities that things arise and pass away in the visual
field just it's their nature to arise and pass away things are inconstant
they're impermanent they're not always there there's this way in which
they change and our noticing that they're changing helps uh shifts our
relationship to them are noticing that they're changing
also makes them more it makes them impersonal in the sense of oh this is
something that's just uh shifting and changing on its own it doesn't have to mean anything about me as a person it's
has its own causes and conditions that made it arise and different causes and
conditions that made it pass away and in the same way I'm
like this what I take myself to be is also just a collection of these
experiences I've been talking about seeing but you know hearing tasting
smelling tactile feeling and we could say also thinking as an
experience we could say that this insight into a not only the things out
there are changing but there's nothing in here that isn't
changing everything in here is changing also it's just a collection of
experiences and so this way of seeing what we might call Insight is a
way that really reduces the suffering and really helps us to find more and more freedom helps us to let go of any
clinging that we might have or let go of our um expectations of how things might
be but instead just to
recognize the way things are and the way that we can if we can
like disengage from our habitual reactivity when we start to see oh
they're changing all the time I don't have to make them stay don't it just doesn't make sense to try
to hold on to them or make them go away they're shifting and changing already
and besides the shifting and changing experiences are all that actually happens there isn't an Essence inside
here to Which experiences happen right there's nothing here like
that has a visual experience and then has a hearing experience and then has a
tasting experience there's just hearing tasting seeing feeling thinking just collection
of experiences that are coming and going and so these two insights can lead
to greater and greater Freedom the greatest freedom I would say we have this shift in our
understanding or this shift in the way that we see things like oh I see it's
not as constant and solid and as I was imagining or thought it was or how I
initially perceived it and I'm not as constant and solid as I had been
imagining or thinking or perceiving myself so seeing there's just the visual
activity of seeing there's the seeing with the Mind recognizing how
the mind really does have an influence on what gets perceived and then there's the scene
maybe we could say scene through the Insight when we start to see the qualities of experiences no longer lost
in the content or just on the surface of what's happening but to see the quality
of it arising and passing away so with that I think I'll stop and
open it up to see if there's some questions or
comments okay
uh what comes to mind to me is the eyewitness accounts of things
are scientifically or empirically proven to be unreliable there you go thank you
that's right that's right how would you um deconstruct that yeah so we all have
biases it's kind of what I'm pointing to biases about what's important uh what
things mean and how it relates to us so it's impossible to see something
actually perfectly clear because there's this uh the I'm using this word biases
that we have so it's relates to like it's not it's actually not possible for
a human brain to see something in the same way that a camera does
even though we think that we are and this is why we like to fight about what's actually there because we're so convinced that what I saw is actually
the truth I don't know what you saw you must have been somewhere else but what I saw is the truth just not recognized and it's actually not possible for to be
completely a like a camera thank you
s anybody else have a comment or
question I got another quick okay um when we go into a museum we we
see art right we maybe we browse through and we see art and then something in US
tells us well I want to go look at that piece of art so I think looking when you're
looking at something maybe you're activating more things in your brain that you're
connecting with or you're um interested to learn about or to to look closer at
so I guess I I think of seeing as a um just a quick overview yeah and then
looking is something that you're you're using to investigate something yeah yeah I would say
investigate and I would say that uh art in particular we we could say that art
has a um is a part of a language that well maybe I don't have to go that far
but to say there's a resonance some pieces like oh we can feel a little stirring in ourselves and then we want
to go look so then we could uh just get curious like what are the types of things that I feel this stirring and
want to go look right is the ugly things or is it the confusing things is it the beautiful things or I don't know
something like this thank you so back
there so would you say that when we're seeing or looking the Lesser
filter we have like the less filter that we have within us you know in our
perception would be we' see trer we'd look
trer yeah this word true right uh let's see so the less filter we have yes but I
think it's not possible for humans to have zero filter but I think the power here is recognizing what are our
filters what what what are we oriented toward what are what biases do we have
when we look at things what uh catches our attention and looks at thank
you thank you so so I was reminded of of um Shakespeare and like much to do about
nothing right where when when you watch a play you as the audience
know information you have information right dramatic irony that the characters don't have and you watch them unfold
this drama that has to do with their perception what they see what they overhear what they think they hear and
you're sort of caught in the story and you know at the end you're like wow boy if they had only known this right they
don't know the whole story and that's why they are you know kind of stuck in this suffering you know if you wanted to
put it into that that context and you know sometimes it resolves well like a much I do about nothing you know it's a
comedy and so at the end everything gets resolved and all the misunderstandings are solved and you
know the bad you know there's one bad guy and he gets caught and whatever and then sometimes you know Merchant of
Venice it ends up very poorly for a lot of people you know and it's kind of the same right so you know it it can be
dangerous and it you know sometimes it can be comedic and we can learn from it so anyway that's what I was drawn to I
don't know others thought about it like that yeah yeah thank you right I mean this the human life is filled with this
right a lot of there's even how many movies are like he said she said kind of versions too right or something like
this yeah yeah misunderstandings misunderstandings but it can be I was thinking about uh one thing about Vision
which is also the same for hearing is to notice the scene to looking because when we that's like can be a way in which we
can notice what what are the things that we catch us the same thing could be happening for hearing and listening
right so yeah thank you anybody else have a comment
thanks so so a lot of interesting ideas here
um in my experience the Dilemma has been
on one hand being very very aware of cognitive biases
and filter of our perception and leaning very heavily on
that at the cost of invalidating or perhaps challenging
my own beliefs and perceptions and so I wonder if you have
thoughts on navigating that line between
acknowledging the limitation of our views and biases and you know the way we
filter and look for particular um things on one hand but on
the other hand um not gaslighting ourselves it's it's a tricky uh
something I've really struggled with so often what I let's see if I
understand this what your what you're point to here is if we have this idea that okay I want to find out what's true
and what's right maybe I'll just use this word true then we're like okay well I know I have some cognitive bises but
then like what's true but instead if we hold things like well this is my current
understanding this is what makes sense to me this is my hypothesis so our views if we just not hold them tightly just
like you know this is what makes sense to me instead of insisting okay this is true it's like okay this is what I think
how is and then we're not lost always trying to find what's right we're not
yeah trying to find what's the most true the least biased because like is of
course we don't want to be biased in a way that's harmful especially but there's I don't it's not possible for
humans to be completely see things completely
true even though we want to we want to think that we can and we want to think that we are and those other people
aren't is this helpful yeah I think
so I guess um so if yeah so if if none of the
beliefs or views we have are necessarily true uh at some point we have to act on
beliefs or make decisions based on our perceptions yeah and
yeah either you act you act on a decision or you act on a perception or belief that
is it could be wildly different two options and
and but we we do like but it's like okay well this is my current understanding
this is what makes sense instead of saying this is true saying like this all the data I have supports this view this
is what I'm going to make a decision based on this we may never know whether it's actually yeah true or so I guess
maybe maybe the question then is the value of uh questioning those beliefs so if something feels and uh
appears true or uh reliable uh the value of really
heavily questioning those beliefs and uh perceptions you on one hand that can be
very helpful in seeing more clearly on the the other hand the danger can be um
like I said gaslighting or nihilism right like nothingness yeah yeah so denying a Truth uh that may be very um
protective for example I'm sorry denying denying a belief that may be very protective
oh I think um denying a belief that may be very
protective or or or aggressively challenging a very deeply held belief oh
here we go are we talking about somebody else's beliefs or our own our own
yeah I think our own it's to to uh
question it I think it's fantastic actually like am I sure about this yeah
I I think so and then just recognize you know when more data comes in we may change our mind or something like this I
think there's real value and looking at our beliefs
yeah interesting yeah thank you you're welcome you're welcome okay so I wish you a wonderful
rest of the evening and that's at the right temperature thank you