so good morning everyone or good
day I think there is an invaluable
tendency or maybe not tendency but an invaluable
approach of offering meditation instruction which is radically
simple but sometimes the simpler and more profound it is the more difficult
it is to enact so one of them so at the beginning
of many meditations I offer something which maybe seems kind of
preliminary and that is I I mentioned to uh let your body be uh posture which is
expresses both being relaxed and alert an alert
posture in which you can relax and
um and any any meditation posture at all can find some balance of those
two if you're uh sitting in a chair or
couch using the back rest it might be helpful to sit up a little
straighter maybe not be quite as leaning back as you would kind of on your own do
but still using the support but uh sitting up more so the chest opens up a
little bit if you're lying down maybe there's a way of also adjusting the
spine the shoulder blades um maybe if there's a pillow so that maybe um the uh
some part of you the chest is more alert the some people will have their arms the
upper arms flat on the bed next to them or the floor next to them but their
forearms pointing to the ceiling one or both and uh and that brings a kind of in
intentionality and alertness and engagement that uh can also help this
alertness but this uh instruction to have a balance between being alert and
relaxed is also appropriate for the mind and for what we do in
fact it's enough that could be this can be the only instruction that meditation is
to stay alert and
relaxed and when we do that uh or say just add one more step
alert and relaxed and let nature take its
course and uh what alert and relax does is makes an
awareness that kind of clarity that allows whatever is there to be known
without us interfering with it just letting it be there let it be received
let it be known let it kind of arise and be there without a a relationship to it
not without a relationship being for and against it without a relationship of
defining ourselves by it without uh telling stories about it and predictions
of what this means very very simple just make space to be aware and why this is so profound
is that that is not what the Mind often does alert and relaxed is to be free of
attachments free of reactivity and so the reactive mind
begins to quiet down but the deeper natural mind the natural
functioning of our body and mind has a better opportunity to show itself to arise to be there some of that is the
are our body and mind's uh Power for healing spiritual healing psychological
healing that sometimes works uh at times is one of the best sources of healing we
can we can tap into at other times it's it's allowing deep spiritual or deep
humanistic um uh goodness wholesomeness to arise and flow that we have a wholesome natural
source within that's often covered over or diminished by the unnatural or or
synthetic or uh UNH wholesome kind of movements of
the mind that require our reactivity so a profound
trust in the natural functioning of our body and mind if we
get out of the way of all reactivity and even even being free of relate relating
to things instead to just be
alert and a and relaxed
to be aware awake and at
ease that's it so to establish
a posture that expresses some simple balance between being
alert and relaxed
letting the eyes be relaxed resting in their
sockets the eyes pointing in a direction where their eyes are
relaxed often it's gazing down 45° or
so and if it's nice gently closing the eyes
and to some degree you are aware there's a degree of
alertness that operates without any effort on your
part for a few moments here notice on the edges of your
attention or ways in which you are
aware without even it intending
to how certain Sensations sounds feelings
experiences that were not intended that you weren't directing yourself to know
come into the field of
attention and part of you where beyond the edges of your tension
pressure agitation there there exists within you probably
also some degree of being at ease being
relaxed maybe the joints of your small finger are relaxed
and so to sit
here breathing remembering the relax
part as you exhale
remembering the alert part as you
inhale all along
trusting that you need to do nothing else
then be alert awake relaxed at
ease in whatever way is easy for
you trusting nature trusting
the natural processes of your body and
mind
e
for
for for
if you are preoccupied in thoughts you are not not trusting the
natural functioning of being
alive to be awake and at
ease so the natural processes of your
life can [Music] unfold free free of attachments free of
reactivity free of
desires for
e
for
e for
and as we come to the end of this sitting could you perhaps for some
seconds for a minute let go of all mistrust
so that sitting here there is no active
mistrust whatsoever rather there's
a a full
trusting of the natural processes of our life here and
now of the Mind of the heart of the
body and being aware is getting out of the
way and trusting just being
here and aware
there is a principle in Psychology that when a group of people
are together when one person
as calm awareness of the situation the group the whole group
moves towards
Health may it be that we are the calm
person not just calm but alert awake
aware attentive to what what's happening happening with
others that our capacity to be mindful and
nonassertive is a clear comes with this clear strength of
presence of
attention of making space and allowing others to be
themselves so some other process can
unfold that is not based on our reactivity our sense of
urgency may it be that our practice that we
do supports the world that we live in to be less reactive
less hostile less
afraid less conceited and
greedy may we support the forces of goodness in this world the natural
forces of goodness may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free thank
you for
so welcome to this third talk on the upay suta those of you are interested in it's
in the numerical discourses the fifth chapter uh suo in bod's Translation suo
159 and uh what I read here is an excerpt from it then I'll read it
again so the Buddha said talking to his main attendant monk
Ananda it is not easy Ananda to teach the dhama to others
the dhma should be taught to others with five qualities when five qualities are
established with oneself which five the dhma should be taught to others
while thinking I will speak step by step
progressively that DBA should be taught to others while thinking I will speak for practical
reasons that dhama should be taught to others
thinking I will speak grounded in kindness the dhama should be taught to
others thinking I will not speak for material rewards the dhama should be taught to
others I will speak without wounding myself or
others and now one of the ways of understanding this text or trans
interpreting it is is it not just about how we teach uh teaching the dhama but
uh how we speak to others that we do we speak in a clear sense of progression
and building a building our our explanations or reasons we speak for
reasons we understand the causes and the conditions and the reasons for why we
say what we're going to say we speak with is it uh we speak with with kindness one of the great questions
is is when I'm about to say kind and um and uh we can speak not for
material reward not for to acquire things and get
things and uh and uh without wounding myself or others my harming Myself by
what I'm saying am I harming going to harm someone else so
uh for these five talks I'm not going in the same order because I want to connect them to the five core teachings from
last week so for today I'd like to uh connect last week's two I will not speak
for material reward and um and uh I'd like to suggest
that instead of speaking for material reward uh we can speak for Dharma
rewards and uh the Dharma is that which is without without conceit without greed
without hatred without hostility the Dharma is that which is free of self-
preoccupation acquisitioning but for Dharma rewards is to the rewards that come from deep
within that uh that part of ourselves is a it's a natural
functioning that we we best create the conditions for it to flow
freely than to engineer it it belongs to the mind of attachment
to reactivity that we're trying to control and fix and get things in some
kind of self-centered way and um and to not be involved in
this U material gain uh pursuit of wealth of Fame of status of um of praise
there's all this stuff that's kind of more surface stuff that belongs to the world of of
attachment of um clinging of
reactivity and uh and so to pay attention so for a Dharma teacher do not
teach the Dharma uh based on any of those things so it takes a lot of self-awareness for to teaching the
Dharma to make sure that they're just teaching freely coming from the Dharma place
not from the greed place not from the um conceited place not from the attachment
to self or the praise or status place and um and so um and so one of the
primary interpretations of this uh uh line uh I will not speak for material
reward is to not speak for uh for for monetary gain and it's interpreted to
mean that when they teach dhama should be taught freely without any expectation for anything in
return material things or monetary things just uh teach him because that's
what is inspired one is inspired to do and um and so
uh um this is a you know ancient principle from the time of the Buddha and one that
some people hold to very closely the monastic community often hold to this very closely and uh and here IMC we hold
to this that uh the people who teach here to teach freely um without
expectation of uh receiving anything in return and um I think it's a
beautiful uh way of teaching the Dharma it's a beautiful way of being in the world and so for those teachers here who
teach this way um it brings me a great joy to see them uh with this kind of General generosity and and um and uh
care and love and kindness that they which they teach so uh but for ourselves you know
outside of teaching um uh not to speak
for uh for material reward or physical reward or um now it's not nothing wrong
with acquiring uh enough uh monetary wealth to live
safely there's nothing wrong with having physical goods and things in order to
live well but uh uh we have to be very
careful that our interactions with others with our friends and our that we're not kind of subtly um or not so
subtly working the system trying to get something trying to have something have
an exchange if I give you uh apple pie then certainly next week you'll give me
uh a chocolate cake and uh kind of expectations for something in return
material in return however if I make you an apple pie and I just love making
apple pies and making and giving it to to others to share and um and my reward
is the Del light The Joy my my reward is the inner sense of happiness and
contentment and and maybe that the shared Joy the shared contentment that
uh we have with others and um and that nourishes something inside of me that
greed and expecting something in return does not nourish in fact it does the
opposite there's this deep feeling of natural goodness or Natural Health in
the heart and the spirit that um gets a little bit or very much squashed and
lost if um we get involved in um the the
whole Market of exchange and expectation and wanting something in back there's
nothing inherently wrong with exchange and wanting things back just that if we if we're caught in
it uh we're limiting uh something much more profound
that can happen so it's not judging something as being wrong so much as
being sure not to limit what's real the best for us and one of the important
roles that something like meditation has spiritual practice has is to connect us
to this deep natural goodness that's within deep natural wholesomeness that
is that kind of arise and be there that um
that the Buddha talks about the wholesome qualities that can grow and become abundant that they can suffuse us
and spread throughout us that this is possible the day and
night uh allowing wholesome qualities to grow and um as opposed to day and night
uh living in a world of that diminishes us or stresses us or brings tension in
us the world of anxiety and urgency and and um demands and expect ations and and
uh judgments and wanting things to be just right in control uh this is a world of stress
that's so easy to fall into and so spiritual practice can help us to relax
that to get out of the way to open up the space of the heart space of the Mind
awareness to allow things to settle that need to settle that can settle and allow
things to um emerge which can emerge
and um and so Dharma life is a life of
emergence not of reaction it's a life of the emergence
of something not the life of emergency and um so uh so for me what
I'm doing here today is tying this quality that of speaking not speaking
for material reward to the naturalistic orientation that I talked about last
week um that uh that I have a deep trust in this naturalistic processes of human
life that the Dharma is tapping into in fact sometimes the word Dharma is maybe
the one of the closest poly words to our English word nature and uh and so to uh trust the
Dharma is to trust our nature trust the naturalistic um uh functionings
activities of our inner life so um May
you know goodness or wholesomeness may you know good
qualities within that can emerge and be allowed to
spread and grow within you and and that you learn
to be careful and attentive and and uh alert to the ways in which reactivity
tensions uh sense of of urgency sense of anxiety covers over these good qualities
diminishes them and um because we have the
capacity to live an abundant sense of
wholesomeness and ideally we're not sacrificing that
capacity for anything at all let our goodness let our
wholesomeness be the source of our gift being a gift for this world of ours may
we all support and help this world with the
gifts we have not through the anxieties we carry so thank you very much