and welcome or good day and welcome to all of you and
uh it's a pleasure to sit here to be
prepared to do the offer this teaching so one of the common
associations with meditation or meditation with on breathing is that uh we're supposed to
be concentrated on the breath and uh stay kind of one-pointed just on the
breath and not uh get distracted not wander off from that and there is a
place for becoming deeply composed deeply centered on
breathing but that comes in its due time when we do mindfulness practice
mindfulness is first and foremost um knowing recognizing being
aware of what's happening and uh with a uh idea that
what's happening is a wide field that it's whatever that is
compelling whatever is obvious to us to know it in a in a qualitatively
different way than how we usually know things and one of those ways is um not
to be identified with the experience not to be defined by it not to have it
reflect back on us in some way that what we can and can't do or what we're good
at or not good at or successful at and not successful at and um and but to know it in a light
way a clear way a full way but without um um being attached to what we know
identified with what we know resistant to what we know so there's a kind of a
light touch to The Knowing but light doesn't mean removed it means just the
right way to recognize what's there without um becoming activated or or
reactive to what's happening and maybe the simplest way for
some of us to say that is to know without being identified with what we know to to know
without being bringing a lot of expectations and and
requirements uh in that knowing just to know so when we people think that the
point of meditation is to get concentrated on breath it's all too easy then that it gets complicated and uh
that uh there's identification with somehow or other I'm not good at it or I can't do it or I'm supposed to do it or
look at how great I am uh because I can can concentrate and so uh so that
concentration will come later but for now uh the um uh as we settle in and
that's an important quality we prepare ourselves we settle in at some point uh
one of the useful things to do when with around breathing is to become interested
in it to uh be interested in how to be
aware in a light way to how to be aware so that the being with the breath is
enjoyable without the pressure of it needing to be in any way or needing to
be concentrated or needing to breathe any particular way so so that's the
background for what we'll do today so to assume a meditation posture
that that's appropriate for you and as I like to say is a posture
which in in your way uh brings into a kind of balance the possibility of being
relaxed in the body but also Alert in the
body and depending on how you are on any given
day one of those two maybe gets emphasized more sometimes what gets
emphasized is relaxing if we're tense sometimes what gets emphasized is
alertness if we're sleepy or dull
or and then to lower the Gaze and maybe gently closing your eyes
and then with a an approach way that is somewhat gentle and kind and
curious gently take a few longer
breaths calm breaths long little bit longer than
usual inhale and a longer
exhale maybe slowing the breath down just enough so it still stays
comfortable just longer still
comfortable and as you
exhale allow your body to
relax the exhale is a kind of letting go releasing and let the body release with
the
exhale and perhaps the inhale is more the
alertness and the exhale is more of the relaxing and a gentle Rhythm between
those
two
e
and letting your breathing return to normal and on the exhale to scan through
your body to see what can be relaxed in your
body maybe on the
inhale feeling and knowing where you might be tense
tight but to know it lightly without identification or
reactivity know it very matter of factly on the
inhale and on the exhale to soften relax that part of your
your
body
breathing
normally and as you breathe without identification with
breathing or reactivity or as little as possible a light
touch not leaning into breathing
or expecting too much with breathing find where in your
body your experience of breathing is most
Pleasant where there might be a subtle
pleasure on the inhale or on the
exhale and maybe that pleasantness is a small piece of comfort in the
relaxation the release of the diaphragm the chest the belly as you exhale
maybe there's a welcoming feeling in breathing
in and that pleasure of breathing might be only in one little section of the
whole cycle of breath but where in your body body is
the experience of breathing most comforting or
Pleasant to know to be present
for it might be in the
belly in the chest
movements it might be and the sensations of the air going in and
out through the
nostrils it might be be the threedimensional expansion of the whole torso as you
breathe in and the coming back and Contracting
as you
exhale
and if there is some pleasure or pleasantness in the breathing the point is not to lean into
that or to hold on to it or expect
it the point is to know
it and if other parts of the breathing are
unpleasant not so comfortable that also is
okay the art of this is not to lean into that or react to that
or identify with that judge
it but with a light touch to know it
and in the Cycles so breathing in and breathing
out to let whatever experience of breathing there is Let It Come and Let
It
Go
okay and if your mind is distracted
and that's completely okay the function of mindfulness of
breathing is to help you see more easily that you're Swept Away in thought
caught in thought and know that with a light touch
we often are pulled in or lean into our
thoughts Let The Knowing of
thinking have a light touch and nonidentification
and then Begin Again with your breathing
where whatever is Pleasant or comfortable with
breathing is the welcoming of attention here feel
this let this be how to to ground yourself Center yourself on
breathing through the door of what is Pleasant in breathing in the
body
for
if you are involved in a lot of thinking if you're
distracted see if there's something in your mind and body
that you can relax soften distractability is connected to
tension that we
carry and maybe on the exhale relax and
soften that tension
for
and if you can as you feel the breathing feel the rhythm of the body
breathing in and breathing out how the sensations of your body
shift and
change the experience of breathing in is different than the experience of breathing
out
and as you feel that Rhythm feel the moment or
moments where some part of that experience of breathing is Pleasant
and let that pleasantness encourage you to stay there with the
breathing and either the experience of breathing or the idea of a pleasant
experience is a reference point to know that part of the breathing which is not
pleasant breathing might be tight or contracted or
forced and if any part of the breathing feels
uncomfortable let that be a prompt
to relax in your breathing some parts of your body can it
soften relax the diaphragm the
belly the
chest the arms the
hands
and with a light Touch without
identification feel the rhythm of breathing what your breathing is
like
maybe with the relaxing on the exhale letting go of thoughts as you
exhale
for
and then as we come to the end of this meditation to take a few moments to
check in with yourself here and now at this
moment how would you know yourself how would
you be aware of yourself as you are with a light
Touch without identifying with how you
are just knowing how you are your feelings your mood your body
feeling how you are are in your
mind knowing it lightly knowing it e
easily and easeful knowing of how you
are and then to prepare coming out of the meditation taking a few long slow deep
breaths so you feel your body more fully so you feel the connection of your
body against any surface your body is touching the
floor chair the
bed letting your breathing return turn to normal
and consider with your heart your mind The Wider Circles of people in your
life people in your neighborhood and in your
[Music] town in the places that you frequent
work and stores buses and Roads strangers and people you
know and to know all beings with a light
Touch without leaning in or leaning back or
resisting with a kind of ease of
knowing where there's room for Good
Will well
wishing and to consider at the end of every
meditation how the meditation supports
you to benefit the world that we live in May our meditation support
us to live with greater good will well-wishing for the people we
encounter may we be ready to wish them
well may they be
happy may they they be
safe may they be
peaceful and may they be
[Music]
free thank
you
so hello and welcome to this third talk on meditation that following these 30
minute guided meditations that are supporting what we're doing each
day and um so in a sense during these this in
this uh course that they're offering here of instructions in mindfulness
meditation uh we're slowly building putting down the foundations of the different elements that are useful to
take into account to be to be inclus included as we do mindfulness
practice and um it'll be 25 talks in the end so there'll be lots kind of go
deeper and deeper in a sense or with greater full applications in our life on
a path to Freedom path to Greater uh
goodwi and um and if uh all of it was kind of compressed into a 15minute talk
it would seem extremely complicated but I'm hoping that by stretching it out over 25 days that uh
it able to support you to stay very simple uh because uh Simplicity is one
of the Hallmarks of mindfulness practice uh even though there might be your life
and your life experience and how it's happening might a multifaceted the idea is to find a way
to stay simple and easeful as we know it as we show up and a present for our
experience and one of the ways of appreciating this Simplicity is to recognize that um maybe
it's a little bit um for the purposes of teaching to make this next point
but the point is that there's always only two things happening there is what is happening and
how we're aware of it the knowing of it so what we're aware
of could be many many varied things of course but how we know of it everything
is known through the lens of knowing everything is known by through seeing
hearing touching thinking about taking it in
somehow uh we passes through the lens of
recognition of awareness and then once it we recognize it or know something then it might get
complicated again uh with the uh memories and thoughts and values and
expectations desires fears uh all kinds of things might happen but there's a imagine that
there's a it's kind of like an hourglass where the sand goes through this narrow neck and um and uh all if
it's very very narrow that neck everything every particle of sand can be
seen as it goes through and um and uh but if there was no narrowing
of the glass you would just all the glass all the sand would just fall very quickly and and you wouldn't see what's
going on maybe it's a little bit unfortunate metaphor this idea of narrowing and
tightening up but the idea is that everything in our experience does go
through a uh a little uh kind of a a
simp simple area of just being known in the most simple possible
way beforehand the world out there might be quite Broad and
multifaceted after we know it um it gets picked up by the mind and memory and
desires and Fantasies and projections come into play but in between there's
this a wonderful door this wonderful doorway of simple
knowing and uh and that's where the domain of mindfulness is whether we know
what's in the world or we know what's going on within us the idea is to have
these two these two areas we know something and how we know it is
important and the how uh is a big part of what we're
exploring here so uh uh it's we don't just
know uh it's kind of unconsciously or just know matter of factly because if we
don't pay attention to how we know how we're aware how we're
attentive um we bring along it's all too easy to bring along a lot of our uh
attitudes a lot of our emotions our desires our agendas our fears and it
kind of colors the way that we know and um and that's okay we don't
have to be troubled by anything when we do mindfulness that's the kind of the
Simplicity of it the idea is to know that too to know that to oh that's how
it is that's how I'm knowing I'm when I know I identify I identify with the
breathing with what's happening when I know something I immediately measure it
or judge it or evaluate it in relationship to me myself as a doer
myself as a victim myself as a consumer myself as as um as
a um you know trying to get something or prove myself it's all kinds of oh that's
how it is that's how it is so when we sit down to meditate with
mindfulness uh the idea is to keep it very simple and not complicated
immediately with ideas of getting concentrated because then the knowing is already biased in a certain way there's
a leaning in and identification and looking for the concentration um it's uh and even the
idea that they're supposed to be continuously Weare uh and not be distracted can be another little kind of
uh cloudiness or agitation for the knowing the idea is to step back relax
enough and then just be content just to know what you can know the breathing is a anchor or the
breathing is a always there breathing is always in the present
moment breathing always occurs now so to keep an eye out for the
breathing not so that you get focused on the breathing but that's that reference point for the present every time you
come back to the breathing and be with it it might help you to see more clearly
how you are that you're distracted you're irritated you're you're sad
you're happy you're relaxed you're tense and that's part of the function of all
this to see that none of it is wrong for the purpose of
meditation in ordinary life we come with all these attitudes about what we know
so if we're happy we're we feel like maybe proud or or hopeful we add we add
those things to it if we feel kind of lousy don't feel good or tense we feel
like Oh I'm a failure I'm wrong or embarrassed or you know something
and so to keep it really simple and this is why for some people find mindfulness
meditation to be extremely forgiving or accepting or uh like they have there's breathing
room to be who you are no matter how you are there's breathing room for it and
part of that breathing room that spaciousness is how we know it oh this is how it is and when you know this is
how it is now you are being Mindful and um in the Paradox is that if
you're distracted and you know you're distracted you're no longer distracted
even if the thoughts of distractions are still going um if you are caught up in some
emotion and you know that you're caught up then you're not no longer quite
caught up anymore part of you might be
so so to feel to notice how you are and in the guided meditation I we just did
um we took another step with the breathing not just using the breathing as a reference point for distractability
or where the where we can to learn where we can relax more but also we can use um
and search for where the breathing is pleasant and it took me a long time in
meditation to learn that I that was fine it was okay it was actually supportive
of meditation to find where find the where where
meditation was pleasant and enjoyable and let that be a support for staying
present not being attached to it or prioritizing it too much but just look
where where is it so where is breathing Pleasant it might be just a moment at the end of the out breath or part of the
end of the out breath is Letting Go and relaxing some people that's not pleasant
it might be the beginning of the INB breath or the smooth feeling of expansion with the in with the in breath
it might be the somehow the sensations of the air going in and out through the nostrils it's got a nice tingling and
and U sharpness to it there might be a softness in the belly uh at some point as the belly
relaxes with the breath it might be possible to slightly
adjust this Rhythm the speed the depth of breathing make it a little more
shallow a little deeper a longer a little shorter so that it just so it's still normal in a sense but so that it's
a little bit more pleasant how you're breathing and the value of touching into
the pleasantness of breathing again is not to feel more pleasure but rather
that also is a reference point to see better how where the tensions are where
the challenges are where the discomforts are so that you might be able to relax
further soften the body soften the mind so you might be able to know
it with this Simplicity of knowing oh I'm feeling sad look at
that but the knowing of sadness is not sad look at that I'm
irritated I'm afraid I'm
agitated but and the knowing of those things is not defined by the sadness the
irritation the agitation it's just knowing so I believe that this is a lot
of words that I've said a lot of ideas and so it can lend itself to maybe now
becoming complicated trying to remember what I said and um but I'm hoping that uh you
will somehow take it in um with this message that keep it
simple and let the breathing support you to be very simple with to recognize how
you are what's happening with you because that is the that's the
compost that's the material that's the the basis for greater Clarity of
awareness is actually how you are not to bypass how you are but to recognize how
you are and how you know is really the
one of the central things we're doing here it's half the picture there's what's what you know and how you know
it so uh as you go about your day today you might see if as you go through
different activities whatever you're doing check in with your yourself periodic quick L and ask yourself how is
it I know my environment how is it I'm taking
it in how am I relating to it how is it being known is it being known through the
filter of emotions and agendas and beliefs is it being known
simply what would it mean to know simply right now without all the baggage I
carry with me just to know that would be I think a wonderful
exercise and I would love to hear from all of you actually uh what you learn
from that I know that's not possible so um thank you very much for
today and I look forward to continuing
tomorrow