so uh so welcome folks nice to uh see the names in the
chat um my uh my lighting situation is
different I uh
[Music] H okay I'm seeing some
chat oh
okay um what did I want to uh thank uh Rosie for sending this light
to me no overhead lighting can see my face more clearly which may be good or not good
um but uh we're here to practice and um I'm happy to be together and uh uh
very as always significant uh love and loss in the chat there so uh let us let
us practice together e
to fully contact our heart we often uh need to relax
if you're sleepy if it's late can still actually
relax but counterbalancing the relaxation with a certain kind of
uh if you're sitting expression of your spine reaching upwards Towards the Sky
maybe you take some Fuller
breaths just kind of filling out your body with your
breath e
and we breathe and relax so that we might become
more sensitive to to
love kind of love that uh spreads
the more settled and still we become the
easier the awareness takes the Hue of Love
kindness for
no contracts with the moment
just offering your heart mind up to it
the posture of our heart is one where no matter what comes its
way pleasure or
pain we trust that it will become love
can you put your heart in that posture
just breathing Into Your Heart
Center kind of deep willingness
to feel our life as it's constellating in this moment it's uh joy and
sorrow
e
e e
we sense the the the pains in our life the nuts
in our heart
and uh just practice bathing
them and Care
kindness sometimes harder to believe from the inside
but you're no different than any other
person and pain is uh worthy of
care
kindness
e e
maybe there's a an image or word a phrase that kind of catches
the thread of your
breathing just letting your heart
soften be softened by
life e
it's almost like our breathing refines out some of
the holding and pushing so that love catches the thread
of our
breath maybe starts to feel natural to in tone
the
words i' be well
may my uh heart be as wide as the
world may I take
refuge in love
just abiding in
care
e e
the attention wanders meanders away from this theme of love uh just uh
forgive forgive
yourself just reestablish yourself
in this
abiding like all the cells of your body become
uh animated by non
violence the heart becomes aligned
because it has no faith in hate or apathy we
go maybe just for this minute we go all
in on
love don't worry about the details of
life right now just now it's okay in
fact very good to go all
in love kindness
compassion
e
e e
even though we know can never
be still makes a lot of sense to affirm the wish
may all beings be
well may all beings be safe and
protected may all beings know
peace
e
e e
okay
so so I have um a lot of uh very reasonable
thoughts and a lot of kind of dumb thoughts uh but uh my dumb thoughts
generally don't get me into trouble anymore
and it's not that I sort of like listen to my reasonable thoughts and ignore my
dumb thoughts it's it's more the sense is like that I I no longer ask my thoughts
to do things for my life that thoughts can't
do and we ask um you know we ask our our
our thoughts to do so much when you get down to it it's like okay how do they
function in our life and in a lot of of beautiful ways
but but we ask them to do too much we ask thoughts to really game out and
protect us from uncertainty to digest uh emotionally painful
experience to make us feel good about ourselves to provide [Music]
meaning and a question arose in a recent um s meeting that like
um uh the the woman uh asked Sarah asked
uh what's the difference between reflection and
rumination and on the one hand um
we can say just you know conceptual understandings of the Dharma are
not themselves liberating but there is a vital place
for contemplation and reflection on the Dharma path and we're instructed you know often
often to hold the teachings in mind hold the teachings in mind to investigate and
reflect to recall the the Buddha the beautiful qualities of the
Buddha uh to recall our potential for awakening to recall the kind of karmic
reverberations of causing harm we're asked to reflect on all of
this thinking but rumination gives thinking a
bad name and rumination maybe we say is a
particular uh spe species of thinking that tries to accomplish what with words
what can only be accomplished with action wisdom letting
go so rumination defined uh kind of you know in clinical world is something like
repetitive prolonged negative very loopy
thinking about one's self feelings one's current concerns
ones uh often you know upsetting experiences
memory and rumination is a little like uh looking the ruminative mind is
looking for the last missing puzzle
piece except you're playing chess
you and sometimes rumination masquerades as kind of existential
seeking you know they sound like ruminative questions sometimes sound like Dharma
questions but they're not and they're it's known to kind of
have uh some you know compound suffering magnifying and prolonging negative moods
interfering with problem solving making people typically less effective in
action and um and reducing sensitivity to like
changing conditions and the context and how to adjust you know and so rumination
is often often when we look at it it's sort of trying to use
thoughts to make things go away often refuses the truth of duka you
know that there is suffering and the ruminative mind is sort of obsessively
looking for some Duca free pathway forward and that just does
not it doesn't exist right we will not we will not the ruminative mind is
essentially trying to like outs smart the first Noble truth but it just keeps spinning cuz
intuitively we know can't outsmart this we keep
thinking rumination um fails to learn from regret and past
disappointment so it might it might our mind might be going over and over the past again but it's not actually
extracting actual wisdom and there's a sense in me that
until we've extracted the wisdom from the pain of the past our mind just will
not put it down it will not put it down rumination often a kind of
rationalization of inaction it feels like our thinking we feel so busy
thinking so you know kind of hermetically sealed off in the world of thought and the
thought is intense and busy it feels like we're doing something it feels like we're getting somewhere and we're just
spinning we're not actually in not the ruminative mode facing our problems
headon but in fact often avoiding avoiding feeling what needs to
be felt maybe some uh disappoint ointment of how
something unfolded or regret for the ways our own pain overflowed from our
own heart spilled into the lives of others maybe it's uh rumination is kind
of like the way we avoid opening to the ambivalent that runs
through the center of the world maybe our ego has been titilated
in some way and we're trying to like Smooth the story of
self with more words to kind of like treat the wound of
self with words in other words uh romanation
really trying to solve what is at base an emotional puzzle
with thought and the word means chewing you
know trying to like digest suffering with our
thoughts but um but as I said thoughts do not function well as digestive
enzymes uh language language is so um it's powerful and it's like limited
uh language is um it's kind of possessive and
domineering language itself words thinking this is Maggie Maggie
Nelson uh she writes um afraid of assertion always trying to get out of
totalizing language language that rides Ruff shad
over specificity realizing this is another form of
paranoia literary CR critic uh Bart uh found the exit to this merry girl round
by reminding himself that quote it is language which it is assertive not
he it's absurd he says to try to flee from language's assertive Nature Nature
by adding to each sentence some little phrase of
uncertainty as if anything that came out of language could make language
tremble our stories don't tremble they
assert and so what what are we to do as practitioners what are we to do
um well first uh Dharma Dharma practice is about perceiving the
imperfection of thought we we it's it's really Vivid on retreat but
we can see it elsewhere we perceive the kind of building up the the construction
the fabrication of uh this kind of world of thought that we temporarily
inhabit that we we often can't see Beyond the Horizon of that
land and then because we're paying attention we like see that world
collapse and when we see that enough with enough
vividness we do not for get the emptiness of
thought we might have to see it a million
times but then we become like just slightly estranged from all
words we digest Feeling by feeling that's what it is to be
mindful of feeling is to feel and this is really
equinity the the development of uh this kind of supple relationship with
emotionally charged Body Sensations and my sense is that um we we
must be willing to actually um to feel our way through something if
we're to extract wisdom from pain
rumination thrives on uh on avoidance
and mindfulness is um it's an approach the orientation is one of approach
gently in our own time with a lot of support behind us you
know but an approach
sometimes that support is love or
s or faith but we in our own time
approach sometimes the antidote to rumination is just like because it's
such quick sand that to even direct attention to it to try to be mindful of
it to try to let go of that to try to to work with it in any way is it's like a
kind of gravitational force field that just keeps pulling us under and so we do something else we do
something else maybe move our
body uh one of my teachers shinzen young said sometimes equinity is expressed um
not by being with something but by being able to put it down being able to put
something down that's a a different species of equinity but uh when we allow something
to become distant background that's not avoiding it's a kind of species of
equinity and sometimes um to break the inertia of the mind we we just must act
we do something anything that moves against the quicksand
uh and um maybe lastly I should note like
um spiritual friendship you know this is uh the ruminative
mind um often needs ACC company the stability
of another stability of their heart so reflection rumination
offer this for your uh
consideration okay so
um yeah I appreciate being with you thinking of uh you
Ela the chat and um I'll
be doing uh gills morning thing 700 a.m. next week
so um so I'll you know those five days I'll do something and I think something
kind of like Dara and interpersonal life you know that kind of uh D relational
Dharma and um I'll be back next week at this time certain Wednesdays it is a certain Wednesday next week the uh
11th and um I uh send you all uh warm warm wishes
okay