hello everyone and welcome to this meditation
session and um for this morning I'd like
to um say something about the importance of
safety that uh when
our psychophysical system our body and mind
really feels safe something settles
deeply something relaxes in the body the heart the mind that
supports the deepening of the Dharma life deepening of
meditation and for many people a fair amount
of feeling not safe feeling anxious or afraid
it doesn't have to do with here and now sometimes with anxiety it has to do
with predictions or assumptions or imaginations of the
future and sometimes it's a deep conditioning from things that have
happened in the past which are no longer happening now and these forms of not feeling safe
or feeling afraid need our care need our love need our
attention for sure and at the same time it's uh we can also remind
ourselves that there is safety here and now that hopefully when you sit down to
meditate you're sitting at at a time in a place in a situation
where it's relatively safe
and that that for now for here and now it's
possible to remind yourself of that safety that it's a offering that you
make to yourself give yourself not to dismiss the fears and anxieties not
to um but to put them in
context to allow settling and a peacefulness that maybe can
hold anxieties with a generosity a care a
love where we're not so caught in them we're not so under their
influence but rather our fears and anxieties come come under the
influence of our ability to offer safety care
love where we're independent of them the influences and direction of us to them
not our anxieties to us so as we sit this
today um to the degree to which here and now
in the room the place you're sitting at this particular time not in an hour hour not later in
the day but here and now there is a degree of safety or
Tranquility or peace
here around you in
you not to override the fear as I said but in addition to it so we're not so
caught in the fear we hold it in The Wider context
and this is one of the gifts of meditation and the deeper the meditation
goes the more maybe indirectly without it being an
intention we are creating the conditions within of deeper and deeper feelings of
peace and safety so something deeper and deeper can let go and relax and open up
so like we did yesterday I'll let this meditation be mostly
silent so that uh you can maybe remind
yourself to the degree of the safety that's here and
now and um and if there's not then
maybe call on your love and compassion for that your
care so when your this meditation when you find yourself drifting off in thought wandering away from the present
moment wandering away from the breath it might very well be an
opportune time to gently remind yourself of the safety
that's is here maybe saying the word gently to
yourself safe safe and then return here and now to the
breathing to the present moment and the value of this is often
what takes us away from the present moment might be some kind of anxiety or
fears something like not feeling safe and if something else takes us away
from the present moment it still might be settling easier to
come
back if you say the word safe reminding yourself of that so we'll
sit silently today
again
e
for
e e
if you are distracted if you're flowing along with your
thoughts consider where whether or not you're
better off returning to whatever degree of safety and
peace There Is Here and Now whatever degree you find it in your
body in your heart your mind or in the location you're
sitting here and now helping you to stay
stay here and now flowing in the present
moment instead of flowing in your thought with your
thoughts
e
e e
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to recognize or feel any degree of calm or peace or
safety that's currently available for
you maybe somewhere in the body the heart the
mind maybe if you gently say the word safe something in you resonates smiles
recognizes
it our body and mind benefits from
bathing in the sense of safety that we can
provide here and now that we can touch into here and
now and then imagine now bringing
safety peace to others the gift of
safety so that people feel safe when they're with us
they don't feel any assertion from us any demands they don't feel a need to take
care of us or worry about us
or protect themselves from us very simple gift of safety
that comes from being peaceful at ease settled in
ourselves may it be that we go through the
day creating safety offering safety to this
world where so many people feel UNS safe may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and to the degree that we know something about these four states
may we create the conditions for others to have the
[Music]
same thank you e
so hello and welcome to this third of five talks
um uh focusing on the poems of the
earliest female Disciples of the Buddha the ones that became fully awakened the
early nuns and yesterday um the poem that I
read had uh involved a conversation between kisag goami and
pachara and pachara the a pachara the venerable pachara
uh was probably one of the most important uh women teachers and in the
time of the Buddha there's more references to her being a teacher especially to other nuns other women
than there is U to any other woman at the time of the Buddha these early texts and so there's in in these poems
there's a number of poems that refer to her including one which is her own poem
which is her Enlightenment poem and um it um and so I'd like to read
that and describes um and you know uh yesterday I told her a little bit of her
about her story uh where she had um phenomenal degrees of suffering with the
death of her whole family in the course of one day or learning about it over the course of one day and two young child
children her husband her parents her brother and um
and so um so she became a
nun but maybe it wasn't so easy for her even as such she practiced diligently
and so this is her story that she tells in a
poem and she's um talking about herself this is what she was
thinking young men gain wealth by plowing
Fields sewing seeds in the ground caring for children and
wife but why is it that I thorough in virtuous
conduct doing the Buddha's instruction not lazy or
proud have not attained release have not attained
neana with feet washed I wa W I watched the water the
foot washing water flowing from High Ground to low so she's sitting outside
and she's doing what is as common in the ancient world as
um as maybe for hopefully for us is for washing our hands through the day and um
people walked around Barefoot so they were cleaning their feet off and with feet washed I watched the water
the foot washing water flowing from High Ground to
low with this the Mind concentrated and like a thoroughbred
horse with this the Mind concentrated like a thoroughbred horse taking an oil lamp I entered my
Hut looking over the bed I sat down on the bed taking a
needle I pulled out the wick as the flame went
out the mind was freed so this is a story of a person who
practiced diligently sincerely but perhaps there was a way in
which he was a little bit more uh trying too
hard um and uh maybe too diligent and so
sitting down to wash her feet uh and then watching the she probably poured the water out or poured it over her feet
and then watching the water flowing down the hill uh uh she became concentrated
she kind of lost her self-consciousness it was something about the movement of the water flowing that pulled her into
the world of the water flowing like being absorbed and watching the water flow in a river going by and so doing
something completely unselfconscious it a simple ordinary thing putting down the
effort to practice um almost like because she would had this momentum maybe of a strong mind strong practice
mind um when she put something to rest and just got absorbed in the water
flowing down her mind became concentrated and uh and then she entered
into her Hut there was no windows back then so the Huts maybe it was evening and the Hut was particularly dark and um
and this kind of Simplicity the radical Simplicity of just looking at her
bed people who get concentrated look they they can see things and everything stands out sharply clearly for itself
there's um you know you see a flower wow just a flower you see an ordinary device
the cup you drink water out of it's just like ju just that the
pristine Perfection of a cup or a flower or or um anything at all and when you're
concentrated you kind of see in a different way and here is you just seeing something ordinary her
bed um and then she sat down on that bed and because it was dark she had an oil
lamp and the oil lamp is a you know it's oil and it has a little Wick that's coming out of the out of the oil and in
order to turn off the light she didn't flick a switch she pulls the wick out of
the oil and um and then the flame went out and in a concentrated mine she was
just right there for the flame just like she had been for the bed and and um
maybe the whole world was just that flame that light and something about when the light went
out something in her mind let go and she was
freed um some kind of peaceful focus on something like a flame maybe as the flame went out even
that Focus kind of evaporated or dissolved and there was a deeper letting go and then she was free
so uh that's pachara story and uh and I love that it has to do with these very
ordinary moments that we're liberating and there's a long history in Buddhism of recognizing that um Liberation
doesn't necessarily happen as we're practicing but as we practice we're
creating the conditions the concentration the Stillness the peace the sense of
safety that uh when we're least expecting it
um there is something can let go deeply we're right here and we let go so that's
pachara story and uh and then there's a two poems or maybe more where she um is the
teacher for a woman or for a nun and
um and uh she kind of refers back to this her first poem the the the way she
is thinking and and uh little experience of washing the feet and um and this
makes sense uh teachers often will teach from their own experience from how they
were thinking about things and then they're that worked for them and they're kind of offering that to others and so
she starts by um referring back to her own reflection about a young man young
men who work hard and can then support their family um as a as a represent
sense or's a metaphor for um for a practitioner can also engage fully and
and hard in order to uh become free so she writes or she she
says um uh and this is this poem is supposed to be that she's teaching to 30
nuns and um and uh or the word is 30
some approximately 30 uh nuns she says
taking a pistol young men P pound
grain so caring for their children and
wife they gain wealth young men gain
wealth do what the Buddha teaches having done it you won't regret
it quick wash your feet sit to one
side and settle on a tranquil
mind do what the Buddha teaches and then as a narrator for the
rest of uh the next two verses narrator says hearing these words of pacha's
teaching the nuns washed their feet sat to one
side settled on a tranquil mind they did
what the Buddha teaches during the first watch of the night they recollected their past lives
during the middle watch of the night they purified the Divine eye during the last watch of the night they shattered
the mass of darkness and then the 30 nuns said
to pachara um well narrator goes on
standing up the 309s bowed down to her feet and
said we have accomplished your instruction we will live honoring you as
the 30 gods honor the great God Indra who is unconquered in
battle free of taints we have the three
knowledges so the simple poem where the pachara encourages them to practice they
do and and not only do they attain Liberation but this is a remarkable
thing about these poems the confidence the clarity the possibility that uh of
uh of spiritual maturation that uh is championed here they attain the same
level of Liberation as the Buddha these three watch of the night the first two
watches are something something that Buddha is supposed to have attained the night of his
Awakening the recollection of past lives uh the Divine eye which is seeing how
people are born and die according to their karma and uh and then um the um um the
the here is the shattering the mass of Darkness Liberation and uh and uh the first two
watches that those are not required to be awake to be liberated but to be a
Buddha fully full potential like a Buddha this is what one attains and the
three knowledges they're called and um and so here they the this is also
possible and the women are pointing this out they too have
this and um so then uh there's one more that pachara teaching to a woman
named utara taking a pestel young men pound grain caring for children and wives they
gain wealth apply yourself to what the Buddha teaches you will have no regrets quick
wash your feet and sit to one side having established the Mind unified
and well settled consider mental constructs as not self as something other
than self then utara says I heard her words
pacha's advice I washed my feet and sat to the side during the first watch of
the night I recollected my past lives during the middle watch of the night I purified the Divine eye during the last
watch of the night I shattered the mass of Darkness I then emerged owed with the
three knowledges then addressing
pachara I have accomplished what you instructed I will live honoring
you free of taints I have the three knowledges so I love these two these
poems that patara becoming awake and then her teaching the other nuns and then uh in
their appreciation of what they were taught that uh they will honor her they
rever her respect her for her gift and um and so here we get a sense
of uh of um at least for you know of ancient nuns we get a sense of one of
the most important teachers of the time of the Buddha and um how she was engaged
and engaged with teaching it's one thing to say in in Buddhist Traditions that a woman could
be enlightened it turns out it's another thing to say that it's okay for them to be a teacher and there are traditions
where they say women can be enlightened but there's still a kind of a discrimination against women uh than
stepping up into the teacher role and here we have these wonderful stories of uh of not only a none a woman
who is a teacher but an Effective Teacher a teacher that can uh guide
people support people to their own Awakening so um
pachara so thank you thank all of you thank pachara thank all the lineage of nuns
and women teachers down Through the Ages who um upon whose shoulders we stand as
well so thank you very much