so hello and welcome and uh to our Friday
meditation and uh we'll follow this with uh the short Dharma talk and then a
community meeting for those of you who would like to be part of it and we'll switch over to
zoom and uh the zoom uh link will be posted here at some point maybe at the
end at 7:45 I'll make sure it gets posted so you can uh get over there and
um I'll say more about it later but
welcome and uh one of the very rich and
important uh kind of interactions or richness of
the P practice is the uh mutuality the
association the inseparability of the experience we
have and the knowing of the experience and uh and or the seeing of
the experience and these two don't really exist so
separate and together uh see seeing them
working together is one means to become free from it all not get entangled not
get reactive to what's being experienced to what's being
known sometimes we emphasize knowing seeing sometimes we emphasize
experiencing sensing feeling the What's Happening Here and Now and so for this meditation you might
want to consider that the purpose of knowing
is to help us experience more clearly to feel what's happening more
clearly and the purpose of experiencing something clearly is to know it better
until at some point these two don't really become two different things uh it becomes very very
simple and you can almost hyphenate knowing experiencing or
experiencing knowing and um but but the important
point is that uh we're here to really be present in our present moment
experience and one of the ways to become wise in meditation is to become wise
about how we get separated from present moment experience either because we get
distracted caught up in thoughts or because we're making commentary and
stories around what's happening and excessive thinking about what's happening is a pulling away a
separation sometimes so much so that we lose touch with what's happening because the stories or judgments we make about
about it so
um purpose of experiencing in the present moment is to know the purpose to
know what's happening at present moment is to experience it and perhaps in some
relaxed easy way way this will help you stay present today it just kind of kind
of flow back and forth between experiencing what's here and now and in
the simplest way doesn't have to be 100% accurate um knowing what's Happening
Here and Now and just kind of flow back and forth stay there maybe in the gentle
relaxing Rhythm so assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing your eyes and with your eyes
closed in your meditation posture globally experience what it's
like to be in this body in this posture globally recognize how it
is and in knowing allow yourself to experience what is
knowing more fully experience it through the
body almost like you're letting the body have its own experience of
itself and then to
know see that experience where the
knowing is not entangled is not reactive The Knowing is has a radical
Simplicity to it almost as if the knowing
itself is free of what it knows
some people like the idea of it's like looking in a mirror and you know what's in the
mirror but the image of the mirror is not something that
you do anything more than to
know and then within the experience of the body
there's the experience of breathing and to experience the body how
the body experiences breathing feel and sense the body
breathing how breathing in is experienced differently than breathing out
sometimes that experience of the body experience of breathing comes along
with experiencing how we are more broadly
emotionally and that's fine let let the breathing let the body hold it
all breathe with it all let the breathing be part of the broader
experience of being alive
and then as you feel and sense the body your being
breathe know the breathing know it
simply lightly almost as if every moment of
knowing evaporates
as the knowing is
complete knowing and experiencing
seeing and feeling both part of present moment
experience trust the
knowing trust the experiencing you don't have to trust the
experience or what you know but you can trust the act of
experiencing the act of knowing when it's
simple nonreactive non-entangled
in the flow of Here and
Now
e
for
e for
for for
for
e
e e
sometimes experience IND directly is the way to be in the
present it's an anchor provide stability here now
sometimes knowing the experience is what is the anchor to Here
and
Now
e
for
for e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting one way of having a sense of or to feel or
to be inspired around the possibility of
Freedom through this
practice is to let your eyes whether they're closed or
open have a soft gaze where the eyes eyeballs kind of
float in the eye sockets not staring at anything fixated on
anything gently
floating
gently moving floating this way and
that just loose and Light
a gaze that is free of fear free of
Desire free of confusion just gently looking kind of like maybe just
looking at a mountain far in the distance appreciating it but not staring
and maybe gently kind of the eyes roam over the edges of the mountain the
details or looking at a tree gently swaying in the wind and the
eyes are relaxed and it is soft sometimes this kind of looking is
very relaxing for the whole body for the
mind that's why looking at the waves on the beach or the water flowing in a
river or even sometimes sitting around a campfire watching the
fire and imagine that you go into your life your
day to be with the things of the day the people of the
day with this kind of seeing with a soft gaze relaxed gaze
maybe a sparkling gaze just from the Delight of being at ease and
relaxed it just feels good to see the others to see the world this
way and if the Gaze is not relaxed soft floating in the eye
sockets why is that what have you been caught by what emotions what concerns
what attitudes desires have kicked
in that fixates the eyes so you stare at what's happening
and imagine that you can come back to a soft relaxed
gaze that gaze which represents not being caught by what's
happening but present to see
it and in this way we are we allowing others to be
free of how we do get caught how we react and it's a gift to
others maybe it supports them to relax and be at ease as
well may it be that this practice we do helps set others at ease helps others
feel safe helps others
feel seen without imposed on May it give people space and room to
be who they are free of our expectations and
needs may this practice that we do help us to help others in this
difficult world may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone and welcome to this last talk on the five qualities of the
Dharma and uh one of the things that Delights me is how I think
each day as I think about teaching about one of the
qualities it becomes my favorite of the qualities and um and so today the
quality of the Dharma is that it's characteristic of the Dharma the teachings of the Buddha is that they are
to be personally experienced by the wise now these five characteristics
reinforce themselves overlap May sometimes saying almost the same thing
and I like this because it's really emphasizing that this is something to be
personally experienced um the Buddha is only pointing to
something and that we have to see no experience for ourselves and there and that what we
pointing to is uh visible Here and Now something to
be seen and uh which is again we see in the present moment it's immediate it's it's
that kind of relationship to the present moment it's it's immediately here and it's
um uh it's invite the teachings are inviting us to take a good look for
ourselves because it is something to know for ourselves come and look come and see it's uh onward leading there's
something about the way that uh the teachings the practice the seeing that
we do uh doesn't it's not static doesn't leave us unchanged it set in motion a
maturation a movement an opening a healing growing and different times different
ones of those words relevant to be personally experienced by the wise and I kind of find find
delightful it's that it says to be experienced by the wise because uh
this is uh directed to all of us to all of you that you're being related to as a
wise person and um respected for that and um and I think that uh part of
that wisdom is that uh you are having the wisdom to understand that this is
something for you to go through yourself something for you to discover for
yourself and to know for yourself to be rooted in for yourself to no one else
can um can uh free you except for your
own practice and your own experience and that that's where the most profound and important freedom is found is here in
our own experience that we have to be present for and
um and so uh along that way there's a lot of small freedoms that that that we
discover and this freedom of staying close to our experience staying close to
what we can directly know frees us from all the fantasies all the memories all
the associations all the fears all the projections into the future ideas we
have that it very easily take us away into an abstract World help us to
separate and disconnect from something and the more disconnected we are from our direct experience the less our
direct experience of being a human being the direct feeling sensing seeing knowing can uh has room to unfold to
grow plus it has space to expand so uh we start becoming Freer of
all those abstractions Freer from all those being caught in thoughts and ideas
and memories and Fantasies and that's a phenomenal freedom on the way to full
Freedom so uh to be personally experienced by the wise and um the um the word for
experience uh in ply can also mean to know it could also mean to feel or to
sense and these different while we have different words in English that can be
know feel experience sense um there's no sharp strong separation of
that uh as the practice goes deeper and deeper as the mind gets more concentrated and still and more fully in
the moment here with the experience it's a begins to become a rich and very simple world where knowing and
experience is not that separate knowing and sensing is not so separate and uh
and and and freedom and knowing the Freedom
sensing and knowing Freedom sensing start becoming intimately Associated
intimately part of the same thing so these five qualities of the
Dharma the five qualities of the teaching when Dharma means teaching so
it's a litmus test for if you hear Dharma teachings that uh are these the
teachings of the Buddha the essential teachings of the Dharma are they something you for you to see yourself
are they something that's visible Here and Now is it immediate something you can experience right here so and right
now right immediate and is it something that uh is inviting you to take a look
for yourself or is Teachers kind of imposing their beliefs on you and um and is it onward leading does
it lead to something useful does it lead to what's wholesome does it lead to what's beneficial for you does a lead to
Freedom so that's when Dharma means teaching sometimes Dharma also means the
the natural law or the natural processes that get set in motion as we practice
mindfulness as we do this meditation practice as we kind of engage in Buddhist practice and um and there also
uh we're starting to notice what's happening within us and uh how is this unfolding thing and what do we it's
right here in our experience that we discover the Dharma here that the Dharma
unfolds in our experience our felt experience our knowing our sensing are
really staying present here so one of the great gifts that this
mindfulness practice has brought me and I think other people as well is a
phenomenal Trust the great trust in the efficacy the value The Joy the the
richness of uh the mindfulness practice itself uh that I trust deeply being
mindful I trust deeply knowing what's happening in the experience I trust deeply
experiencing what what's I'm experiencing and um so the is here is
not the experience itself the event itself that's happening but rather
whether it's in myself or in the world but rather that I not necessarily trust
what I trust is uh bringing a clear attention to that to know it clearly to
feel it to sense it to be mindful of it that uh that I trust and so many
situations in my my life I have not known what to do and I've been confused
even by it sometimes but I've learned that I don't have to know what to do I
just have to show up I have to be present and see and sometimes in a complicated social situation it can be
helpful in a wise way careful way to name out loud um the what we're
experiencing what what what we're knowing kind of mindfulness out loud and
hopefully we've learned how not to uh how to make keep it really simple
and just the events without any judgments or criticism or um or
something that's more than just kind of the Simplicity of the moment but to name it and I've been in Social situation
which You're simply naming wow uh you know this is a tense uh conversation
we're having or uh this is um I'm feeling uncomfortable that that that
begins to shift the Dynamics and other people then shift and change and we're not locked into the conflict or the
tension that we have so this the point being trusting
not the experience but trusting the mindfulness of it the knowing of it the
clear present moment knowing it allows something different to unfold and when I
haven't known what to do I the situation unfolds and almost inevitably uh the
things move in a Direction that's beneficial and eventually sometimes have um have um revealed what is to be
known so I hope that these um five qualities characteristics of the Dharma
have been inspiring for you interesting for you useful for you and now in a few
minutes uh we will have a a community meeting for this 7 a.m. YouTube
community and so if you're able to go to it um uh we'll meet in a couple of minutes
on YouTube and um on on zoom and the
zoom link is when I get down from here I I'll post it on the chat but also um uh
it's on the IMC website um in um on the homepage under
the bottom right there's a box called what's new and there there's a listing for it it should also be in the IMC
calendar and um and hopefully you'll find it and you're also welcome to just stay on zoom on on YouTube uh I'll keep
this uh channel YouTube uh uh videoing uh live and so you'll certainly be able
to hear me and and uh some of the questions and and you won't be able to
see people so um if that works better for you so thank you very much and uh
I'll be back here in about a minute or so after I post the the
um the zoom
link
e
for for
is
okay let's see can you hear me on uh on Zoom fantastic and I trust that those of
you who might have stayed on YouTube can hear me as well and um so this is very
nice to be together and it's been a long time since we've done one of these oh wait a minute I think that uh I should
be on a different oh what happened somehow the mic the audio went
off but also I should be on a different um
oh let me see wait one moment while I adjust the
okay
okay there I think face
so I think that
um I see what's Happ happening okay so I think that now I'm on the camera on the
wall so I can look at you more directly rather than looking down at
my so has to be on so I think that
technology is now set up can you hear me okay again
wonderful and uh so um so
hello and uh so it's been a while since we've had one
of these meetings and maybe some of you have questions you'd like to ask there's a lot of you that are here and uh maybe
we could do a few minutes of questions it helps me warm up a little bit um not quite sure what to
say and uh and then uh maybe we'll do a little uh breakout group so you can meet
each other a little bit and have a little discussion and come back and have some more discussion as a whole
group and uh so it' be best if you raise your Zoom hand if you know how to do that it's uh and um and if you don't
know how to do it uh there's a um uh place down below where I think it's uh
under uh my my computer it's uh under react so this is where you're allowed to
react As You Wish almost by raising your hand down there there's a there's
um so uh
Barb so Barbara you're muted are you able to unmute
yourself
so yeah you're not managing to unmute I don't I'm sending you a message as supposed to
say there now but I'm not getting the visual I don't know why um I'll give you
quickly my question but I'm having trouble with the audio and I don't want to disturb your flow um my question
though you're not managing to unmute oh oh hang on a can you wait a minute uh
because uh my uh technology thing is still not just right I have to um
I have to
uh there so because I'm I'm leaving this on
YouTube for the people who want to participate from YouTube I um
I I was hearing myself speak twice and so that uh didn't work so now I I muted
the YouTube channel so now Barbara I'm sorry so oh now you're muted again let's
see there you hear me now yes okay I'm
not getting the visual but let me just quickly do my question and I can hear you so that'll be good enough um the
first two characteristics of here and now and then immediate um
the um immedi see I understand as having something to do with um you know
relevancy in the past and relevant now and I also see it as immediate here and
now but I'm not really clear about how those two were different um so if you
just talk about that a little that might be helpful for me thank you yeah the the
PO for uh the first is di which means to view to be SE to be
seen and uh and and it also kind of means uh in in context it also can mean
here and now in our live direct experience here and now but literally
means to see and so there's a common custom to translate it as to be visible
here and now but the now part is not needed because that that's coming
next and so it's visible here maybe is a better translation and then the next one
immediate is the now thank
you so then uh
Padma let's see uhuh thank you um my question is
um in any of the practice uh the ways of practicing you
know this morning you just talked about knowing and experiencing or you know of course
watching the mind or you know the breathing feel the body all those things
yes they do work for me but I still feel there is mind involved knowing an
experience for example right I wonder what you have to say about that I feel
like in in in in all the meditations there is still mind involved oh
absolutely yeah the mind is involved all of who we are is involved and uh and the
mind shouldn't be disrespected or it shouldn't be overvalued either but it has an important role and for the for
vasna classic Vasa practice as mindfulness gets stronger and stronger
uh we start seeing more and more distinctions and the are are ordinary
life for many people everything's just a big buzz of chaos so just everything's kind of jumbled together in one big
experience as um mindfulness gets stronger and stronger and we get more
and more settled uh each individual physical and psychological mental
emotional event that occurs uh is seen distinctly rather than a bundle alog
together and so one of the things that we start seeing for example is that or
uh is that um uh you might feel a warm on your
skin and but that distinct from that sensation is the mind has a a cognition
warmth warmth on skin and that is seen is very distinct from each
other uh rather than one and the same thing and how that's valuable is that
sometimes we don't distinguish between uh our our preferences our desires and
the experience so if I see it all as a bundle then uh having a warm skin uh
maybe I don't like it today because it's going to be hot day and so the not liking and the warmth are kind of wetted
together and so you know then in order to satisfy my preference I have to get
rid of the warmth but if you can see that uh that
the that the warmth and the preference the warmth and desire are two very
distinct events then you don't have to get rid of the warmth you have to kind of become Freer of the desire and the
desire is more the the mental activity so we start seeing the we start seeing
more and more distinctions uh uh and uh that's part of where the freedom comes in the Dharma is
uh seeing each individual event distinct from itself rather than somehow blend it
together with everything else does that make
sense now you're muted again I think let's
see yeah I don't somehow I don't hear you yeah yeah yeah okay um yes it does
make sense um but I still get confused with the you know awareness and the
nonself um but I won't take too much time yeah yeah but that's easy to get confused with but uh the non we don't
say non-self in in our tradition we say not self and there's a very important distinction between there's no self
versus The Experience we're having is not self in our tradition we're not making a universal claim that there is
no self we're just as seeing for ourselves that every individual as we
see the distinct these very distinct experiences we tease things apart and see things
individually then um then uh we see that oh this is not
self this is not self this is not self it's always something very particular um and we don't get involved
in the abstractions of what a self is just a particular and it's as clear as
if you uh cut your fingernail and the fingernail clipping is on the counter
and you don't say you'll say well that's not me you know that you know it's was me it was part of me but it's not me now
you don't identify that's that's the self so it's that clear
thank so is
AA hi there everybody um thank you Gil can you hear me okay
yes okay good um I I guess maybe my issue is s no self
I found myself in a meeting the other day um and feeling all these this
hostility coming up towards other participants and and then I had a lot of
Shame coming up fulfilling the hostility and I was with with
it but I felt like I was like immobilized I was not able to
participate in a really helpful um healthy
way because of these entanglements with a
personality thoughts and and struggles
and I even though I I want to be present and feeling it it was not very helpful
to just feel angry and hostile and wanting to like critical of other
people and I I'm kind of don't know what to do with
that I think uh what I'd recommend you do with it is Be Inspired that you saw
it so clearly you see the issue so clearly and rather than feel like you
have to learn a skill or learn a technique or a secret for how to do better in the next
meeting I uh let it inspire you to develop your mind fness practice uh on
the on your you know as you in meditation in daily life and um and start start with small areas small
places where you're reacted to things and see see it in Easy places where you
can step back and just know it maybe without shame or have shame and not have it interfere and just begin slowly
building your uh your your strength of your practice and the day will come when
it your practice is going to be strong enough that you're at a meeting like this and you won't be tripped
up but you have to do you have to do the groundwork which is regular ongoing practice and you you'll find a way
you'll definitely you're you're in a good good position to develop yourself
grow in the Dharma in such a way that you'll find your freedom in these kinds of
meetings so this is not helping you with the meetings but it's it's uh offering
you a wise longer term uh
solution would I would it be a benefit to look deeper into the shame and
hostility absolutely it's useful to do that and sometimes you can do it on your
own sometimes you can journal sometimes you can go to therapy to look at it so that could be very useful but I would
still like to emphasize for you um to uh um you know give your give
yourself over to the to doing the practice to build the practice to strengthen yourself through the practice
and uh and that's a whole different route that's very important as well create the very strong practice
Foundation by developing your mindfulness so meditate every day maybe a couple of times a day maybe um you uh
find ways to develop stronger mindfulness in DayDay life maybe times you're alone at first when you're doing
Simple household chores or or going for a walk or driving and rather than uh
being distracted from yourself or caught up in things learn how in small ways to
let go of being caught let go of being caught and be present inste instead and slowly you'll
develop the strength that will be phenomenally helpful and and uh and it
might not help 100% depending on the strengths of the shame and the issues around it
um but if you do do therapy for example therap generally the par therapists I know they love it when people have
developed mindfulness practice they say it's so much easier to work with
them thank you thank you uh Jade maybe we'll take Jade and then uh Barb and
then we'll uh we'll do a break breakout
group so
hi hi thank you nice to meet you um long
time listener first time caller uh this might piggyback well on the previous
meditators um experience but I've been doing a Eightfold Path program and I
feel like I I really marinate in the teachings around the hindrances and I really struggle in um
friendship and less in the spiritual sa but more in
Social world and knowing that um as adults we need friends and that coming
out of uh the many years of more isolation I find myself struggling and
bouncing around the hindrances quite a bit so I was wondering if you had any
advice um in relationship to the hindrances and adult friendships making
them transforming with them into them out of them and um being at ease in that World
um from these teachings yeah I do have a little book called unhindered which talks about the
hindrances and the pra practicing with them and it might be interesting if you haven't seen it to look at that and
um and maybe uh practicing with hindrances with friends might be uh too
difficult to do live in lifetime when it's you're actually with friends but
maybe there's ways of uh reflection and remembering and and um and uh and uh
kind of um understanding uh inter interactions with
friends afterwards that you can slowly begin to learn about yourself and how you react
and when you react the most and what are the conditions for you to maybe not be so wise in in friendships
and what are the conditions that support you to be wise and how can you put those conditions in place before you're with
friends so there's a way of kind of maybe outside of the the interactions
begin reflecting and thinking about uh what you can learn about yourself through
those the other is to um maybe begin uh it's important very important for human
beings to have other human contact uh and uh maybe friendships is
too high a bar sometimes and volunteering somewhere where you don't have to be friends with people but
you're volun volunteering with other good natured good willed people and uh
and having much lighter interactions with people and allows you to experiment a little bit uh how do you talk how do
you ask about ask people about themselves how do you uh you know uh
offer friendly words to people who are not going to be your friends but just to kind of what do you learn about how to
be together with people and what do you learn about your fears or your worries your concerns uh in situations that feel
much safer and uh not there's not so much at stake um so volunteering for
example and uh and volunteering might provide you with enough uh social contact that you're beginning to
exercise that part of your being so those are some of the and then there
some of things in your question specifically about the Hind ances and friendships um again I think that
relates back to I said to maybe reflect after the the the uh uh a friend
encounter about your for yourself which hindrances came into play for you and what can you learn about yourself and
what can how can you be better prepared in the future and how can you maybe uh next time work with the hindrance as it
arises um how can you be on the lookout for them more and even as we get more
and more skilled about the hindrances we can um see them coming and we can some do a
course correction before they actually arise and so this is phenomenally
important the hindrances in some ways um it's one way of understanding uh
Buddhist practice it's primarily a practice of understanding the hindrances so if you feel like it's a
you know unfortunate that you have to work with the hindrances you don't have to think that way it's actually at the
heart of what we're working with
okay do that uh answer well enough for
now so maybe you're still muted so we'll go on to uh
Barb and then we'll do a breakout group and then I see another person raised her hand Mima so we can maybe do that after
the breakout group so Barb yeah good morning Gil thank you um
I'm pretty new to this group and my question comes from or an observation
maybe it's a question um belonging to another group for a long time and having
that leader be very charismatic and he has recently passed and the group
um how do they explain it there there's um
I think there's a lack in the group of people recognizing their own leadership
or their own value it's Val it has to do with value in their own wisdom and so I liked this morning how
you brought up it's getting to know it's the experience it's our experience for ourselves right that was one of the
teachings that I heard anyway this morning so if you can just say maybe a little bit more I don't know it's kind
of a question but I love like that aspect because it's hard because there's a part of me for instance that is just
meeting you for the first time this morning and then it's like okay and he's a teacher and then and you're
human anyway do you understand my question yes yes great great making any sense sense that makes sense to me I've
I've known a number of spiritual groups where people where that with the leader died or left or something and
only then did people start to grow up only then they were ready to kind of own their own experience and look at
themselves deeply and be honest with themselves in the way they hadn't been before and so maybe if you're still
involved with that group uh maybe uh you can support yourself and others to begin
uh speaking up uh more honestly about and beginning to own your own experience
beginning to tap into your own wisdom rather than looking outside for it to someone else who's going to provide it
and maybe you're the leader you had did you a good service to prepare the ground for it and now you're ready the group is
ready to take take it to a whole different level where they're um you know ready to speak about their
experience and and learn from themselves so so and I and I feel on the
I've actually stepped away from this group probably five years ago so I'm kind of on the outskirts it well that
it's um it's a Val it's something about valuing too they're valuing doing our
the teacher within each of us yes does that make sense it makes a lot of sense and so what I uh so what I like to
comment hopefully it's okay that um that uh the fact that you are speaking up in
such a clear way here with your wish with what your your circumstances are and what you bring with you here um this
is a really good sign you're doing what's needs to happen Okay and maybe bringing that
stupid group yeah yeah okay and it's my
world great thank you Gil thank you so um let's do a breakout groups and uh I
think we can do groups of four and we'll do about 12 minutes and uh and the idea is just
introduce you introduce yourselves to each other and say maybe maybe some very
simple words about you know the value you've had from this uh being part of this YouTube
uh Community or teachings uh or something about some very something very simple about this
week's theme the idea is be very careful you don't spend a lot of time explaining
and talking uh think of it as a listening exercise primarily where
you're really going to because it's such a short time you don't want we don't want one person um going on and filling
the time for too long it's better if everyone is kind of brief in their comments and then you can come back to
you again and again and the value of brief is that and com coming back is that you will probably
change uh as you go along you'll learn new things you'll be ready to say something new that you never said before
um if you are brief and then wait for your turn again and see what comes out and see what comes out um but you know
it's supposed to be relaxed and more friendly and just a chance to say hello to each other mostly and so so please be
relaxed and and friendly and so but it helps if some of you are if
you're not not going to be in the breakout group if you could uh check out of the zoom Now log out and you're
welcome to come and Jo come back in 10 minutes and uh I'll be here to receive you and um and that what that means is
that when we make the groups that um we don't end up with someone with alone in
a group because the other three people decided not to be there so if you could uh kind of log out out and then um and
then uh um we'll see when the numbers
stabilize and uh is it Julie or Nina which one of you are making the
groups I can make them great so so um so
if you could uh if you can not put me in a group I think that's maybe automatic I I
don't know if it's set up for that but um uh and then um and then if
um and then set it for 12 minutes and when you're ready I think we
can probably do it now when if you're ready when you're
ready and then if Nina and Julie if if you guys don't end up in a group you're
welcome to go and and join one and um and I'll stay here in monitor
the the the the
site so okay so I think most of the groups
have been made so uh Julie do you want to join a group
um yeah I can yeah I'll join I I can just press join to anyone you can join
anyone especially if there's one that has three or something but uh whatever one you like you have you have a choice
and uh and Nina are you there would you like to join the group
or um I'm currently still trying to figure out how to time like start a timer oh then it then it's then it's
probably too late to do it now that happens before so uh so don't worry
about it uh it it probably it'll go on forever now is my guess and uh so let's
just let's uh uh I'll look at the clock and I'll close the rooms um I said I see
uh I think I can do that let me see um let's let so breakout
rooms um the're groups of four in progress usually it says uh how long
they're supposed to be and and what you're supposed to do let me tell you can I want to tell you what to do you
normally oh yeah go ahead okay so when you make the groups you create them and then it shows
you that you know who's in which group and then but uh before you open it and
there's that uh settings uh wheel at the bottom left and you click on that and that will
show you how to set the timer and and then after you set the timer then you open the room
okay because they're all gray out right now yeah yeah so it's fine it's fine so you can if you want to join then I I'll
I'll I'll I'll close the rooms uh in about you know 10 minutes or
so um no that's okay I actually have to um do a bio break so okay okay great
well I'll be here if you want to chat when you come back all right thanks Gil bye
bye
for for
so if some of you are on Zoom um I don't know if anybody's still
there it's so 84 people are watching on on uh not on Zoom but on YouTube so we
have a few minutes if uh some of you are there would like to post a a question in
the chat I could uh try to um respond to you a little
bit and um I'll a little bit go back and forth between the
two groups I hope that uh it's interesting for you to watch a little bit this way
okay
oh
hi Nina nice to see you hi I'm back yes good good well thank you
for helping oh yeah absolutely this is um
this is great did you have any trouble logging on in the beginning were you were you the one who opened the door the
room uh yeah I opened it and that that was that was easily enough yep no problems good because uh
yeah so I I had opened it earlier in the day to get the link and then I closed it but then this other laptop that I used
it said something funny about are you going to someone's logging on or it's logged on do you want to allow them to
log on or and I said what's that maybe it was you so I don't know why why it
came that way but so I'm glad it worked out I me yeah
no I mean I understand the security for the yeah for the account where do you
live where do you live Santa Clara oh so you're close yeah I guess compared to some of
the people here yeah yeah sometimes I think like oh I'm like
a little far you know it is like a like a 20 25 minute drive to repid city but
you know when people tell me like oh I'm in you know Minnesota or something I'm like oh [Laughter]
you're how long you've been uh involved with IMC or
IRC um I think just earlier this year is when I started coming around regularly
nice do you have a background in this practice or this is your introduction um so I've done a couple
Retreats at Spirit Rock um I didn't have like a regular group or S
before and this is yeah I think like IMC is kind of the closest one around here
uhhuh so yeah that I joined to help me cultivate a more regular
practice meet some people good and we we are going to start doing some events
slow slowly probably like a year to build up at Hidden Villa you know about Hidden Villa in Los Altos so that maybe
that's even closer for you yeah I was there for the for the um
volunteer meeting yeah so so and I don't know I don't know if the Friday the 16th
in two weeks we're going to have our first event there in the morning
oh um I think I might be busy that day uhhuh um I would have loved to join but
I'm sure there'll be more yeah yeah
yes and do you have a some kind of technical background that they're helping with the technology here or or
um what's your background
um so my work background is more in like office management and Logistics um but
my actually my current job is doing ab uh I work at the Stanford lab Ah that's
a huge job so so you you you help with some of the classes they make that videos and
things like that um I work more in the Live Events
so a lot of the times we'll have like a really big um meeting you know like people fly in and um I work in theice
Auditorium I would say like 90 90% of the time and then some sometimes I
support in um the meeting rooms well I I can tell you hopefully
it's interesting story about the AV at Stanford that um my son went to Stanford
and um and um it wasn't until his last year
there that he learned how to pay attention in class
because he would class the class lectures were so slow he was on his phone he was talking to his neighbors in
the class and you know he this guy likes to multitask and his attention span is
and he was doing fine he was getting straight A's and everything was fine for him but but he wasn't really paying attention in the class then he
discovered that all his classes were recorded and that if he listened to them
at three times speed then he could pay attention then it would then he was engaged and he said
I learn so [Laughter]
much so um so anyway so at least there's one kid who found them extremely
valuable yeah no um when I was in college I actually I'm the opposite well
I'm the same way when I listen to like audiobooks I have to listen to them faster because read so slowly that I get
really distracted but um when I was in school I couldn't watch recordings I
would get really bored um it was a lot easier for me to listen in person yeah
yeah so he he was too distracted in person [Laughter]
so so let's see maybe another minute and then I'll uh we can close you you want
to be the one since you you opened it you want to be the one who closes it uh sure so so it just means you you
go open up the breakout room Tab and you see in the bottom right it says close all
rooms so uh I don't know how it's been set usually it's set that it takes 60 seconds to once it starts but sometimes
it just it's set for different let's see what it is so if you want to um push that red button and let's see what
happens all right let me just broadcast and let
them know that I'm closing them all right yeah 60 seconds 6 seconds
great right and now we wait for the Del
so I think people are back now and um I hope that was nice for you to have a
little chat and meet some of the people and some of the people maybe you've seen their names in the chat sometimes it's
nice to you know you know see them in person on Zoom at
least and uh I think before we uh we went to the zoom rooms there Mimi I
think that was the name was the wanted toas a question and if if Mimi still here that you'd like to
ask yes go ahead if you have to un oh there you are good morning Gail thank
you for this experience um it just makes started off my day on the right note with u meeting different
people um my question is you're the first teacher I ever heard use the term
and I've experienced it but I was wondering if you could say a little bit more about it when we sense like we know
but we sense and it I wonder if it ties in with uh pma's question is that still
part of the mind or what is because when I'm listening to somebody and I'm not quite understanding I get really
concentrated or mindful of like trying to hear and all of a sudden I'm sensing it's like the mind is out of the way and
I'm able to like perceive what they're trying to convey great I love what you say I love what you're saying and this
speaks to the fact that the word sense in English has multiple meanings I primarily use the the word sense to mean
sensing Sensations but uh but sometimes it's used uh in a very important way to refer
to uh having more of an intuitive understanding of what's going on and uh
and I think that as we practice mindfulness and as we bring kind of a careful full attention non-reactive
attention we have access to other ways of understanding than what is so
conscious the subconscious mind is very rich a lot goes on there there's a lot of information being taken in and being
processed that our for whatever reason our conscious mind may be is not tracking but if we real relax and open
up to this deeper way of knowing sometimes we can we can have this uh
intuitive sense of something and uh I trust that a lot I use it a lot but I
don't trust it automatically if there's an intuitive sense I always double or
triple check is this really accurate is this right and I'll wait before I articulate it or act on it and sometimes
if it involves other people I'll even uh check with them first you know this is
my sense this is my intuition what is this is this okay is this right or and sometimes I don't use even use the word
sense because it confuses people uh or in intuition I say you know I have this
interpretation and that and that gives them lots of permission to see it as not being so you know so you know that it
doesn't carry the same weight so but I I love it that you have that and uh and maybe there's a way of
of uh becoming wiser and wiser about how you use that intuitive
sense well I think you help me a lot today um with that response because um I
always wonder what it was and as I practice more it gets sharper um I don't have to really do anything it just like
naturally comes up and so I wondered if it was related somehow so it does help
tremendously so thank you so much great thank you so then Jim
thank you Gil and thank you everybody uh I just wanted to briefly say how much I appreciate your
teachings um you know I my my my we're about the same age I think you're
several months older than I am and uh our path is very much the same in terms
of starting off with its Zen I started out green cul and then went up and was a student of quan
roshi oh wonderful then transition to you excuse
me because you made so much sense you did a paper about the your transition
too and I said this guy is me except he's a little more dedicated
but uh this 7 amm and all of your online offerings since Co you know I moved out
of the Bay Area and um as you know and um it was just very difficult and this
has just brought you you every day uh into my life and your teachings are so
clear and they're so inspiring for me to want to practice more I I just want to thank you great
wonderful it's nice to hear this and maybe you'll come to Redwood City one day in person or maybe you'll come to
one of our Retreats at IRC actually this actually this month I'm in um green bra
so yes great great so and then um what year were you at greenle
uh let's see 88 to um I'm trying to
think was there for about five years so 88 to 93 I see yeah I guess during that
time I wasn't so much at Green gch but I was there for uh 1990 I think for a
little conference with Buddhist teachers that I uh we we had I was I was one of the speakers at the in the wheel Right
Center there and and if you remember ucanda was there the B Burmese monk for the little
conference but anyway May yeah great so
thank Youk you so so thank you everyone and
um maybe that's enough for now and I whenever I I look for opportunities
regularly to uh to U what I can to have these Friday meetings and my Fridays are
often quite full with other teaching responsibilities but I will continue to look for opportunities and and you know
and I wish that we could do them more often than we have and um and uh so
we'll see what we can do and um and I hope that some some of you have
you know have checked out the different offerings we have at IMC we have great teachers and great offerings that go on
here and um and uh maybe it kind of enriches your involvement with the
practice and how you do this and for those of you who live far away uh one of
the wonderful things that came out of the pandemic is that uh there's uh when
I teach at IRC there's an online option that be online participants and
so both as a what we call full participants but also as Auditors for it
which uh is a nice way of participating as well so that's maybe some of you'll
find that interesting and um so thank you very much and uh and I appreciate all this
and if you if you would like to unmute and say goodbye to the whole Community here some kind words it'll be a bit of
cacophony but that's kind of nice and happy way of ending Thank You by everybody
everyone gratitude to all of you like the way the windows bounce
around
when bye beautiful future thank you
[Music]