so uh so welcome folks um yeah I'm glad um we can be together
this evening so
um yeah I'll talk about um this uh this moment or how how it's
um yeah how it how it plays out in my heart for whatever that's worth
but um but let's sit let's remember
um what hasn't changed about this practice even today day like this
so maybe um you begin just
uh kind of um gently uh massage
M some part of your body it might be as simple as your thumb and your index finger
gently rubbing against each other might be a hand to your uh your
belly face or just a gentle massage
for leg
just uh anchor anchor to the subtle pleasantness of that sensation
and maybe the the warmth of that uh
Sensation that kind of expression of uh
care sensitivity to your own
body maybe that warmth the warmth of the
S just kind of ripples out thaws
out whatever may be braced or
Frozen for
and breathe
sensing uh your your breath expanding your belly
up into your shoulders the effects of your breathing
on your the back of your
body
e e
we sort of En liven our body and Al livening it uh
makes more room to uh to feel our way through this
moment e
I'm there's a certain kind of eerie calm that's uh settled over
people but when that um frozenness thaws
out it's actually just some clarity and calm left
and so maybe it feels natural just to let the Mind
get very
vast maybe we say recognize
fastness
for
e
e e
you uh don't need to uh create the
vastness doesn't depend on whatever you call
me
a sense that uh we arise within space we
arise as space
don't fight the solidity within
space certain zones of density body or feeling
don't need to melt that down into space
stay
open
e
e for
maybe it sounds remote in this moment but we can experience ourselves as a kind of
gust of wind the world is a gust of
wind and when those guts meet there's a very
subtle kind of
collision when those two gusts
meet it's called
love for
so maybe we attune to love in some way to the the poignancy of of
life it's almost like we're massaged by
that
e
e e
maybe there's uh other things arising maybe there's
fear Rising
grief or
anger that's all good but uh give it
back to love kind of arose out
of love and give it
back give it
back
e
e e
okay um yeah it's good to uh it's good to
practice with you um yeah you know it's like I don't
know I didn't know what I would guide or what I would say or something and it's just like uh yeah we got to find find
our practice um
so no matter um yeah how you're you're feeling I
think it's it's good that uh that we're here uh together
now me meaning it's a time for uh for Spiritual friendship
K and um it seems like something more
has to happen than just feeling kind of bad
together but I I don't think so it's actually enough for right now at least
that that is enough and kalana
that doesn't mean we all have the same views this is not a political action committee If This Were a different
election I would be saying different things uh but uh given the the what was
kind of that we're really yeah uh voting on Greed hate and
delusion that makes it a special moment I don't assume we're all all
United by ideology but we are united by
a certain orientation to suffering we are united by knowing the danger of greed
hate and delusion we're United by our wish to
alleviate suffering in self another and that's
kalana that's enough that's enough now of course I'd I'd love
to say that um everything will be
okay but cannot because it
won't but something will be okay and something very
important I I've been tracking my mind mind carefully um in the last 24 hours
you know partially just for my own well-being and practice and Clarity partially so I
could teach so I could say something Michelle uh Michelle McDonald
um said uh said the line between things being all right and things being very
bad is thin and the thinness of that
line is called a Nicha
uncertainty years ago a student said to me I think I don't know maybe it's from
the 12 step tradition but um they said to me something like we teach from our scars
not our wounds and that's very good advice you
know uh I he it I don't want to spill my
pain on you I don't want to enlist you in some
uh way in which I'm working out my own Karma but sometimes you just got to show
up you know and uh there's certain kind of freshness in sensing the unprocessed
pain speaking from it so I I've cycled through a kind of
range of Mind States um shock even though I knew it was like
in my mind 6040 or something like that so there's no whatever happens there
shouldn't be a shock but it's a shock and it takes time for the mind to catch
up with anicha you know to catch
up and so uh we are sensitive to the kind of
cool or cold Frozen you know just a little static that buffers us from
contact with Body Mind Dharma it's been cynicism you know like
just like oh my goodness we're just you know a terribly designed
animal given the challenges of being human given the challenges of living
with other Human animals just not welld designed you
know and then there's been energies of just like sort of laying down you know
kind of like uh sort of like an animal that knows it's the end or
something and there's been a certain kind of relief you know like no more waiting for the biopsy I know the
results okay malignant now
what and of course a kind of cascade of grief you
know just like uh this is what we do to each
other the heart um is designed for love
and designed to um to be uh to be broken
um and uh again Michelle I I call on her these
moments you know think one time she said something like like the near enemy of
meta is na the near enemy of of meta loving
kindness is na yeah
well our love just became a little less
naive and groundlessness as we know can make us uh love or or hate
beautiful line from Mother Teresa you know uh may God break your hearts may
God break my heart so completely that the whole world Falls in I God break my
heart so completely that the very beautiful line I went to her website and
there's like a whole page on her website that says like stuff Mother Teresa
didn't say that was on there that was like at the
top but I want to give her credit for it even if that's just a meme on
Twitter that's a good line there's a there's a grief that's uh
debilitating and uh and a grief that's that sweetens you know that
that's that's the opposite of navite so um Leonard Cohen's song uh I I
greet you from the other side of sorrow and despair with a love so vast and
shattered it'll reach you everywhere I sing this for the captain whose ship has not been built for the
mother in confusion her cradle still unfilled for the heart with no companion for the soul
with no King for the Prima ballerina who cannot dance to anything I greet you
from the other side in
the successive breakings of the heart
um there's there is more and more light that gets in I do know that
and I've been trying to to sort of sort through the elements of my pain that
arise Crystal Clear Pristine from
love there's love binds us to a certain measure of
pain but I want to distinguish that from the pain of my own
righteousness or aversion or vindictiveness or lack of
Courage I want to I want to be Discerning I kind of uh we become
connoisseurs of our own pain and
uh and those threads of the pain that um involve the
purity of uh love and care we don't have to do anything about those
threads one of the um the effects of of practice I it's we don't talk about so
much but it's been so so prominent to me is it just
I I I just think about my life much less you know my life as an object you know
know and it's not like I'm trying to be a good Buddhist or ignore myself or be
selfless or something like that it's just just doesn't arise so
much but I think about others a lot and sometimes it seems to me I think about
unknown others in the same entangled way I used to think about
myself like my you know kind of the ways in which
the energy of the self system have been freed up to flow outwards into the
world um it still holds a kind of trace
of the same slightly entangled forms of care that I would
before practice direct towards myself and it's like okay what what
Matthew is like a mature differentiated way of
caring you know comprehend Dua the Buddha
says comprehend Dua suffering what what
on Earth did he mean what did he mean I want to know what
Illusions you know what Illusions must perish in order to truly
take in the enormity of the this truth of
dukka what to do with the power one has
what does love ask of us and how to
refine or relation ship to helplessness how to refine
that is there a way to keep
uh your heart from collapsing even on the other side of
your power is that possible we explore that together
and I wondered you know is the Dharma the same on a day like this or is it
different it's been a perennial question for me there have been a lot of days
like this is it the same or different to say
it's the same feels cold and misat tuned and like a a
lack of empathic courage right and I really want
to give deep permission to feel your pain and mine
and I don't want a Leap Frog into a kind of fake brittle
equinity but to say that it's different forgets all the
things love has already seen all the upheavals the dharma's
already observed and so we probably need to ask the
question of ourselves how is the path the same and how has it
changed what's
deepened on Monday night I had the thought there might only be one consolation for a
day like this and for me for me for my heart
and it was the sense that a a Harris Victory might have induced a certain sense of moral complacency in
me you know and uh shinzen yangang said that you know
don't get stuck in a good place in practice don't get stuck in a
good place and I I don't know say I'm stuck still growing and practicing in
heart very alive but um there's some deeper
expression of care that uh needs to be born I don't know exactly what shape
that takes but um it it sort of crystallized in the the
phrase that I want my whole life
to be a nonviolent
protest so I offer this uh for your consideration and uh take whatever is of
value leave the rest behind will um keep going quite um
grateful to uh know the Dharma to know
you to be together practice okay