hello and thank you for being part of this 7
a.m. practice session with your participating with your interest in your
practice at
uh everyone's appreciated as being part of this wonderful effort
at exploring our life through the lens of mindfulness
and these 10 Reflections we're doing this these two weeks for me they
[Music] are founded on or based on our capacity
to be mindfully present here and now in our direct experience and in a sense the it's a
followup for the long series on introduction to mindfulness mindfulness
part two that we did this a.m. from the beginning of the year until just about I
guess April or so and
um and so with a foundation of mindful
attention Foundation of awareness there's a
softening of our clinging our resistance our
attachments are fixations there's a softening and lightening up and there's
a lightening a lightning lightning up
becoming lighter and in the lightness of
our presence and the softening of our
presence there is it's easier for the heart to respond
the heart to register and be responsive our hearts are designed our
emotional hearts are designed to be responsive and shift and
change with the circumstances around us this morning there was an article about
how anger prevents the dilation of I guess the arteries and veins of the
heart and it's a detrimental to the heart in the same way the softening the
relaxing of mindfulness uh probably helps with
dilation makes things easier so this softening of the
heart this responsibity of the heart gives rise
to a greater sense of care or empathy or sense of being connected
to ourselves in a heartfelt way and to others and so from this mindfulness
practice there can be born four different forms of love maybe more than
that four different ways of caring and these are called
the in the tradition they're called sometimes the in English the Divine abodes there there's something quite
phenomenally valuable about a human being and so some English speakers like
to call them Divine it's a translation of the word
Brahma and um and these are uh
friendliness kindness Good Will as the first the second is
compassion or a certain kind of um empathic concern for the suffering
of others the third is uh often translated
as sympathetic Joy appreciative Joy a kind of sharing in the success and
happiness of others and the fifth is um profound
equin form of love called equinity quid imity love love which is
not easily rattled a love which is not easily um swinging to dismay or anger or
hopelessness or despair or or kind of fear rush to
action but has a wisdom the oversight the overview of the situation to stay
balanced and clear and and loving but not
reactive so to bring our mindfulness to open to
mindfulness to the softness or the lightness of
being and see if there can be one of these four
that can flow through the mindfulness with the
mindfulness so to assume a meditation
posture and if you're familiar with meditation it's meditated for a while
then to close your eyes and maybe feel the homecoming
coming of the posture the familiarity of the
posture occasionally maybe you feel the goodness of being in this meditation
posture that assuming the posture has associations
has has uh its own Dynamic that begins bringing us into
contact with our body and
ourselves and if you haven't gently closing your
eyes and taking some gentle deeper
breaths with the inhale being a
reminder that you are here here this place at this
time and the exhale a softening relaxing into this
Here and Now
and then letting your breathing return to normal on the
exhale relaxing the muscles of the
face and as you relax notice on the
inhale how it is to feel and sense those muscles of the face
on the exhale relaxing the shoulders softening in the
shoulders and on the inhale
feeling the shoulders more fully
on the exhale softening the belly releasing in your
belly and then on the inhale feeling whatever impact relaxing the
belly has feeling it more fully broadly
and if it's available to you on the exhale Relax The Thinking
mind soften thinking mind
quiet
it and then on the inhale let yourself feel and sense more
fully the thinking mind as it relaxes or as it doesn't
and then on the exhale relaxing around the heart the heart center softening opening
and then the inhale feeling your heart
and as you sit here in your body Here and Now with your experience
which of the Divine abodes seems closest and most relevant
for you with whatever is being carried with you in
the present moment is it a basic kindness or
goodwi
friendliness a compassion
sympathetic
Joy equinity
love which of those seems to arise in a kind of simple
ordinary way so that it can accompany your
mindfulness kind mindfulness compassionate
mindfulness joyful mindfulness equanimous mindfulness
with a rhythm of breathing keeping you here in the
present being mindful of your experience
supported by one by one of the four Divine
abodes
e
for
e e
where within do you find a lightness a
softness a
gentleness from which comes from which
arises love of some form kindness
compassion appreciation
equinity for yourself for
others for here and now maybe without even an object for the
love love just
love
e
for
for e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting sometimes mindfulness leads us to a Simplicity of
being a simple almost contentment with just sitting and breathing
we not much else is needed we're not being driven by the future or the past
or responsibilities or desires aversions
regrets just simp we feel the value of a simple
being here alive present
that might not feel like anything
dramatic however maybe it can be
characterized maybe in a matter of degrees but it can be characterized by an absence of ill will
an absence of
hostility an absence
of objectifying others as the object of our desires of some kind expectations
demands judgments
the absence of reactivity tendency to judge or
criticize the Simplicity of being of simple
presence can be characterized by something phenomenally
important the absence of these difficult States harmful states of mind
that maybe have something in common with our human heartfelt capacity
for love for kindness
compassion joy in others and even in even minded men
an impartiality and may this Simplicity of
being this freedom of
mindfulness may it be a channel for all our good will for others our
friendliness our wishing everyone well because in Wishing others well
we help our heart feel well so may it be the heart's wish that
all beings be happy all beings be
safe all beings be
peaceful all beings be
[Music]
free thank [Music]
you for
so hello
and and welcome to this eighth uh discussion of the eighth
reflection and these are reflecting
on things that are invaluable for the development and
growth of our spiritual life or if you to prefer rather than the word spiritual
maybe our heart life the fullness of our
hearts and um so today's topic is kinship and it goes along with uh
yesterday's topic of community and um Community has a lot to
do with the relationships we have with people the feeling of belonging connection the feeling of friendliness
with people so it has a little bit more to do with u Dynamics and
relationships kinship as I understand it involves something deeper than our
relationships it's a way in which our hearts seeks others it's the way in which we feel
that we're family and um I was surprised when I was probably I
was 18 when um I went back to meet some of my aunts
and uncles I hadn't I'd grown up with them a little bit but it was the first time I was maybe close to being an
adult and um and one of my aunts um made it clear in some way or other
that uh we were family that had a deeper Roots than
whether there was we were friends or we liked each other or there was just kind
of a raw basic acceptance of each other because we're a
family and um uh it may be a kinship you
know a family ship and and I was struck by that and
and uh reflected on that and that stayed with me uh in the probably the first 10
years of doing Buddhist practice as it slowly grew this sense that uh there
could be this kinship this family feeling for everyone that we're all kin we're all
family sometimes I Delight in the the thought that yes if we we can probably
all of us if we could trace our lineage our ancestral lineage backwards in time that uh we would all
converge someplace if nowhere else maybe um maybe a million years ago in the
plains of Africa and um and we would um we all
have a common Origins we all part of the same family and we know that this human race
of ours is phenomenally effective at creating division phenomenally effective at at uh
creating alienation and separation and and very strong boundaries between
inside and outside and those who belong and those who don't belong those who are part of my family my tribe my Village my
nation whatever it might be and we make it so strongly that the other sometimes
gets demonized sometimes gets treated is less than
human and um and uh the cost of that is a kind of um
separation from ourselves a kind of truncation a a limiting of ourselves
because if we see others uh as others radical others as
distinct from us as separate from us as being belonging to some other category
than us whether it's other family or tribe or Village or Nation or ethnicity
or race or whatever that um it limits our capacity to be whole limits our capacity to let
all our faculties be open and receptive and and take take in the humanity of
others and so these divisions we live in become divisions that we carry inside of
ourselves and part of the uh the the influence that mindfulness
has meditation has is uh beginning to uh soften and then dissolve these
divisions that we carry with inside ourselves these divisions that come with
ill will hatred judgment bias
Prejudice um selfishness um the kind of selfishness
which is collective selfish for my family selfish for my Village my
people and um those begin to dissolve and if they don't
dissolve uh there's a lot of there's there's maybe subconsciously or not
quite recognized a lot of pain there's unresolved work there's there's um uh
and sometimes this can be very dramatic sometimes they involved a deep
alienation from all people some people carry around with them a a Perpetual
anger hostility even um uh resentment towards all people
anybody they encounter or huge categories of people uh sometimes it's towards certain
genders sexual orientations ethnicities um uh races
um all kinds of ways in which it's carried within us and
um and uh and it can really break people it can really be a lifetime of being
kind of a broken heart or be alienated from oneself even and so as we do mindfulness
practice we start feeling the impact the cost the the hurt of living in a divided
world living in divisiveness and I've known people who have done this practice and at some
point after many years um were able to put down their resentment towards indivi
certain individuals after many years and uh saw through the
inherited uh bias Prejudice racism that they'd grown up
with and uh and I've known people who have changed dramatically from how they grew up
because they saw through how painful that was for themselves to carry this
divisiveness they have and so to heal this and part of
that movement of heal this is to discover what I call uh our Universal
kinship with everyone and I like the idea that we're discovering we're all
family and even people that have we've never met before in some way we can meet
them as if as if we're family uh it had a huge impact for me
many years ago the first time I met this Buddhist monk named Yanda he's dead now
but he was a a Burmese monk who was um first came to live in in the Bay Area
San Francisco in San Francisco to teach this basic mindfulness practice that I learned in
Burma so so uh before I went to Burma I'd heard about him I called him up on
the phone and asked him if I could come see him and just kind of prepare to go to Burma and he said yes please come and
I went to his house which was also his Temple then and um and what blew me away
what kind of was a a little bit life-changing for me I never met this person but when he opened the door I had
the very distinct feeling that he was his friendliness his warmth his
receptivity to me was as if he was meeting an a long lost friend he was
just so delighted and receptive and to have this feeling of someone I didn't know treating me with such a kinship
such a warmth such a POS opened a whole world to possibility for me of how not
so much that I could be the same way which it did but it um May me more
important um that it was possible to drop the divisiveness the separation the
US versus them the and for me it was a lot to do with fear fear of others fear
of opening up that it was possible not to live that way and so as I continue with my
mindfulness practice the mindfulness practice kind of folded in this
possibility that yes this fear that I carried for others fear of rejection
fear of failure fear all kinds of things didn't have to be there the sense of uh
separation from others and treating others with uh certain kind of kind of
uh well separation or just difference and keeping my
distance didn't have to be there and so something began softening and opening in
me and uh and over time uh the sense of kinship grew and grew and grew for me
and I would say that that is a very important guiding principle for me or
feeling for me the sense of kinship with people and uh and I like to feel
it I Delight going to the supermarket to see if there's an opportunity with a
checkout clerk to just have a little bit more human contact to look them you know
at them look them in their eye to ask how they're doing or have some simple conversation where
feeling some contact that's deeper than just a casual hello and often for me
that happens in you know not that I'm staring at people but some kind of
recognition that happens in the eyes meet that sometimes happens to me when I
see certain mammals in the eye something profound happens to
me uh for um excuse me for a moment
something profound happens to me in u the feeling of
kinship so what is your sense of kinship what is your sense of
nonkinship do you have a k sense of kinship that's bounded by a certain community that only for them do you have
that and if that's the case what gets in the way of having that sense of kinship
be wider than the community that for whom it's easy for you do you understand
you know what are the Dynamics in you that create division in our
society social divisions between you and the people who are not in that Circle of
kinship and what is it for you to have some sense of universal kinship allowing that there are
distinctions between how we love and care for and and are friendly with people who are different Circles of
community for us in our lives there are differences but what about a universal
kinship where we love we care for we respect we value um all people as kin in
such a way that we do not create live by the artificial barriers that we
contribute to keep uh people out of our hearts away from our hearts
so I hope you appreciate that this might point to the how kinship might be a
universal human need and characteristic and how does it for you how does it work
for you and and so that's the reflection for these next 24 hours and um and maybe
you can see that there's a connection between your sense of kinship and your capacity to love
so thank you very much