good morning everyone and welcome and uh ended up on the
schedule for today kind of late just yesterday afternoon I think some of you
might be here expecting tens and chokey she'll uh there was a I made a
scheduling mistake and she'll come on the 16th and if you don't know her she's a wonderful uh former totha nun um she's
uh I've known her for 30 years and uh she
um uh is before she was a a nun she was deeply involved with an agency in Santa
Cruz uh working with a County Legal Services and neighborhoods with conflict
resolution training people in conflict resolution and she's a master at this kind of wonderful art that's so
important for us all and then uh she did lots of serious practices at thebet and N I think she
did two of the three threeyear Retreats that they do and uh kind of solitary
Retreats and she kind of did a lot of uh uh practice and study with compassion so
between conflict resolution and compassion you're you're not going to go wrong she's a she's a really so so um
little bit sorry she's not here for you today but she'll be here in two
weeks and um and I'll be at the IRC this next week
and then the following Sunday is my son's graduation from college so um so
then I'll be back the following week on the 23rd and I want to mention that because um I pretty sure I'm going to have a
special meeting after the Dharma talk that day maybe both on maybe on zoom and
on uh here live for people who want to come to it um we were approached a few
weeks ago by the leadership at Hidden Villa for those of you who don't know
Hidden Villa it's a nature preserve and farm uh in the middle of Silicon Valley
kind of it's up against the mouth Los elos Hills there and uh of el el
Monon behind the Community College that's there going back up into the hills beautiful place to go visit and
hike and and before we had our own Retreat Center we did uh Retreats there for 10 years some sometimes as many as
five a year and and um it was just a fantastic place to do
Retreats they have a hostel there so we were approached by the leadership uh
there interest in having IMC back there um and uh maybe a partnership with us of
sorts so we could have regular use of the Hostile again and um and it comes at the same
time that we've been uh uh kind of a little bit exploding the
retreat center and offering Retreats and that the retreat center is fullly scheduled but now we started to offer
Retreats else elsewhere we're called the off-site Retreats renting facilities and
we now have um you 15 PE 14 people I think in our teacher training it's less
than a year left foury year program and we have seven teachers already so we
have like 21 teachers able teach Retreats so that's also an
explosion and so now suddenly to be offered Hidden Villa as a place where we can do more Retreats is a wonderful gift
and uh we haven't worked out all the details but uh there's a long history as I said with hidden villa in many many
ways it's a kind of part of our kind of peninsula family or something of
connections and um but the the real challenge for us biggest challenge of us
to be able to do that is um we do everything on a volunteer basis you know everything's offered freely and
volunteers and uh all the things we do already we our volunteer base is fairly
thin and so to imagine having more volunteers to put on
Retreats at Hidden Villas right you know it's the imagination has a hard time
seeing it and it's very important when we do things that we try to do it without any stress that's kind of like our calling
card otherwise it all volunteers it doesn't really work so um so I I I thought of having a
meeting that day for people who are interested in what we're doing there hiddenville of the option there and and
um to talk about the volunteering people are maybe some of you have been there before and uh done Retreats there and
some of you have volunteered there before we did before did Retreats and so
some of them don't necessarily come to IMC anymore they're kind of in the Woodwork they they're on behind the
camera up there um and uh watching on YouTube and things like that so uh we
thought we'd have a meeting and see who would come to a a meeting like that to talk about the that possibility and how
to manage to put to put it on before we go back to Hidden Villa and kind of
continue the discussions with them and just explore what that partnership might be like so I thought maybe at 11:30 and
the 23rd we could do that so so we'll announce again I'll put it on the
calendar and on the website but U it's kind of a kind of phenomenally fortunate
thing that coming that's come our way and seems like it just like that to
partner with hidden villa to be able to offer Retreats there and maybe other do other kind of Partnerships with them is
a phenomenal thing and uh one of the things also over the last couple of years that I've been
involved in is training people uh in um in in do doing Buddhist Buddhist uh
caregiving in relationship to the natural world like we have this Buddhist Eco chapy program and involved in
training a whole bunch of people to be able to do retreats in the wilderness camping Retreats and backpacking
Retreats other things and so we have all these the hidden vill is right there in the natural world so we can probably do
some pretty creative things there as well
so um as for the talk today so this
um last week uh gave a series of talks on the uh fundamentals or the
foundations or of Buddhist ethics introduction to the Buddhist ethics and um I talked about how part
part of the foundations of it is the is the the the I don't know if I want to
call it a principle maybe that diminishes it but uh the principle of non-harming at the center of it the idea
of U becoming skilled in learning to recognize what is wholesome what is healthy for us in the heart and to live
from that inner psychological health is a foundation for Buddhist
ethics that um another one is uh that we're involved in um uh training
ourselves that Buddhist precepts are not U admonitions or Commandments they're
trainings that understood you're not going to be perfect at it but we're training ourselves and cultivating developing ourselves to become
ethical and um and then as we become more ethical or train train this way
then ethics becomes um second nature it becomes our nature it becomes who we are
and the word for Ethics in Buddhism it's often translated to English as ethics is
the word CA s i l a and that word uh has
two meanings it means behavior and then it came over time to mean nature like a character of a person
like something deeper in person's nature is to and so the word some people then
have translated as virtuous Behavior virtuous conduct and um and so at some point it
becomes a person's natural virtue to be ethical to not cause any harm and it's
not something you have to think about doing it's just who you are you're not going to intentionally want to harm
anyone it's just your nature to be that way and that's certainly that's especially the case of those people who
mature in this practice to what sometimes is called Enlightenment or realization that um and so if if um
anyone you know if everybody hears that you've been hanging out with the Buddhists or doing Buddhist practice and
they ask you how do you know when someone's enlightened uh you now I'll give you an
answer that I think is very profound and that is um that um uh you
know when they don't want to harm anybody isn't that a great answer I
think it is so so but I wanted so today I wanted to do another piece of this foundation
for Buddhist ethics and that is uh Meta Meta is a
wonderful word that has been translated many times into English my most common
favorite translation of it is Goodwill uh sometimes I like kindness
it's often known in popular Buddhist English speaking circles as loving
kindness and sometimes I really like that word uh some people like the word
benevolence so there's all kinds of different ways they they use people use the word and uh and the all the variety
of translations we have speaks to the idea that meta whatever it is is not one
thing um and but it belongs to a family of attitudes of emotions which have to
do with which one hand can be called our social emotions or positive social emotions or attitudes or maybe more
maybe a little bit more kind of precisely the caregiving emotions the
emotions of care rather than caregiving may be motions of care where care has two
meanings care means you want to support someone help someone some care for someone that way but to care also means
that you uh something is important and so to to have emotions of
care is also emotions to have respect for other people to see appreciate them
and value them to Value people because that you care about them and it has this
kind caregiving kind of attitude too So Meta is in that family of things and
rather than thinking it's one thing you take all the whole family of caregiving emotions you can kind of imagine making
a color wheel from them that the color wheel that has no sharp lines between any of the colors and then all the
colors is kind of kind of you know kind of gradually fade into each other move
into each other and um if you SE in a color wheel sometimes the primary colors stand out kind of more intensely but
they don't have any sharp lines between the other Hues of that color and so the
same way so so we have this wonderful wheel of potential caregiving emotions
that we live live in that sometimes in Buddhism we talk about loving kindness meta karuna compassion appreciative Joy
which is mudita and equinity as a form of
lovea and um but there's others generosity could be could be
one um and um so what is this meta in the classic uh language of of Pi meta is
a cognate or connected to the word ma which means friend and uh the some of
the oldest definitions of meta is uh is
um um says it um it is known as meta because it arises in in one's
relationship to a friend so it's kind of some people just like to translated as friend
friendliness that meta as a kind of friendliness with the idea that that friendliness uh is a wonderful thing to
have warm friendly feelings for a friend and um and uh and then the idea is to
universalize that feeling so everyone's your friend wouldn't that be nice and
maybe that's a little bit of a lower bar than saying loving kindness because as soon as you have the word love in
it you know it's a high bar and um it's possible to have goodwi
or friendly attitude to people you don't like and I think it's realistic that we
have people who somehow doesn't quite work for us there something about them that's quite not you know you know maybe
they're aversive and irritating and maybe they're always as cynic and and
just kind of like oh you know here we go again and um so it's you don't quite
like them but you can still have good will for them you can still have an
attitude or friendliness that's genuine that's part of your character your nature that your heart is open to them
and care you care for them in spite of the fact that you know well that doesn't kind of work for me how they are so so I
don't know if I said that in any way that would offend anyone or trouble anyone but I was trying to say something
that that it's nice to lower the bar of what Goodwill could be because then then then it's easier to do it um to think
you're supposed to be loving to every single person you see it's a little bit hard to imagine that you know that's a
high bar to attain um so
um so in terms of Ethics uh
uh I like to think of Buddhist ethics is the Buddhist ethics of friendship the
kind of e way you would be with a good very good friend you I don't think it
feels good to think about killing your good friend like that's not you know you're
probably actually you know you know willing to sacrifice even your life for some good friend it's the opp feeling
feel opposite feeling might be there uh you're probably not going to steal from your good friend this just would just
feel kind of yucky I hope and probably you're not going to uh
you know assert yourself in a violent sexual way and a you know dominating way on your friend to hurt them
sexually and you probably know doesn't feel good to lie to them and this whole and then the last
precept not not getting intoxicated um I've known people who have harmed their friends when they got
intoxicated they somehow that just didn't work for for friends family all
kinds of people there's been tremendous harm being created so the idea is you know careful
with what you take in so you don't harm anyone so um the the the ethics of
friendship is one quality of Buddhist ethics and that I think gives a very different flavor for what ethics is if
the primary reference point is some kind of Western puritanical ideas of
Commandments and ones that involve punishment and you know completely black and white or you know night and day kind
of um um uh you know right and
wrong so um so here's more of this
definition um meta is called meta because because uh it is
friendly it refers to Tender or watery love watery
love the um some people translate this as moist love um but watery I think of like a
wonderful container like a bladder something that holds water and it you
shake it and the water kind of moves inside or shakes inside and this wonderful resonance in the heart that we
have when something happens and the heart kind of is not frozen and it's uh
you know it's it's it's a watery so it kind of responds it's a responsive thing some people have translated this
word as a lubricating uh friendship lubricating love lubricating meta lubricated heart
and that's a little odd because I think of you know the oil for your car but uh but the um but also I have
this means that uh there's no resistance you know things so your heart is
lubricated means that things just flow right through and right in and just available and uh and really well
lubricated heart um is like another metaphor is a heart that's so open that
uh things go into it and pass right through they don't get stuck and when
things get stuck then when we get in trouble and um so um so this um
so um and then here it says the characteristic of meta is to promote
well-being so there's something it's a quality of friendship where we have Good Will and we want well for others that's
the characteristic of it as opposed to having love or friendship or someone and is
characterized by what they can do for me it's about my well-being that counts what I can get in the relationship
there's a there's a this it um it doesn't anyway so to promote the
well-being of the other it its function is to prefer
well-being over I guess ill beinging PR there is something to
prefer there is a prefer to prefer to have a sense of ease and happiness and joy over
unhappiness um its manifestation is the remove removal of
annoyance isn't that nice occasionally one one or two of you probably get annoyed and um and so it's
such a nice feeling when that annoyance is gone annoyance is kind of an irritant for
yourself its proximate cause is seeing the loveliness of others isn't that
great what does it take to be able to see the loveliness of other people
I know that sometimes that's not available because we're annoyed because we're angry because
we're fil filled with the desire we're filled with um delusion we're filled
with confusion fear all kinds of things into fear we're so caught up in our agenda and all we have to do so many
things over being over busy interferes with friendliness over being over busy
interferes with their ability to take in another person so that we see their
loveliness wouldn't that be a nice life if you went around seeing loveliness in
everyone yes but you got to be realistic we have a lot of things to
do what's more important what could be more important
than seeing the loveliness in being of beings it succeeds metto succeeds when
ill will subsides and it fails when it
produces selfish affection I guess self selfless AFF I
don't know what that is but selfless affection no selfish selfish is affection it says I guess I was hoping
for something different selfish affection and
u similar there's another one uh how does one abide with one's
heart accompanied with meta extending outward in One Direction so there's the
idea that you can take this attitude and have it feel like it's expansive and extensive in all directions but you can
start with One Direction how do I abide with a M mind a heart accompanied with
meta extending outward in One Direction just as one would feel friendliness on
seeing a barely beloved friend so does one extend loving kindness meta to All
Creatures so um so I I like very much that uh we have
different English translations of meta so that we don't box her in and think it has to be one thing and what I I uh and
and why it's not a one thing is that the social emotion we have the positive ones
how we have them what they are Depends a lot on other qualities of heart and mind
that we have and those shift and change over time so to come to a conclusion
today this is what meta is uh might keep you from noticing how it shifts and
changes over time and one of the great joys for me or in doing Buddhist
practice now for these decades is to see that my understanding of love my
understanding of friendliness of Goodwill meta karuna all these things um
how it lives in me has shifted and change as other uh aspects of this practice Has Changed Me In in different
ways so for example um and how practice can CH has
changed me so sometimes you sit down to meditate and um I'm
preoccupied maybe I'm a little bit uh tense and spinning out in my thoughts
and I sit down and part of what mindfulness meditation is is getting out of the
way of ourselves so that how we are any given moment has a chance to be seen to
be known and to subtle and uh I've still to this day
I've noticed that my mind tricks me and uh and that is I'm involved in some kind
of intense thought and PR occupation and um and I think the the
whole world centers around that preoccupation I think this is the way it has to be and I have to fix this and
solve this or this person is so terrible and I have to do something and I'm kind of caught up in this world of
something and sometimes it's not interpersonal sometimes it's like um you know like there's not enough time and I
have to have I have to clean the house and have the dishes cleaned but I don't have enough time for it how am I going to do this and I'm rushing around trying
to do three things at once and and um and the world is in this thought bubble
of its own preoccupation so then I sit
down and it's still there but then it gets after a while it
gets softer gets quieter the shoulders go down the belly relaxes after a while
even the eyes relax and soften and I notice that my thinking has slowed down
and after a while those thoughts have stopped occurring and I'm there just with my breath in a simple way and the
pressure and the tension that was kind of compelling that earlier kind of thought is seen and known it's still
there but now it's just pressure my mind or somewhere and I just sit breathing with it getting out of the way of it
knowing it and it quiets down and settles and then when I finish the
meditation lo and behold I realized wow I was caught in a delusion before I
meditated I thought I was living in this thought bubble of that made its own
little Universe of what had to happen and what how things were and what things mean and all that but that was in its
own little thing that I thought was the truth and now I see it very
differently and so what I've learned is sometimes when um I feel like I don't have enough time for things is I'll sit
down and meditate for 10 minutes and after 10 minutes I have lots of
time it's remarkable who who who who had the true
view of reality the Gil who thought they didn't have enough time for things and
the one who sees lots of time after meditation is the after meditation one diluted because I'm just forgetting all
the list um and um so so things starts
settling and changing and my relationship to myself begins to change
so for example there can be um there can be self-criticism sometimes some people have
self-hate which is also one of those thought bubbles those little thought worlds we can live in and has its own
own authority has its own kind of inner Dynamics and working and uh sometimes
um you know they say um you can't solve a problem with the problem itself uh you have to kind of
step out of the problem to solve it so you know some something some some things that seem so intense and so important
and so true in the mind and how the mind thinks you have to find a way to step out of it to see something different so
meditation again can be one of those things there other ways of doing this just spending time at a park going for a
walk and being under trees some people being with a friend exercis that some
people can just do a little bit with but so some point the the um uh something
can shift that self-criticism and it's not we're not operating that's not the operating
principle anymore and then there's a different way of experiencing oneself and maybe at first it's just the
absence of self-criticism but then with time the tender heart the watery heart uh start
to be able to show itself it's been
eclipsed and then there can be a feeling of like it's feeling being content being at peace being calm being settled oh
it's good to be this way and then it starts becoming easier and easier to
view oneself as one's own friend to have friendship towards oneself to care for
oneself to have a positive view of oneself as that process goes deeper and
Fuller feeling finding a peace with oneself a contentment with oneself a
peace with the present moment a contentment with the present moment there's room for all kinds of uh other
positive emotions to arise one of them is a simple Delight a joy in being alive it's one of
the great wonderful aspects of meditation sooner or later some
sometimes it's later um to have uh the bubbling up of meditative Joy that's
there for no reason it isn't like you won the lottery or had the great date or or something
it's just because you're alive and you're just so so content and happy and who would have believe that you can be
happy without getting something you know getting praise or getting things or you
know something Pleasures the in the world but it's phenomenal to feel this
then when we we when you're with your friend your friend um you're not coming
to your friend with a need you're not coming with your friend
wanting something from your friend it's something wrong with having a need and wanting something from a friend at times
but imagine coming without a need and without wanting something from them and
feeling friendly for them a friendship that is without need for
me that's a g big gift to give someone imagine having love for
someone and you have love without a need for someone else imagine having in
love a feeling of friendliness of kindness of tenderness that has no
object that just there just like a joy that has has no reason there can be love
that has no object in particular it's just a state of kindness a state of
love and then your friend comes happens to walk into the middle of that bubble and so you're just loving but
it's not like you're like focused on them that you know that you're going to
have to get something from them and so loving kindness then creates a very different context for ethics
because so for example with uh uh romantic love sexual
love uh that usually comes with desire and nothing necessarily wrong
with that desire it's how how we live it how we live it is can be tremendously
harmful sexual desires we know I'm sure most people here have been harmed by
sexual someone's sexual desire once upon a time but the um or have harmed but the
um uh but if uh meta is the reference
point for romantic love then there's a reference point that is a kind of a love
a friendliness that is free of having to act on a desire it creates a different
reference point than desire desires can still be there but there's a whole other
attitude that then informs how we go about a relationship reltionship
so um and so but that that meta that has
that kind of is free of need free of Desire free of needing to prove
ourselves or get anything is a rare thing to have in this world but that is a phenomenal basis for
how we live a life of non-harming so part of what we do in
Buddhism is to celebrate our capacity for these
wonderful positive social emotions we emphasize the value of learning to
recognize them appreciate them when they're there and one one of the ways that we sometimes emphasize
this is look for the situations in your life where it's easy to have this look
for situation where it's easy to have a friendly attitude easy to have good will
that expects nothing in return look for situations where it's easy to be generous to
someone or compassionate or some for some people it's more difficult is to um share in
their Joy the appreciative joy and their success look where it's
easy and then from where it's easy be happy with it appreciate that
you have this capacity value it this is good and then again to expand it to more
and more people spread the circle to include not
just the people it's easy your family and your friends but start spreading it out to the people who are not your
friends not your family to people who are neighbors further away to people who
are you know who are acquaintances what does it take to have
this positive Goodwill this meta this uh caregiving concern for the wellbeing of
others what does it take to to go out onward and Order make your circle bigger
and bigger that's the exercise that Buddhism um uh
teaches as a way of universalizing our meta our love our
care our compassion and it goes even go so far as how do you cultivate meta for an
enemy and there there's no they don't they don't say anything about not having an
enemy somehow I guess they assume that there are there are people always going to be someone who can be an enemy but
even an enemy uh which seems like a really high bar that you would have some basic
Goodwill basic friendliness to them you might have a lot of caution around them
because they're your enemy so it's not like you have to kind of open your doors of your house and you know invite them
in but uh there is a kind of healthy Good Will that you can
have I remember once uh when uh someone was really angry someone I didn't know
very well hardly at all was really angry with me for uh nothing I had done but
somehow wanted to blame me for the the event and um and came over and was
yelling at me angrily and um and I stood there
listening and listening took a while and uh and I thought about where
what is the kind thing to do here what you know do I justify myself do I
explain myself and explain it away or do I say that he's wrong or what do I do here he gave me a lot of time to think
about it so that was
nice and um and so he finally stopped and uh with the most Good Will I could
have I looked at him and calmly said um you know when you speak that way
to me I feel afraid so there was no blame I wasn't like attacking him or just telling him
what was the effect it had on me because it was I had some fear but it wasn't like I was Fearless in in situation and
um but that's I said if I say that then I may be taking care of myself but also it's my way of not of having
some Goodwill for him some wanting not to criticize him but trying to open the door for some other way and in fact as
soon as he heard that he relaxed and he kind of I don't know if he apologize but he relaxed and kind of
brought the conversation to a close and left and um and uh
so that was my little exercise and trying to trying to find the Good Will
and trying to find how to be appropriate to take care of myself in this kind of challenging situation where at least for
that moment I I must have been his enemy the way he was talking to
me so um so to expand outwards but how do we do that not as I
should not as some kind of you know polanish way to kind of go around kind
of kind of seeing everybody this loveliness as if we were in a pretend
way and one of the ways is that is to become skilled through mindfulness
practice to understand how we um don't do
that part of what uh one of the really important principles of Buddhism is that
there are Buddhist ideals Like Loving kindness or meta peace equinity calm all kinds of
all kind no Buddhism has no shortage of ideals to to to carry as a
burden but um but the the way to uh experience these ideals is to is to be
mindful to study uh what interferes with them what gets in the
way you know I hate people that gets in the way of the love
so study the hate find out what's going on uh I I don't have time for people
because I need to become wealthy okay so then study that
ambition what's going on for you really stay present and meditation mindfulness
is one of the Laboratories for a deep taking a deep honest look at ourselves
to stop enough to really see what's going on and then we begin working through some of the things that
interfere one of the things that uh one of the very powerful things to begin realizing is to understand when we're
causing self harm to ourselves by our attitudes if we're spending a lot of
time being angry at others um they might not even know we're angry at them but
we're certainly harming ourselves uh if um if we're spending a lot of time you
know chasing after you know some kind of ambition and uh it's becoming stressful
for us and we're closing down to everything else we're being harmed from it and mindfulness creates a higher
heightened sensitivity to notice where we harm ourselves by our attitudes our
way of thinking our beliefs our actions the words we have and so as we can
seeing that and that settles down remember I talked about just sitting present getting out of the way and
seeing what's there but allowing it to settle and settle and quiet then we don't have the thing that
interferes with the ideal is no longer there and then what happens
then well then you thought you were supposed to be loving it turned out that's not what the situation called for
this situation called for Compassion or this situation called for
celebration or the situation called for simple generosity or the situation called for
doing nothing just sometimes it's you know to have you know people in this
situation I should leave this person completely alone that would be the best most kindest thing to
do so um so this idea of looking at what interferes so that U
meta so that we can respond with you know positive social emotions because
they are who we are not what we're trying to live up
to so friendliness is the basis one of the basis for Buddhist
ethics so we have a few minutes left I would love it if um you would take maybe
just a couple of minutes to share with another person if anything in this talk
Sparks something in interesting in you uh something that kind of oh that's an interesting idea around this topic of
meta and maybe you hadn't heard before maybe you have but it sparked something
and maybe if you turn towards maybe maybe you should do you know two one or two people in near you just but look
around make sure no one's left alone sitting there like we when everyone included and then just we'll do it about
four minutes or so and then I'll ring a bell and we'll come back for a minute here and if you don't want to do this of
course you can leave or or just sit
[Music] quietly well that sounded
like friendly conversations and
uh I feel a little apologetic that it gave you so little time for that conversation but you're welcome welcome
to stay now and continue there's no hurry to leave this morning I don't think there's a
children's program today there is oh there is 11:15 oh I see so yeah so you
could welcome to talk for about 15 minutes and then continue the conversations
outside and uh so thank you and um may
it be that our Reflections and our learnings about meta and all the different all the different forms they
can take that uh it helps people that we encounter feel
appreciated that we have a world where people are underappreciated and so let all people
be appreciated as we go through our day thank you