hello and welcome and I Delight in the greetings in the
chat the YouTube chat and both the greetings and uh all the locations that
people are connecting from and um I feel
kind of this a radiating field of
Goodwill from all these locations and so thank you for being part of
this uh many years ago I was very inspired
or encouraged by a and and and
uh a little bit Amazed by a very little simple Zen
teaching there's a Zen they have a lot of stories of
of uh practitioner students uh asking the Zen master a
question and someone asked um the Zen master uh what is the Gate of
Zen and I think on the surface of the question what is the entry way to to
Zen and uh and the teacher answered
generosity and that's it that's the end of the story and uh but why it struck me it
struck me two ways one was that generosity is the often seen as the entrylevel
experience uh practice Buddhism it's at the stage for everything
else and also because generosity because a gate is also the way you
leave you enter and leave a monastery through the gate and so you enter and
leave Zen you enter and leave Buddhism through the gate of
generosity you enter being generous and you leave being generous and this is also encapsulated
in a fantastic way that um that many of the kind of words for the great
relinquishment the great letting go we say in English uh that in poly in the
ancient language the word the word for letting go is more like giving away
it has the word generosity in it and actually there's a series of words for
the final deep release of
Liberation that uh has a double meaning to also mean generosity and uh to give something we
have to let go of something and uh we don't give and then hold
on and so the Gate of practice is generosity giving something giving some
releasing something so we'll sit with that today the idea of
generosity and um that we offer something that we
give and sometimes we give our love sometimes we live oura give our
care sometimes we give our Smiles sometimes we give uh
safety sometimes we give space sometimes we give
attention and all these forms things to be given are things given in
meditation we give our attention we give
space we give our respect we give our
care we give our generosity for each step along the
way to see it as an act of generosity not as an act of
accomplishment of getting something of attaining something or making something
happen so to assume a meditation process
posture and to gently close your
eyes and to sit here first evoking in
yourself the very best associations
feelings memories that you have for
generosity for being the recipient of a generous act for being
generous with someone
else and imagine that your generosity comes from
a from deep within you in a place inside which is
stable steady warm and
open and as you take some deeper breaths relax and settle
into some deeper place within
that's the foundation from which generosity is inspired
relaxing settling
in letting your breathing return to
normal and then to offer your body's experience of
breathing to offer it space provide breathing room for your
breathing so that the way you attend to the
breathing is not forceful not sharp and
pointed but light
gentle being generous to make room for the experience
of breathing welcome
and is there a generosity that's not of the mind it's
not something you have to think about but it's a
state of feeling the quality of the
heart or quality even deeper than that of the Torso or the
belly for
and whatever comes up into awareness whatever you know or
experiencing to take a metaphor step
back and have your attention to it be an act of
generosity as if seeing
knowing listening to what's
here is an expression of care care and good will
generosity where the practice is less about being
Mindful and more about offering a spirit of
generosity to all things that are present
for
for for
oh
for
for for
if mindfulness is an act of
generosity how would you be
mindful e
for
for for
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to consider as an thought
experiment if your biggest gift to the world the biggest benefit that you can
provide everyone including yourself is to spend the
day being generous with a spirit of generosity
everywhere you go
and where the generosity is
enacted with smiles of generosity
care opening doors for people making room for
people saying hello to
people but the whole day a day of generosity day of
giving how would that be for
you how would you end the day when you go to sleep a
day in which you abided in a state of generosity
may all
beings be put at ease with our
generosity may all beings feel safe in our field of
generosity where we don't want anything from anyone else
may all beings be
happy experiencing generosity as the
obvious first way in which they are
met May The Way We Walk Through This
World touch everything that we encounter
with a movement of generosity may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and may we contribute and environment that makes this
possible an environment of
[Music]
generosity thank [Music]
you
e e
so welcome to this third talk of a series titled to transform the
world and may it be that The Way We Walk Through This World contributes to it being um
becoming a better world and uh one of those
transformative steps that uh I think somewhere in all
cultures all religions emphasize the value of
generosity of giving and a marvelous Jaa tale kind of
a fable Buddhist Fable involves a um a little
parrot and um in the forest that the parot live lives in there starts a
gigantic forest fire and the animals run from the fire
but they run towards this huge body of water a lake where they can't
swim and uh so they become trapped between the they're going to be trapped between the fire and the
water and the parrot of course can fly but sees all this and a something has to be
done and so the parrot flies into the water to wet its wings and then over
this gigantic forest fire it flies above it and shakes its wings to the drops
fall on the fire and the
uh and so the um and over and over and over again this
uh parrot went and ripped these drops on the Fire
and so this was a great Act of generosity of compassion of care that uh
had such a cosmic effect that it warmed the Throne of the great God
Brahma and uh the the kind of great God Brahma said who is doing this wonderful
act that should warm my Throne so Brahma turned himself into an eagle and flew
down to Sea and found this parrot do over and over again sprinkling
water on the huge fire and the the as an eagle Brahma said
what are you doing and um and the parot said well I'm trying to
put out the fire to save all these animals in the forest and the eagle
said isn't that ridiculous that uh uh how could you with
just a few little drops over and over again have any impact on the fire and uh and the parrot said
um um uh it doesn't matter uh what matters is that I have to
do something I have to try to make a difference and um and this was so uh
this inspired Brahma to and so Brahma then created a big rainstorm and put out
the fire so this idea that to give even when
maybe giving or caring seems impossible and
um there's many stories in the that I've heard of um people the and instructions
when that there's conflict give give a gift don't give anger give a gift
there's a 50 years ago I read of um a community that lived high in the
mountains in the Philippines that have been living as they had done for many centuries and uh the custom of this uh
this community was when they wake up in the morning at breakfast they would tell
each other their dreams they had and if there was a dream about somebody else in
the community that that was um you know was somehow there was a conflict in
the dream of any kind something scary or difficult then uh the custom of the
community is that you would go and give a gift to that person and uh and this community
apparently was known to being a peaceful community known in the other neighboring
territories is living you know up in the mountains peacefully never causing any uh trouble for anybody else
and maybe this act of generosity was was what did it or there are stories of U uh
fables also of um of uh U you know an old poor woman coming
to um to you know
the maybe The Three Princesses of a royal family asking for some
arms and two of the older sisters give nothing but the younger sister gives
something and uh and that giving then transforms the the the fortune of the
younger sister in some dramatic way so there's many stories like this that
giving has a tremendous power but that of the parrot we give even if it's
hopeless we give because it transforms the world who knows who's watching who
knows the impact it will have uh to care for someone to offer something it's a uh
giving is a social lubricant giving is a way of
establishing safety warmth Good Will to others and often uh giving to the people
we're challenged with uh can disarm them it's
um it's uh uh you know it puts a crack in their
defense in their armor puts a cracker in their anger that uh it's hard to be
angry with someone who's given you a gift and it could doesn't have to be a big gift but here have this maybe it's
some cookies we baked at home maybe it's offering them a place at the table maybe
it's all kinds of things and um and uh
and why be generous one reason is that the opposite of generosity to be closed
to be closed to be held back to be
certainly to be miserly but to be just closed and tight or shut down from this
open-handed way of of uh living is actually harmful to ourselves it
actually limits ourselves diminishes our ourselves and so part of the reason to be generous is that it's good for us if
we give gener if we are generous in a healthy and wise way it doesn't have to
be giving away all our things it doesn't have to be big Act of generosity it can be done with gestures it can be done
with smiles it can be done with our attention it could be done
with uh you know things that uh uh you know don't cost
anything and um here can I bring you some water uh but to live generously so that
we feel a kind of release we feel a kind of handing over we don't hold on to
grudges we don't hold on to being closed it's a powerful act to be
generous and uh and it turns out that one of the many of series like three or
four of the different words that uh ancient Buddhism uses for to describe
the profound release of Liberation uh is um has a have dual
meanings not just one word but several word the most famous is the word chaga that means both uh letting go or
relinquishment and it means generosity to give so this uh uh this uh uh kind of uh
inseparability of Letting Go and
giving and letting go of whatever we're holding on to attached to through the
acts of generosity so uh we live in a difficult
world we live in a world where there's a lot of animosity a lot of fear a lot of
tension and it's not obvious you know the solution to the divisiveness of our
times but uh the viess of our times is the forest fire that we live
in and um and maybe each of us is a
parrot and maybe there's something that listens to the small parrot with its
little drops being generous in it in the best way only way that it knows how to
do it maybe something's listening profoundly listening that will come in
support and help this world of ours maybe a neighbor will notice maybe a
colleague will notice and maybe some of their anger some of their hostility will
diminish as they go home to their own family and maybe they're kinder to their
kids and that kindness to their kids maybe uh is the is the very thing that
prevents that kid to grow up in angry and bitter as well just as the parent did maybe
uh we don't know the effect of our acts of generosity and Goodwill on the people
that we encounter it might be profound the Ripple effects trust it and that's what the
story of Brahma this you know uh God uh that Lit that comes down to his
throne is warmed by the parrot's actions speaks to for me that there is um
that there is um something profound and unseen that we can't
see that is the consequence of how we live in this world in with our
generosity may it be that each of us acts generously no matter how strong the
fire is so that the ripple effect of
that results of which we might never see Trust TR those Ripple effects trust the
way it reaches out into the world be a parrot offer what you
can to make this world a better place thank you