so good morning good
day and in some ways some of us are here to today to befriend our
bodies to become intimate with our bodies
to not treat our bodies as something foreign to us something that we take for
granted and Ed to kind
of do the things that the Mind wants to do the self wants
to do can an object of
transport to reconcile or heal our relationship to
the body so it's not something to be aversive to or angry to
or [Music] or ashamed of or all kinds of
difficulties that people have with their
bodies but to have a healed relationship with the body so there's
no wound between you and your body there's no fear of the body no shame of
the body no anger there no ignoring of
it and one of the ways to do this is to listen to the body
deeply as if the body has a voice as if the body
has an expression that wants to be known to treat the body with tremendous
respect with care with love it
too wants to be known and maybe that's a little
bit my own kind of language for that but what something profound happens
when we make room in Awareness for the body to be
itself and to know the body from the inside out from the outside in we could treat
the body as an object and then we can have all these relationships with that object that
thing the body but to treat the body or care for
the the body as a subject From the Inside Out not from the ideas the
memories the histories the standards we judge it
by but from the inside out to allow the body to have its own
experience not mediated by how we compare our bodies to
other bodies don't compare ourselves to how our body was an earlier age in our
life where we don't relate to our body through our fears of what will happen to
the body without judgments just allow it to
be allow it to be itself and if you can allow it to be whatever it is for it to know
itself then there starts to be the wisdom of the body can operate the the
the way in which the body is a a river a stream a move of
movement of processing the body is not a thing it's a process the body is not a
singular event it's an ongoing unfolding and to allow that unfolding to
occur without interfering with our judgments interfering with our fixed
ideas interfering By ignoring it is a phenomenal
process tremendous amount of benefits can come from
that so we begin
by learning maybe not an easy task of how to have the awareness of the
body be simple
without strain without resistance without
judgment and one mode for doing that is to have a receptive attitude towards the
body allowing attitude towards the body as it
is in this moment while
meditating and then to that simple
awareness and then to ask the question as we're aware of
the particular parts of the body what the body is expressing what is this what is this
Sensations what what's happening here but not to get
a answer that you can talk about but rather to ask the
question as a way of kind of stepping Clos closer with open arms stepping closer with an open heart and open mind
what is this to let it register more deeply and this letting it register more
deeply what is going on here so that we begin
to move beyond the concepts the ideas the stories the judgments we have of the
body and we get to feel not the abstractions of Sensations happening but
get to feel the details of Sensations meaning the
particularity of hot and cold and stretching and pulling and moving
and flowing and and um and um hardness and softness all the
particularity not because we're straining to understand it but we're letting that particularity
register and so maybe we it's easy to
know so becoming friends with our body
assuming a posture that is not the posture you
think you should have but the posture you feel that the
body would like so that it can be fully present here for
you for itself a sense of a alert calmness in
the
body and to gently close your
eyes and take a moment in your own way to greet Tre your
body as if you're just just meeting after being aart for a
while checking in how are you what's going
on and in a way that just in a way that
feels nice for your body take some breathe more
deeply and relax on the
exhale
for
letting your breathing return to
normal and on the inhale
allow [Music] receive some part of your body where
there's some tension or hold holding and on the
exhale kindly relax the body
there
for
and then to Center yourself on the body's
experience of
breathing
and then to do a little exercise with exploring the sensations
of breathing what
Sensations Heralds the beginning of the
inhale what is the first Sensation that indicates your body is breathing in
in it might be a little relaxing and
expanding maybe in the belly the
diaphragm or it might be a little movement of pressure diaphragm pushes down
a little movement of expansion as the chest
expands or the first tingling in the nostrils as the
air gets pulled
in as you continue to feel the first sensations of breathing
in you might become aware of different ones there
first or maybe different on seem to occur simultaneously and you're naturally
aware of different ones different
breaths
and then what particular Sensations marks the end of the
inhale sensation of stopping
holding feeling of pressure or
tautness a momentary Stillness where there's no more
movement
and between the beginning and the end can you notice some unique
sensation there some sensation it might be the movements in your body tingling and
warmth expansion how's the breathing
experienced between the beginning and the
end very
lightly now receive the whole journey of the in
breath from the beginning middle and
end as if the windows open
and the rhythm of a breathing appearing blows gently through the
window relaxing any way in which you're straining or
tense so that aware Ness can be
receptive allowing the whole journey of sensations of in
breathing to reveal
itself
and then become aware of the first Sensation that Heralds the beginning of the
exhale maybe a release a
softening a
movement a warm tingling or sensation in the
nostrils a
pulling
becoming aware of the last sensation of
exhaling maybe the final sensations of exhaling
fade
away maybe there's a sensations of settling of
weight pressure or the release of
pressure and between the beginning and end of the exhale can you recognize a s
stion somewhere in the
middle maybe a small sensations of
movement or strengthening sensation of warmth
or tingling in the
nostrils
without being too concerned for the inhale for the next few
exhales allow yourself to feel be beginning middle and end of the
exhale
and now allow yourself to feel
receive the sensations are breathing in and the sensations are breathing
out remembering that sensing and Sensations occur in the same
place it's not something we do from the control tower but
rather an allowing to ourselves to feel what's happening in the
body and like the waves that wash up and down the Sandy
Shore follow watch be with waves of inhale and
exhale as sensation in the
body
for
rather than treating the [Music] body
with judgment or as a foreign body or as an
object that you judge or have stories
about relax and allow yourself to
experience the body's Sensations how the body speaks
speaks and listen
non-judgmentally allowing those Sensations to exist
peacefully without any conflict without being
ignored Maybe by feeling the sensations of your body
breathing
e
for
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to whatever degree that you could experience your
body non-judgmentally without a
story allowing it to be as it
is open that kind of awareness to this world of
ours and giving yourself permission for a few
moments here to allow the world the the world of
people to be as it is without your judgments without your stories
and projections of the future memories of what
happened just allow all things to be as they are at this
moment and you relaxed and open
breathing so
that your deeper heartfelt compassion for care and love and
kindness is unfiltered unobstructed by the stories
and the memories and judgments and fears and
desires and in the special circumstance of
meditation where we don't need to say anything to anyone or do anything for
anyone here to have unfiltered care unfiltered compassion love
[Music] kindness here
now with good will radiating from us in all
directions in front behind to the
sides radiating Good Will May all beings
be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful May may all beings be
free and may the peaceful Good Will that
we end this meditation with may that be the
beginning of bringing Good Will into this you into this
world may all beings be
[Music]
free thank you
so this will be the fourth talk on mind fulness of the body
and an analogy I like to use that um is directly connected to the body is
the body's capacity to heal itself from a cut you might be in the kitchen
chopping vegetables and do a little cut in your finger
and you your job is to keep the cut clean to clean it maybe protect it with
a Band-Aid to keep dirt out of
it but um and then the body can has a
best circumstances in which to heal itself if
um um so our job is to kind of get out of the way but keep it protected
we can't engineer the healing probably no one knows all the different all the different physiology
of healing a cut that goes on but uh the body knows how to do
it so there's all this capacity the body has of healing itself of coming back
into homeostasis coming back into peace calm that if we can get out of the way
and allow for the body's wisdom and innate capacities to operate a lot of
things can benef can happen I've been by with people who have
died and uh sometimes it's remarkable to see uh people's faces right after
they've died because the muscles relax and uh and there's a sometime
occasionally a deep sense of Peace in the face because tension they've been carrying in the facial musculatures have
finally released we get little bit the same kind of at the end of a 7-Day Retreat when we
see people's faces after seven days of meditation so much as softened in the
face and they haven't been focusing on relaxing the face it's just the circumstances of of the retreat of
leaving on themselves alone very deeply allows something to relax and um and maybe little bit heel
in the face in the muscles of the body everywhere so the the uh the body has a
capacity to relax to heal sometimes the body is the first it
gives a feeling of discomfort when something feels wrong something doesn't feel quite right and there's a kind of
feeling of um tension or anxiety in the belly or little pressure or something feeling oh
this is not right and it might that body might know that before the mind has
understood it and uh some people have learned to really pay attention carefully when the body gives this
feeling something's not right here and then by paying attention we discover what it
is so the ability to allow the body its own
process uh gives us access to a lot of uh
Capa much more capacity for health for healing for wisdom for
spirituality than if if all those things are negotiated only with the mind and
part of the reason for that is that the mind all too easily is
hijacked by stories by judgments by Memories by fears by desires by
aversions hatred all kinds of things the mind gets caught up in and concerned
with and as it said it's in Buddhism that sometimes the mind is like a
puppeteer that has these strings from the fingers of the Mind down into all the different muscles and um and some
things that uh some ways of thinking um actually uh create tension
in the body maybe that sometimes a severe tension chronic chronic tension
in the body and you the advantage of being getting calm in meditation is to
then to notice on when we start thinking about something and the impact it has on the body the tension that comes
in and um and starting to appreciate that how what a strong role
the thinking mind has on interfering with the body's own
capacities and so as we meditate the idea is to um no longer experience the
body through the filter of all our thoughts and stories and memories and history but begin to
receive and allow for the body's experience of itself and there's as I've been doing
here sometimes I use the language of allowing and receiving and that's sometimes very
helpful but there's a limit to how much allowing receiving accepting you want to do because
sometimes that lends itself to being very general and kind of have a generalized kind of sense of experience
here and now the deepening of mindfulness meditation comes when we in
this relaxed open allowing awareness we allow things to touch the soft tens
tender part the sensitive part of awareness and really we get to know it
well feel it well and uh recognize what it is as I put my finger on the softest
more sensitive part of my palm then it's not just feeling a finger which is a
kind of abstraction there's feelings of warmth feelings of pressure softness little bit
of uh radiating warmth and a little bit of uh little bit of texture there a
little bit of um uh elasticity there's a little bit of pressure there
there's all these very particular Sensations the deepening of osna
practice comes when we com combine this kind of relaxed and soft receptive
awareness that is not filtered with carried not carried by or influenced by
a lot of thoughts ideas concepts of what is to really start feeling the
Simplicity of the moment of the actual Sensations themselves so even if I put
my finger against my palm and and and if someone says what are you experiencing
and I say I'm experiencing my finger touching my palm that's not exactly what I'm
experiencing that's the concept of finger concept of palm yes they're
touching that's the that's what's happening but the experience the
sensations is not the finger sensation is not the palm the sensation is the
warmth the pressure the elasticity the texture um the the pleasure that I feel
in that contact those are the sensations and the same thing happens
with pain that um uh pain is a little bit pain is real for sure but it isn't
the word pain is an abstraction and uh and if we stay at the abstraction it's kind of like saying the
experience of the finger against the palm um it's not actually what's happening what's literally happening is that there
might be intense piercing or shpat or um
uh twisting or stabbing Sensations there might be a very you know that there's
the pain is there's many different kinds of pain and uh and so what's which kind of
pain is it now and to feel the sensations of it the advantage of doing
that with anything including pain is that as as long as we stay little bit
separate by the concepts the idea of what it is and not in the sensations we're not allowing ourselves that
intimacy that to allow that deep sense of way in which awareness makes room for
those Sensations to unfold to do what they want to do and that is one of the
great Arts of inside meditation is to be so close to the experience in a gentle
soft relaxed way that it's almost as if the awareness make know is not writing
tightly on top of our experience concerned with it struggling with it but rather the awareness is a great open
space that allows things to unfold to unravel to open up to shift and change
as they need to do so it's like uh creating room mind is like creating
space so it's not just a moment of mindfulness we want it's like
oh uh warmth and then allow that warmth to be felt pressure allow the pressure
to be felt um uh pleasure allow that pre the pleasure
to be felt not for the sake of of experiencing it for oneself but rather
to allow the sensations room so that they can move along and do what's next
all Sensations are processes all Sensations are in movement and active
and dynamic and to start living in that Dynamic place that's one of the
functions of deeper inside practice and so what I'm teaching today is a stepping
stone step towards that capacity it's not necessarily easy to rest there
but it's part of mindfulness of the body is to begin uh finding ourselves not
with a gener generaliz general presence for the body but with a relaxed
receptivity to the particularity of the sensations in the body so today in the guided meditation
we did this exercise to do that with the breathing and the breathing is part of
mindfulness of the body and to start allowing oneself to kind of get absorbed by the particular
Sensations that come into play like the Kaleidoscope or the the of these Sensations that flow through as we
breathe in and flow through as we breathe out and
um and uh it's kind of like getting out of the way while feeling in feeling it
intimately getting out of the way where we're really connected we're allowing for the particular sensation s to play
their dance not the general idea of breathing but the actual particularity
of Sensations so um we'll continue with this tomorrow so
if this didn't make so much sense to you don't worry uh the um it might be they
whatever you understood from what I taught today just kind of even if you didn't know how to apply it uh just just
kind of store it away for now and with time I think it'll become clear uh that
how this works in a way that's not a strain not a lot of effort and work so um we'll have one more day on
mindfulness of the body and we'll do a little bit more on this idea of Sensations and uh and that'll set the
the foundation for uh a way of practicing mindfulness of emot
tions and um I won't be here next week so the week on emotions will be in two
weeks and um with this uh what first the breathing last week and body this week
all this sets the ground for um for a wise way of being with
emotions so thank you very
much