okay hi folks welcome um yeah lovely to uh to see see
your uh names and uh be with
you so um we'll do the usual thing I'll say a few words and uh sit and then offer a
DED and uh I think last time last time the inaugural group last time my
meditation instructions were something like uh attention attention is just an
appendage of our wanting there's stress in trying to find
but relief in being found it's like what does that even mean
you know really those are the opening meditation
instructions but um sometimes we get more vague and
impressionistic sometimes more concrete this week tacking back towards the
concrete and so um intention intention
intention to put down greed and distress with respect to the world you know in a
way it's like um we sort of have to have equinity before
we've even developed it right but that's that's uh the instruction we put down as
best we can greed and distress with respect to the world that's the that's the
intention and that means we're we're just actively
relinquishing the intention to solve our problems right the way in which
meditation becomes the workpace for our kind of problem
solving uh we relax that energy and we offer up our kind of heart
to the moment trusting that the moment will do good things to
it so intention and then attention
attention we set the the kind of the anchor for
the attention the the we set the anchor for the attention you typically and we set a kind of aperture
aperture right um where the attention is and how the aperture how wide the kind
of Spotlight of attention is it's not totally right but generally
The Wider the aperture the more more concentration is
required in order to stay out of auditory thinking the narrower the aperture it's
it's not easier it's not a lot easier but it's a little easier uh to there's a little lower
level of concentration needed to to stay out of uh auditory thinking so there's
there's where we place the attention the aperture okay just at the tip of the you know it's breathing but it's not
breathing here it's breathing right here narrow aperture for
example and then we're nurturing a certain kind of vividness
vividness and uh yeah that means like a very um yeah well we know the difference
between dull and Vivid right Vivid this is a a kind of uh experience of our of
sensor sense the sensory World in vividness and we're stabilizing the
attention we're stabilizing the attention uh so that the you know the
telescope is not shaking as much right we we don't choose to do that but but
we're this is um we're cultivating this kind of stability of the
attention and then the fourth piece um is is effort effort the kind of
subjective impression that we have about our current attentional state how easy it or
difficult is it to sustain right we have to modulate that
often the effort right it's like I said vividness I said stability right but
that doesn't mean the effort gets out of control right we modulate the effort too
not too tight not too loose what kind of effort is actually entailed in this practice what what
actually supports you and uh we were're that's a kind of not
constant but often often we're modulating that
right and how do we uh make a kind of
effort that feels sustainable right that generally we kind of we don't want to be
uh burning you know the more kind of effortful our practice is the more we
get this kind of whiplash of real depletion where the attention totally needs to go slack so how can we make a
kind of sustained effort while nurturing these these qualities of uh of vividness
of stability how is the
effort uh of Letting Go different from the effort to make
something happen right the effort of
receiving the effort of listening to the silence feeling into the Stillness that's different kind of
effort than engineering silence engineering
Stillness engineering anything so
um so with this as a kind of preface Let's uh let's sit
together
e
so in whatever ways you can reassure
yourself it's okay for
this period to contribute nothing to the
solution of our problems to the resolution of the first Noble
Truth to the complexities of Being Human we just put it
down rather than extract something from the moment we offer oursel up to
it
we just kind of treat our life for these
minutes is good enough treat the moment as good enough
the energy around maximizing optimizing you
just relax it with that drain into the
ground
we uh place the attention
somewhere maybe uh our breathing or our body more
broadly maybe the soundscape maybe let the soundscape run
right through your head and include external sound and the internal sound that we call
thinking but the attention has a place to
rest and the how of our attention
Vivid
stable but not vivid and stable by making an effort born of clinging not
vivid and stable making an unsustainable
effort
gently nurturing investing our our interest in the object of
attention
e
and when we become identified with the
thought mind wandering kind of
Daydream the uh sense of attentional agency
collapses we just live inside the content of that
thought and then we wake up it feels like the attentional agency
is restored
and then maybe we pit one part of oursel against
another the our fault for uh being
lost but uh this is uh unnecessary
it's all the same
mind so we reestablish that kind of intimacy some
vividness some stability with the anchor of attention
modulate uh the effort up down slightly
different or the
same keep
going
e
these last um few minutes just
uh noticing the mind in a in a kind of holistic
way
in a sense uh move from very concrete anchor to something like the
anchor is uh is everywhere Maybe we say
nowhere just notice all that can be
noticed
e
for
okay good to uh stay with
you so over
uh over the year uh teaching a lot of a lot of um Pain's
been shared with me in one one way or another
and that pain uh has the quality of being both uh
sacred and uh and quite ordinary and some of the the the pain
that's been shared are things that I've directly experienced that uh
know directly and then some some of the pen or things I've not known must infer
must draw from other experience to better
understand and uh when I'm receiving
something like that somebody sharing that in a conversation retreat
something you know I try to uh convey
from my own being from the kind of from the Stillness in me what I try to convey is
this I'm unafraid of your
pain I I will not diminish uh the sorrow
but I'm unintimidated by your pain that's what I wish to
convey and of course I feel it it resonates with my
own pain we feel its weight together
right but I'm not scared by it and I'm not scared by you and that feels
important because people uh need to learn to trust
TR their own capacity to to heal people need to know like oh yeah me
too me too like I am I am also included in the Buddhist
Grace and there's this very I don't know
um kind of yeah sort of an um intriguing way
that that our pain gets threaded together
with uh shame I why is it like that I don't I
don't really know but our wounds and our shame somehow become
one and it's um it's odd in a way that
what most needs compassion somehow becomes the object of
Shame right but um the need that's bound up that's
expressed in our pain somehow that needs to be that need must be hidden must be
hidden and I've read that um evolutionarily um shames sometimes
considered an appeasement display like in the kind of social
history of our animal species like shame is is
uh yeah is an appeasement display it's like I submit I'm hurt don't hurt me
right you know that kind of gesture of a of a a dog or something submissive dog
that rolls exposes their belly as like I
submit and it's hard to be uh to be seen
in in our our pain it's vulnerable quite vulnerable to be
witnessed and something in US often feels like we must hide we must
hide and uh and so so much of Dharma is about normalizing suffering normalizing
suffering D stigma izing it and draining some of the shame that
gets threaded together with the wound and shame always has a kind of an
audience even if that audience is just the internalized harsh gaze we want to see
like okay what's the what through what eyes am I perceiving my pain that
compounds a sense of Shame and so it can be very
um healing to have uh to have our pain witnessed without uh yeah just in a
field that is devoid of Shame
and it's almost like um as we begin we have to treat our pain as like uh as
sacred but then as the shame begins to melt as the shame begins to melt
the the pain becomes very very ordinary it loses its electric
charge now to to to actually receive
another's pain to actually receive another's pain we must know our own with
Incredible vividness to loop back to that word to deeply know our own
suffering our own pain to to experience it a thousand
times with with a lot of vividness uh because until
we uh become unintimidated by our own pain we remain afraid of others the pain
of others may be afraid of them in some
way this is um Norman Fischer from uh training training
and compassion if you've ever been ill he writes uh physically or emotionally
or otherwise in need of compassionate caring you may have noticed that many
people will offer help and kind words but somehow most of these offerings seem
either insincere or otherwise miss the mark they don't feel good they don't
help it's as if these people though they clearly meanwhile and their offers are
touching are not capable of really receiving your pain they want to make you feel better
help you somehow by offering remedies and recommendations cheerful words or
distracting gifts but they seem unable or unwilling to do what you need them to
do to Simply feel and acknowledge your pain they want to be
compassionate but they can't seem to do that and so their presence makes you
feel more lonely and isolated in your Misfortune this is because they are
actually terrified of their own pain and you can feel that they are also
terrified of of your pain even though of course they would never say so and may
not even realize they are feeling
this as we sit as we sit and as
we struggle with optimizing maximizing the moment looking
for Spiritual pleasantness of one kind or another we miss we we we can miss Dua
suffering we can miss experiencing it with uh
vividness and the precondition for empathy the
precondition for empathy is having a very rich Vivid experience to
know our own suffering in an undefended way to know it time and time again
again the Buddha said comprehend Dua
comprehend DOA comprehend to really know to really
know and to really know Dua doesn't mean we marinate in our pain it means the
that that suffering pain difficulty is is we know it in
Awareness we really cannot understand Dua if we're identified with
it we we we will not experience we can suffer vividly but we will not
comprehend suffering vividly unless there's
space and the the space of awareness is what's
necessary and so suffering we come to see suffering
and understanding suffering are very different very
different and how many opportunities do we have to comprehend Dua count the ways
right and so as we we um come to to understand
understand Dua to comprehend it uh part of what happens is we become
less intimidated by it we begin to drain out the the kind of
the moralism that's that's so often attached to our own our own pain the
kind of uh the shame the shame yeah and when
when we um when we do that when we we begin to comprehend Dua to really become
unintimidated by it then we can begin to offer
others our confidence because we've swam in that pool many times we know those
Waters we may not know exactly their suffering uh but but we have had the
Vivid experience of of swimming in those Waters in one way or
another and as we become less intimidated by our own pain we can gaze
upon the the pain of another
and just um see innocence in a
sense maybe they we say they the opposite of Shame
innocence we gaze upon the pain of another and
see uh See the Dharma the unfolding of
suffering freedom from suffering and we offer our kind of
heartfelt uh conviction that um
uh that pain is practice that there's a kind of
innocence in it and
uh that our heart actually can be nurtured by it rather than corroded by
suffering so I offer this for your uh consideration and uh please please uh
please pick up whatever is is useful leave behind the rest and
uh uh I uh wish you all a good uh good week
yeah may we uh may we be happy