welcome welcome nice to see you
all here on a Monday night on a rainy day well it was rainy
earlier so I'd like to start uh tonight's talk by sharing a short little
story that ended up having a big impact on me and I didn't quite appreciate
the magnitude of the impact until quite some time later this was uh back when I was
working in Corporate America and I remember like just being upset or angry
or you know I don't remember the details but I just remember being upset about something that you know somebody had
done and I was telling my friend I was complaining and I was
saying yeah well you know this person said this and and because that person
doesn't like this other person then they sent this email and because that email
happened then this other person came to my office and you know like all this kind of stuff you know all this like stuff happening cuz said this happened
that happened and you know this and I had a whole story of why it happened
well this person thinks that they know everything therefore they did blah this other person never pays attention
therefore they did blah or you know some I was kind of like attributing like you know all those uh motivations or
something like them something like that to these individuals and why I was being you know poor me poor dieta this bad
thing happening and my friend like bless her
heart she said wow that's quite something
Diana so let's see if we can come up with another story that's the same facts
this person said that you got an email and somebody was in your office I'm like
what do you mean another story no this is what happened is the truth it's not a
story this is what actually happened she said okay make three other
stories of what happened I'm like I don't understand she said well let's just make it up how do you know that
that person didn't send you an email because uh they had just got really bad
news from home and they were upset because somebody in their family is really sick and that's not maybe that's
why they sent you that email not because somebody had said this and didn't all that kind of stuff I thought
oh I didn't really think about that I was kind of thinking I had it all figured out like why something it
happened and just this recognition of like oh yeah there are like we could say facts there are events measurable
objective events that happen but then we try to make meaning out of them we weave
them together of course we do this is what humans do of course we do and U there's this person Kim Hamlin
Hart she's a life coach I don't know her she has something written on the
internet that I thought was really great and I'd like to share this she talks
about the same thing about uh how we can like make different
stories that uh based on you know our
experience so again this is Kim Hamlin heart it's not me but she says let's assume the fact
that my mother Kim hlin Hart's mother um was distant and unhappy that was just
her experience of her mother while she was growing up her mother was distant and
unhappy and and She lays out okay well what are some different stories that she can make about
this and here are how it goes my mother was distant and and
unhappy she didn't love me and because she didn't love me I am
unlovable this is a story we could make my mother was distant and unhappy she
was broken and incapable of giving much love and I didn't get the type of love I
craved but I am worthy of love and I'm worthy of
belonging regardless of my mother's inability to love me it's another
story here's the third one my mother was distant and unhappy it was because of
something I did I am responsible for her unhappy
life I need to do everything I can to make her and those around me
happy another story that could be said here's a fourth
one my mother was distant and unhappy I didn't get the love I
needed she ruined my life I can never be whole or happy
because the love I was denied as a child another way we could interpret
this my mother was distant and unhappy because I didn't have a model of
how to interact emotionally I can't get in touch with my emotions and express them in a healthy
way and I can't
change here's another story my mother was distant and
unhappy because because I didn't have a model of how to interact emotionally I struggle with my own
emotions however I can learn and grow and figure out a way to get in touch
with my emotions and express them in a healthy way let's see how many of these are
there's one two three four five six wait did I last count here six or seven six
six different ways to interpret this like one thing my was distant and unhappy I just love this right because
we probably all know people maybe we are one of them that like have kind of like adopted a story around their what
happened to them when they were younger and this recognition of like oh yeah the same facts quote
unquote we could make a whole bunch of different
stories and there's something terrifying about this and there's something
beautiful about this I would say and so I'd like to talk
about this idea of you know stories and making stories and this one of like this list
of however many stories I said we don't want to say that one is right and one is wrong that's not at all what we're
talking about here that's like irrelevant whether right or wrong they're just something that we might a
away we might interpret to make meaning of our experience and some of them are more
helpful than for us to have a big full Rich beautiful life and some of them are
less helpful in that helpful unhelpful there we're not talking about right or
wrong I don't want to go that direction but I think there's a way in
which whatever story that we adopt whichever story that we believe becomes the truth for
us it's a way in which we view the world in which we interpret our other
experiences the way that we um expect some cap our own capabilities what we
are capable of what we're not capable of what we can do what we can't do whether the world is safe it's unsafe or these
types of things and so we might ask a little bit
well what what is this uh stories and there's a way in humans we
are there's a way in which we're kind of like driven to make sense to make meaning of our emotions and our
experiences this is what humans do and I remember being on a long retreat many
months and uh just the mind getting just really quiet and just starting to see
like oh yep there'd be a thought and then like maybe like a physical
sensation maybe like like another like physical sensation and then I could just
kind of like watch how oh yeah I was tying all these things together to make
it mean something but I also noticed that that making the meaning is
extra actually it doesn't have to happen we feel this uh we feel pulled to do it
and I'll talk a little bit about why but it's actually we don't have to do it we
don't have to uh make a meaning and then believe it and hold on to it and say this is
true instead we can say well this is kind of what makes sense to me right now
this is my provisional understanding this is my hypothesis this is what makes
sense to me at this moment as opposed to saying this is the truth this is how it
is and then not even thinking about it just assuming that that's the truth and then you know continuing on just with
that assumption that might not be so helpful for
us so there's a way in which we want to make meaning and these meanings are
expressed as our beliefs our perspectives our attitudes our biases
our mindsets our views all these things kind of get influenced by these stories
the ways that we're we knit together experiences to make a narrative and we
might say that these stories that get created and that turn into beliefs and perspectives and Views are a way in
which we are how we like evaluate or judge experiences things
people the way that we justify our behavior all of these are from the
stories that we have so there's this way that uh the
stories kind of have implicit like this is good and that's bad this is better
that's worse and so much of our life might be constricted by this idea of this is good
and that's bad I can do this I can't do that I'm good I'm bad and not recognize that those are
based on experiences that we had and I'm
using this word story that we created this meaning that we created out of it and I would say that much of what we
take as you know culture and civilization is about these stories because this is what humans do it's not
a like I said it's not a problem so there's a way in which you
know our personal stories but we also have societal cultural stories this a big part of what we can
say maybe what civilization or culture is is part of this collection of
stories and we might even say that like these
days in these uh modern contemporary times there's a way in which we are
often kind of like stuck in our stories the way is we as a maybe even as
a culture where we could say that we are as committed to our stories as ever maybe even more like we are holding on
to them so tightly refusing to even uh entertain the idea
that in fact they might be stories but in some ways we're so involved with uh
our stories and we can see this showing up in so many different ways the ways in which social
media is uh a some people what they post right with there's platforms
specifically designed for this so you can have a curated story that people
think think about you and there's a way in which you have this story about yourself that you're going to show the world in order to be a good person or
valuable person lovable person I need to curate what I'm going to show and therefore this is what's uh going to be
there and I'm going to put on social media or maybe there's this way in this conspiracy theories these days right
that's a way in which people make stories and try to make sense of
events in a way that makes I don't it makes them feel better in some kind of
way and then these conspiracy theories like even though there are different uh
conflicting information somehow these conspiracy theories really can take a
hold and people kind of like you know issue things uh that doesn't support
them identity politics is a part of this
too we versus them US versus them me versus you I'm like this and you're
not like this you're like that I'm like that you're like this
whatever it is it's part of this way in which we as a community as a culture these days we're really tied um holding
on tightly to our stories and maybe I don't know maybe it's partly because we
get are getting exposed to so many different stories maybe there than earlier than we did I'm sorry did
differently than we did like if we think about 100 years ago I mean just the
internet didn't exist so we weren't as exposed to so many different stories and we probably were just um surrounded More
Often by people that were similar to us to the whole idea of story maybe
didn't even make sense but there's this way in
which the story promises like truth and certainty
which kind of like promises like some security like oh yeah okay this is true I can rest here knowing this I don't
have to have any doubt I don't have to wonder about things I can rest here I can feel secure I can feel safe here in
this story and so we want like big stories that like explain
everything it's kind of frightening to think like this doesn't make
sense wait I I thought things were this way and turns out they're another
way again I can speak from my own experience many of you know I'm trained as a scientist I worked as a scientist
for quite some time spent my days in a research laboratory wearing a white coat gloves test tubes the whole
thing and then you know I had like some glimpses of something that that uh some
and some meditative experiences I'm like oh that doesn't fit in my
worldview and it was a little bit uncomfortable not a little it was very uncomfortable like wait hm how how do
how do I hold this how does this make sense and you know here I am these years
later I'm no longer working as a scientist but here as a Dharma teacher
but it's uncomfortable so we want stories that promises truth and
uncertainty but you know these the promises never deliver they never deliver because this
truth and the certainty that we're looking for doesn't isn't showing up in the way that we would like
it we want things to be like constant and reliable and always there
and things change we all know this there a part of
us always know this but there's nothing that's like always reliable somehow we want like to know
the master story that's the one true story that's going to explain all the other
stories and we might even say that essential to this master
story is the denial that it's a story that's like integral of this
master story like no no no this is the truth it's not a story
and then so what is the story that Buddhists have about
stories of course Buddhists aren't immune from the either it's bunch of humans so the stories that Buddhists
have about stories is that you shouldn't be deluded by stories that's the story
that Buddhism has that is don't
uh don't believe everything that you think and in fact there's a way in which
we can see through the beliefs we can see through the subtle
narratives and the obvious narratives and Buddhism talks about and
especially in this tradition talks about right some of you
may have heard this really story that gets uh told a lot which I actually really like where the bu says well the
Dharma that is like the teachings is like a raft it can take you from if you're here
on this shore of this water where it feels uh scary and
uncertain and you can have the sense that over there on the other side of this raging River or whatever body of
water might be is will be some safety and you have this sense like okay if I just get over there it'll be safe
safe and the Buddha is saying there is some safety it's not the way that we
think it is but the Dharma is a raft that we can carry it or sorry it carries
us the other side but when we get
there do we think like wow this raft was really helpful okay I think I'm going to take
this with me wherever I go and we put it on our shoulder and just carry this raft around wherever we go on the land you
know carrying the raft right no that would be silly so this recognition that even the
Dharma takes us to the other side but even something like that we can't really we can't hold on to it's not the their
always in a stable constant way that we may sometimes
wish and there's a way in which recognizing as I said earlier that
things are stories that we have narratives or views there's a way in which this can be really frightening but
it also can be really liberating there's a way in which it can
help bring us some freedom because this there's a way in
which we have this um some of the stories that we use are
like who I am as a person I'm the one that's like this I'm
the one that's not like
that I said that I was trained as a scientist and I worked as a scientist that's a little bit different than
saying I am a Scientist so this sometime I used to definitely think I was a scientist
through and through but then to recognize no I was trained and I lived that life and you
know but that's different than just taking it on board or that I'm a Dorma
teacher sometimes I sit here on Monday nights give Dharma
talks other times I'm not a Dharma teacher I'm a grocery
Shopper dishwasher vacuumer these types of
things so we all have um identities that shift and change some of them move shift
uh really slowly over time maybe some of them shift really
quickly but there's a way that um David ly who is a zen teacher he
writes one meaning of freedom is the opportunity to act out the story I
identify with one meaning of freedom is the
opportunity to act out the story I identify with I appreciate this very
much I identify this way and this is how I want to show up in the world right there's not everywhere in
the world where you can do that but that's a one type of freedom to be able to do
that another type of freedom is the ability to change
stories and my role within them so this ability to move from like a
scripted character to a way in which kind of like the co-author of my life and who are the
other authors kind of like society and our communities so another way of freedom is
to ability to change the stories and then here's a third type of
Freedom these are all freedoms a third type of Freedom that this is what the
Buddhists are pointing to that results from understanding how
stories construct and constrict my possibilities the
possibilities that I think for myself they construct and
constrict sometimes we might think well I'm a person like this therefore I can't do that I'm trained as a scientist
therefore I'll never be a great artist who knows I haven't tried it
yet there's a way in which the you know the stories we make them as I was talking to earlier based on facts things
that actually happen but sometimes they are constricting Us in ways that we
don't even recognize and so there's real freedom to recognize oh yeah there's a story that's
getting created and maybe it's a story that helps support me but maybe there's also
a way in which it constricts me so we just hold them lightly we just told them
lightly instead of insisting that they are the truth because the truth is very often the stories don't really help us
in the way that we want them to I mean they might help us to keep our like life
on Keel or or in an even Keel or something like
as we're making sense of our experiences but they seldom offer like new insights
about how to understand the world or stories seldom offer greater
Clarity instead it's just you know a story that we made up about something sometimes they do but
sometimes they don't offer much well-being there's just a way that they
there's a way it's kind of like diminish us and there's a way in which stories
they really Bubble Up or they really kind of make themselves known or get created or constructed in a way when
we're feeling agitated when we're feeling unwell or
bothered or disturbed stories show up when we act
out of habit well I need to do this because I I will always be like this cuz my mother was unhappy and didn't love me
or something like this but here's something that when we get lost in the content of our stories we
stop being present for what's actually happening here stop being present for
the experiences that we're having right now and there might be a way in which
we're thinking like okay well I'm waiting for some experience to be worthwhile to pay attention
to why not this moment why not pay attention at this
moment it turns out real freedom is here if we're always waiting for the perfect conditions or as soon as that other
thing happens just right now it's good
enough there can be some real ease and freedom that arises if we are just paying attention this moment and this
moment and this moment
so what are some ways in which we can see these stories that I'm pointing
to there's a few ways one if you're doing a meditation
practice do mindfulness of breathing this is a common practice A lot of people do I do this I often teach
it there's a way in which we often can um have this feeling like I'm breathing
and it feels like this like this is just there's a sense of like I'm
breathing as opposed to the sense of breathing is
happening there's a way and sometimes we say like it's raining but we don't really say what is raining we just say
it's raining that's a kind like the way we're describing the weather
pattern so is there a way instead of putting a self at the
center can we say it's uh breathing is happening instead of saying I'm
breathing this is a subtle difference that I'm playing with language here but it can be really
powerful and there's this story that um was trying to remember this uh Jack
petrer that he is quoting uh some somebody else when he's talking about this idea of how the stories that we
make so often have ourselves at the center and the selves at the center
turns out not to be as it tends to be one of the ways in which we constrict
ourselves so as I said dck Pat traner um points to something that's a
naturalist Barry Lopez and he was on this Journey with some indigenous people up in the north and he's describing how
he uh would work with a an event versus the indigenous
people if my companions and I for example were hiking and encountered a grizzly bear feeding on a caribou
carcass I would tend have focused almost entirely on the
bear my companions would focus on the part of the world of which at that
moment the bear was only a fragment my Approach was mostly to take
notes of objects in the scene the bear the Caribou the tundra a series of dots that
I would try to make sense of by connecting them all with a single rigid
line my friends in contrast had situated
themselves within a dynamic event there approach was to let it
continue to unfold to notice everything and to let whatever significance was there to
emerge on its own so you can see how the person who's
speaking here Barry Lopez he's like here observing the bear the carcass the
tundra like he's located himself in one location everything else is out there
whereas the indigenous people are we're just this this whole thing is
unfolding themselves were part of the experience was unfolding and they were allowing what
was significant to emerge like this is this is what's happening right
now as opposed to saying making a story and like okay that bear killed this
caribou and that happened or that happen and kind of like removing themselves but there's a way in which removing
themselves is also the way in which they make themselves the center because everything is like from a distance to
the self that be instead of this experience that Caribou instead of
whatever is happening here in the future if anybody's listening to me rather than uh watching
me with my hands what I'm saying this I'm trying to like
gesture I don't know like how would I describe this like a including my
physical body as well as all the space around me is kind of like this as
opposed to there's only this physical body and everything else out there is
separate so one way we can notice how we tend to do this is even with our meditation
practice just to play around with language and just to say like breathing is happening and to just notice the
experience instead of having this real sense of I'm breathing I better meditate how how I've
uh how am I doing I've been doing this for 10 breaths I used yesterday I only did it for eight breaths so I'm doing
better you know something like that just to be with the
experience and maybe there's a way in which um because sometimes we might say
and I teach this way sometimes because it can be helpful but it also can trip us up like sometimes to have the sense of
like okay I am going to place my attention on the breath but that again
is kind of like making a self at the center so that's one way we can notice
the stories is just uh notice a subtle ways in which we can we make ourselves a
center and often how we're doing that is making things be objects where here's
this the self is the subject and others are the object another way a very different
way is there's a way in which stories have this uh linear temporal continuity
that is you know a led to B led to C led to d That's a way in which kind of like
stories unfold this is part of what makes them delightful and fun and gives
us maybe a little sense of security but if you look at your
experience experience I'm not talking about thinking about it I'm talking about
experiencing you'll notice that let's say let's come back to like this idea of
breathing notice a breath notice another
breath oh yeah I have to remember to take the clothes out of the washing machine so that's little thing about the
future and then uh oh yeah a breath another breath not like that time I left
them in and got all M Dey and that was horrible and the little flash to the past and then you know breath the he
breath so if we are TW if you can get a little bit settled and pay attention
you'll notice that our experience actually is filled with the past the future the present I'm talking about
experiences right I mean logically if you were to talk about of course you know we would say this one person is
moving through time in a linear way but but our experience isn't really that
way and if you really pay
attention you start to notice all these discontinuities and that kind of like
starts to poke holes in this idea of a continuous story and it can be fun and interesting
to even just notice like oh okay that was a past wow that was in the future all that
planning I did wow I was doing that for 20 minutes planning that thing and or something
like that and then but now I'm back here in the present so just to notice kind like the
shifts in between past present and future that
happens in these minds of
ours and there's a way in which looking at uh even this whole notion what I'm
talking about story making even to consider it or think about it or
practice with it is really different than any other practice that we might do
I shouldn't say any other practice but often with meditation practice we have this idea okay we're going
to focus on settle on an object it's
often how we talk about it the breath a sound bodily sensation there's
a way in which we like focus on this but learning to engage with and notice with
the stories that we are inhabiting is not so easy it's not the
same kind of way it's not a way in which we can focus to it instead because stories are complex and
multi-dimensional there's a way in which um encourages us to just engage with our
life and and to notice kind of like these little
quiet thoughts that are happening I notice some of these
repetitious um ways in which we are
constructing keep on using this word stories views and
beliefs so it requires more of like an openness and rather than trying to
search and find them it often can just an openness and recognizing oh yeah
there is this recurring way in which I consider myself or consider
others or which I'm trying to make sense out of my life what happened
earlier it's not easy to do this it's not something that happens
fast it's not something that oh okay that was interesting I'm going to try it and I expect I'll get it to tomorrow
tomorrow morning or you know just if next morning I next time I
sit but this is where real freedom is to notice and to see
through the stories that we have the beliefs that we have the
stories about ourselves about the world about others how things should be how they
are again I'm not saying throw them out I'm saying hold them
lightly be curious about them are you
sure how sure are you about all these stories that we have
just here's just an invitation to plant a little seed of
doubt about our stories and it's quite something because in some ways we might say Buddhist practice is
need to have enough like faith we might use this word faith or confidence to do the practice listen to dorat talks
meditate whatever it might be and we need to have enough
doubt that we're not like holding on to everything like yes finally I found the
truth I'm going to be happy from now on I got it I know when I first got introduced to
the the poly Canon it's kind of like the Buddhist literature early Buddhist
literature scriptures I was so convinced like okay if I could just read enough and here I
will find all the answers I even like learned paully I started translating I'm
like okay I'm sure the answers are in here somewhere the answers weren't there the
way that I thought they would be they were there because I don't know
there was something that just made me happy to be looking at them what was in there and there was a way in
which when I started to see that things weren't neat and tidy I realized oh yeah
this idea of neat and tidy that's another story I have that things need to be neat and tidy I need to understand
them they need to be completely
comprehensible there's a way that unsticking from our stories
is a path to Greater ease greater well-being greater peace just unsticking from them not
completely abandoning them but being open to new stories different
stories and with that I'll end and I'll open it up to see if there's some
questions or
comments
hi um it's kind of a comment I've thought a lot about the stories I tell
myself and for some reason when I think about the I I have some happy what I
consider important stories that I tell myself and when I see those as just
stories it it really it feels very light and I I still like those stories
and and I don't know it's sort of a Gateway
for me to see my other stories which you know I have some stories I really cling
to more negative stories um so anyway that's all yeah
thank you thank you for sharing them and also right just because we're making stories doesn't mean that the emotions
aren't real or the events aren't aren't real or those types of things so the happiness that we experience right
that's real those are real experiences I just um I neglected to say
that earlier and then when you were saying I thought that uh you were going to say when you think that there's
stories it makes you sad but you saying that so you're touching into maybe feeling like the
lightness less less clingy yeah less clinging thank you it's fantastic thank
youse anybody else have a comment or
question I think we can move the microphone down yet there we go thank you excuse me how can
we in a word how can we stop telling ourselves stories
and start to see things as they really are I don't think we can stop telling
ourselves stories this is what humans do we try try to make meaning of our experience think what we can do is hold
them lightly and so part of that is um maybe
I'm trying to remember there was this phrase that um somebody told me a long time ago that I used to use that was really helpful something like uh
something along the lines of am I sure or do is that right is that true like at
the end of each statement that we see just like and just asking that question
we might not know the answer but asking that question kind of like opens it up like okay yeah it seems like this right
now but I'm not 100% sure so that's one way thank
you maybe a completely awakened person doesn't make stories as soon as I'm completely
awakened I'll let you guys know
any other comments or
questions okay well thank you for your attention and I wish you a wonderful
rest of the evening and safe travels home thank you and if you have any comments or
questions that you'd like to come up here you're welcome to come up and talk to me