so um I wanted to uh bring in a
uh a few words from this book that I really like um the name of the book is
called the way to love the way to love here it is you can see all the the
little footnote the the little uh papers I have in there um uh as remind as as
bookmarks uh so the book is by Anthony the Melo it's called the last meditations of anth need the
mow and I've actually given a talk a Dharma a couple of Dharma talks uh on
this on um Audio Drama before um so if you become interested and curious you
can go listen to those but I want to bring something else in tonight so so the um Anthony the
Melo forget now if he was a Jesuit priest or what denomination he was but
he was a priest in India and he was exposed to uh Buddhist teach teachings
and the way he writes it's both Buddhist and Christian very in a very interesting way and and um he he doesn't mince words
he it's it's it's um sometimes his language is is very biting very sharp um
and and I bring in my own I substitute my own words for for what he uses what
he says and yet there's such Clarity to his teaching such Clarity to the ways
like his sword of wisdom really sword cutting so so what I wanted to bring in
tonight is um yeah the a few few lines from this
chapter that's called love one another and at the beginning it's it says what
is love take a look at a rose is it possible for the rose to say I shall
offer my fragrance to good people and withhold it from bad people again he's
using language that you we usually don't use right good and bad but anyway here we go so here with a grain of take with
a grain of salt and yet so I shall offer my fragrance to good people and withhold
it from bad people or can you imagine a lamp that withholds its Rays from a
wicked person who seeks to walk in its light it could only do that by seizing
to be a lamb and observe how helplessly and IND rately a tree gives its shade to
everyone good and bad young and old high and low to animals and humans and every
living creature even to the one who seeks to cut it
down so this is the first quality of love it's indiscriminate
character and of course he goes on but I just want to pause here it's indiscriminate character so here love
really this is the practice of meta of loving kindness It's indiscriminate it's
it's exalted abundant it doesn't hold back from this person or that person
um just because that person has irritated us or
or um or is continuing to irritate us or or has spoken behind our backs or
whatever it might be ah this is this is the extent of mental which is asking us a lot and yet asking
so much of ourselves it it invites us to enter a different dimension of being
it's not the conventional way of Being Human TI for t
uh friends enemy it's it invites us these practices invite us to to
enter this be Dimension beyond the conven itional way of being this this
contractual way of being it these practices this this indiscriminate love
indiscriminate meta loving kindness goodness good will it invites us to
um to enter into a possibility of being above and beyond
what we take ourselves to be what we how we recognize our eles to be so so I want
to invite us to explore that dimension of um
indiscriminate meta abundant exalted not holding back um and again
this this does not make sense in the conventional way of being right in the
conventional being good bad this person I like them I give them my meta my good willll my friendliness or this person no
I don't I hold back but what if like a rose we share our goodness our Good Will
with all beings indiscriminately what what what might happen What might happen
to our hearts to our minds to the to the way we show up in the world um to the
way we see ourselves or or perhaps to the way we have
this vision of what might be possible for us for others and for the way of
being in the world so that's my invitation for our practice so with that
I'd like to invite us to settle into our chairs cushions wherever you are
comfortable let us Begin by imagining that we are a tree
just as Anthony Theo was talking about a tree that offer its shap shade to everyone
indiscriminately let's imagine we are a tree [Music]
sitting here a tree that's well rooted into the
Earth Rec connected to the
Earth feeling our ourselves landing on the Earth relaxing our
muscles nothing to do or accomplish but just to
let Earth Hold Us receive
us does it feel like to be a tree know trees it doesn't seem like they are
working so hard to be to hold themselves up they're naturally held up by Nature
held by the Earth up by their cellulose structure
fibers receiving the nutrients they [Music]
need receiving CO2 the tree being
breathed by the air CO2 oxygen breathing breathing in
CO2 breathing out oxygen we do the opposite but imagine you're a
tree it's all happening on its
own don't have to work so hard to be to
try
offering our weight to the Earth letting this process of breathing
happen on its own Breath by
breath
one one breath at a time calming soothing
settling practicing being a tree
stable tall
grounded and the forest with other trees
and imagine that like a tree whatever you need is provided for
you there is abundance the air is Rich with nutrients
moisture there's water there's
sun it's
okay
now imagine that as a
tree you're providing shade you're providing oxygen clean air and providing
shade indiscriminately
and in this metaphor shade is her good well
producing oxygen is an expression of this being's good will
indiscriminately
seur leave Le a a tree with many leaves full of
foliage providing shade in the hot summer
sun not just for people you cared about let them sit in your shade the shade of
your
goodwi can imagine them having relief from
heat you perhaps you become
happy please that first people you care
about are benefiting from your shade from your Goodwill
and now you can imagine that some people you don't
know some neutral beings also come and sit in the shade
and and they [Music]
too are spared the heat enjoy the Goodwill of your
shade you're being of benefit of
service your good willll is indiscriminate see how that might
feel relating to this
idea
and feel a sense of
delight that might be there feeling your Goodwill your shade benefiting
others indiscriminately and now allowing
inviting some people perhaps that you've been entangled
with in your mind's eye invite them to sit in your
shade allowing yourself to
stretch little bit
we don't want to Define we don't want to limit people we are ENT entangled with
or have been just to our entanglement or their worst
moments or their
misbehavior what if we choose in this moment just in this metaphor for just try it on for size trying on
generosity this metaphor allowing them inviting them to enjoy have a
respit from the heat in our
shade
you're a well-rooted tree strong all full of folage
magnificent with beautiful
shade beautiful Goodwill allowing so many beings to
benefit
indiscriminately imagine them having a picnic relaxing having a cool drink of
water and the Bliss of your
shade
e
we practice generosity of heart for our own sake so that our hearts are
[Music] calm loving forgiving
spacious
may we be of benefit may we
recognize how how expansive our
hearts the generosity the goodwi of our hearts can can [Music]
be
and may we sit in the cool shade of our own
tree be the beneficiary of our own good will not hold it back from
ourselves imagine yourself sh sitting under the shade of your own
tree not holding back the
goodness not holding back the goodness from yourself
may all beings be well and may all all beings be
free and may all beings including ourselves share their Good
Will generously and discriminant with others including
themselves [Music]
everyone thanks for your
practice so
yeah if you joined later I read at the beginning I read these few lines from
the book The Way to Love by Anthony the Melo which the chapter is called love
one another and the line that I emphasized was the first quality of Love is that it's
indiscriminate so maybe I also say as I mentioned at the beginning if you want
to listen to a longer talk about Anthony Dello in this book uh on Audio Dharma
the two talks one is called the way to love and the other one is I think called getting lost on the way to love or
something like that so now I'd like to invite us to explore this this expansion of the heart
as if our Goodwill was a shade of of our tree what happened for you with the
invitation of imagining people you cared about neutral people and then people you've been entangled with to come sit
under your shade did something shift was there an expansion in your heart like oh
yeah this is possible I can actually see you this person being happy and sitting
with their children and you know having a picnic oh yeah it's it's wow under the shade of my tree actually it feels good
this this this metaphor this way of entering into Goodwill through this metaphor of providing shade for others
it's it's a subtle way of expressing good willll it's not that direct may you be well may you be happy but it's a
subtle way of providing happiness and well-being in this metaphor so so I
wonder what you might have noticed so the invitation is in small groups as we're going to engage with one another
in a moment to um each person will have a chance to explore and say okay as as I
explore this this is what happened it surprised me or nothing happened and this was the edge again you're exploring
for your own benefit not to educate not to impress anyone it's just an
exploration of your own heart and please don't comment on each other's uh uh
Reflections no questions asked no uh and and please stay with the practice not
what happened today yesterday just stay with the practice stay close exploring
for your own sake one person will offer one nugget the next person one nugget the next person another nugget and we'll
go around and round around and the order will be reverse alphabetical order and
um if you're new to Happ there is the uh happier breakout room etiquette which is
in the chat you can click on that take a look um and we want to really offer a
space of kindness and care for ourselves for one another it's not just oh go Talk
Amongst yourselves it's engaging respectfully
indiscriminately uh caringly with one another imagine that as you enter the
breakout rooms you're all trees and you all have Goodwill and you you all share
your Goodwill with with one another not judgment but just practice what does it
feel like to share your Goodwill with one another
so so I'm going to create the bre couch
rooms be kind to yourselves be kind to one another there'll be about
um 7 Minutes roughly and I'm going to open them now here you here we
go okay the rooms are all closed everybody's back welcome back everyone
and um we have a a few minutes for Reflections questions um how this practice was for
you and uh like to invite you you can can uh raise your Zoom hand if it's your
physical hand I will not say your physical hand because of uh privacy I have my image um uh uh what is it called
um Spotlight Spotlight so because we're on Zoom uh on on streaming live on
YouTube that's the reason and also if you have spoken recently I ask you to
pull back if you haven't spoken recently please pull forward and you can also type your Reflections in chat either to
me privately or to everyone Amy I see your hand
aloha aloha I really love this thank you so much I um I'm so yeah I don't know if
I've mentioned before but I wrote a poem um around my birthday last year where I wrote about falling in love with a tree
and um and I hadn't written poems as an adult so it inspired me to write
multiple poems and been really struggling with somebody two people who have been so harsh to me and such mean
mean such very challenging words towards me and it's almost inspired me to just
text back like I love you or or something and I don't know if I have it
in me yet but I love the inspiration of it so um it's a possibility in my heart
to do that so thank you thank you you Amy beautiful
thank you so much and and I love hearing your your your relationship with trees falling in love with trees so so in this
practice imagining yourself as a tree providing shade and and also I hear how
doing this practice provided some possibility with the people who've been challenging and harsh with you recently
imagining you didn't say it but I'm assuming seeing them sitting in the shade of your tree open something up
open the possibility of of reaching out and normalizing
relations at least letting them know that your heart is open in whatever way that's appropriate for
you yeah thank thank you Amy beautiful one of you um sent a uh private message
uh I love the tree reflection and it fit in well with an unusual and amazing book
I'm reading the underst story ah I don't know the under story
interesting um if if you felt compelled to to raise your hand and say more that
that if it feels appropriate please do so okay second and last reflection right
now that I see Claire your hand is up thank you Nikki my reason for raising
my hand is much more pragmatic I was wondering if Neil could post the title of the book that you were using uh oh
yes great I have no doubt the information will be shared with you Neil
is a there it is there you go Neil is on top of it okay thanks Claire thank you
thanks Neil that's great Peggy
please oh I was just gonna say I think the book is the over story oh over what
did I oh the over story oh oh okay it was maybe I wrote Under story before Oh yes you're under story it's over under
over you know what over under middle that's
great great any anything you want to share about that or it's
good oh I think you you might have muted yourself already you disappeared so I don't see you anymore but if it's
relevant you can raise your hand there are a few other Reflections let's see
um another uh reflection I hugg trees and when I was
hiking today I hugged a tree and asked what wisdom they could share the tree is
only a tree doesn't doesn't question itself I like that a tree doesn't question
itself I I sit under the tree and I I sat under the tree and I felt the shade
nice nice another reflection or question see I am a little concerned that I want
to have love and empathy for others a little much a little too much there is an element of desperation and
self-hatred on my end maybe overstating that wait I'm not quite following I'm
little concerned that I want to have love and empathy for others a little too much oh I see so maybe it's just like oh
I want so much to have love and empathy for others maybe an element of desperation pushing it too much oh like
and self-hatred I get it so say like I'm not good enough I need to love others more is I think that's what the
reflection is oh my dear dear heart start with yourself sit under the shade
of your own tree start with yourself it's you can't
push um empathy and care for others it see yourself as a beloved other first
and foremost and let it an ease into it um oh I see Neil has also posted the
two talks I mentioned you are fast thank you and Sara has uh shared the the poem the
the um or perhaps Hau by Kobayashi Isa in the cherry blossoms shade there's no
such thing as a stranger Thank you Sara beautiful perfect and
yeah and Miranda says the under story is also a book as it turns out and it
sounds quite good oh my God this is funny so both under story and the over story we've got two books now that is
just great yeah and the person who had asked me about the question about the um
you know the pushing to hard I hope what I said makes sense and and you can send me a private chat if it does it's it's
you know we can't push we can't really um make
the uh empathy for others you really again see yourself sitting under your
own tree um here here here's your chat yes thank you great fantastic
so so dear ones we have come to the end of another happy hour um practicing
together seeing ourselves this these well rooted trees I liked how one of you said you tree doesn't ask questions it
just is it just is it shares its its freeness with others so may
we may our hearts open up in ways of seeing ourselves um sharing our goodness
with all beings everywhere with indiscriminately may all beings be well oh before I I dedicate the Merit I also
wanted to share with you that I'll be teaching and traveling um and we'll be back in early
March to happy hour and there are a team of wonderful substitute teachers who
will be holding space and uh I trust you'll give him a warm welcome and
you'll support them and they will support you so thank you all for your practice thanks for coming in to
community to cultivate your heart your mind and goodness and kindness may we all be well may we all be
[Music] free thanks everyone