so good morning I think I have the technology figured out having been gone from doing
this for 3 weeks it's little bit Rusty and all the all the little
steps so welcome and warm greetings so we're about to do a
meditation and uh what does not often what's often not
associated with meditation is ethics is ethical
Integrity but the two are very closely connected but maybe
uh uh they don't have to be consciously connected but the connection is that
when we sit down to meditate there's all kinds of uh
unethical things we're going to refrain from doing we're not going to
be actively killing or injuring anybody else we're not going to be stealing or
lying or engaging engaging in sexual misconduct um that uh we're sitting very
quietly and still and so physically it's a time
where we're avoiding Behavior which is would be considered
ethical internally we are training ourselves to
not be distracted not be caught up in compulsion or thoughts and um and the kind of impulses
that uh get us uh um reactive to what's
happening and the most impulses to be unethical are ones that take us away
from being mindfully present here now in the present moment so the degree to
which we're practicing present moment awareness going back here we are disengaging
ourselves uh from uh unethical impulses and thoughts they might still come up
but we're not participating in them anymore we're not giving into
them and so there's an inner ethical stance inner ethical space
that we are entering into even if we hadn't never thought about it that way and couldn't care less whether that's
the case or not but uh it is the case and um there
is value in appreciating that and it supports the meditation practice and the
thing I'd like to emphasize today is that this inner
ethical space that uh uh arises in
meditation um uh it is something beautiful there's a beauty to it there's
an a um a Harmony to it there's a
um something uh uh quite lovely about
it and to attune oneself to that beauty to that
Harmony that loveliness to realize oh here there's almost like a work of
art it's uh kind of the beauty of so just
listening with a quiet mind has a kind of Elegance or kind of clarity or kind
of beauty to it Simplicity the beauty of
Simplicity to uh feel and sense peacefully what we feel might not be so
wonderful but the ability the capacity to feel peacefully is
beautiful the capacity to know clearly has a kind of beaut the beauty
of a clear you know Clear Mountain Lake
maybe and even though everything might be confusing and we might be dull or we might be
groggy there can be a beauty in the Simplicity of knowing that that's the
case whatever we can know with Clarity the obvious thing that we can
know clearly there there's a kind of Truth statement oh I'm groggy I'm dull I'm
sleepy and there's something about saying the truth even though it's so obvious is also a kind of beauty to
it so as we meditate today maybe you can
have a sense maybe a glimpse of how sitting in
meditation not only is ethical but even but even more important
maybe more deeply that that the ethical nature of sitting
quietly gives us access to a kind of inner beauty Inner
Harmony inner Clarity something that feels inspiring
in and of itself something that we happy to gaze
upon like we would gaze upon a beautiful object or beautiful
painting So to assume a meditation
posture and to lower the
Gaze perhaps close your eyes
and if you were going to do so in a beautiful way and graceful
way gently take a little bit deeper
breaths and a little longer
exhales seeing if you can feel the rhythm of breathing in and breathing out
that feels harmonious or feels
graceful and then as you exhale
gracefully peacefully let go of your thoughts
loosen up the grip of thinking
as you breathe in feeling your
body a wide experience of your
body relaxing the body as you exhale
and then letting your breathing return to
normal and then be aware of your breathing in whatever way is most
obvious
not straining or trying to do too
much aware of how the bo the breathing appears on its own in your body into
your
awareness in whatever way there's Clarity a clear awareness of of
breathing or part of the
breathing and maybe beginning to get a sense of that there's Beauty
here in the knowing in being
aware if we're not straining or Contracting or judging
ourselves the Simplicity of awareness
and even if part of you feels
agitated to have a receptive
awareness of how you are
where you give yourself permission to be as you are so that the receptive
awareness can feel graceful
generous harmonious maybe even a beauty to it
centering yourself on the body breathing
to see how simple the awareness of breathing can
be with the idea that the more simple the knowing the
awareness of breathing can be the more it is
beautiful there's a Harmony or Grace to it
and then staying with the rhythm of
breathing by being attuned to the quiet peaceful
clear loveliness
of being receptive to in breaths and out breaths
for
for for
Beyond whatever way you're distracted below your
thinking deeper inside than any judgment you can
have is there a place of being of
knowing of intimacy with
yourself that has some quality of beauty or
loveliness gentleness
that is predisposed to having being harmonious with all
things a harmonious
knowing
for
e
for e
whatever is not beautiful within you in this
practice is just a small piece of the
hole to allow your awareness to
expand into the whole wide and
open deep and
still there you might find what is is
beautiful the beauty of being open to the whole all of
what's Happening without picking up anything
reacting to anything
for
for e
and then coming to the end of this
sitting to allow yourself to be still and quiet just temporarily
and gaze upon the world
kindly gaze upon the world bring up to mind the people you'll see the
situations you'll be in and imagine moving through them
beautifully gracefully harmoniously
and how do you have to show up how is it with the support of
mindfulness you can move through your day
beautifully a beauty which is simultaneously ethical
simultaneously avoiding causing harm and a beauty which is nourishing
and
wholesome may we go into the
world with sense of beautiful ethics ethical
Beauty so that we support others to feel
safe they feel no threat from
us may all beings be safe
may all beings be
unthreatened may all beings be able to relax into
themselves may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be free of whatever
interferes covers over their own Beauty may all
beings know that they are beautiful and may we have the eyes to
see that
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to this third talk on introduction to Buddhist eth ethics
or the foundations for Buddhist ethics and bringing together the topics
of the first two days that of non-harming and
wholesomeness those two coming together living in US point to or evoke Beauty a
kind of inner beauty or an ethical Beauty and that one of the reasons to be
ethical in Buddhism is not because of some you know ethical strictures and uh
and uh you know Commandments or righteousness or um sense of uh you know
that Purity maybe depending how you mean what we
mean what we mean by Purity um but
rather to um to be ethical
because we're inspired to stay close to an feeling a
sense an understanding of our own inner heart Harmony
Beauty what is beautiful within us is not harmed is not covered
over by living an ethical life and that we can feel that when we do something
out of hate or greed or if we lie or
want to cause harm to someone else it's uh we lose touch with this beautiful
wonderful capacity within a wonderful possibility within of feeling our own
loveliness our own goodness and um and
uh so one of the words in the Buddhist teachings that can be translated as
ethics or ethical is the word yesterday cusa and today the word that also can
have mean ethics is a word that um and some people some of you know it's
kalana and we know it through the expression kalana Maita often translated
as good spiritual friend however the word kalana its first meaning in all
kinds of ancient dictionaries and modern dictionaries is that it means Beauty
beautiful it also means the trans the dictionary say can
mean Excellence um and sometimes means good
but good is a little bit kind of cheapening something which is really spectacular and
wonderful and um and uh and often in the ancient
Buddhist teachings the beauty or the Excellence that's being pointed to is uh
ethical in nature that a good spiritual friend is someone who knows how to live
a life of non-harming knows how to live a life that is whol some and spreads
that wholesomeness wherever they go and inspires others inspires us in our practice to do the
same and U so rather than calling a good spiritual friend um we can call Kalita
the beautiful friend and that um uh what word and
there's an expression that sometimes uh translated as the Dharma is good in the
beginning good in the middle and good at the end end and certainly that's good
good is good but uh to say that Dharma is beautiful in the beginning beautiful
in the middle beautiful in the end is a is a pointing a pointing to a
possibility pointing to what we're capable of it points to the something
within ourselves which is more than just good um it's uh inspiring in its sense
of uh um how how it feels kind of
inspiringly lovely inspiringly beautiful inspiringly calming or peaceful or a
sense of clarity rather than using the word purity I like to use the word uh
cleanliness something about the inner inner life that can feel completely clean and um and so the sense of Beauty
overlaps with clean or the sense of ethical and overlaps with this deep sense of there's an inner feeling of
being cleansed that why would you harm why would you um Sully that inner feeling of
being cleaned U by doing something which is unethical so it's not uh being ethical
because of rules it's being ethical because there's an inner reference point of something really good and nice that
we don't want to we don't want to harm we don't want to cover over we don't want to lose touch
with and um now I've known people whose dedication to Truth uh is not just an
idea or a commitment you I felt it in their whole being that these people are
are completely incapable of of lying there's a commitment to truth that has
been quite inspiring for me to see I've known people who um they who I have a
deep trust in them because of how strongly comes through them that these
are ethical people these are people who are not going to do anything that's going to harm others not intentionally
at least uh and so to be with them it they there I you know um there's a
safety but also uh what what I I value more is a deep trust or confidence in
them um and a mirroring in those people of what's possible for me as
well it evokes the same kind of orientation for me as well and so one of
the foundations for Buddhist ethics then uh is kalana a kind of inner excellence
and inner beauty and inner goodness and inner you know you have some choice
about what word you want to use to translate kalana but it does uh speak to
something within us that's inspiring something that's worth maintaining or
staying close to something that's worth within us to be inspired by and um and uh and one of the things
that was I tried to say yesterday about wholesomeness is that um we don't want
to be conf a little bit careful to uh assume that there's something
inside that is the thing which is beautiful or wonderful uh that's separate from how
we're aware of whatever is happening how we're relating to whatever is happening
and there is some maybe some element of choice here that we choose to be present
to be attentive to be mindful of whatever is going on in a way that is uh
not harming ourselves in a way that is uh nourishing
for us wholesome making for us that uh a way we're aware in a way that
the the beauty is in how we know how we're aware so it can be very simple
something like the mind wanders off and I've spent years uh being upset with
myself the Mind wandered off and then I um jerk my mind back sometimes in a
harsh way and um and it just certainly was not beautiful how I came back from
being distracted and slowly over time I've learned how to uh um notice that
I'm distracted and then knowing that uh not being in a hurry to judge or
criticize but make space to feel that and know that that feels good it feels
wholesome to just know it in a simple clear way and then if I'm going to come back to my breathing to begin with my
breathing again in a way that just feels nice to do it's part of the meditation
it's part of the the the spiritual life the manner in which I come back to my
breathing so it almost doesn't even matter if I make it back to my breathing
just the the movement itself of the Mind the opening up of the Mind the the
switching to receptivity in the mind just feels so nice it's there's no
harshness there's no demand there's no disappointment no aversion to anything
it just feels so nice just to keep coming back and being here and so how I relate to wondering
off is where part of that loveliness is that kalana is how I can be my own good
spiritual friend or my own beautiful friend or my own uh good friend here
come back be here in a nice way so it's easy to judge ourselves that who we are
or something wrong with us or inadequate or not good enough or something and have a global view that that's the case and
so then it's hard to find something uh uh inspiring within us that we feel is
beautiful and lovely and and satisfying but where we feel s a Harmony or
goodness and so but if that's the case then maybe you
can find it in how you know that you know it kindly you know it with
compassion that you know it with Clarity and uh in the very Clarity of
knowing something there's some beauty sometimes uh mindfulness has a
lot to do with truth telling that we're telling ourselves the truth of what's happening in the moment so if I'm being
um self-critical then the truth would be that oh this here we have self-criticism
going on and there's something about the clarity of that truth telling that frees
us from believing that that's who we are or it creates a different context for
recognizing what's what feels good in the truth telling itself and this
ability to say the truth is uh whether it's uh we directly
see it that way or not is a characteristic of mindfulness that is the continual Act of
being with a truth of the moment continual Act of seeing it feeling it
recognize it and um and in doing so there's something quite lovely and
beautiful and profound about this ability to tell ourselves the
truth and um so uh one of the
important sources of Buddhist ethics
is appreciating something valuable about
ourselves some some some way in which we discover within ourselves an inner
beauty and Inner Harmony and inner cleanliness and Inner Harmony and inner
goodness and that that is uh uh where the motivation to live a life comes
living a life of beauty living beautifully uh rather than
living a life of clutter and hurry and wanting and
reacting and it is a life that requires giving a little extra time to
everything to live beautifully is to give time to each thing if you don't
give time chances are you won't feel the
inner beauty and if you do give time maybe each thing you'll
do will be more thorough and complete and there be less to clean
up after yourself may you live a beautiful
life and may you understand how inner beauty is an inspiring source for living
an ethical life thank you