good morning good afternoon good evening friends hello and welcome to the 7 a.m.
California time sit and talk I'm Nikki murri and uh delighted to be with you in
this moment in time and uh we've been exploring the topic of
sadada confidence Faith this week and uh we'll do a guided meditation and I'll
offer some Reflections some teaching so let's uh let's begin let's begin by coming together by uh collecting
ourselves by collecting ourselves collecting ourselves and
arriving arriving in this moment in
time arriving in this body
however this body is showing up in this moment however this mind is showing up
in this moment it's okay it's all
right not demanding it to be otherwise but working with what
is working with what is
and as if you are greeting yourself greeting
yourself all of yourself no part left
out greeting all parts of your body hello welcome welcome to this moment
and inviting the body to settle
relax to be just as it is here
if there are wrinkles wrinkles in the body let's call them wrinkles or wrinkles in the
mind it's okay let the wrinkles be not fighting with
them letting them be having a sense of gentleness softness
around everything with everything
giving them time acceptance It's a gradual process we know this is a gradual process we know
this and connecting with our breath with the INB breath with the out
breath e
connecting with the sensations of the in breath out breath throughout the
body calming soothing
settling e
and maybe dropping a a uh drop just a
drop of a sense of appreciation gratitude into the
heart for this moment for
the ability to come
together as a community to
practice that the teachings are available there's a sweetness goodness
to the teachings to the community and our own capacity our own willingness
commitment that has brought us here even if the Mind might be distracted or the body achy doesn't matter we're
here we brought ourselves here through confidence through trust we're
here to acknowledge to appreciate to have gratitude
joy for all of
this just a drop if you're taking a dropper with a drop of gratitude and
infusing into your heart and mind mind the goodness of it all the goodness
of it all it's here not to be taken for
granted is could have been otherwise it could have been otherwise
and it
isn't allowing ourselves to to know to be aware to be lovingly aware of the
breath Sensations here here right here right now calming and settling
connecting with this
moment
e
e e
and we've brought ourselves here to practice because we
know we have trust either verified trust we know that from
our own experience or borrowed trust from other people's experience and
Report words that this practice Works more peace ease happiness Freedom
non-reactivity kindness compassion we know we
know and see if you can connect with this knowing with this sense of knowing
trust confidence in your own
Heart In This Moment
is this source of brightness brightness
stability how does it feel for
you do you feel it in your belly in your sit bones sitting more
briide in your heart as brightness how does it show
up the sense of knowing confidence Trust
and notice how there may be perhaps subtle but there is a
gladness there is a gladness there is a delight subtle
Delight or perhaps not so subtle Delight Del light maybe shows up as
brightness p in po p sense of
delight gladness that arises from the sense of
knowing sense of
trust that then helps to settle the Mind
further brings peace and more
concentration see for yourself
and remember it's not about thinking but experiencing
knowing if it starts to become too heady let go and simply be with the experience of the breath in
the body these Reflections have already been
planted don't need to think about
them they will reveal themselves to
you
e
e e
and if you find your mind's wavering remember appreciation gratitude just a
drop of it and bring a sense of feeling
supported sense of confidence and stability
gratitude for the support of
others your wi
sa the teachings appreciation for
yourself we bringing yourself to the practice help you connect the sense of
trust confidence stability
Delight
e
e e
remember recognizing the stability sense of trust confidence in yourself
in your heart in this
moment maybe it shows up as yes
yes this feels right see
how recognizing it it's already here but
recognizing it brings up sense of delight
gladness eat it for
yourself
e
e e
and as we turn to bring this sit to a close
together connecting with a sense of appreciation gratitude for having showed
up having brought yourself to this practice regardless of the outcome
you've planted seeds wholesome seeds no need for any self- judgment for
what happened or didn't happen just appreciation for having showed up
appreciation for the community and that the teachings are available in this
format yay and letting this
appreciation this gratitude help you recognize the goodness in yourself
in all the causes and conditions that that interplay that have interplayed to
bring this moment into being that there is goodness here recognizing there's goodness here
goodness co-created and with generosity of heart
generosity offering this goodness to all beings everywhere may my goodness be of
benefit to all beings everywhere
and this interconnected interplay may all beings be safe happy healthy have
ease may all beings be free including myself
everyone thanks for your practice I'm going to uh transition the
recordings for pause for a moment
greetings greetings everyone good morning good afternoon good evening
wherever you are in the world it just so heartwarming really seeing all the all
your names scroll by very heartwarming awe and all the messages in this
community and This Global community so yeah it gives me trust you
the sense of goodness oh joy joy and Trust that's what comes
up so so we have been exploring this week today is day five out of five
exploring the teachings on sadada translated uh as trust as
um as um confidence sadada the word in poly maybe I'll put it in chat again
I've been doing that so here is
the yeah whoops the word s here we go
impal there um and and just a quick review of what
the aspects we have covered this week so we started by uh discussing the necessity
of having trust and confidence in the practice otherwise we wouldn't start
there has to be some borrowed trust oh yeah this seems to work for others um
um or verify trust to continue to practice when when we verify yeah I seem
calm or Kinder um not as reactive something is happening here so ver
borrow trust verify trust needed to start to continue then we talked about the uh the
trust or confidence in the triple jewels in this classical language which essentially is trusting that I I can
wake up it's possible for me yes I can wake up I can be kinder I can have more
freedom a little more freedom I can um it's possible for me I know it's possible so that sense of trust that
keeps us going trust in the teachings that these practices are verified they
worked for so many people it's um so these teachings are available trust in
that trust in the community that I'm not doing this alone of support of both practitioners
others externally and historically then we uh talked about the
um uh then we talked about what supports yes what supports Sada what supports
Sada what supports confidence and trust and and practicing actually
practicing is the strongest support for S when we practice and both in in minute
ways and moment to moment way we see that oh yeah this is Shifting changing I feel more calmer more more peaceful than
30 minutes ago and also in the longer term when we see when we really bring we
reflect active reflect on how we're shifting and changing very important that
reflection and also ethical conduct um uh is supports supports our trust and
the lack of ethical conduct it erodes our trust in ourselves and in the
practice we kind of waver and fall off the track so and then uh yesterday the
fourth day we talked about the role of sadada in overcoming doubt doubt um uh
which is one of the five hindrances and doubt showing up in so many different ways doubt either doubt in ourselves I
can't do this doubt in practice doubt in community Etc but also doubt can show up in more subtle ways and I invited you to
really consider that when in our practice we kind of waver and we're here and there and everywhere we're not
really trusting that here in this sweet moment of here and now this is the most nourishing place to be or when we uh uh
fall off the path and oh yeah I'll sit I'll sit I'll practice oh yeah I'll listen to a Dharma talk and a month goes
by a couple months yeah it's kind of a lack of trust that this really works so in way so that's a review quick review
just to bring us so today I want to talk about um how um what are the fruits what
are the fruits of s um and
so in the guided meditation also so a couple of things one fruits of s and also a little more about what supports
Sada confidence so um in the guided
meditation if you noticed I asked you to to uh bring a drop a drop of drop a
droplet of of gratitude appreciation uh for yourself for this
practice uh for the community just a sense of appreciation gratitude yay this is good just tasting tasting
appreciating the goodness and that appreciation
gratitude can bring up a sense of can support sense of sadak and sense of
trust and confidence that um it it feeds into it so um it's another way it
Fe Sada support it and then but what I really want to focus on is the fruits of
SATA so the fruits of confidence basically the ultimate fruit of it is is
freedom Liberation nibana that's what the sutas talk about that um that
and and examples of and I'll unpack this in a moment but maybe a a sweet story is
uh from Ananda who was uh the cousin of the Buddha and Ananda was his attendant
was he attended to him attended to the Buddha loved the Buddha and uh heard
heard most of if not all the teachings because he was always with the Buddha attending to
him and fully trusted had had confidence
in the teachings just a sense of sweetness actually talking about the about Ananda there many sweet passages
about him the sense of yeah this um this human being who's who's dedicated to
service and really trusts in in in these teachings in the Buddha and the S and
when the Buddha died Ananda still hadn't become fully awakened um so it was a store point for
him that you know so many people had become awakened and he hadn't and and yet he had full full
trust in the teachings and it is said that right before the first Council uh
of of Elders Buddhist Elders came together Ananda uh became awakened and and
through his trust through his his Sada for the for the practice for the Buddha
and also in the cap capacity of himself to wake up it's a sweet story um to me
um I wanted to share that with you and and in the teachings um there is in the
upan suta it's a beautiful suta Opa suta there's a sequence that the Buddha lays
out that you might have heard about them here before that this leads to that this
leads to that this leads to this and in this particular outline of what
leads to what um sad confidence leads to
Pala leads to uh Delight leads to um uh
this and and gladness Poma translated as gladness or delight and and then there
are other things that it leads to up I'll talk about in a moment but pausing here in the guided meditation I invited
you um to notice to really reflect with this sense of confidence this feels
right this feels right this practice feels right being here right now it feels right and how recognizing
that connecting to that it brings a sense of gladness as I was leading you I
was practicing myself and there was this sense of brightness in my heart and in my body yeah there's this gladness this
feels good this feels yummy it might show up in different ways but there's this gladness this joy that that uh
comes up from recognizing our sense of trust connection
confidence and um and and it's not just an emotional
high but it's a deep sense of contentment and well-being that comes from knowing that one is on the right
path and just to share the rest of this Con
this sequence with you I'll put it in chat and I'll I'll name it um I I'll read it out loud too so um h s s leads
to Joy leads to Rapture um sorry the translation here is
different actually so I like to translate Poma as um gladness or delight
and PT as either Rapture or joy Joy PADI as calmness Tranquility samadi
concentration PA wisdom and nibana Liberation so in this
suta these are laid out so s is really um the foundation of all these cascading
cascading um steps that um just happen
on their own happen on their own it's not like we make it happen when you have full trust the rest the rest unfold on
their own I also want to briefly talk about how um trust so so just really the punch
line is the ultimate fruit of sadada confidence trust is nibana is freedom
and that's there's such a joy in that of delight that that this path leads leads
with confidence and path it leads to more freedom more ease more wisdom kindness for ourselves for others
and the other thing to consider is um confidence is needed trust is needed to
overcome adversity to overcome challenges in our lives um and Trust in
the practice I know that for me uh there there's been trusts in the insights that
I had through this practice that have been that have um supported me through difficulties and challenges and it's not
like challenges and life go away and one of them is the full trust in
impermanence in impermanence it is impermanent um and and that's the Trust
In in the Dharma right in the way things are in the teachings yeah so you might
have uh heard this saying this twoo shall pass this two Shall Pass there's a sense of yeah it's it's going to pass no
matter how challenge seems right now maybe their emotions or difficult this is It's arising it's going to pass away
it's okay just hang in there hang in there um hang in there it's okay this T
sh pass um other insights that that um confidence in in other
ways um that have supported me there's this confidence this that yeah it's it's
um again I I keep coming back to to impermanence um and and also in
personality that it's not personal you especially when they're interactive challenges with with other people that
it's not personal and that's the insight into anata in personality that they're doing the best they can I'm doing the
best we I can we've been in you know in um maybe some who' have bumped against
ourselves because of the causes and conditions and seeing that ah that gives
my heart ease release because I have confidence in that I have confidence I
have trust in that and so many other aspects of trust so I want to invite you
uh to to reflect to reflect on on the aspects of your confidence confidence
that you have in the teachings in the insights that you've had that support you when challenging situations have
come up and continue to come up and also to to have trust that trust in the
practice leads to to to nibana to freedom to all the the steps that I
named to delight and you can feel the Delight in the practice yes I'm on the right path I found the right path for me
there's a sense of joy and Delight in that which let invites the heart to
settle into peace tranquility PADI uh to have more concentration Stillness samadi
ha wisdom grows from the combination of those and nibana
Liberation so it's been a delight to uh to share these teachings with you um
there's so much more to to to share about uh about um uh confidence about
trust Sada and and again it's part of lots of list I didn't say that but you probably know it's already part of it's
part of the five faculties and I think a few weeks ago there was a session on the five faculties so there might have been
one morning B but it was fun to unpack just a little more anyway thank you so
much for your practice for for your trust in the practice may your trust grow may your freedom may your kindness
for the sake of yourself and all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may
all beings be free including [Music]
ourselves thanks everyone take good care be well
oops till next time