we'll give a sound of a bell to
begin Welcome Friends you may be a little surprised
and that I'm here this week um uh Nikki
morer who I was supposed to teach this week was not feeling very well so I got
a call yesterday and and so I decided to
step in uh to be with you all and this is 7 a.m. meditation and uh
practice and so um uh what I had in mind
was maybe uh somewhat simple and uh keeping our practice ractice
alive and so this week uh what we thought what I thought we might do in
our meditation is our explicitly bring in uh
some ways of a practicing that may enrich enliven our practice in some ways
and that's a hope and it doesn't have to um but you can join me however you are
um with uh a possibility to open to some of the uh perspectives if they are new
to you um and then I'll uh talk about a
set of practice skills uh in the daret to maybe elaborate a little more in
terms of uh how we
practice so uh this morning uh I wanted to start uh with a um uh
a uh a practice method that I um have
been practicing with for the last few years and this is um called the arriving
sequence I occasionally have shared this um in uh some of the dayl s and um uh 7
a.m. but this week I like to kind of uh exclusivly uh maybe naming how we
practice with this this is something that I learned from one of my teachers
Philip mfet it has uh really been uh quite meaningful to me and I'm hoping
that this will be meaningful to you as well and I will be expanding standing
from this arriving sequence that we start today to include some different
elements of it as we go along for the rest of the
week and so maybe you can join me in this
meditation by finding a posture finding a space where you can sit
quietly uh for about 40 5 minutes
together and so maybe gently close your eyes uh if that's part of your
practice
arriving this arriving sequence
begins with
arriving arriving here and
now just this sense of arriving May
already evoke some momentary sense of a
presence mindful
presence maybe the sense of a body sitting here or lying down
here
arriving as if you're getting ready to
enter the temple
Within
gentling and feeling and sensing how it feels to be
arriving at here and
now maybe there is a sense
of energy settling [Music] down through the
Torso all the way down to the
ground mindfulness becomes more and more front
and center
and maybe heartfulness becomes more and
more front and [Music]
center very as a no rush to go somewhere
else
we are arriving Here and
Now what's the felt sense of a arriving for
you maybe you feel something in the
body maybe you feel something with the
breath
maybe now you can hear the sound and the silence in
between
allow arriving to be felt
sense and known with the
body with the
heart there is no need to figure it out
at some point you may
recognize that you've
arrived you're now here more
fully becoming available to the lived
experience in this arriving
sequence being
available arises out of having
arrived here and
now
what's the felt sense of a becoming available for
you
maybe a kind of softening
relaxing of the
body maybe the mind and heart is more
receptive
maybe there is a sense of a opening like the opening of The
[Music] Palms
being available to the lift experience that's happening right
now whether it's Pleasant
unpleasant or everything in
between
available to
life letting go or putting down the demands and
agendas
showing up for
this
Maybe by being available we can
notice how we may be caught up in the stories in the
thinking that we become un available to
life without blaming judging
criticizing we simply available
to notice to know and the moment
of CAU up is
happening feeling and sensing
the felt sense of being available is like
this you may know it through the body through the
heart
from this open receptive
relaxed field of
availability and a
presence we move to align our heart and
mind with the deepest [Music]
intentions
aligning without jumping into Concepts
ideas can you feel align
through the body aligning with what's
wholesome aligning with something
that's
aspirational you may feel something in the heart
space aligning feels like
this
the Torso May straighten up ever so
slightly you may feel a kind of
uplift and you may also feel a kind of a
grounding in the body and grounding in the
heart the heart can feel at ease when we are
aligned with our deepest
intentions even one we may not know what they are just
yet the heart may
know and the body may have an
expression
and for me aligning evokes a sense of a taking
refuge in the Buddha Dharma and
Sanaa
aligning my heart and mind with the Buddha Dharma and
Sana
my body can feel at ease with
this stay connected with the felt
sense words are not
necessary being aligned and
available can feel so
[Music]
grounding there may be a cellular level of
relaxation
a deeper sense of ease in the
heart
we're practicing in a wholesome
field
the body may feel more
alive
[Music] yeah
[Music] e
e
it's a field of being aligned and available is a safe
field with our body heart and mind and
Trust the totality of our being can
soften into this
field
there may be emotional resonance bubbling
up a kind of
tenderness maybe
sweetness
Joy there may be a inod the
response
or this may
feel disconnected
we're feeling a little
lost allow the range of experiences to be what they
are
knowing this is a
practice knowing this is a gradual
cultivation and we're simply wailing and that's it
enough
for
[Music] and just reading uh that there's some
background sound um I'm not sure what to do
um hopefully this was good enough for everyone and
um so I'm going to switch gear uh to say
a few words um around the topic and that's kind of in the uh in the guided
meditation and uh let me move my uh notes up
here and so the topic I um brought today um is
about aligning or setting our
intentions as I spoke a little bit at the beginning of uh the guided
meditation that this week uh my intention is to speak uh about a set of
useful hopefully useful practice skills and uh even though uh sometimes
the teachers would say that our practice is simple um but most of us know that um
the practice is actually not easy to do and so for most of us uh we have to
learn a number of different skills that make may be appropriate at different
times and under different circumstances and so um this week I
wanted to start out um today by speaking a little bit about cultivating the
skills uh to set wise intentions of our
practice it may be appropriate uh since this is the beginning of the new year
uh maybe the beginning of the new year does do something in our psyche that
it's appropriate to reflect upon uh the intentions uh that we have around our
practice why we practice and maybe do this consciously
and um uh contemplatively without some conscious
reflection around why we do our practice it's easy uh for our practice to get
misaligned with our wanting mind you know that happens to all of us
and I'm certainly aware of that and just one example and sometimes
when we engage in for example uh Dharma studies um listening to talks or
uh doing reading sutas or um you know
analyzing things and when we're not conscious about why we're doing this
unconsciously we can get into a kind of gaining
mentality um we wanted to gain more information in our head and we wanted to
know all the lists sutas comment
and and as if knowing all the information becomes
the point of the practice and so I've met people who seems to have all the answers by coting
the lines in the sutas and commentaries and if you challenge them
they get very agitated and how can the sutas be wrong
right and then so that's just the one silly example um uh to show that sometimes we
can miss the point of learning and the studying and listening to the
talks uh if gaining the information is why we study the sutta then we're all
just trying to become Google you it's got all the information
there um and this can happen in our meditative practice as well so sometimes
uh when we are unconscious of why we're doing it uh we
could be doing it because we wanted to get something that we like uh you know
Blissful States or we wanted to get rid of something that we don't want or we
don't like like the pain in the body or the annoying boss or you know and so
this may not be an issue when we're consciously choosing something that may
be skillful that is aligned with our deepest intentions because we know the
choices supports the practice along the way but when we're unclear and
unconscious we can become the victim of our wanting mind even though we may have
thought that we're actually practicing so it's very important that from time to time we ask
this question uh why are we doing
this and so this is um why I brought this in aligning in our meditation
today and there is an interesting teaching in the poly Canon sutta that I
was reading recently and that's in angut AA
4.6 uh in the Susa the Buddha pointed out that regardless if someone has
learned a little or a lot of Dharma teachings you know through memorization
listening to the talks and all of those different ways and the Buddha said it is only when
the person is intent on what they have learned they will succeed in the
Dharma and the key word here is
intent and the person is intent on what they have learned and the suta Goes On by
explaining how one is intent on what one has learned and it
says that here someone has learned having understood the meaning of the
teachings the person prac practices in accordance with the Dharma and this is
how one is intend on what has been
learned and so one is practicing in accordance with the Dharma and that's
how one is intent on what one has learned what stood out for me uh in this
line um is um that the intention setting
intention intending is not separate from the
practice itself in fact intention orients and sets in
motion the practice and the teachings uh the in the immediacy of our
Liv experience here and now so intending has this kind of aliveness the vibrancy
in us the Buddha in the sua equates intent
to practicing in accordance with the
Dharma and there are two aspects that jumped out in this line for me one is
that um there is a clear orientation of the
Dharma that is it's about uh practicing in
accordance with the Dharma and the second aspect is that it
highlights that the significant aspect of intending is about practicing with it
itself in our classic teachings on wise
intention in the context of noble Eightfold Path
um it invites us to orient ourselves to live in line with
renunciation nonharming and uh loving kindness so whenever we speak whenever
we uh act or we think we can feel and
sense if our actions speech and the mental activities are aligned with this
wise intentions are they kind are they expressions of
non-harming a non grasping often when we're getting
carried away by the flow of activities and
reactivities uh we sometimes can lose contact with with this kind of deepest
intentions and so that's when we are no longer um in uh living in accordance
with the
Dharma I want to say a few words about how we practicing uh setting cultivating
intentions so clarifying our intentions or making contact with our deepest
intentions don't need to be only a cognitive or
intellectual um activity itself it can be a part of
it um but often our deepest intentions
have a felt sense in the body and in our
hearts and sometimes even before we have award friend
them uh in our guided meditation uh we kind of experimented
with this a little bit sometimes uh the deepest intentions have
embodied somatic expression for me I often feel a kind of uplift through my
spine my torso and it's
energizing at the same time I can feel my whole body and a
heart a mind has a kind of a grounding in it my heart heart can feel at
ease and there may be a kind of a brightness in our heart and
mind sometimes the heart can feel a tender and over time we may
recognize what this intentions are maybe in terms of
words and uh cognitive understanding and they don't always have
to have uh words right away but the something that's deep
inside of us we can know this and we can trust
this so to practice um what the setting
intentions it may be helpful uh first to ask
ourselves or what are our deepest intentions from time to
time maybe in the meditation you can drop a
question kind of like a dropping the stone in a pond uh without necessarily trying to
figure it out let yourself feel what bubbles up in the
body what bubbles up in the heart and there's no rush to get the
answer I remember Gil mentioned that uh he had spent uh um a year to clarify his
intention and so no rush for this and the second aspect of a
practicing with with uh our intentions is to pause and turn
inward often and feel and sense what's operating inside of us in our
activities of Body Mind speech and gently
touching if this is aligned with our intentions our deepest
intentions and allow this to be an inquiry rather than judgment or blame or
criticism and let this inquiry guide you to become more and more
aligned with something our heart and mind knows deeply inside of
us and we'll continue to explore this for the rest of the week in various ways
and expanding some different aspects of um our
practice so thank you everyone for being here and we'll resume
tomorrow have a wonderful rest of the day