good morning friends such a delight to be welcomed by
you all Gil has spoken of this sa as being a friendly a friendly sa and
uh certainly brings a smile to see everybody coming in with
greetings just thought I'd open up a minute early to say welcome and and
Express gratitude for your for your greetings to one
another and to the S very
sweet and in the chat I see old friends and many new
friends great to see
everybody so Gil spoke yes last week uh provided
an overview to Buddhist ethics and the intention this week is
to continue with that and perhaps expand on it by taking a look at what are known as
the five precepts these are five commitments that
we can make in our practice commitments to avoid unskillful action
in five areas of Our
Lives commitments to bring our mindful attention to our
actions and their consequences in the world in a way that
cultivates a heart of non-harming and at the end of his talk
on Friday uh Gil talked about this idea
that from uh effortful cultivating of
virtuous action in our practice there can be a transition to an
almost effortless second nature way of meeting meeting situations with with an
intention to not to not cause harm and in the spirit of that um
Insight of gills let's sit together and let's uh let's
dedicate this sit let's let's BR bring the the spirit of this sit its
inspiration around cultivate around awaking the
heart of nonharming sometimes dormant in
us uh and by bringing attention to the heart we can sort of become attuned to
it and awaken its its potential for nonh harm so join me I'm going to bring Buddha
into the background here let's sit
together and we can take our meditation
posture move into a comfortable position that physically keeps us both relaxed
and alert a relaxed alertness an alert
relaxation can bring the eyes down if that's comfortable bring them all the way down
if that if that's comfortable
and reorient our attention from the outside world the
responsibilities of the day whether those are before us or behind behind us bring our attention inward Inward and
downward inward to this inner life to this inner World downward into the
body and finding in this internal space the breathing
happening this this Breath Right Here is sufficient just noticing this in breath
this out breath and then the next
one we can kind of keep our attention circling around this breathing thing
happening the motion of the body the rise and fall of the abdomen the shoulders lifting
slightly falling slightly and we can keep coming back here to
this to this here and now of our experience the heess and nowness of
things each time the mind gets caught up in things snagged by things each time we
find ourselves each time we find the mind doing
its doing its things looking into the future considering the past thinking
about other people thinking about ourselves the usual without judgment with gentleness
we can nudge attention back to the breathing or we can let the breathing fill out open
back up to become the center of what's happening in our awareness
and the way we return to the breathing the way we let the Mind open back up to
the breathing is so important we don't have to
hurry we don't have to judge ourselves for having strayed
away from the here and now maybe we can remind ourselves that
it's the returning over and over over again that creates a habit of mind to be
here now we create by this return leaving the
entanglement of thought leaving the the
rapidity and some of the tightness of thinking we return to the breath to the
here and now to the body where things are by their nature slower
simpler more balanced as we return each time we
return we create a tendency a
momentum and as we We Begin an exploration this week of five
precepts and given the intimate relationship between mind
and heart we can make each return to Here
and Now each return from thinking to the breath for
example a return to to the heart as
well maybe when we return to the here and now the heart
seems tight restricted
constricted and if we find a heart a little closed
off maybe we can soften just a little around
it maybe just by noticing what it's like there's a softening at least we're here with
it at least we're attending to
it and perhaps we can notice that with returning
from thinking getting caught up in things planning remembering all good functions of the mind can't live without
them maybe we notice that with those activities of mind the heart feels
more closed or tight and when we return to the breathing to the here and now
there can be a subtle opening or softening
maybe the heart feels a little more expansive a little more generous when we
return and there too we create a tendency the
heart in the present moment the heart here and now the heart at rest in meditation like the mind can rest here
in this meditative space this can be the heart of
non-harming
e
e e
so as this meditation period draws to a close
having perhaps touched in with the
heart we can dedicate any Stillness of Heart any
peace we find any openness any generosity of
Heart To A broader benefit in addition to being of benefit to ourselves may it
also benefit Others May it may it enrich our
relationships and may it spread out Ripple out to the benefit of all beings may all
beings know the calm and peace that come with the freedom from suffering
[Music]
so again good morning and welcome wonderful to see
everyone wonderful to be with you all so last week
Gil provided an overview of Buddhist ethics rather a rather a large topic and
in a sense this week we can bring it down to
uh sort of an intimate intimate size uh by taking a look at what are
known as the five precepts five areas in which we can make
a commitment to adopt this heart of non-harming we
can Comm commit to restraining from unskillful
action and today we'll talk just a little bit about the five precepts in general and then we can take a look at
the first precept before even saying before
listing the precepts it may be useful to say that we undertake
these commitments to skillful action and particularly to avoiding causing harm as
supports of our practice they help us be Freer in the
world and as our practice deepens we'll notice that there's a natural opening to
this kind of action this kind of response to the suffering of the
world that moves us away from harmful
action Gil spoke of this Friday in his final comment this idea of
being ethical action don't remember exactly how I put it instead of doing
ethical acts um that is finding that virtuous
action becomes second nature as the practice
deepens so the way these five precepts are presented is very very significant
and very important and they are the following and I'm going to provide them in the form in which they're chanted by
those who undertake them lay practitioners and others
um and they take this form here are the five of them that for the purposes of practice
for the benefit of practice to support practice I undertake a commitment to
abstain from taking life for the purposes of practice to support
practice I undertake a commitment to not take anything not freely
given to support my practice to support its benefit in the
world I undertake a commitment to abstain from causing harm with my sexual
actions to support practice
I take the commitment make the commitment to abstain from harmful
speech unwise speech un skillful speech and finally fifth as a support for my
practice I commit to abstaining
from intoxicated
heedlessness so these are these are not Commandments they're not rules rules uh
they're not that simple they uh instead ask us to they're
much more demanding in a way than Commandments they they ask us to take every situation every interaction in in
the Here and Now of that interaction they encourage us to see
every interaction as presenting a different context the common denominator in all of
them is to avoid causing harm and yet their expressions are
Myriad and and variable something that might be an appropriate way of not
causing harm in one circumstance may not be the the way to respond the next time
or in another circumstance or with another person as we'll
see so as Gil pointed to Friday there's a doing here and there's also an
allowing allowing the practice to respond to situations allowing practice
to come forth and whether that's pausing before we speak um not reaching out to take
something and make it ours kind of um restraining ourselves from an
acquisitive uh movement of mind and heart and
body but there's also um in this respecting practice and um trusting
right having confidence in the practice sometimes when we get out of
the way and let the practice lead let the practice respond we're we're safer
we're less likely to cause harm and of course Gil says this and uh
and Trust Gil's judgment but he says so on good Authority this is something that
the Buddha points to too in one of the ancient texts that comes down to us as a foundation for the Insight
tradition the Buddha says that somebody who's really awake practitioner who
really really is practicing well really awake becomes unable to take life unable
to speak unwisely unable to take something not freely given unable to engage in inappropriate sexual
interaction unable to um unable
to engage in intoxicated heedlessness as I've called it in case of the fifth
precept so we can watch this in our practice as the practice deepens it's harder and harder harder and harder to
cause harm so as we
um it's interesting so much of this practice is about uh
this same way of cultivating these aspects of mind and heart of noticing in
this case of the precepts what how unskillful action feels how skillful
action feels how the wholesome mind states that lead to skillful action feel
how the UNH wholesome state of heart that leads to unskillful action feels
and as in so many other aspects of the practice when we bring attention to to
the state of the heart noticing when there's an urge toward a tight fisted um a lack of um a
selfishness and then noticing a movement in the other direction towards greater generosity towards giving back towards
giving away towards letting go we can lean into that and we can in that
leaning in we can create a momentum a tendency a a
propensity to engage more frequently more regularly in that kind of action
and that's how it becomes increasingly second nature that's how as K put it Friday we
move from kind of consciously doing things that are ethical to just
responding without thought in a way that supports ourselves supports others and
avoids causing harm so let's take a look at the first
precept and in each of these there will be a couple emphases that I think I hope
will come forward uh one is that the focus in this is actions not ourselves
as actors it's not about being a good person or a good Buddhist or a good actor it's about cultivating
actions that don't cause harm avoid causing harm it's the first
thing the second thing is the importance the centrality of mental action for the
Buddha it's actions of mind that are um
perhaps um don't know if I want to say come first but as we uh read in the
first few Verses first couple first vers first two verses of the DAP all action
is preceded by mind and when we act with a mind that's free and clear the action that flows forth from it is
skillful is wholesome doesn't cause
harm so the first precept this is not taking life and uh this will be a
brief a brief sort of look at the first
precept again it's not a commandment and um just because I'm not an Axe Murderer
for example doesn't mean I can just check the box and say okay uh don't take
life on a regular basis uh and I can move on to the second precept it's an
encouragement to notice any movement toward causing harm to other beings to
taking life and uh sometimes it's best to move
from sort of the level of Axe Murderer which I've just invoked uh or global
conflict among humans down to the down to things down to small
examples trying to think of an example humorously the first thing that comes to mind when I talk about think
about taking life and little things I hope this work is
ants little creatures in our lives and the way we inter we interact with them
uh we can notice even as we approach the daddy long legs in the bathtub the ants
in the kitchen sink are pets we can notice the movement of heart and this is the practice noticing the urge to harm
the urge to care the urge to protect and how uh how that moves it's
interesting somebody's just chatted about mosquitoes where I used to live mosquitoes carried West Nile Virus so it
was really challenging but the point is to challenge ourselves and notice how the heart feels when we have an urge to
violence when we have an urge to take life the famous entomologist eio Wilson
was once asked in a lecture academic lecture talking about his research on the chemical signaling with which ants
communicate somebody in the back of the lecture hall said raised hand and said
you know this is great very interesting but I've got ink I've got ants all in my kitchen you know what should I do and EO
Wilson said enjoy them this is a response I love um because it involves a
change of heart so you might experiment with this
a bit little things and you know it doesn't mean um
that we can meet all experience with uh by just enjoying um
the little creatures around us or by not um occasionally finding that we're in
these moral dilemmas around uh ants but what we can do is um
refrain what we can do is avoid feeling complacent or smug that that we're
ethical actors because we have um avoided being avoided gross physical
harm or taking life for example of other humans and focus more on the Mind states
that come up when we um when we feel a temptation to
harm the under the objective of undertaking a precept like this is not
to act perfectly where we're likely to fall short not beat ourselves up for
falling short but rather to um become more aware of how our actions have
consequences we may find ourselves asking more frequently before we Act is this action likely to cause harm to
myself to others may maybe will it cause harm to relationships or is this action
in which I'm currently engaged likely to cause harm to myself or others or is
this action that I just without a great deal of thought just completed is this action likely to have
caused harm to myself to others so to leave with a practice for
the day which I gather is something that Gil sometimes does might notice till we get to the
second precept tomorrow the urge to harm when it comes up uh in our interaction
with the little things maybe and the Lesser life forms maybe just seeing them
as lesser is actually um a movement of heart that we can we
can correct a bit we might notice an opposing urge to protect and we might notice the actions
that follow how does it feel in body how does it feel in mind how does it feel in the
heart which movement of mind and heart has greater stress in it which which has
greater ease and as we notice this we can encourage we can incline we
can um we can support the movement of the heart away from harm
and as we as we do that we create a tendency a momentum in our practice and
in our lives that allows us to be more fully awake to the consequences of our
actions and more fully present in our
experience so that's where I'll leave it for today very much appreciate being with everyone and appreciate appreciate
your efforts to think and bring attention to to the actions we engage in the mind
States from which they emanate and our impact on the world and on one
another do so with a light heart do so with a smile and we'll meet again tomorrow
morning thank you and take care everyone