so happy to be with all of you it's really a delight nice to see old friends and
um old regulars on here and new names too warm
welcome so as you're seeing or thinking about the weather reports you're seeing
in the chat the invitation is also to check out the weather report inside you
don't have to typ it in but just notice is it meta is it enthusiasm is it
kind of tired it's all
good so friends I'm going to start the
recording and the invitation is to start to settle
inwards start to settle inwards and um I'll just
mention the um theme this week is on inner and interpersonal Dharma
wellbeing so noticing just how the word well-being
lands for you feel it in your heart and then turning the attention
inwards maybe turning off any devices or other things that might distract you
maybe as I'm about to do taking that last sip of tea so that my voice
lasts and finding your posture master of
balance connection
groundedness perhaps taking a couple of longer [Music]
slower gently deep breaths
letting the breathing be
natural the invitation is to take an interest in
whatever your internal ecology is
today the feeling of your your
heart the
mood whatever is happening in the mind just greeting it with a gentle friendliness
and allowing the heart the mind the body to settle in this
moment resting on sensations of
breath the overall soundscape your weight your
body all the details of this moment
and noticing that breath and
Sensations are the aliveness the language of Vitality of this body
taking an interest
closely being with each breath each
moment with a warmth the
care falling in love with each breath
noticing the difference between the INB breath and the out breath
allowing the out breath to be a release into
relaxation this here call this home these
moments
e
e e
if you find the mind wanders that's
natural greeting each moment of returning
here with friendliness
interest what is this moment
like and again resting in the flow of in breath out
breath
present
e
e e
in the last couple of moments of this
meditation the invitation is to
recollect gather any moments of goodness good
[Music] intention mindfulness PE
e awareness any [Music] moment in this time of practice
together and let yourself be nourished by
them appreciate them
and then allowing to any moments of challenge or
difficulty and holding them with kindness Compassion
Care these two are moments in the path
and from that place of care
compassion casting your internal gaze outwards to the others in your
life wishing that they may be
well safe
peaceful and
free thank you for your practice
for e
so thank you for our meditation together and it's really meaningful for
me um most of you probably don't know this but I was involved in um
IMC beginning these YouTube sits back at the very beginning of um the co shelter
in place here in California in the US helped out a little bit here and
there and so I watched regularly for quite some time and um like you feel
part of this online Global sa so it's a delight to be with you
and today introduce again the topic for the week for those of you who tiptoed in
late into the YouTube sit and um the week's theme is on inner and
interpersonal sources of Dharma wellbeing Dharma well-being and these
are on cultivating qualities helpful for internal and interpersonal
flourishing and I'll start with the theme a little bit for the week by telling a very condensed story so if you
can picture in Ancient India the time of the Buddha the Buddha is sitting around with a group of his
practitioners probably monks and I picture it being kind of dusk evening maybe they've got a fire
going it's kind of cozy and he's telling this ancient story
of a series of Kings and how through a series of mishaps with
the eighth in this line of seven amazing Kings Society began to have
difficulties a lot of bad things happened and there began to be societal
tensions and Division and eventually um kind of a
breakdown and then he talks about how through developing these inner qualities
especially ethic qualities Society regenerated
itself and then he finishes the story by encouraging everyone to develop
beautiful qualities and relationship to themselves and each other and he talks
about five kinds of well-being practitioners in particular can
develop even in difficult times and they are Spirit virual power or
empowerment true beauty
happiness heart wealth and freedom and I'll unpack each of these
over the course of this week but the theme this morning or whatever time of day it is for you is spiritual
empowerment or spiritual power and I'm going to talk through four
areas of this but first I just want to say they're all kind of held by supported by joyful enthusiastic
engagement with practice and a sense of immersion as best you can in the
moment so the first of these is healthy
desire healthy desire and in spiritual circles and in
meditation practice desire often gets a bad WRA and sometimes for Justified
reasons there can be desire for unhealthful even unhealthy distracting
things or even being overly fixated on a good goal a healthy
goal both of those can kind of run counter to meditative Spiritual
Development but Chanda the word for desire in the ancient language of p is
actually neutral and there's something known as danda desire for the Dharma a wholesome
practice process of being in love with the practice of meditation it's considered to be
skillful at many stages of development and
um it's has these qualities of being kind of expansive or um open rather than
obsessive and constricted it's the difference between this grasping hand or the Fist and an open hand an open hand
holding things lightly in relationship with others this
kind of holding things lightly manifests as a wish Desiring the
best for them and oneself in the
relationship of both it's bringing out the best
so this kind of empowerment I want to empower you to be in love with
meditation to desire what is in the moment and to be present with it
completely this second area of spiritual empowerment or second road to power as
there sometimes called is a sense of balanced energy and vitality balanced
effort Viria in the poly and this has a range
of intensity from heroic effort really strenuous effort like hiking up a big
hill or very kind of soft gentle persistence when you're walking down a
gentle slope maybe a great View and it's helpful to balance adapt
the amount of energy Life Energy and effort we bring to a meditation session
or situation the Buddha likened this to tuning a stringed
instrument and many years ago I lived in San Francisco and I cohabitated at the time with this beautiful baby grand
piano and we had to have tuners come kind of regularly because the tuning of
the strings changed with the weather they it changed with the seasons the conditions changed and the
totness and the strings needed to be adapted and it's just like that for us
in meditation conditions change and we attune a little bit
differently the next one here is to be aware of the overall State of
Mind the intentness or the distraction of our minds the chitta it's
called or chitt some people pronounce it the objective
experience of mood of being of concentration or
distraction it's like the overall weather report the overall landscape or Ambient sound around us it's the just
adal the whole and the instruction isn't to make
it be different instead it's to notice and
appreciate when helpful overall qualities of Mind are there or can be
invited especially to appreciate relaxed
intentness this kind of slow steady interest willpower that can be there and be kind
to any state of mind it's a huge
benefit and then this fourth area of empowerment is interest and experience
fermentation napali word for this is
viaa and it's kind of like being a naturalist for your internal
ecology internal Ecology of the body heart and mind I told this story at
Insight Santa Cruz recently of walking along a forest path and turning a bend
and it's like this kind of remote area beautiful Park area and the friend who
Des Des cribes this story was walking and when she turned this Bend she encountered this young man just
completely bellied down across the path intently studying a little plant and she
said hi and he looked up at her and his smile just lit up his face lit up the
interaction he was a Bist and he was completely jazzed about finding the
details the little foliage differences and textures of of this plant in the
wild and it's that kind of just delighted
interest that it's helpful to bring to the details of
meditation like the breath like the like the
sensations like the mood itself like how the meditation is Flowing or
not to notice get interested in the object of attention it's
called and there can be kind of an art a science to it in the sense of experimentation
too noticing inputs and outputs noticing oh I do this and that happens or this
arises and then that one away it's kind of like a young kid learning to paint
maybe in kindergarten or something and I put these together they do this and when I add
that one it makes brown oh interesting or like a sailor when I
adjust the sail this way the boat does this when I adjust it that way it moves
core it's this process of adjusting core
shifting responding being responsive and a stepping back from time to time just
like a painter to see the overall
picture this interest experimentation this caring interest is helpful in a
meditation session and it can be helpful in interactions like how many times have
we walked by a neighbor or the postman and said hey how's it going but not really engaged just being polite or
casually friendly and that's fine but then showing up with real interest and
maybe stopping in the sunshine or the wind and having a deeper conversation with that
person the difference is the level of interest and sometimes that mutual
interest can connect and it's just like watering a
plant the relationship grows it begins to flourish
[Music] so this is a tiny introduction very
short introduction to the Buddha's teachings on spiritual empowerment
bases supports for meditative success
for internal power taking our own weather with us wherever we
go and I just want to acknowledge this particular teaching emphasizes more
doing than a lot of mindfulness teachings do you don't have to do too much you really
don't these Explorations these kind of playful light
ways of addressing things unfold best in a field of relaxation ease trust in the
practice and if you want to learn more about this particular set of teaching I unpacked them in detail back in December
of 2022 on this YouTube series so you can check them out
then and for this series tomorrow we talk about Dharma Beauty cultivating
Dharma Beauty so thank you it's a delight to be with you thank you very much for your
practice everyone and maybe between now and tomorrow just notice for yourself
if there are moments of a healthy being in love with the moment Dharma desire
moments of fluctuations or Attunement of Dharma energy Vitality
effort moments of awareness of your overall mind and the effect
of delighted interest experimentation on your day on your relationships on your
practice thank you everyone be
well may all beings benefit from our practice together