uh my name is May Elliot um good morning good afternoon good evening wherever and
whenever you are uh wherever you find yourself um today we are continuing our
exploration of the Buddha's five daily Recollections uh sometimes called the five remembrances or the five
Reflections I like the translation the five Recollections because it includes
that word collect so ideally reflect on these teachings when the mind is
collected and settled so uh so today we'll be focusing
on the second phrase I am the nature I am of the nature to become sick I have
not gone beyond sickness or sometimes uh I am of the nature to become ill I have
not gone beyond illness and as with yesterday uh we'll
we'll practice with this phrase in two ways so we'll um we'll sit silently together and then after the mind has
settled in meditation uh we'll just drop the phrase into the Mind allowing it to Ripple through without much
thinking um uh then I'll offer some questions the second way is I'll offer some questions so you can actively
contemplate the phrase and uh just as a reminder um
though we're we are um yeah though we we cognitively know that illness will come
um this contemplation is to help us move this understanding from the head to the heart um and maybe we could even say uh
from the heart to the belly so that we can actually digest these truths more
fully um I might add um if you're not feeling well resourced today and it
feels like a little too much to uh to contemplate the eventual decay of your
well-being uh it's totally okay to mute the sound sit in silence and come on
back back at 7:30 for the D so um so do what feels best for
you and for those who want to join uh for the guided
meditation uh please take your meditation
posture so finding yourself in a comfortable stable
position something that allows your your body to be alert and
relaxed maybe starting with a few deep breaths
inviting relaxation and settling the mind on your
anchor whatever that may be the breath Global sense of the body maybe your
touch points with a cushion or floor
maybe the sound sleep and inviting the mind to rest let
go of past and future prioritizing just being
here simplifying stabilizing settling the
mind go ahead and sit in silence together for some time
now
e
e e
from time to time in meditation can be helpful to among other body to
relax to soften the face the temples the jaw shoulders
[Music] belly bringing some Tranquility to the
mind and the
Heart
e
e e
Sting the mind steadying the
mind letting go of anything extra
before we begin to drop our phrases in for
recollection we can start by bringing an attitude of kindness to the
[Music] mind a little meta a loving
[Music] attitude a little warmth or caring whatever resonates for
you this might be the attitude you'd have if uh you were holding a baby in
your arm
so bringing in this attitude to help bolster us
and support us as we engage in these phrases
so let's begin let's begin with dropping today's phrase into our
meditation so the traditional phrase I am subject to
illness have not gone beyond
illness just allowing that to drop into your meditation and ripple through through the mind and heart seeing what
arises I am subject to illness have not gone beyond illness
and maybe something happens maybe nothing happens and it's fine either way
we're not demanding a response we just noticing we drop the
phrase in and then it's a mindfulness practice to see what comes forth it's
fine if there's pictures or words in the mind just keeping a short leash on them
so we don't go into discursive thought
[Music] memories emotions just noticing what
comes up we might play with a
more modern version of this phrase from Nikki Mir Gori can try dropping this
in breathing in gently I lovingly remember that this body will sicken
breathing in gently I lovingly remember that this body will sicken
your own noun playing with this phrase dropping it in at a pace that feels right for
[Music] you and at any time if you feel ready to go back to your anchor and let go of the
phrases that's totally
fun
e
e e
let go of the phrase coming back into silence
start our engaged [Music] contemplation again offering um a couple
[Music] questions and because this is a contemplation you can allow yourself to
think about each question if there's certain questions
that don't resonate for you it's not important to reflect on each one just choose whatever stands
out so again remembering I am subject to illness and subject to sickness I have
not gone beyond sickness
so when you become sick injured or are in pain how do you relate to it how is
that for
you you do the contemplation staying close to the question such that um that we don't get
lost in discursive thought so keeping a short leash on on
the reflection on the contemplation and including whatever
Body Sensations or emotions arise as you reflect
when you're healthy and the body is working well do you appreciate your
health do you notice that the body is working well and that you're feeling
good or do you only notice the body when something goes AR
what is it like for you knowing that we can't prevent sickness and
injury e
How Deeply do you know that illness will come do you know it conceptually
only or do you know it in your
core e
you might just take a moment to notice what it feels like in the body right
now there's a noticing if there's a mood or an emotion
present noticing what it feels like in the heart
just taking all of this in with a kind and gentle awareness making space for whatever is there
knowing that a great sickness may come for us or maybe already has that some of
you may be ill at this time and that these Reflections can
bring up a lot let's bring in some meta
phrases may I be joyful and
happy may I be strong and healthy
may I be safe and
protected and may I be peaceful and at [Music]
ease or instead of the formal phrases Maybe just it's okay
love there there it's okay it's okay to be
sick coming back to your inchor settling the last few minutes
beings be happy healthy safe and at ease
okay welcome back
so for those who are just arriving my name is May Elliot and we continuing our
exploration of the five daily
Recollections and uh as a reminder uh these phrases span uh aging
sickness death losing those that we love
and all that we love and the teachings on Karma so uh so this is a vast array
um and today I'd like to begin by sharing a Zen Coan with
you as translated in Zen flesh Zen bones so uh it starts with a man traveling
across a field and he encounters a tiger uh he fle of course and the tiger
uh chases after him coming to a cliff uh he catches hold of a root of a wild Vine
and swings himself down over the edge the man is hung over the precipice
by a root while the tiger sniffs at him from above the man looks down uh to where far
below another tiger was waiting to eat him only the vine sustained him
two mice one white and one black little by little start to naw away at the
vine at that moment the man saw a luscious strawberry near him grasping
the Vine with one hand he plucked the strawberry with the
other and the ends with how sweet it tasted
so this um this setup may seem a little absurd maybe like something from an
action movie or a fantasy film a tiger above a tiger
below appearance of two mysterious mice just at the critical
moment uh but surprisingly this is a description of our life um there's no
avoiding the inevitability of sickness aging and death and we can't we can't
avoid these things by going uh back in time that would be like climbing back off the cliff Cliff onto stable land and
into the Tiger's mouth um and we all know that going forward in time bring
brings sickness aging and death um even closer and that's the tiger at the bottom of the
cliff the white mouse and the black mouse represent the days and nights of
our life nibbling away at the vine little by little diminishing the time we
have left and and what happens uh when we
really come to terms with this when we when you really understand deeply that
sickness old age death loss are coming for us um what happens is we can learn to
love this life and be more present for it we can we can be truly present for
that one ripe strawberry we can taste the sweetness of this precious
moment so so this is really what what these phrases are about what these Recollections are about it's one of the
effects of practicing with them as they wake us up to the beauty of what we have
here so today as you know the reflection uh focusing on is I am of the nature to
become sick I have not gone beyond sickness and I love Nikki's take on this
breathing in gently I lovingly remember that this body will
sicken uh in the uh the 10 subjects for frequent recollection by one who has
gone forth uh there is a line that goes
the days and nights are relentlessly passing how well am I spending my time the days
and nights are relentlessly passing how well am I spending my time white mouse
black mouse the days and nights are coming and going are you practicing
diligently so this this phrase that reminds us that sickness is coming if it
hasn't already arrived and we we may not always be well enough to practice with energy she and Zeal to do what we
love I may not always be well enough to meditate or to be able to go on meditation Retreats or whatever it is
whatever way you practice and whatever it is that you love to
do I did a dayong retreat at one point with a man in a wheelchair and when it
came time to do walking meditation uh the way he did it is he would um take
his two fingers and he'd um walk them up and down his thigh middle finger and
pointer finger walking up and down and will this body always be well
enough to practice in an easeful way we don't
know and it's so rare when the body is well that we actually it's so rare that we actually uh acknowledge and
appreciate everything that's functioning properly technotan offered the teaching
uh to be grateful for our non toothache um we so easily fixate on what's going
wrong it can be easy to forget uh uh to acknowledge the great relief of no
toothache of no headache of no pain or sickness on any given day remember I am
of the nature to become sick it can highlight in relief the ways that Wellness is available here and now we
can be grateful for our nonto
fake and uh and the continued remembering of this teaching I am of the
nature to grow sick to become sick uh not only illuminates that which is not
yet sick U but it aligns our expectations such that we're not surprised when illness comes so um so
sickness and injuries are common visitors for me and I've noticed that the mind's immediate response um uh if I
get sick or injured can be oh no not again um so at a certain
point uh I started I started in the morning with the sentiment uh today
could be the day as in today could be the day for a new cold or flu or injury or health issue today could be the day
so this became my short hand for I am of the nature to get sick I have not gone
beyond sickness so uh I remember on the first day I did this practice I was eating and
I bit down on a pebble or something and I lost a tooth and rather than having
this sense of like oh no not again uh the thought was oh well of course today
is the day and there's no upset around it so uh
when we shift our expectations we no longer feel wronged by the universe or singled out or oh for me it's like of
course this is the nature of how things are and there's there's an extraordinary
way in which when we we suffer well we often think that we're alone or isolated
in our suffering why me no one else is suffering how I'm suffering and something I appreciate
about this suta with the five Recollections is that it actually it invites us to not only contemplate our
aging sickness death Etc but that we do this for others as well so this this is
from mut says now a disciple of the noble ones considers this
I am not the only one subject to sickness who has not gone beyond
sickness so I not the only one and he repeats this multiple
times uh so there's no need to get into oh I have more health issues than my
friends or I get sick more often than others we're all in this together at one
time or another and uh often when sick or ill
people people can think uh my body betrayed me or how did this go
wrong so instead uh in this suta each phrase functions with a unique intention
counteracting this sense of surprise uh so uh we I shared the first one
yesterday which was um the phrase is I am of the nature to age um and then uh
the intention is of saying that praise is to overcome the intoxication with
youth intoxication of Youth so today's I am of the nature to become sick and
that's to overcome the intoxication of good health um so that we we don't think
that we're always going to have it um to so that we're not clinging to it it's not that we don't enjoy good
health um but that we're not attached to it or the third phrase I am of the
nature to die um that's too overcome the intoxication with life and it's not
saying that we're overcoming uh our love of life um but rather our clinging to
life in a way that causes us to engage in misconduct
misconduct um misconduct by Body speech and mind um to let go of clinging to
life in a way that causes suffering um the fourth phrase I'm of
the nature to lose what is dear to me that's to weaken and overcome desire and
lust and the fifth I am the owner of my actions which I'll just say in shorthand
for now your reflection on Karma um the intention of that phrase is to become
responsible to abandon misconduct this is just some of the uh
some the different intentions behind the phrases from the
Buddha so ultimately uh all of these cultivate a mind uh a mind of Greater
Freedom they invite us to let go of fear and resistance they help us live with
greater [Music] love and still this practice isn't easy
so be gentle with yourself dogen the the founder of Zen in
Japan he would say speak to sentient beings as you would a baby and one of my
teachers extrapolated on this by saying dear one are you hungry do you need to
have your diaper changed do you need to be held so so we can relate to ourselves
with this sort of tenderness and kindness now please be gentle uh when you work with these Reflections and be
be kind to the child that lives in your own heart and uh today I hope you're able to
stay to stay close to this reflection so uh if you notice that your body is able
to see able to hear or smell or taste uh if it can walk or stand if it
can lift its limbs it can talk and digest its food uh stay close to what's
going well stay close and um uh feel some appreciation for your
non toothache and remember that today could be the
day okay thanks so much everyone take care I'll see you tomorrow