good morning welcome if you've arrived pleasure to be here with you all
today on this beautiful Sunday morning so
um going to offer some words to go into a little bit of a guided meditation for
this period and um by the time we come you would come out up probably have my
jacket off but I run a little cold so I have to keep it on for a bit
and um in going into this meditation I'd like to invite you to take a look at this statue right here
of the Buddha right next to us it's an instruction I
find it's an instruction of a potential a potential for a refuge
so in closing your eyes when you wish As You Wish if you
wish feeling welcomed here exactly as you
are fully accepted as you are however your mind is however your heart is
and knowing that we're here in a refuge and maybe with
time that Refuge takes hold
within witnessing the body Rhythm the rhythm of the breath
but being very curious about the breath like a gentle benevolent
parent who's looking coming into this body to say h how is this
breath a benevolent figure doesn't come and try to do or change
anything just kind of witnesses sees
connects there's inhale there's exhale there's
Rhythm how is it for you watching it like a benevolent
figure would participate
over time as we sit in
silence maybe we learn how to feel this Refuge
within from a deep place within from some place of some basic
satisfaction being here
now a simple place of contentment the
breath breathing
itself maybe a place of Tranquility with
wisdom that holds you as you
are in this body breathing
itself and with feeling feeling some sense of this loving
guide of a
refuge taking note if there's anything that's not
calm maybe a little
agitated and breathing noticing
if you can take that in from a tranquil place maybe there's some other tranquil
place here that allows you to be with agitation
and with breathing happening all in its
own from some deep place
within we can know and receive in Awareness in
mindfulness what's here
this body this fathom long body is
here sensing knowing the body from the very crown of the head down to the toes
to the bottom of the feet
maybe we can know an exhale or two it allows the body
to just rest here a little more all on its
own come down into its
weight and one of the things that we can know be aware
of is how are thinking
maybe sometimes thinking is going so fast that uh there is this feeling of
disconnection almost puts us out of bodyy a little
bit it's okay no problem with
it we can be aware of it
and we can be aware with aware of it from a calm
Place whatever it calm is here embodied
breathing and then it could be a little interesting
wow that thinking is of few steps
away there is this Global body
here to rest release
maybe we can give room to the
thinking feeling the sensation of any tension from the thinking any
pressure not no need to push it away try to stop it
sensing the body breathing and knowing whatever comes
into your awareness
we can also know that mindfulness itself is calming
awareness is calming awareness or mindfulness has its
own
tranquility and it can be useful to know that there are different kinds of thinking
there is discursive thinking that's like a story or running stream
of verbal Expressions visual
Expressions ideas Notions all kinds of things
and with your calm
awareness noticing that ongoing commentary if it's
there we can maybe notice how that commentary
that ongoing story line of thought and
thinking it's a bit of a leak like mindfulness is leaking out as
opposed to being tranquil isn't that
interesting while you go and rest in your tranquil awareness to whatever
degree is there
there's also there's also thinking that's non-discursive
that's just simple a few words oh this is
thinking oh this is
tension maybe I should feel it
oh I felt that enough maybe I should begin to breathe
again very simple thinking that guides the
meditation quiet little thoughts of recognition of
understanding that are probably best when they are tranquil
and then and then the final thinking I'm going to offer
is nonverbal thinking just kind of a non verble
knowing these can be like wise thoughts from deep inside deep in your
refuge and knowing that makes thinking quieter
a knowing that knows maybe the story making discursive
thought is going on can go on in the
background but here in the wise knowing it just knows ah there that is
and then all along continuing to allow
relaxation resting with the rhythm of breathing
relaxing with any exhales that bring
relaxation opening with an
inhale like the body opens up from within and kind of Gathers
than itself to relax and an ex
inhale maybe bringing a relaxation in the hips or the center of your core
and then for the remainder of this sit this
meditation let getting attention being rooted
somewhere maybe it's the rhythm of
breathing maybe it's some deep stability in the
center maybe a tension resting like that
can be like a calm hand on a
shoulder that
comforts supportively
a support that allows well-being to
grow a comforting hand on the
shoulder that gives a sense of sweet tender ease
for e
for
e e
what
e
e for
and an invitation to feel and rest whatever
relaxation is available whatever relaxation comes from
your body resting here breathing
together inviting you to feel the that let the well-being
grow that comes with
relaxing maybe being steadfast letting the well-being fill
you up it's
good you deserve that your
Birthright to feel
well-being and if you're steadfast with it letting
it happen on a
tone maybe it can fill you up like a big broad big broad
Lake and then your well-being spreads out Beyond you
and in the middle of it all you're in this can enter into the center
of your attention
entering to that Refuge that holds you as you
are receives you as you
are and maybe even a little bit bit over time
trusting resting being reassured by that center
of attention at Refuge
inside and there's no need to be thinking reacting responding right now
all the doing can just rest can settle in a reassuring
way like that hand on your shoulder on your heart your inner Refuge
an attention that's steadied still
quiet peaceful
Unified
e
e e
thank you good morning everyone and welcome again to
IMC uh as many of you know our entire Center works on donation IMC and IRC if
you're inclined and all the the teachings are always freely given there's never a charge for the Dharma
here so if you're inclined to make a donation there's a box with the teacher's name and a slot also for
operations near the front door there's also an electronic kiosk near the library door and our teacher this
morning is Francisco Moro Gable Francisco began meditating in 2003 after
a lifechanging accident meditation practice has helped him to make an
unexpected recovery and adapt to his disabil prior to the accident he worked in the
technology sector as senior director Francisco is classically trained in
Buddhist Meditation practices from Southeast Asia and in April he will be
authorized as a Dharma teacher by the Insight Meditation Center teacher training program he is especially
interested in teaching in the Spanish-speaking world and underserved groups such as bipac disabled an lgbtq
plus he was born and raised in the Dominican Republic until the age of 10
at which time he immigrated to the United States good morning Francisco thank you
for being here and thank you so much for your guided
meditation you're so welcome pleasure to be here with all of you today on this
day
abut thank you so on Tuesday
evening I found myself I was at a retreat on a
retreat I didn't schedule it because it happened to coincide on that day it was
when the teacher was teaching that I wanted to be with and I was um
by this Lake Shore looking at these mountain peaks at
sunset for about an hour I sat by the water looking at the mountain peaks
watching the water change into these amazing fabulous changes that water at
Sunset can do with 10,000 foot tall Peaks across this water the changes of
light uh on the water we mesmerizing
it was deeply relaxing and um deeply moving because I was aware that night uh
what was taking place that night I was not watching news of course I was in
silence um silent practice and
um I looked at the Peaks the mountain peaks at one of the most beautiful moments of
light and um I started to sob deeply deeply deeply
inside because regardless of the
news there was no doubt that there would be a lot of
pain and um and so I made a small little gesture
just uh may all citizens of the United
States be at peace may all be at
ease and may all be well and i' continue
sobbing knowing that there would would be pain next to
Joy and so that's how that went for me that was probably one of the
highlights of the retreat for me there was a very challenging Retreat for me physically because of uh the weather
or where I was at so I'd like to share uh
not other words from that night um these are called a prayer for our
times they come from our co-identified
by side side by side regardless of our
differences where there is hate let us stand in Hate's
way with love where others offers offer care we
offer to help where others neglect to care we
offer what we can
where there is respect we offer friendship where there is no respect we
offer
kindness this was posted on the IMC website on Wednesday morning I believe or maybe Tuesday
night and um and so here we are with Buddhist
practice and I'll read one line from the statement that is
posted the greater our challenges the greater the value of Buddhist
practice rather than a practice to avoid challenges or to avoid
celebration it is a practice that prepares us to meet them wisely and
calmly we can meet all our inner life with honesty
and Good Will so we can be wise and
skillful so we can be wise and skillful in these
times that maybe deserve some prayer some good
wishes and some wisdom so we can be calm and strong and
Fierce and ready and alert
so I thought I would share some Reflections about um a
practice that is about I think offers a lot of nurturing
wisdom nurturing that may be needed more now for some and nurturing that's always
needed and it's the practice of mind fness of the body mindfulness of the body is one of
the three great mindfulness practices one of the three great
sutas there's mindfulness the four establishments of mindfulness we all may be aware of the
Sati patana suta there's the mindfulness of breathing the
anapanasati and then there's mindfulness of the body in P it's k
Sati and um I'm going to share some Reflections
from gain in part from a retreat that I did uh in September for several weeks
um because this suta this way of building mindfulness building our
practice building our awareness is ladened and filled with these very
inspiring and softening qualities very nurturing I think because
right from the very beginning the Buddha is putting us into a
position that um has us to build alongside our
mindfulness concentration otherwise known as
Samar so this conjunction of um there so there's a conjunction of
healing the healing practices of somebody all along this suta so your
concentration can be very healing because it gives gives us a
sense of wholeness it builds a sense of wholeness it can offer
Clarity because it allows us to be able to discern and see
and it also gives us momentum in our awareness
so he says the Buddha says the instructions in the the beginning instructions the monks are all talking
as they do and he comes in and he then tells he they're talking about mindfulness of breathing and he said
this is of great fruit and great benefit and uh and maybe you'll think it
is I'd like to point to some of those fruits to see if they're helpful in
building our wisdom in coming to the wise thinking that wise place of
knowing where we can maybe act from in these days in these months and
these these coming periods is this new age that we are
in and it's um the first part is very much like the
Sati batana the four main practices of the body starts with mindfulness of
breathing bodily postures the 31 body parts the elements
um and then the contemplations of the corpse and what's exciting is that right
at the beginning we're asked to cultivate
calming in the first practice the Buddha instructs us to know the
breath know if it's long know if it's short and then to feel it to sense it
how it is in the whole body to sense your whole body to sense the
relaxation and then to linger on that relaxation so to linger on
calm I think it's a very encouraging ing way to start because when we can linger
un calm we connect to this
contentment and then our practice is founded on
contentment and it's very supportive
to linger on contentment to have it as a reference point and to have a reference
point and then right after this um he says gives those four
instructions and then as one abides thus diligently steadfast
resolved the memories and intentions based on the worldly life are
abandoned and with their abandoning the mind is become steadied internally
quieted brought to singleness and concentrated that is how one develops
mindfulness of the body so right away the Buddha is presenting us with as we come here like
we just did in this meditation what we were coming here to this meditation we were taking a moment to
put aside memories and tensions of the worldly life the non meditation life so
for these moments to care for our our ourselves in this way to step into this
place and this invitation it's a respectful invitation because we do it
if we want to we do it if we choose
to and the invitation to put aside discontent
fear dread for some moments is an invitation to go deep
inside it's an in itation to turn toward something else to turn toward the
practicing the cultivation and the developing of something
else the wise thinking that I mentioned that emanates
from a place that's much much deeper in all of us
than all words and all thoughts some essential quality of us
in the discourses that's called the chitta the heart mind in more common vernacular people
use a term like the soul your
spirit the deep deepness within so that is our reference
point going towards this deepness within to care for it to cultivate it so
that it becomes a great fruit and a great benefit a great place to come
from and then I will jump to the end to give you the
punchline because I think you might um so the benefits of mindfulness of the
body I'll just share a couple after it's been practiced developed and cultivated
one becomes a conqueror of fear and
dread doesn't that sound pretty good one becomes a conqueror of
discontent and Delight maybe not the Delight part um but um discontent to
conquer discontent and then there are many other
there are few few others the other one that is that one obtains at will without trouble and difficulty the four
absorptions that means that we have great concentration available to us to
whatever degree we practice mindfulness of the body and as I was saying the con the
samade the concentration part that's being conjointly developed
here is is very good for us
because to reach toward calm and by concentration I'm referring to the whole
family of Tranquility practices Tranquility is
calm Serenity ease
joy happiness equinity
how does that sound so to have more of that right from
the very first instruction is what we're instructed and given the opportunity to
cultivate and invited to cultivate for
ourselves by putting aside for a few moments for the time as much as we
can the Fear The Dread of the outside world even the
Delight of the outside world to feel and
sense something and so there are six bodily
practices that we do and how this works is um is through the physicality of this
being so this this psychophysical system that we have
is amazing and it's full of nerves that go
everywhere and when as we are aware of the the touch the sense the feel of any
touch that we are consciously aware of we're registering our Attention our attention
is registering and is coming alive we're
enlivening the attention and at the same time the tension
of the body can
dissolve and that's very good because there's a lot of energy that goes into holding tensions all the tensions that
uh we make carry so to relax them to ease
them and we don't do this
alone we're given a reference point of
Tranquility so the contentment that
comes is like our guide our accompaniment so we hold this
contentment it's our reference point while we're going inside and doing
this Insight work of touching feeling the touch feeling the sense feeling all
the different manifestations of Sensations knowing
them with support resting with contentment that's the
great supporting thing that's happening in this discourse there's our Insight
practice seeing Fai looking knowing sensing how things are flowing changing
and how our awareness grows that way so we build our mindfulness and we're doing it with a
support because we need support it's much easier to do the practice if it's
supported if we have a helper like a guide like a companion along the way
that comes from within us that is us is our own
contentment and so the body has a lot to teach and a lot to
show to mindfulness and it's very good because the Buddha in this um discourse
has um these great similes for um the kind of mindfulness
that we want there's a lot of water similes here and
uh water is very special when it comes to samadi concentration
because um these these similes sometimes teach us better what we're supposed what
we can feel in concentration in relaxation how we can experience
relaxing so the Buddha says that uh we want to build our mindfulness so that
it's not wet like a mound of wet clay
because the stone can come and squash the
clay so your mindfulness we don't want it to be so
soft like wet clay that it can be just squashed by all the
externalities that come here he uses the term Mara for those external forces that are also
internal forces of all the fear and dread that comes and
squashes our mindfulness so we also um want to have a mindfulness
that's um not like an empty jug of water we
want to have a mindfulness that's like a full jug of
water we also want to have a mindfulness that's strong like a door made out of
Heartwood heartswood is the core of a tree that's the hardest wood
so what does it take for you to have your mindfulness be like
Heartwood what do you need what will what will support
you I asked this so that um you ask yourself and you know for
yourself what do you need what do I need do I need more peace do I need more
calm do I need what kind of support do I need what kind of guide do I need what
kind of steadiness do I need I don't know what do what do you
need what kind of benevolence do you need to hold you along the
way because it's a practice it says here over and over
again one practices mindfulness of the body we keep going back back to
experience the body from the inside experience the body how the body experiences
itself because every moment that we are aware of a sense touch right there
there's a sense touch I can be aware of that I can register that and my
attention is mindfulness is growing so we're full of nerves with
sense contact to build mindfulness from the
inside with the body and through the
body and uh as we keep doing this as we keep doing this along the way we're
moving toward more and more
concentration the practice here after goes through all the body parts then moves into the the four absorptions
these great States of uh meditative calm and serenity and
concentration and um what's really really exciting for me is what happens
along the way because this discourse traces the gradual development of the
whole Buddhist path the whole Buddhist path can be understood as CA
ethics Samar concentration or meditation and Pa
wisdom and so we're being asked we have to as we do mindfulness as we know we we
look at our ethics we look at what is wholesome and what's not
wholesome in our thoughts in our realm right um because the more we align with
the wholesomeness The More We Get true with the whol
ESS the more we can actually have our
concentration and so before the absorptions usually
there's this um process of the hindering forces the
fear the dread the classic hindrances if you know those sensual desire and
restlessness and sloth and aversion not in that order and
doubt and one of the most interesting things about these hindrances I have
found is that hindrance of Doubt to
have no doubt of wholesomeness Doubt is doubt of
wholesomeness can be seen in the teaching in as doubt doubting
wholesomeness so to not doubt
wholesomeness to take that as a stand is tremendously
healing tremendously strengthening it is one of the fiercest
things I have found to make
wholesomeness front and center of
everything it Powers this mindfulness in a way that nothing else
can for me so far because it just allows the flowing
of what wants to emerge to emerge and it doesn't just doesn't Veer
into things that are not useful not helpful that hurt me because it's my own
thoughts this is all happening inside of me when I allow the UN wholesomeness in
here it's here that mindfulness is being
contracted I'm not it's not flowing it's not being aware it's not it put putting
walls so it's really a wondrous things once these hindrances Begin to Fall away
and the the teachings are encouraging us to be mindfulness of the body right so
to be paying attention to senses
and it's like when you know that aversion from a
few days ago stops is not here anymore maybe there was
some nice angry sad thought you had last
week that's not here in the same way so that
absence can be felt that as absence is something to
linger on as our hindering forces go away fade away
there's like this room to feel goodness from that and it's a goodness that's
really worthwhile to feel to cherish and to let
increase that's how deep concentration deep calm comes when we allow that when
we rest in that when we see that oh now I'm not thinking about that
anymore ah that feeling of relaxation that's like a
cheerleader so all those moments are like cheerleaders like go go keep going
keep letting go keep releasing keep going this is good this is the
way this is the way to be completely free in here
so that's what happens as we let ourselves go into concentration and seek
concentration so I'll just briefly mention kind of the verbs that I associate with the E this absorption
States because there are these um meditative states that require a lot of meditative
skill so there's this welling up welling up as we get more concentrated there's
just a welling up that happens after there's a saturation like the saturation
of those Feelgood moments of release when we're no longer being held back by
the thinking process the emotionals emotional emotions that were
that were really darkening us that were really aversive when those go away when
those Flow Away the practice is come notice take that in really rest in that really let
your body be full filled with that and these absorptions um are examples of
being filled up by this wholesomeness and they they met their
water metaphors um saturation welling up um being
contentedly satisfied and then ease and a bright
mind those are the things that await those are the things that are Ava become available through mindfulness of the
body and so we have this then and what what does what do we gain
from this to talk about that I'm going to mention these um two metaphors uh two
water metaphors for that the Buddha uses in this discourse so remember about the water
jug I mentioned so that water jug
when mindfulness has been fully developed it's an an example is that it's like a jug full of
water so what the Buddha says here that
jug is tipped over and the water is set
free water set free maybe water needs to be free maybe water is free in the world
and so it's a it's a metaphor for our mindfulness our awareness when our awareness is able
to is developed then our awareness is set free
to have deep insight has access to deep liberating
insight and for our purposes here it's to to really look at what happens to
suffering when we have a settledness to have a insightful
connection and contact with suffering as suffering
is we learn these amazing things about suffering we learn that suffering is not
constant right and not only is it not
constant there's a gap that opens up when we can see that suffering
ends and it's like we can just become that Gap we are no longer we know that
there's a place where there is no suffering that can become a reference
point the inner eye opens up to there is no
suffering or if there is suffering there is an end of suffering
it it's in constant and I can cultivate my way
there by resting this way in my
body in the awareness and then turning the awareness to see how suffering ing
actually
is and as we do that we tap into that place that I
mentioned in the guided instruction that I mentioned before that nonverbal
place there's a place beyond all the words all the
constructions all the thoughts all the ideas ideas that's just a
deep place of knowing in us and so we
can come from that place to look out to the world to be with this
world to be with this world first and then to be with the outer
world and that can be a beautiful place literally a beautiful place
because that's a place where we can choose from a place of self assurance of steadiness of
calm Happiness joy Clarity and it's really important at
this time more than ever maybe for us in
this age because we can choose what actions we
want to take and we can look at the consequences of those of those actions and choose actions that are
wholesome wholesome actions are beautiful
Karma we can give beautiful Karma which is another other way of saying Good
Karma not bad karma and we can bring this out into this world to meet this
world if you're friendly others may be friendly but if you're hostile others
may be become hostile when you demonstrate care for the welfare of others they may care for
you let's make a better world for everyone who faces Prejudice hostility and
disrespect Let's help everyone Prosper with the necessities of
life and let's build a society where everyone respects respect each other
without demeaning anyone so to do this so to meet our
world from our deepest place of goodness and wholesome by aligning ourselves
completely and utterly with wholesomeness all the
time all the time it's amazing to do
that thank you very much for your attention and for your presence here