so welcome everyone we'll go ahead and get started it's delightful to be
joining all of you this week this week that will take us through the new year
and I'm happy to see so many of you here so this time of year the turning
over of a new year is a time when people reflect and consider what changes they
might like to make and that's kind of arbitrary of course you know the turning of the New Year it's it's all a
continuous revolution around the Sun but uh you know not completely so this time
of uh dark and quiet is a natural time to go Inward and consider what we would
like to encourage to come forth when we have the renewal of
spring and sometimes when people reflect like that it's about uh letting go of
something you know let something that we could be doing less of and other times it's about cultivating
or creating or starting up something so this week we're going to talk about
various aspects of the Dharma that support or surround or provide context
to the actions of Letting Go and cultivation and we'll say more about
that after the sit that's a bit of a a taste so let's go ahead and get started
with our meditation together finding a posture for for sitting and settling
in allowing yourself to arrive mentally for
meditation and if you'd like to you can close your eyes to bring the attention
inward softening the attention bringing it in to the body
maybe taking a long slow deep breath and on the
exhale allowing the body to settle down maybe bringing attention
consciously down into the heart area and even down into the belly
sometimes this time of year is actually quite a busy one with guests or other
activities and just allowing yourself to release any sense of that kind of energy that may be
[Music] lingering we don't have any rush in
sitting here
inviting some softening into this posture
softening the face the forehead around the
eyes the
jaw softening the neck the shoulders
sometimes I imagine a little space between the very top of the spine and the
skull so there's a little dropping of the [Music]
chin letting the shoulders
soften maybe Imagining the shoulder blades sliding down the back
relaxing the arms and the
hands and then all down through the Torso chest
area [Music]
diaphragm down into the Bell B and including the muscles of the low
back and as all of that gently releases to the degree possible we can feel the
weight really settling into where we're sitting chair or
cushion or maybe you're lying down that's fine
feeling the weight settling into what's supporting
us and allowing that to happen really feeling the contact with
where you're sitting and the stability it
provides and also softening and releasing the legs all the way down to the
feet feeling the relative Stillness or
being in a sitting meditation posture
as you release into that seeing if there's a way that the body will
straighten itself up
naturally when we hold ourselves into certain positions which we do all the
time in subtle ways the body can lose touch with a
natural sense of
uplift what as we soften and Trust what's holding us up in this
moment there can be a feeling that the head gets pulled upward spine
naturally straightens without any strain just seeing if that's available
for you it works even if you're lying down
the spine will straighten out
soften and if there are parts of the body that are sore today
or have other issues you can just let them be bringing a sense of it's okay however
the body is right now body works hard for
us just inviting it to be included as it is
perhaps sensing the breath coming in going out natural breath
just temporarily let's direct the mind to bring
up some sense of intention or inspiration or
motivation for your practice it doesn't have to be anything
Grand it could just be today's sense of why are you meditating here right
now or it could be something larger if that's what comes to
mind but just tuning in to that wholesome
motivation however it is for
you and in particular today let's really let that register in the
body one way to do that is to breathe breathe it
in or maybe you can just sense how the body
feels while the mind is attuned to this
[Music] inspiration doesn't have to be any particular way but just registering what
it is in the body maybe you already do that or maybe it's novel to bring the
body into this otherwise mental activity let just see how that is
perhaps you can feel the goodness of a skillful motivation and let that register also in
the
body now we can release this deliberate thought or directing of the
mind and just return to mindfulness of things as they're
[Music] unfolding if you like to connect with the breath or the Body Sensations as
your normal object you can bring that in
just being with the flow of experience in a natural
way
e e
and when you find the Mind drifting off or caught
up in thought which is very normal
you may want to just touch in again briefly to the
inspiration or motivation or intention that you had earlier not at all as a way of
reprimanding the mind but actually as a way of supporting
it encouraging
it maybe Feeling Again that sense of uplift or what you felt in the body with
it and using that as a something that attracts the Mind back
to the present moment and then just go on with the
meditation sometimes the mind is like a small child and that it's easily distracted
but also easily comes back when reminded and
redirected to the present
moment
e
e e
sometimes the mind can even develop a little bit of momentum around
this inspiration or motivation kind of like when we have
momentum on a bicycle small deviations from
being perfectly balanced will rebalance themselves
spinning wheel will move back toward the center if it's spinning fast
enough in the same way if we're in touch with this goodness of
practice it can actually be like when the Mind goes off a little bit it
naturally moves back in that doesn't always
happen but sometimes we can tune into that
energy and if it's not present then just bringing it back each time with the
reminder of our inspiration strengthening that very
quality
e
e e
in the last few minutes of this meditation
we may wish to tune [Music] in to any effects that might have come
from being more consciously connected to your intention or
inspiration during this sit is there a different
feeling in the mind in terms of mindfulness or
alertness or ease or happiness is there a different feeling
of energy in the body it may be a subtle
effect or it may be quite noticeable or maybe you don't notice
anything the invitation is just to see if there's been any effect
and perhaps consider if even if there isn't a direct
feeling is there some way that this seems clearly supportive for you
beneficial to have connected in this
way is there any sense of nourishment or care in the heart that it
brings and just tune into that
and as we are coming to the end may consider also
that what we're carrying in our heart and mind as to what we're doing and why
we're doing as we're doing our various intentions also affect
others even without saying them or having to do anything obvious
the very thing that we're carrying inside does affect the way that we interact with
people there's a way that they can kind of feel that at some subconscious level
so it does matter it does Ripple out into the
world going to the grocery store with the intention of just getting all the
stuff you need as quickly as possible so you can get out is different than going to the grocery
store with the intention to find all the things you need but to also be aware of
those around you or supportive of other people in the store that has a different
effect so what we're carrying in our mind in terms of intention does
matter can be highly beneficial okay
okay so as I said just briefly before the
sit this is a time of year when people are often reflecting on the prior year
and considering the upcoming year and often there is a
sense that we could be letting go of or doing less of certain things and maybe
also picking up or cultivating or doing more of certain things it's kind of a
natural time to reflect in that way and there's a suta from the dapada that kind
of captures these movements I'll give Gil's
translation doing no evil engaging in what's skillful and purifying one's mind
this is the teaching of the Buddhas so maybe we could say not doing what is
unskillful engaging in what's skillful and cultivating the mind um you know
this is the basic teaching that all the Buddhists have offered and I think it's
offered in other spiritual Traditions also so these verses kind of capture what
many meditators are trying to frame in our so-called New Year's
resolutions I hesitate to use that word a little bit it's a kind of a cultural idea that we have here about doing that
um because sometimes we can really create Dua in our relationship to these
kind of year and ritual and you know it doesn't always come out so well when we
um set some Grand goal for ourselves that's not really achievable and you
know we fall off of it within a week or two and then feel bad and somehow
stumble on into February so we don't want to be we don't want to be getting
caught in that cycle so we have to be wise in our actions of Letting Go and
cultivation and um we can notice also that you know that dap verse is very
general it's about just you know being careful about being unskillful and
wanting to be skillful and developing our mind so it's not really about anything special of the New Year it's
also just about how we walk the path so even if you're your mode is I don't Enga
I don't engage in any of that new year stuff that's great these uh what we'll reflect on this week will also help in
just our normal walking of the path doing the practice in our daily life so
this week we're going to talk about several key Dharma topics that support
or surround or provide context to these ideas of Letting Go and cultivation and
so you know maybe we'll put it'll provide some tools and perspectives that help us approach these activities in a
wise way so these are things that will help make letting go and cultivation
more effective more likely to actually go in the direction that we want um and
we'll talk about them overall five days so you could think about using these five days as a way to explore around the
different ways that you engage with letting go in cultivation in your own practice however that looks for you
whatever phase you're in of that sometimes our actions in that area are
are in the realm of relationality we're thinking about working on our uh connections with others sometimes
they're more about personal habits that we want to change sometimes we're not into the kind of external cultivation at
all and we're thinking about you know how can I structure my life so that I can go and Retreat more how can I fit in
a one month Retreat during this year all of those things are things that we need to uh engage with in terms of things
we're going to let go of things we're going to bring forth so wherever you are in your practice
I think these five days will be of benefit the Dharma does not care that
you have a clear exact well articulated resolution on December 31st at midnight
so relax about that and just uh just take all five days as a kind of a unit
can spread it out so maybe one thing to First
recognize about these activities of Letting Go and cultivation is that they are very intertwined
you know it's they seem like opposite movements um but they're actually highly
connected and in particular sometimes um well I want to take both sides both
sides of a uh of a proposition the first is sometimes I think we need something
in place before the heart is willing to let go things that we have cultivated or
put in place sometimes are needed to give us the strength to let go so if
you're having trouble letting go of something consider if there is something that might need to be cultivated
first okay so that's one way we can start to be wise about this I remember
that there was a time when I wanted to let go of resentment that I had toward a
certain person it was so clear that I needed to let go of that it was only harming me it was kind of continual in
my mind I could see that I really wanted to release this resentment I was
carrying and I did have a certain amount of meta for this person so I felt like I
should be able to uh to let go of that but um they kind of these thoughts kept
persisting and finally I discovered uh through meditation practice it kind of
came to me in an Insight that I actually needed to forgive this person um first
and when I did that once I had cultivated I deliberately turned to cultivating forgiveness instead of
cultivating meta and trying to let go once I cultivated forgiveness and that
really came through in me it was so easy to let the resentment go so I wasn't
able to let go until I had cultivated this other thing okay so that can happen
sometimes um because of the intertwining of Letting Go in cultivation it goes the
other way also so there are times where we can't cultivate something until
something else lets go so if you're having trouble cultivating something
maybe consider if you're grasping onto something that is preventing that and it
needs to be let go first if your hand is closed around something it might need to
release that before it can pick up what you're trying to cultivate so the classic example that
goes with this is people want to cultivate concentration or somat a lot
of people would like to have that on the cushion and so they sit down and they try very hard to be on the breath to
cultivate concentration they're told just be on the breath be on the breath and somehow they've forgotten
that concentration happens when we've let go of the hindrances that's actually when
concentration comes it's actually more about letting go so we're often uh
caught up in the hindrances and one reason that we can't release them is
that we actually we're grasping them we like the hindrances that's one of the issues with them that would be a whole
separate discussion but just as a small example there's a way often that we grasp onto aversion or unhappiness or
you know something negative in our life and we've grasped on to that we think we think it's important that we oppose that
or that we we've identified somehow with our dep depression or our unhappiness in
some way and until we release the idea that that's necessary for us to have and
to keep going back to we won't be able to be happy enough to be concentrated so
sometimes we have to let go of something and really turn toward it and figure out how to release it before we can
cultivate what we wanted to cultivate and that's a you know that's a
sort of a technical meditation example but um also I recently watched a
documentary um that included a story about a a woman who had been told for a
long time um that she couldn't do math you know she was kind of pushed aside
and said well you're just not a math person you know you can't really do that and she wanted to pursue a a job that
required her to take some math classes and pass those in order to to get this degree um
but she had been told her whole life that she wasn't really a math person and so she was carrying a false view that
this was just impossible for her very difficult she would have all kinds of aversion and struggle every time she had
to learn math and eventually she realized that this was just a view that she had been told um and so she worked
hard instead to release that idea about herself and she also had you know some
support from teachers who cared about her and once she released that view she discovered that she could actually do
math and she didn't want to be a mathematician but she had to pass these math classes in order to get the degree
to get the job she wanted and she did but she had to let go of a view of
herself before she could achieve that no matter how hard she tried she couldn't
until she let go so we may find that in ourselves also is there some view
perhaps about yourself that you're holding but you can't cultivate something until you let it
go so these are very intertwined and sometimes you know we can't just choose
to let go of something or to cultivate something we might have to do the other one
first sometimes our personality favors uh one of these movements over the other
like it's easier for us in general to let go um and not as easy to cultivate
or it's easy for us to cultivate and go out and pursue and develop but not as easy to let go so um check that out in
your own mind and because we're going to have to learn both of these skills at some point and gain wisdom around
balancing them so
um let's also mention today the um in addition to this uh idea of how these
intertwine uh that the Dharma mentions that there are three wise or skillful
intentions in our practice uh and I want to just name them so that we can see um
how they relate to these ideas of Letting Go and cultivation uh one thing about the word
intention I mean of course all these words are translations um I I hope that the word intention even
though it sounds kind of future oriented um the way I think of the difference between say an intention and
a goal or resolution is that goals and resolutions are about the future they
they put a pin into the future and say that's the point I'm aiming for whereas
I feel like an intention is something that I'm putting in the present I don't
know exactly where it's going to go in the future but at the moment I'm pointing myself in a particular
direction when I walk there I don't know quite what I'll find so it's a little bit different I think of intentions as
being in the present and goals as being in the future and so intentions are really what we have in this practice um
you know more present oriented the three wise intentions are named as number one
is renunciation we're letting go so there we go right there it's named as a wise
intention the second is a non-ill will that's how the PO is listed it's non-ill
will sometimes it's turned into Goodwill or meta something as the positive
movement and the third is non- cruelty and sometimes that's turned into
compassion although we'll talk more about that that term later this week so we have letting go and then the
cultivation of something that's in the realm of non-harming trying not to harm in some way so we see right away that in
the three skillful intentions uh we have letting go and cultivation of certain
qualities so those will maybe frame as we go forward in the week so in addition
to the um the quote I gave at the beginning about not doing what is unskillful doing
what is skillful and cultivating or purifying the mind we can bear in mind
one other Su quote I want to just finish with which is that the Buddha
said it is possible to abandon what is unskillful if it were not possible to
abandon what is unskillful I would not say to you abandon what is
unskillful and on the other side it is possible to cultivate what is skillful
if it were not possible to cultivate what is skillful I would not say to you
cultivate what is skillful so this is all quite doable able this is all quite doable but we do
have to understand the Dynamics of the process we have to be wise about
balancing these and doing them in the right way and at the right time so that's what we're going to get into over
the next several days of this week and I hope you'll you'll join and find some
application of it in your own life and practice so thank you