hello everyone very nice to be here and hearing about the potluck next week I'm
looking forward to coming uh it's great to bring something but don't let that
keep you away if you don't have anything it's fine to come it's just uh just
wonderful to be here so um so you can hear okay everyone
okay so um
I thought I would describe to you a sequence that can be a reference point
for how to meet anything how to be in the middle of whatever is
happening and it can be used in meditation it can be used when
meditation is going to help you deal with the challenges of life it can be
used in stepping forward aom meditation into the world and to find your
way and sometimes it's nice to have a sequence a series of practices to do and
it makes a little bit easier to know what to do because this world is so complicated and um So It
Begins by the practice of not knowing uh and so in meditation it means
you begin by not coming with knowing who you are knowing what you're about
knowing the situation but preparing yourself to know and this idea that we
need of preparing ourself getting ready to know something so and that's just not
that's not only true in meditation but uh some people say Now with uh uh with
this not last election that we just had that maybe now is a time for preparation
for what's coming and so maybe that begins by not knowing not knowing what
to do what's supposed to happen what actually the situation is and there's
value in not knowing because often when we come to meditation come to challenges
in our life the knowing we come with sometimes is not so
helpful sometimes the knowing we come with comes with comes with judgments comes with old memories ideas of what's
going on and um and we're projecting onto the world projecting onto ourselves
uh a kind of knowing uh if you go meet meet meet someone maybe for the first time uh but
the clothes they're wearing reminds you of some kind of person that you think
is not the kind of person you want to hang out with and um and so you're
coming with a pre-existing knowing that you project onto that person based on their
close and but instead to do this process is that you would begin by not
knowing who is this person let me not carry with me my old associations let me
find a way to clear my my eyesight clear my hearing to find out who who is this
what is this let me not know let's not begin by no by knowing let me Begin by
not knowing and uh and not knowing that can
meditation can involve relaxing uh I wouldn't
underestimate uh the tremendous value of relaxation of calming of
settling because when we're not relaxed when we're not calm or settled there is
an agitation or a tension that is squeezing or pushing some of the
projections some of the prej es some of the preconceived ideas that we bring
with us it's kind of like U you know if you squeeze a
toothpaste uh you know tube when the when the cap is off it's just going to
keep coming out and so if you're a tense something's going to keep coming out
pushing and kind of a compulsion sometimes to think certain ways or be certain ways feel certain things and
there's something about relaxing softening gentling settling
calming that stops that kind of pushing of our ideas pushing of our prejudice
and preconceived ideas and our projections of what's going to happen so that we can come into a deep State a
healthy state of not projecting not assuming not re
associating not coming with prejudice preoccupations but showing up
fresh new with new eyes and I call that the the practice of not
knowing so we prepare ourselves and if it's in meditation I don't know how long you have to prepare yourself to meditate
to the next steps that's up to you but maybe it's a few minutes maybe it's longer if you could do a day long like
some of us did yesterday maybe it's the first two meditation sessions that that has this flavor to it
if it has to do with uh International world affairs and uh you you're the one
who's supposed to solve them that preparation might be much
longer to really get really kind of clear your mind clear your heart to be
ready to really do the next step and the next step is to
discover now this is the place where you get to know but now you're you're here
to discover what what's right here discover something new discover without
the lenses of prejudice or preconceived ideas that we tend to bring pre
prejudged ideas and uh and so now look carefully what is here what's happening
so in meditation how are you right now what's actually going on here and now
it's not an easy thing to stop and do because for some of us the mind is keeps
spinning it's thinking about things thinking about our issues thinking about the future fantasizing doing something
that stands in the way of really checking in with ourselves and in meditation one of the I
think very profound aspects of meditation is a chance to meet
yourself to really meet yourself in a deep intimate close way to discover
what's here and not only to meet yourself and do that discovery
but uh to find a way to meet yourself that comes out of this not
knowing but is respectful is kind is caring for this person just like we hope
it would be that way in meeting someone else that we meet someone we we are there to be present to respect to be
kind to to get to know them well yesterday I talked about um
my experiences in life with meeting people uh uh sometimes with
handshakes and um I once met a a candidate for
president many years ago and um and uh I think I was behind a little fence or
something and the candidate was walking down and shaking hands and and um so I I
oh good I get to shake this person's hand and as soon as the person's hand touched my
the person the candidate was already looking over to the next person and and
there was this limp limp hand like oh what was that like you know it was like
there was no contact there was no seeing being seen being recognized it was like
I was just almost like an instrument or something to just I don't know what to pass by and move on to the next person
who was more important or something so um so this you know there
could be that kind of meeting uh there is then the meeting of um of someone really stopping and
shaking your hand in a nice way and you feel like they're really there for you and they're stopping and they're curious
they're interested in you uh you're important for them the equivalent for this when I was
in the Zen Monastery was that uh in the M Monastery there's a tremendous amount
of bowing going on and once I counted how many times I bowed from the from the
time I woke up in the morning I think which was 4:00 in the morning until maybe 10 so and I think I got close to a
100 bows and uh but uh what happens in the monastery is that every
bow carries a little bit of significance like you're supposed to bow to people
when they pass they when you all kinds of times you're supp to Bow people like if you pass them in the pathway you're supposed to bow to people if they serve
you meals which they often were doing theyd serve you their food you'd bow before and bow after and um and so much
was communicated by how you bowed you know like if if you kind of
didn't like them or kind of angry with them you know like you you know you you're kind of like a
little just a little little kind of you know just you know maybe you bow an
inch and and your hands wouldn't really come together but you were about
right uh or sometimes you know You' bow really deeply or sometimes when you the
idea when you saw them coming down the path and you knew you had to P you bow and you pass them uh you just went the
wrong way around so there was a lot of things that
got conveyed through these bows so was part of the richness of the monastery was to study and see all these things
that uh were were involved with bowing that highlighted who we are what was
going on in the the moment so how do you meet yourself how do you bow to yourself
the meeting is really important so first not knowing and then meeting yourself discovering meeting and discovering
being the same thing here really discover what's here and the layers of what's here and I'm surprised sometimes
that uh like you know after the election for me there was layers of emotions and
I had maybe the first recognition that I I felt dismay or something something and
um and that was strong enough uh and I was just operating like kind of doing my
life I I busy doing things and and just kind of carrying this feeling that I
just kind thought was dismay and um but then when I sat to meditate then I saw oh there's layers
here there's fear there's uh there's for me a little
different than fear is alarm there is anger there is all kinds of things and
and as I went through them all it was kind of oh oh I was kind of delighted as
opposed to caught in the grip of them because that's what happens when you
start with not knowing if you start with knowing then you fold what you discover
into that preconceived ideas preconceived attitudes preconceived judgments and it's a lot diffic more
difficult the the advantage of not knowing and you know and you feel yourself what's going on oh look at that
there's fear who would have guessed and and uh and you're but the
how you meet is so important so oh there's fear this needs attention this needs
care this needs kindness so H so so there's a process of
discovery discovery of what's Happening with your thinking what you're thinking about more deeply than that maybe what
you're feeling what the emotions are more deeply that sometimes is deep under
underground kind of attitudes with which we carry ourselves into the world and so
as we relax and calm we start going through the layers and start meeting
more and more parts of who we are and in different days we meet different parts of ourselves as different days there's
different things to meet here and uh and so two people coming
meditating at the same time might have radically different experiences of meditation uh because they're coming
from different events in their life or different things that they're concerned with and they're meeting different
things and because of that meditation uh mindfulness serves a different function
for them because of what their need is given what's happening so so that comes to the third
so not knowing Discovery and then the third one is the
gift the gift what's the gift
here and then that's an odd odd thing to do to ask what's the gift here and part
of the gift can be what's the gift you have to offer how do you like if you're sitting
in meditation what's the generous thing to do here to
yourself maybe this is a time when you do loving kindness that's the gift maybe
this is the time that you um uh really now say okay now is the time to be my
own companion I'm going to companion my anger I'm going to companion my fear
just like a good friend might you might take a walk in the park with them and they they're mostly just there to
accompany through your grief and it's just so good to have someone there accompanying you who's not going
to fix you and not going to judge you and not going to say aren't you over by
now we've been talking about your grief for five minutes you know it's enough already we
have to talk about you know the warrior scores you know that that doesn't work
you know you really just accompany you know your friend so you accompany yourself that's a gift that we can do
for ourselves and we don't know how long that's needed until we go through it at some point you
feel oh yes something releases something lets go something
opens maybe the gift is
freedom and uh and this is kind of the calling card of the Dharma freedom and
so what's the gift of Freedom here and it might be that you give your
fear freedom you give your anger Freedom you give Your Love Freedom you give
your your patience Freedom you you give freedom to what's
here maybe even you give freedom to your thoughts maybe that's what's needed is
not resist your thinking not try to change it not to judge it and be horrified by it or whatever but and and
maybe also what's not needed is to keep fueling it
participating in it but there's a whole other way of giving freedom to your thinking mind will you get out of the
way and so the compulsive fitivity the pushing of the toothpaste tube is
stopped you give freedom to your tube to just be a tube without you you know squeezing the life out of
it and so this freedom and I love the idea that uh the
word emotion comes from the word has the word Motion in it the e is a Latin prefix that means
out so moving out all emotions are moving out or all emotions should be in
motion but we get stuck we resist we hold on we get tight we get somehow
afraid we get alarmed a lot of things that kind of keeps the the gears inside
from moving and so the idea is how do we give freedom to our emotional
life uh liberate your grief liberate your
anger not to get rid of it but rather to let it flow
freely because in in a certain circumstances where you're not participating in the grief not
participating in the anger uh but you're giving it Freedom it
has a chance to evolve and Flow and heal and do what it needs to do it has a
chance to Pro to give you the message that it wants you to
hear and so let let it free and one of the I think one of the greatest places
in the world least for me there's two great places for me for really giving
freedom to my emotional life is in meditation where I know I'm not going to
punch someone out it's safe so I can feel my anger just let it flow and move through me and
then to discover something new about it to see what happens it might be that
there's a relaxing then with the anger or opening up for something and maybe underneath the anger it turns out
there's fear and so then oh that's interesting underneath the fear there might be love
even there might be a capacity for k care and kindness oh that's what's going
on at the root what a great thing to have done giving freedom to my anger led
me through these layers that I tapped into something deeper so the um giving
freedom and uh leaving things
alone and so what's the gift what's the gift we give
ourselves the gift of Freedom the gift of gift of kindness the gift of
understanding it's invaluable to discover deeply and well what's going on
so I said there are two ways I deal with you know strong emotions one is I love sitting like this in this posture and
the other is I love going for a Hikes go alone in the mountains and go for a long hikes and that also just lets it flow
and there's a different way that it flows when when I'm walking because when when I walk I let my mind think what it
wants to think in meditation I kind of stop
thinking and uh and it's valuable to let the mind just flow but because I'm
walking I don't get caught in my thoughts they stay you know I kind of constantly kind of not letting go of
them but kind of staying staying limber loose kind of staying unattached to them and they just kind of flow and flow and
that helps this process also because thinking and emotions have a wonderful Synergy and so there's something
important about how they work together to see deeply what's going
on so the gift and just asking yourself that question what's the gift here and I
say that uh with with the intentional idea that there's two kinds of
gifts what's the gift you want to give to you're the one meeting yourself or
meeting the world and what's the gift of this situation to
you what is it to learn what is it to be what is it what is there to be changed
what is it to be transformed what is there to be received and so from yourself or from the
world and so sitting in meditation and uh and saying what's the
gift here what's the gift of fear have you ever asked yourself that or you just
you know Fe afraid and that's good enough no what's the gift of fear what's
the gift of anger what's the gift of love what's the gift of
respect what's the gift of compassion what's the gift of mindfulness what's the gift of presence
what comes out of it for you what what's the message what's the attitude what's
what's possible to it and one of the ideas of the gift is that
um you've made yourself ready for it the not knowing and then the knowing
the discovery the me really the meeting of the situation it kind of is getting
ready what is the gift so it can register so you can feel it and know it
in a deep way and um the gift of setting an
emotion free inside is that uh maybe now you have
confidence that you don't have to be caught in the grip of the emotion you've
learned that it's okay there's a possibility of having strong emotion but not be glued to it not be entangled with
it not be defined by it identified with it but just it's almost like wow there's
there's fresh share there's breathing room here by giving it freedom in the
context of mindfulness there's breathing room that's the gift who would have
known what's the gift and what's the gift that you that
you want to offer the situation so not
knowing Discovery and then uh what's the gift
and then this third step is to uh after the last step of this process is what do
you want to bring with you now what do you want to uh be different now having
done this process how do you want to be different how do you want to live differently how do you want to act
differently and uh what have you learned that that that has shown you something
that yes I want to be different in some way without a desire to be different
you might stay stuck simply the willingness and the openness to be different loosens
something loosens the the you know up the it like lubricates the gears so
something can move and change again if you don't want to
change well good luck I mean that in two ways
one is then you really won't change some of the ways you're stuck so easily and the other is yeah good luck
you'll change anyway we're always changing but if you're stuck in something you might
change for the worse if you're stuck in your anger and resentments and that's what you're
churning away in and you're not going to give it up and you continue feeding that and
living in that it just gets worse and wor worse something gets kind of debilitating or drained out of
us we're always changing and we could be involved in
having some Choice over what change we allow for ourselves what change we want to how we want to change by asking the
question having gone through this process now what what would I like out of this maybe that first step was so
impactful relaxing they say oh I want to be careful that I don't tense up I want to
be careful and to bring that more of this calming into my daily life maybe I'll set a timer for on the hour to
remind myself to pause for 10 seconds and relax maybe that's what that's what how
you want to change maybe the Second Step was impactful it was like eye opening to
stop and take a look and see what's going on and to learn and you say I think I need to do this more often I
think I need to kind of get to know my when I run into someone take the time to know them before
I say something silly or joke with them or say something I've told the story
many times of a friend of mine showed up and I I just was immediately kind of
silly and said something only to find out that I think his best friend had just died
and I was kind of so you know so so disappointed that I
had acted that way not not taking time to know my friend and find out where who the person what was going on before I
kind of barreled ahead and and so maybe that's the gift that
you how you want to change is to get to take time to get to know people situations before you prejudge
them or maybe it's a the gift of kindness or the gift of giving other
people Freedom or the gift of caring for people's welfare and and uh living
living in a good way in Buddhist Meditation that's often one of the gifts
that is regularly reflected on at the end of any significant Dharma event it
could be your own meditation it could be some Dharma ceremony D and we do at the
end of every Retreat is uh it's called we call it at
IRC we call it dedication of benefit traditionally it's called dedication of
Merit and that is to um consider how the
benefits of this event can be used to benefit the
world and um and so at the end of every meditation I spend a little bit of time
now I've meditated that's nice now is there any way from this that I could
now uh benefit others can I make this world a better place and if you get a
big no because you're overwhelmed and exhausted um then maybe it's simply I
just I'm just going to sympathize with other people who are exhausted I can at least do that Comm
commiserate with them maybe that's nice for them to know that they're recognized and
understood but what is it that how is it that coming out of meditation that you
can be different that you can change and and in the Buddhist tradition
this idea of living for the benefit of others um is done for your own
benefit partly because to not there's something
about not living for the benefit of others that actually limits us it's kind
of a being closed down or being shut down or the heart's not really open
something is is you know is being clouded
over and the idea is to step forward in the world with no
limitation and if we're Unlimited in our freedom I it's I think it's a natural
thing to Delight in people to love people to care for people to want this
world to be a better place if we go if we don't do this
process and we're caught in fear caught in
Anger then there's a danger that what we spread into the world is more fear more
anger I'm struck very much struck that uh um moved uh feel like it's a profound
thing that uh if a parent lives
afraid as they raise a young child the child learns the world is a frightening
place is and is that the best way to raise a child to have that
anxiety so a parent I I hope really takes this idea
seriously in order to want to change to not be spreading more fear
into the world world but to do so it with sincerity and honesty and
authenticity maybe doing this process start with not knowing relaxing
and calming so there can be a deeper and deeper discovery of what fear is and where it comes from and how to relate to
it so that maybe there's a discovery of how to the gift would be to give that
give that fear Freedom or as I like to often say
a a big huge task with chronic fear is to give the fear help the fear feel
safe help the fear feel safe that's what it most wants a young child who's afraid
mostly wants to be held so this is safe now you're here it's okay now you're
safe with me let me give you a cookie you know and they just feel like they're protected a little bit our fear
is that way also so the gift would be help that fear feel safe inside of us
safe from what most likely it's from you because of how we relate to
it and um so how do you want to change so the
world is a better place and one of the ways to really make
the world a better place is to do this process over and over again to meditate
meditate to practice to clarify to open up discover the gifts of what it is to
be a human being and bring those gifts into the
world and um and that's so as I said in the beginning so that's true in
meditation and it's true for not only international events of cos Cosmic
events in this Cosmos we live in uh that we can do this process of not
knowing which is also a preparation to be ready to do
something then Discovery meeting ourselves asking the question what's the
gift and the get what's the gift to offer what's the gift to
receive and then how to how to go from here in a different way to benefit the
world benefiting yourself how do you want to change how do you want to be
different and then go forth into the world and you'll probably forget about
it very quickly so we do it again and it again
and so in meditation you can do this four parts process you could do this
four part process uh talking with a friend let's go through this four part
process let's not know here first then let's discover let's just
talk together what's the gift here and how do we want to change we could do it slowly we can
Journal about it we can spend days on each step if it's a really big thing in our life that we don't know
about so so if this interests you and seems like a nice four-step process
I think it's a wonderful kind of um thing to to live by and a
wonderful way of um orienting yourself in this life and um and uh it's kind of a
reframing of the basic Buddhist practice of mindfulness which is a profound
process and this is one way of understanding this process not knowing discovery the
gift and then living differently going
forth so we have a few minutes and um any comments
questions clarifications anything anybody like to
I appreciate it that you talked about the emotions and kind of welcoming them
and letting letting yourself feel them because for me I've had to feel a lot of
emotions that I'm very uncomfortable with but I feel like that's that is part
of the job right now it's part of what's in front of me so thank you
yeah yeah emotions are a huge part of being human being so learning how to be wise about them and familiar with them
and and uh is part of the task we're not supposed to reject them but you know
what's the gift being in being
emotional it's odd how the word emotional kind of has negative
connotations I think that person is too emotional but what else are we supposed to
do yes good morning thank you for very timely talk this was very important
because I went through all the Dynamics that you described in terms of emotional reaction to the to the election that
happened um but I wanted to ask I this morning I I've been very fearful of what
is might be happening in in uh Ukraine um with the current
Administration and the all bad things that are happening in a theer of war and so forth and I read an article in New
York Times that I essentially the shed a different uh light on the
situation what it what the author said of this in this piece was that um this
war that's going on over there is costing a lot of life and uh is really
not solving anything and the perpetrator of the war are not just Russia and
Ukraine but also United States that in in a process of
providing uh just enough ammunition and help and support and financial and so
forth is are we are trying to diminish Russia we are trying to make Russia
smaller in the process without helping Ukraine win the war so the very fact
that this person administ rtion is planning to potentially this is a part of not
knowing is potentially might be aiming to to really bring this war to a
conclusion but not in in the terms that we have favored in terms of Ukraine winning and getting their territories
back and all that but in but lots of compromise that will make Ukraine much
much smaller potentially but at least stops the um the Bloodshed and all these
horrible things are going on in the upcoming winter and all the grids are
essentially coming down and so forth so I just that gave me a different thought
maybe I was wrong in really having a a Prejudice or pre preconceived notion
that there's there's only one desirable outcome and maybe there's a different
different desirable outcome that is completely different from what I've taught yeah so so to so to then to to
tie it into what I said you had a preconceived idea about this situation
it's one of the one of these International challenges that we live with and then uh something inside of you
off something offered a different perspective on it that was a surprise for you and now you're reoriented around
this and wondering if there's a different attitude different way of responding and um and U that's a
wonderful process to be involved in questioning and looking and wondering and looking for new ways and um and uh
the the art of it all especially in a room like this and meditating and all that is to offer these words without
trying to offer the truth without saying this is now this is not the new truth but rather this is uh part of this
discovery process that we're all in and you've now contributed a little piece to it and um and and you also contributed
to the this wonderful fact that it freed you up it kind of loosen something for you and and which allows you to go
through this process in even better way because now you can relax even more and
discover even more what's going on and see so thank you so out in the outer
hole it's
coming push the button and help it like a
lockar um thank you Gil this was really so wonderfully timely um one of the
things I've been to manage the whole anxiety and
stress and of what happened in the election for me is horrifying is I've been telling myself
it's going to get worse before it gets better and I wanted to get your thoughts about that because to me as reflecting
on what you talked about that it's not that in a way it's not knowing but it's all way also kind of saying it is
knowing right well I'm I'm I'm reconciling that it may get worse and before it gets better um and I just
wondered what you thought about that is that really being unknowing or is it
not well I I don't know probably I'm not going to ask the question uh directly the way you know in terms of how you ask
the question uh it just seems to me that uh for a lot of us who are not in the
middle of the political world where there's a lot more information going on that um it's
it's we're partly in this phase of not knowing and getting and and Discovery
and it's a matter of really discovering and so if you have this idea that things will get worse before they get
better that's a very big generalization and uh it might be that some things get
worse and some things get better uh and uh and so it's important
maybe to make that distinction if we generalize about the state of everything as one single thing then we come to one
conclusion but if we have the ability to tease apart where there's benefits where
there's harm being done maybe it's possible to support the benefits how
things are going to get better uh and and somehow then contend then then we're in better position to contend about how
things get worse and chances are no matter who is going to win the election it would have been that way
think some things will get better some things will get worse and so so so you
want to be very careful that these ideas don't limit our ability to
discover and uh it's reasonable that you have that idea but my my words of
caution is be careful with it as a the generalization U um relax don't know and
then discover what actually is there is that okay that I answered like
that yes it is and what's what's also occurring to you is when when I came out
what I've been pondering is this question of factchecking and that there's been so
much delusion in the media and so that's for me an action that I'm taking is
whenever I see something I really go deep on not a lot of issues but a particularly like let's say one or two
where I really really really look at the source yeah and and for me that's um a
little bit of not knowing like keeping it in mind that I don't know you know yeah I'm being it's it's being said that
this is the truth but there's a lot of there's a lot of um of intention that
isn't really about the truth in those messages that I then I'm so I'm that's
one of the like what to do next is that's what for me I'm doing on and I'm
finding that very helpful very nice I love that factchecking and um and there's a couple
of things a few things that I'd recommend around the news is um when I was in the Zen
Monastery in the 1980s they had something back then some of you probably don't know about it's kind of there were
big pieces of paper and there was lots of what's called print on them and they
F they'd fold them sometimes at first in half and then in quarters and sometimes they roll them put rubber bands around
them and um and uh and I was talk to someone recently who grew up in Palo
Alto and he said all his friends and everyone uh took those and they would
put the rubber bands around them and around in the morning sometimes at 4:00 in the morning and deliver them to
people's driveways there was a whole Army of of teenagers who did that so um
so when I was in the monastery these things with big pieces of paper would show up and uh the the newspapers and um
but they always c not usually they came a few days late because we were deep in the mountains and there wasn't daily
traffic back and forth and and I discovered how different it was to read the news fresh news on the day versus
few days old that there was something that grabbed me when it was like the first day the paper the current paper it
was like was I'd be more alarm more attached more involved more like something but if I read the same thing
and I knew was old news I could do it in an even ma matter of fact kind of more
Curious way and it's gotten worse now because we we don't use the paper thing
anymore so now we're now now it's like minute to minute we're keeping up and so then it's really alarming really get
caught in it so there are ways of changing how we do the news one is to
actually wait and read it on Wikipedia we and uh it's not
necessarily accurate but it doesn't come with a kind
of language that is designed with headlines and first sentences to to to
excite you and pull you in uh there's not that click baiting going on and so
it's you can kind of read it in a different kind of way the other is there is some news services that will present
both sides of of a you know political side of things and one I forget the name
has uh both sides and then who they think is the cists news so you can kind
of study the same piece of news and how it's being presented different ways another one that's more recent is called
tangle t n GLE e which is also trying to offer serious news from both sides of
the of the partisan divide and so you get both and you get it engaged in an intelligent way and and uh so then then
it's easier I think to start being more uh care careful about what you take in
and how you respond to it so thank you all for being here and
being part of this and may you live a life of gifts