happy to be here with you so this is the second uh session on basic instructions
in mindfulness laying down the foundations for what we do and
um so yesterday I said that one of the functions of mindfulness of
breathing uh you know a a sincere but relaxed dedication to being present with
the breathing is not to succeed at that task but rather to have that task
highlight um how distracted we are how busy the mind is what we're caught up in
and one of the advantages of beginning that way is that uh then you succeed
right away uh if you try to stay present on the breathing but there's a lot of
forces of distraction then you can be frustrated right away
the other reason is that um
um that distraction is
um it's useful to think of distraction the more more that we're distracted more
we're ruminating caught up in our thoughts the more we're fixating on something like our emotions or memories
or what's happening around us our body experience the more we're caught up in
it the more it represents stress more it represents
tension and there's a feedback loop between tension and stress and more
distractability more uh T more rumination more distract
distraction so a very important part of meditation is really
relaxation reducing the stress that we have and one of the wonderful very
significant applications of Buddhist mindfulness practice in United States or
in the world now has been a a protocol a process called
mindfulness-based stress reduction and I'm not going to want to diminish the Val tremendous value of
that but from a Buddhist point of view if you study the teachings of the Buddha
they would it would be reversed it would be uh stress reduction based
mindfulness stress reduction based awareness so that we We Begin by
focusing on relaxing and with the proper kind of
softening easing relaxing then rather than a feedback
loop with more thinking there's a feedback loop to more awareness more
present moment attention so to assume a meditation
posture that supports two things supports
relaxation supports some sense of ease in the body
and that could be lying down it could be sitting it can be
standing and uh it could also be walking there's something called Walking
meditation and to assume a posture that works for
you and if all things are equal I suggest a seated
posture and so a posture that is allows you to be to
relax the second thing about the posture is a posture that brings with
it some degree of alertness a attentive
posture something that has some intentionality in it that we're
activating something that we have to be attentive to being present here
with so relaxation and alertness
together gently close the eyes or if you don't want to close them which is fine
perhaps lowering the Gaze so you're not looking at it
anything in particular just kind of a loose Focus as if you're looking at a mountain far in
the
distance and then to if your eyes are
closed also notice if you're have engaged your eyes as if you're looking
at something using your eyes primarily to be
aware and to let your eyes res rest in their
sockets eyes do not have to be
activated and often when we're stressed or tense
it affects the breathing breathing becomes sometimes more
shallow short sometimes breathing more in the
chest often if there's tension breathing is we there's more
work asserted in breathing
to gently take a
few somewhat deeper breaths maybe half as full as you could
if
you and then as you exhale to extend the exhale
it's almost as if there's an added relaxation Letting Go softening in the
body that allows a longer
exhale and relaxing as you exhale
and then to let your breathing return to
normal as you exhale especially at the end of the
exhale soof soften the belly relax let
go so in a natural way the exhale continues for a few
moments
as you exhale relax the
chest the rib cug
Letting Go a softening on the
exhale on the exhale softening the
shoulders
having the shoulders yield to the pull of
gravity
and as you inhale feel whatever tension there might
be in the area of the face and on the exhale soften the
muscles of the
face
if you notice that you're distracted distract the
chances are there's some place of tension
within pressure
contraction it could be in the thinking mind the area maybe in your head where
thinking is congested contracted
pressured as you exhale Relax The Thinking
mind relax the forces of
distraction
for
for and then to drop into your the your
body's experience of
breathing wherever in your body the experience of breathing is most
pronounced for you or clearest or easiest to
feel on the exhale relax
into that experience of
breathing
and if you find yourself being pulled into your
thinking appreciate that you know that that you see
that I appreciate the awareness that can know you're distracted and if you know it clearly
you are not distracted you're
Mindful and then see if there's any tension in your muscles your mind
associated with thinking or
not that you can relax on the
exhale and as you relax to
appreciate the awareness the
mindfulness that results the greater sense of being here
with your experience that
relaxing
evokes
for
as your lungs fill with with oxygen on the
inhale let your awareness spread out throughout your whole
body feeling it and then as you
exhale relax the whole
body release holding throughout the
body and as you relax release soften the
body no matter how little you're able to do even if
nothing see if there can come a natural natural
increase in feeling present
aware here
now
e
resting with your breathing but when you're
distracted be intent to know
that mindfulness is working to know you're
distracted and then see where you can relax
soften let go so that there's a heightened
sense of being present being
aware and into that awareness invite back the
breathing
for
e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to take a few moments to notice how you are right now
how you might be different from the beginning of the
meditation how are you in your
body how are you with your
breathing how are you with your mind
and how are you in your
heart and for the next three
breaths to relax on the exhale to relax as deeply and fully as
you can maybe with an extended
exhale
and then to consider going forth from this
meditation and after my teach teaching perhaps to encounter the world
people animals plants
neighbors people in the
community all places where you find people who have stress and
tension who maybe are suffering some way or other
and from whatever calm or subtleness that you
have to Aspire that the benefits of this
meditation can spread from here to benefit every everyone and everywhere
that your attention goes
any person any being that you think about meet
see may they be
happy may they be
safe may they be
peaceful may they be free
and may I may each of us contribute to that
possibility through being relaxed a relaxed calm peaceful
presence for others
[Music]
so hello and welcome to this second talk on introduction to mindfulness
practice and one of the very important principles
of mindfulness is Simplicity don't make the practice
complicated mindfulness is the capacity to be aware of our present moment
experience in a simple way and one of that areas of
Simplicity is to notice it um things as they are not as we wish
they are so if we're distracted if we're caught up in our
thoughts a successful moment practice of mindfulness is to
know that and then but to know it in such a way it's possible maybe it's a it's it's
sometime in the future for some of you but it's possible that in the knowing
the clear knowing we're distracted so we have to kind of step
back from being distracted our thoughts our thought stream just enough step back
we can really see it might still be going on so that we can almost as if or maybe
we do in our mind say oh this is distraction this is being
caught in thought and uh and uh and to be delighted in that
knowing and even no matter how difficult or challenging the thinking or the concern might be to have some deep
appreciation for the value of stepping back and seeing it knowing it
clearly so that's possible so simply to know that we're
distracted and over time come to appreciate that simple
knowing and that most forces of distraction most
things when we're caught up in anything the chances are that we're tense in some way something is tense inside of us and
the representative kind of example of how this might work is um uh seeing with
the eyes if you take your eyes and you find a little spot in front of you um
and you hold your eyes on that spot just fixate it on the spot don't let it f
move from that spot the eyes will actually tense up it's actually tiring
for the eyes to hold them on a little spot without moving what the eyes want
to do when they're relaxed free doing their own thing without our holding on
to something is the eyes float the the eyes move and Roam and
kind of just float around and we scanning the experience of what's
Happening not fixating on it and we might look at some small area but the Eyes by themselves will gently scan
and move they're relaxed but as soon as we kind of fixate there's a tension that
buildt up so the same thing with our uh distractability there's a tension that
builds up so one of the instructions in meditation is the importance of noticing
that tension noticing how we're tight in the shoulders in the belly and the chest
could be be in the hands in the thighs in the lower back shoulders shoulder
blade area it could be in the throat it could be in the jaw the nose the
cheeks around the eyes and the forehead it could be deep inside someplace deep
inside the skull there's many places where we can hold tension muscles get
tight and remember that just to know something is
the essence of mindfulness and to know it in such a way that it's kind of you really appreciate
knowing it which means that you're not caught up in the judging of it or
assigning meaning to it but rather you're appreciating stepping back oh I can see it I know it so there look at
that look at that tension look at all that uh tightness in my muscles and my
jaw look at that it might be it might feel it might be painful it might be
unpleasant and but don't be kind of distracted by the unpleasant don't be
caught in its orbit just kind of stepping back and saying oh that's
unpleasant but the essence of this then is can you relax can you soften some place in the
body soften the shoulders soften the eyes eyes if they're
fixated soften the muscles of the
face if you have a tension headache it can be really fascinating to scan
through the body to see where you can relax where is the tension and then see
as you relax especially relaxing the muscul of the of the head the face how
does it affect the tension headache the pain soften the
belly sometimes the tension in the body the physical tension is a direct
expression of tension in the mind preoccupation fixation in the mind and it's almost as if the mind this
is the metaphor that Buddha gave that the mind is a puppeteer and it has all these strings
uh from the you know the fingers of the Puppeteer going down to all the different muscles in her body and
constantly pulling and tugging on them um to make us tense and um you know it's
a and you'll probably notice sometimes that you're sitting maybe minding your own business quiet peaceful and suddenly
there's a thought of something terrible something that happened long ago and you get angry or something and the the the
the maybe the stomach tenses up and there's a fear or anger so the Puppeteer
has done its work and um but then there uh so certainly the the tension of the mind
can affect the body but there's a reverse that as the body
relaxes the mind also can relax as the body tenses more then that it fuels more
tense thinking and preoccupation so this movement of relaxing is such a useful One
releasing uh quieting and exactly what the activity
is for each of us it's a little bit different maybe so I keep using the word relax but it could be that for you a
better word is to calm calm the body uh sometimes I like the word gentle
gentle the body and um and uh or release the the body
another word I like is to ease ease
up be easy in the body be easy with how things are ease up on
things so whatever you understand this activity that I I I use as a generic
term or general term um relaxing um this is an Avenue a method
by which to awaken more awareness as we relax as we're more preoccupied more
distracted there's less present moment awareness available as we relax and open notice
how that allows for more simple present moment
awareness as that present moment becomes more available invite in the breathing some
people tend up when you they are told you know now focus on the breathing concentrate on breathing and then they
have the idea they have to concentrate and not be distracted not leave leave it and so they tense up and uh or even just
the movement of the mind we say you know bring the Mind back that movement of bringing the Mind back
so-called becomes kind of even that is kind of a tightening up and so the idea
is to find a way to be to awaken your mindfulness or allow it to kind of
continue so that there is no tensing up and one form of doing this it works for
some people is um once we notice we're back to some state of awareness to
invite the breathing into that awareness to invite it into a into attention to
invite it back into knowing and um and then to maybe rest
with it relax with it flow with it care be be carried by the movements of breathing in and breathing out until we
notice that we are distracted again distractive means that you're it's
almost like you know you are tensing up you are kind of getting preoccupied if there's if there's quiet
thoughts in the background uh and you're able to kind of just stay with the breathing uh just let
it be in the background don't worry about it but when the thinking comes in the foreground or predominates that's
when you want to uh uh let your attention notice your thinking and relax something and in the
relaxing maybe invite back your breathing so in this way hopefully
there's a developing of mindfulness meditation where you're learning not to be in conflict with any experience that
you're mindful of it's that's maybe a tall order but uh when you learn to do
it it actually keeps things much simple simpler conflict is is
complicated so um as you go about your day today um you could try noticing when
you're fixated on something preoccupied by something when you're zeroed in
because you have a lot of concerns or fear or anger annoyance or desires or
ambition or something and notice um the tension in your body
tension in your mind notice the tightening the narrowing and then see if you can relax
relax the body and for this day I'd encourage you to look for lots of
opportunities to keep coming back to your body to relax it relax as you drive
when you sit down in your car to drive relax before you start driving when you sit down to a meal don't just start
eating right away take you know some 10 15 seconds just to relax there and
soften um maybe occasionally between bites or you whatever look look for all
kinds of EX possibilities and see what that does in bringing a mindfulness
attention more fully into this day of yours so it's um stress reduction based
mindfulness as we reduce our stress mindfulness surfaces
so um thank you very much and I'll continue
with this tomorrow