good morning everyone and good day uh this morning's weing
um exploring some different practices skills
um we started the week with learning to
align our intentions uh using this arriving
sequence a way of practicing and then we expanded to
include pausing and then um with a little
emphasis on feeling and sensing of our
experience and today we'll expand a little more you kind of all have already
been doing it but this um um practicing with the don't know
mind and so all of this are something that um were very meaningful for me when
I first learned this um from a wonderful Dharma teacher and practitioner Philip
Moet and so let's begin begin from the side of the
meditation maybe taking a few long deep breaths as we
begin this may be a way of a
pausing pausing to interrupt the flow of thinking
doing pausing to allow mindfulness to come to the
foreground and ini initially mindfulness may feel
flickering in and
out allow yourself to Simply Be with that that's part of
arriving arriving Here and
Now
arriving with the [Music]
sound arriving with a
breath arriving with a felt sense in the
body
arriving
arriving at the Temple of this body mind and
heart with a sense of
irreverence maybe a Little
Tenderness maybe a little sense of a gratitude that we can come
here and now in the temple of this body mind and
heart
staying with the felt sense of this arriving
process allow mindfulness to get become more
continuous not perfectly
continuous but slightly more as we stay with the present
experience becoming available to what's here
sense contacts Sensations in the
body the felt sense of
emotions waving
through feeling and sensing being
available with the body through the
body
let the feeling and sensing come from within the
you can include the felt sense of the heart
space
being available feels like
this or maybe a global sense of a
softening Global sense of easing
up a heart space may feel more
open however you may
feel is just
right a felt sense doesn't
need cognition to justify what it
is being available can feel
tender and sometimes even a little
vulnerable and so it's necessary for us to invite
aligning aligning this being with our deepest
intentions
the aspirations that uplift our
being so ground our heart and
mind so being available is is
protected by this
alignment feeling and
sensing aligning
aligning with the Buddha Dharma and the
S aligning with a
kindness
aligning with something that your heart knows and your body
[Music]
knows
there is no rush in this
process let the body and heart guide the
way
sometimes an image may come forth to
express the feeling of being
aligned for me it's like a sitting
upright the whole long streams of
[Music]
practitioners you may feel
connected
rooted grounded supported by the Earth
underneath there maybe a inner
quiet in your
steadiness or maybe just a hint of
it or a sense of a possibility
being aligned and available feels like
this but a wholesome field the wholesome
ground
from this a wholesome field we open to the felt
sense in this fathom long
body
May sense a feel into the heaviness of this body resting on
Earth
sitting like a tall
mountain study
quiet
letting go of anticipations
Cl
resting
here resting in the
body
the movements of the breath can naturally reveal
itself the dancing Sensations vibrations in the
body natur natur
surface the feeling and sensing happens naturally
when the clouds of thinking and planning and wanting Fades
away
feel and sense a life
breath soften into the
breath
releasing into the aliveness in this
body
as if we're holding a newborn feeling the
aliveness of the
newborn
touching life that's already happening right
here a shift and changes of
temperature tingling
Sensations a flow of
breath
when we open to our life this
way there may be a kind of a
tenderness
there maybe a kind of a joy theight that's
independent of whether the experience is a pleasant or
unpleasant
[Music]
may feel the Stillness all
around Stillness that can hold
the movements movements of the
body movements of the
emotions fleeting
thoughts
sometimes the Mind wants to comment how what we're
[Music]
experiencing know that it's okay to
experience without
commentaries
returning to feel and sense as a
body connecting with the Earth
underneath
maybe the body feels different right
[Music] now and resting on the ground of being
alive mind and available what's the Fel sense
now knowing that you always have a
choice to return to this
ground as you go about the
day you may not feel the same
way and they don't need to feel the same way
that our heart and mind and body can
know that we're living this
life we have a choice to align with the our deepest
intentions
[Music] I feel so good
um I was a little reluctant to
speak but I did bring a topic today so I will
talk and so as U I spoke a little bit at the beginning of our meditation that
uh and this week uh I've been channeling a whole set of the teachings that came
from Philip Moet uh who had offered a lot of this
um withy short teachings that uh was very meaningful for for me and for many
people and so today I brought this uh particular uh practice skill called
practicing with the don't know mind well this is sound a little
counterintuitive because so much of um our um Dharma cultivation has to do with
cultivating a Clarity of knowing uh or cultivating clear knowing so what
does it mean by practicing with the don't know mind and so I wanted to elaborate on
this a bit and so the first aspect of a
practicing with the don't know mind um is that the don't know mind has the
quality of The Beginner's mind we probably all have heard this phrase
of a beginner's mind and so The Beginner's mind has
different qualities in it for example if you're learning a new skill or you have
a new interest in I don't know playing a new music
instrument and uh there is a lot to learn and you're very engaged with it
and uh you're eager to practice and you're open curious
you're very receptive in this kind of beginner's mind and uh as we engage with it we kind
of get energized by it and there is a kind of refreshing um momentum that can
come forth and so the quality of a beginner's
mind um there's a very wholesome
feeling uh um and we all know how it is when we
lose The Beginner's mind uh we can believe somehow at some point we got it
you know we know it and we can lose the sense of the Curiosity and
interest and maybe our engagement is very uh
superficial but in this practice of um
um being present with our lived experience Here and Now each moment of
Our Lives that is unfolding has never happened
before um it's always new but we can have a belief that well
this is the same old stuff that we've experienced before again and again so we
can get bored we can get check out we can get disconnected with the life that is
unfolding here and now so The Beginner's mind uh invite us
to renew this sense of curiosity an
interest and maybe letting go of the belief that I knew it I I already know
this um a recent Retreat and that uh G taught
uh it's it was an experienced practitioner Retreat and he said this that stayed
with me he said that it's not so important to become experienced
practitioners instead it's more important to learn to be experienced
beginners I love that I love that that there is just that kind
of innocence and aess that gets pointed out and at the same time there is also a
sense of a humility and so that's one aspect of uh
practicing with a don't know mind is to have this kind of a beginner's
mind and the other aspect of practicing with the don't know mind is to stay open
and [Music] unassuming I was once uh in a practice
discussion uh with um a teacher and I was sharing an
experience and I made a connection an association and that this experienced um
and this experience must have something to do with something that happened a
while ago and I was very definitive you know I
thought I knew this you know that was because XYZ so I was experiencing
this and the teacher just looked at me and he smiled and he said well that's
one way to understand it that was a real teaching moment for
me I realized that I was fixated on the vi feel that a happened because of a
b that was just a guess I actually don't
know with all the myriads of conditions that we situations we're living
in we can only say that um with some measure some degrees
of knowing but I actually don't really know
if that Association was so and so that was very freeing for me
and once I realized oh there were actually many other
possibilities I don't have to know this only in this
way and so um assumptions
conclusions particularly the grand conclusions like what I had in that practice
discussion tend to connect with fixed views fixed ideas
beliefs and so the don't know mind invite us to stay open in the face of a
situation and make space for the situation to unfold and
evolve and so we can allow different possibilities to emerge as we stay open
and available available two different
possibilities and there was a famous uh Chinese Fable some of you may know this
called Saima it spoke about this old man who
lives in the countryside who raises uh horses for a living for a
living and one day um um he lost one of the one of his
horses and um after hearing his Misfortune uh his neighbors all came and
felt sorry for him wanted to comfort him um but aai Wong simply
asked how would we know that this is not a good thing for
me and after a while um this lost horse
came back with a beautiful uh new
horse and um and the neighbors all came and congratulated saong and said wow
what a good luck you had and then saong said how could we know that it's not um
a bad thing for me and so the time went on and uh one
day hisan went to to ride this new horse um roaming around and he fell off the
horse and broke his leg and the neighbors came again and
kind of shared their condolences to um saong and seone said how do we know that
it's not a good thing for me and then a year later and the Empire sent uh was in
a war with a neighboring country and uh the Army came to the Village to
recruit the able-bodied man to fight in the war and because of the
injury saon son uh could not get off
could not could not be drafted to go in the war so he was spared from the death
very certain death in the war and so we don't know so we don't
always know are we able to or dare to allow
ourselves to open to different possibilities I wanted to maybe End by
saying that the don't know mind is not a blinded mind or a kind of shut down or
disengagement kind of a mind rather the don't know mind empowers us to loose
loosen the grip on the fixed views fixed
beliefs it's not to shut down or simply claim somehow that we don't know and
that's kind of better or something but rather it owers us because it create a
space where wisdom and compassion can arise when we're not F not so fixed
up a certain orientation or certain kind of a direction that we set in our
mind there is a deeper kind of a knowing that I've been speaking about this week
that is a kind of a capacity that's within us when it's not dictated when
we're not dictated by the fixations and this kind of knowing it's
much more direct intuitive and they can manifest in many
ways that maybe are surprising to us and it can also um reveal itself
gradually as the Things become more and more
clear and so do we allow this kind of a
possibility by staying open and un assuming do we dare to allow this deeper
and more intuitive direct form of wisdom and compassion to
arise and so that's an inquiry for today so um May our practice and may our
inquiry Reflections benefit ourselves and may it benefit all beings
everywhere thank you friends I'll see you
tomorrow