good morning or good day welcome and for today's
meditation I'd like to call on or evoke in you your
confidence that um confidence has a lot to do with showing
up fully to engage with what we're doing with a belief
that we can do it that we can uh not just do it with
full confidence not just that we can do it with part of who we are but that we can do what we're doing
with all of who we are we can bring all of ourselves together in a some somehow an embodied
way holistic way and to show up for our activity
we're not divided we're not divided by other interests
preoccupations we're just there's a confidence there's a
wholeheartedness uh we can give ourselves fully to the activity at
hand and I think of confidence as an embodied State it's not only a belief
belief maybe just a small part of it but believing in yourself believing you can do something believing in the value of
it but there's also a even without belief some people can have a
disposition towards confidence that you're there you're and
that's what comes with Dharma practice we're confident in the value of being here
present inhabiting This Moment's
life here and now and so for this meditation the idea
of confidently inhabiting your present moment
experience and letting that confidence be soft
quiet not act not agitating
or energizing in a way that is R Makes You Restless but rather
a kind of a the full capacity to show
up here and in that showing up something full all of
ourselves has a chance to become still dynamically still
something about all of ourselves has a chance to come to rest in the pull of
gravity rather than being activated in such a way
that we're kind of spinning out so confidence so assuming a meditation
posture and add to it some modum of confidence an expression of
confidence if you were someone were see you meditating now would they see a person sitting with
confidence is there enough full involvement of your body
whether you're lying down or sitting on a couch or sitting upright can you adjust your body so
that you are showing or demonstrating to yourself
that you're bringing all of who you are involved in the
meditation a way of adjusting your
back maybe in such a way that the shoulder blades can have a chance to
roll down the back and the chest has a chance to
open spread
out and are the hands in a position that also support the idea of
confidence the feeling of it so the hands are not casually on your
lap or someplace but the
hands are placed as if you're
reinforcing that confidence of being yes [Music]
here embodied presence for being here and
now and the same thing with the feet if you're sitting in a chair and your couch
and your legs are draped over the side is there some way to have your soles of your
feet confidently placed on the floor or some surface
that they too have a feeling of confidence
and gently if as if the expansion of the
inhale carries with it a gentle
confidence that spreads through your body
take some little bit deeper breaths that feel just right for
you spreading confidence [Music]
embodied attention throughout the body
and letting the confidence remain as you exhale long
exhale relax the tensions of your body
letting your breathing return to normal with a normal breath and continue
to let the inhale be an inhale of
confidence even if there's discomfort as you breathe in let the expansion the spread of the
inhale spreading out of the Torso
belly let it be a spreading
of inhabiting your
body being here taking up residence in this
body and and as you exhale to soften relax the
body for
and not so much watching your breathing from the control
tower as inhabiting the body's experience of
breathing as if you're entering your body being your body
breathing
for
e
for for
is there a way you can more fully inhabit yourself a physical
embodiment that gently spreads a sense of
confidence for being here
now in this place in this time in this body
where the living experience of now em
emanates letting the thinking mind become quieter so there's more room and
attention for the embodied experience
of confidence Here and
Now
for
for for
and then as we come to the end of this
meditation to take a few moments to
feel if your experience of being embodied in your
body has changed in any way in the course of the meditation
and if it has might that come along with something
or other that provides you with more confidence
Assurance faith and the value of being
embodied the value of being
aware here in your direct
experience perhaps even a sense of Refuge in awareness of here and
now a refuge in how that awareness lives in
your body even if there's disc comfort in the
body and imagine that with a certain grounding in
your body grounding in a confident
embodiment confident presence through your
body that you're able to meet another person without losing yourself without
getting caught up in the social Dynamic imagine you can stay connected
grounded fully in yourself and in so
doing actually have a fuller
ability to be aware of the other
then if you leaned into the relationship if you got pulled into your
preoccupations and thoughts and stories about what's
happening and maybe imagine that with
confident grounding in your
body imagine that you can now have room for
[Music] more good
will a good will which is confident
or unhesitant or
gentle undemanding free of expectations and
judgments just good will just a sense
of General
friendliness and to bring that good will and friendliness and spread it out towards
all the people people in your life may all
people be happy may all
people be safe may all
people be peaceful may all
people be free
and may my own Peace and Freedom that emanates from my confident
embodiment May that support others to be peaceful and free
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello and welcome to the fifth talk
on the 10 Reflections for a spiritual life these 10 Reflections
the 10 themes are also um Orient ations
or um the concerns that are activated or
present as we offer spiritual care to others people offer spiritual
caregivers might be listening for these themes in people's lives and seeing which one of those uh
is is a challenging for people at any given time and and challenging means
that could be the major challenge of their life that something really has ruptured or been taken away or there's a
loss or and um and then in offering spiritual care is to take to to
recognize this and support people sometimes people don't even recognize they know they're suffering but they
don't know why and um and somehow in the
conversation with a spiritual caregiver that uh somehow it can come out that oh this is where it is
it's uh there's uh what needs to be
somehow addressed is the issues of meaning uh the framing of our experience
in a what is most important for us or framing it in a way that um brings forth
uh our Vitality our inspiration what uh maybe is lacking a
sense of direction or sense of purpose what's lacking is a sense of agency the
ability to do and engage with what's important or what's lacking is a sense
of autonomy a sense that we're capable as an individual to stand up for
ourselves or take care of ourselves or engage with uh as a
independent person with uh with what seems important for
us so today's uh topic is identity and that's one that uh there's a lot of
struggles with that people have and there are what some people have called identity Wars going on in the United
States and maybe other places in the world as well where people's identities are denied and um by others and not just
simply denied and ignored but sometimes uh with active hostility towards who
people are and uh it's phenomenally painful for individuals for societ as a
whole some people don't have um uh never had people who believed in
that you know parents or teachers who believed in them so that who they were
could really flower and develop um we children especially uh
take in the confidence others have in us the others who show us or open up doors
for us yes uh all of you can come here you're capable of stepping forward here as you are who you
are and um maybe haven't had people who mirrored who we are and helped us to
recognize for ourselves the beauty of who we are as a human being and everyone
has Beauty everyone is a Marvel and to be seen with that kind of respect that
kind of care is one of the great gifts especially for children as they grow up
um to have hostil ility and judgment and criticism be what uh is mirrored for
children uh can really distort how children develop as a person and one way
they Distortion is that they they don't really grow into the fullness of who
they are so in Buddhism we in Buddhism we often kind of there's often a tendency
to somehow dismiss the importance of identity I think it was more in the
United States a decade or two or three ago when there was an overemphasis on this
teaching of of uh not self or how it was often understood was teaching of no self
and they were supposed to kind of let go of identity and have no identity which is impossible at least in the way that I
want to talk about identity today identity is who we are and it's this I
like to think of it as a sum total of all the different facets of Who We Are how we show up in the world we show up
with our abilities our capacities our background our conditioning our way of
thinking our belief system our bias um our hurts our Joys all those
come together to create uh uh the integral
whole of in of uh identity and so uh and this is also this
is why identity is very closely connected to the topic of
Integrity that Integrity is when we can come forward with all of who we are um
in a in a way that it's harmonious that it's not ruptured
by uh by any kind of tendency to cause
harm to oneself or to others harm harming is a rupture in in the wholeness
of our identity some people create an identity around being uh aggressive or being a
fighter or being a destroyer even and um but then then there's not
the Integrity of the whole person there and from Buddhist point of view then
identity has become fixated and it's the fixed identity that
Buddhism shows us Buddhist prce shows us is diminishes who we are when we get
attached to a particular aspect of who we are in Buddhism the idea is to have no
fixed identity but let the identity of who we are evolve and change over time
and per in some ways be cocreated by the events we're in
different events call on different aspects of ourselves uh if you uh it was wonderful
to be in the monastery for many years where I was assigned to
very different jobs that I never would have had if I had been in out in the world working and each job that I took
required very different parts of who I who I am and so in a sense my identity
uh chied and changed with the different jobs I had and then when I became a parent uh
my identity as a parent shifted in changes and as my children grew up the
fullness the what was called on me and called forth for me for who I could be shifted in changes as my par as my
children got older and older so to have the fluidity to discover who we are in
the fullness of the moment and to realize that's shifting and changing and in that
fullness uh to to appreciate that who we are and in Buddhism who we are is
phenomenally important not who we are in terms of a fixed identity but who we are
as a sum total of what animates us what drives us what what in what inspires us
to speak and to act and to live in the world that uh if we act from place of
Good Will it's radically different than if we act from place of ill will and so
who we are as a manifestation of Good Will who we are is manifestation of
being ethical nonh Haron in who we are as a manifestation of wisdom and
patience um who we are as a manifestation of joy and playfulness all
kinds of things that come into play and and uh and the guideline I'd like to
suggest from a Buddhist point of view is to be holistic so that uh we want to
bring all of who we are into the picture so there's can be can be a sense of
integrity and what that includes is ways in which we're uh things that are
difficult in us if there's fear um th that's part of our identity
in the moment we're afraid or in the day we're afraid or the year that we have anxiety and to be honest about that to
make room to recognize that and let it be and um and the uh if we have if we do
have anger and resentment there's an art to not pushing that away not denying it
or ignoring it or diminishing ourselves because of it there's a way of opening
up so that too is part of our wholeness that too is uh nothing we need to be
embarrassed about but in in letting that become part of our whole identity the
wholeness of identity then we can be honest about it with other people we can take it in
stride we can work with it wisely and carefully so this idea of opening up to
all of who we are is what it mean what what it can mean to be have a healthy
sense of identity and all of who we are is Shifting and changing every day and and
so this movement towards recognition opening this movement mindfulness to
recognize how we fixated on something or closed around something or or shutting
out something just keep opening and opening and this too is who I am
so in that sense uh people have uh when this sense and other senses identity is
a source of a lot of suffering for people some people do have some kind of
identity that they have relied on and it's they lose it they get ill and they
can't live that way anymore um they uh there's loss in life
and and if identity was tied to particular another person with people
and those people are not there anymore then the identity of that identity is no longer present to keep opening to the
fullness of it all is not to get stuck in that fixed identity but to open and
allow this too this too has to be included and if that involves grief
grief itself is a kind of very special um you know almost sacred state
that this too or to say differently all of who we are that integrity and
everything that's included that is entering into kind of a sacred way of being in this world and so
that um this opening and recognizing uh the areas in our life
that were challenged the areas in life that maybe ordinarily would be embarrassed to show people or you feel
like something is wrong with us a full integral sense of identity
just opens to that too without judgment without a sense that this is wrong or shouldn't be this way and discovers a
rightness and a wisdom and a balance and a and a healthy way of being when all of
it is taken into account and we can shift and change with the ever shifting changing nature of
identity how we Who We Are Who We Are is always changing but we can I think we
can trust um who we are if we are honest and open to all of it um the warts and
all they say so
um so uh I hope that uh this gives you
something to think about over the weekend the next few days and uh what are the identities that you have had
what are the different ways in which you have been
um um CAU in identity which are the
different ways that you've learned to open up to more and more of who you are been more and more inclusive um to affirm your identities
to make room for who you are and um and how you became more whole in that
process and how you've learned not to fixate an identity while at the same
time not denying it any of it uh what are the challenges of
identity you've had what are the joys of it that you've had so that's the reflection that I'd like to offer you
for the next few days and then uh we'll take this particular um kind of theme of identity
and on Monday related to it is the the topic of dignity identity and dignity go
together so thank you very much