okay welcome uh welcome to you all yeah uh invited folks to chat
in um Dharma themes for uh talk I
appreciate everything that's been said I'll find something in there try to speak to it but um let's uh let's
it e
so just um Beginning by by uh sensing the
presence of other beings
the the goodwi uh in this uh Network we call SA
just checking into the the energy in your body
mind you tired you
wired both
settled bright
just kind of uh inclin towards
balance
e e
and we relax what we can relax but we relax so that we know more sense more
feel more more
brightness we relax in other words
so that we can be uh genuinely
alert
e e
we're we're not practicing hypervigilance but there is a quality of poise in the
attention such that some phenomena sprung up
prominent we would uh appreciate it quickly
we're cultivating an attention that uh selects its
object and magnifies magnifies that
object we soak into it the breathing sound
mental images body sensation emotional
sensation and so we're alert and
oriented and develop a kind of uh Fidelity to the object maybe we
say somei concentration maybe just very
briefly but as if uh the attention soaks into the
object and the rest of the world remains in the
background
e
e e
and it can feel almost uh neglectful not to tend to the landscape
of threat and opportunity in every
moment and feel neglectful not to think and
worry can feel neglectful not to give thought it's
due but that's just
habit and for right now it's not neglectful to be
very very
simple
e
e e
we just kind of practice putting
down our
life it's the busyness that is
Samara always something to worry
about something at stake something
vulnerable and part of our practice is opening to all of that and
another part is giving our heart
rest so that we can meet all of that
lovingly
e
e e
don't uh miss the goodness that's already
here don't miss that which you don't need to engineer strive
towards
e
e e
making the object of attention the mind the affective
feeling tonal qualities of our
mind kind of energies and flavors of the Mind
brightness or
dullness agitation
Tranquility grasping aversion peace
just to notice that is enough awareness does its own
work without
you e
if there's some measure of stability
maybe stability itself becomes the object
becomes more grounded more
open
e
e e
okay thanks folks um so I
saw uh grief um mortality contemplating
one's death anxiety uh relation to the world
equinity and uh I think we can I think we can talk
about that so
um I don't recall who it was or somebody
who's maybe done nursing with hospice patients
taking care of people at the end of their life but uh they said something like
um I don't know what I think about this but they said uh the
degree of one's uh non- Enlightenment is
is correlated with the degree of fear around death you
know and
um I thought I was pray pretty free but I don't know one thing I remember I was
going up and cleaning the windows on irc's community room if you've been in
that room as a high ceiling it's a high ceiling and I was on the roof and I
don't know what I'm doing but my job on that cleaning day was to clean
the you know uh whatever the windows up there you know
uh skylights I they were and um and I kind of had some of them were
sort of accessible and like it was not it was not like a clear drop 30 ft but
then some were unprotected and so I'm just out there cleaning the
windows considering how unenlightened I am cuz I was not ready to die on an IRC
work day and okay that's like the visceral kind
of Dimension maybe maybe our body kind of is
always um uh in resistance in some way to that
I I read a piece on uh Rah you know from ROM doss's nurse
the end of of ramd das's life and just as the end was coming as he took a
breath tried to take a breath and couldn't get enough breath
in after all these Decades of teaching so beautifully
about about letting go uh what the nurse described in Ram das's face was uh Was
Fear as touching you know how do we know we're ready to let go of
this life I I don't know that we can ever know but it's a worthy object of
contemplation for many reasons um one just to clarify what's actually
important in our lives you know just to sweep away what we know will be
absolutely meaningless at the end of our life and there's a lot that seems maybe
important now that really won't be that that's sort of humbling just to see that
Gap you know but we already know that in on a hard day or something like
that the stuff you know the stuff of life is like totally totally meaningless
offers absolutely no consolation and so it's worth looking at
like what what offers genuine consolation on a hard day at the end of
a life and so we we were practicing
clearing away that which is unimportant you know and maybe the question about death
doesn't clarify everything maybe we shouldn't take the counsel of death
100% at face value maybe there are some things that won't feel meaningful then
that do feel meaningful now and that's okay maybe but we want to live in the shadow
of finitude and part of the function of the death
contemplation is um is to sort of pre grieve
loss loss for which the heart is utterly unprepared is
always more gruesome and so in a sense we're we're
trying to uh open to finitude while we still
have time to begin to allow our heart to acclimatize to the truth of
anich uncertainty impermanent which is almost always kind of startling no
matter how prepared we think we are anicha is startling but we can make
progress right remember maybe shared this from Michelle
McDonald asking like n you know sadas kind of revered burmes uh monk you know
how he practices he was in his 90s he says when I breathe in I say I know
I will die when I breathe out I say I know everyone else will die and um and then he said and so when
I do I will not be
surprised we uh contemplate death um because
anxiety anxiety is unimaginable without a
future anxiety is directed towards the governing uh what is you know maybe we
influence but ultimately ungovernable and and so the notion of
like a a futur lessness there's no potential room for anxiety in
that and so death is um in some sense
it's the intersection of all anxieties we have like what's the final thing that
we wish to avoid when we wish to avoid some eventualities it's like the threat
to our life is is ultimately what gives fear its power the way fear Tangles up
with anxiety and so to become uh a quanus
even little bit with the reality of mortality um this is this is a way to
cut through anxiety we know how the story ends We Know How It Ends already
there's no drama yeah the wisdom of No Escape
there's no drama here we know how the story ends okay what does that do to the
heart maybe we see the way in which that
um that can free us up but in the process of freeing ourselves up we um we
grieve we grieve right before the three characteristics Tuka n not become
freeing we grieve them we grieve them
and uh that grief as I I've talked about
often it's just like that's the Growing Pains of Dharma you
know it's how for many people that's how it feels to
grow and so
um it is uh it is onward leading and we get to practice with with small losses
or with deep you know brutal losses to find
ways of bearing bearing it you know of
letting our hearts kind of thought out wake up ah this is the
law this is the law this is the lawful unfolding and we like just appreciate
the law you know okay I'm governed by
this let me live in accord with that
understanding and so we we grieve you know we begin to
um begin to let some of the anxiety melt
because it's no longer a question and this is also for me what what feels
important in beginning to uh to open to
um you know the the enormity of suffering in the world it's too much
from the perspective of my stupid little life you know my little life it's too
much too much so pH I used to use as a kid I was told by my parents like last
year they said that was your that was what you said a lot too much it's too
much it was my way of saying like ah
Dua it's too much you know
and it still feels that way maybe I got into practice a way of meeting that
intuitively I knew all about anicha even though my life
was protected privileged in a number of ways insulated from
the the intensity of anicha at least for a while and uh and now as I contemplate
the kind of um Global suffering you know it feels
like yeah my life is too small a portal into understanding
that that the the ascendency of greed Hayden delusion in politics in this the US it's
it needs a broader view climate you
know uh the Florida you know it's like it
needs a broader View and of course we stay very tactical and
obviously like compassion is a verb as tnan says we act now there's a lot we
can do just now and to really open to the fullness
of what the Buddha was talking about the kind of like like truly truly giving up the
utopian fantasy that makes a lot of strength a
lot of strength and it feels like if my view isn't vast it overruns my
heart and there's something about contemplating our own death the sense of like the Horizon is had the the moral
Horizon is somehow beyond the scope of my
life but um that let
us let us plant good
seeds Okay so offer that for your
consideration and uh certain Wednesdays living up to its
name I will be away Retreat next week but um back on the 23rd
and um will not rely on you for topics I will come prepared in one way or another
heart prepared okay thank you uh thank you all