good morning maybe uh let's see I'm G to do a little sound check how does the volume
sound this does it sound okay sound okay yes as Martha said I teach on Monday
nights and hard to believe it's been many many years well many maybe four years now I've been doing uh Monday
nights that's a lot of Mondays and uh here I am on a Sunday
sitting in for Gil while he's H teaching a retreat down at
IRC and I also want to thank you to oh thank you welcome you to Autumn right
today is uh the first day of the Equinox the sun passed directly over the Equator
this morning so it's you know roughly the same length of day and night starting
today so this morning I'd like to share a story that's uh from the Buddhist
tradition from this tradition um I first heard this story many many years ago and
it troubled me a little bit um and so I recently saw somebody
that had um kind like uh fleshed out some of the details of this story a little bit more in modern terms and um I
then it was really then I could start to feel and sense some of the the teachings
and what's valuable about this story instead of kind just being dismissive of
it or just like oh that's from thousands of years ago who cares instead to realize oh no no no there's something
here something for me and I hope maybe something all for all of you too about this
story so maybe I'll just say for those of you who uh care about these things or
know about these things this story is from the commentarial tradition which is a thousand maybe about a thousand years
after the time of the Buddha some of you may know that Gil and I have been teaching the sutas we've been we've
spent a lot of time uh doing the sutas and that's you know attributed to closer to the time of the Buddha and this story
is after that time so this is a story of Kisa
goami and this is a woman and she came from a poor
household and she was uh very thin and frail and because she was thin and frail
people called her Kissa which we can translate as skinny you know so skinny
gotami is uh what they were calling her but uh as it happened she married
into a family that um had more wealth than the family she came from and however the in-laws didn't like
her they uh disrespected her and treated her
poorly that is until she gave birth to a
son and as it happened this son this was the first child the first grandchild and
there was a boy so and you know this happens even in modern times that inls
don't get along with the some of the the children- in-laws but then when there's
a birth of a child like the Dynamics often change there can be a way in which uh things
are a little bit different and then so with the birth of uh her son her in-laws started to treat
her better more respectfully and she was a really good
mother she took good care of her son and this was noticed by the in-laws
and noticed by other people in the village as well so maybe they still called her Kissa gotami but just because
was her name but maybe it wasn't so much with derision it was just more because that was what they knew her
by so her life had changed and she felt like things were going
well she had this child that she loved and was
thriving and then soon after her son had learned to
walk she and her son were out for a little walk in the village and the sun
tripped and fell and didn't get
up and Kissa grabbed the Sun and pulled him up but he was just
limp thinking oh my goodness he's unconscious that must have been a terrible fall what can I do so she kind
of like you know hits him on his face and uh tries to wake him up but he's still not waking
up she's completely destroyed God please wake up wake up and the sun doesn't wake
up and she picks up the Sun and takes home thinking that the relatives will be
able to you know help her her family will be able to help her and her child her son who just needs to be revived and
then soon everything will be okay and she could go back to the life that she had just if only her son would just wake
up so in her anguish and in her grief and trying to figure things out she
wasn't able to see that actually her son had
died she couldn't quite take that in couldn't quite process it so she's
running back home when she gets there the in-laws see
oh my goodness this is uh this is really bad and she's like you there must be
some medicine what can you do help him help him he just needs to wake
up and they were trying to explain to her he's not going to wake up and she's
like no no you don't understand clearly you don't see and they tried to reason with her
but uh she was couldn't be reasoned with she was convinced that simply if they
could just see things her way that they would understand that to he needs some special medicine or need something to
help bring him back and and some thought okay well maybe we just console her and say it's going to be all right can you
just relax and she was like what do you mean relax no that's
urgent have to take care of things now
so maybe I'll say that uh I'll pause here with a little bit of a commentary
and the version of the story that I heard initially it just talked about how Kisa gotami was crazy she went
crazy and I thought well I you know I don't know about that it just kind of
like was just wrote her off as crazy but then when you start to think about it
something that had made I mean a child right I mean this there aren't many things that are much worse than this
right a child dying and then you add on top of that something that had really turned around
her life had made such a big difference in her life and then to see it just gone
in a blink of a moment I mean there's a way in which we
ourselves do this things that are important to us that are very meaningful us and then they they
change they go away there's a way in which there's this
um there's a way in which I mean like how would we feel it's devastating it's
devastating and there can be some times in which society likes to tell us or
maybe we even tell ourselves like oh you shouldn't you shouldn't be upset about that just go on with uh life or oh it's
not really that bad there's a way and sometimes we Gaslight ourselves like oh
it's not that bad I know somebody that was telling me that
uh this one of her her dog had died and it was devastating for her because her
and this dog had been through so many life changes together and so many things together and and people were telling her
like get over it it was just a pet and she was so really really hurt by
this and what are that some of the other things like we're talking of a child here this is devastating a fur family
member is devastating but there's also things about like our youth our
capabilities our jobs you know there's some of these things that when they go away that we
tend to not really uh understand and instead want to just ignore and uh
frantically look for something to restore it to return it so it's not so much that kisak goami
was crazy she just wasn't quite ready I mean this is devast I keep on
using this word devastating I can't think of a better word right now that you know to what's so
important to see it slip away we don't want to see it slip away
we want to deny it
so getting back to the story so kakami so her family wasn't helping so she
thought okay there might must be other people in the village here who understand so um she carrying her son
who's not alive came her son this is just heartbreaking right going to the uh
neighbors please can you help him and uh they were trying to talk some sense into
her quote unquote and like no no no there's no help for your son I'm sorry
and she's like oh I don't know I'm going to the next door and the next door and nobody's was able to convince her until
finally she gets to this house of um some of the
elders and uh the Elder she understood what was happening here she
she could see what was happening and kutam was asking for medicine for her
son and the Elder recognized there isn't medicine for her son but maybe there's
medicine for her and so the Elder she said toisa gami
said to there's a doctor some call him the Buddha he's nearby why don't you go see
him he probably has medicine so kisak goami is like
delighted finally here's somebody who's paying attention to her who's uh not
being dismissive and trying to pretend like something terrible isn't happening
and instead is giving her some direction something to do so kisag goami hurriedly goes to the
ddha to the Buddha and um she goes to the Buddha and
says I beg you please give me the medicine which I need to wake my child
from his sleep and straight away the Buddha understood what was
happening and he replies good woman I do have some medicine for for
you but in order for this medicine to work you need to obtain a small quantity
of mustard seed from a house in the city and Cas a good time is like okay no problem Mustard Seed from some of the
neighbors I can do this but wait you must obtain a small quantity of
mustard seed from a house in the city where no one has died from a house in the city where no
one has has ever lost a loved one k said thinks
okay so she goes to the next House nearby and says do you have some Mustard Seed and she's still carrying her son
and the I can only imagine what the neighbors word imagine when she knocks on the door and they see this and
they're like yeah here let me go get it and they get the mustard seed and they give it to her and she's like oh great
thank you oh and by the way has anybody died in this household
yes my grandmother just died last month oh she gives the Mustard Seed back goes
to the next house do you have any mustard seed yes oh thank you they go to
get it they bring it and has anyone died yes my cousin died last
week oh so then you know how the story's going to go right she's going to go to the house after house they have Mustard
Seed and they also have death she's able to find Mustard Seed a
common cooking ingredient but uh isn't able to find a
houseold that hasn't been touched by tragedy that hasn't been touched by the
loss of a loved one there's this
way that um humans will do almost anything to not
feel helpless they will do almost anything in
order to not feel like things are out of control to not feel like oh my gosh this
is awful it has to be different and I have to make it be
different so the Elder and the Buddha they uh respected kisami they met her
where she was and a State just uh highly
agitated not seen clearly and recognize that it's actually
through experience when our minds get
changed very often it's through when we recognize something for ourselves
instead of just being told it especially these days right with social media you
can find anything you want on the internet that you can you can find any point of view you want if you look hard
enough you can find anything so it's hard to like have confidence in what people are telling us
not only just because you can find any point of view you'd like but it's different right it's different when we
have an experience and we know things in a different
way when my father died a number of years ago I I mean of course I understood that people died but it
wasn't until they died that I I understood it like deeply inside like oh
yeah this this is this is what it means when people die it's a different ex then is somebody
telling you right there's a difference between what we intellectually understand and what we know from
experience and that Buddha he know he knows this he's pointing to direct experience so so much in the teachings
this is partly why we meditate so that we can quiet the mind and just be with
our experience instead of being completely lost in our thoughts which spin any way and every which
way so Kisa goami coming back to the story she's starting to have an
experience she's starting to recognize oh I'm it's not like there's a
malfunction in the universe that I'm having this uh terrible terrible
experience but instead other people have this too
instead this is part of the human condition that there's terrible
loss there difficulties nobody is exempt nobody not
me not you not anybody and we know this right the
Buddha talks about this as the first Noble Truth there is
suffering but there's sometimes a way in which we're kind of secretly thinking at least I know I have for a lot of time
yeah okay that's for other people there's a way in which we think oh this something wrong with me or I
failed or very commonly whose fault is it I have to blame somebody and first we
often well not always for some people they like to blame outside and for some people they like to blame inside
ourselves or blame others but this idea of
blaming and it's quite something for me when I uh encounter the news and uh the
different formats that it's available it seems to me it's always about blame
breaking news this happened and we're trying to find who to blame this happened and here's who to blame and
this happened and these people are blaming that and I'm not saying we shouldn't hold people responsible I'm
not saying that I am saying just notice how this kind of like this wish to blame
is often just a way to distract ourselves or divert ourselves from this
feeling of helplessness from this feeling like oh yeah these things are happening out
there these terrible things that we can't control and it doesn't feel good
but there's a way in which there maybe having the experience like turning
towards experience as best we can to be able to
hold it with as much spaciousness as we're able
to when I first heard this expression from somebody else I thought it was peculiar but now I started to see it
this idea of gaslighting ourselves the way that we kind of want to Discount ourselves or talk ourselves out of some
difficulty or this isn't a problem get over it or something like that or the way that we want to be dismissive and
avoid things but is there a way that we can
recognize that yeah there's really hard things that happen in our lives
lives difficult things and not only in our lives in everybody's
lives the peculiarities the distinctions are different but every single one of us has
difficulties and it makes absolutely zero sense no sense at all to like
compare it's just all of us have difficulties and there's something
about meeting that and ack in that and saying yes this is the truth of
the moment ESP best we can and so what is
one way that we can do that is to tune into the bodily
experience this is uh a sense of Despair and it feels like heaviness in the
shoulders and maybe there's a lump in the throat or um tightness in the belly
or something like this or maybe there's just like oh there's this feeling of helplessness and
overwhelm and then maybe you just feel your feet on the ground just feeling connected and grounded this way this
way there's a way in which being with the body can be such a support because
it interrupts the momentum of all the all the catastrophizing or the
spinning out that we can do some of us don't like to be in the body or feel a little bit disconnected to the
body so this is why I offer just being grounded just feeling your feet on the ground don't
underestimate how this simple thing can make such a difference but when I was working in
Corporate America I uh learned that this was something that I could do like when I was in a meeting that was going
south just somehow like feeling my feet on the ground made such a huge difference from me not to like get
pulled into The Fray and want to I don't know defend myself or or
uh assert uh myself in some kind of way that would have been
unhelpful so getting back to this story about Kisa
goami after a while she realized she wasn't going to find a house that was Untouched by death or by tragedy
and she couldn't help noticing how many houses in fact had lost a
child and then maybe at the end of the day she decided that um she was going to
go back to the Buddha and talk to
him so she was still feeling the pain of her loss it's not like she no longer was
was no longer devastated or was no longer feeling
sad but she goes to the Buddha and she Ed a
verse this is a common in the suas that uh when individuals have a a conversation with
the Buddha they might say something piy that gets captured in verse so here's a
verse uh that kakami says to the Buddha it's not just a truth for one
Village or town nor is it a truth for a single
family but for every World settled by gods and
humans impermanence indeed is what is
true endings changes is this is true for all of us is true
for everybody everything it's a part of us that know this today is the first day
of fall right it's the new season summer is ending fall is I guess
technically here this something about noticing
impermanence in particular is liberating
the Buddha after he first uh became awakened some of you might know this story that uh he went and taught the his
five former Companions and they had practiced extreme aestheticism together
the Buddha abandoned the aestheticism and went and sat under the bod tree and
eventually became awakened these five people had um continued on with their
aestheticism after he becomes awakened he wants to teach them what he discovered so he finds them and he
teaches them and the first person to become awakened after the Buddha became awakened his name is
Kon and um after kund becomes awakened he utters whatever
is subject to arising is subject to cessation whatever comes to be and
ceases it's this impermanence that kund is saying also is like a key insight for
him that helped him to kind of let go of uh the difficulties and anything that he
was holding on to that led to Liberation and then this is a part of
the story that's also captured uh in the vinia this is in the polyan after these five Aesthetics the
Buddha goes to uh teach the exact opposite of Aesthetics a very wealthy uh
Merchant his name is yasa and the Buddha encounters yasa through a
short little story then gives him um the teachings yasa becomes awakened yasa he
says whatever is subject to arising is subject to cessation after his Awakening
experience so there's something about recognizing that things arise and pass away they're not always you know uh
permanent in the way that we think they are everything is always
changing sometimes there's giant changes like the loss of a child and sometimes there are subtle
changes but there's a way to acknowledge this allows us to maybe align ourselves
with the reality of the moment instead of just holding on to yeah but it used
to be like this that's turns out not to be so helpful to be grasping onto a past
or something like this but instead to be able to recognize oh yeah okay things are
different now and it's okay to feel really sad of course there's grief of course
there's grief when there's loss can we allow the grief to be there
can we allow it to be experienced and can we allow it to move through us when
the time is right without identifying with it and saying okay I'm the person that's been sad for
x amount of time I'm always going to be sad and nobody understands instead can we allow the experience to be there and
as best we can feel it in the body again this interrupts the momentum
of the mind that's making all these stories about how things should be and if only that hadn't happened and I'm
going to blame this person or blame myself instead can we just be with what's actually
happening the tears the heat in the
face all of us have cried with loss all of us have had loss it's part of the
human experience when we think of impermanence
we tend to focus on the challenging aspects of it just as I have but there's
also a way in which things ending or changing um allows us to put things in
perspective it's sometimes when something is lost that that can be like kind of like a reset button and we start
to rethink our priorities like wow I didn't realize how much I was taking that for granted I didn't realize how
important that was for me and now that it's no longer here it's awful and then
we start to maybe look at our life in a way that we hadn't before and maybe there is some resetting
of priorities and a wish to make some amends for example or to live life more
fully for example or to be less disconnected just lost in Doom scrolling
or in our social media echo echo Chambers or something like
this and then this is something that's uh obvious once we think about it it's
only because of impermanence it's only because of things change that allows
growth to happen that allows cultivation to happen that allows uh some change in
our spiritual lives changes in our lives that are supportive and help us to find more freedom help us to find more peace
and ease that's only possible because of this change the same change that allows
growth is the same change that is allowing other things that we didn't want to go away to go
away and there's a way in which US humans myself included we want to think
that we know like okay well in order for me to have happiness and freedom I need
this and I don't need that like we have this clear idea maybe it's not uh
explicit or maybe it's uh subtle but like okay I need this and I don't need that I just uh need to meditate more
clearly and uh I don't need um a difficult
body or I don't need this neighbor's dog that uh incessantly barks or you know
whatever it might be I need to read all the sutas uh I'll give you a short cut I've
read probably all the [Laughter] suas and they're deeply meaningful for
me they have impacted me deeply but that's not a requirement I'll just save
you guys some time
but there's this way that we have this idea that we have this think we knew like what's needed and what's not needed
but turns out that we don't really know we have firm ideas of what we like and
what we don't like that's true but do we really know what's going to help us bring the most Freedom we
don't we think we do and certainly are preferences right I mean there there for
a reason but if we only followed our preferences then that's a way in which
we're clinging and that's a way in which we're identifying and that's not a way in which we can find more and more
freedom so there's this way in which wisdom comes from seeing this impermanence deeper and deeper and
deeper ways I gave this story about the obvious
loss and an ending but there's a way in which can we
see how just the changing nature of everything turns
out and is that a way that can help us to not hold on so tightly not to be um
wishing like this has to stay and this has to go instead I first saw Gil do this quite
so many years ago I don't remember when but I'm sure you've seen him do this too this idea right if we hold on to things
like oh I need this and we're holding on to this for example I'm holding this Striker so tightly but uh can we hold
them like this with an open hand just sometimes for me like when I
first saw this visual I felt like oh yeah it's not like okay I have to get
rid of it right now there's a way in which we can just hold it with an open
hand it being whatever is arising whatever your experience is including the really
difficult ones can we hold it care for it respect
it honor it instead of trying to get rid of whatever is
happening that is the way forward that is the way towards greater Freedom
greater peace greater well-being is to honor and respect our experience
including the changing nature of
experience and through this we can find greater and greater
Freedom maybe I'll Circle back around to this story with Kisa
goami so after she meets with the Buddha she has this realization she asks to
ordain for her she now that has seen something deeply she wants to devote her
life to practice you don't have to ordain to devote your life to practice or to have practice be uh essential part
of your life or even a marginal part of your life so she asks to join um the
monastics and the uh Buddha allows her to do so and or ordains her I should say and
then as The Story Goes she becomes an our Hut and becomes a completely awakened person
and she her uh some of her uh verses her Awakening vers when she becomes
completely awakened is preserved in the terata and regrettably I don't have her
verses in front of me here something that I didn't make it onto this uh sheet
here this morning but there's something uh for me that I just appreciate so much
that uh just somebody who was having difficulties and maybe felt like you know world was ending but uh found a way
found a different way and found complete Freedom complete
peace so with that I wish you all a wonderful day today the first day of
autumn may you notice also the changing nature of your experience and to honor
and respect and care for your experience and as best you can also like
feel in the body the bodily experience cuz the mind sometimes is telling us
stories telling us stories thank you