so hello everyone and and uh I appreciate all the
greetings on the chat and especially when there's a new name that I haven't
seen for a long time so thank you for making yourself known this way
and and my fond feelings for so many of you that I know and those
of you I don't know I'm delighted to know you this way
so um one of the principles
of mindfulness meditation is to keep things simple and perhaps radically
simple and I'll say something a little bit complicated to get to the
Simplicity and that is uh I propose
that we assume that anytime we're thinking
about something that's not in the present moment Here and Now something in
the future the past something someplace else that in the background of that is a
belief a belief that it's valuable to do so a belief of something we have to
accomplish or get or fix or REM remember or hold on to or get rid of belief in a
certain um understanding of what it means to be a human being in relationship with other people and a
belief in what is right and wrong and belief in how we've been harmed or
benefited and and many of these beliefs we don't think of as
beliefs uh we're just doing the matter of fact things with our thinking and um
and when we meditate in a sense we really don't need
to think believe in anything or very very little that's
nothing about that's not here and now and so the radical Simplicity is
to say to if you're thinking about the future thinking about the past thinking
about fantasy thinking about something which is not here to in a loving way delightful
way say no thank you not
now not now
and just know that you're not rejecting thinking about these things just not
now no thank thank you and in doing so you're also letting
go of the beliefs that you're supposed to think or it's useful to think or there's value in
thinking about these things which of course there's a time and place for that
but not now not now no no thank you and to say that with enough love or
enough kindness or enough Simplicity that it becomes a gentle
returning to here and now just now just here just with the
breathing and there's so little we need to believe in if we
are if we enter into the world of our present moment
experience I often emphasize breathing
for some people breathing isn't uh so useful to as a focus of
meditation so then some people would just use the body as a whole the whole
experience sensations of the body some people will do sounds as their
home base their anchor and uh just stay let stay in the
present with the flow of sounds Keeps Us grounded in the present and
then we might know other things as we go along but anything that takes us away
not now no thank
you where the no thank you and the not now is a whole it's a warmhearted
welcome back here here in this experience here and
now so gently assuming a meditation
posture and closing your
eyes and feeling your body here in
space supported from
falling falling with a pull of gravity by whatever surface that's holding you
up chair a cushion bed a
floor and feel the weight of your body against this surface
as a kind of definitiveness this is the
place where here
is and then feeling the vibrating in
pulsing or sensing experience of a
body this is the experience of now
and in this wide experience of here and
now is there a home base a place where it's easy for your
attention to rest or stay
focused for
and if you find yourself thinking about other things and other
places other times
to remind yourself not now with a no thank
you welcome yourself back into your body into your present moment
experience and if you're thinking a lot about Here and Now chances are you're believing in
something that maybe you don't have to believe in so much
actively even that you might say no thank
you keep returning to a radical Simplicity of your
experience Here and
Now
for
e
for for
to remain very simple here and
now stay close to your body's ability to be
sensing sensing the body sounds
smells tastes sights stay close to the body's ability
sense rather than staying close to your
thinking rather than being IM mesed in beliefs of what you
should be thinking about
for
e
e for
as we come to the end of this sitting to take a few
moments to feel your way or allow
yourself to be as simple as you
can almost staying close to
the to the simple way that you feel yourself alive right
now without the filter of beliefs interpretations
stories expectations
projections simply being here with the body
with the breathing with the flow of
Sensations a radical Simplicity that for right now for the next few
minutes all needs are put aside
any need that can't be satisfied in
meditation just be here and
now and in this Simplicity of being turn your gaze now outward into
the world and what is it like
to meet encounter think about
others from a perspective of this Simplicity of
being meeting others without need for
anything meeting others without judging anything self or
other meeting others and allowing them to be who they
are in the Simplicity of our
attention and in this Simplicity of being
what form of connection or Rapport do you tend to have with
others Simplicity of being where you're safe nothing is threatening
what way of what attitude or feelings do you have of a simple human
connectivity to
others and without anyone else
knowing from within see if you can generate basic
human Good Will wishing others
well at the level of this radical Simplicity of being simple
connection may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may it be that in your each of our Simplicity of
being Simplicity of attention here and
now may it be that we provide others with
safety with
peace with freedom from any projections and demands that we have
and maybe in so doing support others in their
happiness may all beings be
[Music]
happy thank you for
so welcome to this second Talk part two of core
teachings and uh so to discuss further the second Core teaching that of having
no views and what this means uh maybe it's a strange expression so it needs
some explanation but it means uh finding a way of living being
alive even if it just for a little while in meditation or a little while walking
in nature or a little while just in the evening and maybe looking out the window
at the stars or something of
of not depending on any
belief not depending on any religious belief or political
beliefs not depending on uh any point of
view certainly there are beliefs certainly there are points of
view which are pragmatically useful
and I say that carefully so we don't automatically think beliefs points of
view are true in some absolute philosophical or
Universal way but rather they might be functionally true practically true in
certain circumstances but not in others and uh religious people often
hold on to views very strong beliefs about what is Ultimate and what is true what is right and what is
wrong and it's very hard to let go of that to believe that
anything else is valuable but in the Simplicity of meditation we see
clearly that certainly holding on to any belief
system or actually operating with actively with any belief system
interferes with our capacity for peace interferes with our capacity to tap into
a deep natural sense of well-being Happiness joy
peace that uh is possible to experience completely free of anything
that we are believing so some people then feel it's
it's a it's a betrayal to our beliefs betrayal to our responsibility as human
being to let go of these fundamental beliefs religious beliefs that maybe
we've grown up with and that the very way in which we see the world or Orient
ourselves but as we get quieter in meditation more concentrated in meditation you can see how it those
things if they're operating actively they hinder us they get in the way and there is a a phenomenal sense of
Liberation and freedom that can happen when we're no longer navigating the world navigating ourselves through any
belief system whatsoever does that give us the opportunity to then live in the world
without any operating principles without any functional pragmatic beliefs probably
not uh I think that uh we we have to
understand what what is practically useful uh in our society in the world of
other people and uh different cultures have different practical kind of orientations
points of view that they're operating from and some of them are pretty deeply
ingrained even in the language which we which people speak and um and it's not like uh some
of these core deep World Views views about self and others are right and WR
wrong they are ways in which we manage to navigate negotiate the world together
with other people and they have a pragmatic usefulness but to see them as such to
see them as contingent to see them as being uh relative or uh to see them as
being um provisional uh means that we don't add
an extra layer of holding on or insisting or forcing ourselves and too
often in this world we see conf competing beliefs and people who want to impose their beliefs on
others and too often we see people struggling with beliefs that are very
negative to themselves and make their life much more difficult than it needs to be beliefs that uh that justify
violence and greed beliefs that justify seemingly uh negative
self-use and so to discover it's possible to breathe and live and see and
smell and touch uh in a with a radical Simplicity free of All Views belief
systems clinging of them gives us a taste of freedom but also gives us a
vantage point to see the operation of these views and beliefs that we have to
see them arise see them occur we have a by by kind of clearing the canvas in a
sense we see the pain Strokes as they're made and um and so um then we have much
more choice we have much more ability to see it as being uh a contingent uh
provisional kind of point of view we can look and see how is this useful and when
is it useful when is it not useful uh how do I hold on to it and so
we have much more wisdom about the beliefs we have but we but so so the path of uh Insight
Meditation is to discover this radical place where we're not dependent on any
worldview at all any belief system at all and even Buddhism even beliefs in
Buddhism have to be let go even beliefs in that it's possible to get enlightened
have to be let go even the beliefs that there's a path to practice everything
falls away and um and uh and it's replaced by
something and it was replaced by something very fundamental that is not
that's more having to do with maybe instinct or some deeper Wellspring
inside of a source inside of understanding that um is not based on uh
or centered on or um or um attached to
uh all the constructed beliefs that we have all the ways that we have
constructed uh World Views that uh have an origin and it's you know uh
historians of philosophy and sociology and anthropology can see show
how fundamental worldviews that people have have a history that they come from
certain uh philosophers thinkers cultures in a particular way down through the times and and for example in
the modern West modern America modern California maybe more than some places um the world view that came out
of Freud and young um you know some you know in over the last 100 120 years or
so have radically shaped um uh parts of
modern culture but without us knowing that that's the origin of it and we just
take it for granted that that's certain things are just the way they are it's the way Nature Made
Us and so by getting really quiet and peaceful we can begin questioning or
seeing these operating principles that are not necessarily required to be happy
and free and to be functioning in the world in an effective and supportive way
for towards everyone and one of those like operating principles that is left is that um it's
something as simple as um uh if you get a thorn in your foot uh you pull you you
sit down and pull off the thorn rather than keep walking and having go dig deeper and deeper in is there a belief
system that you take out the thorn you can say you believe it's useful to take it out but um it's a it's such a deep
kind of sense of obvious that you want to stop harming yourself and it's simple thing to do it doesn't
really require believing anything because it operates so on a much more
basic level than having to logically think what should I do here and what's my beliefs and I'm going to go look at
the text the manual for Being Human Being what do you do when you have a a thorn I don't know I don't know what to
believe in here so as we kind of drop into this radical Simplicity of being there's a a
different kind of uh way of responding to the world that's closer to that of
pulling out a thorn and and uh the simplest way that I have of describing this is a radical or
a thoroughgoing dedication to non-harming not as a philosophy not as a
logic that's been worked out but rather as um uh with a from a clear
sensitivity that if we harm others intentionally we are harming ourselves
we are putting a thorn in our hearts and of course we don't want that thorn there
so we'll pull it out and that means that uh we pull out the intention to
consciously intentionally cause any harm to any other people and uh and that is a
phenomenal uh foundation for healthy life and a healthy Society maybe it
doesn't provide everything we need to do and everything we need to organize and every perspective we should have about
what goes on in our society but what a phenomenal Foundation Foundation of
freedom and non-harming and um and it's almost as if
for non-harming is a fundamental belief but it's it's not quite a belief it's
just a uh it's more more almost biological in nature rather than
philosophical in nature so um so this movement
towards uh having no views no views no no religious views no views of what's
ultimate no no religious views that we hold on to insist on this is the truth
this is um one of the core core could I say beliefs maybe so core
beliefs that I have core teachings that I have core pragmatic useful
orientations that point to something that is beyond beliefs beyond anything
dep depends on views and um and to know that as I've said to know
that place to know that possibility then lets us return into the world of
views World Views orientations perspectives that we have on life and
hold them lightly and hold them only in the sense that is this useful and how is
this useful and let's use them for the benefit of everyone including self let's
use them for an more ultimate purpose the purpose of ending all harm in this
world that we live in so thank you very much and um May you
go forth today uh with this that kind of Simplicity of
being that is devoted to non-harming thank
you for