hello and welcome on this
week of the five faculties as the theme and now on Friday fifth faculty is
wisdom and an alternative translation of PA
often translated as wisdom is dis
discernment our faculty our capacity to be Discerning in the moment to have
insight about what is useful and not useful to do what is skillful what is
wholesome to do and uh and this very basic
distinction that guides what we what we engage in what we do with our lived life
as we live it is invaluable that we always have a guide a guide a support a
reference point for how to go forward and that's maybe fundamental to
e every purpose we have the activities in which we engage
in all fall back to a common denominator when we're doing Buddhist
practice we see it with wisdom we see it with discernment
and the simple distur is we know to do those
things that bring happiness bring well-being
build a bring a feeling of ease or calm or peace or and we avoid those things it does the
opposite and so when we sit and meditate we start getting a clear sense
that certain things we do do are not really useful not really beneficial for
ourselves to spend a lot of time thinking planning reviewing
fantasizing is seeing Oh this is not so useful there's a discernment a clear knowing a clear
Insight it's obvious oh there's better things to do than be caught up in
thoughts we can be mindful we can be present for our lived experience really be here with this and part of the reason
to be here this is where the evidence exists for becoming Discerning becoming
wise we see in our own experience that when
we have the hindrances operating it doesn't serve us when there is
greed strong desire for something when there's ill will when we're stuck in fear or CAU up
in fear or toror resistance when there's restlessness and
regrets that we remorse that we're just spinning out on and when we're don't know what to do
we're uncertain we have doubts we're
wavering these are not so healthy for us but to have
confidence in a path of practice where we show up for our lives in a clear
way that we engage with a certain kind of heroic effort like yes being present
here this is invaluable
to accompany ourselves with mindfulness be present for our experience
yes to uh immerse ourselves in the experience to really com be composed and steady
here in our experience yes stay here be here these are the valuable things to
do and we can feel how the UN wholesome stuff creates stress
strain in fact the core discernment is between stress and the
absence of stress between ouch and
a so when we sit today is to sit with mindful discern discernment Discerning
mindfulness where we can discern
oh this way of being is stressful there must be another
way at least we can become mindful of it in a simple straightforward forward
maybe calm way peaceful mindfulness that's how we can
engage so assuming a meditation
posture and gently closing the
eyes and take time to settle into your
body Begin by reorient reorienting
yourselves to your embodied
experience whatever your mind is caught up
in gently tell your mind this is not the
time there's something more important to do
now here to be present and lived experience through the
body and as you exhale to relax your
body with the mind's discernment we can discern and see that
holding tension is not so
beneficial that relaxing the tension softening around the
tension that is wholesome that's a good thing to
do
and then relaxing the thinking mind having mental tension is also
not so
beneficial what is beneficial is to soften and relax that tension
letting the thinking mind become calmer and
slower Maybe by reassuring your thinking
mind that here and now sitting in meditation is
safe this is a time for Renewal and
deeper connection to support you to live your life in a wiser way
later it's okay to let go of your concerns for
these minutes maybe you'll be in a better
place to consider them after your
meditation softening let go of your thinking mind
to and then in the discernments of the Buddha what he he has
discovered is that mindfulness is always
helpful the mindfulness that a companies our lived
experience and then one of the really wholesome ways of doing that is to be is
to accompany your breathing
accompany it with a
peaceful presence peaceful
attention
for
for to meditate with the
discernment of what is the most valuable thing to do right now in
meditation is it to allow the mind to be hijacked by your
thoughts or is it to be to wake up to be
here so that this invaluable capacity you have to accompany yourself be present for
your life is applied to the lived experience
in meditation of breathing of
body being
Discerning to let go of what is stressful
that you can let go
of and engage in what is
beneficial accompanying yourself with discernment
Here and Now
for
e
to gently quietly maybe peacefully be
[Music] Discerning about this moment
and as you go into the next moment how will you engage with the next
moment how will you show up for it that feels wholesome
beneficial without stress or strain not just being present for what
is is this
moment but being Discerning of how you're going to be
now so you can receive the next
moment
for
for and then coming to the end of the
sitting with some discernment some care
and wisdom to bring
forth something in the family of Good Will
kindness basic friendliness for
yourself will you let yourself know that you're here to accompany yourself with Good
Will with friendliness and
care and to extend that good will and care and
friendliness out to into the world
yes to this world this difficult world that we live
in I have the discernment to know how valuable it
is to show up with good
will not with ill will not with
distraction not with a mind hijacked by regrets and
anxieties to show up for this world as a friend of the
world may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free May the way that I show up for this
world contribute to that possibility even if it's only for the
next person I meet may all beings be
[Music]
happy thank
you
so hello everyone welcome to this fifth talk on
the five faculties these
five kind of inner powers that we have
and whereas in the ancient world they call them uh aspects of Indra the great God
So Divine qualities inside in a colloquial English we might say that
these days that there are superpowers that we
have they're so important to these five
indas um these five faculties capacities
so uh they all have to do with action not about just understanding and seeing
except that understanding and seeing is a kind of action is an
engagement and this idea of choiceful engaging consciously
engaging with our life is not something we often hear in
the meditation circles where a lot of is about relaxing settling back being
receptive not asserting oneself and those are fantastic ways is
to engage they're a kind of Engagement there's something we do with choice we're activating something to be
receptive we're activating um letting go and this here
we in the five faculties we're emphasizing the activation of something which is nourishing helpful
sustaining freeing for us and so to to
activate uh confidence in what we're doing what not not to do things out of
habit not to do things out of just because we should not to do things because we're forced to but like when
you come to meditation to choose to engage in a
conscious kind of deliberate way that yes I'm engaging in this I'm going to be
here for this but not in a way that's stressful not in a way that stirs things
up but does the opposite it helps us to ody andh habit what we're doing that
something settles and relaxes um like someone who is engaged
in doing um you know something like yoga or Tai Chi
Chiang it takes effort we have to put ourselves into it but in the movements
of these practices something begins to quiet and settle and let go and we're
more and more embodied in here but there is a choice to engage to
activate and to enter into the activation that something
harmonizes so the confidence in practice is that that what gets us going and
chooses yes big yes let's do it and sometimes it takes heroic
effort it takes uh courage to show up here and now sometimes it's courage
courage because it goes against the the prevailing winds of society that there's more emails to uh answer there's more um
Netflix movies to watch there's more this and that and things to do and get
busy and things are you know Dire Straits we're alarm alarmed by how
things are so we have to kind of get anxious and busy to be courageous that we don't have to do that
in fact we show up better better for the world and care for the world better if
we show up uh calmly relaxedly openly
prepared smart to be able to tune into what's happening so to have the courage to do
this and then the fifth faculty is mindfulness which and this week I'm been
presenting as accompanyment we choose to accompany we engage in this practice of accomp
comping ourselves the world around us as if we're a good friend a non-judgmental friend who's
there to listen and see and hold everything there with care and then uh to steady ourselves in
that to immerse ourselves in this present moment experience like a good maybe in again with these movement
practices of yoga or Tai Chi or Chiang uh or other ones that uh uh we
immerse ourselves in the activity we're doing and almost like we forget ourselves and forget time playing a
musical instrument doing a a craft there are things we do which um you know take
effort and energy but when we finish doing them we feel much more relaxed the steadiness because we
immersing ourselves in what we're doing so and then the fif fifth faculty for
today is um usually translated as wisdom and uh today I'm offering it as discern
because wisdom is always present moment Focus to to see in such a way that we're
wise so which is another meaning for discernment and
um the um and the idea is to discern useful ways to be present for
this world useful way to activate our accompaniment our mindfulness our life
this wonderful gift we're given of being gift we've been given of Consciousness being consciously
aware be Discerning about how we can use that how we can be aware so that it it
it reduces stress it doesn't add to stress not only does it reduce stress it
also brings forth a a higher quality beneficial way of being in the world it
allows for some deeper sensitivity deeper flow of of Good Will and wisdom
and freedom and um not so different again you know doing a movement like
yoga and taii and Chiang that uh we might even be stressed out and hardly able to think very well for ourselves
when we start but at the end of the class uh we're much more present and
ready to have conversations with people and take care of things and be in the world in a nice open clear way
so to be Discerning about what we're doing as we engage in our accompaniment
of Life how do we accompany it so there's less stress tensing up rushing
uh being angry having ill will having desires caught up in fantasies that
obscure how well we can see what's there those are not skillful we can see that
we can feel it and we learn over time that that's not the way to live a
life a free life a productive a useful life is one that we engage and
activate being present with this beautiful capacity of my of conscious
awareness and um and so to inhabit that to to have confidence in that have
courage to show up this way to have the accompaniment that allows conscious
awareness to really flower and to sustain it to be studied
in it composed in it that's what discernment supports us to
do and uh in the teachings of the Buddha uh it tends to be
binary uh that um that this kind of distinctions that um uh uh between what
is helpful and what is not helpful and um and that just that uh
that's my words for the Translating the Buddha kind of my paraphrasing of it but just that is what I'm doing now helpful
is or is it not helpful and um and if it's at all
unhelpful don't do it have enough discernment to recognize oh I don't
think this is helpful and certainly if you're going to make this situation worse don't do
it have enough discernment to know what not to do just that is
life-changing but then if in addition you know have the discernment the clarity In This
Moment how to activate how to bring forth
conscious awareness in a way that is beneficial is
onward leading uh helps you become wiser and clear helps you to be present in a nice way
for this world of ours and for others do it by all means and do it a lot let it
fill your life let yourself be immersed in a life of conscious
awareness with the confidence the Courage the showing
up the giving yourself to being
Discerning having the discernment to know that confidence is good
confidence what is good to have confidence in this
practice to have the courage to know what to do conscious awareness showing
up to have discernment to know the value of accompaniment
that you how you accompany your life is where conscious awareness can
flower to have the discernment to know that jumping around and being scattered
and preoccupied is not so useful that being
present steady continuous being here that is useful so these are superpowers these
are amazing capacities we do have each one of you has
this and in Buddhism these are becoming
activated these are becoming used and uh flowering for us in ways
that uh that are so beneficial and when there when these
becomes uh um strong in fact the Buddha
called them the five powers so to call them superpowers is
Maybe a little bit cute but but uh in fact he called it Bala and Pali and so
strengths and so to have those these strengths then they not only is what we
activate faculties we wake up and use but they become sustaining qualities
that are there kind of carrying us along supporting us in everything we
do so thank you very much and um
so um in the so next week I'll be on Retreat and
uh at IRC and and uh I'm just going to
see who is speaking next week it's Matthew briller is uh going to be here
next week and he's a wonderful teacher and you'll be very good hands with Matthew and I'll be back the following
week and um we'll continue on this kind of introduction to mindfulness part two
that um we're doing now and so those of you who might be new for the beginning of the year I did a 25p part
introduction to mindfulness the basic practice we do here at IMC and then I'm following that with
this now this part two and now we've done 10 uh 10 in the series The Five
hindrances and now the five faculties and we'll continue with this kind of theme uh when I return and um thank you
for being here and being part of it and I certainly look forward to coming back
in in about 10 days oh and the the last thing I want to
say before we quit is that this is the um I think today in some ways marks the
the end of four years of doing these YouTube teachings for me I think that
sometime uh next week I think maybe like the 14th of March or something uh is the
the four foure Mark we started on a Monday four years ago and um so those
are four wonderful years I'm grateful to have be doing this and grateful to all of you that uh I and we have this chance
to meet this way and practice and and teach and um so my appreciation for this
opportunity thank you