so one of
the ways that the Dharma Dharma practice is described is that it's onward
leading and implies Mo movement and uh there's two kinds of
movement that most character characteristically kind of represent uh the dark
uh one is that of a PA usually in English you say a path that we
walk and the other is a current of the
river that we float in that carries us along the path met
metaphor suggests that we have to engage we have to do something with to bring ourselves along we have to walk walk the
path the current and the river current metaphor suggests that not so much we
have to do uh except stay in the current and be carried by
something and uh it's a significant point in the practice when it shifts
from one to the other for people who are beginning it can take a lot of effort a lot of walking a lot of engaging in it
at some point the onward leading feels like it's almost innate and something is
being carrying us uh there's something onward moving and what is that onward
moving that we feel or sense or what is it and
um I find it uh kind of inspiring to think that it's maybe it's somewhat
related or similar to the onward moving nature of a little child
growing what is it that propels the growth of a baby child like I used to
try to stop my son from growing I put my hand on his head and said stop he would laugh you know because you
know it's you know he fed so well in my arms at one point the little baby and I remember those days but nope there's
something propelling him to grow and this movement on up onward movement of
like you know by the time we had the second child I was wasn't so eager for the Milestones to happen you know
walking and talking cuz for they just meant more
problems the first kid I didn't know that like I was like cheering him on couldn't waited you even worry like why
isn't he there yet second one take your
time but you know what is it that propels them to learn and develop and grow what is that natural process and
what is a natural process that propels us in a sense onward in this Dharma practice maybe it's as natural as a
child growing a tree growing or something so this onward leading nature
of the path and there's a very classic description of the Dharma which I find
still very inspiring very evocative that the Dharma is something that's
immediately visible Here and Now it's it's uh immediate so it's it's
visible here and now it's immediate meaning it's not that's not really part
of the past and the future that's not the orientation it's something that really we connect to
here it is um uh it uh it's they use a very
colloquial expression for this um it uh literally in P it's a very simple
ordinary termo means hey hey doesn't say hey but I add that
to make it even more kind of colloquial hey come
see and so some people translate it as it invites inspection it invites us to come and
look but really just saying come come along come see and um see for
yourself and then onward leading and to be experienced personally
by the wise so something that each person uh you're you're this the
description you're the wise one that you're supposed to experience for yourself so that's what the Dharma is
whatever you know it's something that's immediate visible experienced for yourself inviting to you to come and
take a look and so one of the most classic metaphors for the practicing the Dharma
is the notion of a path and um and uh I'm inspired by this notion of
a path and uh probably because i' under the influence of kind of European
English culture where a path is kind of idelic it's kind of pastoral it's kind
of like you know this wonderful little I love you know hiking in the mountains on little paths and then the forest and
little pass and finding my way and you know it's kind of like wonderful thing and for some of us in the American
speaking world at least you know like each person has to you know find their own
path great individualistic thing find your own path you know and um so it turns out that the
word in ply the ancient language Buddhist language doesn't really mean
path um it's the word for road but road is not so inspiring we
associate with roads with asphalt and cars drive on Road roads and um and so
you know the eighth full Road let's it doesn't quite evoke something
as heartfelt as it for many of us as the the eighth fold path at least we're so
you know but there's a difference between a path and a road a path is usually is associated
usually something narrow and uh it's something that's in the woods something in in the wilderness
or something and it's usually a narrow thing and it's easier to kind of feel like you're walking it alone when you
walk on a path and even if you go with a group of people they let's say you walk a path the distance between people
stretches out and maybe you don't see the people in front of you because they're like around the curve and or
behind you or something a road is wide and and for the Buddha who spent most of
his adult life on the flat Plains of Northeastern India India you know the
roads were flat a lot solid and wide and and a road is something you can a lot of
people can accompany you on they can walk side by side you walk together
there's room for if you have if you found your road the road you can invite all your friends to
join you you can do it together in a way that in a path that feels more like
you're on your own but the road you can it's wide enough to hold all your friends all your family your whole
Community it's a wide thing and in fact it's very valuable
this idea of walking the path walking the road uh together and uh and be
accompanied and I like to think of it is that uh we're walking the road with the
Buddha uh that he accompanies us and um the same road he
walked and um at some point uh as we go along with this you have to appreciate
that there's all these paradoxes you know that two things you have to hold both in the Dharma so there's a path
that path the road that you walk and there's also the river you get into that carries you something at some point you
walk this road enough something begins freeing up opening up begins to grow and
develop and you feel like there's an onward leading momentum in the practice
and I have it little bit sometimes when I go for long hikes especially over like you know for many days in a
row after a while um there's a feeling of like I'm not walking there's this
Force this momentum inside of me that energy inside of me like I'm just like you know sometimes I end up walking
faster and faster as I get into it I get in shape I get stronger and it's like whoa just you know cruising along kind
of it's onward leading movement onward leading movement of the walking
something I'm in the the stream now of walking and being carried by it
somehow and um and so it the onward leading the road implies a destination
that we're going someplace at the same time in some ways
we understand the destination is right here now it's not somewhere else so how
do you hold both of those uh we have the idea that and again
maybe has something to do with some of this Western culture that some of us
have grown up in where there's a very strong among many westerners to uh prioritize or emphasize
how great it is just to be and not to do and some like like
sometimes that's been really nice for me and helpful for me because in sometimes in my life I've been too much in like
actively anxiously doing doing doing and being told oh you don't have to do you
can just be ah so that's nice but actually they both
need it for the Dharma practice there's what we have to do and there's what we be and they
eventually don't have to be two different things the doing is the is being being is the doing
the two don't have to be separated in fact to have them as two different things sure changes us so all these
things there's a destination but the dination is here destination is here there's what you have to walk but then
there's how you get carried along there's how you just be but there's also the doing you have to do so all these go
together not to confuse you and get you all tied up in knots but rather to to
appreciate the richness of it and but also uh to not short Change yourself to
to to to choose any one of these SS sides actually limits you eventually
sooner or later all these sides come together and are working together and one of the one I want to emphasize today
is the idea of the of the Buddhist practice being a journey it's onward leading it involves going
someplace and in that Journey it's the point of it big part of it is the journey
itself and and maybe not the destination there's a destination freedom oparation
Awakening but uh this the the journey itself is what we have to settle into
and just trust the journey or just trust the next step be the next step of the journey we'll be changed by that journey
we'll keep grow like a child grows we'll grow in the Dharma just giving ourselves the next
Journey they still remember my son taking his first steps guess
what amazingly a proud parent his first steps
were seven but then he fell oh my my son fell he
[Laughter] failed I didn't think that but I could
have like the point is to walk and by golly he stopped walking he fell and I
could have gotten angry and gave him a talking to explained like this is not how it's done
when you walk you really walk that's what they say in Zen when you walk you walk no no you know of course it's the
point is a journey for kid little kid like that the point is the process and of course they're going to fall and then
they get up and they walk some more and they fall and eventually they don't fall so much until they're old enough to start
that again and um so the
U so just part of the life process so we're on the this journey and the point
of the lot of Journey is just being on the journey what come what Come What May and we just keep practicing and
working but one of the things that can support this journey is and this momentum this both what we do the
walking we do and the stream that carries us is to have a
feeling and understanding cognitively but also a feeling for what
is where is the onward leading nature of this where's the the
inner Sensations the inner sense that oh
this now is onward leading this is where we go forward here
there's the next step and that can be not just a cognitive like idea but you
can actually feel it in your body there's not so much difference maybe when you do walk I have a friend who
loves to walk off Trail off the paths and she explained to me last week why
she likes it so much she says because um all her senses are involved if she walks
in the mountains off the trail and every step is consequential every step she's
she's she say I'm being shaped by the terrain as I walk that's very different
than I walk on the road and and uh and there like every step there's something
inside of me that knows to step a certain way to shift my weight a certain way to turn my foot a certain way to
bend a certain way to turn here and there and go and it's not like she's planning it all out but she feels like
all her senses are involved and something inside of her knows and feels
you know how to make all the little adjustments that have to be made to to walk off Trail in the mountains and she
feels very alive and connected to the Earth connected to the natural world when she does this and so she she finds
great Delight in it but so there she has an on there's something inside of her nose the way to how to find her way
that's more than just you know following a map that she knows she has to discover
it as she goes so the onwards onward leading
nature of it so I want to take you on this journey or take you on a journey so
many of the teachings in Buddhism are uh organized like especially like a lot of
lists that some people are irritated by but part of the lists are they're
actually depicting or representing the onward leading nature
that you can kind of almost if you can feel your way into these lists sense them not just kind of think of them as
you know abstract lists but think of them as or feel them as something that is embodied something represents you and
your inner growth your inner capacity to develop uh that wants to come forth just as much
as a child wants to grow in a sense and that this represents this onward leading
nature of uh of the Dharma as we grow in it so there's a um a list of this this
journey called the parames the 10 Perfections the 10 wonderful qualities
that are developed can be developed on the path you don't want to take this too seriously you don't want to take the
linear way in which is talked too seriously um and uh that you have to fit
into all this but um but what I want what I want to do today is to convey these
10 um as a journey as as kind of a linear progression one building and
setting the conditions for the next to arise and my dream is that uh as I speak
this that I can kind of evoke some inner sensibility in you for
each quality that you'll you'll maybe think about a reference point for each of these qualities that maybe once upon
a time in your life this you have you felt this you experienced this for yourself maybe in some way that's more
than just you know just an idea but some way that shaped you or affected how
you engage in the world how you were and acted in the world or how you felt and
how you experienced yourself in the moment and then as you feel this maybe
maybe you can kind of feel uh into how something inside of you maybe is
oriented towards these qualities something inside of you feels yes this can be good this can be this is
a place that this is something that's worth making room for in your life yes
this is something that you're capable of having your system
maybe not in your ordinary thinking mind but something deep inside it's a source
inside yes yes you're capable yes in the right circumstances yes this wants to
come out maybe not in all circumstances but in enough
circumstances so um so the onward leading nature so last time I taught
here on Sunday I I about the four noble truths at the heart of the Four Noble
Truths is our capacity to distinguish between the
things that we do that bring
suffering and the possibility of being free of that without
suffering the the things that in make it simpler because suffering is a big word
that some people don't relate to or just but be able to distinguish
experientially between what elicits in you
ouch that's a that's not a sophisticated word just ouch oh you know oh that
doesn't feel good oh you know that's stressful and what goes
ah Ah that's good and a cold windy day you know it's
kind of like you tense up and that's a little bit of an ouch maybe but then you stand in the Sun and
something softens and warms up and that's enough we can have the ability to
distinguish between this very simple movement from ouch to
ah and there are times where the ah Direction just as a completely natural
thing to do I've been tense in my life maybe my
shoulders were up in my ears and I've had friends come over and say Gil maybe
they even put their hands you know kindly on my arm and said Gil you know you seem kind of
tense and I didn't know it until they said it and just because they said it and
reminded me I could feel it and now I knew it there was an onward leading movement I didn't have to do it I didn't
to think about it or plan it out or how I going to do that something inside of me gives gave away and relaxed oh yes
I'm tense oh that's true that's the onward leading nature that was something
knows something knows how to go forward in time to create Health to create a
movement of goodness so the for formable truths are
partly teaching us pay attention to this notice this and for that you have to be
in the present moment it's visible it's experiential here and now to
feel ouch and ah it's not really about the past and
the future it's about now it's immediate and there's something about
this that invites us to come and look to inspect there's something about if you really notice your ouches and AZ it kind
of like calls you pay more attention here
and it's um something which is onward leading just as just as dramatically as
I relax when my friend tells me I'm tense so one example of something onward
leading for me when I was a relatively new Zen student I worked with other Zen
students at Zen Center had a bakery back then on Cole and P prases in San
Francisco and uh called the tasahara bakery and I worked
there and so one of the Zen priests was ran the
bakery and um and one day I was upstairs in the office I don't know what I was doing up there but I was sitting next to
him and he was opening opening mail and he read this the letter that
came and he turned to me and asked me how he should respond to the the letter
I was just a little kid I was you know you know I didn't know I didn't know much and U and I was certainly surprised
that he would consult with me around the letter but what it was was a local neighborhood association that was
fundraising for something and he said how much do you think we should give the bakery should
donate and like what donate what's
that I had didn't grow up with any kind of real understanding of donating and
giving and while you would and rather embarrassed to say this especially what we are now here at IMC but it was
true and uh so I was like a little confused what to say I I don't think I said anything and um and didn't it
didn't compute for me and then uh he said oh I think we'll
do $50 which in 1979 was you know more than it is
now and um and I said wow like wow
wow that's something that really made an impression on me it touched something in
me something was awakened in me it was the birth of some onward
leading movement some growth something that was beginning to open in me around
generosity it was a small little thing and maybe it's not worth even a story to
tell anyone except it made a big big impact on me it was the beginning of
something being something was being was born in that witnessing that little experience in what he was
doing and as I went along there were other experiences like this and uh then there were experiences
where I was able to be generous to others and I felt something inside of me
kept opening something I could feel this momentum how good that was an ah this is
good it's not a should it's it's a
good it's not a should it's said of course this is what wants to come out
this onward leading nature I learned that when it's a should
and it doesn't come from this onward leading kind of ah yes it's not so
healthy for me so the first of these 10 parames this
beginning of this journey many times in the Buddha gives kind of description of kind of the path of practice or the
teachings he begins with evoking generosity and some people say that the
path begins with generosity doesn't have to but it's an inspiring idea because generosity puts
you in community you can be generous to yourself
but I you know it's probably good sometimes to do that but uh generally
generosity is something you do with others and to the world and so to be that the Buddhist
path begins with generosity means it begins with our relationship to the world around us it begins by rectifying
or or adjusting those relationships in a way that happens when you start
practicing generosity when you practice generosity from this place of ah rather than should
if you practice generosity not out of you know you know it's a transaction and
I'll get something back but you just this wonderful openness and
giving that um it you have to if you do it wisely you have to pay attention to
the relationships it it clarifies relationships it heals
relationships um I've known people people come to me and talked about you know some very difficult relationship
they have with some family member or someone especially family members you can't get away
from and um and uh seems like the other person is kind of unreasonable in their
difficulty and I say what uh just uh start practicing small acts of
generosity when you go visit that person bring something you baked or cooked they just little things and and sometimes
people come back and say Gil that made a huge difference the person began to relax and began to treat me a little
more kindly and you know so so the act of generosity to change and develop and
rectify and establish kind of a healthy relationship to the world around us that
I think generosity can do it puts us our practice our life in context of that
what we do has an effect on the world around us and the world around us has an effect on us this is a this is where
Dharma practice is not about going sitting in meditation alone or finding
taking your path the narrow isolated path up in the mountains by yourself
getting away from all those difficult people I mean for many some of us occasionally it's like life would be
easy if it wasn't for the people and um but in fact the Dharma
practice is to be inclusive of that and so that it starts there so what is this
onward move movement of generosity of giving to relate to people to the world
from that place where there's a inner growth inner call to get to offer a
smile to open the door for someone to not grab the shopping cart at
the grocery store because you know because you're it's close one to you and as someone else is getting it you just
no I don't that's easier for me just take this one you know but rather this person is a
whole person themselves who knows what difficulty their life has been and what they've been up to in the
moment maybe just like here there's a confusion about who was here at this grocery cart first here
please and the person relaxes oh thank you it's been a hard day and to have someone just offer such
a small thing who knows what it does for them and what does it do for you if
after you do it they say thank you it's been a hard day oh that felt good that
was an ah that I didn't wasn't selfishly grabbed it for myself I kind of offered
it to the person so as we practice generosity in
this way it provides more evidence more
connection to what feels like ouch and what feels like
ah we get more sensitive to that as we get more sensitive to that
Movement we start seeing it in other areas of our life and it turns out that what is
usually in English speaking world is called ethics there's actually no word in poly
for ethics isn't that something that's a whole other
story but from our English point of view Buddhism is very ethical they just don't
have a word for ethical isn't that great yeah it's hard to believe
but as um but they have a word for uh virtuous
conduct so as we go along we start the sensitivity leads us to understand that
certain behaviors in relationship to other people are a big ouch you know if you
kill people that's that's an ouch if you hit people aggressively it's an ouch for
you but to not everyone realizes that not everyone is paying attention to
what's going on inside of themselves some people even say it feels good to hit someone but actually it doesn't if
you're really attentive and if you're you're you're
sourcing your life in this deeper place where children grow where you
grow you would feel the difference between Behavior which is an ouch and an ah in English language
ethical Behavior which is an ouch and an ah so this is called Sila often in P in
English it's translated as ethics but uh the word really has to do with conduct
ethics is kind of a broader maybe more deeper kind of thing but it's so the
common translation these days is virtuous conduct so we start practicing virtuous
conduct which is the walking is the doing we do things
and uh and so where's that onward leading as we live more ethically and
feel more these ouch and awe this Movement we have then what do we feel
next so the next part of me so it's first generosity and then we call it
ethics for now the next one is um a frightening word for some people off-putting
renunciation oh these Buddhists here we go Letting Go
H but this letting go in relationship to the ouch and the
ah is learning that I don't have to do the ouch thing I don't have to do the greed the
hatred I don't have to be so afraid I don't have to tense up so
much I don't have to be so caught in things my pre occupations that's an ouge this this way
of living actually I'm better off if I don't do these
things there's an A in the other direction so renunciation the English word doesn't
provide the richness of the word in po which has the meaning of much more what
much more has meaning of what you're G what you gain by letting go we benefit
this onward leading movement towards growth and freedom is found in
renunciation as we renounce as we let go be this this world of ouches and O
becomes more sensitive more richer the sense of ah becomes more stronger and
stronger reference point the ability to be calm to be relaxed to be at peace becomes more and more of a reference
point so we get more and more sensitive to the slightest little movements of ouch the slightest movement of tension
of feeling uneasy and that distinction is the classic
distinction for wisdom the fourth of these Perfections
we become wise and isn't that because you read all the books about Buddhism and you know
all about the all the lists and you know it's something really simple this wisdom
we're looking for it's this onward leading feeling that we can have when we
recognize this is healthy for me and this is not this is beneficial for me
and this is not and over time that wisdom becomes more and more immediate
more subtle more in all the little details of our life and things that normally we
wouldn't think it was being ethical even it could be as simple as how you sit in a chair
you can feel oh you know this way I'm sitting is not so good for me I've sat in a
couch in a way that totally expressed my
depression I was couldn't slump anymore and still be in a
couch and um and uh and by doing that I
learned I was actually reinforcing my depression
it wasn't healthy for me to collapse into the depression physically on the couch that way and I found that if I
changed my posture and sat upright in a more you know dignified way it didn't
make the depression go away but boy was it a world of difference there's oh there is some here
now there's a some other thing happening here there's an it's kind of an awe there's kind of a movement towards
Health there's something here more than just C cing into the depression so
sitting in a chair you know that me I use that as an example that uh you know even subtle
things that we don't pay attention to start becoming more and more part of the under the scope of Buddhist
wisdom as we become wise like this way then the onward leading nature of the
path comes along is that uh we're more motivated and inspired to act
differently to live differently to engage in our life differently and this
is now the parame me of viia Vitality or
effort that we be we become more interested in living a different way and
sometimes then because of that we make huge behavioral choices some people actually will change something radical
in their life because they realize this what I'm doing doesn't really work anymore I think I have to change
something big and so this Vira this change this effort this engagement
becomes more important and that's what that's what wants to grow that's what wants to come
out as we engage more making more
effort chances are like most people you'll have to be more
patient seven steps and you fall luckily there was that had no meaning for my little son he he was 9
months old the fact that he fell that was a non-event for him I think it's
just like you know that's what happens that's what life is or I don't know he probably didn't think about it he but he
he you know the drive to stand again and walk was was there yeah so but as we get older and we
know more some of us have to be more patient more accepting more tolerant
more spacious more you know patient with ourselves and patient with the path
patient with our life so effort is
good but we don't want to have the effort get in the way of that inner
growth and opening so we need a lot of patience to stand up again and try
again as we are patient then the next part of me is a connection to what is
really true truth and it's still just this ouch and
this a it's really seeing how this applies and works in all kinds of areas in our life and the truth that this
making this distinction and living by this distinction and paying attention to this
kind of movement this path this flow this thing that wants to grow or move through us this is
true and not being living close to it is really a way of not being true to
ourselves so it's some point truth becomes really important with a stronger connection to
what feels true and truthful the next of these 10 is
resolve and uh and so something inside of us decides to become
resolved decides to become intentional decides this is what
I'm going to put my into I'm going to give myself to this this is important
and that can make a huge difference some people come to a point in their life like this is really something I want to
do but resolve can make you a bit Stern and strict and
tight so luckily the ninth Perfection parm me is loving kindness is Good
Will and this also is part of the natural growth I was blown away by meta
by Goodwill when I first encountered it in in this
inside tradition we did the teachers were teaching it and at some point I experienced it and I said
wow this is something I mean certainly the idea of being kind is a nice one but
to experience a kind of onward flow or momentum of Good Will that's deeper than
any idea that we have about it's good idea to be kind this was powerful
and this softens the resolve reminds the resolve that the resolve that we have to
practice should be relaxed should not have any tension as part of it but it's still a
dedication and then the final parame me is equinity and equinity can seem kind of
cold and neutral to people but here it's building on all this other growth and
development over time all the previous nine and now equinity is something that perfects all the others it's like wow
now I understand the ouches and the a of life and how it works and now I can see
that it's much better to not get be reactive I can be at peace I can be
still I can be in this world completely without being tripped up by
it wow this is possible and what that allows in Buddhist
practice is when you're really practicing with a lot of equinity it it puts you in the Stream
remember the stream that's part of the onward moving that you just have to trust the stream and float in the
Stream then the stream can take you to the in the classic analogy the stream
the current of the river will take you to the ocean the Gangi ends up in the
Indian Ocean or somewhere and um so
um so a journey a path an unfolding an onward
leading something like that is in you part of you just like it was you were a
baby once a toddler something in you new to grow and to walk something in you new
to learn speak something you knew to keep growing and developing and and
something is here still for you that's doing the same thing that's available
can you feel it can you sense it can you allow for it can you take time for it
that's what Dharma practices and the Dharma is in you in this way you have to walk it it's a road
that you walk with many people it's a current in the river that you can
trust and it's it's visible here and now but you have to pay attention you have
to take time to look for it it's immediate there something about
it that's right here the next step you take it's it's something about it that
invites inspection come look it's onward
leading and is something to be experienced by the wise so please be
wise so I hope this you could follow this journey I hope it was interesting to do that and maybe that's not the
journey you have to take I was just if you could it all kind of follow I was hoping that it would inspire you to pay
attention to what your way your journey is it is very personal so this idea that
it's your path it's not off off completely but your path is a road with
a lot of people walking next to you everyone's do making their own path on the wide
road so thank you for sharing it with us all
today