so again welcome welcome everybody and uh Happy New Year
I get to say that like with confidence today happy New Year you know sometimes as the days go on you don't know is it
still okay to say happy new year but here I am on the
first and so of course like on the New Year's Day often just marks A New
Beginning often obviously a new year but it's not uncommon for us to set new
intentions I have this idea I'm going to do this out of the other thing I'm going to finally eat more
fiber exercise more meditate more you like all these things that uh we say
that we're going to do and I couldn't help myself I have found myself this past week thinking oh I I should do this
I should do that so and then I would little chastise myself a little bit like oh d just
because it's the beginning of the year doesn't mean you have to set these
resolutions but it's a a time of the year of maybe new beginnings and we might think of these
Beginnings in a number of different ways and in Buddhism in this practice we
tend to talk more about endings than
Beginnings the ending of suffering right this path of practice is all about the ending of suffering like no longer
having the confusion or the sense of it's just not right
somehow or we teach about uh impermanence how thing nothing is lasting forever it's always
ending things are transient all experiences are transient of course they
are but implicit in these teachings even if it's not EXP explicit is this idea of
Beginnings we see this showing up again and again for me often when I'm giving a
guided meditation even if I'm like sometimes I'll give a guided meditation to myself
sometimes I even will use a little uh voice to myself if I'm feeling particularly like
unsettled but I often hear myself saying either out loud or to myself sometimes
if you find yourself lost in thought begin again just simply Begin Again know
this idea of it doesn't matter how many times you've been lost in thought of
what the mind has been doing you always just very simply just come back to the
breath and it's doesn't matter how many times we have to do that
10,000 10 million 1,100 whatever
it also doesn't matter like how long we've been away lost in
thought 10 seconds 10 minutes 10 hours it also that be holds for our
meditation practice like even just coming to the cushion maybe you haven't meditated in years maybe you haven't
meditated in months weeks days whatever it is we can always begin
again and in some ways it's even to be um really
valued there's this of course probably many of you know this book by shenu
Suzuki Zen mind beginner's mind this recognition that in the
beginner that there's this possibility there's some opening whereas the expert has this idea
of like oh yeah I have everything I I got it I I don't need to learn anything new
this is kind of um exemplified by this
story of a Zen or I should say Buddhist Professor
going to the Zen master and saying you know I I understand a lot about uh Buddhism but I
I'd like to learn something from you and the Zen master says great thank you yeah
welcome come on in here have a cup of tea
and the Zen master offers the professor a cup zen master gets the cattle of tea
and pours and pours and pretty soon the
Tea's coming up near the top and starts to overflow and the professor's like wait wait wait it's overflowing and the
Zen master said the cup is like your mind you think that you have all the answers there is no room for anything
else there's no room for me to pour anything in in there so this idea of Beginnings being
valued and not only are they value just an encouragement to always come back
begin again and of course this whole idea of beginning is part of this uh
notion of cultivation whether we're cultivating mindfulness or loving kindness or our ethical
conduct showing up with truthfulness and not causing harm
of course that has some beginning
too so maybe I'm like uh saying again and again this word about beginning but
I also want to share something about the Buddha and his Beginnings some of the ways in which his
the story of the Buddha's Awakening shows up we tend
to idealize the Buddha beautiful fantastic thing to
do we can also emphasize maybe some of the things that we where he didn't take
a clear straight line that his Beginnings maybe weren't
as obvious or straightforward as we might
imagine a story of his seeking for awakening is that he became dismayed
with the life that he was living even though it had so much uh opulence and luxury and sensual
Pleasures probably anything that was available there at that time in Ancient
India and he became dismayed with this after
seeing someone who was old someone who was sick and a corpse
recognizing that that was going to happen in his life also so instead he set out to seek the
Supreme state of sublime peace the Supreme state of sublime
peace AUM
sidam so I went in a with some teachers and learned about some meditation practices and excelled at
them still hadn't found this state of sublime
peace then he did some extreme asceticism still didn't find these
states of sublime piece then he does the middle
way not extreme austerities not extreme
opulence and sits under a Bo tree to discover this Sublime
piece and he
does I like this expression Sublime peace in some ways I think it's all what
we're looking for place where we can
rest have some security a sense of like maybe like this final
exhale but the Buddha he had to find his way it wasn't so clear exactly how to
get there so his beginning of his seeking wasn't always you know just a
clear straight line he knew exactly how to get there and didn't waver didn't do
anything else took him a number of years many
years so then he is awakened and then he doesn't begin to
teach the story is that he hesitates he's like how am I going to
explain this there are so many people that just wouldn't understand this
and he decides to not
teach and the tradition holds that there is a special classification of individ
ual like this they're called Pacha Buddhas the Pacha Buddhas are those
individuals that become completely awakened through their own um without
having heard any teachings and declin to teach it's a valid path not everybody is
intended to be a teacher but then there's some
intervention and the story is that some divine
intervention comes down and says no but you must teach and so he
does and as I mentioned the other day when I was talking about uh
impermanence just mention briefly that he first teaches this former practitioners these uh group of five
that he had been practicing austerities with and when he approaches them they all
agree amongst themselves but we're not going to treat him with respect we will
acknowledge Him but we will not treat him with respect because he gave up the
austerities and is now living in luxury so when he shows up the group of
five speak to him and a what the what the Buddha considers a disrespectful way
but then he convinces them that um no in fact he is awakened and that they should listen to
him and he gives them teachings and even for them who have the
Buddha who's you know just freshly awakened it takes them quite some time
to become awakened the story is of how they had to go out repeatedly for Ms
rounds so days and some of them would go out for Ms and
come back and get food for all the rest before these group of five are
awakened and then the sixth person that the Buddha meets and gives a teaching to
his yasa who is this lay person like
us the Buddha gives him some teachings he becomes
awakened these individuals had been practicing austerities like extreme
austerities took them quite some time a lay person like us got in
immediately we might wonder why is that I don't know we can
speculate maybe the Buddha was still learning how to teach and maybe his
teaching wasn't the best for he group of five maybe these group of five in order
to do such extreme austerities you have to have a rigidness you have to have a
fundamentalist you have to have a very um kind of like narrow way in which to live right to do
extreme to do the type of austerities or you know starving
oneself for example whereas at l person doesn't have
that they have this little bit more flexibility of mind trying things and seeing things
experiencing different things and I'll come back to this later
about the teachings that yasa received that helped him to become
awake but before I do that I want to also just say of course we have all had
our own Beginnings with practice
I remember the first time I ever sat down to meditate I was uh on a Meditation
Retreat I thought I knew how to meditate but actually I didn't I had done yoga
and I thought lying down on the floor with eyes closed for a couple of minutes was meditating but I had a hard time on
that first retreat but you know that was the beginning of my practice all of you had
a beginning the beginning of maybe reading the
Dharma Dharma book or hearing a a podcast or app or com to a dma
talk but one thing about Beginnings is that they're about
change something new when I was working in Corporate
America there was a time in which uh there's a lot of planning happening about some changes that were going to
happen and you know to you know make certain improvements
and and I remember this one individual saying to a group of us saying you know
if we're going to make changes in how the department does things if we're going to make
changes this means you actually have to
change and I remember at that moment feeling like oh I was just kind of
hoping I could stay exactly the way I was kind of comfortable with the way things
are but this recognition of like oh yeah if things are going to be
different it's going to be a little bit uncomfortable have to get out of the
usual and do something new
and pointing to that I'd like to read a poem about Beginnings it's written by
John odonahue an Irish poet and it points to
this about this the beginning the new the new year whatever it is that's going
to begin for you and it starts this
way in out of the way places of the heart
where your thoughts never think to wander this beginning has been quietly
forming waiting until you are ready to emerge for a long time and has watched
your desire feeling The Emptiness growing inside you noticing how you w
yourself on still unable to leave what you had
outgrown it watched you play with the seduction of safety and the gray
promises that sameness whispered heard the waves of turmoil
rise and relent wondered would you always live like
this then the Delight when your courage kindled and out you stepped onto new
ground your eyes young again with energy and dream a path of plenitude opening
before you though your destination is not yet
clear you can trust the promise of this
opening and furl yourself into the grace of
beginning this is at one with your life's
desire awaken your spirit to Adventure hold nothing back learn to find ease in
Risk soon you will be home in a new Rhythm for your soul senses the world
that awaits you this
encouragement for a
beginning I appreciate that in this first stanza is this line this beginning
has been quietly
forming there's less emphasis on Willpower and brute strength and I got
to do this I should do this instead there's this feeling of something that's
growing something that's finding its way maybe like those little blades of
grass that show up in the side walk or after a rain there little mushrooms that
just pop up everywhere are just so delightful kind of unexpectedly and the lawn and the wood
or the a log that has fallen down whatever whatever we see it the beginning that is quietly
forming so there's more of this emphasis on allowing and this unfolding unfurling
this growing instead of okay I should do this I'm
going to make this happen you know that lasts for as long as it
lasts but instead this pointing to something that's you know that's naturally forming and that can
grow and this poem also includes these lines it watched you play with a
seduction of safety and the gray promises that
sameness whispered the gray promises that
sameness whispered and the seduction of
safety how often have our reality doesn't match the
promise buy this do this you'll be happy and it turns out that it
doesn't but instead kind of like tuning in or you know becoming sensitive to
what's happening inside us this and allowing that to unfold and and
furl this does carry this some of this
promise for something new a new beginning but maybe it's not neat and
tidy Maybe it's not even clear what it is maybe like the Buddha we start going
One Direction and realize no that doesn't work okay I'm going to go this direction oh yeah that doesn't work
either but there's this kind of honoring of something inside this uh
seeking this Sublime piece maybe there's something inside of
you that's showing or Whispering something
something about Sublime
peace this poem says though your destination is not yet clear you can
trust the promise of this opening trust the promise of this
opening my practice is all about opening it's kind of like this gesture
of like letting go it's not the gesture of tightening
up and so often there can be the sense of straining okay I got to do
this I know that um I had this idea on a
long retreat that I I supposed to get really
concentrated I had this idea in my mind okay this is a long retreat and this is why people go on Long Retreats as to get
concentrated I strained so much I went a little off the
rails and the teachers are like okay Diana stop meditating and just go outside and go you need to spend hours
out hiking amongst the trees and just kind of loosen up I just got so tense
and tight and I don't know closed down thinking you know that that was the way
to get concentrated it turns out that's if you
want to have the mind be settled there has to be
openness the sense of well-being is an integral ingredient it's it's not
optional the sense of well-being and how we Define well-being maybe shifts and
changes and as we practice but it's part of what supports
this uh seeking for Sublime peace for all of us
I'll read this poem again in out of the way places of the
heart where your thoughts never think to wander this beginning has been quietly
forming waiting until you were ready to emerge for a long time it has watched
your desire feeling that emptiness growing inside you noticing how you
willed yourself on still unable to leave what you had
outgrown it watched you play with the seduction of safety and the gray
promises that sameness whispered heard the waves of turmoil rise and relent
wondered would you always live like
this then the Delight when your courage kindled and out you stepped onto new
ground your eyes young again with energy and dream a path of plenitude opening
before you though your destination is not yet clear you can trust the promise of this
opening unfurl yourself into the grace of beginning
this is at one with your life's desire awaken your spirit to
Adventure hold nothing back learn to find ease in
Risk soon you will be home in a new
Rhythm for your soul senses the world that awaits
you and again that poem is for A New Beginning by John odonahue
and you might say Okay D it that that sounds interesting I want to begin but I
I really don't know where or what or I'm not
sure maybe there's something inside of you but you're don't have a clear sense of what to begin or how to
begin I'll offer the teaching that the Buddha gave to
yasa the first lay person that became awakened and what was the first teaching
that the Buddha gave to this person in which he also gave to yes's
father and then two women and they all became awakened so what was this first
teaching generosity this generosity this sense of
opening this sense of Letting Go this sense of not holding in not uh
clinging but instead you know this this this gesture of
sharing being generous of spirit if somebody makes a mistake not
just immediately pointing it out to them if maybe it doesn't really matter so much
the generosity of giving somebody the benefit of the doubt thinking that doesn't really make
sense to me what you're saying but maybe there's a piece that I missed instead of saying like a person doesn't know what
they're talking about instead to say there must be something here that you must know something that I don't know or
maybe you can help me understand whether this is somebody we
know or somebody that we hear about this practice is not about
acquiring more and more this practice is not about getting Tighter and Tighter this practice is not about acquiring or
attaining or getting it turns out it's all about letting go and then this
something this something this beginning maybe inside of us then has this space
[Music] to Blossom and become whatever it is going
to become when generosity is the first
teaching it's also the last teaching after people are awakened the
Buddha gives the instructions for them to go out and to share with others share
the teachings share the Dharma and we can interpret the Dharma
in a number of different ways obvious ways the teachings but
that's not always appropriate this is we are not about prz and this
tradition but the Dharma maybe is you know just the way things
are this recognition that we don't have to join in
in when there's some harming
happening the drama can be our way of our commitment to
non-harming it can be our commitment to learning about ourselves and cultivating
some mental stability some well-being so that we can be a support
for others generosity is also the ground of
compassion letting go at least at that moment of this sense of okay I'm only
concerned with myself but letting go of this and saying oh here is some
suffering may this may there be an end to this suffering and maybe it's just a
movement of the heart maybe it's something that we actually do but generosity is a part of letting go of
only being concerned with myself or only those people that I like but maybe
there's others who are suffering and to have some generosity and spirit or maybe
it's you know literally with time or service or
money and this practice of generosity we learn about
ourselves we learn about what is it that's easy to let go of and what are
our cherished things what's most important to us and we can see are these
things that are supportive or not we can feel into that what are some of our beliefs that
are the most important and what are the ones that we're willing to
change our beliefs about who deserves things our beliefs about the what ises
money stand for or what things are worth or what's important what's not
important so generosity is such a key and it's a beautiful
teaching and it's awkward for Dharma teachers to talk
about so we don't but I wanted to just say this
because it's can be such a powerful thing and it's it's something that all of us can do because we might have this
idea I want to begin something I want to begin something that's going to support my life and we have these high ideals
I'm going to meditate every day it's a beautiful thing I highly recommend it but it's not always easy we are not
machines we can't just do things like this and sometimes we just have to begin
again but generosity is something that we can do when we're in our daily life
when we meet people when we're having conversations with people as I said giving them space giving them time
giving the benefit of the doubt it's something that we can do in so many situations as a way of
practice and then I'd like to end with this recognition
that the beginnings also have implicit in them endings right you know
beginnings and endings of course they go together and as I mentioned we tend to talk more about
endings but these endings of course is a certain amount of letting go of
course and here's another poem this one's by Rosemary
traumer she I just love her poems she's a fantastic poet she writes a poem every
single day and she posts it on the internet so they're just generosity right just freely
offered and this poem was written on December 24th
2020 you know right of the the pandemic and it's called bonfire of the
heart I thought it was a good poem for the kind of like as the end of the year
and as we're starting the new year Rosemary trummer her poem bonfire
of the heart I throw in any tallies I've been keeping
the ones that record who did what and when I throw in all the letters I wrote
in my head but didn't send I throw in tickets I didn't buy to places I didn't
visit I throw in all those expectations I had for myself and the world last year
and countless lists of things I thought I should do
I love watching them ignite turn into Embers to
Ash I love this space they leave behind
where anything can happen I love watching them ignite turn
into Embers to Ash I love this space they leave behind where anything can
happen at the end of 2020 we had to let go of
all kinds of things but even just a few years later every year we all have these
tallies we've been keeping these letters that we wrote In Our Heads but never
sent places we didn't visit just put those
aside make room for whatever is going to begin this
year whatever is inside of us something that's searching for this
Sublime peace maybe in the same way that the Buddha had this sense yes there's
something better it is possible I'd like to say it's possible I
know it's possible my life is completely different than how it used to be I have found a
piece that uh I certainly did not have years ago so maybe with that I want to wish
you all a Happy New Year and I'll open it up if anybody has
some questions or comments thank
you oh Phil you thought you were oh
I but I'll last one okay now that you're yeah yeah thank you Jim thank you and
happy New Year um that state of sublime peace um you
told us the poly phrase for it could you say it again slowly yeah so um this the
the poly was the highest state of s Sublime piece yeah so let's see here where's the ply I don't have this memor
so I have to read it um here he goes Anam this means highest Santi Santi
means peace VAR is um like
Sublime and padam is state so the highest the Supreme state
of sublime peace Anum Santi
veram ananti
veram uh diah there's a
um there's a question online uh how do you drive consistency
in your meditation habit
yeah that's the question right and we get all year to practice with that
question okay so consistency with a meditation habit I'll just say a few
things there's lots of things and we all get to find what works for us a few
things is to recognize that 2 minutes is better than zero minutes there's something about
just or maybe even one minute so sometimes there's this way if like we
can say oh shoot I haven't meditated for you know x amount of time oh f it I'm
not going to meditate anymore do something like that we often do this right where we just abandon the whole
thing so we are not machines we will do this I promise you everybody does this
can begin and you can begin with one minute two minutes something like this this is a way we find some consistency
two come up with contingency plans we often have this idea okay I'm going to
meditate in the morning before I go to work and going to squeeze in some time
you know there or something like that but what we often don't say is have this contingency plan if for whatever reason
that doesn't work then I'm going to squeeze in 2 minutes 5 minutes 5 hours
whatever it happens to be when I get home from work before I start cooking dinner I'm just going to sit down for 2
minutes or I'm sit in my car for 2 minutes or something like this you know
so have a contingency plan is good um three
is it's helpful to connect to what's important for
us this recognition that you know change is not easy doing something that we
haven't done before is not easy
so on those times when it's tough can we point to or connect to or remind
ourselves or borrow some wisdom from somebody else a book a podcast an app a
Dharma talk like okay yeah I know this is helpful I really don't want to do it
but I'm going to do it anyway there's this way in which we can
um idealize think that every time that we should always want to sit and we
should always sit and it should be a pleasant experience or something but there's something
about keeping in mind the benefits I guess maybe is the word I'm looking for
and even when we don't have that in mind to maybe look at um others or you know
look for some external support I guess that's the word I'm looking for which can be in many
forms coming to a meditation center turns out to be really helpful you can ask all the people here myself included
right and I just came from a retreat and why do we go and Retreats because it's hard to sit that much by
yourself and you know it's if you can with others whether it's online or in
person I'd like to ask you what are what are you that some of you what have you
learned about ways to have some consistency in practice
anybody has something they'd like to share we don't all have to be perfect
but what what are some things that have helped a reminder on my calendar a
reminder in your calendar great thank you it's a great idea we're so often looking at our
calendars right meetings like oh
yeah yeah I to guided I'll teer I
like yeah finding a teacher that you really like and listening to their guided meditations I'm just repeating it
so that uh for the microphone anybody else have some yes I
think and emotions that
wased
yeah
yeah thank you and what is your name namita namita namita was sharing that
she used an app uh 10% happier and uh I
I'm familiar with this app I know most of the teachers on there I can recommend them right Joseph goldsteen was one of
my teachers and he's a main teacher um on that app um and you she was saying that
there's like different topics on their emotions or ethics or loving kindness
there's so much stuff on there and you can choose the duration of the time I think you have to pay for that app
though right yeah namita was also talking about the 7 a Monday through Friday on YouTube uh you
know with Gil and friends and uh I'm just coming
here what about you Jim well well I was going to say so there were two comments
one uh reiterating the the 7 a group on the week weekdays with IMC helps and
also a Audio Dharma is absolutely amazing adio Dharma wow right how many
thousands of talks are on there I don't do guid meditations now there was a time
when I did so I there's lots of guided meditations from me and from Gil and so
many teachers and what about you Jim for your consistency practice what have you what's what's my consistency uh well I
have a u meditation app on my phone and I have it set for a certain number of
minutes on days when I know I'm not even going to do that I always at least start
it so that it shows that that day got used so I I see how many days in a row I
can keep it going Monday is often difficult because I don't use it when I
come here to sit so that this is this is where often where the Gap is I see I see
um you're using an app too right okay all these modern gizmos yeah there was
one other comment that I heard a few weeks ago that was really good about
this notion of getting having some ideal of what the practice is supposed to lead
to and um what Anam tub0 talks about is that
sometimes that can be just another chain of like I'm supposed to be you know
perfectly calm and equanimous he said it might be better to just have the
aspiration to be the person that your dog thinks you are I love it the person dog your dog
Pro I mean if you have a dog or a cat or something you know kind of thinks that you're really this you know kind you
know generous human love it I love it that's so great so that that's more doable in some ways yeah yeah I'd love
that thank you okay so thank you all and Happy New
Year