okay so uh so welcome folks uh yeah nice to
uh nice to see a lot of uh familiar names welcome to uh to new folks happy
to uh to be with you happy to be practicing and
um yeah so that's uh let uh sit or whatever posture body's in
and just take that posture
consciously e
just sensing what it would mean to be grounded this moment
and perhaps the the spine reaches ever so gently Towards the
Sky then we surrender everything else to gravity
we're practicing not being alarmed fed by Sam
Sor by this realm of uh Pleasure and Pain gain and
loss e
and we might use our our breathing it's a way of uh smoothing out
the energetic field of our body
mind
e
for e
we practicing putting down the
project that we call our
life we're not trying to uh fix or help
things
along just kind of trusting that uh as we
surrender help is on its way we don't have to find
it
e
for for
it's just getting so
simple is this body breathing
silence beckoning us
help is on its
way and doesn't require you your
willfulness
e
e e
the phenomena arise fears arise thoughts
arise may become intimidated by them by what they
might mean
and so we freeze time and we try to make
meaning try to reassure
ourselves it's fair enough
but uh we are
practicing knowing all phenomena it's empty
experience becomes so
vivid but uh I L
attenuated
wispy space likee so there and barely
there e
if all we ever do is try to fix
ourself we will never know
ourself
e
e e
maybe we can say the anchor
silence and every bit of noise is
met with infinite
patience
e
e e
okay so uh yeah good to good to sit with
you so I was uh on teaching a a young
adult Retreat uh last week and uh mostly folks in their
20s and somebody asked a question very relevant to that development phase about uh comparing
mind the mind that um the mind that
compares and uh that is of course a time when uh identity you know is being
forged and a key way that we how we know who we are is by
looking at others and making comparisons and judgments greater than less than equal
to and there really they're kind of two Dimensions maybe we could say of this
comparing mind there's the kind of coarser level of me comparing myself
to another and then the second dimension is is sort of almost more fundamental
it's about measuring M measurement any sense of
territoriality and so on the coarser level um we we compare ourselves to
others right we we kind of turn ourselves into a noun into a thing
an Essence we turn others into a thing and then we assess the differences
you know kind of like you know laying one you know our vision of
ourselves against almost like two sheets of transparencies put against one
another seeing what the differences are and uh this is a very painful realm
you know we all know the pain of it uh this is the realm of arrogance and pity
and envy of
Pride shame is an evolutionary psychologist that described you know you described
pride and shame as the universal grammar of social
valuation the universal grammar of social valuation pride and shame and
when I saw that phrase I was like you know that does sound right but it also sounds
very gross you know the universal grammar of social valuation evaluations
you know um the uh SAS Joseph um Epstein was
talking talking about the seven deadly sins lust and gluttony greed laziness wrath pride and envy and said of the of
the seven deadly sins only only Envy is no fun at all right and that is maybe
the Hallmark of the kind of comparing mind you know the the gesture of being a
spectator observing uh the the object of self this
is very painful very painful and uh matu rard says uh in
every every instance Envy is the product of a wound to self-importance and the
fruit of an illusion what can other people's happiness possibly deprive us of nothing
of course only the ego can be wounded by it
and feel it as pain these are the results of our having forgotten our innermost
potential for affection peace
but you know it's not just feeling less than
that's painful even feeling greater than or even momentarily equal to the Buddha
says we have to get out of the game of comparison all
together and as we develop a more fluid sense of
self and maybe we say a not not self that's that's the most true form of
self-esteem as our Insight deepens the less impulse we have to do any comparing
to substantiate ourselves to deprecate
ourselves and then there's a more a more subtle sense of comparison that involves
any measurement the the the budha says like um whatever
one's obsessed with that's what one is measured
by and this is in a sense getting into a kind of Boutique level of
suffering but any measurement any measurement being here but not there
being greater or lesser there being any other side to our love
any other side to our knowing uh um
ascribing any characteristics to me all of that there's suffering it's not
Sublime so in the um godat Su uh this is
not the Buddha but uh monastic said um uh greed is a making
of measurement aversion is a making of measurement
delusion a making of measurement greed is a something
aversion a something delusion a something greed is a making of themes a
version a making of themes delusion a making of [Music]
themes the defilements greed hate and delusion are are all about
measurement about options and optimizing about a sense of
dislocation and lack me
here the object there me here now my happiness somewhere
out there in some future me here and now now and the ideal
version of me just beyond my grasp
me pinned between a messy past and an ominous
future and clinging clinging involves a lot of cognition of measurement of
strategizing and this carries some burden on the heart
we might say defilements greed ha and delusion there a something rather than a
nothing they're a theme rather than themess
Freedom much less of a something
themeless so what what we ask is like the alternative
to to making measurement the alternative to somethingness the alternative to
making themes and of course it's okay to measure sometimes
but if all we ever do is measure something fatigues in the
heart and sometimes the the the Brahma vajar the Divine abodes are described as
the four immeasurables loving kindness and compassion Joy
sympathetic joy and equinity the four immeasurables four immeasurables this is
like alluding this is not a dualistic
love uh meta sahena the the Mind Made
vast made vast with
love and this is a kind of love that um that
can't can't go wrong there's no unfolding that disqualifies this love
there's no other side to it there's nothing excluded from it it's not based on
measurement it's not expressed as a
measure the from again from the suas there's the
case where a monastic keeps pervading the first Direction with an awareness imbued with
Good Will likewise the second likewise the third likewise the fourth thus above
and below and all around everywhere in its entirety they keep pervading the all
encompassing Cosmos with an awareness imbued with
Good Will abundant enlarged immeasurable
without hostility and without ill will this is called the
immeasurable awareness release this is alluding to
um alluding to uh kind
of flavors of somati flavors of uh kind of
formless s body where the the landscape is reduced all measurement Falls
away and the world of experience is reduced to one
thing to space to knowing to
emptiness and the space can be uh pervaded pervaded by by love
and there's um there's no no phenomena are being modeled by our
brain except that space flavored with love not even our
body and we just keep
dropping distinctions we keep not caring
weirdly to develop this love we keep not
caring we trust that um all the alarm Bells all
the alarm bells that go off in samsara that go off in the circuits of our body
are false alarms that no phenomena will hurt
me and so I don't need to tend to it there's a kind of relinquishment The
Silence of Letting Go letting phenomena fade thin
out and there's so much you know there's so much relief in
not measuring you know I I have a measuring mind there's so much relief in not
measuring not being measured by the world you
know and then distinctions are reborn here
and there body and mind you and me liking and
disliking but it's hard to forget just how simple the mind can be and how free
how free one might be when measurement goes
silent this sounds maybe like oh this rarified States or something to Crave
to but um we don't
uh we don't crave our way to non-measurement right this is more
measurement and we don't crave rarified States for
themselves or to solve their our problems you
know we really honor um the
immeasurable mind you know we honor rarified
States for the kind of for the gentle tender
shadow that they cast Over the rest of our lives
the way is we our measurement is haunted by the
immeasurables soer this for your consideration uh sweet to uh to think of
you wherever you are and um even though we're on like an
8C time delay uh feels very intimate right
now okay see you uh see you next uh next week