everyone and
welcome
and it's probably fair to say or
certainly supports deeper exploration of ourselves and
meditation is the idea
from zen master dogen founder of whole Zen School of
Zen where he said that mindfulness of the body is the body's
mindfulness and what that does is it kind of switches around our idea of
mindfulness where there's a very strong emphasis on subject and object
that there's somehow you maybe in the head for some of you who is doing the
mindfulness and that you're in charge of the mindfulness and uh and there's the body
down there below the body is an object of attention and there's nothing inherently
wrong with that separation that distinction but it
can lend itself to a lot of challenges and we build on that to it leads to a
lot of suffering but to say it's the body's
mindfulness is to put mindfulness in the body as intimately
part of the body and maybe if we instead of translate Sati as mindfulness we
translate it as awareness that mindfulness is the body's
awareness and uh we're not aware of the
body but the body is aware of itself both can happen so I don't want
to rule out or all the rich wonderful ways in which
we can be which awareness operates for us but to appreciate and some deep way
in which awareness is the body arises from the
body so one way to understand this is
that sensing and Sensations are inseparable some people
might say that sensing and Sensations are ndu there's no subject object
distinction between the two they arise together when there's a
sensation there's the sensing when there's a sensing the senses are
stimulated there are Sensations without a s without a
stimulus it's almost as if the sensing doesn't exist but as soon as it stimulus
the sensing comes alive and now is activated and so right
there there's this intimacy and so our body is filled with
organs of sensing organs that can experience
Sensations and right there in the location uh of where the sensing
occurs there's the opportunity of
relaxing the being the doer being the one who's straining or trying a lot in
meditation relaxing this separation of the doer being the the sub the
subject being the doer the one who has to perform has to succeed the one who's
not succeeding the one who's the victim of how difficult things are the one who
is s succeeding and look how great I am there's a kind of ability to relax
deeply and when relaxation is it isn't like progress to Deep deeper and deeper
relaxation but relaxation to the point where the alertness can feel that
inseparability of awareness in the body it isn't that we are the
body it isn't that the body is us we're not in the body the body is not
in US these things the sensations The Experience just
is and we re and there's a relaxation to it and our job is to open to allow to
rest in the body to feel this and one of the ways the Buddha
emphasized that supports this is to relax the
body so we'll begin with
relaxing and I'll do a kind of guided scan of the body scan of for relaxation
and U and uh one of the things
to attend to as you relax is how
relaxing the body either relaxes the
mind or brightens the mind it brings a kind of a gentle soft kind of alertness
to the mind and then we can relax some more and
feel the impact that has on the mind or allow the impact on the mind to relax
more so assuming a meditation
posture and
gently lower your gaze
close your
eyes and begin with some deeper breaths maybe 3/4
full and the intentionality of breathing in more deeply supports an intentionality to be
here and now connected to your
body breathing in fully and relaxing as the body as you
exhale breathing in stretching the Torso the shoulders the back rib
cage and some of the relaxing just comes from feeling as you
exhale almost like the desire of the body to soften to
release breathing in breathing out
relaxing and then letting your breathing return to
normal and as you
inhale feel your forehead and
eyes feel whatever tension or holding or buzzing or whatever is
there and as you exhale for the next few
breaths relax around the eyes the forehead the
temple as you breathe in feel the rest of your
face the Jaws cheeks the
mouth and on the exhale relax
soften as if the muscles can fall away from the bone
let go on the
exhale ever so slightly you might let your teeth fall away from each
other or loosening any tightness around the
lips maybe the lips fall apart ever so
slightly on the inhale feeling your shoulders and the movements of the
shoulders tension of the shoulders
and on the exhale with a great
gentleness let the shoulder soften and
relax whenever you relax and then feel your shoulders afterwards
s have the sensations of the shoulders changed at
all continue with your shoulders but take a moment
to adjust your hands and arms so they are
relaxed and are position to support the shoulders
relaxing and then on the inhale halale feeling your heart
center your
chest on the exhale let there be a softening in the chest
releasing releasing this is settling or something in your chest
settles backwards like settling into a
chair
on the exhale feeling the
belly maybe as you exhale to already
relax so as you inhale the belly expands
freely and relaxing on the exhale
too so there's something in the belly that
settles
on the inhale feeling the legs the
thighs and letting there be a way of softening through the
legs
and then as you inhale feeling any tightness or pressure in the
thinking mind any physical sensations of being energized or or agitated
or any of the sensations connected to
thinking and if you feel any physical Sensations in the often in the forehead
behind the forehead it could be in the neck and the
shoulders could be in the back of the skull
as you exhale
soften that tension or tightness
energy and if it doesn't soften directly soften around
it
relaxing the thinking mind calming the thinking
mind and see if you do so if there's a brightening of
awareness not the awareness that you do but the awareness that
is maybe Imagining the mind to be like a large
Ocean and the softening relaxing is a calming of the
Waves so the surface of the Mind spreads wide and
far horizontally in all directions becoming Stiller and
quieter
for
and then becoming aware of how your body feels
now sensing the sensations of the
body in a relaxed open way in whatever way they
appear feeling the intimacy of sensing and
Sensations
the sensations that appear maybe can they're not W or
constructed or made to
happen they occur whatever causes and
conditions of what it's like to be alive right right
now Sensations are a proof of being
alive let awareness
rest in the locations where Sensations occur
so the body feels
itself so that mindfulness is the body's awareness of
itself
for
e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting take a three breath Journey with relaxing more deeply
letting go with each
exhale and now another three breath
Journey this time emphasizing the
inhale as if the inhale welcomes opens
you to The Wider world all around
you
and considering if there's any way known or or
unknown that this meditation session has benefited
you are there ways that you can turn that benefit
around so that it also benefits others
if you're calmer now maybe your
calmness can be calming for someone in distress that you meet
today if you're more patient maybe you can be more patient
with someone who's challenged today
if you feel more tender
friendly maybe when people you meet who are challenged today you
can hold them more kindly with Good
Will May It Be
that the practice of meditation that we do serves for the welfare and happiness
of all beings yourself
included may we live for the welfare of everyone may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and may
we in whatever way that's possible and easy for us natural for
us may we contribute to
that
thank
you
so hello and welcome to this third talk on mindfulness of the
body and one of the important areas of mindfulness
practice is relaxation or calming the language of the Buddha maybe
the word he uses closer to our English word calming if we think of it as a
physical calming and as and many people
associate uh meditation with relaxation with calming a softening a gentling of our
body and mind and heart a significant thing begins
happening if have any degree of relaxation or calmness that's more than
how we live our life normally and that is that we the the
relaxation of the body becomes a reference point to understand ourselves
better and and what I mean by this is that if we're more relaxed than we usually
are then uh we have a chance to notice when we return to how we usually are
because we're tensing up because we're becoming a little bit more
agitated and to be able to have a physical reference point for this is
then we can see more closely can see we're more able to notice when we're
engaged in some activity some way of being which is tensing we can take a see
what's going on better for one thing we just simply see we're becoming more tense and then we can ask the question
do we want to go along with that or do we want to come back to the place we just
were and um and uh and then one
definition of meditation that I've heard is set yourself at
ease and notice what takes away that ease so let yourself be calm and notice
what takes away that calm let your body be somewhat relaxed doesn't have to be dramatic just a little bit more than you
usually are and then notice what takes you away from that and if you do that then you can ask the question um should
I continue doing this is this necessary is there an
alternative what needs to be done be taken care of can I do it without being
so tense what would that look like and as we so this relaxing of the
body becomes a reference point and that reference point is particularly useful
in meditation because in meditation um there's nothing you know we have to do
in the world so this idea of do I need to get tense right now I think it's
easier in meditation to come to the conclusion no I don't need to right now
maybe when the meditation is over I need to but now I don't and so there's a
questioning and a and a doubting the value of of the the the
ways that we get tense up which is also equivalent to the ways in which we get
preoccupied or caught in our thoughts or our feelings and um and then we can see more
clearly what's going on and if we decide there's no need we don't have to and we
recognize that it's physical tension we have then we might be able to soften
that relax it and one of the great ways of relaxing that I found for myself is
sometimes it can be done directly but sometimes it's just to feel the places of tension in my body and then breathe
with it kind of like uh breathing through it uh accompanying the
experience with the Rhythm physical rhythms of the body breathing it's almost like an act of imagination like
I'm breathing in through that tension rather than through my nostrils and breathing out through it it's is using
your imagination a little bit but somehow the pairing up the places of
tension with the breathing the breathing itself the rhythm of breathing can be relaxing the being with the breath that
way is a way of uh feeling and being with something like a massage without
being caught in the reactivities of the Mind around being tense or or with it
the reactivity it's causing the tension so it's shifting our local
of uh of uh attention that way and um and the more we can then can see in our
tension rather than feeling that tension is an unfortunate thing uh it's actually
a door to deeper understanding of what's happening with us so tension is not
necessarily we don't necessarily want to be in a hurry to relax and that's one
way to tense up even even more is to feel like oh this is wrong I need to be relaxed but to be very easy with it and
and uh certainly it's good to relax if it's easy easy to do it but it's also
the being present for physical tension begins and learning how to be
comfortable with discomfort learn just to be equanimous calm about being tense so
about being agitated um is a powerful tool powerful
Foundation for deepening this practice so just like in the very beginning of
this intro to meditation course I talked about how distractions don't need to be treated as the enemy or problem for
meditation seeing we're distracted and being mindful of it that's mindfulness then mindfulness succeeded so the same
thing is true of the tensions and the agitations that are in our system in our
body um uh those that too we open to in mindfulness without the idea that it
needs to be different or should be different and if we have that need or
have that Shing going on that's one of the things that gets highlighted through
this reference point of focusing on on tension and relaxation and if you're very sensitive
you feel you can see how the Shing the needing the wanting is itself a form of
tension Maybe more a tension of the thinking mind perhaps or
something and so this fascinating reference point so much gets revealed so
so much many of the ways in which we the mind is operating in ways that are um um
not supportive of us not wholesome for us uh many of the ways in which we take
the wrong turn in the way we live our life gets manifested intention in the
body and so this ability to relax the body and then feel that as a reference
point to understand ourselves better um and if if you have a lot of kind of deep
experience of relaxation sometimes and there's it registered as a memory that can really that can also
support you sometime when you find yourself really tense and say wow that's really different than how this reference
points I have what's possible and should I just continue doing what I doing now or should I excuse myself from the
situation maybe ask if I can go to the bathroom and uh most people won't
question why you're going to the bathroom and um and but what you're doing is uh going there to breathe and
relax and there is this wonderful uh meditation
Throne that uh you can sit on for a while maybe with a lid down just sit on
it and meditate then close your mind maybe do three three breath Journeys doesn't
have to be long but uh uh to realize how tense we are realize how caught up we are and
question whether we need to continue that and then find simple ways okay let's do a three breath Journey let's
relax um uh this frees
up attention this frees up up mindfulness this frees up the the
mindfulness the sensing of the body a relaxed body is a field of sens sensing
Sensations maybe not distinct always maybe sense of of vibration or warmth or
tingling a um the more tense the body is we might
have some acute Sensations around the tension but when there's a lot of uh tightness tense muscle muscles there's
often a tendency for those muscles to go numb and too much tension and we lose a
connection to ourselves and um and uh and uh and the
relaxation is a re rediscovering that connection opening up to it
again so the theme of today is this mindfulness of the body is the value of
relaxation relaxation can be overdone it's shouldn't be a forever project that
just relax relax relax relax it becomes a kind of a but um but it is a very
important part of this terrain of mindfulness and um and it it's a
self-correcting one because if you pay attention to even the subtlest tensions
then you'll feel that you'll discover when relaxing is no longer needed or no
longer useful or that the focus and the way we're we're trying to relax has t
ention embedded in it and the self-correcting way in which mindfulness
and tension helps us for the mindfulness to be easeful at ease so that's so I
love this instructions that I said set yourself at ease and notice what takes you away from
it so I would uh encourage you today to
continue with mindfulness of the body being a theme and um and uh make uh T
tension holding contraction and relaxation use a physical sense of
unease and a sense of ease to guide you and to inform you and to help you feel a
deeper connection to what's going on and um don't be in a hurry to relax
uh sometimes what's really good even in meditation and elsewhere is don't relax at the first opportunity
you have but if you if there's some tension that could relax take a few
breaths to feel it better there's something about feeling tension more fully that can allow the relaxation to
be deeper feeling something more fully and then Letting Go can let the then the
Letting Go could be Fuller as well so take time during the day and for
those of you who have enjoyed the instruction to the the practice of setting a timer you might set a timer so
that uh periodically and regularly without forgetting about it um you get a
little reminder to check in about what's the tension what's the
relaxation what do you learn what's available with tension
relaxation as being a reference point for your life so thank
you very much and look forward to
tomorrow