so lovely lovely good to see you
all for those of you who don't know me my name is Don Neil and I'm here picking
up a little bit on the themes that Gil spoke about in the last
number of weeks mind his introduction to mindfulness theories breath body emotions and
thoughts and this week I'll be offering a series on the course elements of
mindfulness which are feeling tones and ways of working with awareness ways of
working with attention so that's a very brief overview of the
week and today the first of these elements of
mindfulness I'll be covering is V Pleasant unpleasant and neutral
feeling tone that is a very very simple kind of overlay or
um assessment our systems make about the raw sensory data of
life so that's the basic overview and
I'll ask you to start to settle into meditation I'm loving seeing the
greetings from people in Santa Cruz especially um but maybe weave back and forth a
little bit get yourself in Balance over your hips or in Balance alignment if
you're lying down have your spine and your um head
aligned and just to by way of introducing the meditation and talk about how feeling
tone is a really simple way sometimes powerful way we can relate to experience
so you may want to just notice throughout the meditation if you're leaning in or leaning away from anything
in your experience because it feels good or because it doesn't feel good and this
can be physical mental emotional and remember for the purpose
of mindfulness any object is as good as any
other object of attention unpleasant
experience isn't wrong or bad it just is pleasant experience is
lovely it's not inherently a better thing to pay attention to for the
purpose of mindfulness so settling in to
meditation perhaps starting with two or three deeper slower
breaths and in these deeper slower breaths allowing the exhale to be longer
than the
inhale
and noticing as you settle
in how the breath is today is it
Pleasant maybe tune into the pleasant if it's
unpleasant I call that cardboard breath just notice noticing
that perhaps it's neither it's neutral or some undefined feeling in
between allowing the breathing to be natural maybe doing a quick SK in
through your
body and just noticing throughout your body throughout your sensory experience
of your body areas that are
Pleasant
unpleasant or in that fast territory in between just
experience no need to hang out
there just
allowing and then tuning [Music] in to whatever anchor of attention makes
the most sense for you
the breath coming and going like
waves The
Body Sensations coming and
going scintillating like water
or perhaps it's Ambient sound tuning
in and resting for a while in the lived
sensations of
breath of being
alive
allowing yourself to abide in this
moment just as it is
tuning in again to whatever sensation or
experience is predominant and simply notice its tone
tone it's feeling
tone it's that pleasurable an enjoying
savoring not pleasant
allowing is it neither simply being
with noticing any little motions towards or
away in your
being any resistance any
wanting and also noticing the Simplicity of a allowing just
being
allowing the mind the heart to rest in
experience and noticing any movement towards or
away perhaps gently mentally noting Pleasant
unpleasant and
allowing
noticing if your attention is
pulled by a new sensation or [Music]
sound notice ing the quality of
that is it Pleasant not so
pleasant or just
is
and in the last remaining moment of this
meditation the invitation is to notice that there's a part of the Mind the
heart unmoved unaffected by whether what is flowing
through is pleasurable or
not perhaps noticing the quality of mindful awareness just simple
attention on whatever is unfolding In This
Moment
and as we bring this meditation to a close
casting your inner Gaze on any moments of clarity or
mindfulness ease and appreciating
them and casting your inner gaze outwards to the others in your life
those close or on the margins of your life those near those far
away known and unknown and wishing them
well making the
determination that this practice be of benefit to the others in your life as well as
yourself May the benefits of our practice here together Ripple
outwards
thank you for your practice
this
so good morning again sa special good morning to those of you who may have tiptoed in late into the YouTube chat
into the international meditation s we have here
together it's a delight to be with you
and I'm just going to jump in now with our theme for the day for the
week so the theme this week is mindfulness of the different ways our
systems can know experience elements of mindfulness that
will complement the introduction series Gill has been doing for the last number of weeks
now and the first of these elements today's topic is very simple it's Vena
feeling tone the tonality or the quality of
direct experience in Buddhist teachings all
experience is categorized at its most basic level in one of three broad
categories Pleasant unpleasant or neither Pleasant
nor unpleasant which is huge territory that we often ignore because it's not interesting enough it gets really
interesting if you really be with it V itself is the poly word for this
feeling tone and it's related to the word Veda or V to know to
experience this simple direct way of knowing person
experience okay so it's simple why does it matter well noticing feeling tone in
practice is a key place that prevents getting lost in wanting or not wanting
desire or aversion ending up on those party boats or War boats that Gil often
talks about with thinking where an entire flow of thought
will just take us away from our place place at the riverbank that solid place
of mindfulness and get lost it can also noticing feeling tone
can also clarify how thoughts are thoughts and
emotions or emotions and the impact that a thought
or emotion has on us in a really simple way so here's an example of how Vena can
shift based on context what's
happening imagine yourself on a beautiful day taking a hike or a walk in
the woods Sun dappling through the shade of the trees and the birds are singing
and it's an idilic temperature and it's just
gorgeous luxurious green Fage little waterfalls this can be highly Pleasant
right and and it can be really unpleasant if
you're completely lost I don't know where I'm going all of the sudden my mental feeling tone takes
over and the birds are still there and the dappled light is still there but
there's anxiety there maybe and there's a generally unpleasant sense so that's the power of feeling
tone the context our attitude our emotions
can shift feeling tone in many many kinds of experiences and I'll talk more about that later this week but meanwhile
it's just humbling to see for me how often my experience and actions and
other people's actions are shaped by Pleasant or unpleasant in a
moment in a sit like we just had in a
situation how often do we go through gations move around change things just
to avoid an unpleasant interaction person
conflict and what lengths do we go to to
get or keep just a little bit more pleasantness it's kind of
amazing so there's the how we practiced together with feeling
tone today and just to recap that a little bit it's something to Simply
notice it's something to Simply notice and it's kind of it's baked into our
systems it turns out that this movement towards the pleasant and away from the
unpleasant is kind of reflexive it's automatic for most sent life single
celled organisms move towards sugar and away from a
prod well guess what you and I can be very similar to an amoeba in this way we
move towards the pleasant and away from the unpleasant this simple basic movement
towards and Away happens at the level of physical movement like from a hot stove
and it also happens at a very subtle level of movement in our
minds our attention I might suddenly be touched by
a really unpleasant memory or thought and away from it or conversely
completely hooked by it and building a whole stack of cards a whole huge story
about it maybe casting blame outwards or self-recrimination
inwards and it's possible instead to just tune into that feeling bring a
sense of inquiry a nonverbal question mark oh
unpleasant the whole system relaxes so this is sort of explaining
another reason Vena can be important not only can it prevent getting lost in
thought or help us notice the impact of thought and emotion it can
also cut through whatever is extra even fully lost in fantasy or vengeful
thinking or poor me the Simplicity of recognizing Pleasant unpleasant or neither can cut
through the thicket of confusing thoughts and clear the air oh it's that simple this is
Pleasant I don't have to think about it 50 times during my meditation I can just notice it's
Pleasant simply being with being with feeling tone gives us
Alternatives choice space how to respond wisely rather than
reflexively it can take us back to that powerful place of being able to
observe the river of experience flowing by versus being caught up in
it it can take us back to simple mindfulness
awareness and while mindful awareness may seem neutral over time it can become
a very pleasant abiding especially especially when we consider the
Alternatives so to summarize V feeling tone is a simple way
of parsing experience as pleasant unpleasant or neither Pleasant nor
unpleasant it can prevent all kinds of unhelpful stories projections of blame
distortions poor me to simply walk it down to that
level yes the space between stimulus and
response it can prevent all kinds of unhelpful stories it can cut through the
confusion of mental activity fantasy fear-based projection whatever collapses the whole
house of cards and noticing VD can clarify how
thought thoughts or emotions move through us as processes and that in itself is a form
of Freedom it can begin to help recognize
that oh you know thinking about that ice cream 10 15 times in this meditation
seemed pleasant but it's actually kind of causing tension in my body that's
unpleasant it can clarify our relationship to our attitude toward what's
happening and that really helps to understand the cause and effect the
impact thoughts and emotions have on our system which in itself is a source of
wisdom so that's my little wrap about Vena and we have just a few minutes left
so I thought rather than talking more um I won't be able to catch them all but if there are a couple of questions people
want to put into the chat I might be able to answer one or two so I'll give
it a minute because there's a lag time on my end questions or um comments are
welcome in our remaining three minutes
together
you're noticing In This Moment what's Pleasant unpleasant or
neither oh these are great questions oh so from lraa I hope I'm pronouncing your
name right um more about the relationship with the body and the thought process so
basically feeling tone applies to any physical sensation it also applies to
any thought any emotion so I might feel desire as very
pleasant in a moment and then notice that it's causing tension or contraction
in my attention I'm might notice more about um how that desire causes tension in my
shoulders for example so that's a short answer I'm going to be going into this more and
building on it actually in the next days is Pleasant versus unpleasant a
judgment will sometimes it is so this is a more subtle level it can be an overlay
or a judgment on experience for example if someone touches your shoulder
you don't know who you might find it very pleasant if it's an old friend or a lover or very
unpleasant if it's a total stranger being presumptuous so it can be contextually oriented the pleasant or
the unpleasant and then there are things that pretty much all of us are going to find unpleasant that hot stove for
example so it's sometimes more basic and sometimes it's
highly subjective let's
see if we're wired to run away from negative stimuli sometime why do we
sometimes dwell on them that is one of the great mysteries of human life
um sometimes our minds have the idea that to keep us safe from the negative
stimuli we need to figure it out we need to parse it out
so it can be helpful it can be helpful to again notice the unpleasantness of
the dwelling and that can help cut through the perseveration or the looping
or whatever it is Phil asks what's the difference
between vona and preference
so there are layers there and it's a this is a profound question um
V is simply the acknowledgement the knowledge that something is Pleasant or
unpleasant and a microsc waiter a millisecond waiter most of us have a
judgment preferring the pleasant oh pulling away from the unpleasant so wanting and not wanting in the Abid Abid
in the Buddhist psychology is a separate layer but it is so close and it's worth
noticing for yourself when Pleasant and unpleasant can
happen and not have a reaction there are states of meditation
there are states of mind that allow equinity to be there where Pleasant and unpleasant can just flow
through or when it can um have that little s
overlay of wanting and not wanting
so I hope that that was helpful for all of you I really
appreciate the questions and this is a profound topic actually those of you who are getting into sort of the amibo level
and the reflex level there are ways of relating to this Pleasant unpleasant and
neither that can can give us much more space and a kind of a profound level of
equinity if we're willing to be there with it simply and that's building a
muscle so that's all we have time for today I will wrap some of these other
questions into the rest of the Dharma talks because they're kind of a little bit
cumulative and just to briefly say that noticing Veta helps cut through
delusion so maybe if you'd like play with this over the next day and tomorrow
we will pick up on the next layer attitudes of mind and
heart so thank you all for your practice and may our practice here together
benefit ourselves and everyone around
us joy to be with you SA