good evening welcome welcome everybody nice to see you all practice
together it's a beautiful thing and happy Earth Day today's Earth
Day and it's like so beautiful outside have you guys noticed like I noticed
like oh there's flowers growing and and uh Le last week I went to
Arizona and to teach a retreat and then afterwards I went to some national parks like of course I did while I was in the
neighborhood and it was just so great you know just to see these national parks so I'm kind of filled up with the
beauty of Nature and these things so kind of on that theme I wanted
to talk about uh maybe nature a little bit but I'll start with this
poem and this poem was by gway kennel who is an American poet he was the Noel
laurate of literature in 1983 and this is just a a short poem
that it's pointing to some of the same things I'd like to point to in this
talk the poem is called Daybreak and it's by gway
kennel maybe I should say that um I listen listened to a recording of gway
kennel um speaking this poem was really great he did a great job i' love really
loved how he read it but he mentioned that um he wrote this poem after spending some time on the Barrier Reef
the great bar Reef you know outside of Australia and then um I guess he would go for walks on the
shore so just to give a little bit of context so Daybreak by gallway kennel
on the tidal mud Just Before Sunset dozens of starfishes were
creeping it was it was as though the mud were a sky and enormous imperfect Stars
moved across it slowly as the actual Stars cross
Heaven all at once they stopped and as if they had simply increased their
receptivity to GR gravity they sank down into the
mud they faded down into it and lay still and by the time pink of sunset
broke across them they were as invisible as the true stars at
Daybreak so he's just very simply describing he saw a bunch of starfish
that were moving across the mud and he's a poet so he kind like starfish stars in
the sky but there's a few things that he's pointing to in this poem and one is a
real change in perspective usually when we think of stars we think of stars up in the sky but he's talking about how
like they're crawling up on the mud and like the sky so there's this value in seeing things from a different
perspective and there can be great value right we see things differently when we look at them from a different
perspective and he's also kind like linking these starfish with stars in the
sky not only do they have the same name but you know they're doing some of the same thing there's this movement across
the heaven or this movement across the mud and maybe in the same way as the
starfish are sinking into the mud maybe there's a way that the Stars kind of like sink into the sky as Daybreak
around es so some of this commonality of these like really disperate things usually we
don't link aquatic creatures with the what's in the
heavens but here he does he makes this connection and in the Buddhist teachings
there's also these types of connections what first this value and really looking at things from a different
perspective and not only that to see some of the commonality some of the
things that are shared with just about everything and this can be a certain
particular practice and this shift of perspective and seeing things uh in a similar way
seeing what's common about them what's similar about them turns out can be really powerful can be really
powerful and so part of the way that we can see this is in the
Buddha's teachings on the four elements so there's can be different
ways in which we can describe the Human Experience there's so many different ways so many different perspectives so
many different lenses we might use in the same way that we could describe the
weather today outside in Redwood City we could say it was pleasant that's one way
we could say we could say it's was 73° Fahrenheit or 23° C or you know these
are all different ways to express or maybe to look at things but it's all
pointing to the same thing like how the temperature was the feeling the
experience of the temperature today and we can use different ways to talk about
it and different people and different parts of the world use Fahrenheit or use Celsius or use different language
it's all okay right it's all describing the same thing it's not like one is the truth and the other aren't the truth
they're all the truth they're just different ways and in the same way with our minds
with our uh psychology with our inner lives what is happening there's these
different perspectives of modern psychology we can think about the Mind
differently there's this psychodynamic perspective that Freud brought you know the ID and the ego and the super ego or
there's this like behavioral perspective that I think it's BF Skinner maybe like this idea of the dogs uh pav love I
guess is though the dogs salivate when they hear the Bell just this idea of you
know these patterns these habits that we get into or maybe there's a way we could look at inner life with cognitive
processing this uh like the how we think about things and let we could train
ourselves to think about them differently to have different thoughts or may there's also like a biological
perspective what are the neurotransmitters and what is the whole nervous system doing so those are all
like different lenses of looking at the inner life and in the same way we different
lenses that we can look at this bodily experience what it's like to be a human
in a body what it's like to
be to have a body and so this in the Buddhist
tradition there's these four elements earth water air and fire earth water air
and fire and in modern times we might kind of like scoff at like oh isn't that
cute how that BR is thousands of years ago they thought about these four
elements whereas you know in modern day right we often we think about elements
or those of us who are trained as chemists we think often like you know
well there's the periodic table there's the number of protons in the Adam right those types of things
right but the Buddhists they were the Buddha I should say they were
um thinking more about like the Buddhist philosophy Maybe would say is how could
they use this idea of elements as a support for greater Freedom greater ease
greater peace Awakening Liberation how can they use this idea of
elements which they had at that time as a support for
practice and so one way that they did this is to of course they recognize
uh earth water fire and air but more specifically they kind of like expanded
the definition of these elements to talk about particular principles or
qualities that is in everything all things and that can be expressed by the
Earth element water air and Fire and Air
for example the stiffness the solidity the
softness or hardness of something can be expressed by the Earth
element you know like how solid something
feels and then there's this sense of fluidity or cohesion both of those with
the water element fluidity I think we accustomed to that with that mean know
water and fluidity makes sense but cohesion if we think about for example
um flour you just put some flour in a bowl you have flour in a bowl but you
add water and then all of a sudden it sticks together and you can get a dough
ball and you know you can make dough and make bread from it or in the same way I have this little
suction cup thing on my kitchen sink and uh it doesn't stick unless I put water water between that and the side of the
sink right suction cups they kind of like need water to help with this cohesion or there's a way that water
when it's not wet just these sheets of paper can slide against one another but
when there's water there they glump together so water is a part of this
sense of cohesion this the things holding
together and then fire element is this idea of temperature like the degree of
heat whether it's hot or cold is can be described by the fire
element and then this idea of motion or movement or vibration or oscillation or
something like that can be described by the air
element and so of course if we think about this that's not it's not possible
for these qualities to exist in an
object singularly like all all objects all
things have a little bit of all four of these but one of them may be predominant
for example if we think of a tree I think well that's pretty
solid but of course there's also sap and the tree some cohesion or some liquidity and
the cohesion as you know zo xylm and FL those people know about uh botney right
that the water has to move up from the roots right up to these really really tall trees some of them so of course
there's this movement and there's a degree of warmth or coolness in the
tree probably it's not too different than what the external temperature is but so all things have all of these
elements to them it's just a different way of looking at them or considering
them what is the degree of movement in something like this or what is the
degree of a temperature is it warm or cool or is it in
between so this the early Buddhist analysis of this matter into elements
was more concerned about uh qualities than actual like this is the
truth of the universe or you know this is early physics it's not what's being pointed to
here instead is this recognition that oh if we think about for example Earth
element we can think about well almost all things have a sense of
like resistance or sense of solidness or something that can be pushed
against and there's a way in which this kind of like unites things oh this is something that things exist I mean that
they share in modern times you would say yeah they probably you know have some
carbon and hydrogen and some oxygens or something like this but instead this is pointing to the
qualities and there's something that happens when
the mind starts to pay attention to qualities of things rather than just the
label for things rather than just you like
chair of course a chair has a lot of solidness to it and maybe the movement
isn't obvious you know at this level but if we were to zoom way in
I'm reaching here a little bit but right we do know that uh there's a lot of space and there's movement right when we
get down to the atoms and it has a certain amount of
temperature and it has a cohesion right it's not flying apart into different
pieces maybe that's a silly example but there's a way in which we can do this with
everything and then when we start to consider things by the qualities that
they have then our relationship to them
shifts instead of seeing the chair as something that I sit
in something that Jim very nicely moves around on the Monday
evenings and these particular chairs the seat's a little bit tall for me so I have to put a you know something so like
I have a story with these chairs so all of a sudden I have a relationship that has to do with me and what it's like to
sit in them and I'm not the person that put them there somebody else put them there it's like so all these stories
kind of get tied up with it but it's different if I'm thinking about the qualities oh the hardness of
the rims versus the softness of the cushion there's a difference different
Earth
element so elements these elements or elements or elements right it doesn't
matter whether it's in a chair it's in this spell it's in me it's in you and
the wall behind me and this uh microphone that I'm speaking
into elements or elements or elements qualities or qualities or qualities and so there's something that
happens when we start to consider like the body our own body
because there's this difference there's
this there's these advantages of when we consider our own bodies in term of the
elements and there's practice discussions directing this some of you may know this in the Sati patana suta
like one of the primary discourses of the Buddha that um mindfulness instructions come
from and the instructions [Music] a person reviews their
body however it is placed however disposed by way of the elements
thus in this body there is the Earth element in this body there is the water
element in this body there is the fire element and in this body is the air
element and then a little bit later it says in this way they abide contemplating the body body
internally externally and both internally and
externally so not only considering how this body has these properties of
solidity cohesion temperature and movement but how things out there also
have
solidity fluidity or coh eion and
movement and temperature so then we can ask ourselves this division we tend to create between
the these elements in this body is something that I
am and manifestations things that are out there are something different than I am of course they are on some
level but also of course there's some way in which well we
share these qualities just like the starfish on the beach kind of like the stars in the
sky they shared movement I don't know if the stars move maybe it was more the Earth moves but
you know poetic license here and sinking into the mud or disappearing into the
sky so we might ask ourselves like literally at what point does the food we
eat which of course is coming from you know literally the Earth and literally
water and literally air and literally it has to be the right temperature but we can also think of it
just as you know these qualities of solidity and cohesion and temperature and
movement at what point do we consider that the vegetables at one point there
are carrots there in the ground we eat the
carrot and then it becomes a part of this body that's why we
eat so where is the distinction precisely between what's external what's
internal between what's not me and what is
me the carrot we often think is like it's not me but is it when we start to
chew it and swallow it does it just all of a sudden get transformed as me something that's part of
me and if we really start to think about this that we discover that we can't really find a clear distinction that
everybody can agree on like oh okay it's it's something else and then precisely
at this moment it transforms into this
body and you know the same could be said with the opposite process when is it no longer the body is
like when it's uh has gone into the intestines or when it's gone into the toilet or you like this process of
elimination when is it no longer the body it was part of the body before and now it no longer
is so there's this way in which this division that we tend to create between
what's external and what's internal maybe it kind of puts into question and
isn't so clear or isn't so
obvious because the elements are the elements are the elements and then you might ask well why does this matter
Diana well one way this helps us to feel connected with nature helps us to see
how of course we're part of nature we are nature we are not different
and there's something about that that kind of helps soften the sense of like me and me being so
important and it's all about me it's kind of like self-centeredness that
humans often have we could start to see oh no I'm just part of nature just like
the carots and the trees and the ocean and everything else that's out there
everything that's been many manufactured by humans as well as everything that's
hasn't been manufactured by humans so it helps us to feel connected
to our environment not so distinct as well as diminishing this
strong sense of I and me and this strong sense of I and me is
the source of a lot of our attachment of our clinging we're trying to promote this sense of eye or defend this sense
of eye make it look good or make sure that people see it the way we want them
to see it so we're having to say things or do things or trying to make sure they don't see the certain aspects of
ourselves all these ways and these these ways we kind of pretzel ourselves into
kind of protecting the sense of ey making sure it looks good and that
it's consistent with the way that we want to see it or feel it
but when we start to say oh no we're just part of nature too then that can
soften and then there's this way in which when we start to consider the qualities of the body
these elements how many times have I said this a solidity fluidity temperature and
movement when we start to consider them in the body when we start to do the practices that the Buddha recommend and
that is to like do a body scan which is considering the Earth
element often that can be like with a clenching one's teeth kind of like this
like that's very strong and then the kind of the liquid we can like the saliva in the mouth the temperature we
can just um consider the temperature of how our hands are when they touch one
another and the air is like the movement we can consider the how the body moves as it
breathes so you can do a body scan just kind of like tuning into these different
elements and as we do that as we start to tune into like the
experiences the movement the temperature the fluidity or
cohesion then that's a shift in perspec perspective about our
bodies and that shift in perspective also tends to like minimize this sense
of thinking that the body is this stable constant separate thing that somehow we
can control or somehow is beautiful or not beautiful as the case may be whatever we might think instead of those
types of ideas which are only
ideas they're only ideas it's all in the
mind actually what the body is right it's this collection of experiences that's all it is the mind is putting
saying oh this is separate from everything else or it's special or it's
a stable and doesn't change or you know something like this but if we move away
away from the ideas the Notions the beliefs the views that we have about our
body and other people's bodies and bodies in general move away from that to
the actual experience the tingling in the hand the
pressure of the cushion or the chair against the body the feeling of the
coolness against the skin
then there's this way of which we can really tune into our experience and we
notice that it's changing of course it is it's always
changing and there's this when this we deeply recognize the changing nature of
the experience all of our experiences and we see this repeatedly
and we experience this repeatedly then there's this way in which the mind mind kind of like does this Letting Go
it no longer wants to hold on to this body because it sees that oh no it's
just a collection of changing experiences this idea of a stable
constant body is just an idea it's a useful idea and we need to use it in our
daily life but it's not the only perspective there's this other perspective that leads to Greater
freedom this other perspective that leads to Greater peace and
well-being because often what happens when we have this concept of the body in particular my
body what happens this goes like almost simultaneously or goes together my body
gets compared to others bodies or maybe it starts the other way seeing others bodies gets compared to my body this is
what humans do they compare and this
comparing is part of this like this deep pattern that humans
have the Buddha had a word for it called mana and it's this way of which there's
this deeply rooted sense of uh I
am or I was or I will be this gets the sense of I gets
solidified when bodies are compared to other
bodies this sense of I am is one of the last defilements to go away before Awakening so it's something that until
you're completely awakened is one that you have but when we are comparing our
bodies notice how often there's these thoughts that arise they can be this Myriad of
thoughts or there can be emotions that uh get triggered when we are comparing
like oh I should go to the gym more oh I should eat less cookies or oh I should
go to the gym less or I should walk more you know whatever it is whatever it is
these ideas that we have about our bodies when they're compared to others but if instead if we just see the
body as this interplay of the elements then this conceit this Mana of
I am gets softened and all these thought patterns and emotions that are related
to comparing ourselves to others can fall away there can be so much less
dooka so much less Dua in our lives so again I'm not saying this is
the only way to consider the body right there are useful times to consider okay this is my body it's distinct and
separate from everything else there I'm talking about a shift in perspective and looking at things
differently this a practice that we do and can be enormously
helpful helpful to let us let go of some of the attachments that we have help us
let go of some of the ideas we have about how we should be or how others
should be or should not be or something like this there's so much DOA so much suffering associated with
this so maybe I'll just say that uh one way that the Buddha talked about
this is um well maybe I'll start with uh one way
that anali have talked about this and some of you may know he's a scholar monk
he's a an amazingly productive uh scholar and
he's like an lot of like you really delving into the poly Canan as well as
the parallels that are preserved in other languages and kind of like teasing apart well what
are the meanings here and I really appreciate the way that um he talks
about practicing just what it's like to practice with the the elements looking
at the elements whether it's a solidity fluidity temperature or
movement he says that it's like receiving a parcel that is meant for
someone else so you get this box you look at it like oh it doesn't have my
name on it so there's no need to open the box and look at it and have
emotional response or thoughts about it and all this kind of stuff instead you just look at the address label realize
oh it's not mine and then return it to the male person so it's kind of like what we can
do kind of like with the experience of the body instead of having say like oh this is mine and I'm going to compare it
to everybody else's like oh no it's not mine give it back I kind of like this idea of this
way of working with the how the elements can help us what we might say like disidentify with the body and again I
don't want to say like there is no such thing as distinct bodies or anything like this I'm talking about a very
helpful perspective to use that can lead to greater and greater
freedom and in the same way the Buddha he used a uh simile
that's sprinkled throughout the poly Canon so maybe pointing to the same idea
but using something different which actually in modern times I kind of find to be a little
gruesome and very un Buddhist we might say and um so the Buddha he gives this
simile of a butcher who Slaughters a cow and uh butchers it and sells it so
this is a little bit offensive but he's was just using the ordinary experience of probably what was there in you know
Society at that time but there'd be vendors that would be doing this but he's pointing to while the cow is still
whole we consider it a cow whether the cow's alive or dead if it's long you know it's a
cow but as soon as the butcher this is gruesome um you know starts to butcher
it into little pieces all of a sudden it's flank steak and T-Bone I don't know what these are
you know these different things that are a right there it's no longer cow so in the same way in which kind of
like using this perspective of looking at the elements is a way to help us kind of loosen our identity with our with our
body which is a way that can help support more and more freedom to soften
this sense of self so that we don't always having to be
protecting it or defending it or hiding behind it or something like this so maybe in the same way as gallway
kennel was talking about these uh starfish that are moving across the
mud like the stars that are moving across the heaven like this really
different perspective and yet they're both kind of like you know stars in some kind of way and they share right they're
both moving they have this a certain amount of solidity Stars much less
solidity than uh starfish some cohesion Stars again right
they're kind of like moving out I guess I'm not an astrophysicist but but you know starfish have cohesion
as well and uh temperature they of course have temperature so they kind of they have these things the same so maybe
in the same way here's a poet and the I think I don't know exactly when he wrote this
poem I think it got published in the 1980s so he wrote it sometime before
then he's pointing to something similar what the Buddha is pointing to and kind
like maybe where we can have this shift in perspective that can help bring some
more freedom and ease to our lives so I'll end there and uh open it
up for some questions or comments thank you
and thanks for the talk uh so when I first um came here today I kind of like
struggled to kind of like you know um sit and like meditate um um and um one
of the talks that we had a few weeks back was like um trying to like turn to mundan and like see um or see it in a
different perspective right and I remember um I heard like uh someone sneeze um and it made me kind of just
like be conscious of the fact that um you know like uh we're all like sharing
the same a um which is kind of funny that like you know like the talk today is about like the four elements cuz like
um that concept of like sharing the air um like coupled with like um shifting
perspectives helped me really kind of like remember that like you know I'm not Al alone and like we're all here um to
practice together and um even if like we're all coming from different like circumstances or contexts and after this
we go our separate ways like as we're all here like at this very hour um it's
kind of cool that like uh you know like be in that sense of like goesan and sharing that same movement of the breath
um um and it helped me like really feel Not Alone um and also like helped me
like settle in my into my practice because like I know everyone else is like you know settling into theirs um so
I just found that to be very um timely so thanks for that nice nice thank you
thank you I actually had in my notes to talk about this how it kind of helps us feel connected to others right because
of course all humans have the same the same elements that we do so thank you thank you for saying that
anybody else have a comment or question or something they'd like to
say maybe I'll just read this poem then as a closing it's kind of nice to hear poems again after
you've heard more about them this is called Daybreak by gway
kennel on the tidal mud Just Before Sunset dozens of starfishes were
creeping it was as though the mud were a sky and enormous imperfect Stars moved
across it slowly as the actual Stars cross Heaven all at once they stopped and as
if they had simply increased their receptivity to gravity they sank down
into the mud they faded down into it and lay
still and by the time pink of sunset broke across them they were as invisible
as the true stars at Daybreak I I just I love this poem kind
of it's just a there's some tenderness or sweetness about it I kind of like
so I'll end with that thank you and wishing you all a wonderful rest
of your evening thank you