good morning um is it sound good is everyone can hear great thank
you so um I'm going to uh begin with um
a little story about a a one of the monks at asham brahs Monastery and um Asam Rah is um the
Abbot of uh a monastery in Western Australia that's kind of remote and um
so it's not very easy to get you know back and forth to town and and when people need to see the doctor it's like
quite a quite a track and you know monks don't drive so it's always not so
convenient and um one of the monks was having um a lot of dental problems and
um you know he'd gone back there ones to the dentist and you know and again the problem a different problem started and
um you know so you know a Bram was walking around and at the monastery and
he sees that that monk uh standing by the Woodshed with um uh pliers and
bloody tooth and you know and he realizes uh how that he dealt with this problem and
uh he asked him you how how did you do that you know what you know how were you able to do
that and the monk said well you know when he had the idea he you know he was resting in his coutti and uh he decided
to do this he asked himself you know uh you know he had a dull right at that
point the pain was dull he says well you know does it hurt I'm you know pulling the tooth right this moment he said no
doesn't doesn't hurt now he start walking to the shed and he asked himself well does it hurt now nope and he kept
walking to the shed holds the door open no doesn't hurt and then he put the
pliers to his tooth and he asked himself does it hurt no he yanked you know and
uh was why that hurt you know and um you know and then it was over you know and
um and you know the moral of course is the fact that he didn't spend all that
time caught in dread and anticipation how much more suffering do
we cause ourselves to avoid that one moment of pain or that very short period
of pain you know we can spend weeks in that state some of us uh just avoiding
that and um I told the story to uh one of my students you know and he came back
to me like a a couple months later and said you know I just used that when I went to get my blood drawn you know he
said he used to dread getting his blood drawn for days before and he said I just kept asking myself is
it hurting now no and um but um you know this this
brings me to the topic of the of this talk which is investigation and um that was what uh he
was actually doing investigating what's happening right now you know it's not the imagination of of you know what's
you know the dread the fear what's happening right now there's no pain and right now uh if we just keep coming back
to that you know what's happening here what's happening now um and that's the
wisdom that can come from investigation
um the Buddha taught that everything we need to learn on the path to
Freedom um can be discovered through our own powers of Investigation everything um you know and
he basically what he taught us is to train that ability um you know to to
develop that power investigation that really sees clearly what's happening at
any given moment um you know a lot of us um you
know who grew up with TV shows and things like that you know and uh there a
lot of crime shows you know there's always like the investigation right and the investigation always in my mind was
like you know this um you know they're trying to solve a crime and but you know
what what it has in common with investigation that we use in practice is that in in the crime scene they're
looking at the details of the crime scene what are all the details there and they're looking for what's out of place
what's something unusual you know so they're just noticing everything that there is and in a very similar way we do
that with when we investigate our own minds we know look at the details of our
experience what's really happening here not what we want to be happening here but what's
really happening here and we notice instead of what's out of place or
doesn't belong we notice what causes us stress what causes us contraction what
we're pushing away what we're pulling towards us so we notice those things and
when we notice those things it gives us a choice you know we can either continue
you know pushing something away or we can just look again oh what's happening here oh look this is how pushing
something away feels like and so and this is like the power that we develop the ability to keep uh
seeing what's here and when stress rises in any form uh to make the choice to let
go of the stress in whatever way uh skillful way we
find um you know many meditation and um in in
inside meditation uh mindfulness and an investigation go hand in hand they work
together most of the time when we're applying it we're not we don't we're not thinking of applying investigation
you're just doing it um and for instance if um one way to think of it is like
when we're looking at the um at the breath you know think of it it like an
apple instead okay you're looking at an apple and you know it's an apple you know you recognize it and and you're
paying enough attention that you know it's an apple in your hand but if you investigate it you'll go wow that's got
you know a lot of red on this side some green over here and um you know wow this
one's kind of flat looking Apple I had one of those the other day it was just the flattest Apple I'd ever seen it was
just like kind of squished and um you know so you see all those little details um and um you know mindfulness
just sees that the apple is there and then you have the quality of
concentration that keeps you paying attention so you're looking at the Apple and suddenly you're somewhere else right
and concentration says no this is a task at hand let's look at this apple uh and so you've got all these
three qualities that are kind of working together so when we're watching the
breath and and we're you know just knowing we're watching the breath and then we start fading away and like how
of the mind gets dull we can apply a little more oh what's really happening
here and you start looking at the little details and there's such a difference in
the breath sometimes when you're kind of seeing it like oh yeah uhuh in out one two or you're like really right there
you know sometimes um I've used the term um caressing the breath you know it's
like if you're caressing a young child or or a dog you love love you're not spaced out kind of yeah yeah I'm
caressing the dog you know but you're like you know enjoying it there's a engagement in it and so sometimes you
know with the breath you know can bring that intimacy with the breath that really being there with it very
closely um you know and sometimes you know it's not that everything we do uh
all forms of Investigation are are tiny in detail you know sometimes you know it it's like
looking through microscope right and you have have most of you looked through M microscope once you know or seing
pictures you know and and God it's so alive in there sometimes there's so much going on um you know blood cells or um
you know I saw uh um vitamin C you know in in one of those really Ultra
microscopes you know and it looked like this incredible mandala it was just beautiful and so you know if you look
really closely things open up in a different way you know but then at other times what's useful in practice is to
open up the vision open up your uh scope of attention and make it broader and
it's kind of like looking at the night sky looking at the telescope through telescope right you see millions of
details out there you know it's not you're going to focus on all of them right you go bananas uh but you just um
yeah getting a fruit salad here apple banana um so it's it gets really big and
but within that largess uh we see different kind of details and um you
know and same thing in meditation you know sometimes like you know if the mind's really sluggish you know I'm sure
all of you have experienced a little bit of that sloth and torper that happens on occasion you know where it just starts
drifting and you know paying really close attention can really uh help and
really noticing those really minute parts of the breath but if you're um um
really restless mind you know uh it can be really helpful to uh open up the
attention really big give it room um
the the image we use sometimes is the image of uh Wild Horses you know we put
them in a Corral you know and they're really miserable right they're they they're just you know trying to get out
and you put them in a wide pasture and they're moving fast and happily but they're they're just so so beautiful and
graceful and and so a a fast mind a busy mind a Restless mind we don't have to
change it we just have to know oh it's a Restless busy mind we don't have to push
it away we we see it we investigate it what is like to have a busy mind oh it's
beautiful it's like wild horses up there you know it's like we can allow it allow
it to be that way
um you know we can say there's um like two aspects to
investigation um they're seeing what's there right this is a p pie of paper uh
this is a bell you know seeing the details of my environment you know and I sat down I looked really carefully that
I didn't sit on anything especially the microphone um you know so you see those
details um but the other part of Investigation in in the practice in the
Dharma is the discernment the ability to see distinctions between things right
the details distinctions but to see which ones are help helpful in terms of
freeing the heart freeing the mind and which ones actually aren't helpful you know such as um you know we're we're
meditating and and suddenly we find ourselves in this wonderful fantasy I
mean it's really enjoyable you know it doesn't seem like it's causing us any Duke at that moment any stress it's just
a wonderful fantasy you know and the mind goes oh I'm you know there's uh I'm
in a just spend some lot of time my fantasy I kind of want to go back it was really juicy you know and um you know
but investigation says is is this forward leading to the reason you're
actually here why are you here right you you took this time to meditate right you
can fantasize any time it's not it's not bad it's not a wrong thing it just isn't
what you're doing and so it sees it discerns that's not helpful for what
we're trying to do here which is train the mind train the mind you know it's not making that
wrong and you know and like that's such an important point because I know that
um um you know how many of you have had a meditation and said that was a bad
sitting you know you may not have said it out loud but you know but but you've thought that right you know and um and
that piece of of um unhelpful thinking um is uh really important piece
because um you know we're training we're not training the mind to stay on the breath
we're not training the mind to stay concentrated we're training the mind to
be free of attachment that's what we're training the mind and so sometimes we get stuck and
we mistake that we think that the um the purpose of the meditation was for it to
be a certain way but the purpose of meditation is to show
up enough that we see how we cause our own suffering and the more clearly we see
that the easier it is to begin to have it fade away and to and to let go of it
and so when we think that's a bad meditation that moment is a moment of not seeing
clearly you know what did we learn you know how do we how do we meet uh or EXP
experience when it's not what we want um the other image sometimes I have
is that um um you know I'm walking down a path I'm hiking you know and there's the road
in the you know the the traditional uh fork in the road and uh on the left is
the is the way I always go home it's a short way you know and on the right it's a little bit longer longer way so I
rarely take it and as said walking you know I'm I'm kind of really want to get
home already you know and so I'm ready to go go left but all of a sudden
because I'm being Mindful and investigating I noticed that path is really muddy it's really muddy right now
and the other path is kind of on the sunny side and it's pretty dry and and uh so I make a choice I'm going to take
this side because this is taking me home this is taking me home in an easier way
it doesn't make the other path bad or wrong or a failure or anything it's just
how it is right now that's not helpful and so when the um torments of
the Mind rise right you know the that we all have these Universal things that
happen in our minds you know where we're contracted and and unhappy about our
experience when those things arise oh that's what arose it's not wrong for
being there you know we investigate it and that investigation of that is a
wholesome factor of mind we already transforming it for instance if um your
habit of mind is worrying right some some people really worry a lot they're always worrying about stuff right so the
moment you see oh that's worry you're no longer worrying you're now investigating
you've already changed the picture you've already opened the container up
and this is actually the way to freedom from worry when we do that it weakens
that habit of worry every time it weakens that habit of worry so when the
meditation um ends and we're unhappy with what happened we investigate that
unhappiness oh I had an expectation you know I wanted I didn't get things my way you know that's that's
the Dharma the teachings the Dharma you know getting getting what we want uh you
know needing to get what we want trying to always get what we want is what cause us suffering you know life is going to give
us at least half of what we don't want yeah and so really being able to be
happy whether we get what we want or we don't get what we
want
you know how we investigate you know um when we're relaxed and we're paying
attention investigation just shows up you know if you have you ever had um a
wonderful conversation with a friend and you're just interested you're not working at it you're not uh doing
anything difficult you're just there you're enjoying the conversation you're just interested and in the same way um you
know if we're interested in the breath and we're noticing the details we're not working at
it um but when we get caught by something um it's very easy to lose that
relaxation right when we get caught by um let's say um you know one of my
favorite um hindrances has always been noise while I'm meditating you know uh
that has got me caught you know a really loud noise like um um we used to live in
the desert in this really beautiful pristine Space 2 and a half acres was so
beautiful and quiet and all of a sudden at 6:30 in the morning these young guys
in their motorcycles would come through the dirt roads and just circle area over
and over and over again you know and I would just H rage would rise and and um
you know meditating yes rage would rise you know and uh and you know and so how
do you meet that how do you meet that you know there was the displeasure of
the noise very unpleasant and it came and then went
came and went you know and then there was the idea that how dare they they
shouldn't be doing this there's all this extra stuff that came up all this extra
stuff stuff and I kept um you know negotiating my mind how do I fix it you
know um you know get a water pistol you know all sorts of creative ideas right
um and um you know but but you know what's really important is what do we do
in our own heart you know how do we meet those things in our own
heart um I remember being really impressed When U I heard heard that um uh I think
Bernie Glassman I think was his name um you know is a zen teacher he used to he
held uh um these 10-day Retreats um under a bridge under a very
busy bridge where cars were going freeway freeway bridge and um and
everybody who took the retreat was supposed to uh have no money no
possessions um and just come as they are you know and just to live there that way
with nothing and for 10 days you know and uh um you know and that's really the
practice of letting go of really okay can we be at peace in ourselves when
we're not getting what we want you know when things aren't the way we want them to be including our mind State and
that's the really the real key thing here is to be okay even when our mind
State isn't okay and so for instance you know when I was like very
um uh very very angry and uptight and and I I'm I'm meditating right yeah I'm
going to do some loving kindness towards those you
know um you know that that was the state of my mind you know and then you know it
finally grows the memory of of um aun Su talking about a affectionate
curiosity you know and that's how he likes to describe curiosity the quality of mind that's affectionate you know
this it's not curiosity for curiosity sake it's a friendly curiosity and so I turned the
affectionate curiosity towards my anger and turmoil and and really saw that pain in
myself you know how much worse it was that that unpleasant noise God it was so
much worse than that unpleasant Pleasant noise you so it's able to really apply that you know that that kind um you know
it's a little bit um you know when our mind's having a tantrum you know not
different than when a four-year-old's having that tantrum right it's pretty similar you know a lot of that that you
know I didn't get my ice cream and the whole world's falling down on my head because I didn't get my ice cream you
know it's really serious matter you know for to that four-year-old and and so that's what her mind's doing it's a
tantrum right and so with a child you go you kind of smile you go a you know this
sweet affectionate you know oh look at how they're doing that let me just support them while they have their
tantrum and and it'll be over and and you know and again we can do that with
our own mind you know we can do that with ourselves you know wherever we find contraction we can we can bring
kindness you know investigation gives us that choice investigation shows us we're
not trapped in that in in that turmoil uh that we have a choice to be mindful
to see what's here and to let go of what we can let go not to force ourselves to
let go but to let go what let's go relax into the turmoil you know allow it to move
through us every form of turmoil every emotion every contraction comes and goes
eventually
you know one of the things that we often forget is that um we actually can choose
what thoughts we're going to have in some way by um just by changing what
we're paying attention to what the focus of our attention is you know for instance um um you know if let's say
we're in the car um uh I saw these puddles here so this is appropriate in
my mind so and we find we got a flat tire you know and uh and so we get out
of the car and you know we've done everything we need to do we call work we say we're going to be late and you know
we call triaa to help us you know come and change her tire and um and then we
just have to wait right and you know day like today you know it's um you know and
we can sit there and you know and our mind can just be focused on oh God I'm
you know I'm going to be late I'm going to have all this work to do T all the stuff that goes on through mind that's worried and and having an unpleasant
experience right or we can actually shift our attention to what's here you know oh
it's a beautiful day beautiful sky you know and it's the same thing we
do in our meditation right you know we're caught up in worry we don't have
to keep you know uh kind of uh scratching at that scab you know it's
like uh you know the worry that cycle of worry or cycle of planning where we're
just you know massaging it to death you know and so we can just uh shift the
attention to oh look from to a little bigger point of view you know watching
it you know it's like oh look at that worry going on you know see what's happening you know look at the how the
body feels with that worry you know I'm not relaxed can I relax into it and
allow the worry not make it wrong not oh we got to go away go away you know no
you know we we we just allow it to be there until it goes away it will go away
in its own when we give it room we give it space and when we give it uh
curiosity you know
um when we're caught in something um you know sometimes you know when
things are simple in meditation it's very simple to investigate but sometimes
when the mind is caught in a hindrance and it's it feels like very complicated
you know and so one of the ways that I investigate um you know since it just
feels like too confusing to know what do I investigate here what do I pay attention to there's so much chaos going
on in my mind and so I look look to the body first you know uh how is the body
is the body relaxed here because we can't have a we don't have contracted states in the mind without something
Contracting in the body and then um I might notice uh then
I go to the heart to the to the emotional state you know how how are my emotions right now you know and um and
that's where I notice uh um I might notice I'm unhappy um with uh what's happening this
is just such a you know terrible meditation I'm a terrible terrible meditator and that's well that's more
the cognitive side you know because these ideas if I was a good meditator this wouldn't be happening right I
wouldn't be here um if I was a mature person I wouldn't be having these immature thoughts um if I was you know
all these ideas that we have in our minds so we notice how we feel about things maybe there's uh um fear going on
maybe there's um sadness going on maybe we're lonely all these different things
that human beings can experience so look to the body to the
feelings to the thoughts about the how we are and we also can look to a
motivation you know it's obvious the body heart and mind you know those are the things that are there all the time
but our motivation something that can get away from us we that can go un seen
and and really this is in some ways it's like right the heart of the practice are we wanting or are we wanting to push
something away and that sometimes is just you know the all our miseries I want something I
want a better meditation I want it to be more fulfilling I want want want want
and that moving forward doesn't allow us to see what's here to be with this you
know or you don't like what you're you know what you feeling you want to push it
away you know wanting it to go away wanting things to change neither it it's
funny in some ways they exactly the same thing not wanting things the way they are you know wanting them to be
different but sometimes we experience it as wanting to have something else and
sometimes we experience it as wanting to push away what's there and so however
you feel it in the moment what you your experiences in the
moment and you know just say a general rule that I really appreciate you know when I heard this many years ago um if
we're struggling anytime we're struggling something is being left out of our
attention it's kind of an interesting thought if you really bring that to
heart whenever we're struggling even when we're struggling um um doing
something physical you know um it may be for
instance um you know I remember when I was learning to um uh use a hammer you
know and I just kept trying to control the experience right you know to you know to get it just right you know and
it felt like a struggle you know and um you know it really took convincing for me to let go you know and
it's something that I didn't miss you know I miss plenty you know but but the trust to let go you know and at that
point I I stopped struggling to try to get it right and that made all the
difference in the world stopping the struggle you know so anytime we're
struggling in our own minds and our own Hearts you know there's something we're not seeing it maybe difficult whatever
we need to do it might be difficult but there's a difference between doing something difficult you know like
climbing a mountain where it's really you know Steep and you've been going for an hour and your legs are really tired
it's difficult but you don't have to struggle it's just difficult it's just
unpleasant might be very unpleasant but we don't have to struggle with it we don't have to add all this
other stuff and so if we're struggling what are we not seeing
aversion right we don't like the fact that it's hard and we're adding that to
our experience of difficulty which is a burden actually if we're just with a
difficult it's not as hard as if we're with a difficult and then with the attitude that it shouldn't be this way
that adds a lot of
extra you know the investigation in the deeper practices of meditation you know
it's called um the tool tool for wisdom you know damaya it's the um the wisdom
that arises from this and this really points to the Discerning aspect of
Investigation the part that sees what's helpful what's forward leading and what's not
helpful and um you know this is uh um
Insight Meditation and at every level of practice we have different types of
insights that arise you know when we're um sometimes listening to Dharma talk we
can have very very wonderful Insight you know sometimes a teacher says something
and it really resonates with us you know I'm sure all of you have been coming regularly you know it's one of the
things that brings you back is there so much resonates with something inside you that knows a lot the Dharma is true you
know this this stuff is true it works um and
um and you know and then there's this we uh investigate maybe while we're meditating you know and all these um uh
um the mind is having trouble stabilizing you know and we have the
understanding the an investigation that if we just uh really pay attention to
the breath the Mind event calms yeah oh it does actually calm and
at some point becomes really something we understand we we it's an insight into the way our mind
works and also at other times and you know our personal stories show up and um
you know I I'll give you an example of like for me one of the um one of the
things that happened to me uh I noticed on Retreat you know I was meditating and
I would notice um that there was just something wasn't quite quite right you know it's like I
was staying on the breath I was calm but there was just like this overall tone in my mind that was just slightly off and I
and I I just couldn't pinpoint it I just kept practicing practicing and looking more carefully and what I noticed is
that every time my mind drifted when it came back I feel like I
had failed you know or having gone away and that habit of thinking that every time I
went my mind drifted I had failed was so strong in me I watched it time after
time even while I'm watching it it's going it's doing it again wow you know that sinking feeling of failure that
sinking feeling of failure and so I watched it for a really long time as it slowly got a little bit less and I
wasn't drifting that much it was it was interesting because it was a um on a daily uh meditation I would have
thought I was doing really well but on Retreat you know I'm expecting it to be much less drifting you know and
expectation of course and so um you know and as as uh I started seeing it more
and more carefully you know I started getting more affectionate to it you know more soft with it more and as it finally
just kind of faded you know so I don't that doesn't just doesn't arise anymore for me um but things like that don't
necessarily go away with one time of seeing them I mean I don't want to give you that false idea some things do but a
lot of things you know it takes years sometimes for some of those things to um to be let go of you know and
um I've learned not to um you know I've learned to accept what let's go and uh
and accept what doesn't let go yet you know that's been a big part of my practice is is uh is seeing that the
things we're still holding on to are there you know and it's part of the wisdom we
have um you know and often we you know we have what I call personal insights you
know and I've mentioned um you know the mind can have repetitive patterns you know that whenever the mind isn't
focusing on something it has a fall back right and for some people that fall back might be
planning you know how many of you did some planning while you're meditating right you know it's um oh this is what
I'm going you this what I'm going to do later okay um and you know but most of the planning we do in meditation is
actually often not useful planning it's often just compulsive planning that
isn't particularly helpful um you know and these are personal
insights when we see these inside ourselves and again we don't force ourselves to stop planning but we see
what what's driving that plan planning you know what's driving that um you know
for myself cuz you know I'm a really good planner I mean you know it's a skill and and um was always my tendency
to do this in meditation too um but part of planning for me was enjoyable you
know I like planning you know it's fun and but when it's fun I feel happy you
know it's like oh let's let's plan this project together you know it's always fun and exciting but often I'd find the
planning in meditation was not that kind of planning was the other kind and um it
would be this uh kind of contracted you know we're having friends over for dinner I'm going to make blah blah blah
blah well maybe I'll make this maybe I'll sit this person over here maybe I'll do this you know and just these
kind of you you know unhelpful things that arise from this anxiety or worry
underneath you know and as as we get curious about it you know we don't we
don't need to shove it away and go back to the the breath you know we just get curious about it and we notice oh this
is how worry feels that anxiety feels in my body this is what's here oh okay I
can relax into it I can allow that I don't have to fight it and it will go
away it will just move move away it will change everything changes right
including worry and planning and we allow it and as we return we return
without that have been wrong that having been something that we blew you know
it's just oh back home welcome home nice to be back you know and and um and so
we're developing a wholesome attitude in our in our entire meditation in the
times when things arise that are contracted and difficult and in the times when things feel like they're
wonderful you know it's a wholesome attitude of Mind of
heart um you know and when when the Awakening
Factor investigation is really well established you know and and this is where um
Retreat practice can really help take us much deeper into this and um we can
see um you know we start seeing investigating much subtler levels of
reality so instead of noticing kind of the the grossness of oh my stomach feels
tied uh you know not gross but you know there there're it there's so much more
subtleness we start experiencing and we start seeing that everything on a very
deep level arises and passes away we all know we all know intellectually that
everything's impermanent right nobody would argue with that you know that everything is you know is
impermanent um and every everything goes away there's nothing we'll ever be able to keep so intellectually realize that
if everything's going away nothing can make us permanently happy right you know
so um as we practice in the deeper levels
of practice we start seeing that kind of in a bone deep level that's it's just so
much deeper that um it's not in the intellect it's non verbal it's a
nonverbal knowing that nothing out there is going to satisfy that there's nowhere
out there to look for the satisfaction there's nothing in here to look for
satisfaction um you know and it's a letting go it's a Letting Go a deeper and deeper letting go and that's the why
investigation is the tool of wisdom because it it brings us to the
realization which is not again not an intellectual realization that there's nothing worth
holding on to you know there's nothing worth grabbing on to grasping you know and the
that freedom that comes from that is what allows a very deep peace you know
and we can touch on that at times and we can um live with it at times and
sometimes it just arises for little pieces here and there but however it is
this this is the path of practice this is where the practice takes us to the point of you know not grabbing on to
anything you know to these fleeting lives these fleeting bodies you know these
um um you know everything um everything in life the trees the beautiful trees
and so it calls us to just be here be here with what's here our life's here
not in the future we become good meditators you know it's kind of this beautiful
balance in the practice between uh being fully here and yet um being on a path
that's forward leading you know stepping here here here
but yet also knowing that we're forward leading developing our minds developing
the direction of Freedom so I'm going to just end with a
very short quote by Ashan
sha peace within us is to be found in the same place as agitation and
suffering it's not found in a forest or a Hilltop nor is it given by a
teacher where you experience suffering you can also find Freedom from
suffering trying to run away from suffering is actually running towards
it so thank you
all