hello everyone and welcome to Wednesday morning here in
Redwood City at the Insight Meditation Center and uh already a bit warm the
morning and I am feeling happy and a bit inspired to take
this seat and to be preparing to talk to you
so the this morning meditation the introduction to it is uh
to the instructions is that um when we do
mindfulness meditation maybe when we do most forms of Buddhist
Meditation that um stay close to what you can directly
sense see and know without any
interpretation without any judgment without any recourse
to events that are not here and now to
predictions of the future with that any recourse
to um um
what's outside of the basic sense experience that you have here and
now and so certainly the five senses uh the but also the six sense in
Buddhism is uh the knowing of the Mind knowing of chitt knowing of uh the
thinking knowing of impulses desires and aversion there's a kind of like assume
assume there's like a sense door a sense that can just know that oh that's what it is as Oppo as opposed to going
getting involved in what you're thinking about because if you're thinking about
what you're thinking about it just leads to more thinking uh rather than what you desire
just no desire to think about what you're Desiring again pulls you into the world
of thoughts and maybe even more desires if there's aversion just know
the aversion the Simplicity of it you don't have to go into what you have aversion towards um just a simple
experience so coming back to the basic here if there is a lot of
um wonderful experiences in meditation that you're ready to
interpret as being that you're on the brink of enlighten that that uh that uh this is your karma
that you have this good experience if you have difficulty experiences uh you want to interpret it
some other way that you'll never be a good meditator that uh this is your karma that you're not having good
meditation all that is secondary for this meditation see if if
you can stay really close to the primary experience the immediacy of here and now
that does doesn't require interpretation um doesn't add an
interpretation to it just the experience just a direct sense experience the
direct place where things arise and they're known initially before we
interpret if there is an interpretation just know it as an interpretation
without needing to think about what the interpretation is whether it's right or wrong just know it for that and go back
to breathing and your dire experience so it's a
radical stepping away from anything that takes you away
from your immedi the immediacy of your direct experience and so the center of gravity
for this can be the breathing and it's it's not we're not following the breath which you can't
really see it's exactly what we're doing is we're tracking or being attuned to
the sensations in the body that come into play as you're
breathing and the basic Sensations and again without interpretation without
judgment so it doesn't matter whether it's a pleasant or unpleasant sensation of breathing it just matters that you
know it as that that simple nothing to fix nothing to judge
nothing to be concerned about nothing to build a case that you're great or or terrible just the basic sensation stay
there stay there stay with that and um and see how that's very different maybe
it's very difficult to do but it might highlight for you how much time you
spend in this secondary world of ideas and interpretations
judgments um past and future and and concerned with things that are not
immediately here so assuming a meditation
posture which is the beginning of being
connected to the immediacy of our experience
here posture is always in the present
moment and making small adjustments so you're a little bit more com more
comfortable in your posture but also a little B more aligned
and a posture that somehow supports being
alert to the present
moment lowering your gaze
closing your eyes and letting
the eyes rest in the
sockets let your almost as if you're let allowing
the eyes to look backwards and down so the eyes are not engaged in
anything gently taking a few long slow deep
breaths as the chest and belly expand maybe the shoulders
lift a ritual of connection
to the body to be here and
now relaxing as you
exhale relaxing may be a ritual of homecoming into this direct experience
of
now and then to to let your breathing return to
normal and take some time to feel your body kind of Global Experience of the
body perhaps from the inside out or from the center and your torso
outwards not So Much from the thinking mind
the human body is an amazing
apparatus of sense of sensing we have many many
capacities to sense to feel the environment ourselves
the human body is an amazing array of
antennas amazing array of commun communication
between with all the sense data that comes
in that operates with very little
input from us except relaxing into the
body and allowing us to feel and
sense and within this body
kind of at the center of
it sensing experiencing what it's like for the body to be
breathing our human bodily apparatus
is finely attuned or finely in relationship to the body
breathing breathing is attuned to the
body s softening relaxing as you exhale
relaxing all the way to the end of the
exhale with an Ever So slight pause before you allow the body body to
breathe
in as you exhale soften the thinking
mind relax the tension or agitation of
thinking at the end of the exhale ever so
briefly as the exhale as there's a pause in the
breath let there be silence in the thinking
mind maybe it's an infantes silence but let the thinking mind become
still and quiet for a moment
and when the thinking mind is quiet then it's
easier to stay with the immediacy of Sensations in your
body the immediacy of our direct experience now without
interpretation thinking judging
Orient yourself towards the world of direct experience
letting the thinking mind recede to the
background free of interpretations feel the
body feel your direct experience Here and
to Center meditation in our direct
experience is can be supported by a deep
trust in the natural human
capacities for intelligence creativity compassion
the natural human capacity for healing coming into
homeostasis resting trusting the direct experience allows the deeper capacities
of Being Human to operate
effectively the more we stay in our interpretation
reactions ideas fantasies distractions the more we
interfere with a full and deep natural capacity we
have to be have embodied
intelligence EMB [Music] embodied
healing embody
trust that our thinking mind doesn't have to
find the answer to all
things and as we come to the end of this
sitting to expand that trust in our relationship to
others that our ability to be present for people Direct directly
simply listening well seeing
well without with Clarity without the obscuration of
interpretations judgments
bias problem solving and distraction is is a great gift we give
to
others may it be as we come to the end of this sitting that whatever we learn about
trusting our direct experience is remembered when we stay
present to listen to
others to see others so that everyone we encounter feels
respected cared for attended
to as if they're important and valuable and so they too can
rest in themselves may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may our capacity for mindful
attention support this possibility for others
[Music]
thank you
so hello everyone one and welcome to this third talk uh the series called
core teachings and that's a short hand for the core teachings or core
understandings that underly how I teach Buddhism and I thought it was probably
high time for me to um be explicit about my particular
orientation around Buddhism and Buddhist teachings that um so you don't have to
guess or not know uh and this in the background of
probably everything I teach one way or the other and so how I teach has a particular
orientation that um uh is maybe a subset of what Buddhism
is it is definitely a subset of what Buddhism is but maybe it's a subset of what the earliest teachings are because
of the orientation of what I select and what I'm oriented towards and um so
um the first talk was about the emphasis on um Dua and freedom from Dua often
translated as suffering and the end of suffering uh yesterday's talk was about
um the having no views having no um not
operating finding a place of no views not centering or basing ourselves on a
particular um a dependency on an understanding or a
view view but a freedom from views uh freedom from taking anything as
ultimate views of ultimacy which is common in religion and both of these belong to the
world of our direct experience um the idea of ultimacy that
this is what the Ultimate Experience is Ultimate Reality is is a kind of interpretation and you can ask your
yourself the question where did I learn this from where's that interpretation come from um and uh is it from my
teachers is it from my sacred texts is it from um this a popular idea or is it
from my logic or my my own interpretation of what's going on and uh and uh what are the views that
I have that uh overlay my experience and what happens when there's no views
overlaying our direct experience so all of this brings us into what I would like
to call uh the natural world of our direct experience and I one of the ways of
characterizing the kind of Buddhism that I or oriented towards is naturalistic
Buddhism and what uh that means one of the things that means is that uh it's a
it's orientation in Buddhism that does not have recourse to the sup
Supernatural world and what I mean by super natural world is the world that
the natural laws of science the laws of nature as we know them
today uh are not understood they don't uh that uh the Buddhism I'm orist is
kind of that world which is um relates to uh that fits into the natural laws of
of um nature that we understand today it doesn't mean that there are not
things outside of that that exist but it means that the Buddhism is centered on
that our direct experience what we can know for ourselves and uh
directly and um and so for many people
the experience of um heavens and hells that Buddhism emphasizes is not part of
their direct experience and um it's not something they can know themselves you can read about it teachers can talk about it and
we can believe in it but it's not something most people have a direct experience of and um uh the idea of rebirth for most
people that's not part of their direct experience that uh there is rebirth and so to to uh it's a common belief in
Buddhism but for someone who hasn't had any direct experience of it then we have to accept it on faith or accept it as a
belief system rather than something we can have known directly for ourselves and so um so I don't want to
diminish the value of people or say that it's non-existent ideas of Heaven and
Hell or rebirth uh it's um maybe I'm agnostic about it but it's
I don't I respect people have these experiences people have those experiences but uh they're not my
experience so I'm not going to base my Buddhism on those experience my own practice is not based on it and so I
stay close to the naturalistic world and um and uh and exactly how we Define
naturalistic is maybe a little bit you you know can be variable but um uh and
then I then I take support to doing this that if you go back to the ancient teachings of the
Buddha whenever he's going to talk about specifically like what is the his
Dharma in brief what is his teachings in brief what are the essential things you should be teaching if you're teaching
the Dharma um what are the things that the early tradition was most focused on
memorizing as the the what represented the teaching the earliest texts there were so many texts but within those they
have some uh discussion about what the people of the time the monks and the nuns at that time uh were reciting and
memorizing and directly and and and what you see is that uh in all
these kind of more targeted or uh focused discussions about what's
important in the Dharma it's all naturalistic and um there's no mention
of rebirth as part of it there is discussion about rebirth in the text but it seems to be um not Central to the of
what the Buddha think says is most important to teach and I understand that
because um uh he was teaching a practice he was teaching at practice to the end
of clinging and uh when he talks about the goal of practice he talks about it as
the end of clinging the end of suffering and um end of
craving and those are naturalistic experiences they can experience you can you can experience those and know those
for yourself they fit within the kind of natural laws of what we know and um and
um uh in talking about rebirth is often sometimes a discussion about if you do
that you won't be reborn but it's not that that uh the purpose is not to be reborn he doesn't
say that that's a rare idea it's just almost like a add-on to what is really
core my own teachers in this country and Asia that I had
emphasized uh only believe in what you know for yourself I feel like that'd be
really disappointed in me if I if I had uh relied on Buddhist teachings I can
only know from uh belief there's more Supernatural uh beliefs that uh that
um that appear in the text um the emphasis only know for what Rec focus on
what you can know yourself don't rely on like the kalas famous teaching of the
Buddha that don't rely on tradition don't rely on what you know by faith
don't rely on what you know by your rationed reason don't rely on um uh your
religious texts don't rely on your what your teacher says rely on what you know
for yourself of what is wholesome and UNH wholesome what is uh harmful and not
harmful what is peaceful and not peaceful that's what you rely on and
those those criteria wholesome non-harming peaceful that
belongs to the world of direct experience that we know for ourselves and so we can guide ourselves
and find our way through the practice uh through this naturalistic Cate uh uh
criteria uh we don't have to not Guided by uh or in the practice Moment by
Moment by the more Supernatural beliefs the more abstract beliefs the more um
and um in addition to the metaphysical beliefs there's also met uh Supernatural
beliefs there's also metaphysical belief beliefs beliefs that have to do with the
uh ultimate nature of reality uh beliefs that have to do with
um the ultimate nature of what enlightenment is and enlightened Consciousness and all kinds of ideas
like this and um and this is also something we cannot know
directly and um and that's this is very Nuance when I was in Burma um there was
a tremendous emphasis on impermanence and they emphasized everything is impermanent and and uh I spent a lot of
time reflecting on this teaching that everything is impermanent everything is changing all the time logically it makes
sense and um but uh uh I finally came to
understand that really what I could take a stand on was not the metaphysical idea
that everything is impermanent but rather uh the uh the uh the act of
perceiving in the act of perceiving whatever is perceived can be seen as in
constant and changing all the time that like a mountain doesn't necessarily change that fast but the perception of
the mountain is constantly shifting and changing and I was then delighted to read that the Buddha never talked about
uh impermanence as a characteristic of reality that was a later idea and terad
Buddhism but he emphasized that um impermanence is a perception and once we're into
perception we're into this natural world of our human functioning and human
life so um so um maybe this talk today is a little
bit more abstract and philosophical but it let underpins my orientation to the
Dharma or explains it that I have this very strong natural istic orientation
and so generally that's what you'll hear from me um and it's very rare that I'll talk about things that are
Supernatural uh or metaphysical because uh that is not uh navigating the Dharma
through the direct experience of what we could know ourselves and uh and where we can find the path to practice which is
only found here and now in the natural world uh what we can see uh what's immed
OT and what we can know for ourselves directly and as we do this uh we become
uh this mindfulness practice in this way over time we become more and more uh
um understanding of the overlays we put on Direct
experience uh many people uh who are not practiced will say uh you know that um
you know will will make a statement which says this is my experience but it's really they're
describing something that's through their interpretation of things and
um and uh so I'm sitting here in this this room here and I say this is my
experience of what a meditation Hall is like and uh and so we call it a
meditation Hall so uh it's kind of an accurate enough statement but this could
also be a dance hul it could be a studio which it is at this moment for this broadcast it could be a conference room
it could be a uh during the pandemic I used to have a corner of it with a an exercise machine where I exercised here
I used to have a table this used to be my office and um and so uh to say that
it's a meditation Hall is a kind of a overlay that it's not necessary to have
and so as we practice mindfulness become more and more attuned to how we add a
little something on top of our experience that um that is interpretive
and how much we live in the world of interpretation and how there's a path of freedom to be found when we see that
clearly and find out how not to be attached or caught in those overlays and
those interpretations and we can live more and more in our in this naturalistic world
which is which I'll talk about tomorrow which is a amazingly powerful resource
it's an amazingly the naturalistic world of who we are as a human being is full
of intelligence and creativity and capacity for healing and compassion so
it's a um that also is will be uh you know as a foundation for the my
orientation in the Dharma and that that talk will be for tomorrow
so thank you uh for giving me this chance to explain myself and uh and I do
look forward to continuing tomorrow