welcome to the Insight Meditation Center in Redwood City I'm sitting here in our
meditation Hall and happy to do so and to be with
you all of you this and um some of you are familiar
with a very common metaphor that's I I know of it mostly used in the secular
mindfulness movement and the sometimes in mindfulness of schools they'll use it where uh they'll take
a container of water and sand water and glitter like a snow snowball
bowl and um Shake everything up and then watch as uh all the sediment
all the dust and sparkles or whatever it might be settle into into the and you
see clearly what's there the water becomes clear and
um so another way of maybe saying the same thing which is not so much a
settling which is wonderful feeling calming settling down is that uh in this practice we're
doing we also want to give time for the self
organizing um movement of our body and Minds that as awareness wakes up as we
become more aware of um of what's Happening Here and Now the idea is we're
integrating we're including we're um uh everything that we are and if we take
time to feel and sense into our bodies wake up our bodies feel our bodies wake
up emotionally feel what's happening emotionally recognize what's happening
is in our mind there's something about the simple recognition of it and waiting the simple
recognition and allowing it to be there in the field of attention allowing it to be there while
sensing it especially in a physical way the sensing feeling the embodiedness of
it even the embod embodiedness of uh a
mind which is caught up in thoughts and ideas what is the physicality what's the feeling what's the happens in what's the
sensations of the in the head and the brain that goes along with that and what
that does is it begins to make space for the sediment to settle but more than
that more importantly it allows things to uh recollect there's a recollection that
happens a reorganizing a coming together we uh
start getting put back together um or uh things get pulled together we get
we pull our not that we pull ourselves together but the system our psychophysical system is pulling itself
together and it's a remarkable process of waking up that we become whole
remarkable process by which we get recollected reunified um by
waiting for it to happen making time for it to happen and um and so the
self-organizing rather than the self organizing the you doing the organizing pulling everything together we're
sitting up we're we're staying here and just sensing feeling into it so we get
organized or oriented with all of who we are here and um this is a powerful thing
to do because otherwise we're partial otherwise we might be ahead of ourselves
we might be caught up in some concern we might be pushed around by The Winds of
the world which I talked about a few weeks ago or we pushed around by our fear our hatred or desires our anger
they take the lead and we become uh partial we become only part of us is
driving the show and for a wise life we we don't
want to have any one thing really driving the show we want everything to
be on the stage we want everything to becoming working together in a whole and so part of mindfulness part of
meditation is to be present for all of who we
are and allowing a natural process of self-organizing reorganizing coming
together bringing it all here and it doesn't require much except being
present being attentive feeling into it so maybe some of that this you'll feel
this next meditation will do so assuming a
posture that is the right posture for you that gives you a chance to begin
sensing and feeling as as much of the whole of who
you are in a balanced full
way so if you're slouching too much it may be fine to relax that way
but also it maybe doesn't really allow for everything to become alive everything to become vital
here relaxing too much is too much the settling but not the reorg organizing
into a living field of your
Humanity so if you're sitting to sit up a little bit more
upright if you're lying down maybe there's some way to adjust your
spine how your shoulder blades are maybe against a
surface switching how your hands are your arms
even your legs maybe sometimes having your
legs up kind of bent with your leg feet closer into your
body can give a feeling of being more engaged in the
fullness of
ourselves lowering the Gaze
and gently closing the
eyes this process of feeling sensing giving time to know
what's here without needing to fix anything can begin when you take a few
long slow deep breaths where on the in inhale you feel the stronger Sensations
in the Torso that come from Deep the greater movement
expansion and then on the exhale to soften relax the body the
shoulders the belly
maybe the rib cage can relax and
settle if there's a place where your weight of your torso is most
centered maybe that place can relax and drop bit teeny
bit as you exhale
letting your breathing return to normal and with the
exhale relaxing more
physically relaxing gives time and space
to feel more fully so as you relax on the exhale feel
that part of your body a little bit more as you
inhale so relaxing your face
relaxing the shoulders on the exhale and feeling the shoulders on the
inhale and and the attitude as you feel the shoulders is an attitude of
inclusion allowing yourself to feel and sense how it is without needing it to be
different but then as you exhale you can make a little bit
different soften relax in the
shoulders and the same with the
chest relax the chest the Heart
Center feel it all on the inhale
as if it has permission to be that way just know it as if in the knowing and
feeling you're allowing the self-organizing movement of the body
and gently without trying too hard on the exhale softening the
belly and in this case as you breathe in
both feel the belly but see if there can continue to
be a little softening of the belly on the
exhale on the inhale keeping it soft
and then becoming [Music]
aware of a global awareness of your body not trying too
hard but being content to have the widest sense feeling of being in a
body
here maybe your attention gently roams around the
body maybe there's a panoramic sense of the
body and as you exhale letting the body relax
soften as you inhale feel and allow the sensations of
the
body as you feel the global panoramic
body you don't have to direct your attention any anywhere it can be almost like a
surprise the sensations that the body
shows and as you exhale gently soften
relax without ambition or trying too
hard the light
touch
for
e e
feeling your body on the
inhale settling the body on the exhale
where maybe you can feel the settling as a gathering a
recollecting of all parts of the body into the whole the global body
where the self organizing ability of the body as an
opportunity to include everything even what is
uncomfortable
for
e
e for
mindfulness is a lot to do with remembering to be present
recollecting reming the parts
together recollecting
Fuller awareness of the body on the inhale allowing it all to
recollect as you settle on the
exhale
for
e
e e
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting two and one more time on the inhale to
feel the whole body an expansion a growing of attention
on the inhale outward then beond on the
body not necessarily to feel what's
beyond but to open be available to feel and
sense the world around
you to feel
sense and there is a way when we take time to feel and
sense be aware of who or what's happening that allows for an
reorganizing coming together becoming more
whole that also allows others to become more
themselves allows others to collect and be themselves more
fully so people are not in conflict with themselves or in conflict with the world
World in such a way they become divided in
themselves cut off from part of themselves may it be that the practice
that we do supports others to be
whole supports others to
be aware of the fullness of who they are collected and organized
unified undivided and in that way to be
free may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all be
beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and may the way that we are
whole inclusive all of who we are is included here
help others to feel free and
[Music]
safe thank you for
so hello and welcome to this second talk on not making it
worse so um one of the principles of mindfulness
practice is to in a wise way and particular way to not avoid not turn
away from things but rather uh to turn towards them and
compost them transform them if they're unhealthy or inappropriate or somehow off
so symbolically we're doing this this week with uh the word worse so don't
make it worse that's so that's what we want to avoid doing is to make it worse
but there's the the art of actually turning towards what's worse and in
doing so to become wise about it to allow it to change to allow it to not
run us or be in charge of us and find our freedom and maybe even transform it
into something that's much better so symbolically we're doing this with taking the word worse and rather
than avoiding it turning towards it and making it into an acronym for something that's
better so yesterday uh the W was presented as
wait uh be patient be give time uh wait
and allow and really uh take time to really in the waiting for something to
change and move that helps us understand better how to respond what to do helps
us take in the bigger picture the second for today the O is um
to organize organize ourselves and uh or Orient ourselves to
kind of the fullness the wholeness of who we are but to organize um uh if we're caught up in the
in activities that are making a situ situation worse for example if we're angry or filled with greed or caught up
in really a lot of anxiety that um and so and uh that kind
of uh tends to contract and narrow the focus of attention to the particular
thing we're concerned about it might be thoughts and stories and imaginations
that are producing the fear the anger the hatred the uh the strong greed uh it
might be the feeling the emotions or the sensations of those emotions themselves those
impulses uh motivations themselves which has us narrowed and caught
up uh and um and so um and so we're
people be becom partial all of us is not included and to wait and then allow the
system to organize to allow the different parts that have been been uh
disconnected because we're narrowed we're tight we're ignoring we're pretending it's not there sometimes
there's difficult emotions difficult states of mind that we don't want to look at and we're trying to override it
by doing activities which distracts us from it but those difficulties the
tensions that we carry with us are still there and we're just happily ignoring them and the more we can be distracted
by doing exciting things fascinating things things um the more relief we get
because we're avoiding successfully what's happening the idea of avoiding who we
are Keeps Us partial keeps us not collected as a whole and so um so uh but when we can
become more whole when we're aware of more the fullness of all the different parts of
ourselves um then we have more information we have more understanding
we have more capacity to respond wisely to respond in ways that's beneficial for
ourselves and for others because we start knowing what is beneficial where am I hurt where am I afraid how do I now
include this in a wise way and um what is my greed what is my desire what's
driving that and maybe there's a wise way to respond to that where's my fear
and uh how can I be wise and engaged and fully here in the situation making my being safe but also
being present wholly to it and so this organizing and um and uh what happens
when we start getting organized uh meaning we start collecting gathering together all of who we are so
we can all be here in the wholeness I'll be here in the if we you allow me to say
kind of the the um the basket of awareness the basket that holds it off
or the CED hands of awareness that the cup hands that gently holds all of who
we are uh then uh things or have a chance
to organize and shift around and gather together and we have a remarkable
ability for self-healing or uh the you know just like a cut and a hand or a finger will
self-heal if we allow it to if we keep it clean and and don't interfere with that healing
process uh all kinds of difficult emotions sadness and grief at times can
be self-healing if we allow it to um to
have space and not interfere with it and not believe it or push it away or uh be
aversive to it there's a whole inner process um that can operate for us that
moves us towards psychological and spiritual health uh if we can learn the
art of holding it all in a wider field of
awareness and so uh I call this for today giving time for us to get
organized uh pulling oursel together putting ourselves together again after being discombobulated being stressed
being uh disconnected to ourselves so reconnect
and um and the important thing that can happen there as I've said we get to have
much more information we tend to be wiser we tend to connect to deeper sources of understanding within us uh as
we get more more collected if we're narrow and uncollected and fragmented
and discombobulated uh the source of our understanding tends to be um coming out
of the reactivity itself coming out of um
maybe beliefs that we hold that can feel very real and very true but are so
partial so narrow so maybe projections and Fantasies or uh made up ideas that
we don't really see fully what's happening here and um and uh not a few times I've
had ideas about other people that those ideas seem so true and maybe some of it
actually was true because I was picking up a particular part of a person but as
I became recollected settled of myself more organized myself back and pulled
myself together lo and behold uh I was able to see the other person more as
whole as well I was able to see more of the person than the particular small
little lens that I was so focused on as if that was the whole
person and so it becomes a gift that we can give the whole world when we become
take time to allow the system to get organized and collected and the way that mindfulness
works is we don't have to so much be the one who does the
recollecting except in being aware of what's here it's the awareness of what's
here feeling being present sensing oh here too and one of the tools for this
is breathing as we kind of stay with the breathing it's one of the ways that the
more with with our breathing the less we're caught up in our thoughts the less we're caught up in our narrow world of
projections and preoccupations the more we less we're fixated on particular um
motivations particular orientations particular emotions there's something
that the Simplicity of breathing not always but sometimes can help free us
from the preoccupations of the Mind free us just enough that we start taking in
more of what's Happening Here and then with that breathing there's it can be
the Art of Letting the breathing begin to massage the body or help us feel more
connected to the body to settle and relax into the body and so much of this process of
reorganizing is an embodied process the more we can feel take time to sense and
be with the body the that's where the system comes into a hole if we try to
think our way into the hole if we try to just use our mental powers to imagine or
to that then it doesn't really happen uh we are if we become whole and organized
as a collective um it has to include our body and it's not our raw bones and
muscles body it's the body of our nervous system the body of uh that
allows us to sense and feel and interact with all its different parts that spreads out throughout all these nerves
that we have throughout the body it's how we experience the body
and uh and as soon as we're tuned into how we're experiencing the body we're tuned into this amazing
network of nerves this amazing net of U
ways that information and understanding and wisdom operates in this system of ours so it's being aware of your body is
not just being aware of this kind of hunk of Flesh it's becoming aware of
this amazing nervous system um that spreads throughout the body that is
intelligent um probably we should think of it as as intelligent as the
brain or collectively organized together the whole expansive sense of the nervous
system in the body the nerves the network of nerves together with our brain creates for
greater intelligence because it's the the nervous system then is also becoming
whole so wait and and organize take time to let
yourself get reorganized pull yourself together settled in Wake up in the
body that's the second way to not make it worse and um if you take just that time
to do that then you're certainly not acting on what makes it worse you're
pausing but you're doing something even more important is that you're beginning
to to gather yourself together so more of this wisdom and more of this empathy
and more of this compassion and love and kindness that we can have for our common
Humanity as a chance to operate and we're becoming less likely to make the situation
worse so thank you and I hope that uh you explore on these next 24 hours um
how you can go through the day to take these sacred pauses sacred times of
waiting not just to wait and and endure but to wait so you can feel more What's
Happening Here for yourself and this self-organizing way in which we become more complete um can be a wonderful
Discovery for you and a Ben a benefit thank you