so welcome and good morning good day to everyone from
everywhere and there's wonderful Gathering of all of you and that I see on chat and those of you in chat you for
me you also represent the many people who are here who are not um posting there and
realize oh it's a wonderful group thank you
um
so yeah again I feel a little bit reluctant to speak I feel quite content
sitting here and quiet inside and what is there to
say sometimes silence is more useful than
and speaking we are doing gratitude this
week so grateful for all of you grateful to be able to sit here and reflect and feel and sense
what's happening in this way and um so to begin our
meditation um gratitude is not just something
to think of the mind it's also not just something to feel of the heart it's also something
of the body and sometimes we Express
gratitude with a sometimes a handshake sometimes a bow sometimes um a
smile sometimes offering a gift to someone a small gratitude
gift and it's possible to think think of the meditation posture you're sitting
in as a posture of gratitude and you might want to take a
little care about how you sit right now and maybe sway back and forth a little
bit forward and back just to kind of limber up and and then kind of come back
into whatever posture that is your posture to do so with the idea that now
this is the posture of gratitude it's a very special thing anybody's meditation posture where
they're standing walking sitting lying
down but what it would be like if this posture was the expression of
gratitude a thankfulness and sometimes it doesn't
have to be for anything there can just must be a Thank A A
gratitude just because it's what dwells up from within or gratitude to be able to
practice it's one of the great things in a human life to have a spiritual
practice to have a practice of Liberation so to to this practice
grateful for it it's almost like a reciprocal thing
that we take this posture to practice and we're grateful for the
practice which then helps shape our
posture gently closing your
eyes and what if gratitude now in meditation is a quiet shy gentle
quality within and H how would you Orient
yourself how would you settle yourself how would you listen to yourself
sense so you can be attuned to something that's
quiet deep
settled it's already here under the layers of agitation
preoccupation difficult feelings you might be having to allow
yourself the thinking mind to become quieter so you can
attend care for be with yourself
as a as your best friend be with
yourself as a good spiritual friend that will
listen to you know attend you as you are listening to
what's deep
within and if breathing is a comfortable place for
meditation to breathe with that quiet
depth to breathe out of it and return to
it and if there's no quiet depth in
you then be focused more on how you're mindful how
you attend to yourself to see if you can be the
quiet
companion who accepts you as you are feels you as you are and gets to know
you as you are in whatever way you are
and perhaps what you are then is grateful to have such a
companion sitting here together in a
posture attitude orientation to a quiet
gratitude for now here
practicing
for e
e e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to lead you through a little gratitude
meditation as you sit here lay here stand
here in your
body the whole of who you are includes your
body isn't that you have a body so much as you are a body physical
body you our body mind heart all
together and a huge part of this body that
meditating is made of
water made from the waters comes from the Waters of this
Earth the rivers streams and lakes and oceans
over a lifetime so much of the Waters of the world have passed through
you have had a home in you have been
you and to be grateful for Waters grateful for how incredibly important
water is for our life our body our being
acknowledging appreciating
water as something to be thankful
for another big part of this human body is all the mole molecules made of carbon
where carbon life and all the carbon that makes us
up is a form of solidified
air the carbon dioxide in the air is converted into by photosynthesis by
plants into some molecules that then become
carbon molecules that holds our body together builds the
body and to be grateful for the air thank
you in a sense the air that we don't
see becomes a solidified air that we do
see and then together with the carbon molecules were made up of
minerals that come from the earth and if you mostly eat local
food part of you is comprised of the Earth in your
area with International Trade we're made up of the Earth from all over the world
thank you to the earth the earth that supports Us in so
many ways thank
you and then there's the Sun the
fire that burns quietly for us far away lighting
the days
the light that's converted to boto Senses Into the carbon molecules that
are the source of sugars and source of our
energy that passes through carbonized molecules to be
released as little little sunlights in our body little electricity through our
nerve nervous system thank you son the big one and
the Teeny ones of electrons in our body wow thank
you and then there's the wonderful wondrous capacity that Evolution has
given us slowly steadily all our different capacities
for attention for sensing feeling knowing
recognizing being aware somehow the dynamic processes of
life that brought us this the capacity to be aware to think and to
know thank you all the life processes that brought this into being that we
share in this wonderful wondrous way that we are the universe knowing
itself thank
you and then there's space when we walk through this
world it's because there's empty space that we can walk
empty space makes possible walking and talking and communicating
and doing things moving around moving our fingers and
hands in the same way we have to have space within us space in
our body and our mind in our hearts for all that moves within
us and we offer often fill the space with thoughts and preoccupations and our
pre our focus on the emotional life our suffering our pains our
successes but we have a practice that allows us to give space to live in a
spaciousness that makes so much possible so much more
possible than for hemmed in by our thoughts and thank you
space thank you earth
water air fire
awareness and space always here with
us to be grateful for all that sustains our life
Moment by moment so that we're better
equipped to be with the difficulties and sufferings of this
life may us may we touch into love compassion
good will care is a
culmination of all that sustains our life may we be
grateful for whatever capacity we have for a
kindhearted heart thank
you and may we bring this kindness Good Will into the
world to benefit everyone may all beings be
[Music]
happy thank you for
so hello and welcome to this third talk on gratitud
ude and I present a little bit about the different aspects dynamics of gratitude
which I've called the Ecology of thankfulness gratitude and begins with uh there is
the cognitive aspect of appreciating something and acknowledging it and part
of what the Buddhist Buddhism that the word for the one of the words for
gratitude is um can kind of be more more literally be translated to English is
acknowledgement acknowledgement of what has been done for us and then there's the thankfulness
which is the feeling that and to allow ourselves to feel and there's a way in which allowing
taking in taking a moment taking a minute taking a year taking a lifetime
to take in uh uh the experience the feeling of
well-being that comes from gratitude comes from thankfulness to open up to it to to be
let it register and one of the reasons to do it is not for just
to indulge in those feelings but rather it becomes more whole that way the
Gratitude and so when we say thank you or we bow uh there's much more
embodiment behind it much more here and so there's more that's offered in
return uh if I just kind of keep walking and and wave my hand you know thank you
um I mean I don't know if that's going to really going to touch someone else it's not going to you know it's kind of
like incidental and Casual almost like a um you know unimportant you know kind you know just kind of bark out thank you
you know thanks but to stop with someone and maybe even hold their hands and say
thank you though you have to be careful who you do that with but you know to really stop and bow a little bit even if
you don't put your hands together thank you so so to really feel it so it can be
embodied and then the part I want to emphasize today is expressing gratitude
if this is a extremely important thing again not only for the person you're
saying thank you to but I believe it's important for us that uh this is one of the things I learned from my years of
monastic practice that um there's something about deep appreciation deep
welling up of gratitude that happened to me uh day after day but all the
meditation I did and there was something about the experience the goodness the well-being of meditation that I felt so
grateful so appreciative that it felt like it there was something inside of me
that needed to express it otherwise it was bottled up it was restricted it
didn't really have a life it couldn't be F come to its fullness and so one of the
reasons I like to bow at the end of meditation whenever I meditate is that
um it gives a life it gives acknowledgement it allows a movement
that's happening inside of me to live and uh and have its fulfillment and
that's the that's the Deep feeling of appreciation of gratitude and in return I think it also
then changes me inculcates or it kind of uh kind of reinforces that side of
myself and um and so after my years of monastic practice uh we did a lot of
bowing and it didn't always want to bow it wasn't always out of appreciation but after a while it was something about
putting my hands together and bowing even when I didn't want to it had an
effect on me it was a gratitude posture that kind of little drop by drop
actually did do something to me and by the time I left the in at the monastery we always bowed to each other whenever
we passed each other and uh when I left the monastery after three years I was
walking down the street in in the city of Berkeley nearby and um and I was you
know the first day out of the monastery I was passing all these people on the sidewalk and I just wanted to bow to
them all but you know they were strangers and I think that would be weird and then luckily I saw across the
street down the street someone had had visited the monastery at some point during the summer and I went running
after her and said you know I think I kind of said stop stop wait wait and um
it was really I just wanted to have someone to bow to and uh who I could express my gratitude for just you know
just all these people for the people I was there and give it life so to express it Express gratitude
so certainly to do it with a thank you and words um but let the words be
embodied not just kind of like casual stop and do it say it with you know in a
in a good way and fullness of it there is also um so it's not just the words
but it's also the gestures you use so you know and people who don't know about
bowing you don't want to do that to you that maybe it's weird for them but you know a little nod a stopping and looking
at them there's um uh you know some movement of the hand that's expresses
something maybe just sometimes thank you kind of opening your your hands wide
um um the old days men would tip their hat hats that Express a little bit more of a gesture of
something and um so what's the gesture what's the embodiment of it could be
stopping physically and turning towards the person say thank you these are wonderful uh photographs and videos of
the Daly Lama uh going over to people who he sees and bowing and holding their
hands and just completely with them for those few minutes like they're the most important person I don't know if he's
expressing gratitude UD but there's something deep he's because he's really there the has changed so many people
just by how he greets people and then
um um the um you might want to give
something there's something called the Gratitude gift and uh sometimes you know
later so I want to thank you for what you did for me and here here's a small gift not not a big gift that makes
people obligated to return or but uh you know you know something we bake
something and give them here's i b I bake this for you it's please or or you
know here some flowers I want to thank you for the favor you did me the support you did or that little expression of
gratitude so it's more embodi and fing makes so much more that goes
on and um and then the the other thing I think
about is sometimes it's useful to go out of your way to say thank you um uh show
up go see someone you know and um and walk up to them and say I just wanted to
take the time to say thank you it's clear you're going out of your way you go into their office you walk down the
hall and I'm here to just to say thank you thank you or to go uh to a neighbor
and just knock on the door and say you know I just want to say thank you for yesterday it was really nice to be be
invited over for dinner it was really nice and doesn't have to be a gift it just you know that's that's all I wanted
to say and uh so to go out of your way so again so it's something deeper in it
it's not just a casual thank you it's like we're investing we're doing something and what I'd like to
suggest is that this way of really living in gratitude is a way of um
letting the love or gratitude or the the the uh D Dynamic aspect of Human
Relationships in a healthy way to flow the something cycles of giving and
receiving gratitude and generosity it just keeps flowing and moving just
like all the elements within us the water that we have comes and goes water
that in us now probably some water molecules were there of the Buddha of
of uh the you know all kinds of wonderful compassionate people in the
past wonderful you know so much the it keeps flowing out of us our water in
house now will probably be in some other human being or animal or being um in the
future thousands millions of years and we want to just keep it flowing keep it
moving keep it going smoothly and so it is with our the Human Relationships the Dynam
dynamism of Love of care of friendship keep it flowing and um and uh one of the
ways to do that is uh to Express gratitude and sometimes when we neglect
to do that something stops it you know stops with us and maybe it never
continues again and um so keep it going pass it on through how you say Thank
you so for all of you thank you very much for
today and I'll be here tomorrow in United States it's a
holiday and Friday and we'll do continue this topic of gratitude thank you