good evening everyone as I mentioned at the beginning of the sit um Diana's off teaching a
retreat so I'll be filling in for her tonight my name is Jim
pulski um if you've been following the talk
over the last maybe five or six weeks Diana's been talking about some of the
characteristics or um qualities that are required
to uh achieve a goal you know what what things you need if you really want to
achieve something um I think in particular she's talking about achieving uh freedom from
suffering you know freedom from greed delusion and
hatred a sense of Peace sense of
calm and one of the elements one of those five elements she talked about was
uh energy or effort that it it takes some uh energy or effort if you want to
accomplish something she often reads some poetry I
don't have any but when I think about a song that I know from my youth um you
won't get it wishing and a hoping thinking and a praying so just wishing and hoping and
thinking and praying won't get you uh to where you want to go it does
take effort
um the the Buddha's primary teachings about how to do this are encompassed in
what's known as the eight-fold path and one of them is called right
effort or wise effort or skillful effort um and so that's what I want to
talk about tonight it just so happens that IMC has a nine-month program about
the eight-fold path and this month actually this coming Sunday there'll be
a a half day uh event here all about uh
right effort so if you're interested in finding out more about this uh it's
available both in person and online um but it's the
first first of the three elements of the path having to do with uh cultivating
heart and mind so one of the books for that class
is this one called the eight mindful steps of Happiness by bonti
gunaratna and I've read it uh a couple of times in fact I was just going
through the chapter uh on uh right
effort um over the weekend uh in preparation for this
Sunday and
it's it's part of the practice that isn't well I don't think any of the
practice is relegated to just the times when you're doing formal sitting
practice but uh right effort is definitely something that you can do
throughout the day as long as you're awake
conscious um it's a way to
cultivate uh states of heart and mind that are skillful for achieving freedom
from suffering and for um weeding out those states that
um aren't helpful so uh skillful effort you could
think of as a little bit of way of um mental
gardening it's how do you how do you water and nourish
and um tend to those things that you want to grow and how do you uh uproot
the weeds the things that um get in way that sap the energy from your garden
so there's four skillful
efforts the first one is um preventing the arising of
unisen negative states of mind so if you can catch if you can
catch yourself before one of these things arises um
then you don't have to go through and experience
that it's easier said than done so the second one is
um is abandoning Arisen unskillful states of mind so once
they're there what do you do what do you do with
them uh the third skillful effort
is um
is bringing into being unisen skillful States so how do you cultivate how do
you uh recognize that this might be a time where you can bring forth a
wholesome State how would you do that and then
the fourth one is maintaining an Arisen wholesome state so once it's Arisen what
do you do to keep it going so I'll share some of the things
that uh Bounty good aratana has written uh and some of the things that
over the years I've um acquired either from other teachers or from direct
experience you know what works for doing this uh preventing the
UNH wholesome abandoning the UNH whome once it's Arisen uh bringing into being unisen
wholesome and maintaining the wholesome so the first thing would be
knowing what are these like how do you know what what are wholesome and what are UNH
wholesome
the at a deep deep level there's these it said the the
Buddha said there are these 10 Fetters there's these 10 habits of mind and
perception that keep us FedEd to suffering keep
us um
you know kind of not really seeing things clearly
um and those are things that take some period of time I would
imagine years or decades although some people maybe it's only days or weeks but
I I suspect for most it's it's a long-term practice to see these these
feds and um uproot them in the shorter
term the um there's
five uh conditions or five uh activities of
the Mind called the hindrances which are described as the intense gross manifestations of the
feds so I'm guessing at least some of you have heard heard of the the five
hindrances um if you haven't there's this wonderful book that Gil fransal
wrote a few years ago called unfettered that descri both describes them and
describes particular practices you might do to um work with them get get to know
them and over time uh uh reduce them or
get free of them so the the five feds the first one
is um greed or lust
so I would imagine most people would have some notion on what that is you know that it isn't just desire it isn't
just wanting but it's that maybe compulsive obsessive
uh grasping after something often a sense experience but it could also be um
an object or it might be some kind of identity you know some way that you want to be
seen and so that's one of the hindrances that kind of distorts our perception of
what's going on you know everything is kind of colored or flavored by that
hindrance and so it's one place to start is not by saying
okay I'm never gonna I'm never gonna lust again I'm never goingon to have greet again but
rather to really get to know it get familiar with it how does you know how does it
feel um and what are the
conditions under which it
arises so knowing knowing that is very
helpful in doing this practice um I I'll say essential I mean
I I don't think that you can say I'm I'm going to practice the Buddhist
path and become enlightened but I'm not going to look at greed and
lust it's it's there so you might as well make a you know kind of a conscious
decision that that's something to look at the second one is
uh uh sometimes called um aversion or ill will hatred you know that movement
towards pushing away um
but pushing in away in an unskillful way either not not
acknowledging that it's operating
um you know or or having some kind of Judgment of or
opinion about either some sense desire or some person or some object or some
identity that you're trying to get rid of that
um you know doesn't well that you're trying to get
rid of by Contracting your mind around rather than looking at it carefully just
there's some contraction and some pushing and not really acknowledging
so those are the first two hindrances they're probably the uh often the strongest the third
hindrance is actually described as a pair of hindrances um sloth and torper now those
are words that I suspect none of you use in everyday language it's kind of Old
English what they point at is a certain sluggishness a certain
dullness a certain um kind of low energy that's either in
the body or in the mind so the two one refers to sluggishness of the body one
refers to sluggishness of the mind and when
you're um when those are operating you know it's kind of
like you know trying to walk through a thick mud or something you know it's
just it's it's very slowo and
um hard to see clearly so that's often referred to as
sinking energy the fourth hindrance
is um restlessness and worry so again it's a pair kind of like sloth and
torper it's energy that's fairly high energy
but scattered so restlessness is a physical manifestation of that kind of
uh scattered energy and uh worry is the
mental manifestation of that scattered energy so it's
not just that there's a lot of energy there it's also that it's it's really kind of of all over the
place it's not collected it's not
unified and then the fifth hindrance is doubt
um I've tried to come up with a way a good way for myself to understand that
one and I think one way to describe it is a tendency to just keep self second
guessing yourself like oh should I do this well no maybe I should do it this way know me you know it's it's kind of
like never centering on
one um one track now it isn't that it isn't useful
there there's times when you have to say okay I've I've been I've been following a certain path and this doesn't look
right so it's it's time to maybe try something different but when the mind is continually jumping
around um always second guessing itself that's
that's one way to describe doubt and when that's happening then it's hard to
be mindful you know it's like well what's going on right now no you know maybe this is maybe this is sloth maybe
this is uh aversion so those are the the five
hindrances um ill will uh no sorry uh lust ill will sloth
and torper uh restlessness and worry and doubt and within and you can think of
those as sort of like a basis set that all the
other um descriptions of unh wholesome mind States kind of fit
within one of those five categories
so so it's it's helpful to in starting this to become familiar with the
hindrances get to know them particularly how they work for
you um so if we move from so the hindrances are
really what you're going to be looking for in the first two uh elements of of um right
effort and so to prevent the arising of
unisen H UNH wholesome mind States it's helpful to know
what are the conditions what are the triggers what how can I recognize
that an UNH wholesome mind state lies ahead and do something
differently um the example that came to my mind was
I've now been managing here at IMC on Monday nights for 25
years and I live in Mountain View so I've always had to drive on Highway 101
to get here in the early evening and for many years I would get
on the freeway I'd drive a couple tents of a mile and then the traffic would just stop it's right where Highway
85 comes into 101 and I would immediately feel
frustration and you know a sense of um
you know why is this happening to me
and over time you know it suddenly dawned to me well number one I'd often
have not eaten supper so my blood sugar was low I was kind of tired low
energy um I'd often try to cut it close you
know like not leave any earlier than I had to so then
if there was any hold up I'd be feeling anxious about getting there so there were some conditions that I recognized
that um I had control over you know things that I could do in terms of eating in
terms of timing
um other things that I didn't have any control over and then the other thing
that I had some influence over was
um how I related to the experience that was going on when I looked at it as
something bad happening to me it would really cause suffering you
know it's like it's like these people are sitting in their cars why aren't
they driving you know and you know don't they know I need to be
somewhere so one of the things that I found was changing my attitude towards
the whole experience of okay this is this is an opportunity to practice
patience or this is an opportunity to feel compassion for all the other
drivers that are in the exact same place that I am you know it's not it's not like they don't all have places to
go um so there so over
time after a number of years how too many for me to want to uh
confess I came to realize
that um that I knew that there were
conditions I could change the time that I left the amount that I ate also the my
expectation you know my it was kind of like I had an expectation that I should
be able to do it in 20 to 25 minutes and sometimes I could but sometimes it took
45 minutes so changing that expectation of this is the way life is supposed to
go to um uh you know getting in the car and going
I don't know how long it's going to take so why don't I go early and you know get
a hot chocolate at pizza or
something yeah so so I don't think you can really do
the first element of preventing until you've spent enough time in the second
one of being in the UNH wholesome States and getting to know them and getting to
know what are what are the causes and conditions what
um what are the flags that I can see you know it might be that
um uh if you're going to have a difficult conversation with somebody it might be that there's some times of the
day that you're just more stable and clearheaded than other times you know so
getting to know uh your own heart and mind is helpful in
that first uh
element uh the second one of abandoning Arisen un wholesome
States uh can be more difficult because you're
already in it you're you know like when the mindfulness Cuts back in or you start to
pay attention you might find oh okay well now I'm really really angry or
I'm uh you know really
um anxious or Restless or what whatever it
is and so
the there there's kind of five strategies that the Buddha laid out and
I'm sure there's other ones that you can probably come up with for yourself for when you find yourself in
one of these uh unskillful
States um the first one is if it's not very strong you may be able to just
ignore it that doesn't mean pretend it's it doesn't mean to not
know that it's happening to not be mindful but rather to decide okay I'm
not going to get involved with it like it's there
I know it's operating but I don't need to get involved in it just kind of ignore it and for some
unskillful uh states that can work you know it's
just um I was in a car once with with two people that
were having an argument about or trying to decide who is to
blame for something and I realized it
was kind of a worthless argument I mean like there was no reason for me to even
offer an opinion or say anything because it just was like yeah I doesn't it
doesn't seem like it would lead anywhere useful so sometimes you can just ignore
it but still be mindful so this is not a
delusion uh the second one is to divert your attention
so um like when I'm sitting in my car and the traffic's not moving
rather than kind of watching every single movement of the car and wondering if okay well now we're starting to move
a little bit maybe this is going to be it you know maybe it's over I could just turn on the radio and listen to
classical music you know and just let that be a more soothing satisfying
experience than um getting caught up
in wondering when the traffic's going to start moving
again so that's a little bit more so there's ignoring it there's diverting
your attention there's replacing the hindrance with its op opposite
quality so each one of those five
hindrances you could imagine has some opposite to it you know so uh lust and
greed might be um renunciation generosity you know instead
of trying to get something just giving it away um or recognizing
that trying to hold on to it isn't doing you any good
so uh that's one thing that comes to my mind for being the the opposite of um
greed and Lust For ill will and hatred aversion is uh
Goodwill you know um loving kindness
um wishing well uh offering people uh
harmlessness and safety um let's see sloth and torper I
guess the opposite of that would be bringing some bright energy
uh maybe through investigation Joy uh Restless restlessness and worry
would be you know bringing some can you find somewhere in your
experience a feeling of uh calm and
collectedness and um
peacefulness and uh one of the things that comes to me for
the opposite of Doubt would be some sense of confidence or
trust um
Faith so so that's one of the ways in is
to actually recognize what's happening and see if you
can bring some of the opposite to
it um the next one is it says to reason
with yourself to really examine what are the downsides of being
in this state what you know how does it feel where's it going to lead is this is
this how I want to live my life and so sometimes just bringing the
mind and the reasoning to the experience may help you recognize that um this
isn't something that you want to feed energy into and the last one and this this is
one I've actually gotten some push back from psychologists um is to crush it with all
your might so sometimes if it's just you know it's
just uh Beyond be Beyond ignoring or diverting
or replacing or reasoning you just just use your will
like no I'm not going there now I think the difference is this doesn't mean
repression in the sense that you're pretending as though it's not
that that impulse is is there you know it's
there but part of you knows I'm not going to give in this
impulse so I think of things
where you're ready to do some sort of um damage physical damage or
violence um I
think if you're mindful it it could be a really really strong
desire to take your coffee cup and throw it across the room or so you know or
something like that but just knowing I'm not going to do that so
that's kind of the the the last option that the Buddha
gave and I think it's also maybe one of the least effective so I don't I
think as you cultivate with time you hopefully won't H get there that often
but there may be times when you just need to
um not give in to a very strong
impulse um so some other thoughts um to prevent
negative thoughts from arising maintain mindful
so your mind is always going to be doing something you're always going to have
some sort of State going on so with mindfulness at the very least
you can know what that state is you know kind of be aware not just a name for it
but what it feels like um the emotion associated with it
and then mindfulness combined with um wisdom kind of that knowing
it uh patience and effort can help you uh both prevent and
abandon the UNH wholesome
States uh some of the other advice on this is
the longer that you wait to notice it the stronger it may get so there's a
real value to noticing these unskillful states sooner
rather than later you know like not after a full-blown argument
like oh huh I guess I was angry you know but noticing it before you say the first
word is is is that M much better than after the last word has been
said so then the the last two
the the bringing into being of wholesome States uh wasn't talked as much about in
this book but there's several that come to mind
number one is practicing the Brahma baharas so loving kindness compassion
practice sympathetic joy and Equanimity those are all those are
four practices that you can read about there there's a book called loving kindness by uh Sharon
saltzburg and and others I mean it's it's it's a it's a heavily traveled
topic and so that's something that you can do
either in a period of loving kind in in a period of
meditation or just anytime throughout the day I usually try to do a little bit
before I get out of bed in the morning there was one practice that uh
somebody taught me that when you're waiting in the airport to get on the plane you can just wish well for all of
these Str strangers that are walking by on The Concourse like they're people you've never seen before you'll probably
never see them again but can you just like wish them well like oh yeah you know may you may you be safe you know
may you be happy may you be healthy may you be peaceful
um I think it's a much more productive practice than sitting and
reading a magazine uh you know so it's or or listening to the news on the big you
know television screens in the waiting room in the uh waiting area so there's so those are practices
that you can do for uh creating uh wholesome States if they're
not Arisen um there's a whole series of practices
called the uh parames um that are foundational
practices uh for this so things like practicing
generosity um you know practicing patience
determination uh ethics uh
renunciation these are all practices that you can do
um the don't necessarily immediately create the state that you
want but they set the conditions for it so for example if you're doing uh loving
kindness practice Mata there's phrases that you can uh
create for yourself and you know sometimes you you say the phrases and it
just doesn't seem like much is happening but it's creating the conditions for
um for wishing well for others for yourself
and for others and then so there are practices
that you can do um and that you can make part of your
everyday life for
um um bringing into being on aisen State
on un arisen and wholesome States and then maintaining
them there's the suggestion at least in this book and I and I I wholeheartedly agree
with it is um gathering with likeminded friends and
reading Buddhist texts so finding other people that you can that
are interested in this that you can talk to that
um share the challenges that they're facing you know
um you know that um that support you and that you support
in cultivating wholesome states of mind
um I'm in a group that meets once a week on Thursday uh Tuesday
nights where we we talk about our practice with each
other there another group I meet meet with once a month we do the same thing and then I come here and I get a
chance to talk to uh people that show up um and I usually have a you know at
least some kind of conversation with whoever's teaching that night
um about what came up for me in the course of the
evening it doesn't necessarily need to be even another Buddhist practitioner I
mean there are people in other who follow other
paths that also want to
cultivate um kindness harmlessness uh freedom
and so uh you know you might find a a family
member or a friend or a coworker somebody you other people that will
um help you maintain some of these wholesome
States
um cuz it isn't to use a common phrase it isn't one or done it isn't like okay now now
I've cultivated love and kindness I don't need to do that anymore
the mind has a tendency to go back to the habits it's had over a long period
of time so it's a it's a long-term project to keep moving your
awareness from these um
uh afflictive states to ones that are
uh peaceful and free
so I hope that was useful to you all um we've got a few minutes if anyone
wants to ask any
questions or make comments or sure A girlfriend of mine said Janet
you're talking negatively again everybody could hear that well there's people online oh Janet you're talking
negatively again she reminded me of that last night I thought oh no I need her
around me more often to remind me that I'm doing that
it's thank you um um just a comment uh your anecdote about uh your commute 101
was uh reminding me of of a quote I read online I think it was like a systems engineer or something discussion um but
a lot of people like to say oh I'm stuck in traffic right they tell others and
the quote went something like uh the reality is you're not in traffic you are
traffic exactly and it got me thinking about that so wanted to share that thank
you thank you yeah that's right it's you know you are you are part of it it isn't
something that's happening to
you when I'm in one of those negative States
I uh I think of think of it as could you hold hold it yeah think of it as time to
weather the storm so you know I'll recognize it you know allow
it maybe be with it a bit and then then it fades
away eventually hopefully sooner rather than later yeah but yeah all right well
part part of this practice is if you recognize it you can the very least open your
umbrella I mean you you know you don't have
to you have some valtion in what happens so anyway thank you for
that
okay well it's just about 8:30 so I'll thank you all for coming tonight and
um I'll encourage you to may all your effort be
skillful