so um yeah good day good morning good
day it's good to be with you all this
week yeah thank you for letting me know this is sometimes a easy to forget
um for [Music]
I have the sense that uh quietly seeing the chat messages flowing in really have
the sense of kind of meeting you all uh
think some um kind of mysterious ways
yeah so we'll start
um we're coming to uh the last session of this week uh this 5
days we've been exploring the Sim of the
five Aggregates and today uh were culminating um at the last
one which is um about this aggregate of
Consciousness or uh the poly term is uh Vaya um the translation is consciousness
uh often it's a hard to know exactly what
the Consciousness is um and many people are
still kind of exploring reflecting about this
and and I also don't know exactly what Consciousness is and and yet um the
Buddha is pointing out to something we can know
um what I will say is that we can know there is an aspect of the human capacity
that is able to know uh experiences in different domains
so for example oh we hear a sound you're hearing sound right now and you know
there sound and um maybe you feel
temperature and there is a Consciousness that knows that and um maybe there are some tactile
Sensations in the body and there is something that knows that and so there
is this different domains of capacities that's able to
know in this range in this different ranges of our experience um you know
often in the Buddhism we speak about the six sense uh context that's are kind of
a six domains of experiences that we all have and there is this Consciousness
that kind of can Spotlight on the experience and get to know that get to
know the experience and the Buddha kind of has
this a Mastery of um using Sim um used magicians
Illusions as the way to describe how this aggregate of
Consciousness works I to say it feels like you know in the
magician show um they Spotlight on different things and then it gets lit up
and you see them and they got put together in some way
um that captures um people's audience
mind in a way that's a little bit like how the
Consciousness work at the spotlight for our experiences to
be known and then being a cleaning aggregate we can get pulled into
them and so we'll practice with this and then we'll uh explore this um uh this
assimile in some more details so let's sit I'm going to uh start the Bell
[Music]
coming into a meditative posture
again entering into this Temple
within a metaphor I've been using this
week entering the Temple of this body mind and heart
just like entering into the temple we're not in a big
rush or arriving at a Here and
Now where the kindness where the rist
back with the pace that allow us to
settle maybe it's this momentary
mindfulness being present with the
sound the global sense of the body sitting or lying down
there is no rush to get to
anywhere or steady
one moment of mindfulness and
another and another
at some point you may find
yourself studying
in a kind of
presence a continuous stream of
mindfulness maybe a kind of resting
in the field of
knowing and the experiences began to emerge
from this field of
knowing movements of the breath
Sensations in the
body being available
it's a mindful knowing itself doesn't have to move
it's available
you can start with the embodied experience
the flow of the
breath is
known as the flow of the breath
happens and there is also a Consciousness that can
know the moving
breath it's like the
spotlight lights up
the sound emerges it's
SN either the
Consciousness lit
up Sensations in the body
are know lit
up e
the floating thoughts are
know L
up repos or waves of emotion are
known and lit
up e
then drop a below the narratives the
stories staying with the felt
sense e
when you're [Music] resting in the quiet
quiet peaceful field of mindfulness mindful
awareness you can begin to feel and to
see how the different sense
Consciousness are lit up
one moment of a sound to a moment of
sensation a moment of a mental
activity like a dazzling magician's uion
husary
e e
when the mind is not pulled
into a magic show
a natural disenchantment and the
dispassion can become
available or maybe a sense of mind and heart
resting deeper
within quiet peaceful
undisturbed by the movements of the heart and
mind or in the body
like a still flowing
water
e
for
e e
each of the five BND five
Aggregates the humanly processes that way being exploring this
week can be seen
felt just as they are the foaminess of the
body the water bubbles of the feelings
a perceptions like a
mirage the forces of a mental activities that likes to
construct
realities and The Magicians
Illusions a spotlight of the
Consciousness they are just what they are
by seeing them as they are we shift and change our
relationships with
them we can soften and loosening up our
grip the cleaning of this few humanly
processes and offer our respect and
care for what they
are for
[Music]
so I'd like to read this part of the sutta this last
assim from the Samaya it says suppose
practitioners that a magician or a Magician's Apprentice would display a ma
magical illusion at a Crossroads a man with good sight to
change a person with good sight would inspect it ponder it and carefully
investigate it and it would appear to them to be void Hollow sub
insubstantial for what substance would there be in a magical
illusion so to practitioners whatever kind of
Consciousness there is whether past future present internal or external
gross or subtle inferior or Superior far or near a practitioner
inspects it Ponders it and carefully
investigate it and it would appear to them to be void Hollow
insubstantial for what substance would there be in consciousness
and so I just I really love this similes and I don't know what's in Buddhist
mind and how he relates sees um this
kind of humanly processes and you know but the way that
he's articulating it uh using similes are so powerful right and if we just
imagine ourselves in the magic show that magicians are using all kinds of props
to capture the audience attention sound smell visual you know all of this and
and it's in the midst of the dazzling movements that the magician creates an
illusion of something a rabbit comes out of an empty
hat or a person is cut up in half in an enclosed the box and Etc and
Etc and The Magicians are utilizing their understanding of kind of
some of this humanly processes uh to uh create this kind
of Illusions right but then for us we
know you know this is a magic show so it's Elusive and we don't really believe
them so much we're just having a good time you know we're getting captured by
uh the effects of them and so
um and this is is such a wonderful simile to
illustrate how this aggregate of a Consciousness might
work that when all of this different dimension of Consciousness gets lit up
and the moment after another and the a Sanara that we talked about yesterday
can begin to create something real for us like a magical
illusion except that we don't quite always see it that way we see it quite
real and we get um hooked by the content
of the illusion and the you know dream like thing but when we're in the present
moment we can began to tease apart and see
oh this is not as substantial or as real as I had
thought there is a very famous uh line in the uh Chinese Sutra called The
Diamond Sutra then it says something like all conditioned the phenomenon are like
a dream an illusion a bubble a shadow
like a de or a flash of
lightning that gets kind of you know pointing to um similar aspect of our experience
the conditioned experience I remember many years ago I
went to to an outlet um on the Thanksgiving day you
know shopping day and when I got to the parking lot I got out of the
car there was so many people and the the stores were dazzling with lights and
sounds and very strong smells and you know fragrance and it just very load up
you know loaded up and for a few moments I remember
standing there I felt so disorienting it's really this kind of
elusive feeling and I thought to myself is this really
real what's really real you know so I ended up getting one thing
from a store and immediately left I I I I can't remember doing the Thanksgiving
shopping after that that again
so and so this is the elusive nature of uh this Aggregate and and the Buddha
seems to have a real kind of insight and immediate experience of how this
works and this uh m magic illusion has
two aspects um that I felt like was being pointed out that one is that um
one can see through the magic Illusions and become disenchanted and not so
interested in it and yet magic show being magic show they also have this
alluring quality to it so people get hooked by them the
Illusions gets real and so that's that that forces the V Sankara that can come
in and pull us into it and
sometimes we end up and maybe a lot of times so when we're not paying attention
to what's happening we end up living in the movies that we're constructing for
ourselves
and through this practice what can happen is that um the
Buddha also knows when we begin to see through and unpack see through teas
apart seeing uh the uh as is Natures of this
kind of humanly phenomenon there is a natural arising or
natural um emergence of disinterest in
them and so can say oh this is just how it is you know how much more can I watch
this can I get hooked by the magic show you know after you watch it for a while
there is a natural disinterest in them and so this is later on what the
sutta began to point out that one naturally get disenchanted in them and
dispassionate and eventually that alluring effect
that attachment that is there began to soften and
loosen and maybe dropped released momentarily
and so you may all have had experiences like this and what becomes available to us is
this deeper kind of a peace and a well-being that's there that is not
based on being stimulated by all of our sense
Consciousness sense contact they can still be functioning
those are the functional uh capacities of a human
beings but the clinging to them the attachment to them and that the
um uh ongoing kind of a construction based on the Illusions
began to soften began to loosen
up and that's the power of a practicing um uh with the immediacy of
our experience so I like to read um the last
verses of the suas maybe as a way to
inspire or um you know cheer up uh
through the practice for all of us and so this is what the Buddha said uh at the final
verses says a practitioner with energy aroused
should look upon the Aggregates thus and that is you know he used the words avoid
Hollow insubstantial and just as they are whether by day or at night
comprehending ever mindful they should discard all the
feeds as cleaning attachments and the make take a refuge
for themselves let them fear as with aead a
blaze yearning for the imparable
state I don't know quite how we relate to the last words it feels pretty uh uh
dramatic but maybe I will soften this by inviting
us um to practice when with um care and
respect for a Being Human for the humanly
processes and really allow ourselves to soak in the in the immediacy of our
experience and let that inform us let them guide us in this
way and so may this week's practice and um
Dharma reflections benefit ourselves and benefit all beings
everywhere thank you friends have a wonderful rest of the day
[Music]