start over again with the welcome you all and and uh to tell you that I'm happy to
be back here at doing this uh morning teaching and meditating with you all all
of you and uh the theme I'd like
to uh or the reference point I'd like to offer for this meditation is one of the
probably one of the most fundamental if the fundamental Buddhist principle which is
nonharming and to uh to live with
nonharming to um uh but in terms of meditation to
meditate in a way that is non-harming that meditation itself can be seen as the continual Act of
non-harming and in meditation the chances of harming others uh are small
as we meditate maybe we neglect people sometimes and that's can be harmful but uh the primary person that
we're being harmless towards in meditation is ourselves and part of meditation then is
a not only continual Act of non-harming but the deepening
sensitivity to what non-harming is for ourselves
so that uh we're orienting ourselves to see and understand all the ways subtle
and not so subtle that we are self Haring in
meditation and to shift that to a way of meditating
that is non-harming and uh and many meditators
don't think of their meditation from in this with this reference point but in the the course of deepening and
deepening their meditation uh uh either uh consciously or not so consciously uh the idea of
living with nonharming becomes more and more a theme and so in meditation it can be
something as simple as um being angry with ourselves because we're not getting
concentrated in being critical of ourselves because of what we're thinking or that we're
distracting it can be a striving to uh uh to want to attain some great
attainment and then very striving there's a tension a stress level that uh
you can feel that it's kind of causing stress causing harm to ourselves pain
suffering and so uh to be very attentive that the way that we come back
from the Mind wondering off that we don't jerk the Mind back as it's you know like a like a violent tug or
something but we do so in a non-harming way we we gently bring the Mind back we
invite the Mind back we settle the Mind back or we invite the breath back to the
breathing back to the Mind back to attention so that in some way it is um
uh you know we're not caused adding stress by the way in which we meditate the um you know sometimes we
there's physical disc comfort and to tough it out to somehow um think stoically that I have
to kind of just bear the pain is a is a kind of self harm sometimes there's pain that we feel
inspired in a very wise way to use the pain to develop our
meditation to develop ourselves to grow in our capacity for equinity and self-
understanding and then it may then it uh it might not be a form of self har to sit with a pain uh we're not injuring
ourselves with it but we we are learning and growing and in a in a very
beneficial way that serves us in many places in our lives so so for this meditation to uh
reflect as you do it that how you meditate that it's a nonharming way and
maybe even better it's the opposite it's uh of harm it's um you know it's
beneficial it's uh conducive to peace to to conducive to the kind of deep calm or
a kind of uh delightful sense that um confidence in oneself that no matter how
the meditation goes that uh we're not going to respond in a way that adds stress to our
system so to um to
gently lower your gaze or close your
eyes and to readjust your posture a
bit and gently taking some long slow deep breaths not too long not too deep
comfortably
so and relaxing on the exhale
and letting your breathing return to
normal and then in a global simple
way become aware of how you are sitting
here how you are
meditating is it a peaceful
stance a peaceful way of how you are or could you carry with you stress
tensions maybe even hostilities from the day from the week
from a
lifetime and if there is do not be in conflict with that not
to add stress to it but let the awareness that knows
it be a nonharming awareness that has
space to know to
feel in which the knowing of it all
awareness of it all is a nonharming
awareness an attitude of being
present in a simple peaceful
way that also disconnects in any intentional or active
way which you're participating in what is stressful or
harmful
if you become quieter and quieter inside so you become more and more
sensitive to your inner life can you feel feel your
way towards an attitude of Greater you become Qui nonharming quieter
inside so you become more more
sensitive
e
e e
and as we come to the end of this sitting one way
[Music] to bring the benefits of meditation into
our life is to appreciate
any degree of Peace nonharming
non-conflict in which we
meditate the peace and meditation can be very big can be contrasted with the lack
of it that many people live with in their lives and then one of the gifts we can
bring the world is to become
someone who other others feel safe with giving the gift of
safety making ourselves safe for all beings
so that our capacity to live without harm to
ourselves begins to be extended bit by
bit to learning how to live without harming anyone
else nonharming way of life which gives others the gift of
safety may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings have the safety where there's room to be
happy may all beings feel the safy
that allows them to connect more deeply to the people around
them may all beings be safe from harm and violence
and poverty so they can grow into their full
potential as a human being
and may we contribute to a peaceful world may all
beings be
[Music]
happy thank you
e e
so hello everyone and welcome to this Monday morning uh meditation and
teaching and I'm very happy to be back it's been a while and happy that you've had some
wonderful teachers coming to be here while I was gone and
um so I want to turn my attention from at least next couple of weeks to what
some people consider to be the foundation of
Buddhism and that is um in English we would probably say it's
ethics and uh virtue living a
living a um virtuous life and uh if we think of Buddhism as a
pyramid then uh ver virtue and ethics
would be the foundation upon which the pyramid is built like the bottom layer of it big
wide strong base uh upon which the the
the higher points of the pyramid would go up to a point and the second layer would be um
meditation or suade or cultivating ourselves in a in a Wholesome Way and
the third would be wisdom the top of the pyramid so that wisdom is supported by
meditation uh spiritual practice and that spiritual practice is supported by
ethics and ethics has to do with a lot to do with how we live our lives uh in
relationship to other people it can be in relationship to ourselves as well
um uh the um um but the interpersonal
world we live in is a huge part of a human life some people as adults forget
this because they've somehow um become separated from others
somehow become alienated sometimes become isolated but uh uh uh a healthy way of
of being a human being is to be brought brought up by adults who care for them who feed them and clean them as babies
who watch over them protect them as they grow up the Deep interpersonal world
that human beings are dependent on continues into adulthood if we have uh
children or or there's children in our immediate Community then uh part of what
uh potential for rle for the adults is to care for them and help them grow up
in ways that are safe and and um and uh allow them to grow into their full
potential the interpersonal world of human beings is huge and so when we when ethics is at
the foundation of Buddhist practice it is um beginning to care for the interpersonal World in a in a way that
then supports uh uh our own inner life so that we're in a good place to
meditate and to cultivate wisdom the um one of my favorite uh
definitions but this is all kind of uh circular because one of my favorite
definitions of wisdom in Buddhism is from the buddhis is that a wise person
who's someone who uh avoids harming self
harming others harming self and others or ing the whole world rather a wise
person considers or focuses on benefiting self benefiting others
benefiting self and others and benefiting the whole world so the fact
that this is what this kind of defines or describes a wise person is their care
for how to live in the world with self and others that avoid harming
oneself and instead brings the opposite the benefits others and concerned with
the welfare of the world and so ethics is a foundation for
samadi samadi for wisdom wisdom itself then uh supports further deepening and
uh understanding of the value of ethics of virtue of of
non-harming so it turns out that in the Buddhist teachings probably the fundamental principle that uh lays at
the heart of it all is the idea of non-harming the highest reaches of
Buddhist teachings in the is that is often held in
the to be in the four noble truths and those have to do with suffering and the
end of suffering and the end that we're ending is the th those ways which we are
responsible for our own suffering the ways that we contribute to it so that
it's not saying that all suffering is caused uh by oneself but where we have
the most uh agency the most capacity to make a difference is to make a
difference so that we don't contribute to our own suffering we don't add to it we don't how we create it and it turns
out that uh over time with deep kind of mindfulness we understand that how
phenomenally fundamental and pervasive uh the ways in which clinging
and attemp attachment of all kinds causes self harm or to say it in the ter
terminology of the formable truths causes suffering so and ethics is also in
Buddhism the fundamental ethical principle is non-harming so there's a way of understanding that non-harming
runs through the whole course of uh of Buddhist teachings the Buddhist training
the practice of it and that is a reference point constantly for for what
we're doing and um and it might be easier to understand the value of not harming
oneself and um and uh the idea of not harming others is a more challenging uh
idea when there's issues of safety involved and protection when there's
issues of Justice involved that uh we feel like we're being are what's fair or
right for us is being threatened but uh but
uh one of I like to believe that one of the minimum kind of engagements that
Buddhists have in an ethical World ethical life is using non-harming as a
reference point to understand themselves and to understand how we can live with
others and what works uh for the welfare and benefit for all beings both in the
short term but also in the long term sometimes violence can can cause
can bring results in the short term but in the long term causes tremendous amount of harm that takes maybe takes
generations to to uh to
rectify and um so uh in the last uh two
weeks that I was teaching here I taught about uh these 10 basic human needs um
meaning and purpose agency and autonomy identity and dignity community and
kinship and healing and Reconciliation all F all 10 of those
could be it's a way of understanding them that the heart of all of them is the principle the way of living that
involves nonharming Aima and that
uh that this is and and that uh the purpose and meaning for for the for the
Buddha at the heart of the Buddhist teachings is uh a life of non-harming to have uh to have a healthy
sense of agency a healthy sense of autonomy is a very soil from which a
powerful confident non-harming lifestyle life way of life can arise it's a people
often whose agency and autonomy and freedom is curtailed frustrated that uh
feel like they have to harm in order to get what they need and what they
what they want and so you can analyze all all all 10 of these from the point of view of
that non-harming lies for Buddhism lies at the heart of it whether you agree
with to this is another thing but it's the um
um the um uh it's the reference point that I
think really makes Buddhist practice come alive a reference point that really guides Buddhist practice this or
supports mindfulness really kind of helps us to question ourselves and see ourselves in a deeper and deeper
way uh we don't have to necessarily agree with the principle of non-harming
to use it as a powerful reference point to help us clarify and really understand
what does make us operate what does motivate us what do we believe and then we can look at it more
deeply um the um uh I think that uh to to be
respectful of all beings there's a time also to be respectful that uh how
intense the motivation is for self- protection in people protecting themselves protecting their family
protecting your children that um that that that is what prompts people to be
violent to protect them themselves and what a what a fundamental human need it
is to protect one's family and so it isn't the the call for nonviolence
vience a call for non-harming needs to respect the Deep Instinct we have that
um is not necessarily greed hatred and delusion that leads to acts of violence
but occasionally involves something something very deep and fundamentally human not to justify it but to respect
how people are and only through deep respect can we hope to be able to convey
to others the value of a him the value of
non-harming and even if we don't believe in it in all circumstances it is the fundamental
principle for how we relate to ourselves if what we want to do is to become free
the spiritual Liberation The Liberation of heart that Buddhism uh Champions that
points to the possibility of the profound peace that's possible um is
inseparable from a deep deep Affinity a deep Association a deep
realization of the value the beauty the wonderfulness the wholesomeness of
living a wise non-harming life a
wise life that understands deeply how to engage in the world um in a way that
supports self and others and can do so so that we're safe
for all beings one of my favorite another one of my favorite quotes from the
Buddha is his instruction to make yourself safe for all beings what a
great thing to do so that no one has to be afraid of us and what does that take
what how do we have to grow how do we have to develop ourselves how do we how do we become strong how do we become
skilled in finding our way through this complicated world so that we can can
provide a sense of safety for all beings that we encounter it's not an easy task
um but it's a worthwhile one maybe it's a lifetime task that we're working
towards I I think it's a noble task to become safe safe for all
beings and how that translates
to others to society around us um maybe
that's secondary to how we discover this for
ourselves and meditation and mindfulness is a path to understand the
value um not too to understand but to really see to discover clearly for
oneself to verify for oneself that uh that a nonharming approach to
living a non-harming way of living with our in the world with our body with our
speech with our even our thoughts brings tremendous benefit tremendous goodness
to one who practices it and to know that so thoroughly for oneself that it's not
a no one has to convince you no one has to give you a philosophy or ethical
guidance to understand the value of non-harming it's so obvious from what
has developed in your own heart through this practice that we do and that
to to support this process if you're interested um to use that the concept of
non-harming not as an admonition not as something that you should do but rather
as a reference point to help you reflect deeply what is happening here what in
what way are we harming where is the non-harming how what is the wise thing
to do here in reference to this phenomenal tool
phenomenal um um a teacher that we can
carry with us the teacher of non-harming so this week uh I'm going to
talk about some of these um fundamental principles of uh Buddhist ethics and
this is the one of them the most important one today and then uh
and that will create the foundation and for next week to talk about the
precepts so um thank you and I'm very happy to be back