so good
morning one of
the important characteristics of the Buddha's
teachings is social teachings is the idea of
Harmony some AA and the idea of Harmony is that um
one one image or metaphor for it is for people to milk like to me to mix like
milk and water milk and water Blends
together very differently than oil and water that's they
separate for us to somehow live together in
harmony and the Buddha talks about
uh loving Harmony delighting in harmony devoted to
Harmony and um in the Buddhist manesa Community the only
Community the Buddha was actively involved in guiding put a lot of
emphasis on the community living together in in Harmony and cooperating
together so for this uh meditation I'd like to
suggest that um uh in a certain kind of ways each of
us is a community of people each of us contains a range mult multitud multitude
of different impulses feelings thoughts maybe almost like personalities
depending where we are I was struck growing up and speaking different
languages that um I was and other people I knew had somewhat different
personalities depending on the language they spoke because when we're learning a language in a culture you learn more
than a language you learn a way of being a way of relating finding yourself in
the culture and that can vary from culture to culture and uh so and sometimes we we're divided
in ourselves we have parts we don't like and parts we like we have preferences
about ourselves things we want to hide things ways that we want to present ourselves to the
world so there's a multitude within us and so for this meditation I'd like
to suggest that we sit together we sit here with with the idea of meditating in
harmony with all that we are that all of who we are is invited to
be here and the key thing about being in
harmony is to tell the truth speak the truth here and
now and mindfulness practice can be seen as that that Honesty is mindfulness out
loud mindful mindfulness within is not just being aware of what's here and
knowing it in some simple way knowing it as an act of Truth this is what's
happening my shoulders are tense and and see this is a TR Moment of
Truth oh this is what's true my belly is soft
I'm thinking about the
election and not just knowing it in a casual way or recognizing it in so can't
just just like almost like a dutiful way oh this is what's happening there's something about the
power of saying oh this is in fact what is happening this is the truth that at
this moment this time this is a mind that's thinking
about the election and how to be in harmony with that is to include it as
part of the whole of who you are so it's not sing sing singled out as
something to be obsessed about or caught in but something to which by telling us
the truth of it we open to the wholeness of who we are we're so much more
and if we're distressed about something like the election the whole of who we are
includes a a concern a love for the harmony of all the parts of
ourselves the part of us that can tell the truth the part of us that can want want Harmony the part of us that has
generosity the part of us that has love and care and good will
not to push anything away but to place it in a wider context let it all live
together here so that as we meditate we're freeing up our breath
freeing up our body so we can be at ease in this body
here and now with all of who we are breathing
quietly breathing reassuring re
reassuringly an easeful breath so assuming a meditation
posture and gently closing the
eyes softly
gently in your own way the way that's good for for
you feels right acknowledge how you
are and let that be an act of Truth telling whatever way you
are the kind of Truth
telling that allows us to be present without being caught
even if we're caught in something we say the truth would be oh this is being
caught I am
caught and in saying that that that honestly then opening to the harmony of
all things within you are much more than someone
who's caught much more than someone someone who's thinking a
lot so acknowledging how you
are and then in the midst of how you
are take some long slow comfortable
breaths breathing
in and settling into the middle of yourself settling in settling into being
here in this
body letting your breathing return to
normal and finding some place where you experience the body
breathing where there's the least sense of control least sense of being a
breather where it's most neutral to feel the
breathing could be the movements of the back rib kage
stage maybe it's a small movements in the
shoulders maybe it's a sense of the whole experience of breathing
the whole torso that feels it that's bigger than
any place where there's a sense of Something's doing the breathing
inviting relaxation as you
exhale not doing the relaxation almost like making space
making room for the place places where the body will relax
itself if you open invite
inviting a relaxation in the experience of
breathing Maybe by opening up to give breathing room for each inhale and exhale
inviting the exhale to relax a softening letting go
allowing the inhale to include a softening
and as we continue very as quietly and
softly as you
can tell yourself the truth of the present moment
experience whatever is happening for you here and
now even if it's connected to other things and other
times be truthful about how it's being how it's manifesting
now but do so in harmony with being at ease
maybe with a sense of ease or calm in your
breathing calmly
invite say the truth in a way that invites
everything to join together in the
Simplicity of the moment the Simplicity of being alive and breathing
now a gentle truthtellah
without
conflict
for
e
for for
and as we approach the end of this sitting to softly
gently calm your body a global
relaxation into the body
into whatever way that you feel more
settled calmer than you were when you
started gently calmly acknowledge how you are
now an acknowledgement that is a kind of a
truth-telling and an invitation for whatever you is
happening to be part of a whole the whole of who you are the whole
of this
world as if there's lots of room for all of who you are to be here
in the calm in the harmony
and then imagine that you can be with
others maybe without the need to say anything or do
anything but that your subtleness
your ability to be present and truthful Here and
Now can also include an
invitation for everyone to be as they
are and to be part of
them the harmony of now
A Harmon harmonious presence that you
contribute regardless how others
are and if you do speak
you speak with love you speak with
generosity you speak with
respect May all
beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may we find a way to support that
by living in harmony with the truth in
harmony with car caring for the welfare and
benefit of everyone no one excluded
[Music]
thank
you e
so good morning or good day it's remarkable how
I speak from the terms of where I'm at the time zone I'm
in please uh forgive me if I I want to be able to be inclusive of all time
zones so hello
everyone and thank you for being here as I do the last of these talks on to
transform the world and I offer the talks in the
context of the national and US elections next
week and all the divisiveness that currently exists and the and the sense of conflict
and maybe impending conflict that might be coming and I offer it with the
confidence that it's not necessary to succumb to despair or succumb to
uh paralyzing fear or to hatred ill
will we can be confident I want us all to be confident that we can make a
difference to make this world a better place
and if uh and we can do so in small ways
we can do it in our communities with our friends our neighbors and um and of course it's nice to do it
more widely nice to go out and and um uh you know there's people who going
out in all kinds of all political parties to get out the vote who are actively involved in political action
and El supporting the election and other candidates and things like
that there's ways of uh lobbying governments and
there's all kinds of ways of changing the world but the for me the most important
is that we start with ourselves we don't lose ourselves in uh in the action we do and
I know that back when I was young there were people who were very active in uh
in uh the anti-vietnam war with all kinds of civil rights issues all kinds
of things that were going on back then and some of them got deeply discouraged because the organizations
they were involved in the people they were working with were so divisive there
was so much inner conflict and hatred and anger and greed going on that they
felt this can't go this can't continue this way and so one of the reasons some
people came to Buddhism was to find an alternative and uh and I I do hope that
we find it here and one of the Alternatives is to appreciate that if we
want to change the world for the better we have to change too we have to represent the change we want we want
have to be the change that we want and if we want a peaceful world we have to be peaceful if we want to have a world
where there's no hate we have to stop hating that uh the Deep inner work and
Buddhism sometimes is criticized for creating a lot of people who are maybe too passive or not involved in in in the
Civil Life of our our our culture but that's not true uh there's a lot of
people here coming through IMC for example that I know who have practiced
here for many years and are transformed who then go out and are doing all kinds
of uh good um in their own way joining different organizations joining different things
and maybe I MC doesn't so actively involved because we're a relatively small organization but the people coming
through here do remarkable things in the world and uh and um but hopefully they
they bring with them the the transformation into goodness the
transformation trans transformation into Freedom so they can act in ways that
they are the Agent of Change uh by how they are uh as much as by what they
do and um and so one way of folding all this together that I've done this week
um uh the in a way I've talked about so these different things uh it can be
summarized um love so that others will
love be peaceful so others will learn to be peaceful give so others trust
generosity respect or dignify others because offering dignity offering
respect is contagious and then
today speak the truth with love peace generosity and
respect so it try transforms people's hearts don't only focus on policy and
action and the we really want to change Hearts
so the hearts understand how to live in harmony the hearts can come from Love
and generosity and so if we want to be the change that we want to see in the world
we have to be able to speak the truth for sure and this is where the action is
speak TR truth speak truth to power what power the power of love the power of
Peace being peaceful non-c conflictive non-
contentious uh speak with uh generosity the generous Spirit generous to the
people we speak to so they feel our generosity care our Good Will are
concern for their welfare speak with
um uh speak with respect speak in a way that that sees the others with as uh
with dignity treat them with as dignified people
everyone so it's not a hierarchy it's not some people are better than others but a universal
dignity this is the universal Declaration of Human Rights everyone is
born equal in their
dignity and um and then speaking speak the truth we have to
speak whether and how do we do it in a way that people will listen that's Cooperative that's harmonious that
people feel like we're not uh attacking or not lecturing or not but uh we're
inviting inviting people into cooperation inviting people into a sense
of Harmony when the Buddha talked about speaking uh the first thing he said was
the importance of speaking truth the second thing he said was the
following um do do not repeat what you have heard from others
so as to divide people against each other so don't divide people against
each other so don't spread gossip don't use hear say instead Recon
reconcile those who are divided reconcile those who are divided
be a mediator and uh that's one of my Great Hopes for Buddhism is that Buddhism in a sense
doesn't take sides but Buddhism steps into the conflict in order to mediate in
order to reconcile find a way for people to work together and now so rather than stepping
into one side or the other um that Buddhism enters into the middle and the
middle way to reconcile and I've done that uh locally
by being on Buddhist ethics committees where there was reconciliation work to be done but the Instinct of people was
not to find reconciliation the in Instinct was punishment the Instinct was blame um um
and uh and more divisiveness and how to reconcile so
everyone is inspired by the reconciliation how to find a way forward
that everyone feels like they're cared for and benefited for I believe that's
possible it's not easy so uh so reconcile those who are
divided supporting Unity delighting in
harmony loving Harmony speaking words that promote
Harmony so uh if we're going to act in the world and I hope we act in New World
so we create a better world uh it probably Begins by how we
speak and um and to speak harmoniously to
speak uh in a ways
that that um once encourages others to join
cooperatively encourages others to continue with the work
of conditioning the soil we're all earthworms we're
all working on a deep deep work of changing the soil in which we live the
soil of the heart slowly changing the World by creating rich soil for the
seeds of goodness to sprout may
we find a way to promote cooperation and Harmony
and truthtellah
of Love Of Peace of
generosity of respect and Truth be something that guides us and more than
guides us gives us tremendous confidence that this
these can be the foundation the basis of how we live our
life that these are what heals us from our
own anxiety fear hatred ill
will overwhelm sense of victimhood in this
world of so many challenges let us
become the producers The Confident
manifestors of goodness let us trust goodness
wholesomeness more than we trust what divides us so thank you very much for this and I
appreciate very much this chance to be able to speak to you and um I don't know
what's we all none of us know what's going to happen uh in the United States next week and um I'm going to be
teaching a retreat next week and um the
um and um next week we're very lucky to have anes fredman come to teach here at
7A at the YouTube channel um and I think it's the first time it might be the
first time inz has come inz is one of the senior teachers at IMC and uh one of
the really strong foundations for what uh
we do here in the Dharma and the cor Cooperative world of IMC and IRC you're
very lucky I feel very fortunate that she's coming and uh been trying to get her to come for a long time and um the
more we can get in as the better and uh the other thing is that uh
we don't know what's going to happen next week so I'm on retreat but if uh
there feels a need for it um I'll maybe um host a zoom meeting uh one
day uh in order to support uh all of everyone anyone who
wants to come support them through the process of uh whatever challenges this
nation goes through next week and if the challenges are not that great then um I
will see you in in the following week and we will continue you to find our way
thank you