hello and welcome and
uh today we'll do the last uh exploration of mindfulness of
emotions and I hope that the course of this week that
uh I've managed to convey a deep respect for emotions that emotions have an
important role and place in our lives and that uh learning how to be
mindful of them is a tremendous uh beneficial art and I call it an art
rather than a technique because it has to do with our inner life the depths of
it the fullness of it the range of it and uh something which constantly shifting and changing and understanding
how to be with emotions how to respect them how to learn from them how to um uh
Plum into the depths of their potential is a constantly shifting uh phenomenon
we're finding our way we're discovering and um and it's important not to have a
simplistic idea that that there's a simple technique for just not knowing
how to be with emotions it's uh if there is a simplistic idea it's
the idea that uh we want to be able to show up for them and discover have the
capacity to be able to be with emotions without being swamped by them controlled
by them um resisting them troubled by them uh overly
um succumbing to them but to be able to see them clearly
so that we can uh find the wisdom and find Freedom that uh they point to and
what's possible so in the course of this week the one of
the things was the idea of um like yesterday giving lots of
space to our emotions and so this analogy I've given
before that I think is very powerful is that sometimes when people
think that they're supposed to concentrate on something with mindfulness really bore into something really look
at it carefully or study it it's kind of like the mind everything a lot of mind
kind of contracts and becomes kind of tight like all my fingers coming together to kind of a point in order to
address something and uh and but this movement in the mind to gather together and focus
and causes a strain there kind of a tension involved in that and um the
alternative is to keep the Mind relaxed keep the awareness soft open receptive
in some sense maybe broad not not to tense up anything in the mind but also
not to stay broad like this because if you stay broad we don't necessarily see
carefully and see well and be able to see through something or see behind it
or see the roots of it and so the idea is to uh to come not not go like this to
a point but have a different kind of one-pointedness where whatever we're looking at comes and is the mo comes and
just touches the most sensitive part of the mind just like a sensitive part of the hand is uh maybe the palm and um and
when we like this that the Palm is not available to sense and
feel and so this way so stay soft so as we go like this sometimes the mind will
go tighten up and so we want to pay attention that we don't do that and
rather we come and just kind of gently touch and so and what this means is to
put ourselves right in the middle of the emotion put ourselves right there we get
really close to it and that's where mindfulness of the body is so helpful
because what we put ourselves close to is the place in the body where the emotion is most expressed the way the
most sensations of the emotion are present and in a sense to put ourselves
right in the middle of that maybe in this way that we're kind of just creating a place for the emotion to rest
in the palm of our hands Kind of Wonderful metaphor but so so it rests
and be supported or as if um uh you know the
the the important place is this the point of contact between awareness and
the mind and and the emotion and and just reside right here like just this
becomes a place to just feel and be absorbed and be present so it's very intimate very close to the sensations of
the emotion and and that movement can be like this we can touch in difficult
emotions touch into it and the image I have for that is uh that sometimes when
there's really difficult emotions that uh awareness is like a soft cotton ball
that just comes gently and Taps but we don't tense up we don't resist we
just kind of keep relaxed open mind and experiment with how close can we get and
keep it relaxed you don't have to go all the way just go as far as you can that
before you start tensing up and it might be that you have to stay quite far away to be aware of it and that's okay if if
you're going to tense or resist or get afraid or something maybe stay far away
way but over time to learn how to bring that soft cotton ball it's that
sensitivity just right into the middle of the emotion really be there and um
and then maybe it's too many metaphors but I find it useful sometimes to
imagine there's a chair right in the middle of the emotions and the physical
sensations of it and then I just sit there to be with and accompany the
emotion so this intimacy this closeness it's not always the right thing to do
but uh that's one of the ways to be mindful of emotions so to assume a meditation
posture and this is where with emotions it's actually very significant the
posture you take and so really be thoughtful and
careful about what the posture Expresses in terms of how to attend
to an emotion how to [Music]
be to be able to respectfully make room for the emotion make contact with the
emotion some people find it's particularly useful to be
grounded so with the eyes closed maybe on the exhale to
feel the weight of your body being supported by a chair a couch s a
cushion a bed whatever it is that supports the
weight of the body on the exhale ground yourself there settle
there as if this place that you're sitting is a refuge for
you the actual place that receives your
weight is a place of safety and
grounding and then to ground yourself a little bit into
your body gently take some deeper breaths
feeling as much as the body that's easy especially the
Torso and relaxing as you
exhale
and then letting your breathing return to normal and it's easier to relax the
mind if we first relax the body and if relaxing is
too challenging maybe a softening softening around the tension
and the holding and with every
exhale softening
relaxing different parts of the
body
for
and then to also notice what tension and holding
there is in the mind the thinking
muscle any forcefulness or tightness
pressure associated with thinking or maybe with even
emoting wanting something and not
wanting and on the exhale to relax soften the
Mind soften the energy
agitation pressure of wanting and not
wanting of thinking and planning and remembering
and softening and relaxing the energy of being self-concerned
burn and then centering yourself on the breathing in whatever way the body is
experience of breathing might be comforting for you or
settling or grounding just go look around and
see in what way can you feel the physical experience of
breathing is there a location for that in the belly the chest the rib cage the
nostrils the back rib
cage where it feels grounding or
settling to accompany the body
breathing
for
e
and then to notice
recognize how you're feeling in terms of emotion a mood and
mental state how you're feeling in your inner
being it might be quite subtle it might be strong either is
fine and see if you can recognize if there's
any location in the body that's the center of how you
feel any part of your body that's little more active ated or where there are
Sensations that seem to be part and parcel of your
emotion your state of
being some subtle meditative states can feel like they extend beyond the edges
of the body some emot difficult emotions can seem
like they're throughout the body but whatever it is is
there a center of gravity for
it and if there is let your awareness hold it spaciously
maybe from a distance and allow your
breathing to accompany your emotion your state as if you're breathing through
it or alongside of
it and your breathing gets close to it but you don't not
yet
for
and then to begin centering yourself on
where on the middle of the
emotion getting closer with your awareness so you begin feeling it
sensing it carefully and
receptively almost as like you bring yourself right up against it or right into the
middle at whatever Center there is for how you're
feeling maybe with an awareness that's like a soft cotton
ball maybe all you can do is tap your emotional state
gently feel it stroke it
gently and then pull
away or maybe you can open your hand wide your mind open and
relaxed and receive the emotion in the open mind mind open
hand or placing yourself in the middle of your emotional
state your mind state state of being whatever it might be
and sit right in the middle just being
with not fixing or judging or
analyzing being a good friend who just sits in the middle of it lets it
be ACC companying feeling
sensing the physicality of the emotion maybe it's an ephemeral
sensation whatever it is
gently let yourself be in the middle of it all and see what
happens
and as you do so keep an
eye on whether the mind is Contracting or
tightening see if the mind can stay relaxed with a relaxed attention relaxed
connecting relaxed
receiving while you're centered
grounded in whatever seems to be the middle of your emotional
state
for
and then as we come to the end of the meditation to end the way we
began let yourself be grounded in the place where you're
sitting whatever receives the weight of your body feel feel that
support of the floor your cushion chair couch
bed and whatever part of your body is touching the surface that's carrying
your weight feel the solidity of that feel the grounding of
it in a way it prevents you from Free
Falling being pulled by the by
gravity and taking some long slow deep
breaths and on the exhale feeling the grounding of the weight of your body
this substantiality of your body Here and
Now
and then take a few last few moments here to appreciate your
mind even if sometimes it acts in ways that are not so helpful for
you mostly this mind of ours most of it
operates kind of with without recognition without knowing to take care
of so many of the different functions that takes us to be
alive even if our thinking is not always so helpful
99.9% of the mental functioning supports us all day
long appreciating the Mind appreciating your
heart and then turning your attention outward into the world and no one needs to know you're
doing this doesn't require mean you have to do anything or talk to anyone or help
anyone but you can just now for a few moments
spread your good will out into the world that yes it would be a great thing if
there was more [Music] peace more well-being less
hunger more people being supported out of poverty
and despair and oppression it would be a good place this
world if people didn't suffer so much may it be
so may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and may my good will find a way
to spread into this world nourishing it supporting it making
a difference for this to be a better world for everyone for
[Music]
everyone
thank
you and uh while I drink my water and prepare for a little talk if some of you
would like to say a few words just a few words so I can track them all about what
that meditation was like for you was it helpful was it challenging was it what way might have been helpful or something
and that might help me understand how then to do this teaching in the next few
minutes
e
so thank you for the comments and I'll read more of them at the end and I
certainly sympathize with those people who felt there was a lot of words during that meditation and um but that's the
tradeoff uh between being able to be silence that helps us to settle versus um receiving
some teachings and some approaches that um rather than explaining them in a in a
talk afterwards but some little bit kind of going along and feeling them here and
there's a long history of receiving teachings like this that and then going off to meditate with them um so
um and and um so this week uh mindfulness of
emotions uh I hope offered both different perspectives of how to be present for emotions so the art of it
you can kind of have different choices of how to be and with with them in different different times in different
ways and um but also was a little bit Progressive it was creating a building
the container building the context so that we can do something which is often
quite difficult and that is to sit in the middle of our emotional
life but sit in the middle without being uh caught in it or entangled or reactive
or without feeling that the we're victims of our emotions that we're collapsing under the weight of
them and um to find a way to sit in the Middle where we feel at ease or we feel
free or we feel uh strong we feel um
capable um we have the capacity to be with them and be present and and then to be able to get
to really when the time is right to really be intimate with them to really
feel closely what exactly is the experience the present moment
experience often with emotions especially with difficult emotions there's often a very strong
connection to thinking and reacting and believing or interpreting or predicting
or um somehow relating what the emotion to our our sense of self what this means
for me and uh how this defines me or what I have to do or something and the
idea in mindfulness practice is to learn a radical Simplicity where so much of of the
reactive interpretive uh judging analytical ways of being with emotions that that gets uh
let's kind of recedes into the background or becomes quiet it's kind of
like uh you've been doing some kind of craft at home but there's a loud radio
going on kind of blaring all kinds of stuff that maybe it's political speeches and and um opinions and and um and it's
just kind of difficult to kind of be absorbed in your craft or in reading your nice
book and so um the um uh so the radio
goes off for the radio gets turned down and now you can really be with what you're doing and so to really be with
the emotion and whether it's sitting in the middle of it or coming from
underneath it or in some kind of intimate way uh being the emotion making
room for it to kind of be all of us if it's really strong and everything but all these ways uh with a Simplicity of
attention with a capacity not to react not to judge not to interpret um but
just to breathe with it or make room for it to be what it is and that intimacy and that capacity
is invaluable I would suggest for two today for two main reasons um one is that uh our body the
emotional body that we have has a lot of wisdom about how to uh in a healthy way
to let our emotional life unfold and uh sometimes our emotional
body has much more wisdom than our thinking mind has where we predict and judge and interpret based on life
experience and so if we can relax enough feel safe enough to drop into our body
and just feel intimately what's happening then um uh the inner wisdom
the the process which emotions are emotions are can process themselves in a
healthy way so that's one advantage of doing this and the more close we're connected
sometimes the easier it is for to really allow the depth of what's happening to
unfold the other which is also sometimes maybe even more important at times is
that that intimacy and presence an attention to the emotion that's close in we start seeing that actually in the
cracks of it or underneath it or behind it or something we start seeing that
whatever the emotion is that we're that was going on is is in a certain way is
the surface emotion or is the the U the
louder expression of something that's more core that underlying Source
underneath so for example when there's a lot of anger uh sometimes what's underneath the
anger is fear uh or maybe it's um a sense of hurt
and so so this they have been close to it and feeling it closely and um so that
it can we can begin seeing I like sometimes I think of is the message underneath it what's really
going on underneath and that can be a GameChanger well we thought we were dealing with anger and we had opinions
about anger and important is to express it and you're going to give people a piece of your mind and you have right to
do that all this stuff is just really on this kind of a surface thing if you
really want if you're able to drop into a deeper Wellspring deeper what's really
bubbling and going on and activated in a deeper place within you want to be able
to see below that maybe see the hurt or the fear
and that is more primary that's more useful to deal with sometimes sadness um sometimes uh
uh anger isn't there's not fear or hurt under anything sometimes it's a deep
sorrow and grief and the anger is a kind of uh kind of might be directed outwards
to others but it's a kind of ricocheting off the difficulty of being with our own
grief and pain and certainly we want to be very respectful how diffult it is and
not rush to then connect to it but there might be feeling it from a distance or
soft cotton ball that gently touches it and pets it you know Strokes it I know you're there and then pull it
away so these two uh very helpful processes that can happen one is that
the emotion can unfold the way it will naturally do and generally emotions
unfold in appropriate ways they know how to unfold if we get out of the way and allow them to be there without being
fueled by stories and beliefs and reactivity and um the second is that um
uh we start seeing through them to what's actually deeper and the examples I gave now were
all kind of you maybe difficult emotions but sometimes underneath might be something beautiful so maybe there's
anger but we find that underneath there there's love and somehow the love the
care the compassion for some reason has taken direction of anger but there's
really compassion underneath there and maybe there's another way rather than
anger to let the compassion be expressed um maybe sadness underneath
that is um is also love or care or um maybe there's a sadness that our
generosity or our friendship is not received or
something so um sometimes there's beautiful things to discover and um uh
you know sometimes um fear underneath the fear there might be a very wholesome
sense of wanting to protect oneself care and support for one's own
well-being that feels uh very satisfying to touch into
and to feel that underlying care and desire to be safe independent of the
fear can be also a GameChanger and we can ask ourselves then well is there another way of uh becoming safe if
that's what I what what I want as opposed to somehow contending with a
fear so the world of our emotions is a very rich world and um and as we learn in
mindfulness meditation to be present for it in a mindful non-reactive
way the the uh greatest potential in for mindfulness meditation of learning how
to do this is that emotions become just one more thing to be aware of as things
unfold and move through us and it isn't that the emotions then at some point are
more validated or more important than anything else but rather the ability to settle down set be simple and whatever
arises in attention we just say oh that's what it is this is going on now
and leave it that simple so that the capacity for simple ongoing
recognition presence to what's happening in the present moment uh becomes
uninterrupted without the emotions um being as I said prioritized or or taken
to be uh um more important than anything else it's just one more thing to
recognize and know and that Simplicity of just letting emotions be that way allows for this
deeper settling and con uh into um the uh the path of
mindfulness so I hope all this uh supportive um remember that how
important that uh I've emphasizing respect is for your emotions respect
them and care for them and and be wise about them don't uh and uh no hopefully
what we done this week helps you to understand how to better take care of yourself when these emotions are here
and how to not be um caught in them too much but learn how to when you need to
take a break or need to talk to a friend or need something else that you you will
do so so next week uh we'll talk I'll talk
about mindfulness of thinking and that overlaps quite a bit with the
mindfulness of emotions and hopefully you'll see that mindful being able to be mindful of emotions is really helpful to
get a handle on how to be mindful mindful of thoughts so that when you're mindful of thinking it does impr prompt
you to think more so thank you very much and I look
forward to our time next
week