so good day to all of you those of you who've been here for a
few minutes and those that are just joining now just settling in
welcome we'll go ahead and get started so finding a posture for
meditation maybe taking a long slow deep breath and slowly letting it
out just connecting with being here with your intention
to do this sitting together and close your eyes if it's comfortable to do
so that's encouraged and just tune in to the sense
of the body in the sitting posture the meditation
posture inviting whatever ease is available to
you right now in the
body often there's more available than we think can deliberately bring attention
to areas that we tend to habitually hold and just soften so softening the
muscles of the face around the eyes around the forehead the
jaw all the little muscles on the
scalp the eyes in the eye
sockets and then lowering the attention down into the body
often we keep our energy up High having a feeling of settling down
into the shoulder area chest and
back relaxing the arms
and on the in breath allowing the back to straighten in a relaxed
way I find as the muscles of my back release it actually wants to go upward
as if I were holding it in a slumped
position takes effort to
slum it's often the
belly down into the hips and the legs and all the way to the
feet allowing the body to take the form of Simply being
here however that looks and feels to you right now
and there may be pain or tiredness in the body and that's okay too that's just
part of the present moment part of what we're present
for and I'm going to invite today just one brief reflection to bring
in and that is to turn the attention deliberately
to something that's inspiring or motivating for you related to your
practice why do you practice why are we
sitting it could be just right now today or it could be something some
bigger picture a larger longer term motivation whatever feels right is
fine something it's somewhat
inspiring I know someone who imagines that by sitting there
walking in the footsteps of the Buddha doing what he did to walk the
path to Awakening
or it could be as simple as I'm calming down so I can go to
work the good mindset
today but let that sense of what matters to you infuse your being in some
way perhaps breathing it in or just opening the mind to
it see what that does in the
body and now letting that deliberate reflection
go and turning to practice
for today I'll invite you to tune into experience in some way that works for
you do you usually use the breath the body an open kind of awareness or
meta sensing what
practice will be most beneficial right now
I do recommend choosing something kind of simple not one with a lot of steps that
you go through perhaps the breath if you're
unsure just settling on the breath
and the other invitation is to
consider just bring in the inclination of mind that what you're
doing in this simple practice is planting good seeds for the
future is planting seeds for the very thing that is motivating and
inspiring there may not be an obvious connection between feeling the sensations of the breath right now and
something larger for your life but I'm going to invite the trust
that there is the simple goodness of doing this
practice does move us toward our deepest aspirations
sometimes we can move into a heaviness or obligation about
practice got to do this or another extreme is that we grasp
on to practice going to achieve something through doing
this and in a totally different space is simply doing
it out of its pure goodness and the
inspiration and really eventually knowledge that it does move us in a good
direction there's kind of a blessing associated with just doing the
practice
simply and we'll feel
that
e
e e
if the Mind begins to slip away from practice the present
moment simply reuning realigning if it slips into doing too
much or doing too little re evoking that sense
of simple goodness and joy and just doing the
practice just being
here knowing that it's the best thing to do with this moment
e
e e
returning to
Simplicity and the deep rest that's
possible with a heart that is simple
regardless of what's happening in the body the mind the external
world there's a way that the heart can be
simple knowing that just meeting this
moment is moving us along the
path
e
e e
and in the last few minutes of this
meditation perhaps reconnecting with the
body the body in this space where you're
sitting so bringing in again the awareness of the way place
where you are sense of yourself in this
meditation situated in time there will be something after this just allowing
the mind to bring in more normal elements of
Consciousness and as you do so reconnecting with this sense of of
inspiration or [Music] aspiration and the simple blessing of
just doing the
practice and is there a way in which being in touch with that Simplicity and
that truthfulness about your own spiritual practice is there a
way that can support you today going forward or this
evening with the people that you're interacting with with the things you need to
do if there might be challenges that are [Music]
unexpected could it be that just having some
connection to this inspiration that you
carry could give you more options in situations like that doesn't have to be
something that we bring in like an identity or we're carrying it in a heavy
way but just maybe touching into it in our heart
even as most of our attention is on our life as it only
is one more way that the practice supports others as well as ourselves
there were only four items on our list for this week not neglecting wisdom
preserving truth cultivating relinquishment and training for
peace what shall we talk about
today well let's start with the story that frames the teaching where the
Buddha names these four practices and it's from the majima
number 140 and it features a monk named puku
Sati the commentaries say that he was a king gave up his kingdom in order to
ordain and live a simple spiritual life but even without that detail it's
an interesting story what it says in the suta so the Buddha is traveling
apparently by himself and he asks a Potter if he can spend the night in his
workshop and the Potter says it is not inconvenient for me venerable sir but
there is a homeless one already staying there if he agrees then stay as long as
you like and the one who's already there is pusti and so the Buddha goes to him and
politely asks if it's okay to share the workshop for that night and pus Sati
says that will be fine now puku Sati is a was a follower
of the Buddha but he had never met the Buddha and he didn't recognize him so
remember in this era there were no videos no Zoom no YouTube no pictures
even to look at right so if you hadn't met somebody in person you didn't know
what they looked like so they're both there at opposite ends of the Potter's
workshop and the Buddha spends most of the night sitting in meditation and basati does that also the
Buddha notices and he has the the thought oh this Clansman conducts
himself in a way that inspires confidence suppose I were to question
him so he asks pukas Sati who his teacher is and pukas Sati says it's the
Buddha and the buas asks him if he has ever met this person that he follows or
would recognize him and fukusa says no and so the Buddha thinks H this
Clansman has gone forth from the home life into home under me suppose I were to teach him the
dhama so I think it's kind of nice that the Buddha didn't try to teach him until he knew that he was a follower first he
asks that so then you know now that he's decided all right pukas Sati is a
follower I'm going to teach him the Dharma he gives a long Dharma talk that
includes the teaching on these four foundations that support an awakened person and he goes on for a long long
time and he's very um kind of detailed and he he speaks quite profoundly he's actually speaking
about nibana some of the time and um so pus Sati I'm I'm
imagining this now it doesn't quite say this in the suta but I'm imagining his eyes getting bigger and bigger and he
realizes oh my gosh this is the Buddha and so um when the teaching is
over he bows deeply and he um I'm paraphrasing what he says he says I'm so
sorry I didn't recognize you and so then they have this nice connection right and
of course it also says that the Buddha realized that basati had a
very mature mind and could could understand a teaching like that and um
sure enough he has some some Awakening from that so that's the part I wanted to share um because maybe one way to read
this story or understand the relevance of this story is that we don't always recognize the
Dharma you know things come up in our practice and we may not see what a great blessing they are or we may not see how
they're actually the fruit of our own wholesomeness or that they're supporting the deepening of our
goodness and we don't always know what's going on in our practice while it's
happening so I want to mention then another teaching that includes these
same four items and this is the teaching that's called the four inspirational
blessings which is the title of this week's series even though that's not
those words are not in the suta that we're talking about so there's a Buddhist another Buddhist teaching where
the earliest version of it we have is in Sanskrit and then it was later translated in tibetan so into Tibetan so
it's still used in the Tibetan tradition and it describes what gives rise to
helpful or wholesome actions in our lives that's what the teaching is about
and it calls those things that give rise to helpful actions in our lives the four
inspirational blessings and they are the blessing of Truth the blessing of
Letting Go the blessing of utter peace and the blessing of
wisdom and when I heard that teaching something tripped in my mind and I kept kind of lingering with it and then I
realized oh that's the same set of four from the poly Canon from maim Manaya 140
we talked about these in a different order I've talked about them in the order they are in M40 which is wisdom
truth Letting Go peace and here they've just taken the wisdom and stuck it on
the on the end so truth Letting Go peace and wisdom but it's the same
list um so the this other teaching is things
that give rise to helpful or wholesome actions in in our lives and so they're called
blessings but seeing how this list of four has persisted across Buddhist
history even when they're given a somewhat different context it gives me some real inspiration and respect for
this set of four for me this says it's it's an important teaching and in my own
practice I have considered these for quite deeply I remember one Retreat where I
just wrote down the phrases not neglect wisdom preserve truth cultivate relinquishment and train for peace and I
kind of put it out on the table where I could see it regularly and I just kind of let them uh Infuse The Retreat and
deepen on their own and I found that in so many cases one or the other of them was really relevant was coming up
so returning to hukus Sati in the PO story in fact that he didn't recognize
the Buddha we may not recognize certain aspects of the Dharma until we've
already experience them so maybe there is one more blessing
which is the blessing of just doing the practice just doing it we just do it
sincerely as best we can and someday we may find ourselves in the
presence of the Buddha we discover that he's right there Sharing The Potter's workshop with us
very close by
so how did these four speak to your practice or how are they living in you
after talking through them this week doing practices
that relate to them or invoke each one and it's not that there needs to be
any huge profound realization or shift but just an invitation to let them keep
living in your heart and to trust that whichever one sort of sticks in your
mind that's probably the one that's important for you right now you don't have to figure it out you
don't even have to understand exactly how it's all working
but part of the beauty and Trust of the path is that the mind is attuned to what
it needs and that things will self-correct over time and new things will come in at
the right time this path
somehow moves between activity and passivity
the the good side of both of those let's say the good side of both of those so sometimes we need to do things and
sometimes it's better if we don't so just check in among these
four truth and letting go and peace and
wisdom which one speaking to you at this moment
yeah it feels complete so thank you for this
week and may your practice continue to evolve in a beautiful
way just keep sitting in the Potter's Workshop thank you