hi folks welcome um yeah good to uh good to be with you
uh um I guess we we meditate so
um yeah let's uh find find a a posture that um balances relaxation alert
if you're tired a on the alert side if you're ramped up air on the relaxed
side and uh yeah just gently find your way into
uh Dharma posture your body but also
your Dharma heart e
so just uh see see if there's something especially uh entangling leftover
from the day or the the
week year
just appreciate what that is maybe you even give it a moment to think
through so long as you don't get more deeply entangled
maybe it feels important
to just [Music] feel the presence of whatever is left
over as the fingerprint it leaves in your emotional body
just give your blessing to those that
affective arousal give your blessing to
it e
we give our blessing to everything so we can put it all
down e
and maybe you really notice the uh the end of few exhalations
maybe you listen out for the most faint distant sound
in your
soundscape maybe you don't even know if you're hearing a sound or
silence e
sweet we look to see what what's a skillful way of attending
to uh vitalize the
Mind tranquilize our
body
e
e for
greed is
tension hatred aversion is
tension self is tension Duality is tension
any holding on at all
tension and so we
relax for
you can't exactly relax through more
willfulness we relax the way we
exhale
e
e e
there a certain measure of uh Faith required
to relinquish uh control
to stop trying to engineer to stop trying
to Solve the Riddle of our life of this
moment
instead to [Music] be softened by the moment
don't look for any foothold in some sort
of
e
e e
just breathing into
the space called me mine
relaxing
e
for
e e
when we command ourselves to to relax it's just
a kind of reiteration of the
clinging the way we fall asleep is a kind
of relinquishment of the
willfulness maybe it's kind of the same for
falling
awake
e
e e
your ground is just openness
e
e e
so uh so thanks folks I put a uh Link in the there uh
the chat um for uh any questions I thought next
week maybe uh respond to a question or two so uh that's there that's Anonymous
if you wish to uh to do
that okay so
um yeah a few few weeks ago I was um I
was leading a a sitting group out of town and a dear dear friend you know
colleague happened to be in the same place at the same time and uh she came to the the class
and um afterwards we were you know we were talking about you know just saying hi
and talking and you know and I said um I said something like uh yeah you know
during the meditation instructions I actually teared up a little bit and she was just like Matthew you
always cry and then and then on uh Sunday I was
finishing an online Retreat you know teaching crying I was like oh my
God I'm a crier I cry cry when I teach
what what is the deal you know and
um so I thought to give a talk about uh crying the the kind of different
uh species of of Tears Dharma tears and
and uh I I've interrogated it myself I've wondered you know like what what
are these I didn't cry today not yet stay strong I you know what what are these
tear about like is it's are they appropriate you know like are and I've
asked the question like okay are they are they a kind of over
disclosure are my tears are kind of Burden in in any way for others or the
kind of messiness that others must contend with uh are my tears somehow
manipulative you know a kind of unconscious attempt to manipulate your
emotions to do something to your
emotional world am I displacing you know something
from my own private suffering and somehow the emotion in the teacher seat
is kind of a kind of placeholder for other feelings that are kind of alien to
me in some way and obviously I can't I can't uh I
can't be sure you know but I I don't think it's any of that actually
uh Becket said um my my words are my
tears and I I've read some some research on uh on crying the kind of the
functions and the the triggers of of tears that varies a lot varies a lot and
um and they're generally like crying generally associated with
unpleasant cataly but joy triggers tears too as we know and tears have int
psychic and also interpersonal effects right many um so on the intas
psychic side many people report like some kind of
cathartic relief from crying the tears are somehow like um a kind of resolution
of emotional dis equilibrium and we we there's some
buildup of something some activation arousal State we we're tense then we the
the process of crying is deescalate that arousal I um I almost
never you know cried as a you know one you obviously as a child but
like once I got a little bit older I didn't didn't um cry as an adolescent or young adult
or anything and I still never cry anything about anything kind of like
narrowly in my life generally um infants Cry of course like the the
interpersonal needs are so obvious there kind of signal and the tears announce a
need and as adult s there may be interpersonal functions
of Tears too right um we we people cry for many reasons but
but apparently one of the main reasons that that people cry as a sense of
helplessness the the researcher said like the inability to act
behaviorally may be a common element of a whole range of different tiers
and we can see that sometimes sometimes our tears are a kind of a kind of plea you know like I can't
do this I need you and maybe sometimes our tears are
just soothing some they are kind of like soothing our sense
of uh soothing Us in the kind of face of powerlessness
I barely cried you know but then I started practicing
Dharma you know and uh especially when I
would do heart practice meta compassion you know it was like a lot of
Tears a lot of tears I heard some teacher say I don't
know who I don't remember but um practice doesn't truly begin until you cry deep playe you
know and there were um there were a lot of a lot of threads kind of bound up in
those those early tears early tears of of some years
really and uh in looking back I feel like oh yeah it was some way in which I
was I was sort of like grieving the suffering of my past you know feeling
the suffering of anger of the aversion that had really defined my life just
feeling that I I was grieving the first Noble Truth in a way it's like the the
enormity of suffering the ungovernable quality of it and it's like oh yeah how
long might it take to truly comprehend dukka you
know long time a lot of grieving
I was I was also crying in um in joy you know it's like it was the the tears of
relief like I kind of like cannot believe how beautiful the path is and
just overwhelmed overwhelmed a certain kind of
gratitude aen aino one one time at a retreat
off-handed they just kind of said like as our path unfolds there's more laughter and more
tearfulness kind of weepiness teaching of course is not a um
is not a performance you know not a
performance we enter the Dharma together as
um we enter together as Children of the Buddha you know and
um yeah I've become in teaching practicing
too uh but I become like very sensitive to when my words feel like they're sort
of bubbling up from my body and when they don't when they feel very near very
near every word I speak is like my body is right with
it and even though I prepare a lot and have a kind of careful
skeletal structure of a of of uh most
talks I I try never to abandon my body I try never to to leave space between my
words and my body and in a sense to stay way to stay
with my body that feels like uh a way of
not leaving you either the tears um they sort of come at
un unpredictable time sometimes they they're
um you know kind some kind of grief you know how how does one understand
anicha the the UNG graspability the changing of all
things how do you understand that and not cry how how can you know anything about
the world about war or oppression or wealth inequality or climate or you know
how do you know any of that not cry sometimes and sometimes the tears are
kind of like um public you know public grieving and I I
sort of feel like sometimes for a person of my social location privilege sometimes
tears are just more powerful than than uh words and
expressing sense of solidarity and um but most often most
often the tears come when this I sense a distinction this very Stark distinction
the Buddhist fundamental distinction between uh suffering and
peace the the kind of it's It's almost like um one cloth being held up against
another different shades and the poignancy of that
difference between suffering and goodness suffering and
peace and there's um a phenomena in in Psychology known as moral elevation
where it's like you witness uh an act of moral beauty or something and it
inspires it elevates our own Hearts you know you see somebody do
something really beautiful it's like how can we not be sort of lifted up by
that and the sense I have have is almost like
um I don't even need to see a hero just the actual
perception of goodness even in a vague way just the perception of goodness in
any moment is the experience of moral elevation it want and sort of like I
just want to be better you know and um
and maybe we can say that um the the kind of the whole of the Dharma
is is about becoming sensitive to to goodness you know uh attuning attuning
to it in any moment taking our cues from it sensing that in our body being lifted up
by it the goodness of letting go of on hate
of not trespassing on the heart of
others the clear wide
openness meta loving kindness is is being moved by your own goodness you
know the love the love for others just follows effortlessly from
that and so tear yeah a lot of Tears a lot of reasons to uh to be moved right
and uh tears are not the last word I 1977 interview with James Baldwin
in the New York Times and um said um said uh
people uh people can cry much easier than they can change a rule of
psychology people like me picked up as kids on the street you
know okay I take that to heart too and
uh yeah so we we cry and our tears direct us back to our body embodied
sense of feeling sense of the Dharma here and then we take our cues
from that live well so I offer that for your
consideration and uh I wish you a good week we'll
um yeah see you next time