so uh welcome good morning good afternoon good evening wherever you
are uh my name is May Elliot and here we are discussing the fourth of the
Buddha's five daily Recollections and this uh this one today
is a really difficult one uh the most difficult for many um and it goes like
this I must be parted and separated from everyone and everything dear and
agreeable to me uh and as with previous days I'll
remind you to gauge your sense of well-being and resiliency this morning
and proceed with caution I if you're feeling well resourced today this
session might be really powerful for you and if not just take care with what feels
right so uh as with each day so far uh we'll practice with this phrase in two
ways during the meditation uh so after sitting quietly for a while um we'll
just drop the phrase into the Mind allowing it to Ripple through um without
any sort of intentional engagement just seeing what naturally arises and then after that I'll offer
some questions so you can actively contemplate the the phrase using thinking yes thinking during a
meditation um but keep a short leash on it so the mind doesn't get discursive so that's a little overview
of what you can expect for today um so let's get started with our
meditation so go ahead and find find a posture that's supportive for you this
morning find something that's comfortable this is given uh how these
phrases are challenging um something that feels um like it allows the body to be relaxed
and at ease beginning to
settle letting go of past thoughts and future thoughts inviting the mind to
come into the body into the ne [Music]
beginning with a few deep breaths if that's helpful for
you and allowing yourself to land
connecting with your anchor the
breath the soundscape global sense of the body
sitting whatever the anchor is for you that helps you stay here that gives you a grounding point that you can come back
to when the mind wanders
be this anchor it's something that's either neutral or even slightly
Pleasant can be um can be challenging for the
mind uh and cause the mind to become weary if our anchor is
unpleasant go ahead and take some time now to
settle to
rest and to unify the mind with the
body
e
e e
before beginning our phrases together can be helpful to warm up the
heart bring a Little Tenderness you might consider an image
of yourself as a child
or just the general sense of a younger [Music]
you bringing this to
mind thinking of some of the positive qualities of this
being of this little kid maybe innocent or loving
friendly
playful and as you do this attending to the sensations that the heart
center and noticing any emotions that might
arise and that might be enough to warm up the heart just a bit if so you can
rest in that [Music] feeling if not you might offer some
phrases of [Music] kindness may you be happy dear one
may you be [Music] healthy may be
safe maybe at ease
just bringing in a little softness here
and letting go of the meta and shifting now to our freees so
I'll offer you this fourth recollection and when I say it all to
drop into your meditation just Ripple through not trying to make anything
happen just seeing what naturally arises in the mind and the heart and being mindful of
that breathing in with compassion I gently remember that I'll
be parted from everyone and everything I old dear
maybe thoughts or emotions arise or maybe thing arises any response is
fine breathing in with compassion I gently remember that I'll be parted from
everyone and everything I all of dear
practicing with this now on your own of your own
Rhythm and at any point you can return to your anchor letting go of the
recollection e
we can care to hold whatever you find gentleness and
kindness if it ends up feeling like too much just letting go of the
phrases you want to avoid weaponizing this practice only doing it when the mind has
enough bandwidth to hold it
maybe letting go of the recollection coming back to your inor and
again resting
there's more residual emotion Sensations in the body or
thoughts making room for them taking good care of
them e
shift now to our engaged contemplation so offer the phrase
again and then I'll I'll also share some questions so for this part you can allow
yourself to contemplate to think about how you might reply to these
questions making sure that the thinking is staying close to the question so that
uh you don't end up on an entirely different topic so we're keeping keeping
an eye on having the discursive mind get out of
hand the praise again I must be parted and separated from everyone and
everything dear and agreeable to
me how deeply do you know this do you know it conceptually only or
do you you know it in your
core you remember this when you interact with your loved ones
what would it be like if you had this in mind when you engaged with those around
you how might it impact those relationships e
does it change what you choose to say or how you choose to say
it does it change your actions what you choose to do and how you do
it does it even change how you think about
people in this way perhaps changing all actions of body speech and mind
what reactions come up for you when you realize you must be parted from everyone
and everything you love
here grief acceptance numbness all natural
responses recognizing and accepting anything that arises
allowing the mind to be wide with lots of
space lots of space to hold whatever it comes up
letting go of the
contemplation resting in the wide spacious
mind resting and loving [Music]
awareness e
being kindness to
ourselves just as all beings wish to be happy I too wish to be happy
be happy healthy safe and at ease
be be happy may they be
healthy may they be safe may they be at ease
welcome back
so for those of you just arriving my name is May Elliot and today we are
focusing on the four of the Buddha's five Daily Reflections bu's five daily
Recollections and for many this is the hardest I must be parted and separated
from everyone and everything dear and agreeable to me this is the
pH so in the uh the Tibetan tradition the great lay teacher and householder
marpa who was in the lineage of naropa he experienced the tragedy of
having his son die and one day Maro was out in his
Fields weeping and his students surprised to see that their teacher was so upset
confront them and they said Master why are you crying you know
you teach us that it's all an illusion including death so why are you
crying and Mara replied yes it's all an illusion and the
death of one's child is the saddest illusion of them all and so I
cry so even for the highly realized or the steadiest of practitioners there's
no denying the grief that can come forth from confronting the loss of a loved
one when the Buddha's two foremost disciples died the Buddha said it was
like having the sun and the moon going out at once these two Bright Lights
dropping from the
sky there was a a time for me as my my practice
deepened where I was grieving the loss of my loved ones but what was odd was
that the loved ones hadn't died and not only that they weren't even sick or particularly old so that is having this
kind of mysterious and unprompted sense of loss uh despite the fact that no one
was lost yet and so I started calling this emotion pre grief and I thought
something might be wrong or I needed to figure out how to get it to stop and then I came across uh these
five daily Recollections and this one specifically the fourth one specifically I must be parted and separated from
everyone and everything dear and agreeable to me and I began to realize
that my pre-brief was actually a textbook example of how the fourth
recollection functions and how it can unfold B for us as we come to to as we come to terms
with the rules of the game that we all die even our beloveds as we realize how
samsara functions uh this this sense of grief is really a natural
response and as I got to know this practice I began to realize that my preg
grief actually wasn't a problem at all um on the contrary it was a healthy purification of the mind and heart even
though my dear ones were healthy alive and present that wouldn't always be the
case so it was my system coming to terms with the way things are and this uh this
loss is the truth of things and my mind needed to grieve through these losses
before it could make peace with them I share this so you know that these
phrases can bring forth a lot of strong feelings and uh you can think of it like
a purification it's the purification practice if you put a dirty towel in the
wash ultimately it'll clean the towel but in the process a lot of dirt comes
out in the water so as we begin to wash the mind with this practice though It ultimately cleans the mind it purifies
the mind and heart um it brings it to a place of of Greater Clarity and freedom
in the process a lot of dirt comes out in the wash and that dirt might be grief
or anger or other challenges emotions so we need to be prepared to meet these
feelings um they should be seen they should be known intended to so if
difficult emotions come up in this practice can we give them the kind and loving attention that they're asking for
tenderness patience companionship and let the feelings move
through you don't block them don't stop them but maybe you don't have to take
them so personally either rather If you experience say
grief uh know that this is the great grief handed down through the
generations of beings moving through all of these lives not personal showing up
now in this body asking for our loving attention here in this body we're
receiving the inheritance of fear of Anger of of all the beings that came
before and you hold the power to meet that inheritance with the love and
attention it has been asking for since time IM Memorial what a task like can we meet
our emotions in this way can we meet these um these
feels um with that sense of purpose that sense of care
now of course we we don't do this practice just so that we can feel difficult emotions ultimately we do this
practice because it leads to Greater freedom and
happiness and by reflecting on this recollection it it can invite more
patience a reduction in irritation easier access to
forgiveness when we don't remember that we'll lose everything we love it's really easy to become trivial with
people you we get wrapped up in our problems uh and we forget the great matter of birth and death Suzuki roshi
founder of San Francisco's Z Center uh would sometimes say sometimes I think that you think
that your problems are more important than being
alone you think that your problems are more important than being
alone so this reflection on loss we're putting things into perspective perhaps just being alive is
a and this remembrance doesn't just purify the mind leading to more freedom
it also shapes our actions how do we act with the ones we
love someone asked the Insight teacher James far is what can I do about my fear
of having my son die and James responded tell him how much you love him
every single day and that's a significant action enough to change a son's life
what if every child had someone tell them they're loved every day maybe
that's an action that can change the whole
world Stephen jenkinson a teacher who works with people who are dying and
their families would say you can't really love something until we
love its ending too we can't really love something until
we love its ending too and what this points to for me is to our
attachments uh to the things we love it is our attachment to the things we love
and we might love something or someone but we don't love its ending because we're attached so one way that this fourth
recollection functions is to weaken and overcome
attachment and it may be worth remembering that this fourth phrase isn't only about losing our loved ones
but it's about losing anything that is dear to us not just our possessions but
say even our senses someday we'll need to say goodbye to seeing hearing
smelling touching tasting what would it be like to say a tender goodbye to each one so this this
recollection invites us to awaken or excuse me to weaken attachment to our
favorite music our most relished Foods the sights of sunsets and all the
beautiful things we're not rejecting these things um but
we're we're seeing that we won't have them forever so there's something that
can awaken us to them while simultaneously weakening the attachment
to them and fundamentally these Recollections are engaging with the second Noble Truth
the source of suffering is craving when we cling we suffer so these
Recollections are functioning to loosen our grip as we learn the art of Awakening we
have insight into the true nature of things we see how our clinging leads to
suffering we see the selfless nature of phenomena and we see that all things are
impermanent and this last insight into the impermanent nature of things it's
really Awakening to loss I had a friend who said her entire Buddhist practice was a grief practice because everything
at one point or another will go uh as Joseph Goldstein says loss is
just another word for change uh if if we're grasping a rope
tightly and it's being through pulled through our hands what happens we get
rope burn so as all things slip through our fingers we can either grip them as
tight as we can and get rope burn or we can learn to let
go and Our intention with this it isn't to try to get rid of our attachment that
just ends up being attachment to being unattached so instead we hold our
attention or we hold our attachment uh gently with open hands with great care
and respect and let it soften in its own time so I'll I'll close with this uh
with a some quotes from Francis Weller who's a master of working with
grief this life we have is incredibly short but we've been blessed with
it when we shut off our grief you forget that to let grief work its Alchemy on
you yields gravitas by which I mean the ability to be present with a Bittersweet
reality of Life which always includes loss the work of the mature person is to
carry grief in one hand and gratitude in the other and to be stretched large by
them so may you have the courage to carry grief in one hand and gratitude in
the other such that you are stretched large by them as you go about your day today I
hope you can experience the preciousness of all the other beings that you
encounter the preciousness of encountering everything you love and so
you can stay close to that feeling and as always please be gentle with yourselves today thank you so much
everyone great to be with you have a good day