so today we are going to continue the series on um practicing with the sense
doors and I'm going to pick up on the theme of yesterday at least
initially which is to practice with
spaces and um spaces between mind the
gap so um taking a moment to adjust your posture maybe wiggle take that last sip
of tea greet your friends if you're on the
chat settle into your body and enjoy the silence if you're not
on the
chat and softening the eyes as if looking out
over a broad M up Big
Sky distant Horizon allowing the eyes to
close then noticing any of the variations of tone light color in the
eyelids softening the muscles
and then softening the [Music] tongue allowing the tip of the tongue to
rest on your pallet of your
mouth noticing any lingering
taste and inviting the whole body to
relax
soften allowing your stomach your belly to be
loose and perhaps taking two or three longer slower maybe even deeper breaths
diaphragmatic
breathing inviting the body heart and mind to be
here
now noticing the sensations of each
breath the little space between each exhale and the next
inhale and then allowing the breathing to be natural and normal
and tuning in also to any ambient sounds in your
space distant sound of vehicles or
animals breathe or water
and ATT tuning to a sense of the distance the
spaciousness between your ears and the sound
and then establishing mindfulness awareness at the
Forefront Gathering your attention on whatever your
primary object anchor of attention
is could be the wash of all of these experiences just moving through
or any one of them sensation sound
breath I'll say a few words about mindfulness of
breathing and feel free to adapt those instructions
noticing the swell of the
inhale the fullness at the top of the
inhale and the release the
relaxation as the exhale
begins staying with all the little changes through the
exhale and resting dropping into the Gap at the end of the exhale a little
Still
Point and allowing the next inhale to naturally
emerge whenever it feels
easeful staying in contact with the
moment and noticing
appreciating any of the silent es the still points the spaces
between relaxing
allowing
receiving
e
e e
you find yourself distracted appreciating the moment of
returning to awareness of the senses awareness of
now rather than judging or criticizing your
practice appreciating the shift from the world of thinking
planning back to the Simplicity and space of the sense
doors
e
e e
from time to time noticing the overall quality of
experience Pleasant unpleasant or neither
staying connected
resting in the sensory spaces
between whenever possible and allowing all of the
rest
e
e e
and then the final moments of our meditation together
the invitation is to gather your attention
in your emotional Center your heart your
core the sense of
appreciation casting memory back remembering
any moments of challenge or difficulty in this
meditation with care and
compassion appreciation for your capacity to keep
showing up be
present recalling that any experience
and be metabolized for further growth
wisdom death and from that place of
care compassion also
appreciating savoring embracing any moments of goodness
mindfulness awareness
patience
spaciousness Azure
present allowing them to nourish your heart and mind
these two are onward
leading and then casting your internal gaze outwards to the others this life
touches here near distant
forming the wish that this practice may have a beneficial
ripple effect for them as
well may our practice here
together be a cause and condition for all
beings to feel safe from harm and causing
harm we all beings to be
peaceful content happy and for all beings
everywhere to be free
thank you for your
practice for
thank you dear s and um I'm curious since many of you are
bowing and um offering appreciations in the chat if you might also if you did it
offer what you noticed in the last 24 hours in terms of Surfing the senses or
noticing gaps spaces in your sensory
experience what um what unfolded for you if anything and it's fine if nothing did
but it's fun for other people too to see
listening more
great I love reading all of the little [Music] um pieces people are
offering about what they've been noticing in their sensory experience the fog the
owls the
sun trying to see things without naming so much yes that can be
profound the aliveness of the landscape the
hills appreciating the gift of Senses yes absolutely
quite a [Music] gift clows and rivers of breath
Sensations these are beautiful we could write a group poem this morning
today thank you I promise I'll read the rest of them later probably need to start talking and offer
special empathy for anyone whose Gap was forgetting to notice the Gap that is also human so human and often the first
step in the practice is noticing afterwards
the wish and then slowly it happens right afterwards and then in real time
and then organically at the
beginning so yesterday we covered hanging out at the sense doors which
which was a couple of different practices that I just mentioned surfing the senses and resting in the spaces
between sensory experiences minding finding the
Gap gaps plural today I want to talk a little bit more about that second
practice of being in the spaces being in the spaciousness that's available at the
sense stor and then bring in a related onward leading practice as
well so I'll recap just a little bit because we barely covered this yesterday but yesterday the invitation in that
second practice was to notice the spaces available between objects between what
meets our senses our eyes ears Etc and to rest there just kind of hang
out there and the space in between can be
between Sensations sounds sight objects like between trees or tree branches
between Hills between our body your body and other things or even a sense of the body
occupying moving through space especially when we tap into the
senses this way they can be doorways to easeful and a radical
Simplicity in present moment experience even if we're moving around and about
our day I've had moments of spaciousness happen even in heavy traffic on Golden
Gate Bridge by noticing this so it's
portable there's this possibility of tapping in to just a touch of comfort
Stillness in any sense experience so
eyes finding this at the eye door we call
it it's the difference between looking at something and seeing that I talked
about the first day that finger wiggling practice of tuning into the peripheral
vision the overall Act of seeing rather than looking softening connecting
appreciating visual receptivity itself and then noticing what artists
refer to and photographers as negative space the space between around and above
things the space between the image of my body in the background for example or
the space around your computer
monitor the space around all of the objects in your
room this has a couple of nice effects one is it actually can
be a way of calming the mind if there's any emotional overwhelm there's
something about doing this that's inherently calming and then whether or not there's
any emotional overwhelm emotional activity it can be an entry point
into a much softer quieter place especially if you're able to notice
vastness of any kind the sky is available to most of
us sometimes I find it helpful to invite this practice with wisdom questions I
call them vas Coons and they are for example am I
aware of what in the
senses and what is the quality of awareness right now
and these are not questions that need to be answered with words or even asked with words it can feel like a sense of a
question mark meeting the moment however you might notice if this
practice works for you a shift in Acuity at the sense door and just to
appreciate rest in that sometimes nonverbally moments
people experience resting at the sense doors especially the visual door but it
can be all of them as a kind of transparency like being a window for
awareness in the world yesterday I also spoke of noticing
the gaps the spaces in physical pain and that can be incredibly powerful
for those of us who have had or have have ongoing chronic discomfort or
pain those with practice experience on this um sit may also have occasionally
noticed that the same kinds of spaces the same kinds of gaps can happen
between thoughts and emotions in your heart and mind even in the midst of
emotional pain and suffering and internal storm
can notice the absence of a thought or painful emotion when shifting to another
sense as well I have an anecdote for this um from a retreat I saw this was
many years ago now well over a decade ago and I did something that I don't
recommend any of you ever do which is I had a difficult conversation with someone right before going into silence
phone call and if you've ever sat a retreat you know that
whatever the last few things you did of consequence are often are featured in your mind sometimes for days or at least
hours and so my mind was just reviewing this conversation and trying to figure
it out and work with it and and da d da da da very unpleasant but the practice was
continuing there' be moments of of presence and then moments of distraction with this
and at a certain point the attention just naturally moved to the space in the sky between the
clouds the sun coming through and the mindfulness was strong enough to notice
that boom the suffering stopped and
then the heart and mind the attention could just hang out
there so the invitation is to notice these kinds of
moment dramatic or small notice your own clouds parting
your own mental story
parting you can notice these gaps at the ears especially the perception of
distance between yourself and what's heard or the silences between the
sounds noticing the ends of a taste or the end of a
smell and noticing moments of balance Stillness
equipoise in your body Stillness between
Sensations it's often our minds that stir up distraction or
activity can you find a place in the body that's still quiet
spaceship and if hanging out at these sense
doors it's also really helpful to notice
V knowing simple knowing of pleasant unpleasant or
neither many of us I would dare say most meditators
after you've been practicing for a little while it's more inherently Pleasant to be with the
Simplicity of the body the moment seeing
hearing tasting then it is to be caught up in
the stories of the Mind the virtual reality knowing simply Pleasant
unpleasant or neither is important information and and it can undercut
reactivity stop stories in their tracks and it begins to deepen these sensory
doorway practices in a wisdom Direction which I'll talk about more tomorrow this
is the deeper end of the pool for this practice but meanwhile it's so simple
just to notice every now and then Pleasant or not or unpleasant
a sense of sufficiency can emerge from practicing with the sense doors in these
ways and that sufficiency contentment
Simplicity generosity help to open any
clenching clutching of the heart and
mind so between now and tomorrow your assignment should you choose to accept
it is to experiment with resting in this simple intimate connection with the
world through noticing again any spaces between sensory experiences around
things within yourself and notice the
vena notice what nourishes you in these
practices thank you so much for your kind attention it's a joy to be with you
[Music] and look forward to being with you again tomorrow