Aran in Burling game hi and this is um sorry who was
this ran in Burling game hi marann
welcome Terren and Squam hi Terren rain in San Francisco hi
rain and your name is similar to what we've been getting a lot recently in San
Francisco very true sweet and oh lots of Hell also in
chat from Red who also said hello and Isabelle from Pacifica and and Sara from
Toronto hello Sara uh hi Noella uh from pal Alton hi Amy who says
Aloha from Sacramento I'm used to you saying Aloha from from Hawaii so here
you are visiting probably family that's very sweet any other hellos before we
begin I see Amy says hi from
SF another Amy two Amy and also now friends are joining us on YouTube great
okay so let's uh let's begin let's formally begin
which is the signal verbal signal for Neil to post information about Happ hour
Google Groups and also information about our um happy hour um break bre breakout
room etiquette and meta which I'll talk about later so at this time I changed the settings so that unmuting yourself
won't be possible I ask you to all mute yourself please if you are [Music]
unmuted and I changed the chat settings right
now and um let's see and hi Lucy from
New Hampshire on on YouTube YouTube folks are joining sweet and last but not
least I'm going to to turn on recording for the sake of Audio
Dharma here we go so hello hello and welcome everyone to happy
hour and um yeah so many relevant themes to
practice with today it's the week of Thanksgiving
in the US which is a holiday for giving thanks it's also
giving season holidays are seasons of generosity of heart letting go and
letting go is both um you know what I love this this this word in poly might
have mentioned it before the word is chaga which is spelled c a g a so
chaga is the movement of the heart that opens up opens and lets go so
it's both a gesture of Letting Go and you can imagine that letting go of
resentment letting go of you know if you're this F this week you're getting together as family where you see them in
a particular way Letting Go Letting Go opening the heart letting go of all of
that Letting Go letting go of stuff you don't need physical stuff emotional
baggage is just letting go putting it down putting it down chaga chaga and
it's the same word chaga which also
means um the heart a heart that is generous a heart that is giving because
it's the same action right it's the same action of opening the hand to give someone to someone else so it's
different from Donna we think of Donna which is the act of giving the the
giving itself or the gift that is given is Donna but chaga is a heart that is
generous that lets go so for me I when I learned this years ago I just became so
happy with you know the heart that lets go the same action of the heart that oh
just opens up and doesn't cling to things resentments and thoughts or whatever it is uh possessions is the
same movement of the heart that just you know get lets go to somebody else is
generous is giv so I've I've loved that so maybe we'll practice with that theme
tonight that's so many lovely theme so let's uh let's explore let's explore
together and oh and just to say oh maybe I'll say one last thing because um the connection to happy hour is this
movement of the heart chaga brings happiness Letting Go brings happiness
brings Joy have you noticed for example if you've claim clean up the clutter in your home and and you've given it all
away oh there's so much happiness and lightness and joy okay great I gave it
all away just cleared up woo same with like letting go of putting down
something that no longer serves in the heart and also generosity
when you give some something to someone when you give a gift you are the one who's happy like Yay you know you as and
the Buddha says that a happiness of generosity comes before giving the gift
while giving the gift after giving the gift while before you give the gift Oh yay giving them a gift the heart is
Happy are they going to like it maybe they doesn't matter you know you're going to be generous you can celebrate your own generosity while you're giving
it to give with a heart of happiness and after you've given to reflect on it and
allow this this chaga this this letting go this release into making someone else
happy to um yeah to to move actually as I'm talking about this I just realized
oh yeah this is this is one formula one way I can talk about it so chaga letting
go that makes you happy some well CH when you put something down when you
release you make yourself happy you may also when you that chaga
is an act of generosity you're giving something to others you both make yourself happy and others happy so so
just came up with that formula so chaga can show up in different ways anyway I'm excited by chaga as you can tell all
right so let's let's practice together let's land let's land in our
postures let's arrive and let go let go what
Down release it's a release it's not a throwing down it's not
a disliking or hating it's none of that it's a release the same way that you
would release a helium balloon ah you let it go let go
of any tension relax relaxing into the
chair and when I invite you to let go of tension again not all of it is possible
but maybe letting go of tightening that we can let go
of if you're aware that some muscles are being held tight maybe you're holding
tight your forehead that you are not quite aware of
until I met anent oh yeah I can release can release my
eyes around the socket I can let my forehead oh my jaw
wow feel the tension there I can relax let
go of the extra tightness holding that's not needed extra effort that's not
needed right now
maybe your hands your fists are being clenched as Habit unbeknown to you can
soften let go of this tightening that's not needed
notice in your own way your body they
Holdings tightenings that could be
released let go
of release some more and then a little more challenge
yourself to release just a little more into
deep Letting Go
relaxation and letting go of thoughts there stories that keep
coming thank you smilingly release them right
now later I'll come back to you
later release as much as can be released
and see I how the mind knowing can connect
with the breath in breath and out breath there can be more release letting go with
every out breath that is our practice right now very simple
and each out breath is a new opportunity for release for letting
go maybe a thought has arisen a story don't need this one right now
release thank you release
release into ease into peace
that is our practice keep keep releasing keep releasing into
peace into ease powerful practice simple but
powerful keep letting go keep clearing the Clutter of your
body your mind keep letting go gently lovingly releasing with every out
breath
e e
let go make space make space
space in your mind and your
heart your body and your
life
e e
keep letting go keep releasing keep
dropping imagine feeling embodied feeling as if you're
hope holding a heavy Rock grasping a heavy Rock and then you
open your hand you let it go raw
raw could be Heavy rock you can imagine releasing your feather Letting Go the same gesture of
opening your hand Letting Go letting go whatever your
mind takes a hold of the
instruction is to let go of the grasp of the Mind
release release gently release Let It Drop this is powerful
practice can really settle the Mind into somebody
and deep
peace
e
e e
now as we've been practicing with releasing Letting
Go tune into how release both brings peace and
ease this quiet contentment that's
glad that's
happy this more space brings happiness contentment for you for
me person who's doing this
practice and I like to invite you for the fast for the last few minutes
imagine releasing onto someone else something
you have maybe your time your affection your kind words maybe a
smile maybe a resource you have to another being or organization or
whatever comes up either something you've just done maybe recollecting
remembering this act of chaga letting go
generosity You' released you've given someone something you've had and see how
that brings ease happiness
expansiveness feel into it celebrate it it's the same movement of the heart
also appreciate that on some [Music]
level on some level there is not a giver or receiver of gift
it's all interplay it's all an
interplay of sharing goodness resources as we give we also receive
graciousness uplift in the heart appreciation the person who receives is
also giving gladness giving vulnerability to receive
opening themselves so it's such a deep teaching so many levels
here as we bring this practice to a close appreciating ourselves for having
showed up and releasing any Judgment of how this was or wasn't was
distracted it was this it was that it's okay let it go let it go you've done
your best you've showed up you've planted seeds trust it celebrate the
goodness and joining our hearts to share the goodness of our
practice this co-created goodness with all beings may all beings everywhere
including myself be happy and be free
[Music]
thanks everyone thanks for your
practice so three prompts three Explorations that I'd like to invite you
to [Music] explore and one exploration
is one prompt is what was this practice like this practice of continuously
Letting Go which is quite a profound practice um it's actually one practice
of leading into concentration Som could be very strong practice of course your
mileage could vary and curious what came up for you explore what was it like to
keep letting go Let it go Let it go into spaciousness into ease not holding on
not being loyal to our suffering not being loyal to our stories that's the first prompt for the
first round just feeling us filling it into our bodies the second prompt is what would
be helpful to let go of to release right now exploring that is there an object
that would be helpful to let go of to feel lighter
um for your own sake and then the third prompt is is there something that
actually the second part could be object could be a grudge could be something
emotional or physical to release and the third is
um what would be helpful for you and someone else to release and an act of
giving an act of generosity that again could be an object could be your time
smile forgiveness Joy calling someone up giving them your care
something that would benefit you and others so those are the three rounds of our
exploration tonight with the uh yeah as we as we engage with one another in the
breakouts and um and I'm going to pause the recording
and and talk about practicing meta in in small groups considering the groups as a
continuation of the meditation embracing compassion talking
staying on topic the three prompts I gave you in the three rounds first one
was remember what what the meditation was like second prompt what would be
helpful for you to let go of third prombo would be helpful for you and
someone else as an act of generosity so those are three promps through three rounds you're going to go around and
round in three rounds as much as you get to be brief talk on topic be brief let
everyone share avoiding cross talk commenting on others all that okay so
I'm going to create the breakout rooms and as always want to invite you to practice kindness
generosity care meta look to yourself for yourself and for others caring for
yourself caring for others um this is really the small groups is where the meta hits the road the rubber
meets the road it's the where the mentor meets the road so all right so let's see how the groups
look and uh yeah let's you know maybe I'll hold
on I'm GNA do something here all right I'm gon to open them all
in a moment wait I need to move and
shift one more time hold done okay all right opening the rooms take care of
yourselves take care of one
another
e
e e
you are now in the main session welcome back
everyone I hope you had time for all three inquiries gave you just a little
more time tonight yeah maybe no I didn't have enough time I see some nods okay good if not enough time sorry I would
love to hear from you what what uh what revealed itself what uh yeah what did
you discover your practice would love to have you share in the big group and chat
is open also if you want to uh type in chat
um see there type in chat you can raise your
Zoom hand chat is open and can also raise your Zoom
hand can also raise your hand and wave I might see you not in the main screen but
I have a s oh there Jesse I see you okay
great thank you Nikki yeah thank you for sharing about chaga that was really
helpful for my practice something to Aspire to um yeah the practice for me
especially question two um I found myself coming up with quite a long list of things that I could
let go of and so I felt some overwhelm this is a time of the year
where I I tend to reflect on self-improvement and I'm at a time in my
life midlife I don't know it's like the double Focus I'm a time in my life when
I'm really focusing on what's how can I improve what's my
impact how can I live my vision how can I be of service to the world so it felt
like a lot um but it was a really helpful practice thank you yeah thank
you Jesse I appreciate um what you shared I I I'll tell you one thing that
your reflection uh brought up well many things brought up for me that that you know the beauty of of reflecting at the
end of the year how can I preserve how can I um how can I Aspire aspire to be
um you know the best version of myself this being you know not competing with anyone else but myself and then what one
thing you said which is self-improvement and that I want to invite you to put a question mark next to um which might
seem kind of quizzical like wait what what what's wrong with that there's some
about the project of self-improvement in framing it that way that has could have
the sense of overwhelm that that you're describing that and also the sense of not
enoughness that I'm just I'm not enough and this is not good so I have to improve this thing who's me
self-improvement there's there's a particular frame that particular Trope that the Western culture can fall into
especially there's so many um you know um podcast and this for
self-improvement do this and do that and do this and do this and do I don't know 100 reps of this part like it just seems
like endless like it feels like we got to add o actually as I say that my heart feels kind
of contracted um feels like there's more and more to
add not to say there's excellent advice there's various things that e wonderful
habits that we do want to to um to take on wholesome habits and yet I think I
want to to um to advise you to be more
generous with yourself you know this being the the um perspective as of
aspiration allows for rest allows for letting go yet the frame of
self-improvement can be can become a little tight so just offering that for reflection if that's might be
helpful thank you Nikki thank you Jesse thank you so much
Richard while you're unmuting yourself I see Bill posted one of the Dharma teachers I listen to referred to the
subtle violence of self-improvement yep that's it yeah I wasn't gonna be that
um um yeah that oh what's the word I want to use um ex not explicit but
anyway yeah I'm more gentle in my choice of words but yes I I I agree with that
too there is a cell violence to it Richard you're up okay in my 20s I was
high up on a ladder and I started falling backwards I knew I couldn't stop
myself and without planning or whatever I just sort of automatically felt like a
ragd doile and I didn't hurt myself at all
you know it was like falling on cushions or something and and I've kept that
memory alive that sometimes when I meditate I
just recall that and just you know relax into it and let go
that way rather than one one little thing at a time kind of thing yeah yeah
yeah yeah I I so appreciate you raising that yeah that is one um meditation and
structure instruction that I use as well which is it's like falling backwards
like you're just falling you're you're letting go completely with everything in
your body you're letting go and I love that and I practice that Richard so I'm
so glad you brought that up the idea of letting go a little bit is just to get that idea of what it feels like to let
go so that one feels you know your practice one practices little by little by little so one feels safe enough to
just like complete body letting go so I'm so glad you have that memory felt
sense memory cuz that kind that kind of practice is very powerful very um
opening relaxing and and yeah uh centering that that complete embodied
letting go love it thanks Richard thank you and yeah for others who who feel
safe enough with all the other Letting Go than what Richard was pointing to and
that's yeah ex explore that please Diana
um I love this practice tonight the idea the the term Letting Go has almost
become an annoyance for me I've heard at least a 100,000 times from many of all
my esteemed teachers on tapes in lectures Let It Go
Just Just Let It Go like that so I'm sitting back like this Sly literally
how I go poof and and boing and it's gone whatever the it is and so in this
case tonight and a few other times and i' I've learned it was about process or way to
do it that was with breathing and it was that continuous
um staying with it um on and on that
helped measurably and I began to feel some peace come just staying with with
each time in that slow process and so I just felt such confidence in listening
to that and I thought obviously that can translate into the larger line it seems to me that
the other way that's come to me is is this when I can recognize when I recognize something that and I see
something sometimes there's like a a recognition of something and then it just dissolves or something but um I
just love tonight's practice in terms of just healthful
so I promise to try not to be so annoyed by hearing this all the
time I feel help is now what do I do great di yeah I love I love what you
said thank you so much for sharing yeah it's yeah so helpful for what you said because often when we hear the
instruction which is beautiful instruction very wise but often that comes up and I've heard many
practitioners over the years say like how do I let go what I like I want to
let go how do I like how how do I put it down so so yeah how do I do it so um so yes
there is a method it's it's it's you you observe what the mind what the body is
is grabbing on you you become more observant and then ah you release you're
gently ever so release with the out breath with the body and it's a practice it's a training we learn more and more
how to do it and now that Diana you've you've practiced it what it means I
don't think you're going to become annoyed because you know like oh yeah that's what they're pointing to okay okay that's what they're talking about I
I know how to do that I've done that I I know how to do this I'm going to yeah this is great thank you thank you Diana
oh that makes my heart so happy that's just great Sara sar from Toronto please you
can unmute yourself thank you thanks Nikki um you
said something in the beginning about uh like letting go of objects that are we
don't use anymore but also letting go of this emotional maybe baggages that are not useful and
that was really close to my heart like it really made sense to me and I realize that it's e like some of the things that
I need to let go are related to forgiveness and I find it much easier to
forgive others but it's very difficult for me to forgive myself um and I wanted
to ask for your thoughts especially because you feel like it's not always just being harsh on your self or like
self-improvement but also feeling that like I expect more from myself and just
disappointed yeah yeah yeah thank ah thank you Sarah John I also see hearts
showing up in the chat for your practice and for you
yeah it is very common for all of us
human beings um forgiving others is easier than forgiving ourselves it's of
course it is we're harder on ourselves than anyone else
um and of course of course of course and of course we have high expectations of
ourselves and sometimes we look back and we think oh how could you how could I
how how oh and maybe the other person the person has forgiven us loves us no
it's it's okay with them for example in some cases that could be the case but still or holding on but how how could I
oh so so to understand to really
appreciate that the version of you who was acting at that time the version of
you whom you were at the time she was doing her best she was
doing the best she could at that time given everything she had given all the
physical limited physical mental resources all the stresses she had all
the the expectations all the information she had everything like all the causes
and conditions that came to make that decision that happened at that time if
if you unrolled yourself your present you know hindsight is 2020 have much more information you can see better see
how things unfolded all that but at the time the
person you were this this this dear poor sweet person who was caught in this
challenging situation that was doing the best she could and that's the best she
could do at the time to forgive her for her limited ability for limited Vision
limited information limited resources limited all I forgive you you were doing
your best I know I know I know I see you and you were doing your best I see you
and and let her let her be she's she it was hard enough for her whatever it was
it was hard enough doesn't need the older version of you to beat her up she
it was hard enough what she was going through I hope that was helpful thanks
so much for bringing that in Sor so well the time has come for us to
um yeah close our practice together let's dedicate it dedicate the Merit of
our practice as we've explored today Letting Go
releasing in all its ways and ways that are meaningful for us for for the
benefit of ourselves and others may all beings everywhere benefit from our
practice from our cultivation of Letting Go releasing generosity may all beings be
well may all beings be free including
[Music] ourselves thanks everyone thank you
Sanaa I am going to stop