welcome greetings so today we'll
finish with our exploration of the five precepts at least in this in this uh
Gathering I very much hope that this has been inspiring to people to
undertake some um mindful attention to these the
ideas in these precepts if not the precepts themselves but certainly consider making these commitments to
explore non-harming action in our practice as a support for
practice and take them out into the world may they may they benefit all
beings today we'll talk about the fifth precept I joked yesterday that it was
appropriate for Friday because this is the precept that warns us against or
that's the wrong phrasing encourage us us to abstain from from intoxicated
heedlessness we'll talk about what that means after we sit together but
uh in the joking manner or light-hearted manner I hope I've conveyed also that
this practice of five precepts can be taken on with a light heart with a
smile uh almost with a sense of play it's a it's an opportunity to find out
how we show up in the world and really it's a it's a way to let our strengths
our natural and authentic capacities for doing good emerge by clearing away some
of the harmful activities we're we engage in or that we're tempted to engage
in so let's meditate to start with prepare our minds for the Dharma with
with a half hour Set uh find yourself into your
meditation posture of emphasized earlier this week and the guided finding some balance or
it's actually not finding balance searching for balance cultivating balance as much as noticing the balance
that's there when we bring our attention Inward and downward from the outside world to this
inner life from the head to the heart from the heart to the
body balancing and rebalancing again and again the tightness the wrapped upness
of the Mind in thought with the Stillness that's available here with the
breath the heess and nowness of our experience that's in the center of
things along with the breathing today we'll spend a little bit
more time than we have with connecting with the breath so we can do it in this way this
today in this meditation when we do this activity that strengthens our
mindfulness of redirecting attention back to the center of things back to the
ground back to our rootedness here now using the breath most commonly as an
anchor as a way to
reenter we can we can notice how the mind connects
with the breath and with the qualities that are inherent in the
breathing in ways that let a little bit of the breaths natural characteristics
and qualities rub off on the mind if you
will when we find ourselves caught up in thought thinking about the future
thinking about the past thinking about other people thinking about
ourselves we can notice maybe that it's a little tight maybe the pace of things
picks up the speed of thought is quite quick maybe we notice it's a little off
Balan where we feel a little off-kilter when we return attention to the breath
we connect the mind with the Simplicity of the breath
the slow pace of the breath the uncomplicated nature of the
breath the balance of the breath and these qualities sort of rub
off on the mind when the Mind rests here the mind can enjoy the Stillness
the balance the Simplicity and the slow pace that are natural to the breathing
in meditation
when the mind gets sort of tight caught up around a thought something that's got to be done today something that was done
or maybe left undone yesterday some interaction we expect
with someone else or had with someone else some concern with ourselves the
usual places that the Mind helps us and can get us caught up and
Tangled when we when we open back up to the breathing in the middle of things bringing the breathing back to the
center of attention to the forground
we can notice the Mind connecting with other aspects of the
breathing the breathing doesn't need to plan the next breath
the breathing seems to be extremely confident in this breath
right here this one and now this
one breath doesn't concern itself about the breath five or 10 breaths ago
that it wasn't good enough wasn't adequate fell short should have been
better no the breath is just right
here the breath doesn't criticize itself
for being as it is the breath doesn't aspire to become a master
breather so again a light-hearted playful way of recognizing that when we
bring attention back to the breathing we can connect with all these wonderful qualities of the breath and they're just
natural to the breath we don't have to do anything except for make the connection keep
reintroducing the the mind to this place of rest in the breath and just let those good qualities
of the breathing slow steady
confident here now balanced simple
just let those rub off on the mind the Mind likes this the Mind enjoys this
rest this gentle breathing in and out even if it's sometimes quivery sometimes
deeper shallower slower
quicker the breathing can be a place for the mind to
rest
e
e e
so so as we reconnect again and again with the Here and Now by way of connecting introducing and reintroducing
the mind with the with the Simplicity the slow pace
the balance of the body of the
breathing we can make this a Point of Departure for dedicating the Merit of our practice
today and we share some of the ease and calm that comes to us in the meditation
with others can we lean into a heartfelt wish
that others benefit from the practice knowing that when others
benefit we also
benefit so so wishing all beings well wishing all beings safety security
Freedom from Want wishing all
beings Comfort ease wishing all
beings freedom from suffering may all beings be happy
[Music]
welcome again everyone greetings and thank you for this week of practice together appreciate you including me
in this wonderful Community still following the chat over here um so yeah
today we'll bring our uh exploration of the five precepts to a temporary
conclusion because I fully hope that you'll continue making
these commitments to avoiding harm harmful activity that you'll make these
part of your regular practice
um I think another thing that makes some distinct from Commandments is that they're fun to work with actually
they're freeing to work with and so that can make them quite enjoyable to work
with before I jump into them uh several people asked last time and I I mention
it I mentioned it sorry looking at the chat um because several people asked
where do I teach and this gives me an opportunity to tell you if you don't know already about some other offerings
of IMC because that's where I that's where I teach IMC and Affiliated organizations I teach occasionally in
imc's year round Eightfold Path program if you don't know it's out there check it out um opportunity to work through
the uh steps of the eful path over the course of a year coming to a close now begins again late summer keep an eye on
the IMC website I teach at IRC the re Retreat
Center um and be aware on the IRC website that there are new listings for
what we're calling off-site Retreats offered by um a new group of IMC
teachers and teacher trainees over the next couple years all sorts of different kinds of Retreats that allow us to
expand outside of the IRC um format and uh accommodate many more practitioners
than can be accommodated at IRC and then I also give I also teach
with others um through the Sati Center and I there I teach with colleagues you
may know Diana Clark Kim Allen Ying Chen and I have taught for several years now ongoing
series of study and practice courses with more coming up this summer we also
teach a retreat together and finally occasionally I teach with Andrea Castillo in Spanish
both course of suta study this year and uh at the retreat center so check those
out check out the IMC offerings on the Spanish parts of the website and uh you
know the regular Tuesday night group and if you're a Spanish-speaking
practitioner okay I didn't want to spend much time on that but I did end the meditation a minute
early uh always love to talk about other the
offerings so the fifth precept is a uh is a precept in which we undertake a
commitment to refrain from what I've called over the course of the week it's a tongue twister I know but intoxicated
heedlessness I found myself liking this phrase because I think it brings attention to the the challenge of um
this uh precept rather than again a commandment a rule to
not not you know not take drugs not drink
which um it just wouldn't be super helpful I don't think but the focus is
on in a way heedlessness and other words that can translate the term that's used
in P pada um negligence indolence remissness carelessness
um the particular challenge of intoxicants of all kinds is that they
they lead us into actions that are can cause harm it's not so much that and then can
cause physical harm to ourselves obviously um but the uh it's that
heedless careless action that can result from intoxication that is the that is
the thing to watch one thing that can be noticed in our
lives and practice and this is an ancient thing probably as long as there's been fully modern hom Homo
sapiens there has been the urge to intoxication and in that way
to um
transcend this you know this body this Earthly realm this human life uh even if
it's brief even if it has side effects even if you wake up and not feeling good
the next day um that urge is very old and this precept can bring our attention
to that urge to not only intoxication but to the carelessness or the carefreeness that comes with it and for
interacting with this the Buddha had a framework uh that turns up with frequency in the sutas and it's not as
uh in the discourses and it's not as commonly talked about as Frameworks like the four no truths for
example but it's referred to as the gratification the danger and the Escape sort of a three-part way of looking I
think particularly useful in looking at the fifth precept and are I don't want to say Universal but uh an very common
urge to urge to heedlessness urge to intoxication urge to leaving it all
behind stepping outside of it for a period of time
um the um the idea there is just that in the
things we we use as intoxicants and again the prescription is very specific
in the language actually it's not that specific but it it calls out fermented beverages still
Beverages and other substances yeah Maja other substances
that intoxicate and can lead to heedlessness but I think we could can extend that to behaviors gambling binge
shopping I'm sorry retail therapy binge watching friends there can be a lot of different ways that we um seek to step
outside our suffering or to distract ourselves and that's the tendency to watch but to recognize first that
there's gratification in that that that it's hard life that there's suffering in
it right as we know from the first Noble Truth that this UNS
satisfactoriness and the challenge of living in a world of impermanence and
unreliability of experience it gets to us and it causes um it causes stress
that we would like to relieve and we looked all sorts of ways of doing this some are healthier some are more
skillful than others but noticing that this provides
gratification and what it does in the system can be extremely EX extremely
important because it brings us closer to understanding our suffering the danger can be pretty
obvious we notice that in this case the particular danger of intoxicated
heedlessness is the heedlessness the carelessness the um what was another
word I used remissness the negligence a lot of different words that come in there that help us understand that
that's the danger of of the thing maybe it's the hangover maybe it's the physical harm those things are important
maybe maybe it's you know harm caused to others by our absence or our distraction
or our inability to be present with others but we can notice that the
principal danger is that we we make decisions that we engage in actions that
um don't um have in them appropriate care for ourselves or others and that
cause harm and then finally the idea of the Escape I say finally third the idea of
Escape that there there is from this cycle of gratification and danger that
we can get kind of caught up in there is an escape and of course the Buddhist
remedy is this practice that um this is a way to get close to our suffering
understand it and uh ease it and that this is a way out and this it doubles
back on itself as so much practice does that this way right here even meeting together and practicing
together this way right here helps address the the gratification we find in
um intoxicants and the the danger of getting caught up in them but paying attention um to what's
going on in our experience in the meditation in particular is um you know
is the escapees a strong word but is certainly an antidote to
um an antidote to the intoxication that leads to
harmless uh sorry harmful um
heedlessness so two thoughts for the day I'm going to say a few things and then just spend a couple minutes summarizing
so going a little bit more quickly through the fifth precept than we did with precepts two through four we did do
a little intro with the first precept but wanted to summarize a little bit at
the end so here's a couple thoughts for the day one of the most useful um ways
that has worked for me in in working with the fifth precept
is practice known as urge surfing urge surfing some of you are probably familiar with this again not much
original here the recognition that strong emotions including something like
the Temptation or the urge to to become intox to lead you know to step outside
this human life for a brief moment um or a period of time uh through a uh unskillful
activity uh usually lasts for 90 seconds right any strong emotion typically Peaks
like the crest of a wave in 90 seconds and this is a practice of riding out that
wave as a surfer would I don't surf so the metaphor is a little lost on me but
I have watched Surfers I get the idea that a wave has a Crest and if you can
wait through it recognizing fully present with it noticing it happening
um with after a fairly brief time which can be a difficult and painful time
urges recede and it can be an opportunity to watch urges come and
go um the I think it can be really useful
to watch the urge I uh have for for many years I used to enjoy a cold I I hope
I'm not oversharing here a cold beer in the afternoon and um I've been very grateful
for the um the explosion of all sorts of non-alcoholic bruise of quality in the
last I don't know 10 years what I can bring attention to that's really interesting and I encourage you to do
this with whatever you know intoxicant you've had maybe some challenges with um
and again that can be all sorts of different behaviors is to choose something that um allows you to explore
the urge to intoxicated heedlessness or intoxicated freedom from this
realm um but doesn't provide the intoxication but allows understanding
that urge to that gratification and perhaps the urge to that that
heedlessness um it really brings us it can bring us very close to our suffering what is it that I want relief from oh
it's this it's this and being it allows us to be close with that instead of
papering it over or balancing it with good feelings or all the sorts of things
that these kinds of intoxicants behaviors and substances alike can bring us so use it as an opportunity to get
close to yourself to get close to use the practice to get intimate with your experience including the urges that a
lot of times we look away from we don't really want to we don't really want to know them and
uh this practice encourages us to get close to that stuff step in it know
ourselves know that suffering get close to it pay attention to it learn from
it so anyway think about that Friday night
right so a little bit of review may be useful in the in the closing minutes
um engaging with these teachings with this with this teaching of the precepts
as I kind of discovered for myself in talking with you yesterday uh is interesting in part because the
abstaining from these things is so freeing that they it does support practice to engage in leaving something
behind maybe that should be no surprise it should be no surp surprise to me that letting go is freeing but I it's
interesting that this is what the precepts are about they're another way of letting go there another way of
inclining the Mind toward Simplicity and particularly uh something
that sort of come to me this week is when we let some of these behaviors go um one of the beauties of um the
commitment to abstain or refrain from harm from harmful actions is that it's
not an injunction to do the opposite right these it doesn't say these
precepts don't say engage in skillful speech engage in giving engage in protecting life helping life Thrive
engage in loyal sexual relationships or engage in sobriety they don't say engage
what they do is leave room to see what emerges in our practice right because
the freeing that happens is very individual and has as many variations as there are people here
today and people who practice what we do is we clear those those unskillful activities out of the
way we get out of our own way and then we can watch what emerges what particular skillful activities can I
authentically and naturally offer to the practice to the world to others to myself each of us will be
different and I think when we clear away some of this you know even if they're not super harmful activities they may
not be particularly beneficial and it allows us to watch oh here's this
arising here's an urge to care here's an urge to be fully present with this
suffering here's an urge to give something instead of taking something I could go on and on here's an urge to listen more carefully to give attention
to somebody I've said it several times this week but the more we do this the more
likely it is that end up eventually in a place where we're unable to engage in harmful activity and and beneficial
activity just emerges naturally from our practice we're kind of out of the way as
actors and actions come forth that are that uh are
beneficial and to end on that note I want to quote I've been thinking of this all week actually um from the first time
I said that this isn't about actors it's about actions the famous Suzuki roshi
quote I hope I can get it right or right enough um I think of it because Suzuki
roshi was such an important influence on Gil his thinking his teaching um but he has a famous quote
where he says strictly I think I get it right strictly speaking there is no such thing as enlightened beings there's just
enlightened activity and maybe this is something to take forward
into uh the weekend at least or maybe just the next moment strictly speaking
there's no such thing as enlightened beings just enlightened activity so it's really when we get out of the way in
this way we uh allow activities to come forward when we bring attention to our
activities and stop beating ourselves up for being being bad being not perfect actors we allow this free emergence of
activities that support us support our practice help ourselves help other
beings so with that in mind uh a general dedication of Merit for our
practice this week so much appreciate you uh allowing me to share the Dharma with you in this you know kind of
unusual way for me uh where I can't see anybody um I know you're out there love the chat um I'll be back probably
sometime I think in July to again step sit in for Gil and I look forward to
that very much having done this now this week so take care I'll let the chat run
for a while uh um and follow that after we sign off but take care all have a
wonderful weekend and uh May our paths cross again soon take
care