so uh so welcome folks um uh good morning for most of
you um lovely to see uh See the names and um I just posted at the the the
request of uh some sa members um a link in the in the chat but also it's in the
YouTube video description for today and it's also on the
um IMC calendar posted it with a link
to uh uh an optional Zoom meeting at
8:00 today so 15 minutes after this ends uh if you want to uh come say hello to
uh fellow practitioners um that Zoom room will uh be open at at 8 Pacific
time so in an hour and uh we'll just have a chance to say hello and you know for for you to talk to to each
other um okay so uh so let's um that's
it
e
e e
uh sensing into where feels appropriate to
attend we take our cues from
the teachings from the Buddha from the
lineage
but in an important sense we actually have
to blaze our own
path we have to find how the the Dharma will incarnate
in our
life
e
e e
it's all phenomena as if the the budha were whispering in your
ear to let
go to not be afraid of
Silence
e
e e
just letting the uh silent presence of the
S support
you kind of network of goodwi and care
just to remember how much ordinary goodness there is in the
world let that soothe your heart
make the letting go feel uh
safer
e
e e
we offer a kind of radical
permission for the conditions of our life to be as they are in this
moment and in another moment later
today rest of our life it'll be wisdom that determines
the relative balance of passivity and
activity to say yes deeply to this moment does not imply
passivity for all time
it is to
uh cease disputing what has already
Arisen
now
e
e e
[Music]
for
e e
okay folks uh it's good to uh sit with you it's kind of mostly uh quiet s it's
nice um yeah so thank you uh thank you for having me
this week um uh yeah it's nice
to yeah know enough of of your names that um it doesn't feel like uh
weird substitute teacher gig where students are kind
of little weary or something anyway it's been appreciate the warm welcome and um yeah grateful to all the
people uh who've been supportive um uh you know I was scheduled by Nancy
a long time ago uh uh Dimitra Julie
Kevin helping edit Gil the steadiness of Gil over all these years to uh sustain
this people involved with you setting up the YouTube thing Paul the treasure you
know uh um doing accounting work with donations and just a there's a lot I'm
leaving out a lot anyway point is actually takes a lot of Goodwill and
kindness just to be here together and I'm uh appreciative of
that so
um ajin ajun basa wishes that um that uh all beings
dance at ease in the breeze with Minds left
silent by laying to rest all
things and uh dukka has displaced Dua which has
displaced Dua and in a way it's hard to keep track of
all the things we might worry about is so much
to uh care about so much to to uh to love and it's almost like uh
our nervous system wasn't really designed to care all the time it's how
it feels to me it's like I don't
think ER this system was designed into care
all the time equinity is uh love in the face of the
endlessness of samsara the ungovernability of
suffering and because we can influence sometimes it lures us into the delusion
that we govern something so equinity still
but not rigid aent suito said kind of quiet love
respectful and this capacity is so important because the central biological
impulse is really to
influence conditions to influence this realm s and to act upon the world to control
conditions this runs very deep maybe is the deepest impulse in an
animal and we need to find ways of
resting and so equinity is is um is important
and but it's not alone it's in uh deep
relationship with compassion they they really need each other one
without the other be very awkward so compassion is
essential and caring is costly caring is
costly so this is uh there's a whole backstory to this but there's a research
study from a couple years ago um the author right many suggest empathy which involves sharing others
experience can be biased and exhausting whereas warm compassionate concern is
more rewarding and sustainable if compassion is indeed warm and a positive experience then people
should be motivated to seek it out when given the opportunity here we ask whether people
spontaneously chose to feel compassion and whether such choices are associated
with perceiving compassion as cognitively costly across all studies we found that
people opted to avoid compassion when given the opportunity reported compassion to be
more cognitively taxing than empathy and
Detachment and opted to feel compassion less often to the degree they viewed
compassion as cognitively
costly so these are uh meditation naive people people have
not practiced and I'm sure we can get better
I'm sure compassion can be less costly I'm sure compassion can be more deeply
rewarding but I don't think the cost is ever
zero and so how do we balance our love and our
peace and I I can kind of sense The evolutionary mismatch in the sense of
like what what helped my beloved monkey ancestors
Thrive doesn't totally work in 2024 in
Berkeley it's just intense to care to care about one's life to care about
others to care about the world to care about people wherever they may be in
time future
Generations so equinity is about uh purifying the nature of our
care of making it sustainable of loving
efficiently of relinquishing inefficient suffering a kind of suffering that feels
like our heart has to do but it's doing no good for oneself for
others a flower not meant to bloom all
the time we can consider sleep
which has real risk real opportunity cost a pervasive sense of disconnection from
the environment right totally
undefended but necessary for our functioning for for our you know brain
health for learning for growth sleep's important and what's the equivalent of
sleep for our heart our heart needs to rest too and maybe
equinity is a kind of deep rest for our heart our heart
needs moments of being unstimulated but unstimulated does not
mean closed or collapsed you know we we try to rest
through more stimulation we sort of Chase one intensity with another compulsive
technological use whatever may be we we sort of cocoon in
unconsciousness and I'm not entirely dismissive of that that's a kind of
rest but our heart is still highly stimulated even in the
Cocoon of unconsciousness and equinity is is a kind of true rest
teach us to Care and not to care TS Elliot writes and it sounds harsh what
do you mean teach us not to
care we practice caring but also uh
the appreciation that um our wishes do not govern the first Noble
Truth and in some moments it's actually skillful to put down the all of the
wishing the the Buddha was worried about uh
nihilism um in
emptiness Experience One experience is highly interchangeable with
others in a sense the raw material of samsora does not matter matter much at
all a sight is a sound is a sensation Pleasant is unpleasant is
neutral it doesn't matter at all and sometimes people get the sense
that uh that LE that that nothing means
anything and on the other side we we often live with the sense that everything means everything but between
nothing means every anything and everything means
everything we find our life it's the middle
path this is a kind of balance of equinity and
compassion and the equinity one of its functions it seems
to me is um is to
to purify or compassion to distill out
the what is not pure gold in
it and so equinity is a kind of crosscheck in a way a a practice of
purifying the nature of our care such that our compassion
becomes less compulsive less maybe we say
codependent less grandiose less
self-righteous there's something about moving between uh compassion and equinity that
helps illuminate those grizzled bits of
whatever in our
care equinity uh I sometimes say is is
about refining our relationship to
helplessness even when All Is
Lost all is not
lost so we we want to
find a posture for our
heart that is not collapsed not nihilistic
not apathetic but a way of resting in the
face of our nearly complete
helplessness and can we do that in a way that doesn't harm our heart
and as we do this as we refine our love purify our
care um the actions arising from equinity become more potent
have greater moral force greater persuasive Force than those actions
arising from clinging or the compulsive versions of compassion that we enact
often and so we zigzag our way
through caring and not caring through our power and our
helplessness we do our best to
uh live a good life
offer that for your consideration
so so thank you uh it's touching to be with
you um okay we'll uh we'll close here and uh
again if you wish to um join uh the zoom meeting uh that's
posted did uh imc's calendar here in the
YouTube uh on my website you're going to find the zoom link you know and uh I'll
open the room at 8 we'll uh connect okay thank you uh thank you all
wish you wish you well Gil will be back uh next week he's with uh Andrea and I
think he Nez and be back uh next on Monday