so good morning and good day to all of you on this
uh Friday and at least here in
California and if and to this is the last uh day
on this five-part introduction to Buddhist ethics and in thinking about
the meditation for today in relationship to that um people's ethics how they behave
ethically or how they behave interpersonally uh has a fair amount to
do with their state of mind their emotional state that they're in the degree of stress or lack of
stress people have people who are stressed people who are angry people who are afraid people
who are greedy uh tend towards a different ethical Behavior
than people who are calm at ease people
who are uh filled with love or generosity or
kindness who feel safe and contented uh these different states are
very radically different they tap into different parts of who we are and they
can lead to kind of different ways of thinking or different ways of seeing the world seeing oneself
and because of all that it can even uh lead to different ethical systems
ethical philosophies and what gets Justified and not justified and the basis for
that and um so in Buddhism we have
meditation we have guidelines for how to live a wise life that frees us
from stress frees us from Fear frees us
from greed and hatred hostility and anger um and
then opens up a deeper sensitivity inside a sensitivity that we feel others
more uh closely we feel ourselves more closely we track ourselves better
and in particular we tap into our capacity for positive social emotions
and for different times different ones come into play there's Goodwill meta there's kindness there's
basic care and compassion there's mudo kind of a deep
appreciative um feeling and celebration of others
well-being and there can come uh a greater sense of avoiding harm greater
commit to being ethical not because we think it's a good
idea but it emerges from this deeper sensitivity that can come from what
we're developing here in meditation so for this meditation I'd
like to suggest that um you assume you
trust that you have the capacity to tap into a deep well spring
inside of sensitivity to yourself to others to
calm to a place of ease maybe a place of safety
contentment that is the source of kindness the source of
compassion the Wellspring of ethical
behavior and what is that place inside for you and how is it in this sitting
you might tap into the depths of your emotional
ethical um
sensitivity so to assume a uh meditation
posture and if you're meditating for some time then you begin appreciating
the posture itself is creates a context creates a
familiarity creates a a it starts creating a deeper
connection to being present here with oneself for
oneself and where that connection to your body through this familiar
posture the act of closing your eyes or low or lowering your
gaze allows you to have a heightened
sensitivity to your embodied
experience closing your eyes and
feeling the width and depth of your body
in whatever way the body shows itself to
you with the idea of becoming quiet like you're becoming quiet to
listen to faint songs of birds in the
forest or quiet so you can
allow a sleeping baby to keep sleeping sensitive to
the sweetness of a sleeping
baby so becoming quiet to feel and sense your embodied
experience with an intimacy a
closeness being come becoming St sensitive to the body
breathing not so much focusing on the breath or following the
breath is letting the body be become quieter
Stiller so there's a heightened sensitivity to the body's experience of
breathing
with the idea that there's a partnership between breathing and your
awareness breathing in sensitivity to your
body and in that partnership the breathing is guiding you
leading you inward to a deeper and deeper Fuller and Fuller
sensitivity to your inner life
entering into this partnership with
breathing so that there's a letting up a freeing up of the energy that goes
to tension and stress in your thoughts in your
body that as you feel the stress and agitations the body
mind there's room for them to relax and
settle
for
e
for for
chances are that whatever you're thinking about is not as
valuable as the opportunity to settle into your
breathing into your
body gradually settling into a fuller deeper sensitivity
that becomes the source for kindness
Compassion Care with each
breath
kindness
for
e
e for
for
e
e e
if you feel your way in to whatever degree of calm or
Stillness you have maybe behind or underneath whatever
agitation there might
be how does that place of calm or Stillness
inform how you look upon others how you see the
world can it be a place a source from which to gaze upon the
[Music] world with kindness
with an orientation to avoid causing
harm e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting to
consider how valuable it can be to not give ourselves
over to ill will to
stress to fear
greed to not succumb to believing in these states as being states with
which organizes how we understand and see and feel other
people but instead to stay close to the place to
stay close to being where there's no stress
the one inside who is not
stressed and who can gaze upon the world with
kindness being still and gazing
outwards kindly unto all beings may all all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may each of us
stay close to that inner sensitivity that is the source of Good
Will the source of
nonharming may we enter the
world close to that place that wishes no harm to anyone
[Music]
thank
you for
so then we come to this fifth theme for the in this introduction
to Buddhist ethics and that is that
um rather
than doing ethics and maybe rather than being
ethical as the behavior we do we are
ethical we it's it's who we are there's no understand standing in
Buddhist ethics and Buddhist practice that as people mature
spiritually they become ethical they become someone and and the ethics like
the five precepts are not things that people adhere to or do or think about
they are simply who the person is the person is someone who does not
intentionally harm others a person is a person is their whole
Constitution is built in such a way that of course they're not going to take what
is not given they're not going to steal they don't have to adhere to a
precept they their whole system has kind of been transformed in such a way that
there's no tendency to the Gree to the fear to
the hatred that would lead a person to do unethical
things and so ethics then doesn't become a any kind of out
outward admonitions it's all arising in a sense from the inside but in such a way that
it's not even there's not even a a rising of Ethics it just the absence of un not of
being unethical and so this pointing to how we
are is really key to understanding uh the transformation that Buddhism leads
to and on the way there one of the things we want to become uh uh
increasingly attentive to is how the state of our mind the
state of our emotion emotional state has addressed direct bearing
on how we live how we see the world how
we interpret events that going on and how and in that that way the ethics we
live by um there's a huge difference between
the eth ethical orientation of someone who is stressed and someone who is not
stressed when we're stressed we're much much more likely to to cut cor Corners
ethically or to be uninterested in ethics because we're just trying to get what we want or survive or to manage
ourselves and uh and that's too much to think about you know we're not oriented
to have this ethical sensitivity uh if we're consumed with anger uh we see the world with different
ways and if we're if we're filled with love and the kind of Ethics we justify
change varies dramatically whether we're angry or whether we're filled with love
if we're afraid or Not Afraid if we feel safe or fearful if we have a really
strong uh maybe biological Drive uh
desire um that tends that that will kind of uh obscure all kinds of ethical
considerations or all kinds of heightened sensitivity for other people because the drive
overrides U sometimes real concern or care or recognition and there's a person there it's all about you know this urge
that has to be uh fulfilled and so I my assumption is that
each person lives within an ethical range uh and maybe uh it's not the
dramatically you know wide range but uh simple things like the kind of uh words
we speak changes based on our state of being and so as we do Buddhist medit
Buddhist practice in Buddhist Meditation in particular we start start start seeing how
our mental state changes how our physical sense of um of well-being can
change and we start seeing the range of how this can be and how meditation can step step in and bring a sense of calm
or dramatic difference in our basic mood and state of mind and one of the one of the uh really
important um tasks when this we start seeing this range that we live by and
how meditation or spiritual practice gives us a positive end of that range more and more often is to start seeing
that uh understanding how our words our AC the way we think are influenced by
the state of our mind by our emotional state and um and in particular in terms
of Ethics how our ethical sensitivity uh varies depending on the
state that we're in there are times when there's no ethical sensitivity for anybody It's All About Me Myself and
mine it's all about my concerns my fears my grief my sadness in such a way that
that uh we're not really attuned to others and their needs and what harms and doesn't harm them and there are
other times when we are have this presence of Mind presence of heart
enough that we actually feel attuned we feel become we sensitive to other people
and sensitive to ourselves there's a way in which uh in Buddhist practice there's
a mutual there's a there's a double sensitivity that is a partnership that
really lets the whole work better than the part and that is we're set deeper and deeper sensitivity to
ourselves in such a way that we simultaneously then have a heightened sensitivity for others uh we feel others
more we care for others more uh we care for their well-being
more and um and the deeper sensitivity here also can start giving a freedom
where this the the great the deeper sensitivity in which there is a sense of
Freedom or Independence or not being pushed around not being caught um the
situations in the world doesn't get blocked or stopped in us or activate something within us that's difficult
there's an ease there's an openness there's a spaciousness for that sensitivity to uh uh in that
sensitivity for it to be wise consider it and one of the wisest uh forms of
wisdom is uh wisdom about how not to cause harm how to do the opposite how to
benefit this world how to uh come with kindness with
Good Will in such a way that we are uh
uh bringing out the best in other people that we're bringing out the best in
ourselves in such a way way that um that people feel safe with us because they
can feel that we have no intention to cause them harm we're not saying anything mean or maybe even sarcastical
which is a little bit you know edgy in a way in terms of um uh is it really uh
kind is it really sensitive to the well-being of others is it seeing people with good
will and or are we cynical in such a way that there too we limit our Capac it to
bring forth the best in all of us and um and the cynic is
probably uh being of uh limiting themselves for the best of who they are
to come forward and so this idea of kind of finding the best being sensitive to
the best with a good will with love with kindness with uh the absence of any
orientation to cause harm this is not a as I said it's not a
admonition it's not a commandment it's not an idea that comes from outside and
it's no longer a training that we have to do it it more and more becomes our
personality it becomes our character it becomes our very being um uh and um maybe not so much
because of of what we've cultivated in terms of Jo love and good will but
because we've let go of those inner forces that are UNH
wholesome we've uh we've learned not to give in the UNH wholesome and the AL UNH
wholesome begins to wither away and uh they're not operating and so the very Tendencies to
intentionally cause harm for others as
evaporated and um and for the person who has that kind of
ethical cleanliness or Clarity or openness or Freedom um in a sense um they're not
going to be puritanical they're not going to be moralistic because that begins shutting
down the eth ethical sensitivity the openness it begins to kind of uh bring
in something UNH wholesome something divides something that uh shuts out
people from the openness of our hearts there is another way there always is a
way that maybe not always easy to find but there is a way to change the world
for the better by bringing forth the best of who we
are and uh may that be the the uh
primary characteristic of of Buddhist ethics that we're bringing out the best
in the world through offering the best that's in in ourselves and the Buddhist
practice that we do is to uh make it possible that that comes
out of us with Integrity with wholeness so it's who we are not something we're
pretending or acting out or um but it's a really we been changed in this
way so uh that's um uh that's what um that's the
introduction to Buddhist ethics and next week there is a five-part u talk on the
five precepts and uh these are the mirrors for developing this ethical life
these are the guidelines for uh really being careful Not to cause harm in the
world and uh I'll be away teaching a retreat at Insight retreat center and uh
one of our wonderful uh new teachers at IMC um David Lori will come and give
those talks and uh you'll be in uh very good hands with him and he has not
talked taught on this uh on this 7 A.M teachings uh until now so he'll be new
for many of you and you're quite fortunate to have him come and and um and teach for
you and I'll be back the following week so
um thank you very much and um may all of us
together contribute to the reduction of harm in this world may we
live a non-harming life thank you