hello everyone and
welcome one of the ways that uh practice and even
Enlightenment is talked about in the ancient texts is that um is through the
language of touch We Touch Awakening with our
body and uh and there's something that's very special about human
touch uh so can it can express many things of course hostility certain kind
of way of touching others but there's a way of touching that uh is
friendly reassuring uh gently touching someone on
their shoulder to say I'm here with you uh we might hold someone's hand
touch as I did when my mother was dying I was holding her hand the
um uh a newborn mayy allow babies Thrive with touch and are
reassured and um and so this the possibility of
expressing friendliness kindness love is done can be done through
touch and um and then I think of uh the
Greek myth of uh King Midas Midas Touch everything he touched tur into
gold it's possible through this practice of ours
to not hold ourselves removed from our experience not to be up in the head the
control tower looking down and from a distance kind of analyzing thinking
about our experience it's possible to have awareness
attention touch everything and as we touch everything turn everything into meta
everything into love everything into compassion whatever
the the circumstances call for in the moment but this idea of coming close to
touch with kindness may be
the control tower is feeling sad or angry
upset afraid
distracted but when we approach something with attention approach our breathing
approach approach the sensations of our body approach how we feel emotionally
through how they're experienced in the body if we approach with
mindfulness the process of thinking not about the content of our thought but the
the process the activation the the energy the agitation the tension
that's involved in thinking the physicality of it and all these things
we approach and we can touch touch in the body and touch with me down touch
with love to have not the mest touch turning things
into gold but the meta touch turning everything
into um our friend our beloved
our what we care for to touch so for this meditation today maybe
this idea that mindfulness is a form of touching touching the physicality of
every everything that we experience directly has some way in which is
occurring through the medium of our
body and uh and what is it in the body we when we're mindful we can
touch to recognize it's there to say here I'm here I'm here with you here to
support you here to be be your friend your
companion to care so to assume a upright meditation
well to assume an alert meditation posture whatever posture that might be
for you and
um and perhaps it's a posture of care
in being alert having a certain kind of Vitality in your
posture and in that Vitality be a form of
care if you need to rest deeply certainly take a posture of rest
but have within it somewh or other some place in the body is also
alert adjusting the head the back of the neck maybe
straightens a little bit the midd between the shoulder blades
the spine pulls in a little bit so that the
chest comes out just a little bit more open
and lowering the Gaze gently closing the
eyes the body's experience of breathing is a physical experience of
movement of pressure release of pressure expansion and
contraction as you feel the sensations of the body
breathing Let each Sensation that passes
through be the meeting place of your touch and your body the touch of awareness
as a way of caring for yourself gently ever so
tenderly take some deeper breaths Fuller breaths just so it's right for
you and longer exhale
caring for yourself as you
release the air from your lungs settling as you exhale
letting your breathing return to
normal and feeling if possible is there some place within
you where there's tenderness the kind of tenderness or
softness that's associated with t kind of a soft or Tender Love or
Compassion Care a gentle gentle
place where a gentle
open-heartedness is available
and is it as if mindfulness
tension is at home in this place of
tenderness as you're aware of breathing body emotions
thinking sounds whatever might
be feel the place of touch feel the place
where the sense objects are
sensed where the sensing occurs of your
body and this is a touch spot
the place to touch with attention loving attention kind
attention attention that cares for each
thing
e
for
for for
e
for e
noticing if thinking interferes with your capacity to gently
touch your direct embodied
experience and if so let yourself
again be in
touch with your body with your embodied experience
and each Act of attention is a touch of
reassurance companionship
care
love
e
for
e e
and as we come to the end of this sitting and still while you're in your
meditative mode maybe with your eyes closed
imagine that when you think of anyone when you're aware of anyone in
front of you that you think your thinking and
your awareness carries with it your kindness your care
Good Will and for those who suffer your
attention carries with it Compassion
Care that with it your eyes eyes closed sting sitting in meditation the complexities of the
social relationships can be put aside for
now and for now to gaze upon everyone
kindly as if you're touching them in friendship and
reassurance offering companionship to all fellow
humans sharing the planet with others caring for
others a Radiance the 360
degree willingness in
meditation to look upon this world with a friendly eyes with a
friendly touch wishing everyone
well may it be that from my heart to your heart May everyone be
happy from my heart to your heart May everyone be
safe from my heart to your heart May everyone experience peace
PE and from my heart to your heart May
everyone be free of Affliction free of
suffering free of Oppression free of
poverty may all beings be
happy and May we contribute to that
[Music]
possibility thank
you e
so hello everyone and welcome to this fourth talk on uh the five core principles or
foundations for my teachings my the way I offer
Buddhist teachings and um so today
the what I'd like to talk about is the social emotions
of uh love as an umbrella term for all of them but certainly friendliness and
kindness goodwi compassion sympathy empathy
appreciation appreciative Joy empathic Joy sharing joy and the joy of
others and um and a profound form of
equinity of Peace of nonassertive
non wavering love in the face of challenges in the face of of of of
um our inability to make a difference for people we still have some kind of
our love is still unshakable
equanimous so I talked earlier in the week that um
one of the foundations of that I really appreciate for Buddhism and is the idea
of not having any fixed views not having any ultimate philosophy or ultimate this
is what's ultimate but rather uh a uh not having
that not not experiencing the world through the filter of our philosophies
Our World Views our cultural views our philosophical and religious
views but actually shedding those as if they're kind of a filter through which
we experience the world and the reason why I feel so much so confident in that is uh for what I
talked about yesterday the naturalistic orientation to this practice that we do
that we have a profound wonderful deep capacities that
are often overlooked submerged uh in the hustle and bustle of Life the challenges of life the
sufferings the pains the betrayals we have the busyness of trying to
survive but if we can uh uh somehow um put all those down and put
down our views our opinions our stories that we uh are living in all the time
then um the um it allows that that something deep naturalistic movement this deep
natural movement of of um of that is buried deep inside of us I don't know if
buried is the right word but um functions best when we're relaxed when
we're at ease when we do feel safe that then we're more likely to welcome the
stranger as they come by an Ancient Ancient uh tradition of welcoming The
Stranger not shunning them or being afraid of them doesn't necessarily mean that we welcome them into our home if
that's not appropriate but uh maybe we give them um support and maybe you show
them the way to where they're going but this idea of welcoming The
Stranger welcoming the friend welcoming those we know welcome everyone comes
well into our tenderness our love our capacity for
friendliness and um when when we're caught in views caught in opinions caught in
stories um including stories uh and Views about who I am and who I have to
be and what I who my identity I have to defend that I've created uh sometimes that interferes
with our capacity to uh feel and sense and and respond from some deep place
inside someplace that's resilient some place that is um uh clear enough
to not be caught in even insults even um
uh criticism uh we don't cover it we don't we don't lose touch with this
resilient place that is not actually um troubled by the challenges in our life
it's it's uh it's free of needing to be caught and influenced and and and uh
doesn't react to things and so this fantastic capacity we have for love for
care for kindness and um
and uh the way that I came across this in this practice uh discovering the
tremendous wonderfulness the wonderfulness of compassion the wonderfulness of mea of kindness and
friendliness the wonderfulness of of a very simple uh care and benevolence that
we can carry with us is not because I was told I should or I felt like I
should that I should engineer it that I should Pump It Up and really try to as a duty be friendly and kind but rather it
was a byproduct of doing the meditation practice that I did first Zen practice
then mindfulness practice that something settled something relaxed something
showed up something became alive from deep inside and in that living sense of depth
within there was um the the uh the crust around my heart softened and fell fell
away and that's the way it felt when I was doing Zen practice that all this crustiness all this defensiveness all
this hardness around my heart uh softened and softened and chipped away and fell away until the heart was soft
enough and tender enough uh that when I I could feel the suffering of the World
Around Me Without Fear without reaction without um uh a burden without being
oppressed by it or dismayed by it and there was this beautiful feeling of
compassion I think healthy compassion no matter how uncomfortable
it is to feel suffering of the world healthy compassion has it a beauty to it
and uh it's hard to imagine for some people that compassion can be beautiful when there's so much ugliness in the
suffering of the world but it is possible and it arises from this depth
it's not something that has to be done and with uh with the mindfulness
practice I discover the same thing with friendliness with kindness with meta that um as things cleared away as I was
felt quite settled and at ease and happy just to be alive that uh then there was
this welling up of this natural capacity for friendliness for love for
kindness that um was not I wouldn't characterize it as beautiful the way I
did for for compassion but it uh was sweet it was joyful it uh if it was a um
adjective I would call it a smile smilingly or smile smiling
smilingly um and um and then as uh my my deep my practice
deepened and it wasn't so much uh uh uh
compassion that was the Forefront or love that was a Forefront but there was
some there was a greater and greater U freedom from any kind of attachment and
that kind of not covering over not interfering with life through the attachments the bondage the clinging
that I had the Cravings that i' had before I was surprised by
U by um a very tender a very satisfying form of
care a care that was peaceful a care that uh was not reactive was not
um wouldn't succumb to distress or to anger or to
hostility or to fear very simple and ordinary care appreciation valuing of
things and these things that for me arose from uh something deep inside that was
being freed uh when there was no overlay no nothing would
interfere and uh it's kind of like a flower which when the conditions are right um blossoms and so when the
conditions are right uh this capacity for our social emotions can blossom not
because it's a should but because it's the natural tendency when the conditions
are right and Buddhist practice I'm sure other spiritual practices as well um uh
they um uh
um are what helps us get out of our own way get out of the way for something
profound within that we can trust that um is not even personal so
it's not directly tied to all the ways we think about me myself and mine which
are primarily more views and uh and so to feel the freedom
and the joy and the delight and the freedom of a tender heart of a loving
heart a Caring Heart this is the this is the um byproduct or the
consequence of a path of freedom and um and
uh so for me this is foundational to myself as a human being that the com
first it was compassion uh then it was augmented by
meta and friendliness it was augmented by this sense of care under Kaa that
um I feel like this is in some ways one of the primary organizing principles
that motivates My Life um certainly the end of suffering
uh caring for suffering but that caring for suffering now comes out of this uh
same place of care of compassion that uh this tender heart that
um this seems like be the it's for me it's the most important thing in life is
uh caring in all directions compassion in all directions love in all directions
and to the best of my ability um I have
uh organized or guided my life uh with
uh around this with around this um the motivation of it comes from
compassion and love so um so as a teacher and and
offering these teachings this is what drives it what what animates it this is
what gives it life so thank you very much and
um and I look forward to this F talk in tomorrow in this series