hello everyone welcome and
uh the theme for this morning's meditation to go along with the
reflection afterwards or to cast a light on it is that uh something that I feel
is very precious about precious potential of mindfulness practice
awareness practice and that is uh a way of being
aware where there's no no outside or to say it
differently being aware where everything is allowed to appear in Awareness
equally there's no divisions in the mind between what is acceptable for awareness
and what is not acceptable for awareness there might be wisdom there might be other ways in which the mind um
differentiates between what's happening it might be some things are
seen as being useful healthy appropriate to do or to think some things are not uh
in the bigger picture scheme of things but while we're meditating especially in certain
circumstances um there's a there's also the operation of a form of awareness
that awareness is itself doesn't divide the world up and uh and so everything has a place
everything is included and um in
Awareness it doesn't mean that we are accepting it or condoning anything it
just means that in this world of awareness we're not struggling with anything we're not dividing wanting it
to be different trying to hold on to it uh that can all come later but if we can
learn to uh come to a place of of uh this undivided attention
meaning un uh divisive attention where there's no lines between
what is acceptable to be aware and unacceptable what we're willing to be aware of and what I'm not willing to be
aware of that um that gives us a vantage point to have much more wisdom about
what to do and how to see things but the beginning is this
open and so everything is included there's nothing outside and for me
that's one of the most sacred things is an awareness which uh includes everything there's nothing which is
unacceptable in it and uh and so one of the little
expressions for mindfulness practice uh that supports this is the the
expression this too whatever is happening this too is included in
awareness and um and so um but uh this movement of this to is
included in Awareness is not the same thing as going along with something it's
also not the same thing as pushing anything away it's it's
uh it's coming into a a clear seeing a
clear knowing a clear awareness that is independent of
our participation our engagement our for the ways we're for and
against and of course we will be for and against and then the attitude towards
that is this too is included we see that and that seeing is free the seeing is
where Freedom occurs freedom from being caught in anything being pushed around
by anything the uh free from uh being reactive to
anything and so this is a kind of a non-divided attention or a
non separating attention everything is included this too
so as we do this meditation uh after we kind of get settled a bit you might try using this
expression or just doesn't have to be a you don't have to say it in your mind but you can just
uh the attitude can be there that whatever is
occurring this too is included this too this
too and um and uh and then with that this too
it's almost like you're going to make now more room for the experience without being Tangled in it
just to see it just allow it to be there in its own
pristine uniqueness the own pristine uniqueness
free of our involvement with it this too this too
so uh assuming a meditation
posture
and maybe begin with lowering your gaze relaxing your
eyes and if your eyes are still open see if you
can soft soften the Gaze there's something very profound
about having soft eyes that are not fixated on
anything soft eyes that are just float in the eye
socket and then gently closing the
eyes and as if the inhale Flo Floats or
gently expands allow the inhale to be
more expansive Fuller than
usual and then allow yourself to relax on the exhale
maybe allowing your exhale to be longer by gently letting go near the end
of the exhale so letting go into the exhale
letting the breathing return to
normal and as you inhale become aware of any tensions or Holdings in your body
places that are tight and as you exhale
soften the
body relax the
muscles soften the edges of your body
as you breathe in and out become aware of how you are
emotionally your mood or attitude
feelings feeling them as you inhale and soften them on the exhale
whatever you are feeling let it relax and settle with the
exhale maybe almost like a massage of your feelings breathing in and breathing
out
and then on the inhale feeling sensing
deeply your thinking mind the energy
activity the tension of thinking however
subtle and as you exhale to soften the thinking
mind as if the thinking mind is gently floating
on a comfortable body of water gently
rocked by The Gentle waves the thinking mind
rests and a soft surface of water floating
and then now centering yourself centering yourself more
fully and the movements in the body as you
breathe maybe those movements of expansion and contraction as you breathe
in in and out are like gentle waves
moving through your body
and if something else is occurring for you that you'll be mindful of as you sit here a sound a thought a feeling
sensation in your body an
Impulse be mindful it be know it be aware of it include it in awareness and
it clear distinct way with the attitude this too is
included this too you have space to know and be aware
of no need to be for or against or judge
it or resist it or hold on to it it's
enough just to know it's there this too is included
so that as you're aware the awareness becomes
softer awareness becomes looser lighter
more open
receptive maybe
spacious and then into then into that spacious awareness let the breathing return to it
let the breathing enter into the
space until there's something else to
include this too is included in
awareness
whatever is happening remember to include it with this too
you'll be aware of aware but not
participating
e
e e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to whatever degree you can get a feeling for the
specialness of no outside no divisions in
Awareness that awareness is open and available for everything
equally [Music] imagine in a safe social environment
that you are able to be aware of others in this
way this too this person too can be
known in Awareness simply
fully with no divisions no
separation no for or against
the unique expression of each person in that moment can just be
allowed to be in your
awareness as an open field for a heart heart-to-heart
Connection open field for a full meeting
sensing of another human being breathing living thinking human
being and in that open
field to evoke your good will
your potential for kindness and generosity
friendliness and wish this other these other people
well thinking of some people in your life a single person or group of
people wish them well maybe repeating these words to yourself
silently may you be
happy may you be
safe may you be
peaceful may you be
free and may it be also that this wish of care and kindness of yours each of
you spreads out towards others throughout the
day a theme for the day may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all [Music] beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank
you e
hello and welcome to this nth talk on the 10
Reflections and for today and tomorrow today the topic is reconciliation and
tomorrow it's healing and I associate these two with
becoming whole becoming whole
interpersonally or becoming and becoming whole for oneself h a holistic a
holism that uh we're not divided through fear or divided through greed or hatred
or they kind of a an inclus inclusion coming together a
meeting together I think that uh reconciliation comes from a root meaning in Latin to
come together to meet so um might be nice to go through
these 10 a little bit briefly the um I connect them all with a certain kind of
sequence a logic of how one follows the other and there's other ways in which
they can follow this is not required that they follow this sequence but uh I
kind of delight in this sequence and in uh the story that they kind of
tell that um uh if we find a sense if you find
meaning and purpose in this life then um that gives us a guide for
what we're going to do in this life of ours and so then uh it's important then
to be able to act so to have agency and uh agency a certain degree of
autonomy uh our agency are doing is not something that's permitted by others
only or enabled by other people we're not dependent in others but we have an
autonomy autonomous ability to live a life of meaning and
purpose as we do that as we act and as we act singularly for ourselves in a
certain way maybe together with others that um then uh uh we start to get to
know ourselves in relationship to what's important for us what drives us the the
purpose and and meaning and the actions we do and we can form a we can have a
clear sense of identity clear sense of who we are and that's very important if we're kind of lost to ourselves not sure
who we are um it can be source of all kinds of
challenges but uh in Buddhism uh our identity doesn't come from some inherent
essence of who we are how we're born but uh the essence that Buddhism bases our
lives on is the the um the identity of uh the shifting identities that based on
how we live what we do how we act and um and key to Buddhism is acting ethically
and so it's the ethics that we live by that uh virtues we live by that becomes
our primary identity and um and then from that can
we can have a sense of dignity the dignity the sense of personal value of
knowing that we're dedicated to not harming anyone in fact we might be dedicated to the opposite to benefiting
self anothers and so um and so with this
dedication towards uh action and action for the benefit of others and for
oneself um then we enter into the world of community and uh and just like identity
is something that's shifting and changing Community is not something static and fixed Community is also
something that changes and morphs depending the people we're with and how we're relating to people and and we can
get a sense that our caner community is not it can be more more open more more inclusive of the the people we feel part
of um and our actions our ethics helps create a healthy sense of
community and uh and then with Community we can get to know people in a deeper
way and feel the kinship the common Humanity that we share that we all feel
like we're kin we're all family and uh and with that there can be
a dedication towards uh uh when there's fractured relationships conflict in
relationships and divisiveness in society then we have a huge need to come
back into Union back into Unity back into wholeness together and uh back into
a sense of community and kinship and so there's the work of
reconciliation and um and healing reconciliation has to do interpersonally
and the way I Define these terms um for this purpose here this these two weeks I
think of reconciliation being the interpersonal work and healing being of deep personal work that happens in
relationship to community and others and our relationships and so the work of some
people might you know not see these two as so separate these terms but so
reconciliation and this is a very Central uh movement in Buddhism maybe
without literally that word being used uh the Buddha put tremendous emphasis I
would say on um on the activity
of um uh uh uniting the people who are
divided and supporting the unification of people who are
united wrong speech one of the definitions of wrong speech is to divide
the people who are united and keep divided the people who are
divisive and um so that built into the precepts and the faithful path and and
the whole kind of foundation of Buddhist practice is an orientation to live a
life that's focused and considered and concerned with the sense of unity that
we have with others um the sense of uh coming together in harmony and um in in the Buddha the
Buddha's clearest way of doing that was in his own Community the monastic community and uh finding a way for them
to live together in harmony and unity and not in division and um in fact people who
create uh a real Schism in the monastic Community uh receive the the most severe
I don't know what to call it consequence uh in monastic life is that
you're no longer allowed to be a monastic uh it's such an important thing to create that
unity and um so that takes work and I've been involved with uh conflict
resolution work I was a a chair I've been chair of a conflict uh uh committee
for some 15 years and was sitting as a mediator for lots of conflicts and um and I can tell you that
it's a lot of work but it's really worthwhile work because it's practice
work it's Buddhist practice to enter into this world of of our relationships
with others and really get to the bottom them and really understand ourselves well understand other people well find
Common Ground um uh work with our divisiveness our anger our resentment uh
find Common Ground um it takes a lot of time sometimes but um the
consequences um in the long term tend to be much better than remaining divisive
divisiveness anger sometimes can have immediate consequences pushing people
away for example but long-term negative consequences and um so it's better to uh
to spend the time to invest in the time Upfront for reconciliation and coming
together than it is to take this easy or the simple or short way um that of anger
and resentment and hostility that uh will have uh repercussion sometimes for
the rest of a lifetime for some people so um it is possible to reconcile
and in Buddhism a huge part of this process of reconciliation um is not looking for
forgiveness not looking for apology there's certainly a time and place for that but the Buddhist uh the emphasis in
Buddhism is first and foremost to be able to do this introspection to understand the pain and
the downside of the living with resentment living with anger and even
sometimes being attached to hurt attached to being a victim and um and so really want to look
and see and begin to dissolve in a healthy way appropriate way to dissolve
the anger we have to let go of the resentments we hold on to and then to cultivate a sincere and
and authentic kind of sense of Goodwill for others and this movement of letting
go of anger and cultivating Good Will can look a lot like forgiveness but in
some ways it's simpler because it doesn't require something from someone else it doesn't uh require a a um the
complexity of forgiveness that sometimes exists forgiveness is a form of generosity giving forgiving which I
think can be quite beautiful but the in the Buddhist kind of approach which there are other approaches
is um to do this work for yourself and then uh be in conversation with the with
others um in uh some of the places in the world where there's been reconcil political reconciliation
processes the word truth has been associated with that there has to be truth telling things have to be really
come out in the open um and really life to have reconciliation happen so once we
kind of do our own work and no longer holding resentments and holding ourselves apart and being critical of
others and seeing them through Angry Eyes um then maybe we're ready to speak
the truth talk about what happened talk about the pain the hurt talk about the difficulties we've had but without
attacking people without poking them with kind of mean statements and it's profound work to
look for reconciliation it's not always possible because you know has to be two people in
the in the willing to be do part of the work but um uh it's certainly impossible
if both people don't want to do it if one person does the inner work and creates the conditions and the openness
and the kindness friendliness Goodwill uh then sometimes other people will come along in in time and sometimes
it takes a long time before people are ready for some kind of reconciliation
some kind of meeting to work things out um but then we prepare ourselves for
that and make sure that we're clean that we're not holding on to something that's going to make it difficult when the time
finally comes and um and part of the reason why
reconciliation is such an important thing for Dharma practitioners is that uh if we're
contributing to the divisiveness the divisions the separation uh that's a way of of of
dividing ourselves that's a way of shutting down part of ourselves that's a way of living in a way that we're not
complete we're not whole we're not kind of uh including all of ourselves in the
field of awareness so to become free to use mindfulness to become Freer and Freer we
have to really meet and confront and work with the places where we're divided
we're caught we're stuck and tight and uh it's part of the wonderful gift of
mindfulness practice that sooner or later uh as we do this practice we have
to meet these parts of ourselves that sometimes have been buried been closed unwilling to look at our hurt our anger
our resentments and our unwilling to kind of think about dissolving them or working through
them and it's a work of a lifetime sometimes but it's such a great thing to be part of uh reconciliation and and uh
healing that social healing so um so what is your experience
of conflict resentment Divi div divisions
divisiveness divisive divisions that uh you've been part of and what is uh your interest in
reconciliation how can reconciliation and working on this divisiveness that exists in families and friends and
communities uh how is it really uh uh important for you personally how might
it be important how is it really part of a life effort that has tremendous
meaning and purpose to work through these things and now we're back at the
beginning of these 10 Reflections that uh the very thing of reconciliation itself is part of a very
meaningful life purposeful life so uh thank
you uh very much and uh then tomorrow tomorrow we'll do the last of these 10
Reflections and that of healing thank you