so here we are on gathering together again this is 7:00 Pacific
time and so this week uh the meditation and as I was indicating in
the last couple of days uh were building um upon a metaphor I
used uh that sitting like a mountain and uh the first day uh we were
uh just using this metaphor as a way for us to uh let the Earth element the
earthy body resting on Earth and
um to allow ourselves to feel a sense of grounding gathered
collectedness and then yesterday I uh kind of expanded uh a little bit of this
metaphor uh to include uh the breath kind of this mountain within the Earthly
body within has a liveness to it has a a
breath with us this is a life breath that enlivens us and so um they used the
metaphor as the breathing mountain and today we'll expand to
include even more dimensions of our being and this a live being
has you know the body physical physicality of the body our emotions and
Minds kind of like an entire living ecosystem you know the like the mountain
the forest the animals and it's a whole system and that's the nature within too
and so that's what we'll be meditating with today and so I'll begin with the
sound of a bell
[Music]
let the sound of the Bell fade
[Music] arriving arriving at a Here and Now
maybe a sense of a coming home to this body mind and
heart maybe it's a kind of a familiar feeling for you to come
home here in this body just how it
is not demanding for it to be
otherwise just receiving kindly
if it's a helpful you can do a global scan of the
body [Music] inviting any slight relaxation and
ease that's available to you
from the bottom of the feet all the way to the top of the
head relaxing
and [Music]
softening if that's available to us
one moment of mindfulness at a time
Moment by
moment you can begin to feel a sense of
presence more steady
the weight of the body settling down
naturally and the Torso naturally uplifts
allowing this earthy body resting on
Earth sitting like a mountain
grounded quiet
still to whatever degree that's available to you
the movement of the breath naturally gets a highlight
Ed a breathing
Mountain a life Mountain
within feeling Sensations dancing in the body
vibrating tingling
you may also notice other elements in the
body the
water moisture
feeling like The Mists in the mountain
there may be emotions waves of
emotions like a weather system in the mountain
open to receive feel and
sense this entire ecosystem Within
releasing the demands the
reactivities for
[Music]
being curious about the ecosystem
Within
e
e e
what do you notice as you immerse yourself into this inner
ecosystem aive Mountain
M moisture
coolness
sound weather systems
is there a kind of a wakefulness
here [Music]
now in this nature
within in the Dharma of your own being
there may be natural heart responses to
this kind of
tenderness a kind of a care
Wonder
gratitude for
there a possibility of a simply being
here aware wake
for and Alive may be enough
[Music]
I feel quite quiet with in and be feeling a kind of a quiet from
all all of you also in this last a few days we been uh
exploring the different aspects of refuge and started with refuge in
Nang refuge in Dharma and today uh we'll explore incorporating The
Refuge in the Buddha and as some of you would know this is
the this three um forms the kind of
triple Jam you know that's a uh something that often referred to in the
in the reverse order triple Jam of the Buddha Dharma and
Sana so refuge in Buddha has an ancient root uh in poly Canan
text we often find the words um that I go to the Buddha for
refuge and it feels like it maybe makes sense for those who lived um in the
times of the Buddha and and there was a person the Buddha awakened being to go
to and to follow around and maybe to hand out but what does it mean for us 2,600
years later that was not not a Buddha to hang
out with and so uh what does this taking Refuge uh in
the Buddha mean so for some people uh the Buddha
represented a possibility to be free from suffering
duka and he's uh human being who realized the for Noble
Truth and um became an awakened human
being and that possibility itself and the fact that there is the GMA the
Buddha uh who did it may be inspiring and uplifting or aspiring for
people and that may be sufficient uh for people to
feel uh drawn towards this possibility and to feel the potency of
taking refuge in the Buddha and that's one possibility and it
kind of does a sense of oh I'm uplifted um by this possibility from this
historical figure the Buddha God the
Buddha um and but for others uh the sense of a
refuge uh for someone who lived uh in such a distant
time uh that Refuge can feel somewhat Elusive and
distant and given that we just don't know you know who this person is and uh
and how we relate to them are not completely
clear and so it's sometimes hard to translate the um inspiration or the
aspiration into something immediate uh or deeper inside of
us so how might the Refuge in the Buddha come alive in us and then touch us uh in
ways that feels meaningful and so there may be many ways
some of you may have uh exper experienced uh your own ways of relating
to this refuge and I like to share one aspect of
this uh one way to relate to this the word Buddha means awake or
awakeness the one who knows or knowing
and this is kind of knowing that's different from kind of reading a book and getting some kind of information but
rather this isn't knowing that is from deep within
ourselves and GMA the Buddha became awake through this kind of deep knowing
observing the nature of this body mind and
heart and so this Refuge uh in the Buddha points to the possibility of
being a awake and aware clear
seeing so in a way this Refuge is not asking us to try to become the Buddha
but rather we can cultivate this wakefulness clear awareness within
us in this way the cultivation itself is much more immediate uh um direct and the
possibility is here and now and it's not in some distant past or the
future I want to read this quote from um aan su's book uh intuitive
awareness and this is what he uh described about taking refuge in the
Buddha and so here it is we're asked to take refuge in our own ability to be
awake to pay attention to life no matter what the conditions might be in the
present moment the simple willingness to acknowledge things for what they are as
changing conditions liberates us from being caught in the power of
attachments in struggling with emotions or thoughts that we're
experiencing so might this be a kind of Refuge in the
Buddha take refuge in our own ability to be
awake to pay attention to life no matter what the conditions might be in the
present moment to me that really brought the Refuge in
Buddha close to my life you know it's here and now this moment in the midst of
the happenings the challenges the difficulties and the Comfort it's tangible and it's
practical and it's aligned with the teaching with the Dharma and so it's something that we can
turn to again and again whenever we remember and so right here I can choose
to be present aware to pay
attention you know as best as we're able we're not kind of demanding for it to be
somehow like a big light bulb with some high Watts or something but it's just oh
you know this moment what is here maybe if I'm frustrated or
fearful I can begin to tune into it and really get to know
it and so aan sumo's words this is simple willingness to acknowledge things
for what they are in our meditation I use this phrase
not demanding for things to be
otherwise there is a kindness and compassion right there while allowing
this aware aware awareness uh clear knowing to come forth little by
little so there a phrase that aato would often repeat again and again is the way
it is oh it is the way it is right
now and maybe maybe I'm a little agitated it is the way it
is when we know it clearly we can begin to feel and sense
it's a shift and change like you know in the uh
meditation I used this nature metaphor you know when we're really letting
ourselves soak in the mountain the various
ecosystems kind of softening into this we can begin to feel
and shift and the changes in the micro e uh micro system I was doing a hike this
last weekend I began to notice uh very
vividly as I was walking how the forest just changed the
terrain changes it was not a long hike but I can just began to notice oh wow
the trees have just changed um there was a whole uh kind of
Oak Oak Tree forest and as I walked more and more the oak tree began to change to
something different you I don't even know the names of the trees but they're no no longer Oaks and so we can begin to
feel and then uh uh uh feel the change of
the nature within instead of getting caught up in
our habitual um reactivities oh it shouldn't be like this I must have done
something wrong
and we get clear about the
patterns we began to notice this extra layers of reactivity
are compounding [Music] Dua they are added they're created
extra and so this is what Aang Sumo is pointing out when we begin to see this it's very
natural that we would release it because they make no sense you know to be
reactive like this and so it's possible to then in the
moment by seeing things clearly it liberates us
from being caught in the power of
attachment so we're learning to little by little uh live with lesser and lesser
degrees of this um compounding
dukka based on our judgments and uh our habitual
Tendencies and so in this way I'd like to uh summarize by pointing out that all
three refugees the triple Jam are not totally
separate they have a separate Dimensions or aspects but they
together form a kind of um structure for us to point to a kind
of cultivation within you know maybe we're uplifted by
the possibility of wakefulness like the Buddha and uh we are uh practicing along
um aligned with and the Buddha Dharma and were affected by the Sana so
that each of us can continue to deepen this possibility of
living in um a way that is wakeful aware
compassionate and caring and so that's the possibility and
um May this refuge in the Buddha Dharma and
S um offer a kind of orientation for each of us as we navigate our lives and
may it come alive in each of us so thank you for your attention
everyone and be well and may the goodness within be shared with all
beings everywhere