good morning everyone good morning warm welcome Happy
Friday good to see everyone in the
chat happy to be with you this morning our fifth of five
days I'm just um delighted to see all the names in the
chat all the greetings and want to extend the
invitation to um report back did you notice any
glimpses or glimmers of the heart qualities yesterday in your
life any glimpses of kindness compassion appre of Joy gratitude
Equanimity just a quick quick little homework report for those
of you who want to do it and to be transparent part of why we're doing this
is to um light each other up a little bit
notice what it's like in your
heart oh warm greetings to those of you
still pouring in and um
notice the in your own mind your own heart over the past day if you maybe did
experience glimpses of those heart qualities we talked about
yesterday I see Meta greetings warm greetings joy joy in
singing yeah I I resonate with that increased awareness wonderful
oh visiting a 98-year-old Elder beloved
Elder all different kinds of Joy love
care so thank you for those they're meaningful and those I don't have time
to read now I will read later but as you are settling
[Music] in noticing noticing in your own heart how
it feels to read the greetings and observations of others and how it feels
to look back in your own heart at your day and as you're taking maybe as I'm
about to do that last sip of tea before settling into the meditation
allowing that to nourish you nourish your
heart taking a deep intentional
breath or two and beginning to bring the
attention inward
bringing a heartful attuned
quality to greeting yourself with the same warmth and friendliness you would meet greet an old
s mate or
friend allowing a little extra relaxation on the out breath
letting go into the
moment and letting the breath be natural
inviting all of your body all of your heart all of your
mind to be present
here resting on the sensations of breathing
perhaps on the [Music] sensations of the
attuned art of the
body making a gentle loving determination that for these
moments we are to be present here this moment
now nowhere else the Mind needs to be
attending to the details of sensation Ambient sound
temperature weight or lightness of the
body [Music] aliveness in this
body each in breath its own
Journey with each out breath releasing anything extra letting go
inviting experience to flow through each breath each
moment any flits of thought just to move through like birds
floting across an empty
Sky being nourished resting in the waves of the breath the moment
meditate in silence for a while till near the
end
e
e e
and in the final few minutes of this
meditation the invitation is to let go into the
Stillness the Stillness at the end of the out
breath the Stillness between sounds in the [Music]
room the Stillness between
[Music] Sensations the gap
between thoughts to let go
rest in
quietude
e
e e
and as we bring this meditation to a
close drinking in any moments of
peacefulness calm settledness
appreciating savoring them savoring any
of the heart qualities warmth Attunement that
emerged moments of Engagement immersion
appreciating them all and appreciating with
kindness even any moments of difficulty those two can be onward
leading Gathering all of this up casting your intentions
outwards to the others meditating here the others in your
life making the
determination that all beings your life touches including
yourself May benefit from this practice
that this practice May Ripple outward and bring more
joy nourishment Freedom into their lives
and all of the lives they touch Rippling outwards and
outwards may all beings be free
thank you for your
practice
for e
so good morning again everyone warm greetings to all of you
especially those who slipped in a few minutes
late I'm delighted to be back with you for this fifth of five
teachings excuse me fifth of five teachings on inner and
interpersonal Wellsprings of Dharma wellbeing
this week's theme is on cultivating these qualities and they're in the context of
the Buddha often gave teachings to all kinds of people but
occasionally would give teachings about how to practice when things weren't going so great in the outer world and
gave the teaching of coming home to the practice staying home in the practice
making the practice our field of influence and our
refuge and in this teaching that I'm describing um this week he talked about
five benefits Wells Springs of well-being that get cultivated this way
inner um sort of an inner sense of spiritual
empowerment true inner beauty happiness inner wealth or heart
wealth and this last one that we're covering today Freedom
so Freedom Liberation is freedom from any trace of
mental Affliction any trace of greed hatred delusion ignorance in the heart
and mind no more fuel for that internal
optional kind of suffering I'll talk more about that later and it's freedom from causing intentional
harm any experience of freedom of the heart Letting
Go metabolized carefully can be onward leading in the path towards
Awakening onward leading and can make for a much happier
life so in this teaching the Buddha talks about two sort of ways the heart
becomes free and a fully awakened person has experienced both of these the first
is Freedom by wisdom Freedom by knowledge deep wisdom and knowledge and
the second is Freedom by meditative death and the P depth excuse me
meditative deepness the poly for these areti wisdom Awakening and chti heart
Awakening now the second can be temporary or
permanent in any case it's powerful nourishing it resets an internal set
point or reference point for the rest of life this is
possible so I've talked about empowerment the first day spiritual power and the Buddha really considered
this Freedom this liberation of the heart and mind to be the most
consequential form of power all the good qualities we've
covered this week help contribute to it and to sort of unpack this topic a little more speak
to it I have one more story from the time of the Buddha and this is a story
of two good friends atisa and I think his name was kova something like that
and in Ancient India they were born within a day or two to families in neighboring Villages and the families
had already been friends so it's that beautiful thing many of you have experienced that's if you have kids where your kids friends become friends
or your parents were friends when you were born and so you've been friends with this person your whole life and it's a special kind of
friendship so they grew up together they went off riding horses together swimming
in Creeks going to forests and they were both in their own spheres their own Villages very popular and well
liked so um they went to a festival one day as young
men maybe adolescents together and it was a three-day festival and the first
day was wonderful and they had a lot of fun and it was it's great like folk music and entertainment and plays and
tricks and all that kind of stuff so they signed up for the second and the third day
but the second day they were both kind of less into it and then that night each
of them in their own beds had sort of difficult nights of tossing and
turning and it turns out that when they went back that third day there were much more
each was much more withdrawn and pensive and atisa was having these
thoughts of well death is universal why are we spending our time doing this when
we could be finding a way to completely end suffering to know the truth of life
before we're gone classic classic kind of young
person wisdom young person seeking
so he um notices that his friend is also pensive and asks well we are withdrawn
what's up with you and wouldn't you know his friend kovala said this same thing
and like oh we're of the same mind we should leave the these Villages and go
off and find a good teacher and find a way to really understand the meaning of
life break through our suffering discover freedom and so they
did and as The Story Goes Around the time they did this was around the time that the Buddha to be was getting
married still in his household life and it was years before he left the Buddha
left and became a teacher brought his son into the order and um so they wandered around and
were finding teachers and not satisfied with any of them eventually they found one teacher who was brilliant with
knowledge and skepticism and Analysis and he really taught them
to critically look at what they were learning empirically look at it but he
didn't have any of the deeper teachings and so they learned a lot from him but were becoming dissatisfied
realizing that they really hadn't come to a full
understanding and so they went on and searched out still other teachers and other teachers and then one
day atisa is off asking for his food for the day in the neighborhood when he
encounters a fully awakened man
and he was immediately struck by this person's presence the calm the Stillness
that radiated from him the sense of peace and after they had both gotten
their meal he bowed down to him and said who is your teacher what have you learned you've clearly learned something
and I want to learn it and this monk was a little bit shy
and maybe a little bit skeptical of the newcomers um intentions people often
challenged themselves in each other in those days but he told him the teachings of
the Buddha in brief just like four stanzas or something and then told him who his teacher was and where his
teacher was and upon hearing those four stanas something in aa's heart just
opened up and he knew this is it this is the
way there was a deeper understanding a miniature significant Awakening in
him so he went and found his friend and told him and they went to see the Buddha
and joined a kind of a cohort of incoming
practitioners and because they had been so dedicated for years even decades and
had such Keen powers of some kind of mental analysis and understanding and
meditation both of them became fully awakened pretty
quickly and the Buddha recognizing their capacity made him made them his two
primary assistants of the order so that was an honor but it was also a lot of
work you got to kind of run the sa a lot of administrative interpersonal stuff and they also helped him teach
each and these two men were saruta and Maha molana those of you who are
familiar with the ancient teachings are familiar with them already I'm telling this story in part
because of the importance of spiritual friendship as you're McKing along on the path and in part because these two
people exemplify two different expressions of Liberation while they both woke up both
ways through wisdom and through meditative depth saruta was much more of a wisdom
type he became a great systematizer a lot of details he was kind of like that day's version of a
software engineer or an information architect highly logical rational whereas
mahamana was extraordinarily skilled in meditative subtlety subtlety of the
inner workings of the mind of meditative depth of different
states and saruta tended to bring people into the first beginnings of Awakening first
levels of it and Maham molana tended to train the more advanced practitioners in
depth so those are a couple of examples of expression of freedom I think you can
maybe get a sense of their different personality and there are others the nand Medina in the Buddhist time was
eloquent unsurpassed in her eloquence among the women foremost in teaching
especially of lay people and her Dharma sister pachara exemplified and modeled this
inner beauty that just Shone from her and this dedication to
Virtue excuse me and she became the foremost instructor of new nuns quite a
following so it can take many forms of expression this Awakening I've heard
stories of Awakened people in the Saigon Hills of Burma from colleagues and friends of mine and one exemplifies
utter peace and just radiates it to the point where it's palpable even walking into his space and another was happy and
light and joyful all of these are dimensions of the free heart
so again this Liberation is freedom from being impacted by Affliction from the
LIF denying forces that can come to us through Society our own inner more
primitive urges our upbringing it's freedom to respond with
Clarity without reactivity to whatever life brings not to make things worse for
self others or anyone it's freedom to be okay to flourish in
any circumstances at all so to recap this kind of
freedom is what the Buddha considered the most potent form of
power and this week all of these other good qualities we've covered feed into
that nourish that capacity for the heartre and each Glimpse
metabolized can be onward leading all of them together represent a
kind of efficacy in life a healthy spiritual life
spoon so whether it you're cultivating spiritual
empowerment of healthy desire energy heart qualities
engagement willpower virtue
somma or moments of Freedom it's all onward leading each contributes to Joy
connection self-sufficiency and peace so your assignment over the
weekend should you choose to take it is to notice moments in your life when your
heart feels free not entangled and metabolize it each moment
be nourished by it and if you like share it with your friends thank you so much for your kind
attention it's been an absolute Joy being with you this week May all beings be free