warm greetings and welcome to this uh meditation
session and it's part of a series on an introduction to mindfulness
practice where the second week of the series we're focusing on mindfulness of the
body and so I want to begin today with a guided meditation on the body body mindfulness
it's a little bit of exercise to begin with but it's an exercise that um meant
to uh give you a insiders inside
uh experience of what mindfulness of the body can be
like that uh we want to be the Buddha talked about
being aware of the body in the body to be aware to be mindful of the
body in terms of the body and what that means is that we're not adding a lot of
for any judgments or evaluations or
commentary uh [Music] or heavy handed use of Me Myself and
mine I the doer the uh with the mindfulness with just
being aware of the Simplicity of how the I how the body experiences itself
independent of the more complicated judgments and comments commentary we have about
it so uh it's meant to be phenomenally simple and some people find it's a huge
relief that we don't have to be judging you don't have to be figuring things out
we don't have to be thinking about we're allowed just to in a sense rest the
awareness in the body letting the body do the body
fullness let the body do the awareness fullness of what the experience
is so to begin assuming a meditation
posture that gives you some stability and you might move your body
around whatever way you have positioned your body kind of
wiggle it or rock it or to kind
of find a way to establish the
stability of being here on this spot nowhere else just
here
gently closing your
eyes and before we do the exercise to take a few long long slow
breaths in the way that's comfortable for you letting go as you
exhale releasing near the end of the exhale so the exhale continues a
bit
and then letting your breathing return to normal and feel see if you
can sense or feel whatever degree of stability you
have in your sitting bones in the place where the weight of
your body is received by some
surface maybe a sense of stability in your whole
torso and then to with your ordinary
breathing spend a minute or two relaxing more in the
body scanning your body as you inhale scanning for the tension and the
holding releasing as you
exhale
for
and now to begin the exercise bring your
attention to your nondominant hand and take a few moments to feel the
hand and if in feeling it you feel it you can
move your hand a little bit too so it's better positioned more
comfortable move your
hand and then become aware of the sensations in the hand
it might be pulsing or tingling warmth and
coolness there might be the pressure of the contact of your hand against some
part of your body
being aware of the hand in the hand meaning becoming aware of how the hand
experiences itself less up in the control tower
watching thinking about the hand and
more allowing the hand to reveal itself
reveal the Kaleidoscope of Sensations that appear in the
hand in the palm of the
hand the back of the hand
in the
fingers and your mind your thinking mind the control
tower might have thoughts judgments reactions to what we're
doing but those are distinct from how the hand is experiencing itself
for these few minutes put aside what goes on in the
mind in terms of thoughts and judgments and reactions let those be in the
background in the foreground become aware more intimately
more fully what the experience of hand
is as as if you've never gotten to know your neled
hand feel it for
itself
chances are with this kind of attention to the hand you're experiencing a lot more
Sensations in the hand than you would if we had just stayed with the breathing ignoring the
hand kind of but placing awareness in the
hand more of that hand the experience of
hand reveals
itself and then ending the focus on the non-dominant
hand taking a three breath joury
Journey returning to breathing for three
breaths relaxing letting
go and then bringing your calmly bringing your attention
in your dominant hand and with a calm
awareness feel let the hand feel the sensations that appear in the
dominant
hand
the hand feels the sensations and you make room in the
mind make room in Awareness for the sensations to appear
and show
themselves
and if you find yourself straining or Contracting in the eyes or in the
mind to do this exercise see if you can relax the
Mind relax around the eyes eyes to be
receptive to the hands experience of
itself
and now consider for a
moment where in your body you normally experience your
breathing and more in the belly more in the chest more in the
nostrils more than all three Al together wherever it might
be and without focusing on the
breathing become aware of that part of your body in the way that you're aware of
your
hand letting that part of your
body sense and
feel the sensations that
appear not
specifically aware of the
breathing but as it occurs those Sensations are also part of what appears
and
disappears
maybe with a rhythm of breathing allowing the sensations to be
there on the exhale and letting the that part of the
body receive the sensations on the
inhale
for
for letting the place where you experience
breathing be the home for your
awareness that you return to over and
over but if there's some any Sensations in the body elsewhere
that are more compelling more
predominant experiment with gently
calmly opening awareness in that location in your
body and feeling that the sensations there as you felt the hand
and for a few moments now letting go of breathing and just feeling those predominant
Sensations letting commentary and judgment and concerns weed to the
background so there's space for the sensations
to show themselves whatever way they come and go and move and
shift
for
and after being aware of some other sensation for a
while then return again to the home base Begin Again with your
breathing or more accurately Begin Again in that location we're breathing is most
clearly known and be aware of whatever reveals
itself there whatever Sensations whether of the breathing or
not if there's something strong that arises again in the body let let there be a gentle rhythm
of Shifting awareness to that location for a
while and if it feels like you've acknowledged it enough gently calmly begin again
with the home base awareness of the Body
Sensations of
breathing
for
and in the last little period of actual meditation you could
experiment with not having a home base for your awareness but rather allow your
awareness to gently float through your
body to whatever Sensations in your body call your
awareness whatever Sensations are predominant or compelling without thinking about it or
analyzing it without concerns with being right or
wrong just let your awareness be relaxed and calm
not fixated on
anything and every time the awareness lands in a new
place take some moments to feel it like you felt the
hand and then open yourself up to let the
awareness move on to another part of your
body so breathing is not at the center breathing is just one of the
places one of the
sensations that a free flowing awareness takes in as the awareness is
centered in the
body
for
e
and then as we come to the end of the
sitting to feel the stability or openness calm that might be in the body
and if those things are not there maybe a tightened
awareness of your body and as you exhale to relax the body
more the healing power of awareness and relaxation
together and turning your awareness outwards to the world around
you world with many challenges and a world filled with
people who are trying to help
for all the images of great disasters natural or
human-made there's so many pictures and videos of people
helping helping others may it be that we live in a
world where we help each other we support each other we care for each
other and may the mindfulness and stability and calm that we have through
this practice support us in doing that may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all all beings be
peaceful may all beings everywhere be
[Music]
free thank you
so hello and welcome to this seventh talk on
mindfulness meditation introduction to mindfulness
meditation and uh this week the focus is
on mindfulness of the body and as I said yesterday this is one
of the central teachings of the the Buddha the foundation of his meditation practice is a deep stable connection to
the body to our and part of the reason for this is that we're trying to become free
of the hegemony of our thinking our judgments our biased our
stereotyping our preconceived ideas free of
our uh fixed agenda and opinions and stories of what is and
isn't not because these are necessarily wrong to have but because they interfere
with their ability for a deep Connection in the present moment it would be it's kind of like a
friend who cares for you a lot through some effort maybe the person is
challenged in some kind of way but overcame the challenge so that to make
you a really nice meal took a lot of care in the preparation of the food the
flavors the layout of the table and you sit down at the table and you
don't really notice what the person is done and you hardly taste the food
because uh you're caught up in judgments
about worldly Affairs and who's right and who's wrong and and you're spinning
out opinions and and um ready to argue your case and and you're kind of like
kind of preoccupied that you don't even notice what the your friend has done for you so in the same way we don't even
notice what our body what our inner life what the world is doing for us in the moment
here and there is something really special whether we're suffering or
whether we're happy whe whether the body is in pain or whether it's comfortable there's something very profound that's
possible when we respect this body and respect it with
our attention careful attention to the body and um and the body is not just a
hunk of Flesh it's a there's a lot of wisdom that arises in the body a lot of
information that arises out of the body lot of guidance in how to live our life that comes from being connected to our
body for people who do meditation um focusing of the body is
one of the ways that we begin getting out of our head out of our
preoccupations and start finding a very different way of being here in this body
and the body is kind of like a door that you open and there's many dimensions of
other depths of connection to ourselves and to the world that can happen through
the doorway of the body so in the way that
um here at IMC mindfulness is usually kind of foundational kind of teaching of
mindfulness is to use breathing as the home base so we would rest there we
would ride the breath and the Brea brething is this Wonder for some people
a wonderful antidote to wondering off in thought for one thing it shows us when
we're wondering off and then we can be wise about that and see that clearly and
relax it also is a nice place to rest the mind for some people so that there's
some continuity over time and as we have continuity with the breathing whether it's three breaths whether it's five
breaths there's something during that period of time that helps the Mind begin
slowly to relax and relax because the energy of attention is going into
breathing which is a relaxing or a or a
opening kind of experience instead of the energy of
attention uh going into thinking into preoccupation and thereby fueling it
stirring it up and continuing it more and more more so we're kind of redirecting the food of the
Mind from what is not so helpful to something that's more helpful from
preoccupations and distracted thought to being present here and now with our
experience in this case with the breathing however some people like when
some meditation practices like in like when I practice Zen breathing was a primary focus and just come back to the
breath over and over again it's kind of a concentration practice practice uh in the pra way we teach here
at IMC where we're teaching mindfulness more than concentration um we do use the breathing
as a default uh when it works for people but then when something else becomes more
compelling something else becomes more pronounced some other sensation in the
body then um we happily contentedly um shift the focus of
attention from the breathing to this other thing in the body so it could be
discomfort it could be pleasure it could be any sensations of warmth cold
coolness any Sensations at all whatever it might be is equally valid as a place
to cultivate present moment attention we're just developing that present moment attention with that other
sensation it's possible that it's enough just to acknowledge it for a little while feel it and sense it and then we
begin again with the breathing or it's sometimes it's nice just to stay stay there something it's
very compelling very strong and then just uh enter into that world of that
part of the body like that we did in the exercise with a hand where you're not
necessarily focusing on the discomfort but you're focusing because that's a little bit of abstraction that's an idea
discomfort but underneath the idea they kind of kind of global kind of sense of
what's going on there's a the the details of the individual Sensations
that are at play in that area of discomfort or in that area that's very comfortable or Pleasant and IDE is to
just stay with it and feel it and let that be a place where the you're training yourself to notice the
distracted mind to notice the straining mind the demanding mind the expecting
mind the resisting mind and relax so you can kind of begin
finding a way of being present in a relaxed way non-reactive
way so that's kind of the basic idea is we stay with the breathing something else becomes compelling we let we let go
of the breathing and attend to that for a little while and then come back to the breathing some people as I've said last
week the breathing doesn't work very well for the focus of attention some
people what works much better is to just have the to be open more generally and
globally in the body without much particular focus on the breathing and
then allow the awareness to float or drift or move around the body to
whatever is compelling whatever appears whatever shows itself whatever is asking
for attention but as we bring the attention to the different parts of the body being careful not to fixate on it
not to get stuck there but keep the attention soft and light so that when
something else occurs that's more compelling or calls on you the mind can just gently float to there and so it's
the present moment experiences of the body that are the grounding in the
present moment that are the way of uh of um an alternative than distracted
thinking so rather than the breathing being the primary home the whole body is the home for attention and that way
there's not this kind of uh zeroing in or preoccupation or concern or reactivity around breathing which some
people have that makes it difficult to be with the breathing and um so it even and so both
both ways of practicing are quite wonderful and and what's interesting is
whichever one we start with at some point we come to a point where we move into the other people who mostly focus
on the breathing as they get really stable and settled um there's a way in which their attention opens up and it's
what feels the best is this open awareness to whatever is happening in the body and uh letting it show itself
and let the awareness kind of just stay open to the different places people who start with a more open awareness to the
body at some point will find that things get simpler and simpler and uh more
relaxed and what's the biggest movements of the body then become their
primary subject of attention and those proba biggest movement is the breathing
but they come to that breathing then in a much more relaxed easygoing way where there's not any complications or less
complic there are less complications with the breathing and it can be kind of uh quite nice to just then kind of flow
lightly with the breathing so this it shifts and changes this but for if if all all things are
equal uh I recommend the the foundational way here at IMC is to use
the breathing as the home base and be content to stay there and be with the
breath as much as you can um and um but if something else in the body becomes
predominant um shift your attention to the predominant thing and that might be
for 3 or 4 seconds just to feel it and acknowledge it that's enough and then it can recede to the background or you
might discover that you need to make it the primary focus of attention it might be for five minutes you're just
exploring and feeling and breathing with that
sensation and um so maybe that's enough for today so
breathing and body so as you go about your day today I
would very much encourage you to continue with mindfulness of your body and um and if those of you who set
a timer yesterday that went off periodically through the day or if you other ways of periodically checking in
with yourself um check in with yourself first to feel how you are in your
body and then take the three breath journey and after youve done the three
breath Journey feel what's happened what's shifted in your body and if you do that even just once
every hour through a day I think it could have a very profound uh impact on very helpful
impact on you and if nothing else it's very educational to discover more deeply what's going on
so stop and just notice what's happening in your body take time to feel it
breathe with it then do the three breath Journey just kind of Center yourself on
three breaths as if that's the only thing that you need to do in the world and then open to the body and see
what shifted and that whole process doesn't have to take more than a
minute and if it's enjoyable you could do it you can do it
more so um thank you very much
and I look forward to continuing this series
tomorrow