hello everyone and welcome and
uh so this week's theme is recognizing
the after effects or the benefits the experiential
benefits of letting go of release of non-
clinging and one of them is related to
a term that or an aspect of mindfulness that sometimes I like to
emphasize that being mindful is when we're mindful of
some we're giving room for that thing making space for it giving room to it
maybe we've all had some experience of being in a very crowded place where we
felt kind of hemmed in and then uh we go to some place where we feel like we have
lots of room and we can sometimes we call it bre having breathing room even
and uh and then sometimes within lots of room we can just relax and something
inside of us settles because when we're claustrophobic when things are kind of pressing against us um it's more
difficult to relax so part of uh mindfulness is to
make room give room breathing room to our breathing to our sense experiences
of in our body to our emotions even to thinking though that's
a little bit more tricky uh to give room for it is to not just give room for it
just to continue on kind of spinning out but making room
so that we're not fueling it anymore we're not not squeezing it out so if
we keep our foot on the gas pedal then the car will go faster and
faster but if we back off and make give room for the petal our foot is no longer
on the pedal and then the car slows down so it's like that we're thinking we
give room to it so that we're not uh perpetuating not not fuel in it
anymore so to assume a meditation
posture and there is a way of Sometimes using a
posture that makes us feel bigger so for those
sitting upright it's a sit a little bit more upright to sit a little bit more
maybe with the chest uh expand iive not pushing it outwards but uh letting it maybe by
pulling in the spine between the shoulder blades the chest comes out a little
bit or if you are um sitting in a with a back rest
sometimes putting a little pillow or something between the shoulder blades so
that again you get the same effect that something's being pushed out people who meditate in bed maybe can
do something a little bit similar um maybe there's something gentle that can be put between the
shoulder blades that allows the chest to expand a little more and also how we
what we do with the arms um you know that's an advantage
sometimes of meditating laying down is we can kind of open our our hands upwards have our eye hands to the side
sometimes and upwards and shoulders a little bit rolling back and it creates a little more sense of
bigness so we're beginning to feel our way into a sense of making
space having lots of room for what we're going to be with we have very little room when we
react to things and when we are bothered by
things so to
gently close the eyes and take some long deep
breaths with the in breath feeling how the body expands the
Torso expands in some way rib cage
expands that we in a sense become
bigger
that sense of growing bigger on the in breath can
correct some fixed idea that limits us that keeps us kind
of shrunk or pulled
in feeling the lifting and expanding of the rib
cuge and and then keeping some of that sense of bigness or
largess and keeping it there as you exhale
relax
soften it isn't that the body is kept large
expanded with the exhale but the inner sensibility sense of our size can stay
big
and letting the breathing return to
normal and still as you breathe in
to as you breathe in to feel the now smaller movements of
expansion in the chest in the rib cage maybe in the
belly maybe much more subtly in the back rib
cage and in and in the sensations of the rib cage
expanding maybe feeling there's lots of room for the
breathing to occur the breathing all the breathing
that's happening inside of the rib cage has
room the sensations of expansion and movement
filling contraction Letting Go
emptying then they continue with this settling process to feel the tensions you might
have in your face around the forehead the eyes the cheeks the
mouth if you have them there and as you
breathe imagine that you're making lots of room for those Sensations to be there
they're allowed to be there
spaciously
expensively and then as you exhale to let whatever tension you have
in your face relax relax outward into that
space
and then doing the same for the shoulders if you're aware of any tension
in your shoulders first see if you can readjust
the position of your hands your
arms to ease up a little bit of that tension
and then as you breathe
in to make room for whatever Sensations and feelings are in your
shoulder an expansive space spacious sense of there's room for those
Sensations to be themselves free of our judgments and
reactions and then on the
exhale to relax and soften the shoulders so the tension
expands into the space around them or dissolves into the
space and then on the
inhale to feel any tension or agitation pressure in the thinking
mind with the inhale imagining lots of
space there's room for your mind to be tense agitated it's
okay the inhale reminds you to have a wider
view of the space around the
tension giving
room
and then to relax the thinking mind soften the
thinking mind with the
exhale so the tensions
agitations dissolve evaporate into the space around
them and then to settle into the body experience of
breathing giving room space for the sensations of breathing as
you breathe in releasing letting
go as you exhale so that all
things expand relax outward
into the space around
you
for
e
whatever is happening for you
now recognize it as such making room for for it to be
there taking the foot off the gas pedal making
space so we can relax
dissolve outward into the space around
it
for
e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting
to [Music] imagine all the space that's around
you beyond the edges of your
body that there is more space to hold all things your thoughts your feelings
your body in the spaciousness of the mind
that's as spaci as expansive and open as the space around
you and that any movement of tension of tightening up of grasping on
is a narrowing down a closing
in can even be claustrophobic sometimes when there's lots of thoughts and
feelings we're caught up
in and letting this simple awareness of all things
let that awareness be Broad and wide
spacious so there's room to be aware of other people in that
space we give other people lots of room to be who they
are as long as they don't threaten us
or allow them to be in the spacious quality of the
art where it's a gift to be present for
others and making room from to be just as they
are they don't have to contend with our judgments our
agendas our preference preferences they can just be
there as they are and in that
spaciousness let there be a a channel room for Good
Will May all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may my presence my
attention make room for that possibility
[Music]
thank
you
e
hello everyone and welcome and I feel delighted and have a
good fortune to for this theme this week to talk
about the symptoms of letting go
so the certainly we can become aware of how we cling and hold on tight and close
down and then there's opening up and the release of
clinging release itself that uh is part of the
possibility the potential of this Buddhist practice of mindfulness is more than just to relax
but to really find a sense of Freedom through through it one of the very
profound little sayings that comes from the Buddha kind of a summation of what's
most important he said nothing whatsoever is
worth clinging to he didn't say that nothing's worth
nothing is worthwhile at all he said nothing is worth clinging to the extra
that we do the holding on the resisting the pushing away that tightening up and
um and with enough clinging enough things we're attached to preoccupied with caught up in um the mind the heart
our very life can feel claustrophobic we can feel there's just too much going on just too much swirling
around sometimes it's so much that we can't get our bearing we don't even know what to
do and um I've asked people sometimes to notice the difference
between being CAU up in thought and then when they notice that they're in their
thinking and then they switch to being mindful of it this is what it's like to be thinking what's the difference
between those two states lost in thought and open and aware to what the thinking
is happening and some people report back that uh it they feel really small closed
in when they're caught up in thoughts that something almost goes dark becomes
Things become obscure but when there's this awareness of it the mindfulness of it there's an
opening there's a feeling of clarity and brightness that happens in the mind in our sense of
being and um and this points to how one of the symptoms of non- clinging is
space is room is a sense of expansiveness sometimes the mind can
feel very expansive sometimes a sense of awareness can feel
expansive sometimes the there can feel like as as if there's lots of room in
our body um like there's space lots of space for whatever arises can just be
there um in this ocean of space ocean of
awareness and so uh expansive state of being expansive state of awareness
expansive state of mind it is one of the symptoms that uh results of non-
clinging Letting Go release the kind of spiritual Freedom that Buddha
emphasized and so we can feel that we can begin tuning into it and the reason
for that to notice the symptoms of Letting Go symptoms of
relaxing is that um that reinforces uh our appreciation of that
allows us to notice more often and how it's there when we normally would have
overlooked it we would have not paid attention to it because the expansive state of being has no I don't know has
no monetary value you can't buy it um it's not about having some experience
it's not about our opinions it's not about our getting what we want or it's not about making ourselves
safe in a conventional ways but it's still it's people would
say it's Priceless it's invaluable um because in that
great spaciousness of Mind spaciousness of heart it allows makes room for some
of the most beautiful parts of who we are as a human being to flow makes room for some of most our beautiful
connections with other people to flow and when we lock down get caught get
tight and uh caught up in compulsions and addictions something closes down
something arrows something gets um lost in that
process so to notice the spaciousness to notice a sense of
expansiveness to make room for our experience and sometimes I've used that
as a kind of his own orientation for my practice the question how can I make
room for this and sometimes I wondered really
this too and then the mind says yes this too the practice mind says yes this too
make room for it and why one of the reasons to make room for everything make
space for everything to kind of hold it in the spacious mind is that the alternative is not good for us the
alternative makes the whole situ situation worse the alternative of closing down locking in resisting
tightening up getting narrow shrinking uh is a form of suffering is a form of
diminishing ourselves and so it's not the better alternative but being expansive
open um spacious with everything making room for whatever is
happening is just a fantastic thing to tune into and notice and
appreciate it can come with challenges some of the challenges are
that uh it can be frightening that uh there's a maybe a false sense of protect
of being protected if we tighten up and cling and resist and hold back but uh
we're not really doing ourselves a favor there's uh um and so sometimes we have
to deal with when we're more expansive and open it can feel like we're now more vulnerable it can feel like now there's
nothing protecting us but there was nothing really protecting us before if we're locked up in tense and have armor
on um we're actually harming ourselves and uh but to open up uh be be
afraid is one of the reasons why it's hard to do this but the art of it is to learn how to be
open um and not let the ordinary threats
around us that normally we closed down to let them affect us to let them touch
something for us to learn how not to react to them it's our reaction to some
of the things that are threatening things people say and do that's independent of any physical harm but um
that people say things to us then something inside of us locks up resists feels uh challenged feels
threatened feels hurt and sometimes that's reasonable but
sometimes it's extra it's not really needed and the and the D D that we're
that maybe we're think we're protecting ourselves from external danger um what
we really want to do is try to protect ourselves from the inner danger of shutting down closing up getting tight
so this idea of the expansiveness of non- clinging has its challenges um but uh it's a wonderful
challenge to have to explore and navigate um this new it's almost like a new territory learning a new language
and learning a new coming into to a new city and learning the territory it takes a while to learn how to navigate in it
but it's really worth it so one of the
signposts for freedom for release for non- clinging
non-grasping is a sense of expansiveness um sometime people call it
even uh a big mind since the Mind begs big or big heart the heart feels big our
presence feels kind of bigger and um and um to to appreciate
that to explore it to include it and not worry that it might be a sign of conceit
one of the reasons not to be expensive is some people are afraid if I do that then I'm too big I'm I take up too much
space for people and it's a sign of conceit or being domineering again it doesn't have to
be um it uh it might actually people won't feel us as being assertive they might feel us as
being now safer to be with more available friendlier Kinder so to
uh so if we let go a little we can maybe feel a little
expansiveness we let go more we feel more expensiveness let go let go of lot
the sense of expansiveness can be quite quite spacious quite expansive maybe almost infinite in
feeling so um as you go through today uh you might see what it's like to
make give more room to your experience to whatever is happening can you make room for it can
you make more space for it can you allow it to be there in an
expansive receptivity or an expansive open openess um and then navigate what
happens as a result find your way with it become learn to be wise in that space
of an expansive mind expansive heart and um and appreciate don't don't
have a high bar for what expensiveness mean it can just be a little bit more than how you normally are or maybe it's
times when you feel most contracted that that's maybe the most interesting time to experiment given
this can I make room for being contracted can I make room for this
too so thank you very much and uh I hope
uh in the process of this that the this world of ours our shared world begins to
feel like there's lots of room and lots of space for us to be alive in to be
free in and to be ourselves in thank
you