so hello and welcome and as an introduction to this
meditation uh I'm going to be addressing in the meditation through the
meditation the issue of restlessness or agitation as that's the fourth of the
five hindrances and it's valuable to
understand that um the tradition says that unless you're fully
enlightened human beings will always carry with them a degree of agitation or
restlessness so if you should feel that way uh it just part of The Human
Experience Being Human comes along with that there can be varying degrees of it
of course and sometimes it can take over and sometimes it's subtle but one of the
uh triggers for agit there number of triggers for this agitation that's so
fundamental but one of them has to do with the other uh kind of
hindrances which uh especially the first two uh desire avariciousness sensual
desire and avariciousness and uh ill will or
aversion and these are also considered to be part and parcel of most human beings we're kind of born
with them this tendency so if we have any of the hindrances there's no need to take them personally personally like
you're the only one who has it and therefore you're terrible uh we all all
human beings contend with them they're part of being a human being and then learning to be wise about them is part
of the and uh part of the task and how to hold them without any further
reactivity uh hold them without shooting second
arrows so but the first two uh desire and
aversion uh they contribute to agitation if you have too many desires
and we're jumping around chasing them that's an agitated state if our desires
are frustrated or if somehow we have desires but we can't act on it and we but we
feel the the strong desire to do something even healthy desires appropriate desires if we're held in
check by Society family work anything uh that energy of the desire that we want
to do um is held in check and then it in check it kind of vibrates it kind of
it's there with pressure that agitates same thing with aversion that uh we can have a lot of
things we're aversive to and we're kind of jumping around and searching for it and just everything is wrong and so
agitation itself uh aversion itself is agitating but also uh kind of frustrated
uh aversion aversion which doesn't seem to be able to do anything or accomplish anything that's held in check or held
back or just kind of you know um
unempowered or something not that we should Empower our ill will but still
it's held in check uh and so there's something agitating there just it vibrating and
the pressure there um and also uh the the human being
I think needs one of the basic needs is the need to be able to have agency to be
engaged in something in a healthy way um we're not only supposed to be quiet and
peaceful sitting serenely doing nothing um that doesn't really work for the
depth of our psychology and who we are and so uh when desires and aversions
create agitation when they um the frustration of them adds to
frustration um what we call upon what can really support us is to do
something wholeheartedly that we value maybe that we love that that do something which
really we can put oursel into so the whole psychophysical system can have the
experience of yes we have some agency we can do something here we can settle some
of this maybe inherent agitation by doing one thing really well or
thoroughly and in terms of this doing meditation practice that one thing is
the meditation it is just for example just
you of wholeheartedly immerse ourselves in the practice of present moment
awareness increase the degree of motivation increase the degree of commitment increase the degree of
wholeheartedness without strain without adding some kind of Desire that will just make you more
agitated uh without aversion but there is a form of love there is a form of
Faith or trust yes let's give ourselves just here to the
breathing and um and then the breathing is boring it isn't that the that the
breathing is the source of our life it's the
engagement it's the IM immersion with the breath immersion with your present moment experience that puts us into it
gathers together and some people talk about then uh uh as we do this
wholeheartedly that it puts us in a flow state but for the purpose of today it
puts it begins to settle us it begins to reassure some part of our deep mind that
oh we have something valuable to do here important to do something trustworthy to do and we can do it and then some of the
other causes of agitation can begin to settle down so that's the premise for
this meditation so assuming a meditation
posture and closing your
eyes and to feel yourself sitting
here feel here you get to experience a human
being from the inside out you get to do something that no one
else can do is you get to have for this
person that you are you get to really have a closeness to and really sense and
feel more than anyone else can what it's like to be alive right now
breathing
any Sensation that you experience Pleasant or unpleasant any feeling that
you have is a symptom that you're experiencing
life as it's being lived inside from the inside
out and it's your task to care for this
life it's your task to participate in this life
wholeheartedly and to do so Beginning by taking a few long
slow deep breaths not too big not too fast not too
slow but in a
full engaged way immersing yourself in the experience of breathing
deeply
fully expanding chest as you lifting shoulders
maybe sometimes the front of the rib cage it opens and expands lifts
sometimes the sides of the rib cage
expand sometimes is the movements of the belly or all of the
above relaxing as you exhale not relaxing
mechanically but relaxing with a care and kindness a
love a gentle appreciation for you and this
body letting your breathing return to
normal for some thousands of years years human beings have
meditated following their breathing following the sensations in the body of
breathing in and breathing out people have entered the world of
breathing wholeheartedly they've trusted
it they found it it be a
doorway to engage ING with life in a full immersive way with something very
simple trusting breathing trusting the process of opening and
receiving of
intimacy so we'll continue in
silence and with breathing or any other way you practice
mindfulness Let It Be an act of devotion or trust or love or whole
heartedness to give yourself to the meditation without
strain as if by giving yourself wholeheartedly to
this more than anything else more than your thoughts other
wishes you're providing food nourishment
satisfaction for a very deep
need the need for being fully
engaged the need to feel your
agency and whenever your mind winners often
thought be gentle about that take your time with
that to recognize and know it where the
recognition is part of this wholehearted here I am this is what's
happening just staying present knowing is
invaluable knowing this life as it
unfolds
e
for
here you might consider that staying
mindful is for these minutes the most valuable thing you can
do more than anything else just be
here present for your
experience
for
e
and then to come to the end of this
sitting to gently
relax let go of your effort to practice allow yourself just to be here
and now in a simple
way
allow yourself to be as you are with compassion and
Care maybe with a profound respect for this life how difficult it
is and how good it is
to acknowledge oneself one C circumstances
and to just be still and quiet for a little bit in the middle of it
all and out of the Stillness or out of the sweetness or out of the Care
compassion
to turn your attention outward now to the people in your life the
people here and participating in this meditation
today people in The Wider world around
you and to reflect and think and feel good will to them all wishing them
well may you all be
happy may you all be
safe may you all be
peaceful may you all be
free may you all find your
way with all the challenges and joys of this
life and may we all support each other in this life that we
[Music] share
[Music]
thank [Music]
you
so hello on this Thursday the fourth day of
on the topic of the hindrances and the hindrances
are considered to be some of the primary obstacles to mindfulness and to
concentration really being present here in some way and at the same time they're almost
Universal in human experience and it's often emphasized that uh no need to take them personally
like their personal failure ings they're just part and parcel of what we're born with or come into into our life
with and rather than taking it as enemies or as some personal faults we
take them as subjects for mindfulness for practice for
contemplation and even even for a certain degree of respect that these are
part of the human condition and part of respecting ourselves is to respect their presence
and then learn how to overcome the hindering
quality so there can be desire that is a hindrance and the same desire can be
there and not be a hindrance same thing with aversion and sloth and torper all of them and the
difference is that when their hindrance were involved with them in some way we've succumbed to them we've given
ourselves over to them we' have somehow you know become them and the task of mindfulness is to
step away enough so we they we're not involved with them we're not caught in
their grip we're not gripping onto them and so they can be there but they're not
interfering so it's not all or nothing uh for these qualities It's All
or Nothing with in their hindering qualities we uh in the sense that we can
either have them as a hindrance or we can see them well enough and clearly
enough that they no longer are a hindrance they're just phenomena one more thing that we're aware of and in
that way we're beginning to take refuge or put our faith
into um our life energy into the process of being
Mindful and learning how to be present and aware mindful clearly recognizing what's happening
without identifying with it without reacting to it without being bothered by
it and learning how to be free from it so uh so today the topic is uh
restlessness and regret or agitation and regret or
remorse and um and these are agitated energies agitated ways in which the
heart and mind can be and uh and that can be quite strong you know we can feel like we want a bolt we feel like we
can't sit still um and I've sat in meditation with so much restlessness that um because I
had such strong faith in the mindfulness I made the restlessness the object of my
meditation and it was so much fun because what I did was uh I felt the
Restless energy in my body as a pingpong ball that was just bouncing off the sides of the wall my body just kind like
boom boom boom boom and it was kind of so much fun to um to just kind of be
with it and feel it and and uh and um
and rather than identify with it rather than being bothered by it or reacting to
it even having aversion to something like restlessness is being caught in its
grip it's kind of being involved the idea is to just see it and be with it
and the and feeling it physically however it's also helpful to understand some of the Dynamics that evoke it so
first this idea the universal quality of the hindrances the Buddha said that only
someone who is fully enlightened at the final and fourth stage of Awakening um do they no longer have
restlessness or agitation so even if you're partially enlightened you can expect that the mind
will have some restlessness and part of their reason for this is that um any kind of
attachment we have so for example attachment to desire or attachment to
ill will aversion means that um uh if
that is that that attachment that desire to do desire is wanting something
aversion is wanting something go away if that's frustrated if we can't act on it
in a sane way we can't act on it in a ethical way we can't you know then
something inside of us is held in check and even when there's no attachment involved uh necessarily or uh
if there's healthy desire and healthy averting or saying no but social
conditions World conditions uh uh means that we're not allowed to speak up we can't speak up we can't do what we want
to do and so that desire and and and and know this Di and healthier version is
bottled up is held in check and that uh then you know you can
either either go to sleep shut down get dull or the opposite strategy is to get
all worked up and agitated and you feel this you know like sometimes in extreme way like the water is boiling inside um
but um and um and so that's with agitation with regret this is when we've
done something that we have remorse about and and I like the word remorse
because um maybe regret can be healthy but remorse in the Latin roots of it
means we're chewing something over a morsal we remsing it we're chewing and
chewing and chewing the same thing and uh and usually remorse uh is a kind of
problematic when we're just kind of reviewing and reviewing and beating ourselves up and being critical and not
knowing what to do and feeling we should do something about it and um and uh and so
there again there's an agitated uh energy that gets caught we're caught in the grip of it and
so you know if it's it's it's kind of a a time when our
action doing something is frustrated held in check it doesn't mean that we
necessarily should be acting on the desires acting on the aversions um but maybe we had should
think about yes there is action needed here and what is that
action uh regrets sometimes what's needed is apology sometimes what's needed is to go
make amends to go talk to someone something in the world is needed to do
it's not enough just to sit and try to be mindful and let go and find our Peace by ourselves that actually does a kind
of harm to ourselves to not take care of what really needs to be taken care of in this world I've known people friends of
mine who were sitting on Retreat and they knew like one friend of mine was in
India and he knew he he had some problems an issue that came up he went to his teacher and his teacher said um
um go home go home to America and address this issue and then come back so
my friend did and uh and and um because some things need to be addressed and
otherwise the agitation will stay the restlessness will stay uh sometimes what's needed is that
the human our human heart our human psyche needs to know that we can take
certain degree of I was going to say control and arvas the circles that's kind of a taboo topic to be controlling
or to control try to control your experience so maybe I should try to avoid it but we need our system needs to
know that we will act we will do something we're not just going to sit there passively and let things just
occur and happen and uh and and when it's a hindrances when it's like desires which
are just fantasies or unhealthy or aversions which have more
to do with attachments or hatred or something we don't want to act on
those but the our heart our mind needs to know that we can act we're
not holding ourselves in check and engaging in the process of
mindfulness being mindful of avariciousness greed being mindful of Av
verion and having faith and confidence this is the practice this is a valuable
thing to do there's no doubt that better action is to be mindful of these than to
them to still kind of boil over or the better action is to be clearly present
for them rather than giving into them something in our system appreciates that
we're doing we're engaged and how to engage so that it's
the engagement of mindfulness is not itself
um um agitating is the art that the engagement itself is settling
makes us more peaceful and the reference point I want to make is some an athlete like you know
someone who runs um you know who goes running as a sport and and um and
they takes a lot of physical energy to do a long run but some people get into a
flow State uh they get absorbed in it and certainly and the everything comes
into harmony gets unified and it get really a sense of flow and quiet maybe
even something in the mind gets really still and they're really present there's a way of expending energy that is har
completely harmonious and promotes calm and peace so if meditation is only about
trying to find peace trying to relax and settle and not do and not do and not do
um we're actually do might be doing a disservice to that part of our inner life that needs to feel like we can do
something we can act we can move forward we're not always held in
check and um and uh and then there's a combination of these something like
anger sometimes needs to be given its freedom but not freedom for us to act on
it but if if it doesn't give its freedom to be in process then again there's
agitation and so the Marvel about this medit in meditation and some other
situations in life where it's safe to let the anger flow through us but we
know how to do it without participating in it without getting involved in it or reactive to it and sitting in meditation
learning how to have a good upright posture or doesn't have to be upright
but uh an intentional posture where we're not going to collapse into something or get involved in it by
um and then staying mindful the best we can and like giving freedom to these
movements even of Desire sometimes so we can see it clearly so we can make space
for it so that something can begin to shift in the freedom of letting it
flow we don't want to feed it but we don't want to repress it and that also then begins overcoming
the restlessness of things being held in check so I think what I'm saying today
is not necessarily easy to understand and practice but um
because the the the lesson that sometimes we have to act
engage um is uh can lend itself to somehow being more agitated and more
tense but I'm trying to point to some another possibility and one of the way to
understand it is that one of the most valuable things we can actions that we can give ourselves to and it is an
activity is kind of an action is the action of being aware aware action of
being Mindful and being mindful in a way that's relaxed at ease unbothered by
what we know we're knowing is fully something we trust we immerse ourselves
in this mindfulness practice immerse ourselves in being really here but in such a way that there's no
tension in the knowing and in the end we discover that
uh we can know while being free of what is being
known and that knowing is can becomes really nurturing nourishing for that
part of our heart or inner life that needs to know that we're here and
engaged in doing something very important and as meditation goes deeper
and deeper the act of simple simple clear knowing clear knowing Lucid
knowing uh is more and more valuable more and more sweet more and more
clarifying and it just feels like one of them like a flow State almost almost like one of the best things to put our
life energy into and it's so satisfying and gratifying and yes there's purpose
here there's value here there's meaning here there's agency here there is um
Faith here um and so when you find yourself in the
grip of the fourth hindrance agitation and
remorse maybe it's a sign that's there's 's a really deep need for
Action so that some kind of desire to
act that's frustrated that's causing the agitation something needs to be done
there to meet it that's in in the realm of activity not giving into it and doing
what it wants but some other activity that's healthy and
important and exactly what that activity is I can't tell you but at least
mindfulness the practice of mindfulness the meditation on it is one of the most meaningful things we can do and if we
can really immerse ourselves with faith and wholeheartedness it does something
really good for our heart so may it bring you
peace thank
you