hello and welcome welcome to this next 30
minutes where we'll meditate
together over this medium of electronics that we have that connects
us in a way that respects or
acknowledges the vast vast way web of humanity that we're part of and
that has been interconnected for a long time
between people and people the seven
n kind of layers of Separation that used to connect us is now maybe much
smaller thank you for being here and today going back to basics
and Basics is
not is not meant only for beginners in some ways the longer we've
meditated the more we appreciate the basics as being quite
profound and today the want to talk about mindfulness of the
body and the body and mind are not so distinct
it's hard to really tease them apart especially in our experience of the body
in our experience of the mind if we step back and talk about it think about it we
might be able to come up with Concepts and ideas that keep them
distinct but in our direct experience here and
now and the body is the way we experience the
body sense it feel it is in
separable from the mind for one reason is that we don't
know exactly the beginning and end of the mind but perhaps we could think of
it as being this inclusive of all the neurological
connections uh that exist throughout our body body and it's only with the nerves
all over our body that we can feel the body so those nerves are part of the
mind and how they fire and how they report to the rest of
us is uh contributes to our constructing the the sense of our
body and then we have nerves that pick up all kinds of things nerves are
the body the the experience of the
body is um kind of like an antenna an antenna that receives
information from the world around us invaluable information through the
body the ears the eyes the nose The
Taste and it's also an antenna that
transmits transmits information to the world around us and transmits
information within us to ourselves to the conscious mind where we
register what's happening and what the antenna picks up
is amazingly complex or extensive not
just Sensations on the skin and but but deep in the body
biochemical physiological processes are picked up in the heart and
the stomach and all over and the more we can rest in the
body the more we can be aware of the body the more information we
have but more important the more we are at home at ease relaxed in the body
the more the body will support us to be at ease to feel
peace to feel safe and some of the challenges we have
the body is the ways that our conscious mind transmits information to all over
the body that there's something to be afraid of fear anxiety
desires and aversions so assuming a meditation
posture and part of the posture that you take for meditation let it be a
posture that confidently shows your body your
mind that you are confident
confident and for now for these minutes in meditation that you're
safe if you have any anxieties and fears that are
operating chances are the object of it is not present here
and now in your direct experience
and so it can be very profound to let the
body help you to feel at ease for these few minutes to feel deeply
safe here and now and if we relax the
body a confident postured body it's remarkable the support support
and the care it provides to the
Mind gently closing the
eyes and taking a few moments to feel your body in whatever
way you feel
it scanning through the
body and if you feel any anxiety in your body
body trust it to your body the body is a quite a phenomenal
antenna and support processor for how we
feel rather than churning on in the mind
feel from the inside out the body
and as you exhale to relax the
body relaxing the muscles of the face
softening in the shoulders
softening in the
belly as you inhale feel the
expansion of the rib cage the Torso the belly
with the inhale and the expansion of your
torso feel your body become larger
Fuller having more room to feel what's
here and to soften relax as you
exhale
for for
perhaps relaxing the thinking
mind with every exhale
whatever restlessness or agitation there is in the control tower
of the thinking mind with every
exhale letting that agitation settle
[Music] more settle down into the
body
e for
as you breathe to feel how the body experiences
itself centering attention in the body
rather than having it centered in the control tower of
thinking softening calming in the body so the body
begins to transmit feelings of being safe
Here and Now feelings of being at ease
peace Here and
Now
e
for
for for
as you exhale as you
inhale spread your awareness through your body
so that whatever challenges you have in your body are
resting in a wider space of the
body
e
for
for for
and as we come to the end of this sitting to
gently
softly sense and
feel your body
maybe the body that is just beyond the
edges of breathing whatever Sensations associated
with breathing gently spread your attention
Beyond spread your attention into to the parts of the body where there's a feeling
of Cal
ease and to whatever degree however minor you have feelings of calm or
[Music] ease or feelings of being
safe let that register through your
body let that register in your heart in your mind
and then to consider how wonderful it would
be if others could feel safe could feel at peace and
calm in their body in their hearts and their
minds that everyone who is anxious and
Afraid could be deep deeply reassured right down into their
marrow deep in their body and may it be that how we live our
day contributes to others feeling safe others feel feeling that they can
be at ease at least with
th may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello and welcome to these teachings and this week the topic is the four
noble truths and after doing the introduction yesterday I'll start today with the
fourth the first Noble Truth who is the Noble Truth of suffering and as also as an introduction
to it the guided meditation that I just did was on mindfulness of the
body and the reason for that is that um The Suffering that they approach to
suffering to really know it well is not so much through the mind but rather
through feeling it experientially here and now in the body to know what's happening in
the in the experienced life that we live not in the imagined life not in the
projected life into the future not in the remembered life but here and now the
experienced life the lived life of now and for many of us it's really through
the body that we can feel the greatest sense of aliveness the greater sense of
being connected to life itself and to ourselves and the most useful way of
being present for the first Noble Truth which is
suffering and um the um so the first Noble Truth uh as it's
come down to us is a very simple statement it says um uh
there is the Noble Truth of suffering and
um you know that's it so that requires a little bit of an unpacking and first the
word noble uh it's uh some one translator translated the ennobling truth of
suffering that there's a what it implies that suffering by itself is not ennobling or Noble or
or special um what's uh
ennobling is the possibility of
meeting suffering honestly seeing it clearly and finding a path through it to
the other side to bring suffering to an end but to go through it is to really
know it well to really understand it well maybe to see whatever suffering we
have is uh a messenger and what is the message what is it that needs to be
learned what is we need to be present for here and um and um many people when they
have uh challenges in their lives they have uh all kinds of things they're
grieving or distressed about or stressed or
afraid one of the invaluable reports that can happen is to have a friend who
will listen be accompanied by someone for a walk in the park or sit and have tea together and the friend doesn't uh
judge doesn't try to fix but really takes in experiences compassionately
fully uh in a friendly way in a caring way uh what you're experiencing you can
you can explain you can say what's happening and your friend just receives it and
uh and it's so good to be received to be known to be heard and uh by someone
who's calm and settled and available and so in the same way uh this
ennobling the en nobling attitude of how to be with suffering is to be our own
good friend to really stop and be able to take time for to really know what
this suffering is and that has to be done with a lot of care and love and attention about the uh
how much we can tolerate how much we can open up to at any given time but this is the message of the Buddha is that um the
direct way to Freedom the direct way to uh peace is not by avoiding suffering
but learning how to stop to recognize it the I sometimes in a silly way say that
the the the bumper sticker for Buddhists it would say I stop for
suffering not to suffer more but to really kind of be present for it and
offer this ennobling attention to really know it and see it and the bumper
sticker uh doesn't have any pronouns as I as I talked about yesterday that um
and so we stop if others are suffering maybe we stop to be their friend to uh
accompany them for a while around it to what's going on and support them if we're suffering we stop and pay
attention and um there's many ways of stopping I mean I uh sometimes it's
meditating sometimes it's sitting having cup of tea sometimes it's going for a walk in a in a calm relaxing place so we
can really take time for it as opposed to just go head long into our busyness
or or sit and uh and just kind of have a way of sitting and lost lost in the
Fring lost in the preoccupation lost in the anxiety about what we're experiencing our
reactivity so this en nobling the noble um is not inherent nobility is not
inherent in suffering but it's what we bring and how we are with
suffering and then suffering itself the word in poly is Dua
and um and it's a difficult word for some English speakers because partly the word suffering implies you know really
big things catastrophes and um and partly because
uh in that we're coming to an end of suffering it seems like um our some of suffering we have is we don't want to
end it doesn't seem right to push it away or stop it or you know just seems like it's inherent part of life that a a
parent maybe who loses a child would feel emotional pain and are we supposed
to not have that the the uh the Dua that we're
talking about here is um the emotional pain that arises from our
reactivity not from the deep empathy not from the deep sense of
connectedness that uh where there is no attachments there is no fear there is no
um uh hostility or or conceit around it it it's possible
to experience certain kind of emotional pain in the world have be heartbroken for example and uh and be at ease with
it not only be at ease but feel its part of the fullness of a relaxed free life
to feel both the joys and Sorrows of this world but the Dua the suffer uing
of the first Noble Truths is the suffering which doesn't have to be there uh so it's a a subset
of all the different ways that we can feel some emotional pain it's the emotional pain that comes from uh
clinging from craving from react uh
hostility from being caught in something being contracted around something uh
where the desires are so strong that that there's a compulsivity to the desires where there's compulsivity to
the hostility we have that there is something extra that's going on and as we
start being honest about our suffering stopping and getting to know it uh and
we're experiencing it through the body we start being able to tease
apart that suffering that emotional pain which is fine to have in a certain way
it feels like this is part of a lived life versus the kind of suffering which
clearly uh comes from some kind of reactivity some kind of attachment that
we're really holding on to that we don't have to hold on to that we're better off
without and so the importance of mindfulness of the body is that with through mindfulness of the body we're
learning a number of different things we're learning to be present for our discomfort our emotional
discomfort uh in a relaxed way letting the hold it in the body letting the body
process it letting the body reveal to us what's there that is more holistic than
if we only understanding our emotional discomfort from our thinking mind they
only have it from our thinking about it through the lens of our fear hostility
or self pre occupation in and of itself and so we're kind of breaking the
hegemony of the reactive uh self-
preoccupied contracted thinking Mind by dropping down into the body to feel our
discomfort emotional discomfort and to learn how to be nonreactive to it to learn how to be
present for it in a very simple open caring way to be present for it as if we're own
our own best friend and learning to breathe with emotional discomfort learning to feel it and this is a tall
order it's not easy to do this but the rewards of doing it are phenomenal the
rewards of having being able to have a non-reactive attention that doesn't add
or subtract doesn't uh push or pull is not uh rejecting or accepting but just
there and feeling and being present then we can begin seeing more clearly then we
can see uh at some point that kind of emotional discomfort pain which is kind
of deeply part of something precious as a human being maybe it's part of love
and care and and um that doesn't you know that it's okay to have in a certain
way that it's not troubling but rather troubling it's actually in certain kind
of way enriching because it arises from deep in the heart deep in within us we see that
on one hand and on the other hand we experience that oh this is extra this
has to do with my reactivity my attachments this has to do with my
rejecting or my wanting something so strongly that I'm filled with disappointment and anger that I can't
have it this has to do with my heartbreak that is
not because the discomfort of losing something losing but rather it's
heartbreak because my whole sense of self was tied up in this thing this
person this experience and I was really attached to that in order to whatever
reason and so we start teasing apart that which is kind of comes with human
being in a relaxed and and um maybe meaningful way and that which that
suffering which is extra that has to do with our what we're
contributing and so the first Noble truth the truth of suffering there is
suffering in this world there's no way that a human being is not going to have some kind of
emotional pain going through this life and can we clarify our for our
elves so that what kind of emotional pain we're having so that it's not uh
diminishing in us it's not draining us it's not uh harming ourselves even by
the reactivity by which we feel it and so the path to that one of them is to
get to know the suffering well stop for suffering but learn how to do that learn
how to be present through the body to relax to breathe with the disc uh
emotional discomfort until there's a subtleness and openness that we can now uh begin
seeing receiving from the body almost the information that tells us um whether
this is healthy for us as part of a healthy life or this is unhealthy to
have this kind of caught upness with what we're doing and uh and if we do that then uh
it's en nobling we receive the deeper message uh what needs to
be uh healed and then what needs to be
allowed so uh the first Noble Truth The Noble Truth of suffering and then
tomorrow comes the second thank you