greetings everyone I'm happy to be here with you this
week my name is Meg Galler and I'm speaking to you from a rem remote part
of the south of France and uh the zoom coming out from
my end is being uh transformed at IMC by our
wonderful audiovisual team uh and live streamed out to you on
YouTube so please know that I very much value your feedback in the
chat uh although I can't see it while I'm teaching but I'll do so
afterwards last year around this time I gave a series on training in
emptiness but unfortunately had to cancel on the last day because of Internet
issues so today I'll share with you the fifth guided meditation and talk
for that week on training and
emptiness you all came here for a
reason and the invitation is to begin our meditation by formulating Our
intention which can be as simple as may my practice
serve as a condition for awakening for myself and all
beings in the Buddhist context Awakening means freedom from
suffering and as you know the suffering in this
world is immense so our job here is to free
ourselves from suffering so that everything we
do we can then help free others which is a tall
order in every moment we create the conditions for who we become in the next
moment so keep in mind that this is a gradual path and it requires being patient with
ourselves the Buddha says the wise person gradually bit by
bit Moment by moment removes their
impurities so our meditation practice is to purify our unskillful
Tendencies so we have to begin by holding ourselves in
compassion dropping any temptation to feel
inadequate or to judge ourselves so begin by closing your eyes
or lowering your gaze if that's more comfortable
and whether you're sitting or lying down settle
yourself by aligning the spine into a posture that
expresses the aspiration you formulated just
now inviting the grounding energy of the earth to hold you safely in its
embrace you can fine-tune the alignment of the spine by imagining that the head
is suspended from the sky by a thread an invisible
one and then letting all the vertebrae relax
downward inviting the clear open energy of the sky to come down through
you from the opening in the crown of the head down through the Torso and legs and
out through the
feet offering your body your heartfelt
compassion this is how it is right now
so light a little flame of benevolence and compassion in your
heart and let it protect
you see if you can open the edges of your body and let your little flame of
compassion radiate out to all beings in
all directions may we and all
beings be free from
suffering connecting to the breathing by taking one long beautiful
breath deep breath and then slowly let the breath return to
its natural Rhythm as You Follow the whole cycle of
the breath perhaps visualizing an oval if that
works for you in this oval waves of breathing
moving up the back on the inhale at the end of the inhale over the
crown of the head noticing the little empty
Paws and on the exhale letting the breath Cascade down
the face and the front of the
Torso the end of the exhale comes with another slight pause at the bottom of
the oval as the breath moves past the
panum towards the back again for another
inhale feel the flow the constantly changing nature of
the breath as you breathe
normally following the whole cycle of the
breath Welling in the flow of breathing and appreciating its
inconstancy seeing how it's constantly changing
staying peacefully with a breath is a way of dwelling
in abiding in and knowing the Ever Changing nature of your
experience
the one meditation practice that Scholars are confident the Buddha practiced
himself is anapanasati awareness breathing
in Awareness breathing out
and in his instructions on anapanasati the budha tells us first of
all to go to a Wilderness with the foot of a
tree or to some place empty to establish
our awareness I take this to include
establishing our awareness first of all in a
mind that's empty of self-
preoccupation the Buddha then instructs
us very succinctly always
attentive one breathes in with awareness and breathes out with
awareness that's all we have to do with this
practice and resting in awareness of the
breathing is to be protected from
delusion as we follow the breath we can choose the wisdom of
spaciousness non-grasping rather than self-referential
thinking coming back as often as
needed to awareness of this body breathing
we close your eyes and stay with the breath
the whole
cycle e
if you see thoughts arise take a moment to recognize how
unsubstantial they are thoughts have no real
substance and rather than choosing to follow your thoughts you can choose a peaceful
mind right here empty of the
preoccupation With Me Myself and
mind and by dropping down into the breathing perhaps you can
taste if only for a moment the freedom of just
breathing being present open
receptive this is the freedom of emptiness which allows you to be
available for the experience of breathing available for just being
alive
e e
feel and appreciate the wholesomeness of those
moments however brief when the mind is empty of thoughts
revolving around self-
preoccupation e
feeling the Ever Changing in constant nature of
breathing and letting the breath teach us the truth of
inconstancy the truth that everything we think of as solid is in fact a
process of constant
change
e
e e
you end this meditation let's return to our circle of
compassion for ourselves for everyone in this sa meditating together
here and for all
beings may all beings be safe and
protected being safe may all beings including
ourselves be happily at
ease may we all abide in
peace and may all beings everywhere be
free as I join my hands together and bow
to you all I honor your practice I honor your sincerity
[Music]
for e
greetings everyone um I'm Meg
Galler and I'm speaking to you from a remote part of the south of
France and I'm very grateful to the IMC uh audiovisual Tech Team who are uh
taking the zoom for me and sending it out to you on
YouTube for the last year I've taken a sabatical due to health
challenges and I'm really happy to be back here with you
please know that I very much value your feedback in the chat and although I'm
not able uh to read the chat during the teaching I do look at it
afterwards so as I said at the beginning of the meditation uh last year around this time
I gave a 7 a.m. series on training and
emptiness but un fortunately had to cancel on the last day because of
Internet issues so today I wanted to share with
you the last part of that series on
emptiness focusing today on how we might put emptiness into
practice so my aspiration today is to give you some
ideas for fostering an open spacious mind rather than a mind caught in the
clinging of self-
preoccupation Emptiness is essentially being empty of
selfing this preoccupation With Me Myself and mind
is the motor behind our discursive thinking and our
reactivity so I'd like to begin with the first two verses of the
dhap the beautiful collection of poems expounded by the
Buddha he says all experience is preceded by
mind made by mind led by mind speak or act with a corrupted mind
and suffering follows as the Wagon Wheel follows the
hoof of the ox all experience is preceded by mind
led by mind made by mind speak or act
with a peaceful mind and happiness follows like a never
departing Shadow so a corrupted mind is defined as
having any kind of clinging and a peaceful mind is what we
need for unwavering happiness that stays with us like a never departing shadow
so our job as practitioners is to learn how the mind
works to see our own reactivity to our
experience and all the proliferation that comes from self-centered
thinking without a mind that's empty of proliferating self-centered
thinking and and is caught in reactivity rather than being at peace with what is
we can't even see the choices we have in each
moment much less make wise choices in order to be at peace with
ourselves and with the world so in meditation we're training
the Mind little by little to become more and more
peaceful so that rather than being caught in instant reactivity to our
experience the Mind learns how to slow down enough so that we can see the forks in
the road in each moment of our
lives so that we can then make the wise choices that Foster happiness confidence
Serenity rather than choosing clinging to the illusion of self which leads us down the path to
anxiety fear and suffering the Buddhist stresses that
this is a gradual path and you may have seen for
yourselves in the early stages of practice That We Begin by seeing how
Wild the mind is and this is totally
normal we need to befriend the wild mind and keep walking the path with
perseverance and patience understanding that it's part of
our DNA to want to protect ourselves to exist
and in meditation this desire to exist is often expressed as discursive
thinking with the self as the primary
protagonist many of you are familiar with the hindrances to
Awakening the unskillful Mind states that we need to abandon
as we progress on the path of
practice in ply the word for these hindrances
narana literally means
coverings with the hindrances these obstacles to
Enlightenment we literally cover over the purity of our mind's potential for
awakening and the Buddha's great discovery was that the obstacles to
freedom from suffering had originated in his own
mind and he awakened to the full potential of his own
nature fundamental radiant awareness that is infinite and
indestructible as you know our usual mind is populated
by proliferating thoughts that arise from ignorance and
craving and it's no accident that the vipasana
tradition stresses cultivating mindful
awareness aan Mahaba from the ti for tradition describes our true mind as
simple awareness utterly
pure our Pure mind is unconstructed and has no reference point
in the self and the nature of this pure
awareness is the ease of emptiness the absence of all defilements and
self-centeredness in our tradition it's compassion that is the spontaneous
expression of the Fertile space of
emptiness so our path of practice involves recognizing this Union of
emptiness and awareness endowed with
compassion and then stabilizing our
recognition we know that everything is in flux which is why the self doesn't last
long enough to be able to be reified into something lasting and
substantial emptiness is really the fertile
possibility of endless transformation and this means that we're
not stuck with our wild mind or any of the difficulties in our
lives this path of practice is
transformative and I'm speaking from experience when I tell you
that we can make peace with our difficulties when we learn to settle the
mind and to make more and more wise choices in our lives Moment by
moment what we perceive as our inadequacies are just the starting point
or this transform for ative path of
practice and when we really see that every
moment offers us the possibility of
Freedom we can let go and transform our self-centered barriers and limitations
my root teacher shunu Suzuki said that there is always a possibility
of understanding as long as we live in
emptiness we should always live in the dark empty
Sky even though clouds and lightning come the sky is not Disturbed
Suzuki roshi also advised us when you study Buddhism you should have a general
house cleaning of your mind so the first way of putting
emptiness into practice is essentially
decluttering which is a long process of Letting
Go letting go of unskillful mental
habits and replacing them with wholesome mental
habits and the good news is that we have agency and we have a path of practice
we're learning how to let go of our un UNH wholesome mental habits arising from
greed hate and
delusion to do this we need to constantly cultivate
awareness and calm the mind sufficiently so that moment after moment
we can slow down enough to be able to see the forks in the road and make wise
choices
so if it's of interest to you for the next 24 hours you can try
cleaning and decluttering your meditation space another thing that's very
important for decluttering the mind is to not be in a rush so it's a good plan to um when
you're going to meditate arrive a couple minutes before your meditation to be able to settle down in
your posture mindfully and
calmly I also like to remind myself before I start that for these minutes of
meditation I can leave all my worries concerns obligations and
responsibilities together with my shoes outside the door of the meditation
[Music]
room so this ends the series from last
year on training and emptiness I hope it made some sense and if not and if you're
interested uh you can find the earlier meditations and talks on the audiio
Dharma and tomorrow we'll begin the four-part series for this week which
will be on the theme of trusting our
practice thank you for your attention thank you for your practice