good morning and welcome and for this meditation I'd like
to offer a simile uh maybe some of you have had
this occasion to maybe when you were young to learn to ride a bicycle and um sometimes people learn to
ride a bicycle with training wheels and uh imagine that
uh uh that you are accustoming yourself getting used to
you riding a bicycle with big solid training wheels maybe four of them one
in two in the front two in the back and so you're really stable and it's great to ride a bicycle it feels
wonderful but then uh you're afraid of uh taking the training wheels off uh
because then gravity will have its uh chance on you and and gravity is
dangerous and how are you going to be able to manage on your own and and so
then the attachment to the security of the wheels is quite strong can't imagine anything
else but then the training wheels go off and it's hard to write because uh this
conf this uh the way that we participate with gravity is confused and we don't
know how and we're very strongly ident identified as someone who's under the sway of gravity and and it's
inimaginable how we can be free of gravity and
um and uh then slowly we get the hang of keeping the balance as we pedal the bike
and then at some point just suddenly feel free and in a certain way we're still
under the influence of gravity but we've learned how to manage how to Pedal have
the right speed how to stay balanced and it feels like now we're free now Bic
bicycling can just be like a free thing it feels so delightful and within time you know how to you could even bike
without holding the handlebar and and uh be upright and it just feels so
wonderful and um and now in a certain kind of way we're no
longer preoccupied by gravity we don't identify ourselves as someone who is
under the sway of gravity or someone who is a victim of gravity or someone who's
incapable of responding dealing with gravity the sense of self is so caught up in this idea of
gravity that it's impossible to be free of it but at some point uh the pedaling
and the movement of the bike we now are in a certain way free of gravity we can go about on the bicycle without having
any concern about it no conscious involvement and there's no identification with it there's no being
caught or gravity is no longer a sticky thing for us uh we're unstuck from
Gravity so and that's similar the same thing with awareness with mindfulness
with our capacity to know what's happening to clearly recognize it the
capacity to sense what's happening without being entangled with what is
known or entangled with what we sense there's a freedom that can come
when uh mindfulness awareness has is no longer caught in the gravity of
stickiness of attachments of identification of me and mine I can't
and I can and can't and and uh it's unimaginable to imagine a life uh that
um is is uh not using training wheels and imaginable to use a
life where we're not uh stuck to and entangled with our
emotions or our beliefs or our thoughts but it is possible it is possible to
think to have emotions uh just like there's always gravity and there's a feeling of
non-stickiness a feeling of like oh this is freedom I can go about now with these
things but I'm not pulled down I'm not pulled into into them I'm not caught in them they don't Define me there's a
freedom of moving about this is the possibility with awareness a Clarity of
seeing Clarity of knowing in the clear knowing of what's happening in the
moment in the in the intimate sensing without any
identification there we find our freedom and uh and with this it's not
about putting on new training wav it's not about getting you know a a
bicycle with much thicker uh Wheels getting a tricycle it's not about uh
what bicycle you have even U but rather it's learning to be free and writing it
learning how to balance and all that so the freedom that comes with mindfulness
is not about the experience we're having it's not like having a special
experience but rather no matter what's happening we know how to ride the bike we know how to
be free we know how to be present see know clearly see clearly feel clearly
without being entangled with what is known felt or seen so this becomes particularly useful
and very important when we have challenges challenges in meditation with
our own mind our own heart our own body um that our mind body and heart are
not behaving the way we want that we don't have to change necessarily what's happening but we can find our freedom
with it we're not going to do away with gravity but we are going to find our
freedom with it and so uh some people are expecting meditation and wanting
meditation uh to be really Pleasant and wonderful deep calm and peace of course
that's important that's a a part of it but that's not how freedom is found
freedom is found no matter what the experience is that it's known in this
free way so with that long introduction we'll start so
to assume a meditation posture that for you regardless of your
posture standing sitting walking or lying down somehow or
other um
represents a posture of being free a posture of being somehow in a
dignified way
independent even maybe in C certain kind of mindfulness way
self-reliant adjusting your posture maybe so the chest is a little bit more
open maybe sitting up a little sitting up straighter or adjusting the body with
pillows in such a way that the belly is relaxed and has a chance to relax
gently close your
eyes and now to just start
directly notice in your way your experience how you are
and not how you are in the abstract but how What in in detail
specifically what are the direct experiences that are happening for you that make up how you are here and
now what are the sensations of the body the mind the
heart that contribute to the more abstract way that we say how we
are what how do you experience yourself
now and are you caught in that are you that's sticky for you are
you pulled into it and reacting to it or believing it or prioritizing
something or pulling back or judging
can you know what's happening for you right
now and find a way to know to
recognize that feels free of what is known
like you would hear a innocuous sound in the distance and so clear that you're not
involved in the sound or judging it or reacting to it it's just a sound that
has nothing to do with you and you're free of it not caught by it it's not sticky
or you're seeing something in the environment that's neither appealing nor
threatening neither yours nor anybody else's maybe a cloud in the
sky an unthreatening Cloud floating in the sky
and the seeing of the cloud you're free of the cloud no
stickiness and so to Center yourself on your
breathing and see feel
know the sensations of the body body as you
breathe is there in fact some stickiness for you in experiencing
breathing for you you what way can you begin
feeling
freedom from the experience of breathing while attending to it
for
perhaps taking a little time to relax your
body maybe every time you
exhale the tenser the body the more likely we are to identify
or be sticky sticking to
something e
relaxing the mind the thinking mind
softening in the Heart
Center
for
e
for e
gently quietly
peacefully like you're slowly pedaling a bicycle with freedom and
ease Let each moment of knowing recognition being
aware be a little push of The Petal that keeps you free
from whatever is
known no what's happening while moving on with
awareness no while letting the river of experience
flow through
you knowing mindfulness not sticking to
anything
e
e for
perhaps you can feel a quality of calmness or
Stillness from these minutes of meditation
or a quietness relative to how meditation started for
you or maybe with the
exhale you can relax into a calm or quiet or Stillness
and without making extra effort can you
notice some sense of knowing being
aware that does not is not sticky doesn't stick to what is known or what
we're aware of
awareness is free to move on to allow things to change and move
on available for whatever is new this River of
time letting everything flow
and may it be that our ability to be present with no entanglement no for
against no stickiness allows our care and
love respect for others to be present when we're with
others May whatever Freedom we
discover in knowing
freely be like an Open Door through
which our Good Will can
flow may this practice that we do support
us to meet the world with Good
Will wishing others
happiness safety
Peace and
Freedom may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free and may our good
will support that possibility
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this third talk on the hindrances the hindrances are
five kind of strategy IES that our inner life has
to um to respond to challenges in unhelpful
ways and maybe in some ways life is always has always has some challenges
and so how we respond to them is part of the nature of this practice of ours and I think it's important not to
think of mindfulness practice about kind of floating on a cloud of bliss and joy and just being just
peaceful ful and and have you know and happy ever after a more more valuable way of
understanding mindfulness practice is that we are actually learning how to be
present in an effective way and a Wholesome Way with u the challenges that
life brings that they always bring and um so one of the ways to do
that is to understand the unhelpful ways in which we respond to challenges and
the five hindrances are such things so sometimes we respond with uncertainty
and confusion and running around not being able to make decisions
um sometimes we respond with uh agitation
restlessness uh maybe with regrets and remorse about who we are what's happening how
we're showing up what happened in the past sometimes we are which the topic for
today is that somehow we freeze up we shut down we go to sleep in some way so
we're not having to deal with the challenges that come and then for the next two days next day is sometimes we
respond with uh hostility with aversion ill will with blame with
complaining um with hostility and then finally on Friday
we uh respond with u desires of different types uh sensual desires
avaricious desires desires of greed we want something to uh to fill us
to make us feel good to get away from what's difficult and challenging and and
we want to substitute it with you know something that makes us kind of have pleasure and and so this engagement with
desire and um and some of these uh patterns can be pervasive in in a
person's life some people you can they can recognize that one of these is their calling card and this is where they keep
falling back to keep falling back to so part of mindfulness practice is
become a uh wise about recognizing these
hindrances so vasna student Insight student should really learn these well
and um uh listen to Dharma talks study them think about them read about them I have
a whole little book called uh unhindered that uh you can you know has
my essays about them and it might give you a kind of a clear sense of how they work for you to to read something like
my book and um the um so for today it's a
topic that's usually called sloth and torper and and for many of us the word
sloth as a quality of lethargy or something is not really something that
we that use that word in English much though we most of us will might know what it means and um but when I studied
the poly for it uh the ancient language uh the dictionary says that it can mean
rigidity and um and I think that works a little bit better because sloth and torp
are a little bit too closely connected too too similar but to have something a little bit wider that uh uh talks
through some very common human reaction to somehow to freeze to shut down to get
rigid um to get uh so really tight and contracted in situations maybe from Fear
um uh I think there's it it expands the meaning of this third hindrance in a way
I think is useful for many people and um this is where we feel overwhelmed or feel excessively
challenged by what goes on in life so there's some mechanism of shutting down it's not ordinary tiredness when they
talk about torper but it's a kind of shutting down um and giving up or uh
that uh the system gets so tired so um
dull so uh um um yeah kind of like like
mud in the mind and it's hard to get through it and um and so um things don't
seem very clear and there's a vagueness and there's um not much energy to apply
ourselves and kind of kind of giving up sometimes of our engagement with things
that kind of makes things dull and shut down sometimes they can be quite intense
uh if there's a lot of fear or a lot of anger or the emotional response we have is just so strong that um the other or
the other three four hindrances are just like really uh energized or that um
something shuts down again something uh we don't want to pay attention we there's a resistance there's a a um a um
we're resisting what's happening we're bored uh because we don't want to pay attention we don't like what's happening
so um there's a shutting down again so to pay attention to this movement of of
um the drop of Engagement the drop of energy the drop of of um Clarity is an
important uh part of this practice notice is how that hinders us how this
gets in a way of clarity gets a away of understanding what is wholesome and it's
said that this kind of this third hindrance sloth and torper or rigidity
and torper um is unhealthy is a hindrance is a is a um is an UNH
wholesome movement and it's possible to feel that it feels there's a dulling
there's a shutting down there's a a unwillingness there's
a not engaged in understanding or or reflecting or studying the situation
being curious and interested in it and it can feel this that very uncomfortable
to be in our own skin when sloth and torpor is present in a very different way than you're simply tired or
exhausted or something and um and so as uncomfortable
it is to feel this if there is this rigidity and and um and and torper the
practice of mindfulness is to turn around and really see it to become the expert on boredom the expert on
Resistance the expert on shutting down uh the exert exer expert on how we avoid
and deflect how we you know uh how
we you know get um
dull and uh and how we can change that how we can become different and I think
the wisest way of doing that is to understand that the unhealthy ways in which we're responding to what's
happening around us what's happening in our life um some forms of depression uh
are kind of this hindrance it's a kind of shutting down a giving up that where
the energy disappears and we're not we don't feel any V vitality and inspiration and there could be a sinking
into that so uh and so to be mindful of that
that can be very hard if we are identified with it if We believe We
Define ourselves by it if we are invested into the the strategy of
rigidity and toror and and we we're
so part of it that there's so much stickiness between us and it that it's
unimaginable that we could be any different but in fact we can and one of
the things we can cultivate and what we want to develop here is is not just mindfulness not just being aware of
what's happening but one step further we want to discover the way of being aware
the way of knowing we we where we are independent from what is
known that uh we're able to see into the seeing to understand how
seeing can be free of what is seen the solution in a sense the The
Liberation we're looking for for in Buddhism is not in what we seek but how
we seek not in what we know but how we know of course we have to know but how
we know how we feel how we hear and so if we have sloth and torpor
rigidity and and this dullness is how we know it is important and to learn how to
awaken how to rise up with a sharpness
or a Clarity of attention to bring energy into the mindfulness into the
knowing so we begin to uh be free of what is known this Clarity opens up the
image of a a a Lotus that's growing in muddy water but then when it's going to
flower the lotus flower comes out of the muddy water and is Untouched by the mud
and it's clear so as we get out of the muddy water of sloth and torper
something the wareness becomes somehow this beautiful flower that's untouched
while we know we have sloth and torper which begins to decrease its influence on
us so the traditional um uh discussion about letting go of sloth and torper uh
and it's possible sometimes to just let go of it because because but uh or when
we clearly know how to see it we've learned to recognize its ins and outs and how it works um we see it is an
activity of the Mind there we're doing something we're picking up the strategy and so it's possible when we
know it well enough to see that it's possible to put it down to let it go so
the Buddha WR said having let go of rigidity and toror one dwells without
rigidity and toror mindful with clear
comprehension and consciously seeing doing this one cleanses the mind
of rigidity and torper so they have cleansing the mind so so here the emphasis to overcome this sloth and
torper rigidity and dullness boredom and and shutting down
is to cultivate these attentional qualities of mindfulness clear
comprehension clear recognition of what's happening and um and conscious
seeing so not just seeing but seeing with purpose or seeing with intention or
seeing with uh knowing that we're seeing conscious seeing knowing we're seeing
and uh it's possible to see something be so involved with it we we don't really
know that we're seeing because we' that's kind of taken for granted we're so caught up in what we want or what we
don't want that um that we don't notice that our eyes are popping out of their eye
sockets and so but to to see consciously means to be
aware of the quality the characteristics the the healthiness the wholesomeness of
how we see and so or how we know how we sense
sense so it's in the attentional faculties that we have that we bring
attention in all the different faculties of attention we have hearing seeing
smelling touching uh tasting um the everything all the sense stores in the
in the body and in the Mind's Eye where we know and see what's going on internally with us with the mind all
these attentional faculties can be awaken can be engaged without any stickiness without
any invocation with the challenges that we have and that's my suggestion for you
today is um certainly become aware of how sloth and toror shutting down
rigidity and and U dullness come into play for you in different points going to watch your mind it's fascinating to
watch like at a meeting or something um when your mind mind starts to drift off when your mind starts shutting down when
you get sleepy or dull and when it picks up again what is happening in the room
what's happening in the talking what's happening in yourself and you can watch sometimes the cycles and rhythms of of
being clear and present and being dull and not really paying attention but more important uh see what
you can learn about being present being with attention
where whatever form of attention you're using whatever mindfulness you have is
um independent of what is known that you find your freedom in it and um like like
you find your freedom from Gravity when you learn to be skilled at riding a
bicycle so um thank you very much and um so tomorrow and Friday I'm tra I'm
traveling tomorrow and so um Kim Allen one of the wonderful
teachers here at IMC will finish this series and um and she'll do uh um ill
will and sensual desire for the next two days and and I think it'll be wonderful
and and uh I think wonderful kind of perspective that sure Kim is very
thoughtful well practiced person and I'd be curious very curious to know how she picks this up up and offers her take on
all this so thank you Kim if you're listening and um and uh I'll be gone for
a few weeks I'm teaching uh a couple of Retreats and uh look forward to being
back near the end of October and uh thank you very much