well thank you those of you who uh are listening and reported and the sound on here we're here at IRC and
you can't see much I thought you'd be able to see more um maybe at the end of this I can zoom the camera out and you
can see the meditation Hall today is being uh been claimed
for a training we're doing so it doesn't look like exactly like a meditation Hall
but there's a couple of people here meditating with us in person which is unusual for me in when I'm doing this
YouTube uh teaching so I'm very happy so uh welcome
everyone
and so this week in the morning I've been offering
these little snippet of sayings that you can use in your meditation practice
and um sometimes we can say yes as a way of
enhancing our awareness just be present for what's happening sometimes there's a wonderful no to what's happening no to
being distracted that puts us into the present moment yesterday I talked about
the little saying no comment just to be aware of what's there without adding any
comments that's not all you know not necessarily appropriate and in everyday life but in meditation there's something
very profound about just not getting involved not judging not talking about
what's happening in your experience but allowing everything in AR rise in meditation just be there without any
comment and and uh and so today the culmination of this of these four
little mantras that I offered is um could be another one but
it's what they're they're all leading to and I mentioned in on Tuesday a
little bit this way is as well and that is the word no that's spelled k n o
w that all the others were meant to lead us to a very radical simple
state that simply knows what's happening as it's being
known and yes it can be yes to what
arises as long as it is known almost like we can get out of Our
Own Way in The Knowing there's something very profound it's kind of like um a uh
one of those kids toys a Jack In The Box where you take the lid off and the Jack
jumps up you know Springs out it's finally released its tension because it has space
there's something about releasing tension that allows whatever needs to unfold to
unfold and so today no k n o w just know
maybe that could be the two words just know just know what's
happening keep it that simple what's happening just know it and
if it's not obvious uh how you recognize it or label
it or um it's okay to just know it as something something is being known or
confusion is known not knowing is
known and so in the back of the meditation practice as we settle in on mindfulness of breathing and being here
to um to um
stay close to just knowing so assuming a meditation
posture and there is a a kind of
knowing that happens through the body embodied knowing or the
body not just feeling and sensing but the body recognizing
a posture a way of composing the
body that feels right that feels
appropriate for whatever conditions we have in our
life and gently closing the
eyes and there is a kind of knowing in how the body experiences
breathing it's not commentary it's not judgment but there's a knowing that the
body has of a breathing that's Pleasant or
unpleasant comfortable or uncomfortable a breathing which is
tense with resistance or holding or recognizing a breathing with
its fluid breathing
easily with no judgment no comment
just knowing knowing what breathing knows
what breathing feels the body feels
as nose recognizes as you breathe
and then as you exhale you relax let
go settle
in
e
for
for for
in the practice of just
knowing it's knowing what is obvious without any any need to search
or figure out out or
analyze and sometimes that means knowing you don't
know or knowing just that something is
happening or confusion or chaos
keeping the knowing radically
simple just
know
for
e
e for
for
e
e for
and then as we come to the end of this sitting I would like to evoke
a a little truism or a little aphorism that I've learned from the field of
psychotherapy that adults
uh need to be heard children need to be
seen and the combination of those for me is people need to be
known and that there's something about seeing
hearing knowing that can carry love can carry care
respect that appreciation that we can know we can
offer our capacity to know someone else and that knowing comes along with
these wonderful capacities we
have to see with love see with care with
kindness and may it be that this practice that we do supports us not not just to be
mindful in the world but supports us so that our
mindfulness is carried along with kindness with good
will any one of the social emotions that where we care for each other we
appreciate each other may we know
others so they they feel valued
appreciated may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
is [Laughter]
[Music]
so thank you all very much and I saw there were some comments
about a high pitched buzzing sound and um and uh I'm going to uh turn off what
I think is the input for the sound uh while I drink some water and
maybe some of you can tell me if that uh buzzing sound stops
so I see these comments that the sound has stopped the hissing has stopped but now that I've turn the mic on again is
it better is it back
also I see that um the video camera goes as a couple of
times goes out of focus and I wonder if the camera we have here at the IRC is
very sensitive to the tuning in zeroing in on someone and then if they move
maybe it goes out of focus a little bit I've never seen this before but um
so the buzzing stopped before you concluding remarks it's already stopped very curious I'm going to try
one thing and see if I can get the sound to come
back so there I replicated something that I took
apart before when I saw the sound
so I think it have to wait a little bit here because it takes about 15 20 seconds
for uh this to what what I do here to be broadcast
on YouTube and then to get um
messages so sound was fixed in the middle of meditation the buzzing is back
okay and now it should be completely gone
so I think what the problem was is I had um two electrical devices a a electric
clock on top of my the laptop and also the remote control for the camera on the
wall over there and maybe they were somehow um um The
Crickets so then now it's gone again gone again yeah that's what it is it's
uh I can't have those two things sitting on my computer it somehow has enough electrical
interference so that was a little bit of a different thing so here I am at IRC
very happy to be here with two of the uh
former or present resident volunteers who sitting here with us and and um very
happy to be here and this is a concluding now a talk on uh the themes
from this ancient Buddhist text as I keep saying it's some scholars believe
it's the oldest uh teaching in Buddhism the Buddha's first teachings perhaps and
um in the appendix of the book I go into some of the reasons people think this
and uh the evidence for that and um and that there are three
four themes that I've selected out of this and it's perhaps these themes are
things that are subjective to me um especially this last one we're going to
do today so the first one is uh it's really clear in the text it's repeated over and over again this idea of not
clinging to any kind of views and not holding some religious views as being
better than others or more Superior ultimate just not getting involved in that comparison at all and not depending
on any religious do Doctrine beliefs um but rather depending on what we can know
and see directly for ourselves and in doing so the second theme uh not
clinging to sensual desires because we know and see the downside of that we
know and see for ourselves that uh how we're limited by our by the attachment
to sensual desires so again it's not because someone tells us or there's a rule that you should like let go of
sensual desires but some uh it's to really have understood for oneself seen
and known for oneself that uh sensual desire being caught in them is not
beneficial and it's actually better not to be caught in them so it's not a
Doctrine here that is presenting Authority like this is what you should do it's a teaching about uh developing
your own capacity to know and see for yourself and those two verbs knowing and
seeing are the most common kind of description of the practice that is in this
text and then uh the descript third third theme was the descriptions of this
age and those descriptions like for example of not clinging to anything not
craving to anything might seem kind of pretty far Advanced pretty impossible to
do however it is naturalistic it is something humanistic we can understand
understand that we can understand that we have craving and we can understand those times when they're not there and
um and it's so it's not tied to some kind of Supernatural belief something that uh some ultimate state of um uh you
know of Mind alter State of Consciousness it uh again it's dependent on what can be seen and known for
oneself even though it might seem pretty uh pretty distant to have no craving or
clinging at all and then the last theme the fourth one is training cultivating developing
oneself and um and the remarkable thing about uh this is that uh in this text um
the um uh it isn't so much that training is a training to get
anywhere there is in a way I'll explain in a minute but it's not so much about getting somewhere but but it is um a
training uh to be the goal so what I
mean by this is that um if the goal is non-
craving then the training to that goal is to stop craving maybe in small pieces
gradually over time so that the non- craving grows and develops until the full non- craving is experienced so
we're actually practic practicing the whole goal that we're going towards each
moment if the if the goal is to be peaceful to have a deep abiding sense of
peace in our hearts and uh that the way to tr train for that is to begin finding
peace here knowing peace here letting go into peace
here and so there's not a real sharp distinction between the training and the
goal of the training uh it's like exercising to become stronger uh you
become stronger by doing the things that make you strong and
um and so uh you know if you need to need to get become a strong Walker so
you can walk well you begin walking maybe and so walking is the way to be to
become a good walker so um so the idea that uh so the the goal is not such a
distant one this way it's not like we have to uh try for years to kind of
develop high levels of concentration or really sharp mindfulness or going into
deep states of meditation um those can all happen but uh and they might have their role at
times but uh here in this text the the idea is to find the goal in the
means uh to practice the goal until the goal becomes perfected in a sense and um
so not clinging to views and beliefs maybe it's hard to do that but uh but
then we practice that the best we can and how do we practice this uh through
this knowing and seeing we know and see as we practice as we train as we engage
in our life we can know and feel oh this does not feel peaceful this do this
feels like a lot of clinging here going on and um and so it's in that direct
knowing of the downside of clinging of agitation that we understand the value
of not continuing that which leads to that more of that so here the sage the wise one uh
has all the information they need for doing this practice in themselves through their own abilities to know
and see um
so um the book of eights focuses on
fundamental personal and psychological Transformations for which individuals
are personally responsible quote train fully in your
own Release Train fully in your own liberation and then uh elsewhere it says
a monastic should not seek peace from
others the text provides no help from gods or external forces to many modern
readers this will be less revolutionary message than it probably was in the Buddhist
time in focusing on cultivating behaviors and virtues the book of eights rarely mentions specific techniques or
practice practices stated differently the text doesn't emphasize religious
practices that can be seen as steps towards attaining the qualities of an ideal person furthermore it explicitly
and provocatively says that religious observances and practices in themselves
are not adequate for becoming a person at peace rather it encourages people to
Simply behave like an ideal Sage not to pretend not to act it out but to
in the knowing and seeing to understand how in the moment we can act like a sage
without clinging even if the clinging is close by or keeps
reappearing so I'll read a couple
of um
those who say virtue is Ultimate dedicate themselves to Purity
and religious observances only by training in this will there be Purity they say claiming
to be skillful they are faced with further
becoming further building up themselves and attachment one who falls away from
virtue and observances trembles at having failed at the task and hopes for
Longs for Purity as a PO poor far off traveler hopes for Longs for
home but whoever has let go of all virtuous conduct and
observances as well as all actions blamable and
blameless and who has no wishes for Purity or
impurity lives without indulging not even taking up peace
that's just a radical message um so you don't find the peace that the Buddha is looking for through
virtuous conduct through practices religious
practices but also not without them you don't find it by being blameless in your
actions but you also don't find it by uh doing things which are blamable neither
are the way there this is not a teaching to just be free to do whatever you want
independent of whether you harm others or not but it's not to find your peace in all those things there's another
possibility and don't even take up peace don't hold on to it don't make it it's
there's something else and then also a problematic is says
whoever depends on austerities uh whales for
Purity not free from craving for becoming and not becoming longing comes from wanting and
with planning there is fear but with no death and rebirth as a
concern how could one fear what could one long
for someone asked the Buddha that Doctrine some say that is best others
say is inferior as they all claim to be experts which statement is true
they s Buddha says they say their own Doctrine is perfect they say the doctrine of others is inferior
quarreling so they dispute everyone saying their own opinion is
true but the true Brahman are not led by others when considering doctrines
believed they have therefore gone beyond disputes indeed they see none of these
doctrines as the
best they who are in trenched in teachings who Revere preconceived views
and are not easy to train whatever they depend on they say is beautiful is
Purity is where they see truth however the true
Sage sages don't make up don't make things up they don't follow views
religious views Doctrine or bind themselves to
knowledge knowing the many commonplace opinions they are equanimous thinking
this is what others hold on to free of worldly ties sages here don't follow any
faction in a dispute peaceful among those not at peace a animous thinking that is what
others hold on to they don't hold on to
anything having giving given up old attachments without forming new ones
they neither pursue desires nor get entrenched in doctrines free from
viewpoints not clinging to the world wise ones have no self
reproach they are not an enemy to any Doctrine not forming opinions not closed down and
not desirous they are sages wise ones who have laid down their
burden so that's chapter 13 in this book the
Buddha before Buddhism so this has been an important book for me I spent about 20 years on
and off uh translating I I first started translating it when I was um in graduate
school studying doing Buddhist studies I did it as a kind of had some extra time during a summer break and I was so uh
fascinated by this book that just for my own sake to understand it better I started translating it and and did a few
few of the chapters and and then came back to it over time and spent a lot of
time reflecting on it I read a wonderful book about by a teacher named uh scholar named Grace berford was uh her doctoral
dissertation on this book and that made a big impact on me and added to my love
of this particular text and um and uh now I share it with
you so thank you very much for being part of this this week and that I could share something that's been valuable for
me and in general doing this YouTube for these almost 5 years now and I feel very
fortunate to be able to share uh something that it's so dear and and
deeply loved by me and I hope that it supports you in being a sage supports
you in relying on what you can know and see directly for yourself without
recourse to holding on to religious beliefs including Buddhist ones
including what I teach so thank you very much