so hello everyone and welcome to this
meditation broadcast from Insight Meditation Center I'm delighted to be with you and
the names that I recognize on the chat it's also very wonderful to see thank you for being
here yesterday uh in the guided meditation the focus was on
ease and uh recognizing what takes you away from the ease so the simple
instruction for meditation was could be be uh set yourself at
ease and and notice how you lose the ease or what takes you away from the
ease and doing that we start seeing the activities of the mind where we get uh
agitated or shut down or confused or get caught in thoughts or desires or
aversions and then the question is if you see that um what do you
do and uh what we do is uh we're mindful of it we see it clearly that what we're
doing is kind kind of a truth telling oh look at that look what I'm doing I was
at ease and now I'm less at ease just that information begins shifting maybe
our PRI priorities shifting what we want to devote ourselves
to and uh so today I want to orient a little differently in that
um the um uh at any given moment setting
yourself at ease and calm some whatever whatever is capable you're capable of even if it's ever so
slight let yourself let yourself be at ease and uh don't make it
worse don't make the situation worse uh uh don't choose to
follow the the option which brings you more
unease brings you stress brings you distress kind of makes you more agitated
or less less at ease don't make it
worse and uh it might be the situation is pretty bad pretty difficult for you
some kind of way and life can be that way for sure and um and this simple teaching
don't make it worse and what worse means in the subtlest forms of that is that the mind
gets fixated on something gets stuck on something gets focused on something
where the Mind loses the It's ability to have a relaxed open attentiveness to the
present moment where the awareness does not flow along with the present
moment uh but it gets get caught in something involved in something and
reactive to something it might be caught up in judgments might be caught up in
opinions preferences uh it might uh so don't
don't make it worse and uh whatever way you are and let's see if that could be a
orientation for this morning and see what you learn in that process you don't
have to do it well uh because if you don't do it well
and then feel discouraged or upset about that you're making it
worse H just allow things to be don't make them worse and if anything else let yourself
be at ease so assuming a meditation
posture and gently closing the
eyes and
become aware of your body the whole body as globally as it's easy for
you and do you have more aware of your the
front of your body or the back of the body or equally throughout
are you more leaning to the right or to the left or is it
balanced and within this global whole body taking a few deeper
breaths and relaxing the whole body as you
exhale breathing in relaxing
letting your breathing return to normal with a normal
breath relax your thinking mind soften the
mind maybe the thing thinking mind can broaden and spread wide
as you exhale in whatever way is easiest for
you or however slight set your heart at ease
and then stay attentive to during this meditation to the
breathing breathing in and breathing
out and stay also attentive to what your mind is
doing and is there any way in which you're meditating or doing anything else with the
mind that diminishes the quality of
your well-being how you are do you somehow make it worse
the more calm and quiet and centered you are the more subtle is the recognition
of what makes a situation worse the option which is less
desirable because the mind has gotten activated or agitated
maybe in ordinary life it would be a normal state to be in
and but in meditation there are ordinary states of
being which are not the best
option don't try to make those options but
avoid the options that make it worse stay close to your sense of
ease even if you feel
uneasy be attentive that you don't make it worse
stay with the situation breathe
for
for for
oh
for
for e
sometimes the Mind drifts off in thought
and our state becomes worse becomes more distressed or stressed or
agitated sometimes it's almost second nature to judge
and find out what's wrong and the situation becomes
worse allow yourself to be a simple and as at ease as you
can with ease and
simplicity stay here with your
breathing appreciating how Simplicity and ease and
attention can be a protection
from the automatic ways that we might make it worse for
ourselves
for
e
for for
for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to take a moment to
recognize if there's something about the calm or the
subtleness the ease or peace
Clarity or anything about the meditation that provides you with a
reference
point to recognize when you are making it worse for yourself
Maybe by reacting judging coming to fixed
conclusions resisting pushing
away do you have a heightened sensitivity for
that based on how you are now at the end of The
Meditation and then may it be that as you go into your life
today whatever way is next for you
that the benefits of this Insight the benefit of this
meditation can be applied to not making any situation
worse for ourselves for others by what we say by what we do even
by what we think
and to to refrain from what makes it
worse and may the be may we hope that in doing
so the benefits of this
meditation are something that we can share with others
may we care for Others May their well-being be of our interest
in our orientation may we live for the welfare
and happiness of Others May all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank [Music]
you e
the theme for this week is to try to share with you some of
the building blocks the foundations for my particular orientation for
teaching Buddhism teaching the Dharma and maybe from causes and conditions
life experiences personality all kinds of reasons teachers have their own take
their own orientation and um and so I thought
maybe it' be useful to try to provide you with mine that's behind what I how I teach maybe not always so
evident and um yesterday I emphasized how um at the because it's I feel like
the Rock Bottom Foundation of what motivates me in the Dharma and guides me in the Dharma is uh sensitivity to
suffering and the end of suffering and the possibility of a radical end to
suffering the possibility of a lessening of suffering for myself and for
others and that uh there are times in my life that I thought that was um rather simplis IC orientation to
be the center of my the Buddhism that I practice and teach but uh I've come to appreciate
that it's actually quite a profound orientation and um it's
uh um philosophically profound doctrinally profound buddhistic
profound because suffering and the end of suffering um is at the is a thread that
goes through all aspects of our lives and it touches everything and the the
end of suffering uh similarly kind
of touches everything we do and everything we we are in deep deep way so
it's a profound thing and for me it's enough that's enough for what the Dara
is about if I take it one more step then um
uh the um I have an orientation maybe from my zen practice
partly maybe based on my background that um I kind of have an orientation to not
settle to not Center on any view any
philosophy any point of view um even though I just provided one
the end of suffering and the end of suffering but not to Center not to rest there not to hold on to that as being it
and so if anything the idea of having no view is uh is the view that I like to
not rely on any particular understanding um but rather to rely on
awareness to rely on letting go to rely on showing up fresh for the next
moment not bringing anything with me um and
um and uh so you know as a teacher I listen to
people as they talk to me about their practice their their life and one of the things I'm listening to do they have a
um a view that they're holding on to do they have an orientation that that maybe
is a useful one but they're little bit too attached to it orientation views are
useful and they they have their place in practice and in life um but they also
have their limitation and sooner or later in Buddhist practice we see the limitation of All Views and the
possibility of living without views of being without views maybe even if it's just temporarily in deep
meditation and um and along with that uh is
um uh not not having some idea
of anything that is Ultimate a view about something is the best and the most
wonderful and the Ultimate Experience the Ultimate Reality the ultimate teachings uh that something is Ultimate
and better than anything else uh and this is a orientation that we see in the in the earliest very
earliest Buddhist texts uh that the earliest teachings perhaps of the Buddha
in a text called the in English be called The Book of eights the
ataka and um and I have a translation of it in uh that's published that's a title
of the book is called the Buddha before Buddhism and the reason for that title is that U the orientation there under
under kind of undercuts All Views uh and kind of lends itself to
this idea that there's nothing ultimate to have some idea of ultimate is a view and uh it sets up a contrast with what
is not ultimate and with other people's religion and um and the earliest
teachings of Buddhism uh uh kind of pulled the rug from underneath any
attempt to make Buddhism into a religion that has ultimate kind of value and
purpose and uh some people find this kind of idea maybe even offensive
difficult uh unappealing I find it liberating I find it just delightful to
be able to live without holding on to any View at all related to this idea is uh in later
Buddhism Mahayana Buddhism there's a two two uh contrasting philosophical
traditions one is called um uh the the U
the the middle the middle tradition or the middleness tradition and the other
is called the mind only tradition uh uh and uh or yogachara which means
the practitioners of yoga and uh the um the mamica the
emptiness people believe that uh there was nothing which is not empty
everything is insubstantial insubstantial everything's impermanent shifting changing everything is uh uh
conditional contingent and um and there's nothing no place to land with attention to take a
stand to hold on to anything and this just Freedom just allow everything to
just move through us and for us to be part of the river and of life and just find our way and navigating the river
but but everything nothing no place to stand the yogachara school the um uh
chatra School mind only School believe the same thing that everything is empty
except for the mind or except for consciousness and uh we find uh even in the modern
world uh a divide between those teachers who want to emphasize that uh everything
is empty but there's also Consciousness it's a form of Consciousness or form of mind which is Ultimate and
Transcendent and those who are more mamica these middle length middle people middleness people that
um that believe in uh The Emptiness of all things and nothing has ultimacy
nothing is has any permanence and so I'm more in the this mam orientation I'm more in the
orientation that doesn't want to take anything as it doesn't see anything as uh ultimate as sub as permanent as the
thing and then everything is in the process of flow everything's in the River of Life and that uh to take a
stand anywhere in a view in a position and the idea that anything is um is
Ultimate um makes a situ ation worse it adds a little bit of stress a little bit
of holding on so that's my orientation uh and I to be this this
explicit about it I kind of have some reluctance to do because I don't want to be dismissive or be disrespectful for
people have a different orientation and um people who have a different orientation are uh teachers
have phenomenal practitioners and and to have come to their understanding it
comes from a very very deep practice and uh and sometimes the way to
harmonize these two is that um it's uh like a difference between uh you know is
is light a particle or a wave and they say well it's neither particle or wave or it's both particle and wave and um
and so uh is there something ultimate or is there nothing ultimate um is there
both ultimacy not ultimacy is there a kind of view that we can hold on to or
have um that uh is neither of you or or not of you or is both of you and not of
you or is it two sides of the same coin same two sides of the same hand and uh
depending which way we look at it we come to a different conclusion so you
know we don't have to even take the what I'm offering the view that of no view
the idea the view of nothing ultimate um uh it's not very interesting
to make those views and hold on to those um there's ways of just kind of letting
that go too and not being so focused on it and not making those ultimate and the
thing so in this way um um the um if you know I'm kind of closer
to the emptiness School of Mahayana Buddhism and and I think that uh in
early Buddhism they don't have these schools they don't have articulate the philosophies as much but in the earli
tradition it's just the practice to practice non- clinging to understand the
value of not holding on to anything at all and that the freedom from suffering is freedom from not fixating on anything
including religion including philosophical views doctrines any kind of idea that
something is the ult the thing the ultimate thing and so in focusing on the
suffering and the end of suffering you know it's kind of like that's ultimate for me or that's the
foundational but even that's not something to hold on to there's nothing there to hold on to and Let Freedom from
clinging is um freedom from suffering is kind of like the hand has uh has a fist
has finally been opened opened up and um and it just uh you know know an open
hand is just an open hand there's nothing the the hand itself is not holding on to anything but if I love
that open hand and want to make it into something or and make and grab it then
I've lost the open hand and now I have a fist again so you know so you the end of
suffering can't be made you know you don't want to make that the thing and then hold on to that so there's nothing
to hold on to nothing to hold on to and how profound that is
so um so
um so suffering in its end no View and no
ultimacy are part of my Dharma at least for now and I say at least for now so
that um that's also not taken as being kind of ultimate truth and I'll end with
a little story I'm not sure where it comes from but there's a story of Mara who is um
kind of the Buddhist personification of all Temptations and hindrances that uh
Keeps Us in the world of sensual desires desires and and uh and prevents us from
becoming awakened and free and uh Samara is this kind of being
this supernatural being that goes around and tries to stop people from practicing and getting enlightened and all
that and um and so what there Mara is out wandering around and with his
attendant and they come across a a meditator who's uh doing walking
meditation and um and
um uh and the meditator has some deep realization deep insight and exclaims
how happily I see the truth I see the truth and uh and it Mara just continues
without being concerned and the intendant says tomorrow aren't you concerned this person's discovered the
truth and probably on the brink of Awakening or you know or you know making
progress along the way or and uh Mara says no no I'm not so concerned soon
enough uh the person will make it into turn it into a belief so we can say see things that are
powerfully true but then we make it into a belief and then we're back in Mara's
hands kind of so thank you and I'll continue with this tomorrow