so good morning Sana and good day so greetings from
uh um the Bay Area California where I
am and I'm happy to see all the chat messages coming in and feeling a sense
of a connection right [Music]
here yeah so welcome to our 7 a.m. uh guided meditation
and uh darat uh where will be um starting our
meditation I'll offer just a couple of orienting words um
here uh yesterday we started our meditation uh from this sense of
grounding and today we'll be expanding our meditation uh if you like to stay with a
sort of grounded feeling this sitting like a Inner Mountain feel free to do so
um but we're also uh going to extand uh to
include a kind of aliveness in this being so think of this is kind of like a
live Mountain um if that image or that metaphor somehow works for you and that
includes um paying attention to our life breath the movements of the
breath and so that's the orientation I we'll be working with and we're
expanding to um explore uh the nature
within this aless and enlivening uh
aspect of our being so what start with a sound of a
[Music]
bell pausing to
begin arriving arriving at when where you
are and how you are just as it
is not as what you wish it to be or not
demanding it to be otherwise
gently softly feeling and
sensing here and
now maybe with the felt sense in the body
sound
temperature whatever may be present in this moment
mindfulness is add to the
foreground and maybe heartfulness and body
fullness are here too
sensing this body
sitting maybe the posture
movements of the
breath that's a general sense of the body without having to figure it out
maybe you're feeling the weight of the body settling
down
naturally felt sense of Earth element in the
body like mud settling down in the
water it's natural
feeling and sensing the earthy body resting on
earth like a stones in the river bed
or a sense of sitting like a mountain
within quiet
Mountain Still e
resting here if you like
study
quiet collected
the steadiness of the Inner
Mountain and naturally highlight the movements of the alive
breath
like the breeze in the
mountain open to receive the felt sense of breath
there is an a life Mountain Within
feeling and sensing the movement of the
breath maybe throughout the
body or just a throughout out to the Torso
as life breath enlivens the whole
body you may notice different attening
Sensations in the body
[Music] tingling
ping
vibrating maybe a kind of energetic humming
swaying in the
Torso a liess is being known
when we're receiving the felt sense of
aliveness Within
directly there may be an
effect a sense of a being [Music]
enlightened by this a conscious relationship with our own
aliveness you may stay with the the movements of the
breath or just this a general sense of En
lifening within this fathom long
body a life
Mountain
e
e e
my sense of awe or wonder may come in
maybe sweet joy
happiness by staying in
touch with the movements of the
breath a sense of
enlightening e
releasing ideas beliefs and conceptual
overlays trusting your own felt sense
for
e e
allow the knowing to emerge from the immediacy of your own
felt
sense maybe there is no need for
words
e
e for
e e
in this last a few minutes of our meditation [Music]
together allow this aless
flowing from the movement of the breath to
nourish the whole
body the light the whole body
allow the flow of the breath to dance its own dance
a for
[Music]
yeah so we'll make a transition uh to a little more
words and so this uh darat that um uh this a sequence of uh
dmats that were building upon was from the sua in Sam nikaya and yesterday I
offered an uh kind of an overarching um description of what this
suta was about um to unfold and was was
about and um the sutta started out by saying that knowing and seeing the
destruction of thingss come with development uh or come with cultivation
or you can say practice not otherwise and then the Buddha offered
the three different simes to illustrate some of the
characteristics of um the cultivation and so I wanted to unpack
the first one uh which has to do with a chicken and a bunch of her eggs and so
let me read this little piece uh right now Suppose there was a chicken with 8
or 10 or 12 of eggs but she had not properly sat on
them to keep them warm and incubated that chicken might
wish oh if only my chicks would break out of the eggshell with their clouds
and the beak and the hatch safely but they can't break out and
hatch safely why is that because that chicken
with 8 or 10 or 12 eggs has not properly
sat on them to keep them warm and
incubated and so just like that if the practitioners would not properly
cultivate and wholeheartedly cultivate develop what is needed
even if we wish all we wish we won't be free so just like the
chick and I was struck by uh this little piece um this uh simile right
here uh there are two things that got highlighted and that the the word was oh
the chicken uh had not properly sat on
them and the second word is to keep them warm and
incubated and so the first time one I want to point out is that our
cultivation and development is um rather
specific and so uh this cultivation needs a proper cultivation
and development and in the Susa um the Buddha offered uh that that
the the specific cultivation and development is the 37 wings of Awakening
the four foundations of mindfulness five faculties the five
spiritual faculties five powers and some of you would have known this um and you
know those are all the things that we've actually spoken about in the 7 a.m. Dar
meds seven factors of Awakening Noble Aid fold
path and so the development is uh quite specific and we have to engage in them
and this other word keep them warm and in
incubated in that sense that we have to give ourselves over to commit to this
cultivation and development
um you know if the chick wants the chick uh if the chicken wants the chicks to
break through uh to break through the shells but you know she wanders around
and socialize with other chickens or U go get her warms or something you know
and she sat for a few minutes and gets up and that won't you know the chicks won't
break through right and so in this way um for us
too when we cultivate um uh the Noble
eight-fold Path uh our whole practice um is oriented is aligned with
what Eightfold Noble Eightfold Path is orienting US
towards and I as I was reflecting that um
and there's a lot of nuances in um how
chickens incubate and allow the chicks uh uh to to be
hatched you know I I don't know somehow this kind of a LIF making
processes um probably is never as traval as what we think or what we
see and and I had some birds um incubating and hatching under my
roof I was kind of stuned by uh in the
intricacy the uh the mama bird was um
engaging in this whole process there were times that she had to protect the
eggs because the Big Bird would come and and there are times that she would be
there and sit it so we don't know what's what might be going on
within uh the chicken but my sense is that she's
attuned to this
process she's attuned to um and the
um the chicks uh being incubated in some way
yeah and so for us uh this development uh invites us to be attuned to our inner
process and then the assimile goes on um with another term here and that
the Buddha also said you know I'm going to paraphrase this a little bit and then I'll read it basically said well you
know even if you didn't wish to be free but if you keep motivating and
developing uh the mind and heart properly and to keep developing it even
if you didn't have a wish to be free it'll happen on its own just like the
chicks and so let me read this part and said when a medicant or when a
practitioner is committed to development they may not wish if only my
mind was freed by a from the tins by not grasping even so their mind is freed
from tins by not grasping why is that and you should say
it's because they are developed developed in the 37 factors of
Awakening Suppose there was a chicken with 8 or 10 or 12 eggs and she properly
sat on them to keep them warm and incubated and that chicken may not wish
uh if only my chicks would break out of the eggshell with their clouds and Beak
and hatch safely but still they will break out and hatch
safely why is that because that chicken with eight or 10 or 12 eggs properly sat
on them to keep them warm and
incubate and so this uh what's um interesting or stood out for me or two
things uh in this little um teaching one is that our practice or the
cultivation development is not based on wishful thinking or based on our gohal
or the ideas of a ghost or the results it's not an orientation of
resulting cuz we can wish always we wish and this you know this goal
orientation or the resulting orientation is kind of in the popular
culture right and they were very driven by the goals of often
times and yet our practice
um is not go driven or result
orienting and rather um it invites us to cultivate and
develop uh with wholeheartedness sincerity and aligned in a way that is
conducive to Freedom and uh the other point that uh this
particular simile really kind of highlights is that uh just like the
chicks hatching there is a natural process that
is being born the uh process of Liberation is born with
in so much of us is of it is kind of under the surface level of our being
being there is a natural unfolding and the the chick can't just
uh go ahead the chicken can't just go ahead and break a shell for the
chicks and the inner development has to unfold in its own time and it's in its
own way and the chicken plays A Part in doing
this and as we can see much of this happens below the surface level of our
being and so just uh like this our Dharma practice uh we're partic
participating in uh is kind of um a process of
developing and cultivating or nurturing kind of a w like
environment for the goodness of freedom and knowing and
seeing to grow and to mature sometimes I feel like the
freedoms almost uh like coming out the womb of my being like you know from the
belly center of my being and rather rather than coming from
the head Center and this process we can't rush
it and you know we can't rush it because we want it so badly and if you know if you just hear
that it almost feels silly or it doesn't make sense because clearly that is not
aligned with non-grasping right cuz we wanted so
badly um and so instead the invitation is that we learn to
properly cultivate um the inner capacities that
kind of grow out of our inner uh [Music]
womb with the sincerity with the care with the
patience and a greater degrees of wisdom
and uh love
and so thank you everyone and so that's the Sim of the
chicken and eggs thank you for your
[Music]
attention have a wonderful rest of the day everyone