hello and
welcome so this week
the instructions have been offered on mindfulness of
thinking and uh hopefully it hasn't been too complicated the idea always is to try to
keep the instruction simple and that's the intention today as
well but it might what I'm what instructions I give might not be
understandable so then don't worry yourself about it don't try to force yourself to do it or think that you're
supposed to do it
and the mindfulness of thinking is
valuable and what can be also helpful is not to
be too involved or too focus on thinking there are people who identify
them with their themselves with their thinking they are their thinking their thinking is them there's no distinction
between the two and so and some people being aware
and be and thinking are also indistinguishable and uh there's a big overlap between
mindfulness and thinking but it doesn't have to be exactly the
same and so today I'd like to emphasize that which is not
thinking and uh and uh of course of many things which are not thinking but in
relationship to thinking there are two areas that I'd
like to point out and and that is that um beyond the
edges of thinking or outside the domain of thinking we can sense and feel and
experiences we can hear but we don't have to think we don't have to have
discursive thinking we don't have to have words or images in response we can have Body
Sensations and we don't have to be involved in it and be thinking about it
and we don't don't have to be identifying what it is with thoughts or
images the sensations you just be there maybe
unidentified just uh something in the field of awareness that doesn't get any more attention than
that and the question is how do we how do we experience things
directly without centering ourselves in the world
of thinking without it being the only lens by which
we're aware so what is it what in our experience is not
thinking and so even when we're thinking what is it that's not thinking here and
some of the things I've taught this week um The Body Sensations connected to
thinking they're not the thinking in terms of the words or their images or the
ideas it's Sensations the emotions themselves in
some ways don't have to be wetted to stories and thoughts and Analysis and
judgment and all kinds of ways which we think they can be there without the
thoughts or we can know them without thinking thinking might still occur but
they're known free of thinking just kind of in and of
themselves so this idea of being able to change lenses or shift gears or Orient
ourselves to our experience so we're not experiencing it through the lens of thinking through
the and um thinking might Reed to the background it might be there as a gentle support it might be there sometimes
helpful in a helpful way sometimes not but we're not oriented to it we're not
identified with it so that's that's one thing the other
thing is um there is knowing we can know we can know a lot of
things without words without uh words or
images that inform us what we know so there's I call it sub vo
subvocal knowing knowing that's below the level of of words Concepts usual
Concepts and in some ways that operates all the time because there's so much that we
take in in the world just to navigate the world walk around in the world that we know without it being actively known
without being a vocalized knowing or without an act of identification it
still known in some deeper place in the mind so for
example many of you go through a door or throughout the day open and closed
doors and you might be thinking about other things you might be involved you might be busy with things and there's
no thinking oh that's a door that's the handle I have to touch it all that
happens uh little bit on automatic pilot there's a knowing of the door knowing where the door is where the door handle
is but it's it's uh I like to call it
preverbal so there's preverbal knowing that's enough to navigate and open the
door it doesn't have to rise up into the verbal place in the
mind so sometimes when we do mindfulness practice we can rest in that preverbal
knowing and then finally this is where maybe gets
complicated is there can be preverbal knowing of that which
is not thinking the experiences we have that
are not in their origination their
arising involve thinking preverbal
knowing and this is a place of quiet of Silence that allows for some deeper
knowing a source from deep within that will always keep us in the present
moment that's where this
lives so assuming a meditation
posture and gently closing your
eyes and Orient yourself Orient yourself now to whatever it might be within
you where there's a quiet or a
silence other parts of you might be busy and loud with
thoughts there might be agitation in the body but see if you can find where
somewhere deep within somewhere within where there's a sense of stability and
Stillness maybe even a
silence and as you exhale to relax your body your
mind relax into that place of
silence as you inhale perhaps the inhale
begins in that place of quiet or calm or Stillness
within relaxing back to it on the
exhale
for and then seeing
if the awareness of the present
moment maybe a preverbal knowing can arise from this place of
quiet Within
maybe as the inhale arises from that place and exhale returns to
it so the knowing the awareness the preverbal and quiet
knowing that might be there side by side with verbal
knowing but Orient yourself to the preverbal the silent
knowing knowing without words or
images and let that knowing arise with the
inhale return with the exhale to that place of
quiet
for
what is the nature of awareness in between your
thoughts when you don't use thoughts to answer the question
the question how are you aware between your
thoughts between the end of one and the beginning of the
next
how are you aware be beyond the edges of thoughts
for
and how do you know
when your knowing is without
thoughts without
thinking
The preverbal
Knowing arising from a silent peace peaceful
silence
Within
for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting maybe you can appreciate that the full range of how we
can know full spectrum of being aware and both with thoughts
without thoughts with our body and our
motions the ability to be
present and receptive for all of it present
in with all of it suffusing
us for that to happen it helps to feel
safe if we don't feel safe the mind will
naturally Orient itself in such a way to focus on how to be
safe what to be concerned
about and for a few moments in meditation maybe we can
trust feeling safe enough to not focus on anything in
particular but rather to have the full capacity for
awareness to flow through US Open receptive to
everything
and even if we don't feel fully safe just feeling somewhat safe to
appreciate the value of it value of feeling safe and
safety to come to the end of this sitting and become interested in being
safe for others to support others so they can be them
fully themselves by being a safe
person What a Wonderful World it would be if more people felt
safe in their homes in their communities their work
in this world may we contribute to
safety may we support it and create and make
the spreading of safety be
contagious May our way of being safe Inspire others
may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful and may all beings be
free
[Music]
thank
you
so hello for this fifth uh talk on mindfulness of
thinking and um one of the benefits that I've received from my
meditation practice and especially from mindfulness practice and
um is that I have a friendly relationship with my thinking my thinking and I get along
just fine and sometimes I will I will often
know what I'm thinking about and if that doesn't seem to be the
important thing or the valuable thing or the beneficial thing to be thinking about uh it's relatively easy for me to
change how I think and um so I've so in that way it's
easier to be friends with my thinking because um I'm not obsessed oppressed by
them I'm not they're not forcing themselves on me or I don't live under their
weight and I'm friendly with them and I respect them and give time for my
thoughts sometimes I when I when I exercise or go for walks in the Hills I give my
thoughts free reign just completely let them think whatever they want to think
and in a way that I don't in meditation because then I'm kind of just sitting and being present and and that full
presence to experience means I'm not kind of traveling along with the thoughts and being the thoughts but to
give freedom to thinking in when I exercise or or when I go for
hikes uh it's fascinating because it shows me sometimes you know something
what's going on for me or what's what I'm really concerned about or it it
shows me some some deeper place of some deeper kind of unfolding that might be
going on and thinking about something reflecting on something so so I give
myself time in my days to give kind of unfettered freedom to my thinking to
think as wishes and uh and then I practice with that whatever that might be or try to
become wise about it or if necessary and then other times where I
don't do that not because I'm aversive to thinking but because there's a better
game in town there's more interesting things to do than to be thinking a lot and that's to be aware to be present and
centered in the present moment and to just be aware of what's happening at has things
unfold and um now if thinking about things is what
awareness is and uh some people confuse mindfulness with thoughtfulness where
we're kind of tracking and thinking about what's happening as it's happening where thinking is a verbal commentary
verbal recognition or through images and all that then uh that certainly can be
valuable but we might be limiting ourselves from the deep deeper satisfaction of being centered not in
the head not in the usual place where discursive thoughts happen the usual place where reactivity to the world
happens the usual place where fear arises from but we're centered from some
deeper source of knowing which is has a quiet to it has a peacefulness to it and
sometimes it can feel like it's a knowing without thoughts or maybe it's
knowing which is accompanied by very simple thoughts thoughts of recognition thoughts of knowing thoughts of
questions you know what is this I feel you know a ache someplace in my body and
there's a very simple thought what is this let's bring attention to it what
would be like to be aware of it really close and intimate what would be like to
not be so close into it but kind of observe it from a distance so very simple kind of
that uh kind of questioning contemplating that comes from some place that's deep within or a place that's a
little bit feels more at home from within than where reactivity comes
from and um and part of the advantage of this is that we learn not to identify
with our thoughts we learn not to be our thinking and for many people as I said
um they who who they think they are is inseparable from their thought thoughts if they weren't thinking they would feel
they didn't exist and uh but actually we can exist
brilliantly without being centered in our thoughts and um and
thinking so part of mindfulness of thinking is not just to be mindful of
thinking itself but to be mindful of the absence of thinking and that could be
when the thinking mind gets like the discursive thinking mind the storytelling mind gets really quiet the
mind that goes on and on that's in loops and spins around gets really quiet you can feel the quiet the silence and the
that part of the mind while there still might be some rudimentary thoughts of recognition of questioning what is this
and how should I be with this but those thoughts are very
gentle and uh so that there's a quieting of mind and um and so what is that quieting
the Mind feel like what is it that's not thinking and what is it the awareness
which arises that is not centered on thinking and this is where mindfulness
of the body and mindful Sensations is so helpful because uh the sensations in and
of themselves are not a thought and but they do belong to a kind
of a deeper uh process of feeling sensing
knowing that's not centered in thinking so part of mindfulness of
thinking is being aware of that which is not thinking um to come to the end of a
thought and then what is it that's there before the next thought
arises when you uh so I'll ask a question of you and how would you answer
this question if you didn't use words or thoughts to explain it to describe it to answer
it and the question is who are
you who are you if you don't use thoughts to answer the
question so there might be many responses to this but but uh sometimes we realize
that something different way of being being alive if we don't use the usual
Concepts ideas you know I'm such this person I'm this kind of person I'm this kind of person uh as the
answer those kinds of that if that drops away how do we experience ourselves how
we experience life uh that is in a fuller
somatic uh experiential way that is not
um uh always through the filter of thoughts and I like in this
to um uh being finished with the
menu and no longer studying the menu but actually eating the
food if we're always living in the menu or living in the instruction manual or
living in the screenplay then uh we're not really
living Our Lives and too much time living in our thoughts is more like reading the
menu and so to not to learn how to be mindful of thinking in such a way that
we start becoming free from being stuck in thoughts we become free from
identifying ourselves strongly with what thinking says to us that we learn to be
very respectful of thoughts we can become friends of our thinking we don't have to be opposed to it but we're not
caught in its web we're not caught in its up in it so then I'll end with
a uh an image metaphor that I like to use when I teach this mindfulness of
thinking so imagine that you've gone for a nice walk it's a nice day you're walking in a park it's a safe and
comfortable place and you stop uh By The River and you lean against a tree of beautiful
shade it's a pece very peaceful and pastoral and you're very content and you
have a nice little snack maybe lunch and you're sitting there and you're just
enjoying the water flowing down and some people can be almost pulled into the
endless streaming of water as keeps something very relaxing and just
watching the water flow and flow and gentle little waves in the river coming and going and it's all nice and it's
nice to be alive it's not to be present the hikes been good you feel here
content and then lo and behold coming down the river is a
Showboat with music and dancing and games and casino and great food and and
attractive people and the next thing you know you've been you're on that boat
you've been on that boat for a few days and and you kind of wa how did I
get here I was having such a nice contented time on the riverbank and how did how did this
happen well you get off the boat and you finally make your way to back up to where the tree is and once again you're
there very content and happy watching the river nothing's needed no one to be
no one to become no one to get no one to understand nothing to understand just
there and then down comes another boat this time it's a war
booat fighting the battle fighting the good war and you see it but then the next
thing you know you're on the boat for hours fighting the war you don't even know what war you're fighting but you're
there Manning the guns and directing the show and and then you kind of kind of
come to and say wait a minute what am I do how did I get get there what's going on you get off the war booat you come
back up to your tree you sit there next thing you know there's a
decrepit old raft that's barely alive barely floating just limping along
floating down the river all half drowned it just seems so poor and pathetic and
and you feel sorry for it and as soon as you feel sorry for it you find yourself
some hours later the kind kind of somehow managing to sit on top of
that raft and navigating down the river and you wonder how did I get on this
raft and then you make your way back to the to the
tree and the next boat that comes down the river you lean against the tree take
a deep breath relax and you just watch it go down and
pass and other boats come you watch them go past you don't have to get
on so this is the analogy for thinking all kinds of thoughts can come along all
kinds of boats do you get on the boat and even don't even know you're on it fighting
the good War having the great fantasy um maybe feeling very sorry for
yourself in some way and all those things might be needed sometimes in life but
chances are they're not needed as much as all the boats we get on so
mindfulness is teaching us to stay present on the shore the solid safe
Shore and just watch the stream the flow of life in
a in a freeing way without getting
on so um thank you so I hope this week on thinking has been useful so next next
week I'm going to the retreat center IRC Insight retreat center for a week to
teach Retreat and uh don Neal will come and um teach here on YouTube next for
the next weeks and she's aware of what I've been teaching these weeks on the instructions in mindfulness so she'll
follow up in some way this this mindfulness world is a wide world so she'll follow up with maybe further
instructions or that uh you know can build on what I'm what I did these time times and then I'll come back in a week
and a week from Monday and then um uh I will I'll do the same I'm thinking well
I was going to have this be a five-week series but maybe there's more instructions to give and more way of
staying close to the basics that would be useful for for all of
us so um thank you very much and
um and um I'm sure you'll enjoy Dawn and I look
forward to coming back in a week