greetings everyone I'm happy to be here with you and thank you for your comments uh
in the chat today we'll um end the
meditation just with a bow rather than having the IMC audiovisual team ring a virtual
Bell so yesterday in our meditation I drew on the first two steps of the
anapanasati suta the Buddha's foundational discourse
on using the breathing to establish cultivate and
strengthen our ability to maintain embodied
awareness the task being to keep our focus on the whole process of
breathing being interested in and knowing in
detail the texture of our lived experience during each inhale and each
outaleb moment for many of
us this isn't easy because the mind has such a strong
tendency to revert to discursive thinking you usually in the form of
stories about me myself in
mind so be patient with yourself you may have heard the
expression that nature upor a [Music]
vacuum well so does the human mind when it's not advanced in meditation
practice so the invitation is to undertake this meditation without worrying about the
result we recognize that the monkey mind will want
to run off reating stories about the past and
future and when that happens we smile and say thank you no thank you
monkey mind because we know that we're here to
cultivate a peaceful mind but don't underestimate the Pres
the importance of that smile when you say no thank you to your
distractions we also need to be kind to
ourselves and we just gently with care and kindness bring our awareness back to the
breathing yesterday in our meditation the focus was on the first two steps of
anapanasati in which the practice is to Simply know
intimately the quality of each in breath and each out
breath today we'll practice the third step in which the Buddha teaches us one
trains I will breathe in experiencing the whole
body one trains I will breathe out experiencing the whole
body so we move from knowing to the more active practice of
training we still May Tain a connection with a breath but the focus today is on
experiencing the body the whole body and all the while staying with a
breath in the
background so begin by gently closing the
eyes leaving all your concerns outside the door no need for them now
and enjoying the luxury of dropping down into your lived
experience in the present moment now take a moment to formulate
your deepest intention for yourself and all
beings what brings you to medit Med
itate assuming a posture that expresses the nobility of your ins
spiration taking a moment to visualize your body and saying thank you for
supporting me all these years send your body however imperfect
it may be a wave of gratitude for all the incredible
functions it's been performing to keep you alive
giving a bit of a stretch to the spine it's
helpful to lengthen the back of the neck by moving the chin in slightly towards
the back so that the head is more
balanced and being supported more easily by the spinal column
so let's do a brief scan bringing care to every part of the
body starting with the crown of the head and moving
downward gently carefully bringing awareness imbued with
kindness to the scalp the face
the eyes the cheeks the
mouth and the
jaw softly down the net softening the
shoulders arms and
hands and moving Our Kind attention down the Torso
through the pelvis the upper
legs the lower legs and the
feet now take a moment to establish your mental
posture perhaps letting go of having to be someone and being patient with your
difficulties have having established
awareness in the body and mind take a long satisfying deep
breath carefully observing how the body experiences
breathing as it returns to its normal Rhythm and texture
our Focus today is to feel the
breath through the vehicle of the whole
body and the task is to become aware of how the body
experiences each in breath and each out breath
trusting the body to be your guide and to support you as you
meditate e
staying close to your body like a parent carefully keeping an eye on their
child experiencing the whole body as a way to love and care for
yourself as you sit feel the sensations of the body
breathing and let your mind be spacious and your heart be kind and
soft e
if the mind wander ask yourself if you can
trust that it's okay just to stay with the body
breathing e
let your eyes be soft and relaxed
enough to clearly see the changing nature of your present moment
experience feeling the whole body as it
breathes seeing the Dharma in the body
breathing
e
e e
how does it feel to experience the whole
body as you stay with the
breath
e
e e
as we come to the end of this meditation we'll return to our Circle of
Care for ourselves for everyone here meditating
with us today and for all
beings may all beings be safe and protect
protected being safe may all beings including
ourselves be happily at ease may all abide in
peace and may all beings everywhere be
free and to end the meditation with hands
joined I bow to each of you honoring the sincerity of your practice
what
greetings everyone it's good to be here with you
I'd like to share with you that um I really hate relying on notes for
speaking uh because it's not so spontaneous and a year ago I could add
live no problem but the truth is that I'm not
100% recovered from my illness and my memory is not great
so I'm just more comfortable um teaching with notes and so I ask your
forgiveness the theme for this week is trusting the
practice and the poly word for trusting is Sada which literally means supporting
the heart and in addition to trust Sada is
also translated as confidence
conviction Faith the ability to trust is the first
of the five faculties which everyone has to some
degree and sadada has the benefit of controlling
doubt and when it Masters the hindrance of
Doubt sadada becomes the first of the five
powers though the faculty of trust is well worth
cultivating and when it becomes strong it's a tremendous asset in our practice
yesterday we looked at trusting the breath and trusting our beautiful
mind and in our practice trust or faith means surrendering to things the way
they are in Buddhism this surrender is by no
means based on Blind Faith on the contrary it's based on
confidence born of conviction and in this practice we're
encouraged to experiment to try things out in order to
find out what works best for us
personally and in this way little by
little we become able to be our own
teacher and if we still with this gradual practice we'll know for ourselves when
it's beneficial and this in turn inspires us
to trust the practice one thing that inspires me
personally is to just take a little pause and remember that I'm doing my
best to walk in the footsteps of the
Buddha what a beautiful thing and doing our best is good
enough the Buddha put tremendous importance on cultivating
awareness and in particular embodied awareness
is at the heart of our
practice today I'm going to share with you a number of citations from many different sources
about trusting the body we know from the ancient texts that
when the Buddha died his close disciple Ananda who had memorized all of the
Buddhist teachings was asked where do we go for
teaching now that the Buddha is no longer with
us and Ananda replied mindfulness of the
body so it's quite extraordinary that the early texts
suggest that the best replacement for the Buddhist teaching
is being aware of our own
body and it's true that our bodies however imperfect do have their own
wisdom after the passing away of the Buddha Ananda also
said awareness of the body is a source of joy and can be truly considered One's
best [Music] friend and I love uh payma
children's teaching that it's helpful to realize that this
very body right here right now with all its aches and its Pleasures is exactly
what we need to be fully human fully awake
Fully Alive and Gil seems to agree with
that when he says all the practice can be found in
this body over the months and years as you do
meditation you'll probably find that your body will become more and more
awake and more and more are the source of
intelligence understanding love and
compassion many of the best qualities of the human
being come through being
embodied thank you Gil we already have exactly what we need
and to paraphrase the Buddha within this very fathom long
body with its perceptions and inner senses lies the whole
world the cause of the world the sensation of the
world and the path that leads to the station of clinging to this world
in the same vein aun moon from the forest Tha Forest tradition exhorts
us never allow the mind to Desert the body in your investigation of the
world examine its nature see the elements that comprise
it see the impermanence The Suffering The
selflessness of the body while sitting standing walking or
lying down when the body is true nature is
seen the wonders of the world will become
clear and the purity of the mind can shine forth
let that sink
in the last quote I'll share is from Jack cornfield who to my great
surprise first encouraged me to teach and then authorized me as a Dharma
teacher and fortunately I was able to then train
with Gil for another six years before he agreed with
Jack and authorized me as a Dharma teacher as
well so here's something that Jack cornfield shared on a long
retreat the human body at peace with itself is more precious than the rarest
gem cherish your body it's yours for this one time
only the human form is one with great difficulty it's easy to
lose all worldly things are brief like lightning in the sky
this life you must know as the tiny splash of a
raindrop a thing of beauty that disappears even as it comes into
being therefore set your aspiration and make use of every day and
night to achieve it
many teachers stress that our physical bodily experience is the key to practicing
mindfulness awareness and one of the reasons for this is because when the mind is paying
attention to the body we're by definition in the present
moment and not indulging in distractions from the past or the future
whenever you're experiencing your body you're in your lived
experience another reason that the body is such a great teacher is because since it's
created and conditioned by the mind it can function as a draw away to wisdom to
understanding what's going on deep inside us
mindfulness awareness is to be present with what is without
reacting our awareness needs to be broad not narrow and its main characteristic
is to be embodied so trusting the
practice as Gil says with B the body as our Monastery our refuge
for me the body served as a refuge throughout my whole life as a
kid and a trauma victim I loved being absorbed in swimming canoeing biking in
the woods as a teenager I became a modern dancer and really learned how to
pay close attention to my body and I was so surprised when I first
performed on stage that didn't have stage fright and this was simply because
I was completely in the body with no thoughts about myself and I think this is why when I
started practicing Zen at the age of 21 I felt so at
home and my faith in the practice quickly became
[Music] unshakable I can assure you that just
being totally in the body and in the present moment opens the
doors to penetrate the truth of the Buddhist
teachings and I'm convinced that the more you know and trust your body the more at home you'll
feel in your life the body also teaches us to
penetrate Inc constancy which reveals in turn the
truth of not self and this for me has had tremendous
healing powers while close with a poem on the
theme of trusting and constancy by the Polish American poet
jesla milash he writes the word of faith means
when someone sees a de drop or a Floating Leaf
and knows that they are because they have to
be never allow the m and even if you dreamed or closed your eyes and wished
the world would still be what it was and the leaf would still be carried
down the
river so also on the idea of trusting the body as perhaps our greatest
teacher yesterday the homework was to reflect on what it might be like to live
in Beauty to move in
Beauty and for me I feel like I'm living in Beauty when I step out of being in a
hurry and slow down a little and then when I bring full
awareness to how I'm moving through the day the active mind gives way to a mind
that's empty empty enough to be fully aware and that feels just
lovely we have such full busy lives so if you'd like a little homework
for the next 24 hours you might try slowing down just a little bit in your everyday
activities and bring awareness to how you're inhabiting your
body when you're reaching for something in the kitchen or opening a door or using the
toilet bring your full awareness to how the body is
experiencing what you
do thank you for your attention and thank you for your practice