morning folks good day good evening whatever
time it is for you I know there are people from everywhere um on this uh on
this YouTube um in this YouTube sa IC YouTube sa I'm really happy to be
with you this week filling in for Gil Gil's teaching a a two- week retreat at
IRC so he'll be gone those two weeks and then a third week as well
um so it's it's really a pleasure to be here I'm often a part of the uh of the S
you know um those of you in the chat and uh and today I'll be in a different role
and uh this week I'll be in a different role for those who don't know me I I
live in Santa Barbara and I teach in aanga here um as well as uh for IMC and
IRC are are Retreat Center in uh in Santa
Cruz so let's uh let's begin as we as we do with the with the
meditation and uh I always like to mention posture at
the beginning of a sit I think it's uh it's really important and uh after we've
been practicing for a while we can tend to ignore it you know and uh and the way
our body is held has a really uh a strong effect on our minds as well as uh
our bodies and our on our whole systems and so if our posture can stay uh um uh
in a an orientation that supports being present in meditation then our
meditation is definitely going to benefit so take a little time right now
with your posture just finding a way of sitting that uh encourages this balance of
alertness and ease that is so supportive of of staying present as we as we
said just letting all the muscles that aren't necessary to keep you upright let
them soften and if you're sitting or standing let your spine be upright but
not
rigid and take some some time to notice where there's more
attention in the body maybe in the face the forehead or
the the jaw the neck and the the shoulders the upper
shoulders a special attention to those areas or any any areas where you
habitually hold tension often tension in those upper
areas around the the head and neck and upper shoulders uh is related to mental
tension so easing easing the muscles there it can
sometimes lead to some easing in the mind as well
let your chest be open so the breath can flow
easily in and out
let your belly be soft just uh touch into the way it moves
as you breathe now if the belly is relaxed it
will move with a
breath and softening softening the belly can often soften
tension in the mind just as the the upper parts of the
body softening and soften the
Mind breathing in this being present too the whole body
I'm breathing out and letting the whole
body be in as much ease as possible as soft as open as possible
let the breathing be at the at the center of your awareness and and know it clearly know it
directly don't don't exclude what else is going on within
you just let uh let all the sensations be known as they arise
their thoughts just know them and let them
go just a very simple practice of
awareness
e
e e
and periodically as we sit here it can be useful to just um give a little
attention to your posture again to to notice if there are areas of tension
that have crept back in since the the beginning of the set
might notice if those are associated with particular kinds of thinking
emotion that are arising and just see if you can let
those relax as the body
eases if the mind eases as
well
e e
e
there can be such Simplicity in just uh just attending to what's arising in our
experience not moving into past or future and speculating about the
present just knowing what's happening
it's really it's a real gift that we give ourselves when we do
this there like a bomb with the
spirit it's uh it's so simple and yet it's very
profound it's a kindness
e
for
e e
and uh if you've felt any uh any sense of ease as you practiced this morning
and uh felt a sense of support from from your
practice I invite you I really encourage you to to stay connected to that sense
of ease and and support and to carry it into into the world with you
into uh all the things that uh you do and the people you meet
today let it
spread for
so uh as I said uh before the meditation it's really a pleasure uh to be here
with you um and if you weren't here at the very beginning um maybe you aren't aware that Gil's teaching a retreat for
two weeks uh uh the next two weeks and then he'll be away for the following
week as well so uh I'll be uh sitting in this week and next week will be May
Elliott and we're not quite sure who the third week will be and uh and I also mentioned that I've
participated in this 7 a.m. sit you know along with many hundreds of you uh many
hundreds of times over the last four years it's amazing to me that it's been four years and I'm really happy to be
here in a in a different role this week being the one who speaks and I hope it
will be useful to you
so uh of course there are a lot of different ways uh to approach Buddhist
practice Buddhist thought Buddhist religion if you if you think of it in that way um some people treat Buddhism
as a kind of an Orthodoxy with things to believe in that uh can make us feel
secure in a difficult world something outside ourselves you know a support but
an external support a belief system
and some people um treat the path more uh more often as a um did I turn off
original sound I hope I did yes no I
did okay that was something I forgot to do
um excuse me if there's been an echo there was a something going on so I said
some people treat the the Buddhist path as an Orthodoxy um a support from
outside ourselves a belief system that that makes us feel safe perhaps in a in
this world and some people treat the path more as a a self-help program you
know a toolkit that helps us to be more effective more kind uh happier in our
lives and some uh some some people focus for the most part um on having Pleasant
and peaceful and deep meditations you using the practice perhaps as a a respit
from pain in in their lives and then some people engage with the Dharma as a
a lifelong uh path to Freedom a path to Liberation from
clinging to any any kind of inclination in the mind any movement in the mind
towards uh greed hatred and delusion and you know all all of those
ways of uh of approaching the Dharma are legitimate but of course I'm here to
advocate for seeing it as a path to Freedom it's uh the idea that it's
possible to come to a complete uh sense of freedom of heart and mind in this
lifetime that that's really inspiring to me and whatever our motivation for
practice uh when we encounter Buddhist teachings when we listen to talks when we read ancient texts or uh or modern
books or magazine articles about Buddhism we all relate in different ways
to the teachings that we come in contact with some of us will uh take what we
hear or read on faith not questioning it at all um and some of us might trust the
interpretation of uh one particular teacher might have a favorite um
and when that person presents the teachings we really we really connect and some of us might consider that what
we hear or read that it makes sense we might just be looking at it more
intellectually or intuitively know oh this makes sense to me this fits and
some of us are kind of more skeptical only accepting teachings that uh
resonate with what we already believe about about
life so the boo Buddha the Buddha described three General ways that people
connect with spiritual teachings uh some people the Buddha called traditionalists
those who base their beliefs on scripture or on oral tradition those who pretty much take things on
faith and uh another group he called reasoners and investigators who rely on Logic on
analytical reasoning to make their assessments of what they're hearing what they're reading
in the third group he called experientialist those who base their belief on their own direct knowledge
that is their approach is empirical and the Buddha counted himself among this
third group what he understood and taught he said was based on his own
experience what he had come to know directly as a result of practice not
dependent on an external Authority
and I I think it's useful for us to be conscious of the ways that we personally tend to approach uh any system of
knowledge whether it's religious or political or social just in general in our lives do we unconsciously hold views
or attitudes that come from our families from our culture from what we learned in school you know for I'm sure that's
that's true for many of us for for most of us maybe for all of us do we take
those things on faith you know or do we question them or are we more likely to look at ideas intellectually just
judging them to be well thought out rational aligned with reality or do we tend to try ideas out
and see if they actually make a difference in our lives leading to more of what we'd like to see in ourselves
I think recognizing the ways that we tend to develop views around any subject
that we're interested in is really useful to look at and we're probably
using the same strategies to arrive at the way we relate to the
Dharma so it's good to be a aware you know and maybe we're taking things on
faith that could be investigated with h with more fruitful result maybe we're
depending on our intellectual understanding without testing to see whether our beliefs are really congruent
with our lived experience we're encouraged in our
Dharma practice to investigate to see if the Dharma teachings actually reflect
our own experience we're encouraged to do that we inquire into the teachings we come in
contact with and as our mindfulness uh of
strengthens our Sati our awareness as it strengthens we're able to pay closer attention to our own experience than we
probably ever have before in our lives and we learn from
that when I make a claim about Dharma practice I want to be really clear what
I'm basing that claim on for example you know I can tell you that as I was
getting dressed this morning I was kind of hurrying and uh and I can claim that
if I'm really present to uh and mindful of this the felt sense of of hurrying in
the body as I do it that I'll see the stress in it and I'll be able to let go
of it like I'll be able to let it dissipate so you know what am I basing
that claim on Did a teacher tell me that this is how practice works you know mindfulness can lead us to seeing stress
that we might be ignoring and then allows it to dissipate to let
go is it maybe something I just think makes sense it does make sense for sure it makes sense to me hopefully it's
actually been my experience often enough that I can feel confident suggesting
that uh you know that it works and that's true when I feel a need to hurry
I can I can sense the stress in it right away and I can let that stress soften I can ease up I have empirical knowledge
about that so that's a really simple kind of
um example of course the Buddha considered himself an experientialist one who bases belief on
Direct knowledge not simply on faith or inference or reasonableness so during the me the
mornings this week I I want to talk about six qualities of the Dharma that are related to its empirical nature that
can be uh uh experienced directly in our lives and in our
practice and I think the list will be uh familiar to many of you maybe all of you
but I'm planning also to bring in a list of capacities it comes from a completely different area from the study of
literacy and my sense is that the capacities that I'll talk about can
really support us in seeing and experiencing these these qualities of
the Dharma in in our practice in our lives maybe we could say that one way of
looking at our practice is that we're developing more and more skillful literacy about the nature of our
experience of life we're learning to read our experience really deeply to
make sense of it to make to understand it in deeper and deeper
ways I appreciate when I come across something from social science that kind of uh you know really sheds light on on
Dharma teachings so these six qualities of the Dharma I'll go through them quite
quickly and we'll go through them during the week the rest of the week the the
Dharma first the Dharma is said to be well exp expounded swato
swato U the implication is that the way the Buddha taught the Dharma was
skillful and what's often mentioned when referencing this statement is that the Dharma is good in the beginning good in
the middle and good in the end it's useful All Along The
Path the second uh the second quality um
in this list is that the Dharma is visible here and now stico it can be
examined right here in our own experience it's not something that needs to be taken on face
the third quality is that it's immediately effective or Timeless sometimes is as a the translation a
Calico we don't have to wait until we're dead or until our next lifetime if we if
we um um subscribe to that uh to rebirth
to experience it it's always available it's here in our experience and we can
see its workings in our minds and hearts as it happens
the fourth uh quality is this famous exhortation of The Bu Buddha aaso come
and see for yourself so it's often it's translated as in inviting
inspection so again this points to the Dharma not being taken simply on faith
so we can apply this ourselves we can keep investigating we can keep inspecting keep looking all through the
path beginning middle and end
and the fifth quality is onward leading fit for being used relevant and uh this
is actually my favorite word in the in all the Dharma opo onward leading the
practice of the Dharma leads one on towards Freedom towards
Awakening and uh and this aspect it points to the fact that our practice over unfolds over time it it naturally
moves moves Us in the direction of more freedom of less clinging less craving
there's a a natural unfolding that takes place if we're practicing sincerely
we're gradually coming to understand what leads to more stress in our lives and what leads to more
ease gradually inclining our minds more and more towards what's skillful what's
beneficial and after a while our minds and hearts they just incline in that
direction naturally organically the Dharma leads us
on the six uh the sixth quality is uh that the Dharma is to be experienced by
the wise or to be realized by the wise
[Music] P it's up to us to walk the path
ourselves the goal of practice isn't given by Grace it's not given by Good
Deeds are bestowed by some all powerful god um an analogy that gill often uses
is only you can pee for yourself we have to walk the path for
ourselves it's the only only way that it can be uh
realized so all six of these point to the path's empirical quality you know
there are different aspects of actually experiencing the Dharma playing out in
our our lives and uh since there are six of them
you know I'll talk about two of them tomorrow so we cover them all in in the
in the five days and uh I'll be trying to uh show how capacities that are are
useful for developing literacy about reading texts are really very very
helpful in becoming skilled at reading our own experience so that the dark
can fully unfold in our in our minds in our hearts in our
lives so uh so tomorrow I'll begin with these first two qualities of the Dharma
that it is uh well proclaimed and uh visible here and now and uh I'll
introduce one of the competencies that uh that supports seeing the qualities of
the Dharma really expressed in our our practice and uh I look forward to being
with you then tomorrow so thank you very much for your attention this morning and
uh and uh have a really lovely day or evening whatever time it is for you