so welcome welcome everybody some of you may know that this
is the third class in the introduction to mindfulness meditation it's perfectly
fine if you haven't been at the earlier ones just be building on what we done
before but I'll also be reviewing what we talked about
before so here at IMC we teach mindfulness in a particular progression
it doesn't have to be taught this way there's plenty of you know perfectly valuable legitimate ways to teach it but
um how we teach it here is I think Gil
frol came up with us you know maybe in a few decades ago this idea that I really
like and that is this idea of practice is having concentric
circles so in the center is more stable
then as you get rings around that these kind of get a little bit more wobbly so
in the center is mindfulness of breathing just of the experience of
breathing it's always available we're always breathing or you hope so
right or and then a little bit out there is the body this is also stable right
this the body is always available and it's espcially stable compared to the
third ring which is emotions it's what we're going to talk about tonight and then the fourth is
thoughts right the world of thoughts is like right we always are getting pushed around by them and it's very slippery
and tends to be the least I'm using this word
stable so on the preceding weeks we talked about mindfulness of breathing and mindfulness of the bodily
experience and what I'd like to highlight is that that it's
um it's so much about
experience Sensations as opposed to thoughts or
ideas and sometimes we kind of get confused to like we we think that it's
about Sensations but not recognizing that it's actually we're
thinking and next week we'll talk a little bit more about about thinking but when we do mindfulness it's
it can be like done without any words like the experience can be without words it's just the experience of for example
feeling like the chest expand and release the
stretch just these movements or maybe with breathing the belly goes in and out
or maybe you feel the temperature of the air going in and out of the
nose so it's not so much the concept or the idea of breathing because you know
breathing it's it's not so much what we experience instead we're experiencing
the movement of the body in these different
ways so we start with mindfulness of breathing and just we're having the breath and we're using this word anchor
on then the mind wanders this is what Minds do and then we just very simply come back to the breath the mind wanders
we come back to the breath the mind wanders we come back to the
breath it doesn't matter how many times you have to do this in the beginning it'll be a lot where the mind is maybe
even wandering more than it's even on the breath that's fine that's how it is when we start it's always like
this and then with mindfulness of the body body what we're pointing to is we
have the anchor here with the breath resting attention on the sensations of
breathing and then let's say there's a compelling bodily
sensation just a discomfort in the back I'm just making this up and then you
might feel like oh I can't be with the breath cuz my back really hurts and like
we just try to keep on being with the back but then we're think I'm sorry being with the breath and we're thinking about the back and then want to be with
with the breath oh in the back then going to be with the breath so instead of getting into a
wrestling match or struggling with this we just let go of using the breath as
the anchor and turn towards having the experience in the back be the
anchor and we feel it this might be exactly what you do not want to do but
it turns out that to actually be with our experience is a way to have more freedom
with them to no longer be pushed around by them and to have a different
relationship to our experience and we might say that mindfulness practice is all about
changing our relationship to what's happening so we turn towards the
experience of in my example what's happening in the back
and if we were to use words they would be adjectives
stabbing throbbing pinching hot
cold um vibrant or you know something like this so we're just noticing the
exper the uncomfortable experience in the back we're not thinking about it but the
mind will want to go into a story oh my gosh this thing in my back probably I'm
going to have to check in with the chiropractors as I get home why did I decide to go to a mindfulness class
anyway or you know something like this right there'll be stories that will happen as best we can we just let those
go to the background be with the experience in the
back until it's either no longer compelling it just kind of diminishes
this happens not always it does happen though and then come back to the
sensations of breathing or maybe you're with the back
and it's uncomfortable and the mind just goes off into fantasy or something about
this and you completely forget that you're meditating and then you wake up oh yeah I'm supposed to be doing that meditation thing then start back with
the breath and then when the body is compelling turn towards the body when
it's no longer compelling turned towards the the breath so we're just very easily
gently going back and forth between these different
experiences so now I'd like to introduce this idea of how to be have mindfulness of emotions because mindfulness practice
includes all of our Lives all of it there's nothing left
out emotions are a part of the human experience of course it is so how can we
breing bring mindfulness to emotions well first of all I'll say that
emotions have a two components at least two components often we tend to think
again I'll just use this as an example sadness we tend to think like oh I'm
just sad and I'm sad because I have this grief this terrible loss that happened
in my life of course I'm sad but
emotions have more than one component they have this sematic
signature and they have F mental aspect thoughts somatic signature is sadness
how does it feel in the body like how do you know you're sad for
example very often there'll be like this heaviness in the shoulders kind like maybe a little bit of a
slumping and there can be maybe pressure behind the eyes maybe even feeling like tears arising but
there's there can be kind of like this little bit of a collapsing of the posture maybe there's a lump in the
throat something like this and the mind is saying oh so sad
that so and so a sick in the hospital or so and so died or whatever it might be
that we're sad about and we're going to let the thoughts just
take care of themselves they're going to want to hijack the the experience and that's
okay we'll just let them take care of themselves and we are going to pay attention to the bodily
experience of the emotions and partly because the bodily
experiences they move at a different tempo as thoughts right I mean what's happening in the body is more stable
it's uh slower it's more tangible like we can feel it we can like really have
the get an experience of what it's [Applause]
like unlike the thoughts which are you know running really quickly and going all over the place the past the future
all kinds of things so in some ways that I think about this is that we are like
translating emotional experiences into bodily experiences being with the
experience of the body and in this way we actually are
honoring and respecting our bodily
experience we're not suppressing our emotions we're not pretending that
they're not there we're not trying to wish the that they were different or anything like this we are actually being
with our emotional life and this alone can add so much
freedom to one's life what would it be like if you felt
comfortable with all emotions you didn't have to you know move away from them or
avoid them you could have difficult conversations you could have tender
conversations you could comfort people in the midst of their terrible grief you
could hold your own grief adds a lot of freedom to our lives
CU we start to notice how much that we're trying to avoid emotions or trying to only have particular emotions and
have more of those but it doesn't work that way right we don't get to control our emotional
life we try we try but when we're trying to only have
certain emotions there's a way in which we there's this kind of like shutting down of our
experience so mindfulness of the emotions is this way that allows us
to no longer be in conflict with our emotional life and to have some
confidence with regards to our emotional life but maybe importantly it enables us
allows us to have some intimacy with our life there's this way in which if we're
trying to avoid our emotions that we're a little bit disconnected from ourselves from others
perhaps and then our life just is kind of like passing Us
by this way in which we feel like and I don't know like it's not very
satisfying our life but to be present for our inner life brings this richness
and fullness of The Human Experience emotions are an integral part
of our Lives of course it is so it can be transformative there's
this way in which also turning towards and honoring and respecting like yes
this is what anger feels like I have this heat in my face I feel like my legs
my arms want to move there's this restlessness here and uh
maybe like the chest gets puffed out a little bit too and like some of these subtle
things and we think about with the emotions they can show up but if there's this way in which we
can be with our emotions they can evolve there's this way in which they have the
freedom to arise be present and then pass away this
is the nature of emotions to just arise and pass
away and the physiologists tell us and the neurologists tell us right emotions
really only last 90 seconds and you're like wait I've been sad for longer than 90
seconds I've been sad for days weeks months years
even well what happens is it's like the sadness
arises and then we get tangled up with it and it's the getting tangled up with
it that causes it to persist oh no I wish the sadness weren't here I'm always sad I'm I'm going to be
sad again everybody else is having a good time and I'm not maybe I should do
that thing I saw on that YouTube video where you know I don't know maybe I should go learn to meditate I don't know
something like this that uh but there's often this subtle way in which we're trying to make them be different or go
away or it's often not even noticed that we get tangled up with and
it's the tangled up itness that perpetuates the emotions so instead they
can arise and pass away and so how can we allow them to be
there so that they aren't persisting is to just be with the bodily
experience and I'll talk a little bit about how we can do
that so maybe one more thing I'll say before I do a guided meditation is our
relationship to emotions in general will show up in this way we
might not be aware of it it might not be obvious it might not even be I'll say this it might be very
subtle but for some people they are emotional about emotion
they think that it's the true expression of who they are and they should announce and share all their emotions at all the
time I feel this way and therefore this should happen and now I feel this way and therefore that should
happen on the other end of the spectrum is like emotions they are a pain I don't
I try not to have any of them in fact I'm not even sure if I do have them so we have these two ends of the
spectrum these are two legitimate ways depends on you know so many things
it depends on which uh attitude towards emotions that you have but if you're on
the different extremes I would like to encourage just a movement more towards the center where just the CU some of the
most beautiful Sublime experiences of our lives are
emotions when babies are born right kind of like newborn babies that emotion or
love falling in love or the love that we have for others
or also you know fear right is very frightening of course it
is so the encouragement here is just to recognize that you will have a
relationship towards emotions and can we loose I don't know move towards the
center like we don't have to express every emotion and we don't have to pretend like we don't I'm saying the
word pretend a lot of people are just not aware of their
emotions okay so with that we're going to do a little bit of a guided meditation
here so let's take an alert posture
posture that expresses your intention to
meditate and also has some
ease has some uprightness the spine is
upright if your body Al allows it it can be helpful to not be using the back rest in the
chair but to be sitting
upright and then to connect to
this experience of sitting right now part of that is we can connect to to
the sitting surface if you're using the back rest
feel the pressure on your back from the
chair feeling the pressure on the buttocks from the chair or the
cushion feeling the pressure on the back of the leg
leg the feet we're
here want do a small little body scan
see if check in with some common areas of tightness or
attention the eyes around the
eyes the jaw we're just
noticing what do they feel like the eyes and the jaw
it might be that bringing our attention to those
areas allows some softening of
tension relaxing the shoulders letting the shoulder blades
slide down the back
and then can just check in like what is your emotional state like right
now what is your mood what are the feelings
and then you can notice how you're feeling about how you're
feeling your relationship to whatever the emotional state is right
now and if it's not clear your emotional state can you be okay with that with it
not being
clear and then we'll bring our attention to the sensations of
breathing feeling the belly moving in and
out with the
breath or feeling the chest stretch and the
release of the
stretch or feeling the air moving in and out of
the nose
whichever of those three choosing one of those three
areas and just resting attention there
breathing naturally the body knows how to breathe we don't need to change the
breath in any way we're just noticing the sensations
the experience of breathing
we're just hanging in there with the rhythm of breathing
when you discover that you're lost thought just very simply
gently begin again with the sensations of breathing
nothing in particular needs to be happening
we're just here now noticing the sensations of
breathing e
letting the thoughts just be in the background and being
with what it feels like to have an inhale
what it feels like to have an
exhale
for for
and now and let go having attention on
breathing and again notice the emotional
state the mood or feeling that is
present very simply offering it a kind of simple
awareness and see if you can discover where in
your body that emotional state or mood or
feeling is
experienced what Sensations in your [Music] body that you know that you're having
that emotional state
this might be
subtle might be
vague can you make a distinction between experiences in the
body and what's the mental events that are
happening we're turning towards the bodily experience
and then again can rest your attention on the
sensations of
breathing for
[Music]
so we often we're putting like the breath at the center and often starting with the
breath is a way that can allow the body and the mind to settle down maybe
with a little bit of a body scan to notice if there are some areas that are
uncomfortable and then just to rest there with the bodily
experience until something becomes compelling and this could be a bodily
you know discomfort in the body often Joy too or uh there can be this
energetic uplift joy and happiness this absolutely isn't part of this path of
practice it absolutely is experience that as
well but is there's this way in which we can use
this the stability of that we discover with a mindfulness of breathing to help
us create the container so to speak in which we can be with the
emotions and emotions are often felt not exclusively but often felt in the face
and in the Torso chest throat
belly face these types of
things and sometimes it can be a little bit tricky with emotions because we want
to resist them or judge them um we want to do anything except to have a simple
awareness of them but turning towards the bodily experience is a way in which we can have
this more simple relationship and experience of
emotions and with that I'd like to open it up to some questions or comments about anything I've
said and I'd love to hear a little bit like how that meditation was for you was
that obvious this whole idea of looking for the bodily I like this expression
the somatic signature of the emotions in the bodily experience or was that
perplexing and and Sally's getting the microphone
for us does anybody have any comments about
what I said or how was that meditation I think it's
you can see that's the green yeah and then the yeah that's probably that's I think it's
um yeah here's a great question you have to push the button you know this
right poor Sally she's a is it WR so on the side there's a little button on the
side push that there you go so in my case it was a little bit difficult
to identify the emotion but once I felt it I was just like I just wanted to
start crying and then when you said that we should come back to our breathing it was
very difficult for me to let that emotion go like like I was probably like
blocking the emotion or not letting it feel it completely but once I started feeling it it was very difficult for me
to come back so I just found that interesting mhm and and how do you feel
now at this moment I feel fine yeah I feel good I feel relieved in some way
yeah so that was a little bit of a surprise for you the the crying and the yeah yeah I was not expecting that at
all yeah yeah thank you thank you this can happen right some I like this expression like emotions kind of like
bubble up and they even when we create the conditions when there's some quietness they Bubble Up and there's a
way that I think about it's kind they get metabolized in some kind of way when they get seen
and acknowledged and maybe they let themselves know a little bit more and
then they often just go on their way yeah thank
you so I think you mentioned um that think of what emotions you have
at the moment if you don't know I think you said Leb it's just okay to say unknown I think that I don't remember
the exact words but but you said that that can help a lot because many times I don't know really how I'm feeling when I
look at it and I can't label it specifically as something um that instruction was
helpful I think um my mind automatically labels certain
Sensations in my stomach as bad right it's it's it just has that so feeling
the sensation oh that's bad I need to avoid it uh that that Association seems
very very deep so what irrespective of what I'm doing if that's if that's happening I think it's a bad sensation I
don't know what comes what comes first is it the negative thing in the brain that causes the stomach is it the
stomach that caused the brain or do they happen together that's it's very perplexing it's a fantastic thing to
practice with to get curious about it like what's happening first here is it the sensation in the belly and then the
mind or the mind or the belly it's a great thing to just you know bring some curiosity to not so much that you have
to find the answer but rather than me just telling you something just to like experience and see how it
is and then with regard to having I think I use something like vagueness of the emotion or something like this yeah
it can be helpful to maybe have a sense of um well maybe I'll say this sometimes
I wouldn't like know what I was feeling and I liked this expression out of sorts
just out of sorts I don't know what it is it's just out of sorts so sometimes it would be helpful just to like
acknowledge there's something there but I don't know what it is or there could be some other like uh kind like vague uh
label of I don't know but it's delightful or you know something like
this so there can be and I'll talk about this in a little bit it can be helpful
to have some specificity of our emotions but if there're it's not helpful to try
to figure it out and dig and like oh my gosh I got to get to the bottom of this that's not what we're doing so if it's
just not clear then to be okay with the vagueness but if there feels like there can be some clarity to um bring some
clarity to it is that helpful what I'm pointing to yeah you're
welcome anybody else have a comment or something they'd like to
say question
for anybody was this a new idea to have emotions in the body for me it certainly
was I'm trained as a scientist I have spent my whole life you know bece like
in my mind and then this it was just such a odd idea like what do you mean emotions are in the
body but I discovered that it turns out to be true so bit of a process to kind of like
just uh become acquainted with and I was was maybe back there
while the microphone is traveling I'll just say that um they have they've given like uh a a
pieces of paper that have like a silhouette of a human body and they ask people to color in where is you know
this emotion where is madness where's anger where is Joy where is Envy where is you know just all all these
emotions and there wasn't 100% concordance but there is this general
feeling as I said kind like in the face and in the Torso so if you ask people they can often point to them so yes you
have a beautiful way of explaining this in such detail that it's so helpful for
me especially when you talked about not getting entangled in the
thoughts it's like it gave me permission not to to you know become obsessed with
my thoughts of the day so thank you you're welcome you're welcome I was able to really come down I appreciate it yeah
yeah next week I'll talk a little bit more about this but there is a way in which we think that our thoughts are the
absolute most important thing that are always happening and our thoughts are important
I'm not going to say that they're not but you know so many of the things we think about
you think about them you know the first 1,227 times you think about it is uh
enough we don't have to continue thinking about things so and I think it's like you know holding on to the
busyness yeah right because we're all like working a lot in this area and so
you sit here and you're kind of like oh I'm familiar with this kind of feeling so thank you you're welcome you're
welcome anybody else have a comment or a question or you like to share how the
how that meditation was or maybe all the way you were
here thanks um I I think you asked twice
during that meditation about what was um the emotion that you were
thinking the first time the first time um the motion came up and it instantly
came uh manifest itself into a kind of pressure on my eyes behind my
eyes um kind of the weird light show and darkness and stuff going on and then and
then the second time was um just a um heaviness on my
chest um same emotion but two different ways um that it manifests
itself so the the question I have is in then I was concentrating more on the
bodily the feeling the heaviness and such and not so much on the emotion
anymore is that um is that helping work through the
emotion that you're trying to work through or I guess that's a
question I have this is a legitimate question so I would say that actually
this uh happiness in in the chest for example is the
emotion it is the emotion it's they're not these are not separate
things to have this bodily experience and to have an emotion heaviness in the
chest pressure behind the eyes that's uh emotions they're actually kind of like
primarily bodily experience as it turns out but I appreciate what you're saying
also I think you're pointing to this uh it's not uncommon to have the idea of
like but no I need to um get in there with the emotion and somehow work with
it or understand it or do something with it there's often this idea you didn't
say this I don't know if you specifically have this right this is you know of course
cuz we have you know psychology a lot that's telling us uh that this is uh you know beneficial and I am going to say it
is helpful and beneficial but that's not what we're doing in meditation and it
turns out that these emotions can resolve
themselves if we give them the conditions in which they can I'm not
saying it's fast and I'm not saying it's always easy or straightforward but there's a way in which um the emotions
can I I'll use this word metabolize or shift or change without our having to
get to the bottom of them or completely understand them or connect them to that thing that happened when we were a kid
so I'm uh psychology is helpful and beneficial and sometimes is exactly
what's needed but meditation offers an alternative way and so I'll just share
this and sometimes it's sful to like we don't want to tip into overwhelm that's
not the direction we're going so if we're like it's swimming in this ocean of
grief and like we turn towards the emotion and the bodily experience and it
just this huge well comes up we can see like can we hold it can we
be like wow this is really strong wow this is like just maybe you
you know often kind of like there's these waves like with a sadness sometimes that there might be tears and
maybe a little bit of sobbing if you can stay with a bodily experience that's
great but if you can't and you're starting to feel like oh my God this is too much I just kind of handle it that's
not the direction we want to go it's not so helpful so I would say just open your
eyes feel the pressure against the body like what you're sitting on feel your feet like no I'm here I'm here
now and if it's a particularly emotionally labile time for you it can
be helpful to even before you start the meditation to um look around the room
and like let's say you're in your meditation posture at at home or here or wherever it is and just identify like
some things that are pleasing this like in completely mundane pleasing
I'm looking at this chair it's kind of nice how it has shiny
legs and I'm looking at this cushion here it has this softness to it it feels
like it might be comfortable in some kind of way and and I'm appreciating the
senu of this uh wire that's uh back there on the back wall so these are such mundane things
that we don't usually pay attention to but it can be helpful to like notice some things that are
pleasing mundane and pleasing before we start our meditation and then if we feel
like oh we tip into overwhelm to open our eyes and then connect with these
objects again this is a way to help kind of remind us like no we're here now so
that we don't find ourselves I'm using this word overwhelm I don't
know if there's like tipping tipping into overwhelm I don't know if there's a better word but something like
that so I want to talk about uh another tool that you can use a specific tool
that you can use for working with emotions that can be really helpful so a tool is just like you know
something that's in a toolbx you take it out and you use it if it's helpful if it's not helpful you
just leave it in the toolbox so in the same way this will be this uh idea this
was uh developed by Tanya Weiser who teaches here on Thursdays and Gil
fronto and it has this very nice acronym raft R A
ft and some of you may know like this a raft is what carries you over the flood over to safety this is a common metaphor
that's that's used in Buddhist teachings so raft
or stands for recognize just recognize
the emotion that's happening sadness out of sorts Delight
whatever it is you can use a simple word just a little bit of note yep it's anger
Joy Delight Envy whatever it might be the A is for
allow that emotion is already there you are already experiencing
it can you allow it to be there because it is already there there's often this
way in which we like want to push things away cuz we feel like uh then we'll make it go away or if we ignore for it it'll
go away this is my favorite tactic right I used to like just try to ignore it
always but if we can allow it to be there there's this way in which we are
aligning with the reality of the moment the reality of the moment is that that
emotion has arisen that emotion is being experienced that emotion is
known and can we maybe stop with a often we there's this subtle way in which
we're pushing them away or we wanting more of them or we're getting tangled up with
them instead can there be this movement towards openness and like yes this eny
is here right now it doesn't you can have any emotion
right any emotion it doesn't mean that we're going to jump out of our meditation posture and go out and
express them and I mean we can have murderous rage we can have such incredible anger but we're not going to
act out them we're meditating we're going to stay in our meditation posture and allow the emotion to be known and
felt and experienced so this might be the only
like place in our lives in which we have complete permission to feel whatever
there is to be felt often we feel like you know we should only feel certain
emotions and in certain settings or something like this but you have
complete permission to feel whatever there is include
vagueness of not knowing so just to allow it to be there
this allowing is pointing to having some um for the moment for that just moment
just recognize yep it feels like this and it's here so f is it feels like this and the f is
feel in the body feel the lump in the throat feel
the heat in the face feel those maybe there's a sense of like wanting to get
up and run or something like this restlessness can feel and sometimes in the arms or this leg or the
legs and there's this way if we can rest our attention on the bodily experience
as I've been saying it uh takes the authority and the momentum out of what's
happening in the mind and the mind is making all kinds of stories about oh if
only that thing didn't happen next time I see that person I'm going to do this
or or you know I don't know like there's so many things so we're either rehashing
what happened or planning the future or you know around this or we're saying oh my gosh this means that I'm a bad person
because I'm having this emotion we making those stories it's quite something the Mind likes to take
emotions and really run with them we're just going to let that happen
more in the background and again just turn towards the bodily experience so
feel in the body recognize allow feel in the body and then tea there's two
different ways that we can um think about tea and I'll give both of
them one is to tease apart tease apart
the emotion let's just say it's
anger tease apart the experience of being angry from our ideas or commentary
or or notion about what it means to be angry I shouldn't be angry they didn't
really know that they were being so rude rude and obnoxious and I shouldn't be mad or or you know we just or maybe
we're working ourselves up like oh my gosh I still can't believe this has happened and I'm going to do something
else whatever it is to tease apart the actual Anger from our reaction to the
anger our commentary about the anger often these get conflated and this is
how the Tangled upness happens and the emotions get perpetuated
so just to notice what emotion do we have about the emotion if I'm just going
to make this up again let's say there's anger and then we just have this shame about
anger then we can just turn towards shame that's the new emotion let the
anger do whatever the anger is going to do and then feel the shame oh yeah okay
there's shame here feels like uh heaviness on the shoulders and small little knot
in the gut or something like this so the T can be te's apart the the
emotion from the reaction to the motion and it might be that the reaction is another emotion that's not a problem
just turn towards that emotion and do the same thing recognize allow feel in the body tease apart and you might
notice that there's hatred and then hatred of the hatred and then there's hatred of the hatred of the the hatred
and then there's hatred of the hatred of the hatred of the hatred and off you go that's okay just yep hatred feels like
this so that's one way the tea can be teasing apart the emotion I'm saying
this a number of times because often people will ask me now what what were we teasing apart again the emotion from our
reaction that's one way we can understand te here's a second way we can understand
this letter T Trust
can we trust that at that precise moment we don't have to fix it at that
precise moment we don't have to jump up and do
something because that'll be the impulse often right it's like I I have to make this go away it needs to be different I
have to fix it I got to send that email I have to I don't or we just maybe
just wanted to Simply jump away from experiencing it can we
trust that moment it doesn't have to be
fixed just at that moment it it may get fixed later but at that moment when
we're experiencing it this is related to allowing and something happens when we
can kind of like trust and put down and soften the wrestling that we
do then there's a there some wisdom often
arises when we kind of like open to the experience there's a little bit more space for a new way of seeing
things a new idea a new interpretation something that wasn't seen
before that can really shift our relationship shift our
understanding so trust that you don't have to do anything at precisely that moment maybe you can trust maybe there's
something that's meaningful for you that's bigger than you trust the universe trust your
favorite deity trust in Buddhism we have like refuge in
the Buddha drama and SAA maybe that's meaningful for you is is there that what it's pointing
to here this trust is the movement away from oh I'm feeling this terrible thing
and I have to fix it the trust is moving in the opposite
direction recognize allow feel in the body tease
apart the emotion from our reaction to the emotion and trust it's okay at that
moment our capacity is so much more than we give ourselves credit for it really
is it really is
okay so I'm going to do another short little guided meditation if you'd like to stand up for a moment just to kind of like stretch your legs before you uh
have to sit again can be helpful so we don't
uh get too tense
okay so taking a meditation
posture and I'm going to begin with something that we did last
week and that is just encourage you to bring your
attention to the sensations in your left hand
what the hand is [Music]
touching with the hand but it feels like to have a left
[Music] hand and I'm pointing to the left hand with the assumption that it's neutral
experience for you if it's not neutral then choose another area in the body
what is it like to just
feel the
hand allowing the hand to show itself to
you independent of any any commentary you might have independent of what
you're thinking just the experience of having the left
hand maybe there's tingling
pulsing heaviness vibration
just allowing those Sensations to be
there and then in the same way can you bring that kind of attention
to the emotional experience emotion and
attitude mood might be subtle
as if it were okay for that experience to be
there can you recognize what the emotion
is just use a very simple
label sadness happiness
Delight boredom
frustration can you just allow that emotion to be
there can we just let it be without adding anything to it without insisting
or wishing that it were different
just allowing and then Feeling Again into the
body the bodily experience of this
emotion how does it feel
what are the
sensations and can you tease apart the
emotion from the mental events that are surrounding it
the commentary we might have about it can you tease those
apart can you trust that it doesn't have to be fixed
doesn't have to be different at this moment
and rest attention on the sensations of
breathing for
[Music]
so this idea of raft recognize allow feel in the body tease apart and
Trust doesn't have to be in that order it's a nice acronym but maybe or maybe
you can just be recognizing like oh yeah there's that uh frustration again maybe
sometimes just like acknowledging it is uh sufficient and it just kind of uh
Peters out or there might be a way in which we just feel it in the body first and when
when there's a sense of oh wow I don't really know what this is but there there's a uh something like a tightness
in the chest or a knot in the gut or something like this and then maybe just allowing that
bodily sensation to be there and then there's some recognition oh yeah this is shame or
sadness or whatever it might be so the point here is not to um figure
everything out which is often what we like to do we like to figure things out we like to
understand them they feel more manageable and certainly that has its place but the emphasis with this
practice is to experience them because there's this way in which when we're figuring them out is we're kind of like
shoving them to the side while we're trying to figure them out there's a way in which we're figuring them out as a
way to not experience them or you know we're kind of like a turn moving away
from experience and running into Concepts like oh that must be because of X Y or Z that happened in my life I'm
not saying those things aren't true I'm saying that this is a different way that turns out to be enormously powerful and
transformative to just as best we can to be with our
experience so I'd like to open it up for questions again see if there's any
comments or questions of about what uh I've said so far there's right right
next to you Sally thank you Diana I was wondering if
you could talk a little bit about what freedom feels like um we talk a lot about Freedom when we talk about
meditation uh specifically let's say you're dealing with grief it becomes this thing you carry with you all the
time for a long period of time so I find
that inquiring or sitting with your emotions or noting for instance I was
trying noting today and it suddenly that itself is overwhelming to see how many what a mess you are like
what are the things that are going on inside of you you know um so then the
question becomes okay where is the freedom so I know my emotions but where is that so if you and also about
relating so how am I relating to it really thank you yeah yeah I'll say a
few things about the freedom what happens is uh a few things
one is emotions arise grief it's felt and it's not a problem
it's just grief it's grief it feels like this and it's like it's just it's not a
problem so all none of the emotions are a problem and this is where freedom is it's not like where we have to avoid
anything it's like we can hold we have the capacity to be with
anything and then there I don't then we start to recognize like how much of our life we're trying to make sure we only
have certain emotions and not other emotions but uh with this is we learned
that we can have any and a second way is a big part about mindfulness practice
not just what I've been talking about tonight but just in general is to we start to gain some more clarity and
maybe some seen a little bit more deeper about our inner life and that includes
noticing yes there's a lot of grief for example grief is a natural thing of
course there's grief there's loss when there's human life and there's grief this is The Human
Experience but there's also so many mundane perfectly neutral things that
are happening in our life that we often are just dismissing or there's often even little
Delight the first for me it's the first sip of coffee in the morning I love coffee I just love the first taste just
makes me happy you know just all these small little things that are even delightful we tend to be dismissive of
them so the freedom starts to see like oh yeah there's a lot of
grief and there's other things happening too so we're honoring ing respecting the
grief but we're not letting like our entire uh experience kind of collapse into that does does this make
sense anybody else have a comment or a
question we have this here thank you for asking that question
about Freedom thank you Dona um quick question
on the labeling is it more helpful to label or does it just get you lost in thought or
is it more helpful just to just to stay do you want to share a little bit
what your experience was was this like you well okay
um I think I know what you're pointing to but do you want to say a little bit more so
um so sometimes trying to figure figure it out
mentally that can cause me to you know go on another roller coaster for a long time before I come
back yeah yeah so I would say
um it's helpful to gain familiar for familiarity or for our emotional
vocabulary to kind of increase and what we don't want to do is just as you
described like trying to like oh okay now I have to figure this out does it feel am I this this or that or the other
thing so I know a number of people who have uh spent some time where maybe
you've heard of this I don't know um starting with mad sad glad like okay
maybe it's one of these three it's you know A variation of one of those and they just start with that it's mad it's
not mad and I'm not sad and I'm not glad though or I guess you have to choose one
of those three is a family one of you know an emotion that's in one of those three families but then often there have
been individuals who will um uh look at a list of emotions and say yeah what is
this one feel like not not when they're meditating but at another time Jack cornfield talks about this in one of his
books that uh he you know was uh he was a monk for quite some time in Thailand
and in Burma and then it wasn't until he came back to the United States that he realized that he really didn't know his
emotions at all and he spent time with lists of them and that really helped him to kind of like broaden his uh awareness
of what different things were so this is one way to approach it so I think it can be helpful to have
some uh like I said is it in one of those three families to start there and then
maybe just bring some curiosity throughout the day not in meditation or other settings to have a little bit of a
sense of one's emotions without it having to turn into a big self-improvement project or you know
something like that some maybe to bring some curiosity too so if I could if I
may just have two more followups one is
that sometimes I get like random
feelings that aren't associated tangibly with with some mental formation except
for they cause discomfort right like like I said random feeling exam in in in the stomach for
example in my case uh um so that's one thing the other
thing is sometimes I have this irresistible urge to move and I'm I'm
not able to pinpoint it to one specific part of my body what is it that's just making me want to move right I mean
that's that's another yeah so I'll say that it turns out that they're not so
Random they are emotions and as the mind and the body start to settle then we
start to see connections that we don't see with just our regular mind so that's
one thing and this uh wanting to move there's could be countless reasons and you could just label it restlessness of
we say oh there's this restlessness and then okay maybe that's something you could recognize allow feel in the body
and tease apart restlessness something like that you're
welcome okay so we're a few minutes over I want to let you all go but I'll stay
here if some of you have some questions you like to come up and ask me otherwise I wish you a wonderful rest of the
evening thank you