warm greetings from the Insight Meditation
Center and it's wonderful to come
down from my home to sit here and share the Dharma share the
meditation thank you warm greetings thank you for being
here and there's a
short saying Buddhist saying the shortest version of it in
English could be um for wisdom be
tranquil if if you want to become wise cultivate
Tranquility in fact the terad path of meditation is sometimes called samata
viasa in p and in English that would be tranquility and
insight and part of the function of developing concentration is to have a
good amount of Tranquility so that awareness can do some deep inner work
that's hard for awareness to do if the awareness is hijacked by our reactivity by our
emotions by our preferences and likes and dislikes by the stories that the Mind spins
out and so uh Tranquility is important and there are three different
kinds of Tranquility there's Tranquility of the body Tranquility of the
mind and then separate from those two there's Tranquility of mindfulness
Tranquility of awareness itself
and sometimes if there's can cultivate some degree of Tranquility of body it
supports Tranquility of the mind some Tranquility of the Mind supports Tranquility of
awareness but sometimes that's not possible sometimes the body is agitated
and and uh on fire in some way sometimes it's the mind which is
agitated and maybe on fire for some
reason but awareness can doesn't have to be tied to
the body or the mind and this is the great power and magic of
mindfulness that is possible to know in a tranquil
way the body in any state that's in
it's possible to know tranquil calmly the Mind any state that's in and if the
awareness is tranquil knowing these different things then it's clear that
awareness is not under is not reacting to the body or the mind it's not pulled
into the mood and and agitation of the body and
mind that there's this peaceful quiet
place of knowing of
awareness of observing our experience that
is distinct from what we are
experiencing and it's invaluable to have this tranquil awareness and today the focus is going
to be emotions and emotions drive us
emotions grab us emotions come with authority emotions come with urgency and
desires of in some ways most emotions maybe can be
understood as involving some kind of Desire wanting
something directly or indirectly and so we can get pulled into
them we can identify ourselves with them we can Define ourselves by our
emotions we can judge ourselves by our emotions we can struggling with our
emotions rejecting our emotions trying to hold on to
them and we can know them
tranquil which I propose is very respectful
it allows emotions to be themselves and to do what's inherent to
the emotion that is that it's in motion all emotions are
processes that are unfolding and moving and shifting and changing and passing
through and we get stuck in them we stick to
them and we interfere with the motion of
emotions so to assume a meditation
posture that posture that for you will support you to be alert in a
relaxed way and calm in an an alert
way it could be standing it could be walking slowly
quietly back and forth it could be
sitting it could be lying
down and to gently close the eyes or lower the Gaze
half open eyes not looking at anything in
particular and just sitting this way how would you
characterize your attention the way that you're aware of
your present moment experience
is it more on the calm side or more in the agitated
side does your attention come with a mood an attitude
of wanting or not wanting something of
straining
resisting of reluctance or
eagerness noticing in a very simple
way the quality or mood or attitude in how you're
aware or your attitude about being
aware and then gently
as [Music] you're easing in quietly to a shy
cat ease in to the experience of your body
breathing and in a way that's nice for you satisfying
take a few deeper longer breaths and relax as you exhale
and then returning to our normal
breath let your attention be
open to the experience of the body breathing but some place in the
body where the attention is not straining or
working some place where there's some can be some sense of
ease with breathing itself and with awareness of breathing
maybe some place in the Torso that moves with each
breath but which is not doing the breathing it's a part of your body that
is moved by the process of breathing
relaxing the body as you exhale
and as you exhale relax the mind the thinking
mind maybe with the idea that the thinking mind sits on top of the
body and as you relax the mind it settles into the
body for
and then settling into breathing being aware of the body's
experience of breathing the Rhythm breathing in and out
and then see as you're with the breathing if there's any Center within place
within from which you're aware the place of
knowing the place of directing
attention any place that's associated with doing
mindfulness doing awareness
and as you exhale relax this doing see if you can
shift awareness shift knowing to some other location in the
body in the head any anywhere where there's less doing less
force behind
awareness seeing if you can find a way to be aware
that's tranquil calm
and awareness that is
aware without being involved
with what you're aware of
awareness that has the Tranquility of The Opening space of a
door an Open Door people go
through but the opening is not that agitated doesn't
resist and so an open awareness
experiment with having a moment of
awareness that's tranquil
a lot of small moments brief periods of
time tranquil aware of
this maybe it helps to use a mental
note so you're clear about what it is you're
knowing and the mental note is done tranquil
peacefully e
and then gently slowly become becoming
aware of your emotional state the general mood that you're
in the state of mind
how you're feeling
overall and see if you can know it with tranquil
awareness tranquil
knowing maybe even using a mental label for your emotional
state could be as simple as calling it an
emotion where the labeling is an opening the
door to a tranquil awareness
of your emotional
state for
each time you label name an emotional
state see if awareness can be tranquil for a few
moments until you use a mental note
again for
okay
a cat that goes through an open door doesn't get caught by the door
frame each moment of a of awareness can be like an Open Door
so that the movement of emotions can pass
through without sticking to anything passing
through some moments of tranquil
awareness
for
for for
and as we come to the end of this sitting to check in with yourself
again as we began what's your emotional
state your general attitude state of
mind and how has it shifted from the beginning the meditation to coming to
the end
what difference does it make to you to allow all things to
be but to know them tranquil
and one difference that tranquil awareness could make it can allow us to be more
attentive to the wholeness of other people more attentive to be attuned be
connected to
others in a way that we care for their well-being and their
welfare we would like them to be happy
peaceful where we might
wish for the welfare of others may it be that all our
meditations lead us to Care more for the
people in our lives known and St
strangers may all beings be happy
may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and what a difference we can make if all of us who are here today for this
meditation could contribute a small
piece to the well-being of
[Music]
others thank you
while I'm drinking my water and waiting for the recording to be ready for the next session um if
some of you would like to write uh the explanation or description of uh
what shifted for you in that meditation uh how your attitude your
mood shifted you could be as simple as from X to Y and if there was a
change
e e
wow that's quite impressive to see all these uh little comments and um they're going by so fast
now that I can't see them all but I I'm going to read them carefully when we finish here when I have more
time so good morning good day to this third day of uh their talk on the four
noble truths and the after the first talk on that was
an introduction yesterday talking about suffering today the focus is the cause
of suffering and um when the Buddha talked about the first Noble
Truth uh the way that he described described it is it's uh a
suffering that arises or is constructed by the person who
suffers and um how he describes or defines it the the classic way he talks
about five different ways that we construct um our experience in such a
way that there's clinging and craving involved that we build up a kind of
Cathedral of self Cathedral or building
of of uh of reactivity that the accumulation ends up with one big ball
of suffering and so when we come to the second Noble Truth uh it's the the truth
of the cause of suffering and what one way before I tell you what it's what
that cause is that the Buddha offers but it's important to understand that here
the orientation is what is our contribution to suffering if someone uh walking down in
down the street or someplace steps on my foot maybe even hurts it a little
bit uh that might be uh painful but uh it might be I might get
irritated it might relate to all the different people lately who've been stepping on my feet and I'm just
frustrated and angry um and uh with now
humankind because of how thoughtless they are stepping in my foot and I start spinning out about all kinds of thoughts
about myself and people are doing to me and and how stepping my foot is an act of disrespect and and uh you know I'm
always invisible to people and it just seems like um I'm you know it must be
because I somehow have the wrong kind of glasses and people are I should really get new glasses but I don't know what I
can never make a good choice and I'm such a bad Chooser of glasses and the mind spins out and all these constructs
that can build and create you know huge edifices but it turned out that the
person was maybe blind and uh didn't see you and you actually stepped into their
path and uh you didn't see that they were blind they put a a walking stick
and um and so the whole spinning out was your addition to something that added
something that was not really present at all in that event itself so we can
contribute even though there might be some harm being done step my foot was stepped on we can contribute to whole
layers and sometimes other people are doing things which are uh hostile and
hurtful to us and uh and that should not be uh overlooked or not dealt with
appropriately but even even there we can contribute to the suffering ourselves
and some people see this I've known people who've seen it years later how that their resentment towards someone
was their way of constructing suffering for themselves that that long after the
person who orig the original person maybe even forgot that they existed or forgot the event but but somehow the
repetition the story The resentment is a something we contribute going on so the
particular focus of the Four Noble Truths is not all forms of emotional
pain but the kind of emotional pain that is our that we contribute to and so the
definition the Buddha offers for uh or the simple kind of um explanation for
the cause of suffering uh is called T in
poly t n ha it usually means in poly means thirst and so the idea it's a
metaphor but a metaphor of when we're thirsty there's a compulsion there's a reaching out there's a intensity of
wanting something wanting water and um that can grab us and push us and to do
things and so it's not just a simple desire that arises desires for me are
dime by dozen they can come and I just let them come and go um sometimes I smile when they come and and just shrug
my shoulders and let them pass through and and occasionally they I get caught
in it and um and occasionally when I get caught too much I have uh what comes is
Disappointment or expectation or frustration or or or being upset by
whatever gets in the way of my desire and that but when the desire
becomes strong when the desire becomes strong enough to get in the way of our
ease or peace or calm uh when it takes us grabs Us by the by the nose and pulls
us around uh then what the Buddha this T is U rather than being translated as
thirst into English English translators uh to be more descriptive or more to the
point will translate it as craving and craving is a kind of
compulsive desire where if craving is strong uh we we kind of lose our
autonomy we lose our freedom to um to
the uh to the desire because it it now has Authority it now is in charge it's
now pushing us compelling us to do something uh or at least compelling us
giving us a feel even if we don't act on it it's so such a strong force in the mind in the heart that it churns it
pushes it brings tension it and um and uh and it gets can get so strong that
not only what craving constructs constructs the sense of self constructs ideas and stories about what something
means that but the craving itself is suffering itself there's something about
thirst which is uncomfortable uh when we're really thirsty it is a kind of pain or
discomfort and so the the the cause of suffering in this classic teachings of
the Four Noble Truths is uh a certain compulsive desire that is itself
unsatisfying to have we might be blinded by the object of Desire we might be
enamored with the object there wonderful fantasies about the object or that um or
if the desire is negative like wanting something to go away and there's hostility I want to push it away we
might be caught up not enamored but caught or mesmerized by the hostility
and really caught in the grip and the trance of the hostility so craving can
be for or against something but uh in and of itself
there's tension even there's pain or emotional pain in it when we're grabbed
and pushed like that so this is the definition that's offered by the tradition that uh the cause of emotional
pain that uh to the the our our contribution to the
cause is craving a certain kind of intensity of Desire wanting or not
wanting and and the um and uh and so um we can have a role
because our contribution we can make a difference uh that's where we can make a
difference we can't always change other people uh sometimes other people do do
mean things to us maybe uh say something that feels clearly uh offensive to us
and uh maybe it's something that ideally we should stand up for ourselves and say you shouldn't do that but we don't
always have that ability because of who we are because of situation all kinds of things and so we can't necessarily
change other people but we can change ourselves and and if we're contributing
to the suffering that that part that we're contributing is where we can have the greatest role take the greatest
responsibility take the greatest greatest uh uh uh have the greatest success in making a
difference and it makes a huge difference to be able to turn around and
see how what we're contributing what we're adding that's extra on top of something the way that
we are are tend ing up the way that we're pushing the way we're straining
the way that we're uh uh collapsing or tightening up all over in the heart and
the belly and the shoulders in the mind and um and that's where because
craving this cause of emotion you know of optional emotional
pain is um Can is can be strong can be strong it's often is somatic as well and
that becomes a important way to find relief from it and then eventually
release from it and um by remembering to relax to calm to settle the body and
mind and we can't always settle and relax all aspects of the mind we can't
make pain go away but sometimes we can relax and um and open up and soften
around the edges uh those places that we can relax
we can relax and then eventually we might be
able to offer a presence an
attention uh to be attentive to whatever is going on where the attention has not
been hijacked by craving where attention it hasn't been used in the construction
of suffering the construction of this edifice of of self and stories that we
have that attention has been extricated from all the attachments all
the identities that uh we are caught in so that the awareness itself at least
is not caught the awareness becomes tranquil peaceful still
quiet and in so doing becomes much more
creative much more intelligent much
wiser and uh rather than a tranquil awareness making less of who we are it
actually brings forth much more of who we are from our depths much more the
fullness of what's available and so we come to the the saying that I
mentioned at the beginning of the meditation simplest version is for
Wisdom be tranquil if you'd like to be a wise if
you like to be wise cultivate Tranquility a Tranquility that frees you
from the reactive craving that's seen as the cause of optional
suffering so may you
find the ways in which you get caught in
desires and rather than being identified and caught in
desire identify with something which can't really be the self but still
it's provisionally good to do so identify with tranquil awareness
itself thank you