good morning it's great to be here to be here
at home this is uh uh my home center
and it's been quite a while I haven't been been here in during the morning
Sunday morning so it just really feels like uh I just feel very cozy and
and sweet so
um and so you know with that reflection of you know as I was um reflecting on on
being here today and um what was emerging emerging
to to share to share with you I just had this moment of uh
memories of different teachings and and different
instances uh where it has been wonderful
to to be able to recognize the practice in my life and other times
where it has been tricky he like what is going on you know those moments of being
in a roller coaster and having something reminding me of the
practice and um and and the fruits that that
emerges uh the the fruits that emerge when um when there's a a sense of
confidence and trust and faith whatever however you want to call it in the
practice and one of the teachings that I realized oh in some ways it has been
there accessible or showing me showing me
where where to start or where to go or is the the novel awful
path and so I wanted to share with you a little bit about it um
just because also I think that we're starting or we started already the
program yeah and um it's it it just touches my heart it
just tells me how many times uh it has shown up and how it how it goes deeper
and deeper and deeper in you know in in my life in you
know as I engage in the the practice
um so the eight the eful
path there um is is the is is the teachings that the Buddha offered to us
in the in the Four Noble Truth as part of the four noble
truths and um just to briefly mention on them and
and then go deeper into the hateful path um in a very simple way um if we clean
we suffer that's that's one of the interpretations that I have received
from U my teachers especially Gil uh there's stress there's
suffering and um the one that is being addressed
through the ful path is the one that we add the one that we add as we clean as
we um clean to different aspects of our
lives uh and that clinging is the cause is the cause of stress the cause of
suffering the cause of uh
discomfort and there's a moment that it can
cease why wow yeah that there's a sensation of
suffering that there's a sensation of of
um even some beliefs that we need to be loyal or that we're loyal loyal to our
suffering to our suffering there's a sensation of it and
we feel it we there's something that happens within the practice when when we
continue to engage in this practice that there's a deep understanding a deep
release a deep penetration of of of of that
truth and then there's these four noble truth that I want to talk I want to
share with you the hateful path and I would say that it applies to
all aspects of life is one of those recipes or teachings that you can adapt
to anything anything that is cooking in the pot for
you so um I give you an
acronym Visa LMC Visa
LC and uh um is an acronym for this these um eight factors of the novel
path it starts with wise view continues with wise
intention wise speech wise
action wise life L Hood wise
effort wise mindfulness and wise
concentration and just take a moment just to check if any of these words
resonated for you and just just make a note of that any of these words
resonated more than the other you I talk that about that
later so wise view you know I started I started in the practice thinking
that any way in which I would be in stress or
suffer um was part of me it was almost like a quality like
something like well this is um is part of being
bruny and yes there's suffering in the world there are many
things that um many causes and conditions happening there's
sickness there's um uh old age I'm
sitting on a chair today because my right knee is a little bit tricky
today um and dying you know there all these but there were also other things
that I just couldn't get a grip in it you know all the
identities that you know I would Express in the world all you know
relationships work it was like I'm doing something
wrong and so through the practice I learned about wise
view wise view that uh actions are consequential
and that there is suffering that yes it
happens is is I'm I'm going to get old I'm going to age and I'm going to
die and there are some things we don't we don't have control over but there are other things that we that we do have uh
some agency into setting some conditions that extra suffering what we call
sometimes the the the arrow the second arrow and so wise view help us
understand that things change that things are
impermanent that there's you know not a reason
to solidify you know sometimes when we say oh this never going to change
it's almost like we're living in it in whatever situation it is
huh but when we see how things change and
how um how things happen that you know we
may have some influence but it's not is I'm not controlling how things are
happening you know there's not an independent self if I would wish what this mind would think what this mind
would experience um wow it would be quite something to be
able to choose okay today I'm going to choose to think about this and this and this and this and all that will bring
happiness to me but it's not like that right so there's change there's
inconstancy there's some things we have control other things we don't it's not
like there's an independence self and a vacuum we are interconnected there are causes and
conditions and there's there's Dua in different ways in different
manifestations in this life and with the practice is it's
almost like the the practice become becomes a BAL in some ways
in when we meet these truths these
standings is help is is it's like it sometimes it take at least for me it has
taken me sometimes slowly but surely bruny you're seeing it is sometimes hard
to accept but you're seeing it and no I want it another way and I resist it and
I fight it and I blame and go back and forth and and then at some point this
heart and these mind surrenders surrenders to to that
understanding oh it's true yeah it's happening I have the felt
experience of these four noble truths of this wise view this
understanding and so from there you know in that surrendering there's like a compassion that Stars arising in the
heart some it's been like that many times for
me there's a compassion there's an understanding a
kindness towards uh myself to our other beings
and the second Factor comes in hey why is
intention why is intention is here
wise intention of
um non- greed non aversion of
kindness of Good Will of compassion and of Letting
Go letting go of
renunciation and you know sometimes we just have this
moment in our daily lives we see something or or something is happening
and and out of that compassion there's this
action that arises right um Gil call calls said care
anukampa I like that translation other people call it compassion in action
but there's this quivering this quivering of the heart that that in some sometimes
dissolve this sense of solid self and
like suddenly you're feeling compassion for someone that maybe you were
struggling with or that you love or that you may not even know but now it does
feel like you do know this being is there's this interconnection
there's this Humanity being seen being
felt and out of that compassion there may be sometimes also a
sense of Letting Go and
and a sense of uh shedding shedding all the layers
of the heart a letting go into
Freedom a letting go of the clinging letting go
of okay my
view it's quite something can become very spacious out of the sou but it's
not so sou is you know you're receiving the fruits of the
practice the strength of mindfulness really letting you know Brun
is right here or de is right here you see it
clearly it is like this right
now and we start noticing that the body tells us it's hard to deny
it what feels wholesome and what does not feel
wholesome it's almost a checking in a tune up you know within us like of
alignment if we're disigned if we're struggling with
something so that's a render I like
um aan suito um one of our uh Elders in in our
tradition mentions that compassion arises when
when our hearts you know start seeing start seeing things clearly and there's
there's a sense of even of gratitude there's gratitude that floods the heart
and compassion also arises and what is that gratitude oh my
gosh I saw it it's like Suddenly It's a discovery
you know oh yes it's wholesome oh yes it's UNH
wholesome it's like suddenly we see that there's there's a path there's a path
that we can take there's a choice a moment of
choice and like oh I didn't know I had a choice
yes even in moments of struggle there's a moment of
choice of how we relate to it and how we can relate to
it we can relate to it in a Wholesome Way with kindness with
compassion with
curiosity and so and then guess
what this understanding start being manifested in
US you start talking nicely more you know like like like in more clear way or
a kind way and maybe now you're
like no don't say that don't say that so the factor of wise
speech starts manifesting and that's how I recognize
it there was something in me you know as we as I would be practicing
that would say things that before I would not even
notice that I would be Saye or that you know would cause
harm so there's more um care in how we
speak in choosing the time that will be most beneficial how we say things
and so there's a change we start changing
many times people ask me so especially coming out of
retreat how do you how do you talk to other people about this practice and and
Retreat or the impact that it has had in you well the same way as in daily
life the practice changes you and you start behaving a little bit
differently and people notice and we
notice the speaking is through your actions of body speech and mind but you
know there's something happening it happened to me sometimes with people
will say what so what's going on I say well same as you know there are some things are keep going on and happen in
my life and other things new things and uh some things are okay other things
not so okay and here I am it's okay and I don't feel great today but
you know I'm here or whatever it's like but what is going on I remember my mother asking me but what
is going on there are some people that really have laser you know like no no no
no what is going on so the practice changes you and it will
change it will it will have an impact in your relationship with different
beings how you're relating the
world and so let's see and then we go going to wise action
that I already started talking about and why action actually expands it
give us a framework a
guideline another path of how to act through the five
precepts sometimes eight in on retreat but the five precepts
guidelines guidelines that help us
um support us of being in community support us in our lives in causing
causing um in preventing preventing
harm the the guidelines the precepts the trainings I love tigan used to call is
still calls it the trainings because his
teachings are still with us
so the five precepts of
um um not
killing not um
not engaging into false speech
um not engaging in sexual
misconduct um
and let's see what are the other
um oh thank you not taking what is not given and not Cloud the mind with in
toxicant and so you know when I heard these precepts at the
beginning of my practice it was like there are too many NOS here he's like don't do this and don't
do that and you know there was a sense of
Con well I know that you know I know
that but there are moments just like this hateful path there are moments in
the practice that there are some words that click and there are other words that do
not and at the beginning I show to take the no
out and then make it positive POS you know it has to be positive or something
like that but as I went deeper into the practice wo they were moments that I took that no
back not because it was negative but because it was a
protection it was like don't go there just don't go there and sometimes
we need it sometimes we need a dear friend a Cita friend saying to us don't go
there or hold me because you know I'm it I may
cause some harm so the precepts are like that and
my goodness if we can follow at least
one precept and everyone will do
it sh this will be a different world just
with one you can choose you can choose any of
them I would choose now wi speech you know but all of them all all
of the precepts support support our practice so wise
action I sleep better I sleep better with that precept when I when I review
my actions like the at the end of the day it's like okay how was the day
today and like oh okay this happen oh maybe that okay I do better next time on
this one and okay it's a great it's a great factor of the eful
path and so then we go into wise livelihood and you see how all these
factors integrate each other to live in a way that supports ourselves support
others and support everyone and support
everyone how it is that we relate how it is that we use resources
how it is that we give and receive the practice of
generosity how it is that with think ahead of
time oh yeah yeah how it is that for me keeps me out
of the field of per
Perfection because I cannot
do I cannot do everything I would love to do to you
know to uh
support uh you know billions of people but I can see what I can do in
this moment I can see how my actions could be a domino
effect into the well-being of everyone or a small group of people
or a small group of beings or or the of this planet
and so then we go into wise
effort wise effort and I will be uh brief on this
one because this has been brought up many times in the past teachings
here but it comes to what is wholesome and what is UN wholesome and how it is
that we can we can support what is wholesome and we can decrease what is UNH
wholesome with wise effort we start learning and understanding how it
is that we can prevent and we can abandon actions and habits of
mind that create more UNH wholesome or
unskillful actions and then we have
the wholsome through cultivating cultivating and
maintaining states of mind and actions that support us that bring us peace ease
including ease in the disase ease when what we are knowing is UNH
wholesome but just in that knowing there could be a way a wise way
to relate to what is happening
why is effort is something we tune in is is is is one of these companions in the
practice and sometimes we know okay today we need more I I I need more
effort I need to apply more effort into inclining the mind to a path
of freedom and those moments are moments of
grief moments of struggle moments of
um confusion moments in which we don't have
a lot of energy but there's something that we may
have
and is the conviction in this
practice if in those moments we can
remember how this practice have has supported
us just that memory may be enough to Incline the
mind to shift it just one
degree to reach out to community to reach out to the
teachings to remember our ancestors and the qualities that remind us of our
inner Buddha our beautiful qualities within
us that make us remind also of our
teachers so in those moments in which oh I don't
know what oh I don't know what to do I don't know how to do or how to engage just
remember your conviction your confidence in the practice and just show up on a
Sunday morning or any other day or just click that Zoom
link and then there are other times that effort is just you know not so much to apply
but just to receive the practice letting the practice guiding
us you been you you you start being practiced
and so then we then continue we meet
mindfulness why is mindfulness but mindfulness is in all these factors in
one way or another mindfulness and we see very
basic we can go back to the body wherever you are on retreat at work in
the bathroom thriving eating you name it mindfulness of the body checking in
anytime what's going on here okay touching oh sharpness oh tightness oh
expansion oh tingling okay pleasant
unpleasant neither one I don't know okay feeling
tone was the attitude in the mind oh it's open
Curious yeah there's a little one thing oh there's compassion there's
connection oh and what reminds you this oh I just feel so
happy oh wow what a good fortune oh the Brahma viharas oh interconnectedness
that take maybe a minute checking in with the four foundations of
mindfulness and then it goes deeper that mindfulness goes deeper than we just
naturally start seeing Oh this is wholesome this is mindfulness and investigation working
together and so then we get to the eighth factor which is
Samari or unification collectiveness of
Mind concentration and I will say that this
factor I I I met this Factor this Factor found me as a fruit of this
practice as a fruit of the practice
I was averse to concentration for quite a
while because I didn't like that it will you know like they sometimes it was like
oh I have these moments of being here very present and absorbing what I'm
doing but then it goes away and I'm like that's not worth it w talking about
talking about Corruptions in the in the practice and misunderstanding and
delusion it's just amazing to see how it is that as we
practice with you know an openness of showing up things become clearer and
clearer the the ability to to J just rest in the
breath being nourished at the with the breath being nourished by this
practice wow I thought that coming to this practice was getting rid of
suffering but this other part of being nourished and become wiser and having
more joy and and and a sense of lasting
well-being blew me away it's like oh my gosh this
is much more this is much more that what I
thought so this dear mind is
malleable it's not that you know it's something that is Stu so call
it in one way of being however you call
whatever you call the mind I will not go into details about that but you know
there's there's this this sense that you know sometimes we just put ourselves in
a box and so my encouragement you know
with this sharing of of these teachings is that is is that you know that there's
so many ways in which you can access this practice and if there's a moment if
which you don't know what you know well I don't know bruny those are too many factors well remember at the beginning
when I say oh see if there's any word that
resonates for you just have that list in a love note a
post it somewhere at home look at it and see which words resonates for you and go
there that's the one that's the
one so the noble hateful path a path that support us in
cultivating Sila in cultivating you know with wise View and wise
intention ethical conduct for our
well-being that cultivates the mind and
cultivates also wisdom
is is available to you and some of these factors may be already within your
practice and you don't have to you know I'm offering them now in a linear way
when we start practicing with them it's nice to do it in a linear way but you see what works for
you it could be a circle it could be a triangle of the Eightfold paths I don't
know it's just however whatever works for
you so let me close with this quote from aanu Cheo because is it
it it also complements the full path and is is about conviction and faith and
confidence and this dear
mind this mind can be very fluid and as such can be poured into any
suitable container I just like that how practical
it is you know it can be purred purred in any suitable
container we Pur pour our mind and awareness into the vehicle of faith of
confidence we frame it with
mindfulness and we wield it with
energy we fir met up with Samari so that we can review all things
with discernment I repeat it without
commentary we pour our mind and awareness into the vehicle of
conviction we frame it with mindfulness we wield it with
energy we firm it on up with Samar with unification of mind so we can review all
things with discernment with
wisdom so thank you thank you for your
practice please keep showing up just wonderful that we're on this
path together and we can support each other and celebrate together
too and so there may be time I am losing track of time
here I think it's time right is there time to connect Nancy minutes okay so at least
if you can turn around and say hi to the person next to you just to cultivate
this this this this Refuge of community of s
Jo saying hi I'm glad you're here