hello everyone and welcome to this morning's meditation and uh for this week and last
week I'm somewhat uh connecting the meditation to be relevant for the Dharma
talk I give afterwards the 15minute talk on these 10
Reflections and uh so today the the reflection will be on community
and I had Associated Community with love as been the coraly that could go along
but as I prepared to sit down to lead this
meditation um I couldn't quite get myself
to get connected or to evoke this you know this
uh capacity or interest in teaching about or guiding you in love
or meta loving kindness because uh what superseded it
or what seems to be stronger uh as I bring this to mind is
happiness and maybe there's a connection I hope there's a connection between happiness and love happiness and
Goodwill and so and I don't know which is harder for us for you to connect to
your basic good will for yourself and to others or whether it's more difficult to
connect to a sense of Happiness delight and joy but when I think of community this
morning uh I think of my great delight and appreciation for others it just I
feel so fortunate to live in a world where I have encounters with wonderful people and
and as I've practiced over these years it seems like people are becoming more wonderful the more I get to know them
and the more I'm able to have opportunity to meet them
behind uh they more public Expressions what they reveal most
publicly and um their depths and wonderfulness and I assume in
everyone and the happiness maybe with oneself uh I think I become more and
more of a friend with myself or my mind is more friendly with me or I don't know
exactly what direction it is that sense of kind of certain kind of happiness
with to sit down to meditate and to be present it just
brings a sense of delight and joy
so you're welcome to to ignore my words if the topic of
happiness and the way I present it doesn't speak to you and there's all
kinds of reasons for that some are situational what's happening in your life these
days but to begin the meditation
to as assume a meditation posture that you
enjoy that's nice for
you whatever that might be that you enjoy and is nice for
you to help cultivate a sense of clear attention a
clarity about this moment here if we're too relaxed in our posture it
can be wonderful but it might not be bring the same kind of Joyful
Vitality of something where we're not completely relaxed as much as we can but
we're also not tense a nice balance of alertness in the
posture
gently closing the
eyes and Below or behind the
ordinary flow of your thinking the ordinary preoccupations and
perspectives that are active for you behind it more deeply to
it is there some way in which you can feel a deeper kinship with
yourself a deeper positive regard
appreciation for this person who has accompanied you your whole life in a certain way
you yourself through ups and downs and struggles and
difficulties can you as you sit here in a simple maybe a nonverbal
way sit with an appreciation or
friendliness or a valuing of this person who is
yourself and that meditation is not meant to be punishment
or meant to be demanding of yourself things which
you are not but meditation Beginning by
appreciation and allowance of yourself to be as you
are appreciating
this is there a
way to feel some
happiness of accompanying yourself being in touch being connected
here and now to your
breathing to your
body to not only your emotions right now but for your capacity to feel
and have emotions even difficult
ones and for your mind your
thoughts and so then to
in the midst of
yourself as if it carries with it a wave of appreciation a wave of
Happiness feel the experience of breathing as it moves through your
body breathing with a light
touch or mindfulness with a light
touch maybe with a small half smile
that reminds you that
happiness Delight appreciation is allowed as you meditate
and this happiness of the Dharma it's not something you create or
drive from the control tower in the head but rather it's like a refreshing
[Music] pool that you gently
lean back into to relax and to
feel to breathe with a gentle wave of breathe
breathing
for
for for
sometimes there can be a certain happiness or it may be
contentment from the opportunity to practice
meditation even when it's difficult it's a phenomenally worthwhile
and valuable thing to do in the big picture of things
[Music] maybe better than the alternatives
and maybe there's a contentment or inspiration or
happiness with this opportunity to
practice that guides you into the present
moment here now
and a quieting of the
Mind
for
for for
e
for
e for
and then as we come to the end of this meditation
are there people in your life that you're glad you
know are there people in your life that bring you a sense of delight and
joy and can you can you imagine taking that Delight
Joy appreciation and spreading it outwards
to others so it's not specific or limited
to any individual but something that spreads outwards to all
beings may all beings be
happy and may I may I share my happiness with all
safe and may I contribute safety to
all may I be safe for others
may all beings be
peaceful and may I interact peacefully with
others and may all beings be
free and may I free them from my judgments and
expectations even my needs
allowing everyone an
opportunity to be appreciated and to appreciate
themselves may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank
you e
so today the topic for reflection is
community and to restate what I've said before that these 10 Reflections that
we're exploring this week this week and last week uh were inspired by orientations
that people like Hospital chaplain spiritual caregivers who offer
Interfaith care meaning that they're not prati but they're trying to understand
the people they're with and how they're suffering where their challenges are and that these 10 areas are places where
maybe fundamental needs that many people have and so chaplains will listen for uh
where is it that something is broken or ruptured or challenged for
people and one of those places is community and a community that a person has felt
part of there's a strain there's something that's broken there's a a rip
in the community and it can be very difficult and sometimes people uh who
are chaplains will meet with people who are dying and sometimes the final thing that uh they want to do is to repair
their relationship to others or to their Community or to their family or to a
friendship and um I was surprised many years ago to go visit be with someone on their
deathbed and um you know I I knew that there was a
their death was going to be any hour and I went to visit and the person was still alive enough and clear enough that the
person asked me to be involved in marital counseling in my kind of maybe naive was
surprised that in such a crucial moment the last you know hours of a person life
that that's what they wanted to do but I shouldn't have been so surprised that often the community connections
relationships are so important for people that repairing them um helps us
feel complete or feels like there's no loose ends or you know apologies have been made or
repair has been done so Community begins with
um you know with probably with gestating in our our mother's
belly uh where everything of who we are is really connected and involved with it
a single person and then we're born and and the community is usually fairly
small and um often immediate family and often children are very primarly bonded
to their parents to their siblings to a small group of people and then as we grow up the sense
of community can expand to become the neighbors to become the friends in the
neighborhood to become expanded Network maybe of cousins or it can be an
expanded network of uncles and aunts can expand outward into our
schoolmates to uh the um and so it
expands and expands to be at some point it's maybe the town that we have a sense
of community with the town that we're in and we don't realize it so much until we've moved away and we meet someone
from our town and we feel and how delightful it is to have so much in common culturally and experientially
and then as this process of growing up expands then the sense of or develops
and so Community can become larger and larger and sometimes the community can include people that we don't know and uh
or don't know yet that we have enough in common enough appreciation much value
that we feel like we have a connection to them and we meet them we feel that connection that we have something in
common and um you know someone who went to our same high school who we didn't
even know but when we meet them they feel we feel kind of a sense of connection um sometimes I've been in
communities like monasteries where I felt it was more like a
village and and I didn't have deep friendships with everyone in the
monastery but everyone I felt like were part of was part of my Village and so there there was a kind of a of
a benefit of the doubt or appreciation or valuing or a willingness to kind of
hold them in a wide open heart um with acceptance that um from living the
shared life together so exactly what community is is
maybe not so easy to Define different thing for different people and that the
need we have for Community varies from person to person but it is a fundamental
need for a human being um we don't even develop as a as a
human being without the mirroring the relationships we have with others like
our parents and I for me the representative uh the representation for
that is language that we uh only learn language in community in connection to
others if we decided that enough of this kind of you know you know communal
language we're going to now start speaking our own language and no one else knows then the very function of
language to be able to communicate between people disappears and we learn much more than
just language from other people we learn uh gestures and forms of other forms
non-verbal forms of communication and values and ways of relating and
um customs and a lot of things comes together that uh adds up to what we're
familiar with what we enjoy what we like what we feel at home in and um and so
Community is a a place where many people uh a close Community the kind of
community that really has a lot of value for people often involves a sense of
belonging that now we belong and Community sometimes there's
an expectation that we Community should be easy we should just have it automatically we should be made other
people should help us feel like we belong one aspect of community it has
goes back to the earlier reflection on agency Community is a place where we can
act where we have some agency like we can contribute we can do something and
if it's only one way the community the community takes care of me then um uh I
think that it's much more fragile much more maybe not quite the same feeling of
belonging that has when we feel like we have a role we can
contribute so uh uh so to be a contributor to the community um to give
gifts one of the most classic ways of supporting healthy Community is gift
giving and it can be very small forms of gifts but uh giftgiving helps create
Community um uh acts of listening to others
volunteering doing small acts of kindness um here at
IMC uh one of the ways that uh many people feel really a strong sense of
community is when they start becoming a volunteer um there's other ways of feeling a strong sense of community for
sure it's quite special to just be together and share a practice and the teachings with others who are interested
in it but uh when we can kind of invest ourselves and offer part of ourselves and feel we have that ability that
agency that capacity that's one of the ways that some people help create a
sense of community for themselves rather than being passively waiting for Community to happen uh we are the
Builders of community and um and Community is
difficult social relationships are hard so part of uh being in a community is to
again not expect to everything to go the way we want or everything to be easy but
again to contribute to what does it take to reconcile what does it take to find
harmony with differences and what does it what does it take to um to work
together with uh the challenges we have in community and I've seen over and over
again that sometimes uh uh um community
and sense of connection to others and warmth and friendship and depth of kind of
connection um uh is facilitated by healthy involvement with
the challenges of community life the conflicts that we can have and to really stay there and get to know each other in
relationship to the conflict understand people and understand ourselves and find our way through
it um this is a way of deepening uh sense of investment to a
community sense of value in community a sense of really kind of being
understanding and and and developing a healthy uh sense of belonging because the belonging comes from the work of
helping to create the community and keep it together so of course we can't do that
with everyone but uh it involves many many layers of what we mean by the
community and um you know this year there's an uh in the United States
there's a national election and so what does it mean to be in community with a
whole nation and how do we relate in a way that uh we contribute and support
and work with the differences that we have um rather than shutting down or
creating opposition automatically or US versus them uh because when we have us versus
them we limit the possibility of community of communion of meeting together in Norwegian my
language I grew up with uh the word Community is samun and uh that uh means
meeting together and uh so where do we meet others together whether is there a
meeting of mutual Care mutual support and how do we contribute to that care
contribute to that support so
um um one of the for some people one of the
most fundamental needs and maybe even spiritual needs is a sense of community
and um the sense of having belonging a sense of having
um things in common sense of having a place where we can act and make a
difference a place where we um we um are willing to be in conflict and
find a way it's not uncommon to point out that that sometimes the people we
have the most difficulty with is the people have most in common with somehow our differences and stand out and
highlight and in such a way that small differences uh Loom really big and
sometimes there's you know great Wars between people for you know very slight
differences that from people from far away they can't believe that that's what they're fighting about
and so uh so rather than
fighting uh I kind of one of my definitions for a healthy Community is a
community in which um uh uh the community I want to be in if
I'm going to be involved in conflict and um if there's going to be a
conflict I want to be connected to these people because these people I feel like we can find a way no matter how
difficult the CH the personal and social challenges are that these are the people who whom I I would like to kind of help
find a for us find a way and have the honesty have dedication work work at it
and that doesn't mean for me that it's always the other people want to work things out but uh I have this desire oh
this is the people I want to be in conflict with if I'm going to be in Conflict I hope I don't have to be
so that way uh conflict doesn't rupture the community that actually it's part of the
work of strengthening it developing it making it
grow so um um so for you if you're interested
now you might spend this next 24 hours reflecting on what community has meant
for you what are the challenges what are the ruptures what are the healings what
are the benefits that have that have lived for you in your life and how is
the sense of community your sense of community expanded as you've gotten older has it expanded or has it gotten
smaller and smaller I believe and just my maybe it's just my belief that as people develop
spiritually the sense of community how we hold people in our heart as our
community as our fellow uh humans expands wider and wider
and wider until we have a certain kind of sense that everyone is part of our
community we include everyone no divisions and uh so how does that work
for you has Community for you become narrower has it become bigger in what
ways have you discovered a greater sense of community and greater sense of
receptivity to everyone being part of your community is community something that
you create by how by the quality of your heart or is it something you're
expecting that others create for you provide you I think that um the former the ways
in which we contribute to a sense of community we see and feel as in community with others communion with
others this is characteristic of spiritually mature
people and so what do you think of that so I hope that uh this very
important topic of community his few words has giving you
something to think about and reflect on and uh and I hope as you do it that you
appreciate there are many ways of being a community some of them very unique to individuals so not to have someone
else's idea of how it should be for you but really reflect deeply how it is for you and maybe you'll have an opportunity
to talk to others about it and be mirrored and hear others and and uh
explore this really important topic
community so thank you for this community that we have and my sense of
connection to all of you and and how it creates a sense for me of community
with a wide world out there far beyond Redwood City it brings me great Delight
thank you