hello on this Friday morning hello for this day after for
people in United States day after
Thanksgiving and um perhaps
with whatever good will that exists here in this community
today coming together there's a way of
meditating that even if we Center ourselves on
breathing the attitude of mindfulness the attitude of attention the attitude
is to be open to all things to be aware of all things in all directions
and one analogy I have for this is if you turn on a light bulb in a dark room and if you could slow
down um time to be really really slow you would
see that the light would move through progressively first right by the light
bulb and then it would go further out and it would it would would light up the
objects that are close to it and then it would light up the objects further away and further away
and further away and um and but it would like toot in all
directions of light bulbin kind of an equ equally freely
openly to to touch whatever is there and if it only goes so far because it's in a
room then then it has no problem with that that's the distance it
goes so in the same way I like to think of our capacity for
awareness is like a little light bulb within that rather than directing that
attention someplace we turn it on and let it
radiate let it spread like a light like a lighthouse or something
and let it just take in whatever is nearby now if awareness is centered in
the heart which is the ancient kind of or maybe not so ancient traditional
Buddhist idea rather than in the west we often might think it's in the
brain but if it's in the heart or in the Heart Center and emotional Center in the
Torso the chest then as that light spreads
out maybe it first comes to the movements of the body associated with
breathing it spreads further it goes through the body more
widely maybe in some ways it goes further and notice this thinking and
emotions and if it goes further it goes beyond into the room into the atmosphere
around you and in a sense it just keeps
spreading and your awareness the light of your awareness is ready to take in
anything that comes under its gaze no
problem light light from a light bulb has no problem it just lights something
up so to assume a meditation posture
that maybe has the same attitude of a light bulb that has
no light shade around it open present
available confident in a
posture and to gently close close the
eyes and to arrive at the center arrive in some centered
awareness you might take a few long slow deep
breaths not too full comfortably long
breaths and as you inhale to feel the movements of your body the
stretching of the rib
cage and as you exhale a relaxing a settling
and letting your breathing return to normal and continue relaxing a bit as a
way of settling removing the cover from your
your light
bulb as you exhale relaxing the muscles of your face
as you inhale feeling your shoulders as you exhale relaxing the shoulders
inhale feeling the chest exhaling softening in the chest
inhaling feeling the belly exhaling softening in the belly
inhaling with a broad awareness of your
body exhaling relaxing softening the whole
body
breathing in breathing out gentle
soft feeling the body breathing on the
inhale softening on the exhale
on the inhale feeling the thinking mind on the exhale relaxing the thinking
mind
e
e e
and then centering centering
yourself in the area of breathing
feeling allowing for the inhale to
occur allowing the exhale all the way to the end of the
exhale
feeling the last Sensations in your torso associated with
exhaling that might be the place where the inhale begins
and perhaps you can feel that the light of awareness the little
light bulb is right there where the inhale Hal
begins or maybe you have another place within still quiet
place where the light of awareness can shine be
open equally to everything
where the first thing it encounters is breathing in the
body and whatever else comes into the range of the
light just let it be known with the same
undisturbed quality of light that shines upon anything equally everything
equally allowing your light to spread as far as it wants to
spread
e
for
e e
for for
and then as we come to the end of the sitting to
imagine your awareness is like a
light but a light that is filled with the warmth of Good
Will your good willll in whatever way that that is your
way there's different colors of light some are warm some
are cold some are bright with a warm light of
awareness let [Music] your let that
awareness Spread spread out into the
world spreading to your
neighborhoods your counties your Providence
provinces spread out across the land as if you can gaze upon the world
kindly
as if
every light Ray from your inner
light is a touch of kindness the touches the
world as if you do have the
ability to warm up the world to inspire the world with goodness and
kindness spread your good will out into the
world maybe writing on the wish that you can silently repeat after
me may all beings be happy
may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may the warmth of our attention Our Kind
gaze convey to the world that we want them
well that we care may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank
you
e e
so hello and welcome to the fifth talk on
gratitude and I want to begin with I want to use a couple of quotes from the
sutas the ancient teachings of the Buddha and one is uh the Buddha saying
there are two kinds of people who are rare in this
world the one who helps and the one who is grateful the
ones who help and the ones who are help grateful and they need each
other because there's a circle of giving circle of
receptivity that allows the gift to continue down Through the Ages the wheel
of giving and receiving the wheel of generosity and
care and the wheel of being cared for of receiving generosity both are
important and ideally we play both parts
many years ago I learned that um that uh how unfortunate it is at
times when someone wants to offer a small favor do something to uh say no I
remember once I was going to offer someone a friend to a ride to the airport I was so happy to be able to do it and spend time with my friend and the
person was clearly was very embarrassed or or didn't want to put me out felt
somehow they were a burden and uh said no no no so I finally I kind of let go
and I thought to myself oh this is so unfortunate I had this wonderful delightful feeling I wanted to do do
something for my friend and um and it didn't go anywhere so this idea of receiving and
then being grateful offering gr gratitude and thanks is a form of gener
so so it keeps it going but these two things these are
rare in the world those who help and those who are grateful and I should say
that ideally we play both sides of that when the time is
appropriate I'm inspired by a story that uh or account in the suas of a meeting
of the Buddha with um or the meeting of a king king p
panity with the Buddha it seems like they were the same age they had known each other um for many many years I
think uh soon after the Buddha's Awakening he met uh King p
pacity and um and they were kind of friends uh leaders of in their own
rights and um and so and they knew each other they
died around the same year so they knew each other some from 45 years or so 40
years and um and so near the end of that time uh
the king comes to visit the Buddha and um he bows down to the ground
when he sees the Buddha and he exclaims I am King
panity bante I am bante is kind of like means sir bante I am King panity and I
think in India or in Ancient India especially maybe um it's very very seems
very odd maybe for some people in the United States that you would twice kind
of declare who you are in the presence of a wonderful great person but there's
something about uh the king kind of making it public that yes this is who I
am and I'm bowing bowing down to you fully uh this is a the in the in the
fullness all of who I am is here bowing down to you and
um and the Buddha says why is it that you show so much gratitude and loving
kindness to me to do this so that was kind of a wonderful question why but they the
Buddha describes it as gratitude and loving kindness that he's offering to the king that that the king is offering
to the Buddha and um and uh it's a uh the king
offers a whole series of reasons why he does this but I want to read the first
one it is because the
Buddha basically saying to you it's because you
Buddha uh because you um it's because you
practice for the welfare of many people for the happiness of many
people you establish many people in the noble practice that is the path of the good
Dharma in the way of the wholesome Dharma is for this
reason I honor you with this blaze of loving kindness and gratitude
so um so the Buddha is one of those who
helps people and he received the honor and the
kindness of the King by asking him why is it and so he accepted it and then he let
it continue he heard what the king had to say and maybe he knew this was being
recorded and um and I just love the idea that uh the king would see it this is
what the Buddha is about living for the welfare and happiness of others and as we come to the United
States the day after Thanksgiving um some of us have been
maybe with family and friends for this occasion some have
not and um but it is a kind of kind of coming together and to a small group
often and now it's time to open up the heart more widely now is the time
to expand whatever Good Will whatever thankfulness
whatever love and care there has been close in for yourself for your immediate
family friends your neighbors to now expand it keep expanding and this is the
nature of the Dharma to keep expanding to take love
learn how to love learn how to care learn how to be
generous and um and uh keep it for those
who are close to us don't lose it but expand it open it up wider and wider
there's no limit to how far a light can shine no limit to the the the
360° that the light can shine all around so for us there's no limit to how far
and how all encompassing our love our care our goodwi can be out into the world no
limit to how we to the Gratitude we have for all that supports our life all
that allows us to be uh aware mindful allows us the
amazing opportunity to be kind amazing
opportunity to be generous amazing opportunity to care for
others as we care for ourselves as we care for for our loved ones out into the
world so in this day after Thanksgiving the end of our five days on
gratitude let it serve as a foundation
for spreading our Good Will out into the whole
world and when we don't have that Universal Goodwill
it's okay but don't just don't go along with
it see what it is that gets in the way see what you're doing are you stressed
are you afraid are you angry what's going on for you that your heart is not
open and love yourself in spite of that it's not a
cause for shame or disregard for yourself but that's where the practice
is practice with it because if you do
something inside will shift and change and relax and your
capacity for Universal goodwi in all directions can grow
again you have the capacity it's part of who you are it's a gift for the world
one that the world deeply mean needs may it be that the practice that
you do of mindfulness meditation the Dharma may it be that
it that your practice includes practicing for the
welfare of many people for the happiness of many people
establishing people in the good in the
wholesome and may that good and that wholesomeness spread to every corner of the universe
may all beings be happy thank you very much for this week
and for today and for what's coming in our YouTube
Community very much appreciate it and I'll be here on Monday again thank
you