so welcome those of you who don't know me my name is Kim Allen and I've practiced
and taught here for a while and I'm happy to step in for Di this
evening I want to start with a story that I heard um about that was that was
told by another insight teacher named guy Armstrong and I heard it from someone else so I might not have the
details exactly correct but you can just take it as a teaching story and the story is that um guy was
practicing in Asia and was ordained as a monk while he was there at one of the
monasteries and he was asked by the Abbot of the monastery he'd been there
for a while and you know kind of was getting to know how things were going
and so you know that that's when Abbott start you know giving you little tests
and little things to do as a monk so he asked him guy to give some instruction
to the other monks and um so he was having this
gathering with them and he was teaching some some new monks and he said to them so what would
you do if you had a lot of anger come up in your
mind uh and the monk said I would note it this is a kind of practice where one
basically names what's going on and experience noting practice we we teach it here also and you know you just sort
of note in real time what's going on in the mind oh there's anger oh there's a body sensation there's the breath you
know it keeps the mind on track so they said very duti and correctly I would
note it and he said well that's great and what if that wasn't enough and the
anger kept coming back and they said I would note it
again and he said okay and what if you're sitting there and it just keeps
coming back then what would you do and they said
uh so there was sort of a dir of op ions in their mind now noting practice is
very good and also you know basic mindfulness practice that we teach where you know you be with the breath except
if something comes and distracts the mind in which case you acknowledge what it is and then come back to the breath
you know these are all very good instructions and will actually take you very far if you follow them for a long
time but uh there are other options actually and in fact it's a fairly
common question that we get as teachers where people will raise their hand and say when should I just be with an
experience just be with it notice it note it and then go back to the breath
and when do I get to actually do something about it and it's usually uh people who want to do something who ask
a question like that and so um it's fair enough you know we don't want to be like
the monks that didn't know any option except noting what was happening in their experience
it's very good it'll take you a long way and you don't want to spend a lot of time doing other things but um sometimes
that those mind States just aren't changing right they're very distracting and they're coming back and coming
back so sometimes we do take action and the Buddha taught um a number of methods
that we might apply in cases like that but here's the catch
is that we take specific kinds of actions um in order to help deal with a
mind that's doing its Antics let's say everyone's mind it's very normal to have
things come up again and come up again and come up again sometimes just repeatedly in a Sit you know like my
mind's just really restless right now and so a lot of stuff keeps coming or other times you know notice over over
weeks or months that you have a similar pattern that keeps coming keeps coming
sit by sit by sit and you start thinking huh I'm getting a lot of that one recently so either way we have some kind
of a recurring pattern and it's nice to have a sort of a toolbox of approaches to be able to
work with different things coming up in the mind partly because that's just normal like like the way we would have a
number of different ways of inter acting with people right because there's a lot of different kinds of people so that's
useful not to just have one way so in the same way we can have this toolbox
but it can actually be a little bit more appointed than that also um from one of the discourses of the Buddha he said um
whatever a person frequently thinks and Ponders upon that will become the
inclination of their mind whatever a person frequently thinks
Ponders upon that will become the inclination of their mind it's true
isn't it so what we practice sticks over time if we are frequently thinking a lot
of irritated thoughts we become more inclined toward
being irritated if we frequently think judgmental thoughts about ourselves for
example or about the world then that becomes the usual
climate that we're living in that's the weather we get every day if we practice it enough and it works the other way too
if we frequently think thoughts of gratitude and care for other
people then that will become the inclination of our mind what kind of mind do you want to
live in so it's important not to just
dwell in unskillful thought repeatedly
if we can be mindful of them first of all it's good to know that if we can be mindful of them if we can really note
them like those monks were saying then it is actually okay if you are mindful
of irritation in the mind you're not you're not driving the trench deeper and
deeper you know the the inclination deeper and deeper if you can truly be mindful of it but often we're mindful of
it a little bit and then we get drawn right back in and we're like yeah that's right I am are irritated about that oh
right I'm supposed to be mindful and all the times when we're not mindful we are strengthening the
irritation so um it is important that we have that mindfulness and if we're able
to just stand back and be mindful that's a perfectly good practice um so we don't need to jump at every you know be
concerned about every flicker of aversion or desire or restlessness in the mind if we're noticing that that's
what's happening you're good don't worry um but nonetheless um it is nice to
consider some of these other actions we can take if we keep getting caught again and again and there's quite a few of
them named in the suas so I thought instead of trying to do like a General survey it would be interesting this
evening and maybe more meaningful to take a little bit deeper dive um and
just focus in a little bit so what we're going to do is we're going to talk about one technique that's very useful and
then within that one technique we'll look at a particularly common instance of how to use it one that I suspect we
can all connect with so the the technique I want to share a little bit about is investigating the conditions
that are behind a pattern or a tendency that we've noticed so this is an
alternative to just noting it noting it noting it why don't we investigate what's going on with that repeated
pattern so um first of all uh as I named in the kind of the general uh title of
this investigating the conditions behind an UNH wholesome pattern or tendency so
we have to be able to recognize that what's going on in the mind is wholesome or UNH
wholesome and that's kind of the top level wisdom that we have to be able to
apply so what what do I mean by UNH wholesome so that means something that
is springing from The Roots what are called The Roots the three roots of
greed hatred or delusion those are just kind of the names given to the the
places the places in our heart that these unskillful or UNH wholesome or you
know negative kind of mind patterns come in from and each of those is meant to be
kind of an umbrella term that talk that can can covers a lot of territory so you
know kind of the umbrella term of uh the middle one AV verion greed hatred
delusion hatred let's say or aversion uh covers any kind of a negative response to something from mild
irritation to resistance to anger to unkind judgment
all the way up to like rage and hatred so it's not it's not just one thing it
has a lot of different shades so um I named I kind of Drew out that
middle one because that's the one we're going to look at a little bit more carefully but you can imagine then maybe
what the Spectrum around greed would be you know attraction compulsion grasping
desire these kinds of things and delusion you know confusion
uncertainty um ignorance those kinds of things so then the other thing that I
named about this technique is that it's about investigating these UNH wholesome States what do I mean by
investigating so this is a word you know it's one of those dangers we have in Buddhism is that sometimes we use a very
common English word to mean something kind of specific and and yeah more
specific within the Dharma practice so I say investigating but usually we think of
investigating as kind of a a lot of thought and maybe a pointed probe at
something where we investigate all the way back into the past you know like why
did this pattern begin where back in my distant history did it get inculcated in
me that I should think in this way oh I remember it was that person who told me
so many years ago Etc um that's there's a place for that kind of Investigation
often that's what's done uh in Psychotherapy for example is to kind of tell a story about how we got to this
State um and that can be valuable but I want to name that um the
kind of Investigation that's meant uh as a kind of a Dharma investigation that we
would do maybe during meditation with a repeated pattern doesn't really involve
tracing the story back into the past it's like a present moment
investigation where we understand that if something is here right now things don't appear randomly in in the mind or
at least they may come in for reasons we don't know but they don't hang around randomly in the mind there must be
conditions that are supporting them in this very moment kind of like the way if there are clouds in the sky there have
to be the conditions present right now for clouds right otherwise there wouldn't be them there so if we have a
lot of irritation coming up again and again uh there must be conditions in
this moment that are supporting that so we would want to look at those and maybe if we understood those supporting
conditions maybe we could work with those instead of hammering at the irritation again and again which doesn't
seem to be going away what if we took away the conditions this is a little trick in meditation and in Dharma
practice in general is you don't always have to work directly with thing what if
you could just remove one of the like like taking the leg out of under a table
it will collapse right so instead of working so much with that we could pull out one of the things that's supporting
it so it's actually less important to know
in light of that it's less important to know the whole storyline about how we came to be a person with a lot of
judgment in our mind than it is to know that this particular instant of judgment is being supported by several conditions
in the present moment um so aversion is definitely
worth investigating in our experience that's the one we're going to focus on let's focus on that middle one aversion
having aversion or irritation or hatred or resistance in the mind doesn't make
you a terrible person just let's just say that right up front it doesn't say anything about you as a person um these
mind States just kind of come with being a human being you're born a human you have the three unskillful roots in the
heart and we can work with them the great thing is we have a practice and we can deal with them and we're in a good
position then to to be looking at our irritation of various
kinds so um the Buddha also said that Dua which
is any kind of suffering and definitely we know that aversion is some form of suffering Dua is to be understood so if
something is bringing us duka like our our anger or our judgment then it's worth looking at that
it's worthwhile so I want to focus in on this aversion
thing on even a little bit more this is a deep dive tonight I said right let's
look at the specific case of being attracted to aversion and you might say
what these are the Terrible Things of the heart that are the UN un wholesome Roots I want them eradicated from my
heart and yeah we can get on board with non-harming and kindness and care but
actually um I'm going to suggest that there are
ways in which we are attracted to aversion we kind of like our aversion and what's going on there
what's going on there it's not often talked about really explicitly but I
certainly see it in myself there's ways in which I'm subtly supporting the a in
my mind sometimes um and it's also not entirely our fault so again if you're
starting to think uhoh I'm a bad person I do secretly like my aversion consider that it is actually
supported in our society there are ways in which um it's completely socially
acceptable to have all kinds of judgment hatred look at social media you get so
many more hits if you write about some thing that you hate and how awful something is and or you point out how
stupid something is that you saw and everyone's like yeah that's right you know they give you a whole bunch of
likes for that or they you know in our in our public discourse a little bit more seriously you know there's a lot of
polarization right now and it's really it's supported you know it's considered okay and even acceptable and even you
know you get you're you're sort of a more robust person if you have something that you're out there charging against
and hating great not great actually um not so great and it's
important to be aware of attraction to aversion in ourselves and around us so
that we can choose not to participate in it it's not good for your heart it's not
a good thing to feed in the heart you may not be convinced of that yet if you're sufficiently attracted but
I'm going to keep talking about this and we'll we'll see as we go
along so this is also not only our society let me say that one more time to
emphasize it's not our fault it's not something we need to you know that it's coming in from many ways the Buddha was
sometimes asked to teach What's called the dhma in brief someone would come to him and say please teach me the dharm in
brief I'm about to go off on Retreat just just give me some kind of nugget to practice with and um I think it's great
they asked him to summarize like all of the Dharma briefly but he did it you know each time somebody asked him that
he did give an answer it was he there's over 40 sutas where he discourses where he um does this and in one of them he
said it this way let go of desire for anything that is Dua that's what he told
the person before they went off on Retreat let go of desire for any anything that is
Dua so it seems that the Buddha knew about attraction to aversion or desire
for dooka that would just you know attraction to aversion would be one example of
that so how about in your own mind just take a moment to think are there ways in
which you actually feed aversion sometimes maybe just sometimes supporting it to keep coming back
again it does take some clear seeing to be able to see that in ourselves and
some honesty so I hope I've set us up well enough that you won't feel uh
averse to doing that investigation and seeing if there's a little bit of like there one nun I knew um talked about how
uh in her practice she would often see in in her language she said I see a big fire burning in my mind and I think wow
where's this fire coming from and then I look just off to the side and I see that
there's a part of my mind throwing wood on the fire just off stage and I thought yeah this is um this
is true are there ways that we're throwing wood on the fire of aversion so it's interesting to open to this you
know we we like to dislike things we like to be judgmental of them and to protest
their presence in the world and declare that they should be obliterated aversion feels
powerful doesn't it feels power it has a power to it there's a a strength that
comes from knowing what you think shouldn't be there and being able to say that there's also kind of related to
that um a kind of a crystalline Clarity to a verion it doesn't have any
muddiness about it when you stand up and say no this is not the way it should be
there's a feeling of orderliness it's complete it's tidy and it's
Justified so there's a lot of um kind of this kind of energy can be around a
verion and it can it's a pleasant kind of energy it's it's attractive to feel powerful and clear in the world but does
that have to come from a verion no there are other things that are powerful and clear also wisdom for example or
compassion sometimes um but I'll offer just a specific
example since we're talking about specifics is that a very common pattern
in our society that is supported is what I like to call bonding through mutual
outrage I've talked about this before so if you've heard me say that before uh
please allow me to say it again and if you haven't it's a great one to learn bonding through mutual outrage so this
is this is like where one person people know two people know each other and one of them says did you read about
such and such today can you believe what happened about blah blah blah you know
something that's maybe just happened in the news and the other person says I know it's just terrible isn't it awful
and the other person says yes it's just amazing that such and such keeps going
on and there you go you're bonded together you're enjoying your shared values all shared around the hatred of
how awful this stupid thing going on is bonding through mutual outrage anyone
participated in that ever yeah so um
it's very seductive you know it's very seductive when somebody that we like and that we're connected to and that we care
about baits us with this kind of conversation we want to LEAP right in
yeah great I get to hate what I hate I get to be connected to my friend it's like a double benefit
it um so It's Tricky um and it can take
some strength if you decide you don't want to be feeding that aversion in your
heart which you are when you participate in that um you you need to find other
ways to connect with that person something even needs to be said maybe in that moment or you can try to divert
skillfully but you know bear in mind that there is a cost to that and then
later in meditation you wonder why these aversive patterns keep coming up well bonding through mutual outrage is one
way that we feed aversion in our own heart so it does keep coming
back another way that we like aversion is um often people use anger as a
motivator you when they think oh you know this is of course I have to be angry I have to be judgmental about this
that's how I go out in the world and do my work you know I'm my thing in the world is that I'm against such and such
and I'm trying to create a better world in this certain way and that that's because I don't like this thing
happening so if I didn't have that what would be my
motivation I think if we do this repeatedly maybe we forget that there ever could be any other motivation for
taking action in the world for making the world a better place for standing up
for what matters but there are other things that are better compassion being
one of them wisdom so there are so many other things that could serve as a foundation for
Action the Buddha said anger or reversion has a honey tip and a poison
root and I think we can start to understand that in our relationship to it so the honey tip is the part that we
like of course we're attracted to the honey but we don't realize we don't maybe notice that down below it's rooted
in the aversive UNH wholesome root in the heart so you'll need to check out
your own mind to discover which ways you're attracted to aversion um but that would be part of
the subject of our Dharma investigation so we we can look more clearly if you
think this pattern just might exist in you from time to time you could investigate more directly in your own
experience okay what specifically is going on for me in those moments where I'm attracted
to aversion and we would want to do that uh kind of in the moment where it's happening you know it's we could think
about it reflectively uh outside of meditation and that that would be okay if you weren't on the cushion you could
sort of ponder about that sometime but it's also nice to uh look in the actual
moment and see okay the aversion is here the clouds are here what are the atmospheric conditions supporting it the
the attraction to aversion is here what's supporting my attraction to that
aversion in this moment so I'll offer you know basically what's in it for me
what what benefit am I getting what's the honey there um so I'll offer some
that I've noticed um and you can see and I'll Al offer some uh ways one or two
ways that we could connect in if it's not uh so clear to us how to do that so
A big one is that um is kind of emotional Comfort if if we are
frequently thinking aversive thoughts that's kind of the climate in our mind remember I mentioned that that's how it
can be we actually just like what's familiar so we don't really like the
aversion but we like its familiarity that can happen feels like me feels comfortable to be complaining
that's what I do you know I like to complain about this not because I like complaining particularly or maybe I do
but it's comfortable feels like me so there's actually some emotional Comfort
related to this trying to attain safety or Security in some way if I resist this
push it away I create a safe distance right and then there's some emotional Security in having that distance from
what I don't like um by the way it's not a very secure
kind of safety there are other kinds of safety that are a lot more reliable and
durable um but we create kind of a weak false safety through aversion so we can
be attracted to that not very safe safety another thing that we do which is
really kind of embarrassing is that we do entertainment you know we entertain ourselves through being uh averse to
things it's fun because whatever Target we've chosen in our mind like
complaining to our neighbor or telling off our child or whatever it is they're
not there to respond and react and defend you know we just get the one side of the conversation so why not we can
you know we can just go at it um again not a very wholesome kind of
entertainment and probably the biggest one though is that we might notice in
our invest instigation is that we're bolstering some kind of self-image or a self
story about you know being a person who is opposed to this and therefore I'm I'm
attracted to being able to set myself up as looking that way um someone once
asked me what it means to identify with an UNH wholesome mind State like a version I would say that it means that
we wouldn't know who we are if we weren't in ing that mind State there are
people who would not know who they are if they didn't have their hatred and their anger or their irritation or their
judgment and that's pretty scary so you're avoiding it's not a it's
not attraction then to the um some positive feeling it's the avoidance of
the fear of not knowing who I'd be if I weren't angry so there's an attra
raction in a sense there attraction to avoiding the pain of not knowing who I
am so check it out if you're resisting or pushing away or being irritated do
you think that's who you are who you just need to be in that
moment so that's all that all could be somewhat cognitive so I want to point
out that a a a clue instead of going too much into the
into the thinking about it is to bring it into the body this is a way to bring together all
the things I've talked about so far in the body we can feel the honey tip of
the aversion we can feel the sweetness of it and the power and the energy that
flows it's a very bodily energy when we rise up and feel that aversion so we
feel the attraction really quite literally but we also feel the body doesn't lie
and if we are willing to open to the whole feeling in the body we will also feel the cost in the cost benefit
analysis we'll feel the poison root so in the body we'll feel that aversion is actually a tense state it involves some
closing down some tightening up in some way uh it also involves kind of a stress
a feeling of stress because we've set ourselves up against something um and then there's can even
be kind of a narrowing feeling in the mind or a darkening so um this is actually what
guy Armstrong told the monks to do when they kept saying I would note it I would
note it again he said maybe you should try investigating if something keeps
coming back and back and back and you can do that right on the cushion by
opening to it in the body you know really feeling uh what that feels
like so these patterns in our mind things
that are particularly like sticky enough that we've become attracted to our aversion
for example that's kind of a tangle is if you have something that's UNH wholesome the aversion and you've
wrapped it in like a grasping to it um that constitutes the beginning of a
tangle and then there could be other threads in there right I named self-identification I named fear um
coming in so if we have these things that have gotten kind of bound up uh we
the Buddhist called it by the technical term a tangle or a knot and that is one of the
reasons that they keep coming back either repeatedly in a sit or if you notice repeatedly over weeks or months
or years for that matter uh we might be dealing with what's called a KN and so this
investigation can be done gently and repeatedly and maybe we would just look
at one strand of it at a given time so I'm I'm encouraging you not to feel like
oh that's it now I've got to figure it all out in this moment Kim said to investigate my Avers my attraction to
aversion I'm going to work that all out figure out the puzzle and and that's it by tomorrow I'll be done with this one
it might take a little longer than that um but this gentle approach where we have some ways of investigating in the
moment you know some ways of looking in the body considering the benefit for us
what's going on with that and then maybe going back just to being mindful just be mindful name it note it
like the monks be with it for a while and then if it seems like oh maybe I could look at
that again a little bit more carefully kind of a a gentle back and forth is
like the way we gently work on a tangled knot you can't just say okay that's it
I'm going to rip it all apart we might have to sort of tug at it a little bit be with it hold it underwater let it
soften a little bit so consider this kind of Investigation a long-term project not something that you're trying
to figure out but a long-term project where you let the Dharma kind of help you work on it
be with it look at it a little bit then go back go back to the breath note it
note the breath maybe look at it again maybe we'll look at it next
Retreat slowly over time we are empowered in our practice to take on
even some pretty pretty big Tangles even the fact that we like our
aversion and hence we don't really want to get rid of it right away
so I hope this has helped you to have a sense that there are many options with
how we work with uh our mind and that some of the stickier patterns that might
have several different strands to them uh can be slowly untangled over time as
long as we have a bunch of tools in our toolbox and I hope I've offered several tonight that might be of interest if you
have this particular pattern of attraction to AV verion which is common in our
society the world needs people who are not as attracted to AV
verion so it's nice to leave some time for discussion especially with a topic
like this that I hope appeals um or connects with I saw some
nods about this one so I'm curious what what did this bring up for you do any of
you have attraction to a virgin have you worked with it in certain ways do you have questions about what I talked about
yeah thanks and you could wait for the mic so that you can uh be
heard is there a skillful way to not like something because I know like for
me like um at a certain point my life I started a 12-step program right I really
didn't like the fact that I was acting addicted so it drove me to 12 steps which saved my life so is there a
skillful way to not like something well definitely we don't have
to like everything at all um sometimes there can be an impression in spiritual
practice that um we're going to eventually come to just love everything
and be and approve of everything and accept everything well there's a way we have to accept everything but we
definitely don't have to love like everything so one way um is that I said
at the beginning there was this distinction between wholesome and un wholesome and things that are genuinely
UNH wholesome then we have these ways of working with them we're still recognizing that they're UNH wholesome
so that's actually wisdom is to know what's wholesome and what's UNH wholesome being addicted to substances
of any kind is definitely UNH wholesome we wouldn't want to uh decide that we like that in some way um but there's
maybe you discovered some subtlety through the 12-step program is that you can accept through the practices are
offered there you can accept that there's this addiction um that's somehow gotten into
your being um and yet there's there are empowered actions you can take that put
you on the wholesome side of that so you're not definitely not approving of
you know addiction as a way of being um but you're you're instead finding a way
to then turn the Mind towards something positive empowering a way of being in the world that doesn't rely on
that so I think you you you you did it yeah no what drove me to it though was
the intense dislike of of what I was doing yeah that was the so what would
you call that what would that be called I see I would call that um an early form of wisdom where you you realiz you knew
it was UNH wholesome and and so uh the mind the deeper the deeper sense was the
wisdom of this is not working I can't keep doing this and you didn't yet know
the skills of of how to deal with that uh in a way that you know that was wise
let's say or that was positive so what your mind did was it produced an aversion that got you to something
better so um there is there is wise
turning away from things and that's what you were doing so I call it wisdom Turning Away wise Turning Away wisdom
compassion renunciation has a flavor of this so but is that a dislike or is that
not a dislike why he turning away why is turning away is wisdom
yeah yeah these English terms like you know like and dislike are fairly um
vague terms so I would put a little more Precision on it to say that was wisdom
yeah good
job thanks thanks for your talk I I I really resonated with
recognizing uh the pleasure of aversion and I've examined it a lot um in my
practice and I've know noticed that uh maybe two things one uh the
motivating force is related to um as you said distancing from something unpleasant uh false or weak sense of
security from something is not pleasant and that the feeling of aversion is very
closely tied or almost superimposed with the unpleasant feeling
tone of a stimulus an otherwise benign stimulus a sound a
sight oh has a feeling tone that isant
unexpectedly unpleasant or it shouldn't be it's a benign stimulus but it's has an unpleasant feeling tone and then with
the unpleasant feeling tone there's a immediate superposition of this shouldn't be there
the aversion and then and as you said the aversion is a way of managing the unpleasantness mhm that's good
investigation so thank you the question is ultimately is the goal to dissolve
the unpleasantness of a stimulus or is unpleasantness just some stimuli or
unpleasantness and the practice is to accept that that's a good question um so
the feeling tone of experience is what you're talking about Pleasant unpleasant and neither Pleasant nor
unpleasant I'm sorry to say that we continue to have all three even after
we're fully awake I don't know that personally but the Buddha um had back pain for example which I assume was an
unpleasant feeling tone for him because he would say I'm my back hurts too much
you give the Dharma talk tonight he would say sometimes to his monks um so I
think the unpleasant feeling tone is going to continue and that definitely our uh our aim then is to be able to
relate to all three feeling tones in a way that we don't get entangled with them so when the Mind jumps on a verion
that shouldn't be there that's uh an unpleasant an unskillful relationship
with an unpleasant feeling tone so there are various approaches to you know trying to change that because you're
suffering when you start saying that shouldn't be there it is there right so the first one that we're usually taught
is acceptance so at least start with okay you know accept the unpleasant
feeling tone God thank you yeah I wish I could say
that it'll it'll end up being completely Pleasant I don't think so I guess I just wonder because it's an
unpleasant feeling tone associated with benign stimuli things that maybe you know
arbitrarily negative feeling tone um the negative feeling tone is not the
skillful the unskillful contribution the negative feeling tone is just the world
the unskillful contribution is the aversion in this case yeah you've yeah you've put a version on top of an
unpleasant feeling tone so the the Nuance that comes is that our our
feeling tone respon feeling tone is coming actually in your mind it's a it's an interface between the but there's
nothing inherently you said benign right there's nothing inherently unpleasant about that so your mind
decision that that's something unpleasant can that be worked with not really directly we tend to we get
feeling tone right with contact so who knows why your mind decides that's unpleasant person next to you might
think it's pleasant we don't get a choice about that necessarily but over time we do we do generally have a shift
through practice is that the mind starts deciding more things are neutral than uh
it used to but we don't really get to choose that it's not area that we work with directly great thank you
yeah thanks thanks that was a good talk I
liked how you were picking apart the various reasons why we might have this feeling of aversion and the reasons that
you gave for those made sense it's something that's bonding us with other people it's making us the attraction to
AV verion yeah why we have the attraction to it yeah one of in kind of
reflecting upon some of my own aversions one of the things that I noticed is that
I can sometimes have an aversion to something someone else is doing because it's a reflection of something in me
that I'm uncomfortable with and kind of this self lothing and I was struggling to come up with what's a good reason for
that so that would be part of the one where I talked about the um self-image
so you're actually just talking about aversion not necessarily attraction to aversion well well it's it's you're
you're protecting a self-image so you have a self-image of I don't want to have this part of
myself I'm trying to not I'm trying not to see my shadow essentially somebody
else is making me see my shadow by enacting it and then it resonates and I know that shadow is there but I don't
want it to be so if I'm averse to them I get to I it's just the same as being
averse to that part in myself I get to kind of pretend that it's I'm I'm pushing it away it's this safety through
distance kind of thing and you've Tangled it up with a self-image so it's got two of them in there that's why
these things are called Tangles yeah so but the way to work with it is now that you figured the the
figuring out part is really only at the cognitive level so um touch into that in
the body like what do it feel like in you when you see that being enacted and you you know that's part of you can you
actually instead of worrying about them turn that lens around and be like wow
let me look at that part in me what happened what is with that part like
where's the friction with that maybe you start to have compassion for that part
or at least feel the pain of rejecting it within you and not be willing to put
up with that pain anymore yeah I would say go to the body
yeah thank
you okay good all right thanks everyone