hello everyone and
welcome and I'm quite happy to be back here after being gone for a
week and grateful for David Lori who tght for you all yester last
week so I was on a retreat teaching Retreat
which was quite lovely at our Retreat Center in Santa
Cruz so um I think probably most of you know
that um the the poly word the Sanskrit word
Dua is which is often translated as suffering it gets translated other ways
as well and uh one translator Tanis raiku translates it as stress and one of
the benefits of stress is that um uh
even things which are quite bring a lot of happiness and joy can simultaneously
be stressful and um and so the example that's given is uh
a wedding someone getting married is a quite a joyful event but at the same time it can be stressful
and and um and also uh stress can apply to small things small degrees of anxiety
small degrees of resistance of uh whereas suffering is a big word
and uh people sometimes associated with the major catastrophes of
Life the word that uh sometimes I prefer or enjoy and Delight in as a translation
of Dua is unease and that has some of the same benefits
as uh stress and perhaps that it's more Universal application to feel
uneasy and uh then the opposite is uh
ease ease and unease to feel easy and feel uneasy
about something and uh in meditation those two can be a Wonder ful guide for finding
our way in practice and wonderful way of discovering for
ourselves uh the Dharma path so that'll be the theme for this
morning's meditation and uh so we'll
begin and uh to
um assume and meditate ation
posture or sometimes I like to say enter your meditation
posture if you're familiar with the meditation posture it can be kind of
like putting on a comfortable some comfortable soft
clothes and to
lower your gaze and perhaps close your
eyes and to gently
modestly take some deeper breaths that fills your chest maybe even
your belly expands
and as you exhale to relax the
body as you exhale kind to settle into your seat
into the place where you're meditating
as you exhale let the weight of your
body be received
by whatever holds the body up from the pull of gravity
and letting your breathing return to normal continue to
relax relaxing your body with the idea that you're putting your body at
ease that meditation is a continual process of find finding our
ease in our body our mind our
hearts maybe on the inhale to feel the muscles of your
face and on the exhale to relax the muscles in your face
feeling the muscles of your
shoulders to relax your
shoulders as you inhale to feel the muscles of your
belly and as you exhale to soften the belly relax
as you inhale to
feel the muscles or what can seem almost like the mus muscles of the thinking
mind if there's any pressure or tension
contraction activation associated with
thinking as you exhale
soften in the thinking mind
and then then to introduce the idea of ease
do whatever easy way it it you can do so set your body at
ease maybe there can be an easing up of the body tensions and pains and
challenges easing up being
easy with how the body is
and then to set your mind at ease supporting the mind to take a break
from its worries or [Music] concerns giving the mind the thinking
mind a chance to be at ease being
easy with the mind
and if it's easy enough ease up and easing up and
whatever way the mind is
and then setting your heart at ease whatever emotional Center you have
or emotional state that you
have set it at set it at
ease or if it won't be at ease is ease up on
it be
easy and then centering yourself on your breathing
being easy with your
breathing easing up if that's
helpful breathing at ease
and then for the center of this meditation
instruction with whatever degree of ease or maybe calm that you
have as you're meditating notice what takes you away
from that ease
and when you're ready set yourself at ease
again maybe it's only ever so
slight ease set yourself at ease and know what takes you away
and be easy with what takes you away ease up on whatever unease you
have be easy with the ways that you're you feel
uneasy and as you breathe in and breathe
sound practicing being easy with whatever is
happening and being sure to notice
what takes the ease
away
for
e
for e
set yourself at ease
and maybe then it's easier to stay
aware easier even to be aware of how you become
uneasy without being caught in the
unease
for
e
e for
and as we begin to approach the end of the meditation see if in the last minute of
this meditation if you can set yourself at
ease be easy with whatever is going on
whatever your meditation is like be at ease for the next 60
Seconds for
and then to finish up the
meditation to direct your heart to take in the people in your life your
communities around you the circles
of people known and known as they these circles spread
outwards out into the world and may what you've discovered or
touched into about ease in the
meditation may it help you to recognize how others are
uneasy when they're not at ease
and may we we be a be a safe presence for others may
we talk or be or be present in a way that supports
others to be at
ease may all beings
be at ease with themselves may all beings be at ease in
their communities may all beings be at ease in
this world with its challenges of all
kinds may all beings find enough ease
so that they can be wise and
clear about how to live in an uneasy
World they are living our life
today generate ease
May our ease ease up the suffering of
Others May all beings be free of unease
[Music]
thank
you
e e
so hello everyone and welcome to this uh Monday morning
and the beginning of a new five-part series for this
week and uh what I'd like to talk about is what maybe provisionally we can call
um uh the uh kind of the central or core
teach teachings uh as uh I have come to emphasize as a
teacher that um every teacher has a particular way of teaching perspectives
from which to teach that um
um that um maybe because of what works for the teacher or what they've seen
supports other people um or maybe it represents some of the core values the
teacher has so as a teacher I have ways that I teach and I have kind of core or
Central um aspects of my teaching or assumptions or underlying kind of
premises that uh from which I teach or emphasize so since some of you have been
listening to me for a long time I thought it might be nice for me to try to
uh explain uh at least for this week five different kind of fundamental
orientations that I bring with me uh as as being a
teacher in my teaching and maybe some of you will recognize how I teach and why I
teach what I do because of this uh kind of uh explanations that I'll give this
week so um the the one of the most
fundamental orientations I have which maybe comes as no surprise because it's
in some ways it's emphasized to ltin Buddhism is uh uh to focus on suffering
Dua and the end of it and uh there's a Simplicity to that
orientation um and of course Dua are suffering is complicated so certainly it can be
complicated to delve into it at times but that's the orientation that uh the fundamental
purpose of the Dharma is to end suffering and uh and so there's a uh uh
so if there is a uh you know orientation is the is to not to only point to the
end of s suffering but point to real study and learn how to effectively be
present for suffering to see it and know it and work with it and
um and uh it makes the Dharma much more simple and kind of streamlines it
there's a lot of wonderful spiritual spiritual goals spiritual understandings religious
understandings humanistic understandings purposes that people have for what they want how they want to live their
life and some of them involve uh uh pretty um
Grand goals that are glorious uh that um involve
Great accomplishments in meditation great accomplishment in in experiences
and all kinds of wonderful things and I want um and um
and these are all good but uh the question that I live with is am I
suffering is there suffering here and some great spiritual
experiences uh in the experiences there may be no suffering but the experiences
haven't really uh Plumb the depths of the sources and The Roots and of the
unease the distress the stress the anxiety the psychological challenges
that we live with and uh and so the Dharma is meant
to really Plum that depth to really see clearly and not just have no
suffering you can have no suffering by getting distracted enough to but to
really get down to the roots of where suffering comes from in us so that uh uh
we don't live suffering we don't live with suffering waiting to be triggered in
us so uh uh this emphasis on suffering I think of as a little bit
like if you're a nature photographer and go to the savanas of Africa and you want
to uh take pictures of many different wild animals uh it's hard to go roaming
around the savanas The Plains of afca Africa looking for all the animals that you want to see but if you uh sit at the
watering holes all the animals sooner or later have to come to the watering hole
so if you sit there maybe camouflaged and wait then all these animals will come and you can take a
picture so uh this uh orientation to suffering is that that's the watering
hole that's the place where everything everything that you need to know everything you to study everything you
need to let go of and to realize comes to it comes into play around suffering
so if you if you become attuned to it and study it and see it and learn to be
comfortable with being mindful of our the ways of which we're
challenged um it gives you a vantage point from which to learn to discover
every have Insight in everything that you need really need to know in order to be free of uh
suffering and um and
uh and so uh the um um and
so and so one of the things that orientation around suffering does is it puts the practice in the world of our
direct experience uh suffering or if you pref prefer words like um stress or
unease uh in the guided meditation I introduce the translation of Dua as
unease uh sometimes I've seen translators uh spell it with the hyphen
dis ease and that has its evocative uh suggestive idea is that Dua is a kind of
a dis disease um and um that we have and
and uh so to um it's put us focusing on suffering
puts us in our direct experience that's where we want to be and does not put us
in the books to read about Buddhism you know being a bookand Buddhist who reads all the time ideas are wonderful and
inspiring some people get very calm and inspired and have wonderful experiences
reading but it sometimes it's only you know doesn't go deep inside because it's
not doesn't sustain us the idea is to read the book of our own hearts and so
when we remember that we're looking at suffering not to suffer better but to uh
find an alternative a healthy alternative to suffering to find the resolution of the suffering the the the
dissolution of our suffering and um uh so to um
to uh so the suffering is a direct experience and so it's not metaphysics
it's not things we can't know for ourselves it's not taking us away into
some Transcendent world away from our uh imminent world of here and now and with
other people it puts us right in in the human world uh where we can do the work
of really seeing and being with what is so the question I the fundamental
question I ask myself uh as I go about my life is uh am I
suffering and if I am then I stop so the bumper sticker that I like would have
maybe is um I stop for suffering if I don't feel the suffering I don't
recognize them suffering and then I'll continue what I'm doing if it doesn't cause any harm and um and it it's kind
of makes it very easy there are people who have other goals uh for their religious life
spiritual life and um and they feel there these other goals are grander more wonderful
more important than simply the ending of suffering and um that's fine but my hope
is that um first or in addition they're also working to really uproot the uh
their own suffering it's it's one of the great goals of life to discover the end of suffering and um and whether that
some people might see that as being a lesser goal maybe it's a modest goal maybe there's fantastic things to do in
life and experience in life that are better and greater than the end of
suffering but at least do that let that be the be the foundation um in which by which you do
everything else um and and then uh it isn't suffering that's uh
motivating um to get away from suffering or try to solve suffering indirectly or to bypass
it that drives Higher Goals than this so for me I've discovered that one of the
most ultimate things we can do is uh come to the end of suffering and uh and
this practice of insight is the practice that I've seen for me has taken me to
the end of suffering in such a clear and dramatic and full way that I know
nothing else that does this good and direct job because it's really addressing it
directly and um and uh so for me it's pretty
ultimate uh ultimate kind of experience ultimate purpose that I like to teach for and I like to live for it's not the
only purpose uh in the wake of the ending of suffering there's uh uh
there's more there's then there's a motivation from that to support other people and I've dedicated my life from a
particular moment I had in a Buddhist Monastery to live my life for uh for
support Aid guide whatever I can do to help others get to the root of their own
suffering and uproot that root to bring it to an end and um and as I've learned
to recognize that in myself myself it has inspired me to support other people do this the same thing it is possible to
uh come to the end of suffering and that by putting that at the at the core the
center of Dharma practice my teaching um The Hope is that we're providing a
direct way the most direct way to do it without being distracted or cut up inid
shows uh from that might be you know have their own value but uh can be a distraction from Dua and
the end of it so uh that is one of my fundamental orientations and and um and
with that um the um
um there's some areas of Buddhism that I don't find particularly interesting
because those areas are not the you know pointing directly to that so I'll talk
more about that um over this week but um as a beginning to the kind of core
teachings that foundations to my teachings that I teach this is really at the
center so um thank you and um I look
forward to offering you this kind of background to how I teach for the rest
of this week