hello everyone and
welcome and one of
the emphasis for in Buddhism and the kind of Buddhism we practice and for Insight
Meditation is being with or seeing things as as they are being with things
as they are and that means you know being with things in the present moment
as they are and uh what's directly visible
immediate but there's a subcategory of things as they are which is often
overlooked in this practice and which um partly because if
we focus on it too much it causes a lot of problems but from time to time it's invaluable to
be present for this as well and this is things as they could
be in the present moment there's potential and to be aware of that
potential is uh encouraging it can be inspiring if the potential we're
focusing on is wholesome is good and the particular things that that could
be that this tradition emphasizes is that you could be
free there could be an experience of
thoroughgoing freedom freedom of the heart freedom of the mind and what freedom freedom from all
the ways in which the heart the mind is contracted
constricted all the ways in which it's limited by clinging and grasping and
desire greed hatred
delusion anxiety Prof things could be the mind
could be different the heart could be different and from time to time it's good to take that in that this is here
as well this potential and it's a potential that's not just a concept but it's potential
that sometimes especially when we're practicing meditation you could almost feel that it's close by you can almost
feel or sense or smell that this is a potential and then the idea is to be
wise about that to not spend then all our time thinking about what could be
but rather to use that as an inspiration to know oh I it could be so let's
practice how with what how things are with that in mind and in particular if uh it's useful
to think that how things could be is also a teaching a teacher for us for how
things can be now when we practice and in particular
uh in that freedom freedom from clinging freedom from aversion freedom from uh uh wanting and not wanting in
some contracted way is uh how things could be can we
find how to be how to be present how to be mindful here with what
is with some of that quality with some flavor sense that yes
to be mindful in a simple simple way that is free of being the
contraction or the pressure to want or not want free of
clinging so it means that attention the way we practice has a quality of freedom
of ease maybe some people call it equinity at times or peace or
calm and so the idea is to find how how to be aware so it so it has some of
the qualities of what could be and make it actually what
is and from time to time in Buddhism in Buddhist practice it's
useful to also keep in mind or realize what could be is a
radical freedom a thoroughgoing radical free from all
things that keep us contracted and the
representative um powerful representative modeling or example of this is people who choose to become
monastics where they choose to step away from a lot of the ways that it's easy to
be caught up in uh in life and work and family and relationships
and not that we have to do that ourselves but it's a that freedom does
involve a radical letting go even in the midst of work in midst of
family midst of a relationships not to dismiss them not to
avoid them or be aloof from them but so that we are not suffering in the middle
of them and so when we sit down to meditate
sometimes to see it as a li a particular very special
time to let go fully it's a vacation from all clinging
all shoulds all requirements all for and against it can be a phenomenal
relief things as they could be a total letting go in Freedom here
and now so as we do this sitting
today and your your mind wonders off in thought remind
yourself that it could be different it could
be a full entering into a world of freedom from all attachments all
clinging In This Very
meditation and perhaps how they could be like that you can get a sense of it you
can feel it in a way that supports you to just really stay here for a few
moments really be present really let go into this
moment and your mind wonders away again then remind yourself things could be different things could be be free and
come back to that come back to that take the
risk take the challenge of these next 20
minutes to see if you can
taste freedom in every moment of being aware
of being alive so again as we have this week go sit
quietly
e
for
for for
and as we come to the end of this sitting
there is things as they are right now being present for our
experience present for the rhythm of the body
breathing we're being present for how we are doesn't need to exclude
anything but is free allows everything
without wanting and not wanting pushing away or holding
on giving room to how we are and in that room in that space that
we feel the freedom we sense the the lack of attachment just beyond
the edges of how we are
attached it teaches us something about how we could
be we could be living close to that freedom all the
time the freedom that's founded in the space of
awareness that holds all
things and then when we meet other people together with others we know
about others things as they could be is
important without some sense of that maybe the there's no
compassion compassion is having knowing that it could be
different this person doesn't could be not could not suffer as much as they
are things as they could be then motivate us to live compassionately
caring for others
things as they are and things as they could be a
wonderful mutuality both are there that can guide us in Freedom and
compassion and love in caring for this
world may they work together
May our freedom show us how to
care and may our care show us
freedom May how we live in this world be for the welfare and happiness of
everyone ourselves and others others and ourselves may all
beings self-included be happy
may all beings self-included be
safe may all beings self
included be peaceful may all beings self-included
be free free in such a way
that it's equal it's the same whether we care for others or for
ourselves doesn't have to be any different it's all care it's all freedom
[Music]
thank
you e
so welcome to this fourth talk where I reading some of the
verses the poems of the terries the the
ancient um nuns who were Disciples of the Buddha or
lived in the years after him after him and uh maybe the earliest poetry of
of religious poetry of women that survives and uh before I read some poems
today um I wrote a tentative introduction to my translation and I
want to read just a couple of paragraphs from it it's kind of setting the stage perhaps for what will the
poems the terata that is the verses of the Elder
nuns evokes the struggles in spiritual transformation of ancient Indian
women the stories of their challenges highlight their
success in attaining the ultimate goal of the Buddhist
path accounts of tragic and oppressive lives provide dramatic contrast through
their inspired words celebrating their great Liberation the social constraints and
oppressions experienced by women and ancient India are the backdrops for the
radical inner freedom and peace they achieve depictions of wisdom courage and
determination used to overcome their suffering culminate with confident
Declarations of their full realization and one of the ways that
they decare there's many ways they declare their full Liberation one of them is um
shattering the mass of Darkness to shatter this darkness is to
become free of the of the obscuring influence of ignorance and
delusion as a metaphor the mass of Darkness evokes not only a lack of self-
understanding insight and wisdom it may well refer to ignorance and blindness of
social beliefs that kept women oppressed this includes claims that
women can't attain Awakening because of their meager two-finger
wisdom that's reported in one of the poems to shatter the mass of Darkness
includes Breaking Free of oppressive social beliefs a freedom perhaps
represented most visibly in becoming a Buddhist nun one of the very few options
to live a life independent of the social expectations obligations and the many
limitations placed on the ancient Indian women for some it was the only way out
of the servitude of marriage of that
time so that's the so now I like to read some of these
poems and I'd like to begin with
um a poem uh One More poem that refers to pachara yesterday the last two days
I've referred to poems that either uh featured pachara or uh her her uh
monastic students referred back to her as their teacher and there's one I like
this one but it's uh also has a kind of dramatic
backdrop it's uh Chand which uh her name name means
Moon I was poor widowed without
children without friends or relatives so to have no husband no
children no relatives uh it's basically they have no no network of support
network of livelihood maybe without friends or relatives I
obtained neither food nor clothes taking a bowl and staff I went
from family to family begging for alms tormented by cold and heat I
wondered for seven years so extremely poor homeless
person and it wasn't like there were social services back then there weren't uh shelters for the homeless there were
not um uh institutions that care for
them so she wandered for seven years but then I saw a
nun receiving food and drink then I saw none receiving food and
drink approaching her I said let me go forth into
homelessness with kindness for me she
pachara allowed me to go forth then she advised me urging me
toward the ultimate goal hearing her words I did what she
advised the lady's words were not in vain I am now free free of
attachments so poor
poor homeless no family no friends abandoned by Society perhaps but
then received into the Society of monastics one of the only institutions
that were maybe someone like that could go and in that Society she received
teachings and practices and became free here's a little different
background for one of the nuns this is um fima which meant Pure or unstained and
sometimes the names and then hurt their lives something about the poems either creates a contrast or kind of highlights
something important about the nun so if you remember her name is to be Pure or
unstained she writes intoxicated with my skin color figure
Beauty and Fame relying on my youth I despised
others I adorned this body painted it up
babbled foolishly and stood at the brothel
door like a hunter with a snare laid out I displayed my ornaments revealed
ample hidden Parts performed much Magic and laughed
at many people but today having gone for having gone for
alms head shaven wrapped in the outer robe seated at the base of a
tree I became free of thoughts free of thinking so she's a nun now and
practicing and meditating and then
all attachments are severed both Divine and human all
clinging cast off I've become calm
released quenched so a dramatic difference of how
she lived her life earlier and then some reason she go went forth as a nun and attained something
radically different something that may was not possible in her earlier
life the next one is uh Sia and uh her name means lioness I love
this at her name lioness a name powerful
name from unwise attention I was afflicted by Passion for
sensual pleasure I was agitated about the past had no
control of my mind pervaded with defilements chasing
ideas of what's beautiful controlled by a passionate mind I didn't obtain a
peaceful mind thin Ashen and pale I wondered for
seven years I suffered not for a single day or night did I know
[Music] peace because of this I took a
rope and entered the woods saying it is better to hang
myself than to continue this wretched life I made a strong noose tied it to a
branch of a tree as I put it around my neck then
my mind was liberated so it's possible she was
already a nun and she wandered around as a nun practicing and she could never find
peace something about her mind was so caught and so finally in this despair of
her in her despair she decided to commit suicide and something about that act got
her maybe her attention in way nothing else had done somehow broke the spell of
her thinking her attachment her preoccupation that she Labyrinth of these difficult thoughts it broke it and
she discovered Freedom so I find it remarkable these
stories of the challenges these women had in their lives and how they
discovered an alternative the last poem
her name is MAA k um friend kie some of you might know
that K is a powerful word in in India I went forth meaning went off to
be a nun I went forth in faith from home to
homelessness I wondered here and there eager for gain and honor so she became a
nun but you was pursuing the wrong thing uh trying to acquire things gain and
become famous and honor neglecting the ultimate goal I pursued a
lowly goal I was controlled by defilements I did not know the renuncian
goal then sitting in my Hut this sense of urgency arose
I have entered the wrong path under the control of
craving short is my life I am crushed by old age and illness soon this body will
break apart I have no time to
neglect looking at the arising and passing of my experience as it actually
is I then stood up with my mind
free having accomplished the Buddha's teachings so
she was a nun but her mind was still caught up in Fame and gain and all kinds
of other things that just didn't uh weren't appropriate and then as an old
old person old a nun she finally kind of woke up this is not right I can't keep
doing this and she maybe gave herself over to her meditation and much more
diligently and wholeheartedly and a sense of urgency it's now or
never and she got concentrated enough to really see the inconstant changing
rising and passing nature of all experience dipped into the deeper under all the concepts the ideas the
reifications we have and in the flow of lived life in the present moment her
mind let go and then as so many of the nun say
they had accomplished the Buddha's teachings so these uh ancient teachings
of the nuns they're over and over again telling us with their confidence and
their generosity their maybe compassion for the generations of people later who
are going to encounter these poems they're letting us know it is possible
it is possible to accomplish what the Buddha teaches it is possible to be
free so um May the women of ancient India from
2500 years ago May these words still live in
us thank you