so nice to be
here it's amazing this this 7 a.m. sitting
and and little short dmet it's been going on for more than four years
now that's kind of astonishing to me it's really really
lovely so um let's uh let's settle into a
meditation tending to uh to the posture
finding that balance of alertness and
ease uprightness and
relaxation now balance is something that we're always always looking for in the
in our practice of the Dharma in many
different areas and the posture is a place where we can
start establishing a sense of
balance not striving and not uh zoning out
it's being
present so allow yourself to to be present
to the whole body sense of the whole body as it's sitting or lying
down standing as it
maybe just feeling into what it what it's like to be in the posture you're in
and then just taking a little trip
around the body with the with your awareness your attention and recognizing
tension if it's present and and releasing it just as much as as
possible and knowing it has been
released e
just be uh be present to what's going on energetically in the body in the nervous
system any kind of pulsing your
tingling maybe in the hands and arms legs other parts of the
body any sense of uh agitation or
excitement in the nervous system
itself in the
body breathing into what's present and letting whatever is there as
settle just attending attending to the lives of our bodies with care
the muscles and Joints to the nervous
system finding a place of
balance
e
e e
noticing any any mental or emotional state that has maybe come with you from
whatever you were doing before you joined the sit this this
day just noticing being interested
Let There Be kindness in your interest and your attention to what's
arising within you all the
different areas of life that are going on all the time inside of
us
e
for
e e
know everything that's going on right now in in in inside you in
your physical systems in your mind and heart all of it
it's this is this is life right now it's what it is
this is what we're coming to know what we're coming to know
intimately in our practice our life our own life as it's
lived this is our text
and as we come to know it more and more clearly more and more
deeply it opens up for us and more and more freedom is
possible and we stay
present
e
e e
stay close to uh to your lived experience right now right here right
now in this moment stay very close to it
just let it be known to
you in a kind regard kind and curious
not prying it's gently
Furious is meeting your life with a friendly and interested
regard
e
e e
what would it be like if um if we all brought a kind and
interested regard to every interaction that we had
today wherever we happen to go we go to
work people we meet there people we meet if we're shopping or walk walking down a
street or in our families with
friends a kind and interested [Music]
regard I may we all bring that to to all our interactions with the world
a day and other days as well
[Music]
so um to recap so far uh the Dharma I
yesterday I I talked about the first two qualities uh of the Dharma that are in this list that it's well proclaimed that
it's useful throughout the all stages of practice and that it's visible here and
now um we can see it unfold in our daily life experience and that that's the only
place really where it is visible in our daily life experience in our practice
and those are the first two qualities of these six and in order to make use of the Dharma in order to uh to see it here
and now um we need to develop a capacity for uh mindfulness for sustained
attention sustained focused attention is what it uh the the essay that I'm
referring to pointed to the ability to stay connected to our to our present
moment experience to see the ways that that suffering that dooka that stress to
see the ways that it arises and uh also to see the way that it
ceases and then we need to be willing to not give up to uh when we forget when we
get distracted when we get bored or assistant and this essay that I'm uh
that I'm referring to this week called that a tolerance for failure speaking about students reading texts but I don't
really like to use the word failure in regard to to practice obstacles maybe
bumps in the road you know we don't let them deter deter
us so today I want to talk about the third and the fourth qualities of the
Dharma in this list um along with the uh the capacities that support them and the
third quality is that the Dharma is immediately effective and that's of
course related to it being uh visible here and now we can see it and then we
can see that it works as well and I I mentioned yesterday I mentioned an analogy that Gil uh I've
heard Gil use before about having a pebble in in your shoe what's
immediately effective is bending down taking off my shoe getting the pebble
out there is immediate relief I see the dooka I remove the cause and the Dua
ceases and in our Dharma practice um perhaps um we might not discern so
quickly the choice of which Dharma prescription to apply you know
mindfulness Compassion or meta ethical Behavior truthfulness as taking off a
shoe you know especially early on in practice if I have a
tendency which I have had in the past to get impatient with my partner I can
practice restraint and patience I can in investigate my impatience and then then
I can see how it's really creating stress for me and it's not really having
any effect on on how my partner washes the dishes for example it might take
some time for me to actively recognize that being patient relieves the stress
re actually relieves the stress but when I see it here and now then I can see
that patience has been immediately effective recognizing the stress of
impatience and the release that comes through dropping it is you know it's seeing the for noal truths in
action so sometimes it's clear what would be immediately affect Ive and uh
and the result is immediately visible um sitting in meditation for example and
like like I invite every morning and like most uh Dharma teachers will invite
um being mindful to our breath noticing tension in our neck or jaw um we can
begin to let to relax it to let it go let the Pebbles of stress fall
away and as practice matures and we develop more sensitivity to our inner
State we see this kind of immediate effect applied in more and more subtle
experiences to very mild emotions and subtle moods subtle movements of
mind so um the Dharma is immediately affective I
see that in just many small ways throughout uh throughout my day both in my formal practice and and just in in
daily life and the fourth quality of the Dharma is often translated as inviting
inspection and uh and this
uh uh this this word aaso is the poly word
and um you it's a kind of famous exhortation of the of the Buddha come and see for yourself
and uh so we're invited to just keep looking does the Dharma seem well
expanded is applying the teachings immediately effective do we see it here and now we pay attention to our actions
to our movements of mind we choose to act ethically we choose to act kindly
and we notice what the results are perhaps we apply mindfulness to some
difficult sit emotion in our in our uh in our meditation or in our life using
the rain or the raft techniques that that uh are spoken of so often in Dharma
talks and then we look you know is there more space around the emotion were we
Kinder were we more balanced when we dealt with that particular situation
that gave rise to uh some strong emotion do we see what it was that
hooked us the conditions uh that triggered the
emotion as we practice as we keep coming back and looking seeing coming to see
for ourselves we understand our minds a little bit better we get a clearer picture again and again of what makes
them tick as time goes on we keep coming back you know to see
for ourselves and this might be the heart of the you know the empirical nature of our Dharma practice um and I
mentioned that all these six qualities are they point to the empirical nature of of the Dharma um this coming back
coming to attend to our experience again and again with curiosity with kindness
to gradually learn to distinguish uh more skillfully between what leads to
dooka and what leads to more peace more ease more
freedom and this uh inspection that the Dharma invites is really supported by
two factors that uh Sheridan Blau the man who wrote this essay speaks of in h
in this essay on literacy the first is a willingness to suspend
closure to entertain problems rather than to avoid them and then the second
is a willingness to take risks so suspending closure and taking
risks willingness to interpret for ourselves to respond to to to our our
our practice honestly to what's going on honestly and to question conventions and
question accepted uh interpretations of the Dharma as
well as we practice and learn more about the Dharma um we don't give up if we don't
understand you know Concepts uh that are unfamiliar to us like not self perhaps
or emptiness or some things that seem kind of esoteric we're encouraged to be
curious you know it's essential we apply sustained attention and we stay open to
what arises we keep investigating we don't jump to conclusions about our
experience about what it means about what motivates us or if we do jump to
conclusions we recognize that and we question them we stay open and we maybe
hopefully we can recognize oh there are other possibilities here we continue to look we continue to be
curious you know before he was awakened there's famous stories about the Buddha
the Buddha was asked to teach by two really highly regarded teachers who both said he had reached the Pinnacle of his
practice and he was you know he was ready to pass on the the teachings
but the Buddha said no you know he suspended closure he felt there was more
to learn more to accomplish he had not solved the problem of suffering so he
continued to entertain the problem and then he changed his practice model you
know he came to something new he discovered something new for himself seeing that the conventional approach
that he was following he was doing really aesthetic practice that had you know had him was starving at the time
according to the stories and then he remembered a time when he'd experienced a happiness that
he judged to be beneficial and uh he took the risk to see where that might
might lead and that where it led was to his final
Awakening so I haven't uh solved the problem of of
suffering at this point you know and I want to be willing to engage with
practice as an open question I keep looking what is this what's motivating
this so the the willingness to uh to suspend closure and to take
risks are both really useful as we continue to come and see for ourselves
what the Dharma is how it unfolds Blau talks about these in terms
of an intellectual courage and I think it does take courage to not settle for easy answers to keep an open mind not
come to a conclusion to be curious about inconsistencies and sometimes to change
course to take up a different practice to start doing Brahma vihara practice for instance to move to a concentration
practice from a you know from a mindfulness practice it feels safe to
have certainty but feeling safe can be a way of staying stuck
so we we refine our own understanding by staying open and curious not just by
swallowing everything that we're taught we have to walk the path ourselves no one can walk it for us not even not even
the Buddha could walk it for us it takes energy and sincere intention to keep
inspecting and to stay curious we can come to New interpretations of Dharma Concepts that
that differ from the way we've uh heard them taught and understand under and
understood the way we've understood them in the past and we can check our understanding with those we respect
accepting feedback from others checking to see if our interpretation supports
growth you know seeing the empirical uh nature of the practice does it move
towards freedom and if not you know we stay open to having our interpretation
overturned in our practice it just it's so useful to question our assumptions about uh how practice uh is supposed to
unfold no we have we do have assumptions about that I believe there's that
well-known quote from Suzuki roshi you know the the founder of San Francisco's
Center in The Beginner's mind are many possibilities in the experts there are
few or the Korean uh zen teacher uh sang
his advice only don't know only don't know something you can always kind of bring into your practice I think the
Buddhist invitation to come and see for ourselves could be seen as an invitation
to keep that beginner's mind to stay in the place of curiosity to stay in the
place of an open question and see I've gone on Beyond
because I had it's like I think I was muted for about four minutes I'm really sorry I didn't wasn't paying attention
to the chat I was I was tied to my words but when I was thinking about this
aspect of the Dharma um I thought of this quote from Rainer Maria R you know from his uh letters to a young poet
um that it's this is another quote that's often often repeated in Dhat
Dharma talks and it's quite profound I think you know I want to beg you as much
as I can Dear Sir to be patient toward all that is unsolved in your heart and
try to love the questions themselves like locked rooms and like books that
are written in a very foreign tongue the point is is to live
everything live the questions now perhaps you will then gradually without
noticing it live along some distant day into the
answers so immediately effective and in inviting
inspection aaso come and see for yourself staying open to new possibil
ities continuing to be curious not coming to conclusions being willing to
look again and again and uh thank you very much again
today for your attention um tomorrow we'll look at the fifth of these qualities and I'll try to stay on top of
whether I'm muted or not and in the meantime I encourage you to keep looking keep living your
questions uh with that kind and curious interested regard for your life so see
you tomorrow thanks