so greetings greetings everybody welcome
welcome so this morning I want to drop in a
poem that uh reminds me a little bit of part of the Buddha's biography part of
the way in which he found his way to
Awakening and maybe it's a modernday version of uh part of H his
biography and I'll unpack that later during the dermat and it'll become
obvious to you once I drop in the poem but I I wanted to say just a few
words about uh poetry and that is that to fully enter a
poem there's a way in which we like must like stop and step away from our usual
way of showing up it's a right to really often like we don't think about people
reading poetry uh while they're doing something else instead it I tend to
think in this is my own experience I read poetry when I'm like SE seated when
I'm sitting down and have like a book in front of
me this ISS or yeah often like my the books I have at poetry are you know like
actual books no requirement for that but just this W like it's shifting out of uh
it's not something that I'm doing well I'm fixing a meal or walking or you know
sometimes we see people with their uh devices while they're walking or something like that but instead it's
like to stop and pay attention to a poem is a
way to help kind of like bring that poem to life and so often like we're just caught
up in getting from one place to another doing one thing and then the next thing and often like there isn't a compelling
reason to just stop except this is what mindfulness practice can be now I don't have to stop
but maybe a meditation practice to take a meditation posture and we might say
that poetry is also a way that encourages to stop and enter into to a
different way of being with the moment kind of like interrupt this
momentum that we often have with whatever is compelling us to go on and
on to the next moment so poetry is a way that really encourages us to stop
and really enter into the world that it is offering us
so with that as an introduction let's take a meditation
posture arriving into this
moment putting aside all the going and doing and in some kind of way stopping
we might even say allowing this
moment connecting
connecting to the experiences of this
moment most likely those experiences include pressure against the body where
the body meets the sitting surface
we sitting in a chair and using a back rest or a couch perhaps it might be
pressure against the
back pressure against the back side the
btics feeling that we're planted here we
here this location right now this
moment pressure on the back of the legs
and to the feet whatever they are [Music]
touching going to the top of the body
feeling into the
face sometimes there can be tension around the eyes or the
jaw mouth just noticing
just noticing it might be that our
noticing brings a softness or ease of any tightness and it might not be too
NE sometimes the back of the neck can have some tension
can that be okay
the shoulders letting the shoulder blades
slight down the
back the chest
remember belly
and embodying this
moment inhabiting this
moment experiencing this
moment e
tuning into the sensations of
breathing the experience of the body
breathing e
and when the mind wanders it doesn't have to be a
problem very simply gently Begin
Again
e
e e
and we [Music] allow this meditation
period to be an opportunity to stop all the goings and comings
and just be with this
moment as best we can as best we
can
e
e e
and the story that the tradition has about
the
Buddha his biography his spiritual Quest
it begins with him meeting the Heavenly
Messengers old age sickness and
death there was something about without seeing that that stirred him roused
him to seek an end to suffering
what happens when we encounter Heavenly
Messengers can it be a support for our practice for our life
there's a poem I'd like to drop in it's by padrao
Tuma it's called The Facts of
Life The Facts of Life by Padre go Tuma
that you were born and you will
die that you will sometimes love enough and sometimes
not that you will lie if only to
yourself that you will get tired that you will learn most from the
situations you did not
choose that there will be some things that move you more than you can
say that you will live that you must be
loved that you will avoid questions most urgently in need of your
attention that you began as the fusion of a sperm and an egg of two people who
once were strangers and may well still
be that life isn't fair that life is sometimes good and
sometimes even better than good that life is often not so good
that life is real and if you can survive it well
survive it well with love and art and meaning given where meanings
scarce that you will learn to live with regret that you will learn to live with
respect
that the structures that constrict you may not be permanently
constricting that you will probably be
okay that you must accept change before you die but you will die
anyway so you might as well live and you
might as well love you might as well well
love you might as well
love Facts of Life by padrao
Tuma e
this poem again
effects of Life by pedre Guma that you were born and you will
die that you will sometimes love enough and sometimes
not that you will lie if only to yourself that you will get
tired that you will learn most from the situations you did not choose
that there will be some things that move you more than you can
see that you will live that you must be
loved that you will avoid questions most urgently in need of your
attention that you began as the fusion of a sperm and an egg of two people who
once were strangers and may well still be
that life is unfair that life is sometimes good and sometimes even better than good that
life is often not so good that life is
real and if you can survive it well survive it well with love and art and
meaning given where meaning scarce that you will learn to live with
regret that you will learn to live with respect that the structures that
constrict you may not be permanently constricting that you will probably be
okay that you must accept change before you die but you will die anyway so you
might as well live and you might as well love you might as well love you might as
well not
what if this poem were Heavenly
Messengers for you
e
e e
for [Music]
[Music]
this poem The Facts of Life by P go
Tuma but uh for me when I first read this it it uh had an impact on
me um there's something you know so often like poetry is as I said earlier
like you know it's a change in perspective or helps us to see things differently and I really felt like oh
yeah this did help me to see things differently one thing it helped me to
see is that sometimes I have a bias that poetry should just be uplifting and uh
you know enjoyable or something like this but there's something about this
poem its directness um saying things that uh I
feel like we don't want to say but feels like so much in line with the
Dharma right the first Noble truth is you know there is Dua
and in some ways this is what patri otuma is saying in this poem as well and he's saying it in a way that uh
feels relevant and feels for me touching and I I'll talk about
this or I'll just start I'm making this personal here but this uh one sentence
that you began as the fusion of a sperm and an egg of two people who once Were
Strangers and may well still be it's funny how right when we think
about time well yeah most of us when we think about time we usually do it in
relationship to ourselves you know this was when I was young I guess this might
be like when I'm older or somehow later or something like this but this whole
idea a fusion of a sperm and an egg of two people who once Were Strangers two
people who once Were Strangers kind of like transports us to another time when
we're not at the center of it right there's like we don't even exist yet but
and yet there's still a little bit of a personal feeling to it I love
this it's a way to like honor our parents of two strangers at one time
they didn't even know one another and then just this strict clinical biological thing of a fusion of a sperm
and an egg helps kind of like take us out of the middle of
everything and in some ways this is a deep not self teaching how we're
actually not at the center of everything even though you know we imagine that we are and we
experience that we are and we think that we are but turns out we're
not and another thing that about this poem that I think is really uh beautiful
is he starts with that you were born and you will die and we recognize this as
one of the Heavenly Messengers right death is like okay we know this but then
this one that you will sometimes love enough and sometimes not like this feels
a little bit more personal like oh yeah like we don't always get it perfect we
don't always get it right and maybe sometimes we have fear fear that gets in the way or like maybe we don't even know
what gets in the way but sometimes there we haven't loved enough and sometimes we
have and can we allow the fullness of our life the things that we did well the
things that we didn't do so well can we allow it to be there instead of trying
to run away from those things that we didn't do so well and only Embrace those
things that we did well or maybe we can't even see clearly like what is the difference between loving enough and not
loving enough and the poet he includes that you
will get tired just one sentence that you will get tired like we don't have like you know
the story of the Buddha you know this Relentless you know movement towards Awakening and we have this idealized
version of ourself and our heroes and you know stories that we often neglect
this part that you will get tired I love it it just kind of like
brings the humanity into our lives brings the fullness of our experience into
life and then the next line that you will learn most from the situations you did not
choose yeah there's a way in which um
I mean it's it's almost a a cliche right that I wouldn't wish this on anybody but
you know I learned a lot from it or something like this and maybe maybe that's helpful
maybe it's not helpful but if the things that we choose are things that are comfortable and
familiar and turns out that's not where the greatest growth happens and there's a part of us that knows that that
recognize that and
then how could I not mention this whole idea of love in this poem that uh love gets mentioned
throughout this poem and is like sprinkled in like sometimes we will love enough sometimes it won't that you will
live that you must be loved and that we must love he throws in
here at the end right that uh you might as well love you might as well
love what does it mean to love to love
ourselves to love our life such as it is to love
others and what does it mean to just love without any particular object just
radiating love despite all these things that
happen in our our life despite all the way that our life
didn't turn out the way that we thought it was going
to I'll read this poem The Facts of Life by Padre go
Tuma what would it be like to hear these as if they were Heavenly Messengers
modern day Heavenly Messengers that you were born and you
will die that you will sometimes love enough and sometimes
not that you will lie if only to yourself that you will get
tired that you will learn most from the situations you did not
choose that there will be some things that move you more than you can
say that you will live that you must be
loved that you will avoid questions most urgently in need of your
attention that you began as the fusion of a sperm and an egg of two people who
once were strangers and may well still be
that life isn't fair that life is sometimes good and sometimes even better than
good that life is often not so good that life is real and if you can
survive it will survive it will with love and art and meaning given where
meanings scarce that you will learn to love with regret
that you will learn to live with respect that the structures that constrict you may not be permanently
constricting that you will probably be okay that you must accept change before
you die but you will die anyway so you might as well live and you might as well
love you might as well love you might as well
love and I think I'll end there this
morning you might as well love they're part of The Facts of
Life how might that show up for you today
and tomorrow and the day after and the day
after thank you
you all thank you all for your kind notes and the way that uh you know AA
aonga here online it's beautiful
beautiful for