good morning everyone good morning sa I'm doing a sound
check happy to be with you my name is Da Neil some of us have
been together some of us have been together
before on this um YouTube chat and right now I'm waiting for the lag oh
great thank you sound is good wonderful so happy to be with you today
I'm zooming in broadcasting from Santa Cruz
California and um it's great to see all the different locations the greetings
The Compassion um popping up on the chat really delighted to be with you
today oh I am right on time and maybe a little
bit late so I'm just going to introduce us to the um meditation for the
day and um invite you to settle
in just settle in be here and maybe before we start with the
meditation I want to in like just invite you to orient either Orient to the chat say hello to your friends your Global
YouTube sa and perhaps also Orient to the room or your space as I'm doing now to look
around notice where you are check out any objects in the
distance softening your
eyes and then whenever you're ready closing your
eyes perhaps imagining and being open and receptive as if
you're taking in a broad Vista a mountain range or
ocean and then allowing your face to relax maybe a
smile on your lips and noticing for a moment
moment hearing any ambient sounds in your room or the space that you're
[Music]
in taking a breath or two turning off any devices that might
want to distract you during this time as I just did
and then noticing too the weight of your body in the
cushion or chair or whatever surface you're resting
on grounding in the sensations of this body
grounding in a sense of
place noticing any warmth or cool moisture or
dryness maybe cloth on your skin
and then tuning into the internal
sensations of your
body allowing inviting whatever is there just
as it is this morning or this day this evening for you
can be helpful to intentionally invite in two or three
deeper slower longer
breaths and the tuning tuning into
the movement of the breath in the belly or the diaphragm the
chest a signal these deeper breaths that it's time to
practice and and allowing the breathing to be
natural however it is
today continuing to attune to the felt sensations of each
breath or rising of each sound each
sensation knowing an INB breath as an in
breath an out breath as an out breath
rather than it being a checklist of INB breath and out
breath abiding in resting on all of the
details the beginning middle and end of an
inhale then the
release at the
exhale notice sing a long breath as a long
breath a short breath as a short
breath staying in contact
staying close attentive to your experience
you find your attention called by a sensation a
sound thought emotion it's
fine attending to it as something emerging In This Moment
and then when it's not so predominant so [Music]
strong returning the attention to your primary anchor or
object breathing body this here now
allowing then and there to fade to the
periphery the background
we'll practice mosto in silence a few comments here and there
until 7:30 half after the hour
e
e e
you find yourself distracted the invitation
is to appreciate the return of
awareness noticing distraction is a moment of
mindfulness returning the attention to the sensory
experience of now this
breath this sensation this
moment
e
e e
from time to time rededicate ating yourself refreshing the
attention on this moment this breath this
sensation this
sound allowing yourself to be immersed in present moment experience
ramps
e
e e
and in the final moment or two of this meditation
the invitation is to turn your attention to
your emotional Center your
heart your
core take a moment to
appreciate any efforts any moments of mindfulness
awareness
presence love or compassion
ease gather them up Savor
them from that
place holding any moments of challenge or difficulty with care
nothing left out everything
included and then turning your internal gaze
outwards to the others your life touches
and if it feels right forming the wish that they may benefit
too from this
practice may all beings everywhere
benefit from our practice here
together thank you for the sincerity of your practice
that's e
a warm welcome to those of you who tiptoed into the YouTube sit a little
bit late and a warm welcome to those of you who came early who've been here all along so
happy to be with you today for those of you who missed my brief introduction my name is Da Neil
and um from time to time I I help to cover this sit when Gil is away he's off
hiking with his wife this week so mudita for him and he will return next week so
um this week I'm going to introduce and
explore some teachings of the Buddha that are helpful both for total beginners experienced beginners and for
those with a lot of depth in meditation those who've thoroughly immersed
themselves in the Stream of the Dharma these practices are
simple and they work well in daily life and they work well in formal meditation
sting meditation so the invitation is to step
into your senses this week and hang out there they can be doorways to Greater
ease Clarity vibrancy Vitality Freedom
wisdom and I'd like to first introduce them with something we don't do very
often do occasionally in this 7 a.m. sit which is a bit of a guided visualization
and don't worry if you don't visualize just imagine that you do and kind of follow
along so you can close your eyes if you like
it's helpful and imagine that you're in a beautiful Forest on a warm comfortable
day safe and dry under an overhang on a hill bit of a
Vista and as you're there a rainstorm gentle rain starts to sweep
through the forest you can hear it off in the distance it comes
closer the moisture in the air changes notice what you
feel on your skin as the air is heavy with
moisture and water emerges
notice what is seen maybe the vibrancy of verdant
greens the movement of leaves the pureness of
water noticing not just hearing perhaps the wide swath of the rain coming in
how the individual drops might sound on leaf or ground or
Branch noticing any
smells and then stepping out if you wish from the
overhang to feel the gentle drops of rain on face maybe on
your [Music] tongue how it feels maybe
tastes noticing any emotions
present pleasantness or unpleasantness
and noticing the knowing the awareness of it
all so letting go of that coming back to the present
moment and noticing too that all of what just occurred
however it occurred for you happened in the mind
our phenomenal capacity to imagine to think to conceptualize
perhaps visualize so I mention this because the
Buddha found the mind so powerful in its influence on our experience that he
actually considered it a sense doorway a sense in its own
right in the Buddhist teachings there are six senses not five and the mind is the
Sixth and informs shapes often distracts from the other five the
classic ones we all know sight hearing smell taste and Body
Sensations collectively all six of these are known as the six sent doors or
doorways Gates bases Fields I'm using different
translations of the poly and they're all together part of mindfulness of the
body so rather than spending a day on each sense this week I'm going to offer
different access points through them to Greater presence ease
freedom and they are this is a simple practice
in fact at the moment you may be experiencing this sense of hearing the garbage truck in front of my
apartment noticing the effect of
sound through each sense
are kind of an access point or a portal
to a greater sense of being present being free from the habitual responses
stories chatter of our minds they portals away from the virtual
reality that so often happens within and ways of being in the world
inhabiting the world in a more profound simple
satisfying way neurologists call the ability to
step away from the mind
decentering decentering which means not being centered in our own
stories not being centered in the default Network that's often chatter and
self-judgment or other judgment stories that tend to take us away from being
happy simple content present so they're a powerful Ally in
mindfulness practice and in presence in life and today now that I've given this
little overview I'd like to just talk about stepping into the senses is immersing
yourself which is as I said very simple it involves choosing to attend to to
ground in sensory experience one of their bodily
senses we'll start with seeing so if you have your eyes closed that's fine you can leave them
closed and notice the variation of light
and texture on your eyelids the darks and lights that are already
present there that already is shifting into the sense of seeing and
many of you have your eyes open can notice the environment perhaps the
screen but rather than tuning into the objects on the screen or in your
environment noticing color form shape
tuning into the texture of the moment artists visual creatives of all kinds do
this all the time it doesn't have to be anything
special it's also possible to attend to What's called the visual field
itself the receptive way of seeing rather than looking
at and it's process of letting the world come to you I first noticed this many
years before I started meditating I was an avid scuba diver and snorkler and being in the water immersed in the water
there was something about that that felt almost like being in this
receptive broad way of seeing and allowed this vibrancy of
color shape form this feeling of presence with the world to be
there but we can also be immersed in daily life walking around the block
taking a hike gardening whatever it is even
cleaning the house allowing the sense of sight to be receptive almost like we're
being a a submarine walking through life and there's a way of doing this I
learned many years ago in taii which is to invite this receptivity of
the visual field which is you can start with your hands together and you're look seeing your hands but seeing the area
around them I'm modeling this as best I can on the screen moving them apart and you can start wiggling your fingers a
little and go broader and broader and broader out back towards your
ears noticing where you're no longer able to see the movement in your
peripheral vision and then allowing the eyes to remain
soft like that rather than looking at any one
thing noticing seeing in a receptive Gentle
Way this can happen with hearing noticing hearing the sound of my voice or ambient
sounds smell or taste are not always accessible you may notice the the smell
of something baking or cooking or brewing in the distance and then there's B
sensation which many of the guided meditations in this now multi-year
series cover that all of these are
invitations to immersion in the moment so this
week today grounding in your
senses and if you would like to do some homework between now and tomorrow
morning the invitation is to in your daily life take a few sensory immersion
breaks and just notice seeing hearing smelling tasting sensing as
such it's easy to do it's portable you can do it while walking around daily
life activities and if you like notice which senses
bring you here and present in an easeful way and which do you tend to
ignore so the invitation to sensory
emersion look forward to hearing what you notice tomorrow and we'll see you then
be well stay present and enjoy your practice