so welcome uh to you all I've been thinking about you much
today and uh happy to to uh sit
together so most common kind of misconception
about meditation is that uh thinking thinking is it's the problem if I'm
thinking can't meditate right it's not that thinking is uh the problem
but maybe we can say our our overtrust in the capacity of language to solve our
problems that's a problem and
so language is like the hammer and every problem every
unpleasantness is a nail and part of what we're doing in in
our meditation practice is uh renouncing
the seduction of language
renouncing and the Dharma is um is a
therapy not based in words but in action in awareness
and so um we'll sit with this in mind I'll un unfold this
more uh after we sit so uh finding a a posture that feels
sustainable e
relaxing whatever can be relaxed
relaxing whatever can be relaxed and and whatever tension remains just granting full
permission for
imperfection
e e
part of why we relax is
uh the urgency to fix
unpleasantness recedes when there's more neutrality
so we do what we can to relax and we do what we can
to uh prepare our heart for the
inevitability of unpleasantness of
imperfection of all the things that feel urgent and
become like a very sticky for our attention
rather than be surprised that something any
moment could feel wrong we just know that's a part of the human
condition and it drain some of the urgency
to fiddle with
conditions
e e
just
resting you don't need words to rest
but whenever feeling comes
up we're so accustomed to soothing and medicating that feeling
with our
words so part of what we're doing doing in mindfulness practice is
absorbing the intensity of The Human
Condition without resorting to language as our
savior
e
e e
so there's
breathing we uh might have a kind of
subtle image kind of visual subtle
thought the breath arising and
passing but uh we're just feeling the breath we don't
need or words
e
e e
how much of a n
uncertainty can we tolerate before we need to tell a story about it
God is Not uh the enemy there are no enemies in experience
and we're emerging from our overtrust in
language we're renouncing the ways we habitually use
our language or thinking to control our inner
life
e
e e
there are times when this is not at all the case but very likely right
now language doesn't make us any safer in this
moment and so we let go into the world of feeling we let go into
silence
relax or over
trust words the hammer
every intensity the
nail
e
e e
anich feels like
Risk and words feel like safety
but uh the deeper safety is
um the cultivation wisdom and
love
e e
all for
okay um it's good to uh good to sit with
you
so so I I appreciate uh kind of interdisciplinary dialogue
where uh Buddhist Scholars scientists are are talking genuinely trying to
understand and uh where there's um maybe
we say respect for the capacities or the many chambers
of the heart and also respect for um empiricism
for the for the the sense of um you know that yeah evidence counts
and we can always be wrong so this comes from one of those kind
of interdisciplinary teams uh Davidson and colleagues so I
wanted to to read um their kind of very condensed version of what what they
hypothesize mindfulness meditation training does so the um the authors write and
I'll post uh I'll post the article in the YouTube um description
afterwards so they hypothesize uh they say core capacity is gained through
mindfulness meditation training can be stated as follows the capacity to sustain present
centered awareness is facilitated by the moment by moment focus on the meditation
object meta awareness is cultivated primarily through monitoring for
distractions when as is frequently the case a distracting Chain of Thought captures attention and pulls it away
from the object D reification is trained by recognizing that the
thoughts are just thoughts and not reality nonreactivity to experience is
cultivated by rehearsing the non averse or curious non-judging stance towards
experience and changes in self-related processing occur through
[Music] deification of self-concept and a
decrease in autobiographical narrative
thinking we're going to cover that in 11
minutes so
the the movement of this path and I'm sort of on this trip around it these
days but the movement the the movement of this path is towards a life less
mediated by language it's a kind
of progressive move towards a life that's less uh
mesmerized by the realm of thought and it might seem like language
is just what we use to describe the world I'm using it right now of course
but actually uh shapes experience more than
we we tend to imagine and so the authors say we're
training in present centered awareness there isn't there isn't a thing called
the present that we pay attention to really what's often meant by be
present is simply not to be identified with discursive
thought we uh use the meditation anchor
as as um uh oh you know in a sense it's it's
almost like a snack that we feed our hungry attention the breathing right we we feed
our hungry attention something and we do that because part of
what we're we're cultivating nonidentification with discursive thinking with auditory
thinking and uh this so we initiate and sustain that contact with the meditative
anchor and then meta awareness is cultivated by monitoring for distractions we're tending to the
breathing or whatever it may be but the sense of like the connection to the
breathing is fraying it's fraying meaning the kind of
gravitational force field of thinking is pulling and we can still feel the pull
consciously before we abs are absorbed into it and so these sort of like kind of
like embryonic thoughts that just beg us to think them
and it's almost like if you know the feeling I have is like if if if they could talk those embryonic thoughts it's
like I need you Matthew I need you do
not neglect me you know and then it's like
well I don't want to neglect you I want to take good care of you I'm
a nice person right I'm teasing of course right but
it's it actually it's serious don't neglect me
it's kind of like don't neglect me or you may suffer don't like neglect me or
you may die to make it the most dramatic
right that gravitational pull that just feels like we must be get
involved as I said in the sit a un unreliability uncertainty
impermanence it's it's felt as a risk it's felt as risk the Buddha like
put Finger on something that um it just um un unbelievable you
know the anicha felt as risk and thoughts feel like the only tool we have
to manage anich and so we feel the kind of gravitational
pull and it's like a black hole you know it's just like I don't know anything
about black holes but I think there's like this pulling right there's like some kind of a vent Horizon and before
we're devoured before we cross over the Event Horizon and the black hole does whatever it does to us we reconnect that
frayed connection with the meditative anchor once we cross the Event Horizon
right it's like we're gone we're absorbed in thought we um don't know
we're meditating we don't know we're human we don't know anything we wake up from the dream of
identification and then you know the kind of bubble of that thought pops and
we train then they say in reification thought is known as thought
thought is known as thought mindfulness is about appreciating phenomena as
phenomena rather than phenomena as the world as the mirror of the
world right we normally just take the world to be the world and
we're learning to just appreciate um appreciate the six sense Gates
Right the five sense gates in the mind to appreciate phenomena as
phenoma and so we're no longer mistaking auditory thought as
essentially God's word we're appreciating it as phenomena that arises
and passes D reification and you say like wait wait
wait wait but some thoughts are are true right and yeah for sure some thoughts
are more true than others you know lunch
is uh before dinner not after absolutely
yeah but taking that very simple statement as true does something to the
mind when we're identified with thought there's some
confinement and maybe if we're being um if we're being poetic we might say that
not knowing is more free than
knowing they go on non-reactivity is cultivated by rehearsing uh a curious
non-adverse relationship stance towards experience this is this is equinity
right equinity and it is
absolutely amazing how much smoke arises off the kind of engine of resistance to
unpleasant feeling how much smoke Rises off the engine of resistance of friction in
relation to unpleasant feeling so we we practice as as uh
shinzen Yang called it like a radical permission to feel
equinity as a radical permission to
feel in a way um are that present centered awareness is parasitic on some
measure of equinity right without without
equinity um we're always kind of like rehearsing or
clinging right we've we've um our contact with the
present moment is buffered by the strategizing that clinging
involves and so um we're releasing that
kind of friction so that we can make more and more unmediated contact with
sense experience
and then they make a little bit of a leap to say you know
um that changes in self-related processing occur through
they use that same word deification but this time not of the random thought of dinner or whatever but
deification of self concept and a decrease in
autobiographical narrative thinking deification of self-concept right first
we see the emptiness of whatever stray thought we have you
know it's not so hard to see the thought about dinner whatever you know it's like
um uh it's just phenomena arising and passing the image of whatever the object
of sense pleasure arises and then there's the the identification
is broken you know we wake up to that's a thought we it's
deified it's just we were mesmerized by it for a moment but it arises passes we
become un mesmerized and the thought is it's not
like it didn't happen or something but it's just a million light years away from the project of my life
okay that's a thought about dinner right but thoughts about me about
Matthew oh my goodness the the pros and cons of
Matthew that's kind of a big deal those thoughts are really real
how's this night going this Dharma talk
stupid those thoughts deification no thank you reification right
wait okay no they're made of the same
thing the grasping and aversion we have with respect to our
self view to the story of self that that begins to dissolve in the same way that
the identification with the thought about dinner dissolves more phenomenon
not actually more personal than the thought about dinner or
whatever and so the most potent gravitational force in the universe
me that starts to weaken and we don't retreat to the kind
of house of self to assess our life to navigate the complexities of Being Human
the story of um self becomes dramatically less
sticky and there's less self but much much more
life so I offer this for your consideration and
um I hope that um it serves you in some way look forward to uh being back next
time and um yeah may we all uh I'll be
happy okay