so go ahead and um get started good day to all of you it's so good to be sharing the
Dharma with you again especially this week it's been such a
um a week of challenges for so many of
us so I'm going to continue with the theme of knowing and not
knowing um and uh specifically the topic will be investigation
and investigation is sometimes referred to as the tool of
wisdom so you might consider if um we're walking on a scary ledge high up on a
mountain you know one of the instructions I was given is we don't look down you know so instead of
thinking how far down it is if I fall I can shift my attention to where
we place her next step and that's a choice we actually make out of wisdom right um you know we
investigate what's in a moment we make that choice in a
moment we understand our situation we don't look down we look this
way and um one way of describing wisdom is the clarity of mind that allows us to
understand the situation and allows us to see which decisions we make are helpful and which
are unhelpful in relation to the practice it
means making the choices are helpful for a well-being and happiness in relation to ledge it's the
choices that let us survive um um investigation lets us see what
choices lead to Freedom towards Freedom so the wisdom of practice
develops seeing her experience intimately from seeing the details of
our experience noticing the distinctions between
things for instance we notice a difference between being tense and relaxed and we can make the helpful
choice to relax or maybe we notice between thinking about the breath and feeling
the sensations of breathing and we make the helpful choice to feel the breath
and for many of us processing the events of in the US of the last two days we
have the choice to do so with wise reflection or with
Obsession wise reflection feels intimate unreal it feels
connected and we might feel our suffering we might feel our sadness but if there's suffering there we can bring
compassion to it if we're thinking about it obsessive OB l or about anything obsessively we
tend to feel contracted and disconnected we feel
disheartened if we're cut up in aversion or ill will we can make a choice to let
go of the story perpetuating the aversion we can turn the attention to
the felt sense of the body how this aversion or anger feeling the body
turning to the body sensation stops feeding the aversion and allows it to
dissipate in its own time in meditation practice we have to
see our experience closely to even see where there are choices to be made
sometimes we make the choices very quickly almost unconsciously but that's okay that's
that's a skill you know when you're playing the piano you know whether you're hit the note a little bit harder
a little bit softer let just practice but we're still making those
choices since you practice this morning you might give a little extra attention
to the details of your experience staying really really close to
it so let's
sit so taking a comfortable an alert
posture and gently closing your eyes taking a little time to settle into
your meditation posture making any small adjustments
that are helpful connecting with the body the
body that's always present always here supporting
us and setting aside any thoughts and concerns you may have about your life or
the world you can put them to rest right
now being with our bodies
and from within the body becoming aware of our
breathing however we experience
it noticing the movements the sensations of
breathing maybe the chest and ribs are expanding and
Contracting the belly rising and
falling the air moving in and out of the nose and
throat being at ease with whatever we notice however we feel these movements
taking a few long slow deep breaths with each inhale feeling the
body expanding filling the body with energy and with each
exhale allowing the body body to relax a little bit more deeply into our chairs
or cushions to soften to open
allowing the breath to return to its natural Rhythm noticing however the sensations
of breathing are easiest to feel in allowing the attention to rest
there this can be your home base your anchor
staying close to the breath noticing the changing
sensations of breathing in and breathing
out e
if any other bodily Sensations become compelling
you might gently shift your attention to them to feel the details of those
Sensations to see them closely you might
notice Sensations like tingling vibration
pressure movement warmth it might be pleasant or
unpleasant just notice them however they
are and when they're no longer compelling returning to the moment to
the breath to those Sensations
or if any emotion becomes compelling again you can shift your
attention to it bringing the attention to the physical sensations of the
emotion and letting go of any story or ideas about
it is staying with the bodily
Sensations and when it's no longer compelling just returning to the rhythm
of breathing in and breathing out
e
e e
if the attention has drifted and notice
it and gently bring it back to the present to the moment to moment
Sensations just keep returning to the rhythm of breathing in in and breathing
out or the details of any other experience that shows
up
e
e e
when the sitting I'll ring the bell in a
moment when I do you might take a couple of slow deep
breaths again for opening your eyes
[Music]
so I'll continue with the um theme of knowing and not
knowing um by exploring the factor of
Investigation so when I was um about six years old I
was very very near cited but didn't have access to corrective glasses I lived in
a city which was like totally flat and hadn't seen much nature there wasn't um
there wasn't even a tree on our street so excuse
me so when my family took a train ride across the mountains I looked at the
beautiful Countryside and there were these gorgeous green Rolling Hills uh
and but I wasn't able to see the detail so I assumed they were smooth like in a
picture book I enjoyed imagining what it would feel like to roll down those smooth
mountains and it wasn't until I was 12 and um finally having glasses that I
went on my first camping trip and to my great surprise I found out that nature
was so smooth there were rocks and twigs and thorns and uneven ground there was just
no place to roll down the hill and I now saw all the
details and so investigation is a little bit like putting our glasses on and
seeing clearly the details of our
experience when investigation strengthens as we see the distin itions
of our experience instead of seeing a painful knee for instance we might notice all
the very Sensations that come and go and change in our perception of
pain we might feel the pressure we might feel a tingling we might feel a little
pain some a little sharpness uh a little piercing feeling
all these different things that just kind of come and go they're not just uh one One Big Blob of
pain um this isn't meant to be an act of probing a doing but just an intimate
noticing of what's there engaged engaged with the
experience not dwelling and thoughts about the pain but the details all the
pinching the shifting areas of
intensity so investigation sees the details of work experiences and notices
what's different between them and that allows us to see much more
clearly primarily in practice investigation is used to distinguish
between what's wholesome or UNH wholesome in our minds what skillful or
unskillful we might use the intellect or discursive thought to guide the mind but
as the Mind settles more deeply investigation can become non-discursive
and non-verbal if um we find ourselves
struggling or lost or confused um sometimes framing a useful
question can be part of Investigation it can guide us where to
look now maybe a thought arises in the mind about something we're worried or concerned about and we keep dwelling of
the thought or related thoughts um maybe the mind gets heavy or
tight with unhappiness investigation looks at more closely and maybe we frame a question
such as what am I clinging to here what is it I'm clinging
to as we get closer to our experience you know sometimes we might notice we
want to fix the problem or maybe we're clinging to the idea that it shouldn't be there you know what uh we often call
arguing with reality it shouldn't be this way it shouldn't be this way and then we dwell
on it again and shouldn't be this way um so we start seeing what we're clinging
to and sometimes just by seeing the clinging we see through it and the
clinging releases and other times the clinging is so strong that uh the body has
contracted with the clinging in significant ways and so we might notice the added tensions in the body as we
cling and allow those tensions to release elves relaxing into the clinging
relaxing the clinging relaxing into those feelings relaxing or resistance to the
way things are in the
moment and as mindfulness becomes more deeply established investigation has a
chance to grow and develop it can see much deeper into our experience and can
develop the discriminating wisdom system that can cut through or
delusions so there are two aspects that are particularly relevant what we pay attention to and
how we pay attention what we pay attention to is very important we can pay attention to a
juicy fantasy um you know when we meditate it it can be very helpful to consciously
remember why we're meditating consciously remember to set aside any
thoughts and concerns we have about our lives or the world to pay attention to the present
moment but how we do that is just as important you know it requires that we
look at our current experience wholeheartedly and intimately without
reservations every breath every sensation every emotion that
arises every thought that goes by do we see it clearly wholeheartedly
intimately without reservations for instance if if you were
investigating a dead body but you were repelled by it it'd be
difficult to really see it as your attention will be taken up by the repulsion
I like the term affectionate curiosity as a guide to how to pay
attention it's an attitude that comes from caring about ourselves about others about this
world it isn't a cold superficial analysis it's warm and
intimate you want to investigate without strain without forcing anything just
allowing things to reveal themselves as we pay attention with
care and we can see quite clearly if we if we're really looking if our attitude
is not wholesome if we're paying attention for
for uh so we get more concentrated or for some other reason than just really
seeing what's here affection of curiosity can be the
sensitivity that recognizes the difference between a tight willful
effort and an easeful
one now we could say that suffering is just a bunch of unh wholesome habits of
mind and habits are just that they play out in similar ways again and again kind
of like biting our nails you know we worry about the same type of stuff and we run it through over and over and over
again in our minds as we stay intimate with our direct
experience the factor of Investigation strengthens and we're able to see again
and again the distinction that distinction between what's helpful and
not helpful we see clearly the difference between hating or shoulder pain and
getting to know it with a kind attitude and in one way we don't actually have to
choose it becomes obvious because when it's we see clearly it just feels better
to meet it kindly It Feels Right the more clearly we see this the
more naturally we let go of the UNH Wholesome unhelpful Way of
being so even if we have pain in the body or mind can be at ease even if
there is sadness or sorrow the mind can be at
peace one of the teachings that has guided me is the idea that if we're
struggling in any way something is being left out of our
attention when we're struggling we're clinging investigating allows us to see
the process of clinging by giving the struggle a careful
open-handed attention seeing it feeling it we see
what we might be adding to the experience what's extra an extra attention an extra
resistance an extra idea and this wholesome attention begins
to transform any experience from struggling with it to being engaged with
it in a helpful way it can lighten our grip of
clinging and bring spaciousness so if we're feeling
anxious investigation adds a wholesome quality to the anxiety makes it easier
to experience instead of worrying we're now investigating the
worry so can we explore our suffering without pushing it away without judging it with a warm
careful
attention in practice the purpose investigation is Awakening letting go of
clinging it's really simple we pay attention to the service
of freedom to free your minds from suffering from discontent
and as we see deeply into into our experience to know ourselves not
intellectually but in every fiber of our being to know the truth that clinging
always causes suffering and then letting go of it leads to
Freedom you this factors of play at all levels of practice from when we first
sit down with a wild Restless mind mind investigation helps a steady
attention we use it in establishing a helpful attitude recognizing whether it's a wholesome
attitude or not we use it in noticing the many habits of mind and weeding out the
unhelpful ones but when the Awakening factor of
Investigation is well established practice can lead us to much
deeper understanding in a deeper wisdom where we can see beyond our
personal histories and see the reality that everything is changing all the
time and none of our changing experience will ever bring us lasting
happiness this is not an intellectual understanding but a deep nonverbal
insight into the nature reality we can see that everything
arising also passes
away everything that appears disappears including every concept we
have of Who We Are Everything Changes there no
people no situations no things that can bring us lasting
happiness and when we see this deeply it's what allows the deepest Letting Go
Liberation and
freedom so I'd like to end with a quote by aan
Sha peace within us is to be found in the same place as agitation and
suffering it's not found in a forest or on a Hilltop nor is it given by a
teacher where you experience suffering you can also find Freedom from
suffering trying to run away from suffering is actually to run towards
it we thank you may all beings everywhere be it
is the seen and the Unseen
those living close to us and those living far away throughout this
world may they be happy may they be
peaceful and may they be free thank you all