good morning everyone and good day
welcome and this morning as a way of beginning I would like
to evoke the the
image of a standing on a wonderful high mountain peak
and on a very clear day and this mountain peak is on the edge of
a vast land that's below nothing is higher
and you can see a far distance the Great Plains below the mountain ranges to the
north the ocean to the West Great Rivers
to the East and uh in standing
there on this day you look around and what stands out is all the different
weathers that you can see in some areas you see that it's raining clouds maybe
rainbows in other direction maybe higher up you can see in the distance far from
you where it's sunny you can see that's even snowing
down below you see across where the ocean is you see
fog Banks coming in and it's clear that down in The Valleys that somehow the
wind is turning and maybe the soil is being kicked up so that you see little
tornadoes or wind storms and uh other places further down
you see that there blue skies far to the South and and uh places where looks like it's
maybe almost desert-like and clear warm it looks down there and
so and so you see that there so many different kinds of weather and as you watch it you see it shifting and
changing clouds move rain comes and goes and
um and but what stands out is that even though you can differenti iate these
different parts of the weather uh it's just all part of the
same weather system they're all interrelated you could in some sense say
that um that uh there's no there's a
continuity between all the different weather that you see that uh they're all
there's no line and barrier between one and the other and uh it's they're all so some
ways in relationship to each other the weather is a
whole and in a sense we can know that the weather of the whole planet uh is this global weather
patterns that influence each other and work together and and now we think uh
sometimes we think scientists now think of the global weather is a single ho that is uh
interacting with itself and and so the same way as we
sit on our mountain peak of meditation on our cushion our chair where we're
sitting all that we experience in ourselves can be like the weather we can
certainly see that there are different emotions and feelings and Sensations
happening but there's some way of seeing it all part of a larger
hole to not create strong lines be uh boundaries
between one thing and the other the boundary between your hand and your arm
is an arbitrary line your fingers and your
palm you know we usually don't separate that we think of the hand we can of
course think about finger we can of of course think of the hand separate from the rest of the
arm but there's also a continuity and they all work together as a
whole our heart is part of the whole our whole body the heart
nourishing the body the heart nourishing
Itself by how it works but the heart exists
completely interdependent on everything else in our
body and so in meditation the idea one one way to approach it is not to get too
focused on one particular thing as if that's the most important
thing but rather to see that all that happens to us is
part of one larger hole and often the part of our life that
we're preoccupied with is only a very small percentage of what keeps us alive
and going in any given moment 99.999% of
what keeps us alive and living when activated
and conscious are processes within us that we don't control that we can
support but that operate without our conscious effort
and and we and so the 99.999% of who we are is the larger part
of the whole than the particular part that we're preoccupied with that we Define ourselves
by and so to behold very lightly any way we Define ourselves any that we're
preoccupied with and instead of getting absorbed in
preoccupation stand on the mountain peak of mindfulness and see it all as part of
the weather the larger weather system without being
caught in the divisions that the Mind makes so to take the whole of your body
and assume a meditation POS
and to lower your gaze perhaps gently close your
eyes and as you are what's the broadest way at this
moment that you can feel your body
what are the sensations in your body that appear
flow Express themselves as you're sitting here
and to see it as part of a larger hole
and then within this body maybe as part of
the part of the [Music] whole experiencing how the body breathes
the movements of breathing sensations of body as you breathe
and as a way of entering into your body more
fully take a few Fuller breaths relaxing
as you exhale
letting your breathing return to normal on the
inhale see if you can experience recognize notice what the
thinking mind is like how it feels feels how activated it
is but to feel it as part of the wider
hole it's just a piece of the weather of Who You Are
relaxing the thinking mind
and then feeling as part of the
whole how things are for you in your heart
center almost as if whatever is in your heart center whatever your emotion
is is nested in a wider hole of your
body mind
awareness no need to be focused or fixated on how you
feel there's something better than that and that is to allow it to be
nestled in The Wider hole of your body
and then finally to Center yourself on your breathing
in some ways
breathing the process of Brea processes of the body connected to
breathing touch every cell in your
body as you breathe in let your awareness grow and spread
throughout your body with the
inhale and as you exhale relax back into some
Center the some root stability Within
being with a whole of your
body maybe a whole that includes all things about
yourself thoughts feelings
Sensations
e
for
for e
when there is tension in the body and mind we are compromising the
whole of who we
are for the body and mind to soften and
relax helps us move back into the hole
oh e
for e
e
for
e for
and as we come to the end of this sitting might it be possible for
you to relax more fully into your
body or to allow yourself to sense
your as wide as broad as a field of your body as
possible maybe the humming
vibrating flowing sensations of your
body whatever broad sense of the whole body
that you can rest in
and and relaxing softening any activation of your
thinking mind and in that
relaxation allow there be a broad broading a further broadening of
awareness to take in the whole without centering yourself on
anything in particular
and then to expand relax
outward with a relaxed gaze or a relaxed
sense of all the beings human and others
that are found in your
neighborhood that are found in your city or county province
as if all of them are part of a whole working
together part of the wider biological social
systems that can live that can live harmoniously together as a whole
and maybe feeling a sense of
kinship with all living things all living
things all living things of a common source
origin all living things exist together in the whole of the
biosphere and may we care for the whole and for the
individuals may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free and may
we extend our care to contribute to that possibility
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to this fourth talk on the road L
taken and
um and The Road Less taken the RO the road that's commonly taken for many
people is one that somehow is related to attachments to
clinging and one of the primary attachments that we have is clinging to
self and clinging to being alive clinging to our
identity one of the ways that we do that is to select something out of out of our
environment to be us something out of our whole Constitution as a human being
to be what's important and what's valued what's valued for us what's
valued for others and in doing so divide up the
whole when that division when that sense of identity is created formed made up based on
attachment that identity will bring
suffering it'll also bring a division of the whole we no longer live in the whole of
our experience but we're prioritizing a small subsection of it and one of the ways that that is
physically experienced is through tension through uh tightness in the body
and the muscles and it's very interesting to see how when there's a pre occupation in the mind around
anxiety for example or fear or anger or desire the impact it has on the tension
in the muscles in the body it can be sometimes quite large the shoulders are held tight the chest is kind of
contracted it can be in the hands sometimes the hands are fidgeting a lot
and moving and sometimes the the um it's in the jaw tight sometimes it's in the
eyes the eyes are not floating and relaxed in their sockets but are held and fixated at
something there's a myriad ways in which we hold tension in our body that has its
source in the tensions in our mind so if we're caught in thoughts that are
anxiety thoughts worry thoughts if we're kind of caught in thoughts of ill will
or aversion or desire if we're caught in thoughts about me myself in mind and my identity and
myself as um as the you know as the
responsible one as the victim of it all as the consumer of
experience all kinds of ways in which we create something if it comes with tension um even if it seems reasonable
to have tension as a survival mechanism sometimes what it does is it starts uh
creating divisions in the whole of who we are tends to prioritize and restrict
and limit the experience of who we are and sometimes people are quite
restricted from being eily in touch with themselves some people live from the neck up some people from the waist up uh
some people um are not really in touch with their body at
all and so what in various ways we begin dividing up the whole We Begin centering
ourselves on something that we've kind of taken as being the thing and that can be done
conceptually uh with what our understanding and the focus of things and it can be physically because of the
impact of tension and holding and and where our attention goes and where it
doesn't go and um and so the Buddha emphasized this uh quite a bit and he said that um
greed hatred and delusion kind of the root cause for all forms of attachment is um creates limitations
creates boundaries create creates edges that we then live in between what's
included and what's not and we can feel that physically the way we contract and hold ourselves we can feel how the the
the doors of the heart sometimes close and um or go numb or uh not available
and uh all kinds of ways in which we then live live under limitation and so uh GRE haen delusion
is what limits us and um and what arises out of greed ha and delusion then is a
further limitation so if there's preoccupations and thoughts that come from that it limits us it makes us
smaller in a sense or or a range of who we are less and less and um and a lot of the this
operating system that comes out of greed hate and delusion when it P when it flows
into um uh the thoughts that are kindr trying to get what we want it often
comes along with creating ideas attitudes of who we are and many times
the identities that we have that we form um have the role not of kind of
opening us up to the whole of who we are which certainly identity can at times
but actually limits us and uh and makes us much smaller than who we are and this
idea that the madeup world of identity limits us so if we our
identity is mostly having to do with our physical body that's a limitation we're much more than the physical body if our
identity is around certain ideas and Concepts and we rotating around those
Concepts and those roles that have been we've entered into that limits the whole
if our if our identity and who we think we are is
shaped predominantly by the stories of our life the stories we make up the fantasies we have that limits
us and uh if we uh Focus too much on the nature of awareness itself being aware
or cognition of things that that itself is a limitation on the
whole so the the Buddha call these limitations the five uh bundles of
clinging uh I didn't talk about all five but but those five are are physical
appearance uh appearances um whether things are Pleasant or unpleasant that's what some
people really focus on and they're limited by that always trying to adjust and make themselves comfortable and
avoid discomfort um the things that our ideas of how we recognize the world and
ourselves the stories we have and the and the act the wonderful marvelous Act
of cognition or Moments Of Consciousness which we understand ourselves in the
world the Buddha called those is Center on any one of those is a
limitation and what we're looking for in in Dharma is to bring is to let the
whole this deeper operating system operate an operating system that operates with in the whole so something
like for example the heart our heart generally when it's everything's going well um is completely the operating with
with a interconnectedness with the whole of who we are the the heart doesn't care
that uh our role our career who we're related to all kinds of things the heart
doesn't care it just does its work and supplies the whole of who we are a child
that's growing up up uh the the the the growth of that child comes from the
inside out as it as it um as it eats food and nourished and the whole biological system with which it grows is
is belongs to the whole of the of the child it's not a limited part of you
know the body the feelings the stories the identities that child has so that uh there's so much of who we
are that uh Wells up from deep inside and for the Buddha the deepest spiritual
way of being in the world the deepest emotional way of being in the world is not in the world of attachments and
stories and ideas within the field of those limitations we create but comes
when we settle and relax and allow an upwelling allow the growth allow a flow
allow a a um uh uh our inner development to come
out of and be part of the whole of who we are and part of the role of
meditation is not so much to just get calm or not just to have Insight but
because all the both of those come back into this world of a limited World thinking that calm or pleasure and
meditation is the point to be peaceful is the point I'd like to suggest that one of the real values of buddh practice
and meditation practice is to get out of the way uh or to relax all the
limitations all the edges we've created for ourselves all the tensions by which
we live by that limit who we are so we can sense and
feel something that is not part of our constructed world not part of the world
which we think about or uh judging about or having commentary
about but something that's organic something that is deep
inside that can flow or grow or or feel like it has no edges to
it and so things like um the seven factors of Awakening things like the
Brahma vas love kindness compassion appreciative
Joy um loving Quin imity equanimous love all these things
uh they don't have boundaries they are kind of just something we radiate or or
flows throughout our whole being ideally and um and that's possible it's
possible to have a sense that it's all part of a organic ho um not part of some
particular thing that we're holding on to and fixated on we might have ideas about love but the sense the feeling the
warmth the tenderness the the glow of warmth and love within us um that's part
of that organic ho that we can relax into so to uh to relax the tensions of
the mind to relax the tensions of the body so that we live without edges
without boundaries without divisions inside of ourselves an undivided hole
of our being that um is makes us so much more
than anything that any way that we can think about ourselves and thinking is certainly part
of that whole which makes it kind of fun at times so
um uh the second operating system is one that belongs to more of an
undivided World undivided self then it does a divided self a fragmented self um
that most people live in so um The Road Less travel there's a
fork always and to choose the wholesome rather than UNH wholesome is to choose
that which belongs to the whole and um that which comes out of the
whole to choose the UNH wholesome is choose that which is is only that is a
that is uh restricting the whole or in a in a more limited world that's not whole
it's fragmented it's divided so um May you experiment today
may you sense and feel the ways that you live that
[Music] are closer to taking the wholesome step step rather than the UNH wholesome step
that the way you live that sense to open to a wider sense of how things are than
to a restricted narrower sense to how things are and may that bring you much joy and
Delight May that bring you a sense of being cozy in yourself a cozy nested in
a wider world that than therefore is
softer and uh maybe more receptive to you
so thank you very much and um and we'll conclude this uh talk
tomorrow and then talk a little bit tomorrow I'll talk a little bit about um uh what's planned for the new year and
for this YouTube themes thank you