good morning everyone welcome so
um it may be interesting for you to know that um whereas mostly I give talks like when
I come Sunday morning uh it's always uh my
protection to know that instead of giving a talk I can just answer questions
and it's a wonderful protection to have just oh I don't have to worry that just well if no talk is there then I'm uh I'm
here and um and uh today I don't have a
talk partly because I um all my discretionary time for the
last few days has been filled getting ready to be go away for a month a lot of
mean I couldn't believe how many details there were to take care of and
um and there's still a couple but I'm leaving right after the
butlock I'm going and to long drive to spend three weeks in the wilderness uh
teaching um kind of a Buddhist Wilderness Retreats and uh and then uh and then to
recover from that I don't think I need to recover but uh just the contrast is that then going
to go for a week backpacking with my wife so four weeks in the wilderness and um so I come
here wonderfully empty of Dharma talks so if any of you have any
questions you'd like to ask about anything that seems somewhat related to what we're about here at
IMC practice or teaching or something uh I'd be very happy to respond in some way
uh good morning Gil I just have a I guess it's more of a personal question if you're open to answering I'm just
curious how your practice has evolved over time in terms of when you
first kind of got interested in it and then what's changed what stayed the same
okay so a little bit try to do it short that's mean it's been 50 years
to to summarize here and um so
certainly I've suffered less uh I mean suffering is what brought me into it
didn't bring me into Buddhism I got interested for other reasons but at some point uh when I was about you know was
got started getting interesting interested in Buddhism when I was about 19 but uh it was a little more
intellectual but I was 22 I suffered enough that I thought okay I have to kind of deal with the suffering and uh
and then um and then that suffering has uh Abad you know uh sometimes in big
steps Quantum steps sometimes a slow gradual process and so one way my
practice has changed over the years it feels lighter you know it's a there's an ease
to the practice or lightness to it another thing that's changed is that
uh uh I think what uh
things that uh this practice did to me very important things that it did it it
this part this less and less suffering sense of ease it came with a a really a
decreasing of clinging of of being caught or attachment so there's been a steady decrease of that and I'd like to
believe that in that process there were three phases that happened the first phase was that um compassion was
awakened in me and that became a central orienting organization principle for how to live my life the second was that
loving kindness was awoken in me and that uh changed my way I related to
myself and to other people that made it a little lighter than compassion is not the compassion didn't go but it opened
up a whole different way of appreciating people in a very deep way and the third
phase was it opened up a third kind of social emotion that I call care the poly
word is anukampa which was a uh I a very very strongly associated with the
absence of clinging the absence of distress or tightness and so when
compassion loving kindness kind of meet non- clinging then it can come through
this very simple easeful kind of way of really having a profound sense of care
uh that's different than compassion different than love but it's um it's in some ways I feel it's like the
foundation for it so that was a third phase so is that answer the question
well
enough you can be next that scene Gil just in the last week it is percolated
to the top of my mind that I don't really understand or haven't really understood what vasana means vasana and
is vasana what we do here and um and the meaning of aasana I have intersect with
or or relate to um the meaning of
mindfulness and and the differences between mindfulness and concentration that's kind of a two or three-part
question and but just answer whatever seems most useful yeah I I appreciate that question very much because I think
uh it has been uh confusing about all the different ways the word vipasa is used and insight and mindfulness is used
and so they get some clarity about about it rather than just one big jumble assuming they're kind of the same but
doesn't seem quite right or something so um the the original
meaning uh for the word basana is that um it was not that it was
a practice people did but rather it was a it it kind of it was Insight people
had in doing the practice it refers to Insight and uh and so the the the the
meaning of the word Pana of V pasana means to see so it's a b particular kind
of seeing so that is so Insight it kind of works because the sight is in seeing
you know and the V is just a a emphatic
prefix so you can choose uh how you like to emphasize you should say it strongly
seeing or you can say you know really seeing uh uh some of my teachers or my favorite
translation is clear seeeing to give that emphasis and then the question is what
do we see and the ancient tradition was very clear what you see and um and that
this is to see the inconstancy the changing nature of our experience in some very profound way that you can't
imagine if you're seeing the change in the world which is you can see change all the time time but um but uh there's
a different way of experiencing the changing nature of the way that perception
Works uh when the mind is concentrated when the when the mindfulness is really clear so the word mindfulness
Sati uh refers to the nature of awareness that has the ability to see
clearly so it and um for the again for the Buddha it was Sati was never a
practice people did but it was a consequence of doing practice so in the
modern world these things have become practices so like uh you know come time see and practice mindfulness people will
say um you know you know and yes we do we're doing basana here so what's
happened is over time is these these uh insights uh have been starting to be
seen as be identified with the practices that lead to the insight to lead to this
clear awareness clear Sati and um and some of those things are
the ability to know clearly so so uh the recognition of the present moment
experience is not the same thing as Sati the original meaning of mindfulness but
it's become the meaning of mindfulness and um and then the people
who do that clear recognition of the present moment then that's sometimes over called
vasana practice and uh and kind of we don't use the word vasna here too much
to refer to ourselves we use the word insight and little bit of it it's not just because it's English I guess one
reason and because when um when the American teachers who started this
particular lineage that we're in Joseph Goldstein Sharon salsburg
um Jack cornfield they used insight to describe their first Meditation Center
Insight Meditation society and um and so then different places they call themselves insight to
associate themselves with that so Insight is a little bit little bit like you know Insight Meditation little bit
like a brand name that you know but maybe maybe it's a better word or or Association name for
people connected in this kind of lineage and then there's a different lineage
that use the word vpos basna centers and people say I went to I just came back from a 10day basna
retreat it chances are 99% that they were doing a guenka
retreat which is wonderful but they're different they practice a little differently they the the our practice
and their practice has the same goal but the means to it is different so
there is a difference and the same goal meaning the same Insight the same insights into inconstancy I didn't
finish it before um uh something called not self and something uh called suffering
duka so see those in a deep way so they and the VAS people gr people practice to
have the same deep Insight but get there a little different ways and so is that
enough that was a lot that was a lot know I apologize so Nancy had her hand
up before so pass it it Forward here please good
morning mush mus okay uh good morning Gil um I have a question about something
I've been exploring um some in my own uh work and teaching which is um something
I was inspired to explore actually from my um activities here I'm wondering if
you can talk a little bit about the connection between Beauty and and ethical mind States ah the connection
between Beauty and ethical mind States so uh every three years or so I
teach a year-long course here on uh ethics there's a three called what's
called three trainings in Buddhism there's the training in ethics the training in meditation and training in
wisdom and they're all equally important and so I do a year along course on each of those so in 2025 I'll start with the
ethics again but uh the first thing that we read for that course is an e is an
essay on beauty and uh because Beauty the word
for beauty that's being one of the words for beauty that's I'm referring to in ply um uh is also means being what in
English we call ethics it turns out there's no good poly word Believe It or
Not ancient Buddhist word that represents the English word ethics there
was a one one of the First Western professors of Buddhist ethics was really
amazed when he started looking trying to study ethics in Buddhism and um and he
couldn't find any like books or doctrines or treatises or philosophies
of Ethics teachings of Ethics like he had been used to in Western uh uh
theological studies that you know there's Departments of ethics for example some places and um and so so um
I think he has an article called something like morality without ethics and um and then he describes how
the historically how this word ethics was somehow because of Western cultural
uh reasons was kind of became its own special thing in in Buddhism ethics was
not separated from uh the whole Enterprise of Buddhism the whole enter
from Western point of view the whole Enterprise of Buddhism is ethical from the beginning all the way to
Enlightenment Enlightenment is an ethical uh experience but uh it's not kind of
called that it's just called Dharma it's just called Dharma practice or so you have to kind of read between
you have to kind of read more carefully to see that every step along the way um there's an ethical quality to it and one
of the characteristics of this kind of ethical quality is that um it's a
natural consequence of the mind's or the heart's Beauty and to cultivate this beauty to discover
this inner beauty this wholesomeness this sense of um is synonimous with
culturing cultivating it an ethical sensitivity which in Buddhism is defined
as Inseparable from is kind of Ethics in Buddhism is is defined as um that which
avoids causing harm but but instead causes benefit it's that easy so that's
the whole domain of Buddhist idea ethics and of course it can get complicated uh that you know how to
analyze that in different circumstances but um but that that orientation to not
causing harm is considered in Buddhism is profoundly beautiful and I've met
people you you really clearly feel that that's their orientation and I think they're just beautiful people the inner
beauty uh sometimes I've made meet people who uh are Inca seems like this person's incapable of of uh telling a
lie and so it's just you know just kind of you can feel it in them and I said wow that's so beautiful and so wonderful
so um so rather than rather than shaking my finger at you Nancy say you should be
ethical I'll just smile at you and say let us see your beauty your inner beauty
that would that would serve the world world well so someone back there outside had a
hand that I saw before for so let's uh see if we can bring that
up thank you uh I think at this time uh in the world I I don't want to go into
detail but in our country some people feel a responsibility for addressing uh a potentially very dangerous situation
for our country as a whole and uh when I think about this I remember Martin
Luther King crossing the Pettis Bridge he was leading lots of people in a civil rights protest he was in the front of
the line he was addressed by people making violent threats and he surprised people because he knelt in prayer in the
middle of the March he just knelt down and started to pray uh I wondered if you had any uh help for people in that in
that kind of situation I think some of us find ourselves in right now uh in terms of meditation or some practice we
could do that would help us right now thank you well I think uh all the Buddhist
practice is a preparation for that capacity and I say that because that's
that was really the first uh reason why I got interested in Buddhism was not my
suffering but rather was uh to be able to um step into exactly those kinds of
situations and not be afraid of dying because it's a risky right yeah someone is I'm dedicated to
non-violence action so it's not pacifism in the sense of not doing anything but
rather you have to show up but to do it non-violently and I could see when I was 20 that uh how important that was for me
but that I I didn't know if I could do it because I felt afraid of potential death that would come and uh and I
thought Buddhism had the answer to that that issue of of uh you know of of fear of death
and that in terms of what how it's been changed I'm not afraid of death now I don't I don't particularly want to
die and uh you know I'll be careful and how I drive and things like that but um
but the um but uh I have a in a certain way a
um a kind of a positive orientation to dying uh if I could die if I'm lucky
enough to die consciously because it feel I imagine that it's very much like
a process of the deepest meditation you go into and so I so the idea oh that
would be cool so so but but more specifically
what you can do so all of Buddhist practices this so to meditate to practice and know your own mind well so
that if you get afraid if you get angry in a situation like that um it doesn't take over take you over that you know
how to stay balanced a quanus you know how to stay peaceful even no matter what's coming your way that you're able
to stand there and look someone in the eye as you know there's someone that we know that uh was at the riots in San in
San uh San Francisco State University it's called San Francisco State College back in in the
Vietnam War and was up against a riot police and looking you know pressed up
against him and looked him in his eye and was changed for the rest of her life by that what she saw the humanity of
that person chartman tells that story often and I've known someone who uh was
in the Civil Rights South and um was literally three days in a row was beat
up by the same white racist in in a protest or or two days MH and then the
third day the same guy came to beat her up and he had his fist up in the air to
strike her again and uh he he looked her in the eyes and he stopped and he said
what are you doing here and then they had a conversation and there was no more violence so to
have that ability is phenomenal to know yourself well and then one of the
classic Buddhist prayers that we would do is is we would uh rely on loving
kindness love and kindness meditation and so our equivalent perhaps of of
stopping to pray is to wish the the enemy wish the our people adver who are
fighting against or you know fighting against us um uh wish them well and
cultivate Goodwill and spread that Goodwill thanks a lot thanks a lot
Gil so so you can bring it here's we have
another mic but that helps sometimes yeah yeah here we go yeah you can keep it over there in the back end in case
someone else over there once all right this question is going to seem really trivial after all that but
um when I was first taught to meditate I was taught that one should reflect on one's intention before sitting down to
meditate I never understood that question um and I I also was conscious
of not wanting anything for meditation and so so I would so ever since I I say
my intention is to sit and meditate so I don't know if I if I've misinterpreted that or if so so when you
say that when you establish that intention at the beginning of the meditation does that support your meditation I think so but then I wonder
should I just not even bother doing that so so one of the answers to these kinds
of questions is uh uh find the answer for yourself and what I asked you was
the way to find it did it did it help you meditation to establish the intention to meditate at the beginning I
think so but then every time I wonder you supposed you supposed to have a better
better intention Okay so right you wonder if there the right intention maybe there's supposed to be something
Grand I just always reflect back to that and I said I don't understand this question
yeah the um so uh when I first started meditating as I said uh I did because I
was suffering and uh at some point um uh the
the kind of surface suffering that I had been trying to address kind of dissolved and I contributed to the
meditation I was doing and um and so the so that the reason for why I was
meditating was no longer there but the really weird thing was for
me was that I continued to meditate and I like to do things for reasons I'm kind
of a little bit you know logical or rational or something maybe and um and
so I uh I uh thought this is really strange I I'm meditating for no reason
and uh why am I doing this and I was you know I was doing twice a day I I was a college student you know undergraduate there's other things to do
if you're a graduate and um and so you know every morning every evening I meditated and
why am I doing this and um so I had that question for a long time but I still kept kept meditating so
um so the the for now I'll stop for a moment and say that's one answer you
don't have to have an intention you can just do it anyway maybe something inside deep inside knows that this is what
you're doing you want to do this there's no question which was my case eventually what I realized was that um I was
meditating uh uh as a form of self-expression not as something to
attain and uh and associated with the way that a uh an artist might paint or
dancer might dance as a form of expression it's not about finishing something or accomplish
anything it's the very Act of itself and and that became really important orientation for me for meditation to it
was just it wasn't wasn't the intention wasn't any more than just to let this inner expressivity flow through me that
was Deeper Than Words deeper than my emotions deep really a deep thing um some people uh give that
instructions to to connect to your intention at the beginning of a retreat the beginning of a sitting because um
then people have gave a little bit more sense of um focus on the practice uh
otherwise uh you know we're sitting there and thinking about what should I have for lunch you know or you know my boss
yelled at me yesterday and I really need to come back with a better rejoiner tomorrow and you know that might be
important but uh it's maybe meditation is more important and so uh and so to be
reminded oh this my intention is to and is to really sit and be focused and be
here and so that kind of lets the kind of the extra stuff fall away and we're
more here to do it if it doesn't happen that doesn't help you you're more than
welcome to drop it there's no shoulds in this practice the only should would be
for you to learn how to be your own teacher in the practice so you so by trial and error find out what works for
you what doesn't work but it does help if you have an some kind of sense of why you're
practicing what you're practicing for and um so what I like to do and I
don't want to mess you up even more what I like I what uh um I one of
the great exercises I think is to ask yourself I I did that for a year every
day ask yourself the question what is your deepest intention what or what is
your deepest sense of purpose what's your deepest sense of meaning that you have and uh and what it was great to to
do it over a year was I I started going through all these different answers and I had one answer and then the next day
somehow support me to go a little bit further a little bit further sometimes I had uh negative answers like um I don't
want to be afraid anymore that's my intention but if it's negative then I'd ask myself well
Gil if you were not afraid what would your intention then be and that would
drop me into a deeper place and it would change over time it was really great and
um and and then but then I think this question is so our lives are so
important so valuable that if you're asking answering that question for
yourself and you don't see how meditation relates to that maybe you
shouldn't meditate thank you that's all is that okay answer Al also pretty
lengthy we have questions from the h yes sir so we got two online questions
I'll ask first Pat Ho's question how is Dharma attended to in
personal relationships especially family and intimate others like wives and
children um well I think that in these relationships
there's a higher degree of of
uh um connection emotional connection
there's a higher degree of whether we know it or not there's a higher degree of um impact what we do and and U
benefit that can come from the relationship that um that uh it I think one of the things
Buddhist practice does is for us to appreciate the the the privacy of those
relationships or the depth of those relationships or the potentiality of those relationships and for Buddhists what I
like to believe is that when we have these kind of more primary relationships that um um to
always discover how to love the other to always be able to um find you
know something like love or Compassion or care and at different times different ones will be operating but um but my
belief is that is that least I'll say it for myself at some point uh in my
Buddhist practice I felt it was possible um to find a way to love
everyone and it was only then that I felt uh Inspire inspired or something or
transpired was not the right word word but I felt um I could uh be get behind
being married and uh because I thought this is the person I want to always discover
where I can find the love no matter what happens yes we'll grow separate and yes we'll have different things that happen
and all kinds of things but I I want to I want to always I know you love can be Universal and I always want to come this
person I have committed to always coming and finding it so I think to have that a primary characteristic of the
relationship means that we're dedicated to not letting anything interfere with the clarity and the
openness of the relationship so we don't let hate or angry or resentment or Envy or we don't
let uh greed or expectations or lust or or um um projection projecting our needs
or our values onto the other because all those things makes the water muddy we
want to we want to have this clear you know clear seeing or a clear space in
every relationship we're in and so that takes a lot of self-work you know to really recognize okay now I'm resentful
now I'm angry I guess I have work to do this now now this is part of my practice
and even if you can't let go of the anger or the fear or the hostility or the resentment or or sometimes the the
the worst that can happen to someone is they close they they shut down they
close their heart to some other people I have no anger yes but your heart's
closed and um and so and so the part of the purpose of mindfulness and practice
in Buddhism is to always bring enough attention to yourself to really see
where the tension is where the stress is where the where we shut down where the
UNH wholesome non- beautiful parts of the heart are
taking predominance and to not believe in it not trust in it not prioritize it
not uh give into it and and um that might not automatically help us to love
other people but if we we try to jump over to the love before we do this inner
work the love might not be so genuine so in Buddhism at least always
this deeper look deeper look here look here look this is my work this is my work and as soon as you say this is my
work then you're starting to become free from the to from being caught in some of
the ways that we get attached in relationships and with with deep primary
relationships uh the attachments sometimes are the very uh deepest ones we
have um and so the stakes are pretty high in these relationships because if you're
really going to let go fully whoa that's scary in these
relationships I mean I can't let go of that but Buddhism says you can and the
reason you can is that the love the compassion the care the respect and
maybe the commitment remains that doesn't have to go away when there's no
attachment in fact I'd like to believe that uh the love is actually better when
we we've let go fully and um and so um so so that's
that's so I don't know if that answered the question for how we but that's my best
effort thank you one more question from Jamie
Andrews is there a connection between nonself and emptiness are they from different
Traditions oh well thank you Jamie I remember you fondly from the many times
you sat here in this room so
um uh yes and no there are uh the way that um these top these ideas of
emptiness and not self are taught very in different Buddhist traditions and
there's one school of Buddhism called Mahayana Buddhism which is the Buddhism of kind of East Asia especially Tibet
and East Asia and um and they made a specialty around the philosophy and the
practice and the insights of emptiness so you know so they go to town to talk
about all the different forms of emptiness and and when you spent 2,000 years with the philosophy of emptiness
you can imagine that it's varied and Rich and and if you want to you know you
could you could spend a lifetime as a Buddhist scholar uh digging into the
different teachings on emptiness and but in the earliest form
of Buddhism uh it's there as well but in our tradition um there's a connection
between emptiness and and there's a number of connection between emptiness and not self and one of them is that um
the uh every thing the inside this vipasana that we have the deep inside
the clear seeing some point we don't have to believe in this we don't have to understand it you philosophically or
read a book to understand it but it's something that becomes obvious it's revealed to the eyes in a completely
obvious way nothing could be clear be clear as the practice deepens that uh
nothing in our world of our experience or they say differently
everything in the world of our experience is absent of
self so so you know so so you know of course for many people that's
outrageous I mean what you know well what am I you know do I disappear do I not exist what goes on here and uh and
so no you're just fine but uh but there isn't this uh
coagulation around a concept cep ideas around self even the very simple feeling
of amness I am if there's a feeling for that in Buddhism they say that's not
quite free yet there the very very little constellation of amness we feel
even when that Fai dissolves that's freedom but you're still there you're
still you know fine um so I don't know if that answers Jamie's question well enough but maybe
that's enigmatic enough to u to spark your curiosity around this
topic so there's a question way back in the outer Hall can we pass it back there
and oh sorry about that Kurt you can ask
afterwards um thanks Gil um you spoke a lot about K SE can you turn it up the
volume a little bit I think you spoke a lot about about suffering being a motivation for no no
know it's yeah if you hold it uh horizontally yeah oh there we go okay um
guess you spoke a lot about suffering being a motivation and think that's something that deeply resonates um for
where I am in my practice I feel a lot of sadness still and so I wanted to I
guess want to ask if you have any can talk to more about kind of how to what can be supportive for practice when
there's still a lot of sadness for kind of the sufferings going on in what's around us great great yeah well thank
you yeah with the uh there is a ancient teaching in Buddhism idea that everyone
comes to Buddhism because of suffering not everyone realizes that but one way
other people come that and then the suffering has to take some flavor 31 Flavors of
suffering and so uh I I I have tremendous value uh I really appreciate
very much someone coming up and just saying matter of factly my flavor is sadness you know this is this because it
has to be something and but be so clear about it and open about it I think you're well on your way to finding
finding your way with it so thank you and um the first thing that occurred to me
and I don't know if it's I don't know why it occurred to me I don't know if it's particular to something I'm
understanding about you just with a question or maybe it's just me maybe that um uh the the first thing I would
like to say is uh be a sad Buddha and I say that in the sense that
a sad Buddha means um don't feel like it's don't don't try to fix it or make
it different or feel bad about yourself for being sad it's sadness sadness often
needs needs time it needs to have to be allowed to be there and many people
don't know how to let sadness be there I mean they they they know they know their sad but then they're adding layers of
reactivity on top of it I shouldn't be sad I'm I'm wrong but I'm sad I mean after all I'm a Buddhist I'm supposed to
be always smiling and loving and you know but I'm not now a bad Buddhist because I'm sad so there's layers of
things that we do or just might feel so uncomfortable the body tenses up or you
might feel so discouraged because whatever reason and um so the F so this
idea of just being a sad Buddha is to find a way to just allow it to be there
and then what we do in mindfulness practice is once we can learn how to be very simple make space for it allow it
to be there as if it has permission to be there uh then we can begin maybe uh
seeing it more clearly uh find out uh not to understand it you know to analyze
it but to really get uh deep more deeply familiar what's the roots of it in our
body how does it play out in the body body and part of the benefit of feeling
emotions like this in the body is the body is a processing
center that works much better than the mind and so it's a kind of way of
getting out of the way helping you to get out of the way of the emotions so the motion part of emotions can operate
it can be in moving and all emotions want to move so even sadness wants to do
something and what's sometimes these more uh you know painful emotions uh
before they can heal or become better or do what they need to do um they need to be stronger so then the practice if you
have enough practice you start having confidence it's okay I have the ability to be present to be with it as it gets
stronger and hold it be a sad Buddha and um and um so I have a lot of respect for
sadness I think sadness is something really important inside of us that something and something my idea about
sadness is that it's a The Harbinger the of something that wants to be born
inside and what is it that wants to be born so the ability to just allow it to
be there give it permission to be there to look go deeper see what else is there
and sometimes sadness underneath sadness might be hurt and so maybe the hurt needs more time sometimes uh uh below
that hurt might be love and maybe that love now has a chance to grow and and and and inform how we
relate to the challenges we've been in uh or maybe uh you know sadness and
depression sometimes are not so different and we have a culture I think now in the
west that I think has developed a very negative attitude towards depression that somehow it's wrong and
you should you should fix it as soon as you can you know anti-depressant medication and sometimes uh depression
and sadness is a kind of a a allow is a kind of I think of it as a little bit of
as a fallow time that something wants to work
through or something new wants to come and sometimes we need to give ourselves the time quality time in being sad being
depressed just to see if there's something else that wants to come that we're missing out on that and um and if
we don't allow give that some people don't give themselves that time and they rush into what's next what they think
they should be doing something kind of lingers deep inside that is never that
remains unresolved so anyway is that is that I'm just I'm just talking a lot today but is
that enough or you want to ask another question that because it's an important question so if there's something more
specific please I'll digest that more and then I feel like and then in some other time we
can talk more yeah if there other questions well maybe we're almost ready to stop maybe Kur if you have if you
think my answer can be short well I'm not sure about your
answer being short but my question is this and I and I have to say that all
that you've been talking about today have sort of been answers towards my question I'm about to ask but maybe you
could um elaborate even further my question is this um given the political
nature and I'm going to use words like Trump and Biden um so forgive me
everybody or don't but here's my question um I am
experiencing and I know a lot of people are experiencing um a lot of fear
anxiety uh uh judgment and rage and anger okay so I'm I I find myself filled
with all of those things with respect to this fellow uh uh Donald Trump and I
fear given the last debate I fear that he has a good chance to win so my
question is this Gil can you give some words and thoughts to the how one like
myself can uh respond if in fact he wins but even if he doesn't
just I am so judgmental and and fearful and resentful
all these things so you get it so are there any more thoughts you can give to how one like myself like I can respond
to these possibilities and I know part of it's my future projecting but anyway that's my
question so you know real short answer please yeah
I think one of the huge issues in the world these days but also in this
country here is um not political it's uh
hate and uh and
fear and the and the for the kind of divisiveness that comes from that in all
directions you know uh and uh and
um and if there's going to be a solution that's really going to be
valuable there has to be some deep addressing of this issue of divisiveness and
hate and that work can only
happen at the individual level so it needs to start with
you and if you're so so mesmerized so
enamored so obsessed with what's happening out there
you're actually missing yourself in a profound way and probably the more that
you're Pro concerned out there the more there's a need for you to
really drop down deep inside of yourself to see what's really going on for you
there's probably some form of suffer uffing in you that's actually primary that's responsible for
this orientation and and um that's
external and this um expectation that
the answer is out there and someone is supposed to fix
it but the real isue is hate and that that's divisiveness and the fear do your
work and in the meantime while you're doing that if you're really concerned about any kind of world situations
strong enough uh part of people one of the reason that people feel like what you're doing is they feel
helpless do something do something anything at all that addresses what you're most concerned with even if it's
very small licking licking stamps which no one needs
anymore and uh so um
so that's the hopefully short because because you you know you my answer was supposed to
be short I I want it to
be penetrating for you I hope it did thank
you okay so now that we've we have deep Insight we have love
we have not attachment we're ready to do the practice we have either do or do not have a good intention to keep
practicing um let's bring it all to bear for potluck you're all welcome to stay it's
very nice whether you brought something or not and maybe because it's a polu if you'd be willing to take even two
minutes to say hello to two people next to you and introduce yourself briefly
and then give we need a little bit of time to set up the last of the polu stuff so and if you don't want to even
stay for that that's fine but uh it's nice to say hello and maybe say something
about what we talked about today