so uh so welcome folks
um yeah happy to uh to be with you so we'll uh do the usual thing
and um say a few words and we'll say it and offer some some
Reflections so
meditation involves uh directing directing our
attention it involves making effort it involves exerting a certain
kind of intentionality and
willfulness and it involves all these things and
yet all of those things generally
invoke a sense of self direct the sense of attentional
agency the sense of making effort sense of intentionality or
willfulness and so meditation also is about a kind of
awareness that doesn't depend on attentional
Direction it's about effortlessness the kind of deep
relaxation of a pure kind of receptivity
it's about choicelessness it's about relinquishing all sense of like
doing all sense of willfulness all sense
of autonomy
really it's about all this stuff right and it's not like the self is bad and
and not self is is good in a way you know one of the kind
of effects of practice over these years is the recognition like oh yeah I'm I I really at a deep level don't
care how meditation goes the viscos it of self that
arises it's not one's right the other wrong but we we're learning
to um different chambers of the Mind
capacities and so yeah sometimes and I'm going to have to give instructions in about 30 seconds and I'm going to talk
about directing effort and marshalling the attention in one way or another
making choices these things and
uh and sometimes we do that so as to enter
Realms of choicelessness effortlessness the absence of
willfulness so somehow I felt inspired to say that but I really really do not
know how I will guide this
meditation but uh we will practice one way or
another so find uh find a posture that
uh feels
sustainable e
self is not the last word of the Dharma nor is not self
we're not trying to Vanquish some Alter Ego in us or
something just studying the ways
that the uh intentional direction of attention
the effort we make the choices we make this can compound sense of the
meditator orchestrating all of it
so we begin by making some
choices by directing our attention by rallying our energy
what's the meditative anchor kind of home base for the
attention what's inside the circle that we draw that we call the focus space and
what's outside it maybe inside it is just the
sensations of breathing the rest of the world is outside it
maybe
we Marshall our effort
the effort to let go of discursive thinking when it grabs
us very gentle effort of directing our
attention spotlighting the breathing for example
sense of some measure of autonomy of choice
making of strategizing and
preference all of that's okay
so we establish uh some
stability
e
e e
maybe we give our ourself little mini Dharma pep
talks
reminders the wisdom it would be wise to remember
now
e
e e
it's quite natural for there to be a sense of the doer and the
deed the meditator and the object the meditated
the spotlight and the
stage the worker and the effort
and so much Dharma goodness develops along these lines
but we also don't want
to um miss this other dimension of
practice that uh involves this kind of deep
surrender of the doer and the
doing that leaves no room for the meditator to congeal
where matter and the mirror
merge
e e
this is not something we can
do the doing sense of responsibility is exactly
what for closing is this
possibility to the extent we do anything we
do surrender
relinquishment Trust the
silence offer ourselves up to the dma's
grace
e
e e
the very notion of a kind of
hierarchy not self higher than
self guarantees the congealing
self
e
e e
the Dharma contains so many different medicines
just kind of take what's offered by this
moment
e
e e
okay so uh it's good to say with
you
um Dharma practice we we often kind of I don't know find find a
ourselves circling back to Old loves things that maybe we put aside as
you're practicing or training they sort of become relevant
once again and um I was
remembering uh undergraduate class philosophy
class a professor said um we're we're all IDE is in the mind of
God and they were alluding to uh a that's a phrase from uh George Barkley
1700s uh this philosophical School of idealism the the idea that uh um reality
consists exclusively of minds and their ideas no material
existence and uh that phrase you know we all ideas in the mind of God just like
did something to me and um the Buddha the Buddha was not an
idealist uh in that sense believed in in the the reality of things of people of
trees of chairs but maybe we can say in in
certain ways that the Buddha was an idealist about one
thing suffering the the core of all things the
Buddha said is Liberation the core of all things is
Liberation and the experience of of suffering is far
more plastic more fluid than a table or a chair we've taken
are suffering to be more like a chair than maybe we
should and so the dhap begins all experience is preceded by mind made by
mind led by mind and this is not the claim that the
world doesn't exist or it's all just an idea in the mind of God
it doesn't mean that but what it means is we're always we're always doing
something to experience our mind mediates all of
it as more plastic than we
appreciate and when we think about um clinging clinging this
kind of core problem the Buddha highlighted when we think about clinging
usually think about the very coarse level of clinging of very obvious
grasping aversion the craving for some sense pleasure or something is like very
obvious the aversion towards some unpleasantness very obvious
right but before the clinging even begins there's
clinging and some of what we're doing in our Dharma practice is
noticing the the clinging before the clinging the
clinging before the eruption of very coars level clinging
right and so maybe we we have the sense of like we're just okay I'm just sitting
here right sitting here we're waiting for the world to kind of greet us right
and there sights and sounds and and thought and uh and feeling right and
it's almost as if we we imagine having no mind until
there's sense contct right until something the world hits us there's no
mind or there's no place for clinging to arise
and so it's it's as if like the model of the world that we have are entirely
reactive they just react to incoming sense
data they're inactive or quiet and then with experience the models reactivate
right and then maybe I'll cling but are are
models never idle mind does not Idol does not Idol our
models are being reiterated Moment by moment even when it's very simple even
when there's not a lot of coarse grasping or
aversion right so in that that the chain of dependent
origination the the the the sequence that is often highlighted con contct
feeling craving clinging contact feeling craving
clinging but and and there's a ton of action there right and that's part of
why I think we speak about about feeling so much this kind of like
um yeah the the valance the affective arousal and
Valance but before that even happens right before
that even happens there is uh there's Sanara volitional
formations aito calls the sar's like formative
energies formative energies sar's shape
experience they they're woven into the model we have of
experience of the world and so maybe we say that that's
the clinging before the clinging the clinging before the clinging the subtle clinging before the contact and the
feeling and then the more dramatic clinging that can arise after the
feeling but we're becoming as practitioners we're becoming more sens sensitive to the clinging that precedes
the clinging we're becoming more sensitive to the
ways our our motivations our motivations suffuse
Consciousness even before there's the coarse clinging the ways wanting and
knowing are not strictly separable and so so just in the the
movement of our of our attention was highlighting in the sit
you know the movement of our Attention our attention is often it often functions as
a kind of appendage of our
wanting and so it's a profound kind of Journey it's
subtle work to see what is the mind doing sort of before anything happens
before we're the eruption of more uh coarse level clinging
craving and so we look what what are the effects of the kind of more
subtle I don't know whether we say clinging subtle clinging and shaping The
View so clinging is
um yeah just almost woven into our biology kind
of strategy for for control for
acquisition to to manage some s you know to just to
like to stay okay and is very innocent in that
way want to appreciate the innocence of that but in order to to sort of like
orchestrate our clinging we need to make the world more
solid everything becomes a thing and the world we sort of freeze
the world into things the world gets divided into that which helps that which
hinders friends and enemies and uh in that gesture the self
the sense of self becomes more uh is reified it becomes more real more
viscous more congealed and so the sense of of the
kind of this fundamental alienation of dualism is born out of clinging born out
of clinging and some of what was pointed to
in the as we're sitting right and part of uh what
meditation is about part of what our practice is about is uh
detecting and relaxing these more subtle layers of clinging the formative
energies that uh shape the view and we start to see yeah always to
cling to cling to strategize we um we need a self
basically but Letting Go relinquishment does not
the uh third uh Zen patriarch said when the subject when the subject
disappears there can be no measuring and comparing the subject disappears there
can be no measuring and
comparing the need to make sense of the moment that need to
narrative narr to narrativize to tell a story about the moment the need
to measure and compare the need to kind of freeze experience into
language this is what begins to fall away as we relax this subtler layer of
clinging
and a lot of the there's no room there's no room for
so many the habits that get us into trouble we surrender there's no no impulse
towards measurement and you know comparison and evalu ation
and just everything becomes much much
simpler and wondrous wondrous we were
simultaneously disenchanted with Sam SAR but uh amazed
too and so we practice we practice
we'll uh we'll keep uh keep exploring
know don't let uh don't let the the heart's gesture of relinquishment become
ens snared in the doing of
self okay stop there offer this for your
consideration look forward to uh being back next week