so welcome welcome everyone you know what Jim I wonder if the volume can be just a little bit lower I'm speaking as
Softly As I can there we go thank you that's a little bit
better nice to see you all here on a Monday
evening so tonight I'm going to continue on a series that I've been doing I think this will be the last in this series and
it's perfectly fine if you weren't here for the earlier one but this series is on like efforting or
putting forth energy or having determination or resolve or you know
these types of things like having an aspiration and then moving that
direction I'm just going to flush it out a little bit more on the talk
tonight and I'm going to start uh with a story a story that comes from the suas
that is the literature from the early Buddhist
literature and this um the story is about meia he at this time was the Buddha's
attendant some of you may know that Ananda was the Buddha's attendant this was before Ananda so this you know meia
and the attendant was somebody that would just take care of whatever the Buddha needed and I don't know exactly
but in my mind it was like when people were wanted to talk to the Buddha maybe would be the attendant that would say
well not right now they're talking to somebody else why don't you come back in an hour or you know something like
this so me was the attendant and one day he goes for MMS rounds which you know
all of them did this is how they had food and how they supported themselves was to go to m rounds every day so meia
goes for Ms rounds and on his way back he's walking along the banks of the
kimala river and this is like a a detail why is this added there's no particular reason
in my mind I'm thinking because it must have been a really Pleasant River because while he's walking back to go
see uh after his MMS RS back to where the Buddha is he also notices that
there's this mango Grove nearby and he describes it as really
Pleasant and tranquil and he has just thought oh this would be a good place to
meditate we can imagine right it's not like they have meditation centers Retreat centers or anything like this
right they were having to find just where in nature or sometimes they had buildings too but where would be a good
place to meditate so he while walking along the river found this
spot so he comes back and says to the Buddha I think I'm going to go meditate
at this uh mango Grove and the Buddha says no it's not the
right time right now meia wait for someone else to come here so the Buddha
needed an attendant he didn't want to be without his attendant at this time and then magia says but sir you
have no more work to do and nothing that needs Improvement but I do so I kind of
appreciate this like Magie is like really I need to meditate
and then the Buddha says no a second time I need please stay here until
there's another attendant and then the meia says in
response but sir you have no more work to do and nothing that needs Improvement
but I do so this is the third time that uh
meia is asking and it's part of the tradition if you ask three times and
there's be an acquisition saying yes so the Buddha
says what can I say to someone who is speaking of practicing do as you wish so
let's him go so meia I don't know how he feels exactly
but she he seemed pretty determined that he wanted to go meditate right and kind of insisting like you know he was
putting his own needs in front of the Buddhas at this time like okay I just maybe in my mind I'm imagining that
megie is like wow compared to the Buddha I have a lot of work to do I have no
time to waste I better hop to it we don't know exactly so so uh meia leaves and he goes
to meditate he goes to this mango Grove and he sits and he's
meditating and he has a hard time he finds that his mind is assaulted
by all these thoughts unwelcome thoughts unhelpful thoughts UNH wholesome
thoughts and she's just feels like there's nothing but this uh terrible
thoughts you know he saw this mango Grove and he had this idea okay I'm going to go sit be tranquil peaceful
calm so and specifically he says to himself like wow this even has this kind of this word
wow which uh we can translate in a number of different ways but I think the word wow
is uh could be is the appropriate one and he says I left the lay life and
became a monastic right he's a monastic he left his whole life behind and yet I
am harassed by these three kinds of unhelpful unh wholesome
thoughts these three kinds of thoughts sensual thoughts aversive thoughts cruel
thoughts so thoughts of sensuality of like something that uh maybe it's some inappropriate sexual activity he's a
celibate monk after all or maybe it's you just about thoughts of gee why am I
here when the mang goes it' be so much more comfortable if I were maybe even like next to the river or something has
this idea of wanting comfort you also have these thoughts about aversion like gee that Buddha guy
didn't let me go it or I have to go here because the other monastics are in the
way like we don't know what they are and even thoughts of Cruelty a little bit of like some harming or some ill
will so wow I left the lay life and become a
monastic yet I am harassed by these three kinds of unhelpful un wholesome
thoughts I like this verb harassed sometimes it can feel like this or at least in my mind it can feel
like this maybe for you guys it doesn't happen but for me sometimes it can feel that way so he goes back to that Buddha and
reports what had happened about having these three types
of unhelpful thoughts and and the Buddha gives him some
advice but for me I think it's interesting that here's meia who's he's
a monastic he's dedicated his life to price practice and he has what we could say is
one of the world's best meditation teachers and yet he's having a tough time so kind of like normalizes our
experience like humans are humans we can't just automatically make things go
the way that we want so he tells the Buddha and the Buddha says to
him when freedom of the heart has not fully ripened so freedom of the heart
this is a word chuti we could also translate it as liberation of the mind
so that the word chitta some of you know it can be translated as either heart or mind and sometimes it's sful to think
about for us is it heart or mind that we think is needs to be opened or liberated
or softened or transformed or you know what
way so the Buddha says when freedom of the heart has not fully ripened there
are five things that are conducive to full
ripening I like this the Buddha is saying here's like this idea of ripening
is a natural process you know fruits ripen we don't have to make them ripen they know how to do
it so the Buddha is saying well here are some things to help ripen what's already going to happen it's a natural process
that's going to help it ripen so here are the three things
one good spiritual friends and companions people that are on the
spiritual path with us it's friends and companions actually there's also a word
that can be Associates this doesn't mean we have to have best friends it just means
practicing with others so it can be just being here at IMC practicing together
and it also can be you know having a group of friends that you talk about the Dharma with huge range of what this can
mean second ethical Behavior I think we all know this if we
have some unethical things in our lives it weighs on us we have to hide it we
have to we feel shame about all these types of things third conversations with others
that are about contentment arousing energy and then a list of a number of other things I'm
just going to highlight these for now so this opportunity to share with others
and talk about what's uh what's happening with life what's happening with our practice and we could say that
meia he was able to talk with the Buddha and presumably with some of his fellow
monastics as well fourth applying effort and I'm
going to unpack this one some more and five having wisdom wisdom in particular
about seeing the changing nature the impermanent nature of things five things that support a
ripening of the opening of the heart one spiritual companions two ethical
Behavior three conversations about contentment arousing energy and a number
of other topics four applying effort five having wisdom seeing impermanence
seeing changing seeing the inconstant nature of our experience
three out of five of these guidelines are related to effort number four is the obvious one
specifically about apping effort but it also says in the suta a practitioner
with good friends Companions and Associates can expect to be energetic
like that this can be can support practice to be practicing with others to be motivated by others and sometimes you
know we borrow other people's motivation when ours are lagging or sometimes others bother borrow ours and it feels
good to be able to support others and then this idea that the part of the conversations is about arousing
energy like what is motivating what supports us through the difficulties what helps us come back to the cushion
or continue with our efforts and our um wholesome ethical Behavior like we're
never finished with ethical wholesome behavior in our life it's not like okay check check I got that done I never have
to think about it again in my life like this is something that we're always doing like how can I show up in my life
in a way that I can bring the most ease and freedom from myself and others
that's something we're always will be doing this takes
effort so for me when I thought about this I thought well what was wrong with
magia's effort he was the one that really insisted that he wanted to go meditate like really demanded and the
Buddha even said no and he relinquished and then he said yes so why is the Buddha giving instructions to meia about
effort well here's some a few things that maybe we can uh consider we don't
know of course right but here are some things we might imagine one maybe meia was
procrastinating maybe he was supposed to be meditating earlier and he didn't and he said he had this idea like okay I
have to go now because I didn't earlier and so maybe this uh idea of
procrastinating is one way that shows up here and the suit does we all know what
procrastination is it's this like putting off or delaying something that we need to do should do and don't
do putting it off until a time there's this sometimes it can feel like this force that uh prevents us from following
through on what we set out to do gets in the way of what's important to
us and you know maybe it's not surprising because humans we prefer immediate gratification we want to do
what's pleasurable enjoyable comfortable now and sometimes what we should be
doing is not enjoyable and comfortable so we'd rather just do something else and I I'll unpack this a little bit
more this idea of that maybe we we like to uh we'd rather watch something on
Netflix then then do our taxes for
example so there's a suta passage it doesn't say specifically about
procrastination but I appreciate that the he's calling this out he
says there can be a practitioner has some work to do and they think I have
some work to do but while doing it I'll get tired so let me lay
down so they lay down and they don't arouse energy and they are unable to attain the
unattained unable to achieve the unachieved unable to realize the
unrealized like the unrealized the unattained the UN what's it uh
unattained unachieved unrealized right these are the goals these are the things that are out there and you won won't
reach your goals if every time you have this idea like oh well maybe I'll just lay
down and then uh this it continues it says in contrast a practitioner has some
work to do and they think I have some work to do and while working it's not easy to focus
on the instructions of the Buddha so I better Rouse up energy for attaining the unattained
realizing the unrealized achieving the
unachieved so the Buddha is pointing he's just making this contrast where some people are see what still needs to
be done and and want to the manner in which they do it they want to do it in a way that that's aligned with the
Buddha's pra uh teachings so they Rouse up
energy but there's some people who don't okay but how do we Rouse up
energy like this is maybe it's easy to say easy to be written down but how do
we do this well I'll say specifically one way
to work with uh some procrastination this is I I uh heard
this idea from James CLE probably many of you are familiar with James Clear he's the author of this book Atomic
habits it's like it's been a bestseller for on the bestseller lists for weeks
and weeks maybe even years I don't know so it's a it's often when I go to people's houses I often will see it on
their bookshelf there's one of those books that I think all of us can relate to it's just this idea of but how can
we have habits that uh really support a life that we
want and he James CLA he talks about procrastination and he recommends
something and after hearing this I started doing this and I found it really helpful this idea of taking baby steps
baby steps baby baby steps baby steps like really
small something that can be done in two minutes so this takes a little bit like
we have to creative okay what's the very first thing that can be done in 2
minutes so this for me right I'm having to pull together talks and sometimes I'm
like oh my goodness I better get to that and know I have some ideas in my mind
but they're not organized yet or something like this for me I just uh I
have this something that helps me I have a colored pen that I like I have a few
of them in different colors depends on the mood of the day what color I choose and I have a blank piece of paper and I
write down some of the ideas and I like will draw lines connecting them like oh yeah okay this is related to that and
that's not that's related to this and oh this is actually unrelated and cross it out or something like that this I can do
in two minutes and then like oh okay it's the start starting that
turns out to be really difficult and once we've started it's a
little bit easier so what is something that you can start with that takes just two
minutes and this is my interpretation of one reason why the Buddha when he's
describing some meditation he goes into such minutia
sometimes maybe maybe because he recognize this that sometimes we need to just do one small thing at a
time instead of waiting for motivation to arise instead of waiting for momentum
to arrive we can just do something for two minutes and then act often from that
momentum can arrive motivation can arrive and after we kind of like get the
ball rolling so here's how the Buddha talks about meditation
a meditator goes to the forest or to the root of a tree or to an empty Hut okay
go somewhere and they sit down okay here's another little baby step sit down and
maybe that's all you do maybe you go to your equivalent of meditation and you sit down and maybe that's your two
minutes he continues he says having folded their legs crosswise so there's
no requirement to sit crosswise plenty of people do not sit crosswise and they with their legs crosswise and
are perfectly fine having folded their legs crosswise set their body erect okay so taking the
meditation posture whatever your meditation posture is going to a place
sitting down taking a meditation posture then fourth establish mindfulness in
front of them so a little bit how we translate in front of them there's a different ways we can think about it but
let's just say in front of mind just have mindfulness this intention for
mindfulness mindful they breathe in mindful they breathe out half a
breath and then half a breath out so maybe this is something that we
can think about it doesn't have to be like oh I have to go meditate what if we broke it down to these tiny little steps
going to the place of meditation sitting down maybe that's it for one day that's
maybe that's it or sitting down and then really taking time to get a meditation posture
a way in which you feel comfortable in a posture that uh you think you can hold for some time maybe it's like oh yeah my
knee is bothering me I need to have some support or it's kind of chilly in here and let me get a blanket or a sha or
something taking some time with that posture and then just say half breath in
or half breath out and then what's going to unfold next
is going to unfold next as a way to just get us to begin it's so easy for so many
things in our life right to not to keep on putting them off and our life is
passing Us by this idea of one way to work with procrastination is to take
baby steps another way oh let me actually uh James CLA he
talks about he there's a few advantages of doing these uh baby steps one thing is that you have a
feeling like oh okay I did something I did this I went to my meditation place
and I sat down and there's a little like okay that's a baby step and there's this
way to acknowledge okay I am doing something having like these small little
winds having these small little sense of uh progress we shouldn't
underestimate how powerful that can be just these tiny little winds like oh okay at least I did this I I'm I'm
getting there that's I'm going the direction I want to go doesn't mean you know you're going to meditate for 5 days
or something like this we start where we are and then the second way a second one
of the benefit benefits of this is that um it also helps us uh just have this uh
attitude of productivity this it kind of like shifts a there's a sense of the way that we um
let go of beating ourselves up a sense of like okay I am doing
this which means that this sense of momentum can grow
can is that I mentioned earlier instead of waiting for all the momentum before we sit to
just do a baby step and then to do that creates the conditions in which momentum can
begin so that's one way we can work with this procrastination and that was
specifically about you know doing seated meditation practice it doesn't have to
be for seated meditation practice of course it can be anything in your
life here's a second thing to understand what is it or why do we
procrastinate what's underneath this there's lots of reasons and a big
part of meditation practice whether that is Our intention or not is gaining self-
understanding we learn a lot about ourselves when we meditate we learn a lot about seeing
what our minds like to do we learn about what do we do when it's physically
uncomfortable what do we do when we don't want to like
how do we distract ourselves or there's all these ways in which we learn about ourselves with a meditation
practice but some ways in which we might procrastinate is maybe because we don't
really know how to do something like I know I should do this but I'm not quite
sure how I have this little uh clicker thing
for the garage door like okay it feels like it's I the the
battery is getting low but I really should fix that but I don't really know
how I know I could just go find a YouTube uh video and go watch it but
there's this thing like oh yeah I don't know how like if I knew how maybe I would just go do it but so maybe there's
small things that we just don't know how so we just keep on putting them off or maybe you just don't feel in the
mood to do do it like we're waiting to be in the right
mood that works until it doesn't right because often we're not in the mood to
do things and how can we do them anyway and then maybe a third thing that
I'll say here is maybe we're in the habit of waiting until the last minute maybe we don't like to we just uh
think that we work better under pressure and so we got to do things uh at the last minute and we don't want to do
things beforehand this is just our way that we've been running our life the way that we are in the
world so one way we can use our practice as a support is
to maybe we could drop in some Reflections during our meditation like
why are we practicing often our intentions or our
aspirations are not well articulated is there something that we
can gain some clarity by but what is it what is it that supports my practice why
am I doing this maybe we can touch into this maybe there's something that it touches our heart this aspiration and
that can be a support or maybe something else we can
ask ourselves maybe like after meditation or maybe after like settling a little bit and then asking what's
getting in the way like what are the obstacles that are getting in the way of my best
efforts maybe there's something that we haven't noticed some fear for
example or maybe there's this addiction to comfort this feeling like I have to
be comfortable at all times and if I'm not comfortable it's terrible and I need
to blame somebody or blame something or maybe it's
our ethical Behavior can be cleaned up a little bit maybe there's we have some dishonesty with ourselves or some
dishonesty with others and that takes a lot of our energy or is nagging at us or
impacting Us in some kind of way so another way to work with some
procrastination or why we're not putting forward effort doing what we want to do what's important to us is for us to
maybe not h have clarity about what are obstacles what's getting in the way and
it's worthwhile to ask just do some reflection if it's not during meditation maybe some
writing so maybe for meia maybe he was procrastinating maybe not but maybe
there's something else about effort that the Buddha was pointing to and that is
this uh notion many of you will be familiar with this of right eff
many of you will write meaning like wise effort write as in it's the appropriate
effort right as in if you want to put a nail into something the right quotee
unquote tool as a hammer or something that you can hit it with as opposed to tweezers for example like right as the
correct tool so right effort wise effort is is this
uh defined as like actively diminishing what leads to our
suffering and the suffering of others and actively
increasing what leads to our well-being and the well-being of
others so this actively diminishing what's unhelpful
and actively increasing what's helpful this rise effort like is you
know putting energy and effort in this direction and it does require
effort right because there's this we have to have some activity or some energy is essential if we're this these
teachings this path this idea of greater and greater freeding freedom is going to be anything other than just theoretical
or nice thoughts than we have to do some action of course we do that's true about
everything not just this so This wise effort helps us like
bridge the gap between how we are here and our aspirations that we have our
Inspirations that we have and this this way that uh right
effort is has these different qualities sometimes this effort shows up as hard
work manual labor kind of thing perseverance or this gritty application
just hanging in there and sometimes wise effort shows up
this this gentle opening of the heart this maybe this gentle persistent
turning towards and allowing things like shed allowing things to shed and so that
there can be some calming and some settling so sometimes effort is like some takes energy in a and maybe the
conventional way we think about it but there's Al also can be this effort to
maybe open and soften some of our habits of busyness or soften some of our habits
of trying to prop ourselves up all the time and so whatever it might be
whatever it might be so often when we hear this word effort we think strive and
strain maybe there is part of that but that's not all of it and so often we
discard the effort of maybe we need effort to relax too right our society these days really
promotes this sense of like go go go busy be busy be busy and achieve achieve attain attain and we have this feeling
like oh if I'm not doing that then maybe I'm I'm just you know not doing it right
I don't want to admit this we have some Shame about not always
being busy or something like this maybe it actually takes some effort to say no
actually I can't do that right now maybe sometimes it takes effort to
say you know what I'm going to go to bed early even though I really want to do
this that and the other thing but uh I'm going to take care of myself and my life and in this kind of
way so meia so maybe the Buddha when he was talking to him wasn't thinking that
he was procrastinating but he was just maybe meia was putting effort in the wrong way maybe mea when he was talking
to the Buddha was just um thinking only concerned about himself and not
concerned about others or maybe he only wanted to meditate in the beautiful place and wasn't willing to meditate
where the Buddha was in a place that maybe was perfectly fine like we don't know why the Buddha is talking to meia
about effort but maybe it's something we could ask for ourselves like what is what can
be a support for us for our lives what's important for
us whether it's your spiritual practice or whatever it is in your life what can
be a support what can be helpful and how can we increase what's helpful and
decrease what's unhelpful so I'll end there and I'll
open it up to see if there are any questions or
comments Janet last week had asked can you talk about procrastination that I'm I'm like well okay so here we
[Laughter] are yeah can we send the thank
you I'm afraid this won't be very well posed but it seemed like you were talking sort of like social supports
things that support and I believe it was item one and item three I couldn't really decide
what the difference was oh like social and then friends to talk it talk
over with what's the distinction yeah why two categories yeah I would say that
um this the things to talk about is actually quite a long list and some of
things are things that we often don't talk about so they're saying that you could have uh friends and Associates
sometimes you just see somebody like on a Meditation Retreat or even like here
if you see somebody that's sitting calmly in up right that alone can be a support you're not talking to them you
don't even know them but just practicing with others can be a support and then in
and then in contrast to the uh conversations there were specific topics I I just mentioned two but I think
there's like eight topics in that whole list there so okay that that sounds good
so anybody else have a have a comment or a question you're shaking your head no
don't don't make the microphone come to me
oh Jim has
something thank you for your talk Diana I've been thinking about energy and
effort and things like that and I just had conversations with two of my spiritual friends who have been doing um
having energy blocked and they've been doing sematic experiencing and that seems a little bit
different like it's not so much seeing how thoughts are getting in the way of
energy but maybe there's some blockage and so I was thinking about things like
somatic experiencing or Chiang or some of these or um energy work of various
kinds do you have any thoughts about those I I have I have two thoughts maybe
we could think that well maybe we could apply this to go do one's yoga practice
Chang practice or see their SE practitioner or something like this and
two that uh there's lots of um there's
not so much in the early Buddhist literature about like energy in the body
like moving in the body being blocked or not being blocked we don't see that I I don't know why I know in some other
ancient Traditions it's there and I think in maybe in some later Indian traditions it's there but not uh not in
early Buddhism so I don't I don't know why
honestly any other comments or
questions thank you you were talking about how the right effort could
sometimes be something arduous like really like manual labor and other times
very subtle you know how do you what are the kind of cues to look to to distinguish
between the two or across that spectrum and determine what is the right amount of effort yeah this is a great question
I have a I have a a clear answer is this increasing my suffering or decreasing my
suffering and to see okay there's suffering that leads to the end of suffering and then there's suffering that leads to more suffering so is there
maybe uh just to gain some familiarity with this like okay I know that this is
uh yeah maybe I maybe I don't need to unpack that but you have a sense about it because the whole idea is uh right to
increase our well-being and Peace and Freedom and ease and to uh decrease
suffering so the way that we go towards a Ro suffering there is I'm using
suffering as this really really broad word right something really mild to just something really terrible I'm using one
word for this whole range and yeah that's just something to check in and
often the the suffering shows up if it's not like physical discomfort is a little
thought that uh that supports a certain amount of tightness or tension or
closing down and I would call that like suffering there's this kind of like bearing down I got to do
this as opposed to nope I'm going to do this I'm going to do this and kind of do
it with a maybe like a uprightness and openness as opposed to I got to get this
does that make sense it does thank
you okay okay so thank you all and I wish you a lovely rest of the evening
thank you