welcome good morning good afternoon good evening wherever you are whenever you are nice to see you again my name is May
Elliot and we are on day three of the Buddha's five Daily
Reflections five daily Recollections so today we will be
focusing on the third phrase I am of the nature to die I have not gone beyond
death so uh death is something that most of us don't spend a lot of time thinking about
uh so by centering this reflection we can transform fear we can align our life
with our priorities and really become more intimate with the truth of the way things are so this is a powerful one and
uh as mentioned in previous days as these phrases progress um one through
four they become increasing L more challenging and so this one can have a
stronger impact than the last two um so please consider for yourselfself whether
this topic is supportive for you today or you know maybe if you're a little underresourced or feel like you um don't
have the bandwidth for this totally fine too might be a little too much for today
so these these Recollections they should be um you should be carefully titrated
and administered when we actually have sufficient well-being and resiliency to take them in to take them in so uh
please just take care of your own heart um and uh as with the previous days
we'll practice with the phrase in two ways um we'll sit in silence together
and then uh and then we'll shift to dropping the phrase into our practice just letting it Ripple through the mind
and heart seeing what arises and um and then secondly we'll do
an engage contemplation where I'll offer questions and you'll be invited to think about and feel into what comes up for
you in a more engaged fashion so oh and during the meditation I'll offer um
Nikki map's version of this phrase which is um so sweet and so gentle um and
that's breathing in with compassion I gently remember that this body will die
so uh so I'll offer both the traditional and her her version of that of the
phrase so let's get started with our meditation go Ahad and find a posture
which is supportive for you maybe that's sitting standing or lying
down something that allows you to be um have some energy in the mind so you're
not sleepy but also something that invites calm invites some tranquility
and maybe starting just by softening the the muscles of the body releasing any
[Music]
tension connecting with your anchor the breath the global sense of the body
sitting the soundscape whatever it is for you that helps you really land here
in the
present and any thoughts that arise during this time we're not resisting
them or fighting them nor are we getting lost in them taking them and
respectfully putting them on the Shelf we'll be putting them on the metaphorical Altar for the period of our
meditation anything discursive setting aside
go ahead and take some time now in silence to settle and collect the
mind
e
e e
before entering into the recollection
together and start by warming up the heart we can do that with a little meta
little loving kindness the the approximate cause for
meta to arise is reflecting on someone's
goodness so to warm up our own
heart as these Recollections are about ourselves and to begin we begin with
oursel um and then consider others um we can reflect on our own
goodness just taking a moment to uh to consider your own goodness maybe there's
something that you did small or large that was generous
recently maybe you offered a compliment gave a gift listened
well something you appreciate about
yourself just taking a moment or two to
letting go of this
reflection sending ourselves some
kindness as all beings wish to be happy may I too be happy
may I be
healthy may I be safe and at
ease just bringing in a little care a little gentleness for ourselves
and we'll begin with our our
recollection so I'll say the phrase and then just let it drop into
your meditation like a pebble in a pond and let it Ripple through the mind and
heart just see what naturally arises um and with this there's no we're
not calling forth thinking intentionally there may be thoughts or uh thoughts
words or pictures in the mind that arise and that's fine not we're not deliberately contemplating this
time so let's begin breathing in with
compassion I gently remember that this body will die
just noticing what [Music] arises if there's any duka there if
there's any suffering in the heart or mind holding it with
compassion I am subject to death have not gone beyond dying
breathing in with compassion I gently remember that this body will die
comforting as needed there there love it's
okay in your own time now dropping in the
phrase and seeing what happens
e e
when you're ready letting go of
phrases returning to your anchor and settling
back e
shift now to our engaged
contemplation and I'll offer you some questions which you can actively think about um but keep a
short leash on the thinking in the sense that one thought can easily lead to another and another and suddenly we're
on a very far off topic so um so keeping your thoughts close to the question
as um as in they are gravitating around the
being so the first question when you consider that you'll
die how do you relate to it is there fear
sadness [Music] acceptance how do you relate to death
if you to imagine your death consider how would you like to
die what is that moment
like where are you who are you with
what can you see here smell taste
realizing that death will occur what do you want to prioritize
and in considering this is there anything that you want to let go
of or anything that you want to
begin namely how do you want to spend your time
how do you want to
prioritize and as we deep this of course while we are inviting thinking in while
we're inviting Concepts in also paying attention to the body so we have a wide
angle mindfulness to feel and sense emotions Body Sensations as the thoughts
occur
knowing that you are subject to death how do you want to be with
others does it Inspire patience [Music]
forgiveness expressions of love how do you want to be with others
in daily life are you aware of the blessing of life and
vitality of one more day on this
plan are you aware of the blessing of life and vitality
letting go of any flection now coming back into [Music]
silence sensing the body noticing what Sensations are
present noticing if there's an emotion present or a
mood recognizing whatever you find and allowing it to be there
whatever you find is a natural
response to coming to terms with this this recollection on
death it's okay to feel big feelings right no
feelings and meeting whatever you find with some
kindness we'll close with just a few metap [Music]
phrases just as all beings want to be happy healthy
safe and at ease may I too be happy healthy safe and
at ease
May the benefit of our time together support all beings in being
happy heal healthy safe and at ease
welcome back for those just arriving my name is
May Elliot and I'll begin with the first paragraph of a
book uh which has a title that I love it's called advice to Future
corpses and I think it was actually mentioned in the YouTube chat feed
yesterday and the book begins like
this right now imagine dying make it what you want
you could be in your bedroom on a lonesome Hill or in a beautiful hotel whatever you
want what is the season what time of day is
it perhaps you want to lie in sweet summer grass and watch the sunrise over
the ocean imagine that perhaps you want to be cuddled in a soft bed listening to
Mozart or Beyonce do you want to be alone is there a particular hand you
want to hold do you want do you smell the faint scent of baking bread or Chanel number
19 close your eyes feel the grass the silk
sheets the skin of the loving hand hear the long held
note dance a little smell the bread
imagine
that so I I once sat a retreat with biku
analio one of the great scholar monks of our time uh and we spent the whole week
doing an elaborate series of practices involving emptiness and compassion and
all of these extraordinary Buddhist teachings and he spent quite a lot of time during this week telling us how
incredibly profound these teachings were and how much they can transform us and lead to
Liberation and towards the end of The Retreat someone said somebody asked him
uh if you could only do one practice what would you recommend and he said oh well I actually
wouldn't recommend any of the practices we're doing I would recommend death contemp
ation so perhaps that's sufficient to describe the importance of today's
recollection or maybe this from the Buddha the elephant's footprint is the
greatest of footprints of of all the mindfulness meditation that on death is
supreme so clearly this is an important recollection and here we are in the
third um the third of five Recollections I am of the nature to die I have not
gone beyond death this can be truly
transformational and know uh there are many ways to engage in death
contemplation um this daily recollection is just one death contemplation or mindfulness
of death is called marati and there are within in this field of practices there are chal ground
meditations um there's reflecting on the stages of decay of the body um there's a
simple bre breath practice that can be done when inhale this could be my last
Last Breath exhale let go inhale this could be my last breath exhale let go so
there are many ways to do this the Recollections are just one
and uh one of the core intentions uh of this practice is to move this conceptual
understanding of death into the heart into the belly where it can be
digested um because for most of us uh we really can't fathom our own death Beyond
an intellectual understanding in the in the mahabarata which is a revered Hindu
text the Lord of death asks what is the most wonderful thing in the world what's
the most wondrous thing in the world and his answer that we could see everyone dying
around us and think it won't happen to
us it's uh it's simply amazing that it could be happening all around us and yet
still we don't think it'll happen to us like we know of course it'll happen to us but there's uh uh something in us
that can't necessarily come to terms with that our struggles to so uh so it can be really helpful to
spend time with death if we can really get to know it deeply so we can be changed by it but we need to remember
again and again so that we can actually um so that
we can actually bring that into our and really learn to live differently by
it so a few days ago I mentioned uh an aging app that could be downloaded on
your phone uh so today I have another one to share with you which I kind of love that we can turn our phones into
these uh tools for Liberation um rather than nuisances um so in any case like the app
is called we croak we c o a k uh and the intention is
to remind you that you're going to die and here's what they say on their
website uh each day we'll send you five invitations at randomized times to stop
and think about death we croak invitations come at random times and at
any moment just like death
itself so this in a way is like a modern version of this ancient Buddhist
practice of uh remembering
daily uh I I spent the last eight years or so living at Zen temples and um
whenever it's time for a meditation at aen Temple an instrument is played to call
the s to the meditation Hall to call the community of practitioners to the meditation homeall bendo and the
instrument is called a Han it's it's a large wooden block about a foot and a
half wide and a foot tall and it hangs from the ceiling and this block is hit with a mallet so the instrument
functions a little like a a grandfather clock and that it Chimes the hour um
before meditation so the monks can track what time it is by by listening to the Mallet
Stripes now the reason I mentioned this instrument is because of what's painted
on it so in thick black lettering on the face of the instrument uh is this
phrase uh birth and death are given once
this moment now is gone awake each one
awake don't waste this life so with each strike of the Han this
teaching Echoes through the monastery reverberates through the
monastery grounds birth and death are given once awake each one awake don't
waste this life so it it imparts the sense of SGA of
spiritual urgency and this is part of the function of today's recollection you know wake up
spend your time wisely and I hear this this same
sentiment in the last refrain of a Mary Oliver poem and what will you do with this one
wild and precious life what will you do with this one wild and precious life
I was doing this uh this death contemplation practice and having it
done it for some time at some point uh a very deep sweetness arose of just loving
this being that I've spent my whole life with this being called May Elliot who
I've cared for since she was small so sometimes when resting in loving awareness when
the sense of self arises I relate to her as a child so realizing that this child
is only on this planet for a very short time I think about uh how I would want
to treat her how much more tender I would be with her and rather than living
a life based on gried how could I be generous with her kind patient forgiving
so just accompanying this child this ego to the end no need to fix her or ask her
to be different so knowing knowing that you too will die and the part of you that is
still a tender child will have to die how would you take care of that
one you know really tender here dear one let me wipe your brow when you're sick
let me stroke your hand lay your head on my shoulder
so gentle and can we be with ourselves in
this
way there there are many benefits to this practice some of which I've already
named um one is uh we can learn to meet death without fear and perhaps instead
meeting it with awe or here our final Act of generosity is giving our bodies
back to the Earth that's how we related to it another benefit I mentioned briefly
is the benefit of somea spiritual urgency you know to give ourselves more
wholeheartedly to practice uh another huge one is that
we're more likely to act in ways that are aligned with what we value it helps us priv prioritize in a way that allows
us to live more fully and uh one that Nikki mentions
which I really appreciate is that this practice provides a great gift for our loved ones and that they don't have to
take care of uh of your fear and your Terror death if you've already learned
to work through that yourself so uh so the invitation today
is to stay close to this recollection stay close to the truth of death when
you interact with others um when you take care of yourself dressing showering
eating will lovingly care for this one wild and precious
life and so I will close with a poem and this is called uh for the anniversary of
my death by WS Merwin
every year without knowing it I have passed the day when the last fires will
wave to me and the silence will set out tireless
traveler like the beam of a lightless
star then I will no longer find myself in life as in a strange garment
surprised at the earth and the love of one woman and the shamelessness of men
as today riding after 3 days of rain hearing the rening and the falling seeds
and bowing not knowing to
what and thank you so much for your attention everyone I hope you enjoy your day that
you're gentle with your heart and that you can and lovingly care for this one
wild and precious life take care