so hello and welcome
to this Wednesday morning at IMC meditation
time and one of the very significant and
maybe underappreciated teachings and instructions of the
Buddha has to do with the word don't have to remember this poly word but
bharati which means to um abide and I I love this word abide uh to
dwell uh it's very closely connected for me to the idea of um uh resting in the
middle of what's happening and um and it the Buddha you
in terms of meditation the Buddha uses this word abide to rest
within uh as a as something that happens when meditation becomes mature that we
have the ability to no matter what's happening to find a place of rest a
place to abide in what's happening not away from
what's Happening not to turn away and go someplace where we can relax deeply and
forget about our issues in our life but the deepest thing is when we can find a
place of Prof of profound rest uh that is not conventional rest
but something that is deep within maybe you know at the center of
all things there's a place of rest a place of
delightful vital Dynamic Stillness a place of rich
rich intelligent silence
here so maybe today the theme of The Meditation is
rest and that the emphasis on relaxation which the Buddha also
does uh uh is to not just relax and then
relax again and then relax again but to relax and then in the relaxation as to
the whatever degree of softening quieting relaxing we can have
to appreciate the sense of abiding the sense of
rest the sense of quiet or Stillness that's found in the
relaxing and then to begin to maybe have that as a Cornerstone or the
foundation for how we breathe how we are
embodied how we're present for our inner life of thoughts and emotions and
feelings from a vantage point of a place of rest quiet
Peace So to
take a assume a meditation
posture and not to assume it not to enter into a meditation posture
forcefully or aggressively or but to do so
kindly to do so as if you're welcomed into the
posture or you're welcoming yourself into to the
posture as if it's meeting a
friend the posture of meeting this friend that's here your body
yourself a posture that for you whatever posture you've taken you can adjust in
such a way that it feels like it's the balance between between relaxation and being
alert between rest and Clarity with this present
moment and then to take a few long slow deep breaths
and to relax on the
exhale maybe the relaxation Can Be Imagined as a
wave walking through washing through the whole body
and letting your breathing return to normal and again maybe the image of
gentle waves as you exhale exh Alee relaxing softening in your
face around your
eyes
cheeks Jaws
and to relax around the [Music] shoulders the upper chest
the upper back around the shoulder
blades and as the shoulders in the upper torso soften
relax sometimes it can be natural to readjust the
hands the position of where how your arms and hands
reside softening in the
belly relaxing so the belly begin touching
into a sense of being at rest even if it's just momentary ah
there it is that place of rest
as you exhale allow yourself to relax into the
support your body is receiving from
chair floor a cushion a bed
feeling the maybe solid support of where your body is resting
where the weight of your body and the pull of gravity kind of
meet on some solid surface that holds up your
weight this is the place to rest this is the place to abide here and
now in this place at this time and as you exhale few more
times let all let whatever tension that can soften
relax be felt like a falling away
any tension or pressure in the thinking mind as you
exhale let it soften maybe Fall
Away washing off
and then to feel yourself feel the body breathing
with patience allowance
opening as if breathing is the
doorway to a deep inner
connection relax into the body's experience of breathing
for e
and is there in the body's experience of breathing or close to
it a place within where there's
some sense of being at
rest maybe the end of the exhale
maybe at the be the end of the
inhale maybe with the
exhale relaxing the breathing
body and being sensitive to whatever subtle momentary
very sense of their being being at
rest of abiding within what's
happening
for
e e
on the exhale relaxing wherever you can relax
that's easy and at the end of the relaxation
can you feel something that's more at
rest stay sensitive to where inside their sense of
rest being at
ease and let the breathing
arise out of that return to that move through
it
for
e
for e
[Music]
for
if you allow yourself a deeper
sensitivity or a sensitivity to your depths of your being to whatever degree that that's
available can you find a place of rest
or
ease or softness
Stillness a place where things are at
rest and if you do maybe that can be the center of all
things there the center around which everything
else is organized or is referenced
or from where you're aware
and what is it like to gaze upon
yourself gaze upon the world from somewhere within that's at
rest that abides within the field of
experience e
e
[Music]
and as we come to the end of this
sitting letting yourself be at
rest and gaze upon the world
kindly gaze upon the world of your people who are close to
you not so close CL far away friends and family and
strangers colleagues
and gaze upon them
kindly and is there some way that this practice of mindfulness of
attention of finding a place of rest Within
can support seeing the world in a friendly way kind
way a kindness which wishes others
well may others be
happy May others be
safe may others be
peaceful May others be
free and may I live in this world to support this
possibility and if I
can't at least not Mak good
[Music]
worse thank you e
so hello and welcome to this third talk in a five part part series
where I'm discussing the practice of not making
things worse not making it worse and
um this can seem very simplistic it could seem kind of U
maybe not profound Buddhism is a profound religion profound experiences
of Awakening and Enlightenment and and this Simple Thing ordinary thing just don't make it worse can be easy maybe to
dismiss I'd like to propose that all of Buddhism can be found through this
practice of don't make it worse that it's certainly valuable for
beginner for ordinary life and you know everyday
circumstances but to live this way with my mindfulness attention to don't make
it worse um it's a path that opens to all of what Buddhism has to offer even
full Awakening and um one of the ways to describe this is
that say we're um we're fuming with
anger around some computer device that's not working
the way we want it to work and it's been trying to fix it and make it work for
way too long and and um and you can feel the impact in the impact is you want to
throw that device across the floor maybe through the window and then you hear remember this little teaching don't make
it worse and so you stop and you don't throw the
device but then you hear again don't make it worse and then you feel
oh uh I'm so impatient because I really want to
go and you know get an ice cream today it's
a hot day and the ice cream would be so good and I really want that I'm so impatient and this computer is causing
me problems don't make it worse oh
impatience strong clinging into some idea oh maybe I can relax
that and then you hear that don't make it worse and then you see that oh what's
left is a feeling of maybe feeling a little bit lonely from having been too
much on a computer and away from people and friends and uh and you feel loneliness
is kind of a contraction and tightening and and a kind of pressure inside of
feeling a little bit insecure or a little bit worried about the future and future
without any people don't make it worse and so you find yourself relaxing that
pressure relaxing that sense of the future and the anxiety and thinking a lot what it means to have spent too many
hours on alone in a computer and then you feel look now I'm
breathing now it's okay I'm here it's nice but actually I feel that my
breathing is contracted don't make it worse oh I can relax that
breathing and then the breathing relaxes and then you see you what is don't make
it worse mean now oh it means to quiet the mind and not be thinking so much
about the future just be here with the breathing and then don't make it worse
oh uh let me not kind of be straining or pushing or uh being aggressive around
being with my breath that's making it worse let me be soft and relaxed and
receptive around breathing they'll make it worse and then you feel this and you
feel oh this feels good and then there's a complacency sense in oh this is good I'll just rest back and just not have to
work so hard and then you feel like that actually feels a little bit off there's
a loss of some kind of Vitality and Clarity don't make it worse open up to
the clarity of being with the breath and then start seeing some deeper
places of attachment and those soften and so the whole process goes deeper and deeper and deeper so this idea of uh
don't making it worse is not a not a
simplistic kind of everyday kind of little teaching inherent in it is
something very profound in Buddhism so we turn towards we want to
understand how we make it worse so we can learn not to make it worse and what
I'm offering today this week is there's five different ways of not making it
worse and U and today the idea is to rest so the First first day with the w
is wait so if you if you you feel like you're going to make it worse maybe you
can restrain yourself from acting or speaking and so the idea of wait wait
don't give into the impulses that are going to make it worse wait and then uh as you wait
organize yourself bring your B put yourself back together uh when
they often when we're going to make something worse out of anger frustration fear strong desire uh we're actually
becoming partial we're not fully present for all of who we are we got of narrowed in some kind of concern and
preoccupation and so take time to wait and bring ourselves together get all connected
settled here with ourselves and that allows us then to
begin to be here and be at at rest find
certainly relaxing is important and um but uh relaxing is only
half of what's possible is at the end of relaxation find a place where there's
some kind of um uh rest find a rest
here and uh that's a challenge in trying situations where there's a lot of
emphasis something has to be done I have to figure something else this is dangerous for me I better have the right to rejoin her in this conversation and
what but um and so the lawyers of the mind can really insist how important it is to act impulsively or do something
but no rest and part of the value of resting waiting
getting organized resting is that we're now becoming um we now have a chance to
respond when it's time to respond from a deeper more healthy place from our
wisdom from our Good Will from our peace from our sense of wholeness not our
sense of inadequacy or sense of uh insufficiency or
something and so to be able to find find a place of rest and um not to kind of become a
couch potato and just not do anything but uh the the emphasis in Buddhism of
abiding in our experience finding a place of rest is that it's possible to
have a place of rest from which we operate even in the busyness of life
that we can have a sense kind of like being if you're ever done it taking your
car through a car wash and is chaos of these big brushes and water and suds all
the outside of the windows but uh inside the car it's quiet
it's peaceful it's safe it's uh cozy even and now you can watch this all this
excitement and just watch it in a peaceful way in a way you couldn't if there was no car but you were being
taken through the conveyor belt and all that stuff was spraying on you and brushing against you so it's possible to
find a place of rest inside that's like being in the car inside the car during
the car wash and if we're not being disconnected from the world it actually
allows for a deeper connection a deeper participation in the world so um so to find a place of rest
not always easy but uh the stepping stone to it is the other R which is to
relax uh relax find and relaxing is such a profound thing just as I said that uh
don't make it worse can be a very profound practice relaxing can be a very
profound practice for the same reasons that any kind of anything that's in the
way of profound peace profound Awakening Liberation is something which is tense
is something which is contracted tight and uh and one way of describing the
whole path of Buddhist practice is to describe uh a a deeper and deeper and
deeper relaxation some people might say a deeper and deeper Letting Go a deeper
deeper release but if there's need for release there's the opposite of it
there's tightness there's holding and so relaxing is not a a a lightweight things
to do but then in the relaxing then see do you relax into at
the end of the relaxation is there a little bit of Peace a little bit of rest a little bit of ease a little bit of
release appreciate that feel that be attuned to
it it's very easy in going through daily life to be so caught up in the world of
aboutness the things what's happening what I need to do the ideas the fears the projections
and we Overlook maybe the some of the most important things that we can be in touch
with our own sense of inner well-being our own sense of being at ease at peace
our own deep sense that yes I don't have to make it worse at least I can stay
close to this place where it's possible for the what's most healthy most
wonderful about being alive has a chance to surface and flow through and the
being at rest in the middle of all experience doesn't mean being passive doesn't mean that we don't put effort
into doing things it means that somehow our hearts somehow deep in our belly
somehow deep in the in the at the heart of awareness of
knowing that knowing is at rest there's no need for awareness to be
in a hurry no need for awareness to be assertive and
aggressive the awareness the knowing the mindfulness can be at ease while we
engage fully and healthfully with what needs to
be done in our life so
to rest wait organize your body your sense of
self your experience in the psychophysical being and then rest and
so maybe for these next 24 hours until tomorrow uh you want to uh maybe explore
this concept of inner rest and how how do you understand it how do you tap into
it and touch into it how do you protest around being at rest what are your
lawyers saying and how can you allow some deep
sense of inner rest to be something that you have as you do things in your daily
life and you might begin with things which are easy simple things like maybe
sweeping your kitchen floor or cleaning the dishes or doing some cooking or
something that for you is relatively easy and see what it's like to to do it
in reference point to a place of inner
rest so thank you and um I look forward to
continuing uh worse tomorrow