okay so uh so welcome
um yeah nice to see the names and um we uh we'll set
set
just finding a posture in which you can
be receptive to the
Dharma re receive your own wisdom
Ain suito said something like uh what we don't listen to We
Become what's not received in
Awareness we become identified
with what's pushed to the side
disavowed the uh in our resistance we
paradoxically become it
and so just as we begin we just
listen
deeply so that we don't become our resistant don't become identified with
it it's
received
e
the awareness keeps backing up keeps
noticing the attention that uh Creeps in around the project of meditation the
project of
me notices the subtle transactional
mode making something
happen a subtle demand we issue to the
moment we notice all of this bit by bit some of the static melts
away
me come into the the spaciousness that
uh involves uh
frictionless
e
unless we notice what we want the kind of background agendas of
wanting uh our knowing is um suffused with the
wanting
and so we we notice some of these agendas this tightness this tension this
transaction this bargaining we do with the
moment the way we leverage the present for some
future we notice all of this and in this
way the The Knowing becomes less [Music]
entangled those
agendas The Knowing of the breathing body sound
feeling
e
e and faith in
Awareness it's a kind of confidence that
uh after all my doing all my
effort all my
strategies after all of that dissolved
we can trust what's
left we can trust the awareness that doesn't depend
on me
e
the L we grasp the more self-evident the Dharma
becomes
e
Michelle McDonald asked the question is the the agenda to
uh to connect or to control
maybe one aspect of faith in
Dharma is that
uh okay to let go of
control something will uh hold us even on the other side of our
control
e
to clearly know clinging
control is to want to release
it
e
okay that's good to uh good to sit with you
um yeah I hope uh YouTube is okay it's it started um there's a default that Set
Set uh it as a private video and had to stop the feed this was before we began
but uh it may have been an ex the explanation for couple people having
issues sorry about that okay so
um uh
uh Faith
um there was um there was a period in
uh uh yeah last couple decades when the sort of like uh the educational system
was was um aggressively supporting the development
of self-esteem and is very understandable in a lot of
ways like if you have a more positive view of um of the self it'll
support academic and uh Social
Development but um as it turned out it didn't really work out that way and
the uh improvements in self-esteem when they could be made it's not so easy to make
but when they could be made they didn't translate to that much and to really make changes the kind
of the deep models of self they've been reiterated so
compulsively that it's it's like a song we've been hunging humming you know to
ourselves for many years Non-Stop and so it takes something of
kind of industrial strength to actually uh change that at a deep
level and so this week we've been uh we've been exploring uh faith faith and what does
it mean to have faith in in oneself faith in
oneself does it mean that um we have a kind of rigid
model of what we are and that model's positive positively
balanced I don't think so it's more like
when you know what you're
not is it possible to have faith in
oneself when you know what you're not not then we can actually have faith in oursel when you are no longer kind of
taking refuge in the stories of self you can have faith in
yourself because the the story all the elaborate I making my making the egoic
story is a kind of static really that actually muddles our knowing m
our sensitivity to this moment it it like
the the the congealing of the sense of self actually is a kind of
static and it serves to um buffer our
connection from what's here and so so Faith um in oneself is
not a kind of inflated story about the self it's not grandiose stories it's not
that um I don't know why this came to mind
but um you know I am not a uh I'm not a musical person I have a terrible ear I
can't read music I don't play any instruments I took piano lessons when I
was a kid and I was I you know it's kind
of harsh to say it about a child but I was bad I know effectively nothing you
know but sometimes sometimes when I go to the
symphony and I see whatever uh dudamel or eseka
solonin sometimes I feel like maybe maybe I could be the
conductor just maybe and I got my kind of like in my
head I have my my hand position you know shouldn't I just have faith in
myself no a not uh a not not self is uh the the
truest form of self-esteem the the the
impersonality of one's strengths and
weaknesses and so the this Insight is the end of trying to uh to prove to
prove oneself it's the the kind of dissolving of arrogance and shame which
is the the underbelly of self and then we we start to develop a a
different kind of um of confidence a different kind of faith in
oursel we're very grounded in where we are we come to
trust our our view we come to trust our body trust our mind not the kind of
story of self we relax into
anata and there's a lot of trust that emerges from that Insight a lot of trust
that emerges from an Insight at times may maybe the default
is is there there's a certain kind of deep wobble in the self and we don't trust our view we don't trust our
knowing we defer to others to understand what's what's
real we defer to others we sort of like checking checking looking to this person
that person to gauge what should I what should I think there's a a subtle way we
just keep pinging to others or the prevailing winds to
see what we ought to do
and faith faith in oneself as we become faithful in ourselves this changes we
start to have this um much deeper trust in our intuitive
knowing and maybe it's something like like int intuition you know intuition
some intuitive knowing and in intuitive knowing there's there's
very little doubt and there's very little
self-justification it's very clean very simple kind of uh
knowing you know we know those times where it's like ah should I is is it this is it that is it like a lot of
Doubt a lot of wobble a lot of uncertainty or the other side where it's like
we pick some view or something and then we spend a lot of time justifying it to
ourselves yeah yeah yeah yeah kind of rationalizing it making the case this
kind of intuitive knowing is much simpler much simpler and it it often for
me is just like yes or no this can work it's
whome no this is not going to work out you know and we just become more and
more attuned to that and we become more and more sensitive to the kind of mechanisms of
self-deception the trail of self-deception we we can't we can of
course we still pull a fast one on ourselves you know but much
less and less costly we've become so sensitive to like
how we've deceived ourselves in the past that it's harder to be taken in by the
kind of mechanisms of rationalization self-justification we sort of we're
clearing out some static we're listening more deeply as we listen more deeply we
become um better uh we refine our our
philosophy of Happiness of what it is to be happy what it is to have a good
life uh we become better at predicting what will make us happy what will make
others happy it's very important in this kind of path of
intuitive of knowing actually you know we say be present be present yeah but
it's actually also about making better predictions about uh what completes the
heart what doesn't and so okay given the totality
of conditions given my strengths and limitations uh
what what can work what can work and this is uh
this is a a kind of incredible intimacy with oneself of
of really kind of receiving the totality of data from our own system of listening
more and more subtly taking more and more um kind of subtle cues and for for
me it's a lot in the kind of like subtle
affective you know know feeling cues yeah
what you know how how is this going to be how is
that going to be and I sort of like listen in it may be very quick
process but there's like yeah I actually can feel something relaxes opens or
maybe something gets tense and that's good data we have to learn that's good
data faith in our s is is uh is not
discounting that knowing it's learning to distinguish between
the the commands of our defilements and the kind of uh Clarity of our
knowing and so we we cut through more and more of the static the static that
is the story of self and and then we begin to actually
establish some faith in ourselves faith in in our view in our
view and as um as Phil up uh Philip Moffet says we
become uh we become accountable accountable to what we
know we come into uh
deeper alignment with what we know and so what what do you what do you
already know what do you already know the knowing that's that's free from
doubt and self justification can we stay true to
that this to my mind is is how we uh we nurture
faith in our in
ourselves okay so I offer this for your uh your consideration and uh as always
please please pick up whatever is useful and uh leave everything else
behind okay till uh tomorrow wish you wish you
all well thank you