good morning everyone and welcome and today I'd like to talk as an
introductory talk of sorts of uh something is called the parames in the
ancient P language and uh one of the meanings in it's often translated to
English is as the Perfections which is a dangerous word for some of
us and um but uh the word also means something which is kind of ultimate or
fantastic and um and there are 10 of these 10 parames so I'm going to go talk about
these 10 and some of you might be already disappointed because here we go
one more Buddhist list Buddhism has a lot of lists and
there's actually books of lists lists of lists and um and uh but uh I think it's
reasonable to be somehow discouraged by all the lists that exists in Buddhism and until you understand their
purpose and part of their purpose is that uh they're describing some aspect
of the Ecology of the heart mind the the the natural processes that operate as we
practice the Dharma that get awakened and move through us and develop over
time and the metaphors that Buddha uses for this growth are all organic metaphors of the the growth of a tree or
a plant that flow and develop in contrast to what is made
synthetically so we don't build up the Dharma we don't build a practice like you build a house or or make synthetic
Products plastic or something but uh it's more like a gardener that allow something to grow to develop and so
you're supporting something to happen and so these 10 parames these 10
Perfections are natural qualities capacities that we have that we can uh
we that we can grow that can develop and they grow most specifically when they are rooted or
connected to compassion and Liberation to care for the world and a sense of
non- clinging not holding on tight to things and in fact that's what kind of
defines them as Perfections when they have an intimate connection to compassion and Liberation they both
support the development growth of compassion and Liberation and they're an
expression of compassion and Liberation in the world and uh when I was in Burma a
common uh statement among some of the meditation teachers there was that if
someone was having challenges in their spiritual life they would say oh that
person hasn't developed all the enough of the parames or someone has a really
easy time which maybe once in a million it happens in in Buddhist practice
they'll say oh that person really has already had the parames in place and so
because they were there the person you know was able to practice quickly or
something so I want to talk a little bit more about this this organic process um
it's like a if you ever been through a forest after a forest fire it can be sad
devastating to see everything charred in Black uh burnt and um but how quickly
I've seen in some some areas how quickly sometimes within months um life comes
back and uh things start getting green again some of the trees if they haven't died will Leaf out some of the plants in
the understory begin to appear and um and then uh if some person comes along
and says well it's not supposed those those things that are coming back there those plants that are growing now that's
not the those are not the forest trees we want the forest trees to be to be way it was before so they cut cut away the
things that are growing up um you're actually preventing the return of the forest because there's a natural process
by which um succession of plants will appear after a forest fire each of them
kind of preparing the ground for the next succession of plants until the forest returns there's a natural
succession and a botanist who's following this might make a list of 10
different successive plants and we don't complain like oh 10 plants one one after the other but actually oh
they recognize oh this is how it grows this is how develops one succeeds the other until we're back at maybe in 20 30
50 100 years we're back into the forest that that burnt when I um uh lived at uh I lived
at Green Gulch s center it's in M Beach m m Valley which is um near M Woods in
in Marin County and um uh the San Francisco Zen Center bought the place in
19 I'll tell you the full story because this amazing succession we're we're all living succession of amazing things who
knows why what we have is here because of today uh there was a man named George
wiri who invented the Polaroid camera long ago I don't know they have any more
they make them anymore they do so so uh polar camera and so you can imagine got
a little bit wealthy so he bought a huge Ranch in the
Marine headlines and and ran it as a ranch maybe kind of like a I don't know what
they call a gentleman farmer or something for a while I don't know if he did this or the previous ranchers did it
but they cut direct channels down the down the valley to so there wouldn't be this mandering River Creek that went
through because they they wanted to make fields and farms and they kind of of rectified the the rectified they kind of
changed the wetlands that were down near the beach where the two Creeks came together and they kind of made again
probably deeper channels and made a canal and then they put pumps in the in the uh in the canals and they had Fields
down there and they grew plants and they had horses and cows and hay and all kinds of things at some point uh he
decided to sell it all he was getting older and he sold most of it to the
Golden Gate natural Recreation Area so the state the national park system and
but the the the actual Farm itself he wanted to go some good place and he sold
it to San Francisco's end center it's a remarkable thing to have this Buddhist
center in the merid Headlands this beautiful property and they were able to kind of now have this very thriving uh
Buddhist Retreat Center uh in this beautiful place that was
1972 and I came there Liv there first in 1979 and it was very much like had what
had been and I me remember I used to help with the farming at the bottom the the
bottom Fields down by the ocean and they were kind of salty so they all they could grow was potatoes and we were was
down there harvesting potatoes and helping at some point in these since 45
years since then since I was there someone had the idea that it should be returned to this
natural habitat the natural way the the lower fields at least were a a um
Wetland and partly to allow the salmon to come back up to those two creeks and partly to let it return to what it was
but that took a lot of steps first there had to be a lot of discussion they were going to actually turn some of the
property over to the Golden Gate natural Recreation Area hand it over to them but there had to be a lot of discussion
negotiations and all this and that was so the succession of things that had to happen to return to a natural state it
was a lot of steps there was a lot of discussion people had to be part of it and money had to be raised grants had to
be made and then at some point they had to kind of clear out everything that was
there I don't if they brought in bulldozers or what they did and uh to kind of get rid of weeds
that had come in and I don't know what had come in and then they had to change the the the canals and the rivers to
make it flow the way it used to be and and so river banks could overflow and
create kind of wetlands where things could grow and I hadn't been there for years until I think about two years ago
and I walked by the place where I used to do the fields where I used to grow uh
you know help with the potatoes and I couldn't quite see it anymore because now it was overgrown with the wetlands
and trees and it was beautiful but it took this sucession and
all this planning and step by step had to happen so it turns out that our
Buddhist spiritual life is the same way it's a succession of different things we create a foundation the foundation
allows other things to happen and it's not something that we build but it's something that the conditions we put in
place so that something can grow and develop and a lot of these lists the
Buddha provides if you actually study the lists you see many of the key ones
are actually descriptions of that the the of spiritual
maturation the five faculty starts with faith it's a great place to build to start with you have to have some faith
and some confidence and with that faith and confidence uh you do the second faculty
which is the you put some energy and some effort into studying learning the Dharma practicing the Dharma engaging in
it and as you put effort into it that allows um mindfulness awareness
present moment awareness to grow and develop as you develop more more present
moment awareness and you understand how the mind gets distracted and gets fragmented it pro supports the growth of
concentration and as you get more stable and concentrated that is a foundation
for wisdom so there's a sequence there that follows a progression that's not everyone follows that exactly that way
but but um this is the how way it's presented so many of them so Faith
effort mindfulness concentration and wisdom they're kind of a describes a succession that one grows strong allows
the other one to grow and so forth so the 10 paramas are
this the 10 parames and um in mahayan Buddhism they
have something called that's why I said it paramitas they call it in Sanskrit and they have a slightly different list
of 10 they're not quite exactly same as our school has the
10 and now these 10 qualities are things that are already in the teachings of the
Buddha and way after the life of the Buddha the tradition gathered these
together uh to create this idea of a succession is and they gather together with a brilliant idea or brilliant
brilliant recognition that these things starts with generosity that's the first
one that these things are intimately intimately connected to Liberation and
compassion not that generosity is but for generosity to be a parmy to be a
Perfection it has to have some relationship to our capacity for compassion our capacity for freedom in
the heart's Freedom that's what makes it a part of me it's great to be generous just for
its own sake don't don't wait but U but it becomes a par ofy when
it has this wonderful ful part of an e it's part of an ecosystem that supported or in reference
to our capacity to have caring feelings compassion kindness love uh friendliness
for others and and it has a intimate connection to our ability to not hold on
not tighten down not cling or grasp or crave not be caught in addictions and
obsessions of the mind and the Heart and as we get a feeling for what it's
like not to hold on to freedom of being free then generosity has a can have a
very different feeling because generosity then can be more an expression of that freedom it can be
done with freedom not a few of us will have genuine feelings of generosity but
it gets so entangled with our attachments and our expectations and our
Dias of exchange well I feel generous but they better give me something back
you know it's not just it's not completely pure you know generosity it's then fre with no clinging and
expectations at all and um and then uh yes it could be
nice to be generous but to be generous with a kind of sensitivity to how this
supports others and the key one is compassion which is attuned to the fact
that there's a lot of suffering in this world and we could so we can work as a community as part of alleviating some of
that suffering in the world and so part of the motivation for generosity can be
how to uh support this you know and alleviate suffering in this world which I think is a very profound profound
Instinct that we have so the first part of me is generosity that's the foundation for all
all the nine that are going to follow and one of the brilliant things about it
is generosity is uh done in community you you can be generous to
yourself but chances are it's not quite generosity um generosity is usually
something we do to others to living beings for the planet there can be it's
done in relationship to the world many people start Buddhism in the west with
meditation and it's the first instruction for some people in some schools like us sit down and close your
eyes which is kind of like sit down and shut out the world you know kind of just shut out
your senses to what's around you so you can really focus here it could for some people uh give
the message that being self-serving you know just like it's me myself in mind it's my practice and like all these
people to get in the way and I I just want to become a Buddha you know just you be the best Buddha on the Block
and um it could do that um but uh but the classically the practice begins with
generosity it begins by by caring for how we're relating to others it's a
relational practice that's rectifying or purifying or making healthy the
relationships we have cleaning them up so that they can be have genuine sense of
compassion that's related to our beginning we start beginning some ining
of what it's like to not cling to be attached and generosity is a wonderful
place to learn that because generosity is to be generous it can't be obligatory
to be generous it can't be a should it's a like here please so there's a kind of
a letting go in being generous does it have to be compassionate no but perhaps we can see
where is the compassion here so to give uh you can feel generous to someone and
you might want to give them you know something someone is allergic to peanuts
you have peanuts here I want to give you that's not compassionate uh you
know I had I've had people who I was so full of food already and they just wanted me to eat more and more you know
like please like you know it's now I'm feel uncomfortable because I feel obligated and I'm making you feel bad
and they're just being generous but in a certain kind of way but it just feels like some something's off
here so there generos have generosity to be ATT tuned to people and their suffering and their joy and benefit it
makes makes generos makes generosity to be much much better so so so the first
one is to have be generous is establishing healthy relationships I I would suggest I just told my wife a
story I thought I told her be long ago she said when never heard that story I've told it here sometimes so don't
worry um um I when I was about 19 or something I read a study of it of they
called it back then a tribe and Liv in the mountains of the Philippines and there were uh uh people who uh uh had a
huge practice around dreams and apparently every morning families would get up and at breakfast they would tell
each other the dreams they had and one of the Customs was that if you had a bad
dream where someone in the village someone in the tribe was in that dream like scary or
something the custom was to always go find the person as soon as you could and give them a
gift so who knows you know what was going on socially with that fear that or that bad dream around someone there so
they they didn't necessarily analyze it but they just did something positive imagine you know generosity what it does
to our relationships if that's what we're if that's the Instinct and uh I've done this and I've
known people have done this when there's been bad relationships people are upset with each other and someone comes with a
gift and here and um I've done that number of times with people had trouble
with their in-laws bring them a gift and uh and that seemed to have
worked well so um so uh paries begin with
generosity it continues with another social capacity that helps clean up our
make healthy our relationships so emphasizing how important this is in Buddhism and the
second one is being ethical and so uh being being very
careful not to harm people uh live at least a non-harming life it's one thing
to know how to benefit people but and do you know do what's ethical in a sense it's easier to know
what's what is unethical what is causing harm and the the idea in Buddhism is
that sometimes it's easier to know what's the the the uh what it is to
avoid doing than necessarily knowing what you should be doing so the line is supposed to be quite strong in Buddhism
don't kill anyone how to benefit people and life flourish that's not so clear but don't
kill them don't steal from them just don't
steal don't this gets more complicated around sex but don't cause harm sexually don't
be involved in sexual misconduct uh don't lie maybe it's hard
to understand exactly where those are but you know but still don't lie and
don't don't don't don't get drunk don't intoxicate your mind so that you're not
so you're foolish and part of the reason the argument for not to do that is if uh if you're drunk
or intoxicated sometimes you're more likely to break the first three pre first four precepts you you kind of
people become careless and act ways that they when they're wise would not do that way do
it so the idea is to be ethical and uh and that can include positive ethical
beneficial things but the key thing about it it's relational and how is that tied to
compassion is there a relation between ethics and compassion you better believe
it that if you're concerned with people suffering you don't want to make more suffering for them you want to make it
better is there something a connection between uh non-attachment Liberation and
ethics of course there is because most I would say most the great majority of
unethical Behavior where we actively harming other people we we are clinging
to something you don't break the precepts without some kind of clinging you don't kill people without CL
clinging to something stealing lying these things and so as we get a stronger
sense of of Liberation Freedom then uh you know these are the natural ways this
grows ethics grows from this as we're more generous and we have this healthier
relationship to people around us the instinct is to be more ethical because we have this connection we understand
each other we are tuned to people then the next one takes some
explaining and some of you will flee if maybe if you could politely if you hear
what it is the next one is re enunciation isn't that a big dangerous
word and that's the English word which comes from Latin meaning to announce
again that when you uh when you in in the ancient Latin monastic tra uh
Catholic Traditions when a monastic declares themselves to be a monastic that take vows they're
enunciating these these vows of do uh doing without wealth and all kinds of
things without sex and things so so it's just stating against something so I like
it to see it that way because it's something that's voluntary you
voluntarily renounce something that you know to do and in Buddhism the word doesn't mean
the same doesn't it's a different word of course it's p and the literal meaning of the word is closer to um going forth
freely going forth freely into the inter Freedom it's a very different feeling
than the English word pronunciation but as we are living the
world of generosity as we're discovering the value of being ethical and how it
benefits us and what begins to grow inside of us with generosity and ethics it becomes a natural thing to recognize
when we are harming ourselves by clinging and holding on to things we
maybe we feel pretty relaxed and happy and content and we find ourselves now
holding on to um you know some lie that we want to perpetuate so somehow to
create a better impression on people how great we are and then we feel oh that having that lie
doesn't feel good having that clinging doesn't feel good of course I want to let go of it of course I want to want to
go forth into freedom of course and some people actually come and renounce
announce to teachers um on Retreats it's beautiful I love it when people come
they meet with the teacher and talk and then they come next time and say I want to tell you and apologize I wasn't 100%
honest when I talked to you about how my meditation was going and uh and because people get so
sensitive on Retreats they can feel and sense how how they feel off it doesn't
feel right and to rectify that they feel like they need to just say it to someone
so the renunciation and um so there's a movement towards Letting Go not because
you're supposed to let go because we know this is really good it's something
benefits from letting go and so it you again Liberation is right there
in the letting go and it turns out that compassion too is heightened and
developed in letting go clinging interferes with our healthy social
emotions and so here we have the compassion coming in relationship to
renunciation letting go as we let go more
fully uh it feels good it it feels wonderful to not not hold on
and cling and grab and that becomes the source of
wisdom and wisdom is the fourth of the parames so wisdom here is experiential
wisdom here grows out of what we're learning from the first three parames
we're and we're learning for example that uh how to recognize clinging and
attachment and how it diminishes us how limits us the downside of it and we're
learning something about how good it is to not cling and to have wisdom about that we can't always act on the wisdom
but we're starting to see this Dynamic going on and we see that this wisdom
around clinging and non- clinging is also again connected to compassion and
helps connects to our instinct to for further Liberation to let go because we
understand the Dynamics of clinging that sets the stage for effort for
action for courage for engagement in the practice more because now we have the
firsthand firsthand personal proof of what is possible in this
practice we know for ourselves it's possible to be free it's possible to let go I might be 99% of the time completely
attached but that 1% that I had I know something now I didn't know before and
I'm inspired this is the direction to go I see the downside of being attached I'm
harming myself I'm harming others it's not really healthy let me trust this
path of letting go of compassion and so after wisdom there is
this more effort and that the word in poly Veria could probably be translated
as courageous effort and um and sometimes it takes a lot of courage to do this
path with but once you start making effort you're going to have to learn
patience which is the next part of me so this is a you know this is not like
going like getting onto a conveyor belt you know and just kind of sailing to
Nirvana sailing you know sing along you know there's ups and downs and challenges and and um it's kind of like
a really good romantic partnership where one of the partners is troublesome and one is not and so you know so you're
engaged in the practice and the practice is difficult one of the partners is difficult it's not the
practice it's you and you get to meet yourself and see yourself and all the
ups and downs and the good Bad and the Ugly and your challenges and rather than being discouraged by
now uh you you have enough experience you know this is part of the richness
this the this is invaluable to see this part of course you'll be patient with this and keep practicing and find your
way with patience uh and exactly how this moves to the next stage maybe you
you have a better rationale but remember I'm describing a growth succession of how things can develop over time this
tradition says the next one is truth becoming truthful Maybe if you've been
patient and really can stay present and see what's there the Good Bad and the Ugly that allows us to be
truthful and some of us need to be truthful about ourselves about the things we don't want to look at see in
ourselves things we'd rather not admit but to really be able to have the wisdom
and the patience the acceptance to okay I have to admit this is what I'm
doing you know and so and sometimes that's you know hard to come to that truth
but then to understand that telling the truth about ourselves what's going on can be a compassionate and liberating
move that makes it a par ofy Perfection with truth when you see the
truth that's the condition found for the next par ofy which is
resolve resolve is taking a stand this is where I want my life to be
about this is where orientation this is the purpose this is the values I want to
live by and it could be all the previous parames I'll take a stand I'm resolved
on generosity I'm resolved on being ethical on healthy Letting Go healthy
renunciation I'm resolved on wisdom I'm resolved on effort the right effort
practicing I'm resolved on patience I'm resolved to be truthful these are invaluable if you're
going to your life is going to be rooted in something these are fantastic Roots if these are going to provide the
meaning the purpose of life These are fantastic and for people who are devoted to Buddhist practice the Buddhist path
that's actually the foundation you know that to okay I'm committed doesn't mean I can do it but this this mother
orientation I really want to make my life about gives purpose and
meaning and then uh with that purpose maybe we feel really good about
ourselves with compassion and letting go having a healthy good purpose having a
strong sense of connectivity to other people in our society practicing not only for ourselves but practicing for
the benefit of others as well um is now in the domain of uh of even the social
emotions becoming even stronger feeling even more connected to the world and to others and from this then grows uh our
kindness are meta loving kindness friendliness kindness and um and so the
the ninth part of me is growth of a strong feeling of
kindness isn't that that can't be too bad if after all the the the goal the purpose the all this is this where's it
going it's going to becoming a kind person isn't that nice I think it
is and um and then the last one is not always so inspiring for people when they
hear but in Buddhism if you understand what it is and you understand that it's a powerful state of heart mind that is
only there because the first nine parames have been there first they've
been set in place set in motion these are like the like you like you you've
built a beautiful you've you you grown a beautiful tree in your yard it taken
years to let that tree grow there you had to clear the clear the clear what was there there all this terrible weeds
there it shouldn't have been there invasive plants you had to condition the soil you had to plant the tree you had
to water take care of it slowly slowly slowly the tree grew and you protected it from the deer or whatever it took and
eventually you had these beautiful blossoms That Grew there wow but maybe it's a fruit tree and you have these
wonderful fruits and that's kind of the final so we're growing the
parames and the last one is kind of like the blossoms of the tree or the fruit on
the tree so so if you don't like the word the idea I hope I set the stage now
for you to appreciate a little bit more it's equinity the capacity to be have all
these wonderful parames have them alive in you and with those alive that
support to to be able to look at the good and the bad in this world the good
and the bad in yourself and to have a clear open channels to see to know to be
wise without being reactive staying balanced not being
pushed around or dismayed or crash not be goes up not go up and down
with praise and blame just be completely have this tremendous balance and Clarity
equinity and for that that equinity to be intimately connected to the sense of
Liberation that's possible liberation of heart mind and the sense of compassion
for the suffering of the world these are the parmes and so these were put together as
a list this way probably 3 400 years after the time of the Buddha when people
were beginning to think about how do want become a Buddha and the Buddha became a little
more a distant memory but they wanted to they you know the people who are close to his lifetime they had him and they
were happy with who he was and what he had to teach they were kind of fueled by that but probably as over the centuries
afterwards the idea of him being more distant inspired people to say how are you going to have the next Buddha how do
you become a Buddha so they put together these 10 in this way that I described as
a description of what it takes to become a Buddha you have to cultivate all these qualities to become a Buddha so if
someone asks you what does it mean to be a Buddha to have these 10 Perfections perfected these 10 qualities not that
that's not enough to become liberated but the liberation of Buddha requires this to be in place
first and then down through the centuries after that once this list was created it turned out to be a fantastic
list to support people to understand how you develop your heart mind to in a good
way to develop your own practice towards Liberation toward Freedom how you develop your own uh life of compassion
service in the world and um and
um and so now it's become kind of a reference point and for many people in
the modern world and I don't know about the ancient world but the modern world especially here in the west that where more to Buddhists it's proven to be a
fantastic reference point these 10 parames as things to practice or
cultivate or reflect on in daily life and some people so you know
meditation is one thing but it's you know meditation shouldn't just be about
your private little meditation Life Buddhism is about also how you live your
life and some people then have found that the teachings on the par uh have been invaluable for bridging
their meditation in their daily life and some people don't even like to meditate don't even meditate some of you
maybe but the parames learning them and practicing with them is an invaluable
way of of developing the Buddhist path developing this capacities and
potentials that Buddhism points says that everyone has and so to maybe spend
a month on each of them and I teach programs where we do you a month on each
of the paramis and other people have done this as well and and I think Diana Clark Can Has Done programs here on the
parames and I think she go she rushes through them in five
months and um so um so the 10
parames so if some of you felt that that was a long list I apologize the what the I was hoping to
do through telling you that the narrative around these was to inspire in you that there is you have a capacity
for an organic growth and whether it's you whether it's
your growth is described by these 10 parmes that's not that as important but
there is a healthy way in which Dharma practice meditation
practice and mindfulness practice uh allows something to unfold fold to mature and develop that you
can't make happen but you can be the gardener of your own garden The Garden
of your heart mind and make create the conditions that allow something inside to grow and
develop and uh maybe you'll be surprised by what grows in you when you
begin watching your equivalent
dangerous what I'm going to say your equivalent of the forest fire the what will grow after that and
mature in you and and and it goes you know it can
go quickly things the the The Greener will come back and
grow so the 10 parames so we have you know about five minutes before the
official end here would any of you like any questions or protest anything
or
what hi girl uh thank you for the talk um I wanted to ask why are dadin pares
different from Mahayana pares it's a I have that question too I
I I don't have a good answer maybe maybe if you dig deeply into the doctrines of
of mahayan Buddhism you may see what why the differences are um and um one of
them that's interesting is that uh uh the Mahayana list has jna or meditation
as one of them and uh and the terava doesn't have that listed as one so you
know is maybe meditation more important for Mahayana than is ter I doubt that so
but why that is I don't know and so so I I don't really have an answer for you
thank
you so I'm back on uh the first param gener that's great I'm happy to hear
that okay I'm usually back there too okay starting
over when I'm I'm thinking that I um am not generous in
spirit not so much giving of things but more um when I find myself
judging other people uh assuming things about them that strikes me as not very
generous um and I wonder if you might have some ideas about how to deal with
that in those circumstances what would be generous what would be generous yeah in
the circumstances where you're judging people that way where do you find generosity given that that's what's
happening to you rather than thinking you have to wait is there could you find generosity
even when you recognize you're that way no
oh then I'll then I'll offer you a way okay you'll be you become generous if
you decide to if you decide to discover what would be
generous if you have the desire I don't want to be generous here but I think I'm going to try to understand H where where
and how to be generous that's generous then that begins with that desire to be that way I
would don't underestimate that so that's I'm not answering the question the way you answer asked it because you asked
what to do about when your spirit is not so generous and and I I answered by saying um don't
wait to be generous just do it anyway uh and uh don't wait until you've
rectified yourself and worked with this that's that's one answer I think it's a valid answer good answer I hope what to
do about it though to answer your question the way you asked it is uh uh
become the conosur
of your your lousy
Spirit get to know it really well so well you can see it coming so
well you see the conditions for that that also comes from conditions that are in place that grow that you have to
understand the conditions where that give birth to that for you and what what supports it and makes it grow and become
strong become the and I use the word connoisseur so that um you're not doing it in aers way or angry way or think
that you're wrong for being this way so you but you really get in there and Savor feel or sense until you become the
expert thanks so you can choose between those two or do both ideas both I'll take both oh fantastic so I saw over
here there was a hand yes maybe one more and then we'll stop I can just shout no no because okay
hi um this is a historical question uh about the intoxication part yeah um uh
in modern day there's obviously a lot of ways to be intoxicated with drugs and and all kinds of things historically
what were they referring to back in the Buddhist time alcohol so that was that that was the words were literally
alcohol that's you know they had and they listed the three different types of alcohol in the precept so you know
exactly how we beer liquor gint tonics I don't know what
they list three different types and so it's literally alcohol okay and uh and
by extension uh people have in the modern world have including drugs that
have the same uh s that have the same negative can have the same negative consequences that people get the literal
word in P that will make you careless and uh a pamada careless uh uh
and um pamada careless and um and the um uh in careless means
that you do things that you later regret that are not not healthy is that
good yep yeah okay okay so we're look at that 10:45 we're right on time and so
thank you all very much and if you want to say hello to the people next to you that's always nice but you might not
have time anymore and um thank you for being here