folks nice to see the names over there
um yeah happy to be uh happy to be with you so um so yeah welcome I'll say say a
few things and uh and then we'll uh we'll
sit um
so I was uh at a at a family gathering
uh this past weekend and um was one a
member from uh extended family uh as
a very adorable three-year-old and he was telling me that
uh sometimes uh in the middle of the night a three-year-old wakes up and
says gets his dad says papa papa I'm so
tired and uh something about aside from being
extremely cute something about that made me think of meditation practice and I
don't know what the equivalent is but maybe it's something like Papa how do do I become
aware Papa wears the dhma
right maybe there's more right
here so on this theme of more right
here I I heard about uh a retreat some years ago I don't know
anything more about it than what I'll tell you but it was a retreat and all of
the practice was done laying down and the theme was something like
Awakening through the deepest
relaxation and I think back then when I heard of it I was like well
I don't know I don't know about that right but
uh there's probably something to that was speaking with a longtime
practitioner who uh described in a very lovely way a kind of something on
Retreat that happened and described it as a sizable
relaxation and that that lasted some days
and on the one hand we don't fetishize
relaxation Tranquility gives the notion that
uh tension is the enemy or something like this and on the other hand on the other
hand tension or we could say nonre ation is
the signature of many different currents of
suffering so we could say clinging is
tension we could say selfing is tension suffering is tension greed is
most definitely tension hatred is tension
maybe maybe I don't know maybe even delusion has its own kind of tension the
tension of being out of step with the way things
are and sometimes we we don't have any idea
how tense we are until we actually relax
deeply we don't know the kind of layers of
of suffering to which we've acclimatized basically you know usually we talk about
the desperation of getting rid of suffering and fidgeting our way out of Sam Sor these kind of things but there
may be certain ways in which we're actually resigned to the suffering or we
barely even detect it as suffering and sometimes with a sizable
relaxation or something kind of deep release of some
kind there's um the tension that's been
subtly coating our body mind uh Falls away and we realize that uh what we had
been holding and and
so without turning tension into an enemy into another object of
craving we look look for ways we can relax ways in which we can detect the
tension of greed of hatred of clinging of
self and
relax so what's here Papa I'm so
tired but the beds right
here sit
together
e e
maybe we the way we actually relax is
to give tension
permission to do whatever it wants to do in our hearts
e
maybe we look for a way of of breathing of directing or
breath that brings uh even a kind of Whisper of ease
relaxation
e e
when we uh hike up a steep uh Hill or something uh gravity is not
our
friend but uh here it is
Sly soothing effects of the the downward pull of
gravity maybe our spine extends ever so gently towards the sky but then we
give everything else to Gravity soothed by
gravity
e
e e
the signature of self is that kind of
attention kind of density in our
mind contractive force
can we breathe into
that relinquishing ownership over
everything nothing more to [Music]
prove to oneself to
others
e
e e
you cannot be found
out
WEA e
clinging is a majorly complicated
maybe like trying to fit [Music] our heart-shaped harp
into uh square hole or something like
that letting go simplifies everything
there may be the grief of not getting but it's a very simple
grief e
our hatred can never ever
work
out it seems that that which is deeply
objectionable even
horrific warrants our
hate no
we
relax
e e
delusions of
permanence and more
morality some permanent pleasure that ends craving it's
delusion requires us to avert our gaze from what is
so contains some tension
so we just keep
relaxing
softening loving our attention to death as
teacher rashin and young would
say
e e
keep putting things down until uh awareness feels weight
less
e
e e
for e
okay good to uh good to sit with you
um so uh I'll be away next week it's uh juneth uh there'll be a special program
not on this channel but uh at this time I believe and so check the the website
and um I'll be back on the following week the uh the 26
so um okay
so uh I was asked to to give a kind of uh
blessing at a at a uh family event and um uh kind of religious right of right
of passage uh ceremony and friends and family gathered and
uh and just in the days before that I
just sat down to reflect okay what what do I want to say and it was sort of two
two words immediately arose in my mind love and time love
time and those [Music] are not words that I
usually pair together but there they were love and
time love only becomes meaningful
because of time the limitations of time for for anything to uh to matter in
a sense we have to believe in uh the kind of unique Irreplaceable
value of something someone and
so uh meaning and finitude are deeply linked
this uh writer philosopher hogland for anything to be intelligible
as mattering they write for anything to be at stake we have to believe in the
Irreplaceable value of someone or something that is
finite the recognition of finitude does not offer any guarantees that we will
lead a responsible life and take better care of one another but without the
recognition of finitude questions of responsibility and
Care could not even take hold of us to turn toward you to focus our Gaze
on another and attach ourselves to what we see is the deepest movement of secular
confession we are turned back to our lives not as something that is our
property but as a form of existence that is altogether finite and altogether
dependent on others this is not the end of
responsibility it is the beginning and
so immortality uh might very well
destroy our meaning our love matters because of
finitude and sometimes uh I think about
kind of superhero movies I don't just think about them I sometimes watch them
not that often but
sometimes sometimes and the hero the hero is
almost kind of invincible but not completely right if there were no such
thing as Kryptonite there'd be no drama at all
right and so finitude mortality loss the kind of
inevitability of grief that's encoded in every moment of
love and that's part of why I tend to elevate grief above
the swamp of afflictive feeling it's a it's a special one
believe and uh uh it's tied grief is tied to time to
love I just kind of cannot imagine a spiritual life somehow divorced from
grief time enriches the quality of our
love there are certain kinds of love that just depend on some measure
of continuity across time you know
um just across across the years there's a kind of um a richness to love that that seems
to contain all the time before all the moments before contained in this present
moment of love the kind of um the depth of karmic
entanglement the love over time love over
time the way uh love is bound up with with
um repetition with continuity with Evolution the richness of Love Grows with
time so I say yeah love is Meaningful because of
time but time time is only really meaningful because there is love our
lives are meaningful because there is
love what what are we here to do anyway you know really what are we here to
do fight you know to enact as much craving is as humanly
possible in one lifetime kind of folly of
it uh so much of our life only makes sense
in in light of Eternity as if this doesn't end as if this goes on forever
yeah I could justify that if I were never to die but we need finitude to
sober us up time is
Meaningful because of love and love can look many different ways many
different ways but uh for our lives to be meaningful depends
on love in one form or another the this tradition Buddhist
tradition uh love is likened to the glue of the world that which
prevents dis integration you I like that image of just like oh yeah that love
holds things together holds people together the world trembles in all
directions the Buddha said maybe love like uh is what what prevents
disintegration and the kind of um the barrenness of life in the absence
of love this kind of the absence of love makes every horror
possible and there there are so many um species of love that might make a life
meaningful you know classically it's um it's uh the Brahma vajar is the
Divine abodes kindness and compassion Joy equinity yeah those are beautiful
species of love but yeah it's just the beginning in a
way just the beginning of the ways we might love and maybe it's
worth just reflecting on all the different faces of
love in relational life
uh which is on my mind at this uh ceremony you know the the kind of the
intricacies and the beauty and the particularities of the heart of the
other whether that's a a friend or a lover child partner what family of one
kind or another it's like the their particularity their their sort of beauty
and even their Neurosis their radios syncrasy the particularities of the
heart of of others evokes its own species of love you know it's like our
heart constellates in a very particular way
depending on what's in front of us
and so how many ways are there to uh to love we we sort of just
keep looking exploring love and time it's good
to to Mark time to to keep track of our time to keep an
eye on finitude to keep track track of our love
and maybe maybe we treat treat each day as a kind of right of passage you
know each day uh a kind of
story about love one way or another it's a story
about love each day
offer this for your consideration and
uh yeah wish you uh wish you good uh couple weeks and uh we'll gather back
then 26 hope to uh uh yeah hope to practice again with
you very happy to be with you okay folks