Welcome to our Thursday morning
meditation there's a maybe it's a little funny to bring up the analogy but there's this uh famous
saying that if um a tree falls in the forest is there any sounds
made and a tree falls in the forest no one's there is there a
sound and uh I think part of the image for me is when the tree falls whatever
vibration of the air that goes on that would travel to someone's ears and
vibrate the air drums those vibrations move through the forest
unin until they meet an air of some creature and then vibrates the air and
then there's what we call sound and um but until it and so this
idea that the sound moving through space is being
unimpeded or a bird moving through the sky
unimpeded so freedom in Buddhism has a quality of being
unimpeded but there's it's a kind of an odd unimpeded in that uh it isn't a freedom
to do whatever we want to do which is often associated with freedom it's
primarily a freedom from impediment from picking things up
fueling things being involved with things being involved with desires involved with
aversions and uh and so uh and with thoughts so thinking thating can happen
there can be a thought but for the thought to become thinking
there has to be some engagement with it some involvement with it some picking it
up some participation in it some Associated thinking that goes on or
Builds on it and uh to be free in the mind is to create a vast space where
things are unimpeded so that a thought can arise
like a bird in the sky or a cloud in the sky it just drifts by and Fades
away so that uh uh cognition arises
knowing arises almost preverbally uh almost like a a sound in
the woods when no which no one hears there's just space there's not any there's no clinging no resistance no
picking up no judgments no reaction just vast space in a
sense so um so the freedom in
Buddhism is a freedom from clinging from
resisting from judging and in that freedom
from what is created is often associated with uh vast
space so as we sit today in meditation maybe there's some way
to partially maybe not fully but in some small way to have a sense of this kind
of freedom freedom from self-de freedom
from our past and our future freedom from being someone or not
being someone freedom from being right or being wrong
and uh there's kind of sense of space where there's room for things to
occur without any involvement with them and it can be seen as kind of
profoundly respectful of each individual unique phenomena that arises that um we don't we just allow it
to be itself we don't fuel it we don't get involved with it just let it be and
what will happen with more freeway we are things just move through us like a
river just moves through the riverbed just keeps flowing by and flowing
by or like it clouds in the sky so to assume a meditation
posture and with the posture there's also some way of finding a posture where we feel
unimpeded in simple ways you can loosen the belt
around your waist if it's tight make sure your clothes are a little bit loose not constricting your
body in any
way adjusting your legs your knees your hands your elbows their
positions so they all feel a little loose light
when I was first taught Zen I was taught to be like a chicken and flap my elbows until so we really keep the
elbows kind of unfrozen
untight gently close the eyes
and relax your
body soften around the body
breathing follow the exhale to the very end of the exhale and wait however
briefly for the inhale to begin on its
own allow the inhale to be what it is as unimpeded
as is easy to do
and in the top of the inhale let there be a
release with the beginning of the exhale
with the exhale let there be a release or relaxing of the thinking
mind acknowledging any pressure or Force
in the thinking mind to be
thinking and if you can on the exhale relax that pressure that Force
if there is pressure or force or power in certain
emotions that were born in the past or concern the future
on the exhale see if you can relax
release that force that pressure
letting the inhale be a time to make space
room for the inhale to Simply arise here and
now
unimpeded in a space where there's no distractions just the inhale
and and then find in your body wherever in your body there's a
soft Stillness doesn't have to be
dramatic but is there some place of soft
Stillness in the softness in the Stillness there is no reactivity or
judgments or involvement in
anything whatever else is going on around it Beyond it is allowed to
occur without that soft Stillness being agitated
and maybe there in that soft
Stillness is some
Freedom the kind of Freedom where there's space for all
things without getting involved
and with every inhale and exhale that soft
spilless soft Stillness expands grows
outwards making space within which all things can occur
like clouds in the sky
like water in the river and Drifting by
unimpeded for
for
for for
perhaps where there is a soft Stillness or an open
spaciousness [Music] however mild those might be in
you can they be a
reference for allowing whatever occurs to
occur freely without any resistance any
involvement like a sound in the forest where there's no ears to
hear or water flowing through a river without any resistance
where there's no building of self defending self asserting
self being a self
even where in some radical way we can
just allow ourselves to be as we are
are a freedom of just
ourselves without needing to work at anything
and that is maybe a profound form of respect allowing each thing to be
itself without appropriating it by our desires and our
aversions our preferences
and in doing that for ourselves does it teach us does it teach
you something about how to offer that to
others to allow each person to have the experience of being known and
seen without our projections our preferences
our expect ations our ideas of how they should be
or shouldn't be profound gift of
respect each thing each person's allowed to be
themselves and there's so much space within us
that there's nothing to be afraid
of there nothing that can be threatened in that soft
Stillness that has room for all things
and from that kind of soft Stillness open
spaciousness with that kind of Freedom Good Will has a very
powerful impact it's clean it's clear
it's just a goodness a kindness that allows people to be as
they are where they feel our respect and Good
Will May this practice we do support
us to look upon all beings with profound
respect Through The Eyes the ears ear of our own inner
Freedom may all beings be
free may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
safe may all beings be happy
and may our ability to smile convey this for others
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to the fourth of the 10
Reflections that this series is focused on
and uh the fourth one is autonomy so to review there was
um this week yesterday it was uh a sense of agency so first
meaning then purpose and then with that uh it makes
sense to act in the world and so to have an ability to act the ability to have
agency to act according to what's important for us our values our sense of
purpose is an essential human need and when that is inhibited broken
made difficult uh denied it's profoundly uh
difficult for a human being and to support people in their
agencies and empowerment is one of the gifts that we can offer others to believe in people to have
confidence in them some people grew up without anyone believing in them and
their capacity their ability and then the fourth is
autonomy and uh autonomy is uh very important in hospitals medical
situations where a patient is um doctors are constantly supposed to uh think
about um how to respect the autonomy of the patient meaning their ability to
make decisions for themselves and I think we have a profound need to feel like we have a
choice and the choice is not taken away from us by other people who choose for
us and um and to not be limited and oppressed by other people's
choices but to be respected for our ability to make a choice our ability to
do things for ourselves and uh in thinking about this
I think about uh growing up from birth to old age that you know before we're
born and in in well we're just daating in our mother that
um everything is kind of done for us but when we're born then we start breathing
for ourselves and soon thereafter start digesting food for ourselves and slowly
as we grow up we're able to do more and more things for ourselves we're able to sit up able to stand up able to walk for
ourselves and get around without something having to carry us at some point we're able to go to the bathroom
by ourselves and clean ourselves and shower for ourselves and and at some point we're able to use forks and spoons
by ourselves and be able to feed ourselves at some point we're able to take the bus by ourselves to school for
example or go to the store by ourselves or um walk down the street to our
friend's house without someone accompanying us and so it's a slow process of growing up of greater and
greater autonomy uh doing things for ourselves and something profoundly problematic
happens if that growth of autonomy growth of doing things for ourselves is
curtailed as we grow up and uh some people um are not given a chance to grow
up because they have people who are constantly doing things for them um taking care of everything for them and
so and protecting them so they can't really kind of go out and experience
that possibility of how they find their own way in their world and uh so just a healthy growing
up is a greater and greater capacity for autonomy until finally at least classically in modern culture that um
you know some point we leave home and go off and start our own home someplace
else and move away from our parents perhaps and um go to college and locally
in local cultures many people go to college and or
something and um and so growing a sense of autonomy and um the um one of the
Milestones is maybe sometimes when our parents can't take care of uh of themselves
and we now have the strength the ability the autonomy to be the one who cares for
them at some point as we're dying um some people find that it's wonderful to
have loved ones around Some people prefer to die alone but dying is a profoundly personal thing that we go
through um and so to have the capacity for really to have grown and developed
over the course of a lifetime to enter into the dying process with a very
healthy sense of this is just me this is my process and uh and and be able to
follow through with some confidence and letting go and
Clarity so discovering and having autonomy is really
important and uh we can't uh there's things we can not
uh expect other people to do for do for us uh we don't ask people
to generally unless we're sick or something we don't ask other people to
shower us or we don't ask other people to pee for us or all kinds of things we
have some things we have to do ourselves and there's a profound human need for
autonomy and where we don't have it it's a problem where we do have it how to
have a healthy sense of autonomy is a very important thing to reflect on and to explore
it gets complicated in U in some some culture subcultures of the United States
where um individualism is uh has a lot to do with self assertion where uh
there's a building of self and asserting a self and where freedom is confused
spiritual freedom is confused with a freedom to assert our desires get what we want seize the day um be ourselves uh
assert ourselves on Tik Tok or on social media to be someone for others um
there's so many ways in which to be free to do that is actually harmful for the people who are doing it it's
reinforcing something UNH wholesome it's enforcing an attachment a clinging
delusion even fantasy sometimes and um and so this the strong
need for autonomy gets confused sometimes with uh the strong impulse to
get our desires met our attachments met to to our to assert ourselves in some
way and uh in Buddhism autonomy is not about
assertion it's something different it's something very profound not
interfering not uh grasping onto not adding pressure
or judgments or ideas of right and wrong but allowing each thing that arises
to arise freely without feeding it without
getting involved in it without fueling it and um and to discover this kind of
autonomy uh gives autonomy to each thing that arises and so we become The Giver of
autonomy not the taker of autonomy that we have a certain autonomy because we
are free uh from there's no we don't resist anything we don't hold on to anything
we're not pushing anything away we're more like we're open space and things can just go right
through and it doesn't land nothing lands on our identity nothing lands on
the way in which we've built up a sense of self or holding on to some sense of self um we can still be completely who
we are and even some ways you can say we can be more fully Who We Are
when we're not trying to build and assert who we are and um so to find this profound
place of autonomy of kind of freedom from other
people's projections other people's judgments other people's Prejudice uh
find a inner place where we're free from that um is a powerful way of not exactly
fighting what people do to us uh but not giving into it uh not participating in
it and uh and in a certain way in that way may be uh uh standing against it but
not assertively we don't give in to what other people are pushing on us demanding
of us but we also don't need to assert ourselves in that process we can just have confidence in our capacity to be
free in that moment in those times so to discover a kind of
autonomy that uh that uh is
nonresistance autonomy which is non- clinging non-assertion that uh that uh it's
beautiful because we can be fully who we are but it we don't have to be anybody
at the same time uh we can be space for all things with without uh being in
conflict with anything as I began the week with that he have non-c
contention so uh healthy autonomy so as I've been saying this
week I'm offering you my Reflections on this I'm not saying that this is the
best way for anyone to understand these Concepts I'm offering so today I'm not suggesting this is the best way to
understand this idea of freedom and autonomy that I'm offering but I want to give you just enough um
orientation around this topic of autonomy that uh you can grapple with it
for yourself you can consider and explore it for yourself what it might mean for you and um and maybe even come up with a
different word that's related to autonomy a synonym that may be is more meaningful for you and um but I think
it's a very significant concept to use to reflect on yourself and see
how this works what's your autonomy and where do you don't you feel you don't have autonomy
Choice uh agency these kinds of things where do you feel like it's really good
for to have some sense of Independence uh not uh or say more more
subtly different in Buddhist language rather than Independence uh Buddhism talks about a
nondependence where do you have a place of nondependence on anything the subtle difference is
that sometimes in America Independence is uh can be interpreted as
an assertion independent enough to assert ourselves nondependence means that uh
we're free so autonomy and um and uh the fact that
it's such a it's a central ethical principle one of the three or four Central ethical principles in American
uh Medical Practice it's a very important Concept in our society as a whole and um so I think it's well worth
kind of grappling or considering this topic and maybe there's um um and
certainly it's a important followup of the idea of agency to have autonomy in
our ability to act uh as we see is necessary important for us autonomy to
practice the Dharma so um maybe you'll consider it uh today
and reflect on this in different ways that you might have including talking to friends about it and um then we'll
continue tomorrow with um what follows from this uh which is the concept of
identity and uh which is a little bit of a hot topic for Buddhists so um we'll
see what how that goes so thank you very much and um I wish do well with your
reflections