all of the friendly greetings and
interactions happy to be with you
and I'm wondering if anyone noticed anything
about their senses yesterday and pop that in the chat for just a moment if
you wish what senses help you stay most connected where you might not notice as
much great so we have a bit of a lag so I'm
going to move on and go ahead and start with the meditation here but um I will check the chat for
any responses about that in a few minutes
so the invitation is to notice that you're
sitting many of you watching the screen some with your eyes
closed and notice how it feels in your body to be present
maybe noticing the warmth of familiarity of the
company any heart qualities that might be
present noticing cause and effect of being present as you drop in become
present to the meditation and then if it feels
right after you've made any greetings you want to
make starting with a couple of longer slower deeper breaths
really letting go on the out breath releasing any extra
tension and letting go into the moment into
this softening your eyes and when you're ready closing [Music]
them and perhaps imagining gazing out over a beautiful
Vista vast Ocean or Canyon or
landscape and then letting go of that [Music]
imagination allowing the continuation of the softness of gaze
allowing the breathing to return to
normal noticing your jaw perhaps your tongue
the tip of your tongue at a pallet with your mouth
and shifting stepping into your
senses all of the sounds around you and the silences between them
all of the sensations of each
breath perhaps the Gap a little pause at the end of the out
breath before the in breath begins to fill your torso
tuning in to whatever sense area
experience keeps you most consistently
present I'll offer instructions on breathing
however if the flux and flow of sound or overall
body sensation or the flow of
now is more hospitable please allow that to be your object of
attention
of dedicating the
attention to the beginning of the in
breath the gradual filling of the lungs shifting of the
diaphragm perhaps Sensations at the nose or throat
noticing the moment of fullness at the top of the in
breath and then the moment of
release the ease of the out breath
staying in contact with the
entirety of the in breath the
pause the release of the out
breath and perhaps noticing resting in that tiny Gap at the end
of the out
breath that moment of
Stillness riding the waves of breathing
if another sense experience sound
stray sensation [Music]
smell moment of flavor or experience of Mind pulls the
attention noticing that too bir into
being last and change for a while while and then
fade and then when it's no longer
predominant returning your attention or allowing the attention to
be naturally drawn into
the flux and flow of the next arising breath sound
object
usefully staying with the flow
we'll practice mostly in silence for a while I might add a few little invitations here and
there
e
e e
if any New Sensations arrive or
shift or become more acute noticing
that savoring any bits of comfort or ease or pleasure
and being with with kindness
compassion and interest dis passionate interest with
anything
else
e
e e
noticing [Music] appreciating not leaning into or away
from not clinging to the flux and flow the change of
breath [Music] sensation sensory
[Music] experience allowing the heart the mind
to be open [Music] receiving
allowing
e
e e
and in the last remaining moments of our meditation
together the invitation is to turn your attention [Music]
to your core your physical core and your
emotional Center perhaps of the heart or throughout the
Torso to notice with kind appreciation whatever's
there just not it
and [Music] then cast your mind
back over these moments of
meditation with an appreciative receptive
sensibility savoring steep in any moments of pleasure
goodness
presence any moments of flowing with riding the
senses and appreciating above all your own dedication to showing up
for however long in whatever
way and from that kind appreciative
Place lovingly including any challenges or difficulties that
arose without a need to judge
criticize
push it's all included it's all onward
leading nothing needs to be left
out and from this place of
integrated appreciation
offering a sense of kindness good willll
outwards to your companions here on this sit to the others in your
life may our practice here together Ripple through our own hearts
and minds and lives to all of the lives we
touch and all of the lives they
touch onward and onward may all
beings experience the joy and benefit of freedom of the heart and mind
[Music]
thank you for your
practice
for e
so warm greetings again everyone everyone who's been here the whole meditation and those of you who tiptoed
into the zoom YouTube chat room and sit just a little bit
late so today is the third of five talks
on the sense doors sight sound smell
taste touch or bodily sensation and the heart and
mind and today I'd like to talk about ways that spaciousness ease can be
available at the scent stores and offer a couple of tips that about meditation
that fit into the general category of hanging out at the scense stores
stepping into to sensory practice and spending some time there not a lot of
effort required so these two practices are surfing the senses and resting in the
spaces between or simply resting and I'll start with a little
anecdote so some weeks back I was meditating at the ocean open
eyes it's actually a pretty remote location not a lot of people
but there was a surfer very um dedicated Surfer camped out on the beach a little
ways away and occasionally he would glide through my
visual field on this wave just completely one with the ocean in perfect
balance and not unlike that Surfer though with a lot less effort perhaps
and practice we can ride and be supported by in harmony with the
waves and flux and flow of sensory experience flowing
through our sense doors it's this flux and
flow we can serve our senses so
noticing with your eyes and do it now if conditions allow
changes in light Shadow motion changes in Focus or
softness just noticing perhaps noticing the movement
of wind in the grasses or flow of the trees or
birds flying all all of that can be a way of
tapping into staying present with the flow of
change I um practiced taichi for many years quite seriously I still do it on
Retreat and one of the instructions we got was to allow the hand to move on the
in during our different postures we were moving through the visual field without
looking at the hand but rather allowing the hand to move through just like a
bird or a cloud moves through the sky and then there's the flavor or
texture of the moment literally like when tasting food or drink you might
notice a good tea or a good coffee changes in flavor from beginning to end
of sip sip sorry and there's the taste on the front
of the tongue the middle of the tongue the back of the tongue the different and
sort of variation over the lifetime of a single
swallow this kind of Surfing the senses involves noticing the very slow and very
fast and we've all done this sunrises and sunsets are very slow
change thunderstorms can be quite fast the
flickering of an oil lamp or a candle fire can be mesmerizing and
languid or very fast even the mind and heart as aan
suito says can change faster than the flick of a horse's
tail I'm actually very touched by stories of Richard Fineman may he rest
in peace he loved to discover that he was wrong and to change his
mind and changing our minds can be delightful if we're open to
it it's noticing the flavor of the moment as it were in a more figurative
way changes in attention same thing and then there's the general flux
and FL flow the sound of wind chimes the flocking of birds there's so much
Beauty and in unfolding in constancy whirling around and within us everywhere
all the time the rapid turning of a bicycle wheel or the flow of swiftly
moving water scintillating waves on the ocean or a lake or that child's game which I
recommend to adults of watching clouds form deform and reform into different
shapes it's all Cloud but cloud is a process not an object a constantly
changing process different warar shock like
shapes all of this can be beautiful and it's otherwise
known as anich that's the poly for the perception of
inconstancy the invitation and surfing your senses is to let yourself feel
interest wonder even a pulse of Joy surprise
Delight let go into the flow the possibility of delight lives in the
details of each moment of change freshness novel
is the gift of inhabiting here and now and the only purchase price for this
Joy this ease is to pay attention to be there closely completely
with intent dedication isn't that
nice so I got to tell you many of the classical Traden teachings the old older
um teachings that formed in the wake of the Buddha's life emphasize the
suffering in this kind of inconstancy and there's wisdom in those
teachings in that they encourage us to let go very famous
teaching from aan cha a great teacher in the Thai Forest tradition likened
suffering to rope burn to when we hang on when change is moving
through so noticing the suffering of change can result in letting go however
this surfing this senses teaches our minds and hearts to let go in a
different way by finding the ease the spaciousness and being in the flow of
momentto moment experience without clinging just enjoying the
ride just enjoying the ride suffering is only present in this
practice if you try to make something happen resist something happening or hang
on this way of rioting the senses means appreciating changes and differences for
their own sake in real time and that too conditions the mind and heart not to
cling through positive reinforcement it's like that very famous teaching in
Insight Meditation that we should be kind when attention returns like being kind to a puppy when it finally comes
when you call it that begins to teach a different
orientation to how to show up for the joy of seeing feeling and letting
go this can to have practical benefits too so many of you know that I came into
the Dharma through What's called the dooka doorway the and dooka dooka pain and at a certain point in my life
far too early in my life I encountered a medical condition that seemed to just
cause an intractable block of pain to be there all the time and as I started
meditating with very many expectations I have to say I discovered that this kind
of Flux Of change was really good news because rather than a solid conceptual
block of pain that seemed to be there all the time and last forever Sensations
changed shifted broke down altered and then I started to notice
lifegiving gaps in the pain breaks where Ease spaciousness comfort Joy
existed and that was the beginning of a profound journey of
healing so I'll probably talk about it more in the coming days of this week but
I want to just briefly say that that transitions us to the second practice which is noticing the spaces
and the gaps in sensory experience the Brits have the saying in
the underground mind the gap mind the gap
indeed notice the spaces between the spaces between
Sensations objects trees or Hills your body occupying and moving through
space every single one of our senses can be a doorway to ease and
radical Simplicity and Present Moment awareness it's another way to relax hang
out at the sense doors and step back from any internal thought and emotional
flurries resting into the natural spacious
available today I'll only mention the eyes because we talked about the useless
gazing in the corners this is a similar practice now artists notice negative
space the space in between the space around objects above you around buildings or
trees or mountains or forests or oceans or fields that can also be an entry point
into noticing a spacious OAS allowing a sense of that space in
between to infuse inform our experience of this
moment so I'll say more about this in the coming days but
meanwhile as you go about your day the invitation optional homework is
to notice if there are moments where you can surf the senses or notice mindly
gaps rest in the spaces would love to hear more see more
in the chat when we see each other tomorrow thank you very much for your
practice may all beings benefit be well