so good morning and
um so for this talk I want to start in a different way I would like to partly for
to make a point better maybe to do a little ritual with you uh some of you
who don't like ritual will call it
theater a and for this I need h four volunteers
there are four envelopes here and in each envelope there's a question and so
you would read the question when the time comes so don't open the envelope until it's your
time use the mic maybe it's good to use the mic
yes and maybe the other mic is there yes
so up here in the front because uh what's your name moed mad is number one so each of you have a number so if you
once you have the mic Phil if you can bring it to Mad here or there
okay so so now you can open it and ask the
question from where comes love from wisdom
so then number
two from where comes wisdom from
love number three who has number
three oh so she needs the
mic what is love to care
what is wisdom to care
well so the topic today is wisdom and but wisdom can seem abstract
it can seem heady it could seem like it has nothing to do with
love and um maybe that's the case sometimes but in the teachings of the
Buddha there's a distinction that he sometimes makes I don't know if he makes it but it stands out as I read the text
between wisdom and being a wise person wisdom can be found in a
book and as long as it stays in the book it doesn't benefit
anyone being a wise person is found in
living a life and that's what the Buddha was
emphasizing was how we live our life and so the purpose of wisdom is to live
wisely and so but what does it mean to live wisely what is this W was wise and
in that little question answer we did I'm uh I'm
putting love and wisdom closely together which they often are not
and so I want to read a quote of from one of my favorite uh teachings from the
Buddha I some of you have heard me do it before because I like it so much and it's uh the Buddha description
or definition of a wise person wise
people of great wisdom do not
think of harming themselves of harming in others or of harming
both rather wise people consider their own
welfare the welfare of others the welfare of both and the welfare of the
whole world in this way one is a wise person
of great wisdom so here the wisdom that's being emphasized the way of being a wise
person is to have your heart have in your in your field of
concern uh the welfare of self the welfare of others the welfare of both
and the welfare of the whole world and uh that means to care to care
for the world to care for oneself and how do we care for ourselves
well that takes wisdom how do we learn how to care well
well that next love because here wisdom is not
apart from our relationship to other people sometimes when we focus on
Buddhism or the Buddhist teachings and Buddhist practice it can have at times
in appropriate way a kind of a very personal orientation but you said and
close your eyes and meditate and you're kind of like you know tuning the world
out and other out and you're quieting your mind so you're not thinking about
you know who you're going to give a gift to over the holidays you're just sitting here with your own breathing and the
kind the stereotypical criticism of people who meditate is that they're just watching their belly
button you know it really gets focused and um but um but it's there's a
way in which that's appropriate to do that and how it fits into this definition of wise person there's
something profound that can happen when the attention gets
organized uh unified collected here in the present moment so
that awakens within us a feeling of holess feeling of wholesome wholeness
that can happen a a feeling of sombody that uh is a whole a holistic
state of phenomenal well-being now it's possible to be
focused on that for the purposes of just being your own pleasure or your own
relief from the difficulties of life but in the Buddhist teachings this deep
experience of samade of wholeness really kind of going Inward and is to be turned
inside out you have to go in but then you get turned inside out so that uh the
focus now is uh becomes how do we care how do we meet the the world how do we
meet ourselves in a caring way and so the inward Focus that is part of
Buddhism uh is not supposed to leave us isolated from the world or not attuned
to the world it's meant to do the exact opposite and uh just like if uh you
really want to care for people well and really have have people relax
around you and just really feel like you're accessible and they're happy to sit next to you and be close maybe even
happy for you to give them a hug in the right circumstance it would be useful from time to time you really went into very
private into your own privacy away from all people and took a
shower so sometimes that's what you know meditation does you're just cleaning
up get getting cleansed on the inside side outs and and then you're ready come
out and you know you come out in a whole different way for the world
um so
um so the the development of this caring wisdom wise caring is to come to a place
where it's possible to care for the whole world and that
includes the people who are our enemies the people whove betrayed us and
the people who have offended Us in all kinds of ways that's a tall order that's
not easy to do it's easy it's not difficult I mean it's very difficult to
deal with one's own hurt one's own pain one's own fear to be able to have it
that big and that's one of the purposes of this inward focus is to really
address and meet all the barriers all the unresolved ways we are all the wounds we carry so that we can get
turned inside out and be able to have care for
everyone and maybe in this in this context we don't want we don't need to use the word love that kind of is a for
many people a high bar or it becomes something maybe to
hallm Marky but uh but the care is really much
more humble much more basic and I would say very profound to offer care to care
for the whole world no one left
out and um so to learn this wisdom to understand
this wisdom does not require books book reading
it doesn't require Dharma talk but but stay until the end
please uh it it doesn't require exceptional
knowledge it doesn't require mystical States or Supernatural
experiences and it doesn't involve metaphysical ideas abstract metaphysical
ideas what it involves is it deeper sensitivity in
oneself a deeper sensitivity to
wellbeing to where sense of your own welfare is because the more you have a
sense of welfare for yourself what brings you own your own goodness the more you two things will happen you'll
appreciate that's possible for other people and you'll have a profound
appreciation for uh what it feels like to care for others it feels good it adds
to that well-being it can done the right way and so in the some of the path
models of Buddhism like where you begins there's there's a number of different path models that have different
Beginnings but one of them um uh called the parames the 10
Perfections uh begins with generosity and uh and generosity is
relational you you you can be generous to yourself but it's too very easy then to be selfish but it's possible um but
generosity is generally considered to be something we do for others and um for the world and uh and
the idea of generosity is it's non-obligatory so it has to be the the
source inside from which it comes cannot be logical or reasoned out because then
it's not quite generosity though reason and rationality can have a role and it
certainly as I said can't be obligatory can't be a duty because generosity is this
something that's freely given from some uh generative Source inside some feeling
of openness some feeling of delight some feeling of care for the person that you're giving it to you want that
thought this person would like it if we have cultivated capacity of mindfulness for
ourselves we can feel uh the joy the Delight the the pleasure that this kind
of generosity can be if there isn't some kind of pleasure in being generous it probably isn't being generous it has a
good feeling this lightning and offering and freeing of something and offering it out
then we can feel how we're a better person because of it we can also feel that the joy
hopefully that it brings other people and so it can bring us joy and satisfaction the fact that we've you
know offered something to someone else and it affects our inter can affect
our interpersonal relationships with others it tends to create positive interpersonal Rel relations to be
generous chances are it's more likely to create positive personal interpersonal
relationships than uh being stingy and uh which doesn't usually held
up for good friendship and uh and so there tends to
be a field of mutual appreciation Mutual maybe maybe gratitude maybe even Mutual
gratitude uh I felt very grateful sometimes when I've been able to give something to someone because I feel so
lucky it it does me good it's so nice so I want to say thank you to them and um
but this gratitude and appreciation and there's something that I learned in Zen that when you give uh you you don't give
casually like look the other way and had it to them as nothing even if it's a small thing ITA is that relationship is
important the respect is important so you're supposed to in Zen you're supposed to give something with two hands and you're supposed to so it's
really like you're you're all of you is present and you're present for the other person that you're giving to and so so
because that relationship is important the respect and care is important and so
it creates a kind of positivity in the interpersonal sphere some people use
generosity maybe maybe it's not generous always but use giving uh as a way of
healing interpersonal relationships that are strained or to shift the Dynamic
it's hard to uh you know to be angry at someone or be mean to them at work or
something if they given you a gift you know they came with cookies for you or they came and gave you something
or or maybe you came out of the parking lot at work and your tire was flat and
you didn't know what to do and the Very person you've been meeting with all day long kind of could they came over and
said oh I'll help you I know how to do T to change the tires or fix it and and like what
next day you know you're not going to probably start you know being mean again not right
away so generosity giving is sometimes used to kind of do something good for interpersonal
relationships so in terms of wisdom what was very important what I just described was all the good all the
good feelings that arose in that act of generosity something so softened inside
something warmed inside something uh relaxed maybe something some Joy or
Delight or pleasure arose in one way or the other in that act of
generosity and it's in the interpersonal relationship and in this path model that's where Buddhism begins if you want
to start practicing Buddhism don't start with meditation start with
generosity and um and uh so what does that do to you
to a person who has that feeling of well-being one one of the things that does to you the person is be become more
sensitive to how that is diminished how that's broken how that is taken away
so uh so you you know you feel the goodness of something the generosity and
now you have a reference point for how what not to do because that would cause
harm you cause harm to yourself by maybe diminishing or breaking the relationship
breaking the kind of inspiration that you're coming from the goodness you're coming from that if you felt kind of
lousy and miserable and stressed out to begin with um you know it's it does it's
like not a big deal to do something with your middle finger like you know that doesn't that
doesn't make anything worse you know so might as well but if you're feeling good and calm
and peaceful you can feel that a certain you way of using your middle finger
actually diminishes you actually harms you your welfare take something away and
so why would you do it so the more you have the sense of well-being the more
you recognize and feel that there's the difference between what brings harm and
what brings welfare and that is the key key aspect of this wisdom that I'm highlighting
today the wisdom to be able to see feel know experientially this brings harm this
brings benefit so then uh so the generosity
then sets the stage for that that's part of the function as part of the path
model the second uh step in this path model is generos is U is uh virtuous
conduct and virtuous conduct is primarily defined by um in this early tradition uh
by um uh restraining yourself from causing harm so you would abstain from
killing people or physically harming them you'd abstain from stealing from people you'd
abstain from causing harm to people through your sexual behavior and you would avoid
lying and you avoid intoxicating your mind making your mind kind of confused
and maybe crazy and um and so these are these are consider The virt Virtuous conduct to
avoid these things why would you do that well if you one reason is if you
develop this warmer sensitivity to others through generosity you can feel how doing those unver virtuous things
diminishes The Joy it diminishes the quality of the relationships so you you
have a foundation for appreciating why it's important to be ethical where it no longer becomes a rule to be followed but
rather an inspiration to maintain something good to avoid causing harm to
yourself and causing harm to to others because in order to intentionally cause
harm to others it involves a fracturing of the wholeness of self it involves
diminishing the wholesome kind of joy and well-being that the Dharma practice
is kind of developing in people and growing in people now it's considered in the
teachings of the Buddha that do avoiding those five things not killing stealing
sexual misconduct lying and intoxication is a gift we give the
world and uh and maybe usually we we don't think of it that way but it doesn't take a lot of analysis to
appreciate how much killing stealing sexual harm lying intoxication goes on
in their society it's tremendously damaging and uh and the only thing it
seems to benefit is politicians and uh and so and newspapers
who right about it but uh but if you know what would the news be alike if PE
if the whole world stopped doing those things it would be dramatically different than what we consumed now in
the in the you know in the main news of the day and so um so it's a gift to the
world for to for you to meet someone who you feel their ethical Integrity is so
good that you feel like you you feel safe with them is
remarkable I've met transformed people
who I trusted deeply I trusted them in a certain kind of way to my son when he
was 18 and the people who was transformed uh uh had been actually were
still lifers in prison who had murdered someone I mean that's considered some of
the worst of the people but they had gone through this the the grip program that we've had presentations here about
in such a thorough and transformative way that it was remarkable to
feel how that transformation in them so I was able to bring my son when he was
18 just just old enough to get Clarence to go to S Quinton and sit in a room of
30 lifers who were there because of murder and I was a little bit
worried but uh it was remarkable to feel how they've been changed it's Poss
possible to change people can be transformed and
um and so um um so this idea of ethics and how
good that is and in classically in Buddhism that uh being ethical by
abstaining from these five things is meant to be a source of joy and this is
something I couldn't understand when I first came to Buddhism I thought it was weird that people felt Joy because they
were ethical because that was I had done nothing in my background that made sense of that and um and then uh when I went
to Thailand and uh and my first Retreat there was 10 weeks long and 10 weeks was
a long time to be in silence and to practice and uh and in the course of that Retreat something shifted inside
some kind of settling relaxing calming opening a sense of well-being a sense of
I remember feeling very very clean on my inside remember the shower so very clean
on the inside and uh and lo and behold I felt
this joy for not being inclined to doing
anything unethical and uh it came up a little bit in the course of that that um there had
been uh before I went there I'd met this woman woman that I had a certain
um you know I hope this doesn't offend anyone something that bordered on
lust probably not lust but something bordering on
it and uh and uh and then when I was sitting in that Retreat uh I could feel
that that I had no inclination in that direction that having that actually felt
like I was going to harm myself and I felt this Joy not having that kind of unhealthy relationship to another
person and so um so again to live an ethical life
creates a different reference point for wisdom because it shows
us what causes harm and what causes benefit in ourselves in others in the
relationship between others between self and others and then maybe to the whole world
so then the third step of uh then we're getting to What's called the Perfection of wisdom so we're building here so the
third step in this path model is uh a topic I talked about a few
weeks ago which popular is at least thought to be unpopular is uh
renunciation and uh but the thing is that it's after these first two so uh there's a now the practitioner
has gathered a lot of information they've learned a lot about what feels good they a lot not just good
in some H hedonistic way but what feels good ethically what feels good interpersonally what feels good coming
from our heart coming from a deep generative place inside and so from
there um it makes sense to begin letting go of of
course uh I remember I would when I took my kids to school when they were young
uh I would get up and meditate and then they and usually they would I try to
meditate because they'd get up early and then I had this great idea that this
fantasy will be so great I'll be meditating and they'll come and and really young they come in I have them
sit on my lap and I put my I had a Shaw and I put on and it'll be such a wonderful
conditioning for them influence on them they'll just feel the goodness of that and meditate together and so sure enough
they wake up early sure enough they'd be willing to sit on my lap and it lasted
half a second so I never I was never fulfilled in that area of
parenting but I would feel kind of good and uh anyway just been sitting a little
bit or whatever I did and and um but by the time I made breakfast for the
kids got them dressed did drove the carpool to school I was ready to come
back and take a nap and and one but one of the things I said this this is exhausting this is
stressful what's going on this is back in the old days in the ancient times where um they had something called
newspapers and so it turned out every morning I wanted to read the newspaper
but that was what made the whole morning stressful because it made much like I didn't have enough time for all the
other steps so I had to renounce the newspaper and I was so much
happier because I knew there was happiness I knew there was well-being I knew there was harm and this so
something that I enjoyed doing had to go for the greater good so that was a
renunciation so so that no good goodness
to know that being stressful stressing out is is you're losing something when
you get stressed the Dharma question is
why be stressed why agree to being stressed why go along with the forces
inside that cause you stress some of you will have brilliant answers to that why you should be
stressed what I'd like to encourage you is don't argue with
me uh but uh uh engage those mental
lawyers that are justifying stress and really question them really
engage in a deep conversation with it is it really better is it really worthwhile
to allow yourself to get stressed I've known for example at times
that um I've been stressed and trying to do something and then I had to do it
over again it would have been faster if I had done it calmly uh the first
time so um but anyway the sense of caring beginning to care deeply for
yourself care enough to not be stressed care enough not to sacrifice your own well-being for greed for hatred care
enough so that uh you do the kind of things that nourish and support a
profoundly inspire ing inner life so your inner life inspires you wow can you
believe this there's something here which is maybe not me but it's better than me which is this generative place
of goodness or warmth or wholesomeness that can live inside of us and so
renunciation is part of that training and part of that learning we learn to let go and then renunciation
brings even more sense of well-being that's the point of it it's not meant to be
deprivation and in the in this teaching that I'm uh kind of relying on for this
talk it um uh uh renunciation is uh
includes the practice of meditation that's where it kind of fits in there's
a lot of Letting Go in meditation there's a lot of letting go of thoughts letting go of impulses motivations
learning to sit quietly and peacefully letting go of all the ways that we're harming ourselves and one way of
understanding meditation is a progressive lessening of self harm and it's hard for people to believe
and know how much we're actually harming ourselves by the ordinary stressful ways
that we're thinking and caught and fixated in thoughts and feelings and what we do in ordinary life but we start
seeing that and relaxing and softening and part of the function of meditation is to soften let go of all forms of self
harm and um that's the purpose of the for Noble Truths which are really they
usually use use the word suffering there to address it to talk about it so meditation then produces a sense
of wholeness deep peace deep sense of well-being and again it becomes an even
deeper reference point for wisdom now we know better and better and
better what it means to avoid harm what it means to not harm
others what it means to benefit self stay close to the inner welfare and
happiness what it means to to benefit others how to really benefit others in
some good way and um and it might be
that you know you give someone cookies at work and that might be nice but it
might be that how you give it might actually make all the difference in the world and so there's some
inner movement in how you give that is more than just you know throwing it on
on their table and so so it's based on this now
that in this path model I'm talking about moves into discussion of wisdom
wisdom here is not something you learn first and foremost the practical wisdom
of the Dharma is gained through these first three steps many people in the west begin
their path with meditation and so that's where they learn this eventually and then they feel and from that they learn
oh it's good to be generous or maybe first they learned it's good to be ethical and then they learn it's good to
be generous so they kind of do it backwards sometimes in the West because they start with we start with meditation
I mean how many of you would you of you would come to a course at IMC five we introduction to mindful
generosity you might you might some of you might come but but you know uh you
know our our introduction here is 5way course in mindfulness
meditation and so um so these deeper reference points that
we have so that that's what we're trying to look for in this practice and
um and how do we learn this reference point how do we
learn this kind of way of living by living it action is needed action in Body
Action in speech and action and mind there's activity this is an active path to the Dharma even though Med meditation
can look kind of passive it's actually kind of active also it's actively doing
less and um and this is a path of action of how you live your life and in living
it you then learn the feedback loops that you recognize and feel and know
what causes harm and what brings benefit and in doing that then you have the
basis for wanting to care care comes out of
that care is a deep place inside where we
feel um uh we have a concern we have empathic concern we have a sense of
shared Humanity we have a sense of it's important to that humans humans and
their well-being their inner life are invaluable that everyone has the same kind of basic building blocks of an
inner life that you do building blocks that uh where there can be a completely
natural instinct or impulse to care for the world it's not an
obligation one of the most beautiful little uh stories I like in
zenel someone asks the Zen master in China uh what is it like to be the
embodiment of compassion there's a day called the Quan embodiment of compassion
and his Z Master says oh uh it's like uh uh rearranging the
pillow when you're sleeping at night I mean it's like
what the idea being that it's completely done
unselfconsciously of course if you're uncomfortable something inside of you kind of re the pillow to make yourself
more comfortable to sleep better there's almost no thought going into it that's the source in which the embodiment of
compassion cares for the world it's just no there's no thought exactly it's just kind of a
course you know if um if you have three pillows and the person sleeping near you has none and
they're uncomfortable here take a pillow take two um you know how do we share how do
we this this this deep kind of caring Instinct that we
have and I was really touched when my mother was in um the memory care home
here in Redwood City um to watch people who in conventional way of using the word love
didn't didn't love my mother but it was remarkable the care that they offered
her it was as if they loved her and their professionalism their calm their
dedication their their unwavering this for the year and a half or two years he was there was phenomenal to watch and
see the level of care they had and um and this is the possible for all of us
we can live in the world with care and
um
so so I'll read that quote again and then I'll make a statement to close more
theater so just wise people of great
wisdom do not think of harming themselves of harming others or of
harming both rather wise people consider their own
welfare the welfare of others the welfare of both and the welfare of the
whole world in this way one is a wise person of great
wisdom so to conclude because this is practical
wisdom this is wisdom that comes from how we live our
life it is up to you whether what you
do for the rest of this morning no matter how M
mundane it is that you do it is up to you whether it's wise
wholesome and Wellborn from this Caring Place
Within it's really up to you in all the things you
do and may you experience the wisdom that allows you to live with this
kind of care with this kind of self-care with this kind of
generative way of bringing well-being and may it be an act of
love so thank you