good morning and a good day everyone so we're coming to
the last day of this week or
weekday um in our series I feel rather quiet right
now and just savoring this sense of songer and con
connectedness and so so maybe that's enough for us to begin just sense of a welcoming to the
Sanka to the collective blessing to be able to practice together like
this and so close your eyes if you like
and coming to a meditative
posture with the celebrations and joy
Delight mud with
feeling goodness
already coming home to The Refuge of
Thea coming home to
ourselves the Dharma is in be good
here and now
awake and aware to this
moment sitting in our own bod mind and
heart and also the
collective Maybe the sense of boundary of this
being is soft
we can feel the connection with the earth a
space The Late Late TNA Zam
Master coined the T we interent
our we are interbeing
each of us is
uniquely ourselves and
yet we are in a collective
e e
e
for
e for
a poem from the late tikn H called
interbeing the song has entered
me the sun has entered me together with the
cloud and the river
I myself have entered the
river and I have entered the sun with the
cloud and the river there has not been a moment when
we do not interpenetrate
but before the sun entered me the sun was in
me also the cloud and the
river before I entered the river I was already in
it there has not been a moment when we have not interb
therefore you know that as long as you continue to
breathe I continue to be in
you
e
e e
[Music]
yesterday I spoke about um this notion of living as our own
Refuge or make ourselves a refuge and then let the Dharma be one's
Refuge uh when we practice with this uh little by little
what we may discover is that we become
more and more safe to ourselves maybe all parts of
ourselves not just the parts that uh we like or are
pleasant but also the parts that um may feel challenged or
challenging maybe the in secure or the Shy part of ourselves can feel safe and free to
be herself himself or themselves within
ourselves without feeling that um somehow they might get diminished or
they have to be defensive you know somehow I shouldn't
be like this I should be stronger or whatever and that's just demanding uh
for our ourselves the parts of ourselves to be other than what they
are and it's a hard enough to be uh insecure feeling
pain uh why add more demands why add more
pressure why contract more
and so through uh this process of living
creating as The Refuge for
oneself and gradually we can begin to feel the bigness of this process there's
something opening up within us it has a capacity to hold uh the whole of
ourselves and it doesn't stop
there when we are safe and when we are vast for
ourselves others can feel safe with us other beings can feel safe around
us and so in this way living as a refuge
uh of One's Own can also be a refuge for others
other beings The Whole World At Large and this is what I'd like to share
today and which is the notion of being refuge for all
beings and there is a wonderful sutta in Maj man nikaya called the simile of
cloth some of you may know this towards the end of the suta and the
Buddha shared this verses I'd like to read for
you to make yourself a refuge for all beings and if you speak no
falsehood nor do harm for living beings nor take what is not
offered with faith and free from Everest
in the process of um making oneself a
refuge one's own virtuous heart virtuous
conduct creates a virtuous field and so when people are around this
kind of field they don't have to be concerned that they're going to be light
to or they're going to be harm uh in ways uh in different
ways and the person's uh calm and ease uh is a field for others to feel as
well and maybe it helps to come and ease others anxieties and
fear and I've mentioned the Tik nahan a few times today and the late Master Tik
nanan was a prime example of such a refuge or such a
sanctuary for so many people who were struggling at the times of the war or
times of the difficulties and so there a process of
living or making refuge for oneself has a natural
extension to being a refuge for all
beings and there is a re uh effect uh as well the more goodness
and safety there is uh in this world the more support each of us will have in our
own cultivation and then we feed out to the world and so this are kind of two sides
of um the coin um cultivating uh being a
refuge for ourselves and being a sanctuary for all
beings and there is one thing I would like to point out this notion of being a refuge for
all beings is not meant to create some sort of identity for ourselves and look
at me you know somehow others should come to me because I am so and so and
so and that's just turning the Refuge into an ident entity into a
s you know just saying that you might begin to feel the tightness the
narrowing the contraction that comes down it's losing the the boundlessness
and the vastness of this aspect of being a refuge for all
beings and so this is not uh being the ref future for all beings is not uh uh
to create Identity or create a sense of
self rather uh people feel around the people
who expresses Natural Care natural responsiveness and wisdom and
compassion and this uh this sense of being a sanctuary is a natural Dharma
manifestation or
expression and in our meditation uh you may begin to feel this um through our
inner cultivation and the deepening of insight into our own
nature it can become increasingly clear that we are truly interb being we are
truly interr as Tian uh
described there is a deep connection between all beings and the
environment the whole planet whole
world so when we're not caught up in our own um selfing
edes we can feel this kind of natural
interconnectedness uh everything belongs nothing is outside of this vast
being and so there is a refuge for ourselves and there is a refuge for
everyone for all
beings I like to close by reading this a poem again uh poem I dropped in in our
meditation and this is the poem of interbeing and I received this uh from
um uh a teacher Philip maet one of my teachers on a poetry day uh it really
attached to me and so by tikna it's from his poetry
book call me by my true names and so here it is
again the sun has entered me the sun has entered me together with
the cloud and with the river I myself have entered the
river and I have entered the sun with the CL out and the
river there has not been a moment when we do not
interpenetrate but before the sun entered me the sun was in me also the
cloud and the river before I entered the
river I was already in it there there has not been a
moment when we have not intervene
therefore you know that as long as you continue to
breathe I continue to be in you
so with that we end this weeks of
exploration around Refuge the different flavors of it the
triple Jam The Refuge of our own and for all
beings and may this exploration be something
meaningful and evocative and maybe even
confusing which is all
good and so may whatever benefit and that arose out
of uh this exploration and our practicing
together may it nourish our own heart and mind may it enliven our bodies
and may the benefit be shared wide o open in all
directions may all beings have clear Calm
Mind peaceful and loving heart may all beings have vital healthy
bodies and may all beings no
wonder peace joy and the liberating wiom in this life
just as it
[Music]
is thank you friends be well