hello everyone and welcome and
U so for this uh meditation today maybe
I'll do a little less guiding but more um setting a context for the
meditation uh Community SA spiritual
friendship is uh very important very supportive for Buddhist
practice and when I was uh living about three years in a Buddhist
Monastery uh it it was a very important time in my life and the practice was
important and I could not have done it without the support of the community being Community with people I didn't
have I wouldn't I would say I didn't have good friends in the monastery but I had a village I had uh regular
social contact with people who were nice and and um and it was
a a wonderful place to be and so I had this wonderful balance between spiritual
friendship and ability to be kind of also at the same time um not having the
social life complicate my life um and allowed me to settle into the
practice uh having having my teachers and that was a little bit slow to understand but in retrospect I've
understood how important my early teachers were and their their support
their encouragement was invaluable for me to to continue and to this day uh I feel very
much that uh the support part of the fuel part of the inspiration for my
practice is the spiritual Community communities that I'm part of
IMC and now for the last almost over four years here on YouTube with all of
you coming here there's something very uh valuable that uh the association the
connection the shared practice that we have and this goes back I feel very much
that uh uh that um sometimes I sit down to meditate and I appreciate that there
are thousands tens of thousands hundreds of thousands of people at this very moment uh engag in Buddhist practice and
meditation around the globe maybe more and that um we had there's a
shared uh Community for this practice here and now we don't know each other necessarily but the fact that so many
people are practicing and that is important for me and then if you go back through time uh
my many teachers my teachers teachers they teachers and that there's been
people doing this practice for you know over 2,000 years and we're in the
lineage we're in the wave we're standing on the shoulders of the people who went
before us so that's the context for this meditation and to have that sense of
that Mutual support the circle of friends that are around us spiritual friends spiritual community that then in
a symbolic ways are around us all the time to support us but not too much not
to complicate our lives not to entangle us in uh
in the complexity of social life social
needs and concerns and uh at least the the Dharma
Community ideally is a community we feel supported by but not we don't invest so
much in it or we don't um expect such a high thing from it that we get entangled
in expectations and in that combination Sometimes some of the best relationships
some of the richest uh social connections can be in Dharma communities
support so um so in this kind of symbolic way I know some of you have had
complexities with Buddhist communities but this symbolic way we we are not here
without the support of others and to meditate today today have some sense of
that you're not meditating alone you're meditating with this online community uh meditating
here and um and don't let it be too much of a of a thinking some you think about
and fantasize about but if you find yourself wondering off in thought thinking about other things um as you as
our means to come back to Here and Now appreciate the circle
of spiritual Community Dharma Community meditate meditating
community that uh is here with you and that uh you're not alone doing
this and let that be the bridge to coming back to here to feel that support to feel that
encouragement to feel the inspiration so whenever you wonderer off wake up to the
community and through that wake up here to your lived experience at this
moment so with that today I'm going to have it be silent the rest of the time
and um and uh many of the guided guidance I
do for these meditations Begins the same way more or less the same way and you've heard it many times most of
you but uh the idea that you're inclusive of the community is new so I'll just be quiet now and those of you
who are inclined let there be the support from
all these Circles of Dharma communities that past present
here and far away that are here that are supporting us
all thank
you
e
for
e e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting to appreciate that
coming out of meditation is to come out into a
community though maybe you're meditating at home
alone there's all of us sitting here on with this YouTube
Sitting that is coming out of meditation together
here to meet me again to meet each other again those of you reading the chats to
read the chats participate with each other coming back into a community that
has been continuous now for a long
time and then not to take this for granted but this that uh the very
existence of this YouTube Community has allowed this YouTube
event practice to live and occur and to for me and other IMC teachers to show up
here and and to be inspired to teach because of all of you and and how we
come together so every single one of you who's here contributes to
that so and then coming out of out of sitting
into community to do so slowly gently without high
expectation but appreciating what we have here and let
it be an inspiration that this practice that we do is for the benefit of our
communities this one our neighbors our friends all the different communities
people strangers and no known that we meet may it be that we ENT the
world with more friendliness ready to be friendly in
simple undemanding ways generous ways for all beings that
we encounter may we be friends to the
world may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be free may all beings be
peaceful and may we be friends to all
[Music]
beings thank you for
so hello and welcome to this second talk where I'm uh reading from my translations of the
poems of the ancient Buddhist nuns the early first bu Disciples of the
Buddha and as Paul it's called a Terry Gata and
uh and the um and so for this poem uh this is a
poem of uh Kisa goami and uh and it's a very touching
poem and it involves a conversation between
kizami and pachara and I think in the modern West
Fair number of people know about kiso goami and um not so many know about
pachara but we have a beautiful statue of pachara uh at IRC and uh there's about
five different photographs that uh cycle through on the IMC homepage and
one of them is of pachara of um an beautiful wooden
statue that was given to us uh made for us and given to us
by and uh and so these are two famous uh
early Buddhist nuns so kog goami is um
is known as the for the mustard mustard seed story uh Kisa means frail so it's frail
gotami and um so maybe she's not that well she's she's uh maybe somewhat weak
or sick maybe or she's certainly poor and uh she has the circumstance of
being married into a family probably an ranged marriage back then and her status
uh was very low and in Ancient India the status of uh of a um bride they join you
don't just join a husband you join the husband's family often and the status is quite low and difficult and often uh
expected to kind of be a servant almost and uh so we don't know exactly
what the circumstances are but um she she then had a son uh and that changed
her status then she had a place in the family she has a status because back then ma male Prodigy was really
important and so there was a lot of things the mother probably loved her son
but it also put her in secure in a secure place in the family and society and then the son died as a baby
and she was distraught and she refused to believe the son had died and she went carrying
the dead baby around asking everyone for help for medicine and someone finally
said to her there's someone who has medicine and that's the Buddha with great hope she goes to the Buddha and
the Buddha says yes go to uh around and and collect mustard seeds which was a
very common spice that people had in the kitchen in Ancient India so everyone had
mustard seeds that they would grind up for cooking and G and gather a mustard seed
from all the households that um have not experienced death
and uh she starts going around and she discovers that everyone every household
that she came to has experienced death of CH children of parents of siblings
somehow death has been part of everyone's life and um and at some point
she realizes that and realizes then that uh the universality of death and that
she could accept the death of her baby and she went back to tell the Buddha this and and um and then he taught her
and she ordained and attained Awakening but aara the in this the
second person in this conversation uh uh she also had a tragic
uh uh death of family but there was kind of a massive uh death all at once you
know at the same time uh she was giving birth to her second child and she wanted to go back to her be with her parents
Family Home and but then she started giving birth uh during that walk and the
husband went out to try to find some grass and something to create an cushioning or bed for her to for um to
make her comfortable and he came across a snake that bit her bit him and he died
distraught uh pachara then uh gave birth and and uh was going to carry go to her
family's house me crossing a river and she first crossed over with her baby
and put him on the on the other Shore and on the way back to get her other uh
child um a u some big bird or prey came in and grabbed the baby and flew off
with it and while she was trying to yell and try to do something about that uh the
younger one ventured into the river and drowned so then she did go back to her
home Village to only discover that uh her mother and father and brother had
all died and were currently uh on the funeral PES being
cremated so a tremendous amount of suffering all at once and whether this story is a fable or an actually thing
that could have happened back in Ancient India I we don't know but I can imagine it could have happened these kinds of
horrible tragedies so these two women had huge tragedies both of them became nuns both
of them became enlightened and they were friends friends and so this is a conversation
between them and it's important to understand as you hear this poem that uh
they are both enlightened they're both free and what they talk about they do so
uh not the burden of their suffering but seeing it clearly knowing it clearly and
knowing that they are now have a degree of Enlightenment or Freedom so the poem begins with an
introductory three introductory verses and it was probably uh chanted in the
ancient world and there was probably three voices that chanted it so it's a little bit of a performance a little bit
meant to kind of highlight something and the the first three verses are probably chanted by a chant leader or someone and
it sets the stage for the conversation between these two nuns and um and so the first two are
quite lovely and uh the sentiment about spiritual friendship
in this world the sage has taught and praised spiritual
friendship by associating with a spiritual friend even a fool can become
wise associate with good people and wisdom will grow by associating with
good people one will be freed from all suffering so two verses
uh promoting the value of spiritual friendship being around good people good people is here in the context of the
ancient tradition means people who are ethical and know about the spiritual life and it can point you help support
you to uh understand and address and learn about the core Buddhist teaching
which what is presented in the third verse one should know suffering
the arising of suffering and its cessation and the Noble eful
Path and so these are usually called four noble truths and it's a little slightly different than that here but
it's for our purposes but the uh this is the task with our spiritual friendship
spiritual support from Wise people is to really know suffering and to know the
arising of it the cessation of it the ending of it and the eful path Noble eful
Path and now we begin the conversation between the two nuns and um it starts
with kisami and this is maybe difficult to hear but it speaks to the tremendous uh
difficulty of ancient life we're talking about the Bronze Age before medicine and hospitals and doctors and when people
giving birth had to do maybe alone without any help or with just local uh you know
um and um and so uh kizami and pachara are
going to demonstrate that they know these core Buddhist teachings they know
suffering they know the the rising the cessation and the noble a full path and
so you'll witness now the conversation kind of is a is a demonstration of
spiritual friendship with these two friends and that both of them really
understand the whole uh point of what the Buddha was teaching so K gotami says
Womanhood is suffering Womanhood is suffering
declared the trainer of people to Be Tamed being a co-wife is suffering and
for some so is giving birth even once some women cut their
throats those who are discreet eat poison some fetuses within are
killers with misery for both mother and fetus so for some the ancient world
being a woman was very difficult for all for for biological reasons and for
social reasons and then pachara responds and now she's talking
about herself walking around about to give
birth I found my husband dead before I reached my house I gave
birth on the road for miserable miserable me two
children died a husband dead on the road mother father and brother burning on one
funeral p and then kagami speaking about pachara responding
to her friend miserable with family destroyed your suffering was
immeasurable you have said you have shed such tears for many thousands of
births but theara answers and now she continues talking about her suffering
after the death of her family I lived in the middle of the
charnal ground where my children's flesh was
eaten with family killed I was despised by
all but then with husband dead I
attained the absence of
death and then um um kogami then
speaks and replies as well similarly that she also has attained I cultivated the noble
Eightfold Path leading to the absence of death I have realized release my
translation of nibana I have realized nibana and have looked into the mirror
of the dhma I removed the arrow laid down the
burden and done what had to be done so these two women who had maybe
for some of us unimaginable suffering great difficulty and
um but uh they experienced this the new
suffering that's for sure and they just show that they show that this is something they know and they knew the
arising of it they see it they experienced it appear and they experienced the end of
it the cessation of it they uh they were not stuck in their suffering there was a
way out there was possibility of freedom and then they knew the Noble eful
Path that sometimes that's understood as being the path to that freedom and sometimes it's understood
the path one lives how one lives After experiencing that freedom that nibana
that absence of death that attainment of freedom of cling freedom from clinging
absence of clinging and they're explaining it very confidently they have attained they
pulled out the arrow laid down the burden done what had to be done so in
this uh conversation with two friends they're sharing with each other yes we
understand the Dharma and we've seen it to the end both of us and uh and they're
they're spiritual friends for each other and having this Dharma conversation and they speak about their attainment with
confidence and with that they're able to look back and talk about the horrendous
suffering they had uh with freedom with Clarity with matter of factus without
suffering anymore because they had once suffered so badly they were
free and um and and so I find this poem very touching that
uh it's meant to demonstrate the spiritual friendship this two good people having this conversation about
the Dharma and a conversation about uh what's possible uh uh as an alternative to
living a life that is so difficult um we
can lay down the burden pull out the arrow and we can experience the absence of
death a very strong metaphor very strong metap symbolic idea of the absence of
suffering absence of clinging so may
you see this path to the end of your
suffering may you be able to stand there and be present and talk about about the
suffering you've you have had with the same Clarity and honesty and directness
that is untroubled by it just this is how it this is how it was and now I'm
free so thank you