Neil in New Hampshire hi everyone hi Neil and toino British Columbia hi Kim
we're International here's Barbara in Oakland and I've got Fred
here hi hi welcome welcome welcome to both of
you thank you
let's see oh a bunch of other hellos are coming in from uh Bill thank you Bill I am feeling
a little better tonight a little under the weather but better than yesterday thank you marann from Burling game hi
and Amy Says Aloha from Oahu and we're also live streaming now on YouTube FYI
so anybody else wants to say hi before we we uh begin
Joan from Santa Maria California hi Joan over so you're not just back it like
that there okay all right so let's begin let's formally
begin thank you Neil for posting information about happy hour Google
groups in chat uh on Zoom if you are new to happy hour you are warmly welcomed to
join the load traffic um mailing list uh to receive more information Etc quotes
that are shared resources Etc and also if you're new you may want
to click on the breakout room etiquette uh I'll go over it later when we open
the breakout room so at this time I changed the settings so unmuting on
wouldn't be possible so the space stays quiet and I also changed chat settings
so the chats will only come to me but I ask you to keep the chat um that channel
quiet because it can be distracting and last but not least I'm going to turn on
recording for the sake of Audio Dharma here we go
great so hello and welcome everyone welcome to happy hour hope you are as
well as possible Wherever You Are in our world on our planet at this
time so for today's practice
um in honor of election day in the US um I wanted to invite us to practice
the fourth of the Brahma viharas the fourth of the Heavenly abodes the first
one being meta second one meta or loving kindness friendliness second one being
compassion passion third one being um vicarious Joy the fourth one being
equinity so it's a good time to practice Equanimity which is really related uh
closely related to good willll Clos to related related to compassion um and allow allows us
invites us to have a sense of presence and stability and peace even when things
are not stable or peaceful or whatever they might be um
so with the level of anxiety that that folks are reporting in the media and the
News no matter which side you're on it's practicing equinity kindness and
compassion for yourself and for everyone else who's in the same boat so it's great opportunity to practice so so with
that like to invite us to to settle arrive in our posture if you need
to move and shift
finding finding center of your gravity your
base your wide base so if you need to roll your
shoulders back a bit to open your chest it's a good idea so that you can sit
tall like a mountain sense of
integrity and feeling how your sit bones can have a sense of stability or
posture take a moment to really stabilize your
posture feel sitting in a chair can you really make sure that your feet
are solidly planted on the earth with a wide
stance that your chest is open your shoulders are wide you're not
collapsed there's a sense of Integrity
dignity to the brightness of how you're sitting in this
moment and as teacher Steven LaVine used to teach used to say strong back strong
torso back and soft belly
strong back soft belly
and can our belly the whole front of our body can it be soft can our heart be
soft while our back or sit bones are
strong stance of our
feet is stable grounded take some time to really feel
into what this means for you in your posture
and allowing awareness to
be soft relaxed noticing it attending to the
breath receiving receptive awareness receptive receiving the breath in breath
and out breath whereever in the body it's more
salient
e
e e
feeling your feet grounded stable in the
Earth and your torso upright as if connected to an invisible
string pulling up vertebrae by
vertebrae sitting tall while you are well grounded
receiving each in breath and out breath
settling
e e
and as we release let go of thoughts
ruminations and stories and invite the heart and mind to
be right here right now present with the breath settle for a few more
minutes before we drop P the corid
reflections
e e
you can stay if you wish with just receiving the
breath present calming and stilling grounding
embodied if you like you can drop in like a pebble in a calm
Pond still Lake drop in the reflections of
equinity going to offer a few phrases choose your
favorite whether or not I may understand it things are unfolding
according to a lawful nature the law of causes and
conditions or may I be at peace
with the comings and goings of things with the impermanent arising and
passing unfolding of events
or simply things are as they are right
now may my heart have
stability the midst of unfolding of causes and conditions
[Music] or as much as I
wish as much as I wish to impact
others happiness and turn of events I
acknowledge that there are many causes and conditions unfolding
may my heart be at peace with things that cannot
change and remember being at peace does not mean
resignation may I have peace
may all beings be at
peace
e
e e
h for
and as we begin to turn to close this sit together i' like to
invite you to wish well
friendliness for everyone all beings no matter what opinions
or or political party there they might belong to all
beings all beings putting down opinions and ideas seeing
people's Humanities we all want to be happy you might agree
disagree but can we wish Each Other Well hatred never ceases through
hatred but by Love Alone does it end this is an ancient and eternal love
as said the Buddha can we share our goodwi for our fellow humans
regardless may all beings be happy may all
beings be well may all beings everywhere
everywhere all human beings all [Music]
animals all sensient beings may they be free including
ourselves thank you everyone thank you for your practice
and the invitations tonight in the practice were very simple at first we
begun with settling in the body really stabilizing the body that
can go very very far whenever you feel find yourself overwhelmed notice what is the posture
of your body is it a collapsed body is a distressed body can you open your chest can you plant your feet just a sense of
a posture of integrity and dignity sitting upright planting your feet
stably on the earth and I brought in this this way of
teaching from Steven LaVine the late teacher who talked about strong back and
soft belly strong back a sign of this The Stance of
stability and soft belly soft heart is sense of kindness compassion for
ourselves and others meta
kindness and then I invited us after taking some time to to stabilize with
the breath in breath out breath
stabilizing silently to drop in any of the equinity phrases that might work for
us at this time may I accept the comings and goings of things the unfolding of
things according to a lawful nature and what does lawful nature mean it's the law of causes and conditions because of
this this AR this arises because of that that arises so many causes and conditions leading to something to what
what arises in in our world um as um as a famous physicist has said
I'm trying to remember his name now it's I'm blanking on it but this statement is the quote is if you want to to make an
apple pie you have to create the whole universe first so everything depending on everything else
really and another statement of equinity is whether or not I understand that
things are according are unfolding according to a lawful nature whether or not I like it whether or not I like it
or not whether or not I understand it or not so this a statement of yeah things
are like this right now things are like this right now and and um acceptance is
not the same as giving up acceptance
means you accept that things are like this right now things causes and
conditions have led to what is arising so you're accepting the reality of the
situation not fighting the reality of how things right now are it doesn't
equate with resignation those two are very different
anyway and then I invited a lot of Silence maybe 10 or more minutes of
silence at the end for us to just settle as is supportive for us
um so so now we do have an opportunity if you like to join one
another to check in with our practice and I want to invite us to avoid any
political conversation because it's important for everyone no matter what their their opinions their beliefs are
to feel safe to feel comfortable and the invitation is really about our practice
what supports your equinity what supports equinity and please don't get into you know thinking and opinions but
maybe what supports my equinity is embodiment if I really come to this moment and and breathe deeply or or come
to a sense of compassion for myself or others come in humanity so stay with
your practice stay close to your heart stay close to your practice what supports Equanimity at this time and if
anyone in the group starts talking politically you know invite them to to avoid and just let's stay let's St stay
with the practice uh what support us supports us maybe being in nature maybe
just turning off the radio and going for a walk supports your equinity doing mindful walking or or listening
to sound of the birds and the invitation is to practice
meta with one another and reminding us what the practice of
mea is I will put it in chat
again the invitation is to to um
mindfully speak and listen is the m create breakout groups as a continuation
of the meditation it's really where the rubber meets the road Embrace compassion
if any internal resistance comes up or any discomfort meet it with compassion
and kindness it's beautiful it's it's U really the a Sandbox for practicing
compassion for ourselves and others these small groups stay on topic and the topic I've
given you is how what supports your practice of equanimity take turns
briefly offer one nugget and let's go in alphabetical order according to first
name offer one nugget let the next person speak the next the next will come back to you and avoid cross talk
commenting on somebody else's practice giving advice etc etc really creative
get a safe caring environment uh for one another practicing meta
MTA so so take care of yourselves take care
of one another be kind and I'm going to create rout
rooms now [Music]
and all right let's see creating the
rooms me a moment to [Music]
adjust okay all right I'm gonna uh let's see here hold on one
sec be patient please have a coity for me
trying to do this in real time there okay it's opening all rooms
here we go take care of yourselves take care of each other with meta
e
e e
you are now in the welcome back everyone all the rooms are
closed and everybody's back and uh we have some time for for Reflections
questions um yeah how is it going how did it
go oh wait there it's fix that ah Jerry
there we go am I unmuted yes you are muted what's up thank you uh it
uh sometimes you never know how what um other people may hit them
tonight when you said your feet firmly on the ground that anchored me
I felt okay I'm on my I'm on planet Earth there's no asteroid at the moment
hitting the Earth and I feel my feet firmly on the ground it was a great way
to Anchor and stay in equinity thank you beautiful thank you
so much for sharing this this is so great oh it gladdens my heart to no end
that this seemingly simple but profound shift
was was experienced by you oh yeah feeling my feet on the ground it seems oh it's so simple yeah whatever but yeah
it's it's profound thank you jar really appreciate your reflection that's
great oh and I forgot to uh change chat because you're also uh invited to to
post your Reflections or questions in chat either publicly to everyone or just
privately to me in which case I won't read your name there's one question sent
to me privately question that I wonder if you could address my question from
yesterday how to give meta to a parent when constantly being hurt by a parent distancing is my go-to but still it
doesn't work yeah yeah um yeah it's it's hard it's painful so
in that situation it could be a parent could be anyone else but in particular with a parent you
can um you know um you can create some space
but but not take them you know with a friend perhaps leave them and and not
have them in your heart which actually reminds me of this beautiful teaching by um Sylvia borin who says um um don't
take don't take anyone out of your heart even if you might leave them out of your life so question sure if that might work
with a parent but anyway so um the invitation in that case is start with
compassion self-compassion for yourself of course and let your heart be uh full
let your heart be full with self-compassion for yourself and and you
may need to reduce contact or or um
really support yourself so you're you don't get hurt and see try to see if you
can this is actually this is what can open your heart to compassion and meta for them to see their goodness because
our mind focuses on what's bad what's difficult the ways that they don't see us the way they hurt us but see the good
in them see how they have helped you and supported you or love you in their own
way um or maybe see their good qualities because not everybody I mean a human
being is not filled with is not uh we're all mixed bags that's what I'm trying to
say we're all in mixed bags so try to see the good in them and when we see the good in another that can open our
heart to um yeah to kindness when we
allow ourselves to see the good in another being and of course it doesn't mean that you completely open yourselves
or open yourself to being hurt you can still protect yourself in ways that are
wise but don't let your heart be completely closed it's not good for you it's not good for the other person I
it's a nuanced answer so I hope again this is recorded you can listen to it
later again I made a lot of different points um you are welcome the person who asked the question says thank you you
are very welcome okay I see arbara and Fred your hand is up
please by thank you Nikki uh I I was struck in our group by how the many
things we identified as being helpful in
approaching equinity uh how they're all free you know that uh no license require
no special training no tools don't need to go any place uh you know getting good
sleep exercise reaching out to people we love you know uh practicing with the
intention of equinity are all things that are within our in our grasp for most of us most of
the time and um I don't know that just strikes me as
being you know really different from a lot of American life where
there's you know presumably so much equip equipment and other things needed
to proceed in whatever you want to do in life and no here it is just the array is there at our fingertips
thank you thank you Fred well said well
said yes well said thank you so much indeed yeah and I was touched also by
what you said highlighting the intention really it starts with the
intention um for for equinity for wisdom
for awareness for um presence yeah the
intention beautiful thank you for for those
Reflections and let's see in chat oh yes there is a gratitude for having the SAA
practicing together tonight after separately going on Retreats with you my husband and I are so glad to be able to
share the space together oh that that makes my heart very happy but thank you for the person for the for the couple
who WR sent that appreciation yay so so glad that you can
practice together here in this sa this this sa is very dear to my heart um The
Happy AR very special thank you all for practicing and coming together to make
the songa so special thank you
all Diana I see your hand uh can you hear me yeah yeah okay
uh one thing just struck me uh in your phrase in the phrases offered that this
time really stayed some um and it was
about I had the image of an old time situation where we're sitting around the
table and somebody's offering a prayer at a meal and and and your words were
were to the effect may we you know put down our opinions and seeing others with seeing
the others humanity and everyone wants to be happy and that person I'm I'm thinking of this
because I have people in my family where we have such we're just so different
I'll just leave it at that in our views and um it it really struck me that I
that I think this is something I can do I can I can finally
see and S our practice here another's humanity and and I know that he and they
want to be happy I know that they're human beings and seeing the good person's a wonderful father a wonderful
this this is I can see these but just putting down the
opinions what uh that's a big deal but it maybe not be such big deal um after
all so I could hear that even another 10,000 times and it it really opens up
opened me up so thank you thank you Diana well said well said and and as I
was leading and and planting these Reflections again and again for the I
don't know nth time millionth time again my heart opens even more and more we have to remind ourselves oh always of
these Reflections um so that they become the
they become the inclination of our minds as the Buddha says they might just
drop at a particular time when heart and mind are ready and um wow it just wow
you as if we hear it for the first time and even if we've heard it again and again keep reminding ourselves keep
reminding ourselves of of the Humanity that everybody wants to be happy and
again not condoning um harm hurt but but also
seeing people's humanity and that essentially we're we all want to be
happy even if different values are more important to us um maybe this is a good
time for me to bring um this reference that I've shared some time before which
is a um research uh and book book by Jonathan hate the um
psychologist and researcher Professor I forget which university but but um he's
done very interesting work about um in about finding common grounds and
and when people disagree it's it's often about them prioritizing different values
so maybe one person um prior prioritizes loyalty more and another person values
Innovation more I don't know I'm just pulling these values out of a hat and it's not that one value is bad and the
other value is is good it's just different people have different values and and he's also done a lot of research
on say political disagreements and different people have different values
um that are more important to them in their ranking and and so it can really help find um um more compassion
understanding meta Common Ground not bad or good people different values so I do
refer you to uh look up Jonathan hate h AI d t h a DT Jonathan hates work and
one of his books is one of his very early books is called uh the happiness
hypothesis and he has one chapter dedicated to it but dedicated to the but
he's done a lot more work since then I believe
anyway so we are nearing the end of our time together thank you all for joining
for supporting yourself supporting each other and supporting all beings
everywhere the cultivation of your heart towards Good Will towards compassion
towards equinity at at this time when our world really needs needs it so I
deeply deeply thank you for for practicing these practices may all
beings be happy may all beings have peace may all beings be well may all
beings be free including
ourselves thanks everyone I'm going to stop recording
stop you YouTube wait stop YouTube wait