thank you so much so in the beginning I invited you
to take a snapshot of how things were and so I invite you again to take a
snapshot like how's your heart your mind your body in this
moment this is such a simple practice to to redirect the attention back to the
present moment that we can do at any time what's happening in the
mind how's the heart how's the body so one of the things that's
important to me is supporting people in practice in meditation practice and and
to that end I'm wondering if there's anyone new to the center is there anyone here that's here for the first time oh
welcome welcome welcome yeah so this is my first time
too it's my first time teaching here I've been here I think the last time I was thinking the last time I was here
was um oh uh who was
here oh it's gone now was a
monastic and um but this is many many years ago like eight years ago or
something nine years ago so and and anybody newer to meditation practice
ice anybody else newer to meditation practice yeah yeah okay yeah I was
pretty still in here I'm like ah people know what they're
doing and you know at many points during
our you know know our spiritual Journeys or our meditation Journeys
there are places that get a little sticky aren't there maybe there's things that happen in our meditation we're like
what do I do with this you know it and it can be like difficult places in the
mind but also when our hearts start to open and expand it can feel really
uncomfortable like what's happening I remember this visceral experience that I had like of settling into practice and
being so open I'm like oh I don't want like it it felt so
vulnerable right and so I had to go to my teacher and say what well one what is
this what's happening I don't like it right and then how do I meet
it so I just want to give just a few minutes for a couple of questions if
there's any places in your practice that you notice today or maybe this week is you've been practicing where there's
some stickiness or something arising that you're not quite sure what to do
with or that's hard to meet and it might take some bravery in
this this group but so this wasn't recently but I do remember sitting some
years ago and a wave of Rage crashed over me and I've always
been afraid of anger and yet like I survived what I didn't think that could
happen and so I think there are a lot of surprises yeah in practice there are so many surprises in practice yeah yeah
thank you thank
you okay I'm with an expert group no problems in meditation you
dropped right in you're like I'm good the mind stayed steady it didn't go to
the Future it didn't go to the Past didn't get caught up in fantasy
amazing uh now I get caught up and all of that my my mind often is racing at uh
100 miles an hour and um I I try to sit comfortably and let that let that happen
um I think where I get a little stuck in this maybe you can help me uh would be
trying to understand when I'm trying to or maybe trying is the wrong term when
I'm sitting and letting these thoughts roll one after the other through my mind
at a pace um uh I feel that uh I'm one
uping myself in a certain sense right I'm
observing with kindness these ideas that are rolling through my
mind sorry I'm observing these uh ideas that are rolling through my mind at a
great Pace I'm trying to understand a little bit who's the
Observer um am I just W uping myself into studen scene so maybe you could
comment on that or or help me understand that a little yeah who's the Observer it's such a good
question um and and I think there are some questions that are living
questions um which is the teacher speak for saying I'm not going to answer the question
like and and but I what I will do is it's watch the mind getting caught in
trying to figure out who the Observer is while you're practicing can we simply
know oh there there is something someone that we're calling Observer
knowing the arising of experience knowing the thoughts arising knowing
what you're calling a racing mind right and and and can you include
it all can you include the the trying to figure it all out and then come back to
Simply knowing direct experience oh thinking oh racing oh wanting to figure it out and
then we can go a little bit deeper and see is there in the wanting to figure it out something that that is uneasy in not
knowing right and can we meet that with a lot of kindness oh dear one yeah of course you want to know because maybe
this is a way that keeps us safe can I be in that disease and you know in this way we we
drop deeper and deeper and deeper and and get to some
both like like some discernment about how to be with and um
like some refinement in in how to be and what to
be with right is that is that helpful at all very yes okay thank you all right
good thank you so any other questions specifically about practice yeah thank
you good morning hi I have trouble sometimes giving myself permission to
settle on one thing when I'm practicing I will kind of um
you know let the mind go at the beginning and see where it wants to settle and then when it does I have
trouble saying it's okay to stay here and examine it
closely what what what is the thought that you should be doing like what um I
think part of it is is there something more important or is there something
that is making me a obsess about this in particular rather than approaching it
with more kindness and less judgment and accepting that it might be important for me to examine yeah yeah yeah we won't
know unless we check it out will we so there's that part
um but also there's this like you know this indecision we we
can call that a hindrance of doubt right and and so we want to recognize doubt
quickly and drop it and and then stay and there to might be something like it
might be a little hard and so there might be something protecting like I don't I we're not
ready right and so we also have to honor that yeah and and so if there's really a
we're not ready what can we what can we support
that will help us get ready like what can we incline to and so maybe we need
to stick with some loving kindness practice for a little while oh yeah okay
um and then and then go check it out and and here's the thing with practice sometimes we think we have to go to the
I'm going to fix myself I'm going to go in to the hardest thing and I'm going to
make it okay by by changing it and figuring it out and getting rid of it is
that our practice Yeah so some people are saying yeah that is what I do but is that our
practice right our practice is to be with things the way they are like to
meet them with a lot of kindness you know and sometimes we're ready and and
so then there's many skillful ways to to go in and go out we can go to someplace
neutral in the body right and just rest there and and get some steady of mind
right and then go check it out with real real gently and then we can come back
you know or rest our attention where like where it's easy
where there's some peace or joy and then come back and check it out like it it's
not supportive it's not I don't know I don't think it's such a good use of time to just like go in and yeah and it's not
so kind right yeah thank you thank you
yeah okay there's another question how do you recognize when your
mind is about to slip um without giving into it so how do you
recognize it and kind of like stay in the present
yeah um how do you recognize so so are you saying by how do you recognize the mind is going to slip how do you Rec the
mind ni the mind is about to go into thought without it like indulging in that thought yeah yeah with a lot of
practice Yeah and and and watch if there's any belief that the mind's supposed to
be doing something else and any judgment about it slipping and include that too
right the the mind what does it do it thinks thank goodness like it's so helpful for us to get through our lives
right so the mind will go off this way and this way and this way and and our
whole practice is recognizing when it's gone off and then coming back right and
at some point we take it as an object too right we can include all of it but it's but I want to say it's not a
problem right it's not a problem this is what the Mind does let's include that too yeah and and and you can notice at
some point like oh it's about to go right and be like whoop nope and it also
becomes less interesting and then it's not like there's not us doing it the mind just stays there's some steadiness
that's a possibility okay and a follow-up question often times when I found that uh when I find out my mind is
slipped and I'm uh not in the present i' like to trace my thoughts backwards to figure out where it got distracted is
that helpful or and maybe it's more thinking yeah okay yeah yeah I think it
is helpful maybe to to to know where it went and and notice patterns like gen General patterns oh planning right right
and then and then we can come back and notice like oh is there something is there a worry here like that is I think
coming back to the body and saying oh what's here what's What's um maybe the
the mind is helping solve or avoiding right I think that is a more useful way
yeah thank you you thanks okay maybe that's good for now I have this piece of paper that I'm going to pull out with
some notes on it
and then we'll see what happens isn't that what we're always
doing we're just seeing what happens our minds our
hearts at the top it says refinement and discernment right
and so it's so heartening to be here with you you know I still haven't except for
um at Retreat centers you I teach at Spirit Rock and IMS and another Retreat Center called Vitos which is in the New
Mexico Northern New Mexico
um a lot of groups aren't in person yet still right and so it's really a joy to
be in person I don't take it for granted you
know
um and it says like oh there's something that you all came for I hope it wasn't
me [Music] um but there's something that that calls
us or or or maybe in the beginning of my practice I was a Seeker like there just
was something that wasn't working in my life right I had a lot of anger
and fear and doubt sadness and grief and
depression right when I of started on my path and it wasn't like path to Buddhism
you I took this went to found a church that I really liked and and eventually
found the dhama and and you know and it was
always there in some way like it was very presentent in my life because my
stepmom practiced Buddhism and had her Quan altar outside my room right and
would chant every day um but you know as often and like
with our parents things we like not doing that that's you
know and Somehow Here I Am um which makes her very
[Laughter] happy
yeah and so something brought you here today and maybe for some of you this is
always where you come on Sunday morning and for some of you maybe you're a little bit newer to practice maybe a
friend brought you they're like check out this thing called mindfulness there's a center you should go
right so there's something that brought us and then there's something that keeps us
here right and and for me and I I reference
This Heart opening thing that happened it was on the first Retreat that I went to at Spirit Rock and I didn't know what
was happening and I didn't like it but I knew something was changing like
internally that I was gaining access to something that was like good in the
sense of non-harming that was helpful and
supportive to me being the person I wanted to be in
the world
and so I think it's so helpful to like reflect on what keeps us coming like
what is it that we're curious about in our practice in our hearts and our
minds right and also what are those
edges what are those places that we notice
maybe we're not showing up in ways that um are so
kind or
helpful like externally internally and
both
right and and our practice our our meditative practice Can can support us
in this discernment and
and this thing called mindfulness or
awareness hopefully you don't only do it here but maybe that's where we start
you're like oh maybe for 5 years we just come and like this is our practice and then it goes out the window the rest of
the week that's a possibility and it's not a problem right I I uh taught a
retreat last year and there was a student
who was pretty um like angry at the conditions
of the retreat the people that they thought should be there wouldn't weren't there
and um they didn't like the silence and didn't get the whole meditation
thing but yet we're at a retreat and and so they kind of they
didn't show up to everything they kind of did their own thing but they had lots of questions and they kept like going
where I was and showing up and ended up living at a couple of different Dharma centers but still
didn't meditate and like almost a year in they're like okay can you teach me how
to meditate I'm like okay I will teach you how to meditate I was kind of excited and so I
just like all right let's sit down we tried a different couple different meditations and I was like can you just
do this for five minutes a day for five minutes a day so maybe that's where we start five minutes a
day and and they recently came to visit me and like Victoria for the last 40
days I've been sitting for 30 minutes to
day you know so something shifted it took them a minute to to to get it and
their way in was through Community they went to live at these centers and get to know the people and
and what they were being shown is how people were living their lives what their values were right that they were
living with deep integrity and inclining what their
Minds their words and their actions towards that which was helpful that which was kind that which was generous
that which was beneficial right and that got them really
interested oh if if in this scene there are these good
people that show up in ways that I want to show up there must be something to this
right and then and then we we get in there a little bit and we're like oh this place is
hard this is this is I don't like this quality of my
mind or or how the mind reacts
to particular stimuli [Music]
um and then we're like what do I do with this what do I do with this how do I meet this so often I ask
students like okay when you notice something in the mind this is the question I ask how did
you meet it how did you meet that and they're like what do you mean
meet it I didn't meet it I I just put it down I went back to my
breath is that helpful all the
time no right yeah um so we can start to notice as we
as we refine our practice like all the
parts like how are we meeting ourselves how are we meeting these broken hearts
or joyful
hearts and so it seems that sometimes people miss this part
about how we are with ourselves it's often so easy to be
generous and kind and stand up for others and not so easy to do this for
ourselves and it all matters right so on the cushion off the
cushion you can we we start to stay
here right right here present with things whatever they are more often and
when we say here with whatever is arising more often then we have more Choice don't
we right we have more choice because we we're in real time meeting responding to
what's arising and we can't do that if we're not here for it not here for our lives
like and sometimes it is so difficult right and so then we have to
find find these ways
to have some balance all right there's so many
moments in a day like just mind moments if you will right
and we can't ignore the ones well don't ignore any of them right but also really
don't ignore the ones where there's some peace and joy and
kindness and I know generosity and love like
both internally externally and and both
right because this is so supportive in our
practice this um like inclining to that which is wholesome and
helpful so my teacher in in has anyone been to
Nepal anyone been to lumini yeah what's lumini why is that a
famous place birth yeah birthplace of the Buddha yeah
um and so my teacher is very interested in what's happening in my practice right
like I don't know okay what what are you paying attention to how long are you staying
there right so that's part of it like there's every day there's a little refinement you know six days a week when
I go with them they're they're checking in about my practice and then like okay
just do a little bit more of this aing bring in a little bit more Equanimity bring in a little bit more
concentration okay back off a little bit right like there's that that kind of
discernment um but you know what they really want to
know is what am I inclining the mind to is there more kindness
Victoria are there more wholesome States arising every day
right they're very interested in that and why are they interested in that they're interested in it because it's a
it's a supportive condition for me to stay
present right and so we can check at any moment
in our day like oh what are we what are we inclining towards what are we
feeding do you ask yourself these questions like with that snapshot okay what's in
the mind right now oh I'm being harsh on
myself right can I meet myself with kindness do you think it matters do you
think it counts it does I mean and check it out for yourself don't take my word for
it but it does you matter be kind to yourself
you know what are you cultivating it can be helpful to
remember why we're not just doing it for ourselves are
we we're doing it for our communities our families our
friends we don't keep it and you couldn't
right even if if you tried I'm going to keep all this goodness for myself
no right the generosity comes
out the love comes out the joy comes out the exuberance
comes out and
likewise the frustration the irritation the Judgment the ways that we aren't kind
also come out and and you know I don't mention
those things to to judge or
um yeah to judge but but it's but we need to be honest like oh what's
actually here like and is this helpful is this kind is this is this beneficial to the
world that I want to live in or not and so we have to be real honest
with ourselves like really honest with ourselves not in order to beat ourselves
up but just to have the information so we know what we're working with you know
in the beginning I knew what I was working with I was working with a lot of anger and fear
and and he didn't know that there was fear there in the beginning um and depression
right but I had to be really honest with myself about that so I could learn how to meet
it and learn what the antidote
was you know the beautiful thing about this practice is like whatever we're
doing whatever we're meeting or practicing wherever we are on the
path um we deepening if we're paying attention
right I often joke um you know I like to wait for people to come into the
room um and so I often joke like oh this is waiting
practice right how often do you do waiting practice in your
life um and if we can stay there and hold it as waiting practice
then maybe it doesn't tip into frustration or judgment here they are they're late
again or you know or the like I drove down and I live in the East
Bay and guess what on a Sunday morning there's no traffic I got here so fast it was
amazing right and um so there's many gifts of living in the Bay Area where we
can practice patience traffic is one of them and so what are
the ways in which we can we can integrate um these principles that
support us in deepening in our practice in everything and can we catch it can we notice more
often right and and our like the still
meditation practice we do supports this setting of the mind and supports
interest in staying present with things the way they are and sometimes s we're stuck in
traffic and can we know and meet like the frustration or the worry about being
late and watch what the Mind does okay I'm going to be late and then
I'm going to like I don't know they're going to be mad at me or like whatever the thing
is and my suggestion and I'd say the Buddhist suggestion would be actually let's stay here with how things are okay
some frustration here but here we are in traffic let's accept that and see what
happens instead of making up a story about what's going to happen you know have you ever been late
to something and you're meeting a friend and you put so much pressure on yourself and then they were late too and it was
perfect I was like oh and you spent 20 minutes being hard on yourself for not
getting out of the house on time right and in reality it wasn't a problem
so even if we can just get to that even if we can just get to actually like meeting what's actually
happening in real time more often with some
kindness we making a lot of progress instead of they're
lamenting the dream of the past or giving this madeup
future right maybe you had some idea about what was going to happen this morning and it's totally
different right I had lots of ideas about things I was going to talk
about but this is what I'm talking about like a you know there like a light
little script but I kind of threw it out the window so can we stay
here and what happens when we
do and it was so fun to like go into meditation and then I heard people come
in and then I open my eyes I'm like oh more people oh what a joy and
Delight right so what are we cultivating do you
know what you're cultivating are you paying attention
what are you cultivating In This
Moment let's pay attention to that what do we want to Incline
to can we incline to more generosity to patience to
kindness to compassion
and and when we notice that that's not what's happening in our
experience can we not
then be harsh with ourselves or cruel because then what are we doing we're
we're supporting cruelness and harshness right let's meet ourselves
with kindness and then then that's what we're doing then that's what we're inclining towards it's it is that simple
it's not so easy but it is that simple and and then at some point like
along the path we wake up and we've met our
mistake with compassion that's
huge maybe not for you maybe like you just came out this compassionate being with yourself but I
didn't right or though we find we're stuck in
traffic and it's not a problem or waiting in line and it's an opportunity to practice oh wow I get a
practice for five minutes with this cacophony of sound around
me right then each moment is like a gift cuz we get to inclin
towards these supportive conditions that are not dependent
on external conditions but on internal conditions to support our our deepening
and Awakening and refinement in our
practice H it's all pretty exciting to
me maybe that's enough for me well we do have a few minutes for
questions y all know what your edges
are yeah Scott please or get your a
mic good morning hi I found myself very thinky this morning uhuh and U I would awaken to
that fact and bring myself back for kind with kindness and bang I was off to the races
again thinking and I guess I'm I feel like I'm meeting
the moment with kindness like to myself but it sort of feels feudal in a
way that that it just was so strong this inclination
and uh yeah I even tried welcoming it in you know that you know come on in you're
here and um I was just wondering if you had anything to say Beyond sort of just
keep on keeping on with that yeah yeah
so I mean there's a few things I can say
you know one
is sometimes we just have to say oh we're not going to do that's not what we're doing right now like we're going
to stay here and get what's your
anchor anomaly my breath but I sometimes have find it productive to abandon that
and just kind of go into an open awareness you know what were we doing this morning uh perseverating on my breath I
guess and not very successfully you know like that so yeah yeah and is that where the mind went was it was was it thinking
about the breath actually or was it in some thought World about the future or something yeah it was in the thought
world yeah yeah planning or like what category of
thought you don't have to say but yeah I was stupid yeah okay oh that's a
judgment right catch it it's embarrassing I you don't have to say you well no let me now I want to share it so
was I was just like reviewing this proof for the Pagan theorem I mean like the silliest thing yeah you know yeah yeah
yeah and and what was here this morning like did when you came back okay you're like you
came back with love to your anchor right yeah and and did you notice like in the
body was there any tension or anything hard to be with or any
emotion was there anything that you were avoiding is my question or was there boredom
present or or
something I was aware there I was kind of being judgmental about my experience
and I know that's not a good practice but you know uh so so you're being judgmental about your about your
experience because because the mind was going and then you were there was judgment about the Judgment maybe yes
but then I was also kind of forgiving myself for that too so it it was busy yeah you know okay it was busy so yeah
and and and it is sometimes like this and then we can know what it's like to be busy like can we actually
feel the suffering of the busyness and feel the suffering of wanting things to
be different than they are and what happens when we drop into like oh this is how they are right now dear one this
is hard and like bring a lot of care into that all right um but the the
fighting it it maybe isn't so helpful but the resting and meeting
in the suffering of wanting it to be different now that's
getting us somewhere right can we meet that fully and then the mind is off again and then we come back and then the
mind is off and this is strengthening something and so do you think every sit
that every teacher has is like so like ah or Bliss out no right and and there's a way that that
we can just we can observe the the mind going
and the irritation like I'm doing this with my hand the irritation that is there with or
agitation like of the mind or the restlessness or wanting things to be different and include it so can we
include all of it like it's not a problem and sometimes I tell myself it's
not a problem okay the mind is thinking can I just stay with oh I want it to be
different right guess I felt like I just I need to
do more of this like I I sat earlier this morning too
and the second session was a little
marginally well that's passing a judgment on it again but it seemed it felt like it was a little bit
more meditative or yeah uh inclining the mind in a more constructive way yeah so
so let's be careful of thinking that
they're supposed to be a certain State happening for you to be practicing it's
not about any state it's about meeting what's actually
arising fully in real time and that's that's the practice that's always the practice that's
it and sometimes the mind is all over the place and there's agitation and there's Restless restlessness in the
body restlessness in the mind can't we meet that that's the practice that is always the practice
it's not about a state and sometimes States happen sometimes calm happens right so trust me on this one
like let go of like that part cuz that's just torture
yeah okay yeah so I think we have to stop
now um but I'd like to dedicate the Merit of our practice and our time together if that's okay let's take
another minute or
two just appreciating our willingness to show up this
morning to show up to practice meditation to hear the dhama to be in
community to appreciate ourselves for our willingness to
meet things just the way they are and so first May the benefits of our
practice benefit us in our deepening and our Awakening and our learning and our
discernment in our inclining to that which is
wholesome and kind and then may our practice be of benefit to all beings everywhere without
exception may all beings be safe and protected from all internal and external harm may all beings be peaceful and
happy and healthy and as strong as possible and may all beings be free
[Music] thank you so much for your kind
attention and for your practice I'm going to hang out there's a potluck apparently