oh it's time so welcome to our YouTube Community everyone um as um I mentioned a minute
ago my it's my first time here uh doing a YouTube live um it's here in 7 am in
California I'm in Sunnyvale um and I'm delighted to be
sharing the Dharma with all of you so um I'll begin with just a little
bit um uh a few decades ago there was a global meditation event um it was called
the harmonic convergence where uh people all over the world celebrated a rare Celestial event
and um and meditated together uh no matter where they were though they had
parties and celebrations and um and a couple of friends and I decided to join
them in spirit you know and to do it at Sunrise by meditating the top of a
nearby Mountain it was a beautiful a inspiring
Vista where we sat it was just and it was you know just daylight had just started and um we made ourselves really
comfortable bundled up in our blankets and just getting ready to really appreciate and joined the world
in meditation and um when a fly started by messing
around and very very quickly the little Annoying fly became much more compelling
than the beautiful Vista than the feeling of harmony with the
world and um in mindfulness practice we can pay attention to what's
easiest to notice to what's obvious so I became mindful of the
obvious how much I dislike The Buzz it was going to land on me the tension
my body was tight I wanted to take action against the fly um but I began to see the aversion
clearly and I saw it clearly the body relaxed and it gradually
dissipated and then what was obvious was that the fly had landed between the
three of us and it was the largest fly I'd ever seen I saw the body and the wings of the
fly and the way the sun reflected on it with the blue luminescence it was
beautiful and then I noticed a sense of affection for the little being that had joined our
meditation so just by seeing what was obvious it allowed my relationship to
the fly to transform from aversion to affectionate curiosity
so it can be helpful at the beginning of a sitting to just take a couple of minutes to establish a supportive
atmosphere in the mind a welcoming attitude to whatever
arises an attitude that says yes this belongs whatever shows
up so let's
sit take a comfortable and alert posture
gently closing your eyes taking a little time to settle into
your meditation posture arriving
here in this body in this
place in this room on this Earth
setting aside any thoughts and concerns you may have you can put them on a
shelf for the time being being fully
here centered in this body
and from within the body as part of the body becoming aware of your
breathing however you experience it noticing the movements and sensations
of breathing maybe you notice how the chest and ribs expand and
contract or the belly rising and falling
or the air moving in and out of the nose and
throat being at ease with whatever we notice however you feel these movements
now taking a few long slow deep breaths with each in breath nourishing
the body with air feeling the body expanding
and with each exhale allowing the body to relax a little more
deeply to soften to
open letting go of any tensions any bracing
allowing the breath to return to its natural Rhythm noticing however the sensations
of breathing are easiest to feel and allowing the tension to rest
there this is your home base your
anchor it can be helpful to bring in attitude of friendliness to whatever
shows up we're here to discover what's present
what arises to get to know the mind more
intimately and if ideas or concerns show up
put them aside in favor of her actual physical
experience being intimate with the breath with the rhythm of
breathing
e
e e
if your tension has drifted you can notice
it and gently escorted back to the breath welcome it home
and then just keep returning to the rhythm of breathing in and
out
e
e e
if your attention has drifted can notice it in a friendly
way and gently escorted back to the
Breath Again welcoming at
home
e
e e
just as it's helpful to take a few minutes to settle into
meditation it's useful to do so in coming out a simple way to do this when I ring
the bell is to take a couple of slow deep breaths again before opening your
eyes
[Music]
thank you
that the theme this week will be on different aspects of
both knowing and not
knowing it can be said that inside meditation is based on knowing the mind
for the purpose of freeing the mind of being fully at
peace but only by deeply knowing how our minds work can we free the
mind and we can only know something well if we pay attention to it
closely in this Insight practice we value the quality of how we know
something we develop our ability to pay attention but we do so with
equinity so even if what we want is unwanted we can meet it with respect and
meet it with careful attention um asham brah there's a story
that aan brown tells about one of his monks um he's a Abbot of a monastery in
a remote area of Australia and um one of his monks was
having trouble with his teeth and he was procrastinating going to the dentist you
know knowing he had to have a tooth pulled and it was so such a long trip and of course monks don't drive so one
day a br saw the monk Standing Outside The Tool Shed with a pair of pliers
holding a bloody tooth it was obvious he had just pulled his own
tooth so he asked him you know how are you able to do that didn't it
hurt and so the monk responded that he was in his coutti in his little Hut when
he decided to pull out his own tooth but he hesitated at first you know and and
he asked himself um does it hurt now and he
answered himself well no and so he walked over to the shed across the long
field you know and in that time apprehension arose so he again asked himself does it hurt now
no and so he reached the shed and put his hand on the door handle and he asked
does it hurt now no and next he found the pliers and held
them to his tooth and he asked himself does it hurt now no and then he yanked the tooth out
he thought to himself that hurt but not for long um the point being that during his
walk to the shed he didn't cut up get CAU up in the emotional pain that can
arise and we're afraid in anticipation of pain or anticipation of something we
don't want so the monk was mindful enough moment to moment that he was able to see
clearly there was no pain in the moment until he yanked the
tooth was a lot less suffering than anticipating the pain all the way to the
shed when we worry about future suffering we're not seeing that in this
moment the imagin pain is not there the imagin situation is not
here and that all the pain and worry is extra it's
unnecessary and um going to continue with the teaching that rahula gave his
son um the Buddha gave his son rahula
uh from maim Manaya 62 and he said rahula meditate like the
Earth for when you meditate like the Earth Pleasant and unpleasant contacts
will not occupy your mind suppose they were to toss both
clean and unclean things on the earth like feces urine
spit us and blood the Earth isn't horrified it's not repelled or disgusted
because of this in the same way meditate like the
Earth for when you meditate like the Earth Pleasant and pleasant contacts
will not occupy your
mind so to know something to learn something as I said requires your
attention it requires or interest which arises from a curious
mind in mindfulness practice the object of attention is not
as important as the observing mind the idea is that whatever arises
whether it's a physical sensation an emotion a
mood a state of mind is present whatever arises is worthy of our attention so we
can meditate like the Earth and sometimes things show up that
we don't like fear anxiety restlessness physical
discomfort or maybe things we're not interested in like boredom
impatience we can bring interest to something we're not naturally interested
in we can bring interest to something we don't like and we can do that by inclining the
mind to be interested what I mean by that is that
um as first we see that we're rejecting what's present and we can aim to be interested
and not force anything we just know in our hearts that okay that's the direction we're going for I'm going to
engage with that uh with whatever it is we're not wanting we're not
liking and in the same way that um you know uh let's say for instance we need
to get up in the morning extra early and uh we have to set the clock
you know we we want to set it for you know just in case we don't wake up in time but our unconscious mind can wake
us up before the clock maybe you've experienced that already and in the same
way when we incline the mind to be interested um you know the unconscious
mind does the work of bringing the interest in of it as we turn towards the object we're we're looking to get
interested in um an example for myself um I once was a
project manager for an extensive building renovation at the retreat center where I
I had to make major decisions about the two septic systems there
and I had absolutely zero natural interest in septic systems at the
time I had lots of resistance to the amount of learning I needed to do I had
no background but I was committed to letting go of my resistance and I
persevered with it it became pretty obvious to me that
every moment of resisting was a moment without learning that it took a a lot more time
to learn something if I spent a lot of that time resisting it so I began to approach the process by
reading just one paragraph at a time or one diagram at a time and gradually my
interest grew and as the interest grew I was able to
learn and things gradually began to click into place in my mind and there was such a rewarding
sense of now now that I understood what was happening with the septic
system uh and I knew what I didn't know I knew what I needed to know and I started to understand how to
go about making a
decision so generally speaking knowing something gives us a sense of
confidence we know how to do our job you know how to do cook breakfast when we learn a skill
like playing a piano we may start out not knowing how to do it we become more and more confident as we keep
practicing and so you can watch an infant go from falling over backwards to walking with confidence in a period of
months so every moment of knowing develops um a confidence in the practice
a confidence in our s knowing what's here right now at any given
moment what's here regardless of what it
is and as we learn to meet all our moments in our life with mindfulness with careful
attention including the challenging moments we can develop an inner strength
and confidence and the trust that we meet that we can meet all our moments as
they change
and um and they're they
um we know what's here and we don't know what's next even if we have an idea of
what's next we don't really know what it's going to be like it's always different and there different aspects of
not knowing that that are really useful to hold with an open hand we don't know
what the future holds even whatever we imagine is not
real uh if there's confusion in the mind you know we may not know what's happening within
ourselves or confusion Our Lives we may not know that or there might be a larger not
knowing of not knowing the universe not knowing the whole of life we can't know
all of that but knowing that we don't know allows us to connect with our
experience Suzuki roshi said in relation to having an open mind in The Beginner's
mind there are many possibilities but in the expert's mind there are
few a beginner's mind supports a mind rich with curiosity
an attitude of not knowing helps us be open to others opinions other ways of
seeing things new Solutions new ideas new
experiences confusious said to know what you know and what you don't know that is
true knowledge there's a lot more in the universe that we don't know at any given
moment there's a lot more even in just our minds and body at any given moment
that we don't know there's a lot more about the future
about our life ahead that can't be known every future moment is unknown in
the present only imagined
but knowing the future can also be seen Through The Eyes of the excited Explorer
traveling in a new territory in a foreign country not knowing what will
happen next interested in everything they see it's all new to
them we can have a welcoming attitude to both what we know and what we don't know
wanted or unwanted
the know the knowing of mindfulness develops in US trust and
confidence to meet whatever shows up being interested in what we don't
know allows us to grow being aware of our moments allows
our lives to flow and like a river or lives flow into
the
unknown so tomorrow I'll continue the topic um of knowing and not knowing with
a focus on knowing and clear
comprehension so may the benefits of her practice together Ripple out into the
world may all beings be happy all beings be peaceful and
free so thank you all for your practice thank you