so the um the meditations this week will
be pointing toward various wholesome qualities in our experience and those ones that we have
might have something to do with the attributes of the Buddha that we are exploring this
week so these various wholesome qualities are a sound basis for
beginning our meditation and also for deliberate
reflection in Buddhist practice we're meant to let the good register on our
body heart mind uh the Buddha knew that our heart needs that and that it is
possible to do that without any conceit or UNH wholesomeness coming in now those
things could come in if we build ourselves up in some way
or um grasp onto these qualities or something but it's also possible to do
it in a very simple um easeful uh Happy kind of way and it's not too hard to
land on that with some practice so the Buddha very much encouraged this registering of the
good so today we'll bring in a a brief reflection or recollection of our virtue
Our intention and ability to have wholesome speech and action in the way
that we are in the world and it's always tricky uh as a teacher to use that word
Virtue or ethics or ethical conduct um because it tends to bring up
in people you know all the times that we didn't do that or all the ways in which
we feel like we're not there yet or something and so I want to say very
clearly that the the point of the reflection is not to bring in a comprehensive assessment and make a
chart and have a plan for how to improve it's what I said earlier it's a
registering of the good on the heart and everyone who's here who is interested in
the Dharma and who has come to a a sit and a talk like this has quite a bit of
good manifesting in them so uh we're going to touch into that to the degree
that we can and then we'll um and we'll we'll continue to explore that in the in
the talk later so finding a posture that is
upright and relaxed it's also okay to be lying down
but just have a straight great straightness to the body in some way so that our posture is
dignified sometimes it's said to be Noble that the word doesn't work you can
choose dignity some degree of self-respect
there confidence and bringing the attention
inward closing the eyes if that's appropriate
for you allowing yourself to settle back and
rest down sometimes with the computer we can
lean forward toward it so we can balance our
posture maybe even tuning in to the place where you're sitting or standing
or lying down and finding a place of balance on those contact points so
letting yourself settle into the the place that feels easeful and balanced
where there's not so much effort to be sitting in a upright
posture for me it feels like there's kind of
a like a bowl shape around the position I'm sitting in and I can settle into the
bottom of the bowl where it's easy to to
rest and then maybe on the next out breath softening the
body just letting it settle into this
posture mental we can in a sense accept
the support of what we're sitting on sometimes there's a habit of trying
to hold ourselves up by ourselves like a bootstrap kind of
approach and um it's also nice to just let yourself be
supported by the chair or the cushion or the floor that you're lying
on and ultimately the Earth and feel that
rest I find when I do that there's almost a response in myself of of uplift
it's like oh I know that the base I'm sitting on is stable and so the body has
some lightness and r R is up it's a nice balanced
feeling softening the eyes and the eye sockets and the
jaw shoulders the
belly the legs places where we tend to brace a bit
just inviting inviting some ease it's fine if there's still some
tension or if you have pain in your body
today that's all fine softening the mind
and now we'll invite the skillful use of the thinking mind the mental
function to bring to mind the intention that we
carry of non-harming to whatever degree that
feels present for you I know it's there to some
degree and um we're not racking up all the moments we miss or little areas
where we're not sure about that generally speaking we're walking
through the world not intending for and send into that feeling in the
heart the body even the
mind can you touch that
feeling it may not be easy to describe there may not be words that go
with it but is there kind of a
feeling for me is kind of a gentleness to it and there's also a
Clarity that comes when I connect with that nothing specific but it's like the
the air clears around me a
bit and maybe as you breathe breathing that feeling through
the body if that if that makes sense and can be
done softening the face
feeling any sense of goodness
Beauty Health that goes with this
feeling kind of a
gem and then further uh you can bring to mind some moment
where you manifested this through an act of kindness or a
Restraint of some comment that wouldn't have been
useful no need for a long story but more just the
moment feeling into that moment with that person if there was someone else or
an
animal if nothing truly nothing is coming to mind for you you can imagine
when you witnessed it in someone else and noticed oh that was a nice
thing that they
did feel the energetic effect of that on the world on
you now just taking a a breath and on the out breath letting that reflection
go returning to the present moment sense of your body
sitting or whatever posture and the presence of
mindfulness knowing this moment as it's unfolding tuning into the body and the
mind noticing any after effect of that reflection in the heart or the emotions
or the mood and then connecting in with the
breath simple flow of Life In This Moment
breathing in breathing
out if there's any feeling of ease or [Music]
calm allowing that to settle into the
body and just flowing along that
way letting practice continue to unfold for for a
bit
e
e e
if the mind wanders off into thought or
story concerns or memories which it
will when mindfulness re arises and we
remember that we're meditating we can bring to mind that
that momentum to come back to the present moment and stay with the
practice is also a manifestation of our goodness we've cultivated that
momentum to remember to return and to reorient so we can have some
happiness at this goodness and then continuing on letting the practice
continue to
unfold
e
e e
is there a way in which your appreciation of
and commitment to nonharming are
manifesting at this moment can we feel perhaps a softness in
our connection to the the
body or a way in which when the Mind
brings forth a harsh voice just see that with mindfulness
okay there's that
one or a way in which we deliberately speak to ourself with with
kindness or with
respect even when we're not acting quote unquote out in the
world there's a way to be with experience in a nonharming
way notice which aspects of that are present for you right now and appreciate
them
e
e e
so we've spent some time during this sit connecting in with the feelings
associated with virtue with nonharming with meeting experience in an
ethical kind way
might there be a way in which the understanding or the direct
knowledge that we've gained from that can serve us as we move out into our
lives for the rest of the day or the
evening we carry with us an inner understanding of oh this is what
it feels like to have this clarity about nonharming could I carry that into an
interaction or situation of driving or writing an email or even preparing a
meal reading a book something fairly simple or something
challenging this inner reference point of knowing how virtue feels for us
inside helps us to Be steady in
manifesting that in our speech and our
actions and that will help us to stay
balanced and it helps others they can see it they can feel it even if it's not
conscious for them there's a way in which they
will just have an intuitive sense that oh this this feels good this feels
safe this feels non-confrontational non-c
contentious it doesn't mean every interaction will go well
but it will go as well as it could based on the total conditions if that's what
we're able to [Music] bring so wishing
intending that our care for ourselves and World
Can Be steady in us and brought forth in the coming hours and
days such that others may also find this in themselves and experience the safety
and the ease happiness and peace that
come from from this beautiful heart quality of
virtue may all beings discover happiness peace and
freedom right in the midst of daily life
so the this week we are going through nine qualities that
are used in a practice called the recollection of the Buddha and their
epithets or attributes names or qualities of the Buddha uh that are
meant uh to be touched into with our mental qualities we're actually meant to
kind of reflect on them and turn them over in our mind mind uh with I'm saying three three
purposes to uplift and Inspire to see aspects of them in
ourselves in some degree in ourselves and also to uh touch into practical ways
that we can use them to inform our daily life practice that's the hope as we go
through each of these I um I remembered uh as I was
thinking about this topic that there was a time when I was on Retreat long ago one of my first Retreats that um Gil was
one of the teachers and when he would arrive to to teach he would um bow to
the to the Buddha Rupa that was on the stage and then he would sit down and one
of the other students on the retreat asked during one of the Q&A sessions you
know why do you do that that what are you doing and um Gil said oh it's mostly
gratitude and appreciation um and sometimes a little
reflection here any kind of motion to his heart area and he said it very
humbly you know he wasn't saying I'm like I'm you know I'm the Buddha but he's like mostly gratitude and
appreciation but sometimes a little reflection here and that worth a bow to him so I I
think we're you know we're meant to see some aspects of the Buddha in ourselves so there are these nine or
technically 10 but only nine are used in the practice um attributes I think I
mentioned just briefly yesterday that the poly word for them is the Buddha
gunas um and I don't know if that's such a great sounding word but that's the
poly word the Buddha gunas and yesterday we did AR and S
buo um which were about being fully wholesome and today we'll do two more we
go through two more of them so the first I'd like to talk about
is um the poly is V Char
Sano and what that means is is accomplished in knowledge and
conduct Sano is accomplished via is knowledge like the
opposite of aicha ignorance and charana is um actually it means kind of to walk
around but it's meant to uh refer to our conduct how we are in the way we act and
literally move in the world so it's one thing to have
liberating Insight internally and it's another to fully manifest it and apply
it in the world and the Buddha did that completely such that he was always
consistent his understanding internally and his way of being in the world were
always in sync and always fully liberated let's say so the
knowledge here refers to the liberating understanding of how not to get caught
in any experience so um whatever was happening for the budha you know he
still went around the world and encountered people who asked him questions and he had to deal with food
and you know animals and sleeping and all the things that we do as humans but
all that that came in he had full understanding of how not to get caught up in whatever was happening so there
wasn't reactivity in his mind mind and so as a result he was free in the way
that he could act and speak which made him fully safe fully skillful in how he
was um and we're meant really
to to tune into this in our world to the degree that we can so we're meant to
notice and be inspired by and some texts even say imitate the goodness that we
see happening around us it's good to attune ourselves to that um so Gil Tells
a Story one time when he was living at tasahara of looking out his window and
seeing the head cook walk across the courtyard you know just going to the kitchen to start work for the day and
there was but there was something about the way that he was walking um very present clear on what he was doing not
rushing not caught up or worried oh my gosh I've got to get to the kitchen it was just doing you know just doing that
that was the next thing to be done and Gil as an early practitioner felt very
inspired by this oh it's possible just to be in the world in a straightforward
direct deliberate way unhurried way and you know you may know
practitioners like that or we've seen people doing that on Retreat or have Med
ation Center and you realize oh huh there's something about the way
they're they are that feels wholesome looks looks um worth emulating in some
way there is a suta that says that uh lay people should look to other lay
people who have four qualities virtue
generosity faith and wisdom and to the degree that we can emulate those
qualities and I like the way it says it it's the framing of the language is a
little bit careful such that it's not expected that we know people who are accomplished in all four of those at the
same time or all the time but we may know somebody who is seems to be
particularly accomplished in one of them and you know we think of that oh yeah
you know that person is often consistently generous and we just think of them that way so the encouragement is
well great if you if you admire that in them try to be like that try to do more
of that yourself not that we're going to become them or put them on a pedestal or
anything but we can uh absorb the good qualities around us and bring those
forth in ourselves I once had a friend who was very dedicated to the protection of
animals that was her work and um so she was very attuned to animals always uh
when I was with her I would notice more animals I'd notice the birds chirping I would notice you know the praying mantis
on the plant we were going by um we were walking we were near the ocean one time
and she pointed out all these otter and you know fish and things that I might not have seen um just below the surface
she could say oh look look you can see a little Shadow there it was great and so I realized oh right so we easily attune
to what um comes forth in other people and of course that can happen with the
UN wholesome as well we have to be careful but if we have this care in our heart for what is ethical what is
virtuous what is wholesome we we're more likely to see that and then we can learn to resonate with it so you may find that
as you do this um you start to be able to do things that are different I mean
we can deliberately emulate certain things in a conscious way but often just
being around somebody who has those qualities we will see them come forth in us and we'll realize oh I just I just
did something differently than I normally would have and this can give us a deeper
understanding of what's called ethics you know we usually from
various ways that we've been brought up tend to see it as prescriptive this is a list of things
that you need to do or live up to or try to be rules or precepts of some kind um
but actually there's another side to ethics which is that it is descriptive
also it describes somebody who has a commitment to non-harming they are going
to be those ways and so so we can start to see that it deepens our understanding
of what's meant by virtue maybe it comes from
within so that leads us to the next
quality excuse me um which is sugato
sugato and literally um Sue means good or well it's positive um prefix and Gat
means gone so it means something like well gone which isn't a great literal
translation uh sometimes it's translated as the happy one the Buddha was the happy one um we could say a little bit
more casually that the Buddha has gone happy he's gone happy like some people go crazy but U he's gone happy and um it
has very much to do with well-being you know the well-being that comes from the
wholesomeness from the manifesting of goodness who wouldn't be happy doing
that and um you know in the Buddha it's more deep it's that the the piece of
nibana is always present for him he always has access to that um we don't
always but nonetheless there is a happiness that comes from our connection
to goodness and it's really good to tune into that um there's a
story um where the monks arrive in a Brahman Village intending to go to the
well to get water but the brahmans are not very friendly in this town and they
fill the well with grass and chaff so that the water can't be accessed and the
Buddha asks Ananda his attendant to go fetch in water and Ananda explains the
situation I can't the the well has been filled and the Buddha says well go get me water
from the well and Ananda says again no it it's not possible so the Buddha says
a third time go to the well and get water so Nanda gives up and goes and he
as he approaches the well this is one of those mythical mythical Stories the well
throws up all the grass and chaff and stands filled to the brim with pure clean water and nand is very impressed
by this and gets some water and takes it back to the Buddha and says wow how amazing that this could happen here's
water to drink and the Buddha says again remember this is mythology he says what
use is there for a well if there is water everywhere when Cravings root is
severed what should one go about seeking so this is not literal the
Buddha's body still needs physical water but he's making a Dharma point that it's
Poss possible to find peace anywhere under any conditions freedom is not a
place that we go or that we need to go um it's right here and if we have
this understanding that there's always a wholesome thread that we can follow we have enough wholesomeness in us to meet
any situation it's like there's water everywhere everything can be the path
nothing can block us from having a wholesome moment in sense and what's
interesting about this Su by the way is when the Anand comes back and he says
drink the water he says um drink the water lord drink the water
sugata it's the same word sugat very rarely is the Buddha addressed as sugat
sugat by somebody else so I found that interesting that when I was I actually
was reflecting on this um finding water everywhere quality and this suta came to
mind and when I looked it up it has the word sugat in it so you know what about
for us since we're not always in contact with niana well we can as I implied a
moment ago we can learn to see in a given situation a thread of ease that we can
follow uh a way that we can be with it that is wholesome so this is easy when
conditions are Pleasant and agreeable like listening to a Dhat for example but
maybe they're not maybe we're in a tough conversation with somebody or somebody has just done something that is you know
terrible in our view is there or our mind is misbehaving it's like we're
depressed or angry or so know sad in some way or we've experienced a loss so
the dharm practice says even those moments are part of the path if we can
bring in just the simple calm awareness this is how it is that's enough to make
the moment wholesome to know wow my mind is really caught up right now wow I'm
really distracted wow I just I just missed the moment on that one and but if
we know it we've reestablished wholesomeness there's water
everywhere every moment can be the darkness
so one phrase maybe that you could use in practice that's commonly said in the
sutas is I see you Mara I see you Mara so it's okay when the mind has UNH
wholesomeness in it as long as we see it it's not what we wanted at this moment
but seeing it is good enough I see you Mar so these two qualities that we at
today V Charo and sub relate to the Buddha manifesting his
pure mind um it's true that this list of nine by the way doesn't break up neatly into
sets of two so I'm you know putting on my structure a little bit but I think it works pretty well you can see as the
week goes on so we'll say that today is about manifesting the the Purity and the
goodness which leads to Wholesome happiness which is a happiness way of being and um see if so see if you can
notice today the manifestation of wholesomeness which we do quite often without realizing the moments of
goodness and can you find some happiness in that soak in that if you will to
bring in the water image be happy about it the more soaked we are in our own
goodness and our willingness to be present and do the best we can with our mind
the better we're able to see actually how the mind is working and how the
world is working knowing in seeing things as they are is a fruit of
goodness and happiness that's what we'll talk about more
tomorrow so please come back if that's of interest and otherwise have a
beautiful wholesome day thank you