[Music] so taking our meditation
posture and posture that reflects Our intention to bring attention to our
experience so some uprightness and it also has
ease and this can be a practice in itself how to have some uprightness
without stiffness some uprightness with also
some flexibility or
malleability this week I've been starting us off with bringing attention
to our sitting surface the pressures against the
body I think I'll continue with that this
morning what does it feel like to feel connected grounded to the
foundation upon which you're sitting
doesn't matter whether it's couch chair bed
cushion can we feel connected touching the surface having
the Surface touch us
feeling the pressure against the
body we don't need to use words we're just feeling the
sensations coming back to them when the mind wanders
sitting cross-legged and for me feelings in the bcks as it's sitting
on the zof is predominant
if you're in a chair maybe it's the back of the
legs if you're on a couch maybe it's the
back it leans back if you're lying down maybe it's the back of like near
the
shoulders wherever it is just br moment more resting attention
on the contact with the sitting or lying surface
and then bringing some attention to the front of the
body the face
lips touching maybe some Sensations around
the eyes
the chest can there be a
softness in the chest area sometimes we guard ourselves by
closing the chest in some kind of way
there be an opening a softening
and the
belly can we let the belly
relax however the belly is can it be okay
this meditation period just let it relax
as we pay attention to the front of the body we might naturally be
noticing the experiences as the body
breathes let's rest our attention
there noticing the sensations associated with an in
breath e
notice the sensations associated with out breaths
and those Sensations with the transitions between INB breaths and out
breaths
it's often a place where the Mind likes to
wander
e e
and when the mind wanders as it's apt to
do can it not be a
problem and it just be an indicator it's an opportunity to be begin mindfulness
practice
again
e
e e
when we wake up after being lost in
thought this can be a good place to notice what kind of
stories are we are either the content of the thoughts but more
importantly the stories we say about ourselves as
meditators when we discover that we've been lost in thought
sometimes there can be a oh shoot I'm lost in thought
again I'm never going to get
this they're just thoughts
we don't have to believe
them
e
e e
[Music]
morning welcome welcome today is our the fifth day
Friday in this uh series about stories and um I'd like to
start the this morning the conversation the offering with a
poem and this poem is by Rosemary traumer this beautiful wonderful poet
who lives in Colorado and uh and this uh poem is
entitled sometimes like today we remember again this is Rosemary
traumer and the first the title of the poem leads right into the second line of
the poem and I know sometimes people like what was the name of that poem so I'm going to say it one more time
sometimes like today we
remember sometimes like today we remember that
everyone even the driver in the white Jeep who cut in front of you yes even
the elegant woman in the dairy aisle and
the man who seems lost on the library steps and the child sitting alone on the
bench yes everyone has a
story fears and hopes and something to
learn and someone they love and someone who's hurt them
and someone they long to hold and though their stories are mostly
invisible they're always more complex than whatever we
project and they're every bit as real as our
own the woman in the dairy a Smiles at you and though she is wearing diamonds
in her ears she looks lonely or is it you who is
lonely is it all of us all of us longing for someone to
truly see us and that driver you're cursing don't
we all sometimes feel as if we need to move forward any way we
can and that boy on the bench notice the empty seat beside
him perhaps you could sit there too in the
sun who knows what might happen
next I love this uh poem partly because right it just brings so often the our
some of these like mundane experiences we have getting caught off cut off as
for driving grocery shopping going to the library and just seeing somebody on the
bench as we're driving along or walking along just these uh ordinary experiences
that we see every day and without our even recognizing it
we're like projecting something onto these individuals and we're project maybe not
only just projector what we might not notice is we're projecting a story onto
them like in this poem The Poet is or the
person in this poem is uh projecting a loneliness onto this person who you know
just who knows why they uh the poet thinks that they look lonely they just look
[Music] lonely and I love what's being done here it's like wait like turning this around
I'm projecting that outwards but is it really about
me and this is such an interesting thing for us to consider all the stuff that
we're attributing to other people out there is it really about
us is the way that we're noticing it is uh because there's something about us
that we're trying to disown and instead we're projecting it on others out there or is there something about us that we
uh we're a little bit ashamed of and and we don't want to see it we don't want to
own it so we're projecting it out there who knows why we project things onto
other people out there but what would it be like to notice the stories we're
attributing to others and then just to consider just to have some curiosity is
this about me clearly it's about that person you know but wait is there something here
about me me to this can be such a learning point and
uh I've been practicing with this for some time when I'm thinking to myself oh that person is X Y or or
Z and like why am I uh thinking this and what does it say about me it's been
really helpful for me to consider do I have X Y and Z inside myself and that I
wish I didn't or do I think that I have X Y and Z and that's why it irks me that
this other person has it so maybe that's one thing we could take away from this
poem is that here here um this Rosemary traumer the poet she
writes the woman in the dairy aisle Smiles at you and though she is wearing
diamonds in her ears she looks lonely or is it you who is lonely I love this
she's wearing diamonds in her ear so we're assuming she must have everything she needs she has wealth or she has this
uh certain indicator that suggests there's wealth so she must be happy
right she must have everything she wants and then like but wait maybe she
has uh maybe she's lonely just because some people have
some things that maybe be on the surface you know we're projecting a story oh she has wealth so she must be fine but no
wait she has wealth but she looks lonely this says a lot about
us right these uh stories that uh we're projecting onto other
people and then I'd love that Rosemary traumer she has this uh one
sentence and though their stories are mostly invisible
they're always more complex than whatever we project and they're every
bit as real as our [Music] own there's this way with this example
with this woman in the dairy aisle we're just kind of making her flat like with no depth there's a person who seems to
have wealth and looks like she's lonely like full stop not uh kind of like appreciating
the complexity and the depth maybe the um you know of course I'm just making
this up how could it be anything otherwise but maybe the earrings were given to her at the death of somebody
near to her that was meaningful and she's looking lonely
because now the family is torn apart after this death right then there's something like
completely different than um what we were projecting onto her or maybe she's
wearing these earrings as a they were something that um as she had this major
achievement maybe she just uh um became cancer free after battling cancer for
some time and uh the earrings maybe they're not even really diamonds maybe they're just a something that's sparkly
and from a distance look like they're diamonds but something that she wanted to buy herself as a that she made it
through this really difficult time battling cancer and
you know there's so much stories right that we can give to this but what I appreciate is that this poet here Ros
Mary traumer she's saying they're always more complex than whatever we
project so instead of saying the person in the white Jeep who cut us off like ah this person's a jerk no maybe they
are um in a hurry or maybe they're just not paying attention because uh they're
so confused their boss wanted to call them in at the last moment and say have a very important thing to talk to you
and maybe they're afraid that they're going to get fired so they don't want to be late to this meeting in which that
they that the boss might even think that they're going to get fired right we could just go on and on and on right
just building these stories but there's a way in which when we make them just
two-dimensional kind of like flat and simple it's there's a little bit of a
way in which we're kind of dehumanizing them oh just a jerk bull stop just
somebody who has money that's bull stop or the person uh who was this other one
who seems lost on the library steps somebody maybe a visitor from out of town or maybe somebody whose memory is
declining and um is trying to navigate the confusion of like wait where am I
wow how could we uh not be impacted by that and
then here's what I think is such a key part of this
poem and though those stories are mostly invisible they're always more complex
than whatever we project and they're every bit as real as our
own every bit as real as our [Music]
own there's so many ways to uh understand this one is we tend to think
our stories are real and legitimate everybody else's stories not so much those are just their problems and those
are just stories but mine is true mine is real mine is the most important and
authentic and how things really are for everybody else they're just stories
right now notice how we do this notice how we tend to think that ours are just as you know the most real and everybody
else's are uh just you know some Fabrications that they
have news flash ours are just Fabrications
too right of course they are of course they are they're the way that we're
trying to make meaning of our experiences and they might be really uh meaningful and supportive for our lives
but but some of our stories not so helpful not so
helpful the stories of the world is out to get me the world is
unsafe the I deserve better you know some of these kind of stories they're
based on events that have had but the way that we uh um construct these stories and then project them onto
everything else out there not so helpful for us doesn't let us live our best
lives so other people's stories are every bit as real as our
own which I'm sorry to say they're not so real our stories are just in our head
like the rest of the universe is not uh um I don't know can they're not uh don't
even know about them they're just things that are inside our minds they're
thoughts they're just thoughts I don't want to say this to be dismissive and to say that uh people's
life events and difficulties I don't want to be dismissive of them but I'd like to encourage us to look at what
stories do we have that um aren't so helpful and is there a way that we can
hold them Loosely hold them Loosely I'll read this poem one more
time it's by Rosemary traumer
and its title is sometimes like today we remember so the poem goes like
this sometimes like today we remember that everyone even the driver and the
white Jeep who cut in front of you yes even the elegant woman in the dairy
aisle and the man who seems lost on the library steps and the child sitting
alone on the bench yes everyone has a story fears and hopes and something to
learn and someone they love and someone who's hurt them and someone they long to
hold and though their stories are mostly invisible they're always more complex
than whatever we project and they're every bit as real as our
own the woman in the dairy aisle Smiles at you and though she's wearing diamonds
in her ears she looks lonely or is it you who was
lonely is it all of us all of us longing for someone to truly see
us and a driver you're cursing don't we all sometimes feel as if we need to move
forward any way we can and that boy on the bench notice the empty seat beside
him perhaps you could sit there too in the
sun who knows what might happen next who knows what might happen next
when we put aside the stories and actually engage with life engage with
individuals engage with what's actually happening so thank you all for
practicing with me this week as we talk about stories I'll be here next week as well and I look forward to practicing
with you some more so thank you thank you
thank you thank you it's nice to read your comments
and even if people are not able to see all the comments they're interacting with YouTube and a in a in a manner in
which they don't see the comments sometimes I feel like oh maybe I'm just paying attention to the comments but I want to say thank you to
all of you as well who are not on the comments it's nice it makes a difference
right to practice together
and today is Friday wishing you all a wonderful
Friday for some of you it's the end of the work week I saw a um a little meme recently
that I thought was so funny it said um it's only the first five days after the weekend that uh takes so that are the
hardest I thought oh that's kind of cute so
I look forward to being here next week with you all as well starting on uh Monday
yeah it's lovely lovely to practice
together thank you all for joining me this week on this topic of
stories and I'll see you in a few days