so I'd like to uh offer some thoughts Reflections on the topic of agency it's
a topic that for another program that I'm thinking about these days so and then agency in a spiritual
life agency and particularly for a Dharma life how did these come
together and um and one of the reasons for this is that sometimes in doing Med
meditation practice doing a Buddhist practice spiritual life people don't
feel they have the ability to do it so in that sense uh they feel that there's no
agency and if they sometimes they do feel they have the ability to do it and and maybe they don't think they have
agency but in a way they they do they they can sit down to meditate they can
go in Retreats they can spend time maybe reading spiritual books and it's very
meaningful part of their life so to introduce this topic some
more um in the very important uh uh
teaching in in Insight work in mindfulness practice Buddhist mindfulness practice
is a teaching that uh whatever experience you're directly having in the present moment so you have to really
clear like whatever you're feeling sensing experience in the present can be
um distinguished or divided or distinguished as having three tones
three feeling tones it can be pleasant unpleasant or neither Pleasant nor
unpleasant and now for some people they find it phenomenally fascinating and helpful to just see that recognize that
that's the case because something can be amazingly complex and like some kind of
social drama that you're involved in maybe you know at a holiday party and
boy lot going on here and it's difficult and and social dynamics are a ancient
and difficult and you know and then in the middle of that well Buddha said there's a feeling tone to
experience so what's the feeling tone of this holiday
event it's unpleasant
and suddenly the whole complexity of it has been simplified enough that then you
say oh I know how to be with things that are unpleasant I'll breathe I'll slow
down I'll be mindful of the unpleasant and find find my stability my grounding
again so it's a way of kind of finding yourself stable again or finding some kind of stabil you know some kind of
context for how to be by just kind of seeing this is part of it and I can just
if I don't see it's unpleasant then I'm kind of reacting to it perhaps because sometimes our inner life is reacting to
um you know aaik to our experience it isn't necessarily that we're reacting to
all the things we have opinions about in the room in this holiday event but uh something about just it's
just unpleasant for us how we experience it and that's what we don't like and so
as soon as you say it's unpleasant it changes the orientation how we understand it how we see it and it might
be much more easy to then engage wisely in the event that you're a part of so
this thing I do dividing things into these three feeling tones can be very
helpful but in this uh mindfulness tradition there's a a second distinction
that's made within the category of feeling tones there are two general
areas of feeling tones that we can have one is in relationship to the outer
world and the other is to the inner world and that's kind of my language
it's it's it's uh it not doesn't quite work out in a in all ordinary ways of saying inner
and outer and um but for now you know so outer certainly is that uh you know
there's the feeling tone of um of uh being so
delighted that I won the lottery or delighted that it's um you
know that it's sunny outside or you know happy
that you know that um I was praised wow that was pretty good that I like that
that feels Pleasant or and then we get criticized and that's unpleasant and you know and
that's affects us and changes our mood quite quickly and so things can happen
in the outer world that we take in and somehow register in ways that uh are
Pleasant unpleasant or neither and um and then there's the
inner world and these are things that can Bubble Up from the inside that really in and know themselves have
nothing to do with the outside world um so and this is why uh it's
where the the sharp line doesn't quite work out because uh
if you're spending uh your inner world is waiting for the lottery to be run for
the lottery ticket and you're sure you're going to win and you're already
planning your vacations and your mansions and your all the kind of you
know recreational activities you'll be doing and you're just so delighted and happy um that's you in in in an ordinary
sense that's coming from the inside your thoughts and ideas and all that but it still belongs to the operating system
that's oriented to the world around us we have a different operating system
within that is really deep inside and um and uh I like to call it
the dhic operating system someone else might call it a spiritual operating
system uh someone else might call it the heart you know or some people might call
it the soul some people might call it the inner Spirit you know there's all these kind of languages with something
inside maybe that um that uh belongs to
a different operating system than our desires and aversions to what's happening in the world and what could
happen in the world and what we can get from the world or not get from the world that can exist there independent
of what's happening in the world you go to that H holiday party that's so
complicated and kind of unpleasant on that surface level but you've had this
really good meditation before you went and it's like you know you know you've never been so centered and equanimous
and calm and you're like it's like you're like feeling like in this happy
way kind of like you're inside the car going through the car
wash and going to the holiday party you know like wow wow look at all this
craziness here wow you know but you feel like you're not getting wet you know he
not not touching you because you're have this deeper Wellspring of something another source where you're living
in and then U maybe at this haray party they serve really lot of really good ch
cake and coffee and you have you know a lot of it and pretty soon that deeper spiritual
operating system no longer is operating and it's been taken over by a
whole other kind of way of being and that's now is kind of like completely interacting or buffeted
around by what's happening at the party so you can lose it and uh so but there's a steep ER
operating system and I call it the dharmic operating system and um and that can feel very
wholesome it can feel very uh uh integral to who we really want to be it
can feel like now we're really centered on ourself in a deep peaceful way it's a
place of inner peace inner well-being inner authenticity inner Integrity inner
wholeness that we can we can experience and so um and so the Buddha when he
talked about this kind of dharmic operating system inside it can be pleasant unpleasant or
neither Pleasant or unpleasant so how does that work it can be pleasant if we're really
having the inner the wholesomeness and the goodness and the joy and the happiness of that inner dharmic
operating system flowing through us it can be
unpleasant when it's not and we don't have the agency to do
the practice so this inner operating system is practice dependent initially as we're
kind of finding our way with it in in Buddhism and so it might be the only way
a person has access to it is to meditate
or maybe they can tap into it by going for a long long hike in a nature preserve and be
quiet for a while and then they feel like they touch into something but somehow their life doesn't allow
them to do it either maybe uh they which I knew very
well maybe um they they have young kids at
home and um and I found it hard to meditate when my kids were really babies
and quite young at home and luckily I had to meditate for
work so so that was helpful or maybe uh you're caring for a
family member or parent or someone who's quite sick and elderly and I know I had
my mother live with us for a while when she had uh dementia and that took a lot of time and effort and there wasn't much
time for other things take and um or there's responsibility of work
there's responsibility of all kinds of things that we might have or uh uh there
can be so these worldly responsibilities we have might keep us from touching into
something that's valuable for us and so there's a sense of lack there's something unpleasant there in it in it
in this deeper operating system it feels like a deeper place of of um sometimes
they call it the most extreme versions of it they call it Dark Knight of the Soul uh I had that uh period short
period because I I my whole life when I was young at some certain point was uh
became really important to be able to go on a long Meditation Retreat I'd come to a point in my life kind of a dead end
all the different ways i' gone that was the only way forward that I knew and and
um and the ability to do that was being frustrated and so I kind of like you
know something inside of me really felt this like oh I don't have I can't follow through on what's most important for me
in a sense I had no agency to do what was most important the circumstances around me that got in the
way and um so this inner operating system can be
inspiring and it can be discouraging or depressing or deflating if we can't have
access to it and practice with it and um and there's a a at some point
have people been introduced to Buddhist practice and meditation um there can there can be
inside a uh to use a maybe a kind of Christian term a call to do more of it
in Buddhism we call it an onward leading uh feeling that oh there's a there's a
there's a pull or a slide I'm on and I just want to take that slide and keep
going I there's a doors opening up and I want to keep doing it there's um there's
an inspiration there's a flow that wants to happen here and I have to make room
for that flow to keep grow or is the inner growth that's happening and I want to let that growth happen but uh in
order to do that all I know how to do is to meditate or maybe you do some
meditation and at some point you feel uh wonderful thing moment in meditation is
um is not uh is when you keep doing it and at some point you feel that inner
operating system say uh I really want to do this like there's a there's an inner
call or an inner momentum this is what I want to do
uh you know now you know this is the most valuable this is what's important as opposed to you know I should meditate
I'm supposed to meditate I want to meditate I know it's good for me and I just can't get to it and at some point
something shifts and it's more like you
know I know I know I'm supposed to vacuum the living room
rug but I'm meditating I want to meditate I know I'm supposed
to you know do some things but this is what something this is what the pull is
it's and um you know it's kind of like this may be a very unfortunate example
but you have to forgive me and also to reword it for yourself it's kind of like
you know at some point you have to go pee and it just like this is what has to
happen at some point there going to be that feeling like now I have to meditate
like oh this is what should happen this is the most meaningful thing I can do and so in that regard at some point
people can have a feeling that uh I want to go on Retreat then I had that when I was young
I was meditating for a while for a couple of years and at some point and I think I was meditating daily for about a
year and I decided that I should I wanted to go and Retreat there was a call something about meditation felt
good and right and just felt good to kind of follow through on it and and see what a week on week of meditation would
do in terms of allowing this nice opening that was happening to have a
fuller chance to keep opening so I signed up for a
retreat and um week-long Retreat and then about a couple of weeks before the
retreat started I called The Retreat Center and said something has come up
and I can't go and they said okay we'll just take you off that was easy I
thought what had come up Was Fear so the thing that was interfering
with my desire my inner impulse to kind of follow through and this what was happening on on the inside was myself it
wasn't responsibilities out in the world it was actually I was afraid and so sometimes what interferes
with our agency is not responsibilities and circumstances around us but rather
it's uh what's inside of us and uh so we might be afraid we might
be um afraid of what's going to happen to us we might be afraid it's going to change our life too much we might be
afraid of what we're going to have to face and see if I slow down and really look at myself and that's that you know
so anyway so I chickened out of my first retreat and my karma of that is
[Laughter] that I have to be a Dharma
teacher and uh so um so then at some point um then uh about a probably about
a year later a year later I ended up going on a week long retreat and I
thought that was really great to do it it was really it was a life changing for me to be there but by the time it was
over after the week it was okay that was great but I'm not doing this again for a
while it just I felt you know just required so much energy and intensity or
something of me and um and so then gradually uh over the next months after
six months there came the call something inside of me said okay now I'm ready I
want to do this again and uh I did it and when I finished that week it was
good but no more not for a while and and I would just I continued my daily
meditation practice and then about about six months later the call came again I felt now I'm ready to go and luckily for
me at that point I didn't have the inner inhibition I didn't have the fear anymore and now I was able to follow
through and at some point uh following through meant to go further into the into Buddhism and then further into it
and so I went to live at aen Center I went to live at the aen monastery and and then as I went along
uh this inner call of this of this you know spiritual operating system uh just
kind of became the primary organizing principle for how to live my life it took me to Asia it took me to become a
monk in Burma you know and and eventually brought me here to do this what I'm doing
now as a life and um and so this inner call now
it's easy for people to hear my story and be my my ability to be able to at a
young as a young person to you know just keep answering that call and you know go
to a retreat go to live at a center go to a monastery go to a Asia you know
some people you know can't do that it's inconceivable that they're going to do that um as a young person because maybe
now you're no longer young and um and so now I can't do that that's not available to
me and um but luckily the um it's not necessary to do
that for this practice um uh the primary orientation
that Buddha gave for finding her way with this dharmic operating system the
to find the the pleasure of it the Delight the with satisfaction of it where we can find our
agency is um in being able to recognize what is
wholesome and what is UNH wholesome that's and the wholesome here
means that which really speaks to and awakens or nourishes this inner
operating system the inner goodness the inner sense of wholeness or Integrity or
peace or sense of of the spirit or the soul it's it's not exactly so clear
exactly how to name it or describe it this thing that's deeper except that it's something which is not dependent on
what's happening in the world it's not dependent on the lottery or praise or or
criticism it's not dependent on whether you're living at in a in um endless
holiday party you know that just goes on forever and ever you know it doesn't you know
that you can find your peace in whatever difficulty situation you have it's
difficult to do that it takes time and effort and practice but it is possible
to find the wholesome within you even if the world outside of you is mostly UNH
wholesome and so and so the Buddha said um you
can practice the wholesome if I didn't think you could if
I didn't think you could do it I wouldn't tell you to you can avoid the UNH wholesome if I
didn't think you could you you could do it I wouldn't tell you to avoid the UNH
wholesome so that's what the whole all of what he has to teach is reduced to
that statement that he believes in that we have agency he believes that we have the
capacity to act and do what we need to do for this purpose
and maybe not go off to Asia to practice and be a monastic maybe not do long
Retreats maybe not do any retreat treats maybe you can't even meditate because of the circumstances you have but even so
you can do the wholesome you can avoid the UNH
wholesome you you you once you start getting the hang or some sense that
there is an inner life there is a life of the heart there is a life of the
of in some some Buddhist circles Buddhist uh they wouldn't refer to the heart as being this the Locust for this
they would say it was in the belly uh which is maybe some people find that kind of odd but it's even deeper
than it's even deeper in us than than um than what we call the heart maybe in
Modern English and so this deep Source within and how do we find
it uh we can find it and the sense of agency that it's up to us is
encapsulated in this very very powerful poem uh in the dapada I think it's
powerful that uh this just paraphrase it um it says something like the
Buddha merely points the
way it's up to you to walk it the Buddha just explains what you can
do but he can't do it for you someone can tell you where the
bathroom is but you know what you have to do only
you you know for yourself can can go to it go find it right so um so the the
Buddhas only point the way it's for you to practice it and so the Buddha
believes that we have agency he believes there's a reference point within us that
we can follow it's not about reading books it's not about listening to Dharma talks but
little bit it's okay and U and it's not about um um it's
not and in some ways it's not even about what you
do which is a little odd since that's what the topic of the talk is
but what you but really it's a what you do with this inner life do you pause enough do you pay
attention enough to uh notice what what's the quality of your
inner life what are the characteristics what does it feel like inside or are you too distracted to
notice or is your mind spinning with thoughts and you would say well I'm mostly just agitated and spinning in my
thoughts yes that's might be true but if you identify that as a center of your life
you get one answer but if you can go underneath those spinning thoughts and the churning
and Fantasies and ideas and judgments and commentary and really drop down
deep what do you find there and what we find there is not
always good what we find there is not always Pleasant it's not always so easy
to be there because it can be very uncomfortable able but that is where we can start
finding what is wholesome now that I feel how I am the
quality of my inner life how can I meet that in a Wholesome Way how can I relate
to it how can almost like how can I be my own friend how can I have compassion for
that how can I have care for that and that is beginning to to act
engage in the wholesome life you have to have some
agency when you touch into the difficulty within you have to call on
agency call on your ability to offer something to it that is wholesome that
it's healthy that's good that's compassionate that's caring and as you do that then that's
also Awakening this new operating system this deeper one and so if
you're home caring for people and cannot even meditate perhaps you can
breathe breathe with what you're doing when you're changing the
diapers at 3:00 a.m. in the morning
breathe breathe and harmonize your activity of changing diapers with the
breathing that you're doing and see if the breathing can help you tap into something deeper going on here the
breathing can give you a little pause as you're taking care of a parent who has
dementia can you find some way to find some kind of stability some kind
of spirituality in what you're doing as you
do it you don't have to go off on Street you don't have to go to Asia you can do
it in your ordinary life and um and you and and sooner or
later that's what I had to do and one of the things that happened for me because of the way I my my my
route through all this was that um I didn't really start
learning how to bring it into my daily life until I had children it was a whole
different thing I done all this monastic life but the the challenges of that life
were were so different that I had to kind of now now I have to do it
here so but you don't have to wait you know you can if your life
doesn't allow you to meditate you can still practice you can still find your
way but it requires you to have agency it requires you to make a choice to act
in a c certain way to call upon what's wholesome to recognize what is good in
you and try the best you can to live with it and you probably fail a
lot and um but you know failing is not bad failing
is how we grow it's it's like you know a child
learning to walk the kid falls so many
times the parents don't go oh my God my kid's a failure you know he doesn't know how to
walk and this is the end and I I just I'll
give I'll give up I'll give up on this kid no you say great you have to you
have to f fail a lot of times to finally learn how to walk you to keep falling spiritual life is that way too
you you start again start again start again we have
agency and the question is to use it to use it to let this deeper operating
system begin having a chance to operate in your life and it doesn't require you
to go off runway into but what might happen is that as
this inner operating system begins to come stronger for you it's it's Beautiful Moments will
happen where you feel the onward nature of it you feel that it has you your has
your back you feel that it wants to grow in you it it wants to support you
there's something here that is really here to serve you that is not the usual
self that you identify yourself with there's something marvelous within you
that is not yourself that's here to support you and be with you and help you kind of Find
Your Way onward and grow in this uh with this
inner goodness this dhic um place within that um that we all
have we all can do so agency
people who have no agency it can be very very hard they
feel like they have no capacity to do anything to grow or do anything for
themselves or be safe or take care of their family it's a really hard
thing agent being able to have the freedom to do things and feel like you can make a
difference is crucial to a healthy human life and when we we come into this
practice that we talk about here at IMC that agency is applied to this
inner spiritual or inner operating system that uh we want to bring forth
and use as a reference point and let that have a chance to grow and be the source of how
we live our life and um and we start
over again over and over again every time we fail but we have to
start if you don't exercise your agency it won't
happen so I'll end with a little saying I do that maybe irritate some
people so I say it this way it's a little bit of theater goes into saying this so I
say mindfulness does not work unless you do
[Laughter] it
so so now it's your turn if you have any questions
protests that you would like to offer or testimonials or anything anything you'd
like to do say ask Gail I loved your example about the child learning to walk
very humorous and and a perfect example great thank
you is there mic over in the back I Martha's coming
with thank you um Gil I noticed in your description of your
um Retreat desire that you didn't use the word desire or wanting or tanha or
thirst yet I could imagine somebody with um probably honic addictions having that
same sort of feeling feeling tone that would be underneath that desire sure can
you maybe talk about the difference between those two like I guess it's healthy desire and not healthy desire or
I'm not sure yeah well if um yes I really want to go on a
retreat because I've noticed that the people who really uh get a lot of praise
and spiritual Circle circles are the ones who go and Retreats there something about Retreats and I'm going to go and
not only going to retreat I'm I'm build up a resume of all the Retreats I've done
with all the great teachers and if I can have that resume I'll be a really hot shot guy and it'll be exciting to be you
know praised and delighted and Everywhere I Go people will see me as as if I'm walking on clouds and they'll bow
to me and boy that'll be a great life so that is a lot of T that's a lot of
that's a desire which can bring me a sense of delight when the in the imagination imagination of it but it's
going to be a dead end and it's going to feel like if I really pay attention really mindful I'll
feel the stress of that I'll feel the pressure I feel the unsatisfactory nature of that desire I feel how easy it
is to have it uh to uh be be U pulled around by the nose and a in a certain
kind of way the loss of agency I think that I'm acting on you
know my free will but it's not exactly free will when these addictive compulsive thoughts grab us by the nose
and pull us along so I think you can feel the difference and uh and for me I
think of it you know there's really two different operating systems and you can feel that one has a a sense of if you
really drop in has a feeling of rightness and the other you can see has you can pay
attention you see it's mostly to do with the external world uh it's a desire having to do with what the praise I'll
get as opposed to its satisfying in and of itself so that was my effort my my
attempt to offer you something is that you feel like it answered your
question
great you talked about um something coming up for you the first time you wanted to go to a weekl long retreat and
that that was fear and then you ended up going on a retreat a year later could you talk about how the fear went away oh
you know I I you know I know it was fear but I don't think I was so self-aware
back in those days to know what I was afraid of I just knew I was
afraid and um and I think the reason I was easier uh to to do go
back I think it was no it was more than it was almost two years before I went to the SEC I went back to do it again and
uh by that time I had moved to San Francisco and started uh uh I Liv in
there San Francisco Zen Center in an apartment and I started going and sitting every day with this Z Center and
uh in their meditation Hall and I started doing dayong retweets they did
and so uh 3ars of a year of doing that living in that close to that Zen Center
and in that environment and sitting every day with them I think that prepared me so I I don't think I had I
think I I didn't have fear I might have had some fear I don't remember but I didn't have the uh Fe
fear that um prevented me to go I think because I'd been I had become
familiar with that whole process I'd done enough meditation it just feel felt like a cont cont every day I sat you
know for I think we sat two hours you know two 2 40 minute periods every morning and and so I was I felt like I
it was just like a continuation rather than a big jump
and so for those of you who are interested in going on on a retreat some some people do really well being with beginner's luck they just jump right in
without knowing anything but I think for most people it's good to kind of build
up for it to it and um and so here at IMC we have what we call them we call
them half day Retreats um uh I told that to a monastic once and and he he was
like looked at me like what our Wednesday mornings here we have two
two sittings and we call it a retreat and um but we have these you
know these mornings to do practice here and then we have day longs on Saturday and so kind of to build
up thank you
can oh there hi Gil um so to
part of your talk about having a calling or feeling this calling uh it made me
think about how sometimes um you have more than one calling or things that um
really activate some energy and also maybe think about the fear around
callings and I'm just thinking I'm just wondering if you could speak about uh um
how practice can kind of help you navigate the complexity of life in that
way yeah uh maybe it
can't they uh you have to something something else
will have to operate to help you find your way um I think uh a wise life it's
there's so many callings so many great things to do in life and there's a kind of kind of uh in the kind of modern
world there's so many options so many calls so many things that we we can do and think
we should do in a way that's never happened in human history before and so
uh people want everything um so a wise life especially
a spiritual life or dharmic life uh uh does require making
choices and and they have to figure out what the choices are and occasionally you can do two things or three things
and manag to balance them but uh uh sometimes you have to
choose and sometimes it's very hard to choose um but I I've been up against
that in my own life a number of times and um and sometimes I spent I me I've
spent at least a year uh gwing and struggling over this
question what should I do what path should I take here and um
and every time the gnawing the think i' go for walks I would think I would reflect spend a lot of time thinking and
wondering and it turned out that thinking uh was valuable I believe it
kind of was it was kind of like composting what was something inside so something can grow but the answer never
came from my thinking for me it just something inside suddenly new was always a sudden thing
now I knew what to do what I had to do so that was my way um um sometimes if
you don't know what to do you might just flip a coin and sometimes flipping a coin
whatever the result is you oh oh
no and and you know that that reveals something much more
clearly and the other thing is um I can offer is that uh I don't know what your
you know what the options are for you but sometimes um uh doing one thing
really well opens amazing doors so that uh maybe what the other
thing is can come and join it later or you find a way to do it later it just
right now I'm going to do this really well and create a foundation and and then something else can happen so I feel
least that's happened to me because um I don't know if I do it really well but I give my life to this kind of practice
here uh slowly over the decades all these do doors started opening up um in
society and in the Dharma and doors to do things so things that I wanted to do
when I was young U now I can do them in a whole different way I was for example
I was a Environmental Studies major in college I was I wanted to work with
ecology and and the environmental issues and now as a Buddhist teacher many years
later I started a Buddhist Eco chapy program and I taught uh uh nature Dharma
teacher training to support people to be able to teach this kind of practice in the wilderness and I feel like oh it
came back you know by doing this well enough that I could be train people to be teachers I got to train people to be
teachers in the wilderness so so anyway so just do one thing well and see what
comes out afterwards okay well thank you very much
and we do have the tea today so it' be nice if you just turn towards someone
near you especially if they're new so they feel welcomed and um and say hello introduce yourself and and if you are
new uh you're you belong here now for today so you can welcome the person
you're who says hello to you too so so thank you okay