okay so uh so welcome folks yeah appreciate seeing the
uh the uh chats uh over there I did ask
for suggestions on how to meditate and uh saw gentleness and equinity sounds
reasonable to me so um yeah let's uh let's settle into a a
posture
just being held by the
silence even if there's noise we can be held by the
silence e
we're encouraged to bring a spirit of radical honesty to experience the
Dharma never asks us to pretend
ever it's r iCal honesty and then it's paired with a kind of
radical nonviolence directed towards the entirety of
our sensory
life e
this is our path deeply
honest and deep trust that we do not have to to fight to
heal we do not have to fight to wake
up e
we just kind of cook in our own
juices Moment by
moment experience uh softening us
kneading the dough of our being
just filling your body with
awareness
e
e e
we don't associate force with gentleness but we can make it
such our strength
and courage and our willingness
can be very gentle
the awareness just blend
blessing its
objects with uh Fidelity but uh
gentleness
e e
we're connecting rather than
controlling then controlling the push the pull that's uh not
gentle and gentleness is not self-indulgence
we being invited to stay
to give radical permission to the
ambivalence that runs straight through the center of the
world
we practice staying and being softened by what's
here
e
e e
how uh gently might you want wash a baby's
head kind of make your hands
soft but clear
maybe that's the spirit with which we hold our
experience we just cultivate this
deep Trust
and kind of surrendering to the
flow of pleasant and
unpleasant
for
e
e e
you can only know your mind when you stop trying to do anything with your
mind perhaps that's the ultimate gentle
this
e
e e
clinging is busy
love is
still
e
e e
for
it's good to um good to sit with you
okay so every every now and
then I uh like to ask the question like
Matthew do you know what you're doing like the whole teaching thing whole
Dharma thing do you know what you're do and that sounds like it comes out of
like self-doubt or something uh but I not
really it's just that uh as a teacher the way you talk about dma gets shaped
by forces you cannot clearly see you know just as our lives are
shaped by a million unseen forces one's Dharma is also how one
talks about it is also and so I just asked the
question you know what's happening here and to answer that I have to
consider another question which is something like what's the function of a
Dharma talk what's the function of a Dharma talk and um classically from one kind of
prominent uh suit the the numerical discourses um the the Dharma should only
be taught with the thought of I will speak step by
step not doing great on that front I'll speak explaining cause and
effect the sequence of cause and effect also a little shaky speak out of compassion okay fair
enough speak without um being motivated by material reward okay and speak
without disparaging others pry good nor disparaging
oneself little shaky but the truth is I only mercilessly make fun of myself because
of uh love so so what's the function of a Dharma
talk what's the counsil on how to offer things um is a talk meant to be an
exchange of information or something
else uh in some ways yeah some
ways you know this this path is is about learning the way we learn anything some
of Dharma can be learned in the same way as that we learn anything
else and you know experience just The Human
Condition is so bewildering it's amazing you know that the the Buddha and that
the tradition sort of arrived at like
distinctions that are so valuable you know just just you know carving
nature at at its joints you know and um
it's really powerful just to know okay you know I have maps that there are
three Wellsprings of suffering or seven factors or different aspects of
mindfulness species of love all the all this it's like yeah we got to learn that we got to learn that
and in that respect um Clarity is important you know it's not good to be
massively confused it's not good for me to be massively confusing on that
front but information transfer is it's not the only currency of
exchange and sometimes the Dharma is meant to be bewildering
we we don't we don't really like that usually but it's If you're sort of like
it's weird to say but if you're not being bewildered you might not be
learning a a dear uh Dharma friend said to me um that uh you know she's been
practicing a really long time and she said when she first heard Dharma talk
she really really did not understand much you know she didn't know
she there was not a lot of information transfer but what she could hear and
what made her keep going was that she could hear that the teacher loved
something and knew something that she
didn't and so out of that that what the the she wasn't understanding what was
being said exactly but she could sort of sense the faith that was animating those
words and she just followed that thread and
now she knows everything that they
knew we uh learn more we learn more when
we're not highly intolerant of uncertainty when we can roll with
ambiguity and consciously experience conflicts with our current mental
models you know part of what Spurs our long kind of learning I almost made the
slip of longing you know part of what Spurs that is that um we get hungry to resolve some
of those tensions how is this you know like it's a it's an awkward place to not
have a coherent model and so it mobilizes something in
us that um to try to resolve those tensions in other words it motivates us
to grow to learn sometimes uh a Dharma talk
um is uh is just meant to
inspire Faith or love for the practice just to to Really Gladden the mind to
Gladden the mind and
um yeah sometimes I can be a little I don't know I'm just uh part of me is
like real renunciation and you know just this
kind of eagerness to experience the UNP pleasantness with equinity and yeah it's a good thing for
sure sometimes to be willing to feel bad but uh other times it's
really supremely good to feel
good and
uh sometimes uh Dharma talk functions um
like a kind of soothing bedtime story you know
uh like when I when I used to teach teen Retreats kind of groups of you know 40
kids 15 to 19 part Retreat silent retreat part Camp part group therapy
roughly you know group come together uh and um and those teen
Retreats they would end on January 1st and so the last night was New Year's Eve
and we would stay up late and have a dance party and the kids would get kind of a little wild and we would do a
community share like a no talent show kind of vibe except they were all super
talented and uh and dance the New Year in right and then okay what are you
going to do with 40 rabid children on New Year's Eve you know who are uh hyped
up and uh having vasana romances all over the place you
know and so we just get the kids to uh to lay down in the meditation hall and
then tell you know lights down eyes closed okay it's story time it's Dharma
Story Time and uh that's one function of Dharma
talks uh Dharma talk is a kind of co- meditation where we're offering each
other attention you know it's just that simple I offer my attention you offer yours and
in that kind of currency there's a lot of of care right I know I've quoted my
uh friend and colleague Mar Belzer who said like the willingness to pay attention to another without
agenda very closely related to love to love well is to learn to pay attention
well and in this way we're um we're really both listening to each other you
know listening to each other I'm trying to listen to How the words arise and uh
the ways in which they facilitate kind of sense of connection with
you and that means that I have to stay really close to
experience so it's kind of a tension flowing out flowing
down and just abiding in that is is um
can be nourishing I'm also very conscious that
I don't own my words I don't control the meaning meanings that they make and I
feel often like my words might say too much might say not
enough the literary critics say something like the author's dead you know meaning that you are left to
construct the meanings to find the resonances to discover something about
yourself in these words it's not my job nor my
inclination to tell you what to do or how to to live there are a lot of right
ways to live and so in this sense uh a Dharma talk
really merely clears a space whereby you can find
yourself maybe the the um the most important function of a Dharma talk is
something like just to inhabit a d field together the kind of space between
us becomes Sanctified even here without seeing you
that's enough it's enough and that space becomes filled
with Dharma that space runs through us we become much more
porous you know and when there's a sense of we're
doing something together when the Dharma field to use language from Ain Saito
when that opens up I I really have no idea who I am you
know and uh but this is how we dwell together the
Dharma is a transmission in a sense it's a just a merely
modeling particular mind States Moment by
moment and the teacher is is just inviting the practitioners into their
mind and expressing whatever it may be in that moment love or grief or
emptiness compassion
and I have you know I I take care and how I structure a
talk and um notes that I follow a kind of outline
that I follow um but uh the words are
really only vehicles for expressing a mind
moment and when I'm putting together notes the kind of skeletal outline of a
talk uh that's what I'm attuning to what what
words can we dwell in together and so this is a function of
resonance um I'm only pointing to that which we already
share and so the teacher depends on the sincerity of the practitioner a Dharma
talk there's no Dharma talk without sincerity and uh kind of when I'm on my
own just in that day I I don't I don't feel like I know anything you know like
like wisdom it's like it's like comical you
know uh I don't know anything but then we get together you
show up then there's Dharma and
so uh this is not a kind
of performance but um something like
uh just uh co- meditation some some
vulnerability in the exposure I think I I don't know what it means
exactly but I saw a dayong on taiichi or maybe it was a book I was titled there
are no secrets there are no secrets I love that title you
know uh here too no secrets meaning some of you might
know me better than I know
myself this is a this is
s yeah abiding um together in
Dharma so I offer this for your consideration