so try again here and welcome you again to this
morning and of meditation and as I started to say that
we had um some of the emphasis last couple of days has been on the wise use
of no as a support for meditation and uh today I'd like to
suggest that uh the little phrase that you can use in the meditation either say
it or just keep remembering it as you go along maybe at every exhale you can or
beginning of the inhale somehow just have some reminder to say this and see what effect it has on
you and uh and this is the two words no
comment whatever is happening to you no comment Let It Be
and uh let it be alone and uh uh don't get involved with it don't
be or against it don't accept it don't reject it and
don't participate in it no comment just leave it alone so you might have the most wonderful thought ever and it's
tempting to keep thinking about it no comment you might have an awful thought
and you might be horrified and want to kind of get involved with how terrible it is to have those kinds of thinking
and rather in meditation no comment the meditation is going really
really well no comment it's going really badly if such if if that is
possible no comment just stay present stay with what's
happening uh no need to comment on it just stay aware stay here with what
is so to assume a meditation posture and
to maybe lower your gaze 45 degrees to the
floor letting the eyes relax and be
soft and if it's comfortable for you to close your eyes
and maybe feel whatever tension or agitation there might be in the
eyes no comment but you might want to see if you
can let your eyes rest in their
sockets sometimes I've imagine that I'm looking backwards and down the 45 degree
angle in my head backwards that there's a way of doing
that that helps me settle into the back of the eye socket here relax to the
eyes no need to be looking at
anything including with the Mind's Eye
and as you exhale relax any bodily agitation
or tension you might have in
your maybe feeling it on the inhale and exhaling on releasing relaxing on the
exhale
it might be after feeling and relaxing the body for a few
breaths you might want to readjust your posture a little bit maybe the position of your hands and
your arms like just now I just brought my hands back on my thigh a little
bit that allow allow something to release in the shoulders and even in the
belly and let the inhale continue a little bit longer than
usual just a brief few moments almost like you're enjoying it
and just linger with
it and the same with the exhale linger with the
end so almost on its own it continues for a couple of moments more
not an effort to have longer breaths but just linger and allow
it you're allowing inhale and exhale to be more complete
and to be with breathing for a few for a little while
now with no comment which includes no judgment about
the breathing and if there is
in spite of yourself commentary that arises in the
mind think of it as a almost like another person who's
speaking and your reply is no
comment and return to breathing
to be making comments and judgments stories about what's
happening is to be entrenched is is to
be under the influence of what's
happening to say no
comment is to stay independent stay
free not living under the influence of how things are
going but instead living aware of what's going on
without being under its influence no
comment
e
for
e e
remember no comment including about things that are
not here and now no
stories no reviewing
planning there is a way when you do those things that you lose a certain
Freedom the freedom of not being under the influence of
preoccupations the freedom to be here and now
now
aware
e
for
for e
no comment
and then as an alternative to
comments to consider as we come to the end of this
sitting bringing how you are when you
practice into the world for the benefit of others if you are
calmer to go into the world supporting a calmer world if you are Kinder bringing
kindness into the world if you are
mindful bring mindfulness into the world to see and understand and to
appreciate this world and those you
encounter if you're more free less
preoccupied let that help you listen better to
others may it be that this meditation that we do serves for the welfare and
happiness of the world may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all
beings be peaceful and may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so welcome to this fourth talk on the Buddha before Buddhism and before I
begin again I'd like to make a couple of announcements one is that the scenery
will change tomorrow for this I'm going down to our Retreat Center inight retreat center for a short kind of
teaching that be doing down there today and tomorrow so in tomorrow morning I'll be in the meditation hall or in the
walking Hall of the retreat center and
um so you'll see me there and then the other is that um at this
time of year as many organizations we have an end of the year letter that goes
out and uh fundraising letter and um and
some of you might be interested in Reading what I wrote It's a letter from me about IMC
IRC and uh it's uh the link to it is on the YouTube um under the title of this
this uh YouTube event uh right there uh there's a link and also you'll find a
link to the letter on imc's website on the homepage um under what's new and I
believe irc's website has it also so um you might be interested in seeing yeah
kind of the The Wider bigger picture of uh that we're connected to through this
YouTube um teaching
um so today uh we're talking about the third theme in this ancient text
called that I I kind of uh well my translation of it I call the Buddha before
Buddhism uh and um it is um the First theme was uh not
clinging to any of views the second is uh not clinging to any sensual desires
and the third theme that goes through the book is a description of the
sage one of the primary uh names of someone who's mature in this practice
and what the Buddha is teaching is called a wise person a sage and a monei
sometimes the Buddha is called shakya monei the money the wise person of the shakya clan that he was born into
and um and what stands out to me as I translated this text is that
um the um uh lot of the other later
descriptions of people who mature in this practice uh uh have uh a
descriptive of things which are not directly connected to the practice and the realization itself so for example we
have uh the word arot for people who are fully enlightened but uh I don't know if
the atmology is that important but that comes from the word to be worthy to be
worthy of respect to be worthy of of donations and so it's a word that uh has
it Source in the social relationships we have um people who are not quite fully
enlightened sometimes are called um once returners and non- returners uh once
returner is someone who will die and then be reborn one more time before they become fully enlightened is is what they
say and then the non-r returner is not fully enlightened but will will somehow
finish that work after they die and never be returned as a human again and here so here again it's not
descriptive of the what the person is now but rather has to do with some ideas
and theories of rebirth that are used to describe what they've attained in the
in this book of eights this uh book that I translated um it's a wise person and um
and the descriptive of the person is always in U in uh some some quality they
have here and now so even the wise the Mooney translated a
sage uh what are they wise about and so there's descriptions of what what they're like what they what wisdom
they've attained and interesting the wisdom they attain is always
described they're wise about delusion they're wise about how they get caught
they're wise about clinging and um and uh and so in that
wisdom they can learn how not to cling not to get attached it's not wisdom
about emptiness or wisdom about not self wisdom about some metaphysical or
Supernatural ual thing it's uh really a wisdom about how we suffer and the
causes of suffering and to have wisdom about that is is what makes the person
wise especially if they're wise enough not to get caught and um so it keeps coming back to
the describing the person the practice the realizations the insights what they do that's very naturalistic it's what
very humanistic it's just what what you see what you live in what humans are like in their life directly without any
recourse to metaphysical ideas doctrines that are kind of abstract that uh uh
something you have to take on faith and belief without really know being able to
experience it for yourself maybe or something Supernatural so it's a remarkable kind
of uh humanistic or naturalistic description of the sage of the wise
person so I'm going to read to you some um of these
um
um so here the introduction a significant attribute of
sages is their ability to know and see and sometimes their name their title
is uh the ones who know they do not see the nature of Ultimate Reality or some form of
ultimate Consciousness rather sages know and see the ways in which people
struggle they know what is not harmonious and what is dangerous they know the problems that come from pride
and holding on to opinions they see how people selfishly trash about get a lated
and deflated in their disputes speak with arrogance and cling to teachings by
having insight into these afflictive states a wise person knows not to get
involved with them and to and instead to let go of
them um being at peace and having overcome
Cravings sages become independent knowing the Dharma through their own direct insight and experience
so here so someone asks the Buddha question
the question is seeing what and behaving how is one said to be at
peace uh talk about this Gama when you are asked about the
Supreme people then the Buddha said free of
craving before they die independent of past and
future not making up anything in the present they Revere
nothing it's almost like the whole religiosity of religions that have sacred and reverence and um is kind of
uh put aside for the fa for in favor of just becoming confident and present in a
peaceful way free of anger free of fear not boasting
not worrying they are sages who when speaking teach without
agitation not clinging to the Future nor grieving the past they see seclusion in
the midst of sense contexts and are not Guided by
views they are neither clinging nor deceitful not greedy or stingy neither
impudent nor offensive and don't engage in malicious
speech neither addicted to what's Pleasant nor given to arrogance gentle
and intelligent they are faithless and don't free themselves from
Passion they are faithless it's fascinating uh uh here they are
faithless means they don't require Faith they don't have to believe in something because they know themselves faithless
has a kind of a I think even back in Ancient India I think it was kind of like probably a little shocking to refer
to someone who's a sage as faithless uh because uh I think it just as in English
that means someone who's maybe dishonest or betrays or something but here free of
Faith um
and then this also says they don't free themselves from Passion uh it's also kind of you know shocking to to say but
the reason they say this it's a kind of a pun or a play of words or a kind of a
little Zinger is that um uh they don't have to free themselves from Passion
because they're already free um they are not upset with lack of
possessions they are not hindered by Cravings they don't covet tasty
Foods always equanimous and mindful in this world they don't think of
themselves as equal Superior or inferior they have no swollen
Pride depending on nothing having known the Dharma they are
independent they have no C saving for becoming and non- becoming for living or
dying I say they are at peace they who are concerned with sensual Pleasures they who are not
concerned with sensual Pleasures they have no bonds and have crossed Beyond
attachments not greedy nor selfish sages don't claim to be superior equal or in
inferior to others being free of comparisons they do not compare even
saying we're equal is a comparison taking nothing in the world as their own having no sorrow for what
doesn't exist and uninvolved in doctrines they are called
peaceful so the idea that they're peaceful uh this is what describes them
and only these other ways might seem pretty far out pretty unattainable in some ways um but they are things that're
very humanistic something part or parcel of human life that we can kind of see for ourselves see it in others and we
can see degrees of it in people some people are really greedy really attached some people are less so and so it's part
of the normal world we live in uh and uh even though it seems pretty extraordinary maybe but uh it's free of
you know doctrines and beliefs and Supernatural and great states of meditation and and something much more
direct here and now um so
um so there's a way then in this way to
understand that this can be about you that you can be a sage you can be a
peaceful one uh what you need to understand to be a sage is not endless studies of
Buddhist texts and doctrines and but rather it's to really understand
yourself the Dharma book that we study in Buddhism is in your own heart and your own minds understanding how you get
caught and knowing how not to be caught the place to find the Dharma for
yourself self is when you find a degree of Peace Here and Now peace from all
these things comparisons and conceit and arrogance and and uh fear
and so this is the message of this ancient text this is the perhaps the
earliest message that the Buddha made once he set forth to teach uh what he
had discovered with his Enlightenment so thank you very much and
uh I look forward to seeing you in um from IRC tomorrow