okay again good day um everyone in the
IM amc7 a.m. YouTube
channel I'm happy to spend this week with you I'd like to offer uh just a few uh
orienting words for this week and then we'll begin our
meditation and uh the daret and so this week uh I wanted to share
some Reflections on the teachings of five
Aggregates and many of you and may have heard this before or if if this is new
um you know uh receive this as a new teaching for
you and in particular uh this week uh I'd like to share a sutta that has
very Vivid uh similes that describes this five uh
Aggregates and the PO term is condas and I think Gil uh translates this as five
BOS this days it's a very Central teaching um in the Buddha
Dharma and uh the reason I picked out uh the simile is because
uh the Buddha uh seems to be quite a master at using similes to point at the
felt sense of um this five bundles of
human processes and so simile are very Visual
and uh we can feel potentially we can sense how it is in
us and the Buddha repeatedly um point out that this five Aggregates or five
bundles of human processes are to be seen to be felt
clearly to be known clearly for what they
are and they're often um said to be uh
called as a five cleaning Aggregates or five cleaning bundles
and partly because this is the where the cleaning Force tends to uh gets get uh
involved and so it's important to see this processes uh just as they are and
noticing how the cleaning began to come in and learning to soften and relax the
cleaning and so in this 5 days days uh each morning in the
meditation we will be uh I will try my best to evoke some felt sense of what
the simile are pointing to and then in the daret uh I'll
elaborate some more using words and so you can think of this week
almost as if as if it's kind of a a longer
meditation 45 minutes of meditation if you like uh
where uh the meditation and the dads are very connected and so my
invitation is that uh I will still be raining Bell at
uh the half an hour mark and then transition to offer more words and
elaborations about out at the simile each of the
simes but maybe you can sit in your meditative
bubble and receiving the words almost as a continuation of a
guided meditation maybe the teaching will uh kind of settle into your system
in a different way and so that's an invitation and you don't have to and if
it feels like a you want to switch the mode feel free to do that
um but that's an option I wanted to uh uh point out maybe at the beginning of
this week so with that uh we'll go into the
meditation and today we'll be working with the first uh aggregate or the first
bundle uh which in which the Buddha used a lump of
foam that forms um and the rivers kind of you know he was sitting by the river
ganji and uh he saw like big lumps of
Foams floating on top of the river Ki or some
rivers and he's pointing out that well this is how our material body is
like and look at this carefully um attentively and see how this is for
you and so we'll
[Music]
begin so settling in with the sound of the Bell
maybe taking a few moment imagine as if you're entering
into this sacret Temple within this
body mind and heart
if it's helpful take a few long deep breaths as you
enter
within as you breathe out out settle into the Inner
Space maybe there is a felt sense of coming into the
body coming into the body sitting or lying
down or whatever posture you may may be taking right
now gently softly
inviting mind and heart to
enter with the body and maybe through the
body becoming
present present for this moment
maybe the sense of a Here and
Now becomes more
obvious foregrounded
being available to the present moment
the present moment is available to
us one moment at a time
maybe the sound
silence temperature different parts of the skin
and the breath
a movement of the breath is available to
us are you
available to this life
breath Happening Here and
Now e
a breath may have a sense of flow to
it a
rhythm a felt sense in different parts of the body
expanding
Contracting belly rising and falling
allow this movements of the breath to be received in the
open kind soft field of
knowing e
the movements of the breath May permeate throughout the whole
body en livening
that energetic flow of the breath animates the body
you may notice the dancing
Sensations
vibrations POS
there a Riv of
life we can feel the energetic formations of this
body
what's the felt sense for
you maybe Airy
light a little bubbly
like a lump of foam on the floating lever
dancing Sensations maybe like soap
bubbles a layer of so
bubbles rising and bursting
away
e e
resting in the immediacy of your
experience releasing
ideas conceptual overlays
trusting your own F
sense
e
e e
maybe this
energetic breathing
body has a kind of
Foy feeling to it
the sensations ever shifting and
changing
e
e e
relaxing softening into the sea of the
sensations of this
body the breathing Chi
body maybe a sense
Emeral light
Hollow so the sensations are ever arising and bursting away
now ring bell in a moment but if you like to stay in your
your felt sense meditative
bubble please feel free to do so
[Music]
and so I'd like to offer some
Reflections uh about this five Aggregates in the first one that we
started with the simile of a lump of a foam that's used
to point to this felt sense of of our
material body material form and I like to read uh this part of
the suta for you and since you're kind of in a
meditative space right now maybe this
simil as um offered in the sutta um has a certain flavor for
you this is in Sam nikaya number
22.95 and it says that the Buddha was staying on the bank of the ganes
river as see imagine yourself kind of sitting in the Bank of a River floating
River now maybe he's sitting there kind of
surveying the S right there and he said this to
them practitioners suppose this ganes River
was carrying along a big lump of foam and a person with clear eyes would
see it and count cont template it examine it
carefully and it would appear to them as completely
void Hollow and [Music]
insubstantial for what substance would it be would there be in a lump of
foam in the same way a practitioner
sees and contemplates any kind of a for form at all this is a material form of
his body past future or present internal or
external Co or fine interior or inferior
or Superior near or far examine it carefully and and it
appear appears to them as completely
void Hollow and
insubstantial for what substance would there be in the material
form and so in the immediacy of our experience
um we can feel and sense what is this material
body can I imagine this lump of for Foams floating on uh a floating
River and the Foams are light Hollow you know
they are gathered from different little pieces of a foam and they're formed and
they get dispersed first as they Traverse down
stream and maybe small lumps of foam grow bigger and they kind of gather with
each other and their shapes would shift and change as they float
along and eventually they get dispersed
um and so the image is quite evocative and
Vivid just like this the Buddha is pointing out and this is how our
material form is like kind of the the material form that
we uh embody or inhabit it's like this lump of foam
floating on the River of Life past and future
present course or fine and this keeps on changing um as some of
you may have experienced in the meditation and um you know sometimes I
would imagine like um the little kids and when they were born kind of little
small lump of foam and they grow as um as they they become bigger and
physically and then eventually they kind of St stabilize um but the physical form keeps
on still keeps on changing and eventually um they fall apart right this
is a kind of a material form is like this and that's one way to relate to
this assimile maybe on the larger time span of our lives and there's also a
scientific way of relating to this assimile and we all know that um our bodies in
the cellular level are ever shifting and changing I read recently and said
something like the mass of cells that we lose every year uh through normal cell deaths is
close to the entire body weight for me that was kind of amazing
isn't it they basically kind of a different person physically each
year um and we don't feel like that way you know we feel like it's the same person
somehow um but the Buddha is pointing at look at this
carefully and the way uh they were imagining this P this uh
body are based on a conceptual overlay and we can grasp on it it and
create a sense of a self on it and this is uh what the Buddha was often pointing
to in this um five aggregate teaching or five bundles teaching and this is where
we tends to exert a sense of a self I Me Mine my body my thoughts my
perceptions but in the immediacy of our experience
we ourselves can feel and sense in this embodied
experience uh in our meditation we can drop into this
microscopic level of Sensations and energetic feeling and that's also
present that we can know for ourselves it's like kind of the the
bubbles in the foam that arise and bursts
away I know for me uh I've heard people reporting how in the meditative practice
when we're kind of uh immersing ourselves in in this energetic Chi the
Chinese word chi uh chi body it literally feels like the whole body
melted into a a thick layer of soap
bubbles and this the Buddha is pointing at a very felt sense way of
knowing this kind of um material
body and when we are able to experience uh this for ourselves
directly in our experience we can begin to question the usual ways
of how we relate to this body which usually can be a rather
persistent and a permanent thing and we can misappropriate it
as my body I me mind you know I am
this and there is a real cost to this kind of Mis appropriation or misp
perception because uh there can be Dua arising out of
this this conceptual overlay that we put on top of the Ever Changing shifting
experience obscures the reality the changing nature
and we can end up grasping and clinging to things that are actually not
graspable graspable right how can how can we grasp the empty
foam and yet we do and we do when we're
constructing this conceptual layer that we feel that's more persistent or more
permanent so through the direct experience of our
material form without the stirring of the grasping
Force we have an opportunity to offer our deep
respect and gratitude and care for this material form to be just what it
is so like the forms of uh the lumps of the foam on the flo floating
River it's a wanderous AFF formation wand is a formation of the
nature coming and going offering whatever they may offer
to this world and so we can have a different
relationship to this material form just as it is
it's a wondrous formation that's ever
changing has its own Beauty has its own shifting and changing
sense which is bow to this maybe that actually offers a kind
of a nourishing feeling to our heart and mind offers a kind of a a freeing kind
of a feeling to our heart and mind and rather rather than this kind of graspy
feeling to us and so my invitation uh for the rest
of the today is as you go about the day maybe
um you know feel and sense the foess of this material
body and see what you discover allow kind of a shift to shift
of perceptions to come forth and shift of
relationship uh to this aform to the
form and may that all offer nourishment nourishment care and the freedom to our
heart and mind so thank you everyone and we'll continue
tomorrow uh to expand uh into a second um
aggregate so be well everyone and we'll see you soon