happy Friday I am YouTube Casting from Foggy Santa Cruz where I'm
seeing um palm trees in the fog thank you very much for the sound
feedback it's good to be with you and [Music]
um love to just um see the greetings and
um want to invite you to whether your participating in the chat or sitting
silently to notice notice your
environment notice whatever is out your window if you have a window whatever's around you in your
room take a look around and not just the sound from um my
voice and your computer about any ambient sounds any ambient sounds from outside
your space notice any mood or warmth or joy
in your heart and of satisfaction from getting
up early to meditate Taste of a last sip of coffee
or tea before we settle [Music]
in and noticing too the weight weight of your body on the cushion or bed or
chair this feeling of being rooted settled in the
moment and then when you're ready allowing the eyes to
soften become receptive and turning your gaze inward
can be helpful to take a couple two or three longer slower deeper
breaths into the
belly and releasing releasing the
breath letting go of any tension along with it
and then allowing the breathing to be natural
normal closing the eyes when you're
ready and scan rning through your
body noticing the sensations of air or clothing on [Music]
skin the amount of moisture or dryness in the
air warmth they
cool and then letting the tensions settle more deeply inward in teros
setion to the aliveness of your
body perhaps rolling your shoulders and inviting any excess
tension in the muscles of the neck and shoulders to release
softening the eyes even more softening the
tongue allowing the tip of the tongue to rest on the palet just behind your teeth
top of your
mouth allowing the spine all the way from the base of the skull
through the sacrum to
relax and also be
steady allowing the muscles around your
core to be easeful trusting the bones
allowing the core of your body to be known the viscera
the Motions of breathing in your abdomen belly
diaphragm rib
cage bringing awareness to the hips and buttocks the weight of the body
and allowing awareness to fill the legs and feet from the inside out not the concept
of legs and feet with the internal feeling
pulsing
aliveness vibration or
Stillness being in
contact with the aliveness of your whole body
nothing left out
and then as you are in contact with this whole
body inviting the whole body to relax
and then inviting to may this heart and mind be clear open
soft and the tuning tuning in to mindful
awareness at the Forefront of your attention
staying in contact with each
breath each sound each sensation
simply noticing the beginning
the very Inception of a breath sensation or
sound and allowing it to move through with all the
[Music] variations flowing through perhaps to the swell of the
breath of fullness
and then the release fading away of air or sound or
sensation and contact all the way through to that moment of
Stillness that space between
staying closed allowing experience sensory
experience to flow through unobscured
unimpeded relax allowing and
receiving we'll practice mostly in silence with an occasional prompt
perhaps
e
e e
if you find the Mind lost and
thought the invitation is to graciously
kindly appreciate the return of awareness of the senses of
now and to notice the difference between how it
felt to be lost in thought or be
present is it more pleasant or unpleasant which is more pleasant don't
pleas or is the experience very simple
neither
e
e e
and in the final moments so of our meditation
together the invitation is to cast your gaze
back over these moments of
practice with loving appreciation
kindness including any challenges there possibilities for being Stepping
Stones rather than obstacles with
generosity and [Music] then gathering
in savoring soaking [Music]
steeping in any moments of clarity
wisdom ease peace mindful awareness
kindness letting them nourish your heart and mind
and from that place casting that internal gaze outwards to the others
this life
touches and offering
them sincere wish with the benefits of your
practice touch them as well
May others be happy
safe peaceful and free and may our practice here together
be a cause and condition for greater love
Liberation wisdom and peace in the world
[Music]
thank you for your presence and your
practice
e e
so warm greetings everyone warm greetings and thank you for your
practice I'm curious as um we start to settle into the Dharma talk portion of
this morning together what you noticed in your sensory doorway practice
yesterday what did you notice would love to see in the
chat which senses were most helpful in helping you stay present what
did you notice in the spaces were the difference between
being in the senses and in the mind
a slowing down and opening up of time beautiful yeah I think many people
notice that difference in internal acceleration versus the face of actual
sensory
experience any
others noticing happily
beautiful tuning into what's left of a sense very powerful the
fleeting quality bear attention
peacefulness and quiet with young ones young grandchildren and a sense of
Attunement with other creatures I love reading these These are
great so because of the lag I'm not going to be able to read all of them as I continue but as I promised yesterday I
will read all of them once I'm done talking I love learning about the vibrancy
aliveness [Music] tenderness all of it grounding centering
that you're experiencing and today as I promised
yesterday we're going to play in the deep end of the pool of sensory doorway
practice and I want to start with an image this is an simile from the ancient
teachings the Buddha talks about imagining pure light coming into a window at Sunrise
open clear clean window panes and that if there's no clutter in
the house no furniture it lands on the far wall the Western Wall
unobscured beautiful the Buddha said that when
Faith confidence settledness in the practice are
deep practice of the senses can be like this in other words the five sense
faculties become like those clear window panes for awareness
itself so when Clarity that kind of Simplicity
exists by directly experiencing the senses its possibility for wisdom to
arise it's possible to know the difference between the contact of a sense object
like a bit of light with your retina and to notice that simply with simple
cognizance vanana it's called and that all of this happens a split second
before any evaluation any evaluation of pleasant
unpleasant or new Neal V that we talked about yesterday and that that is often a clue
a way of loosening any hook not what the Buddha called
Fetter sometimes shows up as resistance that might
arise so this is useful because it stops the
mind and heart from cascading to all kinds of other unhelpful stuff and I I'll give you very simple example so
back during covid lockdown shelter in place I was um doing a lot of these
online Retreats at home um my job had a spurl because of the kind of work we were
doing and um I was practicing walking meditation in my living room which looked out over a back porch that was
basically mine but the neighbors who owned to the place um would access it occasionally and I was doing Simple
walking there beautiful morning light striking I noticed this big pile of
clutter my neighbor had left on the porch or so I thought like I noticed the
light striking something and unpleasant come up conditioned by past experience
with the neighbor memory and a split second later the Mind parched
that object dis clutter and then I could see the story
arising about the neighbor and the grumpiness not huge grumpiness but mild
grumpiness but what was so fascinating was I turned and of course my walking
path took me right back that by that window again and oh my goodness what I
thought was quter it was actually something else so I say all of this
because the act of perceiving itself that moment moment of catching
the unpleasant allowed me to have a little more space from the evaluation and the
judgments and to see the process of that very clearly and it also allowed me to see
that our preconceived notions our memories our attitudes our
biases our views can actually shape how we see and even what we see and this is
true for the other senses as well so in this case aversion came up in
other cases it might be desire or resistance or um any host of other sort
of secondary emotions Envy or um Shaden fra
or appreciative Joy whatever's there so in Buddhist teachings often
noticing this link between Pleasant and unpleasant the contact of our senses Pleasant and unpleasant and the next
thing is often taught as simple greed or aversion and that's
absolutely true these are very basic responses but the Buddha also taught
this about emotions so in a way today is emotions
2.1 we talked about them earlier in the week but um the Buddha taught in
particular about the difference between householder or hooked emotions and Dharma emotions emerging
renunciation emotions and they fall into three basic
categories of sadness or grief joy and
equinity and the um sadness or grief I'll just touch on very briefly because
we talked about working with it a little bit earlier this week and that is the difference a a hooked sadness or grief
is sadness or grief that arises in conjunction with what comes up
in the senses by grabbing onto it so the true
sadness for example of loss about hearing or seeing that happens naturally
for many of us as we age so that's not to denigrate it it's
truly there but rather than allowing it to inform and shape and
um become a problem the Buddha talks about not using the second Arrow not
adding on piling on extra extra grief
extra attitude extra judgment with any of it but rather rather than obsessing
over something being with it kind L turning
to the body holding softly with love
awareness and then Shifting the term he uses is by by
relying on this abandon that allowing any sense of grief or
sadness to inspire motivate
our practice to let go of any ways we make things worse any sadness that makes
things worse any um involvement or entangling and rather
shift to a longing or wish or
commitment to letting go to being
free and then relying on that to allow
simple Joys simple Joys to inform us the simple
joys of what's left in my visual capacity I used to have eagle eyes and
now I wear glasses almost all the time unless I'm this close to a screen but appreciating what's there and
there's so much good and nothing wrong with simple joy from being present with
the senses turning to towards that however the Buddha does
recommend not becoming hooked with them and all of us are hooked at some point
all of us are hooked at some point but to notice when that hook arises that fetcher
arises if there's grasping towards something pleasant you
may notice it actually decreases the pleasantness of it and it might decrease the joy too
it's hard to experience Joy fully when hanging on really
tight so this kind of hooked Joy is a greed need for more the planning the
protecting the defending the hanging on and
instead the suggestion is to savor and
allow savoring and allowing means it can be transient and even appreciating the
moment of transient change and then the Buddha
describes that kind of Joy the joy of non-grasping emergent Joy of being
present as Dharma Joy renunciation Joy this can mature into the joy of insight
itself clear seeing the way we surfed the senses
earlier this week the non clinging
itself the presence itself can be a source of
Joy the last emotion he talks about is equinity and how equinity can be
specific to a particular experience a particular sense experience of object of
sound striking the ear for example or it can be more General a
general sense trust in the practice of okayness
equipoise allowing and how while both kinds of equanimity are helpful the second kind
is onward leading portable useful and by relying on that equinity
eventually it's possible to let go of identification and
instead rely on non- craving non-c conceit not having
a need to construct anything at all from sensory experience but rather resting
there and eventually that kind of non- clinging opens a practitioner up to the
most beautiful of spaces absences and joys of all nibana Nirvana freedom
I'll close by saying the Buddha had another simile about window
panes and that is Imagine That Pure Morning Light flowing through the
window but rather than striking a wall on the other side there's no wall and
there's no ground the light just keeps going pure
beautiful radiant and that is one of of his similes for
awakening nothing there to obscure so thank you very much this week
for your wonderful attention your practice your exploration of this with
me and to say that I spoke of the full path of practice very briefly today that
these moments of quiet space Joy Simplicity every single moment is on W
leading like drops in a bowl fill the bowl with water so trust them enjoy them
Savor them and trust your practice thank you it's been a delight
to be with you this week and please be well until we're together again