thank you Martha and thank you everyone hi good morning hi familiar faces new
faces well you're all familiar I mean we're all
cousins distant cousins good morning is the audio is the
sound okay can you hear me all right great fantastic so
before I begin the uh remarks this morning I want to ask you to
um appreciate or join me in
appreciating it always Str strikes me really when I come to IMC since Co what a privilege it is to
come together to be able to come together I don't take it for granted as
I was walking up here this morning just I don't take it for granted here we are
as a community being able to be together in physical form and practicing together
what a gift it is a community
so the triple Jewel really the triple Jewel the third of the triple Jewels is
community is community not to take it for granted so before I begin my remarks I want to
to ask us um to
uh say hi to a few people around us and as if and I'm going to uh link it to the
theme of my Dharma talk which is say hi to a few people around you as
if it's the first and last time you'll ever say hi to these people first and
last time it's so impermanent right and
the invitation is say your name say hi say your name if you want to say where
you came from pronouns if you wish and give him a Goodwill message a little bit
of meta may you be well or may you have a good day or may you just something
like give each person a gift and when they give you a little gift receive it receive it wholeheartedly oh oh may I
have a good day how nice is that this person is wishing me a good day all right let's enjoy each other's commun in
each other's presence the jewel of community all right
go
ah how lovely
what did that feel like you want to throw out a few words hard hard
hard thank you it felt hard at oh did you hard at the beginning was it hard through party oh party I hurt hard I'm
like I wanted to acknowledge everything party oh my God that's sweet party there
this this joyous aspect of Jo yeah yeah beautiful what else warm and fuzzy warm
and fuzzy nice warm and fuzzy exhilarating
exhilarating what else anything else from this side of the
room the these guys had a party on this side how about you guys ener energizing
yeah warm warm alive alive did they hear
that right alive yeah I heard some sweet sweet yeah lovely love who said lovely
thank you lovely yeah touching
touching yeah was there was a brightness and and one person came up to me thank
you because I wasn't participating nobody came to say hi and one person did it was so sweet it was so sweet to
receive their wish for me to have a good day and wishing them and they received it I'm like oh so s sweet to connect
with another human being and really wish them well so it's it's really remarkable
right this power of community this power of community this power of connecting
with people and um the power of what's called weak ties
in Psychology so special since the pandemic as many
people have moved to working remotely working the is the sound still okay kind
of seems variable still comes out awesome thank you as many people might have switched
still to working remotely and working um not not not being as connected as we
were before so there's studies showing that weak ties or these connections
these just saying hello and greetings to the people we don't know um say at the
grocery store our neighbors just these weak ties of course
the strong ties people whom we're connected with or friends family Etc the
the relationship we have with them the connection and spending time is important for
our well-being but also the weak ties just saying hello and and sharing our
Good Will receiving Good Will some studies show that actually that's even more important um for our well-being but
I take well-being as a way of thriving thriving and and um really showing up as
best as we're able to fulfilling our potential as a human being being the best we can be through these weak ties
as well not taking weak ties for granted not coming to IMC and just sitting and
and then going home but actually connecting with a couple of other people in the community and and sharing our
Goodwill our meta and not waiting not really waiting
not not not waiting for any of this so so just to say
um that this part that we just did and my remarks are are EXT
extemp I can't say it they're extemporaneous thank you came came through my first language is farsy so
sometimes the the accent still gets me and all that extemporaneous yes so the
title of my talk actually is don't delay don't DeLay So the theme that I brought
in as if you were speaking to the people around you for the first first and last
time because we really don't know how much time we have we assume we're going
to have a lot of time this keeps moving so I'm going to adjust it until it gets
right it's all good hold on I there I
think I just have to twist the top part oh that's much better now it's standing in place ah there see great all he had
to do I know that's right all he had to do is wish me well and give his Good Will and may this stay in place and
things just happened
so so it might for some people it might seem perhaps like a morbid recollection
but it's actually it's um it's not morbid at all and it's it's it helps us
align with our life with our true value values with how we want to show up in
this limited time that we each have um as human beings in in this life In This
Very life and it's it's a brief flash of
lightening so this this reflection um there's a
reflection that I loved when um I was a beginning practitioner and I remember
hearing it in the Dharma talk and it really stopped me in my tracks and I um wrote it in on a piece
of paper and I had it you know in the mirror in the bathroom mirror and the reflection was and it it's it's been
alive for me for years and years for decades actually this
reflection and the reflection was the days and nights and this is from autta
the Buddha said reflect thus then the days and nights are relentlessly passing
how well am I spending my time the days and nights are relentlessly
passing how well am I spending my time I want to invite you to drop that
reflection in for yourself the days and nights are relentlessly
passing how well am I spending my time
am I living according to my values am I delaying some things that I
know I need to let go of or or do in
life especially gratitude and forgiveness Etc I'll say a little more about
those how well am I spending my time the days and nights are relentlessly passing
we're aging no matter how old you are sitting here in this moment in this room
you are aging I am aging we're all aging conditions are shifting and
changing and how well am I spending my time how well in some ways hopefully
well and maybe in some ways it could be better anyone getting sucked into social
media anyone anyone right or any anything else that um you know you're
about to do something and you actually were joking with with some friends recently and uh and um and one of them
was saying you know I I pick up my phone to you know look up a word or synonym or
something and then there is a notification then I'm gone I'm gone and 30 minutes later I'm like oh what was I
doing and another one saying yeah me too you know I write this um I create this
document and you know uh offline and and and then I come to email and send it and then are all these other emails that I
respond and I forget to send the document and sometimes it never gets sent so anybody else and then I have a
stories like this too I'm about to do something that but something else comes in and it's the end of it and I still haven't done that thing that I wanted to
do so anyone else yeah this I This Is Us in the information age if you're not
raising your hand I'm I'm wondering um but this is us
so so bringing so there's so many dimensions to this talk and I probably
won't get through all the various points that I want to make which is fine it's okay to go off script and also I um
appre I'm going to leave time at the end for questions and reflection so that this becomes more of an
interactive exploration so so back to um don't delay
really appreciating bringing to the Forefront of our Minds that life is
impermanent it is fragile it is it is an aspect of being alive it just is that we
don't know how much time we have we might have less time than we realize um and in fact in the
maranasati angut nikaya 619
um the the Buddha says that that I will die and I'm not exempt from dying and
it's impossible for for um someone with a body not to die and one must reflect
on this that life is uncertain and death is uncertain I never know how much time I have um and that that brings a sense
of spiritual urgency that brings a sense of spiritual urgency how am I spending my limited
time and the Buddha also said as if a person
person's head were on fire so one would
act with such spiritual urgency and one should Le live
heedfully um when the fires of birth aging and death burn so this sense of
urgency to have the sense of urgency not not delaying like oh yeah I'll have time
I'll have time because we don't know if we're going to have
time so if with with that if we don't know how
much time we have and and also to say maybe I'll bring this in now instead of later there's also a balance for us to
strike it's so important to strike this balance of our hair being on fire this
sense of spiritual urgency in the way we we live our lives both for the sake of
ourselves for the sake of those whose lives we connect with our family friends
loved ones and all beings everywhere to balance that sense of
urgency with the sense of of peace and calm and equinity right because we don't
want to get so overwhelmed ah what do I do is a sense of anxiety that can
completely be unhelpful and some of you might wonder well wait I'm doing this
meditation to become calmer and more still and and um
yes absolutely so what is what is that that balance for us to um to keep in
mind so so really reconciling this Paradox of
urgency with with peace ease and equinity so how do we go about thinking
about this well if you don't have a sense of if you
don't cultivate a sense of peace and ease and
equinity Stillness of the Mind Stillness of the
heart then there isn't there won't be the
wisdom to make wise decisions about what to do or what to let go
of so that sense of peace is needed that sense of stability in the
heart and mind are needed to have access to one's values to know how to live and
how to again how to what to let go of if they're UNH wholesome habits to let go
of or wholesome actions that need to be cultivated there needs to be that access
to wisdom and what gives us access to that wisdom is cultivating stability is
cultivating peace and peace and ease and stability don't necessarily mean
slow that's another mistake that some people make that you have to some
sometimes they are they go together sometimes you have to slow down physically in order for the mind to slow
down but not necessarily the mind and the body and the Heart can be at peace
and Stillness and yet there could be spe in the actions but there's a sense of Stillness
within and there are many practices as we were practicing together
this morning meditative practices to bring the sense of stability and
connection to to to peace to um a sense
of yeah the the peace within one of the practice is that we
practice U mindfulness of the breath for example how many of you are practicing
mindfulness of the breath this morning as we're sitting silently together most of you many of you um how many were
practicing mindfulness of the body this body sense yeah great this is wonderful
who is act practicing mindfulness of sounds a few people not this is really
fun anybody practicing meta anyone practicing meta this morning oh this is
great this is a kind of yeah bringing it in yes so these are the practi and many
other practices anybody practicing mindfulness of death this morning yes couple of people yeah awesome yeah yeah
yeah sweet again they're many practices to bring us to our I left many many pra
I mean for example the Buddha teaches just you know there the practice
of vasana insight and then there's the practice of U Insight or vasana or
mindfulness we tend to call one basket of practices that we do then there's another basket of practices which is
concentration practices or samadi or shamata practices which they go together
but say for the basket of shamata samadi practices there are 40 different objects
that the Buddha teach us so there many many different practices that's what I mean so many different practices
mindfulness being a primary practice that we do mindfulness of the body mindfulness of of the breath mindful
that but the breath is part of the body also it's part of the Sati patana
mindfulness of a mindfulness of the foundations of mindfulness mindfulness of Mind mindfulness of uh various
mindfulness of death cultivating meta Etc so so many different pra and and the
bu taught different practices for different people so and it's important
to stick to one practice for for a while instead of shopping oh wow she
said there 40 different practices for shamata like oh my God I'm going to go shopping and and look them all up and
stick to one for a while stick to one for a while so that you can cultivate a
sense of stability remember stability and peace
so that you can cultivate a sense of stability and peace so there can be a
connection to values there can be a connection to why am I doing this what's
my goal what are my values how do I want to live how do I want to have lived this
this short life of mine I want to touch into a couple of
other things one is not delaying because I'm mentioned earlier not
delaying um abandoning what's UNH wholesome and
not delaying cultivating what is wholesome those the Buddha always talks
about those two
aspects
so the um abandoning of what is UNH wholesome what is not helpful what um
gets in the way and the primary I would say that the
primary um Foundation of our practice is ethical
conduct so abandoning any actions that are not ethically sound are not aligned
are not um they do not lead to What's called the Bliss of
blamelessness it's such a beautiful phrase so so the Buddha teaches that
when we live according to ethical conduct and and there are five basic
precepts in in Buddhism there many more for the monks and nuns but five basic
precepts not killing not killing another living being
not stealing or actually the Buddha sets the bar even higher not taking what has not been
offered which is even different which is even higher bar right you see the difference still not taking what has not
been offered um someone has to specifically offer something for us to take it even if um I'll just leave it at
that so not killing not stealing not engaging in in sexual misconduct in ways
that hurts ourselves and hurts others and again that's a um Buddhism in the
teachings is not a Puritan um um philosophy it's just a way
that that considering what might be harmful to us and to others um with the
use of our Sexual Energy and that might be different for different people different conditions but basically bringing our own wisdom to abstain from
from sexual harm to ourselves and others the fourth one abstaining from
speech that is harmful speech that is untrue lying for
example again there's research in how lying erodes are um trust in ourselves
and our ethical Compass our ethical Compass starts to
get messed up if we lie if we lie more and more then it becomes slippery slope
really interesting research showing how people are put in situations where oh they just said you know told a little
white lie and then they were they're measured in fmri so at first when they
told that little lie their their um brains would kind of feel uncomfortable
you know they would show up you know there would be lighting up in areas that would would indicate lack of comfort
like oh that awkward that didn't feel right that I said that little lie and then they as they contined to be in
situations and and they did say more and bigger and bigger lies than the um the
activation of brain areas that uh showed discomfort silenced it went down which
is pretty wild right so if we continue to to um say
untruths to lie our ethical Compass which is our bodies really telling us
ooh don't do that we shut that off that's scary to me right and in other
areas too stealing Etc other ethical um um transgressions we we we
mune our um our ethical Compass does that make sense is is that clear enough
if it's not giving me a a no okay it's clear enough that is quite profound so
and that is oh and then just to go through all all the five so the fourth one abstaining from unwise UNH wholesome
speech including uh speech that is untrue it's that's harsh um it's ill
meaning it's it's um not time so um uh basically unwise speech and then the
fifth one and there many more teachings on on every one of these and the fifth one being
abstaining uh from intoxicating the mind because in in Buddhism again it's not um
supposed to be uh puritanical but in in this philosophy Clarity of mind is so
important Clarity of mind is so important that we don't want to intoxicate the mind so that it's not
clear it doesn't have that clarity so the very first um you abandoning if
there's any way that ethically we're not aligned ethically we're undermining
ourselves according to these five ethical um precepts to abandon those to
really make a decision do not delay not delaying don't delay abandoning any of
the um any way that we may not be living according to to ethical
integrity and then not delaying any expressions of
Love gratitude forgiveness the the ways that we can actually um you
know again part of it is the the interactions with others and part of it
is how we want to show up as this person who is me not delaying
um expressions of gratitude for example um the Buddha
says this is said gratitude practitioners is rare in this world one
who is grateful is and thankful is a rare I say is that us is he talking
about us how grateful are we for all the blessings that we have in our lives do
we focus on on what's lacking what's not there what what the what the
problems are instead of balancing it with gratitude for
everything that is there and the list is infinite
and yes that is us because as humans we tend to focus on what's
negative we just tend to that's our evolutionary gift because the the
ancestors who survive D and passed down their genes were the ones who were tuned
into the negative stimulus there were Nega they were tuned to the to the
woolly mammoth they were tuned into the Tigers they were tuned into all the negative stimuli in the environment
those are the ones who survived and passed down their genes those who were tuned to positive stimulus oh the
berries the birds the nice things they didn't make it they were eaten by the
Tigers they didn't pass down their genes so whose genes do we have people
cousins we we're tuned for everything that is NE it's not our fault it's not
our fault and yet it's good to know when you know what is h What You're Made Of
then you can do things then you can be be aware
of ways to um to counter it so when the Mind goes and becomes a velcro like
connects with what is wrong this is wrong I'm wrong I'm not doing this right they're not doing this right not to say
we don't want to to make changes in the world of course um there is wholesome
action of course but do we want to balance our heart State and mind state
with a sense of balance about ourselves about other people so balancing with gratitude and actually I
I found I don't know about you but um when when I go through tough times
challenging times for me gratitude is my lifeline is what brings me back to
balance when things are challenging then I start to think okay in this moment right here as I'm sitting or lying or
Walking In This Moment okay what am I great like I bring it to not he here and
there but right here right now what am I grateful for
and often something very simple comes up well I'm grateful for this air I'm
breathing it's clean clean enough air right it's not the orange Sky day in
California it's clean air like wow I'm grateful for this breath and then it starts there and then another thing
comes up okay I'm oh I'm grateful for for my feet that I'm walking or sitting
or the sensations that wow I I can feel I'm grateful for that and then it just
becomes a snowball it becomes a wholesome snowball that then my mind
becomes more balanced through gratitude that is my lifeline what is your
lifeline what is your lifeline what are the ways that you you practice
wholesome um actions that you bring your mind into
balance is it through gratitude is it through love giving love giving meta to others
that's another Lifeline receiving meta from
others know other there people who care about me or I care about other
people so a lot more to say but um you
know maybe I'm going to pause here and leave some time leave yeah for some time
for questions Reflections um anything you want to share there's again there's so I've covered quite a wide uh sorry
all good you yeah that's our transition thank you Martha that's her transition
to to Reflections so any questions what anything you want to share what what
what connects for you or or what doesn't connect for you what what brings up but
but great your hand shot up and say your name if you like to
hi my name is Paula uh thank you so much for your talk today um when you first
started out um with the phrase don't delay
um I had panic and anxiety um until you got to the point of
let's work on our equinity and those types of things so um I've got a lot CH
changes in my personal and business lives right now and I was noticing this
week as some deadlines are coming up that my mind because I've been attuned
to be such a doer my mind was spinning through the days in terms of what else
can I do what else can I do I can do more I can get more done yeah and I had
to remind myself that doing isn't n the
ultimate goal but it's hard and I'm wonder if you can talk about ways you
must recognize it some in yourself that you were saying we need to balance
absolutely and thanks for bringing that in absolutely especially in our lives
right now in Silicon Valley but where we are physically and and hello whoever is joining us online from different places
in the world um in in this time in this Zeitgeist there is so much priority
given to doing doing doing accomplishing accomplishing to-do list and that is how
we are um we yeah we oriented
so so we need to carve time to to be to
absolutely be and cultivate that stability that St I'm assuming that stability is there which is a big
assumption but or we're making time for that stability because we are here meditating together this and and
cultivating that sense of stability and then not delaying and and delaying
wholesome action delaying letting go of but that that stability needs to be there otherwise we're going to run
around like a headless chicken and right and and the Headless Chicken
state is not a a productive state in any way it's not productive morally it's not
because we make decisions that maybe we regret later we're not our best it just it's uh maybe we get a lot done but
maybe we would have been better off getting less done but doing it more wholeheartedly and more from from a
balanced and loving place so when I say don't delay it's it's
not yeah it's it's also don't delay um yeah maybe expanding that in
our mind or in your mind that don't delay um establishing a calm and
equanimous place inside don't delay that because that's what this means too right
because that's what the Buddha is teaching otherwise we wouldn't be sitting here this morning meditating in
silence or seemingly doing nothing right so don't delay doing that don't delay
making times and space for deep reflection for still for calm
for the goodness for touching into into the goodness yeah thanks for bringing that
up
please thank you very much you know as as I was sitting here before your Dharma talk um a lot of the same themes were
sort sort of resonating and uh so so we have um an elderly dog that has stopped
going upstairs so he sits downstairs and he's kind of Grouchy and he barks for
his food and you know it takes some patience to deal with our elderly LG but you know everything with a body and so I
said you know well he won't be here we don't know how long he's got he's 10 and he's been there with us and he's been
there with our kids and so you know we're kind of going through that and uh made me think about my dad who's about
in human year is about the same age as my dog and my dad barks and I go to dinner with him and you know I sit there
and you know Dad you know but you know what I'm not going to have my dad forever right and so and then I got a
son who's in college and he calls and he barks you know and he's a dad I got this and but he calls and so I'm not going to
be there forever right so those themes kept resonating for me and and your point about compassion was really core
so he just you know breathe in breathe out and and let that kind of compassion fill me with time to be there with them
because we're not going to have them forever so you know so thank you very much it really resonated with me this
morning yeah thank you so much thanks for your Reflections yeah beautiful and I I so appreciated you sharing both um
this sense of compassion and care for these loved ones uh brought in with a
sense of gratitude that sense of urgency brings in s I'm not going to they're not
going to be my life I'm not going to have the privilege of the of them barking at me one day I'm going to miss
this part so it brings this sense of gratitude oh okay it's and it lights it
up in a different way so beautiful thank you for sharing that with with all of us yeah thank you for this talk it's a
wonderful reminder to me and I need reminders from time to time I find
periods in my life where I feel more um uh stagnant if you will uh or resistant
to change and maybe that's uh protection or something like that because
continuous change is difficult uh but this is a great opportunity in our life
to um evolve and grow and
um uh so you know letting go of the things that are are you know maybe in
our way and then uh drawing our way towards things that
are helpful um yeah it's a great reminder thank you yeah thank you thank
you yeah and and shift and change the only thing that is constant in
life is change the only thing just change all the time our bodies Our
circumstances or relationships Everything Changes all the time
um yeah don't delay don't delay and again
the don't delay for each person might be different don't delay letting go of what's UNH wholesome or what doesn't
serve any longer what's not helpful or don't delay cultivating a peaceful heart
uh equinity don't delay cultivating more love for yourself for others don't delay
more compassion don't delay what dot dot dot actually that's the title of the talk so you fill in the dot dot dot for
you what is your dot dot dot don't delay dot dot dot thank you other
Reflections I I was actually um thinking about uh along the lines of don't delay
that how do I want to choose how do I want to spend my last few years or
months who knows what as I um have the great gift of old age um and what came
to mind was this heroic um hearing reading years ago about this uh elderly
people in Japan around Fukushima and how they said to the young people we're old we've had our life
we'll go and clean up that nuclear plant
and uh I thought well I don't think I'm up for anything that heroic but I I I'm
inspired yeah thank you so much for your talk thank you thank you Martha yeah
yeah Gifts of service don't delay service however that might look for you
in your life don't delay service to others because when we serve
others the more we give the more we receive so it that that particular story you
mentioned it seems incredibly sounds incredibly heroic and yet Perhaps the
gift that they felt it didn't seem like a great it is a sacrifice from the
outside but for them maybe it's a big gift of ah I'm giving to these future Generations such a gift of Life of My
Flesh and body it's yeah don't don't delay underestimating your own Humanity
right and en joyful yeah that's right exactly it's not a grim Duty yeah it's not a grim
Duty so we have come to the end of our time
together time flies right so you have not delay
cultivating wholesome PL planting wholesome seeds by coming here this
morning practicing together in community saying hi to someone else giving them your Goodwill receiveing their Goodwill
and then sitting with the reflections whatever they might have come up might have brought up for you so may we not
delay dot dot dot thank you all for your practice may you be well may you be
happy may all beings everywhere be free including
ourselves thanks everyone be well m