so good morning friends let's go ahead and uh start
meditating together so settling
in and finding a a good posture for
meditation if you're comfortable doing so please close your eyes
eyes and just sensing the body from the
inside letting go of ideas
about your computer or the day before
you coffee whatever has been on on your mind as you're moving toward this
session and allowing the attention to become
simpler just oriented toward sitting in this
posture supported by the chair or the cushion or the
bed wherever you're
sitting
maybe taking a couple of long slow deep breaths and on the out breath softening
the
body feeling into the stability of where you're
sitting your weight [Music]
resting down onto the chair or cushion or
bed the
floor allowing yourself to tune into the kind of basic
physicality that is ever present but we don't always put our attention on
it and it may be that the physical being is not so comfortable at this moment
that's always the possibility in the
body but just allowing that to be as it is [Music]
also gently inviting softening through the face the
eyes down through the shoulders and the arms
and
hands softening down through the
[Music]
Torso the muscles of the upper back diaphragm
area belly and the low back often as we soften the muscles that
we habitually hold rigid there's a new sense of support or
[Music] straightening almost from the inside
out that we
liberate through allowing ourselves to be at
ease releasing the hip joints
down through the legs all the way to the
feet tuning into the Natural Balance of the
body trusting it to find its alignment in
gravity
when wheel is well balanced the axle right in the middle of
the wheel and the wheel is round if you spin it it's said to spin
true this is one of the meanings of [Music]
true can your body sit in a posture that is
true aligned balanced
simple however that looks for your
body and bringing attention also to the
mind the inner
life perhaps looking upon that with just natural inner
gaze like we might just see what's there are there emotions
present
thoughts intentions over other kinds of
feelings
looking upon these with ease and
softness inviting the mind also to relax
in the simple awareness of
mindfulness as with the body the Mind may not be entirely comfortable at this
moment entirely Pleasant or [Music]
easeful and similarly we can let that be as it
is
just
knowing
if you're familiar with the noting
practice You may wish to do that for a few
minutes this is a way of just gently
naming what is arising in the
mind and it changes you know we may have a moment
of sadness but then we
move to
hearing and then a sense of softness as we
exhale and
ease and then a
thought so we say thinking gently in the mind
or if a word is too much we can just have kind of an
impression clearly knowing each
experience through the impression it makes in the mind like feet make
impressions in the
sand
this kind of simple noting is
a way of being clear about what's happening in experience rather than someone
disconnected but perhaps just as
importantly it's a way of being honest about what's
happening the aim of noting is to really know what
what is
arising and if it's anger then we've done the task when
we've labeled it to
anger and then we move on it's not oh
anger oh I shouldn't have that how can I get rid of that that's
one of the
hindrances instead it's just a note that was anger and then the next
moment maybe something
else it's okay if what arises is something that you would call
a hindrance or an UNH wholesome mind
state if you've noted it it wasn't taking over your
mind wonder if we were really open and honest just labeling
everything as it comes with no concern that it says
anything about you or your
practice
so if you'd like resting in that space of deep openness and
honesty there's a lot of care in that
e
e if the mind has drifted away and moved
into [Music] thinking then we note
thinking the mind is back to the
present back to sensing things as they
are if there was any concern about that or judgment then it's just
judging it's just what the mind is [Music]
doing
just as we said about the well balanced
wheel that it will spin [Music]
true there's a way that when the mind is just willing to be simple and
present then the mind mind has come into
true it's just its so knowing
itself and there can even be a visceral sense of
relief when we really [Music] know what is happening
honestly it's such a relief allowing that ease in the
mind of being
true
e
and now gently bringing in again the awareness
of the body sitting or [Music]
lying posture that you're [Music]
in maybe feeling the breath coming in going [Music]
out
sensing if there is some sense of alignment or
integration is there a way that the Deep honesty with the Mind
informs some connection with the
body feeling of
Hess you might it be that this Foundation of really being
clear about what's happening moment to [Music] moment feels like a
reliable foundation for navigating
life starting from this place of really
knowing without our projections ideas
judgments that might be that we would then choose not to say something or
choose a particular action but when we do so from
this deeply truthful Foundation it's much more likely to be
beneficial this way of perceiving being open sprad
from us to others we can include other people also really seeing
them as they
are really seeing them freshly not through the filter of
yesterday or last
year and there we can choose how to respond which parts of
reality to speak
to but always starting from this place of
tress and tress within our own being it's a very beautiful offering for
the world and it's
done just internally privately quietly what others
can feel it without us having to
say so considering what you've learned from this basis of deep
honesty for being with others
[Music]
for
so we're talking this week about four
foundational practices that are very simple to name and pretty simple to start doing in some
way and then they can keep unfolding in our practice for a long time eventually
going quite deep so I like things like this where they're immediately accessible but then
if we really follow them for a long time they are onward leading and keep opening
up more and more so we're talking about them first as practices and then uh near near the end
of this week we'll reframe them as beautiful benefits in our
life so these are these four are to not neglect
wisdom to preserve truth to cultivate
relinquishment and to train for peace so yesterday we talked about ways
to keep connected to whatever wisdom we've developed and we all have some
because it starts right away when we begin practicing sometimes the bigger issue is
that we don't remember to be in touch with what wisdom we have it's less about
I don't have enough wisdom yet and more about I'm not accessing what I do
have paraphrasing Sharon saltzburg mindfulness is easy but remembering to
be mindful is difficult but when we do
remember to be aware of just this and to bring in a wise perspective
we have more clarity in navigating our life whether on or off the
cushion So today we're moving on to preserving
truth preserving truth so if someone for example the Buddha
said to you preserve the truth what would you do with that how
would you do that so when I consider such a phrase it
strikes me that the verb is to preserve so what is true is therefore
something that could be preserved or maybe not and and when we don't what is
that what does it mean to not preserve the truth is it mean kind of allowing it
to Decay or covering it over or distorting
it but instead we can practice with preserving it
I visited a state park a few days ago where ecosystems and certain species of
trees are being preserved and I've also visited Wildlife
preserves where animals are protected so I see preservation as
something beautiful that is done out of a sense of care out of a sense of deeply
valuing what is being preserved along with the accurate
understanding that it could be lost if action isn't
taken so do you see truth in that way is it something that you deeply value to
the point of wanting to actively preserve
it maybe we need to look at this word uh
truth sometimes that can be a little bit of a sticky word the poly
word is simply Sacha which is always translated as truth and it it's pretty
much a direct translation and in pully just like in English um there are multiple shades of
meaning of the word satcha the word truth I can say with confidence that the
Buddha does not appear to be advocating a fundamentalist kind of Truth an
absolutist truth that is rigid or dogmatic I think it would be very hard
to read the sutas and get that impression so instead there's an
understanding that there are different layers or levels or aspects of what is
true and part of the art of Dharma practice is to align ourselves
appropriately with some kind of Truth if we're out of
alignment something is off something is not well oriented in
us so I guess I'll I'll say that I'm not I'm not really afraid of the word truth
there are things that are true and things that are false or deceptive and that can be known in ways that are
appropriate for a given situation budh is teachings support this
this way of thinking about the truth so don't worry we won't be analyzing all the kinds of Truth for
today I just thought it was important to clarify that term a bit we're just going
to consider what we can clearly know in our life know the basic the basic kinds
of truths that we may wish to preserve in our actions of body speech and mind
and some ways that we can do that so if we're not neglecting wisdom
then we are in touch with some kind of Truth so for example this cup uh is
warm and my sweater looks reddish to my
eyes and there's a pressure of my feet against the floor and it
feels it feels like it does right now I can feel it from the inside and I'm
speaking these words and I know that I'm speaking there's no Distortion there no judgments or Pro C or
[Music] abstractions so maybe consider for a moment just a few things like that that
are true for you in this moment can you notice any feeling of clarity in alignment with just those
basic things that are that are true at this [Music]
moment so one of the best ways to practice with preserving truth is in our
speech in our communic ation so once we get into these truths
that are where we're sharing communicating with others it can get a little bit dicier now we have to be a
little bit more precise about what it means to preserve truth in a more public
way but just as an example um something I do when I uh write in an email to
somebody um we're arranging you we're calendaring together and I write to them I've put this in my
calendar I actually pause in writing the email I go and I put that into my
calendar and I save it and only then do I press send on the email it would be
easy to dash off the email saying I put it in my calendar and then go do it but
that makes the statement in the email not quite true doesn't it I haven't put it in my calendar yet so um I put it in
my calendar before I send the email these little details can be
important so you know as noted we have to be clearer when we're when we start
sharing or communicating with others then we have to look at this truth there
is a teaching in the sutas maim Manaya 95 where somebody asks the Buddha how to
preserve truth it's a Brahman and he literally says in what way is there the
preservation of truth how does one preserve truth we ask Master godma
that's the Buddha about the preservation of truth and the poly verb there for
preservation is rockety which is also means to safeguard or protect so and the Buddha replies to
this Brahman if a person has Faith they preserve the truth when they say my
faith is thus but they do not yet come to the definite conclusion only this is
true anything else is wrong and if a person reaches a conclusion based on reasoning then they
preserve truth when they say my reasoning is thus but they do not yet come to the definite conclusion only
this is true anything else is wrong and so on the Buddha names five things total not just faith and
reasoning so it's clear I think what this teaching is saying cite your source so rather than just
asserting something as a definite truth we carefully say how we know what we're
saying or why we have come to think that maybe we're believing it because we read
it in the Wall Street Journal or we read it in Al jazer or we heard it on Fox News and we trust that platform of
Journalism so we say this is where I read this or this is where I heard this
or maybe we thought about it and we're trusting our own logical ability so we say that or maybe we did a
scientific experiment and we're quoting data from
that so you know yesterday I watched the eclipse using a pinhole camera I didn't
exactly see the sun being eclipsed because we can't look at the sun um but
I saw a projection of the sun with a curved portion cut out of it during the
time frame when the eclipse happened so if you ask whether I saw the eclipse I could say yes but I could also
preserve the truth more by clarifying that I saw it in this particular
way so this might be a wonderful practice to do if you're interested you could try for a whole day
or just a morning maybe to say the source behind every declarative
statement that you make so options include um trust you
trust where you heard something or maybe you have uh sense of approving of
something this is aligned with my values so that's why I'm saying it or this is
how our society conceives of something so I'm saying it out of cultural
tradition or I'm saying it out of logic I thought it through and this is how I
see it or maybe you reflected about somebody else's View you know my friend
told me this and I thought about it and that makes sense so can you preserve truth through
your speech in this way other people may look at you a little funny for being so careful and
clear but that just shows how loose we usually are with being being clear about
preserving the truth in this way and then by the way the other part
of preserving truth in what the Buddha said is that we don't believe that we're certain you know we don't come to the
definite conclusion only this is true everything else is wrong so this is more
of a mental Act of preserving truth is that even when we make statements and we declare this is why I think it's true we
keep things open in our mind maybe this is how it is and this is why I think so
but in in our mind we remember maybe it's not maybe I don't have all the information maybe my trust wasn't
correct maybe my logic was faulty this time around can we keep things open in
our mind it's interesting that preserving the truth includes remembering that it
might not be completely
true we can also preserve the truth through meditative contemplation and
this is a very important skill for living a Dharma life or for living gener
with Integrity a friend of mine who's a teacher in another tradition Buddhist
teacher from another tradition um paraphrased it this way I
want to say something about what he said about a practice that he does that I've done too and really
like so he says in every situation particularly difficult ones take the
time and make the effort to know what is true often there are multiple facets to
a situation physical emotional and spiritual which is true all of them we
practice with this by simply including all of those different perspectives just
holding them in intention not doing anything with them with time and some
trust the truth of the matter will reveal itself when we're able to see or
understand what is true and accept it even though it may be very painful mind
and body relax we find relief just from allowing everything to be there as it is not
suppressing or projecting what comes out of that easing of tension is almost always good and
wholesome I really liked the way he said that and how he points to a a visceral
feeling that happens when we get aligned with the truth he calls it an easing of
tension have you ever felt this when you were finally able to accept the full
reality of a situation I have we can know in our very
being that we are touching into what is true it can be quite a process to get
there because we don't get to choose how long it takes for the truth to reveal
itself but if we have this practice of staying open wanting to include more and
more keeping things in alignment then eventually we
can get this direct feeling of Yep this is it this is we've landed on at least
as far as I can know the truth with my ability at this moment and that can be a guide or a beacon on the path this is
what the Buddha is calling in the foundation truth that's what he's calling it so our deepest experience of Truth
can become a reference point for further deepening
so I wish you all the courage to live in this kind of non- deception this kind of
alignment of tress and to preserve the truth is one of the most beautiful things that we can
start doing immediately at the level that we can and it will deepen and deepen and deepen and it can go all the
way to the deepest truth so thank you
and may it be a wonderful day of Truth so
tomorrow