good morning friends
welcome I uh I'm just slightly late I wanted to respond to a couple requests
yesterday and the day before for the texts that I'm referring to this
week some people you know that's that's useful in their practices bow to you and
other people it doesn't make any it's not supportive so I've stuck them in the
chat there and lost a few minutes in the lost a few minutes gained a few
minutes in the in the so doing so welcome Friday um it's been a
lovely week for me and uh to be with you all and to share some Dharma and to sit
together and uh to explore for me this particular text of teaching which is as
I said at the outset um of
seldom referred to uh as far as I know and uh quite quite sweet and uh again
the theme for the week has been the Buddha smile this idea that as this text
suggests that when we cultivate a meditation practice when we deepen the
Stillness and the collectiveness of the meditation in particular that five knowledges can arise uh and will arise
Naturally by themselves and I've further suggested that as we notice those and
they come to attention that they're strengthened and uh maybe I'll review
them briefly when we when we later in the in the darat um but uh that all of
them can be accompanied by a sense of ease a sense of pleasantness and pleasure and thus deeply sort of settled
in our minds as being wholesome and being onward leading that I think is uh the source of
this smile that comes in meditation and that we can see reflected in depictions
of the Buddha and take as a as both inspiration and instruction so today interesting we get
kind of tactical the fifth knowledge that arises in the meditation
is that uh I quoting here I mindfully enter into and emerge from this deep
meditation and uh as I'll say a little bit more in the guided and then in the daret um sometimes we we we rush in as I
did today get here right at 7 and you know settle into meditation and just as
quickly the bell rings and boom you know we're we're back into daily life and I
think this today's teaching brings bring reminds us that the entering the way we
enter into the meditation and the way we leave are really important in sort of
protecting the practice and in some Buddhist Traditions there's a whole sort of um culture of protecting the
practice and that will be our Focus today we get a lot more instruction
about entering in a way because as we start a guided typically teachers will
give a sense of how to enter the meditation we get a lot less about how to leave and that's where I'll Focus
comments later but in the meditation today maybe I'll I'll try in the guided portions at the beginning and the end
maybe I'll I'll bring a little bit of sort of entering and leaving uh a little bit more to the
four Great to the meditation then that over there
so I'm going to take a sip of tea as I encourage you to prepare for meditation
and this is the most important thing maybe about entering is to do so as this
text suggests mindfully and I'm going to say deliberately
intentionally and I'm pausing to take a sip of tea if you have a cup of tea handy you might do the same and prepare
to meditate think about oh what what condition can be put in place that will
help deepen the meditation and along with a sip of
tea and maybe uh settling into a physical location and I'm starting to bring the
eyes down because that's what I do to bring attention inward maybe we can also
bring to mind intention what is it that we sit for why
do we sit together and just touch base with our desire to
be free and remind ourselves that as we
settle into meditation that the mind with which we prepare the
meditation uh is an important part of the benefits that we can expect from the
meditation we bring an intention for our own well-being and the well-being of others
into the meditation as an inspiration as an intention
and thus we prepare the mind to
meditate so instead of just sort of plopping down on the cush cushion or in our chair it can ease in
gradually and touch in with our fundamental intention for the
practice maybe it's just some ease maybe it's some momentary relief
from stress and maybe it has a deeper course
in our lives maybe it has to do with um more
spiritual oh I don't want to say objectives or aims spiritual
orientations that we want to be free we want others to be
free and and in addition to relief we want release and that this is a wholesome
aspiration in our practice the meditation as I suggested
yesterday whether it's returning to the breath or settling in can be
unhurried and in this un hurriedness there's wholesomeness
meditation is a place where we let go from hurry we let go from
striving we balance effort with allowing as we said
yesterday and we take our time as we take it
easy so inter interestingly the meditation is deeper
this day's teaching suggests when we enter mindfully and I would suggest that
part of that is entering without
hurry we enter with ease we enter with good
intention because these provide important conditions for the deepening of the meditation
and now after sipping tea looking around
settling in carefully and unhurriedly touching in with
intention intentions for this sit to be here now and maybe for the whole practice practice to be
free having done these useful skillful
Preparatory actions now we can make contact with the
breath and we make contact with a breath in a way that brings these intentions
with it and today every time we return attention
to the breath every time we open our attention back up broadly when it's become tight and
contracted we can retouch with this intention to be fully here to let things
arise and pass as they will and want and this intention to find ease to
lean in toward ease to L the Mind toward
ease and now well prepared with intention with
instruction we can settle into some time in
silence
e
e e
so this teaching this week encourages us to mindfully leave the meditation as a way
to deepen it
interesting so let's just slowly bring attention back to this
meditating being in the
world maybe start to take some stock of our surroundings perhaps there's a handy
sound perhaps there's a sensation of the body
against the cushion or the chair that can help sort of start to bring us
gradually unhurriedly and gently sort of back
into um the different more
energetic interaction with the world with our experience in the world
and in the daret we'll talk about some specific ways we could do this
don't have to do them all each time we leave the meditation but for Here and Now what
comes up is perhaps touching it again with Our
intention maybe we had an intention for this particular meditation period to
just be here with experience without fighting against it so much and whether or not that was the
experience of the meditation it's useful to reconnect with that
intention oh yeah yeah and kind of compare maybe our
experience with that intention and notice places where yeah there was some greater ease
with experience have a choice here to maybe focus on the
the positive what felt good what was
wholesome as we touch in with those mind States they're
stronger and we could touch in too with intentions that go further than today's set
and have to do maybe with why we practice oh right there's
this strong desire for well-being there's an aspiration to be
Freer and there's a heart that would like to be open to
others we can just recall those intentions for our
practice these are this is a realm of intention in which we take the intention
for this little meditation period or returning to this breath in this moment even and we bring it out into the larger
world to meet experience without struggle so that we act and interact
with the mind in
peace anyway touch in with intention as a way to leave the meditation mindfully
and as we do so we can commit to sharing the benefits of
the meditation with those around us and by
implication spreading out in concentric circles with all beings
[Music]
so welcome friends
um leaving the meditation mindfully continues now for for me but for all of
us and uh I'm reaching for my cup of
tea I feel the mug I note that it's cooler than at the beginning of our sit
I take a sip and in all of this I'm aware of
leaving mindfully which will be the main focus of darat
today so though to to say yes day five of what we call the Buddhist smile we
call I mean I called this week we called I didn't mean to say we call like it's a
common thing no this week's Focus became the Buddhist smile
the idea that in the meditation understanding about the meditation arises understandings about
how to make it deeper how to keep feeding it keep encouraging it and that
with these understandings comes a smile a sense of contentment sense of ease that maybe
inward maybe outward may be shared with
others um for those who might be just joining now I did include in the
chat pointing out I'm like push that Bell And subscribe or whatever but I I'm
just saying I guess it's over there in the YouTube chat I did responding to a request
yesterday provide uh the name of the suta the discourse that I've been
riffing on this week and also because a couple people asked the specific sutas
in the majima Naya the collection of middle L this courses of the Buddha where the particular topic of this idea
of cultivating the pleasantness or the pleasure of meditation are are
uh brought forward um all right mindfully entering and
leaving meditation I call this daret protecting the practice uh and I'll say this probably
at the beginning at the end but the idea of protecting the practice I really love
that I ask we ask so much of this practice and we can we can also ask what
can I give the practice go what my the practice benefit from that I can
provide and um one thing we can do for the practice is give it um our sort of
full attention and consideration our respect
almost and we can do this in the way we we enter and leave the
meditation so regarding entering where I feel like there's more instruction provided uh you know we we get a lot of
instruction around uh connecting with the breath and how to return to the breath in those first 15 20 30 minutes
depending on his personal things in the day the weather interior weather
exterior weather how long it takes sort of for the mind to settle because it takes time for
everyone um we learn a lot about that entering process to to those kind of
familiar instructions I would add a couple uh additional
ideas one is just begin begin meditating before you sit down begin meditating
before you meditate set things up bow smile whatever whatever you do that's
part of the it doesn't have to be a ritual but just uh a habit because this
is a wholesome habit that replaces less wholesome habits however you prepare if it's in my
case walking upstairs you can walk upstairs to or downstairs or around the
house to the place you meditate you can look around the place you meditate you can sort of take stock of
this ambient sounds what's happening in the body is there hunger
um you know any is there gurgling is there a need to use the bathroom is
there um restlessness is there still some sleepiness whatever notice what's
happening in the body notice the quality of attention in the mind you know is
there ease is there hurry is there anxiousness is there contentment is
there warmth is there Stillness whatever and as I think I've emphasized
quite a bit this week don't hurry take it easy as I said yesterday but don't
hurry there's no hurry needed here hurry is
counterproductive in this practice unlike you know much of the rest of our lives when we sit down to meditate
there's a way in which we leave to one side we don't push them away we don't
have to pull them out by the roots we're just setting them aside while we meditate some of the um some of the way we strive and
approach life outside of the meditation and it's very very nice to set them down
set them to one side side for a period of meditation so don't hurry um Gil says
I don't think he made it up but I like it when he says it reminds people that
in this practice the quickest way from point A to point B from here and now to
where we want to be the quickest way to get from point A to point B is to be
fully present here at Point a it's here we want to
be and we don't have to hurry to be
here um in fact when we get hurried we sort of you know we're less here now
we're more there then be here now we say
another way to say that might just be don't hurry there's no reason to hurry we're not trying to get
anywhere um we're not trying to get anywhere else okay having said that
about mindfully arriving mindfully entering the meditation here's a little bit more
about mindfully leaving or exiting the meditation which I think we we you know
we hear a lot less about the talks the guidance tends to come in the beginning of the meditation and so it focuses more
on entering so when we come to the end of the meditation these are things I didn't
do in the guided but they're useful to keep mind take a few deep breaths and bring awareness back to the body and as
you do so notice any sense of ease that's there
be with the awareness that noticing it strengthens it so kind of notice where we are
sometimes you'll notice this most um
forcefully when we Open the Eyes there will be awareness oh the eyes are really kind of focused like the mind in this
middle distance you know and it takes a while maybe for Focus to kind of come
back and just be aware of what that's like before stirring before moving from
the cushion another thing that's very useful to do is come out a teacher an early
teacher sort of once taught me come out the way we went in retrace our
steps whatever that means if there's any depth that's come up in
the meditation any ease excuse
me um come back out the way we went in so
that we're creating a path it helps to remember how we got in
to go in next time and this may be things like um just
noticing uh you know what was the breathing like where was the Mind
centered um what led up to Greater ease or greater
contentment and then sort of make a mental note of that and sort of be prepared to try
those same steps uh the next
time the conditions we created both entering and leaving are really important in deepening the the
meditation there's also this there are in some Buddhist Traditions the Tibetan the Maham mudra in particular really
quite sophisticated um approaches to what's called sometimes protecting the
practice and um in this case and I'm quoting here protecting entails a
comparison of immediate experience of the medit ation with the teachings
given and this can be a very powerful thing to do as we leave to meditation is
to notice that oh there was greater ease when there was less attention to
self or there was more letting
go when I returned to the breath without judgment these are really important
things to notice because they connect the experience of this particular sit with the teachings that lead
onward and I love the idea of protecting the practice taking care of the practice you know we look at the
practice as a tool and
um just thinking of my father and the fact I have some of his tools and I don't take care of him like he would
have and uh this is a place where taking care of the tools you know after we've used a tool as I was taught you know use
a shovel wash it off let it dry in the sun don't let it get all rusty in the
garage I've got to wash off my shovel later um but protecting the tool taking
care of the meditation is something that can really powerfully deepen it that's
the point of entering and leaving mindfully as it helps the meditation grow deeper
so this is all before we stir from the cushion so and then before you get
up we might take time to feel grateful for the time we spent meditating almost
you know thank the practice and don't leave
entirely right throughout the day we can keep practicing we can keep the breath in mind for
example and then if we sort of keeping the breath in mind keeping some of these instructions in mind keeping some of
this ease in mind keeping some of this peace with us yeah we create a more
sustained mindful awareness throughout the day and it's there next time we go
to sit down that is where all we been with the breath we've been we've been
preparing so not leaving entirely is a way of you know kind of always being
ready to enter so that's what I have for this
week um and maybe I'll kind of in a couple minutes that
remain just refresh our memory our Collective memory for this
teaching and uh I'll I'll read some of it sort of verbatim
practitioners this is addressed then and now to us to people who practice develop the
meditation deepen the meditation cultivate the Stillness and collectiveness and well-being of the
meditation and when you do so five knowledges will arise what
five um that this meditation is
pleasurable now and results in benefits in the future Pleasant
benefits we can lean into that that wholesome contentment a wholesome
satisfaction that arises in the meditation that this meditation points on toward greater
things toward deep spiritual um knowing and
release that this immersion this um deep meditation we cultivate in Good Company
one another and other people who share these aspirations who seek to open their
hearts who um seek to be act with a mind at ease mind at
peace and ultimately we practice together with the Buddha and others who
have awakened in this practice Thursday yesterday with the
take it easy idea the knowledge arises in the meditation that this peaceful this peace
this Tranquility this unification or collectiveness of mind isn't held in
place by force that we are better off when we balance effort with
allowing and then finally today that we benefit the meditation we strengthen it
with when we enter and leave um and maybe it's a usually uh this is an interesting order ing for me uh because
it's tactical most tactical at the end and yet it's perfect for this 7 a. sit
in that um it gives us something very specific to do when We Gather again uh I
won't be with you Monday as in the teacher seat but when the group gathers again next week um there will be this
renewed opportunity to enter and leave mindfully in a way that strengthens the meditation
it's always a pleasure to do this I uh I'm happy to be with you I uh um
appreciate people coming together to support one another one another's practice in this way always happy to sit
in for Gil with my wonderful teaching colleagues Yang and Kim and um the many
others who who uh sit the 7 a.m. with you so take care everyone till
next time our paths cross and uh yeah take good care of your
practice take good care of your practice