so good morning everyone welcome and for today I'd like to begin
by reading a Buddhist prayer for
peace it begins this piece with a quote from the Buddha and the quote
goes hatred never ends through
hatred by Love Alone does it end this is an ancient truth the
Buddha so the prayer goes begins this way Only
Love Can end the pain of hatred may all beings everywhere be
freed from the sufferings of War violence and hatred May those who are injured be
healed May those who have lost their homes and Country countries become guests in every home in every
country May th those who are devastated be fed clothed loved and
elevated May those who are scared be given safety May those who fight learn that
killing an enemy does not create peace it makes enemies for future
Generations May fight Fighters learn to fight with truth love
and respect which is how lasting pieace is possible
love is the best way to kill enemies because then they are
transformed into friends may we do what is more complex
than War may we create peace through intelligent and strategic nonviolent means
may we call on all our goodness and Good Will to contribute to the end of War
everywhere may we contribute to everyone's welfare and happiness with no
exceptions so by the end of this talk I'd like to
address the situation in gazam and maybe I'm addressing it already with this
prayer and so maybe the whole thing is but to explicitly be kind of near the
end and
um the um so I grew up
in living in many countries many places moving around quite a bit I went to
change schools 12 times in my first 12 years of school
and um but one of the consequences of that was and I'm I was then I was a
Norwegian Citizen and my wish when I was 11 or 12
was to have a not be a Norwegian citizen or an American citizen but I wanted to
have a United Nations passport uh because I wanted to belong
to the whole world I didn't want this thing of being you know it seemed kind of too narrow or too restrictive or too
nationalistic just to belong to a country that way and that was my
wish and uh and I love the idea of living in a Cosmopolitan area with lots of
diversity of all over the world and when I moved to uh San
Francisco area here uh in my 20s uh it was a lot less diverse than it
is now I mean certainly there was plenty of but but uh you know I think it's changed
dramatically and certainly this area of the peninsula Silicon Valley has become
dramatically more diverse place like Fremont and different places of the bay and uh I treasure it I find it's
fantastic this is the case and uh I kind of I have myself love the idea that
immigrants from all over the world come here to this country and find their way and are included and I'm know those
right so of course I would I kind of like that but um but then as uh what happens
when there's so much diversity from all over the world it's also a recipe for more
conflict and uh I was asked to somehow address an issue
that happened recently with um um right here in our neighborhood not
here but in in San Jose at the
uh State University of San Jose I don't know if some of you saw the news a few
weeks ago that uh the police were needed to be there for Professor who was going
to give a public talk a professor of Jewish studies who was going to talk about um the little history of the
conflict there and and the history of a two-state solution and someone who was
oppos to the violence that they're now in Middle East but it seems that there was a a
call out from Hamas to uh that there should be this should
be disrupted right here in our neighborhood and so that was that were
people were informed about this ahead of time and they um so the police were
called in and to be prepared and they decided to change the V menue of where the talk was going to be
given and uh in fact there were 100 people who came who to demonstrate and
and the way it was reported to me by people who were there there was calls for uh killing
Jews and uh then it was impossible to give the talk and the people who were
the speakers of the of that had to be taken out um under police escort there's
a large group of police and City Police at least waiting nearby because of they were expecting that there was going to
be some problems so I mean the Middle East Gaza
is not just in Gaza what's happening in this International world we live in it's
spilling over and the divisiveness of the Middle East is also becoming
divisiveness in our communities here and
uh and uh so somehow you know it's coming home I
felt like oh it's here in our communities as well and so how do we address it how do we live with
it how do we take it into account how do we understand it and
[Music] um the um so one way to understand
this and I don't want to diminish the the the suffering intensity difficulty
of this but there is an analogy that's used that comes from
Sports and that is that uh there F fans of teams that are playing a sport like
baseball or football where there are referees or umpires who have to make the
call when someone is you know done a foul or stepped offline or
something and uh sometimes the people making that called referees umpires make
a bad call or sometimes it's a little bit ambiguous maybe depending on the angle which you
see it or something and the phenomena is that if the umpires make the wrong
call the opposing team the fans get
furious even if it's ambiguous they're Furious if it's against their
team but the the team that got a favorable ruling you know that's the nature of the
game you know it's you know that no they they didn't really do it you know that was some you know the umire got it right
and you know there's never and never never you it's always kind of allowing for it or forgiving it or it's okay you
know and so there's this bias against the opposing team that elicits a kind of
anger but there's a kind of hypocrisy in that because for the home
team one's own team that people are willing to forgive them more or see it differently or don't see it it's not as
a big deal or it's not so serious it's not an ethical thing so much so this happens with uh politics it
happens with war between countries and people and there the issues are much
more intense because it isn't just simply the winning and losing of a team but it t ties into people's core
feelings of safety core feelings of identity of who they are as of people
core in issues of the suffering that they have gone through for maybe
Generations my father-in-law uh who uh was in the Nazi
concentration camps Jewish man who was a teenager was in the camps and with his parents his
parents didn't survive but uh he survived Bergen Bergen
bsum and uh barely survived and
um and that was pretty challenging for him the rest of his
life and he died 70 years or so after being released from the
camps and um I knew him right up to the last day of his life and the intensity
of that experience was with him 70 years later it was it carried it with him to
his death so the suffering that goes on and you know and I don't know how much it's
carried over into his children my wife um my my children have a grandfather who
was in the camps I wonder sometimes I wonder if it's more intense for them to
have heard the stories than it is for me because he I married into the family they're it's maybe a little different I
don't know if it's a little different or not but and my kids are relatively young so this the suffering uffing that
we carry for so many years and so the suffering of Jews in Israel I think you
know the the what happened in Germany now it's what 80 years ago and more is
still alive but the suffering of the Palestinians for now for maybe almost as
long in in some ways is very alive and one of the as I've told this story
before one of the formative experiences of my was being at the Zen Monastery where we
were isolated kind of deep in the Los Padres National Forest here where the the news was always late back then there
was no internet there was just the newspapers would come in and news magazines would come in and they'd
always come in to you know some days late and it was very interesting to get
uh old news because um fresh news is is
alarming but if you get if you read the news two or three days later it has a very
different feeling and it's more like uh it's not it doesn't elicit in me at least the
same level of present moment alarm it's like it's serious but it's has a
different feeling but anyway there was a Time magazine that came in and and I was in
the middle of a three Monon Retreat so I was pretty open quiet receptive in a
very different way than you are running around town and um and I opened up the
Magazine and there was um a spread of
photographs like I don't know four or five pages of the magazine of the Israeli bombing of a
Palestinian refugee camp in Beirut and I told that story here once
and a man who was sitting over in that corner turned out that he lived across the street from the refugee camp at that
time and he was one of the first people who responded to bury the dead and help
the wounded these things are not so far
away and um and uh innocent people were killed
children were made orphans that was 40 years ago and so
you know that suffering in that you know in Palestinians is still
there and that's just one own example and there's examples on both sides they're pretty dramatic so the idea that
you know you're rooting for your own team and willing to overlook what your team does I think makes more
sense uh when uh the stakes are so
high and um so
and I've been to Israel and I was
stunned to hear the animosity that the Israelis
some Israelis had for the Palestinians stunned I went into the government
tourist agency in Jerusalem and the person behind the desk called
Palestinians dogs wow could this
be and I've been stunned by the hostility of Palestinians
and Arabs towards the Israelis it's just unbelievable that
people carry so much hatred and hatred doesn't
work hatred produces more hatred when you hurt
people through violence they will hate it's so easy so
so obvious you know as almost as a way of protecting oneself and or wanting
revenge and so it continues the cycles and I think the Middle East isn't
that the representative of for centuries Millennia of the cycles sometimes I'm so
surprised that they haven't learned the lesson it doesn't seem to have worked violence it just goes on and on
you know and and um so is there an alternative to
hate is there an alternative to demonizing other
people and and as long as people buy into this demonization that the politicians do
that societies do you you can't really find a way forward it's not going to be
possible it means you just keep it's in Annihilation pushing people
away so this you know and so this phenomenon the sports
phenomena I've done this thought experiment in my mind of wondering if the Palestinian somehow or
other magically had the upper hand right now and we're doing to T aiv doing to
Israel what Israel is doing to Gaza I think many people in United
States would be absolutely horrified and angry and upset would probably be
justifying the United States coming in uh with soldiers and
defending Israel and but the level of alarm among the general population of
what's happening the level of violence in Gaza is pretty Hamp
down given you know that you know just a phenomenal I mean it's just unbelievable
that over 30,000 people and civilians have been killed and they say that something 40%
of them maybe are children it's unbelievable I mean that's like
astounding and um so that's the context of where we're
at right some somehow so what does Buddhism have to say say about this like I I I study the
teachings of the Buddha and very interested in it and he has some things to say about
beauty and um and then he has this interesting statement that um what is
more beautiful than beautiful that doesn't make sense right but what's what's what's the what's
things are some certain things are beautiful but what's even more beautiful and the contrast for that is
what is harmful and what is more harmful than
harmful so what you know that's a kind of interesting statement and so um the
um so so this is what he says what is
harmful killing taking what is not given sexual
misconduct speaking falsely speaking
divisively speaking harshly speaking speaking
pointlessly being avaricious having hostility these are all
harmful and what is more harmful than
harmful encouraging others to kill encouraging others to take what is not
given encouraging others to involve be involved in sexual misconduct have others speak falsely
speak divisively speak harshly speak pointlessly be greedy be
hostile so any encouragement being a catalyst support for other people to be
this way that's more harm even more harmful maybe because the harm grows and maybe even expands exponentially some
point so then the Buddha said what is beautiful and the word for beauty kalana
also can mean excellent certain kind of but it's more it's a moral Beauty it's a
moral Excellence that's being talked about you'll see now so what is
beautiful abstaining from killing abstaining from taking what is not given abstaining from sexual
misconduct from speaking falsely speaking divisively speaking harshly
speaking pointlessly being greedy and being
hostile so that's so now you know probably what what's more beautiful than
beautiful um abstaining from killing yourself and prompting others to abstain
from killing abstaining from taking what is not giving and prompting others to abstain from taking what is not
given and so forth so this idea the prompting others encouraging others the
Buddha is kind of championing this so that Buddhism sometimes is seen as a non-violent religion that's often
interpreted as being a passivity but this is not
passive what's the best thing to do is not just to be ethical yourself but
encourage others to be ethical there's nothing in here about prizing Buddhism like what the best
thing you could do is make people people Buddhist the Buddha over and over and over again emphasized being ethical not
causing harm that that was a high highest value for this tradition this
religion for what the Buddha was about over and over again that was the reference point when he talked in public
to people and um and one of the important things about
being ethical this list is not being divisive
people who are are um div he describes that wrong
speech is being divisive speech where people love affectional ISM they love
creating divisions between people what the Buddha wants is a
language which is unifying that brings people together and supports those who
are already unified to be more unified so how do we do that
when I talked to about Kaza here in October I I spoke a little bit about it
they offered kind of a bu Buddhist point of view which was not to take sides but
offer kind of I don't know if a middle way is the right language but offer an alternative way that didn't involve taking sides I got um um emails from an
uh Israeli and a Palestinian remarkably they both had almost exactly the same
language to each other the the Palestinian criticizing me
for what I had said and the and the Israeli criticizing me for what I said and I thought wow I think I hit the
sweet [Laughter]
spot and um and so you
know and you know maybe what was at play there was the sports analogy right that
these people hear it different way and you know and are waiting to hear something that's for their side really
explicitly but is there a way of not taking sides is there a way of U and I talked
about back then about uh the example of tick nadan who was a peace activist
during the Vietnam war and he wouldn't take sides and' be in the in the division itally geographically between
the two opposing war sides Northern and South Vietnam and neither side trusted him
neither they were all angry with him thinking that basically thinking that he was part of the other side if you weren't with us then you're not if
you're not with us then you're against us and so this it's so hard to have this middle line when people
have think they have a tremendous need for to maintain the division so that to
really defend themselves or protect themselves or to or to be able somehow
defeat the other and
um the Buddha said somewhere else he said among the types of beneficent
conduct among the best is prompting settling and establishing an unethical
person in ethical Behavior
so again this emphasis on being ethical so in terms of
Gaza and uh many people are calling for a ceasefire some people are demanding
it and um I think of course we want the killing to stop of
course there's another way of course something else can be
done of course all these people should stop being killed but can we ask for a ceasefire
can we encourage it not as a demand but in such a way that the
Israelis become inspired themselves they realize this is not a good deal there's
a better way of doing it because to come down with the demand
it's maybe more of the divisiveness So I myself would not like
to would not like to be in a situation people have asked me to sign things and stuff that more like
demands and um that's not what I think I want to do but of course they should
stop doing it I have no doubt about it I want to encourage Israel to stop but the
way that how do we do this in a way that is effective maybe for the long term or
effective for the short term and um the
um and so but it's an act you know it's for
some people it's very difficult to imagine an alternative way the the the
imagination it it it uh challenges the imagination that there's any other way
besides VI violence for some people that's the only way you can get your way and it has to be that way
and is it that really the case and is it to degree the violence to the degree
that's what we're seeing it is in Kaza right now I mean these are really important questions it's really
important to look at ourselves what we defend what we feel is right what we how we buy into some of
the rhetoric um and what's motivating us to take sides for example where does our
sides come from and what is our belief system what's understanding about social change and what's our understanding
about impact that violence has in our societies do you know maybe Israel will
get something of What It Wants by destroying Gaza my
father-in-law was impacted for 70 years rest of his life by what happened in
Germany what's going to happen to the Palestinians and how long many years are they going to be impacted by this and
not forget and
um so calling for peace of course we should do
that but we shouldn't just do it we should also be available so in this situation at San
Jose State University I was asked to write a letter to the president of the
university and I did je Jewish man asked me to do
it and so I wrote but I said to him you know I'll write the letter but I don't know if if it's what you what you
want but I'll show it to you first and um and
um and then you know the short version of what I said was I asked the president to
um to uh not be uh to be asked her to be
impartial to be concerned for the welfare and happiness of everyone on her
campus and including the ones who she hadn't been caring for
yet and then but then I said um I presented myself as a local
Minister and um and I said that
um um and if I could be of help to you for this process let me
know so how do we help what do we do the final thing I'll say about this
is that um there's been uh times very important
important moments in my life that I was changed by what happened in the world in fundamental ways so the time at tasahara
when I saw the bombing of the refugee camps in Beirut that was a huge impact
on me partly because I was in the monastery on Retreat partly because I had been to
Beirut as a child so I knew the place partly because I grew up part of my
growing up my cosmopol and moving around was I lived on the edge of the Mediterranean in Italy and um and so
it's just down the corner around the corner you know with Beirut and you know it's just part of all the same
world so to see my own world being bombed was was such a big impact on me
and and uh and it changed me and part of that change is why I'm here today it
part of that change was I decided I was going to use my life to to address suffering in this world through Buddhist
practice and I thought this was the for me this was the way that I wanted to do it because I felt the it's the only
thing I knew in my life that touched the root causes of suffering in a human
being and I was going to do other things to try to support the world but I felt that um I did the other things I
wouldn't actually be able to touch the very root of suffering in the human beings and I didn't think I'd be
effective as a Zen priest then monk but at least I was trying to address the core issues of suffering the attachment
the deepest attachments we have so that that took took me in this direction before that the big impact on me was
when I went to first two years in college was at the University of California of Santa
Barbara and I was there right after there was this huge oil spill one of the biggest maybe one of the first biggest
oil spills in the country um and um
and that had a big impact and going to school right after that and taking classes enironmental studies had a big
impact on me and that was a catalyst for me to really want to live a life adult life of trying again try to address some
of the problems of our society and I was going to become environmentalist I got a
little bit sidetracked a different kind of environment and then um the next one
that had similar impact on me was 911 and um so this is what I I want to tell
you this for a particular reason is that um so that was huge for
the country for those of you who remember it it was huge a big big impact and and um I'd seen similar things not
of that magnitude happen um where kind of seemed like everyone went back to business as
usual you know things things didn't really change and I thought you can't with this can't happen this time this is
so big that I have to be different something has to change I I felt like I
would do a violence to myself if I wasn't changed by 911 so I spent about nine months
thinking what what how how am I going to be different what am I going to do is different and then I decided that uh
what we would do would we would create a Buddhist chapy training program didn't
address the issues directly of you know 911 but it addressed uh the issues of
the issue of addressing suffering in our society in a very different way and so the Sati Center of Buddhist
studies that I help founded in 1997 was um mostly doing classes in
Buddhist history philosophy practice he said that's not enough we have to do something addresses the conditions of
our society so we created a Buddhist japany program and that it's been going on now for 22 years and we've traded
hundreds of people in Chaplan SE and I call it a pyramid scheme for
Joy because all these people go out into hospitals and prisons and hospices and
homeless situations and do this wonderful compassionate work it's really
really a great thing and that's growing and been very successful it's actually doubled in size in the last year and and
that's going well so that was a change the reason I'm telling you this story is because for me personally I feel what's
happening in Gaza right now is of the same magnitude and I feel I have to be I have
to be changed by this I can't respect what the impact and the value of this
and just go back to but I don't know what to do and I can give a talk about it
now but that's not enough so I'm wondering so it it took nine months last
time to know so people are demanding that you know some people demand that I do
things and um and that's not how I
operate but uh but so I don't know I'm I'm watching listening being present for
all this seeing what is what what will I do how will I be different what will I
what what has something has to change
so now you know what's more beautiful than beautiful maybe it's
complicated ethically what's going on in Gaza for many of us for many of
you and exactly what the ethics of it are and how you understand it is maybe a
difficult thing to sort out and figure out but
even so the Buddha thought that the most beautiful thing to do more beautiful
than being ethical is to promote ethical life for in others to encourage it to
support it not to demand it not to prosze for it not to make anyone feel
belittled by it but it's much more difficult
work the work of somehow inspiring others to live ethically I think that's
the movement for the Buddha he was never in a position to demand anything of people or assert or be aggressive about
it but how do we Inspire it more ethical world that we live
in and um I think it can be done but it
I think it's a very sophisticated thing to do it takes intelligence it takes
strategy it takes care and but most important if we want to inspire ethics
and others we have to be
ethical if we want to have an ethical world that we live in we have to feel
that this is important and one of the biggest ethical
principles in Buddhism is to avoid causing harm
and this contrast here between the most beautiful versus the Widow doesn't say what's ugly
and what's more ugly than ugly he talks about what's beautiful and more beautiful but what he says is what's
harmful and what's more harmful than harmful in another place where he talks
about similar contrast he uses a different word for beauty for good states of mind but for bad states of
mind and the on prompt on unethical activity he calls them
unskillful so it's very polite you know because you know not trying to create division not make anybody feel bad about
themselves and how do we do that how do we really Inspire goodness in all of us
how do we Inspire some different way how do we disp Inspire uh unification Unity
how do we Inspire other people who respect each other each other dare I say love each other how do we inspire people
that they don't want to spend their life hating what does it
take so I I'll read that to end I'll read this the poem by the
Buddha hatred never ends through hatred by Love Alone does it end this is
an ancient truth so may you
love may love be at the center of our practice for yourself for others and
even for your enemies and this prayer I think is very powerful statement for me that yes if
you want to fight and kill your enemies there's a way of killing
them you love them so much they become your friends they're no longer enemies like the enemy
has been killed but you didn't kill the person you transformed
them may we transform our enemies into our enemies into our friends in this
process so thank you