greetings from here all right it's time to
begin so we'll continue today with an exploration of the second precept in our
week-long exploration of the five precepts these these commitments
to uh Aspire these commitments to act skillfully in five different areas of of
life today we'll talk about the
precept that guides us to only accept things that are freely
given to avoid taking things not freely given and the guided meditation
will will uh support this this idea this this theme
so we can find our meditation
posture looking for a posture that's
balanced in the very posture we adopt for the meditation we
can find some of the balance of practice ice between effort and
allowing between alertness being present being attentive to what comes
up and adopting an attitude of Letting Go letting
be letting whatever arises come
up without adding too much judgment too much
opinion too much preference just nicely balanced in the in the
gentle momentum of the practice one breath leading to the
next in the spirit of taking what's given freely and giving freely
ourselves we can in this meditation ask the question
what can I give to the practice we want we expect so much from
the practice we ask a lot of
it and today maybe we can just bring our hearts a little bit
to what can we offer the practice what can we give freely to this
practice and one thing we can give freely of one
thing of which there's an inexhaustible store is our
attention maybe the sweetest gift we can give to ourselves and to
others and we can do so in a way that's free and we can do this every time we
mind that we're caught up in thought maybe not quite
here maybe a little pressed down or a little tight maybe the mind is a little
contracted around something perhaps our field of awareness
becomes narrow limited
constrained and we can open back up to the breathing bring the breathing back into
the the center of attention the center of
awareness and as we do so and as we feel coming back into presence opening back
out into the breathing perhaps we can feel this as a
gift a gift freely
given just to let our attention spread out again into this middle space where the breathing is happening where the
body is sitting where the weight the body can be perceived in the bench in
the chair on the cushion if we're standing on our feet if
we're meditating in a ly down posture we can feel gravity holding us
over and over again particularly in the first minutes of a
Sit the mind gets snagged on things thought spirals develop little knots and
Tangles of thinking emerge usually around one
of well-known axes of our minds the future the past other people
ourselves and before we hurry back to the
breath today we can notice maybe some of the tightness that's there whenever we
find the Mind caught up in these
things it's quite a quite a gift of the mind to us that it can do these things
project and plan into the future recall remember think about others think about
ourselves in the world for the meditation we just keep opening
back up to the here and now when the breath falls into the background we we bring it back to the
foreground we foreground
it as we open back up each time building this habit of returning to
presence strengthening the tendency to keep coming coming back
here we can understand it as a gift of attention paying
attention showing up for ourselves showing up for our
experience so instead of maybe feeling some frustration that the mind has wandered off or that I've got tangled up
again or all the other things we can add to that experience shouldn't be like this should be otherwise no good at this
this doesn't work for me all that stuff all that extra added on to experience
just the mind getting tangled up in things the mind being mind the mind
being mind when we come
back we can instead of hurrying back we can notice that from that tightness from
that place of concern from that place of worry or preoccupation you can come back
to a place that's at least marginally more still more open more simple more
slow and this coming back coming back to Center coming back to home coming back to here back to
now today let us conceive of this as a gift a gift
freely given
e
e e
so as we bring this meditation to a close we can dedicate
Merit as a gift freely given and maybe we can think of it this
way today in the spirit of engaging with the second
precept any Stillness that arises in our meditation any benefit that comes from
our practice we can offer we can
give to others we can make it available to other beings that need
it and we can do so freely that is without any expectation of reciprocity getting something
back sometimes this giving away of the benefit of practice some of the
Stillness of the meditation sometimes you can feel the heart close a little around that we want
to hold on to it we're not sure that it's okay to give it
away what happens to that precious portion that benefits
us and here's the teaching on that we give away from an inexhaustible
store of goodness and a benefit from the
practice and even more as we give it
away it grows giving away the benefit of practice dedicating it to others
offering it freely in the world doesn't diminish it in quite the
opposite it strengthens it increases it so in the spirit let's dedicate the
mer of our practice to all beings spreading this gift of attention
of Stillness of meditative calm of the gifts of practice as broadly as freely as we find
possible in this moment that it may benefit all beings
may all beings know some of this Stillness some of this
sweetness some of this Joy some of this calm some of this ease may all
beings be free from suffering
[Music]
so welcome again greetings to
everyone seeing that many people joined us during the sit
uh so today we'll take a look at the second precept this is the precept that commits
us or that in which we undertake for the purpose of supporting our
practice refraining from taking anything that's not freely
given and uh the guided meditation for those of you who were here try to help
support this um in our practice by suggesting at least two
things that we have the ability to give the gift of
attention in our practice we have something we can give to our practice
that allows us a way to know in our hearts what it feels like to give freely which helps us
understand when something's freely them freely offered freely offered to
us um and then we also can take the benefits of practice and
share them knowing when we feel maybe a little tightness around that if that comes out
does for me sometimes uh that we take from an
inexhaustible store and paradoxically perhaps but our practice is full of
paradoxes that as we give it away as we let go we we don't diminish the store in
fact it seems to increase so the second precept as we
take a look at each of the five precepts that support can support our practice this
week is this commitment to abstaining or
refraining from taking things not given I add not freely given because I think it raises the
bar much as we've seen with the first precept this isn't a commandment in
other words it's not um it's not a Commandment that thou shalt not steal
for example but rather and here's I'm going to be precise in the language it's a
commitment to abstain from the unskillful making things our
own unskillful expression of an acquisitional urge maybe we could say
it's more complicated don't know if I like the way that came out but refraining from unskillfully
making things our own so in I think it's an invitation
unlike a commandment where I can say okay I didn't steal anything today I don't intend to steal anything today I'm
not somebody who typically steals things uh it's just not that simple or that
rich or that supportive that that wouldn't be as supportive of practice than this
invitation to bring careful attention to our habit of wanting to make things
mine trying to think of some ways to illustrate this and uh during the meditation one of
the one of the places my mind went off was how would it be to share just a
brief clip of um The Beatles song George's song I think I M Me Mine those
of you who know this song can maybe bring it to mind I decided not to share it because I wasn't
sure that doing so would be making use of something freely given and I know I can probably get away with using less
than 15 seconds wouldn't be caught by YouTube's what is it that content ID
algorithm no ads would appear or the video would be blocked probably but um
just made me reflect maybe it's not freely given somebody owns the copyright I don't lose sleep thinking
about whether that person needs um a fraction of a scent that would come from
anyway um the the weariness in that song and again
I encourage you to listen to it in your paid service Spotify Apple music whatever uh where you're engaged in an
exchange um commercial exchange uh the weariness of that voice
that says I me me mine all through the day all through the night I me Me Mine
this this urge to make things mine it brings with it a weariness that's the heaviness of the self that we impose on
things just coming to sort of influence our interactions in the
world and this makes me think that the internet may be a really useful way to practice to explore a little bit this
urge to make things mine um and also to notice ask ourselves whether the things
we make use of are freely given there's a lot of Realms we could do this in but the internet is one that I expect um
many of us will make use of later in the day in point of fact we use it at this
moment and just noticing wondering question questioning ourselves is the
content I'm enjoying is the content I'm making use of if it's another kind of
content is it freely given particularly the content that's
embedded in things we enjoy or things we make use of uh is it was it freely given
would it be freely given this just provides a way to um
keep asking this question keep practicing with this precept in a way that's probably very immediate for most
of us logged on here to YouTube
um I'm aware of this little thing don't know if this occurs to anybody else but you know I enjoy content I make use of
content I'm going to use YouTube as an example where uh I I just as as I um
practice with the second precept I'm aware that I'm frequently encouraged to hit like button and
subscribe sometimes I'm directed as they do I can I do this to the link to some
free something Bell or whistle in the below just click on this link and I will
send you a free this or that if you share your email with me and just that I'm making use of
something that actually I'm not I'm not I'm I'm taking I'm taking something that isn't freely given it's actually and um
there's an invitation to engage in a exchange that
I'm I'm not choosing to engage in and thus taking something that's
actually only partially freely given at any rate it can get very um detailed and
precise but that's part of the purpose of these precepts is to really get us to engage in careful thinking
about our actions the the implications the consequences they have in the world
world and maybe more than anything how it feels in the heart what is this sense uh when I want
to make something my own what is this um self that get created around the
enjoyment of this content and I could go on
um so this suggests that the central problem with taking things not freely
given making them my own is that it reinforces uh self or selfing reinforces
an idea of self an idea that we know has stress and suffering inherent in
it and this selfing process can get in the way of an otherwise free flow of
things freely given freely
accepted so whereas by making a practice of only taking things freely given by
developing a habit of giving freely ourselves we can reduce harmful consequences of this incessant imposing
self on the world when we don't engage thoughtfully
with this kind of precept we're just going around Our Daily Business Without
um really engaging with uh whether harm is caused by our uh accepting things or
taking things making things mine
by um abstaining or refraining from not taking things freely given we're
actually letting go sort of uh we're we're letting go of
an unskillful habit of letting self get in the way of this kind of cleansing
purifying flow of things that are in fact freely given accepted freely given
freely so this may sound sort of abstruse and
theoretical but um each of these precepts in a way takes us to the heart
of the Buddhist teaching or various aspects of the heart of the Buddhist teachings and in particularly with the
second precept I have this sense that it allows us a way to hold self more lightly in a way
that's freeing um when we accept things we
question is this something that is freely given and I can accept freely we we're letting go of something
that um really is quite stressful to hold on to and maybe in taking this into some
sort of daily practice today and I'll give a few suggestions you can bring some attention
to what that feels like to hold hold the things we hold to hold
hold the things we hang on to U with a little bit more lightness perhaps let go
a little more so how to take this into the day I
could just say don't steal today I'm joking that would be uh that
would be too simple and it would let us off a little too easily but perhaps we
can um in sort of our orientation to others orientation what comes at us in a
huge torrent fire hose from the internet today we can ask this question of is
this freely given particularly is the content embedded in this Tik Tok video this
person is this is this this person's experience in the past is this freely
given um and the orientation inward might be is there an urge to make this
mine in some in some
way and again it may not be a thing that there's an urge to make mine but an
experience that I desire to make mine in some
way and returning to the top of the hour and the guided
sit this idea of giving something to the practice this too might have have an
Inward and an outward orientation today for yourself for
ourselves might think about what can I give to the practice today this practice from which I expect
so much and want so much there's a lot of eye in there my benefit my
freedom what what might I give it it's an interesting question to ask when you sit down to meditate or when you're find
yourself bringing practice into daily life what can I give to a practice here
what might it need you know maybe that's another 15 minutes on the cushion maybe
that's a certain way of uh being in the world uh the world of
experience and then in an orientation outward to others
um maybe maybe giving the gift the sweet gift the precious gift of
attention giving it freely listening to somebody
without any expectation of it being reciprocated just giving the gift of
attention listening carefully to somebody without asserting an opinion or without um judging or without having to
say anything ourselves but just giving the gift of uh
of our attention the more we pay attention in
this way um the more we create a habit of being able to do
it and these little exercises over the course of the day can help us create a
tendency in the mind to make this the second nature response that comes when
we're in a in an actual situation that as we said yesterday we
eventually become uh practitioners who are unable to take something that's not
freely given we don't have to spend a lot of time time doing the exercise we just know this feels uh like an exchange
in which uh good practice doesn't need to be involved it's not freely given and I can
I can move along so anyway thank you for coming today thank you for supporting
each other's practice and I look forward to seeing you tomorrow take care take
care