so welcome uh welcome all uh good morning
to most but I know Switzerland is in the house
so late afternoon I think
um yeah lovely to see uh See the names all right uh that's uh that's
it
e e
maybe uh for this first minute uh just uh
don't don't do
anything in a sense see how many things you might stop doing how many things you
think meditation asked you to start
doing whatever consciously can be stopped just
stop
e e
it's a certain kind of confidence that
uh freedom is on offer that there's already goodness
here that it's not the self self and the self
efforting that uh claws its way to
Freedom for
sometimes our doing our effort Our intention our
direction of
attention all of this actually crystallizes the sense of
self
sense of the meditator pulling the strings behind the
scene
and so we experiment with that
relaxing relaxing all the conscious impulses to do
something rather than to trust
something
e
e e
if there's something you can't stop doing that's okay don't double down and
try to stop what you cannot stop
just practice relaxing the Deep
impulse of doing
performing
e
e e
now that let us uh practice doing something but almost like with the
spirit of non-doing doing something but somehow
doing it in a different way than we've tended to do
it somehow
not repeating that kind of subtly desperate
energy of uh doing
this but instead very [Music]
openly receiving your breathing e
don't congeal sense of you the meditator
behind that receptivity just
receive this beautiful rhythmic flow of our
breathing
e
e e
we're care careful not to Source our meditation
instructions from
places voices within us that are impatient
unwise
moralistic we're not letting the super ego do our meditation
that's not the headquarters but we instead Source our
counsel and motivation from something deeper in us
more intuitive and
embodied and so it's safe to ignore every voice
place that's harshly
critical or full of
self or full of compulsivity doing
this we just find the threat of our practice
elsewhere
e
e e
for e
okay so we'll uh continue on with this uh interpersonal
theme and today is something like honoring
honoring Neurosis the Neurosis of the other honoring Duca
suffering so sometimes I've I've had the thought
just did a a retreat on the four noble truths with uh friend and colleague uh
inz Freedman IRC and we did the four noble truths but
sometimes I've thought the first Noble Truth sort of contains the other
three you know the truth of of suffering cause you know that there's a cessation
of the cause and there's a path but the first truth you know the
truth of of uh dukka uh usually rendered a
suffering that is no joke like and we
may say uh yeah I get I know suffering everyone
knows suffering that's why we're here it's why we're practicing and I've suffered and you've suffered
and yeah we know it but do we comprehend it the Buddha said comprehend dukka do
we realize it realize it as an
insight and this is not a process that is for the faint of heart and we
actually really have to stop fighting it at least moment
arily to comprehend it and yet most everything in
US rallies the troops to
fight and so it's actually a major project to open to one's
suffering but sometimes the suffering of of the other is even more
evocative and it can be evocative in a way that opens us to kind of very deep
compassion something in just seeing you know a loved one suffering
it's like oh yeah may may you be free but sometimes
our our care gets tangled up with um
with with uh with a sense of control with some strand of our own
clinging and so the question what would it be to follow the Buddha's instruction
of comprehending suffering for another's
life and we've um entrusted entrusted our heart
to uh to another either by choice or by
birth and that essentially means that all of their suffering feels like
our business right when you're a child right
the suffering of a parent has huge implications for your own safety it's
not really a cause for compassion their pain is
destabilizing it's a threat you know I I I don't know an
exact moment but I kind of remember the sense of
being you know a little bit shattered when I had the the kind of fantasy of my
parents omnipotence you know was um
dashed and it was like okay that fantasy crumbles and then
the recognition of like we're all this vulnerable
right and there's something like the echo of that
destabilization still haunt my love for adults now and their suffering does
something of that sort to my
heart and so there can be this deep wobble when we see loved ones in pain
when we see their Neurosis when we see them acting out their greed hate
delusion and just like goodness can kind of resonate with goodness we feel that
often we feel that in the Dharma field it's like oh okay yeah our hearts resonate we see somebody see the beauty
of someone's heart and it just does something to us and reverberates
and in the same way like two Bells resonating suffering can resonate with
suffering Neurosis can resonate with Neurosis something about what they're
doing uh lands in a certain way in my heart that spins me even more deeply
than if that suffering were purely my
own and researchers have done um you know brain Imaging when when you
know seeing uh a loved one suffer with some kind of pain task you know some modest
amount of of pain but partner's in the scanner you're sort of somehow
seeing uh a uh a loved one
suffer and a lot of the brain lights up regions
associate with with um understanding you know the the inner
states of others mentalization with emotional resonance some of the same parts of the brain that
would happen if if we were getting the
pain kisoro and um tanisa the the monastics for for many years many of you
may know them sat with them but uh I heard this this response of what what
you know what is it like to you know what is it like to be in relationship you're both uh these darma people what's
it like to be in relationship having been you know monks and nun you know for
a long time and I think Kitty soro's response was it's like relationship is like two
people under one robe two people under one robe they're
like very potent answer you know to recognize like okay
what what as a monastic was the okay I was working with this system it's now
working with two two people under one
robe and we know that seeing suffering in our own life can get us scrambling to
reorder circumstances and
when we see the suffering of of someone we care about deeply it's the same we
often have to like yeah we work with the impulse to like reorder them who they
are you know and compassion devolves in something like this desperation to
change them to make them grow this is not this is not actually compassion this
is a certain kind of compulsivity uh because I can see oh it's my aversion
or fear or worry or something is driving the show are they are they going to be
okay or or sometimes it's even more basic is like it's like is this who I
love you know we love other imperfect
beings right but at some level I think what I want in all of my relationships I
want them to be fully enlightened orats you know that's what I want from
everyone in my life me I can be just like a basket of defilements but you I
need you actually to be free from GRE hate and delusion then maybe I would not
be triggered you know that's kind of the
fantasy so we know we know when we respond to our own suffering
with that kind of desperate you know scramble it's often
unproductive and somehow it's harder to resist that when it's interpersonal
suffering and it maybe takes a kind of balance of of melting and freezing
melting and freezing what I was talking about I
think yesterday yday so we melt in the sense that we become clearly aware of their pain we
almost inhabit their mind this is empathic
connection but uh then we we then there's some freezing too there's some
freezing too so in the melting you know this this
um line that I I quote offering from a novelist who was ask you know if and how
literature changes people and he responded I don't think people change very much to the extent they change at
all it's because of some encounter that has love in
it people change at all it's because of some encounter that has love in
it we know it's hard to change we know that well it's hard to change it's hard
to grow at depth and if we're going to do it love will be
involved and the kind of cruel perverse irony is that the people we most want to
change are often the ones we're most enraged by even though we know anger is the
single worst way to get someone to deeply change we
might shape them moment but that's not a good behavioral modification program to run them on
anger and our judgment and harshness so there's love there's
melting but then we freeze too if their pain freeze in a good sense not you know
not in the kind of dissociative sense like freeze in the sense that if their
pain becomes pure emotional contagion it just spins us too
much and so there's some sense of boundaries too we care for the other as
if their pain were our own but without losing the as if condition Carl Rogers
said something something like that and so this is the equinity side of
relating to their pain to their Neurosis to their habits that they can't shake
out of This is Love in the face of helplessness I cannot rescue you from
this suffering I desperately want to I would even be angry if I could do it if the
anger would work but I know that's a dead end I
can't and so the equinity needs to counterbalance The
Compassion otherwise The Compassion can devolve into an insistence that someone
else change that's not what's called
for deep buing
acceptance we forgive which really means just
to understand to understand their inner life to open to our own ambiv that we
must tolerate uh the mixed feelings we have about any other person we must tolerate
that maybe there's some sense of loss of
grief and we open to that rather than the anger and the kind of pseudo
compassion which is often some attempt just to discharge the energy that feels
like too much for our system them can we soothe our own heart it's not
self-indulgent to move into some measure of self-compassion when you see the
other suffering because if we're spun our interventions
will always be misdirected and
so we tend to our own heart the deeply
evocative pain you know of witnessing a loved one
suffer and that love is soothing it uh
it weakens the kind of compulsive pseudo compassion compulsive interventionist
Spirit of our love lives with Partners
or parents or children or other loved ones
so again uh L Cohen uh I wish there were a treaty we
could sign I do not care who takes this bloody Hill I'm angry and I'm tired all the
time I wish there was a treaty I wish there was a treaty
between your love and
mine what would that be a treaty between your love and
mine in the realm of relationship uh that's a deep
question so I offer this for your uh consideration and
um we'll uh gather back to tomorrow uh tomorrow okay