hello everyone here and hello to people
online
so I thought a littleit abrupt for me to come out of meditation
and now suddenly have to
speak um
so so what I'd like to do today is to uh bring in a perspective
and orientation on our life or in our practice Buddhist practice from another
uh domain another field and that's often can be useful because it kind of you
know helps us to kind of see what we're doing in a new way whether it's looking at our Buddhist practice a new way or
whether independent of that almost looking at our own own life in a new way that's kind of the hope for this
talk and I like to think of that what I'm going to point towards is um um
the the depth of the Dharma but rather than thinking of the Dharma as something outside of you um
it's the depth of your Dharma or the depth that's potentially yours how to
understand yourself in some deep way and the orientation I'm going to
provide is a way principles or point of view
that chaplain use when they offer spiritual
care especially here in California uh chaplain who work in hospitals are
offering offering spiritual care to anybody who willing to or wants to have care for from them including people who
are atheists and non-religious and um and chaplains are
in California are are even though there might be Buddhist or Christian or Jewish
or Muslim chaplains they're explicitly working in the hospital as an Interfaith
chaplain so as an Interfaith CH chaplain you're not there to prze you're not
there to Pro provide people with the mean meaning of life that you have from
maybe your own religion you're there to discover uh what's going on for that
person in some deep way understand them deeply for for example in terms of the
meaning of life uh you might want to discover what is their understanding of the meaning of life or in what way is
the meaning of life for them been ruptured and their suffering maybe like in hospital there's they represents
someone who's maybe going through some tremendous loss sickness old age all
kinds of things can happen with people in the hospital and so it's ruptured maybe what was meaningful for them what
a meaningful life meant for them being debilitated maybe having their life
radically changed overnight and never to be the same again and so there sense of meaning has been
ruptured and so a chaplain is there to meet that and care for that without prosing without providing them with
meaning so this idea that there's these orientations that chaplain use used to
understand people deeply so that they can support people deeply in times of
great difficulty and so there are five paired areas that chaplins are looking
at looking at considering people that um I'd like to kind of present here for us
today and as you listen and think I'm most interested in is to maybe it
supports you to be able to or want to kind of look at yourself more deeply to
use these five categories to really look at how does this work for you and not
just your first ansers for them but uh there's the art of think well that's the
first answer but but you know if that's true what's deeper what's
more deeply true around the same category and keep kind of going down
deep so I'll say I'll list what these five categories are five areas they're pair pairs of things and uh don't try to
memorize them now because I'll go through them slowly and you can always go back listen to the talk if you want
to get all of them but now just listen and see what what uh what kind of seems
important for you to for yourself so the the the five pairs are
meaning and purpose agency and um
autonomy identity and dignity community and
kinship healing and Reconciliation and they're kind of in a
very interesting list they're kind of progressive in some ways where they could be seen that way
so the first meaning and purpose you know the big question is what's the meaning of life
uh a subset of that is what's the meaning of your
life and um and I would like to propose that everyone has some sense of what
their meaning of their life is whether it's implicit or explicit whether it's
conscious or unconscious and many people receive a sense of mean meaning of life what life
is about what's important in life to do and and and uh from their society from
their religions from their family in such an early age that people don't even know they're living that way it's just
like you know this is how things are and um and uh I saw that with my my children
they were quite young that uh how much I was acculturating them to a certain
point of view about what it means to be a human being what it means to be human being in relationship to other human beings at first I was a little bit
horrified you know to see see the conditioning we were doing but it has to be this way uh everyone has to somehow
everyone who lives in a society and a culture has to some way or other um have
a language to speak with people and we don't then they communicate and find our way and you know it isn't that you know
this two-year-old who's learning to speak um you know uh is being oppressed
because you know this the way English words are
spelled doesn't make a lot of sense you know you know I'm one of those
people who complained for 60 years 70 years about this kind of an inest but um
but you know you know you just have to go along with certain things so it with speaking people you can give you you can
communicate so things are passed on in a very early age and I saw for myself as I
started doing Buddhist practice that those layers of ways I was conditioned got uncovered and How Deeply it went I
can't tell you if it went all the way to the bottom but I certainly saw a lot of ways and that's why I so so so see it so
well what I was doing for my children and so I was conscious of it but I tried to do it responsibly and care carefully
and not to limit them but still I knew that you had to teach them language you
had to teach them how to be in a culture and in a certain way and um so but so what's the meaning
of life uh uh some people the meaning of life as I said and like in hospitals but
many places is unfulfilled they think that life has a certain meaning like to have children
and some women some people don't have children and their meaning is really ruptured
it's really painful because they grew up with that that was their primary purpose in a
sense for other people it was to fulfill their parents' ideas of what kind of
career they're going to have and that was the primary meaning which operated in their life some people uh without it
being called the meaning of their life it's um if you watch them you say
wow from all I can tell the meaning of their life is to
hate you know that's all they seem to be about and uh or the meaning of life is
to be wealthy to have desires and to have status and that seems to be what their life is about and but it's
unexamined and if you ask them you know what's the meaning of your life they might not be able to say anything deeper
than that that's the operating principle of what their life is about and um but is the meaning of life
to live in resentment is that what life is should be really about the purpose so
meaning and purpose are closely related uh many times so the meaning
gives us the orientation of what we want to do with our life what we want to accomplish and um and
so um you know is is life just about becoming wealthy is it is it more about the
quality of relationships that that there's love and community and that we support and are engaged in is life about
feeling fulfilled in some deep inner way that has nothing to do with material
well-being and status and these kinds of things and um so you know what's the
meaning what's the purpose and people who have no purpose sometimes find themselves disoriented feel lost feel
like they don't fit into society don't fit into this world they're confused sometimes they're depressed by it all
some people who think some one way something something of a particular is
Meaningful in a particular way and but they can't fulfill that meaning again it's very challenging for them some
people have a meaning that they thought was the purpose of life but something happened that pulled the rug from
underneath that and either they can't fulfill it or it doesn't make sense anymore um some people their their
religion they grew up with with provided meaning and and amazing meaning the people community people were all their
whole meaning of life was centered around the meaning provided by their religion but at some point they could no
longer Believe it or follow that and then they were lost like what do I do now how do I find my way so chaplain in
offering spiritual care are listening for this and they're not prosti they're not telling people what it should
be now as a Buddhist teacher I'm not a chaplain in that way so For Better or
For worse I'm offering Buddhist meaning and Buddhist purpose uh and uh but often what I try
to do when I meet with people is one-on-one is to listen first and foremost what the people I'm talking to
want what is their intention for their life and then see how this practice can support that in the appropriate way and
the exception for that is I'm also listening for suffering how's this person suffering and and is it there is
do I have a role to be a mirror for that or engage them around that and to support them around that because some
sources of meaning some orientation around meaning and purpose cause just more suffering for themselves and maybe
for other people as well and that's one of the purposes primary meanings that I
think Buddhists offer Buddhism offers and that is um that one purpose
of human life is find Liberation or freedom from suff
uing this can seem to be not so Grand or altruistic or something that other other
meanings could be but it's a powerful one for Buddhists The Liberation from
the freedom from suffering and it's not the end of it all
but there might be more meanings to it for example you could ask well that's nice for you and when your suffering
ends then what what's the meaning of life then and some Buddhists will say then oh the
meaning of life is to help you end your suffering or to help end the suffering for the people other people because part
of the meaning for life is that we are related to each other and our wellbeing
our purpose in life is also related to the well-being of those around us the purpose of Buddhist life is not
just to end suffering which seems like a neutral thing it's also to thrive in a
very deep way and the Buddha didn't use exactly the word Thrive because he didn't speak English but he there were
other words that he used that are related to the to how what we mean by the word Thrive to live in a sense of
abundance expansiveness and um and so the purpose
of life is to is to free this inner possibility from a Dharma point of from
Buddhist point of view uh it's the Dharma want to live in harmony with the
Dharma aligned with the Dharma but the Dharma is not in a book The Dharma is
something that lives inside of us and Buddhist since in the west we often say
that we want to so that you have a power you know power greater than ourselves you know
something you know we want to be aligned to higher P power is a kind of language
some people use I think the Buddhists would say something like I would say yes that's
great we do but the higher power that we can find is within
ourselves so it's it's not exactly us it's not exactly you but it's not apart
from you but it's this uh inner movement of something that can happen when when
something is set free set free from what set free from all the restrictions that
we live under all the limitations we put ourselves under and so this movement towards freedom from suffering is a
movement that sees and feels how we limit ourselves how we restrict ourselves how we oppress
ourselves um because that's suffering and so to
begin uh seeing and feeling oh look at that not only my suffering but I I can
feel how this is a limitation to my growth I see how this is a a um a not to
my growth but just limitation to how life wants to grow how life wants to be expressed the Dharma wants to be
expressed here and this thing that higher power that's within us is our own maturation or inner maturation growth
set free that we're amazingly capable of to live with tremendous sense of of
Peace of joy of strength of wisdom that it's very hard to take
personally and so uh so this idea of being free from then limitations and
restrictions ties into the next uh chaplaincy orientation and that is uh
agency and autonomy PE and this means that uh we're
not living under oppression not living under things that keep us in certain
kinds of prison restricted autonomy me autonomy means that uh in this context
is that other people are you're not controlled by other people you're not controlled by institutions that have
greater power over your life than they should have uh you're not um coerced
into living the way you want to live uh you are not oppressed and but you can make your own
choices you can follow your own guidance do what you want to do the
representation of of uh you know that represents this kind of restricted life is prison that uh it's awful to be in
prison so much of the autonomy is Tak taken away explicitly and I've met prisoners who
have all this kind of ordinary autonomy Tak taken away and they have more inner
freedom than many people who come to IMC it's remarkable to see where they
find their autonomy autonomy about what their inner life is about what they
choose to respond to and how they respond and they found a certain kind of freedom
to make choices for themselves that you can see and Fe look in their eyes and see what they
have and um so this idea so uh uh agency the ability to
act to not be restricted from doing what needs to be done so for Buddhists to
have some sense yes it's possible to be free it's possible to let this Dharma
onward leading Dharma move through me and grow it's possible to open my heart
in such a way that I can be of service to others or love others be connected in a deep way it's possible but I can't do
it why can't I do it well I have responsibilities I can't go on Retreat I
have you know to read the newspaper have coffee in the morning I can't
meditate I have I have no I have no autonomy
you and um and then of course you know so so then so there's these things that
keep keep us in check and so you know so we don't feel
like we can act do what we want to do me some people have responsibilities and families and and uh some things some
people feel like they can't practice because they can't go and Retreat because of family responsibilities and I tell them well I
learned maybe more about myself in the Dharma with the limitations of having
raising kids that I did on in monasteries I lived in it's a great
practice and in terms of learning autonomy learning agency and where it
really counts uh you know for me I learned tremendous amount under the limitations of
parenting that uh I wouldn't say it's like prison
but but uh but I do want to refer back to what I just said about these prisoners who
found the freedom right so if the prisoners can do it in that setting maybe I could learn something about it
in family you know maybe so
um so then so we have purpose me um we have um meaning and
purpose and then agency and autonomy and then we have um
um uh identity and dignity one of the ways that I
understand chaplains is that they they one of their functions of these hospital
chaplins or any chaplain I hope any human being I hope is um I've coined a
new English word um because I believe English gives
us that freedom sometimes I have loving arguments with friends about this you can't do
that um uh chaplain are dignifi you see I have enough autonomy
in agency that I can make up a new word dignifi and um and so they dignify other
people they bring out the dignity in people and respect them and honor them and value them people in our society not
enough people in our society are honored are respected in deep ways and sometimes when people are under
challenge like in tremendous difficulty in hospitals their dignity has been taken away and chaplain come and that's
one thing chaplain offer identity and dignity identity and worth and identity
is a kind of awkward thing for Buddhists to talk about sometimes unfortunately because uh
there's been a long history of this teachings of no self and you're not supposed to have an identity like of
identity let go and it's true there's a tremendous amount of letting go of
self-de of holding on to ideas of self that Buddhist do but
only when the practice shows us that the identities we're living under restrict
us limit us some identities don't do that some
identities actually do the opposite that kind of give us more space
so uh someone who is a calls themselves identifies I'm a Buddhist
practitioner well if they come and tell me that as a Buddhist teacher I say
great I'm not going to take that away from you that that teaches me it tells me that you have certain values and
purpose and meaning for your life of what you want to do with your life that I want to
support and if there's some attachment to being the pr practitioner which then
I'm not worried about it because the practice the mindfulness um the Dharma will show you
sooner or later where those limitations are and so that all that all comes out
in the wash and but identity is very important identity know means you know where your
place is in society you know how you fit in society how to find your way in society you know your place in your
family you know your role and roles are Maybe sometimes like hats you wear you
take on and off but still you know what hats you're wearing at any given time you know something about yourself you
know yourself well you have confidence in yourself you have understanding of
what makes you work you understand what drives you your your values your meanings your
purposes uh you have a clear sense of how you live in relationship to other
people and how to interact with it and how to care for yourself in relationship to other people all this fits under the
title of identity and many people are deeply challenged around identity some
people are challenged when the identity they had seemingly has been removed from them or lost or you know so some people
when they retire feel completely lost because that role that identity is no longer
there and um and so chaplains listen where's is that you know where is that the
suffering that people have and how do I care for that and meet that and support people I can't provide to anybody with
identity but uh chaplain listens to the suffering at least that's there because
and then sees what can support this person to find a new identity what can support the person to let go of the
identities that have been harmful for them no longer
needed so meaning and purpose agency and
autonomy identity and dignity and Buddhism is a lot about
dignity the some of you know that the the people who attain some degree of
Liberation in Buddhism are called the noble ones you know that's kind of highlights
this is important movement direction we're going and then there's uh community and
kinship and I think most people for most people we understand how important Community is family friends uh our tribe
our village uh the people around us that you know uh help our mirrors to help us
understand ourselves people who help us feel like we belong that we're connected That We're Not
Alone um many many of the ways in which we as human beings grow and develop um
as children is clearly in relationship to other people clearly in relationship
to our parents and we're we're ired for that relationship to affect us for a
lifetime and if that something goes a skew with a parent child relationship
when the child is Young it can be challenging for that child the rest of their life you know we call it sometimes
attachment disorders nowadays and if something goes well in that relationship
um the child feels secure in the world by feeling Security in their family in the first 5 years they're alive then
they go into they feel oh the world is a place it's okay to feel secure in and so it makes a huge
difference and so you know we we we learn from each other we influence each
other we're influenced by each other we um it touches something very deep inside
of us when I was walking down here to teach today uh somewhat narrow my house
is a is a house that I've walked by a lot and uh it's been being remodeled for
years and I I I it feels like almost like it's a hobby house for someone or they seem
to work on the weekends or evenings and they come with all their buddies you know it seems like just a nice time and
and they seem to be doing a really nice job with this relatively small wooden house so I've kind of admired what
they're doing and but this morning there was someone with a uh pickup truck kind
of looked like they were going to do some work or something and um so the first first time I said hello I said are
you working here and the person was a little bit cautious yeah
sometimes so I said I've been admiring this for years and it turned out that he was the owner and he's been doing it for
years and and uh and so we had a delightful conversation I appreciated his work I really appreciate how nice
they done in the house and appreciated his work and what he did and then finally he asked me what do you
do so so that's a little bit of a you know personal question right and and so
I thought what do I say you know what is this because sometimes I've told people what I do here in Redwood City like when
little league with my kids they're the Little League parents as soon as I tell them they walk
away Buddhist Buddhist teacher right or something so I said I'm a meditation
teacher because that's a little bit safer you know I I I could say I'm in
[Laughter]
entertainment and so um what i s meditation to he was like wow you know said you know so I can't you must sit
still or something and uh and so we talked for a while and it was kind of
nice and I and I told them that I've been a Buddhist monk for many years and
and um and he said you really must know how to be still I can't still still a I have to always be active and I said yeah
I you know I can be still but I love act activity too um I mean it's you know
that doing this kind of work you do is so much fun and it's engaging and I love it to do that kind of work and I used to be a farmer I said and and um so what
was I doing in that conversation so a number of things were happening community and
kinship first one that happened was I was walking down the street and I saw this man there and
and I thought I can't stop and talk to him I want to come down here and be here early at IMC so that I can be in
community and kinship with some of you and um but I could feel that the the
resistance I had to stopping the sense of like there's some other place to go didn't feel right that's where the
suffering was that's where the strain was I didn't want to live with that that didn't seem right so what happens when I
let go of it hi are you working on this house or
something I just kind of just s like the most natural thing in the world and that was the person of the moment to be in
community with and kinship with there was some commonality perhaps because of seeing that house for years thinking
about it just you know he's only about 10 houses away from me and um so it's part of my
neighborhood and um so it is that the meaning of life for me to connect to
people and Community I don't know if I would say that is it the Dharma in me that's
coming forth and being expressed I would say yes that's just life coming forth in
me and um and then uh I was in community with him and then I felt kinship with
him when he said he's you know has a trouble sitting still but he likes being active I loved it you know I thought
that's that's a beautiful thing I felt more connected to him and it's kind of kinship and I wanted to share that sense
of kinship with him with a sense that I too like to be active and to do work and
you know it felt wonderful to have that wonderful connection so by the time I was ready to leave he offered me his
hand to shake it and it was felt a wonderful little contact there and you
know a little friendly engagement and so community and kinship
is something that is a wonderful part of human life and that gets ruptured sometimes it gets broken it gets
challenged and and each of these five areas uh relate to each other they
influence each other or connect to each other and each of these five any one of
these five areas can be broken for people can be challenged could be uh deficient in people's
lives each of these five areas are ways in which Buddhist practice comes alive
for us one of the one of the answers to the
uh to the question what's the meaning of life is from I would say from a Buddhist
point of view the meaning of life is to be alive is to live and why that's a
significant answer and uh rather than you know kind of avoiding the question is that uh
Buddhists when we do this meditation practice we understand intimately
personally acutely how much we block our life how
much we restrict our living how attachments how clinging how fear
resentment even desires that we have actually limit us rather than having un unfetter
desires to use your your credit card as much as you want is actually a
limitation to be the most wealthiest person in this planet it and live just
for that purpose probably it means a truncated life something is blocked and
restricted and anyway whatever whether that's true or not we can to the degree to which we interfere with our life
being lived fully and freely that's something we can feel what happens when our when the our
life is being lived fully it's so then we can feel then we
can feel like this is good this is being alive in a way that's satisfying and
deeply meaningful there's there I don't know if it's a study or whether it's a thought
experiment but I've read about um comparing two people on an assembly line
doing the same mundane assembly line routine one person is
bored and the bored person their life energy is gets drained from them they the other person
sees it as a game how fast they can do it how well they can do it and just completely absorbed in doing it and
enters into a flow State and a flow state is a state of of
of well-being of joy of Engagement of self dropping away in a certain way and
it just feels so good to be in the state it doesn't matter that it's a mundane
boring activity from the external point of view just being a alive is so
great so this idea of the purpose of life is to be alive works if you believe that the
Dharma the Deep our deep self has wisdom and love and care and Community as part
of it and that's what we can discover when we do this practice in fact there's a tremendous resource within us that can
provide us with meaning agency
identity dignity Community kinship and oh the last one healing and
Reconciliation so some people that's their primary need at chaplain C uh in
the hospital or other places that all the other needs are what they are but the limiting factor for the person is
healing and Reconciliation and uh something is broken and healing is usually with
reconciliation was with other people healing is with something else with oneself or with what one takes as being
the purpose of life or the meaning of life for that which is Ultimate and
sacred and um so that's the task mindfulness can have a powerful role for
that mindfulness is a healing movement to feel and see where the break is and
allow the Dharma to move through Us in such way that a tremendous amount healing can happen from the Dharma being
allowed to move through us the heart knows how to heal and so we're allowing that heart to
heal through this practice so I'll go through the name
them again maybe as I name them this time why don't you see if any one of them might be kind of the one that's
more interesting for you to spend time considering me
meaning and purpose agency and
autonomy identity and dignity uh community and
kinship healing and
Reconciliation we could say these are needs we all have and is any one of them a need that
is more you oh today that's the one that seems up for me or it's just the whole
catastrophe so um so thank you for listening to this and I hope this kind
of gave you a different perspective especially those of you been coming listening to these talks Buddhist talks
for a long time it's a new A New Perspective to kind of look at yourself with and and maybe to have conversations
with friends so in about about um 7 minutes or so or 10 minutes
there'll be this potluck you're all here welcome to attend and even whether you
brought something or not where it doesn't really please don't feel like you can't stay if you didn't bring
something because that's not the kind of potluck we're at it just bring
yourself and um and since we're doing a potlock maybe it' be nice for you to say hello to people here uh just to break
the ice a little bit and um maybe just say hello and then you can go to say hello to someone or maybe find
out a little bit more about them or maybe um tell them which of these what
you thought of this talk in terms of your own life or which one of these five Bears was most interesting for you or
something as you wish but if you can kind of turn to two people next to you so that no one's kind of left alone kind
of looking well who's going to talk to me so thank
you