so uh so welcome folks good morning to uh to most of you not all of
you uh whatever um whatever time it is for you uh a warm
welcome my name is Matthew I know a lot of these names but
not all of them and uh anyway I'm one of the IMC teachers and substitute your
substitute teacher and happy to to uh be be with
you so uh we'll do that meditation thing now and
um and see what uh see what happens so uh please uh settle
in e
meditation is a way of being deeply honest with the
moment and trusting that in in meeting
the moment as it is uh the heart
unfolds trusting that uh the deepest healing does not
come from
pretending but from a kind of
fidelity to how life is in this moment
and so taking some Fuller
breaths breath that reaches down into your belly up into your shoulders
breath that says to some part
of your mind that doubts
it it's okay to be
here like this
now
for e
in the Deep habit of treating the moment as a kind
of problem to
solve we just uh
relax and trust that uh whatever the raw material of this moment is
whether it's uh Pleasant or unpleasant it all has equal potential to soften our
heart to wake us
up so we just relax into our life as it
is
through our
breathing
e
e e
it's almost like we use our breath to give us the the courage just to be
here so let your breathing animate the front of your
body but also the back of your body
feels like life is in front of us but it's all around
us bringing awareness to the back of your body
letting the movement of your
breathing Ripple through uh not just your torso
but through the lower half of your body
too e
our breathing can enliven what is numbed out and
soothe what's overactive
activated so there's a sense of our body
being unified by
awareness
e
e e
to solve our worries we have to
think but to dissolve
them we breathe and relax into awareness
we don't insist that the the knots and complexities the worries and the
problems untangle themsel immediately but there's a kind of trust
that our whole life looks different from the vantage
point of
Tranquility
surrender so we let our breathing ground us help us
sit more deeply in our bones
help us appreciate the subtle
soothing quality of
gravity
e
e e
maybe some place uh in your body the
your breathing is uh most prominent mouth or nostrils
your chest or
belly maybe a sense of the whole body breathing
but you can just take
refuge in this
moment
e e
and the nature of thought is they all feel somehow
important but we uh we come to trust that there is something
even more important than our
thoughts
e
e e
there's a sense that no matter how life unfolds what problems
get solved and which don't this
will have
mattered to have honored the moment in this
way to have developed a sensory
Clarity kind of refining the landscape of this
moment stabilizing the heart mind or
attention resting from the tussle with
experience this will have mattered
e
e e
for e
okay so um yeah good to sit with
you so a a friend uh a friend of mine described moving
from what she called uh egocentric life to to Dharma Centric
life and that that means that we're we're moving out of kind of narrow
self-referential existence so much of our existence can be
self-referential moving out of that into the sense of Life animated by Dharma
Dharma uh kind of infusing all spheres of our life and that of course
includes our um our relational lives the theme for this week interpersonal
life that uh a Dharma Centric life blesses the
relational realm in many ways we of course affect each other
right a life is many Ripples and a Dharma Centric life
perhaps we say ripples out uh joy and
safety and peace those are the ripples emanating from the Dharma
heart what um we might ask like what makes a life worth living
and there are many answers to that but one very good answer is other
people um Delights that are simply not possible in
isolation there's some help we can never
give ourselves there's some healings we need others for
Tony uh Kushner said um the smallest indivisible human unit is two people not
one one is a fiction from such Nets of souls
societies the social World human life
Springs the sense of of belonging of relatedness that's considered
fundamental fundamental in the sense that if it's frustrated we
suffer and how this practice is about perceiving ourselves perceiving our
minds clearly but how do we do that how do we actually see our minds our habit
energies how do we see what is not conscious to
us we we rely on other people we cannot see the back of our
head and so we need others to develop
wisdom I was told in the uh in the Quaker tradition that Revelation is never held
by an individual it is in fact a property of
groups I was always touched by that that consider like or maybe Enlightenment as
a property of the group sometimes I've uh thought that
one one aspect of mental health is something like the congruence
between self understanding the story we tell about ourselves and how a kind of
collection of well-intentioned people in one's life would tell the story
me how much does that do those converge between how I see myself and
and how a group of people of Good Will would collectively describe me or
you this interpersonal realm is uh one of
uh you know incredible humility and
longing and grief and ecstasy and courage and vulnerability and
shame and Grace and healing it is like many many Dharma themes in this
interpersonal life and as sometimes say that uh that
other people are are like steroids for our parames and our
kesas for our the beautiful qualities of our heart and for the habits that get us
into trouble other people act like steroids for those habit
energies and So Lisa the the brain scientist emotion researcher Lisa
Feldman Barrett says the best thing for a human nervous system is another human
and the wor worst thing for a human nervous system is another
human when I was like three or something
and my younger brother Gregory just learned how to sit up on
his own you know like had the whatever abdominal strength to sit up and we were
at some like I don't know family gathering or something and everyone's
cheering my brother on as uh he he's uh
demonstrating this newly acquired skill you know and
uh and I did not appreciate the relative
balance of attention being paid and uh I don't remember saying this but I believe
it I just whispered me knock Gregory down
and I ran tackled my brother which he was not able to sustain he was knocked
off center by that and uh still to this day anytime I'm being a little
domineering or something with my younger brother he just says me knock Gregory down you
know that's three I was like eight you know and
really kind of seeing the ibility and suffering of my
parents you know and uh kind of not being able to
stand it just spun me so deeply their simple
fallibility their inability to like insulate me from
dukka at 12 being like I don't even remember what but kind of heartbroken
over some social drama and I concluded I remember like oh yeah like the
conclusion in my young mind was like insecurity is at the center of emotional
pain it's the Bedrock as a teen being so angry and
having no idea no idea how to deal with it discharge it channel that diffuse it
and just spilling out you know exclusively within my family I sort
of managed it outside of the nuclear family but spilled you know
into uh home life in a really U profound
way at 16 not having had a sexual relation reltionship any kind of
significant romantic something and just like am I going to be okay like is there
something not okay with my heart and at 18 going off to to school
to college and feeling so um yeah just
intimidated by others and kind of quietly becoming more judgmental and
competitive and arrogant and we all have our our moments
and those are moments from what is a very fortunate life there are of course
moments of incredible cruelty and
danger so our relational life our life
is uh um is about sending and receiving
sending pain receiving pain sending
love receiving love
and so our practice must be a kind of relational practice
now and on the one hand it's important to have some aspects of of practice that
are untethered to any outcome we don't do it for any result we we don't do it
to get better to heal ourselves to be better neighbors Partners whatever it's
like no just for the richness of it just for the Delight of
it if this were the only moment there were no future I would want to just be
poised in Awareness but from another perspective
our practice is indeed dedicated to an outcome and the outcome is the welfare
of others that our practice be of blessing
in our life and
so we fold in you know this these
relational kind of question and Dynamics to our practice how how much have the
lessons we've learned on the cushion generalized to the interpersonal
realm right we we know like oh yeah greed hate and delusion those are dead
ends but all of the sudden often in the context of other
people they seem pretty appetizing right
when I'm alone you know my Neurosis doesn't bump up against other
things and then it does usually aided by
another and it sort of shatters some idealized Vision I have about myself and
I want to have Fidelity to those realizations when I teach or practice I I try never to
forget my freedom nor my suffering and the interpersonal realm is this Zone
where we investigate what aspects of our insight has stabilized and what hasn't
what's generalized what hasn't what have I
realized meaning like what parts of the teachings are
real not merely intellectual but like muscle memory they're real we see in the
interpersonal realm what's been realized and what remains slightly
intellectualized understanding of the Dharma this is a realm of um courage and
patience and self forgiveness and we approach it with some
wonder and freshness an opportunity to see our minds to realize
the teachings more fully uh with a kind of reverence for
what gets evoked in us what we evoke in
others and so as we we come to uh the end of uh our time this morning um we
the invitation is to something like investigate you
know what what happens to your mind mind uh
when alone when with others what gets soothed by others what gets activated
the Gaze of the other is a very reliable way of evoking the conial sense of self
what happens in that just notice with
care yeah and so um
we'll gather back uh tomorrow we'll uh sort of unfold uh this this theme
together and uh happy to to be with you and uh wish you a good good day look
forward to uh practicing together tomorrow