so uh so welcome folks good to uh good to be with you this evening
evening here in Berkeley
um yeah all right let's uh let's do that
thing that we do find uh
yeah maybe maybe take a little extra time to get into your posture whatever posture that is just get
uh feel good as good as bodies can
feel in a
posture e
and we're not just sitting
here we're in a in a
lineage kind of continuation of wisdom and love started long long ago
we don't have to invent wisdom or
love just T take our cues from the momentum of the
Dharma
e e
just let your whole
body settle e
give your blessing to every
imperfection there are always a thousand things right and a
thousand wrong we afford ourselves
the luxury of not needing to sort all of that
out so with a Supple heart we take what's
offered
e e
the less safe we feel more unprotected we
feel the more urgent and sticky our thinking becomes
so we relax our body relax our mind and attempt
to reassure ourselves our
system that right now it's safe
enough to let
go to fall into the
present
e
e e
h maybe uh we can say that all thinking is
coping coping with uh some
s coping with the intensity of being an
animal sentient vulnerable
but we practice knowing Pleasant is pleasant
and unpleasant simply as unpleasant
we practice listening to the alarm bells that go off in our
body but not over interpreting them
not reading them as alarm Bells but simply as
unpleasant a kind of sense of safety and seclusion
grows and there's less need to elaborate our
life to conduct our ritualistic safety behaviors checking on
this and that
we deepen our Peace by making peace making
peace with imperfection
e
e e
uh our thinking is so uh so
innocent how can we blame something that's been conserved
across eons of evolutionary time
but the silence beckons
us welcomes you with open arms
Just As You
Are
e
e e
okay it's good to uh good to sit with
you so uh Agnes card uh
quoted not so long ago um she says when you're feverish you're
not healthy and that you cannot engage in your normal productive function
something's wrong with you your body's arai fever is a form of
sickness but a fever is also a healthy immune response to the presence uh in
your body of some kind of infection if I lost my susceptibility
for fever that would be a sign that things had gone very
wrong it would be a way of getting sicker not healthier so while it is clearly not
quote best to be weak feverish sleepy and
incapacitated it might nonetheless be the best option on the table a fever is a healthy way of being
sick I have much the same view about
anger fever is a healthy way of being sick and the argument here is that
anger you could say is a healthy way of being
sick a healthy recognition that something of
value is under threat
and yeah I have of a
fever anger anger um is not Health it's not balance right
a fever is not Health but nevertheless a sign that our
body is trying to return to balance and
so uh I begin in this way just to to
note yet okay in me some fear some
anger and the anger and fear is set against a
much larger backdrop of love and anger may be a kind of um
important first word but anger can never be the last word a fever
in other words is not meant to keep you
feverish and if we truly care about
suffering we give love the last
word if we've seen deeply enough into Patia Samu conditionality this is
because that is or that was this is because that
was if we see that clearly enough we give love the last
word if we've known fearlessness the jewel of
mindfulness we give love the last word
in the penumbra of cessation of
release not even um a trace of fight
left just peace we give love the last
word and in times of of hate um we
become even more acutely sensitized to
love when you touch into love you know the tears shed
testify to a kind of heart longing you know the pain bound up in
fear and hate and helplessness and so the tears they
they're like a kind of emanation of our own longing to move back towards love to
move towards Health the fever to
break and so I I will not tell you how to love but merely note its
necessity the the question how how should I love that that um that never
gets answered that never gets answered the people who think they've answered
that question stop growing spiritually
ethically how do I love that is not a question it's a
Coan aito uh domination talking about
domination so not love uh domination is in fact the thing that
needs to be fixed it's based on an unawakened response to uncertainty and
diversity the ignorant chitta heart mind reacts by demanding hard and permanent
Solutions fixed boundaries and simple strategies that will defend it against changing
conditions that it can never control cultivate investigate purify and
release the chitta from self view has to be the starting point when you enter your true territory
the domain of heart Consciousness you get the message in your intimate territory
control and domination don't work you can't even control your thoughts and
emotions you don't even own this body here there are no hard borders
everything permeates you from the air you breathe to the memories that well up in your
mind you have to cooperate forgive and allow inner
changes that defy your identity you learn to give up craving
for simplistic Solutions and fixed positions instead there can be an
acceptance of life's uncertainties and frustrations rather than feeling threatened by them as we stop projecting
our personal failings and dissatisfactions outward we see otherness as a basis for increased
understanding and even wonder a love based on the Miracle of sharing life
gets born and a relationship based on Harmony rather than
coercion the great Conquest then is over self view this has always been the
teaching of the way of the supremely awakened ones
an un awakened response to uncertainty
diversity We Want U predictability understandable we want
the known but there's uh so much aliveness
in not knowing in newness n said that um truth is a
portion to one according to their strength and maybe we say wisdom is a
portion to one according to their comfort with not
knowing in your intimate territory Aang goes on
to control and domination don't
work don't work uh we have to discover that a million times
on our
cushion when we start to release the territory we call I me
mine is it its own kind of claim of ownership and control and
Dominion but
um that doesn't work it's an
illusion we release the territory we call I Me Mine my country my country I'm
a US citizen well yeah country is not
self empty my home my Earth even Earth
not self the world trembles in all directions the Buddha
says we have to take in the implications of
that and knowing that brings some relief maybe a
lot and all the suffering still matters it's not blotted out but it matters in a
new way and what is left in the wake of this
Letting Go a love a love based on the Miracle of sharing
life love based on the Miracle of sharing
life and so between between everything means
everything and nothing means anything we
find our life the kind
of middle path between frenzy
nihilism and this um this miracle of sharing
life uh that um leads us in into
uh a lot of uh yeah giving love the last
word sort of like the the urgency of care
compassion so flipping through um Shanti Deva today and uh saw this line May um
May no one who encounters me ever have an insignificant
contact oh how beautiful is
that to live for all of us to
live the sense of uh yeah may my life
bless this world in its beauty and Brokenness
so I offer this for your consideration and uh I'll be back next
Wednesday again talking in one way or another about uh
love okay folks