hello my friends and it's uh special for me and maybe all
of us to gather for this meditation thank you for being
here so today I would like to associate
meditation with something that perhaps is seldom seldom associated with but I
think that uh we many of us at times will
definitely bring this quality to it and that is
courage meditation sometimes needs courage it's often associated with meditation about being calm relaxed
unassertive being um quiet
peaceful uh and so so and maybe also with associated with being
um um
um maybe even kind of dsel or something but uh sometimes we need to
have courage and sometimes a lot of courage and
uh certainly the courage takes a lot of courage in life
to sometimes be ethical sometimes they take courage to
not give in expressions of hostility or
anger not give into strong compulsive desires that we
might have and that can play out in meditation as well that uh we take our
place and show up to be be here in a clear and courageous way so we
don't give in to distractions we don't give
into um the distractions that keep us from recognizing what's really happening
here in important ways that we don't uh give in
to um uh avoid the difficult emotions that
we have but to show up to our grief our fears our even our
angers to really be honest about them and show up and take our place in the middle of them sometimes we talk about
sitting in the fire when meditating so we have I have behind me a
statue of the Buddha the night of his Awakening and his posture that's
dignified and upright is a posture Ure that represents taking one's place in a
dignified clear complete way that you're allowed to inhabit the place where
you're practicing like you can be there you don't have to diminish yourself or apologize for yourself or and to and to
show up and uh the part of the uh imagery
symbolic imagery that you see there is that he's touching his um uh the Earth
he's touching the spot in which he's sitting and so for you to touch the spot
where you're meditating yes here you will be and you'll show up courageously for what's
here and not the kind of Courage that makes you agitated makes you tense but
actually the opposite sometimes it takes tremendous courage to be relaxed be at
ease in the fire with the difficulties courage to stay in your place stay
present stay here not giving in not collapsing not
running away but staying here with what is and sometimes it takes courage to do
that even when things are going really well in meditation because of the strong desire to to enjoy it to like go into it
in a way that we're not really that
present so to take a
posture that for you is a posture of relaxed
courage a certain kind of relaxed strength
yes this is not a casual thing to sit down
to meditate it's a heroic act in a world
where people succumb to Greed hate and delusion all the
time and to assume a posture that for
you allows you to have a heroic stance in showing up here really showing
up here for your experience mindfully with clear
awareness and closing your eyes and feeling that
posture taking a deep
breath relaxing relaxing but not giving away
your strength your courage
Your Clarity of purpose that here you will
be as you exhale relaxing
around that Clarity of purpose that yes to being here in the
fire in the winds whatever you have here through
earthquakes just sitting
here not in contention with any
anything and not in favor of
anything with an impartiality to Pleasure and Pain to
success and failure just
here and every
breath is propelling you into through the ocean of
here bringing you back here
now and if it makes sense for
you to have the courage for an ongoing relaxed
awareness of breathing of your
experience of meditating in the middle of your place
here with whatever is happening stay staying present awake
clear courageous to do
and then as we come to the end of this sitting to
consider that in a world with there so much hatred
animosity divisiveness
greed it takes
courage to be compassionate to be generous to be
kind to be honest it takes courage to stand in the
midst of of Injustice and name it as
Injustice what how is it or in what way might the courage to
meditate translate or be applied to the
courage to live in our life
in a fuller clear honest
way and to have the courage to be
kind friendly
generous to have the courage to wish people
will to want the best for them knowing
that the best the very best is to live
without any greed hatred and delusion that's where happiness is
found so even to your enemies you can wish them well
sincerely and maybe show up in a
way that you express nonh hatred non-
greed non- delusion the
courage to avoid those things may all
beings be the recipient of our non greed our non hatred our non
delusion our non-bias and Prejudice may all
beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and may we live today in such a way that in small or
large ways we contribute to that possibility even if it's just for one
other person may all beings be
[Music] happy
thank
you
so welcome this is the second talk on the five
faculties and when we translate this word poly word indria as faculties we
are kind of um diminishing
or hiding the power of the word indria the
strength of the word word The Faculty just seems like oh it's just like a
potential that we have maybe we have a faculty we could use it the word um means of Indra Indra was
in the time of the Buddha the the head god of the pantheon of go
of gods and maybe in ancient Greece it would you would say like you know
qualities of Zeus or in Norway qualities of of uh of
um Odin or some great God and
um the um and so these are qualities and
the and the reason then they qualities that of of um that uh can take charge
can really guide and help us to take control in a certain kind of way of our
life in in American Buddhism it's the controlling controlling ourself has
often seem as as not appropriate but there is a way of it's
very appropriate to show up and really take charge of our practice in a in a in
a certain way we have these faculties we have these capacities that really Infuse
and enliven and give strength to the practices we do and there's nothing
wrong with doing Buddhist practice strongly calling upon a capacity for
inner strength maybe even a capacity for inner power and it's uh strength and power
that can support us to live without hate
without greed without conceit without asserting
ourselves or wanting to dominate other people or be
aggressive not but a power that also keeps us from being being weak or
succumbing or collapsing or running away and so this word indria is a
powerful word as is the word that's usually transferred as effort the second
faculty Viria but viia also is a powerful word and that effort kind of
just uh domesticates it in some way or or temps it down just makes it kind of too ordinary and doesn't really uh carry
with it that uh in the Indian context is a word of power or strength and um and
so in the ancient India and Tibet uh this word sometimes is associated with
being heroic heroic effort and for today I was associating with courageous
effort and there was a time in American Buddhism when I was growing up in Buddhism where and my when I first
started teaching that um uh chances are I would have been criticized as a man
using languages like courage and hero her heroism because it's would seem like
too masculine or too something and certainly there can be problems with it
huge problems with it but also it's a gift it's it's a necessary part of life
is to have a certain degree of heroic effort so that we don't give in to
our own personal Tendencies to be weak or to be complacent or to be to eques to
our attachments and our clinging and our um
aversions the courage to not give into the five
hindrances and so this severia again translated as effort heroic effort
uh uh is the uh is the corollary to uh the second hindrance
which is ill will hostility aversion and um and and then uh the
connection between the two where they the bridge or the meeting ground of the two why they're Associated is that um uh
ill will has energy in it has power in it anger especially has tremendous this
power uh uh that's kind of bubble up sometimes I can feel a volcanic the way that anger is moving through
us and um but if anger has ill will with it then um uh it takes a kind of hero
heroic effort to not give into that volcano uh in a way that causes harm the
heroic effort to avoid any causing of harm that's the heart of what this her
heroic effort courageous effort is in Buddhism Not to cause any harm
whatsoever to oneself or to others and so the um so with uh the the
energy of anger the idea is to uh have
the to channel that energy don't don't give up the energy of anger unless it's
just over the top uh energy engagement that Vitality that's there um is part of
the reason some people like their anger they can make them feel alive but if we could take that sense of
alive energy and let go of the hostility but keep the energy of anger
then it's available for heroic effort powerful like yes let's not yell at
anyone let's show up let's be present but and not be hostile with our body our
speech or our mind and uh and to do that towards ourselves not to have any hostility
towards ourselves uh not to succumb to these forces inside that uh debilitate us uh
deprive us um harm ourselves so to have faith the first
um uh of the five faculty or confidence is sets us on the course
of practice we know something about practic this is what I want to do this is important and the second effort heroic
effort is like be serious like this is what I'm going to do this is not like
you know with the faith there's no doubt with faith there's Clarity
confidence yes I want to do this it doesn't mean that we are in a hurry or
that we strain or that we put ourselves in a situation where we're going to be
discouraged by our you know that we can't we're not making
progress but an embodied way of saying yes I can give myself to this these
values this way of living this approach to life that I'm going to avoid any
causing of harm and to do that heroically with
courage and um and sometimes the forces of distraction that we're practicing
with in meditation are themselves a running away it's a comforting avoiding
of what's really happening here for us and it's kind of harmful to do that to
avoid not show up honestly for ourselves and sometimes meditation practice is
sitting in the fire is showing up for what's very difficult here with us and learning how
to metaphorically stay still take our seat be in the middle of it and not be
overcome find in a sense uh some Inner Strength Stillness inner
capacity to stay with what is very difficult rather
than getting distracted and if uh Things become uh
quite peaceful and wonderful in meditation and uh it seems like that
kind of heroic effort is too much probably that's true that
effortful heroic effort maybe it's no longer needed maybe it's still
heroic um I've been in medit I've had experiences of meditation where I became
very very peaceful and coming out of meditation I had to had uh courage and a lot of
confidence or faith that it was okay to stay peaceful when all the people around
me were kind of insisting that I should join them in their anger join them in
their uh condemning people joining them in gossiping joining them in greed and
and um Behavior which you know is not uh harmonious with this deep settled
feeling of peace and so it's kind of a heroic thing to say this is where I'm going to
maintain this peaceful inner life and be present for what's happening here but
I'm not going to uh succumb I'm not going to give in I'm not going to give
it up and so to uh so faith is what begins
the practice confidence we have confidence confidence this is a Way Forward even if we're going to experiment even if we're unsure where
this Dharma practice goes but we are willing to give it a try there that's
some indication of some degree of confidence and what follows that then is
uh is really kind of if you're going to do it you know do it with some
commitment do it with some strength do it with some courage uh not anything that causes you
to be tense it's a the courage to not be tense the
courage to engage in a peaceful way and as I keep saying the courage to
be nonharming but to show up with
embodied energy an embodied Vitality where we take our
place the Buddha took his place the night of his Awakening and the classic
statue that uh as I just that just like behind me the Buddha Knight of his
Enlightenment is touching the very ground upon which he is sitting in a
sense asserting this is my place doesn't have to give in to his
forces of greated hatred and delusion that assailed him on the night of his Awakening but he stayed upright still
courageous unwilling to give into it unwilling to collapse unwilling to run
away but to sit there and be present really present here and
now so I hope that uh this talk on courageous effort has hit the right spot
that it encourages you to
um to be encouraged you know the word encouraged has the word courage in it so
it encourages you to have some courage some strength some give yourself uh to
not necessarily kind of what you know the practice in terms of meditating and
what you do but rather the courage of how you
are certainly practice but practice be courageous in how you
practice um and in such a way that um it helps you to take refuge in Your
Capacity to be peaceful at peace and a
Emissary of Peace in this world so thank you very much and um
tomorrow we'll do the faculty of um mindfulness
Sati