so I'm seeing as I sit down getting ready to teach here all the chats that
offer such wonderful greetings both morning greetings and seasonal greetings and uh it kind of
makes me kind of feel H kind of very happy and delighted
to for to be able to be here sharing this time sharing this purpose for we're
gathered here and thank you for being here um so in the way that this was
going to unfold here this week the different forms of love that get
emphasized in Buddhism Monday I talked about anukampa
the word I translate as care yesterday meta which I mostly translated as
friendliness and today we have the word uh
karuna which is normally translated as compassion and um so this is one of the
inspiring and beautiful qualities of the heart but it's kind of a mixed thing
because uh compassion arises is born from the experience of suffering in this
world and so the idea is to hold them both
to hold the the suffering of the world and
and then maybe simultaneously to hold a certain kind of profound sense of goodness within us
which is compassion compassion free of fear free of distress free of feeling
helpless or hopeless compassion that can flow freely
uh as the simple wish the aspiration I love the word
aspiration because it's connected to the word for breath respiration in
Latin um the simple aspiration the and profound aspiration
to uh wish others well wish others that their suffering might end that their
suffering might dissolve or pass past for
them and for me in um uh in my early
years of doing Buddhist practice uh it was uh not
intentional that I sat with my own suffering I knew I was practicing to
come to an end of my suffering because but um but what
I uh what I was taught to do was simply to be present for it
and then not try to fix it not try to understand it and not try to dissolve it or not to use not to use an
antidote but just to be with it and uh and to learn how to be with it really
simply and the effect that had on me it uh it it was it it tenderized me it
softened the edges of the suffering soften the reactivities I had to suffering soften the second Arrow that
were added on top of the first and that process of softening
tenderizing then started to not just be on the edges but started to penetrate
into the suffering itself and that was what uh began to
dissolve some of the big sufferings I brought with me to the
Dharma and uh so there wasn't like this you know rapid end there wasn't like
this magic Insight that suddenly now I'm free of suffering but there was a thawing of it
the melting of suffering and um and so learning how to be present for
suffering is in fact part of what the Dharma is but how to do it
so it doesn't undermine us how to do it so we don't get depressed or feel like
we're suffering more and how to do it with faith and confidence that that it's actually very
wholesome there or there is a very Wholesome Way of tending um maybe in a friendly way in a
caring way to our suffering and one of those is in fact to
um to um meet their suffering with
compassion to recognize in us that there is the desire to have it melt to have it
go away way to have it not be there not out of aversion not out of
desperation but rather something deeper than those in the heart it's the heart's
song the heart heart sings compassion may I be free of suffering
May others be free of suffering and in that way it's actually
possible to connect uh compassion to a kind of a Joy
or kind of a something really good within us and have that also
spread so I'd like to offer you uh a form of practice that I call um
practicing the cycles of Dua and Suka uh the cycle of just like there's
the U water cycles in Environmental Studies or oxygen Cycles so there are
the cycles within us of Dua and Suka of
suffering and happiness and to they can coexist in a beautiful important way and this is
somewhat like tongling practice in Tibetan Buddhism and um and it uh but it's the
the cycle goes in two different directions uh when we're feeling our own
suffering then in the in the exhale uh
uh exhale let it flow out of you and not into the world but maybe up into the
space let it flow out of you and uh and then on the inhale um the
um uh and and in that flow and then they inhale feel the happiness feel some
well-being feel the joy or the goodness or the rightness of just being there to
feel the suffering so feeling happiness some kind of Happiness as you breathe in
and then sending the suffering out as you breathe out that's one direction of
the cycle the other is when uh you feel pretty stable and somewhat uh resolved
in some of the deeper uh scars we might carry because we don't want to activate them more
there comes a time when sometimes we can do it the other way this is more like tonglin where we we actually imagine
ourselves breathing in the suffering of the world we receive it because it's
really helpful for people to know they the others know their suffering are witnessing their suffering that they're
not alone in their suffering and then on the exhale to um to uh send out your
joy into the world so when it's your own suffering to
breathe in joy and happiness and exhale suffering out when
it's the suffering of the world breathe in that suffering and offer out to the world your joy and
happiness so if you'd like to do this if it feels appropriate for you you can do
it I'm not going to lead you through it uh it's because I I don't want anyone to feel like they have to do it but if
you'd like for this sitting today you might try uh these two cycles of duka
Suka Suka Dua so to assume a meditation
posture and part of assuming a meditation posture is in a subtle kind
of way organizing your body so you're beginning to P gather
together all the different parts of your body so that they work
together part of the reason to relax the
body is because it helps that bringing it together Gathering it together into
one organized Cooperative
body and feeling the body more broadly as part of this Gathering organizing of
the body taking a few long slow deep breaths
a lengthy
exhale and in and then breathing in deeply and
exhaling fully feel your
body to see if anything can be shifted in your
posture so your body is more aligned
more in harmony with
itself then letting your breathing return to normal and centering yourself on your
breathing where the rhythm of breathing in and
breathing out is like a gentle
massage or the gentle lapping of waves up upon the
shore and then to in you in this simple way and if you would like if it feels
right to you you might
practice the Suka Dua
Cycles breathing in feeling Joy breathing
out spread sending out your suffering ing out of
yourself or if the opposite is appropriate breathing in
suffering sending out
joy
e
for
for e
as we come to the end of this sitting to appreciate that while we
meditate when we feel
suffering when we have compassion it's not necessary to
understand it the way we're present for it can be
much
simpler we offer our pray presence to it we offer to be
present and are willing to be open and
receive whatever it's like to feel and sense and know
suffering but in not knowing it understanding
it without judging it it or making a story about it it might make it easier not to be
stuck in suffering or stuck in
Joy but rather have it move through
us so it's not exactly us but it's not not us it's just something that
moves and as we end this sitting that
movement can be intentionally inclusive of all
beings wishing that somehow this practice we're
doing will serve help us serve the
world to reduce the amount of suffering the world has to increase the amount of happiness
and joy
so without understanding just letting it
move on the inhale breathe in the suffering of the
world and on the exhale breathe out whatever Joy
well-being you have give it away
don't hold on to your own Joy let it go out into the world in such a
way in such a generous way that it generates more
joy breathing in and the suffering of the world breathing out May all beings be
happy
breathing in suffering and transforming it
into may all beings be
safe breathing in suffering of the world and letting that inspire
and Inspire dedication may all
beings live
peacefully breathing in the suffering of the world and
exhaling may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
hello and welcome to this third talk on the aspects of love the different forms of Love or flavors of Love
or qualities of love and for me I kind
of feel that the first one I talked about the simple sometimes quite humble
care to offer care um makes the others a lot easier
makes the others less likely to be something we latch on to or get attached
to that it's just simple care that gets expressed as friendliness or care that
expresses compassion provides the love the friendliness provides the compassion
with a little bit of ease or openness or
maybe in some ways supports it from being too heavy and certainly compassion can be
heavy can be a big thing can be overwhelming at time but that's because it's not only compassion we feel
compassion in my understanding I don't want to make a claim for everyone but my
understanding is compassion always has something light something feeling
rightness to it even with there's pain with the compassion it's all happening in a field
within us in a heart within us that feels this is it's good given that they're suffering there's a rightness
there's a goodness to to feel that
pain and for some uh sometimes compassion is held up in Buddhism as the
the most important social emotion and some and sometimes that can can feel
that way or it can be that way when we realize the magnitude of suffering in this world and um one of the ways to
understand the magnitude is not to read the newspapers and see how big it is in Somalia and Gaza and
Ukraine and around the world certainly that's
huge but understand that uh in your own mind
how this a percentage of the it's the way we think has stress in it has
suffering in it and then we realize these ordinary ways of thinking that has some kind of tension built into it
unnecessary tension unnecessary Dua uh if this is true for me then it must
be true that the level of suffering is so much faster than I ever thought that
human beings carry with them every thought they have sometimes is comes with stress comes with fear comes with
aversion comes with greed and um but to encounter the the
Nority of it all and have a humility or simp it in it
uh to not be the savior of the world not feel like we have to be responsible for
fixing all the things but to do something much more profound and that is to be there to
witness the humanity of others who are suffering to
witness it and listen to it and be present one of the big um moments for me
with compassion was uh in the early 1980s I was living in the monastery deep
in the mountains and we didn't get news very often but one day there was a I think it was a Time Magazine appeared
and I opened it up kind of randomly and there was a multi-age spread and
discussion about the Israeli bombing of refugee camps in
Beirut and um and I'd been to Beirut as a child and I'd lived on the edge of the
m Mediterranean growing up good part of my growing up and so um right next to
the right next to uh what now Yugoslavia town called triesta in
Italy and um and uh and so to have to to kind of
witness through these photographs the suffering of these refugees and the and the how many of
them died uh deeply moved me and one of the strong EST feelings I had was I had
to go there we had to Bear witness how important it is to Bear witness and let
people know that they're known of course we should do things as well but that was
such a big I didn't feel like I I wasn't motivated to leave the monastery the work I was doing there felt very
important but this strong urge and um it was very clean and I've learned in
looking at Compassion myself that it's not always always clean uh it can be
burdened it can be entangled with shoulds ideas are shoulds and shouldn't it can be entangled with uh a necessary
burden of sense of responsibility that I have to fix it that I have a
responsibility that I'm somehow un unnecessary degree of of kind
of being attached to it or or reacting to it or and adding levels of attachment
that take the form of Despair or discouragement dis stress or fear or
anger and um when those when those movements of the heart involve
increasing suffering we're actually um causing harm to the
suffering of the world we're adding to it we're adding to the distress we're not showing or meeting things with the
alternative a different way of doing it and so uh some people have a lot of
emphasis on empathy how important empathy is and I think that's depending how we what
we mean by that word empathy is really important but if EMP empathy is feeling
what other people are feeling uh in exactly onetoone correspondence I don't
think that's necessarily healthy um if someone else is suffering
if I'm suffering I don't want someone else to suffer the same way I am to feel my suffering and suffer the same way
what I'd like is someone recognizes the suffering maybe something inside of them are is
moved that in that um they feel a certain ache they feel a
certain heaviness or seriousness or they feel something that tells them yes this
is a human being suffering yes this is unfortunate yes uh I have some sense of
what you're feeling I I know that you're suffering but without taking it in
myself so if anything uh other people's suffering go through me I I feel it and
allow to change me and motivate me and and feel compassion but it doesn't stick
in me it doesn't it doesn't become more complicated so a big part of Buddhist
practice mindfulness practice is to disentangle compassion disentangle love
from all the ways we get stuck with it all the ways we get caught in it and tighten around it all the ways that we
suffer because we love we suffer because we have compassion because somehow it's
gotten mixed up with other things so to sit in in mindfulness meditation is part
of this disentangling learning where the stress points are where the tensions are where
the extra arrows are where the belief systems are that are all added on top of
this Simplicity of compassion so that compassion can
shine and when compa compassion becomes cleaner and that way or comes simpler
that way then acting from The Compassion is much less tiring then if we act out
of compassion together with all the attachments and fears and entanglements
we might have so one of the great tasks of a human life is to clarify clean out
out love clean out care and compassion so it becomes clean and direct and
simple and see it as part of it is not just certainly not just the empathy to
feel someone else suffering the key component of the form of love that is compassion is in fact the desire the
wish the aspiration that others do not suffer and it's good to act on that
sometimes strong compassion um is difficult because something that aspiration that wanting
to support and help has been bottled up there has no Outlet we don't know what to
do there's always something we can do it might not be for the suffering we we'
encountered in the world but maybe it's local so one of the things that I do when I read about horrendous things in
the world is that there's too much of it for me to think that I'm going to make a difference I can't give enough donations
to all these different places to help but I take it in and the aspiration to
end suffering is stronger because of it and then I try to do my work as a
Buddhist teacher even locally better I I'm more motivated to do what I do and
that's where it's channeled into doing this for other people it might be channeled into caring for their
neighbors or having more care for people their colleagues at work and might be
that they have a particular cause that we're motivated to support and so experiencing suffering elsewhere and
feeling compassion that aspiration to end suffering gets channeled even more
into the cause we already have so
compassion as a gift to the world compassion not as a drag because it's a
drag if we're caught in our attachments and it makes our life harder and more difficult and we're overwhelmed
but to um but to uh have the gift of compassion for this world we know
that the world needs it and get and compassion can be a
present and if that's too difficult or nots
clear then uh being present becomes the present that we can offer being
attentive being standing being present in a full
way may that be the present that you offer this world on this day that's
often for many people associated with giving presents so thank you very much and
um and I hope that uh uh you spend this
day um stay close to either care care
friendliness or compassion as what is needed and tomorrow we'll do appreciative Joy thank
you