so good morning good day everyone welcome to this Monday and I'm happy to be back after
having a two week vacation which is uh not so
often that I do something like that with my wife and um did a lot of
hiking and uh now happy to be here
so um
many years ago I met a monk in Thailand I was staying at a
monastery and um he was somehow known for his great
meditative accomplishments very deep practitioner and I met him and there was
something very special about looking into his eyes and seeing both this something had never seen such depth in
someone's eyes and such peace and um so I asked him what had he
attained in his years of monastic practice and his answer surprised me
given how the buildup of this is a person of great meditative
accomplishments and um maybe attainments and he said he had attained
not nonc contention and this was this was said in
Translation so I don't know what the PO exactly the tie word was but the translator said nonc
contention and that uh really made a big impression on me and one of the first
times that I was being introduced to this Insight practice was at that Monastery and so the here's idea of
non-c contention and the way that uh it's been
for me very inspiring to practice mindfulness for all the different
purposes that mindfulness can fulfill or can address and one of them is this
ability to uh sit with ourselves and not make anything worse simply to sit with a
respect a non-c contention a feeling the tremendous
value of non-reactive attention non-reactive clear
seeing that something very profound begins happening when we can see clearly
without being for and against and reacting not making it worse with our judgments just seeing clearly The Good
the Bad and the Ugly clear
seeing and just that is enough but then to learn that clear
seeing can lead to to freedom freedom from the reactivity freedom from our
attachments that the clear seeeing begins uprooting so many different
things ways that were attached and clinging and holding on and Afraid and resentful
and and these slowly maybe sometimes quickly to begin to fade and we find
ourselves free of these afflictions that can follow us for a lifetime
and so to see and know that this is the purpose of mindfulness this is the
possibility this is how mindfulness provides a tremendous sense of
meaning and to take it further and to realize how this non-c contentious
attention this freedom from Affliction allows us then to enter into
the world in a deep way in a friendly way in a way that we don't
lead with fear we don't lead with aversion we don't lead with desires and
and uh wanting things from people but we lead with love with care with kindness
with respect so I mention these because one way to sit in mindfulness is
to really appreciate the value of mindfulness the importance of
it how meaningful it is and not perect purposeful it
is to awaken our inspiration that kind of fa faith that
is energizing us yes I will do this yes
I want to be here and inspiration yes this is important so that the other
things we're inspired to do with the mind to worry to be anxious to review the past to spin out
in fantasy that they don't have as much get
as much energy from our ourselves fuel from ourselves because
the fuel the energy of our life is inspired to go into
mindfulness so to assume a meditation
posture and to
now maybe not close the eyes right away unless you already have but rather to lower your
gaze and allow your eyes to be
soft soft eyes that may be gently float in the
sockets not fixating on anything not stuck on anything
soft eyes and now perhaps to gently close
your eyes letting the eyes be soft
gentle and taking a few gentle deep breaths just deep
enough so so it's not uncomfortable for you you so it's enjoyable for you to breathe
in
deeply exhaling as you relaxing as you
exhale and maybe in the way that you soften your eyes as you exhale
softening your body maybe softening the edges of where
you're tight
frozen stiff
and then letting your breathing return to normal and on the
exhale softening in the face around the
eyes on the exhale finding where there is softness in the
face and let that spread
and if there are places that are not soft it's okay let it be held in
softness on the exhale softening in the shoulders
on the exhale softening in the belly
and on the exhale softening in the mind as the Mind
softens maybe there's more space to be
inspired more space for faith in being present here and
now e
as you exhale to soften your
heart so that more of your life energy the energy of the heart
can be inspired to be attentive here and
now and then settling in in to be here and now with your
breathing having the breathing being at the center of all
things even if other things require attention breathe with those
things the massage of breath
the word inspiration is related to the word
respiration stay close to your
breathing so you can be stay close to your inspiration for being
present
e
for
for for
remembering to come back to the present being reminded by what inspires
you to be inspired to be here and
now
e
for
for e
and then coming to the end of this sitting to
consider in ways the ways you understand the value value of
mindfulness the value of your practice of
mindfulness in the way that you relate to other
people how does mindfulness support you in being present with kindness
respect care love
honesty generosity
wisdom equinity so many things that can come
from the practice of mindfulness what is it that it comes
from it for you what might come for it for you today
as you go about your life with other people with strangers with people you
know
how are you inspired to bring M
mindfulness into your social life
today and may it be that you're able to do this may it be
that your practice of mindfulness this morning that our Collective practice together as a community
Community combines to bring a tremendous amount of good into this
world tremendous kindness respect care
love
honesty may all beings be happy may all beings be be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free and may it
be that our practice supports us to contribute to this
possibility thank you all very much
[Music]
e e
so hello excuse
me hello everyone and welcome and
um I have a little
me I seem to have a little heness and um this
morning possible from traveling yesterday and possible from allergies the last week or
so team s that goes away usually goes away after a while in the
morning so um this this morning being Monday I'd
like to start a new series of teachings and I'll do that for the next
two weeks week so it's a 10p part series and it's um 10 areas of
reflection for a Dharma life and so each of these days we'll be
giving one of those 10 and I'm hoping that the words I say
will uh inspire you to think uh reflect on these
Concepts uh I'll be offering my own ideas uh about these concept Concepts as
go along but I don't want to offer them as being the definitive presentation this is what these things can be but
rather I want to uh bring up some things that you then will reflect on on your
own and and come up with ideas for yourself how it works for
you and um this these 10 qualities these 10 Reflections are being uh uh um
adapted from uh my studies of chaplaincy spiritual care
that's done in the world of chapy of hospitals and prisons and all kinds of other places that chaplain work and
chaplain have a particular orientation especially since they're Interfaith chaplains they're not looking for
particular uh religious ideas but they're looking for
Spiritual qualities or characteristics that are Central to people's lives that
they want to address because often chaplain are meeting people at times of Crisis personal and family and social
crisis and in times of Crisis something is often broken something is really challenged for people in their spiritual
life in their personal life and so these chap chaplains can have sometimes these
10 different areas that they're paying attention to to see where is something broken where is something need to be
healed or worked or understood or reflect Ed on in a deeper way and I find
it very useful to take these 10 qualities from chapy and address them to a Dharma
life and so I'll try to do that for these uh two weeks and as I said hoping that you will
reflect on them and make them your own or see how it works for you so um uh these 10 are are really
five areas that each area has two qualities two characteristics I'll briefly do the five the 10 today
and then um and then I'll will uh go through the each one
today so when we're divided into just five categories they have to do with
meaning with a uh agency with
identity with community and with healing and these five uh I've
associated with with uh uh when they're when these go well when these are healed
or resolved or developed well for people um they correlate to five positive
emotional states and maybe you'll think about the correlations and come up with
different ones for yourself but for me I was thinking that the meaning corresponds with
inspiration agency corresponds to Freedom identity corresponds to
confidence and Community corresponds to love and healing corresponds to
wholeness and of being whole so uh each of these five then are
are divided into two so meaning with to the world of meaning is added the idea
of purpose meaning and purpose to the world to the world interesting I use
that word here here this world the world of agency uh is added the idea of
autonomy to the world of identity is added the concept of um of um dignity
value worth and to uh Community has added the
idea of kinship and to um healing is added the
idea of reconciliation so uh it begins with
meaning and I probably in my history of my his personal history with Buddhism
especially with Zen starting off in Zen Buddhism I would say that I had a kind of a challenging or difficult uh
relationship to the idea of meaning I I probably thought that it was
overlaying some concept some something on top of our direct experience and I
was more interested in just showing up and being Pres present for things as they are not adding some some things on
top nowadays I think that's still true that's inv valuable to show up for things as they are but part of how
things as they are is meaning that meaning isn't an overlay
meaning is its own thing that the the UN meaning meaning has to do with value
what we have most see is most valuable uh with our values the values
we live in organiz our life by the the orientations that uh that we organize
ourselves for deciding how we communicate with other people how we relate to them relate to
ourselves that uh all this fits under the category of what do we find is the
meaning of our life where do we find meaning for what we do why do we do what
we do and I find um and in my zenier years
I avoided the word meaning but instead I used the word intention and uh I think that the word
the meaning and intention don't have to be so separate where we have meaning we find intention where we have intention
there is something that has meaning or importance for us and uh and I found in
my studies and myself for my intentionality that there were layers
and layers of intentions that I might have an a surface intention and I
wouldn't stop there and say that's the intention I would keep looking what's was there something underneath that what
fuels that what fuels that um what is it that's most important here what's the
most important fundamental intention that's the intention prior to all the
others what do we hold most important in our life what is most meaningful for us
is it family for some people that's most important is it uh a sense of
contribution contributing to society is it personal fulfillment is it
having fun and Adventure is it um is it
um um understanding and Truth discovering and
learning I don't want to High make a hierarchy of one of these being more important than the other but I want to
give you a sense of possibilities that different people for whatever reason for the personality the way they were born
born the way they they're raised by their culture will have different things that they hold as being important as
being meaningful meaningful enough that they want to live by it it guides them for how they want to live their life
guides them for what's important and to do and what they want to like to do and when there's no sense of meaning
when something is meaningless people get depressed people feel a sense of hopelessness and feeling lost and some
people have done things which seemed meaningful certain phase of their life but as they got older didn't hold any
meaning anymore and the certain work certain uh um um things that we were
pursuing um they they kind of we were kept doing them beyond the time that
they were had any value for us and so there was a sense of vacuity or
emptiness or lack of energy or inspiration around doing it
so when there's no in Inspiration is it because something about what's meaningful for us has been challenged
what's meaningful us can't be fulfilled we can't act on it or what we have been acting on for as being meaningful is no
longer meaningful we feel deeply betrayed and discouraged uh We've devoted oursel to something we thought
was really meaningful and then we found out the people involved somehow were um
weren't what living up to what we thought they were or the whole thing was kind of a a facade
or didn't seem to be what it promised to be on the surface and
um and so get they be discouraged and what was meaningful is no longer meaningful and the sense of meaning the
sense of how we organized and oriented our life is no longer being supported
and then we have to look around and see what what is what can I rely on as being meaningful as having meaning
so humans there's a tremendous amount of human suffering around the topic of meaning and there can be a tremendous
sense of inspiration and joy in finding meaning and having meaning uh there are people who go
through tremendous crisis in life who when they have a meaning that they find in the middle of it can go through it
with confidence and success uh there was a Victor Frankle the famous book he he uh
he wrote uh Man's Search for meaning uh was inspired by his experience in the uh
Nazi concentration camps where he had observed that the people who uh had some
meaning about their life in the concentration camps the prisoners that that was enough to keep them alive or
keep them going and the ones who had no meaning whose meaning was destroyed or lost they're the ones who most likely
were going to die in those circumstances I probably didn't say it just right but
uh the point being that um meaning uh is a real what really can
animate a life and help us through tremendous challenges in our life
tremendous uh difficulties that otherwise would be discouraging we can
stay inspired if we find meaning what's that what's the meaning in it and for in
Buddhism uh there's tremendous meaning in finding uh practice mindfulness
finding a path knowing there's a path a tremendous meaning in not succumbing to
hatred and to Greed and to fear not be over overwhelmed by these kinds of
forces there's a just knowing we're in a path to become free of those we don't
have to be free of them but just knowing we have a path that's so meaningful that leads to freedom from being
uh oppressed by ourselves um and uh and at least not
find um uh add our own
suffering uh our own contribution to suffering to the difficulties of life it's like that we can become
free this can be tremendously inspiring and can help people go through
tremendous difficulties and we'll see later as we talk about autonomy and the agency how
important this is as well so for today it's meaning we I would like to propose that
uh human beings have a tremendous need for meaning and
meaningfulness and um even people who don't recognize they that in themselves
it with a deeper reflection you probably see that there's something that or around which they organize themselves
that's has to do with meaning so what is your meaning where do you find meaning what are the layers of
meaning that you have layers of importance of what you really want to organize yourself around the values the
sense of purpose the the um how to be in the world the why to be in the
world so that's my proposal that those of you who'd like to reflect on this and
think about it for today next 24 hours and you might want to uh write about a
little bit if you person who likes to do that something different happens when
you write about these kinds of profound things and then go back and read them that allows us to kind of reflect even
further and deeper and deeper or to have conversations with friends around this topic of
meaning and then uh we'll continue tomorrow thank you very much