so welcome welcome back we'll continue today the third day
of this exploration of the five precepts commitments that allow us
to uh find greater freedom in our daily activities focusing on five Realms or
Arenas in which we can avoid unskillful action avoid harm cultivate skillful
responses and today we'll focus on the third
precept the uh abstaining as a way to support practice from unskillful
expression of Sexual Energy it's the way I'm going to capture it for the moment before we meditate and we'll talk a
little bit after the sit uh about ways to ways to hold ways
to think about the the uh idea and definition of the third precept
so let's settle in for a set and because I think it's a useful support for
exploring the third precept the guided meditation
will at least it's the intention that the guided meditation will will focus on
balance that at least is the intention going in we'll see how that how that
comes up so taking our meditation posture settling the body
into posture that's comfortable and at ease but also
alert easeful energetic posture for meeting our
experience posture that balances alertness
energy attentiveness attuned Attunement
with an attitude of being open to what comes
up we can bring the eyes down if that's comfortable closing them all the way if
that's supportive and if and as we bring the eyes down or
close them we can lean into the rebalancing that
happens naturally with that movement moving away from
the visual realm
to the inner life the inner world
we can feel a similar rebalancing if we bring the attention in and down inward
into the body downward
from the Mind into the
body and here too can lean into that
rebalancing even if it's early morning for us
walking around with our eyes open we may find ourselves already just a little out of balance it's useful to
notice the rebalancing that the meditation can
provide we can bring our attention to something in our experience in the meditation the breathing
that has within it for the vast majority of us in most cases has within it a Natural
Balance when we connect our attention with the breathing we're connecting with
a phenomenon in our experience and our bodily functions that's naturally balanced
can settle in with confidence connecting with the breath
and feeling the way that the breath knows what
the appropriate the wise the skillful amount of oxygen needed
is and just how much waste gas to expel with each out
breath and today as we engage in this exercise this practice
of bringing our attention repeatedly back to Here and Now connecting over and
over again with the breath we can be aware of this rebalancing that happens without any
effort we nudge or gently pull attention back to the breathing when we find the
Mind caught up in thinking we can do it without hurry without
judgment and we can notice the rebalancing the world of
thought so attractive with all its Pleasures with all its Delights and with
all its with all its anxious
meanderings we can notice is sometimes a place of unbalance
we find ourselves a little off balance as we return to the breath as we
open back up to the breath bringing the breath back to the
center of our attention we can notice the sense of
coming back into
balance just a balance that can have both thought and ease in
it it's a place where we can rest the Mind by connecting it with the natural
breathing balance
each breath offers an opportunity for balance and
rebalance just this breath no need to be concerned about the
previous
breath the breath itself is unconcerned with the next breath doesn't need to plan doesn't need to
fret whichever breath we find ourselves with when we return to the breathing bring the breathing back to the center
of attention this is the right breath this is the breath where balance is available
and it's okay to wobble it's okay to get off
balance much like riding a bike pushing a scooter or even
walking we rebalance connect with the momentum of the breathing
and like those activities maybe the rebalancing can also be
pleasant of the enjoyment that's available in the
meditation this lovely feeling of rebalancing again and again
this is an enjoyment this is a pleasant this is a pleasure
even that the Buddha has encouraged us to cultivate not to
fear but to lean into this natural balancing available in
the meditation is a safe place to enjoy ourselves
enjoy
e
e e
so as we bring this meditative
meditation period to a close we
can return to this exhortation to enjoy this enjoyment this pleasure that
comes with the meditation doesn't need to be
feared it doesn't depend on external conditions it's free
and it allows us to develop a wholesome relationship with
enjoyment we can let it come and go and because sometimes our enjoyment
of things is sticky we get
entangled we can in dedicating Merit today make a practice of letting it go
by wishing it to others may all beings know some of this
pleasure may all beings know some of this enjoyment this free
contentment may all beings no ease may all beings be free
from suffering
so welcome
again greetings
so we'll explore today as we have been in brief
fashion with a focus on actions instead of actors with a focus on mental
action another of the precepts today the third precept which is a commitment to abstain
from unskillful expression of sexual energy or unskillful
entanglement with the enjoyment of sexual
expression the wording we use to capture the third precept can be really important in guiding us
and I like this idea that just came up in the meditation that the uh that the enjoyment that we
experience can be experienced in a a free way in the
meditation and that it can the meditation has a place in helping us understand how to how to
respond skillfully or in a in a with a wholesome mind state to the enjoyment
that is a natural part of
living sometimes householders lay practitioners like most of us here think
that monastics have it easy and in regards to the third precept um
monastics at least uh uh have a clear
rule to abstain entirely from sexual relations for the lay practitioner it's
quite a bit more um complex again it's not a commandment it's not a rule that
we abstain from sexual interactions uh and yet it's a it's a it
can be a commitment to be attentive to the way that we react to respond to the
enjoyment and pleasure that come up in our in our sexual behaviors our sexual
expressions the uh we can expand the definition in I think some useful
ways from the focus on sexual
which in many cases implies social that is interactions with other people to
include uh aspects of expression of sexual energy that is private or
erotic in nature rather than social or interactive and in some cases the
precept is expanded to include our interactions with all sensual Pleasures
not just sexual pleasures among sensual pleasures and uh this is the in in a way the
literal meaning of the phrase that's used in poly to to express this
commitment to abstain from certain behaviors and it might be a little too
broad but as we'll see in the daily suggestion for a daily practice today
that sensual pleasures of lesser sorts or less heady sorts or less complicated
sorts whether that be you know chocolate or
uh another pleasure you encounter today um Can again give us a a small thing a
little thing to practice H with how we how we respond to pleasure signals in
the brain how we respond to enjoyment uh things so in the case of this
precept it can be useful to invoke the other four precepts two of which we've
already discussed and two more of which are to come so we can ask ourselves for example
with the first precept does this uh sexual activity in which I plan to engage am engaged or have just
engaged is it does it cause harm physical harm to myself or
others we could also say does it cause cause harm to a
relationship to harm to myself harm to others harm to
both in regards to the second precept which we discussed yesterday does this
sexual activity involve taking something that's not freely
given I suggested yesterday that a valuable practice is to watch the way we use the
internet and this is a this is a place where there can be entanglement for some of us around things not freely given
that find their way into our expression or our enjoyment of Sexual
Energy in regards to the fourth precept um which we'll get to
tomorrow which involves avoiding unskillful speech we might ask whether
this sexual activity this sexual interaction this uh expression of sexual energy is
deceitful does it involve for example uh keeping making something Secret
instead of just making something appropriately private and again it's a way of asking ourselves learning more
about how we're how we're responding to uh an action of of sexual expression
or enjoyment and the fifth precept the one that asks us to abstain from what I've
called intoxicated heedlessness we can ask and sometimes it's useful to ask whether our
entanglement with the pleasure or enjoyment or expression of sexual energy
is uh is compulsive or uh
is um avoidant or leads to
heedlessness again a way of querying quering our action so aside from the kinds of harms
kinds of harm that might be um referenced in each of these
uh ways of applying the other four precepts it's it's useful to just bring
to awareness that it's not pleasure or enjoyment of sex or of erotic activities
that's that's problematic it's rather our relationship with that enjoyment or that pleasure how
we respond to it how we get entangled in it or whether we can remain free of
entanglement with it the the pleasure we experience this
is true for all beings I think I can say that pretty broadly that um pleasure provides one of
the most important signals to the brain to the being and it has a very
um very forceful influence in in our lives and so learning to work with it
seeing it not as a problem but as something where we can problematically respond to
it helps us forward and this practice this practice of mindful attention to
what's Happening Here and Now that the Buddhist Traditions give us uh can be a
very valuable way of helping us meet this Universal
experience so we can't expect to make problematic pleasure go away that's not
how it seem in the Buddhist uh view but rather we can we can definitely develop
skillful ways to meet what is very likely to come up in in our
experience so we can notice the stickiness of pleasure stickiness of sexual
enjoyment and useful to notice that it's not inherently sticky it's the mind that
gets stuck to it it gets snagged gets entangled gets caught
up the sticking to it or the entanglement the knottedness in
it and also the selfing around it right some of the shame or guilt or all the
sorts of things that the Mind adds unhelpfully to our experience and alternately the sense of power or
arrogance or superiority that can come with uh responses to
pleasure and we can bring these kinds of ways of responding into our practice
they're not separate from our practice they don't have to exist in some different world that we can make them part nothing as Gil as Andrea fella the
co- guu teacher of IMC say you know there's nothing that uh is outside the
realm of mindfulness there's nothing we can't bring this practice
to so we can let our growing understanding that develops with the practice of our minds of our
hearts when they feel closed when they feel open we can let those U that
growing sensitivity or Attunement let us help us understand what forms of sexual
interaction enjoyment might best be refrained from
and those which we can enjoy without uh without entanglement or without harm to
ourselves or others we can start to look to it the
attitudes we have toward these activities and again our practice can help
us notice how physical desire how pleasure in the Physical Realm the
sexual realm um which which activities actively
support practice which attitudes toward these things are a support for our practice these are precepts that in
encouraging us to obstain from harmful activity support our practice and this is true here too that we can actively
contribute to creating stronger relationship stronger connection with
others we're with ourselves with our own natural um our own natural patterns of
arousal and expression of
pleasure this is a nice thing to keep in mind just kind of tumbled over this
right now but this is a good reminder that these precepts are to support our
practice so we bring our practice we bring these these aspects of life into
our practice instead of keeping them apart so what might this mean for what
to do what kind of things we could engage in today and I think a couple questions like we've sort of proposed in
previous days might be useful in this realm this Arena this kind of heady
space of the enjoyment of physical activity that's sexual or
erotic I think a good one might be something like um how fully present can I be in this
experience how mindful can I be here David said gills said Andrea fella this
is I hear it in Andrea's voice says there's no place mindfulness can't go right there's no place outside it it's
never it's never too small so what would it mean to ask uh or what value might it
have to ask how mindful can I be of what's happening in this in this
expression of this Natural Energy in this enjoyment can I be fully present
that's a good signal if I can be fully present there's some wholesome response to uh what's
happening another similar one is can this pleasure can this enjoyment and I
like by the way I noticed it in the meditation that enjoyment for me the
word enjoyment I should be clear lands in a different way than pleasure a lot of associations with the word
pleasure when I think about it as sexual enjoyment or enjoyment of you know
natural sexual sexual um interests activities Expressions that come along
with having being born in a human body being born in any body um enjoyment somehow helps me
lighten up a little bit around it I don't know if that's true for anybody else but here's an encouragement to find
a word that helps support your practice so can this enjoyment be skillfully held
can I enjoy it and not add a lot to it you know can I enjoy it in a way that's
not causing harm and then um maybe let it be less sticky maybe when it causes
no harm it's less sticky so
like uh I think the first day when we talked about ants here too it might be
useful to start with something uh very small and here there might be some
utility in a broad definition of the third precept that focuses on sensual
pleasure pleasure of the senses rather than restricting it to sexual pleasure a good way to begin with
our uh relationship with the pleasures of the senses would be something that
is perhaps not as heady as a sexual sexual activity
but maybe maybe comes a little bit close I mentioned chocolate at the outset I guess for me that's that's something
that can bring a lot of delight a lot of enjoyment and also can be kind of sticky I don't mean literally on a warm day
like apparently it's supposed to be in California today looking at the chat but rather um I can get I can start to get
wrapped up in wanting more chocolate wanting better chocolate cholate wanting my friend Kirsten's
chocolate um so choosing something small that for you has enjoyment and has
Delight in it and then watching how present can you be right can the
pleasantness can the pleasure can the enjoyment whatever word works for you to support your practice can it be
skillfully held and perhaps can it be let go of you know could it be shared
with others in a way that helps um skillfully hold a
pleasure so that's where we'll leave it for today really appreciate everybody checking in I'm distracted a little bit
like by looking down and to the side at the at the chats as they come in and it's really lovely to see uh See people
exchanging well wishes and checking in may you be well till
tomorrow and uh maybe find some some wholesome some skillful light and
enjoyment in the day um we'll see you tomorrow morning take care till then bye