so hello a warm hello from Redwood
City warm hello from
this maybe in certain kind of way at the center of this wonderful online community for
these this gathering for meditation and teaching thank thank you for being
here and
um so today I'd like to uh make a very important distinction for in mindfulness
practice and that is that um there is an important
distinction between what we
see and how we see so to take it literally with seeing with our
eyes that um you know we what we see we could see any object at all a mountain
in the distance a person um some delicious food that's in front of us
that seems appetizing whatever it might be something unpleasant something pleasant
something neutral there's the object and then there's a wide range of
ways that we the ways we could see it the what comes along with
seeing uh there could be seeing That's goes comes along with fear and so the
eyes are part of the scanning for safety scanning for where the danger is and that's the
orientation there could be seeing that's uh oriented towards what we want our desire and looking for what's good and
wonderful and what's in it for me there's the we can see through the
lens of what we don't like aversion what we want to say no to what we want to
pull away what we want to resist we can see through skepticism and
cynicism we can see through hatred we can see through uh intense infatuation
and and uh craving and so the way the eyes work
varies and what the eyes see how the ey sees varies we could be uh staring at
something intensely with anger and people feel the the heat of our the daggers in the eye
we can uh gaze at something lovingly and kindly and people feel the warmth and
the kindness so there's all these different ways that we can see in mindfulness practice we want to
recognize how we're seeing and learn to
see uh in a way that's free seeing that's free seeing that's
freeing that liberates seeing from all this extra baggage that goes on and so
we can see clearly directly open
ly where we free the
seeing from entanglement with what's being
seen so that's kind of I'm talking about it more literally but there's also seeing with the Mind's Eye there's
knowing we all the same thing applies to how we know how we're mindful
H and and uh and as important as sensing
is really being embodied really being embodied feeling sensing what's going on there is also a
distinction between what is being sensed and how we know it how we see
that and so in that it's in the how that we find our
freedom not in the what so whatever you know whatever you
see that can answer the question what is it that's not where freedom is founded
so it's not in a particular experience a particular understanding a
particular something that we see but rather it's how we see
and this means that if something is uncomfortable difficult if we're
suffering there's the art of where we find our freedom is not by getting rid
of the suffering per se but rather learning how
to see it freely see it so we're not for and
against it caught in it and um and then we see better as long
as we're caught in something we don't see it really as it is if something is really wonderful and
where it brings us happiness that's wonderful but the art of mindfulness is
to see it in a better way a more satisfying way than seeing it with the
happiness it's seeing it with Clarity and openness there's a higher level of happiness that comes when the seeing is
free so if this makes sense to you then we'll we'll do maybe you can follow
along in this guided meditation today so to assume a meditation
posture and to kind of just maybe Rock back and
forth sway the body a bit in order to kind of feel the moving body
as a invitation to feel your body to be in your
body and then gently to let your body become still a soft
Stillness not held or
tight maybe do the same thing with head just let the head rotate
[Music] around move back and forth gently not
too much but feeling little bit loosening in the
neck and lowering your gaze so that you may be feeling a little
bit softening and relaxing in the eyes
and softly closing the
eyes and without doing anything
else Softly
Let the Body let your body feel the movements of
breathing how does your
body how does your body experience breathing
and then gently not too much just a little bit
deeper breaths so there can be a little bit more
Fuller sensing of your body on the in breath and a little bit
more opportunity to relax the body on the
exhale without
ambition content to do this in small little
ways for
and then letting your breathing return to normal and then in the rhythm of
breathing in and breathing out kind of riding on in breaths and out
breaths movements of the body feel the body and relax the
body softening the
body e
and if there's any way that you can also soften the thinking
mind without a lot of ambition small little micro
relaxations on the exhale Relax The Thinking
mind maybe imagining that the Mind expands and spreads out
horizontally like a lake that spreads wide and the waves quieting
down
for
e for
and then to Center yourself again on the
breathing the body is experience of breathing for
and then become aware
notice how you're mindful of breathing
is there any strain in being mindful
any attitude that comes with being
mindful any belief that's coming along with being mindful of your breathing
on one hand there can be a straining and a trying
hard and another hand there can be a complacency or boredom
or indifference
that's being added both are being added to the Simplicity of being
aware there can be tension with being mindful
there can be a for and against the
experience and if mindfulness is a kind of mental seeing knowing of
experience can you experiment to see if the knowing the
seeing p simple clear
open just mindful just aware of what is of
breathing without a for and against without an attitude
maybe you can have this simple clear
awareness in one part of the cycle of breathing where you can see and
recognize that there's no interference nothing extra just the experience Maybe the
transition from in and out breath out and in
breath maybe at the beginning of in breath beginning of our
breath so the how you're
aware is not adding anything more than just being
aware that in the how you're aware there is some simple maybe
humble feeling of
freedom freedom from what is being
experienced awareness independent of the breathing but that knows the breathing
knowing or a seeing which is radically
simple free of ideas of what it means to be seeing
or be knowing just whatever
way it simply occurs on its own if you're present
if you allow breathing to be present in awareness
how simple can The Knowing
be and knowing or seeing a
mindfulness or a how we
are is free knowing freely
knowing freedom in The Knowing
itself
e
for
e for
and then as we come to the end of this sitting can you imagine or
visualize someone that you trust
seeing you looking at you being with
you without any projections without
any for and against without any a agendas or desires or
aversions but the person sees you as you are and it and in being being seen
completely as you are the warts and
all you feel that the person accepts you as you
are but an acceptance which is not a thing to
do an acceptance is like how the Wide Open
Sky accepts a bird flying through
it and can you imagine yourself gazing upon someone
else kindly gently friendly with an awareness that
otherwise is not for or
against an awareness that sees clearly and accepts the
other with an acceptance which not a thing to do an active acceptance but rather an
acceptance like the vast Sky accepting the bird that flies
through it
may it be that our ability to see and know
others where the how we know and how we see has an element of
Freedom we know with freedom knowing is not burdened
by beliefs and attitudes and
judgments to see clearly
freely and out of that seeing May there be
born kindness love care
so from the depths of our being we wish may
others be happy May
others be safe may others be
peaceful May others be
free and the how how we know them how we're with
them offers some of that may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so hello and welcome to this fourth talk that's focused
on the I I believe the very significant practice of not making it
worse if um if that's all we do
we be make a much better world and
um so and how we're talking about it is with taking the word worse and turning
it into an acronym and so if you want to practice
not making it worse then there's these five different ways of steps to how you
can do that besides just doing nothing so this way not making it worse
actually makes it better actually enhances something and allows something
more significant or profound have a chance to arise and happen in the
situation that couldn't happen if we just Barrel ahead and just do the thing that makes it worse that expresses the
anger or um acts on the greed or acts on
um bias and
so uh so first is to wait if you feel that okay I I don't I'm going to about
now to make it worse I'm going to create more division separation divisiveness I'm going to uh give this person a piece
of my mind so that they feel lousy and belittled or I'm going to you know uh do
something that I know in the past um makes me feel lousy afterwards
um and so I know I know this make make it worse and
and yes I know an alternative I know something something to do in this
circumstance I know the specialness the wonderfulness of pausing and
waiting wait wait just wait a little bit a sacred weit a momentary
Sabbath a generative waiting let's let wait make room for something to happen
here and be known and then um to organize to orient
yourself to bring yourself together pull yourself together because generally if we're going to make the situation worse
we're probably not all of us present we're probably caught in some desire
some aversion some fantasy some thought construct and so wait so you can then
feel and bring yourself together open up to feel your body and give Time by
feeling your body for different parts of your body to come together and contribute to the whole to settle
down and then um uh rest
relax find a place of rest find a place to relax to pause in a deeper way where
the bodies are kind of at ease so you're not struggling to hold
back from blurting out the thing that's will make it worse and then uh now we come to the
S and uh the S uh has two things as well uh first is to
sense take time and this is like where the where you harvest the benefits from
waiting getting organized and resting or relaxing is now
you're going to be now you have greater capacity to tune into all the different
ways in which the body your physical body um can sense and feel what's
happening there's a tremendous amount of information in the body that reveals
what we're feeling what uh what's what we understand what's happening around us
um the body helps us to understand our environment helps us to understand the
people we're with and what we're doing the the body sometimes has will understand and feel the tension in the
room maybe sometimes faster than um the thinking mind so if we're caught up in
our thoughts and ideas and what we want to say we might not really sense and feel the tension in the room or the or
the or the suffering that someone has or or the the uh nervousness that's there
or the joy that's there or the all kinds of things that we start becoming aware
of so to sense and we sense what's happening with ourselves more deeply the
um the um um you know uh that there's a depths
of attitudes of response of emotionality of of um
layers and layers of how we're responding and reacting based on our history and our experience and our
deeper beliefs and so a lot of that information is starts becoming more
available if we take the time to sense and feel and the more we practice
embodied mindfulness slowly slowly sometimes over years the the deeper the
sensitivity is in the body deep to sense and feel so much of what is carried in
the body um if we think the body is senseless it's senseless it has
no sense to be in the body um then it's true then we're not there to pick it up
the sensations but the body does have sense both in the sense that it has
Sensations and we can sense things but it has sense in terms of it has meaning it has purpose it has information it has
all kinds of things that's there that we can discover so take time to sense What's
Happening Here what feel your way into it what's happening you can overdo this
sensing uh and only be in your body and and then not get and that also can be
limiting to the the whole and that's why the other s for uh uh for This Acronym
is to see uh and see with the Mind's Eye and this is a little bit more active than
just sensing perhaps there's an intentionality to let me look here let
me look more closely What's Happening Here uh now that I've paused and gotten
more present and have sensed and um and relaxed um let me look at the situation
let me take a new look a fresh look at the situation that I'm in uh take a look
at my myself maybe I need to really pause for a moment and step aside and
understand myself more deeply what do I see what's going on here what can be named
seeing clearly is closely connected to being able to name something sensing can
happen without you know the the words or the naming or or uh cognitive
understanding but the seeing at least in uh mindfulness practice is closely
aligned with close to a kind of cognitive clarity about what is
happening it doesn't have to be words it could be a kind of wordless knowing
cognition but there is a kind of clarity so we start looking and seeing where's the what's happening here and that could
be the situation around us we we choose to okay let me look at this these people
are talking very loudly and now that I've kind of settled down and not
yelling at them or not overwhelmed by it all uh now I'm in a position what's
happening here and we're looking and we're seeing what's happening here what's going
on and um and the um said take time to
take take time to see I'm just what's coming to mind repeatedly as I say this
is uh the example of my one of my sons
when he went to uh kindergarten he went in and a lot
of the kids in the kindergarten already knew themselves but he didn't know anyone and as far as we know what he
what how he responded to being in kindergarten the first I think a couple of weeks or three weeks um we don't know
think he was afraid or nervous or or uh challenged to be there but he did
something very unusual um he got one of a teeny little kids chair that they had there and he
put it right in the middle where all the action was in the school in the classroom and he just sat there for you
know two three weeks just watching all the kids watching what was going on and uh and then eventually he got off
the chair and then he started participating and engaging and but uh he just first want to take a good look
what's happening here and understand it I guess and understand the people and who they were and
and that was kind of so to see to really take a deep look and see what's
happening here and um and then that gives the
opportunity especially if you're a mindfulness practitioner to see how we
see to be aware of how we're tuning into the situation are we tense are we
reactive do we have attitudes do we have biases do we have preferen do we have
agendas what do we bring with us and in what way does that prevent clear seeing
clear seeing of ourselves and clear seeing of others so um wait or get yourself
organized relax rest in the situation so that now you can take a good look at
what's going on sense and see the situation and what do you discover what
becomes richer and Fuller uh what is what are you missing what becomes more dynamic or
or uh more connected and better understanding by taking time to sense
and see rather than making it a situation worse and one of the things
that you might see is that you might see that the s that the people you're with the
situation you're in even yourself you'll see that there's layers
of of beauty layers of value layers of things that you can respect layers of
suffering that need to be addressed need to be seen uh we start seeing life in a
deeper Fuller more valuable way when we're not riding on the
tip of let let's make it worse let's make it worse let's attack let's
complain let's criticize let's be cynical let's be skeptical just let's
just just let's pause so for today if you're at all
interested and you like the idea of an assignment uh the assignment is to in the situations where it's
appropriate um take more time than you normally would to sense the situation
sense yourself sense what's information that's coming in and all the different see you know uh all the different ways
that the body can be tuned in to the heart can be tuned
in and then uh practice seeing ask your you know even with a
question what's Happening Here let me take a deeper look let me look again and
then see what you learn so thank you very much and um and
I hope all of us as a collective in not making it worse for others this week is
making this a world a better place