so good evening welcome welcome nice to see you
all many of you know that I've uh did a series of four um classes on introduction to mindfulness
meditation and now I'm going to do two I was thinking like what should I call these like ancillary or extra credit
or I don't know but uh two um two two more weeks and each week will
be a different practice that is a support for mindfulness practice or it can even just be a instead of
mindfulness practice and tonight I'm talking about Brahma vajar more specifically meta and yeah so the the
word in uh poly is Brahma vajar you don't need to know that word it's uh
like warm-heartedness loving kindness compassion these types of things
maybe I'll just start by saying I appreciate this so much that in this practice there is this recognition and I
can say that I have this from my own experience as well this recognition that we don't have to wait you know just for
the perfect conditions to arise you know where we've had enough sleep and we're
not hungry and the people that we're with are perfectly behaved until we have
all this feeling of warm-heartedness or Compassion or care for others instead
it's something that we can actively cultivate at a particular like in a meditation practice and then it just
starts spilling out just starts spilling out at the grocery store with the family while
driving these types of things and it's quite something it's quite something that we can intentionally cultivate this
uh warm-heartedness so some of you might know this is called a meta practice I
did think it was kind of interesting that when Facebook renamed themselves so we pronounce it meta and we use that
same pronunciation for this polyd meta so loving kindness Facebook I don't know
well I'll let you decide maybe Facebook have a little bit more meta maybe that's their aspiration
so they renamed themselves that so I'll maybe I'll start a little
bit with a with a confession that uh I was on a long
retreat and actually this was a short Retreat and uh all this like rage just
showed up I had like no idea like it wasn't for any individual in particular
it was just so much anger just about everything it was really really striking
I was like just like consumed with this rage and anger and when I spoke with the
teacher about it the teacher recognized this like yes this does happen and I I
have seen this also now when I'm a retreat teacher I do see this uh this sometimes happens in practice we might
even say it's a particular stage of practice but uh the recommendation that
this teacher gave to me is like oh you should do meta practice I like I'm not
going to do meta practice I had this idea like oh that's too sentimental or that's I don't need
warm heart I just need the world to be different or you know something like this but now I wish I had a different view
from way back then I have a completely different view now but I just wanted to share that sometimes when we first
encounter this we might feel um I don't know it's a it can be a
little bit awkward in the beginning not for everybody for some people they take to it like fish to water but for me I it
wasn't initially wasn't uh something that I uh initially took to but I did um
subsequently I finished I guess I spent five years teaching loving kindness few
times a week for years and years and I can just say wow my life just really changed not only doing it for myself but
teaching it and really really uh had an impact on my life so I'm just offering
that as uh something to consider so what is
meta and what is meta practice what is it that Diana is talking about
here well I uh maybe I'll introduce it by saying that Jack cornfield who many
of you might be familiar with he has a number of well-known books he's uh one of the senior most
senior teachers in this particular tradition and when he talks about
mindfulness he's no longer using this word mindfulness he's using loving
awareness loving awareness this way of being aware but
that also includes the heart that also includes some um care or maybe this
loving awareness is a way that noticing whatever there is to be noticed but with
an attitude of it's okay it can be here it's all right this is how it is
right now as opposed to so often when we're doing mindfulness practice we might not
even notice it but there's this um maybe a little this quiet little voice in the
back of the mind like I'm doing mindfulness so that I can get rid of
some feeling I'm doing mindfulness so that I can manufacture or create or
engineer or somehow have some particular experience arise and this loving awareness instead
is a whole different way it's like no we're just noticing to uh to notice and
to care and show respect and honor for what's actually
happening So Meta meditation is the loving part of uh loving awareness it's
a distinct practice from uh mindfulness meditation I brought in that anecdote
about Jack cornfield just to show how it's an integral part of mindfulness but
the practice is distinct and uh I'll talk about that today and we'll do a
little bit of that today So Meta can be translated in many
different ways including benevolence good will care
warmth maybe even a certain amount of respect loving kindness I how I learned
it was as loving kindness or loving friendliness or something like this you
know it's just maybe I like kind of the expression warm-heartedness it's a way of uh you know not being cold or not
being disconnected or somehow but instead uh not disconnecting with our
head but bringing our hearts to whatever it is that we're doing
we all know what it is to love we can't say that it's to care for
and we could say that it's um to have some um some intimacy with or to have
warmth towards and we often you know have love for our family members and
those people that are close for us and different types of love for different uh
individuals and so is kind of what we might say is a maybe
expansion or a maturation of love so it's has love but it's not
exactly the same as what we would say in um English like today for
love and what do I mean by that that expression like expansion and
maturation meta has it's a quality of the
heart that um is the way the direction we're going is
that it's just towards this warmth this care is for whomever and whatever comes
in the mind or crosses our path it's not reserved just for those specific
individuals that we know and have relationships with it's just this sense of warmth and care right for
everybody it's quite something it's quite something to feel care for
people even though you don't know them so instead it's it's a different type of
love so it's not based on um necessarily intimacy but it's based
on what was the word unconditional yeah it's unconditional love thank you yes
and it's based on but it's more like this uh I'm going I'm holding my hands there in front of
my chest here cuz it's like the heart gets soft and warm
and it uh kind of like a uh offers just this warmth to everybody and anybody so
it's this we might say this basic wish for Goodwill maybe that's a good way to put it goodwi for all beings
and maybe I should say also uh meta like it persists despite you know
difficulties or despite uh whatever might be
arising you know even though like it might we might feel irritated it doesn't mean that meta isn't there
also So Meta is one of the Brahma viharas this is a word that I said
Brahma vihara uh vihara we we can translate it
as a abide in and Brahma there's a number of different ways we can uh
translate that for this purpose we'll do like Divine and so it could and vihara could
be uh an abode so sometimes it's like the Divine abodes like the Heavenly
Realms almost like so when there's this when your heart has this meta in it it's
a like a Heavenly experience is what's being pointed to so there's four different
um flavors types of the Brahma vajar
the I'm trying to think do we have a I guess the Divine abodes a good English
translation So Meta as I just described is like this good will for whomever and
then as meta as it grows and proliferates it just starts going out to
more and more and more beings and it's natural that it'll meet beings that are
suffering that are having difficulties there's plenty of beings in the world and S ourselves included that are
suffering so when this loving kindness meets suffering it turns into
compassion it turns into this wish for the suffering to end this compassion is
this this recognizing the suffering and this desire for it to end and then when this loving kindness
goes out and it meets the opposite somebody who's uh having great fortune
and the good things are happening or maybe they just you know graduated or
got a promotion or have a new baby or getting married or you know any of these things there's so many things then um it
turns into we could call it um sometimes we say sympathetic Joy or could be I
I'll use sympathetic Joy so this means I'm happy that you're happy just to see them happy makes you happy like it's
just great to see their happiness so it's a little it's contagious like our joy grows so when this meta meets a joy
it grows in us and then the fourth one is
equinity equinity shows up in a number of different uh ways in this tradition
and in this uh way in this setting with the Brahma of is with these heart
practices it's this recognition equinity is this recognition
of feeling connected and warmhearted with others and recognizing that we
can't control their lives we can't control what's going to
happen to them or what they're going to do so even though we might be able to see you know you'd have less suffering
if you did X Y or Z and there's often a temptation to want
to tell them or somehow uh make them control them to do X Y or Z
or something equinity is this recognition that we don't control others
we care for them we love them and we wish the best for them but we ourselves
can be connected and warmhearted and not at
agitated when they are agitated or something wanting something that they
can't have or what whatever for whatever reason and I'll talk a little bit more about equinity uh in a moment I'll guide
us in some meditation um with
equinity but first I just want to say a few words about cultivating uh loving
kindness there's two primary ways to do this and one is uh which I'll be leading
Us in this evening is we bring to mind a
lovable being this is a uh somebody you know and is part of your life or it can
even be an imaginary some people do kittens puppies babies this type of
thing so a lovable being something that just causes the heart to smile and some
kind of way like there's a little bit of a uplift so we connect with
that and if it's available to us feel that in our bodies feel the this little
bit of uplift and warm-heartedness and then we will repeat
phrases just as a way to kind of help the Mind keep on coming back to that
loving feeling because if mindfulness practice tells us anything it's how the mind likes to wander and so instead of
coming back to the breath we're coming back to a phrase that expresses a
goodwi so these phrases are not meant to uh um create something out of thin air
necessarily but it's just uh a reminder of Our intention of connecting with this
warm-heartedness so that's the first way that we can uh
cultivate meta and what all be leading us in a second way is to just
visualize there's can be like elaborate visualizations I'm less familiar with
that um visualize something or someone or imagine something or someone that uh
brings this warmhearted feeling and then like tune into it and
then just practice pervading it so the sense of like it baming out of one's
heart out there so it's a less words and more of
a I don't know maybe it's more of a feeling thing of just pushing or sending
meta out
so I'd like to um guide us in a meditation here but before I do I'd like
to say that um it's help to be comfortable when you're doing meta in particular so you're welcome to get any
extra cushions or to move or to do anything that you would like that uh if you think it would be helpful to be
comfortable it's hard to be warm-hearted if you're when you're
uncomfortable Okay so taking a meditation
posture and we'll begin with just
connecting to the surface on which we're
sitting the chair or the cushion feeling the pressure against the
body
feeling the feet on the
ground and to start us off we'll do a little bit of mindfulness of
breathing to help the mind and body settle so
bringing attention to the experience of breathing
just tuning into what it feels
like to have in breaths and out breaths
when the mind wanders we just very simply gently begin again with the sensations
of
breathing and now to begin the loving kindness practice
practice bring to mind a lovable
being someone with whom you have an uncomplicated
relationship for some people this means it might be somebody they don't know
very well might be a teacher coach
Mentor could even be somebody you've never met maybe an author
or it can be somebody in your life or you can imagine a kitten or
puppies or a
baby and bring this lovable being to mind
and can you connect with the care that you have for
this lovable being the warmth the
love for some people that connection will be felt in the chest in the heart
for some people it'll be more just a general sense of warmth and
relaxation and for some people it's not quite so
obvious it's all perfectly
fine so staying connected to this lovable being
you can repeat these phrases in your mind after
me may you be
safe may you be happy
may you be
healthy may you live with
ease may you be safe
may you be
happy may you be
healthy may you live with ease
may you be
safe may you be
happy may you be healthy
may you live with
ease connecting with the lovable
being connecting to your intentions of sending this Good Will well
wishes this care warmth respect
to this lovable
being may you be
safe may you be happy
may you be
healthy may you live with
ease you're welcome to modify the phrases if those words feel clunky or
awkward just a recommendation to keep it simple
connecting with the lovable [Music] being and
maybe checking in with oneself in the
body is there a sense of warmth or care or softness
or and if so allowing that to get as big as it would
like key word is
allow if you don't feel anything in particular that's perfectly fine too
may you be
safe may you be
happy may you be healthy
may you live with
ease for
and in the same way that we're extending this warm-heartedness and Good Will to The
Lovable being let's extend it to
ourselves of course we deserve loving
kindness of course we do
may I be
safe may I be
happy may I be healthy
may I live with
ease wishing ourselves
goodwi may I be safe
may I be
happy may I be as healthy as I can given
the circumstances I'm
in May I live with
ease
for for
may I be
safe may I be
happy may I be as healthy as I
can may I live with ease
and then to end this meditation connecting again with the
sitting surface you're
here feeling your feet on the
ground and when you're ready you can gently open your eyes
[Music]
so with that meditation I started with us just connecting to hear sometimes can
help you know the body and the mind to settle down often they're you know off doing whatever they're
doing and then I usually start with just a minute or two maybe even three of Just
Breath meditation just as a way to kind of like allow some settling and then bringing to mind a
lovable being sometimes it can we can feel like oh no which lovable being should I choose and not sure who it
should be but the recommendation is an uncomplicated relationship cuz often what happens is
somebody in our family we love them of course we love them and then we're doing this practice
then we start to remember that thing that they did that time and then it starts to get a little bit it's less uh
unconditional love and more we starting to little bit of a something else uh
coming in so that's why often people uh choose individuals that they don't know
so well it's easier to just uh have this uncomplicated relationship with don't
worry there's uh definitely time to do uh meta medit meditation loving kindness
for everybody in our family but just to start here I did with the lovable being because in theory that's the
easiest and the uh encouragement is to really start where it's easy and stay
where it's easy a lot of times people want to jump and run and do all kinds of
things with love and kindness meditation for example work with one's anger and
you know that would be great if it worked but it doesn't the human mind and heart can't just flip around to go from
anger to love that fast in the way that we're wanting to cultivate here so in
that meditation we start with the lovable being with the idea of kind of like you know priming the pump or
lighting the Kindle under the fire kind of thing so that there could be some warmth that's starting to be generated
and for many people that's all they do is just stay with the lovable being and
there's something about just repeatedly you know directing the Mind towards that
uh well-wishing it just makes it easier and easier to come to that uh place in the
heart and mind and it just starts showing up in people in one's
life often when you least expect it when you're kind of relaxed and you make a mistake and uh or for example you might
say like oh it's okay sweetheart whereas before you would have chastised yourself or something or you might uh find
yourself uh being okay the person that's driving erratically or maybe even unsafely just backing off and like oh I
guess that case person's having a bad day or something's going on with them whereas before maybe there would have
been anger so there's these subtle ways in which it starts to show up and then
it just starts to show up just more and more that's the more we practice the more uh scenarios in which it
arises and then on that meditation I also kind of like ended doing a little bit for
ourselves it turns out that this often is not so easy to have loving kindness
for ourselves there's a inner critic that's often alive and well and is
um trying to you know tell us that we have to do better
and that we're inadequate and in some kind of awful way but I'd like I'd love to hear from
all of you how was it to um do that guided meditation and or do you have any
questions about uh the teaching that I've done so far about uh loving
kindness maybe I'll ask a specific question how was it to go from from The Lovable being to yourself that's one
question was it like easy peasy or was it like wait what did it feel
awkward there's a nodding of the head yes anybody want to say anything about
that was it easy to determine like okay who The Lovable being is going to be did
you try out a few like okay this level NOP okay I'm going to try this one nope not going to do that I'm going to try
another one anybody do chose my cat first but quickly decided against that
just for the purpose of the recording I'll say that you chose your cat first but then decide to change your mind is
your cat like a Mischief maker sometimes oh yeah a feral cat
yes and then did you uh did you have to go through a lot of uh beans or was the
next one that you did picked my knce next okay okay kind of bad that I picked my
cou no no no so I just for the purpose ofra will say that she chose her niece
uh after that I think that's actually great like like nieces and nephews are perfect and grandkids like these are the
perfect uh like ones to to
do what about the phrases did they feel awkward and clunky or was it like or did
it feel like a support for tuning into
and wanting to send well
wishes where you put that microphone back there thank
you um I I think the phrases were fine for me but um I've also practiced this
before I was actually um curious about the interplay between mindfulness and
meta is it is it sort of akin to like mindfulness is for the brain uh whereas
meta is more for the heart is that sort of the how they compliment each
other um I think in the beginning it's that way and then they they kind of like the
difference uh starts to not be so clear because the difference between mind and
heart starts to not be so clear also but uh I think that's one way we can consider it but it's uh yeah just have
warm-heartedness in our life is just like such a great thing it just makes everything better
and yeah and this is just a way to connect with that but I I find that uh I
think probably most of us find that doing like mindfulness meditation which is just being aware of whatever is
arising um won't necessarily bring warm-heartedness or cultivate that but
yeah I I actually find The Meta like way easier than mindfulness I don't know why
it's just like easier to concentrate on or something yeah and so I often if people find uh meta easier than like
mindfulness I encourage them to do a lot of meta there's no reason not to this uh
they will like when we really cultivate these they end up going to really similar if not the same place
takes a little while to before they get there but uh I would always start where
it's easy it's start where it feels good and it's fun we're not always chasing our
preferences but if mindfulness feels like something that's hard to do then then we're just not going to do it
whereas uh if meta is easier I would say stay with that thank you
I asked in the chat if there were any questions online would you may want to just are there any questions for the
people that are on the other side of that camera that would like to type in a a
question CU they're nobody typed in anything but you you typed in something yeah I just you just typed it
in
okay what about when I said uh see if there's any like feeling in the body
that's associated with L kind was that like obvious or was it like I don't know
or you're not in your head was it for obvious or for you or I don't
know actually can we yeah the microphone's right behind you right here there we
go um I I focused on my
older grandson who when he walks in the room my heart swells and
um this this was really hard for me because I have a very good friend he's
20 whose grandson just was killed in a motorcycle accident so it was really
really sad yeah and as much as I tried to focus on the good things about my
grand son I turned it into loving kindness for my friend but really hard
beautiful and you know what you're describing is exactly what happens I'll just say this that of course when we
like set the direction that we're going to cultivate this warm-heartedness it's just natural that everything that isn't
warm-heartedness shows up including grief with loss and this it's just Perfectly Natural that it comes up and
it's perfectly natural to do what you did just to like turn towards uh your friend or something like this we don't
have to you know bulldoze our way through uh doing what we initially intended but yeah I'm I'm sorry about
that loss that's that's hard [Applause]
yeah anybody else have a comment or there is one question
online um would someone who practices the Brahma Bahar is ever get
[Laughter] divorced I don't
know I mean how would I know that right so I'll say that
um Rara practice is conditions our
hearts so that warmth and this uh care
just SCE to just be a part of our life and then your life unfolds differently if you have a lot of warmth and
care it is not magic and that the person that you are imagining is all of a
sudden going to feel love and behave differently it's something that we're
cultivating for ourselves so it's not going to necessarily you know make other
people behave differently that being said you know when we behave differently people we
have relationships with you know often behave differently too but it would be a
an I think it's it would be a misunderstanding to think that uh because we send loving kindness to
individuals that those individuals are going to change it's we are going to
change and the loving kindness just becomes easier and easier and more and more uh settings so I guess that's my
answer if they would ever get
divorced so now I'd like to talk a little bit about um well maybe I'll say just a few more
words about loving kindness or maybe um yeah I'll just say that often there's
a a progression start where it's easy lovable
being and then sometimes it can be a good friend it's still easy but you know
you know them well and there's that time they were late and they or whatever you know there's this it's not as clean
necessarily but you still you know love them of course and then it can be
there's you can do it in a number of different order orders including um do it for a neutral oh
sorry do it for oneself and then a neutral person that
is somebody you don't know somebody ideally it would be somebody an
individual that you recognize maybe somebody that you see in the
neighborhood maybe it's the person that works at the grocery store that you see
you know regularly or something like this so an individual but you don't know them you've never spoken with them you
don't know their names but just to uh have well- wishing for somebody that we don't
know this is such a powerful practice because right the majority of people we don't know we don't have relationships
with and this actually can be a little bit difficult to do the neutral person there's a way in which the Mind wants to
be like oh it doesn't matter or the Mind tends to be a little bit dismissive but it's the neutral person often can be the
most powerful to spend time there and then a difficult person a person with
whom we have tension in our relationship or we dislike or something like this so
the way that I often Envision it how it works is and this maybe based on my
experience too is that um there's like a um like a fountain that um the we'll say
love and kindness comes out the top and then it goes to another Pool and then it overflows that pool and then it goes
down to another Pool and then it overflows then it goes down to another Pool and then it fills up and overflows
and goes down to another so it's kind of like important to fill up each pool as
we're going so to fill up with The Lovable being to start there and this
takes time there's absolutely no need to be in hurry with this there are plenty
of benefit benefits there's you'll see a change with just doing that simple practice is doing loving kindness for
The Lovable being I know people have spent a year doing just with the lovable
being so then maybe like to a good friend or a family member and then to
oneself and a neutral person and then a difficult person but each time uh
spending each time you shift to spend uh time there I know that um some times I
know a number of people have done like 3mon Retreats and they'll spend like the first month you know 10 hours a day
meditating just with the The Lovable being and then it's just starts to ooze
out of them and then everything else just happens easier I'll also acknowledge you know
that some meditation teachers will run through all those categories in one you know sit 30 minute or 45 minutes sit or
something if you can do that that's great but uh if you can't that's perfect
fine too just stay where it's easy stay where it's easy and allow it to just fill up and
overflow as is what I would say and then I'm I could talk a lot about this I do
want to maybe reiterate what I said earlier don't be alarmed if things other
than loving kindness arise there's something about when we touch into the heart you know the heart is filled with
all kinds of things including grief and anger and you know hurt and there's a
way in which loving kindness practice is a purification practice that we're creating the conditions in which some of
these things that we maybe aren't in touch with come up and if you feel like
oh there's a lot of anger or rage then I would say switch to mindfulness practice
and just be with the anger and be with the rage feel it in the
body and make space for it so you can like just switch over to mindfulness
practice if that arises yeah what are some of the other
maybe yeah we we'll use the um so what are some of the other
mantras or phrases that you might use if you do feel like these ones maybe are a bit more they don't quite resonate as
well for you yeah so these are based on like you know classic teachings um
so may you know peace well I'm using may you and for some people that that alone
feels clunky but um the reason to use
kind of language like that is to support an intention of sending or you know like
we want them to have good experiences so we're not like trying to
evoke some power that's going to um uh zap them into having whatever
experience so is is that the clunky part the Mayu or is the clunky part the safe happy healthy
ease or all of
it I like the piece one more yeah I think it's the
yeah yeah so so rather than may you maybe there's
uh something like uh wishing you peace wishing you
wellbeing the the little bit problem with saying like wishing you is because then it makes it clear that there's a me
here that's wishing you out there
um you know if you were to Google like phrases for Brahma varara you'll find
all kinds of things but I guess the idea is like you don't
want to have that distinction between I and you you're just it's sort of all
Universal yeah it's um yeah we don't want to emphasize yeah that that yeah
I'll say that I wish you ease or you know
that even I mean that is what's happening but there's a way in which uh
when we are emphasizing like I and you then yeah it's the separation that gets
emphasized I'm here wishing you something else so without going so far as like we're all connected but just not
emphasizing separation okay any any other questions
before I move on I want to say a little bit about equinity because I think this is like such a good practice to do
sometimes with loving kindness practice and Diana there's another one it's a little long um do we need
mindfulness while practicing loving kindness towards the world uh so that we can exercise a
little bit of discernment in potentially dangerous
situations so to exercise discernment so I would say that
warm-heartedness is not passivity it is not being a doormat it is not uh not
having boundaries uh I would say the opposite actually if we're doing loving kindness for ourselves if we really care
and respect ourselves then we set clear boundaries like okay this is acceptable
for people to treat me this way but not that way um this is tolerable in the
world and not but um when you say it's not tolerable in the world then you uh
you're able to go out in the world and do things from a place of care as a
opposed to a place of anger which is you know a world of difference so to come from a place of love like this is the
because I care for these people this is what I want to do instead of maybe a mind thing that uh says that this is
what should be done so I would say that loving kindness for like the whole
world um I gave that an of like you know filling up the pool then spilling out
spilling out I would have the all the whole world only do that after we have all these other categories there's a
there's a just warm-heartedness for all beings
and just allowing that to happen otherwise it starts it ends up becoming something in the mind right the if we're
saying to the whole world then that's just a concept and it's not something that we can be really connected to so
that's uh that would be my something I'd offer [Applause] there okay so just to say a little bit
about equinity here is that um equinity gets spoken about in
a few different ways in this tradition and in this type in this uh setting I
want to talk about it in terms of this heart practices this uh warmth practices so
equinity it um it's this type of love but it's a love of we might say of
Truth so it's we can use that as an antidote to feeling out of balance but
it's a it's a truth or it's a recognition of what is actually happening it's a recognition of what's
like the big picture and seeing it within a balanced
way and here's what's so important about recognizing equinity in this setting is
that it's um it's definitely connected just like meta is we're really connected
equinity is re connected cuz sometimes people when they hear this word equinity they think
aloofness this is not aloofness they think a disconnection this is not
disconnection or they think there's a passivity or like I don't care apathy or
something like that no this is connected caring and
stable not being pushed around or not getting agitated
and sometimes why we need equinity is because when we're doing loving kindness
as I said earlier for individuals that are you know we could see that they're
making decisions that in our view is not in their best interest and we really
want to essentially control them we don't think that in our minds we're not using
that language but we want to we know we really want them to behave differently and and then we
there's an agitation that arises like oh dang it if you would only do this or if
you could only see that that there's a way that this or if you would only stop
doing this or you should start doing that and there's that that shows up as
an agitation an equinity is this recognition that everybody is in control
of their own life they make decisions for
themselves they might know how much we love them but they are still making their own decisions and sometimes we
just need to remind ourselves that and it allows us to maybe get a little bit
less entangled connected but not Tangled and connected in such a way that
because we love them we respect that they can live their life in the way that
they can of course right I'm talking about adults you know children we need to guide them and things like this but
there's a way in which equinity can really support
um sometimes the disappointment
or yeah this feeling that sometimes uh that arises when we really really want
somebody to be happy and they're not happy and then that's you know it's a
little bit of a heartbreak that happens so how can we you know sincere and
continually sending them a meta Goodwill even though that they're just
behaving the way that maybe they they won't be happy maybe they won't
be it doesn't you know it doesn't stop us from wishing it
so there's different types of uh phrases that we can use with
equinity these phrases are something like I wish you
happiness and I cannot make your decisions for
you you can feel that right there's this warmth but also this recognition that you know people make their own
decisions or another phrase is I care about you and I cannot keep you from
difficulties this is the nature of the Human Experience humans have
difficulties and even though we love somebody dearly it's not enough to protect them you know from all the
difficulties that can arise in one's life the third
phrase your happiness and unhappiness depend upon your
actions not upon my wishes for
you and then the last one is no matter how I might wish things to
be otherwise things are as they
are just wishing something was different doesn't make it different and sometimes we're funny I've
noticed this like the ways that we think or maybe I should speak for myself sometimes I would have this idea like
okay if I wished for something hard enough then it would happen but just wishing doesn't make things happen I
mean to say that out loud sounds silly but there's a way in which we find ourselves kind of like doing this in the
back of our minds kind like pushing really wanting
something so why don't we do just a short little meditation practice here with uh equinity
so [Music] again feeling connected to our sitting
surface we're
here and just tuning into just a few breaths here
feeling the body
breathing and then we'll do a little bit of loving kindness for The Lovable being
again just connecting with the lovable
being may you be
safe may you be happy
may you be
healthy may you live with ease
safe connecting with the lovable being may you be
happy may you be as healthy as you can
may you live with
ease stay here for just a few more moments with the lovable
being connecting with a sense any sense of warm-heartedness
allow yourself to feel the care you have for this lovable being
and now bring to mind somebody you have a relationship with somebody you care
about and somebody who sometimes is a little
irritating not the most difficult person in your life somebody you care about but
sometimes is a little [Music] Annoying bring this person to
mind connect with them visualize
them and for this person we'll do equinity phrases
I wish you happiness and I cannot make your choices
for
you I care about about you and I cannot keep you from
suffering your happiness and unhappiness depend upon your
actions not upon my wishes for you
no matter how I might wish things to be otherwise things are as they
are and I would recommend choosing one of those sentences and just using a
single one we'll go through them again
see which one of these resonates with
you I wish you happiness and I cannot make your choices
for you
I care about you and I cannot keep you from suffering
your happiness and unhappiness depend upon your
actions not upon my wishes for you
no matter how I might wish things to be otherwise things are as they are
and then to end this meditation feel your feet on the
ground the pressure of the seat against your
body and when you're ready you can gently open your eyes
[Music]
so with that meditation I started with you know being
present here few with the breath and then some loving kindness with the lovable being and I think that's a key
aspect because we want these phrases to come from care not from a you're
responsible for yourself you know it's uh we want it to be a way you know to express how much we
care for others and respect others and while maintaining
um while not getting out of balance ourselves sometimes we're leaning so far
in and trying to fix and make things happen and sometimes it's really appropriate I'm not saying to not to
help others that would of course not but it's the way that sometimes like our
sense of well-being gets uh compromised if we are insisting that things go a
certain way without recognizing the autonomy of other people of
course so I offered four phrases it's a lot of words I would just choose one
phrase and just use that one repeat l or maybe there's two that uh Mak sense
to you um I'll also say that uh at IMC we have
what we call happy hour so it's from 6 p.m. to 7:00 p.m. Monday through Friday so 5 days a week There's a guided
meditation on loving kindness acronymity all four of the Brahma vajas
and so this I taught for a number of years and now there's like a a collection of uh teachers who are doing
this so it's it's a great practice and there have been people it's quite
something that have been going there every day for years and they're talking about how their lives are just different
you know just having tuning in on Zoom it's a zoom thing you can get the link on the IMC calendar so I recommend this
if you're interested in exploring this to you maybe some guided meditation you're welcome to do that or um all the
recordings for that happy era gets posted on Audio Dharma so hundreds and
hundreds of recordings so uh you'll be able to hear some of
those also uh Sharon salzburg's book loving kindness if you don't know about
it it's kind of the classic here and I think it's a wonderful book so if you feel like you want to learn some more or
dig some more into it and I didn't manage the time so well
this evening so we're at the end of our time together but um I'd be happy to answer any questions or if anybody has
some comments about uh equinity or loving kindness practice or Brahman
vajar practice if anybody has something they'd like to say or or you're welcome
to come up here afterwards too okay so next week we'll do something
a little bit different uh but also uh to kind of build on our mindfulness practice so thank you