okay we'll get started
um so in this uh last few days um we've been doing a sequence of a guided
meditation and that is related to um opening to explore the nature
within ourselves in this body heart and
mind and we started the week uh with a um uh sense of a grounding grounding
through uh sitting like a mountain Inner
Mountain uh letting the Earth element to resting on Earth and then yesterday um we added an
aspect of a breath and kind of the aliveness and movements of the breath
and kind of alive Mountain within and so offered this sense of En
liening and today we'll expand even further uh to include our emotional
thinking world uh in our this in our
exploratory um Discovery I guess and the word I'll be using is
enriching and so grounding enlivening and then
enriching and today and we'll um explore
that and my sense of the emotional thinking world is a rich world you know sometimes
our relationship to them is a little tricky um and yet overall it's a very
enrich enriching Dimension uh of Being
Human so those are my uh introductory words and then we'll go into a
meditation right now
[Music]
arriving here arriving
now arriving at where you are and how you
are just as it is
you may notice how easy and quickly the Mind wants to go somewhere
else but we always start with where we
are and how we are
taking a few long deep breaths as you breathe
out settling downwards towards the Earth
sensing the ground
underneath allow this earthy body resting on Earth
feeling the skin flesh bones making contact with the floor
chairs beds
resting on the ground of Mother
Earth it feels like
this for
you may feel
pressure Sensations in the
contact temperature
the Earth element in the body is
solid heavy and a firm
grounding with the felt sense of the Earth element in the body
sitting like a mountain
within quiet
Mountain releasing commentaries
Stories the stability and the Stillness of the Inner Mountain May
highlight the movements of the breath
naturally open to receive the felt
sense of the movement of the
breath a life Mountain
where the breeze
went your breath May expand and contract
throughout the
Torso it may expand throughout the
body en lifening the cells and the nerve systems
of the whole
body open to include a sense of Al
liess tingle in
Sensations pulsations
vibrations shimmering
the movements of the breath en livens the whole body
open to include the felt sense of the movement
of the emotions or emotional
thoughts are they just the thoughts
they may have a kind of embodied energetic feel to
them may feel like a waves or a thought bubbles
[Music] this aspect of being
human is Rich filled with a range wide range
of emotions and thoughts and
without going into the content of the
thoughts feel and
sense the rich
Dynamic of the emotions
there may be lightness or the
weight associated with thoughts and emotions
or maybe a sense of color associated with [Music]
them open to receive the richness of this aspect of Being Human
like there are weather systems in the
mountain releasing judging
releasing
ideas open to receive the richness
this aspect of a Being Human in
riches our [Music] experience e
may stay connected with the breath while
opening to the felt sense of emotions and
thoughts
e
e e
and surely the mind will wander off from time to
time into this stream of thinking
thoughts whenever you
notice simply come
back
period and I'm in it period
releasing judging criticizing
complaining blaming I should I could
just here and
now again and
again and again again
with the humility and the
dignity now we're back on the path
[Music]
so this week in our dads um I've been uh sharing some um ancient similes in the
poy Canan sutta and yesterday I shared a simile that spoke about and how chicken
um incubate and hatch uh allow the uh chicks to
hatch as a way to highlight the process of cultivation and
development and and this particular Sim kind of described how and there is a
need for a proper cultivation and wholehearted sincere
committed cultivation like the chicken sits on the
ex and then um but the Buddha wasn't done with that and so apparently he has
more to say so he offered a second simile and to describe
how um and the kind of characteristics uh we
have in cultivation and the development and this is a simile of uh
o or you know I'll say acts maybe that's
something where we can relate a little more and this is a carpenter with um
using the Hearts uh in some way let me read this um similarly to you from the
sutta and the Sut is Sam nikaya SN
22101 for those who are interested in looking it up and so here it is suppose a CER or
their Apprentice sees the marks of uh his fingers and and a thumb on the
handle of his ass they don't know how much of the handle was worn away today
how much yesterday and how much previously they just know what has been
won away in the same way when a practitioner
is committed to development they don't know how much of
the TS or defilements were worn away today how much yesterday and how much
previously they just know what has been worn
off uh this is quite interesting that I thought uh wow this is simly carries a
very different flavor or a texture uh than the chicken and the eggs um and
this similarly kind of point out another aspect of the
practice um particularly it's highlighting that the measurements of
our practice how long it takes how much it has been done how much more is
left I mean this kind of questions kind of make no sense because honestly we
really don't know oh and so in the
sutta the words used here they don't know they don't know how
much was worn off yesterday or how much was was worn off
previously and so that's the truth of it that we really don't
know and this can be so challenging for uh our human psyche or the ego's
normal way of orienting Our Lives is we really like definitive lines at the end
of the race track you know the goals the expectations uh ever since school days
you know we have grades to measure ourselves and we have I don't know
uh bonus to to measure how we do at work and um
we have all the things that we use to measure ourselves against did you get a
house did you get married and so we are very trained in this way of orienting
our lives and uh this kind of a Tendencies
can lead to quite excessive judging evaluating
calculating comparing fixing striving so you name it
right and yet the Dharma doesn't work this way the Dharma unfolding doesn't happen
this way um I remember there were times that in
my my own mind I'm like constantly asking myself am I there yet am am I
there yet you know and not knowing what they there means but that's the kind of
orientation we can have
um the nature of the Dharma unfolding is not based on our logical
analysis measurements or expectations it is
lawful and yet
unfathomable I'm aware that uh you know many of us may not have been uh in
carpentry um yet with this assimil um we can feel into this process
and Buddha used this assimile I thought quite vividly that
illustrate um our cultivation process and for example
and this is simly at the beginning of our practice for a long while that may
not be very obvious signs of thumb prints fingerprints on us or we can say in our
practice uh there's nothing really visible on the
surface that uh changed and yet are we still practice
with commitment and as best as we are able I remember early days I was really
kind of uh sitting with the community maybe I'm borrowing the faith or the trust from the community I'm practicing
with or borrow borrowing kind of a trust from the
teachers and um intellectually the teachings make sense and so there are
this different ways to allow us to continue to
engage and um the thumb marks the finger marks uh may become kind of a visible um
after a long process but it doesn't mean that we
wouldn't know anything uh in this unfolding I think that will be pretty
hopeless at least to my mind you know so and that's what the cryptic and
the Intriguing statement at the end of this assimile comes in it says they just
know what has been worn off so you know you're holding the ax
and you keep using it at some point and you do see your marks on the on the
[Music] handle and so the statement is and they
just know what has been worn away I don't actually know exactly what this
line means but I can think of some different
cases that may be relevant here so I'm going to share a few different things
here for example through the practice um in the
moment sometimes uh we can know that maybe a moment of
frustration arises and they fade it fades
away when we don't react to it or criticizing ourselves or others and so
there is a momentary knowing of something Fades
away that so often that we otherwise would have reacted to it so in this way
we can know for ourselves oh we're actually suffering
less even if it's just a for a moment and also through the practice
over time I don't know exactly how long this may be kind of U for
individuals uh rather subjective for individuals to feel in their own way and
there's no for formula you you know we can reflect for
ourselves sometimes at times we can recognize that the some of the habitual
reactivities or unskillful reactivities of a a body mind speech has a lessoned
or they thinged out like yesterday my husband and I um were sitting over
lunch and uh he made a comment com to me I said oh your sharp edges is softened a
lot still comes out occasionally and I took that as a
compliment so so there's a process it does allow us to smooth
out uh some of the sharp edges of our
reactivities and allow us to have this um uh marks of a change uh in uh in
our uh in our ways of being and I myself want to share a a
story that I discovered um in the process of my U
practice there was a very habitual pattern I recognized and that U I think
through my early years that I um was very Thrifty
and so I would uh notice that I often stand in the grocery line and looking at
items prices and discounts and I would have started calculating you know how
much would I save this even though I've got everything in my heart you know I don't need to buy anything but this
would just start churning and at some point I realized
wow this is kind of a weary sum
in my mind uh why would I keep doing this and so I uh started a letting go of
this whenever I notice this calculating mind is
happening and at some point one day I stood in the grocery
line waiting to check out I noticed oh there was no more
calculating in my mind that was
interesting and so um through the practice some of the patterns do s thing
out so we can know this for ourselves and they may not be completely
gone but we can notice and their momentum has maybe settle a bit and so
we can know something about defilement the things uh being worn off worn away
and so that can give us a kind of a trust and confidence in our
practice and so that's the simile of um
o may we all grow uh the degrees of confidence and Trust in
our practice may we all benefit from it and may it benefit all beings around
us thank you for your attention and
so be well everyone see you tomorrow
[Music]