everyone to this edition of happy hour practicing loving
kindness um so for today's practice
um yeah you know instead of invite introducing a theme I think I like I
will introduce the a theme while we're practicing and we'll start as always by
settling our bodies with the breath and getting
settled um and uh um yeah let's let's just do that I want to talk don't want
to talk too much ahead of time so let's begin let's begin and see if your body needs a stretch as a way of as a way of
meta for your body see what it needs how does it want to sit in this
moment and a moment of care for the body meta for the body and inviting allowing
your your body to be comfortable sitting in a posture that has Integrity
sitting upright but not stiff upright doesn't mean stiff in
fact consider
consider your base the base is very important in how we sit consider your base your sit bones as
they land as they connect
the cushion to the chair and let your spine Rise Up from
this base in a very relaxed way as if there's an invisible magnet on top of
your head rising up not being pushed
up and then let the rest of your muscles relax soften
feeling the connection of your feet to the
Earth and feeling the breath moving through your abdomen perhaps through your chest
through your whole body e
and allowing inviting the breath to be natural however it is in breath out breath
not controlled but peaceful whether deep or shallow fast or slow
allowing awareness allowing loving awareness to know this
breath no the
appreciation e
imagining that the breath is moving in and out of the heart center
the center of our chest and maybe putting a hand on the
center of the chest connecting with
yourself with this being who is you with a sense of
appreciation as the breath is moving in and out the center of the chest the Heart
Center
bringing more appreciation and good will for this
being who is you being who is me perhaps recollecting one one act of
kindness that you did today doesn't have to be huge maybe you were generous with
your time or generous with a smile or called up a
friend or you were kind to yourself you were not harsh on yourself
today or yesterday past few days bring this act of
kindness generosity to your heart and appreciate yourself as if you're appreciating
someone else who had done it
that was nice that was nice A that was
sweet I was caring or
generous let yourself Savor and appreciate this expression of goodness
Good Will from yourself from you
to someone else or to
yourself and maybe another act of kindness comes to your mind comes to your
heart that was
nice that was kind of me I went out of my
way could be any time the past few days it doesn't have to be
huge maybe it wasn't an act of kindness so much but it was an act of restraint
you could have said something or done something that wouldn't have been very kind or wise and you didn't so
appreciate yourself for that
is a tender could be very small Act of recognition of your own goodness don't
belittle your own goodness could be an act of
Courage stepping a little out of your comfort zone to do something skill
[Music]
again if you don't have a hand in your heart center in your chest try doing that and see how it might
actually enliven this practice this somatic gesture
and born from this appreciation wishing yourself
well wishing this being who is kind generous
as
goodness sharing your blessings your your good will your
good wishes freely may I be well may this being who is
me be safe as safe as possible knowing that
the world is not completely safe so it's not attaching to the idea of safety it's
just wishing safety offering freely may I be happy as happy as
possible again not attaching to the idea it's not a demand just a good wish may I be
happy I be healthy as much as possible not as an intention or
affirmation just as a gift with no strings attached may I be
[Music] healthy and may my life have
ease made it unfold with ease and make sure it's not demanding
or or it's a prayer strong like I want this to happen it's just you offering
every gift of good willll to yourself wishing this being well may I be
safe may I be happy
may I be healthy may I have
ease if the phrases are too complicated you can just say may I be well if you're
new to this practice that's
fine and if the good willll runs dry then then remember again another act of
kindness kindness or Goodwill and connect with that otherwise stay stay with the sense
of Goodwill good wishes and phrases for
yourself
e e
sometimes it might be easier to wish yourself well if you see yourself from a third person's perspective step out of
yourself and wish yourself well or perhaps see yourself that's it's
a younger version of yourself wishing wishing yourself as a baby
may I be [Music] safe may I be
happy may I be healthy may I have
EAS
e e
or maybe it's appropriate for the phrase to be may I may I love and accept myself
just as I am or if that's not
available I Aspire may
I I may I grow into loving and accepting
myself just as I am
or if it is accessible I love and accept myself just as I am I love myself I accept
myself allowing a sense of enoughness which is not equal which is
not the same as resignation but the sense of enoughness to be
here not a sense of
lack maybe the phrase becomes time
enough
e
e e
see which raise works best for you maybe the phrase might even
become I love
myself or perhaps even if it feels right I am love I am
love may I live may I live with with love in this
world may I radiate love for myself and
others may I radiate kindness good willll friendliness from myself and
others may I be safe for myself and
others see it feels
right e
as we turn to bring this sitting period to close
together notice notice what your body is feeling
is there a little more calm peace space perhaps kindness tiny tiny tiny bit more
compared to
before trusting that we're planting seeds of goodwi kindness for ourselves
for others the world and may our practice these
planting of seeds be of service to ourselves and everyone to
grow in kindness Good Will happiness and well-being in the
world may all beings be happy may all beings be at
may all beings be
[Music]
free thanks everyone thanks for your
practice so we uh began tonight with um
turning towards appreciation for ourselves recollecting um perhaps a kind act
something generous that we had done perhaps um and and
um turning towards appreciation for this being who's
me and from appreciation turning towards goodwi for
this person who's me Goodwill meta for myself and I offered a lot of different
uh phrases um today um the sense of well-being that
the the four phrases of meta with safety happiness health and eats just simple well-being or um
if the sense of appreciation for our for myself or this person who's me could be
um uh leading into meta to be a it may be
uh available as acceptance as a sense of love and maybe radiating love so or
enoughness so there are a lot of ways that tonight today this practice um
inviting you to experiment meta is is a creative practice we see where we are
what what really works it's more practice to be done as a
feather with gentleness nod as a hammer and chisel so now happy hour on Zoom at this
time we turn to in invitation to to practice together uh we were doing
silent meta now we do interactive meta for six minutes 7 Minutes in small
groups and and the invitation for the interactive meta to is to enter into
these small uh groups of three or four with a sense of Goodwill for yourself
for other people there's nothing you have to say really right or wrong um but
maybe you just silently hold space for others if you feel like sharing a word
or two about how this practice was for you feel free to do that but please stay
with the practice right here right now um and and
the invitation is to go to speak in alphabetical order the first person we'll just offer something not a long
monologue just a brief monologue a brief bit and could be anything like tonight
my mind was distracted and or I was sleepy and or oh I really like the I am
enough it just felt right for me tonight that's that's what I needed to hear or not or whatever it is just very simple
and and then the next person will offer something the next person will come back to you so it goes round and round and
please don't comment on each other's practice or ask questions just let there
be a sense of a it's a stone soup we're sharing we're sharing with one another and just whole loving kind space it's
rare it's beautiful to have these safe spaces so please make it a safe space
for yourself and for one another um not too much chitter chatter and stay with
the practice this is a formal practice in small groups and if you see somebody is not doing you know just talking about
today and yesterday or talking about politics like no no it's okay it's you know let's let's stay with practice
let's stay with practice in a very kind way very kind way so so with all that I'm going to uh
create the small groups the breakout uh rooms creating them and
um yeah uh be kind to your yourself be kind to one another okay here we go back
in the main room welcome back everyone and it's it's always nice to see Smiles
after you've connected with one another that's sweet and okay if not it's all
good so we have some time for um Reflections if you like to
share um with everyone how was this for you and and your Reflections support
everyone um and also questions questions are welcome Reflections
questions um you can raise your Zoom hand um that way I can see you because
because of uh privacy reasons I I have um uh my image is large so that the um
how should I explain it quickly uh because this is streamed on YouTube so that your images are not streamed on
YouTube only mine is so I only get to see a few of you on top I don't see everybody so cloudia I see your Zoom
hand first asking you to
unmute um okay I I want to first of all thank you for being here I just love
your voice and it's just so beautiful for me to hear it because it really helps me with my um selft talk and for
whatever reason your voice really over the years has just been doing it for me and just to hear it today has just been
a complete blessing and I first of all want to just tell you how grateful I am to have you here thank
you thank you Claudia I'm so said that I need to say one more thing yes please
please I was waiting I was just gonna thank you back for for for for for um
for your practice and and just yeah deeply deeply grateful for your practice
doing this practice and and using whatever support is available including this voice not me not mine it happens to
be this way so take it please whatever supportive this is so lovely thank you
cloud my heart is brighten and the next piece yeah definitely a connection thank
you um okay so the next piece is a little bit more difficult because I was in a group and you gave very very very
very very very clear instructions very clear yeah
yet it wasn't to me it was to another person that person did not have a safe
space and I could not unmute fast enough to say um excuse me let's remember but
it just I really don't understand year after year after year this keeps
happening and I've been also on the receiving end of people commenting about my stuff and I don't really appreciate
it but I was on the receiving end of being a bystander today and I don't
appreciate it and I felt bad about the other person so whatever meta we created
it could be you know we were talking about perception we create things in our own mind sure this is something that I'm
creating in my mind however this is a group that as a whole we have agreed to
certain boundaries and I don't understand how literally 10 seconds
later this does not happen yeah yeah I I appreciate you raising this and know we
try of course and there's more I'm going to say about this I really appreciate you raising in and also raising into the
group because it um yeah it can be an ouch for the person
who receives for an ouch for the person who's witnessing ouch all around so I
really appreciate you raising this and and cloudy I would really U if you would please stay afterwards i' like to to
connect with you a little more about this um uh oneon-one especially about
what happened in the group and if there's more care care that's needed both for you and and for the other
person so I'd like to if you would be so kind as to stay for just a couple of minutes after afterwards I would
appreciate it thank you um and it's um I like to think that
we're doing the best we can and it sometimes in the social situations if
somebody says something perhaps I don't know what the situation was but if someone says something that's difficult
or Tender the other person maybe is trying to make it okay
somehow like comments on their situation trying to support them and make it okay um so that they don't feel bad they
don't feel uncomfortable and that's something that can happen also uh on it's not helpful in meta spaces um we
need to also be able to practice equinity to just allow what has been said to be there and hold space with
kindness without fixing it so maybe that's a comment that from now on I'm going to bring in when I
set up the the groups you know don't try to fix each other just let each other be
accept with meta love each other just as you are don't try to to um fix each
other I think that that might be again I like to attribute that to Goodwill but a
little misguided not enough wisdom there is Goodwill but not enough wisdom and if you would if you would um
if you would uh stay that would be great we can we can check in afterwards I really appreciate it
cloudy Nick
please yes I'm Gonna Keep mine very quick but sure it was why did I turn
cash it was what oh it turned close captioning on was seeing what I was
saying on the no it was it was a really beautiful set and as I shared to the group um it turned into something very
joyous and almost Whimsical for me because I've got a window open on a
beautiful Sunday Chicago or beautiful Chicago evening in the summer and I could hear the ice cream
truck in my neighborhood for about 20 minutes to the 30 minute set and it just
kept this brought up all this just joy and especially when you brought up the
phrases in I am enough and I have enough that really resonated at that point for me so thank you oh that's beautiful
thank thanks for speaking about how um you know you're Incorporated the sounds
of of life of Living the ice cream truck and the joy of that and um instead of oh
the ice cream truck is is is distracting me from my meditation right that that could be where the Mind goes instead
letting it really including everything as a part of our practice thank you so much Nick appreciate it yeah lovely
[Music] Jerry um first of all I
Echo U Claudia's comments so uh it's great to see you back and uh uh your
voice is amazing and your work uh the question I have uh have comment and that
a question so uh I was a friend once uh recently said to me my may you is so
compassionate toward others but may you seem to be very critical of yourself and
uh of course my work as a physician I try to be compassionate and keep clear
boundaries but uh when I then come to judge myself well I I push harder and
then why haven't I done this why haven't I done this and and then of course uh
that comes back and so um and and uh she said you need to be more compassionate
with yourself so of course this was fitting for what we talked about tonight and I guess I uh uh wondered if and so
the question is uh in this tradition of terana is loving kindness uh which I
love meta is it more prominent than in other traditions and in in Buddhism or
is it prominent in Buddhism generally I don't know so yeah yeah so um the first
question that an implied question about kindness to yourself right meta and compassion to
yourself and meta and compassion as you already know by now they're related but not the same thing compassion is meta
when meta meets challenge pain suffering self-criticism it becomes
compassion so that is what's needed so please please keep practicing kindness
meta compassion for yourself and it works we know that it works and we know that it works so um and then with the
question of whether this is um uh more
prominent in this uh tradition or another tradition um in in all
traditions of Buddhism meta is there in the in the Tada uh Buddhism meta is the
primary one and in the other tradition in the um uh Tibetan tradition
compassion is the primary so compassion which is meta meaning suffering and in
Zen it's there it's it's not leaned into as much emptiness is lean into more so
it's it's it's part of all Buddhist teachings but uh anyway that's the theoretical part in terms of practical
part keep practicing Jerry keep practicing yeah thank you thank you thank you than thank
you so there was a question earlier from P pava I hope I'm saying your name right
panova reflection in the happy in the group happy era I convert habitual
judge uh thought to habitual ah let me try that again in the group happy a I
convert habitual judge thought to meta through thought to group members because
I realize judging doesn't help me and others thank you everyone thank you
question do meditation when mention lacking I feel like my Sati Samar and
vasana is not fulfilled yet um this is the most important part but I feel but I
feel lacking of this area may I ask what I should do ah right I appreciate it I
appreciate both uh both you wrote both of what you wrote um
so the um I'm going to close chat right now there we go actually it will just
come to me so um so with the question that you have
this sense of lacking um if you for for your somebody for your practice not to
have completed not to have come to full fruition there could be a a
um uh um you know if if if it uh supports
you you and it inspires you let it be inspiring instead of a feeling of lack
let it feel inspiring that oh yes there is more so that it can be onward leading
so that the practice can continue to be onward leading yes there is more instead of like oh I'm not enough I haven't done
yet that can be contracting and can limit your progress um I hope that makes
sense right there's you can still have this feeling of I want to to practice I
want to fulfill my potential but from a place of aspiration so that it lifts up
your heart instead of a feeling of lack I'm not enough and those two feel very
differently and you can chat me directly I hope that makes sense um as an answer
to your question so um so I'm going
to yeah um direct question comes to me Megan so
uh where does self forgiveness play into the practice of meta yeah self-
forgiveness is related to the practice of meta even more the practice of uh
self-compassion actually because there is pain and suffering so um and and and self-
Compass self forgiveness is is quite a practice quite a development and given that there's only a couple of minutes
left and it's quite a practice I'm not going going to uh bring it all in it's it's maybe another session and if you
search for forgiveness on um on audiio Dharma you'll find uh self forgiveness I
also see other questions about various things that uh yes P of us so
inspiration that means there's still progress yes so in inspired to make progress instead of like oh out of lack
out of like I'm not good enough so shift that um I see there are more
questions um about group process etc etc
and what's appropriate um and what I would like to do is um let's see there's there's a lot
and so what I would like to do is to end the session formally I see there's
there's comments from uh uh Claudia Serena um and if you would if you would
stay it would be great to just have a conversation and I can answer those questions and it would it would be
really helpful for the sa if you if you could spare a couple minutes and stay um yeah and and parents ask Micki
is it okay to name teachers who have been a source of inspiration or skillful means that's that's okay but not so much
as a um I think it becomes a little difficult when you're saying well well you you you go do that right if it's
more of a uh it depends the spirit in which it's offered right it's all depends on this so you sound like this
you know this teaching or this this teacher or this other person has been inspiring to me you know speak from your
own experience instead of telling oh you need that it's like it's that's the
spirit in which things can be um shareed really speak from your own experience um
instead of telling others what to do I I think that's another uh important thing to keep in mind um and when in doubt say
less less is more less is more when in doubt less is more all right dear ones
it's 7 p.m. well it's the end you know could be any any time in your time zone
it's time to to say goodbye so thank you all for your practice deep deep
appreciation for all of you for coming together and and doing our best here we
are all doing our best and some times our best is a little clunky and it's okay let's let's uh keep practicing
together in community may all beings be well may all beings be happy including
ourselves thanks everyone take