and our teacher this morning is tenzen chogi she's a teacher of workshops and
programs that bridge the worlds of Buddhist thought contemplative practice mental and emotional cultivation and the
latest research in the field of positive psychology she first became interested
in meditation in the early 1970s and in 1991 she began practicing
Tibetan Buddhism uh while studying in India and Nepal
she completed several long meditation Retreats and took monastic ordination
with his Holiness the Dal Lama practicing as a monastic for nearly 20
years since 2006 she has been teaching in Buddha centers around the world and
she has taught in prisons for 15 years she's also a certified teacher of
compassion cultivation training and the cultivating emotional balance program
tensen is especially interested in bringing the wisdom of Buddhism into modern culture and into alignment with
modern cultural values such as racial and gender justice and environmental
awareness she feels strongly that a genuine and meaningful spiritual path includes not only personal
transformation but social and cultural transformation as well she loves
Interfaith collaboration and is a volunteer for the interfaith speakers Bureau of the Islamic networks group in
the greater San Francisco Bay Area she also finds time to create her unlocking
true happiness podcast which you can check out at unlocking trua
happiness.org where you also find her current teaching schedule and she's currently based on traditional awaswas
olani land in what is now known as Santa Cruz California and good morning and
welcome to IMC t Chi thank you Martha how's the sound is
working yeah thank you all for coming it's nice to be here again I realized I
was just thinking of the last time I taught here I think it was 2018 it's
definitely before the pandemic and I was still a monastic and my friend aan
chondo and I taught a day long called the bodh SAA and the arot comparing the
main in Traditions and had a good time I don't know if anybody here was there at
that time anybody remember that no okay too long ago so this morning because my
tradition is a little bit different in the meditations I lead or slightly different we're going to flip the script
a little bit and do most of the Dharma talk before doing the meditation and
then have time after the meditation because it might be a different style for for you to have some discussion
question and answer and so forth but before all of that we'll go ahead and settle in we'll just settle in for a
couple of minutes with breath awareness and set Our intention for our time together before I introduce the practice
so I'll invite you just to get into a comfortable posture relaxed yet alert these two
qualities are complimentary not contradictory we try and get
a alert stance in our meditation mostly
through that nice upright spine as if there were a cord pulling up from the crown of your head and then your body
relaxed around it so just taking a moment to settle in
and perhaps moving your attention through your body noticing if there's any tightness or tension deliberately
relaxing we often hold tension around our eyes so noticing your forehead and
the area around your eyes and relaxing and your jaw generally were
breathing through our nose when we meditate if we can unless we have some sort of sinus problem or
obstruction but even though our mouth is closed our jaw not clenched and your neck and shoulders is
another place we often hold tension so I invite you if you notice any tightness there to just deliberately relax and
release perhaps releasing on the exhale your belly relaxed your
buttocks and then let's round off this initial settling of the body with three deep breaths deep diaphragmatic
inhalation and
exhalation and then just turning our attention to the sensations of the breath wherever we can feel it in the
body is a way to arrive in this space in our bodies in the present moment it
might be full body awareness of breathing perhaps the abdomen as your diaphragm
Rises and Falls perhaps you can notice the breath more by localizing your attention at the chest with your lungs
expanding and Contracting and perhaps that very subtle
sensation at the nostrils so just spending a few moments with either the
localized attention or that wide angle lens of full body awareness of breathing
and when you notice your attention wandering or you get distracted by a another sense object like a sound for
example just releasing the distraction and returning to the
breath for
and now let's take a moment to reflect on Our intention our motivation for
being here this morning in Buddhist practice we say we get the most out of any practice session
or even a study session or even a discussion if we're clear about Our intention and
set our motivation you thinking of what brought you here this morning perhaps you're a
regular attendee at these Sunday morning
sessions maybe you're here for the first time maybe you just heard
about the center and your checking it out curious maybe you're going through a
hard time in your life right now and looking for ways to help you
manage The Unwanted experiences you're having you heard Buddhism has something
to offer just taking a moment to reflect on your intention
and we always also try to add a altruistic intention to our
motivation thinking May whatever I experience this morning in meditation in
discussion and the discourse may it benefit me but may I get some insight some
experience that will bring benefit to others as well so trying to generate that
altruistic intention
[Music]
just relaxing your posture and coming out of
meditation so some more people arrived while we were doing that settling practice and just to just to say again
that we're going to have a slightly different structure this morning I'm going to be introducing a guided meditation and then
leading you through it and then having some time for discussion and question and answer so it's going to be a little
bit different and again so nice to be in this space uh I met Gil actually all the
way back in 1992 I was the director of vajani Institute at Tibetan Buddhist center in
the mountains in outside of Boulder Creek and he in Mary Grace
ore just rocked up one morning checking out Retreat centers to see if there is a
place they could hold their annual Retreat and that became a 33-year
relationship that started with them leading 10day Retreats at that Retreat
Center kind of through the Whole Decade of the 90s I think it wasn't until maybe
Spirit Rock opened up a residential place that they moved there and even then they didn't want to because you
know we had established such a groove of them coming every year for 10 days to do
Retreats so we're old friends so what I want to talk about this morning and this
you know sometimes there'll be something in the air that keeps coming up and I've had no less than four conversations this
week with people from different organizations about how to bridge the huge divides
that are so obvious to all of us in our communities in our nation globally and
so forth through dialogue bridging Community
conversations and so I think Buddhism has so much to offer to this endeavor I
think we all would agree that you know just even speaking about our own Nation
such big divides politically not only between you know
the two main political parties but big divisions about the war in Israel
Palestine the war in Ukraine so many issues that are dividing people climate change climate Justice and so forth and
so you know what do we do to actually come together and talk and I think it
really goes back to you know using some of the techniques from Buddhism for
developing empathy and compassion and we can bring this out of the interpersonal
to the community level and even the national level so I wanted to kind of
revisit some of those techniques for how do we generate empathy and compassion
for people that we think are other right are very different from us and you know
that we may not be even very interested in having empathy and compassion for
those kind of people and so in Buddhist practice we emphasize what we sometimes
call mental cultivation through contemplation and in the four Brahma
viharas for example which are found in all Buddhist Traditions there's this idea that we can cultivate qualities
Like Loving kindness and compassion not just for our loved
ones easy everybody does that that's no big deal we don't need to work hard at
that maybe we need to work a little bit harder to develop compassion for ourselves that can be challenging right
and a lot of people find that self-kindness and self-compassion but what about extending
compassion to people we see as other in in in some way because of their beliefs
because of maybe their ethnicity because of other differences and one of the things that
we do in Buddhist practice is attuned to what we call the common
Humanity my teacher one of my main teachers who ordained me I lived as a monastic for 20 years and I was ordained
by his Holiness the Daly Lama who I think just about everybody in the planet
admires I mean there are exceptions but not many very exemplary person and I
remember once listening to one of his main translators who translated for him
in the early days especially when when he first started coming to the so-called West and you know needed a translator in
maybe the 70s and so forth Jeffrey Hopkins a Buddhist scholar and he says
you know every time I translated for his Holiness at Ali Lama didn't matter what
the topic was within the first like couple of sentences he'd always say the
same thing all beings are the same in wanting happiness and wanting to avoid
suffering and so Jeffrey Hopkins said I could only come to one of two conclusions either he didn't have
anything else to talk about or this is really really really important and
that's the common Humanity we're the same in terms of our
basic human feelings our basic human needs and this is just talking about humans in Buddhism
of course we expand to the more than human realm but for the purposes of today just talking about The Human
Experience you know we all have the same feelings emotions the same basic needs
and so even when there are superficial differences even when there're really extreme differences because this doesn't
say that all beings have the same lived experience at all so it's not to erase
difference in any way to say that people don't have very different experiences on
the basis of race and ethnicity and gender and gender
identity sexual orientation all the things that make us different for sure
but there's a base that we can drill down to that is the basis of that
connection across difference in the way that we can sometimes make the
difference so that we dispose of people or discount their them you know their
full Humanity or somehow just refuse to connect to them and I think you know
holding this interesting dichotomy of there may be somebody I really disagree
with there may be people that even does something that's really harmful that I'm
trying to kind of protest or stop them or whatever but can I still have compassion and empathy for them as a
human that's the hard balance right so it's not giving people a pass for harmful Behavior at all or not saying oh
we'll just erase the differences but it's saying can I have that connection
nevertheless to their Humanity because that's where real connection and
communication that I think can really help us especially in these divided
times now traditional Buddhist practice just kind of focuses on the
interpersonal and so we have practices and we'll do one today of Imagining the
friend imagining The Stranger Imagining the enemy right and that's kind of more
of the personal person that hurt your feelings or the really annoying co-worker or the relative that you have
the dis you know difference of opinion with but I think we can generalize some
of those practices for Buddhism to social groups we see as friend enemy stranger also right and try to try to
bridge these divides and there are a lot of um organizations now doing this kind of work but I just wanted to bring up
this idea of you know kind of connecting to that idea of the common humanity and
it's interesting because people who have studied altruism just
psychologists and you know social scientists who've investigated why do
people do kind of these altruistic acts even at Great risk to the themselves for
others like what's going on there this Common Thread and there's a book that I brought with me and I'll read a quote
later on it's called the heart of altruism by a researcher called kren
Monroe and She interviewed people who' done these altruistic acts for total
strangers and there's a chapter Where She interviewed um Gentiles non-jewish
people in Europe who at Great personal risk to them and their families hid Jews
you know we all kind I think a lot of us know the story of Anne Frank who was hidden in the Attic of the family for
like two years or some crazy amount of time you know and then they all ended up kind of getting carded away and she was
asking these people she did her research in the 90s when a lot of them were still alive like what's up with that how can
you risk you know and she said herself as a mother she goes I can see my
husband and myself making a you know taking a risk like that but for my children I would do
anything to protect them I would never do it so even these people that did that and they all said the same thing and the
Common Thread was how could we not they're human beings just like me right
so there was something about these people who were altruists that was a Common Thread that they saw and they
didn't see us and them in the same way right and they just were like how could
I not so there's this idea in Buddhism of our inner connection and again it
doesn't mean we're all the same it doesn't mean we all have the same experience but in Buddhist practice we
really tune into you know this fact of our interdependence on each other this
idea that's I mean I've lived and traveled in all of these countries and I'll tell you right now Americans are
the worst I'm telling you the worst in this hallucination of Independence
like we're just a satellite in floating in space with no gravitational Pole to
anything and I'm like are you kidding me right now I just went to the restroom as one does turned on the water I couldn't
even have a drink of water without it I don't even know where the water comes from how does the piping work where does
it go no idea someone did that good thing otherwise it'd be carting a bucket
to some where's the the closest stre dream no idea right my car don't even
get me started all the things that we depend on others for everything we do
and often still it's easy for us you know who grow up in a culture that even
prizes this Fierce Independence oh I'm all about it you know no I don't need
help I can do the thing and I can help everyone else and I don't ever need to ask for help and it's just a hallucinate
ation like I said it's just false so connecting in that way and connecting to
you know at the very Baseline of our common feelings and needs there's a a
clinical social worker who works a lot with people with trauma and I really like her work and her name is Stacy
Haynes and anybody who's taken nonviolent communication classes which
some of you may have done there's long lists of feeling ings and needs and those can be really helpful she drills
it down to three basic needs and I love her list very short list and I think it
kind of is an umbrella for a lot of those longer lists she says
safety belonging and dignity or respect
right and so do what everyone is doing is trying to fulfill a need for either
safety super basic right we all want safety
belonging wow that's huge how many times have we done something or not done
something that we felt like was right because we wanted to belong and fit in
right so belonging so huge very evolutionary basic human need and then
dignity or respect or even to borrow from Dan seagull just being
seen right just being seen as somebody with some kind of value and so that's
kind of the Baseline that we can drill down to I teach a a training uh in conflict
management skills I actually did it for gills teacher training Retreat a couple
of months ago he invited me to come do this conflict management skills training and in that we talk about we kind of
show a diagram of two icebergs and we say above the waterline are the person's
positions like you're in a disagreement with someone and you both have these entrenched positions and then under the
waterline is feelings needs values ideals and then we have a the in
the diagram the two icebergs overlap and we call that the collaboration sweet
spot like you found some shared need or value or interest and then that's where
you can come up with a solution into the problem that's not either one of the
first positions but that's where something new can emerge and so I think
that's true interpersonally too even when we don't have a conflict with
someone so what we're going to do in the meditation practice this is going to be
a guided practice probably more guided than maybe you're mostly used to but again I've got my Tibetan Buddhist hat
on you can't see it but it's there so we do a lot of guided practice with
visualizations and so what we're going to do and this is very traditional practice for
cultivating compassion and empathy and this is a technique from Tibetan
Buddhism that was actually also used to develop Stanford's compassion
cultivation training this secular program that some of you Robert cusk who's who's a teacher here is one of one
of the teachers of that training and I am too so the idea is we start with a
priming step of thinking of someone easy to have compassion for so we kind of get
the juices flowing and get that felt sense of what it's like and then gradually over time we expand to First
the stranger the neutral person who is who we often will just feel indifferent
who cares whether they're happy or suffering I don't care I don't even know them they just put my groceries in the
bag at Trader Joe's whatever right and then beyond that even the
difficult people and for this practice especially if it's new to you don't pick
a 10 on a scale of 1 to 10 of the most difficult person don't pick it's always the ex's right the exm Mother-in-law the
ex partner the ex whatever it's always the people really close to us that broke our heart and betrayed us it's always
don't do that maybe the annoying irritating coworker we've all got one of
those or even if some people say oh I have no one in my life that I dislike
and I go okay you can think of a public figure but again maybe not a 10 on the
scale of 1 to 10 I'm not sure there is one they're all like zero or 10 there's
hardly any but anyway yeah maybe a 12 maybe a 12 but
you know maybe of kind of three or four or five on a scale of 1 to 10 cuz I
don't want a you know room full of really triggered people and memory is also a trigger of emotion so we don't
want that and so I'll guide you through and what we do is if we can get a visual
image of the person seated in front of us some people it's hard to have a visual image just in your mind's eye you
kind of imagine the person there and get a felt sense of their presence to or
instead of the visual image some people are like I just can't visualize it all and that's fine get a felt sense of the
person's presence and then kind of tune into What feelings come up and then
we'll try and generate this feeling of the common Humanity okay and see how it
goes it might be hard I did this practice once you know I had a nemesis
that was also an X and it took me literally years maybe it's too
discouraging if I tell you this but it did years to shift but I trusted the
practice so don't expect miracles today but over time if you keep doing it these
practices really move to shift sometimes our strong reactions towards people of
different groups or people that in our own lives so we'll give it a try and then we'll have a chance to discuss and
see what questions or Reflections or experiences come up after the practice
all right so I'll prompt you with something to think about I'll give you kind of an instruction of how to think
or visualize and then pause and then follow the instruction as best you can
until I give you the next prompt if you lose track as we do when we're doing breath awareness meditation just
reprompt yourself you know you might be like oh my gosh what am I going to have for lunch and I've got 60 emails
okay wait no the neutral person I'm supposed to be thinking the neutral person so just kind of bring yourself
back to the practice all right so I'll invite you to get in a comfortable
posture with your back straight again and if you're sitting down your legs
cross comfortably on the cushion if you're sitting up in a chair just making
sure you have a nice stable posture with your shoulders
even if you have your tongue resting on the top of your top of on your pallet your upper
pallet right behind your teeth that can keep you from having to swallow
constantly and your eyes can either be closed or in a slightly open hooded gaze
if that helps you to stay awake stay alert but you're
not looking if your eyes are slightly open letting a little light in you're not looking
at whatever is in front of your eyes you're withdrawing your
gaze so we won't do a full body scan but I'll just invite you for a moment after
settling into your posture to check into your posture in your body see if there's
any tightness or tension or constriction and release relax
and then just settling with the Breath Again wherever you can follow the
sensations perhaps the full body awareness of breathing or the
diaphragm or the lungs or that subtlest place the air
moving in and out of your
nostrils for
and just release any distracting sounds any distracting thoughts that pull you
away from that awareness of the sensations of the breath just release and
return for
and so for the first step we're going to practice self-c kindness and
self-compassion and so taking a moment to think of a time when you
felt great difficulty maybe you were in some kind of emotional or mental
distress or perhaps it was physical pain
maybe a breakup of an important relationship or a big
disappointment and if you can imagine that self your past
self seated in front of you facing you or get a felt sense of yourself in that
experience just take a moment to really feel clearly yourself when you're
experiencing that unwanted episode whatever it
was and as that memory becomes clear notice how you feel how does your heart
feel you have feelings of care and tenderness and kindness
towards
yourself and attuning to that natural natural sense of care and kindness and
compassion you have towards yourself I invite you to recite the
following verses silently may I be
happy may I be free from suffering may I find peace and joy
sending those thoughts of care and kindness and compassion out to
yourself may I be happy may I be free from
suffering may I find peace and joy
and I invite you all also as you recite the phrases if it's helpful sending out
a bright light from your heart and that light symbolizes that care and compassion you have for yourself just
imagine it touching that replica of yourself giving them peace freedom from
suffering happiness may I be
happy may I be free from suffering may I find peace and joy
and then let the visualization of yourself dissolve back into the the space of your
mind and now think of a loved one and so this is someone for whom you naturally
feel strong feelings of wishing that they have happiness wishing that they're free from
suffering that heartfelt care and concern it just comes
naturally with this person maybe it's your best friend maybe it's a relative
someone who really sees you who really gets you someone whose company you really
enjoy so again imagining them seated in front of you or if it's hard to get a
clear visual image just get a felt sense of their presence imagine they're here
in this room with you meditating with you taking a few moments to really feel
their presence get that image
and notice as their visual image and that felt sense of their presence
becomes real notice What feelings arise in your
heart might be a feeling of warmth and
openness you might feel that you have so much in common with this person they're
a lot like you so to empathize with their feelings
and their needs come so easily
so letting that feeling arise in your heart and become real that natural sense
of connection and empathy and care you feel towards your loved
one and again if you'd like to visualize a bright light going out from your heart
as you breathe out and recite the following phrases in your mind may you
be happy may you be free from
suffering may you find peace and joy sending that compassionate wish out
to your loved one may you be happy may you be free from s
suffering may you find peace and joy
may you be happy may you be free from suffering may you find peace and joy
with each out breath sending that bright light imagining that
that care and love and concern and compassion Act
freeze your loved one from any problems they might be
experiencing any unwanted experience and gives them
peace
for for
and now I invite you to bring to mind a stranger so someone you don't know
well you have neither any strong feelings of affection for this person or
any feelings of aversion but it's somebody specific in your life somebody that you
recognize it might be the Barista at the place you get your morning coffee or
your regular Uber driver or a cooworker
that you don't know very well at all or maybe a neighbor so someone
specific but someone for whom you don't give much thought one way or
another neither affection nor aversion
maybe don't think of them at all unless you happen to see them and then don't even really think much about their life
what's going on for them so someone specific and again
trying to visualize them seated in front of you or get a felt sense of their
presence inviting them into the meditation taking a moment to build up
that feeling of their presence
and as you get that clear visual image or that felt sense becomes clear just
noticing how it feels noticing What feelings come
up might be just just indifference not much one way or the other you might even
notice your attention wandering more why am I even thinking about this
person and now taking a moment to try to tune into this person's experience you
may know nothing about them you may not even know their
name but just because they're another human being someone cares for them someone
loves them they experience love and care for
others and wish to be
loved just like you they felt
disappointed sad maybe
lonely just like you they felt anger frustration irritation
just like you they felt joy laughter
connection just like you they need safety
belonging dignity and respect and when they don't get it they
struggle so even though you don't know anything about this person you know all
of these things to be true just because they're a human being just like
you and their life is just as important to them as your life is to you
and so with that feeling now of a more heartfelt level of
connection and empathy and compassion sending that bright light out
to that stranger and thinking may you be
happy may you be free from suffering may you find peace and joy by
knowing that their happiness is just as important to them as your happiness is
to you their freedom from suffering just as important to
them may you be happy may you be free from suffering
may you find peace and joy continuing to send out that compassionate
wish from your heart along with that bright light with every out
breath and feeling that heartfelt wish that that person who's a stranger find
happiness and freedom from
suffering for
may you be happy may you be free from suffering may you find peace and
joy
for e
may you be happy may you be free from suffering may you find peace and joy
and now I invite you to think of a difficult person and again not a 10 on a scale of
1 to 10 not the most difficult person in your life but perhaps someone who's just
hurt you or someone you find irritating and
annoying or someone who's disappointed you or someone whose views you feel you
just don't understand so thinking of such a person
again someone very specific in your life and imagine them seated in front of you
or get a felt sense of their
presence and noticing even as you begin to bring them to mind you might notice
that aversion arising the thought that I don't really even want to think of this
person I definitely don't want to visualize them or feel that they're here
in that room just notice whatever resistance might
arise take a few moments to really get clear get a sense of this
person noticing your response to thinking about
them we so often perceive people through the
lens and the filter of our own relationship with them and what they can
do for us perhaps what they have done to us or
for us but now try to think for this person
too they have a whole life that's just as important to them as your life is to
you
they wish to love and be loved they're an object of care and
concern and love to
someone they care to be happy they try to avoid any physical or
emotional pain or disappointments or stress struggles just like
you they feel anger despair
disappointment frustration just like you
they feel Joy and connection and
happiness just like
you their basic needs of safety
belonging and respect and worthiness are just as
important to them as your needs are to
you and just think perhaps if their needs were met perhaps if they received
more love they might not be as annoying perhaps if they received all
that any human wishes who knows they might
change maybe it's all of their disappointments that has made them so
unpleasant to be
around and see if by connecting to that level of common Humanity in terms of the
the feelings the emotions the needs if with that in mind you can send
out a heartfelt wish may you too be
happy may you be free from
suffering may you experience peace and joy and sending out that bright light
from your heart even to the difficult person they too wishing for happiness
wishing to be free from suffering just like you may you be
happy may you be free from suffering may you experience peace and
joy
and notice it might feel harder than for the other people the loved one and the
stranger and that's fine just noticing but your intention to at
least try it's aspirational may you be happy may you
you be free from suffering may you experience peace and
joy imagine that bright light going out and imagine that difficult person
actually having peace of mind having happiness that you're able to actually
give them happiness and relieve their suffering
may you be happy may you be free from suffering may you experience peace and
joy for
and now think of all three people together the loved one the
stranger the difficult person and
thinking even though you have a different relationship to all three of these people
from their side they all are exactly the same and wanting happiness wanting
freedom from suffering and that there's no difference at all the same as you the same as each
other so sending that compassionate wish out to all three may you all be
happy may you all be free from suffering
may you all experience peace and joy breathing out that bright light from
your
heart may you all be happy may you be free from
suffering may you experience peace and joy
and then expanding that compassionate with with even farther thinking of everyone seated in this room right
now all of us here exactly the same in terms of our
basic human feelings our needs our emotions all of us wishing for
happiness wishing for freedom from suffering and so expand imagine that
light from your heart expanding going out to everyone in this room May everyone
here be happy May everyone be free from
suffering May everyone experience peace and
joy just expanding feeling that warmth from your heart that bright light going
out to everyone in this
room then to everyone joining on the live stream
and then imagining expanding to all
beings imagine that powerful compassionate energy from your heart
there's no boundary it just streams forth sending that same compassionate
wish to all beings may all beings be happy may all all beings be free from
suffering may all beings experience peace and joy
and then releasing the visualization returning to the breath for just a
moment and taking a moment to rejoice in your own practice
your own cultivation of this openhearted immeasurable
compassion just take a moment to feel Joy in your own
virtue thinking that even in the level of your imagination you've been able to bring all the suffering in the universe
to an end
and then dedicating the positive energy from our practice that all beings have
happiness all beings have freedom from suffering
and taking just a moment to relax your posture very gently come out of meditation
well I really feel like that should have singlehandedly brought about world peace feels that way to me
anyway so we've got about 11 minutes and if there's any questions or
Reflections or experiences or any epiphanies doubts
struggles any of the above don't be shy we'll pass the mic
around anything come up at all because I know that was maybe a slightly different
type of practice than some of you might be used to so yeah there's a question
here good morning thank you so much um our son is college age son is coming
home today who we love dearly and I wouldn't be surprised if that was the
loved one that both of us thought of um but as with all young people today and
in the past and in the future um he struggles some with who is he
going to be what is he going to do um he has ADD and needs to deal with
that and um recently I found
myself stepping back into kind of the executive function role
and I can feel myself getting more rigid dealing with him in terms of have you
done this have you done that and we're both good about conversing about that
but I'm wondering if if you have any suggestions about in the moment are there things
that I can be thinking of to stop the mind's all fear-based right
I just want the best for you and yeah exactly let me help you out I I do as a
matter of fact unsurprisingly do have a couple of ideas one thing though that your question makes me think of is the
when I teach the longer course I teach the 8we Stanford course and we have a lot more unpacking of all the steps
including choosing the appropriate loved one and so we often say Teenage children
that don't come home by curfew maybe a complicated relationship clearly you
love them dearly and they drive you nuts also and the spouse who doesn't wash the dishes and I was teaching in prison I
taught in prison for about 15 years before Co and I was doing this in prison and then there was another example that
I hadn't even thought of and I felt this one of my students who's experiencing incarceration and a couple of weeks into
the class he goes I'm really struggling with the meditation on the loved one and I was like what's happening and he goes
he was thinking of his mother in this little village in Mexico that he's the oldest son and he can't take care of her
which he's meant to do in that culture because he's in prison in California so along with the love he has for his
mother comes guilt and shame and all these complex emotions so just to say in
terms of the meditation we say sometimes just your besy that it's uncomp like all
human relationships are complicated admitting that and maybe a less complicated one and I think I don't have
children in this life so I just speak from kind of conversations with people
and just my own you know but kind of just realizing I mean from a Buddhist
perspective it's really help me and and trying to help other people is go they
have their own Karma you can be a condition to maybe help them or not but
you cannot live their life for them you can't force them into choices all you
can do is try to gently seed kind of the field with some suggestions and so forth
and then you really do have to let go and then sometimes even by letting go they'll come to and talk to you more
than they would and you can actually be more effective you know they say it's like there's a a sort of like with
meditation practice like you hang on too hard and try and control your mind too
much you just drive yourself crazy and stir everything up but it shouldn't be too LAX either and I think that metaphor
works for almost everything including relationships like you're holding but you're not squeezing and gripping so
tightly and it's so hard as a parent I know because you want their happiness more than anything and you just jump in
front of the speeding freight train to save them and just realizing the boundary of what you can do and what you
can't do and and yeah the just realizing kind of a realistic boundary of what is
helping even look like and what's actually the best way to help and often with people just being more of a
listener is the best thing we can do like empathic presence and listening is
absolutely 100% people are always going what do I do with this person and they're taking drugs and they're doing
this and that just ask them questions and listen and listen and listen and listen and that can be the best way to
really be supportive and then maybe regain or establish even deeper trust
that then they can will ask for and even take your advice after lots and lots of
empathic presence so that's what's coming up for me I hope thank you I had taken the 8we seare
class about 18 months ago oh did you so the one thing when when my son and I
realized that we were following back in Old patterns a couple weeks ago I I told him I said I'm sorry that I
haven't been an active listener because if we're if we're going to be support
for you if we're if you are going to rely on us to reach out and share your
struggles it means I have to sit in the active listen and it's hard it's hard
it's a hard the more you care the harder it is weirdly but the more it helps so yeah yeah thank you there's somebody
behind you yeah I think for the YouTube people
really want to break out and song and dance when I get this um I oh thank you you in front of
everybody I'm Ania and um I really resonate I don't know your name whoever
just spoke but I really resonate with the space that you're in but I will keep that for um after this I'm a mama too um
I wanted to share that first of all thank you it's such a good one it's such
a good one if we could just ask that the whole world stop at one moment and do it
together yeah um that said I noticed having done this before that when I got
to my person that I felt um a little bit of resistance too
um I noticed what was going on in my body that I needed and granted if we had
done this for hours it might have dissipated but I noticed my B my body tighten in a way
that I was protecting myself m and I noticed immediately that forgiveness
floated up and I realized in order for me to be truly
connected there there were things that that needed to also be there in addition to compassion yeah and it was much
easier to step back and and be in that
space with someone I don't know yeah yeah yeah and I and I you know I can
probably analyze the heck out of that because I'm a therapist but that said um it was interesting to watch and then
just let it be there yeah yeah yeah nice really just keep opening the heart and sending the light versus really thinking
of any characteristics yeah right or wishing for them I just wanted to
envelop them in light and space nice so they could be who they were and I could be yeah right right right anyway and
sometimes even oh this is such a long we've got two minutes what do I even
say when I teach the the longer class I show this diagram that originally comes
from education and you might have seen it and there's like three concentric circles and there's the comfort zone and
the growth Zone and then sometimes called the stress zone or the overwhelm Zone and so in the
training you know whether it's 8 weeks or 90 minutes with you guys I'll kind of
introduce all the steps but then in our practice we we want to push the edge of
the comfort zone obviously if you stay in your comfort zone forever it's just the loved one and it's your bestie and
no big deal so we want to stretch into the growth Zone but not so far and
sometimes we don't know that until like you you're in the middle of the practice and you're like too much a little too or
you need to realize okay I'll just send a bunch of light out but I don't want much of a
connection to you yet it doesn't feel safe and then there's a whole long story
about forgiveness that we often mistake forgiveness means reestablishing trust
and letting the person back into our life in the same way they were before and there's a beautiful book by Bishop
Desmond Tutu and his daughter mafot tutu and he's like no you can choose to release the relationship create a new
boundary if the person is really not trustworthy or you just don't don't want them close but that doesn't need to
prevent your forgiveness but you're like you used to be way up here I can forgive
you but I want you out here now and I think it's our thinking that forgiveness
and reestablishing trust always go together that prevents us from
forgiveness so that's a that's an interesting thing yeah real real quick we're at time but yeah real quick to add
on
okay YouTubes I got you um you can tell I'm old in low Tech because I don't know
how this goes just quickly wanted to say in that in our Humanity in our bodies I
think there's a degree of safety there's an emotional safety piece and it lives in here and so even without the thought
that forgiveness means trust and and duplicating what was um there's still a
natural physiological reaction and it needs honoring yeah AB here we are thank
you so much yeah yeah and this is yeah this would be a whole another session I
yes no doubt I'm at time and I want to finish with a poem because that's like an Insight thing isn't it I've this
Tibetan Buddhist has gotten all into poetry since I've been hanging out with you guys but there's a poem that I want
to close with and just to thank you all it's great to be here in this space with
you and thank you for engaging in that meditation and I'll be around for a while if people want to keep keep
talking I was told that's okay for me to lurk around for a while so I I'm happy
to do that and then just to close our time this is actually a poem that was
sent to me by Bob Stall who some of you may know who's the was the Insight Santa
Cruz guiding teacher by Rosemary Wata traumer and it's called sometimes like
today we remember sometimes like today we
remember that everyone even the driver in that white Jeep who cut in front of
you yes even the elegant woman in the dairy aisle and the man who seems lost
on the library steps and the child sitting alone on the
bench yes everyone has a story fears and hopes and something to learn and someone
they love and someone who's hurt them and someone they long to
hold and though their stories are mostly invisible they're always more complex
than whatever we project and they're every bit as real as our
own the woman in the dairy AIS Smiles at you and though she is wearing diamonds
in her ears she looks lonely or is it you who is lonely is it all of
us all of us longing for someone to truly see us and that driver you're
cursing don't we all sometimes feel as if we need to move forward any way we
can and that boy on the bench notice the empty seat beside him perhaps you could
sit there too in the sun who knows what might happen
next thank you Oh Happy Father's Day also I just
realized there's at Le how many how many fathers in well Happy Father's Day to
all the dads and all the families great thank you so much hope to see you again