so uh so welcome folks uh welcome to you all yeah nice to
see your names um I have a different
Zoom backdrop today I'm at the Mother Ship
uh in uh Redwood City IMC and um
yeah happy happy to be here I did not deliberately position my head above the
Buddha which is a no no but that's the the the angle here we got going anyway
um let us let us uh let us
practice
e e
so settling
uh settling the way we've always
done settling as if for the first
time e
just letting your attention drop first into your chest the Heart
Center expansion contraction of your
lungs for
and dropping down again to your to your belly
my my head and my heart feel so run
through by space but
uh my belly belly I associate with the
Earth groundedness stability
gravity e
just keeping contact with the
Earth e
breathing in such a way that
uh each breath connects you more deeply to the
Earth to the Earth element to sense of
groundedness
rootedness
e
e for
we pay attention in part to
discover what we
love to discover our love
to let the subtlety and refinement the
Attunement sensitivity of our
attention reveal our love and
care what actually matters to us Moment by moment
for
e
e for
we don't insist upon answering the question where is my love what do I love
we or just very patient offering our
attention letting the the poignancy
of having been born just come to us in its own
time e
that sometime in due
time the uh necessity of Love dawns unmistakably
from the groundedness of our
belly begin to uh fill out our
body with uh the heart energy he
heart trembling in the face of all phenomena
sensitive flexible
very strong because it's flexible
becomes very natural to wish ourselves
well
e
e e
how can you express care for yourself
care for your life with your attention in this
moment
e
for
e e
as we uh become grounded
open just one drop of uh love flavors everything
hatred becomes a kind
of fever dream
easy to put down I will not
betray my heart my
love it hurts uh too much whatever job hatred is supposed to
do something else can do it
better so we breathe we feel our
love e
for
[Music]
e
okay good to uh good to say with
you so um
du uh usually rendered as um
suffering is uh is everywhere everywhere
and obvious um but also kind of
shocking from the uh the maim andaya
the the Buddha says this this D I have reached is deep hard to
see difficult to awaken to quiet and
excellent not confined by thought subtle
sensed by the
wise Dua in other words is is both easy and hard to
see when there's some hard moment uh there some part of us that
can barely believe it you know like how could it have unfolded this way how
could the universe do this Hal Alan an artist and um
psychologist wrote this kind of uh grief poem
um or she included the lines that the the patients who come to me swarmed with
misery and astonishment their hearts like newborns
after the first needle Duke uh can uh can feel like
that and the question how should I love how do I respond to
this that that never gets fully answered people who think they know how to
love think they've answered the question how should I love they stop growing how do I love is
not a question it's a
the Buddha asks us to to comprehend suffering to comprehend
suffering and the act of comprehending highlights the necessity of love if we
actually get close enough to perceiving
suffering you don't need to be told about the necessity of love it becomes
self-evident because you can sense that there's no way to meet meet the
intensity of The Human Condition without crumbling or clinging unless we steep
ourselves in love and the alternatives to
love really are something like hate or apathy
nihilism and so it's sort of like yeah there's some details to be worked out but the path is
very clear so today
compassion compassion love in the face of dukka the wish that it be
alleviated and it's a love um infused with wisdom part of compassion is coming
to a more nuanced understanding of our suffering so often we
misdiagnose our pain our suffering and we tend to
embrace um single cause models you know like it's this it's the that person that
thing that tangle that pain but the truth is almost always more
complex so part of compassion is actually appreciating
uh Patia samua the dependent arising that that there's a very complex causal
webs that bring suffering to our heart if we get too simple if we make
the wrong diagnosis it sets us out on the course of the wrong treatment
approach and so we are developing wisdom
a of nuanced understanding of the nature of our own
suffering and um excuse me um so often so often we we want to uh
control our suffering rather than understand it and
um compassion makes us peace patient in our
understanding for for um many
um the kind of gateway to compassion is is something like
um uh is mingled with grief with loss with
the changing of all things with anicha anicha
and um Katherine uh Schultz is so
um articulate on this I like to quote her so she writes
um uh and this is uh reflecting on on the death of her
father um she says um this is the essential avaricious nature of loss it
encompass purp is without distinction the trivial and the consequential the abstract and the
concrete the merely misplaced and the permanently gone we often ignore its true scope if
we can but for a while after my father died I could not s stop seeing the world
as it really is marked Everywhere by the evidence of past losses and the
imminence of future ones this was not because his death was a
tragedy my father died peacefully at 74 attended throughout his
final weeks by those he loved most it was because his death was not a
tragedy what shocked me was that something so sad could be the normal
necessary way of things in its aftermath each individual
life seemed to contain too much heartbreak for its fleeting duration history which I had always
loved even in its silences and Mysteries seemed like little more than a
record of loss at an epic scale especially where it could offer no
record at all the world itself seemed ephemeral glaciers and species and ecosystems
Vanishing the pace of change has Swift as in a
time lapse as if those of us alive today had be been permitted to see it from the
harrowing perspective of Eternity everything felt fragile everything felt
vulnerable the idea of loss pressed in all around me like a hidden order to
existence that emerged only only in the presence of
grief we take that in and uh what is there to do other than to
love wisely love knowing
change compass um it's not uh it's not an unmeshed love
it's not emotional contagion you know my my conditioning
around love is a kind of in mesed model you might say like
your pain is my pain is your pain love and space are somehow
intention rather than space affording room for love for a
compassion that um feels sustainable and so I found that
um that certain kinds of suffering suffering of loved ones can spin me in a
distinctive way where my words masquerade as compassion but are
actually an expression of my own intolerance of their pain and the impact
it has on my heart and that makes sense as um as
children the suffering of a parent or caretaker is not an opportunity for
compassion it's an existential threat our safety depends
entirely on their power and maybe those early formative
experiences encode some sense sense of fear in the face of the suffering of the
other but we remember compassion is not an insistence that someone change
and it's not it's not even in the insistence that someone stop
suffering it's love in the face of suffering
we're distilling out some of the compulsivity our own
intolerances compassion is not not empathy um affective empathy kind of
emotional empathy is feeling the the inner emotional life of the
other um and that that's maybe a comp opponent of
compassion but um but that's not but compassion the the
dimension of Love is Central if if it it's compassion
entails a willingness to grieve but that cannot be the last word
of our compassion grief cannot be the last word of our compassion there is
this sense of of a love that actually holds
it compassion's not a demand it's it's maybe it sometimes it
feels like um a prayer directed to who knows what some Sor don't know
but a kind of quiet prayer not a
demand and it's incredibly intimate
because your pity allows some space you know but
compassion compassion you're like truly undefended in the face of their
suffering and sometimes the insistence that their suffering is relieved is
merely another defense another way of blunting the full
impact sometimes the advice giving that we extend is merely another way to blunt
the full impact the intimacy of meeting suffering together
with love and to let suffering in
Deeply One must trust love deeply one must
trust that the last word of
pain is love
and as we'll get to I think in these Realms one must also
trust that other Brahma vihara UPA equinity
true love Tian says never makes you
suffer but um that means there that love needs a
lot of wisdom infused into
it that love needs to come from um a place of of real deep refinement in
ourselves as we practice we start to release our own pain and the pain of the
world ceases to resonate with our wounds but instead with our
heart when the pain of the world resonates with our wounds there's a kind of
Intolerable desperation around compassion and intolerance so suffering
when it resonates with our heart our love
becomes steady patient knowing the more free we become the more
potent our compassion becomes it is an emanation of our love
rather than our fear so I offer this for your
consideration and um uh yeah I appreciate the chance to um
reflect on these things with you and uh we'll be back tomorrow
Joy okay