welcome second day of 2024 second Noble
Truth delighted to be back with you this morning I hope the practice was fruitful
yesterday let's see what today
brings so we're starting this first series of the year on the four noble
truths returning to the root as it were to the the uh basic frame that can hold
all of the Buddhist teaching most of the Buddhist teaching
discussing uh what's taught as the spiritual problem uh in Buddha
[Music] Dharma along with the Buddha's analysis of that problem and then it's
uh the promise and possibility of freedom and the way to that
freedom it's inspiring for this this one here so
let's uh let's begin with the
meditation
preparation for this meditation as yesterday is an
image so as you settle into your
seat or whatever is supporting
you beginning to feel
stable I would invite you to bring this image to
mind I can imagine that
you're maybe standing maybe SE did next to a cool Clear
Lake this lake is
vast it's broad it's wide and it's reflecting the the Open
Sky and you
you're safely on the ground but you're near the
depths this moment you notice there is a weight in your
pocket and you reach in finding The Three
Stones maybe different colors and textures you can feel them in your hands and see them in your
hands maybe they're warm from your body
heat and after appreciating them for a moment
you realize you don't need to hold them anymore you extend your arm over the
Deep cool water and slowly start turning your
[Music] palm you can feel the rock
nudge then slide and
disappear dropping out of your hand and punk into the
water you can watch them fade and returning attention to your
hands feeling what was await is now an
absence empty
light
at the time of this
meditation as we gently kindly attend to the body this body
breathing do we not need to hold
anymore
what can be let go and offer it to this vast cool
L
breathing in breathing [Music]
out letting go of what's
Extra
may find that we're staying close to the
senses the senses without the added weight
of reactions and
involvement
breathing and letting [Music] go
making room for a a welcome
nothing
being near the senses and letting go of what's
Extra letting go of what's
extra what do you notice about what's left
behind
in these last minutes of the sitting
sensing
breathing having let go of what's
extra to appreciate the
possibility the possibility within the
absence
they all GS
everywhere have the conditions to let go of what is
extra to let go of what's weary
making making room for this
absence possibility and
peace
de
and again
oh what wonder that absence keeps turning into
something oh what might emerge for us
today so today we turn from the first Noble Truth to the second Noble
Truth in our Reflections on this Core teaching of Luna
Dharma wanted to open with a a story from the suas there's a
um uh a householder named upali who goes to have a conversation
with the Buddha a few circumstan an es transpire and then it's this that I want
to share for how it it says the Buddha prepares up Al's mind to receive the
teachings on the four noble truths doesn't Dive Right In And this is an important point the the four noble
truths we often introduce um as like the the first the first teaching but you can
see in this in this little section from the ancient teachings that actually the
uh the Mind does to be prepared to receive the for noble truths and this is how it's uh written
there so it goes then the Buddha gave the householder upali Progressive instruction that is
talk on giving talk on virtue talk on Heavens he explained the danger
degradation and defilement and sensual pleasures and the blessings of
renunciation and when he knew when the Buddha knew that the householder up Al's mind was
ready receptive free from hindrances elated
and confident he expounded to him the teaching special to the
Buddhas suffering its origin its
cessation and the path you might recognize these as the four noble truths in brief and it says
that just as a clean cloth would uh evenly take on dye so to the householder
upali as he sat there had this spotless Immaculate vision of the Dharma arise in
him it's so beautiful it's amazing to me also that
just hearing the teaching um was transformative for upali I think that shows the power of
reflection and for the the the power of uh cultivating the supports for
understanding and wisdom and well-being so the tradition often
teaches the four noble truths as uh Dua suffering the origin cause of suffering
as the second Noble Truth the sensation of suffering as the third and the fourth
Noble Truth as the path the way to the cessation of suffering now Gil gives some great talks
on u a distinction he brings in something called the four liberating
insights where he points out that the um four noble truths as such aren't named
so many times in the in the sutas but the um the direct clear seeing of Dua
and its arising clearly seeing the arising of Dua right here in experience then
clearly seeing its cessation and clearly seeing the path that these have a liberating power to see these four
things it's a really powerful framing I think uh and it points us back to the
practice happening right here in this mind in this body in other words our experience of
Dua our experience of suffering is constructed or made or born out in this
mind that's how we experience it not to say that's the only condition of
course so I think that this is uh this emphasis on the mind is well expressed in uh the
beginning of the the first verses of the dapada and say all experiences preceded
by mind led by mind and made by mind speak or act with a corrupted mind and
suffering follows as the Wagon Wheel follows the hoof of the
ox all experiences preceded by mind led by mind made by mind speaker act with a
peaceful mind and happiness follows like a never departing
Shadow such is the importance of the mind so as the task of the first Noble
Truth was to understand comprehend Dua in indirect experience the task of the
second Noble Truth is to abandon to abandon what and abandon in
what sense so first uh abandon in what sense um the word in English abandon has
a has certain connotations but when you look at the teachings what you find is that it's much more like letting go of
what's not needed anymore or uh the way we use abandon in the term Abandon Ship
this like this the ship is clearly going down it's time to get off for our safety and well-being that kind of abandon ship
and what are we abandoning we're abandoning the the conditions that give rise to
suffering the conditions that give rise to suffering and this points this points to
um something important about suffering and that is it arises based on
conditions just like everything else in our experience that um because suffering is
conditioned it's not uh an instance of suffering isn't forever stable forever
permanent it's bound to change so the conditions that give rise
to suffering uh in the classic teaching it says that the the origin or the cause
or the arising of suffering is um a certain kind of
craving now of course we um in in Buddhist circles we uh uh we might run
the risk of generalizing and saying something like all desire is the the the
cause of suffering but this isn't quite right if you look if you look closely what um the sort of craving that
leads on to suffering is what we're looking for and the Buddha points to a few
um the p is K tanan and
viaan and piku Bodi the great the prolific translator summarizes these
like so he says the the desire for pleasure and
possessions the drive for survival the urge to bolster the sense of ego with
power status and privilege that these are the sorts of
things that we need to um we need to watch for keep an eye on because they can lead
on they can lead on through clinging creation of identity to the sort of
suffering that uh the Buddha is helping us to
eradicate so if we want to abandon the conditions that give rise to suffering we have to get to know them really
closely the Buddha's analysis of duka of suffering and craving traces its origin to a sort of darkening of the
mind we that we term ignorance in po the word is actually the
the opposite term of wisdom so for today I want to I want to
um for the the next few minutes talk about a few examples of how in the one
of the Buddhist descriptions we go from sense experience to clinging and look at
these links pretty closely and in a few ways so so that they they can um be practiced
with these few links uh of the 12-fold chain U say like a 12 factor analysis of
how suffering arise just just going to zoom in on a couple and these
are first is a moment of sense contact that's like a sound coming to the
ear with that as a condition a feeling arises that is a feeling of pleasant or
unpleasant or neither Pleasant or unpleasant or neutral with feeling as condition the
conditions are in place for a craving to arise a thirst sting to arise an Impulse
to um get closer or to move away and this impulse can condition
clinging upana it's grabbing on grasping and then grabbing on grasping
as condition comes identity making becoming so we can we'll look at this in
just a few ways so let's take this example of a sound
it comes to the ear say say you're sitting in meditation and you hear a bird outside you happen to like the
sound of this bird first thing that happens if you're noticing very very closely sound comes to the door there's
a pleasant feeling that arises in the body maybe in the ear
itself and if you watch closely that Pleasant feeling arises oh here comes
rving oh the bird has faded away and I'm wanting sound of the bird is faded away
and I'm craving for more sound of bird that was so pleasant or I'm or I'm craving for more pleasant feeling that's
Arisen that craving arises and then we grasp on we start strategizing about how
we're going to hear more birds fantasizing about birds um and then all
of a sudden we have created an identity that's oh I'm I'm the person who likes and seeks Birds we've gone from the
simple sound sitting here in meditation AR Rising a Pleasant feeling wanting it
and Clinging On and then all of a sudden we've created a self
imagine so this um that's sort of an innocuous example of how that can happen with a
pleasant sensation or a pleasant sense contact that arises also also can um we
can take the example of maybe um unpleasant speech let's say we're
having a conversation of and let's say at our ear again we come into contact
with a sort of everyday but innocuous speech um there's no like particular
boundary issue that needs pushing back on there's no threat there's just the experience of
unpleasant speech comes to the ear again unpleasant sensation this time and
then craving comes up in the form of wanting to push away push away push away
want to push against the experience and then all of a sudden we're grasping onto the
pushing doubling down on the pushing if we will so pleasant and unpleasant if
you're watching for it it's happening all the time throughout the day you can
you can see and feel and sense the way that that uh Pleasant and
unpleasant they don't remain just themselves they can we have the power to
do this with mindfulness but very very often if we're not paying so so close
attention if ignorance is in the way what happens is our our pleasant
experience becomes craving clinging and we just go full in we become fully
committed to an Impulse we're no longer in control of our body and mind craving
and ignorance and clinging have taken over so my encouragement for today might be
um if you happen to notice this uh Pleasant and unpleasant sensation get
really close to noticing how it influences us influences the Mind influences the
body and the way this fulfills the task of the second Noble Truth it supports Us
in abandoning craving because we can see and observe and recognize how craving
operates we understand suffering as suffering we sense it we see it and we
can maybe have the opportunity to Let It Go but we'll start with just getting to
know it getting to know suffering and then through observation and patience practice letting go of this
this cause of the second Noble
Truth thanks so much for your attention today and tomorrow we'll pick up with
the third Noble Truth may all
beings may all beings have the conditions for Freedom may all beings abandon the
causes of suffering and no true happiness take
care