so good morning everyone and I hope you can hear me maybe it would be nice to have a sound check I am at
um Insight Retreat Center some of you remember mahapajapati
the Nam um pachara the uh one of the early nuns who
was very important in early Buddhist tradition a teacher for many other nuns great teacher and now we have a
wonderful statue of her in the walking meditation Hall good so the sound is
good great and uh so I'm here in the walking meditation Hall at Insight
retreat center and I'm here um with
a helping to teach a our IMC teacher training program we have 15 people that
we're training to become next generation of teachers and
uh and and um delighted to be able to be back
here um two of those are Liz Powell and and Cotto conin who taught for the last
two weeks and delighted that they could be here at 700 a.m. and teach with you
while I had a vacation and um I'm very happy to be back here and to be with you at the
beginning of the year
the uh the the plan for the next five weeks that I'm here I think there's a there's
a one week I'm away but for those the the weeks that I'm here is to offer um
the basic teachings that we teach at IMC the basic teachings that I teach when I teach mindfulness meditation at an intro
to meditation class or somewhat the structure the format used for
Retreats and uh and but to do it uh uh
uh there's five areas uh breath body emotions thoughts and then life itself
the rest of it and uh and I want to spend a week on each area to be able to go into some depth and some nuance and
some application of these five important areas and so what we'll do is like this
week we'll be breathing and um and each day we'll go a little bit further uh in
with this topic of mindfulness of breathing and and uh and uh and then we'll do
repeat the same for the body so um to begin with the most basic
way of doing meditation which is relevant for people
who are new and relevant people who are very experienced and uh I think the more
experienced we are the more useful it is to return to Basics and the more experienced we are
more more we appreciate the Simplicity of the basics aspect of meditation that
we're not looking for fireworks we're not looking
for something very special beyond the specialness of being fully present for
life as it comes to us to be present for as it is and uh and Delight or
appreciate deeply our capacity to be conscious to be aware of what's happening and and
find a refuge in that awareness and so the most simple way of
understanding or I I propose today a very simple way of understanding the beginning of
meditation is uh to become aware of how distracted you are to become aware of um how your we
not in the present moment that we lose our sense of kind of poignant awareness
of the present we lose touch with the fact that it's special very special kind
of a a marvelous thing a Marvel to be conscious even what is it how did the
universe arise so that the Universe could be conscious of itself in this way
that is through through us and um so the for I'd like to offer
then would meditate one that I like very much to use is that of
a um of a very clear Mountain
Creek and uh you're sitting on the edge of the creek and this is based on
experience I had up in the mountains not far from here and uh and
um not being able to tell whether the water is Flowing or not it's very clear
seemed very very still and so I took a stick and put it into the water um
vertically and then I could see that there was a little current um little wavelets that were formed on the edge of
the of the of the stick and so I saw oh there's a current water is in fact moving and sometimes it's difficult to
see that our mind is moving a lot it's distracted and CAU what it's caught up in because we're so caught up in it
um we're too distracted we're distracted from our distractions by our
distractions and um and so something as simple as returning to the breath returning to the body here in the
present moment um what rather than thinking you have to be successful at
staying with a breath staying present with the body every time we
return and stay with the breathing for just a little while uh if it
highlights how you're distracted how the mind is wandering off that's
successful that's a good moment to say oh that's how I'm that's what I'm concerned with that's what I'm caught up
in oh this is a busy mind this is a distracted mind this is a preoccupation
with my feelings and what's going on this is what's taking me away from this
moment being present conscious here this is how I lose touch with the miracle of
mindfulness the miracle of awareness so
um so um some people are saying the sound
is low it could well be I'm using the the the um I'm using
the the mic on the laptop maybe if I come a little bit closer maybe and I'll
try maybe I'll try speaking a little louder um maybe my voice is particularly
soft when I'm at The Retreat Center so to assume a meditation
posture and um and it's a posture that is
to um Express an
interest a dedication to being present to really
being here and if we take a posture that is sometimes too relaxed to you know n no
muscles could be are being used to be present then there's less support from
the body to be really be here it's fine to be laying down if
that's what how you meditate but even then it might be possible to uh have one
one or both arms uh maybe the elbows on the side but the forearms pointing to
the ceiling so there's kind of a um intentionality to be here a kind of a
physical participation and yes here I
am for those sitting in a chair to uh if it's Works to sit up a little
straighter so that the spine or the chest belly the head are a little bit
Express are expressing this capacity to be
present supporting our ability to
notice when we become distracted when we get it's pulled into
the world of thoughts or feelings so we're no longer
aware of now to lower your
gaze and if it's comfortable to close your
eyes and to spend a few moments preparing yourself for the
meditation by taking a few deeper breaths just deep enough that it stays
comfortable for
you and a long
exhale deep deeper breaths Fuller breaths slower
breaths can be a way that helps our muscles in the body to
relax slow little deeper
breaths seems to function as a reassurance to for our nervous system
things are okay for these
minutes and as you
exhale to relax your
body and then to let your breathing return to
normal or almost normal it might be nice to let your breathing continue to be a
little slower a little longer
deeper and as you do so to relax your body
me
and then settling into your body to become aware of the body's
experience of breathing some people will feel the breathing in
their chest as a chest Moves In and Out expands and
contracts some people feel their breathing the body breathing in the
belly the expansion and contraction of the
belly some people feel body breathing with the air going in and out through the
nostrils
and some people feel all of that kind of a global
experience of
breathing and then
not so much trying to stay with your
breathing but rather to have the connection to
breathing highlight for you when you lose that
connection when you you get pulled into distractions or thoughts
preoccupations and rather than drifting off in those thoughts and
preoccupations no clearly no this is what's happening oh here is a
mind that's thinking that's preoccupied that has
concerns and if you have that kind of clarity you're not really
preoccupied you're present you know what's
happening and then Begin Again with your
breathing over and over again return to your
breathing and notice when you lose touch with
that when you're pre preoccupied or swept in up in your thoughts and
concerns again may be
delighted that you can see this you can know this for some of you maybe it's kind of
fun to do it like a little game noticing it's best you
can where the mind is like a
little kid toddler who's playing hide and go
seek the mind is kind of running off by itself so that you don't notice that
you're thinking don't notice what you're caught up
in and you're delighted to say hi I see
you and then Begin Again with your breath
breathing
for
for this meditation there's no need to be frustrated with not staying on your
breathing the function of breathing is to mindfulness of breathing is to help you become clearer
more observant of when you're not with your
breath and what is it that takes you away to clearly see
that almost like you're taking a backward step and looking back oh this is a thinking
mind this is preoccupation this is being pulled into
the world of emotions this is what takes me away
from being present for this moment as it
is
for
if you know you are distracted you're not really distracted
anymore you simply know you recognize the forces of
distraction that are operating in you without being lost in
them
for
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to appreciate or recognize that
the more meaningful or more direct or connected ways we have of being with
other people requires us to be present with
them the more distracted we are the more we're caught up in our own
thoughts concerns the less friend active
friendliness care love
kindness respect attention do we have for
others to become be able to recognize when we're
distracted to be wise about
it to not be distracted by our
distractions but to be able to switch
gears to offer our presence our attention here and
now so we can feel and appreciate the full Humanity of someone else
else and in so
doing to better be able to be friendly kind
respectful well wishing for
others and one of the very important aspect of Buddhist spirituality
is to awaken our good
will for others people animals for life
itself may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe
may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may our ability to be present for
others with our Attention our kindness May that contribute to the
welfare and happiness of
everyone thank you very much I'm bowing to all of you I don't have a bell here
to Ring to end the sitting so um this is now the
end
so again hello and with this talk I begin now a week
on um mindfulness of breathing as part of a five week series on introducing the
basic elements of mindfulness meditation as taught at IMC inside meditation
center and um I'm hoping that to spend five days on
each of these five topics of these weeks breathing body emotions thinking and
then bringing the practice into our life that uh over the five days we're laying
down a foundation and moving into a fuller experience of it that uh maybe it
will be appreciated by people who are well experienced in practice as well and
for those of you whove had instructions basic instructions in mindfulness before I hope that it's a
little bit different um what I have to offer so so it has a little different
perspective um and maybe it goes a little bit further about the potentiality of this wonderful practice
that we do so um so we're here to prac practice
mindfulness and um the synonym I use for mindfulness is
awareness and um but in kind of developing a lucid awareness or a
Clarity of awareness that we're we're really present for our experience and
we're knowing it we're feeling it seeing it we're really there with the
experience in a way that it feels a little bit like a miracle which is uh maybe it's not a
miracle exactly who knows what a miracle is but what a Marvel what a special thing to be conscious to be
aware and um and just to really feel that awareness to feel that to know that
we're here and present I mean this is we're not going to be around and alive for that long and this is the special
time that uh for us to be conscious to be aware to be present the spark of life
is spark of Consciousness that will soon soon enough pass and someone else will
have it um there's been many people over the thousands of years who had their
time to be present now we have our time and to use that
well uh to discover the miracle of being really
aware the the potentiality of it and how it leads us to both a freedom and
a in a catalyst evoking for the emergence of really beautiful potential
that we have that comes from with freedom so it starts very simple the
instructions and mindfulness and I would like to suggest that it starts first and
foremost by just becoming aware that we're not aware that we're
distracted to recognize clear clearly that we are distracted when we are distracted and
when we sit down to meditate uh the basic kind of instructions is to meditate with
breathing um be mindful of your breathing um but rather than thinking that you're supposed to stay focused in
the breath and that that something you're doing something wrong if your mind loses touch with breathing uh some
people can barely be aware of one full breath before the mind wanders off
um and then they get upset that the mind wanders off and they're not doing what they're supposed to be doing the
beginning instructions is not is to use the breathing as a basis or Foundation but
not to be undistracted but rather to have the breathing help you see how distracted
you are and sometimes what we discover when we sit down to meditate is that the
mind is a hurricane the mind is a is a um kind of waterfall cascading of
thoughts or a fountain spewing out things or just a chaos
something and uh and rather than thinking that then you're not meditating or doing it wrong for mindfulness
meditation that's a fantast that's the first Insight that we many people
discover the mind is out of control wow this is the wow the mind has a mind of
its own it's just thinking and and uh and fantasizing and remembering and
planning and arguing and complaining and wow it's doing all this stuff and that
wow that's see oh that's what's happening that's the moment we're not
distracted to know that we're distracted paradoxically is at that
moment we're not because we know what's going on and um and and then we're doing
the mindfulness practice so this is a very important point because if you don't understand
this point and think the point is to stay focused and continuous with the breathing and then get upset when you're
distracted then you're just agitating yourself some more you're just being even more distracted by the
upset but to not be upset by a distracted mind is part of the training
of mindfulness to learn learn how not to be activated or
reactivated by uh our likes and dislikes what we think should be happening and not
happening how we judge ourselves for what's happening but simply to learn the
art of clearly seeing clearly recognizing oh that's what's
happening so to take a meditation posture that gives you some
stability so the posture itself expresses a sense of being really
present I'm inspired by little children maybe children who can't even walk yet
and um maybe still in their diapers I've seen sometimes we know where they have a bare chest a bare torso there's no
clothes in a warm day or something and how they can sit upright on the floor
and that the uprightness of those spines is so beautiful to
see the alertness the presence and their bodies are completely kind of relaxed
they're too young to carry a lot of tension sometimes but the beauty of just kind of alertness of the body taking a
posture it's clear that they're attentive and present or like a dog standing at attention in a relaxed way
but it's clear the dog is you know really attend attending so the idea is
to kind of find a posture that can be relaxed uh not tense if there's a lot of
tension then want to emphasize a relaxing posture but sooner or later
it's not only about relaxing it's also about uh kind of a a um sense of strong
attentiveness or a alert attentiveness like with through the
body so take some care with the posture and uh the U and then um
and then relax soften and take some deep breaths both
to help you relax further but also to begin becoming familiar with what
breathing is like let the breathing then after a while return to normal and then
notice how you're distracted notice how the mind wanders off notice the
preoccupations and once you have a Clarity of knowing that
without ideally without judgment if you're judging it that's just one more distraction that you can
be aware of oh judging judging thinking just seeing clearly
what's going on the tricks of the mind and how you get pulled away from the present moment in
it and uh or or pulled pulled away from it or you know into other times and
places or see how you're so judging or so reactive to what's happening at the present moment that the quality of
attention is not fully present it's kind of now being through a filter of
reactivity and pulling away or wanting something different and um and the idea is we're
starting to become familiar with all the ways in which we
are not fully present without judgment about it without criticism about it
and learning to appreciate that that is a moment of attention that's a moment of mindfulness
to see how we're distracted and in after a few moments of
that Clarity and Rec oh boy I'm really spending a lot of time planning my day
this is planning my day or I'm reviewing that conversation yesterday and
complaining or coming up with a better response than I did or I'm just living in my regrets reviewing over and over
again the terrible things I did that's what's happening um so instead of oh that's is
terrible I'm a terrible person or or without just justifying I need to plan
I'm supposed to plan and come up with all the all the different reasons why you're supposed to be doing it the idea
is to is to find that place where we can very matter of factly Simply directly
know I'm distracted raed uh I'm caught up this is how I'm
caught up we're starting to become familiar with the tricks of the Mind how the mind takes us away from a
qualitatively rich way of being present here and now so do that for a few moments and
then come back to the breathing and at this point in the practice this very beginning point the function of the
breathing is not something to stay focused on that's certainly nice if you can do it but rather to help you see
clearly how much you're wandering off you have a reference
point to see the movements of the mind um and if we don't have a reference
point then it's too easy to be pulled into the currents of the mind and not even know that we're being pulled down
the river of the mind um because we're so in it but we have a reference point
so imagine it's kind of like you're in the you don't even know you're floating in Cur into the river but you grab onto
a branch from a tree over overhanging the river and um and you're you're held
there for a few minutes and you're not being pulled along in the current anymore and then you feel the strength
of the current wow it's a strong current or no today it's this area it's a weak
current and then you let go and you're in the current for a while don't even know you're in it until another Branch
comes along and so so the branch for in
in mindfulness meditation is breathing and we hold on and we see more
clearly what's happening and and then we do it again and again seeing how our
mind is distracted and this way distraction is not proof that you're meditating wrong
distraction seeing distraction is how you know you're meditating oh this is how this is what's happening this is
what's oh now I see this is what's happening and um so
um so for and then over the next days we'll
talk more and we'll talk more also about you know getting focused on breathing and staying more continuous with it but
this exercise lays the foundation for our ability to do that in a in a productive useful
way so um
so if you'd like the homework you could do is to do this in your daily life as well
not just in meditation become aware of how you are um distracted in everyday
life how you get pulled into your thoughts and preoccupations so the the attention is not qualitatively rich for
being fully present here for what's happening with a conversation you have with another person for the activity of
in the kitchen that you're doing or cleaning or driving or whatever you're doing start
noticing um how you are uh the tricks of the
mind so um thank you and uh tomorrow I will um be back at IMC and so
I think the quality of the sound will be better I realiz in this room here it's kind of echoey it's and uh it's a big
open room we use for walk meditation and I don't have the the microphone on and
and um so I apologize for those of you with uh who are like me who are uh maybe
not you know need hearing aids or something that uh my voice is soft and maybe didn't come across so well today
so I will but tomorrow be back at IMC and I look forward to being with you and
I hope that you appreciate the nun pachara who is sitting in such a
wonderfully good model for an alert dignified really present way with just
here now um relaxed and
aware so thank you very
much