good evening and welcome welcome everybody it's nice to see you
all for those of you who don't know me I'm Diana Clark and I'm always often
here on Frid on Fridays wow today's only
Monday I'm here on Mondays um except when I'm off teaching Retreats or
something then there's substitute teachers and I want to start by uh
talking about this uh simile this analogy that gets used a lot in uh kind
of in the Buddhist tradition a way to describe practice as a way also as a way
to describe like this whole path of practice to uh Liberation kind I want to like tease it
apart and look at it and see if there's some things that we can learn and like how we can apply it to our own lives
today and way that we can understand and appreciate some of the maybe some of the
finer elements here when we sometimes don't think about or aren't so obvious when we talk about this simile in
particular or also about our practice and I'll start with this notion
of this idea of crossing the floods this is an expression that shows
up a number of times in the early Buddhist literature and maybe it's not surprising ancient India right there in
the gangas plains and you know there's this monsoon season and things flood and
you have to wait till the end of the monsoon season to cross the flood nowadays how many rivers do we
Creeks do we cross and we don't even know it right cuz we're on a freeway or a highway or something but then it was a
big deal that you'd be separated from whomever whatever for months at a time
simply because you couldn't cross over the water and not only is it like separate
you but if you get caught in the flood like you know you get carried away to
presumably some place you didn't want to go so this flood is something that's
overwhelming it's just like takes you over and you don't have a choice so you
get uh carried away to Downstream
presumably and maybe it's you know even incredibly
dangerous so aan suito he's a teacher in this tradition it's a well-respected uh
teacher and he writes about this idea of about crossing the floods and he writes
that it's often um there sometimes people come to practice
practice because they have this feeling of being overwhelmed and things are a little bit out of control and it's just
too much and it's not going the direction I want so maybe there's this feeling of being in the
floods and they wish to be on one of the banks no longer uh being you know
subject to this big body of water that's uh flushing
through this um to this aidea about crossing the flood is then going you
know from getting to where one wants but recognize that it's not going to be so straight forward to get
there and then maybe I'll introduce then the simile that I'd like to spend some
time unpacking today and this is called the simile of the raft it's very common
it's shows up a number of times in the sued teachings and sometimes uh sometimes even like people say well you
know the raft they'll as a shortcut kind of like you know some people today might
say well you know the turtle and the hair and that's all you have to say they like know the whole story the one's
faster than the other and not the one that you think is going to be faster in the same way sometimes this idea of the
raft so here's the simile and then um I'd like to talk about it so this is the
Buddha speaking and he says imagine a person in the course of a
journey arrives at a great expanse of water some translators use the word
flood whose near shore is dangerous and whose far Shore offers
safety but there's no fairy booat or bridge to take them across the
water so the person thinks what if I collect grass and twigs and branches and
leaves and bound them together and create a raft and then supported by the raft and
by paddling with my hands and feet I should then be able to reach the far Shore get across the
flood so then the person does this and succeeds in getting it across to the far shore on arriving at the far Shore it
might occur to them wow this wow I added that that's not suit
us this raft has been very helpful what if I were to hoist it on my head or Lord
load it on my shoulders and proceed on my journey so this idea like okay this ra is really helpful I better carry it
with me everywhere I go and then the Buddha says now what do you think by carrying it with them would
that person be doing what should be done with a raft and the people are listening say no
venerable sir they so then the Buddha ask so what should the person what
should the person do with the raft and then
the Buddhist says having arrived at the far Shore the person might think yes
this raft has been very useful but now I should just haul it onto dry
land or release it and set it a drift in the water and then go wherever I
want in this way the person would be doing what should be done with that raft
so there's a lot of little stories in here that we can empties apart about this and so first of all this is uh some
of these different elements is it starts with imagine a person in the course of a
journey arrives at a great expense of water whose Nearshore is dangerous and
whose far Shore is Safety First is just to notice the near shore is dangerous and this word
dangerous we could use as a simile or as a to stand in for it's not a refuge it's
not a place that will uh can provide some lasting happiness or lasting safety
or lasting ease instead it's going to be difficult
and and some of uh you might have even noticed this during this 30 minute sit
there's often this sense like okay I'm going to sit I'm going to meditate and then what
happens right I think uh all of our minds like human Minds have this idea
that uh maybe there's you notice that the mind starts to wander and uh maybe
it's um thinking about things that you're planning that you need to take care of or maybe there's a memory that
arises or maybe there's a fantasy about something that doesn't even exist yet or
you're rehearsing a conversation that'll happen in the future and they're like oh right I'm supposed to be meditating this
idea like you know okay come back to the meditation for many people it's having mindfulness of the sensations of
breathing but it doesn't take long with a meditation practice for us to be
reminded or aware of we don't control the mind we don't of course we don't if we
did you wouldn't need a meditation practice so there's this sense of like
we don't control where the Mind goes we can't only think happy thoughts we can't
only be like focused exactly when we want to be and be uh relaxed when we
want to be it doesn't work that way and so that's part of like this near shore
being dangerous is that the mind right can get us into all kinds of trouble to
be sure it also can supply all kinds of beautiful fantastic experiences
meaningful experiences and can support us on our path but we don't control it
in the way that we think we might and certainly with practice there's a neuroplasticity right so the
mind just starts to become more and more capable and used to and gets into the
groove of settling down and meditating but it doesn't mean that we can when we're not meditating for example we're
only thinking certain thoughts of course not it doesn't happen I will say with practice though the thoughts start to be
less problematic it stops to be less uh of an
issue but this idea that we don't control them as part of recognizing okay
this far Shore or sorry this near shore isn't a permanent
Refuge but it's not only that it's that
uh there might be this simple activities that we're doing doing that we don't maybe give a second thought to have a
certain amount of dissatisfaction a certain amount of
stress or unease or things just not being quite right or just feeling
downright bad there's this um another assimile
I'll shove in a assimile inside this other assimile that uh that Buddha gives
about doing something that would have been an ordinary thing for people getting in Ancient Ancient India to do
and that is right if they needed light light back then of course was associated with a flame of course and so
the Buddha he gives this uh simile suppose a person took a blazing
grass torch and went against the wind so it's one thing to be lighting your way
but what if the wind is coming this way what do you think if that person
does not quickly like go of that blazing grass torch wouldn't that blazing grass
torch burn their hand or their arm or some other part of the body so that they might incur death or deadly suffering
because of that so this is just an ordinary thing just having to pay attention like okay
if you hold something that's on fire and that's windy chances are you're going to get
burned so too so the Buddha says an a practitioner considers sensual
Pleasures have been compared to a grass torch they provide great disappointment and great trouble while the danger in
them is great so he's saying this some things that we might do might hook us
and we might just be always looking for these Pleasures this addiction to
comfort or this idea that we have to have um everything has to be pleasurable all the time it's not helpful some
examples of this might be that if you notice how you feel like after you've
been like watching too many videos on the internet there's this way
that it's like this icky feeling afterwards you feel drained and the brain is uh at least this happens to me
for those times I've done this I feel like oh my gosh was awful I have a headache and I feel like either what I
was watching was uh makes me feel bad because what's happening there or bad about myself because I my life doesn't
look like their life right of course this type of thing so there's a way in which some of
these things that we think that they're pleasurable actually turn out not to be pleasurable in the big
picture so the Buddha is pointing to just noticing some of the difficulties
that are here in on this Shore but then the simile continues and
it says a person arrives at a great expense of water whose near shore is
dangerous but there's no and the farshore offers safety but there's no
ferry boat or bridge to take them across the water just this recognition oh yeah we
want an easy way we want to have to not even get out of our cars just drive over
we don't get wet we don't even notice but that's not possible for what's being
pointed to here of course we want river boats and
fairies and bridges and something that these things uh imply is that somebody else has done
the work to create them and that maybe we kind of secretly wishing somehow that somebody else will
do the hard labor and we can just benefit from it and in some way I mean the Buddha did
do some hard labor and we are about fting from it but uh he says very
clearly that he shows the way but we have to do the
walking and so this path of practice we actually have to find our way like we
know where to go we can see where we have to go on the other Shore there and we have to figure out how are
we going to do this how are we going to get there so in the simbly says well the
person said says um what if I collected grass Twigs branches and leaves and
bound them together as a raft I love this this grass Twigs branches and
leaves that's just what's right here like this person he's standing on the
banks and that's what's right there he doesn't have to go searching for something specific he doesn't have to I
don't know go contact a Potter and have them make some something or you know it's just nature it's just right here
what's happening and that's true for us also we don't have to wait for just the
right moment just the right conditions we can work on finding our
way to Greater freedom and ease peace Liberation working with exactly what's
happening right now at this moment feel UNC comfortable your mind is
racing feeling very happy have a lot of ease whatever is happening we can work
with that and be part of our practice we there's a number of ways and
that would be a whole Dharma talk like how we can do this here but maybe one way is to not uh get tangled up in them
not get tangled up in this uh these leaves they should be bigger if they were bigger then would be better for or
the grass should be longer you know to recognize how we are always trying to
make things be different we have so much resistance to what's actually
here and instead to put down the resistance and just to work with what's here and it's the putting down the
resistance and paying attention to what's actually here is how the raft
gets built this is that what car carries us across
really and so this simil continues it says supported by the raft
and by paddling with my hands and feet I should then be able to reach the far Shore so I I like this idea like
supported by the raft and paddling with my hands and feet so still having to do
effort even though it made a raft it doesn't mean that like it's just a
downhill from there on or you know smooth sailing but this idea of creating
the conditions in which maybe we could do something that we couldn't do before
now we can do some paddling where before all we could do was walking or something like this and so much of our practice is um
increasing our capacities our capacities to be with discomfort our capacities to be present
for ourselves to honor and respect our ourselves to honor and respect
others and when these things start to happen this honor and respect and
capability of being just uncomfortable then things unfold in a different way
they unfold with greater ease they unfold with
a more I'm going to use this word
ease without us trying to like you know manufacturer and no I don't want this
trying to make sure it doesn't go that way or something and we're blaming and
criticizing and getting angry and upset and but instead like no okay I have
grass leaves twigs and branches this is what I'm going to work with going to
work with them and create a raft that's then going to help me move to the other
side and then you know I stop to paddle when I get there and I I love this idea
of kind like paddling with hands and feet yeah with what you have maybe everybody doesn't have use of
all their hands or both of their feet but you work with what you have I think that's what's being pointed
to here so there's this also this we're having
to notice that the other bank is not dangerous like this wish to want to go there in the first place
and this requires that we have a sense of oh yeah less difficulties less
suffering less stress less dissatisfaction is
possible we have to have that sense it is possible otherwise why would we
bother and chances are all of us know this because we touch into it
sometimes maybe as part of medit ation practice maybe there's just times in our life when we have a certain
ease hiking with the redwood trees sitting at the beach waking up
from a fantastic nap where you feel really refreshed having loved ones nearby
grandkids kids siblings parents whatever it might be whomever it might be there
might be this time that we recognize oh yeah it is possible to have some more
ease and some spaciousness they to be willing to do
this part of the problem is is humans have a negativity bias and we tend to
like when there's a pleasant experience some openness and spaciousness and I'm defining Pleasant
in this way of like you know ease not necessarily eat having um non-stop
chocolate ice cream for example or something like this but more just having some it's like some radical contentment
like yeah yeah it's okay and often we tend to dismiss these
moments because we're looking for the big bang you know Wahoo roller coaster
type of experiences thinking that's really what happiness is fireworks and celebrations and cake and ice cream you
know these types of things those are great too but the truth is most of our Lives we do
have moments where it's okay maybe we finish doing the dishes and the
kitchen's all clean and it looks very nice and maybe that's just a moment it feels
feels good like oh okay so this recognition that it is
possible and that's possible for you for me for all of us and that there's way
that we can find our way where that's more and more of our experience instead
of something that you know some person did thousands of years ago and oh isn't
that cute instead like oh no this is something for all of
us and so this far Shore it can for um
sometimes we think of it or sometimes drama teachers will talk about it as neana but it can just simply be a
refuge a place where we feel like we can rest you know this kind of a sense of
where we can relax it is possible to not have so much
uh dooka of course it
is and so maybe returning back to this idea of
effort there's this two types of effort one one is like cultivating the raft
creating making the raft developing and the other is employing the raft using
the raft and we might think about that you know these different ways of doing that
uh practice asks of us this cultivation as well as things like
reflection or meditation or ethical Behavior you know things that
we're doing in our daily lives
so there's this um then when the person on this assimile
when it goes back when they uh when he gets to the far Shore he has this the Buddha asks this inquiry whether to
carry the raft or to leave it behind like I'm getting my notes my page number
is a little mixed up here but um this idea that once you get to the far
Shore so this question is well this raft was so handy should I carry it on my head or put it on my
shoulders and I think the important thing here is this little simile or this little note that's in the simile is well
to either bring it on dry land maybe you know that there might be some rivers or
Creeks or floods to cross and maybe you don't need at that moment but or maybe you can
uh come back for it later or maybe you send it down the flood because it's just
leaves and Creek uh twigs and branches anyway so just let it
go but at the end of this assimile he says just let it go and then go wherever
I want so this the freedom that's available if we are able to let go of
even things that at one time time we helpful doesn't mean that it will always be
helpful and to recognize okay what is helpful and when is the time to use
these things and when is it not the time and um this week I'm teaching the 7
am I'm substitute teaching for a Gill and I'm doing a theme on the inner
critic and there's something about the inner critic is you know the inner critic maybe there was a time in which
it was helpful to uh kind of give ourselves a little pep talk like no you
didn't do that right you can do this or or maybe we internalize something that we heard when we were young but the
inner critic is often not always but is often something that we drag with us into our adult life from the our when we
were really young so in this way some of the things that we learned some of the messages
that we heard or you know what maybe at one point were helpful and maybe this inner critic is
just trying to protect us from what it perceive something that will be really
terrible but we can think of it as okay maybe it's time to put that down in the
same way that we would put this raft down and no longer be something that we
would carry with us so this assembly of the raft this
idea of uh being on the near shore flood of water wanting to get to the far Shore
because there's safety there then building a raft with whatever
one finds using that raft and putting forth some effort to get to the far
Shore and then when there putting the raft down so we might summarize this as in a
way of practice I mean the way the simile Goes The Story Goes it's a linear
but we might summarize it in a way that's not necessarily linear but as
noticing doing releasing so kind of three different
aspects of practice towards a greater Freedom noticing just noticing and being
present for our life so often we're disconnected and distracted and maybe we're disconnected
from ourselves disconnected from others but kind of like just noticing what's happening and noticing what's helpful
and what's not helpful what brings more ease and what doesn't bring more
ease noticing is there a way that we're showing up in the world that's causing harm for ourselves or for others just
being sensitive to this tuning into this and then
doing you know sometimes in the buddist teachers we talk about you know don't do and sometimes we talk about do so it's a
little bit of both right but this idea of like cultivating that's why we have a
meditation practice is to like cultivate a wholesome helpful mental States so
that they can support us in our life and they can help us abandon these things
that are not so helpful the inner critic would be an example like this so just abandon this
turns out not to be hopeful instead it tends to discourage us and deflate us and demoralize us in a way
that gets in the way of our showing up the best way we can or for us to have the best life we
can so this caring is or the I'm sorry the
doing maybe this La the raft uh maybe we do something and is and maybe part of it
is bringing the raft on sure and thinking like okay this was I learned how to build this and it's going to be
useful I don't need it right now but maybe it's will be useful
later and then releasing the raft is Left Behind at
that moment here in this simile this practice is not about
getting and attaining and having more and more and more it turns out the way
forward is releasing opening and that just means that
sometimes that um in order to let go to release there has to be some
cultivation there's a things it's so much easier to let go or soften if
there's a certain amount of wellbeing we all know this that when
we're happier it's easier to like oh okay that's not a problem that uh you know lost that I don't know where my
sunglasses are it's not a good thing nobody likes to lose things but if the
if losing one's sunglasses happens on top of so many terrible things that
happen that day and already a bad mood right that's very different than like okay woke up from that nice snap and you
want to go for a hike and like okay I don't have my sunglasses I guess I'll just wear a hat you know something like
this so part of the cultivating this doing part is to to have a sense of
well-being have a sense of like nourishing our inner life there's a way in which so
often there's a way in which we are so hungry or feel like we're starving and
just not enough uh inside and so part of this practice that
doing is for the nourishing makes it easier and easier to release and I could say part of the
nourishing is releasing some of the things that maybe we are taking in that
aren't nourishing but we're spending our time filling our minds and our lives
with these things that aren't supportive maybe that's part of the releasing too is you know okay this isn't helpful this
is uh I thought it was helpful when I started but it's no longer is or something like
this so noticing doing and
releasing as maybe three different aspects of practice that they are all intertwined and sometimes it's helpful
to tease apart these different elements and sometimes it's not so helpful but this idea of you know to
help us get across these floods these things that overwhelm us
and they feel like H it's just too much we feel like we're getting maybe submerged and and whatever life is
bringing us simile of the raft as noticing doing
and releasing not necessarily in that
order and now I think I'd like to open it up to see if there's some questions or
comments
this idea of paddling with one's feet hands and
feet you guys have an idea like what would be a modern day
uh like a what would if like how would could we interpret that if we're not
going across the raft across for not using the raft
across the flood Diana I something that came up for
me as you talking about the raft was uh I had a relationship to it with trust or
confidence that it keeps you boyed above you know not sinking into the water that
that that there's some some element of support um associated with that
fantastic fantastic do you know that uh ton and Gil and I have um we teach this
teaching it's called raft practice R A ft and sometimes the t is trust the same
idea that you know this confidence that it can keep you uh AF flat some kind of way but did you want to say more about
that Jim uh no no I like this I like this how partly
you know building the ra kind of cultivating things is does give us confidence certainly like you like okay
I can handle this in the past I wouldn't have been able to or maybe maybe the
confidence that uh that we can um maybe if we don't handle it perfectly but that we can recover like oh okay I don't have
to beat myself up so badly as I had in the past or something like this thank you thank you Jim was did I see a
question over here where did you have one question can you put the microphone over there
thank you Scott so this raft building um I was
thinking about it in terms of my own life and one of the issues is that
um uh the near near shore of this uh water
is dangerous but I have no idea what the other Shore is so in the simil it said
it was safe but I me maybe maybe somehow the ref Builder knew that it was saved but I never know I keep on building refs
but I don't know whether the other Shore is safe is that an issue that the Buddha
addressed that we really don't know no in this he is saying you know
it's a simile to talk about like getting to safety but your point is a valid one
like okay we don't absolutely know what's on the other side of the flood but sometimes we don't have a choice but
sometimes life brings us okay where we were standing just doesn't exist anymore for you whatever reason our things in
our life change and you know that just the Nearshore changes and we have to we
have to go forward in some kind of way whether we know it's safe or not
right yeah yeah I think I think we would all like to have some reassurance but uh
it's not always there of course yeah thank you and then I think over here right you did
you have a I
was I came here today I haven't been here in a couple of years and
um I just found that I had some can you hold the microphone just a little bit closer I had some empty time in my life
for the first time first evening in a about a couple of months and it felt empty you know it
just felt empty and I felt right about coming here uh but while I was meditating of
course I was rerunning scenarios with my
family and um so not knowing what the
other well basically trying to fix it how am I going to fix it and so I
started thinking about the raft and um paddling like sometimes paddling for
me is just making a phone call to somebody to say what's on my mind so
they I can get feedback because I'm not always thinking correctly and um but then there are
other times when I'm just I keep keep Gathering grass and sticks and whatever
you know you can pile a lot of stuff on you can go to therapy then you can go on
the internet there's a million people telling you what you should at least a million at least a million right and um
more vitamins more this you know and and the idea of releasing today was so
helpful for me of realizing that you know if you go
to therapy you don't have to go for the rest of your life you know or if you
have a relationship it doesn't have to be the rest of your life the way you don't have to behave the same way all
the time that's right and trying to approach my daughter in a different way
is it's a it's a little scary you know yeah because both of us are going to
have different reactions but um
it's I'm having trust that it's going to be okay either way nice you know either
way thank you very much you're welcome you're welcome and you also don't have reassurance I mean we don't you don't
know exactly what's going to happen but you're going to I don't really need it you know if I if I really am releasing I
don't really need it that's right that's right thank you anybody else has comments or guests
back
there thank you um I really enjoyed got a lot
out of that talk for me um the
noticing that I'm in a spot um that maybe isn't the
healthiest is kind of the easy part relatively speaking for me the doing
um like what to do uh is where I find a difficulty um
and you know looking at it with the uh you know you're at the shore and there's water and you got to get across okay
that's I know what to do but um in my
situation a lot of times I don't know what to do and wondering if you had any
thoughts on that I can say something general of course right I guess that's the one
thing I can say here here I'll start with something that's obvious well if you will never regret never
regret and it will always support you if you follow the five precepts so behave
in an ethical way so this is something that will always be a support for you
doesn't mean it will always be the easiest it doesn't mean it will always be comfortable but that's uh sometimes
when our life is really in disarray and we don't know what to do like sometimes
that's uh I've heard a dma teacher give this uh advice to somebody else who was
really have her in a tumultuous period of her life and that the um advice was
hold on to the precepts as if they are a raft that are carrying you across so
that's one thing I can offer is we'll never have a regret with that and then
you know the eight-fold path if you're familiar with that that can read really help to this idea of like right effort
is paying attention like okay what's helpful what's not helpful and just noticing that sometimes just saying okay
I'm going to notice what when I do this does it is it helpful or is it not and
really like intentionally investigate that I guess maybe so thank you you're welcome you're
welcome anybody else have uh something anything they'd like to say or
comment okay so wishing you a lovely rest of the evening and may your rafts
float beautifully thank you