all right good morning everyone welcome to the third day of our
meditation this week the series on elements of mindfulness from Vena
feeling tone yesterday we started with the kind of wanting and not wanting that
can layer on top of Vena if we don't see it clearly acknowledge it
clearly and um today talk about some other attitudes of Mind other healthier
or more helpful ways to move into
dedicated meditation so warm greetings to all of you from Santa
Cruz and the invitation is to begin to settle into a
meditation posture as I'm doing you can kind of
balance yourself over your hips align your head with your
[Music] spine can be helpful to take a couple of
slower more intentional deeper
breaths and just check out check out how your posture is how your body
is maybe scanning through briefly and noticing where the weight is distributed
maybe over your hip points buttocks feet if your back is against a chair
really taking that support
in and SC Banning through and noticing the
aliveness of your body the
vibrancy warmth and cool tingling or
pulsing the motion of your body
breathing
then to checking in with your internal
posture are you leaning forwards towards or
away against wanting or not wanting in this
moment or is there a balance
of internal posture balance of mind and
heart the
encouragement is to be receptive in these moments of meditation
together and allow experience to flow through without leaning forward W or backwards it's fine if you do just
notice but noticing also moments
of
okayness peacefulness
mindfulness and with that encourage enouragement relaxing just a little bit more on the
out breath and then allowing the breathing
to be
normal
natural tuning in to the felt sense of the
moment the wave like action of in breath and out
breath or the broader field of aliveness of
Sensations or perhaps the coming and going of other sensory
experience like
sound choosing whatever anchor of attention object of attention works for
you and resting
receiving allowing the body heart and
mind to come together in the experience of this
moment
now
whatever your chosen anchor of attention
is dedicating dedicating
yourself to being in contact with
it thinking in
interest appreciative interest in each breath each
moment
if anything unpleasant arises acknowledging
it
simply no need to push away lean away
allowing space around
it if anything Pleasant
arises allowing it perhaps savoring it without trying to
hold on to it allow allowing this to to flow
through unimpeded balanced in the
moment
I'm time to time checking in on the internal posture the internal
stance during this meditation leaning
towards pulling away or
balanced
allowing allowing the flow of
experience to move through
and as we begin to come towards the close of this meditation
together the invitation is to
recollect these moments spent in
cultivation
appreciating steeping in any moments of
peacefulness kindness allowing
[Music]
accepting any kind of goodness and from that
place being with with loving attention anything that
may have been not so nice not so
pleasant allowing that too with kind
attention and from that
place of an open heart casting your gaze
outwards to the others in your life other beings people
animals and if it feels right setting the determination that this time of
practice your practice in general perhaps your
life benefit
them may our practice here together benefit all who our lives
touch
[Music]
thank you for your
practice
so good morning good day warm greetings
everyone appreciate our time here together
meditating and lovely to see little bows in the
chat the warm greetings from my fellow Santa crusan Hello nice to see
you and special welcome to those of you who slipped in a little bit late to the
zoom room glad you're here so today is the third day on our
series of core or essential elements of mindfulness meditation
this week so far we've covered Monday feeling tone or Vena that
very simple parsing of experience as pleasant unpleasant or
neither and mindfulness of Vena can undercut all kinds of problematic ways
of spinning out or building houses of cards of thinking and
stories and in Buddhist psychology it underpins another simple kind of layer
of experience which is wanting or not
wanting otherwise known as Veta or not sorry not veta
craving and wanting or not wanting can be as simple as a little pulse of
wanting or strong as desire strong greed the not wanting can be a simple pulse of
pulling away or a ver all the way up from mild irritation to
hatred hostility the reason this is
important is that between feeling tone and this wanting and not wanting there's
a choice we can notice versus start craving wanting not wanting and even
when craving has appeared it's possible again to notice it rather than having it
run us which it does a lot of the time right if I'm seeing my experience
through the lens of greed even my meditation might have cultivation of
greed as it's outcome if I'm seeing my experience through the lens of through the filter
of aversion I might actually be increasing my aversion my dislike
towards something so yesterday I talked about recognizing
and working with these unhelpful attitudes or proclivities of
mind and today we're going to talk about some of the more helpful attitudes or
frames of Mind how they can support practice and um touch on ways of recognizing and
perhaps cultivating them so that's where we're going for the next little while and there'll probably
be time for some Q&A again today so first I want to plug in
um neutral Veta neutral feeling
tone neither Pleasant nor unpleasant so this can be a real source
of instruction about frame of mind about this kind of filter we might bring or
attitude the Mind might have when attended to
with an aversive frame of mind even a very neutral experience can begin to feel
unpleasant you've all probably experienced this for example if I'm doing dishes there's just water running
over my hands there's contact with the cloth there's contact with the dish but
if I'm resentful and rushed or stressed
then that becomes an unpleasant experience on the other hand if I am
washing a dish for a good friend or with a good friend and it's a point of generosity or connection The Experience
can actually be quite Pleasant that generosity that wholesome
beneficial attitude of Mind shifts perception of a lot of experience for
us one of my parents' neighbors my parents are in their 70s and they're in a snow
town a ski town and one of their somewhat younger neighbors absolutely
loves snowblowing or shoveling his neighbor's driveway he'd far rather do
my parents driveway than his driveway you've all felt this right it's
that generosity or impulse of friendliness or kindness meta can Infuse
an activity and shift the vant of the feeling tone
of it art students or photographers sometimes notice that the simplest
subject becomes far more interesting the more they study it recognize the details
naturalists notice this too it could be a very simple plant but
wow you start noticing all the details of the weaves and the way they interact with the stem and the habit of the way
it grows go it suddenly becomes more interesting
and more pleasant the breath and meditation can
be like this moving from neutral maybe to unpleasant if we have expectations or
having trick tricky time breathing over to very pleasant if we're
on a roll and the attention settles on the breath rests in the
breath so again these differences in breath they can be differences in what's
happening but many times it's less about what's happening with the object of our attention and much
more about the frame of mind attitude of mind or other mental
factors such as interest or steadiness of
mind so attitude of mind is key balance of mind that clear undistorted form of
mindfulness awareness and the attitude or the Mind
state that we're having can become the object of our attention a number of
people we're calling today St meth's day I love it that today could be meta
day meta kindness loving kindness friendliness is another attitude of mind
that in this tradition of Buddhism is often intentionally cultivated
and we notice it and it becomes a source of wisdom when we begin to notice its absence versus its presence intention
versus the rising so sometimes no matter what you
do it seems you can come into a a period of meditation with a very unhelpful
attitude irritation wanting sadness um whatever sadness
doesn't have to be a problem for example if the mindfulness is brought to the
experience of sadness if it doesn't need to be another way and if we don't
necessarily need to believe all the thoughts that spin up from it mindfulness brought
two unpleasant states of mind is a completely different experience than
mindfulness experienced through them mindfulness brought to wanting or not
wanting greed or aversion transforms them it transforms
them so here are some ways that can be
possible to shift from an unhelpful attitude otherwise known as frame of
mind to a helpful one not notice the simple knowing itself
the mindfulness itself sometimes this is enough knowing
that you're mindful being aware that you're aware to begin to Simply Be with whatever's
arising it can if that doesn't seem accessible to you for some people it feels quite easy for other people it
feels impossible then simply noticing the absence of problem s by the way
folks I cannot read questions while I'm talking so if you hold your questions till the end of the talking the chances
of um me answering them are much higher because they will disappear up the chat
box and I won't be able to find them again so hold them or copy them and paste them at the end okay I can see
them but I can't talk and respond simultaneously
here so noticing the absence of problems tiat Hong called this noticing the
absence of a toothache second take a step
back take a step back if a difficulty feels charged
notice the charge and if possible
bring kindness compassion patience to it so body pain knee pain you can notice
the pain pain with aversion and that will make the pain worse if you notice the
aversion with aversion that will make the aversion worse if instead you notice the aversion
with kindness things can start to
transform finally trust the process trust the process confidence or trust in
the process is so helpful it can be a key condition for emerging
from Duca from suffering into Joy or into other beautiful states of mind if
there is trust so awareness awareness of what is
happening is key and attitude towards what's
happening can shift experience no matter what level of experience you're talking
about the simple contact with
experience the attribution or parsing of Vena or feeling tone can be shifted by
attitude and even an unhelpful
attitude despair anger Etc can be shifted Again by kindness patience trust
in the process so that was a lot but just to
name that Discerning what conditions what attitudes are helpful for your
practice is a learning process and it's helpful to keep in mind
that it benefits from acceptance or acknowledgement of what's Happening
rather than contention a sense of allowing or open
interest kind regard so
all of the things I just named are beautifully balanced attitudes to bring to meditation and to these craving based
attitudes that you may notice frames of mind and attitude are the same here that
you may notice and for the purpose of mindfulness meditation any object of attention is
valid so get interested can be fuel fuel for wisdom discern discernment and
Awakening thank
you so friends we have spent another 45 minutes together
and I just want to dedicate our time
together for the benefit of all beings thank you for your attention and I will stay back for another 3 or 4 minutes to
answer questions for those of you who put them in if you want to put them in again I'll do my
best thank you for your
practice oh Charles Le is it possible to have wrapped interest in neutral V or
neither Pleasant nor unpleasant Veta without the experience becoming Pleasant or
unpleasant I would say check that out for yourself in my own experience wrapped interest actually is a synonym
for p which is a synonym for Joy or pleasure so I would say it's possible to
be very immersed in an experience and have it be neither but probably not have wrapped
interest again check it out in your own
experience
who in so as I mentioned a couple of times after glimpsing this um in the
chat your question how does frame of mind relate to Vena I was using the term frame of mind synonymous with attitude
or craving in this craving potentially or um wholesome states of mind so if you
think of it as a layer cake contact with sensation or contact
with an arising Veta or feeling tone is the simplest parsing of pleasant
unpleasant or neutral and attitude of mind frame of mind is the response to those two things
sometimes it can be if we're very mindful the response to Bear sense experience or more
frequently attitude of mind is more of just the gal frame of mind is a gal an
attitude towards the pleasant unpleasant or neutral or attitude towards
attitude so they do interplay with each other but usually vona is more
fundamental Leila that's a great question the relationship between equinity and
neither or neutral V so equinity again is most often a mind
state or attitude of mind so we can have extraordinary experiences of pleasant or
unpleasant and still be equanimous about them and there's a form of equinity in
embodied equinity in which all experience can in
deeper states of meditation be experienced as neither Pleasant nor
unpleasant so I hope that's helpful and I'm just reading
here yes good observation lorine a shift bringing mindfulness to worry from blame
and hust hostility exactly exactly it walks it down to a
simpler level of experience and that is part of what this practice can teach us
as ways to Simply Be with our experience without
needing to project outwards and to blame or hostility so thank you very much
everyone for your kind attention for your questions and most of all for your practice and your
sincerity and we will be back tomorrow so hope to see you
then