hello from Redwood City the Insight Meditation Center and uh welcome to
this uh day's meditation and uh as an
introduction there is a a wise approach to or a very direct
approach to mindfulness practice uh and that is is that to the
degree to which Insight vas is involved seeing a form of clear
seeing some people are looking for something but what what we're it's
useful to think of that what we're looking for is how we're
seeing what we're looking for is in the seeing itself not in what's being seen
uh you know through the eyes or heard through the ears or tasted through the
tongue and so forth It's the manner by which we know that we're
aware that is the that's where the secret the key is
found so an analogy would be that if um
we are given um uh uh someone someone says I have a
wonderful means by which for you to penetrate the depths of your
spiritual life and you'll find it uh with this Stone and the person hands
hands you a little stone that you can easily hold in your hand but there's no
more instructions and uh and your freedom is
found uh through this Stone and so you spend a years studying the stone
analyzing the stones boring into the stones with the drill trying to find out what is about the the stone that's going
to bring you freedom and then finally you go back to the person say I'm not finding anything
you explain what you've done and maybe the person laughs or cries or no no you
misunderstood it's not the stone itself it's how you hold the stone
that's where your freedom is found if you are bearing down on it if
you're intensely straining to understand it to analyze it to figure it out if you're looking Beyond yourself at the
stone you're not going to find your freedom but if you look at the manner
which you are holding it and seeing it and being with it and knowing it that is
where the freedom is found and I could have given you the person says you know anything it could have been piece of
wood or piece of paper or and it doesn't matter what it is it all is a means to Freedom if you
understand that it's in how you are with it that's important so for this meditation then
I'd like to encourage you to those moments where you feel like you
can really see clearly or know clearly this is is what's happening now whether
it's an in breath and an out breath or knowing you're thinking or knowing there's a feeling or knowing there's a
sensation knowing there's a reaction whatever it is that you know a sound that you hear doesn't
matter whatever it is you know uh see if you can discover how to
know it how to be aware of it how to see it so there's an ease or a peace or
Freedom a spaciousness an openness a
lightness in the knowing and if there's none of those things then U let let your yourself
really see the strain or the heaviness or the stress or the tightness in how
you know in how you're trying to see or understand and hold that gently just
allow that to be in the field of awareness not as anything that's wrong
or to be fixed but one more thing to discover how to be free with what you
know so hopefully this is clear enough so to assume a meditation
posture and there are many postures for meditation the Buddha listed
for standing once you start walking
standing sitting and lying down and different mornings different
ones of them these might be most relevant for
you and lowering your gaze before you close your eyes maybe
lower your gaze and see if the you can have a relaxed
gaze maybe not looking at anything in particular soft
eyes and then closing your
eyes
and so that the how you're
aware can be more relaxed at ease it helps to put the body at
ease and one way to do this is to take a few slightly deeper breaths than
normal feeling the Torso the rib cage the body as you breathe
in and as you exhale to relax the body soften
on different exhales you might soften different parts of your body the shoulders the
arms the lower [Music]
back the
belly the lower arms and hands
the
legs and then letting the breathing return to
normal and with a normal breath on the inhale feel these different parts of the
body that I'll mention and on the exhale exhale soften
relax that part of your
body beginning with the forehead and the
eyes softening the forehead and the
eyes the cheeks and the
Jaws the shoulders
the chest and the Heart
area the belly
and whatever sense of the global body you have feel that and soften on the exhale
and then feel the thinking mind there's
any pressure sagit or
tension maybe in the area of the brain or anywhere else associated with
thinking as you exhale relax and soften the thinking
mind
and then notice any way in which you're present for this
moment any way in which you're mindful
or any way in which you're viewing your present moment
experience on the exhale can you soften and
relax how you're present how you're
aware how you know to continue knowing
continue feeling and sensing your
experience but without any strain pressure
tension what we're looking for is found in how we look
moment after a
moment experiment with a
relaxed soft
nonstressful awareness of present moment
experience
for
e
for for
each moment of mindfulness the next
moment see if you can continue being
mindful but in a non contentious way non-striving
without attachments just know just be
aware in a radically simple way and in that
Simplicity appreciate the
freedom
for
e
e for
and as we come to the end of this sitting preparing ourselves
for what follows what follows for the
day it's important to keep in mind that regardless how
important other people are for you how you are with other
people is the most important for
you regardless how important or unimportant your work is whatever work
or activities you're doing is what's most important for you is how you do
them how you do your work how you do your activities
and discovering how to live this life with good
will the absence of ill will discovering
how to live this life without aggression but to live it
peacefully to know how to live this life and participate in this
world without causing anyone to be
afraid but rather being unafraid
ourselves and discovering how to be free in all our encounters with others
and activities and things in this world it's how we
are that's onward leading that shows us the
Dharma that's visible Here and Now
immediate that we can investigate for
ourselves may this practice that we do this learning a new how to
live be for the welfare and happiness of everyone we
encounter May everyone we
encounter be an occasion for good will our wishes for their
happiness our wishes for their safety and peace our wishes for their
freedom may this practice support us with a universal good will
will to help the suffering world may all beings be
[Music]
happy thank you for
hello and welcome to this third talk on the five qualities of the Dharma
and or the five qualities of the Buddhist teachings and one way of understanding
these five is there a litmus test to understand what is and isn't the Dharma
what is and isn't the Dharma of Liberation the core teachings of the
Buddha and for it to be core teachings it needs to have these five qualities it
needs to be something that is directly visible directly known in our experience
it needs to be something which is immediate seen here and
now and the third one for today uh there are
teachings which are not requiring you to believe not imposing beliefs on you but
rather there are teachings that are offered with an invitation to come and see for yourself
to look into this inspect them for yourself are these
true and um so the the the the poly word for this
third quality is a Paso and um
ehi uh is a basically means come it's kind of colloquial expression come come
here and Paso means to see come look come see and uh it's kind of
like an invitation hey come here come see come look come look for yourself and
I love this kind of the colloquial expression in poly it's not you know a
technical you know uh definition of the Dharma it's it's
it's a wonderful kind of soft inviting idea come and study this for yourself
learn for yourself find out for yourself if this is true true find out for yourself how this works for you come and
look come and investigate and um and uh so whatever teachings you see
you hear you don't have to believe them they're not about believing they're
about experimenting they're about trial and errors trying them out and seeing
for yourself how do they work and with time how do they work
um with um um with supporting
you in reducing the suffering of becoming Freer of developing love and
compassion kindness how do they support you in developing wholesome qualities so
you know for yourself oh this works this is this is good and um so uh there is a
uh tremendous emphasis in Buddhism on practice more than
belief the the teachings are just enough hopefully just enough instructions to
try something out to engage in them uh being a a nightstand Buddhist is may be
a fine thing to be but uh that's not what the teachings are for the teachings
are for us to put him into to practice and find find out for ourselves and in a
sense to become our own teachers so that uh uh we are finding
our own path our own way with these teachings and one of the things that can
be really helpful in this regard is what I taught in this most recent
meditation and that is that um when we're looking investigating how this
works what's going on that the investigation is deeply
personal uh it's not an analysis it's not a logical figuring things out but
rather it's a discovery of how we are as we practice how we are as we go
through our lives what are we contributing what are we bringing with us so if there's a tremendous challenge
in the world it might be easy to want to be upset and complain or criticize or
blame or uh try to change the world and that sometimes certainly those things
might be appropriate but that's not where the Dharma is found if what we're
interested in is the Dharma we always ask how how am I in regard to this how
do I find my freedom in regard to this how do I find myself not stuck in it or
reactive to it there still might be a called to do and change something in the world
but uh but the Dharma practice is about first maybe not first but the Dharma
practice is always about here how am I and so one way to think of
this is that um the freedom we're looking in looking for in
Buddhism is found in how we're looking that uh how we know how we're
aware how we practice this is how we're relating to anything that's going on
that is the key that's where we F come and see come and see in yourself in how
you are in relationship to yourself in relationship to the world in relationship to what's happening and not
a few people take on the Dharma uh without being really careful
about how they relate to the teachings and to the practices and there can be a lot of striving a lot of judging a a lot
of conceit that comes along with doing the practice there can be the the
problem of perfectionism I have to do it right and perfect I can't make a mistake there's a holding on to it for de life
like I have to kind of get an A or I have to you know Advance further than
anyone else in my neighborhood in my block the how is not looked at because
we're so the how propels us into the future propels
us into what we're trying to what we want what we're projecting onto the
world what our need is what our desire is that we don't see the desire we don't see the
motivation and so part of the purpose of mindfulness is to settle back enough
that we can see how we are we're not rushing ahead uh being
ahead of ourselves but we're settling back in being in ourselves
being here fully enough to track and see how am I in the activity that I'm
doing am I being mindful am I being relaxed am I being at ease am I being
free or am I straining or tense or pushing or caught in desire or caught in
ill will and there are plenty of times we'll discover that we
are that's not the problem in and of itself the problem is when we
give into those and participating in those but having them occur is one more
occasion to then ask well how do I relate to this now is there a healthier
way of relating to strain and desire and ill will and the healthy way of relating
is to see it clearly without strain see it again without see the strain without
strain see the ill will without ill will see the desire without desire for it to
go away there's something about seeing what is UNH
wholesome that makes room for the wholesome to grow what's good in us
flourishes so how we are and so in that last meditation I the beginning I gave
an analogy which I like to do again for those of who didn't hear it that maybe the the similar analogy
kind of uh will bring more clarity to what I'm
trying to teach here that there's this imaginary teacher
out there who is very famous for uh really helping
people and uh so many people travel to this teacher and uh and they explain
their difficulties and the teacher then uh goes into the back room and comes
back and offers everyone a a small Stone and says here with this Stone
you'll discover how to you you'll discover your freedom and um and so most people are
confused they thought they would get a teaching some piece of wisdom but just to be given a stone in the exercise that
with this Stone you'll find your your freedom but some people take it
seriously and Trust the teacher and and uh but they're think that the answer is
going to be in the stone and they study geology and they study the Rock and they
look at it and measure it and weigh it and maybe even crack it open or maybe
wor holes in it and get it chemically analyzed and uh do all kinds of things
to the stone and after many years of kind of trying to figure out what the stone has
to teach they go back to the teacher and she no no you misunder tood the answer is not in the
stone how you the freedom is found in how you hold the
stone don't strain don't push it don't St don't bang on it don't bore into it
don't shake it to get the answers just hold it lightly and freely in your
palm no need to cling to it just hold it and discover that in the light handed
holding holding something lightly that is where the freedom is freedom is not
in trying to get something out of the stone and
um and uh the um and it's how you hold
it and the teacher might have said I could have given you anything at all it could have been a piece of paper a stick
anything and it doesn't matter what I gave you give you it matters if you conf
uh discover how you're with the the object it's with the how that you'll
find your freedom so
um Liberation is not found in something in some belief in something
external but Liberation is found in how we seek
Liberation freedom is found in how we're looking for it
so we don't seek it with tension we don't look for it with strain we don't
look and feel and sense and know our experience with fear and dread or
resistance or aversion we discover how to uh be
free and so in this way the Dharma uh is pointing to your own
experience saying come and see come and see for yourself in your own experience how this
works the Dharma is visible here and now it is immediate it's right here and
now and uh the teachings
offer you the invitation to come and check it out for yourself so those are the first three
and tomorrow we'll do uh the fourth which is its onward leading which is one
of my favorite of these five and um so thank you very much and I
have one announcement and that is that uh on Friday uh after this uh our
YouTube time at 7:45 uh all of you who would like to are invited to to have one of these periodic
Community meetings we have have for this YouTube SAA um and we'll do that on zoom and um
the zoom link is now posted in the on the imc's website um uh on the what's new section
of the homepage down the lower left right hand side and I'll announce this
again and make the the link uh OB uh available in other ways as well but then
we'll meet at 7:45 and we'll have a chance for some questions and answers some discussion maybe a small breakout
group so you can meet some other people who are part of this YouTube sa and um and I look forward to any of
you who can come thank you