good evening good evening welcome
welcome so the other day I was struck by was uh talking with
somebody and this person was convinced about you know how the future was going
to be had the certain amount of certainty you know this is going to
happen and then this is going to happen happen and and that's going to happen and I know I was really struck by well
how do you know I like of course you know we can imagine how things are going to be but
you know why do you have such a sense of certainty and this individual had a you
know a lot of emotion around it too so I've just been thinking about
this idea of certainty and then um the other day I had uh some
discomfort on my face and I thought oh it's that
tooth and I made this whole story my dad my brother and I the three
of us just don't have such good teeth it comes to find out and uh we have all
these Dental issues and I had this whole story about oh there there's this pain
which means you know this which means that and then this is going to happen and oh my gosh you know and I knew it
was a story I knew I was making it a story I was making it up but there was a
way that I was kind of like invested in this story like oh because it means this
then I'm going to have to do that or you know all this kind of
stuff and you know because I had this story I called the dentist I went to the
dentist and they're like have you had any problems with your sinuses lately those of you in the room
here did you hear me cough there's it's not uncommon this
time of year I have some allergies uh that come up they like it's just sinuses and like oh of
course you know I had the certainty that it was going to be a certain tooth in
this whole story about it turns out not to be that
way today is Veterans Day November
11th I guess this uh holiday started out as Armistice
Day way back when celebrating the end of World War One celebrating that it was the end of
the war that was great going to end all wars yeah has maybe the certainty or
maybe a certain optimism but there have been Wars since World War
I so that you know this predicting of the future turns out not to work so
well I mean sometimes it does sometimes uh it works
well but there's this way in which uh when we are facing
uncertainty which I'll come to talk about turns out to be all the
time but we somehow uh neglect to remember that or aren't tuned into that
but in the face of uh uncertainty of things that we're not quite sure about
then we make assumptions and then based on those assumptions we make predictions
I'm assuming it's my tooth has the same tooth I had problems with blah blah blah
you know all this kind of stuff and then uh I'm going to predict that something very uncomfortable is going to happen
you know with the dentist's office or something like this this is a perfectly legitimate thing to do this is what
humans do this is partly why we have a discursive thinking this is what our minds and brains are been trained to do
in our life is to make some assumptions and make
some predictions but there's this way in
which we are making assumptions so often in so many ways and
in so many places things that will be similar to
how they were before is this implicit assumption maybe underlies so many of our
days we're just thinking like yeah it'll be like how it was
yesterday in some kind of way I'm reminded of uh sometimes when I
I use uh this um digital assistant and I sometimes ask
what's the weather and then they'll say uh you know blah blah blah later today
we'll be more of the same you know every day it's kind of like later today will be more of the same it's not I'm
exaggerating it's not every day but this it's not uncommon for it to be that way here in
California and so there's this way in which we so often are thinking like oh tomorrow will be more of the same the
day after that will be more of the same so there's this way in that we are we
assume that there's this degree of stability this degree of sameness
in our lives and we just we're taking for granted the continuity of so many
different things continuity of our possessions that our car is going to start in the morning or that the
computer is not going to die in the middle of some critical uh activity know
for the most part we can r on these things these days continuity of our physical
well-being right nobody wakes up in the morning think like oh I'm going to get in a car accident this afternoon like
nobody thinks that right I'm going to get a terrible
diagnosis somebody uh close to me is going to get a terrible
diagnosis and then of course we're making predictions based on this but
what happens when things turn out not the way that we've planned
what happens when things completely unexpected happen or when we maybe it's not part of
us it's not so unexpected where we had some assumptions we made some predictions and then those predictions
turn out to be wildly inaccurate or maybe even just a little bit inaccurate but just their degree of inaccuracy
makes us feel uncomfortable oh why why didn't I see that
coming oh I should have paid more attention to this thing or that thing or
something like this because the truth is I grew up here in uh California those of
you who have been here in California a long time know this idea of earthquakes right I kind of just really
grew up with this idea any moment now there's going to be an earthquake and
when I was in school we had hid under our desks you know we had these earthquake drills and there certain
things you know I keep a certain amount of water a certain amount of food at home certain things that are charged up
you know for Batteries just I'm always I don't get down to an empty tank on my
car all this kind of stuff just because I think well there may be an earthquake and uh I need to
prepare so what do we do even though we're
prepared even what do we when we're making predictions that are based on what we think are valid
assumptions and yet something really unexpected happens or just even mildly
unexpected there's this way in that we this noticing that things aren't the
way that we were anticipating them to be sometimes can touch a deeper sense of
insecurity a deeper sense of recognizing we don't control
things we're vulnerable there's not a safe place the
place that you can be completely 100% safe you know guaranteed all the time
that doesn't exist and we don't like to feel
this we don't like to feel any of these things the vulnerability or the sense of
uh insecurity or the sense that things are out of control we can't control
them and so then there's often ways in which we will respond a myriad of ways one is that we
just feel like oh no no no I need to some certainty I need something that I
can really hold on to and count on and plan on plan with or okay I I got to
find some certainty and we'll look to find it in whatever way that we can or
in whatever way make sense for us we have this kind of like we might
become fixated on finding you know the truth
the absolute truth because then we can hold on to that and uh that won't uh let us down or
finding okay what's the actually the the uh precise
rules what's okay what's not okay and I don't want don't get me any of this gray business you know I just want to know
it's a you know perfectly gray and perfect or perfectly black and perfectly
white there's this way in that we find we kind of we get uh fixated on trying
to to like imove remove all sense of Doubt or uncertainty and it's fascinating how
just this looking for this certainty this wish like wanting to find the certainty perpetuates
uncertainty because we more we look and look and I got to find this in order to feel okay and we won't find it we won't
find it we won't find it and this can lead to a spiral of just
wait this this isn't uh reliable this isn't reliable so this is one thing that we
might respond by just really like craving some certainty and really trying
to find out which spiritual tradition is the best one is the true one which
teacher is the best which practice is the best which uh experience meditative
experience is the best we might have this way in which we start looking for these types of things or maybe there's
this way in that uh we just start searching for information when
we discover some uncertainty we might look for just maybe overly relying
on opinions or views of other people okay well surely they must know
more than I do and we might be like seeking validation or guidance from
other people which can be a wise thing to do but there can be a way in which we
are kind like giving uh our uh author or our own discernment over to other people
think like okay well this person knows whatever they say and this kind of like look for looking for
certainty we might you know just well I clearly don't have it I'm filled with
doubt and I'm not quite sure how things go so but this person they claim that they
do or they look like they do so I'll just
uh look at them what what they are saying or maybe the information we're
just consuming information with the news social
media wow we we've created a whole society that is just filled with this
you want information here you go it's astonishing right how much
information there is and it's also astonishing how much of it conflicts
right how much of it like there's some incompatible views going on and then and
then this wish for certainty ends up to even having more agitation looking for information but then wait which one is
right which one is right and then that maybe just feels uh
fuels this sense of insecurity that we often
have I mean all of us do this to some regards I mean probably when we have
some new medical symptom Google what are the da d d da
you know WR this and we uh look up the symptoms what does it mean and is it
time to go to the doctors or what should I do about it or something like this or maybe there's this way in which
uh we buy into conspiracy theories because conspiracy theories are part of
their Allure is like nope this is the truth everything else is wrong yeah just
ignore all that other stuff maybe it's the same reason why people uh join Cults this is true and
everything else is wrong this feeling of uncertainty the vulnerability
insecurity it's uncomfortable it's really
uncomfortable some other ways of responding when we feel into this or we uh experience it maybe there's just
sense of fear like what's going to happen like I don't know this fear of
the unknown this recognition like wait if I'm not so good at predicting or if this
now I I don't even know what to think about this there can be some fear that
comes up this is a natural thing right fear of the unknown but there's this way
in which the fear can if it might lead to agitation
or this like a paralysis like I don't know what to
do people do awful things based out of fear they do nothing know things they do
nothing out of fear out of avoidance
maybe or maybe if uh things like if we had this sense of way things are going
to be and they turn out not to be that way maybe there's some anger like maybe
there's like even it's not so well thought out necessarily but a sense of betrayal but wait I thought it was going
to go this way and it turns out to go a different direction and then this anger
over like well we have to blame somebody sometimes we blame
ourselves what why didn't I pay attention to the signs why didn't I know
well it would have turned out the way I thought if only those other people didn't do X Y and
Z there's this way in which this um when this feeling of when things don't turn
out the way that we're anticipating that we often are looking
outside of us looking for information blaming
others trying to find the answers Somewhere Out There
the truth is there really is
uncertainty right I mean there's likelihoods of course of course there
is but there's this way that the human mind often overlooks the inherent
uncertainty of Life inherent uncertainty to just bad
everything we're never guaranteed things are going to turn out the way that we
plan we anticipate that we
expect there's this way that if we had to like kind of like admit that uh
things are uncertain they arise due to causes and
conditions but what are all these causes and
conditions I don't know you don't know nobody knows we don't know all of the
reasons why things happen there's all kinds this is why you know there's people over here will say
Well it happened because of a b and c and then these people are here no it happened because of X Y and
Z well maybe it happened because of element op
but the it just there's a bunch of things that come together to make
everything happen I'm sitting here because uh I I wanted to say I didn't
die today I was supposed to be here I didn't think I was going to die I don't
know if people usually are thinking that but I mean there's so many things here that
came together for me to just uh be here and for you to be here to be listening to a talk wow my
had to there wasn't a family emergency that I was required to take care of I
wasn't uh away and another Retreat that uh I was needed to teach her or that I
was teaching or I didn't get in an accident on the
way here you know all these things that we don't assume are going to happen but they didn't happen for me to be here and
then for you guys to be here each one of you individually and then for the microphone system to work and the lights
to work right how many of you were here when the there wasn't any power right that was like a whole different uh
situation here so we often overlook this uh
inherent uncertainty and partly the reason why
it's uncomfortable but it's also really highlights how we we don't
control nearly as much as we think we
do and partly this feeling of things being
uncontrollable is uncomfortable we like to think like okay
I can make my own destiny I can make things be a particular way I can
influence outcomes I can make things
happen we can help create the conditions that
changes the likelihood of things happening maybe it's a way to think about it but there's no guarantee that
there's not something else that's going to arise that we didn't
anticipate and so this idea of unreliability
the Buddha talked about this he pointed to this as one of the core
teachings and like really understanding this and aligning with
it is a way towards greater peace and ease and
freedom so the Buddha talked about how things are are
changing an inconstant
impermanent and sometimes we hear this and we think like oh yeah of course right it's fall now the leaves are
falling from the trees things change it wasn't full a few months ago the leaves were a different color a few months ago
and we just feel like okay yeah that's a change but just pointing how everything
is actually changing there isn't anything that's like inert completely in
the sense that it will Until the End of Time be the same the time frame on the
which ways things are changing is different but everything is changing and
partly like we are changing too all of us have heard you know about
how the how many cells you have in the body and they change every seven years I
don't know if this is true or not but our minds are thinking changing
we're learning things every day we're making assumptions and our assumptions
uh are supporting some predictions that we're making so even if uh the Bell seems like
it's exactly the same but the person who's ringing the bell is maybe a little bit different and
I learned from uh maybe at a retreat center I was teaching that recently how
uh delicate one needs to be with the striker so now maybe the the experience
of the Bell isn't exactly the same because I'm a little bit different and now I'm striking it a little bit
different but the Bell you might say but it looks the same but is only the way that something look is that everything
about the Bell maybe it's also sounds maybe it'll sound different
I'm just making this up just things
change but that was only one of the characteristics right that the Buddha talk about there's three characteristics
one is the changing nature and then following from that is Dua the
unsatisfactory nature because things can't be reliably predicted upon there's
a sense of une easiness that goes with this there's nothing that is not
changing changing is the constant we might
say so there can't be this source of reliable happiness in the way that we
are looking for it in the way that we are expecting
it and then as I was saying the part of us means that we can't control it we
can't control well we can't control ourselves we can't stop the Aging we can't stop
getting sinuses uh sinus sinus
issues we can't stop you know illnesses they arise even though we
might be doing our best to protect ourselves and this kind of like lack of
control at the fact that we uh can't completely control this Human Experience
the Buddha pointed to this too and it's partly what he's talking about a self
he's saying if there were a self the way that it was being defined
at this time in Ancient India and partly how we can understand it in contemporary times then a self would be something
that we could control if it's actually yours you could control it that's part of the definition of something that you
own that you have you own is you can control it and well we there's we don't completely
control this this self how many times have you had thoughts that uh you didn't
want to have or expecting to have emotions that you didn't want to have or or this as I
said this body right these bodies they're they're doing their own
thing
so what do we do about this and I'll say this is partly why we
have spiritual practices really is to help us to be with some of
these uh difficulties with this feeling of insecurity this feeling
of uncontrollability this feeling of
vulnerability part of this spiritual practices to recognize
difficulties yeah this is uncomfortable not to repress it not to
deny it not to Gaslight ourselves I love this expression Gaslight ourselves try
to pretend like oh no no no that's nothing but instead no to say no no yeah
this ouch I don't like this at all and part of a spiritual practice is
to be able to See Clearly to see okay this actually is the
reality and to be able to meet it and hold it in a way that makes one's life Fuller
makes one's life richer makes uh the On's I don't know
brings some beauty and Grace to one's life as opposed to collapsing and or
trying to make uh something different something completely different so part of a
spiritual practice is so we can have a mature response to when we're noticing that oh
yeah this didn't turn out the way that I thought it was going
to can we have a mature response that says it didn't turn out the way that it
didn't want to and not to collapse but then not to also go the opposite way way
and say well everything's uncontrollable and unpredictable therefore I'm not going to bother wearing a seat belt or a
helmet or or uh exercise and eat well
and you know all these types of things that we do to try to uh protect ourselves we could say well we we don't
know what's going to happen that's so why should I even bother to uh do things that uh might provide some safety a
mature response is to recognize we don't actually
know so we plan and recognize we don't know it's going to work out that way we
take precautions and recognize we don't no it's not a guarantee it's going to protect
us so there's this way this kind of aligning
ourselves with this truth of impermanence the truth of
uncertainty is a way that actually provides the
security it's not by um finding that one thing that we can just hold on to like
okay great I found it I don't have to search
anymore but instead just to recognize yeah things are always
changing and so it's about our relationship to that
can we hold our expectations
lightly can we still make them and recognize them as expectations recognize
them as predictions based on assumptions and those assumptions may or
may not be true but just to hold them hold them
lightly and then let go of all these attempts to try to control things that
actually we can't control letting go of trying to control
other people have you tried it did it
work do you like it when people try to control you I don't I don't like it I'm just
going to say it I really don't like it when people are trying to control me I have this little inner rebellious person
that uh inside here that some just Roars when there's a some of that kind of
thing H trying to happen so how do we work with this uncertainty align ourselves with the
truth of impermanence I'm going to use this word truth I'm holding it
lightly let go of the attempts to control things that are beyond our control
and then one thing that will support us in doing this is just a mindfulness practice just to be present for our
lives just to be present for recognizing that the stories that we're making the
Fabrications that we're doing about the future they're 100% fabricated they're not based out of
nothing most likely but just to recognize oh yeah this is a story I'm making up
about my this pain what it
means so notice mindfulness practice also helps
us to notice just the changing nature of things those of you who are familiar
with the satiana sua this is the key text in the Buddhist literature that
points to a mindfulness practice and there's this refrain that gets repeated like like 13 times and it talks about
noticing impermanence noticing the changing nature of things and this can
be a real practice that can be really beneficial just to notice how things are
fluid they're not constant and there's this way in which
we when we notice that then uh there's just this natural kind of like loosening
of the grip that we have on things on how we expect things to be or how we
want to be maybe this mindfulness will also help
us this way in which we're kind of like often maybe in a subtle way wrestling
with our experience like no it it should be this other way I predicted it to be
this way I want it to be this way and there's this way that uh there's a we're
pushing with experience and trying to morph it into uh something the way that we think it should
be I'm not saying that we shouldn't make changes but it starts with just
recognizing okay here's the truth of the moment here's the reality here's how I'm
responding to it I don't like it I want it to be different and then starting from there then go with the next thing
is but often we don't even notice how much we're trying to push and pull against our experience how much we're
trying to make it be
different so we can practice some mindfulness that can help us
to notice the changing nature of things and notice
how much we're trying to control and then I would say also to
nourish our in our lives there's this way in which you
know it's so much easier to have some stability and some maybe uprightness or
I'm using uprightness like uh figuratively like to be able to sit
upright instead of collapsing maybe is what highlight it's the opposite of
collapsing when something unexpected and unwanted happens
it's so much easier to do that if we are nourishing our inner lives and what do I
mean by that to do something that feeds the
heart being in nature looking at Beauty for some of you maybe it's
meaningful to uh have a devotional practice something where there's uh or
maybe it's simple as lighting a light a candle before you uh meditate or maybe
some of you have an altar with things that are meaningful for you or maybe some of you have a chanting
practice or maybe just singing or dancing or some of these
things so there's so much it's so much easier
to meet meet difficulties if there's a part of us
that feels nourished and sometimes when we're feeling this insecurity and things
aren't quite right we're go looking for information as I was talking about information can help a little bit but
I'm pointing to also these other ways for me I love to be hiking with
redwood trees I just I every time I few times a week I'm out there as much as I
can and I'm if I'm hiking with somebody else I can't help but I'm always saying
like wow it's so great to be here where I just feel so lucky to be living in the
Bay Area we have these amazing redwood trees that I don't know for me I just
feel nourished and supported by them and then there's this way that I
also want to highlight that this uncertainty brings promise and beauty
also I was talking about how it can be a bummer if you're expecting one thing and
then something different shows up but there's this way that poetry and
art the ones that are like really touch Us in my view I have like this
combination of the familiar and yet a little extra something that's unexpected
that brings a little bit of uh Delight or maybe there's this way that there's a
sense of freshness if we are tuning into this sense of yeah things aren't as
predictable and this freshness like brings a certain aliveness to our our
life maybe there's a way in which we would have some curiosity about oh I'm
not quite sure what the day is going to bring I have this idea it's going to have a b and c but I'm not quite
sure and to be like engaged with your life you know instead of like ah a b and
c here we go which is easy to do right it's easy to do
that so there's this way that this uncertainty brings some of this uh
promise and beauty also then maybe I will end with this
poem
this poem is called never the same by Rosemary
traumer never the same by Rosemary
traumer sometimes a person wakes believing they are a storm it's hard to deny it what with all
the rain pouring out of the gutters of the Mind all the gusts blowing through all the
squalls all the gray but by afternoon it seems obvious
they are a garden about to sprout by night it is clear they are a
moon luminous radiant
faithful that's the danger I suppose of believing any frame
let me believe then in curiosity in
Wonder in change let me trust how essential it is
to stumble into the trough of the unknown Marvel how trough becomes
Wings becomes Faith becomes math let me trust un certainty is a
sacred path I'll read this
again sometimes a person wakes believing they are a storm it's hard to deny it what with all
the rain pouring out of the gutters of the mind all the gusts blowing through all the squalls all the
gray but by afternoon it seems obvious they are a garden about to
sprout by night it is clear they are a moon luminous radiant
faithful that's the danger I suppose of believing any
frame let me believe then in curiosity in Wonder in
change let me trust how essential it is to stumble into the trough of the
unknown Marvel how trough becomes Wings becomes Faith becomes
math let me trust uncertainty is a sacred
path I love this notion of the stumble into the trough of the
unknown and then Marvel how trough becomes Wings Things are unfolding this changing
business this unpredictability we aren't when we're in the trough we're not expecting them to
become wings but they do things like change and
then they they become known and then she then she says trough becomes Wings
becomes Faith becomes math for me I'm turning math I'm interpreting math as
look oh yeah okay now we can make predictions based on this the likelihood is the probability those of you who took
statistics you like we could just turn it into a probability problem or something like
this because it becomes known and becomes something that from which we can
build upon in our life so maybe we could think about this
idea of moving from prediction about how things are going to be to
presence to being how things are
now and part of the way that they are now is
uncertain and with that I'll open it up to see if there's some questions or
comments thank you
um I was thinking about uncertainty for me and I feel like in certain parts of
my life life I really like uncertainty um and those are probably
things I enjoy doing you know but I kind of love that I'm cooking without a
recipe and I don't know how it's going to taste or I'm dancing with this band
I've never heard before and I like that so I was thinking
maybe I can think about that and then the areas of uncertainty that I don't
don't like um maybe that will help
me you know uh loosen up a bit about it um I
mean I already like I have kind of a thing about parking in San
Francisco um so I I know I have a problem with this like why am I anxious
it always works out somehow um but I'm just thinking maybe if I
can I don't know kind of think about how areas of my life where I'm really
totally comfortable with uncertainty and then I I don't know if I can uh open up
more in those areas where I'm don't like the uncertainty yeah I was struck by uh you
made this small little comment about parking in San Francisco well it seems
to always work out yeah so it's interesting I think to notice like oh yeah like things often aren't turning
out the way that we planned or expected but they did turn
out in some other way whether we liked it or not so that things are always unfolding and then we work with them and
or or not if we don't work with them then we're stuck and filled with anger or something like this but just this
recognition that things are like always uh I don't know now that I
say this maybe it sounds silly but things are always unfolding and there's this way can we just trust
that what's going to happen next is going to happen next whether we are like
it or don't like it and is there a way that we can have some confidence and so maybe part of how we
gain that confidence is just by noticing oh yeah things are always
changing they're not as in the way that we expect but I like what you said about oh yeah other places
it's fine cooking dancing I like it parking not so
much thank you I think this is the end of our time
here so thank you for your kind attention and wishing you a wonderful rest of the evening thank you