welcome everyone today we'll take a little look at the the
middle faculty of these five faculties Sati or mindfulness and as I promised yesterday
because this is familiar to so many people I'm going to sort of try not to
say the uh some of the same things that we might usually say particularly to a
group like this with some some experience and some familiarity with
mindfulness Gil sometimes talks about mindfulness Sati in the context of these
five faculties as complete presence complete presence and uh to sort of take
that as a theme for the daret and also for this guided meditation complete
presence seems to me to be a gift a gift we receive kind of a patrimony or an
inheritance something like the other faculties deep with in that we can
access that we can cultivate without reaching outside without accomplishing
something um but rather something we can cultivate by bringing our attention to
it our ability to our capacity to be here now our capacity for complete
presence is a gift that we in addition to receiving that we can give in the
first instance we can give the gift of attention as I like to think of it to ourselves or to our experience really
paying attention to our experience showing up for ourselves in this fundamental way and the more we cultivate it the
more we feel comfortable giving our gift giving the same gift of attention to
others so that's our theme for the guided the gift of
attention so let's get comfortable in meditation
posture for me that always means kind of resetting the body this is part of the settling into the meditation we talked
about yesterday bringing some attention to the energy that we bring to practice and seeking a balance of
energy we might notice that when we seek to calibrate our energy to the present
moment that the mind sometimes doesn't have a clue what that means and so we look we look to the body to help us
understand what's the appropriate balance what does what does self-care mean right now oh it means letting the
shoulders relax a bit noticing any tension around the eyes bringing attention to the jaw each of us holds
tension in different places and yet many of us hold the weight of the world on our shoulders and the cares of the day
in our faces our eyes our Jaws in our heads so just softening around these
areas wherever we are aware of tension in the body our objective isn't to make it go
away but to show up give the gift of attention to our bodily
experience and we can do this throughout the meditation
practice think of giving a gift to our experience this gift this precious gift
of attention this ability to direct our attention to hold our attention
to um provide places where our attention can come to
rest is a wonderful and unique gift that comes along with human
birth so maybe resting our attention in the breathing
and how in the breathing well just in the sensations of breathing we don't even have to think of it as the breath
which is adding a concept to our experience but just noticing the rise
and fall of the abdomen the expansion and easing off of the
chest the gentle rise and fall of the
shoulders just noticing the sensations of the in breath just this breath in
here and then the out
breath this gift of attention is one we give to our experience without adding
anything on to it just being with the first the primary experience that comes
up to us
we rest giving the gift of attention to the body just as it is just these sensations
of bodily movement perhaps of tension or holding
or bracing in the body tingling throbbing alertness
potential whatever we feel in the body just
accepting body his
body and accepting is part of the gift doesn't mean we like it doesn't mean
it's Pleasant maybe accepting it is really
just acknowledging as it is what's what's coming
up and today in giving this gift of attention
we can make use of the fact that the mind will get caught up in things snagged in things get kind of
concentrated or wrapped around things usually thoughts of the future
thoughts of the past thoughts of other people thoughts of ourselves the usual courses of the
mind and before we feel that we've gotten lost or
wandered off or doing it wrong we could just notice some of the maybe bodily Sensations or emotional
currents that are related to those thoughts bringing our attention slowly gently
back to the present these things that come up in
meditation they want our attention the body's Sensations the
feelings of whatever they happen to be today inadequacy
Joy loss
exhilaration we can just notice these things and give them that little touch of
attention we don't have to think about them we can just sort of go oh that's
what's here now so instead of feeling when we find
that the the mind's wandered off into the day coming toward us or the day past
these creations of mind can bring our attention tug it back to the center of things but also along
the way give attention to how it feels to be here
now one way we can give this gift of attention is by when we notice the mind's caught up in things are wandered
off is to not hurry we're going to do this a lot in
this sit and in our future sitting we don't have to hurry we don't have to jerk the Mind
back to here and now in fact we can notice what it feels like to
come back to Here and
Now feel the balance and ease and simplicity and slowness of being here now in contrast to being there
then and today we can think of this as giving a gift of attention to ourselves
to our experience just noticing what's it like to be here
now
e
e e
so as we near the end of this
sit let's reflect a little on this giftgiving
capacity and one gift we can provide ourselves is a gift that's an absence of
judgment if we didn't get lost in thought we
wouldn't have the opportunity to come back here and each time we return to
give ourselves give our experience the gift of our
attention the capacity to give to ourselves and to others it needs
exercise it needs to be strengthened and this is how we do it
we give ourselves an important gift when each time we return we don't kick ourselves for
having found a need to return from wherever the mind got tangled up no it's
an opportunity to give and it's an opportunity to strengthen the capacity to
give may we benefit from this growing capacity to give in our
lives and may other beings also benefit not just from the gifts but from our
capacity to
give may all beings be safe
secure may all beings receive the gift of
presence may all beings be free from suffering
[Music]
good day and welcome again to everyone turning now from a guided
meditation focused on the gift of attention the gift we give ourselves and
the strengthening of our capacity to give we can take a look at the third
faculty of these five faculties that which is frequently characterized as
mindfulness Sati and a faculty that Gil sometimes
refers to in this context of the five faculties as complete presence
the uh what might complete presence be and how might it be related to this idea of
giving in the classic instructions that that support this practice many of you
probably know mindfulness is never defined rather we are given instructions
on how to cultivate and strengthen this attention to be this Capac capacity to
be present so it's not something we acquire
it's something we do it's not something that we achieve and hold and make our
own it's a way we meet experience over and over
again and this I tried to point to even in the guided you know the return to
here and now the return to presence it's the return that's
important and the returning I said yesterday it's not like we hang on with our
fingernails as much as we celebrate this ability to keep returning and in part
the I don't know if celebration is the right word but maybe just the enjoyment of the ability to return is that each
time we return and each time we enjoy it enjoy its balance enjoy the
Simplicity enjoy the um slow pace of it the lack of entanglement the absence of
attachment each time we enjoy that we strengthen
it so um we should enjoy it fully and the instructions we get the encouragement we have uh from the from
the tradition is to enjoy it fully to cultivate that enjoyment of being here being
present so in the instructions that undergird the practice
of mindfulness the cultivation of mind mindful attention or complete presence is the idea that we meet the experience
of the body as body that we meet the experience of bodily Sensations and
mental Sensations as bodily and mental Sensations that we meet the mind and
mind States as mind States and finally in the fourth
Foundation that we meet patterns of experience as they are as as patterns of
experience what does that mean exactly body as body Veta as Veta or feeling
tone as feeling tone mind as mind dumus as dumus or patterns of thought patterns
of Mind as patterns of mind it means that we're not adding
anything we're just aware of for example and this is why we come back again and
again to the breathing we're not even labeling it is breathing we're just noticing oh this this movement of the
body this in and out this up and down this expansion and contraction as it
is without adding opinions about it being different or what it's going to be
like in two breaths from now regretting the way we took those
breaths three breaths ago they weren't as good as they should have been all of that is adding to our experience and the
reason we begin with the breath in the body is it's easier there to not get all all entangled in what it means or how it
might be better or different because it's just easier to accept as it
is each time we move forward gets a little bit more challenging to take the feeling tone
Veta we could say the quality of Sensations in body and mind whether
they're Pleasant or unpleasant that's a little harder to take without adding something if something we feel hurts or
something feels good the Mind tends to add extra add more like oh I want more
of that and oh I don't want as much of that and the uh the the being completely
present with that means being there without without going down those roads but just noticing oh this is Pleasant
this isn't Pleasant this is in the first instance that is as we first as experience first
arises and we beat it with attention we just notice observe feel
know with that effortless knowing that's free what's going on similarly with mind States we notice
oh the mind seems foggy or the mind seems clear we don't add anything to it it's
not that it shouldn't be foggy or it shouldn't be clear or shouldn't be foggy and it's nice that it's clear we just
notice oh it's like this now and this is a gift that we give ourselves the gift
to just be here without without adding a bunch of stuff onto it
yet I say yet because we have a choice about what to add on to it we can meet
experience with a mind that's open or we can meet experience with a mind that's
already judging how things should be should have been might be might have been
Etc and finally with patterns of experience as patterns of experience we can
um we can meet our experience noticing oh is there a lot of self-doubt creeping
in here that would be the fifth the fifth hindrance to name it is there a lot of
Doubt happening is that part of the attitude with which experience is being
met or is there oh confidence and some energy and some presence and maybe some
um some um Stillness or collectedness with which
experience is being met just noticing neither's neither's has to be labeled
good or bad just the gift of saying oh it's like this
now that's what we mean and by complete presence and why it's useful to
characterize Sati as complete presence it's a way of saying maybe getting beyond the label of
mindfulness which has become almost universally excuse me used to
characterize a wide range of experience and to and to be very specific about
that it's a gift of attention that in fact or in part is a gift because it
doesn't add anything so
having said this I also want to add this which is it's maybe when we hear the
phrase complete presence we might we might understandably think that what's
being referred to is perfect presence maybe that's just the way our minds go I
don't know about you all uh 206 of you so I can only speak for myself but um
there's a perfectionist streak that runs through um a fair amount of my
life if not focused on Perfection certainly on accomplishment achievement
and all that has been useful actually in certain Realms of life doesn't need to
be pushed away or excluded but there can be a recognition of that this is a path that moves in a
different direction this path of practice where perfect isn't the
goal um maybe maybe complete presence can be a useful aspiration in fact I
think it is and yet that doesn't mean that we need to uh achieve accomplish
strive for perfect perfect or perfect a perfect
presence instead what we what we seek to cultivate is sufficient presence
sufficient mindfulness sufficient for what
sufficient to develop a mind that's free enough of all that extra that we it can
see clearly so this can help ratchet down
from complete presence as a as a unattainable goal to something that we can do right here right now in this
moment which is be sufficiently present you may have some distractions going on there may be kids I saw somebody with
canines and kitties uh there may be other things going on there may be a meeting coming
up in uh 21 minutes there um so presence may not be complete
or perfect but it can be sufficient to be here now with enough absence of extra
being added on that it can help us see
clearly and um a phrase I love that I I think I may
be made up so going to trade market I'm kidding
it's freely given take it and use it I hope it can help serve your practice um
came up in a conversation with an old friend yet another perfectionist I know I've known
many um many just like me that um this
person said for this person they said for me
only perfect is good enough and I said well what if good
enough is perfect so you might keep that in mind and this practice it's not about getting
perfect it's about developing sufficient mindfulness sub sufficient collectiveness of Mind as we'll talk
about tomorrow sufficient samade so that we can see sufficiently
clearly anyway this helps reduce the striving
the orientation toward accomplishment the the orientation toward making achievements that are mine uh it frees
us up a little bit to just be here now without all that stuff added in and on that I think we have time for
a story I was going to try to leave a few minutes for a story I think this is a
story from Gil's book a monastery within just came to me in the meditation may not be um it may be
and maybe another story but I'm going to put it I'm going to put in the framework of Gil's book a monastery within and if
you don't know the book it's a book of very short stories that all work with the idea of creating within ourselves um
these capacities among others that we've been talking about this week creating a
space of seclusion and safety and refuge from which we can um or in which we can
cultivate the Mind states that allow us to meet the world's SK skillfully the world of experience the world around
us um so the story goes something like this if I remember it well which is one
day a person a practitioner like ourselves shows up at the monastery and has a meeting with the
abbis and uh they say to the abbis the person who leads the monastery and and
uh provides counsel to the to the practitioners in the monastery
this person says to the abbis so if I practice really diligently if I practice
hard um if I sit daily if I read all the right books and if I how long will it
take me to awaken and the Abbot says probably about 10
years and the person says 10 years I don't have 10 years I I I'm used to accomplishing things and you know
getting ahead what if what if my practice is perfect what if I make my practice perfect I have perfect
mindfulness perfect Sade perfect wisdom um you know I think I can really I
really can make that happen um because I'm good at that kind of thing making things
perfect then how long will it take me to awaken and the abbis says in that case
it'll take you 20 years and the person says wait wait why what if I really
redouble my efforts like I've done in other Realms of life and I work really hard and I don't just sit one once a day
I sit twice a day and I go on Long Retreats and I I read even more and I find all the best teachers and then how
long will it take me and the Abba says in that case it'll take you 30
years you probably knew that was coming that punchline the point
here um is that we
um the point is that uh we don't need to develop a perfect practice in fact that
orientation towards perfect is counterproductive you know and who knows
if it will take longer because the practice eventually teaches us this it teaches us that we don't have to be
perfect it teaches us that one way we can be with ourselves in complete presence one way we can provide this
gift of attention this mindful attention to ourselves so let go of all that that
gets in our way whatever it is for others it's different things but for many of us this kind of striving of
approach can really hamper our efforts to develop a practice that supports Us in life can really diminish our ability
to give um because it diminishes our ability to cultivate this capacity to to
give this gift of attention to ourselves to our experience
um and with just a minute remaining on the clock I want to point out that in the text sorry in the uh what do we call
this the chat feed that's scrolling along somebody it's a few minutes ago makes mention
of the concept of good enough parenting uh that was developed by Donald winnott
and uh this is a sort of obscure reference to many of of us although wot's work if you know anything about
him it it it it it absolutely um is universally referred to in many ways the
importance of play in childhood development for example is something that develops with Donald wot's work I just mention it because this idea of
good enough parenting is very closely related to this and it's one of many ways that psychotherapeutic approaches
can support our practice and vice versa because the same idea is that um
striving for perfection in parenting is can be counterproductive not only for the parent but also for the child that
in our practice we need imperfection we need the road to be bumpy we need the
mind to wander off that it needs so that it can be drawn back we learn something really important about this practice
that it's not about perfection it's about um it's about
being meeting meeting our experience with sufficient wisdom so that we can be
free so enough said for today appreciate everybody being here uh I hope the rest
of your day goes well and um we'll meet again tomorrow
let's meet again tomorrow same time same place where we'll take up the fourth of these faculties which Gil characterizes
as wholeness others say unification or
collectiveness and this is particularly true in the meditation practice but I think it's a quality of experience and a
capacity that uh really helps us in meeting meeting the world we live in so
take care everyone uh till tomorrow bye