so good morning everyone here in California good morning from
here and uh good day and I'm sitting here quite happy
to looking at the chats that are coming through
um wonderful good mornings good morning everyone wonderful good morning so it's
quite nice to to
just I have to turn
okay I'll try again so happy to be here with all of you and
to start this new week of teaching and uh what I'd like to do this
week is to go back over what I did last week um
I believe that there's much more to say on each each of the five topics and
given how Central these ideas these
practice approaches are to my teachings maybe it's not a surprise that
it's nice for me to be able to go through them
again so for today I'd like to keep this instructions quite simple and so I ask you
to um find a way that you can make these
work for you what I'll what I'm about to say uh it might be challenging for some
some of you for sure to hear this and um or many of you will might come up with
exceptions that this can't be Universal what I'm going to say but um uh probably
i' i' would agree with you that that's the case but still there might be a way a perspective that you could use that
you can find this beneficial it's not Universal it's not
uh going to be true all the time and it might not address all of your
concerns in practice but still it might uh at least
for these next few minutes and might be a different orientation different
perspective from which you can learn something and sometimes we even learn something deep when it something doesn't
work for us so the simple idea
is that Buddhist practice is oriented towards suffering
and the end of suffering but it's an orientation that one way or the
other um brings happiness is oriented towards happiness
as much as it's oriented towards suffering that um the very orientation
the very perspective the very PR ability to practice with
suffering can be a source of joy happiness be so lucky so fortunate
to have a practice in spite of whatever suffering
we have wow we can practice with this not many people have that and to
understand that the practice always has something to contribute when we're challenged and
when we're not and that there's happiness in just the
engagement or practice the ability to do it happiness of the faith of engaging to
it there's the happiness that somehow
exists side by side with suffering that these two
sometimes don't live so separate from each each other that the more we suffer
maybe we can feel our way and to it our way to the other side of
suffering we can maybe even see the possibility of a ending of suffering
kind of through the cracks of our suffering so as we sit to this
morning we'll sit mostly in silence and now um but Orient yourself
towards a realistic happiness and by realistic I mean not a denial of the
challenges you have or the suffering you have the pains that you have no way is
this meant to be a denial or a avoidance
exactly but it's is a way of Shifting the orientation from being preoccupied with
the suffering from being caught in the suffering reactive to the
suffering to having some form of
happiness joy together with our
challenge so that we are more appreciative more
nourished more supported by the happiness of practice
and that happiness maybe allows us to be even more realistic in a healthy
beneficial way about suffering so assuming a meditation
posture gently closing your eyes
and gently taking a few conscious
breaths with as much Consciousness awareness as you can relaxing as you
exhale
and maybe it's not so much that you are aware of your
breathing as your body senses the
breathing the experience of breathing senses itself
and if there is any discomfort or
suffering any UNH wholesomeness or tension or strain dis
stress pain through this
sitting perhaps perhaps the experience of breathing or perhaps not the breath the
whole
body or if not the whole
body the kind of listening or sensing to the space around the
body allows you to shift from being focused on
suffering to feeling the goodness of having a
practice of being
present
e
for
for for
a happiness here and now that
orients the thinking mind to become
quieter
Stiller so there's a more
sensitivity to being with the
wellbeing that is
here
for for
for
e
for for
and as we come to the end of this
sitting to continue breathing
mindfully tapping into whatever sense of ease or
calm or happiness
well-being that might be here for
you and with that as a reference point to turn your attention out into
the world that you'll encounter today or
tomorrow a world that's
local that's far away and may it be that your ability to
gaze upon the world kindly peacefully
inspire you to go forth into the world that in a world of
suffering you bring happiness in the world where people feel
unsafe are unsafe you bring
safety in a world of war and conflict you bring peace
and in a world where so many people are caught in attachments and
how to bring the greatest benefits to this world around us may all
beings be
[Music]
happy thank you for
so before I begin this talk I one announcement to make about an upcoming
event here at IMC and it'll be on zoom and uh IMC is
going to for the first time do a kind of um
kind of a celebration of the federal and state holiday of juneth day which is
this Wednesday and um it's one of the I think feel like one of the great holidays in the United States because of
commemorating a a long overdue Freedom liberation of people here in this
country The Liberation From Slavery the people who uh this the date when after the end
of the Civil War uh slave owners neglected to tell slaves in Texas that they were free and
so it wasn't until this day that um the US Army came into that part of
Texas to make bring the news and to free the slaves the final
Freedom It's a Wonderful celebration wonderful celebration of painful part of American
history and um suffering and happiness together and um so very fortunate to
have an Roy to come and uh lead us in this this uh event and she'll give a
little Dharma talk and and the information about it is uh on the IMC
website on what's new and on the calendar and it'll be at 6 p.m. California time and um look forward to
seeing any of you who might come there to be part of it thank
you so for
the the talks for this week I'd like to go through again the topics from last
week's talk which were the core foundational teachings that uh I rely on
or that are underneath how I teach Buddhism and I thought it would be
invaluable for people for me to just lay it out how it is for me so that um
you're not guessing or or assuming a lot about me and uh this
um um topic I is something I'd like to
continue with for this week and go through each of the five topics and um
and offer some more thoughts on it uh with partly with the idea that you will reflect on this uh some of the
value of these uh YouTube teachings that I do uh
will come to you when you reflect on them and consider maybe have conversations with friends afterwards or
um journal or think about them for yourself and how does this work for
you so the first one is uh maybe that's why it's first it is so Central
is that um it's an orientation towards suffering and the end of suffering many
years ago when I was first getting involved in Buddhism and um and uh I went to have
dinner with uh a friend and she asked me you know
what is what's this teaching of Buddhism is about what is Buddhism about that you're interested in it and I was a
little bit thrown off I was new to all as I was young and so I proceeded to
explain to her the four noble truths it was I didn't give it that Dharma talk I just it was relatively
short and uh so that was kind of the end of that part of the conversation and then I went to
um as I was walking home afterwards I thought to myself wow uh that was a
pretty simplistic uh account for Buddhism and my involvement with it and I felt a little
bit uh kind of embarrassed that I would do something so simplistic and uh many years later I
came to appreciate no that was really the heart of it that was like the best explanation I could do that uh this
addressing of suffering the conditions from which suffering arises the end of
suffering and the path to the ending I mean what a fantastic thing and I've
spent a lot of time in my life reflecting and thinking about the for noble truths and I find them ever FAS
ating and deepening and opening and I just feel so delighted by the Simplicity
and the directness of this teaching and one of my favorite kind of reworkings of the Four Noble Truths is
um that there is suffering in this world um the um it's actually like goes
like this um if you cling to anything you will suffer
if you let go of that clinging the suffering ends the suffering from the
clinging so um and uh that's a to me it's very powerful little succinct way
of saying it that shows you we have a role to the end of suffering if
suffering we're addressing not all suffering but the suffering we're addressing in Buddhism that which arises
out of clinging then we have to somehow take a deep look at ourselves to
understand what we're contributing to the suffering so one of the tasks of
having suffering at the center of of the Dharma of practice is not to suffer
better but rather but just so just so we suffer better have more suffering but
suffer better in the sense that uh to suffer in such a way that we start
looking and seeing what's the Ecology of suffering what is this suffering it's
like putting a question mark next to it what is this and in the very questioning
of it begin to find ourselves free from it uh very questioning of it we're no
longer locked into it no longer caught in it but we begin to kind of oh step
back what is this and it's a very powerful step to ask that question what is
this and part of this question what is this suffering is the question what is my relationship
to suffering that might not go to the heart of suffering yet but how do I relate to
it some people relate to it uh with fear some people relate to suffering with
dismay and discouragement some people Rec uh relate to it with attachment
there are people who are attached to suffering uh who hold on to it in some way and it's it's a bizarre some people
think it's bizarre that they're told that maybe they're attached to suffering but uh or enchant would have talked
about people being enchanted with suffering and uh somehow uh uh some
people are so familiar suffering has been such an important part of their life such a big part of their life that
they can't imagine who they'll be without it and they're afraid of letting go of it because then who will they
be some people form a very strong identity around their suffering uh and so and it's an identity
sometimes that um other people support and in fact part of the reason for the
identity is to get other people to relate to them through the lens of that suffering feel sorry for them or take
care of them or something um so the relationship to the suffering
and one of the core ones that reference a core practices we do to look at this
is a teaching called the five hindrances when we suffer when we are
feeling emotional distress of any kind at all then um do we succumb to some
kind of Desire sensual desire take us away from it um addictive behavior for
example um or when we have this kind of psychological distress do we um have
aversion do we get caught in blame or aversion or hostility towards anything the suffering or or others or the
situation or ourselves do we get do we freeze do we get rigid do we get uh um
uh resistant do we get do we shut down in some way do we fall
asleep um do we um uh then the fourth hindrance is do we are we do we get
Restless running around in circles or do we um uh get full of remorse and regrets
because of what we've done or because of how we are and then the final is U doubt we
have just lived in indecisiveness uh not be able to make any commitment not knowing which way to
go so these are all this is very you know just basically giving you the list
but we're beginning to question what is my relationship to suffering and that's a different question is why am I
suffering and sometimes in this practice it's more useful and more important to say how am
I relating what's the that's kind of like the outer layer of the shell and without having some sense of
of the relationship we have to it we can't really ask the question why or how
or what's underneath it we have to kind of clear out the air clear out this Mi space around our suffering and not be so
locked into it or caught in it and so uh uh being caught in suffering is the
relationship being resistant to suffering is the relationship and learning slowly you see that suffering
and the way that we relate to it are two different things and uh and as we start teasing
those apart we see that we can create space we can create distance we can create
Freedom towards the suffering if we're so locked into the idea that suffer
happiness only happens when the suffering goes away we miss a very important part of what this Buddhist
practice can bring us and that is a certain kind of well-being a certain
kind of delight and joy that comes from freeing our relationship to
suffering and I'd like to propose that that's an easier job than getting rid of
suffering but if we think that our Rel if we don't see the difference between our relationship and the suffering
itself then um you know it makes the task so much more difficult and part of
the reason why people practice concentration practice is that it's a way of kind of
um uh shifting that relationship uh by not understanding
what it is we get really concentrated and the complicated relationship Falls
away and we can see more clearly but in mindfulness practice we want to
understand how we relate to suffering how we're caught in it and resistant to it and all this and then be so happy be
delighted that we have a practice that helps us to understand that that helps us to kind
of separate out the extra that we add to it and so we can learn to suffer with
nothing extra and that is special to have no
just I don't know if it's a inspiring concept just pure suffering this
Simplicity just the suffering itself without the stories we add to it without the predictions of what means in the
future without the fantasy and Concepts and constructs we layers and layers we
add to it just this is painful this is difficult this is
hard whatever is going on in the Simplicity of that that statement and then to find there's a happiness in
having a practice that puts a question after suffering that we have happiness
and joy and faith and inspiration that oh we have a practice that addresses this um I can sit and
meditate I can follow my breath I can do some concentration practice just little just enough to be able to look more
carefully and um and uh and then in the process of that there's a way in which
we are so happy to engage in a practice to give ourselves
to a practice of u meditation of Med mindfulness of honesty of Engagement
with this process that the very engaging of it starts to kind of feel almost
physiologically good almost like you're involved in a craft or an art or some AC
ity that you really get absorbed in and just the activity of doing it feels so good so believe it or not really giving
yourselves over to a practice to come to the end of suffering brings happiness and um and
so uh in the kind of simplistic way that I think sometimes is helpful to
hear um so there there's Buddhism teaches there's suffering and the end of
suffering the path in between those two how to get
from suffering to the end of suffering is a path of happiness happiness is that
important and uh and uh and it's realistic to engage in our practice in
our life and pra in such a way that happiness is the guide
well-being uh is the guide to the end of suffering so Buddhism offers a
realistic assessment engagement with our suffering an honesty that about our fact
that we're suffering and that realism is a is a catalyst for
happiness not to take not to paper
over the suffering but rather in the midst of it to know there's another way
to know there's a possibility of freedom and to be delighted to engage in a
practice that is honest about suffering and has a also a realistic
sense of a joy a delight a happiness that can come from a path a practice to
the end of suffering so may you
um find the Delight The Joy the happiness that can
come when we practice with
suffering so thank you and um I look forward to it tomorrow