it's good to be with you I am uh yeah happy happy to be practicing on
this uh day this kind of quiet uh strange week holiday week for some and
uh I don't have my headset which means you can see my ears which are fine they're just ears
I'm not embarrassed but I'm used to my Gamers headset and uh here I am in a hotel
without it so you know
flexibility anyway uh it's good to uh good to practice in this time and
uh um yeah conscious some people may be inundated with people others feeling a
lack of people a lot happens in this time and it's easy to get uh
disconnected from Dharma and uh kind of fog comes over and um easy to forget a
lot and so um we're here to to remember of
course and um and so let's uh let's sit find our
way
together e
it's just uh kind of uh beginning with the the whatever sweetness of the S there
is so we're we're linked up here by
technology sincerity
Love by a lineage of uh 20600 years that's seen it all
we uh find a way to settle
in to bring some some measure of soothing into your
body
e for
just feeling your your body on the
earth kind of uh Embrace of sorts of uh
gravity
for for
maybe meaning whatever agitation or
tension numbness whatever remains with
u sense of patience and tolerance
like very willing to Lavish our unsettledness with
awareness and a quiet
love
e for
and sometimes the Dharma just feels a little
remote the muscle memory of wisdom and
love isn't there
the rich set of associations and
silences feel
distant don't try to brute force your
way into the Dharma
field just lovingly tend to the wall
that seemingly separates you from
it
e
e for
we recall Buddha dhama Sanaa to help us
remember e
we enter this kind of Realm of of sensitivity and care
you remember the the poignancy the great urgency of this matter of life
and death
our hearts becoming more Supple
simultaneously more strong
is the courage of meeting this
moment as it is never satisfied that we fully know
what this moment is
we keep
looking willing to be surprised by this
practice
e
e e
we uh we don't insist that the Dharma
work we just keep offering our heart up to it no
strings
attached
e
e e
okay um so uh yeah good to sit with
you so um one of uh one of the the Hallmarks of
a of a successful animal animals like us is the um the
ability to stay secure and
protected and in a sense if you want to be safe
you better know a lot about danger and you better have a kind of
robust threat detection system system
and fear serves that function so here's bra brain scientist K Tha she writes
fear is an intensely negative internal state it conducts orchestration of
coordinated functions serving to arouse our Peak Performance for avoidance
Escape or confrontation fear resembles a dictator that makes all other brain
processes from thinking to breathing subservient fear can be innate or
learned and Nate fear can be a response to environmental stimuli without prior
experience such as that of snakes or spiders and humans fear associations are the most
rapidly learned robustly encoded and retrieved and prone to activate multiple
memory systems so in other words
um our system is pretty good you know you could say
that how many times has fear kept me safe I don't even know how do you even
count million right and how many times has the alarm
Bell of fear gone off but there's no actual
threat probably a hundred times that so on the one hand I'm glad we have
fear mechanisms but we've probably overlearned the lessons of
fear and so why why do I begin with all of this um couple weeks ago I think I
was talking about the difference between sensitivity to suffering and fear of
suffering and uh and I was very cognizant of being sensitive
to suffering even as a kid but I maybe haven't realized that just how much fear
is still still bound up fear of suffering particularly the suffering of
others and so today I wanted to to continue around this question of fear
but I'm thinking about the relationship between fear and love and
generosity so there's a story um I just came across it again I read it seven
years ago when it was published and saw it again this week and um um and so the
the author writes a quiet man named uh jow quit his job running the human
resources department of an insurance company in Rio de Janeiro and began selling french fries from a street cart
the fries quickly proved popular in part because they were delicious thin and
crisp and golden even more enticing jaah often served them up for free all he had
to do was ask and he'd scoop some into a box no charge what money he did take in
he frequently gave away to Children begging in the street or used to buy them sweets day after day he came home
to his wife and son without any money in his pocket in his previous life jaah was
been Stern and serious prone to squirreling money away but after
surviving a Health crisis at the age of 49 he wanted to live differently I saw
death from close up he would often say say now I want to be in High Spirits and
nothing made him happier than giving what's most interesting about
Joel um though is that his new outlook resulted not from a spiritual
awakening but from a brain damage caused by a stroke his neurologist says he became
quote pathologically generous compulsively driven to give
his Carefree attitude towards money led to confrontations with his family especially his brother-in-law who
co-owned the French fry cart but even when his family berated him and the cart went out of business and he was reduced
to living on his mother's pension joah refused to stop giving simply made him
too happy so what's the what's the lesson
from this you know was maybe a surprise that pivoted
into a brain injury right rather than some spiritual awakening right is the
lesson maybe we might ask like if you don't have a brain injury if you have normal brain
functioning you're right to be less generous than
Joel maybe maybe
not right our our brains we have to remember are designed for to help us
survive not be free and
um as the story unfolded the um we learned that uh Joel's um the the kind
of nature the damage to his brain you know associated with regions associated
with long-term planning and goal directed Behavior in a certain sense you
could say it eroded his capacity to worry it eroded his capacity for certain
types of fear and of course this is a loss in
some ways his family was suffering as a function of his generosity right fair
enough maybe we say that's not honorable here's the story concludes
uh we can talk about generosity in terms of dopamine hits or pavlovian stimulus
response Theory and that's not necessarily wrong but it overlooks something important about Joel that
giving truly did make him feel happy and fulfilled the Neuroscience researcher
said Joel was one of the happiest people he's ever
met and that made me wonder like okay I don't
want to throw away all of the mechanisms of my
fear but what would my love look like if
I were less afraid what would your love look like if you were less
afraid even if it were just 5% of
joal what would your love look like I can sense in me that that
my my love feels constrained by different forces it's not that I'm
not a loving person or something but I can feel that it's it's still
constrained it's constrained among other factors by fear fear this sense of like and it fear
just puts us into the deepest in Innocent but very primitive
corner of self where the world is populated
essentially by threat that's the only Salient feature of the world what is
threat what's not threat and um how different how
different right would our vision of Life be
when the most Salient feature of the world is not threat but instead
goodness and
need my love feels constrained by um by social
custom you know in some ways we we celebrate generosity in some ways but um
view it with suspicion in others you know
my love feels constrained by the kind of prevailing standards of how much we're
entitled to privilege our own well-being over that of
strangers you know and there is just um for me just
like uh just reading reading about um
that story it it was a very kind of deep um d
you know just a deep Delight in it and it didn't feel sullied by the fact that
it was a brain injury rather than a spiritual awakening that led him to give
away all those fries and the the the kind of um the
Delight in doing that like I actually get I get that you
know right like the sense of um
yeah this sense of like this latent love in all of us you know that is somehow
constrained or somehow we're self-conscious or there's fear that um
limits Us in some way there's social niceties or whatever con you know just
following conforming to standard models of what goodness entails you know
but like I want to give away some fries bad you
know and I know I if I like did that for 15 minutes each day before
meditating that would be a nice sit that would be a nice life I think my the
condition of my heart and mind would be improved by that you
know and so the encouragement here is um
to uh to understand the relationship between fear and love more
deeply I'm cautious about simplistic formulations of you know the opposite
of um you know fear is is is love you
know the opposite of Love is fear rather than hate or something like that like that in intuitively makes a lot of sense
but I'm sure it's complex but um it's worth even
considering as a kind of thought experiment what what shape would your
heart take if the nagging worries and control and
concern and fear Abad it you know even just a
little Tian says uh the only way to ease our fear and truly be happy is to
acknowledge our fear and look deeply at its source instead of trying to escape our
fear we can invite it up to our awareness look at it
clearly deeply and it's my
sense that in in gathering some of our courage and feeling a little bit more
secure in opening to finitude and mortality and knowing we all already
know how the story ends that that helps melt away some of
the worry we become more um radical or our
love okay for this for your uh consideration so uh thank you all I'm
happy to uh to be with you this evening and um look forward to uh to
next uh next week see you next time yeah wish you a good week okay folks thank you