so uh so welcome folks ah
sweet okay um so I'll uh I'll say a few words and
we'll uh we'll sit
um so to let let go of um our kind of Nar
narrative project what we call our life my so-called life to let go of our
narrative project that's that's hard it's difficult it's um it's difficult not to
sort of embed all phenomena in a coherent narrative
web and we sort of just keep adding the
moment to the kind of story of me just keep adding a tiny thin little
chapter to our autobiography and we don't check that
habit at the door when we start to meditate right it's sort of
like every meditative phenomena every experience with concentration or
distraction with Pleasure and Pain all of that gets kind of of incorporated
into this this narrative structure it's like sometimes like the sort of Morgan
Freeman Dharma voice over you know with our meditation
right and uh it's very natural and adaptive in a lot of ways
and awareness renounces language
beginning to pick up on this uh theme week ago awareness kind of renounces
language been reading um uh a a book uh
kind of hundreds of case reports a book by uh Thomas metzinger the elephant and
the blind I I'll post it MIT press actually made it free for download and
I'll post it in the the YouTube um description
after um but met singer interesting very interesting character kind of like you
know traditionally trained analytic philosopher meditator and um and got you know I
think something like 1,400 reports from meditators about awareness something
like this and so he's using kind of philosophical Precision with a lot of
direct reports and and his own practice at one point um he uh he writes
um phenomenologically sort of in the level of subjective experience uh
phenomenologically deep silence is the uncontracted quality of Silent knowing itself empty
cognizance lacking any form of grasping or inner
agency it's not only non-conceptual it's also characterized by a principle of
mental inaction it never reacts it never makes
a choice it never initiates an action as one person participant put it
pure awareness is that which never speaks pure awareness is that which
would not even say I am that which never speaks that which says I am that which
never speaks is something else this is an entirely silent and
non-conceptual experience of the phenomenal character of awareness itself
when the object the object is just the capacity to know all the kind of objects
of the ordinary phenomena of awareness uh those those uh fade out but
the the capacity to know the phenomenal character of awareness itself that is
what is known and the meditation instr
instuctions in a way are what we say to do in a way are mimicked by the
qualities of deep silence so we say let go we say don't fight we say
choicelessness we say relinquish willfulness we
say tolerate the disorientation of non-thinking right we give all these
instructions all these things that in in a sense we we try to
do but then when we've done them when we've done them uh
the these are these become actually effortless natural qualities of
awareness itself all of the the relinquishment and
the willfulness and the the the choicelessness the kind of depth of the
surrender the way in which we have we're no longer uh tinkering with some SAR you
know at all uh this is this is the the quality
of of uh of awareness and so um I'll give
instructions things maybe we do or things that plant Dharma seeds in the
mind and uh we in a sense just um are
developing developing trust that at the end of our doing there's um
effortlessness and at the all these instructions are are pointing uh
pointing to something instructions mirror the fruit in a way maybe we
say I may be venturing out of my terad and territory I'm not really sure to be
honest but um this is what's occurring to me so uh let's uh let's set
okay e
so maybe a really full
breath just relaxing whatever can be relaxed
developing certain kind of uh frictionless with
uh the first Noble
Truth frictionless this with uh imperfection
friction requires a
narration there's friction we have to understand it we have
to embed it in a narrative game it out
to e
so equinity is a kind of stance in relation to
experience where we're not fighting not generating friction with
imperfection this way we uh invite a kind of
Silence
e e
perhaps we we make some
effort effort to attend to say the
breathing make some effort so at some point we can
relinquish all
willfulness all choic making it's like all the forks in the road that we always
imagine dissolve
e
e e
who you are and what you want and what you hate all the the administrative
details of Any Given
life just lose their uh seductive
power the moment is no longer a problem to be
solved to be
optimized e
so we do but only so we can not
do
e
e e
maybe we can say we trust silence more than sound
e
e e
your life doesn't depend on you
awareness doesn't depend on
you not something you do
so it comes to feel
safe to uh
rest
e
e e
okay so uh H good to uh sit with you and
um just to say that I I sort of uh presume some familiarity with practice
uh in these these sessions and so it's unfortunately if you came here to
kind of like learn meditation as a first go um there are lots lots of good
resources at at IMC to uh you know intro classes and lots of great recordings and
lots of stuff anyway that's not trying to absolve myself uh completely uh of
irresponsibility but um uh just to uh to flag
that okay so
um sometimes when a um a a monastic gives a Dharma
talk the S says at the end you know s sadu
sadu sometimes that's rendered as as well said or it is
well um but it it connotes uh that the words have been received that there's
some some kind of uh nourishment in the words nourishment in the words
and I you know love words is it when somebody said
you know it's like I was talking all about silence silence and then somebody said like yeah but you love words it's
like yeah I do I love words I try to be careful with words try to use them in a
way uh my own you know as best I can to create a
kind of atmosphere of of of Dharma where this sense of the Dharma is more um
palpable and um and I I've always been
kind of skeptical about attempts to essentially deify silence and demonize
language you know like sometimes when when when people say
well the the path or this experience it's ineffable it's it's
unspeakable often have a sense of like well I get that but actually we can say
a lot about that experience we can say a lot about this aspect of the path or
that aspect it it's not that we can't say anything it's just that language sometimes seems
to defile the beauty of such
experiences so we can we can say a lot
and um I'm becoming more aware of the ways that that language language
functions as the primary tool in Mara's toolbox you know Mara this kind of like
embodiment of suffering um forces of
suffering and uh okay Mara's toolbox language functions as a kind of primary
tool in that and I'm becoming more aware of the
connection between uh fear and language fear and
thought thinking is usually described as um as
the kind of um the the cause of Dua the cause of dukka you
know U but it's also the effect of duah
uh suffering right thinking is the cause of Dua we we get that right to sort of
wrong view wrong understanding all of that our life project becomes very
muddled very muddled when we're hold wrong view when we hold the view for
example that hatred Works life gets extremely muddled and so the Dharma is a kind of
cognitive therapy that helps us change our thinking our schemas to reduce
suffering but the the flip is also worthy of our
consideration that thinking is the product product of
suffering rather than just a cause thinking is the product of suffering
maybe we put it like this um where
there peace and security we would not
feel any compulsion whatsoever to speak or think about oneself or the
world but fear as as um the brain scientist K Tai said she said fear has
an authoritarian command over the rest of the
brain and the challenge of of anicha
uncertainty is so huge its effect are so pervasive the Buddha like put Finger
right on it you know the effects of the pervasiveness of like grappling with
anicha grappling with anicha this kind of small very soft fragile creature
amidst unimaginably vast forces what am I to
do think
right and so we're preoccupied with arranging our security and so we we
differentiate and conceptualize and categorize friend and foe threat and
opportunity put everything into buckets uh uh explain it in relation to
everything that's come before what I know about this information is sometimes described
as the reduction of uncertainty information is the reduction
of uncertainty to have information is to reduce the measure of uncertainty and we're so hungry for
information so hungry to decode this feeling or that sound or
that whatever right in our practice just to what what
does this mean right anicha anicha as I said last week I
think like anicha feels like Risk you know like a kind of ongoing
threat anicha and meaning
making revolves around this kernel of
fear in other words language is the the tool we use to manage
an to manage it to reduce this the to generate
information to reduce the sense of uncertainty we talk about the pain of
thinking for sure oh my goodness for sure but there is a deeply self soothing
quality we should also investigate even when the thinking is
really Bleak as painful as thinking
is to not think is more
painful it's more painful and so fear fear sends us into
the kind of dingy Workshop you know of our mind the
headquarters that I call Matthew right
and clinging clinging is um clinging the implementation of
craving clinging is strategizing and strategizing perhaps always involves
some measure of language language is kind of the tool we use to
orchestrate our clinging you know I use that word orchestrate deliberately to
orchestrate it language is the hammer every problem
is a nail and so every problem every
problem uh needs needs a
subject the the arising of a problem the arising for it to arise as a problem it
needs a subject a kind of egoic form of awareness with me Matthew at the
center and so every problem involves measurement and comparing and a
subtle sense of of alienation a kind of the World
experience as heavy the alienation of a subtle kind of
dualism object Weighing on
subject the uh third in Patriarchs like 1500 years
ago or something when the subject disappears there can be no measuring and
comparing subject disappears there can be no measuring and no comparing the
very like sense of of um of self is is um involves
measurement comparison involves that the sense of the weightiness of
problems involves the kind of alienation of
language and maybe we say Awakening Awakening
doesn't uh does not um solve our problems Awakening arises
when we have no problems when we have no problems when we have no problems we
don't need language we don't need language and we don't need a
self we don't need to orchestrate the moment into a coherent
narrative well okay yeah but what what on Earth could it
possibly mean to have no problems given our sensitive bodies given the
first Noble Truth given everything what could that possibly mean
right well all these words are just upaya
skillful means maybe not even so skillful but they're all
upaya right this is uh
one way of um nudging the
mind but to have no problems means even even for just a
moment we trust letting go more than holding
on even for a moment even for a moment
awareness feels more urgent more important than
anything else it's it's like awareness is
fully
satiating and there's such a a deep sense of safety in that that all all
phenomena are treated as false alarms false
alarms like all all phenomena we're no longer trying to decode the meaning of
this sensation or that sound all phenomena are um The buddas Plea to let
go and then we we begin to
um to really place are a certain kind of faith faith in
silence faith and silence which which is not a kind of willful gesture it's like
we trust the karmic momentum of our practice of our
wholesomeness place our faith in silence and then
everything gets very quiet except
awareness so I offer this for your consideration and
uh do remember every teaching can be used or misused we do our best to uh to use
teachings uh so may they uh be of benefit for uh for you those you
touch okay
folks wishing you a a good week
okay yeah happy to uh to be with you