okay so uh [Music] welcome uh yeah warm welcome to to all
of you uh I'm Matthew um and
uh yeah let's uh let's let's practice I don't know what we'll do sort of find
our way together for
very natural to just keep reiterating our
s effectively to
predict Matthew for the next moment to predict yourself your model of
Self in the next
Moment One neuroscientist said I predict myself therefore I am
what would it be to be genuinely
open to the next moment not overly structuring it with
the expectation that I'd be exactly the same
person in the next moment e
what kind of openness might we
know if we didn't expect to find
exactly our self in the next moment
if we didn't know how we would feel how life would
feel if we didn't know who we would
be what Stories We would tell
you've been humming the story of self for so long
and now we know the melody so
well we know when the chorus is
coming can we relax all of this for
we can't simply direct our attention to our breathing or our body
feeling because we bring the and reverberations of that
song into the attentional
field so instead we we make uh opaque
what was transparent
the song we've been
humming that's just felt like me actually becomes an object of
awareness
we become slightly
alienated from every song We Sing of
myself every story of
me they don't all become false but we just
become little fatigued alienated from
them
for
e e
we don't fight self with more
self we uh to use a phrase from shinzen Yang we love love it to death love the
self to death
and this frees us up to pay a different kind of
attention to our
breathing somehow less crowded
less crowded by the childlike moralism of what we're supposed to
be as crowded by the moralism of the story of me the
pros and cons
Matthew a crowded by the expectations of what the next moment will be must be
ought to [Music]
be as crowded by the kind of Baseline
Assumption of what my life feels like
who I'll be in the next
moment and so we surrender into our
breathing
e
e e
we tend to put this moment on
autocomplete like the SS being
finished in a text message except it's our life
so we're relaxing some of
the predictive business
becoming more intimate with our
breathing
for
e
e e
we can't make our home in a in a
story story of self or any other story for that matter
no Story withstands the test of
time and so we become awake if we make a home for ourselves at
all it's in that wakefulness
these last few minutes just becoming
globally awake to the phenomena that we call our
life internal
external e
not trying to take up a vantage point anywhere
particular just opening to the
space
for
e
e e
okay thank you uh thank you good to practice with you
um so who this uh theme of um interpersonal life Dharma
and interpersonal life and the question who Who Am I who
am I we uh uh don't often explicitly ask that
question but it it's a question that has a venerated spiritual
history and every answer we might give
feels a least a little wrong somehow
inadequate or incomplete or
inauthentic and in our alienation we we have
uh an answer you know who am
I and before the Mind actually reaches for an answer it stops and it creates a
certain kind of Wonder and mystery and we come on this path to love
becoming mysterious to ourselves that that kind
of moment when the familiar all too familiar autobiography just kind of
peels open you know that feeling it's
um scares me a little bit but uh Delights me and livens me
too and sometimes I say that uh sincerity sincerity spiritual
sincerity is the willingness to be
surprised but our tendency of course is to get to
knowing to knowing about ourselves about
others and interpersonal practice you know this
realm is about knowing but it's also about not
knowing it's about knowing it's about empathy knowing the
inner life of others right sometimes described as
theory of mind or in the psychoanalytic literature
mentalization being able to richly ACC accurately model the inner life of the
other and sometimes if a person has dealt with a lot of misattunement
maybe um uh a parent or something that
that simply just could not understand the child's inner life capacity for
mentalization is is compromised we almost come to an understanding of our
inner life colle collaboratively and when that's that's
not there this capacity for mentalization this deep empathic
capacity can be compromised and so sometimes we have to ret ourself something we have to learn
ourself in a new way and mindfulness is a kind of self-directed
empathy we uh we learn we learn a lot about what
it's like to be human what it's like to be incarnated in this
life and we through that process we become dramatically more attuned to the
feelings and needs the beliefs the action
Tendencies of uh of others we become more attuned to our our impact on others
and so you could say a lot of the way that into Dharma practice functions we
become more more knowing empath empathy is a kind of knowing
understanding but as the the uh Zen story that I'm fond of quoting says not
knowing is most intimate not knowing is most intimate the
practice is also about not
knowing uh Simon ve said uh I I am also other than
what I imagine myself to be to know this is
forgiveness often other than what I imagine myself also other than what I
imagine myself to be to know this is
forgiveness I was very very curious with that to know this is
forgiveness and perhaps it's only in our knowing in the kind of
overdetermined model we have of ourselves our certainty it's only in
that that we can truly indict ourselves and to know that we are also
something other it opens the space of
some of not knowing of
forgiveness and the child the parent the the spouse the partner the the best
friend forever they they are also other than
what we imagine them to be to know this is forgiveness
yeah so maybe you know the experience it
happens kind of most often with those we we know most those we love
most but over the years we we become so familiar with them that at some point we
actually stop looking at them and the sanctity of our tension becomes
degraded they become buried behind a wall of Concepts and the
concepts sometimes feel so thick that it's like I cannot reach you I cannot reach
you and sometimes maybe after after years or
or even decades we might deeply look at
them and ask this question who are you
really because we're we're animals and
vulnerable and dependent on many conditions and dependent on on in a
sense making life predictable this is our our deep habit
not inditing this is um Stephen Stephen
Mitchell says um we learn to love in the context of the contrived and necessary
safety of early childhood and love seeks perpetually a kind of safety that
screens out the unknown but in human relationships safety and
predictability are difficult to come by we endlessly strive to reestablish
that illusory sense of permanence and predictability when patients and uh he's
a psycho you know was a psychoanalyst when patients complain of lifeless
relationships it's often possible to show them how precious the deadness is
to them how it's carefully maintained and insisted
upon Love by its very nature is not
secure we keep wanting to make it
so so with our our escalating dependence on others
we try to make them predictable too we we certain like
routinize the connection routinize the love
even and how we actually try to connect with uh not knowing the openness of the
others being is from uh the Phil br novel The
Human Stain about it there's a Classics Professor being described by the
narrator uh and the the the
uh narrator says um previously concealed was the small popey is T Blue Tattoo
situated at the top right arm is of the professor's arm just at the shoulder
joining the words US Navy and described between the hook-like arms of a shadowy little anchor and running along the
hypotenuse of the deltoid muscle a tiny symbol if one were needed of all the
million circumstances of the other fellow's life
of that blizzard of details that constitute the confusion of a human
biography a tiny symbol to remind me why our understanding in of people must
always be at best slightly
wrong at best slightly
wrong when we get to knowing and relate to others as a kind of concept we
sacrifice certain intimacy and
spontaneity we we sort of orchestrate a a kind of predictability but that
orchestration also leads to a certain kind of flatness and I'm very
sympathetic to that I mean how much an Nicha can we take how much can we take
it's not adaptive to only ever be focused on
groundlessness we need a measure of predictability but that same
predictability can muffle the wildness of loving another
person and
so we uh we come back to not knowing because we don't wish to ignore the kind
of fullness of the other's experience we get into these um highly
choreographed routines with each other and we each play our role with great
Fidelity maybe as a way of soothing ourself and soothing the
other but then there's this wildness
and we want to remember that we know them only in our relation to them we
kind of freeze them into a parent or a child or a spouse or
whatever and we in essence confuse their role in our life with who they
are but they are only that in relation to you to everyone else they are
something else and sometimes I
glance at someone I love maybe they don't don't even see me looking maybe
they're alone ued in a
way and there's something very powerful in taking in their
being in as it's completely apart from
me the role that we play in each other's lives
and so we cultivate this reverence for not
knowing we put down what is known we attune to the wildness of
loving another person so offer this for your
consideration and uh please pick up what's useful leave the rest behind and we'll uh we will keep going
uh tomorrow wish you all a good day