all right so um I see some people I know some people I don't so hi to those I
don't know nice to meet you I teach on Thursday nights Dharma practice Thursdays at 6:30 so come by sometime if
you like to connect we do small group discussions and you get to another way
to get to know your songa um it's a nice nice
evening and um I'm a student of Gil and Andrea uh Gil frol and Andrea fella I'm
in the four-year teacher training program that's going on we're just finishing year three so I am a student
and child of dhma at IMC this is my Dharma home and um so you
know Martha I appreciate you bringing up the center being Donna based
um I was kind of of one just feeling a sense of awe and wonder this morning
yesterday as I was thinking about coming to teach today because I didn't have to tell anybody I was coming I didn't have
to arrange a place to offer the teachings I didn't have to pay for
anything I didn't have there's all this stuff I didn't have to do because of the way the center everything is freely
offered so Martha right thank you and than thank you what thank you vany thank
you right and Hillary out there thank you and folks the T folks and who El you
know going organizing walks everything here absolutely the paint on the
wall seriously the car all of it is Donna the building itself is
Donna out of generosity because the people before us wanted us here they
wanted you here so I'm grateful to the Buddha the Dharma
and the S including this s right so what I want to talk about today
is um reactivity and
non-reactivity [Music] um yeah this is to me this is a big
topic and it's tied to a lot in the Dharma but you know reactivity is pretty
unpleasant thing isn't it really
uncomfortable and uh you know I I I I feel very yanked around when I'm being
reactive and um you know it I'm inevitably walking away feeling
remorseful regretful you know when I've been reactive like why couldn't I
just be he still why couldn't I just meet this
moment without adding all this flopping
around and really this is uh why I came to the practice was
because I was not able to meet what was happening in my life it was too hard
things were falling apart and I kept you know it was just
too painful I kept reacting and reacting and reacting so I wasn't able to there's
so much I wasn't able to meet and I kept trying and I'd say Okay I want to do this I want to be able to calm and talk
about this or respond kindly and but it was just oh the feelings inside were
just so intense and um you know that was that
was true um and one of the relationships in my life that's really motivated me to
practice is my relationship with my kids and um now it's really important to
me I want to be a good Mom I wanted to be a mom that could meet her kid or kids
where they were to make them feel you know like I trusted them I believed in
them and uh I kept failing because my reactivity would get in the way of the
message I was trying to deliver so I I when I finally came to the
practice because of so much reactivity I was pretty darn motivated and I kind of
just Dove right in and was in on Retreats almost right away and I I just
over and over again it was just like there's a way there's another way to
meet this life there's another
way I was recently thinking about this um
and um I was remembering an image that I
had you know been taught from one of the sutas early in my practice and the image was of a fish
flopping around doesn't that just sound like
reactivity like a fish flopping around on the ground in a puddle you know like
that and that is exactly what for me I felt inside of myself was like this fish
that was just relentlessly flopping around and so I uh looked up the
sua again recently and I'm going to share it with
you um the suta you know the Su the Buddha
does an amazing job of providing writing these similes these images these
metaphors analogies for what we experience in our inner
life and um you know this is an example of one of those you know analogies or
similes that has just really stayed with me and there's something so visceral
about it and so for me the practice is an
experience to have to engage with so these kinds of similes um are are really
helpful because when I feel it I'm reminded of the Dharma so may may this suta be there
inside of you deeply connected to whatever your version of a f fish flopping around is you
know yeah put your mic closer because I'm not able to
internet sure all the
help is that any better doesn't S doesn't sound any better to
mezy still a little far it's still a little far how's that oh that felt
better right yeah okay okay so the Su is called the uh Aon
ATA Su and it's been interpreted by a number of poly Scholars um some call it
the rod embraced some called it call it arming oneself um another name is the thorn in
your heart and
um the this is um a suo that the Buddha
gives when he's called to deal with a con conflict in
community and um
he he he shares a lot about his his own emotional response to conflict in this
suta it's really quite touching and the the while the suta is
about external con conflict right between people I invite you to feel into this as
the same as internal conflict and by that I mean um we can
take up arms against others but we also take them up against ourselves and we might not take up
physical arms against others but if we take up arms in my in my mind about somebody if I'm angry at
somebody we have an internal experience that
is results in suffering if I think about myself
critically there's a way in which my experience of this is that then my image of myself becomes
akin to an enemy that when I think about myself my physiology responds to myself as if I am
a threat my very own self because of my own view of myself in some
circumstance so please don't limit yourself s to thinking about this is only about those other people who fight
with other people if there's any degree of inner conflict inner criticism if you have an
inner critic which I imagine you all do this applies to
you when embraced so let me just I should say this first too there's so
many translations I have a number of different them that are mixed together here so if you go to look up the
suta you may find a different version or you'll see that I've mixed versions
together here when embraced the rod of violence breeds danger and
fear fear is born from arming oneself just see how many people
fight I'll tell you about the Dreadful fear that caused me to shake all
over this is the Buddha speaking I'll tell you about the Dreadful fear that caused me to shake
all over seeing creatures flopping around
like fish in shallow and water too shallow so hostile to one another seeing
this I became
afraid another translation of that little two lines is I saw this
population flounder like fish in a little puddle seeing them fight each other fear Came Upon
me the world around was Hollow all directions were in
turmoil wanting a home for myself I saw
nowhere he also says in another translation it trembles in all all
directions this
world seeing people Locked In conflict I became completely
distraught who here has felt distraught seeing the conflict in the
world yeah me too I longed to find myself a place
unscathed but I could not see
it seeing people Locked In conflict I became completely distraught but then I
discern hear a thorn hard to see lodged deep in the heart
what does this bring up for you this idea of a thorn in the heart
typically it's greed hatred and delusion right it's craving
clinging it is only when pierced by this Thorn that one runs in all
directions right when we are you know really in the grip
when we're not in the grip we don't run in all directions and if that thorn is taken
out one does not run and settles
down there's another translation of when struck by that Dart you run around in
all directions and I like the dart image because it reminds me of the Aros
simile but when that same Dart has been plucked out you neither run around nor sink down and I like that too run around
or sink down because I have seen this too where there's this running around
reactivity and you know that is acting out and trying to escape and all these
things and then there's a giving up or giving in that is like a sinking down
like just a complete kind of sunken place it can happen
the um the one title of this is the rod embraced and the rod symbolizes taking
up arms right usually back then it was a
stick but the the simile should be understood to understand that the rod of
violence has three forms physical verbal and mental so this goes
to the words that we use toward others ourselves the way we treat ourselves
physically the way we treat others physically and the way we imagine things
the may we think of things the views and opinions we
create and one interpreter says um the cause of
this is the misplaced wish for security driven by
desire and the suta goes on to talk about the solution which is all the ways
we learn to let go in this practice all the ways we learn to let go
and you know these are pretty common things that you'll
hear and I'll just say a little bit about them but a sage should be
truthful overcome greed overcome the
hindrances essentially sloth and toror and among others should not sink into false
speech should understand and greed as a great
Deluge stand close to the truth develop
wisdom and transcend this desire for sensual pleas pleasure letting what is
gone be
gone being free of Cruelty
and not seeing oneself as any of the following not seeing oneself as
equal welcome back baby I love the sound meditation this
morning so sweet so we we don't see ourselves as
equal inferior or Superior is that hard to
imagine what's that how do we what is the yeah I have
something that I learn from psychology but I've never heard anything from the
perspective yeah well I can tell you how I interpret it Genie thank you
um so I think that I mean our language this language to me is quite binary it's
very you know um one way or another we we're you know this or
that and um when we think about equality or equal being
equal if we think about ourselves then you know we want somebody else to
be equal to it there's a real math equation here right there's this like sense of you can weigh two things on the
scale and they weigh the same but they don't we don't weigh the same our experiences can't be
commodified in that way so if we can go beyond this idea of mathematical
equations and we can just think about the uniqueness of each being that there's no
way to measure you know this this equality
thing not that one is more important or less important both are important and if
we can see people as unique as special
as kind of what that whatever it is they are we're going to be much more inclined
to be curious about what does make you you and what does make me me so is that
helpful Genie yeah great I'm
glad so I think that
um one of the teachings I grabbed on to when I
couldn't when I was more reactive more often maybe then
I am now was just don't make it worse it's a really really good
teaching just don't make it worse I remember you know hearing um the
teachers talk about um to try and sit and be with whatever came up right like
turn towards your experience with curiosity you know don't try and change
it be with your suffering and um when I was first
practicing I I couldn't even be with my own mind for more than 5 minutes it was like 5 minutes was the
time that was the that was the minimum you know that was the the marker okay sit for five Tanya try and sit and I
believe it was hard to sit still it was hard to sit with what was coming up in
my own mind and not be flopping around like a fish I wanted to get away from
what I was feeling I wanted to feel calm I wanted to be at ease I wanted to be happy
I was not it was hard so the idea of not making it worse
was like okay can I just you know if I'm reactive this much can I just not make it worse not be more reactive right and
not react to my reactivity but the words while I
couldn't quite do them did wake something up in me and then this V Vision this idea of
this fish came alive in me and I started to feel the
fish more and more and I could feel the fish as something something that was
going on in me it was instead of it just being everything a feeling and in my
mind and my thoughts being everything my whole experience I could start to see oh this is this is something that's going
on inside and then there's reactivity to
it I'll come back to this but I I just want to say that it is really hard to
listen to be receptive and impossible to love when we
are flopping around like fish when we are trying to escape from what we're
feeling what's happening we cannot love because we're
our our Attention our energy is fully consumed with trying to get away trying
to change it and sometimes in life we're asked to sit
through things that are hideously difficult
and I want to love through those things
too I really [Applause]
do I'm just giving my heart a minute
here baa yeah
you know one of the crown jewels of the practice of the
teachings is developing wisdom understanding this heart mind
complex yep so understanding what's happening
will bring peace to the mind and once you understand how
precious the process is of being able to look and see and understand from the
perspective of what the Buddha teaches us joy becomes more possible and we feel
more and more motivated to keep looking so coming to understand what's
happening inside of us with this fish wiggling around jiggling around
trying to get air maybe the simplest way to understand
it and if you were here the last time I spoke you know a lot about how I feel about
Dua I wrote I I gave a talk a couple months ago called becoming a Dukat
tracker so if you're interested in hearing more from me about Dua listen to
the talk so Dua what is Dua for those of you who don't know Dua is the poly word for
suffering so the you know it is said the Buddha said he taught suffering and the
end of suffering the whole
Continuum and so suffering can be translated in this huge
range from very subtle like just the slightest like you know
fabric that rubs a little bit on your skin creates a little bit of tenderness
maybe there's a little bit of a a rub to maybe this idea of fish flopping
around in a war huge amounts of suffering and pain
so this great big scale so this is duka and I like to use
the word duka because it has a different um context for me than the word
suffering which I don't really like maybe because I don't like to
suffer but there's also um a couple other translations that can be useful
one is stress right another is
pain which I like too and then uh one teacher Lee
brazington suggested the term bummer
which I happen to love because it communicates our attitude toward the
suffering so when you find yourself that's a bummer oh I'm clinging there's
something here I don't like
right it's also described you know um well the Cause right the cause of Dua is
clinging so for me I'll just say quickly Dua itself is not really for me it's I
am so grateful for my Dua I am incredibly grateful for my Dua
and in fact I was thinking this morning wow who am I to think that I should take anyone's dooka
away who am I I needed my Dua I have needed that that stress that
suffering that pain that to to wake me up to what I've been cleaning
to so may I let you all have your
daoka so the cause of Duca is something that is incredibly helpful to understand
so speaking of growing wisdom we grow wisdom when we start to understand understand that Dua itself is for me a
guide Dua itself is pointing to the fact that I'm
clinging it is a symptom of clinging when I cling It
Hurts So if I can see Duca when I feel that pain that hurt the discomfort the
stress I can stop and look in the mind heart
body to ask myself why do I want to be different right
now what am I what am I clinging to what what is going on here what is it you
know what I a view I have an opinion I have a belief I
have what's going on and the Buddha taught you know in one
of his teachings three kinds of clinging so I'll just name them to help us
because it's helpful right to sort of look oh there's sense clinging to sensuality feeling good food tasting
good like oh bummer this dinner sucks okay clinging to wanting it to taste better right very simple probably not a
huge amount of daoka in that unless maybe you know you're serving the dolly
llama or something you know and and it there's a
natural you know amount of wanting to be comfortable it's really
okay it's really okay that we want Pleasant things and we want to feel okay
and not be in pain it's it's really fine I was thinking about um babies
probably inspired by our guest and um about how from from
birth you know babies know what they want and what they don't
want they go toward what they want and they cry and push away what they don't
want like this is just part of being a human an animal even right living all
Liv even in amoeba you know like they we all go toward what feels good so you
know okay we're human beings we're living beings this is how we survive
this is how we get through life so clinging to sensuality wanting to feel pleasure wanting to enjoy life and feel
good welcome to the world right it's when we start to really
cling we get in trouble the other is clinging to
becoming what does this mean clinging to becoming it's sort of like I want to
become you know a world athletic Olympic swimmer at
56 right How likely is that to happen not at all but I I have this Vision this wish I wish I could be
this and and we imagine it and we fantasize it and we get kind of caught
up in this idea of becoming
something and it triggers a lot of mental kind of fabrication a lot of
story making I want to be the this there's a lot of clinging that can get going in
this and and the opposite of wanting to become is clinging to non- becoming and
this is really painful if you have social anxiety you go into a room and you you don't you want to you know
disappear you don't want to be there or you feel suicidal you don't want to you don't want to be alive anymore this is
clinging to non- becoming not wanting to be not wanting to be the person that makes this mistake
or does that thing or isn't this right so these are three of the ways that we
can look for how we might be
clinging so um this is not to
say that I shouldn't want to become a great swimmer it's not to say you shouldn't
want to become a great meditator or a good Buddhist or whatever it is you want to
become keep your desires get rid of your
Cravings hold it all
lightly there's a way in which um in the poly canon in the Buddhist teaching
there are a lot of analogies that talk about this Paradox of you know don't cling don't
have desire you know get don't get caught up in sensual desire but we need to have our desire we
need to want to do things we need the baby needs to want to eat right it's
okay and one of them is this teaching on um the
raft the Buddha talks about building a raft to cross the floods of greed hatred
and delusion to get from the shore of suffering to the shore free of suffering I want to I want to be over there but to
get there we have to get ourselves across and essentially my view of it is
we build this through creating um a mental
state that allows us to stay present aware non-reactive to put enough energy
into getting across to have Clarity and we cross the
stream and then he says when you get to the other side what do you do with a raft that you use to get
across you put it on your head and carry it around with you everywhere you go no you leave it on the
shore because you've crossed over you used something to get where you need to go well the same is true with you
know the desires that we hold we we need them to to want to meditate we need to
want to meditate right it takes commitment and effort and some hope some
Faith hopefully confidence to do this practice it's not an easy
practice there's a roomy um quote the hurt you Embrace becomes
Joy call it to your arms where it can change that
sweet yeah I'll read you the whole whole poem it's a couple lines longer than
that the hurt you Embrace becomes Joy call it to your arms where it can
change a silkor worm eating leaves makes a cocoon each of us we leaves a chamber of
leaves and sticks silk worms begin to truly exist as they disappear inside that
room without legs we fly the hurt you Embrace becomes
Joy call it to your arms where it can change Gil will talk about practicing
with Open Hands allowing whatever it is that we're working with face like a bird
you know letting it sit here and then when it's ready to go it goes and we're not holding on to it and trying to keep
it but we're giving it this nurturing space to come in and do what it needs to
do and transform on its own so when we stop fighting the way
things are we have access to love the joy
when we block parts of our experience when we try and
resist difficult emotions or difficult experiences that are
happening we end up blocking both the difficult and the
Beautiful the joy and the anger
so when we stop fighting the way things are we have access to
love pemin says fear is a universal
experience even the smallest insect feels it we wait into tidal pools and put our
finger near the soft open bodies of seeing enemies and they close up
everything spontaneously does that it's not a terrible thing that we feel fear
when we're faced with the unknown is part of being alive something we all
share fear is a natural response to moving closer to the
truth and she goes on to say embarking on the spiritual journey is like getting into a very small boat and setting Out
on the Ocean to search for unknown lands with wholehearted practice comes
inspiration but sooner or later we will ALS Al encounter
fear for all we know when we get to the Horizon we're going to drop off the edge
of the world no wonder there people thought the
world was flat right like oh yeah if you're venturing off and you really have no idea you're probably afraid you're going to fall off oh there that that
that's how that idea came about like all Explorers we are drawn to
discover what's waiting out there yet knowing if we have not knowing if we have the courage to face it and this is
this is big there's 10,000 Joys and 10,000 sorrows in this life we can't block the Sorrows without
blocking the joys we don't get to just have the joys it is a crazy ass ride out
[Laughter] there yeah we're just depriving
ourselves really if if we try and control it it's not possible
anyway so how do we just sit down and buckle up put that resolve take resolve to just
be there and open to what's happening in our lives even when it's not what we want
even when it's what we're terrified of who am I to take
away somebody's suffering who am I to take away that which could liberate
someone with if they have
wisdom the moment you accept what troubles you've been given the door will
open this is Mor roomy welcome difficulty is a familiar
comrade comrade joke with torment brought by the friend Sorrows are the
rags of clothes and jackets that serve to cover then are taken off that undressing
and the beautiful naked body underneath is the sweetness that comes after grief
the hurt you Embrace becomes Joy maybe we can learn the value of
staying present engaged and available to life we can learn how to welcome more
and more aspects of Life the beautiful and the difficult and this is how we
don't make it worse this is how minute by minute
moment by moment just don't make it
worse there's time for one last poem maybe if you can hang in there this is
by Rosemary wola traumer it's called skiing Into the Storm
I love the days when it feels right not to turn from not to turn from the storm
but to move deeper in when the body doesn't shy from the cold and wind when
the smile arrives as the storm magnifies and a whoop rises from the lungs like a
Fierce and Hearty bird what is in it what is in what is it
in us that feels more alive in these moments
thank you for your kind attention