okay welcome uh welcome folks nice to be in the chat just in case you don't know I am
Insight Meditation Center there uh in case you think I have a very
intuitive assistant but um anyway it's sweet to
uh yeah sweet to see your uh names and checking
in um okay let us
uh let us practice
sometimes we get into our Dharma posture very
gently the same way somebody might get into a yoga
ASA where they getting in is as important as the getting
to but other times it's counseled by one of my
teachers shinzen Yang who would say start on a dime
sometimes we have to do that in our life and so here we
practice kind of ruthlessness with respect to the trail
of distractions and dramas
we start on a
dime maybe it feels like wait a second I need to tend to all those loose
ends I need to uh patch things up figure
things
out it feels like neglecting a loved one to put down our
thoughts but put them down and if there's pain that comes with
that if there's a sense of vulnerability or incompletion just feel that
e
e e
the renunciation involves the willingness to
feel renouncing a thought that feels
important to tend
to the egoic
wound that feels important to
nurse the [Music]
uncertainty the ambiguity that feels necessary to game
out
for our life that life to become less sticky
involves the willingness to
feel to not use
The Pacifier we call thinking
just breathe and be with your
body tend lovingly clearly to the emotional circuits of
your body that make a
plea about the necessity of
thinking
e
e e
we practice bringing equinity to the emotional
activations one of the effects of this is that
everything becomes less urgent
e e
you're not pretending the rest of your life doesn't exist but right now
this is your
life it won't commence when class
ends tomorrow
begins this is your life
may we uh be
free
e
e e
the closer we get to experience the more fully we need to forget ourselves
to cease pinging to the Tower of I
amness feel safe enough
in the wondrous
dark
e
e e
for [Music]
e
okay good to uh good to sit with
you so I had a a memory teaching um few
days ago um of um a few few times as a
as a kid um I remember I don't know 10 8 10 something
like that and uh I remember kind of playing
this weird thought experiment game in my mind and
uh and it would go something like I I would just and I don't know where this
is from and maybe this is uh uh uh I needed some help or something but I
I felt okay emotionally but I remember I would imagine things falling
away and first that I was never born that was quite
conceivable and then uh my brother and my parents
family never existed okay what what about our
species what about no no history no time no
Universe nothing nothing and I would kind of hit this
point of like real abiding
nothingness and then sort of freak out and I would freak out out I you know
in retrospect probably for a few reasons so first I was was
actively imagining my death and the changing of all
things and um that's a lot you know for a
kid but more radically I I think I was I was imagining something even
Beyond on nihilism not merely that nothing mattered but that nothing could ever
matter uh that there was no no meaning no love no no nothing I
was like trying to get my mind around that and I kind of just something
blotted out and of
course it could have been that way and that there is
something is extraordinarily
wild but in that you know thought exercise uh I
was also trying I I think to to
essentially think my way into
emptiness not that there is nothing but that the something is much more like
nothing than we realize and emptiness Emptiness is
characterized a lot of different ways but one aspect of it we could say
and I'll unpack this language one aspect one characterization maybe would
be um emptiness as the progressive
deification of the self
model so deification that um that that word
um was typically used to describe in meditative circles
to describe the process whereby thoughts become mere thoughts rather than
reality and generally the voice inside my head
is confused for the voice of God right to think is to be identified
with thinking and there are wise thoughts right but all thoughts involve some
measure of identification a collapse of of
metacognitive awareness and mindfulness is about
appreciating phenomena as phenomena rather than phenomena as the world so to
see to recognize visual impressions are arising rather than that's the
world to reify things is to make them more sub substantial more real right the
thought of some food you love makes you salivate the thought of
some something scary makes you afraid it's reified right that thought
is the world it's very real and deification moves in the
opposite direction deification recognizes thought as a passing
phenomena an auditory thought I am a bad
person I am a whatever is heard in the same way that we
hear a sound no more meaning in I'm a
bad as this and So what had been
transparent becomes opaque what we had been looking
through becomes an object of
attention so the thought you know I need lunch is just as
real as anything in the world and then becomes an empty arising
it's the process of disidentification [Music]
deification to use um the philosopher Buddhist practitioner meditator uh
Thomas me metzinger's language the representation of
lunch is not automatically integrated into a transparent self model
we recognize oh that's a thought about lunch it's deified it's rather than I want lunch
it's remains transparent and then gets integrated as
a the agent Matthew model of myself wants lunch
needs lunch and then we go about fulfilling that craving or
whatever but there's a lot more to dis disidentify
from than the thought of lunch and new new
meditators take so much for for granted
um about the self model really the only thing new
meditators uh disidentify with is just distractors you know
like whatever a simple thought about lunch or whatever it may be okay
thinking coming back to breathing or something but what distracts
us is not nearly as problematic as what is always
assumed what is assumed is
transparent and so
it leaves many layers of the model of self self view transparent they must
become opaque so we start to hear the different
ways in which we incessantly hum the song of
self and we're almost constantly reiterating our
position sandwiched between our past and our future each
moment a kind of addendum to our
autobiography this is who I am this is where I've come
from these are my papers they say who I am you know
and the position of our body you know we
keep tabs for understandable reasons but
we keep tabs the places where I end the world begins this is reiterated and integrated
into the self model again and
again so part of what we're learning to do do is this process of
disidentification to disidentify from our preferences right because
unnoticed preferences unnoticed little knots of
clinging um create a motivational
urgency that gets integrated into the self model
and part of the the function of equinity
is to help us disidentify when when we don't have
equinity with you know craving or aversion it's um it's very hard to
disidentify with it it feels like we must enact
it and the craving and aversion that that is not equinom
mised our preferences and points of
clinging holographically project a sense of
self the the sense of
um the sense of ownership sense of ownership is assumed often
transparent this is me this is
mine the majima majima um only when there is what
belongs to a self is there a self only when there's what belongs to a
self is there a self this this ownership these mechanisms of
ownership are transparent we're making them
opaque and to disidentify from all of this is not to dispute the content not
to say I'm someone else but it's to recognize that the
identification the reification has important effects on The View
so we get quiet we get quiet quieter you get ramda says the
more you can hear and so we have to get quiet
enough to hear the noise of our self
model thear said um what is known
cannot be self and so we become more more
comfortable in uh without some of the reference
points having made opaque what was transparent more
comfortable and not knowing more comfortable in uh
emptiness so uh offer this for your consideration this talk came out a
little bit more technically bulky than I had
envisioned it's a little late especially some of you on the East
Coast but it's a certain Wednesday you just kind of
this is what we did so but I'm happy happy to be with you
and uh happy to practice and um pick up what's useful leave the rest behind and we will uh
continue on next week okay you uh take good care