so good morning and welcome again and I believe all the buttons and switches and
things are in place I was away for three weeks at the
teaching a three-week retreat at uh our Insight retreat center and uh that was
quite uh wonderful and I'm still somewhat with
me and this week I'll be teaching um something that uh came from that Retreat
so for me it's a little bit of a continuation of the retreat and for you maybe a little little kind of taste of
the teachings from that Retreat and
um so one of the
invaluable personal States for doing
meditation is confidence and of course confidence is not easy to
come to and um so maybe a different word from
the ancient tradition might be helpful and that is
certainty to meditate with certainty and the core thing certainty
that uh that the tradition emphasizes is not exactly what you you
do but how you do it we do our practice with
confidence we do our confidence focusing on practicing in a way that
benefits us that nourishes us and to have certainty about the value
of doing that as opposed to maybe unconsciously
having certainty the value of doubting oneself or criticizing oneself or
feeling inadequate in some kind of way the rumination the repetition of
thoughts and attitudes toward ourself that undermine what we're doing uh can
be quite uh uh quite pervasive and difficult and the idea is to come to a
way finding understanding the teaching in such a way that even in the simp
simplest way that uh no matter what the background what the past experiences we
have we can have some confidence in the value of showing
up in a clear way for this moment for this
experience whatever the P however the past expresses itself in this
moment it's this moment that we want to have confidence in how we meet
it to meet it in a way that does not undermine ourselves does not um deflate
us and so to sit with some evoking some Inner
Strength some inner certainty in the value of seeing knowing
what's Happening Here and Now in a way that is not
deflating that is maybe even nourishing or
meaningful so assuming a meditation posture and this idea of sitting with
certainty or confidence can begin with a posture so even though it can be very
difficult to call upon confidence sometimes
assuming a confident posture will begin calling on
that so with a certain certainty about the value of being here and
now having a posture that feels
grounded on here the hear that is supporting your
way the contact against the cushion the chair the bed the
floor where the weight of your body settles here on this
spot to know with confidence to know with
certainty that here you are in this
place on this little place
that supports your
weight taking a few deep
relaxed inhales as you
exhale relax into this place let your body settle
as you breathe in Let The Filling of the
lungs also be a filling of yourself with confidence in the
Simplicity of being here
now and then to let your breathing return to
normal and there's a way of relaxing the body where there's a confidence or
certainty in the value of softening in the
body that this is a good thing that this is a way to be more here
in your body as you exhale to soften the muscles
of your face
as you exhale to soften the
shoulders exhaling softening the belly
exhaling and softening the whole
body relaxing any ways in which you're bracing yourself against life
as you exhale softening the
Mind relaxing the thinking
mind with certainty or confidence that the mind works
better when it's relaxed soft
and then to settle into your
breathing relying on the simplest most direct
way that you can feel your body
breathing if it's difficult to feel your breathing you might put your hand on
your belly or your chest to feel the movements there
with the idea of keeping meditation radically
simple let yourself have confidence that you're able
to know the present
moment simply you can know
breathing in whatever way is obvious for you for you but have confidence that that keeps
you in the
present knowing feeling the body breathing
and having confidence in the value of doing
that without any harshness aversion
or without doubt or that the knowing itself can be free
of anxiety
find a way to know
simply having confidence in the value of the simple
knowing of the
present
for
e
e for
seeing if you can practice with a calm
certainty with a calm
assurance that calmly being present for the Simplicity of this
moment is enough nothing to figure out nothing to plan
nothing to fix just being
present here and now in a kind
way in a non-critical way in a way that doesn't
deflate to be mindful in a way
that we're nourished by the confidence of in simple
knowing
e
for
e e
and then as we come to to the end of the
sitting to take a gentle deeper
breaths to feel and sense here and
now to find a way to sense and feel and know here and
now in a simple Gentle Way
Simple Kind
way where we allow ourselves to be present to the Simplicity of the
moment maybe calmly and in a way that feels
good for whole whole system our whole nervous system just
here allowing ourselves to be the way they are the way we
are confident in this value of Simply
knowing and having confidence in the value of being present for others in
simple ways be present to listen to
see to experience others without the filters of our emotions
and agendas and preferences and
fears to be present with others that allows them to relax allows
them to feel at ease with us so perhaps some deeper part of who
that they are has a chance to surface may it be that this practice we
do gives us the ability to set others at
ease may it be that it brings forth makes room
for the capacity that others have to feel
happy safe
peaceful and free may all
beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be
free thank
you e
just a minute here for
so again being Rusty from this technological process of being on
YouTube I one more thing I had to do and that was to plug in my laptop I used to
see you all
chats so welcome on this Monday morning to a new week of
um on a new theme for our practice together and it's not exactly a new
theme since there have been times before that I taught on this this and it's a common topic for vasna teachers to teach
on and that is the five hindrances and uh I'll be teaching it
differently than how it's normally taught perhaps and uh for one thing I'll teach
it uh in reverse order the five hindrances the order is usually sensual
desire ill will uh usually called sloth and torper
the third one fourth one restlessness and regrets and the last one is usually
called doubt so I'll start with the last one and the reference point for all these
hindrances will have a common reference point and that is that of homeness and
UNH wholesomeness skillfulness and unskillfulness that topic of my Dharma
talk yesterday morning Sunday morning at IMC that um maybe in some ways was an
introduction for this week and um and I'll be teaching uh the first
three of these uh sessions this week and then um I'm traveling on Thursday
morning and I'm very happy that Kim Allen will follow up and finish the
series and um so uh um and then Kim will
also be teaching next week while I'm away so I'm delighted that this wonderful teacher will be here with you
so the five usually called the five hindrances the poly word for them are
called the five coverings that's what the word means literally that's something that covers over something and
covers over and kind of hides or covers over and makes inaccessible and
um and so the question is what is it covering over what is inaccessible and one way of
understanding it is that the five hindrances in and of themselves in order
to be hindrances and uh are un wholesome unhealthy unsupportive for a good life
for spiritual life and um and so uh they're un wholesome
unhelpful and so what they cover over is the wholesome they cover over what's
healthy for us they cover over what's beneficial and uh for a good life for a
spiritual life in particular they cover over our capacity to have be settled and
unified to have a sense of being present in a in a holistic way in a way that we
feel fully here um that in a way that uh has has qualities of Freedom has
qualities of Peace because we're not divided in ourselves we're not covering something over there's a place for all
of who who we are to be here in a but not but he to uh to be here in a way
that is supportive that's nourishing that's Health producing and so some of this has to do
with how we show up for ourselves how we meet our experience in the moment so not
just ourselves but how we meet the world and to meet them with these so-called hindrances is to meet the world in
unhealthy ways and um and there might be things that are uh
close kin to each of them that uh sometimes is confused with the
hindrances um so not all desire is a hindrance not all aversion is a
hindrance if we understand aversion to be an averting a turning away from something which is harmful for us or
doing something which is harmful there's a healthy way of doing that and um and
there's healthy doubt if we translate the last one as out so what makes the
the hindrance is this unhealthy quality and so certainly there can be a way in which we relate to ourselves to
our experience and to the world to others uh we're in the grip of um uh
Greed for pleasure Greed for sensual pleasure Greed for the things of the
world uh Greed for meditation experiences and if that uh and the greed
itself if you really feel it it feels like it's it it's grading for the Deep
life deep inner part of who we are it's grading for the the heart there it
creates strain and tension and it contributes to a division within us
because we're overemphasizing an object of Desire rather than opening up to the
wholeness of who we are and having some kind of healthy desire surface from that wholeness
uh ill will uh is a very intense form of uh wanting of
hostility and uh wanting to harm it could be towards ourselves it could be towards our experience it could be
towards uh the people around us it can be to the world some people carry with them a lowgrade hostility that uh
pervades everything they see and touch and do and if you're really attuned to the
to it then we can feel how that's UNH wholesome even though sometimes desire
for example has a joy and delight and promise in it even though ill will sometimes has a
certain pleasure of power of strength of righteousness in it that gives it a
sense of Vitality if you really pay attention to these deeply they feel it
can feel how they harm ourselves they uh
they nurture us they diminish us they divide us so the same is true for the other
three and um and so uh here the reference point I'm trying to use is
wholesome and UNH wholesome uh skillful and unskillful healthy and unhealthy for us and this is something that hopefully
we can feel for ourselves and uh in similar almost in a
seat or in a sematic way you don't have to think your way into recognizing how
it's unhealthy you it's clear so it's uh it's the way you would maybe feel if
you're really parched and thirsty and you're able to drink a nice refreshing
cool glass of water and and with that something begins changing in your mouth
in your arms in your whole body as the as the water begins coursing through your body and uh and nourishing you and
something begins to shift and change and that refreshment that tingling that goodness that can come or if you've been
really cold and you stand in the sun you can feel the goodness of the body warming up and you feel this kind of
pervasive uh saturation of beginning the warmth in the extremities maybe or in the skin and coming
in sometimes uh being hungry uh eating a good healthy
meal and starting to feel how that we get revived uh and this kind of good feeling of of
kind of energy coming back in a nice clear way getting a good nap and uh
waking up in a very clear way that it's the whole body it's you can't pinpoint exactly the refreshment how refreshed
the body is but there is a re there is a clear way the body feels just better and
awake and clear and has kind of a simple energy that's very nice in it so um so
this inner sematic reference point uh that can be in the body as a whole in
the heart and it can even be in the mind in a somatic almost
way so then we come to the the the starting with the fifth one which is um
usually translated as doubt uh the U poly word literally means
uncertainty uh vacillation indecisiveness and um and so and and of
course in this complicated world of ours there's a lot of things that we don't know and so we can be indecisive we can
be uncertain about things but uh uh in the classic kind of definition of uh
this hindrance it's indecisiveness or uncertainty about how we can live from a
wholesome place so there might me many things we don't know what to do many things we don't understand but how we
are with the uncertainty of Life the ordinary uncertainty uh we meet it with
certainty that we see the value of coming from a wholesome Place coming
from a a u healthy place from us within and so uh the letting go of
uncertainty the challenges of living in uncertain certain tentative life and indecisive life not committing to
anything and um certainly having doubt about what to do and not to do um can be
quite draining quite debilitating sometimes it freezes people to you know not act at all and do
anything for a long period of time but the idea in that as a hindrance is to turn more deeply in because we as
a practitioners there's always something healthy we can do uh it's the how we're
aware the how we meet um the um uh our experience so if we're
uncertain about you know something then uh what to do we maybe uncertain about
how to fix our like today I had to fix some of this technology and uncertain
how to do it uh uh it could be frazzled could be afraid could be angry all these
things can come that are Den nourishing in but if we have confidence
in the value of what is wholesome that how we go about addressing the issue um
let's do it in a Wholesome Way in a way that we meet it with a calm presence a
kind presence a clear presence that we don't succumb to ill will we don't
succumb to anxiety these things might happen for sure um but but the idea is
not to Center ourselves on them so we live a divided life but a mindful life
is a mindful life that opens up to the whole recognizes what's there but in the
recognizing of it the recognition is not anxious the recognition has no aversion
in it the recognition isn't ruminating about what I should do the
recognition is always very simple this is what's happening this is what happening
and I can't tell you how many times in my life um I've been uncertain about
what to do and uh rather than being caught up and walking around in circles
trying to figure out something in a way that didn't actually allow for the creativity and the intelligence to work
properly I've gone to sit down to meditate and sometimes just meditating
for 10 minutes enough for me that then then the Mind begins to organize gather
settle be be here and there's in that calm settled mind then that I'm that
I've confidence in then I can find my way better with
the issues of my life so um to let go of
uncertainty the uncertainty of how to be how to show up and to um when then the Buddha says
having let go of uncertainty one dwells having overcome
uncertainty without indecision about wholesome
States one cleanses the Mind from ruminating about how one should respond
how one should do things um so
ruminating but one has confidence in the wholesome the how we
meet the simplest way what's here even if we don't know in the bigger picture what needs to be done we can always be
confident about the value of not diminishing ourselves not undermining
ourselves deflating ourselves by an UNH Wholesome Way of relating to what is
difficult so um thank you and um tomorrow's hindrance will be
restlessness and regrets anxiety and regrets and
uh and we'll go on so thank you very very much
and may this day be a day where you
find a way to be certain to be confident in the Val in showing up how
you meet the situation and uh rather than getting swept away by the uncertainty
that you might have so thank you and