so good evening nice to see you all as many of you know I'm continuing
this uh introduction to mindfulness meditation Series today is class four
it'll be the last class on mindfulness meditation I'll be continuing on in
other weeks uh after this um with some other topics related to meditation but
uh the introduction to mindfulness meditation was the four
[Applause] weeks so maybe I'll just give a brief uh review of uh what we talked about uh the
first three times we met the first time I emphasized
mindfulness of breathing just resting the attention on the experience of
breathing and I'm emphasizing this word experience or Sensations
rather than you know thinking about breathing rather than Imagining the breath going in and out or some other
things that's that's a another way to meditate but for mindfulness we're just
staying with actual experience and this alone can be a
practice to distinguish well what is it about to think about breathing and what
is it to experience breathing and for me I sometimes would
uh think about uh think I would consider that the experiences don't necessarily
have words it's just an
experience whereas to think about breathing is words primarily so that
could be one way to make a distinction and so when I'm doing guided
meditations I'm often talking about the sensations of breathing rather than the breath or breathing just
to highlight this embodied um
experience of just the body breathing the body knows how to breathe we're just
tuning into it so that's at the core of uh this mindfulness meditation at least
uh like in this mindfulness Movement we might say and certainly here at IMC we
have that kind of like as the default mindfulness of breathing for some people the breath is not such a good uh object
because it's not very neutral in particular if you have asthma or something you might be associations of
you know not being able to breathe well or something and in that case we can recommend uh doing mindfulness of sounds
just kind of like opening up and just listening to sounds it's surprising that even though
we're all sitting here silently there are plenty of sounds there's a outside
inside all this kind of things so that can be an alternative to the
breath then on the second week talked about mindfulness of the body recognizing that sometimes the body is
uncomfortable in fact if you were to just notice or maybe if there were a video uh
camera on somebody who was just sitting in a chair no audio just a video would
notice that they just their post posture you know every few minutes it's just what we do and the reason why is because
there's a little bit of discomfort we don't even notice we just shift our
posture but with mindfulness meditation we're for the most part maintaining the
same posture and then we're noticing oh yeah that's uncomfortable you know have
it itch or my knee hurts my back is bothering me or something like this and
of course of course we don't want you to injure yourself or you know push yourself uh Beyond what's appropriate
but there is an opportunity to see if you can learn something about
how what your patterns of behavior are when there's something
uncomfortable and to stretch your capacity to be with things that are
uncomfortable turns out that this Human Experience has a lot of uncomfort
comfortableness and there's freedom to be found if we don't always have to avoid it but instead we can acknowledge
yes this is uncomfortable and not have to run away and not have to make it be different so
that was the second is the breath and then the body and one way they work
together is we have the breath as the anchor and if the body becomes
compelling it I I'm saying knees and back because this is what's very often uh what's
uncomfortable when we're starting a meditation practice and we just let go with a breath and be mindful of the body
the bodily experience feeling it sensing it tuning into it when it's no longer compelling
we just come back to the breath so in a relaxed easy way breath body breath
breath breath body breath could be something like this
third week last week I talked about emotions and recognizing that emotions
are you know a beautiful part of the human experience and sometimes they're troubling
too and freedom and this arena is to have the freedom to not be afraid of any
emotional experience to have the confidence that I can feel terrible
grief I can feel rage I I can feel Envy I can feel bitterness whatever it might
be and so to have this way that okay I can experience them but I don't I won't
feel overwhelmed I don't have to act them out I don't have to avoid them instead I can allow them to arise and
pass away and one way that we do that is to
tune into the what I like to call the sematic signature for each emotion
how does anger feel in the body often like for example there's like
heat in the face sometimes there can be like this uh like energy in the
hands sometimes the body leans forward a little bit it's not necessarily the same
for everybody but there's some common things that uh we might recognize with
uh each emotion and then to tune into the bodily experence and let all the
thoughts just do what thoughts do they spin around we'll just let them do that
and we'll tune into the bodily experience and in this way we are honoring and respecting our
emotions taking care of them we're not repressing them we're not pretending they're not there but we're also
not uh getting falling into them and being pushed around by them instead
there's a certain amount of dignity like maybe I've blend done plenty of
meditation with tears with sadness I've also had tears of immense Joy with uh
meditation so to tune into the bodily experience part of the reason to tune
into the body is so much more tangible it's just easier to feel bodily
experiences Sensations in the body whether it's tightness or tingling or heat or
throbbing or the sense of wanting to jump out or sense of wanting to collapse
all these things are so much easier to tune into and we often have less um
judgment about them so we can hold them like yep sadness feels like
this and to feel it and allow the motion to rise and pass
away so this week I'd like to build on all
the three preceding weeks and talk about mindfulness of
thinking of course thinking is such a big part of our life our
experience and there's a reason why it's the fourth week and not the first week
there's two primary reasons one is it's not so easy so it helps to have had some
uh practice with some mindfulness in general before we turn towards mindfulness of thinking because the
usually what happens is we are just maybe like turned towards the thought and off we go we're just lost in the
thought and the planning what the groceries we're going to get or rehearsing that conversation we had
earlier that irritated us or whatever it might be whatever it might be so one
reason is just have a little bit more experience with mindfulness before we turn towards mindfulness of
thinking and a second is turns out that the body mindfulness of the body is a
tremendous support for mindfulness of thinking
also in some ways this is a false dichotomy but in some ways we can think
about we can consider that The Human Experience has the bodily experience the
somatic kinesthetic embodied experience and
there's the mental experience where there's the thoughts that just do what thoughts do they go
around and round try to solve things make things better of course they're a beautiful thing
thoughts but I'll I'll touch on to that a little bit later tonight about how mindfulness of the body uh can be a
support for mindfulness of thinking but before I do that I want to just
uh ask you to imagine something this isn't necessarily a guided meditation
but just to imagine that you're sitting on a
riverbank I got this from Gil ronto I learned this so many years ago but I just love this so you're sitting on a
river bank and the temperature is perfect it's warm
you're not too much sun but there's a little bit of [Music] Breeze maybe you just had a very nice
lunch so you feel content nowhere you need to
be you're sitting on the riverbank in a way that's really comfortable however whatever way is
comfortable for you on a bench or something and you're just just
enjoying watching the river go by maybe you hear the
birds the waterers just passing by it's lovely it's very
nice sense of ease
contentment and then you see a big fairy boat and there's a huge party on this
boat there's dancing and singing all this loud music there's Buffet tables
there's food you can see all these people and before you know it boom you've jumped on this boat and you are
at the buffet table singing along dancing and having a great
time and you continue to be dancing and singing and but it just starts to get
feel a little empty a little bit and then you remember oh right I was sitting
on the river bank and then you go back to the river
bank sitting there wow it's not nice to just feel
like nothing needs to happen just
peaceful and then a battleship comes you can see the cannon on board and there
the soldiers are Marching and there's all kinds of artillery and and there's U
people with binoculars looking out and and before you know it boom there you are on this warship and strategizing and
all this planning of how we're going to make everything safe and take care or retaliate or whatever needs to be done
and there's so much work to be done on this Battleship and to check all the
artillery and make sure everybody knows their orders and then this gets
tiring oh yeah I was meditating I was sitting on the river
bank and then you find yourself on the river bank [Music]
again pH
just sitting there enjoying
it and then you see this poor beat up raft is just barely floating by seems
like it's held together with bubble gum and Sho string it's just barely
floating this poor thing it's dilapidated not taken care of
and before you know it boom there you are on this raft trying to hold it together and make sure it doesn't uh
sink hoping desperately that it'll stay afloat paddling with your
hands this poor raft so you're not sure if it's going to make
it and this gets exhausting to a certain type of tiredness
and you realize oh yeah I was meditating and you find yourself back on
the River
Bank probably doesn't take too much imagination to this simile of the boats
on the river as often we jump on I'll call
these boats s that are just going by and there's a
way that we jump on them and forget everything else and get completely lost
in them and get caught up in whatever is on that boat
entertainment anger Revenge poor me poor
raft there's a way in which we might have like a have a pattern of jumping on
certain kinds of boats might have a pattern of you know
preferring to jump on some boats and other boats we just let those go by but the other ones you jump right on
them what would it be like to just stay on the river bank and watch the boats go by maybe
even be amused by the boats going
by turns out that much of our Lives is lived on one of these
boats sometimes we don't even remember that the river bank is
available to us place of some quiet and contentment
so I'm do a guided meditation
here taking a meditation posture a posture that has both some
alertness and some
ease feeling the pressure against the body or the chair or the cushion is
contacting the body we're here
feeling the pressure on the back the back side the back of the
legs and feeling the feet what they are touching
feeling connected
grounded then rest your attention on the sensations of breathing
tuning into the experience of breathing
feeling the body move as it breathes
and when the mind wanders as it's apt to do for now we'll just very simply
gently begin again with the sensations of
breathing
e just hanging out with the
breath nothing in particular needs to be happening we're just noticing the
experience of
breathing for
just coming back to the breath
stabilizing quieting the mind and the
body for
and now when you find yourself waking up
after being lost in thought just notice is there a category
a type of thought is there a type of
boat planning remembering
entertaining just make a small mental note like a whisper in the
mind planning and then come back to the
sensations of breathing
we don't have to turn thinking into the enemy or something we have to get rid of
for now we'll just note the
type of thoughts and come back to the sensations of breathing doesn't matter how many
times you do
this e
[Music]
in some schools of meditation thinking is like considered more you know something that you
absolutely don't want to do but in this style of meditation it
turns out this whole idea this whole notion of distraction doesn't
exist instead we just can turn our mindfulness towards whatever is the most
compelling whether that's uh emotions bodily thought or the experience of
things in a moment I'll talk more about how to be mindful of thoughts but there's this
way in which it's about a shift in our relationship to thinking with meditation we're not
making them the enemy nor are we just following them and doing whatever they say like we often
are doing during the day instead we're taking a third stance we noticing
them and but not getting in involved with them not necessarily believing them
not necessarily um following whatever they are saying but instead just maybe like
emotions honoring and respecting them and yet keeping a sense of
stability not so easy to do this it's uh so often we are identified with our
thoughts and we might even feel like well who am I or what does the world even exist if there aren't thoughts or
something like this I'll talk about that in a little bit too but before I go there I'd love
to hear from some of you either there any questions about what I've said so far or did you notice uh was there like
one type of boat that you liked to jump on more frequently and did you know that
about yourself was this new or this whole notion of even the possibility of
being on a river bank the bank rather than on a boat or was that a new idea or
anything you'd like to
share so the boat I realized I was jumping on was like a worrying
boat and um yeah I just find it interesting uh just realizing that but a
question that I have is is the point of meditation trying to realize when I'm
jumping onto that boat not when I'm meditating like on my day like normal
day or on another activity or is it a goal that I should just like focus on
while I'm meditating like realizing the thoughts that I'm having and just like come back to the
breath it's it's just like that question is it something that I can also like apply on a day-to-day basis or is it
only during meditation yeah yeah thank you this is a great question so I would say meditation is more like a laboratory
in which we can explore and learn things but it's really for our life it's really
further our our whole life and part of maybe I would I feel funny kind of
saying this word goal but let's say the direction we're going the orientation we're going is for more freedom for more
ease in our life and it turns out sometimes we get stuck in thoughts where we're just thinking the same thing over
and over and over again and the 5,000th time we think it's just not helpful or
there's a way in which we are always you know planning and feeling like our whole
life is just one long to-do list I got to get take care of it and meanwhile our life is passing Us by but we feel like
we need to plan so first is to just recognize what we are what we're doing
and then meditation helps us helps the mind and the body to recognize oh yeah
there's this you working on this simile it's possible to sit on the river Bank
while doing our chores while working while doing anything talking to people that we care about getting an argument
with people that whatever it is it's possible to be embodied and connected
and steady and not being pushed around thank
you and I would say maybe that's the freedom is to not avoid and the freedom is to not be pushed around I mean life
is going to bring us what it's going to bring us if we don't get to control the Universe of course wouldn't it be great
if we could anybody else have a a comment
[Applause] or um for me especially this week it's
been election stuff um there's been just been so much
insane stuff on the news um and I feel like I've spent some time this
week realizing I'm on that boat and I've also spent some time on this
week choosing to be on the boat and choosing to get off but sometimes that's not so
conscious for me so I've been having kind of both experiences and if you had to um give
kind of like a general tone or mood or attitude or something like this for the boat what would what did you say with
the you said election Stu that's more kind of content but is there a is it
uh um with the election or maybe like lots
of things that are on the news um I think there's this feeling
like there's something urgent going on that I can't do anything
about um so there's definitely like this feeling of a sense of urgency but without anything specific
ific it's not necessarily it's not like planning where I can if I'm planning a party I can think about what tasks I'll
do to get ready for the party MH whereas with the news it's sort of like there is
that urgency but there's not at least for me there's nothing
specific that I come up with right in the moment it's more just I kind of just ruminate on in thoughts about what other
people are doing and what's happening far away yeah yeah this uh you didn't
use this word I'm going to use this word but this feeling of helplessness like wait there's all this stuff going on and
what what can I do and it's just happening and all this yeah yeah it's uncomfortable feeling and it really
grabs us and as a society we've created these news outlets who are designed to do this so they're very effective right
these are not they're not I'll just this is Diana's opinion they are not uh let's
just say this they are for-profit businesses so you know let's they're
going to do what they need to do to be profitable yeah thank you thank
you anybody else have a comment or something they'd like to say or question
so maybe I'll talk a little bit about uh like how to thank you how to maybe help us to not
get so Swept Away by thoughts and or maybe not to find ourselves um always uh
jumping on the same boat or if we do find ourselves jumping on the same boat like what's something that we can
do and one is that um
usually I don't I don't if I can say 100% of the time but it certainly is my
experience and many others is that if there is a certain like this uh uh
pressure for thinking this certain sense of I have to think about this there's
this maybe maybe even a sense of urgency or a sense of something needs to be done
and then we just find ourselves kind of like in this Loop and not really going
anywhere we can just ask ask this very simple question we could just drop in the
question is there any motion that's underlined
this chances are yes
fear sadness that we don't want to feel anger that we don't want to feel
these types of things are like underneath and like little volcanoes they're supporting all the thoughts are
happening up here and this is kind of what's uh the emotions are spewing or
fueling fueling them let's say that that's kind of what's the energy
behind these uh boats and what maybe also kind of propels us to want to
be on those boats so one thing if we find ourselves kind of like stuck with our thinking is to just drop in the
question is there an emotion underneath this and it's not so much that we AB
abolutely have to find the precise answer at that moment it's the asking of
the question because the asking of the question is this kind of like is turning
towards with respect and kind of like an opening up to to listen to or feel into
what's happening it's something other than
thinking because what the mind would like to tell you is no no no no you have to think about the thoughts
and then you just think about thoughts and that's just thinking so it's the way to like it's to
shift uh our relationship and to change the experience from being lost in
thought to being more embodied so it might be sadness and maybe just the word or maybe
there's a sense of sadness shows up and then we mindfulness
of sadness mindfulness like oh yeah there's a lump in my throat pressure behind my
eyes shoulders feel heavy and just be with the bodily
experience let the content take care of themselves thoughts will just do what thoughts will do we don't have to worry
about them but work can be with the emotion that's fueling them because once
the emotion it has a chance to be seen and recognized then it'll stop fueling the
thoughts so instead of trying to put out a flame instead we're going to just take out you know put the cap on the fire the
the gas hose I don't whatever you know what I mean I was thinking about where were
those in Kuwait remember when they had those all those they couldn't put the fires out the oil wells it's feels kind
of like that where there's just all this Fountain and this fueling coming
up so that's one thing to do is if you notice that there's a lot of thinking or
certain pressure around the thinking just to uh drop in and to ask is there an emotion underneath here chances are
very high it's yes because there's this way that
um we can't think our way out of thinking even though that's you know
this is our habit it's what we do in the modern world we've all been acculturated
this way we've been educated this way probably our professional lives are this way thinking is very
important and we don't need to do it as much as we
do in the way that we do thinking is necessary to solve problems there are
problems to solve but you know even earlier today I
was trying to remember there was something I had to do and I just found myself thinking about okay don't forget don't forget don't forget you know and I
just there's this way it was just staying with me staying with me you know like the fourth fifth sixth 20th time I
thought about that's probably enough but there's a way in which we just kind of get stuck often in these
loops and then you know our life is passing Us by and it's pushing us
around so that's one way to be with the thoughts another way is I uh during that
guided meditation encouraged you to maybe you make a little note planning imagining remembering or
something like this and there's a way that making a little note can be really
helpful because to make a note creates a little bit of Separation there's the one
who's making the note and then there's the thinking and that little bit of Separation helps
us to um have a little bit more breathing room so to speak so even if you don't think about
uh or don't make a note like planning or remembering or whatever it might be you could even use something like oh
thoughts and this is sometimes what I I'm doing I'm just saying like thoughts and then just come back to the bodily
experience whatever whatever doesn't matter which bodily experience often it's uh can be like
pressure cuz that's the most obvious so pressure on the bottom of the feet or if we're sitting pressure uh against the
buttocks or something or another one um say oh thoughts and then maybe turn to
sounds and then uh tune into whatever the sounds are maybe turn into the birds
the point is to interrupt the momentum of the thinking I mean more thoughts will arise
and that's perfectly fine but there's a way in which we want to just not be lost
in them and just following one after the other you know from when we wake up
until we go to sleep just being pushed around by them so that's a second way is
to thinking about the the
um oh my gosh I just uh to use a small little note and then to turn towards
either a bodily experience or a sound here's a third way is that uh thinking
is uh we might say there has uh two parts to
it one is the content the details of exactly what the thoughts are and the
second is the you won't be surprised to hear me say this the experience of
thinking and often we don't think about this but the question could be when you
think when you have thoughts are they
images is it a voice what are
thoughts how do you experience them are they all the same like all are
all your thoughts like have the same color if they're images or
and so this is another way in which we can shift our relationship to them so we're no longer lost in them but instead
we are a little bit separate and we have this Gap and we can see them oh yeah that was a very interesting little short
video there just you know remembering something that happened today or oh my
gosh that was a the voice of one of my parents yelling at me here I am decades
later still hearing this or you know whatever it might be and so that's another way in which we
can like honor and respect our thoughts we're not trying to get rid of them we're not saying they're bad we're just
no longer being pushed around by them and again we let the content take
care of itself we're looking at the process the
experience so one could be is it an image or is it a voice
and sometimes for some people not everybody for some people there's a feeling there can be like a little
energetic Buzzy feeling like in the body when there's a lot of thinking there's a
way in which uh there can be uh maybe pressure or sometimes in the
head maybe that's uh obvious or available and maybe
not so in this way we don't have to to let go of or you know get rid of our
thoughts and we don't have to say oh this is terrible or anything like
this instead we're just creating this space and interrupting the
momentum and in that space is where more freedom
is for me sometimes it feels like um
like maybe having been underwater comfortably swimming swimming swimming
and and then come up out of the water like oh wow I can hear better out here
it's easier to breathe and it's uh I can see further
it's kind of like that when the thoughts start like Abate there's a way in which there can be more
clarity and you kind of feel like oh yeah that's right I'm here I'm doing this
because there's this way in which um that's you know it's kind of funny to
think about it but if we were all to
imagine kangaroos in this room tall
ones that you know have the small little arms and they're moving and we can just bring a kangaroo
to mind I was just doing that like oh but then I'm actually still
here the kangaroos aren't here I'm just here and you say well of course Diana
but there's a way in which we tend to think that our thoughts are real but
they're not they're just thoughts they have no substance
whatsoever and you will have another thought you know just a moment whatever you're thinking now so we give them so
much auth Authority and we let them Define ourselves and we let them Define
others so much suffering associated with that so much
suffering so they're useful we need them but we don't have to be pushed around by
them so let's do uh another guided meditation
taking a meditation
posture and this time let's begin with just
three bigger breaths just as a way to tune into the
experience of breathing and to relax
then letting the breath return to normal and just letting the body
breathe and again we'll stay here for a little bit
maybe we'll just take a moment to acknowledge the Brilliance of the
thinking mind a lot of
evolution has come to permit us to think whatever it is we're thinking
and thinking mind is
amazing but we're going to put it aside and just be with the sensations of
breathing for now you can pick up your regular thinking in a moment
can you settle into the experience of breathing
this feeling in the body the movement in the
chest movement in the Bell belly
for now we're letting the thinking recede into the
background and the sensations of breathing being in the
foreground for
can you give yourself over to the sensations of
breathing e
and now if you find that thinking is taking
prominence can turn towards it with calmness deliberately
see it clearly and maybe make a note thinking
or planning or remembering whatever it might
be and if it persists see if you can look at the
process of thinking letting the content take care
of itself is thinking images or a
voice if there are images are they in Vivid color they in sepia black and
white
if it's a voice whose voice is
it what's the tone of The Voice
and then returning to the sensations of breathing
if there's a certain pressure with the thinking can gently inquire if there's
an emotion that's fueling that thinking underneath it
and if they're thinking has quieted down just can return to the sensations of
breathing and relaxed easy
way might take a little bit more effort or determination to not get swept away
in the think in the
thoughts
for e
[Music]
so we've spent a lifetime developing this habit this pattern of
thinking and primarily we've been concerned with the content but during that guided
meditation I asked you to look at the experience of thinking and
to look at it maybe or consider it a different way with thoughts or images
or maybe you noticed that I don't know maybe i' love to hear from you all was
did you notice it was more thoughts or images or both or was it clear was it
not clear or anybody like to share
thank you yeah I can I can start sharing about my experience so I see a lot of things
so I realized that in my case it's images they're colorful
um and and one thing that I realized is that when I acknowledged them it was
like okay they're still there but yeah they were like pushing it was like if I was like pushing them a little bit away
or they were like just pulling away but in one case there was like this very
intense thought even though I was acknowledging it it was like still there it was not not leaving and I'm just
curious in those cases what would you recommend me to do so what was your so I I call those
like sticky thought thought that are a little bit sticky yeah it would like come back or yeah even though I was like
yeah I'm thinking like I see you you're there it wouldn't go way and I tried like coming back to my breath and it was
still like hanging out there and so what was your relationship to those sticky
thoughts so I was feeling uncomfortable I I wanted it to like go away like I had
enough of you thank you uh so yeah that's how I was feeling yeah yeah so of
course this isn't uncommon when we start to see like all some of the thoughts that we have we have crazy thoughts sometimes we really do and
um so sometimes it's helpful right to notice and they do just go away but
often there's thoughts that don't that there's they are persisting and then what we notice is if we are like
acknowledging them and uh being present for them we often have an agenda I'm
being present for you so that you'll go away and this kind of so that you'll go away is a way in which we're getting
tangled up with the thoughts and that's that kind of aversion is fueling having
just getting tangled up causes them to persist you like this what you resist persist actually turns out to be true
yeah so yeah makes sense so part of it is to um is there a way that we can take
some of the authority away from the thoughts it's just a thought or a family
of 10 bazillion thoughts that you know and is there a way that we can say okay
these are thoughts I'm going to have different thoughts in just a few minutes or you know that's so that then our
relationship can shift so that we're no longer um resisting them or aversive towards them and then they will um kind
of like start to Peter out but this definitely is not easy and it's not fast
or quick right we've spent a lifetime of our thoughts you know running the show
essentially and for us to have a different relationship with them takes a little bit of time but I appreciate your
observation it's great oh thank you maybe way back in that corner
there um I really appreciate the suggestion to observe the experience of
the thought because um I feel like that's a really quick way
to help with my own cyclical thought patterns I've noticed that I have
thoughts that I'll continue going back too um so I'm just excited to try this
exercise that whenever this I I like whenever a sticky thought pattern comes up to um just really take a good look at
it um because sometimes I feel like I'll
want to do like a deep breathing exercise for example to help me get out of that pattern but that's not always
accessible to me but I think again like that seems to be an easier Channel mm and then maybe
eventually I can get to like a deeper breathing uh practice um if I can first
just observe the experience of the thought so thank you for that um and I
also just wanted to say that it was super relatable to hear about um uh what she was saying earlier um
this lovely woman in front of me about um just like feeling helpless right now
that is one of my sticky thought patterns and uh yeah anyway it's more of a
comment but um it's uh yeah it's
validating yeah and I would say feeling helpless is one of the like one of the
things that humans dislike the most it's just nobody likes this feeling of
helplessness and so very often we're doing anything just so that we don't have to feel so helpless and then you a
lot of unskillful things happen yeah but just to be able to acknowledge like oh yeah here's that helplessness feeling
and I don't like it even just to recognize that can just make a big
difference actually in one's life this because what we'll do to not feel helplessness is quite something so thank
you I actually do have one more I have a question um because I think I I have like some form of add probably like my
thoughts feel like a fever dream sometimes where it's like an image a word like um and it just kind of flashes
and I'll jump from thought to thought so um yeah I would love some advice on just
how to like slow down that like uh
Montage if you will of Randomness well maybe uh a few things
maybe to be curious about the randomness is it really random you know maybe there's you know a a a theme but you
just not aware of them and then maybe to have some curiosity about an emotion underneath is is there something there
that's connecting all of these maybe that's so that's one thing to think about a second is you said that
there's images and uh voices maybe have a little bit of curiosity about oh is
there often maybe I'll just say the question what types of thoughts are
images and what types are thoughts or voices and so to uh that's just a
different way to engage with them and again that also kind of like takes the
authority away from them and so maybe it's also can give you some insight like
oh that was an image so what is you know whatever you learn about what images are
for you they're not the same for everybody or or uh voices are for you so just maybe bring some more curiosity to
that anybody else have some comments or questions
somebody on this side of the room do does anybody have anything you'd like to
say you know I have a question on a different topic but it can wait I I'll be back next week so I don't want to
disturb the if the topic is okay so we'll see if there's any more about
thinking and what do you think do you have any thoughts about
thinking you have a comment sure
great yeah I just I just think I was very much like the I felt like I kept on
going into these random dreams um that in the first meditation I was stuck in
one so when you gave the the thought about just um returning back to breath and
and um I did that and I was able to get out of them this time um but I'm curious
next time to try you know is there a feeling behind it is there you know what
is the purpose of this dream I have because they just seems super random yeah um so anyway yeah thank you thank
you it's quite something it's quite something when we
start to really look at what's going on in here right it's quite something that's a a big part of what meditation
practice I know certainly for me and I actually I know for a lot of people too we just didn't realize we had just been
you know living our lives and not really paying attention of course and then when we start to pay attention it can be
surprising what's in there yeah thank you
so I have a few like concluding words here unless uh somebody wants to ask
something more about um so I'll just
um say a little bit about uh mindfulness I talked about how um you know we have
this breath body emotions thoughts and often if you were to go to a Meditation Retreat they would also kind of in that
order with would uh those would be the instructions uh during The Meditation Retreat in the morning and then then the
afternoons would be uh derat talks so if you wanted to take uh really build on
your mindfulness practice Meditation Retreat of course is a great way to do that not everybody's life situation um
permits them or maybe they don't even want to to go to a residential Retreat for a week or so but I think many of you
know we have a residential Retreat Center associated with us we have a sister
organization uh down in Santa Cruz beautiful location beautiful down there
I just love it down there um but we also have at least once
a month uh I think uh here on Saturdays a half a day where it says sit walk sit
so U some walking meditation they'll give instructions on walking meditation so that is you know ends up being a
couple hours and there's something that's really special that can happen if
we give the mind and the body a chance to just kind of just uh get more and
more quiet it's different than you know here with the shorter meditations and
yeah something different can happen so we have half days on I think one Saturday month as well as uh day longs
so you know like from 9 to four um one Saturday a month and those
are also sit walk and they have different themes and there'll be different amount of teachings depending
on the teacher you could uh look at the description that's uh on our calendar and at IRC Insight Retreat
Center are plac out in Santa Cruz we do have some uh 4-day Retreats but most of them are 7 days and we also have some
online 7-Day Retreats and for a lot of people we have hundreds of people
attending these it turns out to be really uh ful and impactful and very
powerful it gets uh it's can be surprising how you can turn your own home into this Meditation Center it just
uh I think it all of us are surprised by how effective and Powerful this um has been with the pandemic you know we just
kind of started that so that's one way to do to support this uh mindfulness
practice of course you can come here uh to IMC you're welcome to everything IMC
offers um so of course on Monday nights I teach
on Monday nights Jim is often helping out sometimes he's a teacher also thank you Jim very
much and um probably many of you know also on Sundays we have a a sit and a a
talk and on Thursday nights Thursday nights Tanya Wiser teaches and hers is a
she teaches there's a little bit more give and take well we've been doing give and take here and uh so it's a nice way
to ask a teacher questions and engage with other people meet to other people and just talk about how your practice is
doing and learn different things so just um offer that that uh IC
is everything here is freely offered it's uh in the spirit of
generosity some people do like to express their appreciation kind of like their heartfelt like wow this was really
helpful and uh and so they would like to donate if you're interested absolutely no pressure If you're interested there's
a donation box near the front door and there's a little kiosk in kind of like this direction if you want to do
something with credit cards also are the founder here Gil
fronto uh he's written a number of books and one book is freely offered it's
called issue at hand it's a it's a great book I think it's great so one of the those books it's just a a collection of
short little essays you can just open it up wherever and read it um they're on
the near the front door and I feel like them in Spanish they're on the back wall
over there and there's a newsletter also that has our schedule there's uh lots of
things happening here at uh IMC we have all kinds of things happening
here and I think you had a question uh uh the English ones near the front door
the isue at hand are just the the cars the books were there like two weeks ago
I wondering there more caries they're all gone it's just the you know the QR code oh oh the Spanish versions but the
English ones are gone okay well I know I know which cabinets would hold them so after this I'll go look in those
cabinets and uh see uh if they're there but yeah it might might just be the QR cards right now we do uh order um like a
whole bunch you thousands at a time turns out we even like uh damaged the
ramp up here because the books were so heavy coming up into this thing that we damaged the ramp out there so just a
little aside that we do try to have copies of the book here but it's also freely available on our website so
there's a QR code if you want to just U download it our website has so many articles that Gil has written and
probably you guys know about aiio dma thousand my
talks it's quite something how many are up there and
uh the app is great as well what was that the app is great as well oh yeah so
there's an app that uh a subset of the dma talks are just automatically go up
on an app with I think me and Gil and Andrea fella and Matthew BR Sil and a
few of us few of our talks go up on there too am I forgetting anything Jim that you think would be helpful to
say uh no I think you covered quite well okay thank
you so are there any last questions as we uh close this up I mean just this
mindfulness of meditation session I'll be back on next Monday I'm going to I have an idea of what I'm going to talk
about it'll be like an extension of mindfulness actually I think uh I'm going to talk about some Brahma vajar
practice uh next week Brahma
vajar mindful this uh loving kindness and compassion and kind of like more
heart-c centered uh practices turns out to be quite
powerful okay okay so thank you all for your attention and your practice thank
you