good morning
friends enjoying people signing in and saying hello to one another here in the
chat trying to resolve for myself some little
technical technical issues but glad to see everyone I think
I lost some of the early chat hellos
but good to see you Samantha Jamie Lana lesie
Alice Joyce welcome and many
others so yeah welcome I'm David Lori let me just
um let me change my name here so you can see
who's sitting in for Gill this week
there good morning everyone good day
welcome so we'll begin as as we begin with a sit and uh let me set up the sit
by tell you what what I intend to share this
week I'll share this week a teaching referred to as the five faculties
sometimes the five spiritual faculties and this week I'm going to
going to think of them as I share this this teaching as the five Divine
faculties another way to think of them and a particular spin I enjoy is to
think of them as five human Divine faculties these are aspects of
our of our sort of inherited um capacity to be present and
to be free and there's no chance that in these various years teaching uh this five
weekday program that Gil has not also shared these teachings and uh you'll recognize you'll
hear Echoes of Gil's teachings but one of the wonderful things about uh sitting in for Gil is the
opportunity to share Gil's teachings for each of us Ying last week myself this
week others of Gill students in the coming weeks refracted through the
prison of our own practice and our own experience in life and uh so these will
be familiar teachings but they'll have a particular flavor I'm going to make a a point of
sharing some of the ways that gills uh approach to these five
faculties has shifted over time that's sort of my teaser that toward the end of
our toward the end of a brief daret after we finish sitting I'll share some of what I take to be ways that Gil has
come to appreciate these teachings in the new light in the last few
years so the five faculties the five spiritual faculties the five human
Divine faculties beginning today with with the confidence that grows as
our practice deepens and it's in it's in specific aspects of the practice that we
can attune ourselves to the confidence that the practice provides us in life
and our confidence in in being in the practice I'll say more about that after
we sit after we sit and after we dedicate the Merit of our of our practice
together I'll guide only briefly and only lightly but find
yourself into your your meditation posture whatever that is and no matter
what posture of the various postures that we can adopt for the meditation
we seek to find balance in the posture any posture and all postures
that enable us to be here fully present alert and awake and at the very same
time relaxed receptive any posture that allows us to
balance our attention between effort and
allowing is a legitimate posture and as we perhaps bring our eyes down
Close Our Eyes fully if that is feels safe and comfortable for us we
can we can notice a natural rebalancing that happens in each of the five faculties we'll explore this week I'll
emphasize that these are capacities within we're not reaching outside ourselves to acquire something that we
don't already have what we're doing is paying attention to to capaity within
and as we pay attention to them we cultivate them as we bring our attention to them they're
strengthened and we can do this as we first sit with just noticing balance taking place our eyes turn
inward and our uh attention comes from the visual external Realm
to the uh to the inner
life at the same time we can feel the attention moving
Inward and downward sort of from the head to the heart from the head to the heart to the body
and we can by bringing our attention to the breathing we
can notice the natural equilibrium that
the breath establishes for us right in the center of our being the breath is
balanced I like that the breath is so confident in what it does knows the right Cor quantity of
oxygen needed the right quantity of carbon dioxide and other waste gases to
expel the breath doesn't concern itself with the future or the past the breath
just sits here and by connecting our attention with the breath we take on some of these
qualities whenever we return our attention to the breathing we reconnect with the Natural Balance in our
experience and again as we connect with it it strengthens
when we return attention to the breathing after the mind gets caught up and things snagged by thought planning
for looking forward to the day review if maybe the day is already
passed thinking about other people thinking about ourselves the natural field of the
mind whenever we bring it back to the breathing nothing's gone wrong we didn't
do anything wrong in fact each time we come back to
the breath There's an opportunity to strengthen the capacity to be
here so we can celebrate each time we come back instead of perhaps judging
that we shouldn't have or we're no good at this or it doesn't work just kind of let go of those kinds of thoughts and
just feel feel quite happy and content to be able to keep coming back here
e
e e
so as we come toward the end of
this period of meditation maybe once again we can touch
in with that sense of rebalancing that happens when we direct our attention
back to the center of things back to the here and the now of our
experience we can do this by touching back in with the breathing the sensations of the just
this in breath here just this out breath here
we can be sure that this coming back to Center
is good and we can reinforce this habit of mind this
ability to come back to complete presence simply by noticing what it
feels like when we come back back to the center this is a
pleasure of coming back home or coming back here from wherever the mind's gotten
wandered off to or caught up in this particular pleasure of return in
the meditation returning to equilibrium returning to Center returning to ground
returning to home the teachings encourage en US to
enjoy it's an important signal to the brain and the being that there's a
wholesome pleasure here in the
meditation so we can feel confident that this is a good
place to come back to sometimes it's good and enhances the
sense of return to bring a couple phrases to
mind whatever's coming up in the practice for you that's what's supposed to be coming
up we can trust the practice to lead
us toward wholesome mind States and skillful action
there's nothing that's coming up that needs to be excluded or
rejected and you don't need anything more than what's right here right
now we don't need to reach
outside we have sufficient right here inside our
experience sometimes it's useful to use the phrase I belong here
and we can share this sense of confidence with others simply by returning
here Gil sometimes says points out that the world that we live in the world
around us really needs people who can be confident in their direct
experience who can be settled who can cultivate a peace of
mind that can hold strong
during moments of turbulence
so we can share the confidence we feel in the
practice with other beings everywhere wishing all
beings well wishing all beings Safety and
Security wholeness and body comfort and contentedness and
mind may all beings know
something of this sense of balance and home that we can experience in the
meditation may all beings be benefited by this
practice and may all beings be free
[Music]
so while welcome again everyone The View I have of you is the
lovely greetings you share with one another in the chat I appreciate everybody being here and I see bowing
Emoji so I return a bow yeah so I want to talk about the
five faculties this week the five spiritual faculties as they're frequently known Poncha Andrea in in
ply and uh I had the wonderful experience of teaching the five
faculties last week down at the retreat center in Santa Cruz the Insight retreat
center with my wonderful colleague Andrea Castillo we talked together in Spanish for a
week and uh the notes I have to share about these teachings are in Spanish I'm
going to sort of um just let them come into English as
they as they do but um
yeah when you take these teachings and you bring them into practice each time they they have a
lovely way of um expanding to meet the circumstances of a particular particular
place in one's practice and uh what I think will come forward this week as we
talk a little bit about each of these five faculties is the way in which their
their innate Capac aties within each of us and possibly in all beings and that we
cultivate them by bringing attention to them this I find really reassuring and
uh quite a gift of practice that we don't have to look outside we don't have to go anywhere we don't have to be any
different uh the capacities we have to be fully awake are are right here and
always available we may not see them clearly we may not um be as aware of
them as we can in practice and that's what we that's what we do when we explore them as teachings and bring them
into the meditation the first of these faculties
is Sada uh which I like to translate following following Gil as
confidence also like the word trust and what I wanted to bring
attention to in the guided meditation today and I was a little thrown by some of the challenges I was having with the
IMC YouTube account I think we wrestled and um and uh sharing the Dharma
one um today the um but the in the
guided part of what I hope to point to is that it's in our direct experience of
of of the breath of the of the being here now that we can have
confidence uh you know there there's a lot where it's U as soon as the mind
starts adding judgment for example around having the Mind get caught up in
something else as soon as the mind gets caught up and adding extra to our experience preference or wants wanting
something different or trying to push something away or exclude something from experience this shouldn't be here this
shouldn't be happening as soon as that starts to happen we sort of lose contact with direct experience that is our
primary experience the things that arise in our experience before we add stress
to them before we get caught up in them in that direct experience we can have
absolute confidence and that's one of the reasons we keep going back there in the meditation and it's not important
that we're not there all the time this isn't the practice isn't about hanging on with you know by our fingernails to
the breath it's about coming back to the breath over and over again again the
sense of return the sense of rebalance the sense of refreshment and pleasure
that come from coming back to here and now that's the manner in which we remind
ourselves of this innate capacity to be here and as we come back each time and
we reconnect with direct experience our confidence can grow oh this is what's
happening now and we can start to feel that what what's happening now is what's
what's meant to be happening in the practice it's not supposed to be otherwise we don't have to exclude
anything that comes up in the meditation none of which practically none of which is random as being not appropriate here
the things that come up and the things even that draw us away those things want attention they they want the gift of our
attention and once given the gift of attention they ease up we can come back
to Center we'll talk about that particular aspect
of the five faculties later in the week
so what does it mean to have confidence or trust in direct
experience I like to think that the things that draw us away from the here and
now these are things that they have sort of a destabilizing effect they knock us
off center they they take us away from the um Natural Balance that we can find
within they um distract us from a wholesome quality of mind and a
way of knowing experience that is naturally
free and they can uh in various ways make us feel either that we don't belong
in in the practice or we don't even belong in our own experience or that we don't have what it
takes to be free and to the extent that we engage in
those kinds of um thought patterns we uh sort of diminish our own
capacity to to be confident in what we can know directly in our experience
so when we return to here and now we um reconnect with the experience
of this moment it's like this now we can use phrases to remind oursel
that this is the way it's supposed to be in the practice this practice that's
developing right now is the one that um is the right one the correct one
the skill skillful one and we can um trust what we what we
come to know in the meditation I think the particular thing
I'd point to today and this can be a little challenging for people perhaps who come
from some of our backgrounds certainly for me is it
something I tried to point to and the guided to this morning is just that we can trust the pleasure that's there in
the meditation the um the pleasure of the
meditation which the Buddha encourages us to
cultivate the Buddha says in various various places um that this pleasure of
meditation this pleasure that comes from connecting with our direct experience the here and
now this pleasure is to be cultivated this pleasure is not to be feared
this pleasure is part of the path and that's because the pleasure of
the meditation doesn't depend on anything outside US doesn't depend on external
conditions but rather is something that comes from within and something as a result that we can trust that we can
have confidence in and as we become more intimate with
our experience we can lean into that pleasure that accompanies the return to
Here and Now and there's actually something quite
important going on in the brain here the brain uses pleasure and and pain as
important signals and what we're doing is retraining a bit the brain or um
we're we're um encouraging the mind to notice that ah it's
pleasurable to be here now and as we do that we um reinforce
that that important signal in the mind that this is a place to find home that this is a place we can trust and this is
this can be challenging because sometimes we we quite um understandably
and rightfully we are hesitant to um to
take pleasure in things because sometimes it leads us astray sometimes we find that uh we're caught up in
seeking pleasurable uh experiences Peak experiences in um in ways that are
harmful to ourselves or others and so this is an important reminder that this
experience in the meditation of making direct connection with our um with our
lives with the Here and Now of our experience whatever is going on trusting that the
practice brings up brings us uh into the experiences that need
attention um this particular uh signaling does point in a in a wholesome
Direction and I promised at the outset that one thing I would do in these five days is
reflect on the way most recently Gil has captured these um these five faculties
this faculty this internal capacity this this ability to be present in this way
this first faculty is frequently referred to as confidence or trust or
faith this is something that we're reminded as the practice develops this
direct experience is something we can have complete faith and confidence and Trust
in the word that Gil has recently used to gloss to um characterize this faculty
is love and uh it's it's a wonderful thing
uh to recognize as Gil does that this ability to feel comfortable and
confident to have confidence to have trust and faith in our direct experience
of Life free allows us to it that it in a sense is a form of
love and that it frees us up to share our love with
others when we're confident in what we experience we can share it openly share
it freely and it allows us to connect with others and it allows us to um get get
out of Our Own Way in a way that allows us to be present for
others so this first faculty this first inner resource this first um capacity of
mind is to be comfortable and confident enough in our own
experience that we are engaged in a form of of deep
appreciation for the simple ability to be present in
our lives intimate with our experience and share that with with
others in the world so as we go forward this week we'll continue to look at each of these
in a way that hopefully is very um really comes right out of the meditation that we engage in together and that all
also connects with some of these recent um more recent ways that Gil
characterizes these five spiritual faculties or five human Divine faculties as I'm as
I'm characterizing them this week all right uh best wishes to everyone for the
day and I look forward to connecting again tomorrow morning
tomorrow we'll return to the idea of balance the second second faculty is energy viia
and we'll take a look at how energy uh plays an important role in The
Meditation practice and also in how we how we can balance our energies
throughout throughout our engagement in in daily life so take care till tomorrow
morning