so tonight I'd like to talk a little bit or share about a story that uh is in the
suit does and I think that uh at least for me and actually I know for a number of people that I've spoken with it's uh
has some important or meaningful or helpful uh messages in it or something
like this so so it's a a story about this person
named Prince bod who is a prince not surprisingly and uh the
Buddha and Prince bod he had um built a new building like they call
it a long house which I guess was not uncommon in that time in Ancient India it's just like it sounds a long building
in which people would stay and Prince bod named it the pink
Lotus long house and I just had this thought like right as uh Jim was ringing the bell
pink Lotus long house thought if I ever open a restaurant you know it just kind of has like a nice sound to it
so I don't think I will ever be opening a restaurant but if I were so Prince bod had uh built this uh
Pink Lotus long house and he invited the Buddha and his
monastics to come and to to um have a meal
there and and the Buddha agreed and
so Prince bod at his own house has uh overseas and has all the food prepared
for the Buddha this is very common at this time that uh somebody would like
oversee the preparing like it's we don't know how many monastics but it could have been a lot so it might have been like a big deal to make all this
food so he makes his food and then um
he's Prince bod is waiting outside his house house uh when the Buddha and his monastics show up so Prince bod like
welcomes pays homage to the Buddha and says you know please like uh after you let's go to the pink Lotus long
house so the Buddha uh walks to the pink
Lotus long house and Prince bod and all the other monastics are behind them and I guess they're bringing the
food and um they get there it's not too far away and Prince had like put this
white cloth like we that went through the hole of the building and then down the front
steps maybe we could think like the red carpet treatment is kind of what I was
thinking and that Buddha walks up to it and he stops before he gets to this white
cloth and uh Prince Booty says Venable
sir please step on the white cloth so so that it may be for my welfare and
happiness for a long time and the Buddha just stands
there he doesn't step on the cloth he doesn't say anything he's just standing
there Prince bod a second time venerable sir please step on the white cloth so
that it may be for my welfare and happiness for a long time the Buddha still just standing
there he's a patient guy right so he's just standing there doesn't say anything he doesn't
step on the cloth and the third time Prince Boi says Venable sir please step on the white
cloth we don't know right this is a little my embellishment of the story of course but so that it may be for my
welfare and happiness for a long time so like Prince bod somehow is really invested in the Buddha stepping on this
white cloth and he we don't know exactly what Prince bod was thinking but he clearly has this idea that it would be
helpful if the Buddha would step on this
cloth for it would be for his welfare and happiness for a long time and
somehow I was kind of thinking about this you know it's not unusual sometimes we have this secret wish like oh if only
like something out there would shift and change and be different or somebody else
would do something then I would be happy then my life would go right you know kind of like waiting for somebody or
something else like out there in our external life to be
different kind of like in some ways expecting you know somebody else to make us happy and kind of like issuing the
responsibility we might have so Prince bod he's kind of like this so after the third time that he
asks the Buddha looks over at Ananda Ananda is his assistant uh and his
cousin his attendant I should say he looks over at Ananda doesn't say anything just looks
over at Ananda and Ananda I give Ananda a lot of credit and what Ananda does he
says fold up the cloth Prince the Buddha will not step on the white cloth he has
compassion for future Generations so I like that Ananda
doesn't chastise Prince bod or doesn't say anything like that or doesn't say the Buddha like what why are you looking
at me what do you want me to do but instead like Ananda understood that okay
if the Buddha has been asked three times and he still doesn't do it it means he's just not going to do it and so he so
Ananda says well fold up the cloth the Buddha's not going to step on it and then he adds the Buddha has compassion
for future Generations Ananda understood what was happening that if Prince if the
Buddha had stepped on the cloth and Prince bodh said yay this is going to be for my happiness and Welfare for a long
time then that would kind of like undermine this idea of practice and people would think that oh
yeah just the way to have some happiness in your life is to get somebody else to do something for
you and it's also is a way that um kind of if in the future somebody were to
let's say if the Buddha had stepped on the cloth and Prince bod did have a great life what would happen if in the
future a monastic stepped on a white cloth and somebody didn't have happiness
afterwards that would like undermine the whole monastic Community undermine the whole idea of practice so this just
doesn't work this whole idea have just find a Buddha get him to
step on a cloth and you'll be fine turns out it doesn't work this way even if if you have the Good Fortune to meet a
Buddha so so then we getting back to the the
suta the prince says oh so the prince he had the cloth folded up and uh he prepared the seats
where all the monastics were going to sit and then um Prince bodh he offered a food by himself which is kind of a big
deal you know he's royalty and usually has servants doing these kind of things but he himself Prince bod offers food to
the monastics and they eat and then they have their fill then afterwards he has a
little conversation with the Buddha and he
says pleasure is only gained through
pain this is what Prince fod says to the Buddha pleasure is only gained through
pain you can only have something good if you suffer for it now it kind of like
makes sense why Prince bod wants the Buddha step on the cloth because Prince bod thinks to practice is going to be
painful in order to get to have a better life or have something that's uh pleasurable or find more freedom more
ease more peace you have to do something really painful so Prince bod is saying pleasure
is only gained through pain and so then uh the Buddha
responds well before my Awakening I also
thought that pleasure is only gained through pain and then in order to make the point
the Buddha gives a little bit of his autobiography why the Buddha himself before he was awakened kind of like
thought that okay pain is a part of practice a necessary part of practice many of you know this story
story of the Buddha's Awakening he leaves the palace that he was living in
and goes to practice he wants to find Freedom find peace and he practices with
some esteemed meditation Masters discovers some meditation how to
meditate but didn't find Peace and Freedom there so he went from one
teacher to a second teacher and then he said well maybe some austerities some
really intense austerities aestheticism is needed that's the way to
find Freedom and this is where the Buddha is saying yeah I used to think that pain was the way to
Freedom so he said um this the Buddha is telling this story
to Prince bod and he says they after he had left the teachers he said seeking
the state of supreme peace I set out to discover what is skillful what is
skillful so if this meditation isn't going to work what is and then the
Buddha says traveling I came to sanama in urua and there I saw this delightful
Grove a lovely piece of ground with a clear flowing river and pleasant smooth
Banks and nearby was a village for Ms so an ideal location to practice water food
it was a pleasant place then the Buddha speaking he said
so having found this lovely place I sat down and I thought this is a
good place for endeavoring for practicing striving working applying
myself and the Buddha says why don't I with teeth clenched and tongue pressed
against the roof of my mouth squeeze squash and Crush mind with
mind like a strong person would grab a weaker person by the head or throat and
squeeze squash squash or crush them so that's what I did until sweat
poured from my armpits this quite something right he's like really in there striving mind
crushing mind this idea like okay I don't know exactly what Awakening is for
how to get there but I'm going to force my mind to do something there's no details here exactly what that was
was but just like through force of will with his mind so then he says my energy was
roused up and unflagging and my mindfulness was established and Lucid but my body was Disturbed and not
tranquil because I pushed too hard with that painful
striving so the Buddhist recognizing this Crush mind with mind doesn't
work and then the Buddha continues and then I thought well why don't I practice the
breathing less meditation to not breathe holding one's
breath so I cut off breathing through my mouth and nose but violent winds cut
through my head like a strong person was drilling into my head with a strong
point my energy was roused up and unflagging and my mindfulness was established and loose but my
body was Disturbed and not tranquil because I pushed too hard with
that painful striving so here's a second practice that the Buddha did it didn't
um he couldn't find Freedom that way and then he includes there's a few
more um aesthetic practices that he did and they all say well then it didn't work and it was quite painful and I
didn't become awakened and they all end with this my energy was
roused up and unflagging and my mindfulness was established and Lucid so he had energy and he had
mindfulness but he was just exhausting himself so then he says after he
describes a number of aesthetic practices he had done he said whatever spiritual adapts have experienced those
painful sharp severe AC feelings due to overexertion no one has done more than
me so just saying I did everything that's humanly possible describing starving himself you know all these
kinds of things and then he says you know that he
had a different idea like okay clearly those meditation Masters didn't work
this aestheticism didn't work so there has to be a third way and many of you
will know this is kind of like the middle way between this uh asceticism and indulgences and this is like the
road of practice then he found the bod tree another Pleasant place to practice
eventually sits down and becomes awakened that's all kind of the story about how that
happens so the Buddha is telling the story to Prince bodh kind of say like you know look I really tried this
painful thing and it didn't lead to pleasure it led to this exhaustion and
due to my overexertion and straining and
striving and it wasn't until you know that Buddha went another way that's this
third way between the extremes of indulgence and austerities but the way
to practice um the way that the Buddha described it his own practice doesn't mean everybody has to do this but his
own practice included the janas these are meditative states that are quite pleasurable
so instead it was actually through pleasure that he found his way towards
Awakening so it's that pleasure is and happiness and joy these are intrical parts of
practice right many of you might know the seven factors of Awakening include happiness and joy and concentration
including the Jas doesn't have to be the Jas but often
is so then after he tells all this to uh Prince bod so then Prince bod says well
when a person has the Buddha as the teacher right because the Buddha did this without a teacher so he had to try
all these things and discover what didn't work so Prince bdy says oh well now that you know that it's works it's
got to be easier so Prince Buddha says when a person has a Buddha as the trainer how
long does it take to become awakened why we don't blame him for are asking this
question right I think all of us would ask these questions is it going to be hard and how long is it going to take I
think we ask us about so many things in our lives right is this am I going to do this how how hard is it going to be and
what is it going to take and the Buddha replies with a
question to the prince instead of saying right away he asks the prince a
question Prince Booty are are you skilled in the art of wielding a hooked
go while riding an elephant I don't know exactly what a hooked goat is but it's
something that one does when they're writing an elephant Prince Bo here's a skill that
you have or do you have this particular skill and Prince boy says yes I am
skilled in that so the Buddha asks him some
questions well suppose a person were to come to you Prince bod and asked you to
train them in working with an elephant with a hooked
good if that person did not have any
confidence could they achieve what could be achieved if they did have confidence no well are you like can am I
saying that the negative right if they didn't have any confidence you can't achieve what you could achieve if you
did have confidence kind of makes sense right and then the Buddha says if that
person had no Vitality could they achieve what a
person who had Vitality could achieve no if that person were dishonest and had
no Integrity could they achieve what an
honest person with and integrity could achieve
no if a person had energy did not have energy could they
achieve what a person with energy could achieve no if that person were unwise could they
achieve what a person with wisdom could achieve
no so the Buddha is outlining five qualities here
and SP is saying you know wow if they
had if that person had even one of those qualities they could train under me like
one of those five if they had confidence
Vitality Integrity energy and wisdom they could
practice under they could learn from a prince bodh and then the Buddha says
well these are these five five factors of endeavoring is is a list in the Buddha
teachings that we don't talk about as much but I think it's such an interesting list because this is a
common question like how much effort to apply and what does effort look like and
is that the only thing that's needed because sometimes when we get stuck we feel like okay I just have to push
harder I just have to do the same thing but more I've did a lot of that in my early
practice and I tried to crush mind with mind I didn't know that expression but I somehow thought that I had to make my
mind be a certain way and there was this tension and I would like meditate with like this you know this kind of a thing
you know just really trying to strain and strive it didn't
work it didn't work for me I one of the time s when I
um really started to feel like there's some movement some real movement in my meditation practice was this time when
um I had some uh physical difficulties and so I had to lay down I
couldn't meditate sitting up that was quite something because you
can't strain it's hard to strain as much like when you're lying down and uh I just realized oh
this is a whole different way to practice with still with this commitment to practice with some diligence and some
sincerity but without the tightness and the straining I just felt kind of like a a
certain like a deepening and a letting go and a settling that started to point the way like oh this is the direction to
go not this real straining and striving that I had been doing and to be sure the
teachers had been telling me Dan you know back off you're a little too tight and I was like what do they
know you know like this worked for everything else in my life if you just have to work really hard because it's
true right for some things in our life working hard really does is the right
way the get through school sometimes it's a lot of work to have difficult
conversations with people so that you can like really allow your relationship to grow and mature it's a lot of
work sometimes jobs are a lot of work to work with difficult people or maybe
they're taxing in all kinds of different ways deadlines so this idea of kind of like
pushing is familiar to us because it works in so many areas of Our Lives it doesn't work the same way in
meditation we need a certain amount of effort
but itely goes as far as it goes I mean it'll work until it doesn't kind of
thing so I'd like to unpack a little bit this five factors of endeavoring five
factors of applying oneself five factors of working five factors of
um I'll just maybe say endeavoring is kind of an odd word endeavoring
working but something to for anything you want to do and pra this is being applied to
practice but anything you want to do confidence Vitality Integrity energy
wisdom confidence it makes a difference whether
you think the task you're embarking on is even
possible I don't think that I can fly I am not practicing flying right I just
because I just don't think that it's possible so you have to have a certain
confidence that it is possible maybe even this goes without saying but sometimes it can be
worthwhile to you know investigate like do we have confidence that a it's
possible to find greater peace ease
Freedom happiness well-being do we think that's possible for
us in this lifetime and do we think that we have
the capabilities you do have the capabilities if you're sitting in this room you have the capabilities and I'll
I'll go over that a little bit more here but just so confidence right just to
it's kind of like sometimes goes without saying but a certain amount of confidence is needed and it's not an
accident that this is the first item in the list right we have to kind of believe
yeah this is possible and humans can do it and
um and I can do it and so the Buddha um he also says
this whole idea of confidence I'm I'm sorry I missed over a part but
that's okay so this um also gets this word s in ply
Dharma teacher Paulie would say Sada but if you're yeah paully is Sada and it often
gets translated as conviction so like just yes this is possible or
faith but often when we hear the word faith many of us think about uh this
unverified belief you you know just beliefs you have to adopt and that's not what's being pointed to here it's the
faith that greater peace freedom and ease is possible maybe you haven't experienced
it yet but this idea that more is possible that's what's being pointed to here is
Faith and then Vitality this sense of just like having
some uh enough maybe like energy or Consciousness or
awakeness and it can be just enough Vitality to just hear a Dharma
talk maybe it's not even like coming to a place driving to IMC but maybe there's
even people on YouTube who are lying down in bed listening because they're ill and that's
all they can do and that's all that's needed it's just this Vitality just in
enough to be able to like just be aware of what's Happening there's a suta where the
Buddha is sick and he is laying down he's very
sick and somebody comes to him and chants and the Seven factors of
Awakening to him and this is what was kind of like needed for the buddas to
maybe have some more energy and maybe that was all that at that time when he
was really sick he was capable of so the sense of Vitality it's not asking
a lot from us but maybe this um idea of being able
to take in some information and process it sometimes when we're in extreme pain
we can't do that or you we can't do that so maybe Vitality is also pointing to a
certain amount of a wherewith all
Maybe but I would also say that a c enough Vitality also to understand okay some
things are supportive for my practice and some things are not supportive I think all of us when we've
been injured or sick we all have noticed that if we get riled up and filled with
hatred and rage towards the sickness or the injury or someone else or some
institution or just getting filled with hatred and rage does not in the long run make us
feel better any pain that we have does not go away it just becomes more
acute instead it's when we can open and relax as best we can and whatever way is
available to us at that time as opposed to just you know being filled with Rage
or hate hatred so the Vitality is being pointed to is to recognize this just to know
this oh yeah when I hate that this is happening to me makes it a lot
worse if I'm able to say okay this is what my life is like at this
moment to turn be able to turn towards it as best we can as best we
can then it's better so the typ of Vitality point to to recognize that it doesn't mean that
you can stop the hatred and rage you know right then this is a natural reaction a lot of humans have this of
course when we have injuries we're really sickness or we're really
sick so I want to be careful here
because sometimes this uh this poly word is um
gets well I guess literally it's a a gets translated as a little like
oppression like there's little of anything that's holding you down so it's not you're not being held down too
much and um a Tano it's also kind of like the sickness isn't too much that's
uh with these words that I'm translating as Vitality sometimes people use this word
health and then you start to get this feeling like but I'm I'm not
healthy because the Dharma world is filled with people who found their way
to the Dharma because of sickness because of illness and I can imagine it would be
demoralizing to hear like wait I have to be healthy but I I'm not so it's more
about Vitality just having this a certain enough kind of energy
there so confidence vitality and then Integrity is the third
one and this is related to not being deceitful not being
fraudulent um not being devious but instead to be forthright to be open to
be honest to be authentic that's also what's being asked
as part of this to this uh quality of endeavoring and um in the sutas it
points to in particular to be open and honest with
one's teachers or companions in the spiritual life it's kind of the language
that's used so there's a way in which we might want people to think the best of
us I know when I was practicing I kind of wanted the teachers to like me and think I was a good student
and so you know I was reluctant to show them all the ways that I was
struggling and that's normal right I think all humans we do this often we
want to kind of like give our best impression but this is pointing to like
you can do this you can tell the things that are going well but in order for people to really be able to support you
they need to know where you really are struggling and in order to know where you're struggling there needs to be some
authenticity and some honesty doesn't mean that you have to tell everybody all
the time and be worn on your sleeve but people on the path with you or your
teacher to be able to say you know this is what's going on and
I would say it's most helpful to say kind of like what's going well and where the struggles
are a full picture like this forthrightness this honesty and this
openness so that's the third quality is integrity the fourth one is
energy so the energy is this the energy here is the one that's related to right
effort on the eight-fold path if you're familiar with the eight-fold path and this points to the energy to
not only recognize that for example feel hatred or rage towards not feeling
well um isn't helpful or that uh to recognize that
having a little bit more ease or openness towards what's actually happening in the moment is helpful the
energy is pointing to having the having the intention kind of like
this okay I want to turn away from the hatred and rage that is AE habit and I
find myself falling into and getting overwhelmed with I want to see if I can turn away for
example so that takes energy to even set that intention okay I can see this isn't
helping me is there another way and that this the energy is pointing to that
cultivating what is helpful and letting go what isn't helpful this is what the
energy is about and for some people it's just to be able to recog in initially it's just to be able to
recognize okay I can't help myself but I know this isn't the way that's
helpful and to set the intention to be able to go another way that is helpful
so the energy is about this and then the last one is
wisdom and the wisdom is pointed to here in a particular way it's defined in a particular
way it's about recognizing that experiences arise and pass
away they come and they go They're impermanent they are
inconstant they are not steady everything all of our experiences
arise and pass away and having this like seeing this
having this wisdom like really understanding this does a number of things including it helps us to put our
priorities in order like okay things aren't going to last forever nothing lasts
forever doesn't mean that uh this particular ailment I have I'm really
focusing on sickness here but this works for people who are healthy as well doesn't mean that this is going to go
away it doesn't mean it's not going away it means that maybe it fluctuates in its intensity This Love that I feel for
somebody doesn't mean it's necessarily going to go away but but it's going to change it's going to have seasons of
course it is just like everything so recognizing that helps us
to put things into priority maybe we're not going to live
for maybe recognizing that we're not going to live forever helps us to say
okay this is what's important and maybe it's not so important to prove to others
that I'm right all the time or to correct them when they do things wrong or something like
that so there's a way this impermanence help might help us put our priorities
kind of shift our priorities when we recognize we're not going to live forever and what we're experiencing is
not going to last always it's going to wax and Wayne and maybe disappear we
don't know impermanence also of course um
helps us to recognize this is where growth and development cultivation is another
way of saying impermanence means things are changing so there's a way that we can
say oh yeah just like this is changing this uh this this uncomfortable feeling
in my knee in the same way my ability to sit
still for however long is changing too so impermanence also right is this
idea that things grow and develop and maybe a third thing that I'll just say about impermanence here is it just
doesn't make sense to hold on to things that are changing that are in constant and are
going away coming and leaving so there's just naturally a certain amount of Letting Go that
happens so I believe this is why wisdom is like the fifth element in these five
factors of endeavoring confidence Vitality
Integrity wisdom I'm sorry uh energy and wisdom so then after the Buddha gives
this talk to Prince bod remember he asked well how long how long is it going to take to become awakened and the
Buddha answers him he says he says I have to get back to this
so I can like quote uh here
[Applause] he says oh my goodness
um I have to go back number Pages here
um so the after the Buddha he had gave uh Prince bod these confidence Vitality
Integrity energy and wisdom these uh five endeavoring and then he says if a
person has these five factors of endeavoring they can realize the Supreme
end of this spiritual path in seven years but let alone seven years they
could realize the Supreme end of the spiritual path in six
years well let alone six years if you have these you can do it in five years
let alone five years if you have these five factors you can do it in four years
let alone four years you can do this three years two 2 years one year let alone one year 7
months let alone 7 months 6 months five months four months the
Buddha just keep on going down right two months one month seven days you know where this is
going right six days one let alone six
days one can realize the Supreme end of the spiritual path in five days let
alone 5 days 4 days 3 days two
days and then he says let alone one
day one can be instructed in the morning and Achieve Awakening by the
evening and prince the prince bod is delighted and he says oh oh Buddha oh
the teachings how well this explains the teachings that one can be instructed in
the morning and Achieve Awakening in the evening and then someone that's standing
near Prince bod says to him yeah though you speak like this Prince B you don't
go for refuge in the Buddha dharm s right he's not taking the Buddha as his
teacher and then Prince bod says oh don't say that I've heard I've
heard and learned the teachings in the presence of my mother when she was pregnant with me she took refuge in the
Buddha Dharma and SAA and then when I was really young and I had a wet nurse
They Carried me to the um where the Buddha was and the wet nurse took refuge
in the Buddha Dharma and sa and then I can imagine everybody's going that doesn't
count then Prince bod he finally says I take refuge in the Buddha Dharma and
SAA so this is a story of somebody who's trying to figure out like how much work
do I need to do like how long is it going to take how much work needs to be done and I think the Buddha he's
pointing to it's not just about straining and striving because he tried that it didn't work instead to think
about this confidence or Vitality or Integrity maybe these are some things for us to think about do we have
confidence that we can have some more happiness health well-being and Peace
and Freedom and if not is there something that we might do are we being open and honest with
those people that are that could help us and support us in this practice sharing our struggles as well as what's doing
well and I would say sometimes we have friends that we just struggle with We complain about how hard it is maybe
being forthright and is to say you know these things are going
well and then having the energy to say you know I want to cultivate what's uh
helpful and skillful and then the wisdom to recognize yeah things change they're
always changing and this is how one can find
the way towards Awakening to Greater peace freedom and ease
so Prince bodh and maybe I'll say for those of you who don't know Bodi means Awakening this for me has been a real
head scratcher why is he called Prince Awakening when he's the one who doesn't really want
to practice so I don't know this might be something to maybe there's a secret
meaning there that I don't know but so thank you thank you for your
attention and I'd like to open it up to some questions and
comments