good morning good morning welcome welcome good afternoon good evening and
maybe even hello to the Future right some people listen to this uh I'll be listening to this in the future so we'll
send warm-hearted greetings to them as well but I'd like to start this guided
meditation with just looking around your wherever you happen to
be and uh just notice two things that
uh feel I don't know a little bit uplifting or fun or you have nice memories
too I have this little elephant on my desk so for an example I don't know it
just makes me happy I just like this uh little elephant so maybe you have something maybe there's a beautiful
plant maybe there's something on the wall that you put there years ago and
don't notice as much and what whatever it might be so just
uh just allow yourself to maybe connect and appreciate something that's in your
living space maybe if it's not an object maybe it's a color or maybe there's a sense of
spaciousness or maybe a sense of coziness whatever it might be is there
something that I don't know makes you smile in some kind of
way and then we just taking a meditation
posture few deep breaths with long
exhales just allowing the physiology to
settle maybe to diminish some of any agitation that might or might not be
there and letting the breathing return to
normal and bringing to mind somebody some being that uh like
makes the heart feel warm this can be
absolutely anybody any being
anything we just want to have an orientation towards warmth and
openness and in whatever way feels accessible to you right
now connecting with this delightful or
lovely or heartwarming being or
object just allowing ourselves to feel the appreciation or warmth or
openness or however it's experienced for
you
and then to feel into the experience of
sitting in this body at this
moment feeling the pressure of the chair cushion bed couch wherever you are
against the body I feel the pressure against the
back if you're using a back rest
or on the back side all of us are unless you're standing I guess you
would have pressure against the buttocks as well in the back of the
legs and chances are the feet are touching something as
well so feeling these places of support
connection being felt this pressure against the
body and noticing if there are any areas of tension or
tightness bringing some warmth and care to those
areas can we allow them to be there and greet them or meet them
with some warmth and openness as best we can not always easy
e
then can we bring this sense of connection sense of
warmth this attitude of maybe some
spaciousness openness even if it's just a small
amount can we bring that attitude
to the experience of breathing hello
breath
e
just feeling the body breathing a stretch in the chest
orbe a feeling of the abdomen the belly going in and
out or feeling the different temperatures of air going
in and out of the nose whatever feels
comfortable available just resting our attention on
the sensations of breathing with an attitude of
connection warmth openness ease
e
it wouldn't be surprising if the Mind wandered and we just invite it back
in welcome attention back in
the experience of [Music]
breathing no need to chastise ourselves condemn ourselves beat ourselves up
because the mind is wondering that's all
extra we're just keeping it
simple tuning into the inhales for
example turning into
exhales how do they
feel
about the transitions between inhales and exhales can we receive
them tune into them be sensitive to them just
noticing what does it feel
like
e
at the beginning of this meditation I encouraged you to
connect either an object or an individual
or any type of being
it supports a sense of warmth and openness [Music]
smiling what would it be like to meditate with either that
attitude the connection and smiling or maybe
with that [Music] being what would it be like to feel
accompanied the support support the
Delight encouraging a mind State and attitude
a direction of kindness and
warmth
e
e you might have to recharge this attitude
of WTH and connection sometimes this inner critic
can slip in just encouraging an
orientation towards openness
care and simplicity
as we rest the attention on the sensations of
breathing
e
[Music]
for [Music]
welcome welcome for our fifth and uh last day
that we're talking about the Ino critic I did a little typo when I
initially was putting the title for this session I put five of 50 inste of five
of five and it seems like we could do 50 right right seems like the inner critic
maybe it just maybe it's just me which I feel like wow there's a lot of stuff that we could do
here I I've been describing the inner critic as this uh Dynamic that often
happens not everybody has it but a lot of people do a surprising number of
people do in fact there's a way in which uh it's seems like so many of us are
moving through life like projecting I got it together I know what I'm doing
and it's quite something because so many people don't actually feel like they have it together and but we're all like
pretending like we do it's this uh I don't know part of how our culture is these days so this inner critic of this
Dynamic of putting us down belittling us and blaming ourselves nagging at
ourselves kind of maybe comes with a sense of Shame like shame for just who we are in some vague kind of way and has
this uh feeling of harshness that's certainly not uh
Pleasant this feeling of you know I'm not enough or I'm not worthy or you know something like this that are often
subtle and pervasive so they often can be unnoticed and there's this way in
which it can just like creep in and it might be a little bit familiar so
familiar like okay we just are like putting on uh some clothing that uh or
shoes putting on a certain amount of shoes but shoes are you know a little bit uncomfortable but they're the shoe
there are shoes so we put them on there's something like how this inner
critic can be subtle and uh um constricting and we feel like okay well
it's going to help us in the same way that shoes help protect us from the environment you know rough things that U
pieces of glass or sharp objects of any
sort and so often this inner critic kind of like is masquerading or trying to convince us that it's
really helpful because it's protecting us and that certainly was true When We Were Young most likely but now this this
uh this inner critic this way in which we're feeling um inadequate or just
getting attacked for just the slightest thing just this small thing then kind of gets globalized just because um maybe
you didn't say the perfect thing to that person at that time that now you're a
bad person you know it goes from one little example into something really big it's
generalized but this feeling attacked by this inner Dynamic a completely natural reaction is
to kind of like close down to tighten up
to maybe have like a shield or to harden and maybe like hide behind
that maybe in the same way that like shoes might be constrictive ill fitting shoes that are constrictive and
uncomfortable but we think well okay so I have to do it to uh look good make so that everybody think they look good or
to protect ourselves from something but there's also a way in which shoes like Shield us we might think it's helpful
but when it comes to the inner critic it causes us to maybe like
Harden to brace and contract and close
down and there's this way in which doing this becomes um we're a little we get a
little bit Frozen we get a little bit stuck without malleability and
flexibility to move with what's happening as many of you know the Buddha described his mind before Awakening is
one that was really malleable wieldy when the inner critic is up and
attacking ourselves a natural response is to close down brace ourselves and
contract emotionally Frozen in some kind of way because this contraction puts uh
on hold any natural unfolding any natural processes that
might be working as we metabolize and work with uh the heart work with our
life experience but also like when the inner critic is up and running and then
there's this contraction then some healing also gets put on hold there's
this kind of like frozenness in which uh everything kind of gets
stagnant kind like drains the energy and the joy and the all the beautiful things in our life
kind of like drains out as we're protecting ourselves from the inner critic but at the same time cutting
ourselves off from life really so this inner critic it's trying
to protect us and it's telling us like okay this is what you need to deal
effectively with uh whatever life is bringing you
but maybe as you know in your own experience the way
forward the way to have more joy and openness and ease in our life is the
opposite movement of the inner critic whereas the inner critic wants to protect and shield and tighten us and
contract The Way Forward is this certain amount of opening and spaciousness and
some warmth and kind of the way forward is like shedding some of these protective layers that are keeping us
Frozen so this the opposite direction we might say
if the inner critic is some
vulnerability is some emotional
sensitivity willingness to expose oneself
to uncertainty no guarantees that it will
we won't get hurt right if we are open so this
vulnerability is the opposite of the inner critic the vulnerability is a Way
Forward not easy it takes courage yeah of course it
does so vulnerability begins or I say might begin just admitting to
ourselves what we're feeling and maybe that's just
journaling maybe it's um speaking out loud maybe it's allowing ourselves to
say oh yeah there's this Terror inside of me or there's this deep sadness or
loneliness or whatever it might be that's uh sometimes the inner critic
is getting um perpetuated as a way to encourage this
frozenness so that we don't don't feel this sadness this loneliness the
whatever it might be whatever it might be and so the way forward is
vulnerability which involves risk and involves
fear and risk and fear of course cause some anxiety and then the inner critic
loves it oh yes okay you don't want to feel anxious therefore you should you
know buckle down and stay contracted and closed in some kind of way so it's so
easy to get into this Loop of just staying closed down and
disconnected the way forward is some vulnerability the vulnerability is the
as we might say the birthplace the conditions for this
connection to ourselves this honor and respect to ourselves this honor and respect this
connection with others and it's through this connection
where we also have this love and sense of belonging and
joy that so many of us are looking for maybe we even came to spiritual practice
because we're looking for this and so this um vulnerability this openness
this spacious that's willing to be with whatever is arising is exactly what the
inner critic does not want you know there's this way in which it's
preventing us from experiencing what we actually want and this leads to a life that feels
uh maybe not with meaning or some way we feel disconnected or separate
from everybody else in some ways kind of like separate from ourselves like watching ourselves go through this
life but when we are vulnerable and actually show up for our lives great
things can happen and it does not mean we won't get
hurt it doesn't mean that we won't be heartbroken it's just uh also means that
beautiful things can happen that we can't even imagine when we're in the
kind of closed container of the inner critic we can't even imagine some of the beautiful things that might happen on
the other side of vulnerability on the other side of willing to
feel what's to be felt on this willingness to expose ourselves to
ourselves and maybe even expose ourselves to others depends what your life
circumstances are depends how your life is how you are you get to completely um
be in control of the vulnerability is it just with yourselves is it with
others but there's this way in which we grow up thinking that vulnerability is this weakness but it takes strength and
it takes courage to step into uncertainty to connect authentically
with ourselves or with others and it will kick up the inner
critic but Beauty love Grace Joy
connection all these things that so many of us are starving for in some kind of
way so it can be helpful to just think about um okay vulnerability is part of
the way forward and it can start with just being vulnerable with
ourselves and so might have add this onto what I've been talking to in the earlier days of the week so can we
approach kind of what we did earlier so Monday I said we could um say to
ourselves I'm doing the best I can right now there's a way in which there's some vulnerability right
there can we feel into that like okay yeah I'm doing the best I can Tuesday
was how am I right now like kind of like tuning into ourselves our experience of
that moment can we be vulnerable and say actually I'm not doing so
great and not tip into overwhelm feel a connection to wherever we are I started
this guided meditation with an invitation to look around the room and see if there's something there that
brings some Delight this can be tremendous support in our daily life and
in meditation to it's called resourcing to just like what are the resources that are available here from my heart and my
mind Wednesday I talked about judgment is like this when we feel it like oh
ouch this inner critic that's creating this brace this uh shell around us in
some kind of way can we be vulnerable and like it feels like this and it's really
uncomfortable and on Thursday I uh said maybe we could drop in what does the
heart say maybe the heart says ouch Maybe the heart says pay attention
to me whatever it might be being vulnerable can we like ask these questions and
really be open to what the answer might be and again you know all of us have to take care of ourselves if we have a
trauma history or if we you know however we are able our capacity at that moment
when we ask our capacities fluctuate throughout the day throughout our life so we have to be sensitive and wise to
that and vulnerability is about taking risks
about stretching our capacity
so this vulnerability is part of the way forward with the inner
critic and I wrote uh in the description like the clash of the critic and the
candid because vulnerability and the inner critic will always be kind like in a dialog AOS one
another the inner critic is going to say no don't do it can you do it
anyway and whatever way feels comfortable for you and whatever way is available for
you so this week I've been talking about the inner critic and there's a lot that can be said but um there's a way in
which our meditation practice it can really sneak in there as soon as we discover like oh I'm supposed to be on
the object and I've been uh off uh you know planning or fantasizing or
remembering or whatever it might be so thank you it's uh it's been really
fabulous to uh practice with you all this week and maybe I'll just say some
people have been reaching out and like Dana where where can I uh find where you're teaching or something like this
I'll just mention briefly in case it's of interest if you've ever thought like oh I'd like to go on a retreat but I'm
not sure well if you're in the Bay Area or willing to come to the Bay Area Tanya
Weiser and I are teaching a non-residential retreat for those people
who are curious about Retreat and want to know how do I do it what is it like what's going to be expected so it's
specifically for people who are new to retreat practice and you can find
information about that on the IMC website and then I'll just say I'm at
IRC in June and aug August in October and I'm in spare Rock in September and
Cloud Mountain in October so it's just just if you're interested on doing some Retreat practice and I'd love to
practice with you all it's a beautiful thing to practice
together so I hope this week of the working with the inner critic has been helpful and supportive and if it hasn't
just you know put it away and just take what is helpful just to take what is a
support for you and with some heartfelt wish for I
don't know may your day your practice your life be filled with ease and warmth
and connection and spaciousness in a way that's available appropriate for
you wishing you all the best thank
you
you guys are beautiful it's so great it's so great
right to uh to practice together such a beautiful
thing
just wishing you all the best it's been such a joy to practice
here with you all and it's very nice to read your comments
Eric asked a phrase for Friday I thought would there be a phrase and I didn't
have one but I've changed my mind I think I'll just like to bring some vulnerability to the other four
phrases I think maybe that's a maybe be a better way to
support you guys are so great it's so much fun to teach with you
all yeah Lana there wasn't a phrase for Friday it was um just bringing
vulnerability to the other four phrases and then those other four
phrases might come alive in a particular way in a deeper way
maybe Cindy writes see you at the day long tomorrow Diana yes I'm teaching
online uh with IRC doing a day long tomorrow maybe I'll see somebody there
Julie writes thanks for waking up extra early this week yeah I think it's not so much waking up it's having to teach so
early I'm usually awake but uh you know not uh having to speak you know to
others or something but it's been such a
pleasure well writes you know how when you have dinner and it's time for everybody to leave but they stay at the
end yeah it's kind of like that too right but that's very
sweet can you repeat the four other phrases Monday I'm doing the best I can
right now Tuesday how am I right
now Wednesday judgment is like this and
Thursday what does the heart say and maybe I'll invite all of you who
would like to have a phrase for Friday to make up your own phrase what was what's a phrase for you that can help
you with um being vulnerable while you're asking these other four phrases or just
um in your everyday life I thought about words like courage
or yeah I don't there's a number of different
things no phrase for Friday Lana no phrase just an encouragement to bring
vulnerability to the four other
phrases
how can vulnerability help me move forward and it's I am okay bravely go on
oh yeah these are some nice phrases maybe just try one on find one
that works for you that can help you that supports
you TD says mom calls is the Danish goodbyes standing out by the car for a
half hour or so more that's right I maybe I'm doing that and I do do
that sometimes with my friends like okay bye and then you know just hanging out talking
yeah doing this with you guys
too okay okay thank you all thank you what a
lovely lovely week it's been to practice with you all may all beings be free from
difficulties and suffering and may the practice that we did together be a
support for all beings everywhere without
exception