so uh so welcome folks yeah nice to see your uh your
names um when I logged into this Zoom account
I did not know that the default setting was for my face to be touched
up so I've shut down that function and if I look more grizzled
today than yesterday uh that's the explanation it
wasn't a rough day yesterday you weren't hard on me
um so with that critical
announcement complete can meditate
uh but um before uh before we do uh line
from uh Simone V she said um attention attention taken
to its highest degree is the same thing as
prayer attention taken to its highest degree is the same thing as
prayer taken to its highest you know
classically attention is said to be a kind of neutral Factor you know wholesome or UNH
wholesome but uh I what I believe she's pointing to is um yeah the
the the more deeply intimate we
get uh with experience the more profoundly a sense of the meditator
falls away the meditator becomes the meditated
and the attention that normally feels like well I'm operating the spotlight of
attention behind behind the scenes in some
way that falls away and the kind of effortlessness of awareness The
Emptiness of awareness the enchanted devotional Inseparable from a
certain kind of nonviolence
uh attention becomes uh prayer becomes
prayer and the the sense of of the view wise view wise view isn't
something that gets added to the attention it's like the attention and
view converge and and
uh we know what the Buddha was talking about
and there is something uh very deeply devotional heartfelt becomes
prayer so may uh yeah may
we pray together
so letting your uh body find its
posture
e
we uh maybe start practice with
a more dualistic sense sense of uh the
willfulness of some instruction ctions relax your body
release tension allow whatever tension remains
to
remain
direct your attention
to your body or your
breath to the soundscape to some attentional
anchor
we begin to uh to Kindle kind of uh fires of
devotion prayer
reverence
e
e we we offer our heartfelt
forgiveness for
imperfection our heartfelt forgiveness for Sam S this kind of Realm
cyclical suffering
How Deeply can you
forgive and of course whatever you think you
are the that is fully
included in the
forgiveness
e
sometimes our our love and our attention
uh migrates out to other objects or love
of safety of pleasure of knowing
Security even our worry testifies to a certain kind of love
protectiveness and we are
recommit to this this kindling of uh the sacred it begins even
when it feels like we're in uh low gear something feels
clunky we keep offering our
attention until until it becomes
prayer until the effortlessness of awareness that which
is not
me as a parent
and it no longer feels like uh the meditator behind the control
panel directing the attentional spotlight to the breath or the body or
whatever
the clunkiness of me directing my attention towards the
breath becomes
the grace of uh
awareness
emptiness
e
that kind of clunkiness of I amness the clunkiness
of self of feeling like the meditation is all up to
us sort of uh
yields to that which uh it doesn't feel
like we own control Direct
almost like we uh relax all the mechanisms of doing and
selfing and let awareness find
us
e
e the sense of self manifest
as agenda
tension sense of uh
responsibility responsibility to
uh work out our redemption in the Rag and Bone
shop the
heart but the meditator becomes the
meditated
a certain kind of uh Faith In Love
awareness then we can let
go be groundless and something will catch
us
e
for
okay folks so uh it's good to uh good to say
with you
um this is um Louise uh
cook uh my body now that we will not be
traveling together much longer I begin to feel a new tenderness
toward you very raw and unfamiliar like what I remember of love
when I was young love that was so often foolish in its
objectives but never in its choices its
intensities so the theme uh has
been uh faith faith and uh the manifestations of uh of Doubt faith and
the manifestations of doubt and said um yesterday that that
information information is the reduction of uncertainty and
doubt can't take in information it's all noise no
signal and today uh wanted to to speak about another aspect of faith that
that's been important to me and what I was um alluding to in the sit and it's
the faith we we develop in in love Faith in
love love is said to be uh excuse me said to be the
glue of the universe that which prevents things
from disintegrating
and we know this aversion hatred
aggression this runs so deep in us this is with us until we're very very very
free and to actually manage
our aversion to manage our hate we uh develop something akin to a faith
in love in our in our evolutionary history
you know across millions millions of years of our animal ancestors like
aggression appeared before affiliation you know maybe we
say doesn't sound great but hate hate predated love something like
this uh and so it's this very potent force in
us it's been conserved over forever you know and hatred breaths its own kind of
fundamentalism there's so much certainty in a mind that's mired in
hate it admits of no uh
nuance and um it's very it's a very seductive force
in the mind it's like well there what's the point there's hate everywhere I want I want in you know it feels like the
only way to respond and
uh yeah but if there's a point of our life
if there's a point of our life if there's a point of anything it it'll
involve love and
so here Faith inserts a measure of doubt doubt in the The View doubt in the view
forged by aversion we cultivate uh a faith
in love a faith in love a kind of trust
in its uh Redemptive power you know like where where else are
we going to look to redeem suffering and changing this and
finitude death like where else like where
else where else should we pray and so there's a kind of trust that
develops over time over the the months and years of practice that deep
happiness is utterly dependent
on on uh on love they're inextricably bound like
there there is there is no um closee hearted
happiness there's for sure Cloe hearted
pleasure there's closee hearted excitement but like deep
happiness that that that entails
open-heartedness and so uh maybe we say something like oh yeah
love love love is somehow aligned with the architecture of our nervous
system uh yeah if we're to to be at peace it
will involve open-heartedness and so we have these like very Vivid repeated conscious
experiences of the dead end of anger the dead end of it
and of course of course like I acknowledge uh that anger sometimes has
uh something vitally important to tell us that some boundar has been crossed or
something can't be condoned some no the know of Love must be
issued I don't dispute that at all and for some people uh coming into anger
embodying that knowing it permitting it uh finding ways of expressing it this is
a critical kind of developmental milestone uh but whatever wisdom is
there in our anger in our aversion there's always a kernel of delusion
too and so how many times do do I need to feel regret about
my aversion to learn that it can't end well how many more times will I
need we become devoted faithful in
love we see the kind of confusion that must be nurtured to like stay fully
mired in Anger the the Buddha said that uh to see
causality conditionality is to see the dhma paa
Samu uh the kind of conditionality uh of life everything
depending on everything else and to see this Patia Samu like
Patia samua is is [Music] incompatible
with hatred there's no no place to paint the
hate but paa is fully compatible with
love it's important to see in our anger we sort of like fail to
follow the the chain of like cause and effect
far enough we stop when it's convenient we like look and
yeah then we stop because we have the sense of like if we keep going if we
keep following causality if we keep investigating conditionality I'm going
to have to give up this anger and as practitioners we keep going
we keep going we we
don't get off the kind of train of Investigation where that maintains our
hate we keep going we develop a kind of faith in
love that some emotion emotion held with
wisdom terminates in love
emotion held with wisdom terminates in love we follow the thread of our emotional longing this happened that
happened I felt this sense that we follow we follow that thread and there's
a certain kind of trust that it terminates in
love Martha um npam said uh said our emotion life maps
are in completeness emotional life maps are in completeness and what she says like yeah
all of our emotion testifies to need all of our emotional life
announces human need and need in its own way is
innocent and so we we we develop this faith in love and we follow the kind of
emotional thread to its root we follow it to
innocence we practice in ourselves
consciously um sensing the dissipation of emotion the
end of a feeling the the sensation of of a
feeling and what what is left you know
what's left when feeling
dissolves the the lesson of that following
following the intensity the dissipation the ending of feeling the
the the following uh
never leads us to the conclusion of hate but
non-hate and a certain kind of Genius of the um the the brah of V Horas of of um
of kindness and compassion Joy equinity
um it's like we follow the thread of our
emotional intensity and it's like
uh our emotion terminates in one of the four Brahma voras terminates in one of
those and so we follow the thread we keep looking and
we uh have this trust have this trust if we look fearlessly
deeply this kind of profound attention if we look deeply
enough uh we don't land in hate we find ourself in in kindness compassion and
joy equinity and uh this Faith
um deepens and deep and begins to kind of cast a shadow over our
hate it's the thing we can remember even as we forget so much in the grips of
aversion of resentment of hatred uh the kind of shadow of uh of
Love is is there a faith we develop in love is
there so I offer this for your uh
consideration and
um yeah I wish you uh wish you all a good
day