oh good morning welcome welcome everybody this is the third in this
series I'm doing on the Poetry of practice and something I'd like to say about some of the power of poetry and
maybe part of reason why some some of us not everybody appreciates it I certainly
did not appreciate poetry earlier in my life I thought it was frivolous and I
didn't understand it and uh but uh now I have this much greater
appreciation but part of the power what excuse me
here I had to mute myself while I was uh cing so I wanted to say part of the
power of poetry like some of the impact or its um Beauty I might even say is
that it lets us see things in a different way see things in a different way or
maybe even just see different things that we might ordinarily like just
ignore or not notice but poetry kind like often like points us to this way
and to see things from uh maybe like a different perspective and sometimes this is a a surprising perspective you know
maybe a little bit different one and maybe there's often this very subtle
sense of delight like oh like Oh I thought of that or oh it's
not interesting and there's this way that this subtle sense of delight is not
so different from that subtle sense of delight that we get when we finally kind
of like align ourselves with reality and start and they're Mindful and present
for what's actually happening in that moment even if what's being experienced
is not pleasant if it's uncomfortable but there's this subtle sense of
like yeah okay it's like this instead of
you know trying to convince ourselves differently or Gaslight ourselves in
some kind of way so this subal sense of delight that poetry allows and I would say that
mindfulness like being present for whatever is happening whether it's ordinary Pleasant unpleasant neutral
just uh to be present for what's
happening so with that is a short little introduction let's do some
meditation those you who have been here earlier in the week know that um oh guide us a little bit in some meditation
and then I'll drop in a poem and then I'll talk a little bit
about the poem after the
meditation is there a way that we can bring a sense of
collectedness like bringing in all the different aspects of our
experience to be here sometimes the mind is in one place
while the body is in a different place can we combine them and be here
maybe there's a way it makes sense to have the imagery of dropping into the
body like maybe there's the the Mind joins the body and drops in or something
like that touch that we inhabit this bodily
experience so that we're present or whatever there is to be
present for right now right here
feeling connected and supported with our sitting surface
you shouldn't underestimate how helpful and supportive it can be to feel
grounded connected
you're sitting to allow the posture to rise out of the groundedness the
foundation
connectedness e
in the attention on the experience of
breathing not the idea but the experience
the felt sense
feeling for example the stretch with the
inhale and the release of the stretch with the
exhale e
that body is experienced this morning today right now this
moment can you be okay just for this session can you be
okay with however the body is at this
moment
e
e e
the mind wanders doesn't have to be a problem it's what Minds
[Music] do just very simply
gently begin again with the sensations of
breathing
e
e e
so I'd like to offer a palm
you don't have to do anything with this poem it's just an
offering allow it to be experienced you don't have to figure it
out or understand it or don't look it up or anything like
this just allow it to join you in your meditation
this poem is called mindful by Mary Oliver mindful by Mary
Oliver it goes like this every day I see or hear something
that more or less kills me with delight that leaves me like a needle in
the haystack of light it was what I was born for to look
to listen to lose myself inside this soft world to instruct myself over and over
in joy and acclamation nor am I talking about the
exceptional the fearful the Dreadful the very extravagant but of the ordinary
the common the very drab the daily
presentations oh good scholar I say to myself how can you help but grow wise
with such teachings as these the untable light of the world the
oceans Shine the prayers that are made out of
grass e
read this poem again mindful by Mary
Oliver every day I see or hear something that more or less kills me with
delight that leaves me like a needle in the Hast stack of
light it was what I was born for to look to listen to lose myself inside this
soft world to instruct myself over and over
in joy and acclamation nor am I talking about the
exceptional the fearful The Dread the very
extravagant but of the ordinary the common the very drab the
daily presentations oh good scholar I say to
myself how can you help but grow wise with such teachings as
these the unable light of the world the oceans shine
the prayers that are made out of
grass
e
e e
[Music]
thank you for meditating together it's my way to meditate
together so continuing on this uh theme of poetry is practice say a little bit
more about poetry there's this way that in poetry
you find like this comp of expression like where things get said like a lot gets said in a few
words and maybe there's a certain amount of directness but maybe not in the
directness that uh we often think about in Pros there's like a it's
pointing with um some cleanness or
Clarity of where it's pointing but that's the manner of pointing is not direct direct would maybe to say
something or label something specifically but this uh Clarity I would
say maybe is similar to this a non-distracted mind like when we're meditating there's a certain Clarity of
the mind and so in the same way poetry has this uh Clarity in the way that it
points to things and maybe you know the way that poetry points is through the we
might say the magic of metaphor or use of other senten senses you know the way things smell or
how they look or or maybe there's a way in which um
they highlight different ways of experience things but it's pointing towards experience so often at least the
poems that I'm uh bringing forth for this and there's maybe one more thing I
want to say about poetry here is that it can shine a light in some kind of way
towards something that maybe otherwise we just wouldn't see or the light helps
us to see things differently with a different perspective this is part of
the what I'm calling the Poetry of practice it's like how poetry and practice of this uh
relationship not only using poetry as a support for practice but uh in ways in
which the experiences in some kind of way uh share some
elements so this morning and during the guide meditation I introduced this poem
called mindful by Mary Oliver Mar Oliver many of you knows an American poet she
won the petzer prize uh like in the mid 80s and then this poem she wrote got
published in 2005 when she was 70 years old I just love this right you know she
was in the later season of her life and
she was still writing poetry still offering things of beauty to the world
this meaningful for me that it's not like we just have a only one season of
our life in which we're offering things that's of value but uh here's Mary
Oliver when she's 70 years old offering
things so here's this poem it's called mindful by Mary Oliver
every day I see or hear something that more or less kills me with
delight that leaves me like a needle in the Hast stack of
light it was what I was born for to look to listen to lose myself inside this
soft world to instruct myself over and over
in joy and acclamation nor am I talking about the exceptional
the fearful the Dreadful the very extravagant but of the ordinary the
common the very drab the daily presentations oh good scholar I say to
myself how can you help but grow wise with such teachings as these the untable
light the untable light of the world the oceans Shine the prayers that are made
out of grass I don't know this uh poem just uh
makes me happy and each time I read it like you know of course I read it a few times before I offered it for you guys
but while I was reading it during the guide meditation I had some new ideas about it and just now I had some new
ideas about it and for me this is something I love about poetry that there's this depth to it it's not like
it's just one dimensional one way to uh interpret it or understand it those of
you may know I've also taught a lot of suta study Through The Years both in the academic setting and uh and in the
Dharma setting and this is also something I love about the sutas there's such a depth and a breadth
of meaning it's not like the first time we understand it it's the first time like okay I got it next you know it's
not like that with poetry or with sutas so I'll offer some things here
about this poem but maybe you find you found something different that was helpful and meaningful for you and again
the encouragement here is to take what's useful and just leave behind what isn't so here are some of Diana's
thoughts about this I appreciate that she's pointing to the maybe we might use this word uplift
uplift of the heart and mind she's uh saying this kills me with
delight instruct myself over and over in Joy so she's using these you know
obvious words kills me with delight over instruct myself over and over in Joy but
she's also using some of this uh less um uh direct language this is what I was
born for right there's a there's a an uplift of the heart when we feel like oh
this is what I was born for so she's pointing
to brightness you know obviously joy and Delight but uh maybe I'll use this word
brightness but I love that she's not uh assigning this to some Peak experience
she's not saying okay there's Delight because I got what I wanted it's not Delight uh because um I am feeling love
in some some particular way with a person I finally had the perfect relationship or the perfect job or
perfect anything she's pointing to the ordinary and in some ways we could say
the very first line of this poem you guys can't see the page breaks unless you're looking at it or I'm sorry the
line breaks but uh she starts this poem starts with every
day this is the ordinary stuff stuff that happens every day and then there's
this expression in the poem nor am I talking about the exceptional the fearful the Dreadful the very
extravagant so when I was reading that um just now for you guys it occurred to
me like oh this kind of sounds like the news something else that is every
day but the exceptional fearful Dreadful and extravagant this is what makes it
into the news these days right it's uh if it bleeds it leads you know if it's
going to um provoke us and poke Us in some kind of way that's what gets in the
news and that's not what Mary Oliver is pointing to here instead she even says
right um in the poem she says explicitly the ordinary the common the
very trb the daily presentations
ordinary the common the very drab the daily
presentations I think she's uh encouraging us not to wait for something
that's extraordinary not to wait until
something you know noteworthy quote unquote shows up and before we start to
feel some Delight to start to feel some um some of this uplift and I appreciate
that she's not denying that there's D fearful Dreadful
extravagant extravagant in terms of like whoa that's too much that's too extreme
she's not denying that that exists she's not pretending that it's not that it
doesn't exist but she's encouraging us can we just look towards the the
ordinary the daily
things and also there's something about this ordinary this the last line of this
poem are prayers that are made of grass I scratched my head a little bit
like prayers that are made of grass what what is this but maybe there's this way
we can think of like grass is one of the most common and maybe unremarkable
things right that is on this planet it like there's grass everywhere different types of grasses in so many different
types of ecosystems and there's so many different ways in which grass shows up
like even like between the cracks and the sidewalk type of thing like we just think that grass is
just everywhere so the prayers that are made of grass so bringing something maybe this connection with the Divine or
maybe a prayer is kind of represent something that's heartfelt and meaningful or maybe there something
about devotion that says ordinary and maybe everywhere is
grass maybe we can consider maybe even uh grass as something a connection to
something bigger than ourselves and then here's something that
I want to point to that um really um I think is so important also in this poem
and that is oblique in the pointings to it and now how she's pointing to with
this delight and this uplift and connection with the ordinary no longer being the exact
center of everything there's a lack of self-centeredness in this
poem there's a lack of I finally got what I wanted there's a lack of I
finally made the world work the way it should there's a lack of
I um I I don't I don't know we'll have to I'm sure we could fill in the blank with
so many different ways but here are some of the oblique ways in my view in which she's pointing
to this she writes every day I see or hear something that more or less kills
me with delight so kills me there's a sense of
the me goes away and it's just Del light it's not that oh I'm finally happy
I'm finally feeling something good it kills me with delight and then the next
line is that leaves me like a needle in the Hast stack a needle in the Hast
stack right it's one thing that's just like the other so no longer having to be the center of attention but happily
being in the with the other things you know
indistinguishable and then she also um has this line it was what I was born for
to look to listen to Lose
Myself lose myself right often when we are at the center of
attention or the S I should say you know that expression isn't quite right when
we are uh feel like we're at the center and everything is all about me me
me then it's that's it's about me me me because there's something not quite
right we're trying to fix something or we're trying to get something but uh part of this delight is being part of
the universe not being the center of the
universe and for some of us that might feel like no no no no no I need to be the center of the universe I need to
because I have all these needs that are not being met and and there's a way that
I think Mary Oliver here she's pointing to so much of
the uplift of the heart can happen if there's a way if we can
soften if we can let go if we can not
cling so tightly but to allow uh our experience to be part of the
Universe maybe in the same way that she's talking about this un trimmable
light of the world and the oceans shine these I would say like pointing to
Radiance things that are like moving out and being shared with indiscriminately with
everybody everything things that are boundless they're untable they're shine they
they're just going out and don't have an end this is part of the way that we can
show up in the world we can find the Delight we can experience the delight and share the delight and joy of the
world this boundless Radiance that she's pointing
to I'll read this PO One Last Time mindful by Mary
Oliver every day I see or hear something that more or less kills me with
delight that leaves me like a needle in the Hast stack of light it was what I was born for to look
to listen to lose myself inside this soft world to instruct myself over and
over in joy and acclamation nor am I talking about the
exceptional the fearful the Dreadful the very extravagant but of the ordinary the
common the very drug the daily presentations oh good scholar I say to
myself how can you help but grow wise with such teachings as these the
untradable light of the world the oceans Shine the prayers that are made out of
grass my wish for you is may you find joy and delight and the untable light of
the world and maybe even the oceans shine thank you