good evening it's nice to see you
all so tonight I want to talk a little bit about there's this way in which we
can approach our meditation practice in a similar way that we approach
everything else in our life everything else that we've done with a certain
amount of striving and like just kind of like goal oriented I got to get this
thing I got to get more peace I got to get more freedom I got to get more ease
hurry it's this way there can be a certain amount of pushing I mean of course we we might say
of course we are because this is a way in which we can push towards other goals in our lives whether it's professional
goals or maybe there's in a time which some academic goals or maybe fitness goals you know all these types of things
which we might do and we have a certain amount of
striving but what's a little bit different with the meditation practice
is that often with this striving we're not noticing that what's happening is
often there's this measuring that's happening am I there yet have I gotten
there yet am I peaceful yet is this easeful is am I is the Mind settled am I
happy yet there's this certain measuring
and if there's measuring that means you're not there yet so there's always
this sense of lack this is subtle but something that's getting reinforced again and again if we have this sense oh
I got to be somewhere else I got to have some other
experience like and then suddenly what's happening right then is this is the
wrong experience whatever it is because it's not the one that we had in this goal
and not only that it can go further it can have this sense of this well there's something wrong with me or the sense of
inadequacy in fact we could say that happens anytime there's a in a recurring
measuring of oneself or one's experience and so this having this like
wanting to push towards a goal creates the conditions in which this is subtle this isn't necessarily obvious but
there's this always sense of like oh I'm not there yet
and is there's something maybe wrong with this moment cuz it's not that other moment that I've dreamed of and dreamed
up and am aiming towards and it's this sense of
inadequacy or insufficiency about oneself often shows up and that of course is creating the
conditions in which there isn't peace and ease and freedom
so there's this way in which we aren't maybe noticing the way that the way that
we're approaching our meditation practice is creating the conditions in
which there isn't as much up settling or peace and ease that might other be
otherwise be and so maybe in addition to what I
was saying if we have this kind of like striving and this real strong goal
orientation I don't want to say there's anything wrong with having goals but in particular if we're bringing this sense
to our meditation practice also implicit in this which can be subtle is the sense of yeah well I'm
going to get it later yes this this uh sense of ease or happiness or whatever
it's going it'll be happen later it'll happen later again kind of taking us away from
this present moment so if we there's a sense of this present moment isn't right
and that something better is going to happen in the future this kind of disconnects us from
what's actually happening this moment and that's so much what
meditation practice is about right it's just to be here for this moment is to be with whatever our
experience is to to be present for whatever is
arising we would say this is what mindfulness is is just to be able to meet each moment with some awareness not
being lost in thoughts or completely
disconnected and I think uh many of you won't be surprised if I say that I have a poem by Rosemary
traumer she's so great and um it's called waking up
and at the beginning of the poem uh she has a
epigram and it's a quote from John terrant who is a zen teacher and EP I
think it's called epigram those little thing that's often at the foot at the at the top of a chapter she says uh so John
tarant the zen teacher is saying wait a minute what if this is it
so Rosemary traumer is writing a poem in response to this it's called waking
up this is it I think as I lie in bed
not wanting to leave the warmth this is it my feet meet the cold
wood this is it I water the Orchid this is it I boil water make tea
I think I'll be a better person tomorrow this is it me dreaming a Fresh
Starts this is it defuzzing the sweater this is it paying bills
answering mail frying eggs washing pans no life but this
one no fresh start but
here this is it the cat sits on my papers this is it the phone doesn't
ring this is it the floors need
mopping the letter needs written the class needs planned this is it me wishing I could be
more perfect this is it
this this only only
this this is it this flutter in my chest when the sun enters the room the natural
leaning toward the light this is it this
silence this cold this warmth this longing this song on my lips
so waking up by Rosemary traumer she's pointing to being present
for every experience I was talking about having these goals during meditation
practice and she's pointing to let just be present for your whole life whatever
is happening I love this line defuzzing the sweater it's like such
a you know I don't know it's kind of a funny thing such a mundane thing but it's also
just this recognition of something so simple and maybe it represents taking
care of ourselves in some kind of way defuzzing the sweater just to be present for
that but something that I really appreciate about this poem is that it's she in there's no
sense of like hurried there's no sense of like something else should be happening or there's no sense of uh
trying to get somewhere this is just ordinary things watering the
Orchid frying the eggs washing the pans so there's also a sense of
ease not not not so much of a sense of striving but just a like okay this is
the next thing that's arising can we meet it can we be present for it
sometimes we think like mindfulness practice or whatever practice we should be doing is you know should happen in a
special meditation posture sit on the floor or some kind of way and this Palm is called waking
up and I love how she does a little play on words it begins with this is it I
think as I lie in bed not wanting to leave the warmth so this is her literally like waking up from
sleep but also this waking up to each moment to one's life
otherwise we're always trying to be somewhere else or be someone else or do
something else and our life is passing Us by while we're busy trying to go find
this peace and ease and freedom there's a few more things about
this poem I'd like to highlight I appreciate this first line it says
um this is it I think as I lie in bed not wanting to leave the
warmth she's recognizing this mental attitude not
wanting so often we are just don't even notice this we're not even tuned in or
sensitive to this but she's recognizing oh yeah there's this resistance to
what's going to come next or this this pushing away or uh maybe yeah just
generally not wanting to do something not wanting to leave the
warmth but then she does and the next line is that uh but my
feet meet the cold wood and then we might even say uh in
this uh poem that there's just a little bit of walking
meditation those of you who are have here on Wednesday mornings or I've done day longs on Saturdays or I've done uh
residential Retreats know that in addition to sitting meditation there's walking
meditation and she's talking about this you know when her feet meet the cold wood so often with walking meditation is
just feeling the pressure on the bottom of our feet while we're just doing ordinary things walking and watering the
Orchid and then there's this something here that I think is just
fantastic she has this line I think I'll be a better person
tomorrow I think I'll be a better person tomorrow okay I'll take care of all
these things that uh will support me having more peace ease and freedom later
I'll take care of that later but then the next line she
says I have to this is it me dreaming of
freshh starts so then again she's recognizing oh yeah okay the mind was drifting off
and thinking like okay tomorrow things are going to be different maybe fantasizing and then she
comes back no this is it just recognizing that in fact this is what the mind was doing it was off
fantasizing or about being a better self so often when we have a meditation
practice or we have this idea of being present for whatever our experience is
we often aren't thinking about being present of the not only the specific contents of
our thoughts but of the way the maybe type or category earlier she was having
like not wanting there was this like subtle sense of resistance and here she's pointing about I think I'll be a
better person tomorrow there's this uh also a little bit of resistance like
okay it's not going to happen now it's going to happen later but this idea
of what is what is it this is it me dreaming of Fresh
Starts so kind like fantasizing I just appreciate that she's
through all these lists of things that happening through the day some of them are her mental States this maybe flavor
of the state so
this whole idea of just being present with whatever
our life is doing Rosemary trauma she's having all these uh lists of ordinary
things so often with this uh in this tradition and this lineage we practice
to be with uh sensations of breathing is often if I were to sit up here and to
give a guided meditation I would start as probably with mindfulness of the breath or mindfulness of the body the
bodily Sensations different days I do it I would do it differently and this how I
when I was doing a lot of guided meditations I would do it that way but sometimes what we don't uh point
out so much is that in meditation just like in daily life we can open up our
experience so maybe we're just with the breath or or bodily experiences feeling
the pressure of the chair cushion against the body for example and then just open it up after
there's a little bit of settledness happening to just be with whatever is
arising including this I'll be a better person tomorrow and then noticing oh
yeah this is it me dreaming of Fresh Starts just noticing oh yeah the mind is
going there and coming back and just noticing yep that was the mind
doing whatever it was doing okay sometimes we have this idea
that to be present is to be present with like clear tangible experiences that have edges
that have a a beginning and an end and a some way in which it's um you know very
clear but I'm pointing to something that's a little more diffuse and maybe
even subtle or even vague or maybe unclear in some kind of
way so there's this whole idea of being
present as a as a support for having this is it often what we're looking for
instead often is actually instead here and then there's this idea that we
have in this Buddhist tradition about taking Refuge
often it's in the Buddha Dharma and sa but just even this whole idea where
is it that we find safety where is it that uh we feel protection protected in
some kind of way because this whole idea of
Refuge being is a place where there's can be some safety and we can find
that being in the present moment has a certain amount of safety like to just be here with what
we're experiencing in this moment in a simple easeful way as best
we can is a way in which there we can notice how so much of the I
what we're afraid of or what's maybe exac exacerbating is our thoughts our ideas
about things or our belief about things but actually the experience that's happening right
now can just be this experience that's happening right
now so I like this uh uh notion of
refuge and maybe safety as um maybe like
sitting underneath a big giant tree maybe a tree that has a big limbs on it
and maybe there's some uh rain outside and you find yourself underneath
a tree that you're protected in some kind of way but it's not like you're completely separate and
isolated I'm hoping that this sound is not something problematic was no I I I you feel I
don't think you need to thank you though yeah maybe Jim thank
you just want to make sure that whatever it is that's happening out there is uh
not something that we need to I don't know do something
about so this idea of Sheltering under a large ancient tree one thing that I like
about it is like chances are you'll get a little bit wet less wet than if you were out there but you're not
disconnected from what's Happening you're still experiencing what's happening but you're there's also a s a
certain amount of feeling protected and sheltered as well cuz sometimes we feel
like oh in order to be safe I have to completely remove myself and create a
barrier between me and whatever it is is feeling threatening but in this way this idea
like no I I can still be in I can be here but also feel a certain amount of
shelter with this with the with these branches that are reaching out and plus
there's something about just being with trees that uh can be some uplift in the
heart I know for me it's that way having spent some time with trees
today there's such Something Beautiful about it and we're so lucky right to live here in an area where there's
Redwood trees and oak trees and so many beautiful trees this way of I don't know feeling
the steadiness maybe that they offer as a
certain kind of Refuge but also we could say that going for Refuge like even this
recognition that to want to be with a
I'm using this word protection or safety I'm not sure these are the right words but maybe there something within
you that feels like like this this
movement in towards that direction it's of been found in the heart it's like this heartfelt movement
towards you know I'm going to go in this direction where
there's recognition of more ease or more peace it's this can be something
that we want to do like wholeheartedly or maybe the heart is touched in some
kind of way we want to go refuge in this
direction but I would say that this I'm saying like going this direction another word we could use like having this
orientation and I'd like to suggest here that we could have this orientation towards being in the present moment and
as a place for refuge and refuge is
an direction we can think of this idea of going for Refuge is this turning towards
in this uh particular way and maybe this gets highlighted if we talk about it's
the opposite of feeling lost it's the opposite of feeling like there's no like
I don't know what to do and which direction and feeling completely disoriented it's more like okay maybe
everything isn't clear yet but I know that this direction is towards greater I'm using
these words peace ease Freedom well-being
happiness and there's this way that when we're present for our
lives it does bring this kind of safety and
well-being I know that uh I've certainly spent so long the so many years of my
life not being present trying to be anything but present trying to get out
there and make something happen or just or just distracting myself or
entertaining myself in some kind of ways and there's this way in which we can kind of get in this habit
or maybe this way of this um it just becomes I don't know to just
not to to be disconnected to be not connected with ourselves becomes just
the way we think that life is about or it just maybe there's not as much
uh uh energy towards just being with our
experiences and when I say experiences I'm pointing to often something very simple just like sense experiences
feeling the for me I'm feeling like the uh the fabric are underneath my hands
here sounds that of that car leaving visual
field looking seeing what's in front of me here our experiences can be this
simple and just coming back again and again to our sense
experiences this is a way to show up for our lives to have some Refuge is to just
be with our experiences and then there's a way in which the mind is going to Pro I said no no no no no it can't be that
simple there has to be you know more there has to be something about this it
has to mean something or but what would it be like to this
be completely embodied with our life we discover that there's actually
some uplift that happens in the heart when we're can just meeting whatever is arising just meeting in the next moment
in whatever way so is this going for refuge in the
present moment is like just orienting towards the present moment finding the
protection finding the safety in the present moment and then maybe I'd like to add a
little bit more to this I would say be in the present moment and and having this orientation
towards not causing harm not causing harm for oneself not causing harm for
others and if you're with the present moment in the present moment you start to become more and more sensitive to the
harm that you that's being caused to others and to
yourself and so this maybe I'm saying and adding this on top of this not causing harm but maybe in some ways it
just flows naturally when you're you start to become a little bit more sensitive to like oh that that felt
awkward that conversation I had with so and so or oh it's
um trying to always look good is exhausting and uh and I'm it's harmful
in some kind of way the way that I'm getting obsessed about always having to look good or and I don't know there's so
many different ways this can show up but there's this way towards orienting
towards not causing harm flows naturally out of being present because I would
also say that this being present is kind of also what's skillful and helpful and
beneficial opposite of harm so these are going together our
let's say our ethical behavior and this choice this uh
inclination this orientation towards being with what our experience
is there's this way that just this repeated
orientation is transformative it's so easy to be
dismissive of just okay I'm going to let go of that thought train and I'm just going to be uh with uh this felt
experience of the chair or the cushion against the body in this moment okay I'm GNA let go of that
thought train and just uh turn towards uh my thoughts and there's this way we can think like surely that can't be that
can't provide a way towards greater ease and freedom it turns out a
can it turns out that so much of our suffering is in our
thoughts and taking particular thoughts holding on to them and thinking like okay this one's true all those other
ones that I've been having aren't aren't necessarily true but this one is this one is
true but what if there's a way in which we just kind of let all of them go and just be with our
experience where's the there might be discomfort in the
body there might be pain but that's not the same as
suffering the suffer uing is the I got to get rid of this I got to fix it it's
so and so's fault and this is some terrible thing that's going to happen and I got to fix it right
now but can we just be with yeah this is uncomfortable and it feels like
this so this kind of like this Refuge we might say is this
orientation and orientation this Refuge finding the Refuge in the present moment
experience sometimes I'm telling people when they're describing some difficulties that they're having in
their lives like I'm telling them you know it could be really helpful just to feel your feet on the ground just feel
your feet on the ground just this very simple thing and that's part of the way
that kind of disrupts the momentum of thinking and uh brings the attention to
some tangible felt experience and often I'm giving this
experience because I myself have found this very helpful back when I was uh
working and uh and having to attend a lot of meetings and stuff and I had first heard this idea and there'd be
meetings that were like uncomfortable and like a lot of stuff was happening on and a lot of Mis Behavior people blaming
other people or whatever but just this idea of like oh just feeling the feet on the ground and it's like oh no I'm
actually here and this body I don't have to get lost in my thoughts
and spill out some unskillful language or something like
this so this poem this is
it maybe there's a Maybe This Is It orienting towards these ordinary
experiences defuzzing the sweater and watering the Orchid maybe it's not only
a way we could describe some Freedom it's it what we want or maybe
it's also the way to have this Freedom maybe it's the goal the means maybe
they're the same I'm going to read this poem again
and the at the beginning of the poems it says wait a minute what if this is it by
John tarant this poem is waking up by Rosemary
traumer this is it I think as I lie in bed not wanting to leave the
warmth this is it my feet meet the cold
wood this is it I water the Orchid
this is it I boil water make tea I think I'll be a better person
tomorrow this is it me dreaming of Fresh
Starts this is it defuzzing the sweater this is it paying bills
answering mail frying eggs washing pans no life but this
one no fresh start but here
this is it the cat sits on my papers this is it the phone doesn't
ring this is it the floors need mopping the letter needs written the class needs
planned this is it me wishing I could be more
perfect this is it this this only only
this this is it this flatter in my chest when the sun enters the room the natural
leaning toward the light this is it this silence this cold
this warmth this longing this song on my
lips wake up by Rosemary
traumer I think I'll end there and I'll open it up to see if there are some
questions or comments thank
you is anybody have something that they'd uh like to share or ask or
question or comment
start um can you hear me yes okay um this reminds me of uh the poem
especially in the theme of your talk about everything is
practice and practice is all the time you know and
um not thinking there's going to be a magic moment where you know you're going
to feel you know enlightened or great joy I
mean you those things will happen I think but understand that the practice
is so much of the routine and the everyday yeah yeah except you know I
might use a little bit different language because you're saying the practice is the everyday in the routine
but as soon as we use this word practice we're kind of like separating out like okay here's something that's practice
and then there's everything else so I think what's being pointed to here is like it's just our
life and we do have not to say that we don't have formal meditation practices too but I think that what's being
pointed to here is yeah it's just being present for whatever is
arising agree great thank you
s thanks beautiful poem every Monday I'm thinking
I should buy a copy of this Rosemary TR book it's not here's the beauty it's not a book it's all on the web every day she
she uh posts a new poem and so online online that's 100% online oh I can copy
them but what I wanted to say is as you were reading the poem and saying that I'll be a better
person tomorrow uh I could the the I saw it was a little different that I saw her uh
smiling a little bit with a little impish smile saying that because we
often uh uh hoping for a fresh start uh thousands of times perhaps but
this time she caught herself this time she saw what she was doing so I thought oh that's very
nice I'm not sure that's what she meant but that's what I heard nice nice thank you thank you like she noticed like oh
yeah tomorrow there'll be a fresh start nice thank
you maybe over
here thank you uh yeah I had a similar thought as you who just spoke uh in that
I would maybe I'm a little cynical here but I thought she was kind of being
like like a little satirical over how the the narrator was like kind of making
a big deal out of nothing things like in the sense that like this is it like I
have to mop right now like like and maybe I I picked that out because I kind of relate and that when I meditate I
sometimes try to like tune into every little thing to the point that it almost feels more artificial and less like the
raw experience more like me trying to pick something out of nothing um and
like also with the your tone of voice like that this is it this is it like she's always like unsatisfied with the
last thing and like oh like I kept messing up and doing it wrong but like
now I have this fresh start but like oh that one didn't work so this is the real fresh start like she kind of keeps
being kind of like oh there I had been doing something wrong and so now like
there's something to fix and so I'll fix it now but that was never fixed um which
is funny CU that's kind of somehow the opposite of the the main interpretation but somehow I feel like
both both can be true here that it's like more I don't know skeptical but
also more like wholesome that another in another sense like how you explain she really is just like very content with
everything yeah experiencing everything so I don't know there's kind of two sides to it nice nice so you're implying
that there was this like no not that other one this is it something like this
oh yeah yeah kind of yeah it's you know I uh didn't know how to read this like
this this is it this this is it or this is it like like how to read this and I
think what you said about my tone of voice is true like I could have uh you we could uh uh do this in different ways
the way that it gets uh read but yeah not I'm not criticizing the way I
thought it was interesting how it kind of made it seem like very much like like always trying to one up the last one
kind of like this is it like this one so I don't know but and and maybe would that
discount what had happened before or like saying okay no no no sorry I thought that was it but that's not now
now this is it yeah kind of the vibe I got but I see I see open to
interpretation yeah yeah right the this is part of the beauty of poetry right we don't have to say no this is the only
one truth here but uh I appreciate uh
this little I'm calling it epigram I think it's what it's called the at the beginning wait a minute what if this is
it wait a minute what what if this is it
like all these other things are that I'm thinking are going to be out there and
saying well wait what what if it's right here or maybe it could be the next
thing very nice thank you thank you are you familiar with this PO
apparently you are yes yes yeah I'm sorry can you use yes you do there's
people online oh I'm sorry didn't realize that excuse me
thanks uh the reason I asked that whether or not you were familiar with her is that I'm not and uh uh I'm
curious is she you've read or heard a lot of her stuff is she into meditation yes so do
you I F it sounded to me like she probably was in my interpretation of it with no knowledge of her in just in
hearing it for the first time was that she was trying to tell us that
each of those things is it and individually without all the Clutter of
the day-to-day I got to do this I got to do this oh hell I was supposed to be here 10 minutes ago and what happens if
Mary's still mad at me when I see her this weekend and you know instead of
that just being able to sort of be in the midst of a practice
and a knowledge each of those things as simple as some of them are making tea or
just the very simple things to be able to stop everything else and make tea and
that's it then the next thing will be it so it sounded instructive to me rather
than um an expression of frustration yeah yeah thank you that was the way
that I was holding it as well yeah thank you
anybody else have a a comment or you you have one Jim and then and then maybe
yeah this is fairly short having a luxury of having a computer right here in the internet it
occurred to me when you were talking about Rosemary traumer yeah that thinking back to the 70s when I
took German that in German tra is room is dream so I was thinking Rosemary
dreamer oh very nice I don't know if it's spelled the spelling is different for her name than the the German word
that was a thought that came it was it for a while thank you I think Peggy behind you
had to um it's interesting
that about the tree um I love that analogy of Refuge gender
and I different meditation tradition that I went to this morning the teacher
read a rosemary Traer poem and I was like oh my God and it had trees in it too oh there we go it was um it's just
cool to me that that you both would mention it and um
also I love the In This Moment being
here with this and uh the last I decided to turn my TV
off for a few days which normally I can never do unless I'm away from home in some lovely place but so I decided to do
that and what I kind of noticed is a lot of daily activities I think you know oh
this is boring this is a drag I got to finish this so I can do this and when I just stop and kind of be present with
what I'm doing it's not boring anymore it's actually kind of peaceful and relaxing so I just
wanted to say that beautiful beautiful thank you thank you it turns out that this is exactly what happens right if
we're just present with what's happening it turns out to be fine yeah it's a
setad of this sense of we have to be elsewhere or should be elsewhere we having different experiences nice yeah
although sometimes some feelings come up there's some hard things in my life and but it's kind of okay it's better than
when they're at a distance yeah that's right hope that made sense I did that made sense for thank you
so maybe one last comment or
question okay okay so wishing you all a wonderful rest of the evening thank you