so warm greetings and happy to have this next
half an hour together for
meditation one of the frequent teachings in Zen Zen
Buddhism being the first Buddhist practice that I engaged in uh was the idea of not knowing
there's even a saying that not knowing is most intimate and I think it means that if
you don't know then you can really see clearly what's there you can know what's there in a closer way Fuller way but as
soon as you have we we in Zen the idea if you put a filter of knowing
understanding expertise uh opinions between you and the experience or the person you're with
that you can't really know them it's not very intimate and uh so not
knowing another uh teaching is uh something called great doubt a certain kind of spiritual doubt
that is not indecisiveness it's not uncertainty
exactly it's uh it's a questioning our assumptions questioning our perceptions
even our understandings and maybe it's like adding at the end of a some
understanding we have Maybe not maybe maybe it's not like
so maybe not so that we're more open because many times we have these
understandings interpretations and they close things down they limit us rather than making us fresh and available for
what happens next and so this idea of not knowing so
that we can be more fully present for our experience can be very helpful in
meditation that even if we might recognize something like recognize an in
breath as an INB breath um it's like you know I don't
really know what the breath is I don't really know what this experience is not
knowing and if you come to a conclusion that during meditation uh I'm not
meditating very well then um you know maybe not maybe it's
different maybe not that way so always kind of putting a question mark not to
seow the despair of Doubt or the uncertainty of doubt the confusion of Doubt but rather to do the opposite to
let go of the overlay of Concepts interpretations stories predictions
judgments we have on our experience um not knowing maybe not
judging not interpreting not making a story out of
it maybe it's not the way I'm thinking about it let's instead let's be more present
here so that would be the meditation today so to make it simple you can just
say not knowing when your mind says it knows something um more than just a
simple simple recognition of you know breathing in or an itch or something like that uh anything you add to that I
don't know don't know don't know and it happens and then we I Wonder
If that's poison oak from hiking in the Hills here yesterday don't know not
knowing let's just not know for now later you can investigate later you can
find out what things are maybe if it's appropriate but try in this meditation to practice not knowing m
mind and not knowing mind that helps you to be here and now in the middle of your
experience directly being with it as it
is so assuming a meditation
posture a posture that's appropriate for you that helps you to be both relaxed in
your body and Alert in your body
body to softly close your
eyes and maybe breathing a little deeper than
usual but not completely full maybe half full compared to usual half
more so there's a gentleness in the breathing in
deeper letting your belly expand as you breathe in
deeper and then relaxing your whole body as you
exhale softly
relaxing letting your breathing return to
normal and becoming aware of the Rhythm of breathing in and breathing
out if your belly is relaxed if your chest can be
relaxed maybe the breathing the rhythm of breathing is a little bit like waves
maybe not waves crashing against the coast but waves out in the ocean
swelling up and down lifting up and down
that the experience of breathing creates a kind of wave
throughout the body certainly in the Torso and
expansion
lifting and the inhale a contraction settling
releasing and with a wave of breathing in and
out relax your body on the
exhale relax different parts of your body
the waves are breathing in and out the massage of
breathing let those waves that the undulation spread out into your
heart center maybe feeling the Heart Center
emotional Center expand as you breathe in
lifting and relaxing as you exhale
and letting the rhythm of breathing spread up into your thinking
mind feeling the thinking mind as you
inhale and relaxing it on the exhale
being attentive to any softness or
gentleness that's found in the breathing or around the
breathing or in the global experience of the
Torso e
and then at the end of the or as part of the exhale
if anything any thinking has crept in
whatsoever let there be in you a not knowing don't
know don't know if this is true or
false maybe it's not the way I'm thinking about it
don't need to know not
knowing so you're fresh for the
inhale
for
e
for for
practicing not knowing because
perhaps for this meditation you're better
off thinking about things you think you know don't
know so you can be intimate with
here
for
e
e e
Can You Feel the force or weight of the
knowing the certainty in what you're belie leaving
or
thinking or the force or the knowing of the aversion to what you're thinking
imagining and if you can practice not
knowing so there's no Force no force of certainty and no force of uncertainty
just here with
this e
and then to bring this meditation to a
close to gaze upon others to gaze upon the
world without the burden of having to know
having to understand having to interpret or to
judge to gaze upon the world free of responsibility and
duty to gaze upon the world with a not knowing
mind because you don't need to know it's enough for a few
minutes just to gaze upon the world as it is not taking
responsibility not judging not knowing is most
intimate and imagine meeting the people you'll meet
today where you begin this
way you don't start with your assumptions about who they are what's happening to them you don't start with
your judgments but you
start being
upright not knowing
so you can know them in a deeper
way may our ability to [Music] see without the overlay
of ideas help us promote the welfare and
happiness of others may all
beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all beings be
free at least free of our judgments and assumptions
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello for this third talk
on the bundles of grasping the bundles of
clinging so the Buddha um puts a tremendous emphasis in being free from
grasping clinging attachment but you don't want to be in a
hurry to do that do that to do it automatically and quickly you want to
understand well what it is that you're attached to and how you're attached you
want to become a student of grasping of clinging take a time with it to really
know it well because if you know it well then you'll see its tricks in the future
you'll see how it operates you'll see it coming and you can leave it alone but if
you haven't really understood it um all kinds of attachments will creep up on
you and catch you by surprise and then you have to do the de the much more difficult work of learning how to let go
or how to not have them interfere with the the full freedom of
your life and um
the um so he has the Buddha talks about uh five areas primary areas for
attachment for clinging and because we have multiple attachments to these and we keep those
attachments we keep them close to us we're we're attached um he calls them bundles we bundle them up together and
there's five different bundles and Monday I talked about appearances physical
appearances that we perceive through our senses the attachments to that yesterday
it was about feelings V Pleasant and unpleasant and today it's about
recognition perception Sona and poly and uh this is the simple acts of
perception that involve a recognizing a recognition uh Rec
recognition of of what we're seeing and what we see is not the raw basic sense
data coming in what we see is based on often about memory and Concepts and
ideas and a process of selection that we select what we want to focus on and we
have preconceived ideas of what we're seeing and um and it's very innocent
some of it and we do it kind of in a subvocal sub almost subconscious way
throughout the day where um if you're at a having a meal
and it's a soup and so you don't pick up the fork you pick up a soup spoon and
you know you recognize the difference between them you know what one is different than the other and it's an automatic kind of to
do that and and because it's automatic we can do so much more in our life than we can if we had to consider what
everything was every time we were going to deal with something however uh because it's on automatic
it's kind of subconscious that we perceive we recognize things we don't
see that the recognition is a a factor of the mind that we're contributing it
to it and um and there are things you can see it clearly sometimes when you
see that there are things which um can be different can be perceived as
different things in different contexts so here at IMC we we have this
Bell and here we recognize it as a bell a very similar Japanese solid Temple
Bell about this size I saw in downtown San Francisco one day and uh it was a
homeless person using it as a begging Bowl so for him it wasn't a bell it was
a begging bowl for someone else they might find it useful as a place to store
pens and they have you know all kinds of things in on their table you know their desk with pens coming out and it's a pen
holder someone else might use it as a soup bowl and uh and um a um and they're
things this size in Asia which kind of look like a bell like this and this could be that used for this function is
a spatoon it could be that we someone turns it upside down and uses it as a
door stop and so they see a door stop so there's it could be many many different
things and um and uh uh and so the function is often how
we see something however it's not just the different functions our acts
of recognition comes along often enough
with associations judgments assumptions bias with it so that um uh we don't just
see the person in their wholeness we select we recognize them by some feature
of what they are so for example if um some person uh is coming
down the sidewalk and the person is not just a person for you you recognize them as being tall or short and with the the
recognition of tall and short comes associations with that what it means and
uh maybe if you're short it's like oh one of my people and it's I'm so glad because it's so awkward with all these
tall people around um if it's a tall person and uh
but they're really tall they're 6'8 or something um uh it comes maybe with a
sense of intimidation like oh this is a little bit dangerous now for me and so
the perception can be one hand can be familiarity can be comfort and the other
hand can be discomfort we have bias around people
that those people look to us like if someone looks to us like an enemy then
we treat them in a we see them in a certain way and the perception is Not Innocent we're perceiving them now as an
enemy if we see someone as a potential friend uh then now you know they may or
may not be but it's it's a we're adding something more than just the raw data of seeing them we're seeing them through a
lens of interpretation so uh the is these ideas that we add on
top of the raw basic data and there can be a lot of attachment to those ideas
there could be clinging to them there can be a force force a forcefulness to them a a
um a certainty in them a kind of uh that come along with all kinds of things if
there involve fear it's a certainty of fear it's a force of fear that's operating that's contributing to the
attachment if it's desire if it's hatred all these things come along and the
perceptions are not innocent there's attachment there's clinging and a lot of
a tremendous amount of suffering in this world uh has to do with how how human
beings perceive each other and uh with bias with prejudice
with racism with class ISM with ableism but we see people through a particular
lens we perceive them through a particular lens that limits them that diminishes them that makes it
problematic we don't see the wholeness of the person or we don't see them where we give them the freedom to be who they
are with respect and care and love same thing towards ourselves there
can be negative bias towards oneself and we see ourself through that lens you
know I'm I'm a loud ly person I'm a inadequate person I'm a unsuccessful
person I'm an unwanted person and so there's a kind of perception it's a judgment that becomes a perception and
this is what we see and Ne negative self- percept
perceptions there can be a lot of attachment a lot of clinging a lot of forcefulness compulsivity to it it's
like there's has a it has a force of its own that's in US driving along and it just seems so authoritative and
full so one of the primary teachings in much of Buddhism is to be very careful about
perceptions perceptions are not innocent they're not perceptions are not innocently what we out there we have a
contributing factor in constructing our perceptions constructing our
recognitions constructing the way that we understand the simple understanding of what something is
and um and uh we select out of something out of the hole we're partial we see
things for a certain purpose we see things for how it relates to me we see things um you know and
so uh this is one of place the bundles of clinging and so we can feel the
forcefulness behind the ideas we have we can feel the weight of them or this the
largess of them or the the clinging the attachment comes with a sense of uh Authority like this
is the way it is and a sense that it has to be this way and a sense of like
pushing it Forward into the world and um and um and there's you know as I said
there's a lot of suffering because of this so to practice not knowing to
practice a healthy kind of doubt maybe it's not this way this person's coming down the street and
they look like my enemy and then oh maybe not let's just see let's maybe
step off a little bit to the side to be make sure I'm a little bit safe but let me look more clearly and make sure that
uh I'm not just projecting fear onto this person
and sure enough as a person gets closer you see the person's actually looks very friendly and gentle in fact when the
person come and so you smile and the person smiles and says hello and wasn't nice hello as the person
goes um and we feel so glad that we took the time to doubt our initial perception
it's not always that way so today if you like you might spend the
day uh so one way or the other taking time to question your
perceptions to look at when you perceive someone or something through what lens
are you seeing it is it what it can do for you is it the function is what your relationship to it is um and what you
need to do your history your past
experiences and do you limit your your whatever is you're
seeing by perceiving only part of the whole or is it limited by a judgment you
have or an interpretation or an association take some time questioning perception
and this is a fun thing to do with another person um maybe you're sitting on a park bench or in someplace in
public and uh you kind of do the exercise of explaining to the person
your what your first percept perceptions are of something or someone or something
going by and then the two of you kind of questioning that and saying well is that
really all there is is there more is that limiting try to kind of get a
handle on how much perceptions are
projections and maybe in understanding that you'll understand how valuable it is from time to time to practice not
knowing not knowing is most intimate so thank you