so hello and welcome to this fifth guided meditation related to the
hindrances the five obstacles to staying
awake aware in the present moment and the five are desire sensual desire and
greed ill will aversion
then uh sloth and toror I call it rigidity and
toror and then restlessness and remorse and then the last one today it's
usually translated as doubt but it has uh the ancient meaning
is closer to um not seeing not
understanding what needs to be done and so that
[Music] our choice of where to put our life
energy goes to something which does not serve us the ancient texts say that one knows
what serves and what doesn't serve and uh and
so uh what serves us the most and to answer that
question the text talk about uh someone who has this so-called doubt doesn't
understand doesn't uh doesn't reflect doesn't their their way of understanding
does not come from a profound Source within
them that it's more surface thinking where the Mind jumps around is
distracted so you would say that if someone who spends a lot of time fantas EMP izing
about pleasures and something in their mind thinks
that's important that that's something that uh we should serve the pursuit of Pleasures
we don't think that way consciously but apparently something within us says thinks thinks that otherwise why would
we do it someone who has is profoundly
connected to themselves will understand that the way to serve ourselves is to
wake up is to be really present and clear to really this is what's happening
a definitiveness a Clarity of here I am and here this is what's
happening so it's not choosing to do anything
more than being clear about here this is
a person this is a mind that's involved in
fantasy but just to check that off like just to know it doesn't count for much but to know it from some kind of place
we know this is important this waking up and this deeper place of knowing what
to serve and not to serve also know something about um yes it's valuable to
develop steadiness and stab ility it's valuable to be grounded here so I can
see clearly so I will give myself to breathing or some other object of
present moment attention that is our home base our anchor
yes yes here so knowing what to serve and what
not to serve and some times we it's not just
sometimes we certainly can have doubt about what that is but sometimes we're just off we're serving things that don't
serve us we're giving our life energy to what doesn't serve us
well so to begin our
meditation and maybe closing your
eyes and feeling your body here the weight of your
body the substance of your
body the three-dimensionality of your
body and then in a
moment taking a deep breath and as you exhale say to yourself in your mind
here here I am and have a definitiveness definitive
recognition of the simple fact that here is where you sit here is where you are
so with a deep breath on the exhale
here
and taking a deep breath and as you exhale relaxing into
here softening the shoulders the
belly relaxing the muscles of your
face here and then letting your breathing
return to
normal and continue relaxing a bit
softening but as you're relax relax relax into the depth within
you softening into some place of deep stability deep
steadiness deep at homeness
here as you exhale relaxing the thinking
mind
softening quieting the thinking
mind here
and you might during this meditation say gently this word
here maybe added by here this is what it's like
now here this is what it's like
now as a clear alternative to wondering off in
thought being distracted or being involved with your
experience in ways which don't serve you which
involve greed or craving
wanting which involve a ver I Hill
will which involves shutting down or allowing your allowing something to
run off with your worries and
regrets keeping it really simple that the way you serve
yourself is to just be here this is how it is
now and then giving yourself over to the
breathing to serve you serve yourself well by centering yourself on breathing
in and breathing out you serve yourself
well by staying
Mindful and to have no doubt about that to know that this what this serves
you so that you can give yourself over to being mindful here with whatever
is happening here with the ongoing flow of
breathing
e
for
for and as we come to the end of this
sitting to again gently just the right amount for you and how you are
now take a deeper breath and on the
exhale relax and let go into
here into the here which is found found in and through your
body if there are any ways that you are bracing yourself against
life on the exhale soften that
tension
and where within where in
your realm of your personal subjective experience of body and
mind do you find a place of
calm a sense of depth or
intimacy where inside of you in your subjective experience
is the source for living a life of
Integrity on the exhale letting go into that Source or
letting go into where it feels intimate
and at homeness within
you and then with your eyes closed let your eyes rest in their
sockets almost as if the eyes can settle back into a deeper place inside
of calm or peace or even
Integrity the source of
stability and from there let the eyes imagine the eyes are now gazing upon the suffering
world that we live in without losing their
ease their depth the Integrity just gazing upon the
world with care
compassion kindness wish
ining well for everyone may all
beings be free of suffering may all
beings be [Music] free of poverty and
oppression may all beings be free of war and V
vience male
beings know that there are people who
care let all beings know there is kindness in this
world and may we as we go through this
world may we be calm and peaceful gazing upon the suffering world
with kindness bringing
kindness as medicine in our actions our speech and
our thoughts may all be be
[Music]
happy thank
you
so well sometimes I have to wait here a few moments for the recorder that we have
to somehow upload or process or do something with the
recording before I can start the recorder again and while we're waiting I just want to mention that uh
tomorrow I'm uh teaching a online Retreat a dayong retreat uh on
mindfulness of the body uh through are the Insight Retreat Center if you go on the Insight Retreat
Center website you'll find there under Retreats listing for dayong Retreats and
and um you're welcome to join and you can welcome to join for any part of it if it'll be on
Zoom so um let's see what we have
here so so today the topic is the fifth
hindrance which is usually referred to as doubt as far as I know all the English
translators and teachers uh refer to this as doubt the meaning of the ancient word is
somehow to it means to uh think in faulty ways think in unskillful ways and that's
how the ancient commentary understands it it's a way of thinking it says quoting them that uh knows the
distinction between what is skillful and not skillful what serves us and what
doesn't serve us or what should be served and what should not be served with our life
energy and um it's very useful to understand this fifth hindrance is doubt
because it's a obstacle that many people are struggling with um especially I
think maybe more so uh for practitioners in the west who come to Buddhism to
meditate because it's all little strange uh we're doing something that is maybe different than what we grew up
with even the values we grew up with the religion we grew up with and um and
maybe it's also very different from the values of our society and so and what
we've been taught by Society about what's important and even uh what we t thought by our society about who we are
and what we should be about with our desires our aversions our wishes or way
we think about oursel and so when we start settling in practice it's natural to to have doubt
have uncertainty and not know how to go forward not know where to commit
ourselves what what activity to give ourselves to and uh should I be doing
this should I be doing that should I be um uh uh you know I can't let go of
my you know my the anger of resentment I've carried all my life and um but here
I'm practicing and they're telling me to you know let go or to be mindful of it or settle more deeply and I will don't
know who I am and what should I do um so there can be doubt about the practice doubt about the teachings doubt
about oneself and one's ability to practice and it said that this kind of doubt can de derail us from doing the
practice but the important thing I want to emphasize here doing the
practice that um uh the way that the Ancients under Buddhists understood this
fifth hindrance it was a kind of faulty thinking that sets us off in the wrong
direction it's thinking which is not very profound which doesn't arise out of our
wisdom or out of the Yono Manara out of the profound profound way of thinking from
somehow in our depths when I uh began meditating on my
own in college I started doing it twice a day and
um and I had good reasons to do it I was suffering and I wanted to
somehow deal with my suffering and then an unusual thing happened after practicing it for many
months is when I when I was meditating the suffering that I was
trying to contend with just wasn't there anymore it wasn't I had solved it or figure it out and it didn't actually go
away so much in my daily life but in meditation was no longer there and since I'm kind of U like to
have reasons for things I wondered why am I still
meditating and uh and I felt compelled to meditate it just felt like the right thing to do and I had no doubts about
that I should do it but I didn't have a reasons and I thought that was really strange and U so I lived with this kind
of question for a while and then one day I felt oh what happening here is that uh
when I sit down to meditate this is the most profound expression of my
expression just that it's available to me that's no different than the way that
an artist expresses herself in with paints or an artist expresses themselves
with um uh dancing or someone plays a musical instrument that it's a kind of
expression that is fulfilled in the moment it isn't like for a purpose Beyond
itself and um and uh and it just felt like this beautiful expression of somehow The
Depths or uh somehow my wholeness or for me I used the word integrity at the time
and then the task for me uh became how do I bring that sense of wholeness
Integrity the sense that what was what wanted to be expressed from my depths into my whole life outside of
meditation and um so then the question is was how do I speak how do I present
myself to other people what are the things I do with my life what are the actions I do the question was when I sit
down to meditate uh what is it that connects me to this what is it that that
comes out of this feeling of of um depth that I have that feels wholesome that
feels healthy that feels this is a a meaningful way to live a life is to come
from this feeling of connectedness and presence and that came out of here and
it gave a direction to my life and it gave a a a clarity about what I was
doing in meditation there was uh I'm here to sit and wake up and be present to relax and
open to this depth that's within this place of freedom from contraction I'm
here to no longer live with tension no longer live with craving and desire no
longer live with conceit all these things I could feel were diminishing myself making myself less than I
actually am in some way and um and uh so it became very
clear that when my mind started drifting off in thought and those thoughts didn't serve myself I knew it oh they were kind
of an ouch they were kind of like a diminishment of the wholeness the fullness of who I was I am and so of
course I wanted to return here to this moment here and I found it was so
profound just to say the word here here I am this is how it is now we're sitting
in the heess of the moment that there was something very profound even if the heess of the moment
was my suffering or was thoughts that were unskillful in saying out here and just
being alive being present feeling the totality of it and somehow I was no
longer participating in it but I was also not condemning it I was not fighting it I was not just I'm here with
it not giving into it so I had Clarity so part of this
fifth hindrance and as I'm talking about the hindrances overall for this week uh
have a lot to do with action the Buddha was said to be a teacher of action how
do we act how do we engage what do we do with our life energy meditation can often be seen as
POS passivity like we're not supposed to do anything it's not right in Buddhist
meditation is an action it's an activity that we engage in it's when we engage in
in a peaceful way in a calm way it's when we engage in that Stills and quiets
the overactive mind the Mind might become quiet and peaceful but it our
action is still very peaceful and calm and settled soft but it's still showing
up in an activity it's still being here at some point uh this inner Express
expression of Life coming through us to be alive to be present is not something
we do self-consciously it's just here flowing through
us but it's still an activity that we're here showing up here being here in this
full way so this last uh hindrance often called doubt sometimes more
interestingly considered to be indecisiveness uh not knowing what to decide what to do
but at uh in the original text the original teachings it was more than
those it was faulty thinking the kind of thinking that doesn't understand what is
for our best and what's best for the world how to show up for ourselves any
moment in a healthy way in a skillful way and uh not to know that and the
ancient text talks the way we know that is not from the surface mind not from
the mind that thinks in a shallow ways jumping around and and the mind that thinks from you know anxiety or worry or
or um you know uh kind of greed or hatred but the mind that's deep the mind
that that kind of a deep Source within that's settled that's
peaceful that's not easy to have but that's part of the function of medic
meditation is to wake up relax get
settled create a sense of of uh Unity or Harmony or
wholeness with being here where we're not divided against ourselves we don't
divide ourselves fragment ourselves by our desires and our versions by our fears and
our shutting Downs by our restlessness and our Regrets We Do the opposite we show up
for all of it warts and all but from this profound
place of wholeness of Integrity of willingness to kind of open and
feel so to have V vetta I think it's
pronounced in poly to have this uh uh harmful way of
thinking faulty way of thinking that gets in the way of doing the practice
because it takes us in the wrong direction and so we're called upon not
to read Buddhist texts so we have no doubt about you know what the teachings
are about we're called upon to develop the inner sensitivity that we can
understand from our own inner experience this is healthy
not only is it healthy but if we're going to serve something profound serve this health serve this
wholesomeness it's the same health and wholesomeness that will support you to
serve and care for the suffering of this world the world needs us and needs us to
do this healthy work so that in small ways and big ways
we can make a difference in this world a difference in making it a better place for
everyone so thank you for this um week of exploring the hindrances I hope this
was useful for you and I'll be back here on Monday for uh continuing this what
I'm I'm what I'm calling part two of introduction to mindfulness
meditation and um thank you
you