good morning everyone and welcome then I'm happy grateful for
Nikki and Ying who taught here while I was away I was
uh back in the country of my birth Norway for Memorial services from both
my parents and um wonderful to be back there and see relatives I haven't seen
for a long time and I'm happy to be
here so
um for this meditation today I'd like to uh evoke an unfortunate
term that many people live with and that is time
pressure living under the pressure of time not enough time there's uh not
enough time to do what we have to do with our responsibilities or there's so many things to
do and uh and we live sometimes under the burden of time the pressure of time
and if instead of calling it pressure which kind of implies maybe that it's kind of something coming from outside of
us we call it uh tension time tension We
Carry in US tension related to time that uh the way that a big part of how
we relate to time is a construct of our own mind independent of any
philosophical ideas of what time is the way that we relate to the uh time aspect
of life has a lot to do with our constructs our beliefs our orientations
our plans our expectations our to-do list all kinds of
things and when we sit down to meditate one of the opportunities is to
step out of time or to enter into a sacred
time a time that um there is lots of
time spacious time a time that is not something that
we have to be tense around or be pressured by don't live in expectations when it'll
be over all these are things we overlay on top of this momentto moment life that we
live on top of now and to from time to time like when
we sit down to meditate or when we have a Sabbath sacred time off is
to be willing to question how we live in
time to use the reference point of time to see is the ways that we're attached
and we're caught up somehow connected to time and different time than now past or
future feeling a pressure around doing and accomplishing that has to do with
time and can we relax relax the ion
relax the inner pressure around time and find
time as being spacious maybe no
time maybe outside of time maybe a sense of abundant time for these few minutes
that we're meditating here a pause and all things having to do
with time
and to feel part of something that's deeper
Fuller rather than being in time or pushed around by time or preoccupied
with time one way or the other there's the idea of being
time we're intimately in
time not out of
time not doing time but being time just being
here so may this meditation be one where we
relax all and every tension and pressure around time
and if being sensitive to how we relate to time or live with time is
um challenging you know not interesting for you you can just put it aside but
maybe there's a very light and easy way to step out
of time tension and pressure that allows these few minutes
to be an entering into the timeless present the sacred
present where this moment this present time is allowed to just be
itself not under the dictates of the constructs and ideas of
our mind just now so assuming a meditation
posture and gently closing your eyes
and gently taking some gently deeper
breaths so you can feel your torso more fully maybe feeling some of the tensions
and
pressures and as you exit exhale longer than usual
relax and soften relax in your body
letting breathing return to normal and even with a normal breath
normal enough letting go any preoccupation with
how you're breathing just breathe in whatever way it is
relaxing on the
exhale maybe on the inhale finding places of tension in your body
holding and on the exhale
softening and the more the body relaxes and
softens either directly or indirectly We Begin
softening the tensions and pressures that exist around
time time pressure is not
inherent with being alive and present now it's not necessary
on the exhale softening and relaxing in the thinking
mind time pressure has its origin in the mind and how we think and believe
and Orient
ourselves softening the thinking mind
and then centering yourself on breathing
allowing the inhale to show itself to be there your
body without a before and after In This Moment Timeless
moment just breathing in just breathing out
less your breathing as the body's
breathing less you are experiencing breathing and more the body's experience
of breathing
and if you find yourself drifting off in thought you might take a moment to feel
or notice if those thoughts have any connection to time
past future pressure
tension relax and return with your breathing
for for
for
there's a way in which being distracted in thinking takes us out
of living time living in
time the live time of now the live time which inherently has
no tension or pressure as part of of it it's just
now
for
for for
what is your relationship to time
is there any pressure or tension that's Tim
related and if there is don't try to relax it at this
point instead see it clearly
feel it as fully as you can the tension the
pressure and allow it to be there and see what happens give space and
time to the pressure you
feel
for
e for
and as we come to the end of this
meditation you might consider that attention your
attention can be a gift we can listen to ourselves or
listen to others as a gift we can take take time to see and
appreciate others and that seeing and
appreciating is a gift for people who are seldom seen seldom
appreciated there are people who or say differently that to see and
appreciate and listen also involves the gift of
time slow down take time to really be with others
with yourself sometimes only if we give the
gift of time can other gifts be
given kindness friendship love
compassion generosity patience and
forgiveness joy and Delight
all can Thrive if there's time for them the gift of
time and as we come to the end of this sitting May It Be
that whatever way we're going to benefit benefit others whe whatever way we're going to benefit for the happy live for
the happiness and Welfare of others consider it
begins with the gift of time without there being lots of time
open time available time without
taking time giving time being in
time so many other things are not possible or or or
undermined or Limited in some
way may it be that as we go into the day today
that we offer the gift of time to those around
us may it be that we can live for the welfare and benefit of
others by how mindfulness teaches us the gift of
time living in time here and
now may all beings be happy be may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you
so a warm hello on this Monday and happy to be back after being
away for a couple of weeks and
um had a very nice time going back to my homeland Norway birth country and
having wonderful time with my relatives there and so I've certainly brought my
practice with me but it was more ordinary in the sense that I was not reading Buddhist books or
thinking profound Buddhist thoughts or something it's just living in this present moment and as free and
generously as I could and so today following up on that
I want to offer for this week uh something very simple and basic that
maybe we don't have to even think of it being Buddhist it's just a wise way of
living and it has to do with a little saying that I'm very fond of and I've
certainly mentioned it here uh in this teaching uh YouTube
teaching a few times and that's the teaching uh the idea that as you go
through your day especially when things are difficult and confusing and maybe you don't know
exactly what you should be doing or should be saying [Applause] saying that um a a wonderful
guideline is don't make it
worse whatever it's happening don't make the situation
worse so if you're angry be careful don't make it worse by speaking The
Angry Words so they hurt people or so they Sever and and ruin relationship
ship were in so they divide rather than to
unify if you don't know what to
do maybe running away makes it
worse maybe you don't maybe you don't have to know what to do
maybe it's enough just don't make it worse and sometimes uh it's so powerful
to not make it worse part of that is that it gives time to the situation
we're in it may be rather than fing the time or
feeling being feeling pressured to react or do something now or say something now
and then later regretting it there's uh by holding our tongue by not attacking
someone or not doing something that makes it worse uh
not going for some substance that's going to
somehow bring us into Oblivion or disconnect us from what's Happening or bypass what's happening that in the long
term will make it worse whatever it is don't make it worse
and that gives time for something more to happen so that's going to be the
topic for this week don't make it worse and how to live that way how to live with that
guideline and uh I like acronyms sometimes because they help us remember
and kind of Orient us and so I'm going to I have an acronym
for the with the word with the word worse and that's what I'll talk about
this week and the W uh can stand for
weight the O the um can stand for
organize or Orient the r can re uh stand for rest or
relax the S can stand for sense or
[Music] see and the E can stand for Express or
if you prefer empathy so um
um so today it's uh weight so part of uh not making it worse
is to uh also is is is can be uh
enhanced by understanding the benefits of waiting of taking
time giving space giving time for the situation to unfold I probably it's uncountable how
many times my life I have not known what to do
and sometimes in meditation sometimes socially sometimes in figuring things
out when I'm on my own and um and I find I found that if I
just wait something unfolds something happens
that makes the path forward clear sometimes uh some new thought and
idea arises that uh I couldn't have thought
about or understood if I was writing tensely on top of the issue the problem
I had to relax and allow something else to kind of be there sometimes
um it's uh the situation I'm in the social situation I in uh some things
begins to switch and change some conversations I've been in um when I
wait uh sometimes like I have the opinions that I feel like okay I have to tell this person I have an opinion I
know what's right I know what we supposed to do here I know what how to fix this thing that needs to be fixed or
something and I can feel my impatience sometimes like you know to really assert
myself and I've learned that uh it's not really useful to act that way and from
that way and it's useful to wait and then so many times by waiting the person
I'm with says something or opens up the door for something for the conversation to take a different direction or they
have the understanding that I was going to assert or they know how to fix something or do something and uh it's so
such a wonderful I think profound experience at least for me it feels this way to have not asserted my solution my
way and seeing how things evolve and that in some ways in small ways maybe I
kind of allowed to let the situation unfold sometimes the Su situation wasn't
solved by that but new information came along that allows us to figure out
what's going to happen what to do so I think that uh human
intelligence and human social interactions uh do really well sometimes
if we give conscious clear time for things to show themselves to reveal
themselves takes time for us to see and understand what's happening and sometimes that can be uh
you know intentional where we ask questions tell me more tell me more you know I don't understand everything here
can you explain that in a different way or what do you think um so we're giving time for the other person to
speak sometimes it's uh maybe if we're alone and have some kind of personal
challenge maybe we give it all time we wait but go in the way we do it was to
go meditate and I found that sometimes in my life when I have some tension and
pressure feel like there's a deadline I have to do something I can't figure something out I can feel the tension in
my forehead or behind my forehead or different places in my body and at this
is you know I realize this is making the whole situation worse let me go and
meditate and sometimes just 10 minutes of sitting quietly meditating or
sometimes I'll go for a walk and just kind of stepping out of um the pressurized time that that I
was giving myself into an unpressured time of just going for a walk and these
meditating or going for a walk creates a whole different ecosystem it allows something to shift and change inside
something to relax and open gives time for something some inner process to
unfold that uh when I finish even 10 minutes sometimes um there's so much more clarity so much
more understanding some sometimes becomes clear what to do uh in a way
that I couldn't otherwise wait don't make it
worse uh uh give time for the situation to clarify itself to unfold to become
more obvious uh give time so that uh maybe
you understand or your confus confused but maybe the other person hasn't understood what the confusion is yet and
just wait and give time for that person to find their way with the situation um so not making it
worse uh is not only an issue of just restraint holding your uh hold staying
silent and don't blurting out what you want to say not doing the thing that's
impulsive but it's also um more profoundly by not making it worse not
giving into to those impulses um uh there's a kind of sacred
waiting or if you don't like the word sacred there's a kind of generative
waiting that wait let's see what else wants to unfold here let's see what else
wants to happen um it doesn't things don't have to happen on the tip of my
own assertion the tip of my own preoccupations the tip of my own fear or
anger or desires that are pushing me or pushing into the present moment in the
situation um relax don't have that pointed pressure
soften open feel sense see wait to for a
deeper understanding wait so don't make it worse
and by not W making it worse give yourself time to have a kind of
generative waiting a kind of
uh uh exploratory waiting a discovery waiting uh and a time for intelligence
waiting a time for deeper feeling wait to feel to sense to know what's
happening here wait so that's the
W so if today if you the next 24 hours
uh you might want to um um give yourself
the the learning opportunity to spend time allowing more
waiting in all kinds of situations um and see what you learn
what happens for that and there's so many different ways that can happen but say for example you have
some and nothing's happening you're waiting in line you're waiting for something and you find yourself pulling
out your phone to look at the news or email or text or something because you
don't want to wait you have this time you want to do something don't do
that don't disconnect from your environment don't
in his way also disconnect from yourself take the time when you're
waiting for something anyway to do a generative waiting a sacred
waiting allow the waiting give space and time to see what else can unfold and in
the in just being here present for your
experience so thank you and um and I'm happy to be back here and
look forward to joining you again tomorrow