good morning s warm greetings I'm so delightful to see you all in the
chat I like seeing the warm friendly greetings from people all over the place
BC from Scotland Santa Cruz Bellingham tolino
Mountain View and many many other places it's great to see so um
wishing you all well this is a sound check among other
things why I'm on a couple of minutes early and
um I'll mention for I'm looking at the chat Eric's benefit this is Dean Naya
26 Long discourses 26 is the Sut reference that I put in the chat last
night so warm greetings everyone this is also I'd like to offer a followup on the
homework so yesterday thank you for the soundcheck friends yesterday I invited
you those of you who stayed to the very end to notice little glimmers of Joy or
happiness contentment in your day and if you have a moment if you're
saying hello to everyone anyway maybe um offer a short example in the chat it
will light everyone else up to see it as well
so here we are giving the pause that it
takes we have a bit of a lag between um what I say and what gets broadcast you
all probably know that from sitting with Gil
so again
watching The Morning Light change other glimmers of Happiness
meeting with my dear friends and prison support group
nice for those of you just joining the invitation is to just note in the chat if you had a little glimmer of happiness
or joy yesterday contentment
the warm greetings themselves are a kind of Joy the grateful to be
alive going on a walk and talking chatting with acquaintances and strangers Joy of playing with my kitten
oh yes so just an invitation friends to
read what your fellow practitioners are writing in the chat um mated pair of
eagles flying overhead
lubert the Sun a mama crow in the nest Joy of success from a
student hearing spring peepers yes Awakening to the
birds so thank thank you all for
that and noticing for yourself how it feels to
recollect moments of contentment Happiness
joy and how it feels to read that of others if you are
and now as you take that into your
heart taking any glimmers of Joy contentment ease
happiness heard about read about or experienced into your heart
and when you're ready beginning to turn the day gaze
inward yaling the appreciative joy little smile maybe from other
people's sharings or an appreciative joy for yourself gratitude
for any blessings any goodness in your
life and breathing with
that letting that feeling suffuse into your body maybe your chest around your
heart or just in the face with a subtle [Music]
smile the
memories and allowing that feeling to echo
through a glimpse of goodness
appreciating appreciating this
moment the nourishment of this breath
the Priceless opportunity to be present and practice
allowing the Mind heart body to
settle receiving the in breath with
appreciation offering the out breath back into the world
and if it feels right intentionally cultivating a
sense of Goodwill
kindness or compassion for this moment whatever is arising in the heart
and mind
appreciating Joy or contentment if they
arrive and allowing a sense of
ESS equinity with whatever comes and
goes just inviting these qualities to be there in the back
ground and settling
deeply into this
breath this moment
e
e e
if the mind wanders the invitation is to greet the return of
awareness with appreciation
welcoming with kindness
and returning all of the
attention this breath this sensation this moment
flowing
through
e
e e
and in the last remaining moment of this
meditation the invitation is again to to tune in to the quality of your
heart whatever is there is
fine meeing that the sense of appreciation or
acknowledgement kindness or [Music]
compassion perhaps Joy
cultivating an overall sense of spacious
okayness noticing the noticing of all of it unfolding
and then casting your mind back over these moments of
meditation and Gathering up any moments of
goodness savoring them Ste deeping in [Music]
them allowing them to nourish
you and then offering them
outwards towards the other is practicing here today or later with the
recording towards the others your life
touches directly or
indirectly may all beings benefit from the blessings of this
practice may all beings be safe from inner and outer
harm be peaceful and may all beings know the
highest Joy of Awakening
for
thank you for your
practice e
friends welcome welcome dear online Global farflung
sa it's good to be back with you today special welcome to those of you
who slipped in a few minutes late nice to see old friends familiar
names and some of the new names so today is the fourth of a
five-day series on qualities of inner and interpersonal darma well-being
Wellsprings within us that can help us be at home and
ourselves if we come home to the practice the Buddha taught that
practitioners can cultivate these particular kinds of dharmic well-being
flourishing even in difficult times s by staying with the practice staying with
contentment with the practice and there are five qualities I'm covering
today not today sorry five qualities I'm covering this week though I will be covering five qualities today too just
not the same ones the five this week Are Spiritual empowerment or the four four
roads to power the teaching is sometimes called true beauty
happiness inner wealth or heart wealth and
freedom and yesterday we covered happiness today we cover that sense of
inner wealth heart wealth becoming rich in the heart qualities the forms of
Buddhist love and by way of introducing this topic I'm going to continue with another
little vignette from Queen Jasmine's life this Buddhist myth or fairy tale
that I brought up on Tuesday and I actually introduced it in site Santa Cruz last week and to summarize so far she met
King pacity when she was a low cast very poor daughter of two flower Growers out
Gathering flowers for her family's business in the field and based on her generosity her kindness her confidence
he fell in love with her and it turns out lifted her out of obscurity to become his first and most beloved
Queen now earlier this week I talked about how she encouraged him to go to
the Buddha and thus prevented a very ill-advised large
sacrifice of animals and after this experience he began to trust her even more began to trust her and her um
inclinations her compassion a little bit of her wisdom and um perhaps it's after that
time that the commentaries don't make it clear but this story happens when the
two of us are in a private moment I picture them on the balcony of their
Castle surveying their realm it's dusk that kind of indigo duskiness has settled over the
farmland and can just see the Himalayan Foothills and the peaks of the mountains
etched against the sky it's kind of a romantic
moment and In This Moment the king turns to
Jasmine and he says he asks in all of the world my dear who do
you love the most now the commentary is say that this question happened from a place of kind
of smugness or entitlement that he lifted her out of poverty and that she must be so grateful and love her love
him above all else because of this but that's not how I
read Jasmine Malika was dear to his heart and she
turned to him and took both of his hands in hers and held them and looked into his
eyes and he said in all of the world
beloved husband it is myself I hold the most dear it is myself
I love the most well the King was a little bit startled by this one
imagines but he stays with it and she stays with him hands still on
his and after pausing for a few moments for him to drink that in she asks and my
love who is is it that you hold most dear who do you love the most in all the
world and upon contemplation he kind of reluctantly has
to agree with her it's himself that's the center of things he holds himself
most dear this conversation it made an impact and
so the King goes to the Buddha and relays this conversation to him and the
Buddha nods sagely and says yes Jasmine Malik
is Right each person each person holds
themselves most dear holds their life Central within themselves and the
significance of that is that this it's a basis for this profound empathy that all
people all beings are the center of their own lives their lives matter so much to to
them and that because of that this wish to be alive this wish to be happy no one
should ever harm or kill another
so I tell this story knowing that self-love is kind of sometimes dismissed
as new age psycho Babble or a modern add-on to ancient Buddhism and it isn't
to hold oneself most dear on a conventional level it's not full
Awakening by any means however it's an assumed easy
basis for the profound cultivation of heart and mind it's the
beginning of meta loving kindness for oneself and all beings as
all as to all as to oneself if this is challenging for you consider
that one of the most beautiful gifts you might be able to offer in your life is to cultivate healthy
self-regard not better than not worse than but
incomparable that kind of spiritual Assurance flows out to other people
overflows and lest there be protests in the audience want to note that healthy
self-regard is something that the Buddha exemplified on a relational level for 45
years of teaching well after he had penetrated to full Awakening Complete
deep Insight so if it's too heavy of a lift
or if it doesn't feel like a good fit it's okay to start elsewhere but to consider no matter how
buried hidden disguised Ed Twisted that wish to live that wish to be happy
weaves through us all and it's the basis the beginning of
a profound empathy this kind of empathy the pow
anukampa is a spontaneous quivering or movement of the heart a caring
impulse a wish for non-harming and it can manifest as
helping yesterday I talked about the tale of suata in the Buddha this woman
who walked by and noticed the Buddha to be practically starving and fed him out
of compassion kindness ANUK the heart
qualities meta loving kindness karuna compassion appreciative joy mudita and
UPA equinity those can all emerge naturally through mindfulness practice
dedicated Buddhist practice and they can be cultivated directly as many of you already know
through intentional practices for many mindfulness is enough at first and
then it could be skillful to interweave direct cultivation of the heart
qualities this can be through directed attention with phrases through radiating
broadly or through more receptive forms of noticing like we did today noticing
in the meditation they've been covered extensively these practices elsewhere
including by Liz Powell earlier this spring so I'm not really going to go into them I'm just going to touch on
them and how they fit into these Wells Springs of wellbeing for a few
minutes so first to say that the
immeasurables the Brahma viharas predated Buddhism they were considered four
facets of brma the ground of all being the Creator in
Hinduism but later the Buddha operationalized them as practices
and they became known as Divine abodes Divine abiding because they are so Sublime and so powerful at the upper
reaches of their cultivation from a Buddhist perspective
these are ways of inclining the Mind towards the qualities helpful for
Liberation and they can also just arise spontaneously the
expression of an awake aware heart and mind towards whatever is arising and
experience if you picture clear light a Sunbeam shining through a
prism the awakened awareness is the clear light
when it strikes the prism it fractures into these different qualities of the
rainbow and these colors are different Expressions based
on conditions of the world different expressions of awakeness
awareness responsivity so the first loving
kindness is a baseline friendliness towards self others and
experience compassion is when that same responsive heart's
awareness responds to
suffering appreciative Joy is the response the healthy awake
response aware response when others experience Good Fortune good good things
like celebrating the success of a child or a grandchild or a friend you're
rooting for and then equinity is the awakened response to
that which cannot change ESS
space and finally gratitude are what some call the fifth B
of vihara and it's kind of a dimension it's so closely related to this quality
of appreciative Joy gratitude could be considered inner and outer directed
appreciative joy for our own good fortune and those conditions or people
that caused it even if it's very modest Good Fortune it's a very beautiful
onward leading quality so how is this wealth inner
wealth well in addition to being beautiful in their own right and wonderful experiences to
have ancient commentaries and science kind of document some of the benefits of
these that a person according to the ancient text is beloved by humans and
animals alike and this manifests as greater interpersonal Harmony social lubrication
group cohesion which has been documented in metaanalyses of people practicing heart
practices after just 6 weeks many people experience more joy and satisfaction in
their relationships both the ancient texts and science agree that attentional
control and concentration improve immune response improves and a greater sense
purpose so in short cultivating strong heart qualities whether through mindfulness or direct practices
nourishes our minds our emotional lives and relationships it's a form of true
wealth and it can culminate Express in a freedom chti of
the heart in which no one is better than worse than or even equal
to and this is also an enduring understanding that the awakened heart
fully awakened people have and Liberation that liberation of the heart
is something that I will touch on tomorrow so thank you for your kind
attention everyone I'm going to put in the chat by the way that I am offering later this
summer a half day on the use of loving kindness as a concentration practice
stabil and S so if you are
interested go to my website and look at the teaching schedule there and that will have a few Retreats that are coming
up and also this half day for the Sati Center so
friends thank you for your kind attention and your assignment should you choose to accept it for tomorrow is to
notice any glimmers moment of kindness
compassion appreciative of Joy gratitude or
equinity thank you