good evening welcome
welcome so maybe I'll start by um just sharing a
little bit that uh sometimes at the end of Retreats we have a closing Circle and
people talk about how their experience was and you not all closing circles are
exactly the same but sometimes you know it's not uncommon for people to share something that happened that was
meaningful for them that was noteworthy that uh something they want to take away
perhaps with them and sometimes not every closing
Circle sometimes I say something like whatever you found here that was
meaningful some new understanding a feeling of peace and
ease or some settledness in the mind and the
body or maybe a connection with uh somebody else you know that might happen if you did a job together or something
like this I often say give it away just
give it away so this idea of maybe as you get in
your car to leave the retreat and there's other people in the lane next to you here have some peace here have some
Stillness here have some sense of well-being just give it away give it away like actively we do doing this
there's something about sometimes when we find things that are meaningful or helpful we want to hold on to them of
course we do of course we want to hold on to them but right those of us who have been
practicing for a while and certainly the Buddhist teachings are pointing to this this idea of clinging right is leads to
dooka leads to suffering and so there can be a way in
which you're like oh this is uh so meaningful that I have to hold on to
it but the act of holding on sometimes um transforms it from an experience to
just an object to just another concept or memory and it's no longer a lived
experience for me this was a very powerful I think I've told this story maybe more than once that uh I was
sitting in a long retreat and after quite some time on Retreat I uh I ended up I I needed to go
to the doctor's it wasn't it turned out not to be serious and turned out to be fine but when the you know when your
mind is really settled and you've been practicing I think at that time maybe it' been a few months that uh you know
any small little thing turns into something giant so anyway so I was off
to the doctors and um you know I'd only been doing like walking meditation
slowly for a long time so it was so exciting to be in a car we were going so
fast you know like 35 mes an hour you know like wow but I
remember having this idea of like okay I'm coming from this place of you know incredible Stillness and peace and I was
having a lot of ease and just giving it away to people in the car in the other lanes you know going the opposite
direction or something and just my heart just starting to overflow
and then showing up the the I don't remember now if it was an urgent care or just a doctor's office but you know
there's a lot of suffering in the waiting rooms of you know medical centers and just like giving it away
like okay here's here's whatever sense of peace I have here have it here's here's a any sense of well-being or
stability and there was something magical about this and one thing of
course is we discover that it's these aren't Commodities there isn't a
limited quantity of course not they're unlimited and giving them
away helps them grow helps them
expand and so there's this movement this openness this willingness to open up and maybe like
share as opposed to kind of like hold on that is a really a big support for
practice and this shows up in so many ways but this what I want to highlight
is this practicing generosity that leads to this I'm using this word generosity
this uh this willingness to give away here it was some
experience and maybe I'll back up of course when we come off Retreat for me
I'm often writing down some notes that was like what was really meaningful and helpful for me and sometimes look back
at those notes maybe I don't always so I'm not saying that we shouldn't ever like remember things that happen that
are really meaningful and supportive for us it's the clinging and like oh this is
I have to hold on to this this is where we're going to get into trouble and the opposite of this
clinging is this movement of maybe we would say sharing or generosity or letting
go and it it supports this openness
this spaciousness this sense of uh having
enough like undermines a sense of uh inadequacy or insufficiency or this uh
sense of lack this like freely giving away turns out to be a tremendous
support and the bruda pointed to this and some of his uh teachings paraphrasing uh maybe some of
you have heard this but the Buddha is one of his teaching is if you knew what
I know about the power of generosity you wouldn't let a single
meal go by without sharing it so he's just pointing to this openness and we
might also say this recognition of connection to others how we impact others and of course we're impacted by
others too so this we might say is a little bit of a paradox this idea of giving away
makes us feel like we have more CU it to undes this feeling of I
have to have more have to hold on to this in some kind of way but I think all of us uh have this
recognition that when we have this feeling of I don't have
enough then all were there it's really um and it's true right I want to say
sometimes we don't have enough sometimes we don't have enough money that we find ourselves in a lot of debt or we find
ourselves uh not being able to take care of some additional responsibilities we
find ourselves having or whatever it might be so I mean it's perfectly legitimate that sometimes there simply
isn't enough I'm pointing to money right
now but if there's a way in which uh we're primarily concerned with okay I
got to get more I got to get more then it kind of it leads to a sense
that really supports this sense of insufficiency and there's this maybe this gwing anxiety that goes with
that there's this you know that kind of supports the sense of there's not enough so this can be kind of a tricky
territory like okay I need to get out of debt and yet I don't want to feel like
everything isn't enough one way we can look at that and I'll talk about this in a moment a
little bit is uh to bring some wisdom to this maybe money is one thing what's in
the bank account what's on the credit card versus what is there some what do
we have enough of what do we what can we give away
our attention so much suffering in the world
is about people feeling like they haven't been seen or haven't been heard
or haven't been met with somebody giving them their full attention it's quite astounding actually
if we look at that and notice this so maybe we can give our attention with
care to somebody who comes to talk to us or even on just small
things the person The Grocery Clerk just to you know make eye contact and
acknowledge and if it seems appropriate you know say a little Hi how are you
kind of thing instead of there's a way in which we could just be just just you do your job so I can get out of here as
fast as possible instead of kind of recognizing our common Humanity
or maybe we could have be generous with some kindness kindness for ourselves and
kindness with others maybe this is some warm-heartedness and maybe that uh takes
the form of sending a card like a physical piece of paper that goes in the mail like these are seems like special
these days right like precious things when I get something in the mail like you know now it's you know text and
email seem so easy but send a card to somebody it's a feels it's a sense of
uplift some kindness and some care so this idea of like generosity and
giving when we talk about it here in the Buddhist centers and then certainly in this tradition in
particular where we really highlight that everything is offered freely everything here at IMC right
offered freely everything at the retreat center offer offered freely all of our Retreats offered
freely and then when we want to talk about generosity you know sometimes it can feel awkward but there's a way in
which maybe perhaps like conflating maybe mainstream ideas of generosity and
giving with what I might say the Buddhist ideas I I want to highlight a
few differences here first of all I'll say that
generosity often translated as Donna and we sometimes you hear this uh
language Donna da a it turns out to be a foundational
practice in the Buddhist teachings it's just this recognition of
the openness this of uh and the of sharing
maybe connecting with others is and in contrast to the opposite of like um I
have to have more which again I want to say sometimes we do need more I don't want to say that
we don't but it's part of this with ethical Behavior this like openness this
willingness to share whether it's attention or kindness or time or
material objects money or something else is really foundational to the
practice so it highlights how we are in the
world as opposed to okay I just got to get some meditative experience and then I'll be fine it's really highlighting
the way that we impact others and we are impacted by
others so in the list of parames some of you might be familiar with this list
it's a list of 10 um qualities that are usually described as off of the meditation
cushion so something that is done in one SL life the first is this orientation
towards sharing this orientation towards giving generosity it's also often when the
Buddha is giving teachings to somebody in these stories and um he encounters them the first teaching he gives them is
about generosity Donna and then CA ethical behavior and then b in a um this mental
cultivation so just this recognition that generosity so often is just this
orientation towards some openness and it's this orientation that
turns out that can have such a big impact on our
lives this is maybe in contrast to I what I might say a mainstream Society
the orientation is getting I got to get more give me more I got to attain I got
to achieve I got to have what can I get and what can I get away with and you know this opposite you know this it's a
society we created you know we can choose to participate in that or not in a way that uh makes sense to us but
there's a real different uh emphasis on what kind of an orientation to
have and so we might say that also in what I'm going to call
Mainstream these days like this is what what we're in here at IMC is not so
different than mainstream we might say but I going to say mainstream versus like these Buddhist ter Buddhist uh
values and mainstream there's often this way in which giving or yeah I'll just
use this word giving is transactional you gave me this I'll give
you that or you know maybe there's a sense and again this it's a natural
thing but well I had you over for dinner and I'm kind of expecting that you're going to invite me over for dinner or that if
you're offering me dinner then I better show up with something that's of value or and I'm not saying that these are bad
I'm just saying there's this uh often a transactional or maybe there's just you know the Girl Scout cookies okay I'm G
to pay this amount of money for the cookies or something that will uh support the Girl Scouts so there's this
clear expectations I might say of uh reciprocity or maybe there's this clear
expectations of tangible benefits I'm G to get cookies now that I uh gave money
to this young girl that rang the doorbell or that is sending in front of the grocery store as the case may
be so I would say a mainstream society that kind of the reciprocity and Tang
tangible benefits but um with a Buddhist idea it's more of an internal experience
is the uh is the Orient or is the emphasis I should say whereas this external okay
what am I going to get versus what is the experience like is it supporting
greater freedom is it supporting greater ease greater peace and my movement
towards trying to find my way through the suffering I have in my life
and also we might say in kind like mainstream giving sometimes there's this
giving that's done out of a sense of Duty or a sense of obligation a sense
of um well this what's expected of us
there's this maybe kind of these Norms of a certain communities or there's this you know expectation that you should
give you know in in this particular setting whereas in contrast to that I
would say like the Buddhist teachings on generosity is more on this emphasis on
cultivating an open heart cultivating and open
mind and this recognition that the heart and the mind and our behaviors of course
they're connected and they go all directions the heart affects I'm using heart to mean
maybe um maybe a a felt sense or maybe an
Intuition or a feeling I'm using mind to be more like thoughts and
Concepts and then behaviors are the things that we actually do all three of
these behave uh sorry uh influence one another and the influence goes all
directions so of course what's in our mind influences our Behavior but our Behavior influences our minds and our
Hearts as well so this recognition that uh generosity flows out of this openness of
heart and mind but also the behavior of being generous supports this sense of
openness in the heart and mind as well it's and it's also about like
cultivating we might say this inner disposition of not only openness but
maybe some kindness and some care that often accompanies when there's some
generosity when there's some giving so there's
this maybe this movement of uh giving we as I pointed out earlier
also is the opposite of clinging so it's the
cultivation of something that's the opposite of what leads to
suffering this cultiv ation of what leads to Greater peace and ease and
sometimes it's this uh when we're doing the opposite of something it highlights
its opposite for example the feeling some of the openness with generosity
really starts to highlight oh yeah there's this tightness when there's um this feeling
of stinginess for example I might say that's not a very nice word I don't feel good saying that word the s of
uh holding too tightly maybe I'll just say
that so just this maybe I I'll say use different language the being in
generosity supporting the openness and it highlights the tightness that we can
feel in other areas of our life including when we feel like no no no I I
I'm not I can't share my attention or my time or my energy and I feel like every time time I
say something like this I also need to say there are times in our lives when we
have a lot of suffering and we don't have the capacity to meet others where
they are there are seasons perhaps when there's a lot of illness or a lot of Dua
in whatever way so I don't want us to feel obligated like oh yeah okay I have
to give even though we feel so depleted even though we are starving for
some ease we more in the midst of
difficulties having said that that part of
the um connection between generosity and some
happiness is we see this happen a lot on um big scales hurricanes these terrible
hurricanes that were just in the South North Carolina and Florida for example I'm just using this as example there's
so many terrible things that are happening in the world that when there's this tragedy and
things are I'll just use this word
awful horrible yeah sometimes people come
together and share what they have with others or they share they help pick up
the rubble or they help literally or metaphorically when they and there's
this activity of like when we're sharing helping others that can bring this uplift of the heart that even though
there's this Devastation around perhaps I feel devastated the the uh Act of being
generous of supporting someone else kind of reminds us oh yeah I I have something I can
give energy time attention whatever it is and there's this uplift of the heart
that can happen with that so sometimes I'm saying when we're really down and out maybe we don't have the capacity to
be generous and it might be if we do have the energy to be generous in some
kind of way might provide some uplift a little bit of Joy some appreciation and
maybe undermine some sometimes we often have this sense of a we don't have agency like we can't do
anything or it's just not enough of anything and being generous can counteract
that so also there's this way in which I'm going to um contrast like mainstream
idea of generosity versus like the Buddhist ideas of uh
generosity is that kind of in the Buddhist ideas there's a real emphasis
on having some wise discernment in one's
generosity I would say maybe in contrast like mainstream um requests or
or I'll just use this word requests they're often lying relying on and I
don't want to say this is bad I'm just saying this to highlight how with the emot with the Buddhist one is
different the mainstream they often are relying on relying on emotional impulse
is like oh like a certain break heart brokenheartedness that can Happ when you see a photo a particular photo of often
it's a child right that is um in distress there's a lot of research
around this right of course so people have done research okay what makes it most likely that somebody will donate
what kind of photos and they've determined that usually it's just one child is better than more than one and
you know there's all kinds of stuff on this but so there um relying on the heartstrings getting
pulled as a way to uh be generous or maybe some uh social pressure uh to be
generous some religious traditions for example uh openly share uh how much uh
individuals donate they have it like publicly listed so and so donated this much so and so don't donated that much
or some religious Traditions say well some of our religious tenants are only
available to you if you donate enough or you know something like this right so
there's other ways in which mainstream
uh requests for donations are using certain um approaches in contrast I
would say here we're really pointing to wisdom needs to be here this is an
opportunity to cultivate wisdom this is an opportunity to use wisdom
so this an encouragement to be attentive to one's own needs and
limitations this uh like okay what's appropriate for you in your life
situation in terms of the amount that you donate or this encouragement like do
you feel like inspired or um appreci appreciative and want to help see these
uh continue these teachings continue or these offerings continue and some wise discernment like is this something
that's valuable for me if so then what can donate so L's relying on emotional
heartstrings and also this the sense of wisdom but the wisdom
also comes with a the sense of responsibility of like not harming we
don't want to harm ourselves that we're being generous and to a way that is inappropriate for us for our
life we've all heard these stories of people getting in terrible debt so that
they can donate to some organization and then that organization ends up just dissolving or going away or being a
bogus one it's heartbreaking whereas here there's this um in the Buddhist tradition there's a
real uh encouragement to practice generosity and wisdom
together and so there could even be a way in which our generosity like
compounds difficulties for example there might be
a situation in which we feel like okay well here's a one of my co-workers who is um doing a lot of
complaining maybe about their boss or their spouse or the government I mean there's no end of things that we can
complain about and maybe we feel like okay well I heard I'm going to be generous and
really listen to them but we might start to notice that the more the person is
complaining and complaining the more that they're feeling dejected and we're feeling dejected and they're starting to
feel even more agitated not only that they did this can you believe it oh my
gosh and and then we're starting to feel like oh yeah it really is awful and
starting to feel helpless and hopeless or something like
this so if we just listen feeling like we're being generous then maybe they
might believe that they're that we're condoning their behavior and thinking that oh yeah this is a way to Greater
Peace and Freedom or maybe they might even think that we are agreeing with everything that they say and would go to
somebody else and say oh yeah well so and so agrees with me they didn't say
anything when I was complaining about this that and the other thing so just this encouragement to have some
sensitivity about you know the manner in which we're being generous and make sure
that we're not causing harm to others or to ourselves and maybe I'll also add this
idea of generosity requires us to be sensitive to what's happening with other
people what is the wise thing to do are we just being generous because we feel
uncomfortable and we want to stop feeling uncomfortable or are we so closed off and concerned with ourselves
that we don't even notice when other people could use some help could use
some attention could use some kindness so there's this way in which
this uh idea of generosity is used as a foundational
teaching just as this openness of this of the heart but also as a way that
supports the teachings of course but supports our own path towards
Liberation it's this way that I've been talking about this openness of heart and
mind but some of you might have be familiar with this teaching that uh one of uh the
three sometimes gets called poisons is greed this sense of just I need to have
more more more more this causes so much suffering in the world for us as
individuals and then you know just the wider world and so I generosity is an antidote
to one of these poisons that shows up in so many ways and complete freedom is described
as the absence of greed the absence of hatred and the absence of delusion so
this is like fundamentally pointing directly towards some of this uh movement towards greater
Freedom so maybe maybe I'll say a little bit about
um some of the something else about this uh the Buddhist practice of generosity
or this Buddhist emphasis of generosity is it it's also a great way
in which we can learn about ourselves a big part of this practice is
some greater self- understanding how we are in the world how we show up
in the world as a way to help us find less suffering and more
[Music] ease so we might just have this query
what areas of Our Lives do we feel generous and what areas do we not feel
so generous not that it has to be bad or good but just to understand ourselves
and then maybe to stretch ourselves a little bit I'm not saying we have to um
condemn our the way that we are or but just an encouragement to find more and
more openness and so an obvious sway is like between uh time and resources some
people are like oh I don't have any extra time but here you can have some money or maybe some people are like um I
don't have any money but I have time to share or I don't have so much kindness
I'm cranky and my world is falling apart and I don't have kindness or I don't want to give you attention or not so
much I don't want to give you like I can't give you attention because I have so much suffering here and again we
don't have to say it's bad or good we could just have this recognition well how is it for
us and is there a way with this greater understanding of how generosity shows up
in our lives is there a way that we could have greater Freedom if by just
maybe stretching a little bit because we learned these ways of how we
are how generosity generosity is in the world most likely from our families from
our societies our our communities that we grew up with we don't have to make
them bad but can we learn something and when we look at this when we look at our
practice of generosity we'll probably notice that we most often have MI
motivations when we're generous maybe some of it is this natural uh wanting to
share and maybe there's a like well it's kind of expected of me or or we might
say and um I want them to like me or I want them to appreciate me or I want them to remember me or whatever it
is and can that be okay because we might say well if it's mixed motivations it's
not pure openness then maybe it's not even worth while what happens is it I would say it
always starts with some mixed motivations and then as we practice both
with mindfulness and um just spiritual practice in general our motivations
start to get more and more I might use this word purified they start to become more and more generous and open as we're
finding more and more ease it's just naturally flows that
way so this idea of
giving and we might say mainstream giving versus maybe kind of this Buddhist idea of generosity which turns
out to be a foundational practice as it points to this openness this open-heartedness
open-mindedness or we might even say open fisted maybe in this way that we show up in the
world that leads to Greater Freedom less harm and peace and
ease so thank you thank you for your kind attention and I'll open it up for
some comments and questions thank you
um I had a couple of thoughts about like the intention behind generosity
that I look have seen this in others and I look for it in myself if it's kind of
an unhealthy um I want to do be generous
this way and get some recognition for it to me I
uh yeah I see that as as greed you know Greed for recognition so not
um you know not not real open generosity um and then the other thing
when you were talking about if if you're depleted yourself you know maybe it's not the time to be to be
generous I was thinking well maybe that's the time to be direct your generos it to yourself very nice yeah
yeah yeah yeah I like this idea of me having generosity towards myself I love that
some self-care in some kind of way yeah and this is interesting about being
generous so that you can have some recognition I'll say that uh there is a
back when I was in Corporate America uh you know there is a plaque I'll say here
in the Bay Area that has my name on it for you know my generosity for something
so you know but uh I will also say that whenever I uh see that or I recall it it
gives me this uplift to the heart it was something that was meaningful for me and I kind of I don't know makes me very
happy that I was able to do that so maybe there was some greed there of
recognition I did like the idea that my name was going to be on this PL and um I I uh heard this idea years
ago from Joseph Goldstein on he's one of the elders in this
tradition and uh about generosity and he said that he had started this practice
of Whenever there was a like a request for generosity to just do it to just do
it even though the motivations may be mixed just to do it and you know being wise with one regards to one's means and
I started to do this as well I left it it just made me happy and I also not
noticed how my motivations were all over the place and but there was also just
this uh recognition of being generous with material Goods or with uh time and
attention it um cultivates this movement of maybe like of letting go so I don't
know if this addresses your comments yeah thank you thank you
so you mentioned that that uplift of the heart and I was thinking about this why
you were talking uh uh in my experience it only comes then
it is difficult to be generous so contributing to organizations like save
the children or doctors in their borders that's easy and there is no uplift of the heart in that sort of
generosity putting myself in a situation that is difficult talking to someone that I feel uncomfortable but it's
helpful that has the uplift of the heart is
that so you saying the uplift of the heart is more if it's difficult to give
I see uh that hasn't been my experience but I think this is great thing to
explore like okay what is the connection there between if it's difficult to give or not to give thank you for bringing up
that I don't have an answer I'm just explaining my experience seems like your experience is different I think it's a
great thing to explore I'm I'm contributing to these large organizations because that's the
right thing to do but that's not doesn't do anything for me
inside thank you thank you
um so one one area where I feel a little tight is um I like things to go my
way and um especially socially uh there's uh control and um wondering if
you have suggestions for working with uh giving that away giving agency um
allowing for things to go the way that I don't like
what does it feel like when uh you said that you feel tight can you say a little bit more it's just yeah it's like oh
things it would be better if I you know if I told them this is this is the my
way the better way to do it
yeah that this is a such an interesting topic you know about uh controlling
others and of course Kevin you probably know right it does we don't get to control I mean we we think we can but we
don't really control others um I I what comes to mind is something simple about
uh just being present in the moment an obvious thing is you like feeling your feet on the ground because often what
happens when we're trying to um control others is maybe maybe even
you said this Kevin is to not feel the discomfort and so we feel like okay well
if they would just stop doing that or start doing that then I wouldn't have this discomfort but is there a way that we
can just acknowledge feel our feet on the ground and like yeah this is
uncomfortable and that's the truth of the moment right and that's the reality of the moment and can we be with that as
best we can and so often probably what will happen is like oh yeah this is uncomfortable and they really should be
doing all this kind of stuff right we'll slip right into that and then can you just come back to wow this really is
uncomfortable but what man you probably have this experience too that if we
don't control often things unfold in a way that we don't expect and maybe they're even better like maybe people
have different ideas that turn out to be better than the ideas that we have had so takes a little maybe trust and
confidence and the unfolding of things and maybe if it's not
better can that be okay too I wish I had an easy answer for you
Kevin like that was good thank you you're
welcome anybody else have a question or
comment go okay okay so may you find some flow of
this openness of the heart uh as you go home this evening and every day
thereafter thank you wishing you well good night