good morning everyone and
um one of the surprises to me when
I went to practice in Thailand when I was first introduced to tabot Buddhism and to
basana was that um the topic of Sila or ethics or virtue was one that brought uh
people a lot of Joy it was a joy topic it was something that brought
happiness and um that was not something I had ever imagined uh growing up or in the western
cultures that I had lived in fact uh I was grew up somewhat mistrustful of
people who had overemphasized ethics that it was um somehow a little
bit too puritanical or dogmatic or judgmental of people or hypocritical
even at times but the idea that they would bring you
Joy and uh it wasn't just a surprise to discover people who had that
orientation it was a surprised that as I started doing long retreats in Thailand
that something shifted inside of me and there was a uh something got cleansed
something got emptied something got uh space for something new to arise
that I had never felt before that uh that felt uh as something that uh
brought joy for living a life of
non-harming living a life that avoided the kind of unh wholesome behavior that
felt like it uh did a kind of violence to this inner place that was developing
through the practice and so the reference point of joy for ethics
for ca for this kind of living this life of cusa and kalana wholesomeness and
beauty and one of the things that uh is very Central to Buddhist the Buddhist
teachings is that the mind is malleable and nowadays we might call
neuroplasticity that uh the mind can be a trans transformed and made uh workable
wieldy so that it's not stuck in a rut but can be become soft enough to
workable enough to be able to uh do the inner spiritual work that Buddhist
practi is about and that's encapsulated in the idea of a training that Buddhist practices about
training ethics is about training in ethics not about
perfection so we don't hold ourselves up against a standard of either or either
we're doing it wrong or doing it right perfectly but that we're
training and many skills many things we do in our ordinary life we train to become better at riding a bicycle
playing an instrument um cooking a particular dish we do it a few times until we feel like
we can do it easily without continuing to look at the recipe and being reminded or something
like like that so we're training we're learning we're developing and to orient yourself around
meditation that uh it is in fact Not Meant to Be Perfect it's meant to be a
training that we enter into with sincerity a training where we do our
best knowing that we'll fall off the wagon and we'll just have to uh get back
on again or off the horse I guess and back on again and back on again um developing
ourselves and as we do so we're developing a wholesome attitude towards
ourselves as a meditator wholesome attitude towards our meditation a wholesome attitude to whatever
experience comes up in meditation a beautiful attitude and one that we can understand
has some quality of Ethics in it that it brings us joy and happiness to be
training to do our best to train ourselves to meet our situation with kindness and
nonhostility and and so we're training which means we do our best and knowing that our best is
the best we can do and not have any more standard than our own ability
to do our best and our best is going to vary from day to day depending on our energy and
our tiredness and life circumstances and this wonderful
sincerity of living this practice the best we can and uh seeing it as a
training seeing it as something that we're slowly developing over
time so to assume a meditation posture and that also is a training your
body is slowly shifting and changing over time as you repeatedly enter into your
posture some people talk about developing a yoga Body by how we
meditate and the body itself will make subtle shifts stretch become stronger in
particular medit ways that support this posture it's a training in posture
meditation posture and to lower the
Gaze close your eyes
and see if you can adjust your attitude sitting
here to from whatever attitude you find yourself sitting
in to an
attitude of getting ready to
train to do your best at being here
an attitude of being at ease with non
Perfection as a training you can't be perfect
already there has to be imperfection for training to have a role in our
life and so an attitude of being great ious generous
kind shifting from any UNH wholesome attitude we
have to at least a mild wholesome attitude of Good
Will and then beginning the training by tuning in attuning yourself with a body
breathing breathing sits at the Nexus of life itself in so many different ways
Nexus of our emotions our mind our body our external world
and to sit there gently quietly attuned to breathing the body
breathing to give yourself a little more fully over to breathing you might take a few long slow
deep breaths just enough so it remains
comfortable relaxing on the
exhale for
then letting your breathing return to
normal and for a few minutes
here if there's anything happening for you which is more compelling than
breathing you're thinking a lot there's emotions and feelings
Body Sensations sounds around you be aware of
them while accompany those experiences with your
breathing breathe with them breathe through
them where the we're an emphasis on breathing right
in the middle of these other experience es is a training and not being reactive or
caught and these other things that are happening breathing is like a massage
that softens the pull the
attachment the way that we might be bothered by something else
just breathing with it a training and allowing things to be
for
for for
and then in the middle of all things Center yourself more
fully on the body's experience of
breathing wherever in the body the breathing is easy is to attend
to let there be a resting point there resting
or sent centered on the
ballast of the body breathing a
training in staying present a training in beginning again
when your Wonder off a
training and not being bothered by whatever is happening
that instead of being bothered being aware
for
for for
and then as we come to the end of this sitting to gaze upon the world
as an imperfect place no expectations of things being
perfect but for us to practice
train and gazing upon that in an unbothered kind way
here to support ourselves our
world to see it all as a work and
progress and for us to contribute the best we have to
offer to improve and benefit the welfare and happiness of of all
beings may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and May may we engage in a
training and a development and a growth that that can be the case
[Music]
thank you
so at this talk I offer the fourth discussion about introduction to Buddhist
ethics and the emphasis for today today is on
training that the or orientation that the Buddha had on becoming ethical being
ethical is that it's a training a continual training uh to be as ethical as we can
to live as harmlessly as we can and this idea of training is very
different than the idea of uh right or wrong or or Perfection and imperfection
or um you know um uh you know that there's absolute
morality we are measuring ourselves against the the way that the five
precepts are worded in in uh in Buddhism is that they're worded to be trainings
rather than committing to not killing it's uh I commit to train and not
killing I commit to train in not taking what is not given I commit
to um or I engage in it's not even the word commit might even not even be Nepali
maybe that's a strong kind of Western tendency I have to insert a a little different idea of Ethics um but it's uh
I engage in the practice of training I Eng engage in the training steps
sikam um and uh so the
um uh the emphasis on training and training implies that you
need to train you need to cultivate and develop and so uh uh rather than
being all or nothing we're working towards something we're developing ourselves and it's not develop not
working towards Behavior necess necessarily but more deeply training the
heart and mind in such a way that we live uh ethically we live a life of
non-harming uh and we live a life that's wholesome that's ethically beautiful
because of the quality and nature of the heart uh it's not the external
formalities that we're trying to live by and uh but rather to be transformed on
the inside so being ethical is a natural expression of who we
are so the training is uh the uh training ourselves to appreciate and
develop the inner qualities that support ethics the learning how to lessen and
maybe even eliminate uh the strong forces within compulsions within
attachments within that lead to unethical behavior and to replace those with
wholesome be wholesome uh attitudes wholesome orientations within so that
those wholesomeness naturally get expressed in Behavior which is what we'd
call ethical um and so but training means that we have training to do we um we
want to kind of begin to um uh understand that we're trying to
develop ourselves cultivate our eles more than we're trying to adhere to
ethical strictures uh to do to know what to do that's right and then behave accordingly
might actually override and do a kind of violence to be a strong language to who
we are what's going on inside and so an ethical life that's really based on a
strong emphasis on mindfulness strong emphasis on awareness self-awareness so
we see and know what's going on inside so that we've healed some of the unresolved issues and emotions and
challenges that we have on the inside not to override them sometimes I had the
impression that some of the people who uh live um uh their behavior is is
strongly or uh Guided by the wording of the precepts um are trying to best fit
into that Behavior Uh sometimes are overlooking and maybe even running away from or
avoiding uh unresolved issues or deep forms of of something inside that needs
to be healed uh rather than um doing the healing taking a good
look and resolving what's going on deep inside so that the ethical training in Buddhism is not just be training in what
can be seen as ethical behavor Behavior but really involves looking more deeply
inside of ourselves to what needs to be resolved or work with or liberated within us so in that sense um the
precepts sometimes are seen as mirrors that we see ourselves ethical guidelines
in Buddhism we call them guidelines not rules or Commandments are seen as
mirrors so if we go up against um uh you know wanting to kill someone or har
someone if we go up against wanting to take something not given or involved in
sexual be Behavior which maybe causes harm to others uh or breaks the
precept that we're stopping to wait wait a minute what's going on here with me
not wait a minute I'm being a wrong person but rather wait a minute um I think there's something for me to check
in to find out about myself understand myself so it's a training of turning
inward to see what's really going on here and clarifying that and maybe
transforming that into something that we feel really good by uh really um uh are
nourished by it's wholesome something that we begin feeling is beautiful and um and so that we have a
reference point for how wonderful it is how delightful it is to live a life of
non-harming the um so um so to think of Ethics as being
involved something we train in rather than something that's either or and I
think this is a very generous attitude towards ourselves because we're not expected to be perfect ethically perfect
uh what we're expected to do if anything is to uh be sincere in doing the
training doing our best we can and if somehow we we mess up somehow we don't
live up to what we're training for then rather than spend a lot of time berading
ourselves or or being uh uh caught in in the remorse uh the idea is to take an
honest look at what happened um we look at our mistakes we look at how we've been unethical to learn from it so we
can uh do better in the future training has a lot to do with being forward-looking not being stuck in the
past we learn from the past past we learn from our mistakes so that we can
do better in the future but the emphasis is on let's see how we can do better to be inspired to be motivated yes uh I
will try now to do better and sometimes we have to restate that intention many
times a day okay well that was didn't work out well but I will try to do better as opposed to justifying what we
what we did you know it's the other person's fault they deserved it or something um it's always kind of looking
at our elves and can we do better and how do we train how do we um become a
person who naturally is going to be an ethical person and
um so one of the interesting things about this for um is that the
Buddha uh in these training precepts like you know not killing not stealing
not involved in sexual misconduct not lying and not engaging in
intoxication that um for late people there's there's as far as I know I've never seen any teachings of the Buddha
that um describes or provides punishments for people if they break the
precepts the Buddha didn't have a relationship with lay people that he was in a place that was his job or his
orientation to um to somehow intervene and and uh judge people that
way or to to uh punish people or to uh
advise that these people should be punished in any kind of way for being unethical his monastic Community had
institutional ethics Behavior which there were consequences for and things had to happen in order for the monks to
kind of be in good standing or have Harmony in the community but um uh and
we have in our society institutional ethics we have things that uh our
government wants and and uh different institutions we're part of have ethical codes of
conduct and um but Buddhism has codes of
training and uh and there's no sense in Buddhism that there's some kind of
Buddhist idea that you're a terrible person or bad person and you will
somehow be punished by the Buddhist Church or something like that or the Buddhist Church has a role in doing that
kind of punishment um there might be institutional reasons why
a Buddhist Community might decide on certain things but from Buddhism itself that doesn't come from doesn't come from
Buddhism uh rather what the Buddha was involved in was to continue putting
people away from living an UNH wholesome life a harmful life and training to live
a good life training to live an ethical life and training means that uh sin for
training is cultivating ourselves developing ourselves um uh growing ourselves into
something different and that's a slow process and it's a wonderful process and
it's a really worthwhile process to um and it's possible and this is part of
the good news of Buddhism is that the heart the mind is valuable it is it can
be changed and it can be changed for the better and uh and that involves practice and so
another synonyms for training is practice we practice we're practicing something so we get good at it uh we
practice so we develop proficiency develop skill in what we're doing and so
there's Proficiency in being ethical one of which is um to engage in
ethical reflection some of the issues we're involved in our life are e ethically
complex and uh it's not obvious what the least harming thing is that we can do
and so developing a training ourselves to begin reflecting on principles
reflecting on consequences thinking out and and uh is part of uh I think a wise
life to train ourselves to be able to wisely reflect about um the ethics that
uh impact of our lives our decisions how we we vote different
things so an ethical life is not just simply a life that lives by the precepts
but in a complex society that it's also being able to U uh be deeply reflective
about uh what is going on for you know in this wider world of ours so it's a training we grow into
being ethical and I think that's been one of my great joys of practice is to
slowly um maybe way pretty slow um but to slow grow grow in kind of an ethical
sensibility grow in an ethical Clarity and wisdom that uh about how to live and
where to come from in such a way that our heart and our minds become our best
friends we like it there we enjoy ourselves because uh we know that we're
not oriented towards causing harm to anyone self or others we've trained oursel that way to live wisely
effectively in this world uh with a way that is ethical wholesome beautiful and
beneficial for all beings so um so the theme so far for
this week as foundations for Buddhist ethics is the importance of non-harming the importance of
wholesomeness wholesome qualities developing wholesome States um looking at the issues of
Ethics from the point of view is it wholesome or UNH wholesome or skillful and or unskillful then Wednesday
yesterday I talked about beauty um this this sense of inner
beauty that can be developed that's closely connected to uh being
ethical and then today the idea of training in it all that is something we train in and develop over time and then
we have one more talk tomorrow on the foundations of Buddhist ethics so thank you very much for this
chance to talk about this and um and I hope that uh you find
Opportunities to train today may you might think ahead into into the day and
think about situations that might be challenging for you and how might you train to enter into those into those uh
situ situations with a uh uh so that you train in being ethical or maintaining an
inner beauty your wholesomeness in what you do thank you