good morning folks good day good evening whatever time it is for you where where
you're located in the in the world and again I'm really happy to be
here with you this week while Gil's teaching and retreat at at IRC or
Retreat Center in Santa Cruz and I think uh
here it is the top of the hour and let's sit
together so I can hear you all adjusting your posture as the chairs squeaking and
cushions moving so if we were in a hall
together so uh as I suggested yesterday you know taking taking a posture that
allows you to stay connected to your experience whether you're sitting on a
chair or a cushion or lying down possibly standing up that's a completely
legitimate posture for for meditation um really key into
what's what happening in the body is there upright
lightess is there uh
alertness along with a sense of relaxation so you might just
scan scan for attention to any of the kind of Habitual places that you
know you you carry it and see if you can let that just
relax a little bit ease up as much as possible
those common areas in the head and neck and
shoulders the belly sometimes the chest can
be contracted so the breath doesn't flow well
just taking a little journey around the body to see where there's tension and seeing if that that can ease
up we want a a a posture that really supports us being present that supports
being aware of what we're experiencing in the body and in the
mind and I I encourage you just to to revisit any
habitually uh tight places in the body occasionally during the sit just letting
them soften if possible each
time just becoming aware of what it's
like to be sitting here
be meditating preparing to meditate however
you think of it
perhaps you can hear the the beep beep of
the the garbage truck outside my
house Tuesday Morning
special one sound can just be heard
it rises and it
passes and I I invite you to let your breathing be at the Forefront of your
awareness for for a time this
morning the the rhythm of the of the breathing
be a a help to settling the Mind settling the body if that works for
you think that the rhythmic aspect of the breath can can help to calm the
whole organism both both our minds and our
bodies
e
e e
our practice of mindfulness mindful awareness is
uh is to know our experience as it
unfolds excuse me and become more and more intimate
with our our lived EXP experience to really know it to know our
bodies to know our minds it's quite simple our our
experience can be known just as it
happens so let let let the mind be awake aware and uh and whatever is arising
within you whether it's uh bodily sens Sensations other than the breath
sensations of breath thoughts emotions movements of energy tingling
pulsing just let it all be known whatever is
rising and if you find yourself not knowing but just lost in thought can
always just turn the awareness back to whatever
is
arising and we get more and more closely more and more
intimately
e
e e
even confusion and distractedness can be known they show up
the Dharma asks us to to stay
present and when we get lost soon as we notice
it we become present again and each time is just a simple a
simple activity here again knowing
each time is simple and over time we get lost less
frequently and become present again more more
quickly we're practicing
staying and as we learn to stay Our Lives open up to
us we receive
them
e
e e
this is our life sitting we're lying down we're
standing breathing
body mind and heart all in the same
place Sensations coming from the
outside like temperature and pressure Sensations just generated
within the body
sounds breath
thoughts emotions
moods it's all here and we can be open to all of it
right now
our practice invites us to become so intimate with our entire
life every bit of
it to know it with a kind
regard
e
e e
[Music]
for e
I was uh was looking at the chat just now so nice to see the the greetings and
so many names are familiar to me and I'm seeing your names here before of
course in the chat and also from Retreats and other programs IMC and IRC
and and also from my home s here in Santa Barbara it's a delight really I'm so
happy again to be part of this sa this week ael's teaching at IRC
so um uh yesterday I uh I introduced the theme for uh for this week which is a
list of of six qualities of the Dharma qualities that all point to the Dharma
being empirical being something that's evident uh in our experience
discoverable through uh through practice and life experience not something that
we simply learn from hearing others or from reading books the Dharma it comes
alive in us through our practice through living our lives through paying attention to our
lives really close attention and I said yesterday that I'd
be relating these six qualities to a list of capacities that support what is
um called performative literacy an ability to read uh difficult texts in a
skillful way that leads to deeper understanding
so uh long long ago many years ago when I was young uh I was in an English
teacher credential program at at uh UCSB here in Santa Barbara and I had a professor Sheridan
Blau who is um a just a very passionate
uh supporter of investigating how people learn especially about how people learn
to read and write skillfully and then teaching them how to do
that and uh over 40 years ago he wrote a paper that is still uh cited today by
those who train teachers he actually still is a uh active he's at the
Columbia Teachers College now in um in New York City and this paper that he
wrote it identified this series of capacities of skills that those who are
what he called successful readers of difficult texts display and they're all
ways of relating to what's being read and I think that each of them also
describes ways of relating to our experience that are really supportive of
recognizing uh these qualities of the Dharma that uh that we're going to be looking
at so I each of us um human beings on this planet could be called a difficult
text you know I think we're all complex beings with with so many threads of
conditioning that have affected the way we see and approach all of our life
experience including the way we see and approach the Dharma in our practice and
I think we are texts that are definitely you know worth reading and learning and
reading well so the first two in the list of
qualities of the DAR Karma um are that it is well proclaimed and it's visible
here and now well proclaimed swato taught skillfully you know in a
way that people can relate to um in a way that they will listen to and put
into practice that can serve them serve us all the way along the path beginning
to end remember good in the beginning good in the middle good at the
end and then visible here and now stico
so it's not just some promise about understanding the Dharma in the future but it's accessible to those who are
willing to look who make the effort to pay attention the Dharma is seen by us
in our experience as we practice here and now you know I was trying to point
in in the meditation to that uh that's what we do we look at what's
going on within us and we see it and we come to see it more and more clearly
here and now it's not just described somewhere you know that we're to take on
faith we see it
so examples of where we see it you know excuse me I always have a frog my
throat it's like my continual Companion now at this point in in my
life so Gil one time spoke about these qualities of the Dharma using the uh
example of having a pebble in your shoe that's causing pain with every step you
take so a pebble in the shoe that's something pretty obvious something that we can see here and now and the solution
removing the pebble is pretty obvious too unless we're unless we're seriously
distracted we don't need a lot of mindfulness to see that problem and its
solution but more subtle kinds of pain and stress might require um a bit more
attention for example uh maybe I I text a friend uh suggesting that we get
together have a have a meeting see each other and the friend doesn't respond and then um maybe some
sense of being ignored or unappreciated arises and uh and I might
make an assumption that uh my friend just doesn't want to see me and then
some resentment might arise out of that and if I don't notice what's happening
pretty quickly there might also be memories of other times as friend try
seemed to ignore me or wasn't kind or you know all that kind of
associative thinking that can happen and I can get lost in a in a maze of
speculation and blame but if I'm actually looking if I'm being mindful I
can see pretty quickly before any spinning out and recrimination or all
kinds of other unproductive thought that I'm PR I'm projecting meaning onto the
situation I'm making an assumption and that that assumption really is the s s of the dooka I'm
creating for myself and so there's the Dharma right there seeing the arising of Dua when
there's resentment when there's defensiveness self-righteousness impatience any of those kind of niggling
things that arise in daily life I can see them and when I'm mindful of
resentment for instance sensing into how it feels quickly not it doesn't take a
long time how it robs me of my peace seeing immediately oh I've just my mood
has changed when I see the clinging the contraction in the mind and I'm able to let go that's visible also right here
and now both the arising of the Dua and the ceasing of the Dua are plainly
visible right where they happen and uh to bring in the um
capacities from the literacy essay the first skill that's list listed in the essay is a capacity for sustained
focused attention so you know it's pretty clear I think the relevance of
that to our mindfulness practice to the ability to see clearly in order to develop mindfulness
we need to sustain focus on on what's arising and uh Blau uh points out in his
uh in his essay that often students who complain that they can't understand a
text assume that it's because they just don't have the intelligence or the skill
to understand it when the problem is actually that they just haven't given it
close sustained attention and this is really just really
resonant for me in relation to seeing the Dharma here and now I think so so
many of us humans are just so used to taking for granted that what we're
thinking and feeling is simply how things are the correct picture of our life we have to be trained and our
practice trains us of course to look more closely we assume without actually
looking and our practice is just you know it's a training in looking more closely looking Beyond
assumptions so we learn to be more attentive to be more mindful in order to
see the Dharma here and now in our experience and new meditators you know
trying to develop mindfulness they often complain that when they're when they're sitting when
they're trying to practice their minds just go crazy thinking nonstop and often
they imagine that means that they can't meditate just like the students that
Blau speaks of who imagine they can't read difficult texts students can have the expectation
that simply being able to read should result in deep understanding just you
know the simple ability to read and meditators can have a similar expectation that simply closing our eyes
and deciding to pay attention to the breath or whatever uh we're attending to
that staying present staying connected becoming mindful will just
happen but I think we all know that what's needed is developing this
capacity for sustained focused attention and we learn to stay by coming
back of course again and again that's how we develop the capacity Minds really like to think you
know and after 20 years I think it's probably it's maybe it's even more than 20 years of web surfing and swiping left
and swiping right and following links from one topic to another modern minds
are way more distractable than they were in the past I think so it takes more
effort to to develop this capacity but the only way to develop it is to
practice coming back again and again and another of the of the
capacities in blouseless that's re related to this is a tolerance a tolerance for failure a
willingness to reread and reread again and you know that's what we're
doing when we you know we often talk about cultivating uh continuity of
mindfulness trying to string the moments of mindfulness together really staying present and this is the key to that not
giving up when our mind wanders when we're sleepy or bored when we really
would just rather go do something else we don't give up on cultivating
mindfulness because our minds like to chatter I think it doesn't usually take
too long for new meditators to recognize that that it's not just in meditation
that their minds are pretty much out of control it's the nature of the mind to
just do its own thing to think and plan and react and reflect on its own time
schedule and in daily life if we aren't engaged in some activity that uh
requires a lot of focused Attention our minds will usually just wander where
they want coming to realize that's the case
is often a really big motivator for us uh for many of us to develop more
mindfulness those of us I think here in this worldwide Sana we didn't give up
because our minds have minds of their own as Jack cornfield used to say maybe
still says instead we we saw the need to develop steadiness a capacity for
sustained attention and we came to recognize that the way mindfulness
actually gets established in the mind is due to our willingness to fail at it
again and again to keep returning to our present moment experience learning to
stay learning to stay that's what pemma children calls it and it it comes after
not staying many times you know failing to stay and then the Dharma can really
reveal itself to us we recognize that it was always right here visible here and
now we just weren't paying very good
attention and uh as we more and more develop the habit of paying attention
the Dharma becomes more and more visible to us we learn to read our experience
more skillfully to become more and more intimate with it to understand it in a a
in more uh a deeper more subtle ways I'd like to uh I'd like to close
this morning with a um a reading of something I'm sure probably a lot of you have heard it before something that's
often read in Dharma talks and Dharma situations it's called autobiography in
five short chapters by Porsha Nelson chapter
1 I walk down the street there's a deep hole in the
sidewalk I fall in I am lost I'm helpess
it isn't my fault it takes forever to find a way
out chapter two I walk down the same street there's
a deep hole in the sidewalk I pretend I don't see it I fall in again I can't
believe I'm in the same place but it isn't my fault it still takes a long
time to get out chapter 3 I walk down the same
street there is a deep hole in the sidewalk I see it is there I still fall
in it's a habit My Eyes Are Open I know where I am
it is my fault I get out immediately chapter 4
I walk down the same street there's a deep hole in the sidewalk I walk around
it chapter five I walk down another
street so mindfulness allows us to see the hole
and to see the way to avoid falling in it's visible here and now right here
right now so that's what I have for this morning
and I thank you for your attention and we'll continue tomorrow looking at the
the third and the fourth qualities of the Dharma and uh and some skills that
really support uh them coming alive in us so again thank you have a have a
lovely uh rest of your day see you tomorrow