greetings good day
Alaska yeah good people good friends checking
in from all over and thus We Begin the day and
today returning to this theme of
the understandings that arise in the meditation as we practice and that as I've been saying
may bring a smile to our faces that Echoes that that reflects the Buddhist Smile as we see in much of the
iconography of Buddhist practice around the world and today the uh knowledge that
arises is the uh that it's the wise the
noble the uh those of good heart who engage in this
practice and so want to sort of uh celebrate the community of
practice that we that that support our practice and and to which we give our
support something that arises in the meditation is that this community of
practice is wholesome and supportive and uh helps us
as we develop and deepen our our
practice so let's sit together in meditation I'll guide just a little bit
this morning and as we close the eyes bring
our attention Inward and downward connect with the breathing with the body with the perhaps with the weight of the
body the the the settledness of the body we can connect too with the
Simplicity the slow pace and the uncomplicated
nature of the body's knowing sensing of
experience just as a way to whatever we've been up to so far this day slowing
down simplifying and balancing and rebalancing our attention
and as we settle into our own meditative place or
space today we can bring attention to this community of practice that
meditates together these mornings
and perhaps feeling the benefit of that support for what is our individual
Private Practice feeling that
the experience we meet in our practice the challenges we feel and also some of
the lightness the ease that comes with our practice is shared in this community of
practice and that both the challenges we face and
the lightness and ease are supported by this
community sometimes when we meditate together in a physical
space and we open the eyes after we finish a period of meditation and we
look around and uh if we're meeting the Gaze of
others we may exchange a smile SM it's a smile of knowing that comes
from the meditation experience something deep that comes up that knows that this
companionship this camaraderie this partnership or partnering in the path is
wholesome sometimes we know very little about our Dharma friends
people with whom we meditate but what we do know and something a knowledge that arises by
itself from the meditation as per this week's teachings there's the knowledge
that we are facing some of the
same challenges that we're experiencing some of the same ease or
peace and that by doing this together in
community we support one another's
practice so today the smile that can come up in our meditation with this understanding I'd
like to suggest that we can bask in this glow of what is
a a shared Act of generosity in our practice
we generously give our support to one another by showing up to practice
together and then we open up and receive that support from
others and this can be a knowing that comes up in the meditation sometimes it's hard to ask
for sometimes it's difficult to ask for help or support
and in this community that's part of what we give is
an openness to receiving the support of one
another in the path of practice anyway and see if you can feel
the community today even if mediated in this Thoroughly Modern postmodern way
through devices and screens and
electrons feel other people sitting other people at ease other people
struggling other people willing to give time and attention other people willing to
receive and see if perhaps a gentle inward smile arises
e
e e
so as we move toward the end of this sitting
period we might reflect again
on the beauty of a community that gathers to
practice to support one another to receive the support of
others we might reflect that in this community
practice we join the Buddha
and other awakened ones in the meditation
practice it's a vast Community people who've practiced in these Buddhist
Traditions people who seek to see clearly to open the heart
and it's a knowledge that arises from within the meditation that this
goodness that's possible this ease this this place for the mind to
rest that this is shared by others
who Orient themselves toward freedom
there's a knowing that arises that this meditation is practiced
by people like ourselves
who have become aware of a mind or heart that wants to be free
our acknowledgement of this understanding that arises in the meditation strengthens our own practice
and also strengthens the
community and let's end the meditation by committing ourselves to not making it
an exclusive Community but one that that's
inclusive we don't know where people are on the path we know that all people like
ourselves have their quirks their idiosyncrasies their
warts their shortcomings their
failings their rough
edges and we can expand our care to meet all of
them may all the people in the community of practice may all the people in the larger Community affected by our
practice together know some benefit from this
goodness of heart this ease in the
mind may all beings be free of suffering may all beings be
free for
good morning again friends good afternoon good day good evening
even depending on where you are and what salutation is appropriate
welcome today I'd like to continue with the the third of the five knowledges
that this particular text tells us arise for
us in our EXP experience of the meditation all we all we need to do is
notice that along with the meditation as we deepen
it there arises an understanding that the pleasant the pleasure of the meditation is
wholesome that was Monday that it um is good now and good
in the future yesterday and today that um we're we have the
great Fortune of practicing along with others who share a commitment
to to being Freer being awake or more awake in the
world and um The Meditation the smile that arises
the Buddhist smile is uh a recognition of the the shared experience of the
meditation and the the act of generosity uh that brings us together to
practice together so a couple comments on on this
and again I'm just going to reread the just with focusing on today's
understanding but I think it's useful to hear the opening encouragement the encouragement is
to develop a meditation that's described as
Limitless to deepen the practice to cultivate great collectedness and great
Stillness great ease in the mind and the text goes on to say that
when we do this as we are alert and mindful that is as we pay attention to what's coming up
in the meditation five knowledges arise for us
personally and the third of these is that this meditation is practicing
by um well-meaning good-hearted people and that it
includes the fully awake and the
Buddha when we immerse ourselves in this Community
Practice one of the understandings that arises is that we are in good company you know with one
another and also with others who've practiced this practice before
including the Buddha so that when we as the phrase is
and as I titled this Dharma talk Sunday when I Was preparing titles when we
associate with the wise when we come together with other
practitioners we're in the company too of the Buddha and others who've become
fully awake in this practice we enter what's referred to sometimes in the
texts as the Buddha's
dwelling sometimes practitioners ask why did the Buddha continue meditating after
Awakening and it's an interesting question many
ways to answer it but in a sense uh from Once
awake the Buddha's mind is always in this deep meditative state that sees
clearly it's a place where the means and the ends are the are the
same and that settling into this Pleasant abiding of the
meditation as we said in the last couple days produces good outcomes helps us in
our actions and interactions um and it also keeps us in touch with
what it's like to be more awake it's a way of practicing
Awakening practicing being present for our experience in a way
that's non-judgmental doesn't isn't filled with projections and
attachments in which the heart little by little becomes fully open
it's also said that the Buddha continues to meditate after Awakening out of compassion for all beings that is as a
way to support others on the practice sorry others on the path and this I
think um is uh something that we keep alive when
we practice together this commitment to helping one another in our practices and
by extension helping all beings so yeah this is a lovely
community that we practice in community of people who share some dedication to
being more awake in the world meeting experience with a with the heart
that's always opening more what could be sweeter
right just as sometimes people ask why why did the Buddha keep meditating after
Awakening sometimes asked why do meditators meditate together it's kind
of a practice we do alone you know when we close our eyes or leave our eyes open
when we enter the meditative experience we're very much in our in sort of a the
internal the inner life as Gil sometimes calls it attending
to uh what's going on in the realm the arena of the inner
life and uh why do this together uh why do it in this fashion
right mediated over great distances by devices screens and
electrons and uh today I'm suggesting that uh we do it as a we do it as a way
uh we do it as as an act of generosity and we can receive which is hard to do
sometimes we can receive that generous uh impulse from others who practice
together with us in this community there's a fun story that some
of you I'm sure familiar with uh
that is is a helps us understand a little bit what happens with when we
practice in community when we benefit from the
companionship the camaraderie of practice on the path and when we we give our share when we contribute to the
support of others in the in the path of practice um one day goes the story and
I'm just going to sort of remember it uh off the top of my head one day the
Buddha and his longtime attendant probably a a cousin of the Buddha man
named Ananda are sitting alone together on a hill overlooking the plains of the
ganes and um Ananda sometimes on these occasions when he and the Buddha are
alone will share uh some of his Reflections uh or insights with the
Buddha and Ananda says on this particular particular occasion something like venerable one dear
teacher it seems to me upon consideration that half of the spiritual
life is good friendship good companionship good camaraderie
ship for good comradeship and uh I mean when you speak
in insight to the Buddha you're probably uh pretty uh you you're a little cautious
in advancing a view of this sort and so Ananda is probably a little
taken back when the Buddha says not so Ananda don't don't say
that um and the Buddha says far from being something like this far from being
half of the spiritual life spiritual friendship is the whole of the spiritual
life good friendship good companionship good comradeship
and the Buddha means several things by this the what we from what we understand of the historical Buddha uh among among
the idiosyncrasies we pick up and this personality is the uh the light in word
play and the Buddha is saying here that um that this practice in community this
practice with others is he's saying think for sure that this is an extraordinarily important part of the
practice and he's also saying that uh he
is that spiritual friend with whom by extension we all
practice Ananda for sure but also um Millennia
later ourselves so when we engage in this
community of practice and part of what brings that smile that inward smile something that arises in the meditation
with this understanding is that when we practice together with other people dedicated to
Awakening other people dedicated to opening the heart as fully as we can that we are in
the presence of the Buddha that this meditative EXP
experience that we settle into uh along with its pleasure along
with is pointing toward its onward leading nature I had to check what I talk about
yesterday it has this characteristic too of bringing us into the community of
um Millions hundreds of thousands many many many practitioners over Millennia
who shared this commitment to the open heart and the free
mind so by extension I think we can say the Buddha the dhama the teachings and
the S all provide spiritual friendship to
us and the meditation when we enter into it in this way this third understanding
arises naturally from the meditation that we're in touch with um very uh very
um that we're in we're in touch with Awakening in the meditation if we pay
attention we find ourselves in the Buddhist dwelling we find ourselves deep in the
teachings in the Dharma where instead of the meditation being a means to an end
it is the end we seek or the end we seek is within it there is ease and Stillness
there is an open heart there to be
cultivated and we find ourselves in the company of other good-hearted people like those here today greeting one
another from around the world or quietly without engaging in the YouTube chat
that's most of us um you know quietly enjoying
company um quietly being
together and I I I I I don't have an ending in mind for today but what I'm
gonna what I'm going to just end with is the memory probably shared by many of us
just experienced this over the weekend took a drive with my adult daughter
who's 40 and we we drove up into the motherload country of
California I was down for a visit and um oh I don't know 20 minutes 25 minutes
in it shoulder toosh shoulder winding up the hills um sort of had this
realization that we were sitting together in companionate
quiet and this I think is how I would
characterize what our meditation can be like in community that sense of complete familiarity with others that's based on
some trust or confidence in their company and some sense that even without words spoken even without um
conversation even without
participate in the YouTube chat but also to all of us sitting together
quietly enjoying the company and noticing in the
meditation um the goodness of the community and maybe recognizing again um
a sense of um a sense of an inner smile
that develops as we recognize that community and it's
blessing so thank you till tomorrow looking forward to it bye