so welcome welcome welcome we are in the second of five day series this week
happy to be with all of you and the Fay series is on these Wellsprings of Dharma
well-being inner and interpersonal well-being so noticing the well-being of
being together with sa of sitting being here
and since we start with a sit I want you to start by noticing if
you're one of the folks who engages in chat notice how it feels to be engaged
notice how it feels to see greetings from old companions long-term companions
new companions on the path and take that into your heart
take that into your heart including
acknowledging the beauty of Love even love
lost so a warm warm heartfelt meta to
all of you especially anyone experiencing loss and
grief and noticing those of you who are tuning into the conversation the
feeling in your heart and letting that spread
through your actions through your thoughts through your body
and then when you're ready turning inward maybe taking that last sip of
tea finding a comfortable
posture softening or closing the eyes
and attuning to any sense of
care Beauty well-being
within if it's helpful noticing the way you feel
supported held by the chair hair or
cushion perhaps your feet in contact with the
floor held by Gravity by the boundless support of the
Earth by the presence of virtual
sa and taking a deep breath or two
longer slower gentle
breaths and allowing the exhale to soften your body heart and
mind into presence being here
and allowing the breathing to be
natural tuning into the felt sens ations of this life's
breath noticing the ambient temperature warmth or cool
weight or
lightness
spaciousness and inviting the body to relax may my body relax
may this heart and mind soften and relax
meeting whatever Rises with respect and
care simple acknowledgement is to
and allowing the breath the body the moment this
awareness to be your
compass allowing the moment to flow
through
e
e e
and in the last five minutes of this meditation the invitation
is to stay grounded in your whole body in this
moment and tune in attune to your emotional
Center perhaps your heart or Heart Center
tuning into to whatever intention brings you to
practice practice together today or in
general be nourished by it
[Music]
then Gathering up any moments of goodness
inner silence mindfulness care
compassion patience any little glimmers of goodness from
this meditation
practice and offering [Music] them to yourself through yourself
out towards the others in This Global sa offering
them friendliness
care kindness
meta knowing as you're offering it that you're also receiving it
then turning your inner gaze outwards to all of the others your life
touches directly and indirectly
and offering them these good wishes
too may they be
safe happy free from inner and outer harm
may they be peaceful no
ease may they be free
radiating these wishes
outwards and letting go of them trusting they will reverberate
through your mind heart and life
and resting in the moment
noticing the quality of the heart and mind In This Moment
thank you for your practice
e e
so dear online s today is the second of five days
dedicated to exploring Wells Springs of Dharma
well-being inner ones and how they flow from our hearts our minds Our
Lives excuse me out to the others in our
lives we'll mostly be talking about the internal part but to keep it in the back of your mind that the
benefits of practice in general and the benefits of what we're talking about
this week they naturally spill over flow into relationships into other
others lives as well to trust that so as I mentioned yesterday sometimes
the Buddha would tell stories about difficult times past
myths and um make recommendations to his
followers in particularly to his practitioners for practicing in a way
that created an inner home a sense of an inner Homeland or field of goodness
and um in this teaching that I'm teaching from he talked about the way
that practi practitioners can cultivate particular dharmic kinds of well-being
and even flourishing yesterday we talked about spiritual power or empowerment a
teaching known as the roads to power today we'll talk about true
beauty and then the rest of the week heart wealth happiness
and freedom so that's the road map and today as by way of introducing this
topic of true beauty inner beauty I'm going to continue a Buddhist myth of
fairy tale that I started actually at Insight Santa Cruz last Tuesday and um it's the story of a
humble beautiful Confident Woman Jasmine the daughter of flower Growers
who based on her confidence kindness and
generosity um meeting King pity he fell in love with her immediately and they
eventually became married and this story happens after that so she's traveling
back to visit her family and the King has a series of 16
horrible nightmares all in one night those kind of nightmares where are
voices sort of yelling or groaning and and it's all kind of confusing and it's
very kind of tormented feeling and emotionally Laden and he wakes up that morning quite
Disturbed and his wife who he's become accustomed to relying on for why counsel
is out of town she's gone so he turns to some of the local soothsayers fortune
tellers um advice givers maybe they're in the court maybe
they're just in the town I don't know and they convince him that his
nightmares portend a terrible invasion of the country with mass amounts of
suffering and that the absolute only way only way for him to
prevent this Invasion and all of this death and suff offering is to hold a big
sacrifice and this is back in the bronze ages this is ancient times
so the king resists this at first but he really really does not want greater harm
to befall his country so he sets his mind on it and he orders preparations to
start to be made so pits are being dug fire stations are being set up the um
animals are being gathered and it's to all this hubub that Jasmine
returns and she looks around and she ask what's going on and someone tells her oh
we're preparing for this Mass sacrifice and she's like oh no no no this is terrible and goes and finds the king and
she can see from how set in his mind he is and how
anxious he is that he's not going to listen to her immediately so she recommends that he go
to the Buddha who he has met before and on her recommendation he
agrees to seek counsel from the one more Sage this last Sage the Buddha and in conversation with the
Buddha the Buddha offers a different interpretation of the dreams one that
points to virtuous behavior and that suffering
result from killing and that that the suffering that he was experiencing may
have been a sense of the suffering others experience when they do horrible
wrongdoings and the Buddha encourages the king not to kill and the King takes his counsel
there's something about the Buddhist Clarity that cuts through his fear and his confusion his agitation and he
returns and he calls off the sacrifice and not not only that he bans the practice of animal
Sacrifice from then on so I tell this story because
Jasmine's role in it as well as the Buddhas are significant not only are
they committed to not killing they encouraged the king not to do this
horrible act and in the Buddhist teachings it's
beautiful very very beautiful to refrain from doing harm and
to do good but what's more beautiful than beautiful is to do good and Inspire
others to do good Inspire others not to
harm so that's the story and in this short talk this inner beauty as by now
you're hearing is about virtuous conduct walking through the world in a way that
is nonharming I won't go into the classic five precepts the guard rails on
Behavior I'll just name them briefly not killing not stealing not engaging in
sexual misconduct not lying and not engaging in harmful
intoxication as important as these conventions are these guard rails
are the focus today is the guiding principle the underlying
intention and that is that we can use a compass an internal compass for the path
of practice for navigating life in P it's the compass of cusa and
ausa skillful or not skillful harmful or not
harmful so wholesome or not wholesome sometimes are the words
used and this simple distinction can be a compass of care that guide behavior
and even decisions guide the journey the true
north of the compass is where wisdom and nonharming
meet so this Discerning factor of wholesome or UNH wholesome skillful or
unskillful is kind of a a form of contemplative analysis it's a
thinking through for a lot of people on certain levels and then as we begin to really take it in it
becomes more of a visceral heart-based gut-based guide for intention intention it's this
way of embodying the great intelligence and wisdom of the Dharma in each
moment it can be a visceral feeling into a friend of mine recently talked about
how for her it's almost more of a feeling in her heart or her body a sense
of not quite right or contraction and that resonates for me as
well it's this kind of subtle not rightness in the
body in the heart that then checks us for a moment
stops oh what's happening here and that can cut through all kinds of confusion
ambivalence flurries of thought or worry or J justification even strong
ambivalence desire or fear it's a powerful form of strength and
discernment and if there's not a strong gut feeling
or heart feeling sometimes dropping in a simple question can be really
helpful will this lead to Greater benefit or greater harm for
myself for the other person for both of us or for everyone
concerned it's that simple that simple
question this kind of respect for non-harming right sizes your
relationship with reality it right sizes our relationship with ourselves with all other sensient
beings and the benefits can be significant the Buddha described ease of
concentration better relationships greater trust in oneself
and greater trust from others a sense of integration inner
wholeness and integrity and finally the Bliss of
blamelessness the Bliss the happiness of not having to worry about having done
something wrong and I'll add because most of us have not lived perfect lives
up to this point that Bliss of blamelessness also spills over into a
sense of self forgiveness there's more and more subtle subtle
levels of mindfulness that come into being in when we start to focus on the inner
beauty of virtue it's a mark of development in the practice that's something that might be barely
noticeable at first like a human ha hair in the hand eventually becomes more like a hair
in the eye o so I'll close with a short Story
another myth ancient times I think ancient India and this is in fact I'm
certain it was ancient India this comes from the Jaa tales and it's about a king
who offered half The Treasure of his kingdom and the Hand of his daughter the
princess in marriage to any man who could steal something without anyone at all finding out about
it this announcement was proclaimed throughout the land and lots of young men started showing up with various
items of stolen perined treasure necklaces chariots the whole thing
saying no one saw me do this no one knows and each time the king would say
forget about it well thanks and people got quite
confused except one day a young man showed up with nothing and he said I
don't have anything and the King saidwell why not and the man saidwell it's not really possible to steal
something with absolutely no one knowing about it because I myself would know
about it and this was the right answer the
King was seeking an air with wisdom and an air with
Integrity so this little story points to the link between discernment
wisdom and the beauty of virtue
for a mature [Music] practitioner virtuous conduct becomes
more and more of a mindfulness practice a wisdom practice and as practice matures
completely it becomes a natural expression of Dharma of maturity and
that is what the Buddha considered the most profound beauty of all thank you so much for your kind
attention tomorrow we will talk about happiness so
stay tuned and thank you for your practice