good morning welcome those of you that are uh watching on YouTube you can see that the
title is poetry of practice 3 those of you who don't know I've uh
earlier done two weeks on poetry of practice so I just want to distinguish
that's what this three is for I think uh the two happened in August of 2023 and
poetry practice one I think was in in April 2023 but I might have those dates
wrong so I'm just going to say a few words about this whole idea of poetry
and then we'll get into a guided meditation and that is that there is
this way in which we can engage with practice that is
uh an emphasis on you know the list the Buddhist list and this certain amount of
technique have these 16 steps of H P Sati or there are the 13 types of uh
practices for mindfulness of the body in the Sati patan you know these types of things and
especially when we are teaching uh five days it's you know it's tempting for
those of us that are in the role of Derma teachers to find uh a list that has five you know it's just a nice
convenient way to do things for five days but which is a perfectly legitimate
way but it kind of then you know gives the sense that maybe the D is all about
this formulaic one through five or these lists so that's perfectly legitimate way
I love to practice that way I do practice that way and I also practice
another way a way that uh invites maybe another
way of engaging with practice another way that's less with
the uh mind and the thinking and more with the
heart different way of relating to our experience a different way of relating
to practice we might say a different way of coming
home it's a way of recognizing or tuning into something that's a little bit
different that our continual grasping of understanding or evaluation
or finding the next moment and where am I in this list or something like that instead there's this way of practicing
we might say with poetry with verse that lets language
touch us in a different way guide us in a different way than
these lists so we'll do a little bit of poetry
of practice this week so this morning I will going to drop in a verse during our
guide meditation I'll lead us to settling a little bit then I'll drop in a verse and then during the Dhat um
we'll talk about the verse and as it happens um this verse is written like a
short story so as I'm saying it it might sound like a short story rather than a
poem it's perfectly fine you might say it's a poem because the poet said it's a
poem and um I'll say the name of the poem and
the poet at the end okay
so again our meditation
posture feeling into the sense of this
moment what is it like to be in this body at this
moment putting aside any ideas of how things should be and tuning into how
things
are is there a way way to inhabit the
body bring a sense of aliveness a sense of
presence to the bodily
experience letting go of any ideas of how things ought to be or you want them
to be but instead bringing some curiosity and some
engagement to how they are
and we set the orientation the
direction of our practice as one of
kindness and okayness can I be okay
however you find the body at this
moment and you be in a body that perhaps has discomfort or
pain can that be okay for this meditation
period e
maybe doing a gentle body scan bringing some care and some
presence to any areas of the body that feel like they could use some
care and presence some warm-heartedness
e e
settling into the sensations of
breathing turning into the experience of
breathing inhales and
exhales as if it were okay as if this were
sufficient right now just to be with the sensations of
[Music]
breathing e
in particular needs to be happening just
noticing the experience of inhales feeling this stretch perhaps in
the
body and the release of to stretch with the exhales
resting knowing a body knows how to
breathe we don't have to make it breathe we don't have to change
it and we allow the breath to be just as it
is
e
e e
if we find ourselves lost in thought we don't have to build a story
about what it means about us as
meditators just very simply gently begin
again with the sensations of breathing
in a relaxed easy
manner
e
e e
to drop in this poem absolutely nothing needs to be
done just allow the words to be
received you don't have to interpret it you don't have to understand it you
don't have to remember it what would it be like to just simply
experience it moment after moment after
moment I'll talk about it in the dant for now just experience
it the poem goes like this maybe I should say it reads like a short
[Music] story not much
chance completely cut loose from purpose it was a young man riding a bus through
North Carolina on the way to somewhere and it began to
snow and the bus stopped at a little cafe in the hills and the passengers
entered he sat at the counter with the others he ordered and the food
arrived the meal was particularly good and the
coffee the waitress was unlike the women he had known she was
unaffected there was a natural humor which came from
her the fried cook said crazy things the dishwasher and back laugh a good clean
Pleasant laugh the young man watched the snow Through the
Windows he wanted to stay in that Cafe
Forever The Cure ious feeling swam through him that everything was
beautiful there that it would always stay beautiful
there then the bus driver told the passengers that it was time to board the
young man thought I'll just sit here I'll just stay
here but then he rose and followed the others into the bus he found his seat and looked at the
cafe through the bus window then the bus moved off down a
curve downward out of the hills the young man looked straight
forward he heard the other passengers speaking of other other things or they
were reading or attempting to sleep they had not noticed the
magic the young man put his head to one side closed his eyes pretended to
sleep there was nothing else to do just to listen to the sound of the
engine the sound of the tires in the
snow there was nothing else to do just to listen to the sound of the
engine the sound of the tires in the [Music]
snow
e
e e
[Music]
but that poem was called Nirvana by Charles
Bukowski Nirvana by Charles
Bukowski so um welcome welcome for those of you who
are joining us late or just joining us here for the Garment or this little
talk Jane hersfield who's a well established poet she's a beautiful po
she some amazing poems and um she's also a Buddhist practitioner and I love this quote that
uh she has she says Science and Mathematics and Engineering exist for answerable
questions poems exist for questions that have no answers but still require a
response I like this this idea that you know poetry is a way of responding but
not in a way like an answer which tends to be you know a I don't know have edges and be really
uh like okay this is the answer this is the truth this is how it is next what's the next thing is poems are a response
and we might say I'm going to say a response of the heart it's a different
part of us that's a resp responding and so one question that we
might have it's natural question with this practice with this tradition is
this idea of Nirvana or nibana this idea of you know what is it
what is it to be awakened what is this about uh Awakening and there's a number
of different ways we can understand in P the word is nibbana in Sanskrit the word
is nirvana the exact same word two different languages so Charles Bowski is
using Nirvana um and in poly and in the poly County
it's but so there's different ways we could say to understand this but maybe I
would say what's more important than
describing exactly what it is is maybe to uh point to the impact it has on
somebody who is experiencing it how are people transformed what is their
experience by attaining narana so staying more with
the empirical the Practical The Experience rather than getting into
metaphysics and philosophical which is just stories right metaphysics and
philosophy or just stories that we're telling ourselves in our mind so instead can we point to what's the
experience and then you know something that we hear a lot um and read a lot if
you explore this idea of uh Nirvana and even in the nibon in the poly Canon it
talks about how it's Indescribable and
ineffable so this poem by Charles buosi who let's just say
he's not known for being a Buddhist practitioner in fact uh he had a colorful life I don't know all the
details of his life but I know enough of it to know that uh he was uh fond of drinking and wasn't known for his uh
following the precepts let's just say but you know he wasn't a Buddhist
practitioner so notice if you can feel into a theme of this poem like the sense
of it maybe the experience of it if uh as I read it again and then I'll I'll say say a few words so again this this
poem is nirvana by Charles
Bukowski not much chance completely cut loose from purpose
it was a young man riding a bus through North Carolina on the way to
somewhere and it began to snow and the bus stopped at a little cafe in the
hills and the passengers entered he sat at the counter with the
others he ordered and the food arrived the meal was particularly good
and the coffee the waitress was unlike the women he had known she was unaffected there
was a natural humor which came from her the Fred cook said crazy things the
dishwasher and back laughed a good clean Pleasant laugh
the young man watched the snow Through the Windows he wanted to stay in that Cafe
forever the Curious feeling swam through him that everything was beautiful there
that it would always stay beautiful there and the bus driver told the
passengers that it was time to board the young man thought I'll just
sit here I'll just stay here but then he rose and followed the others
into the bus he found his seat and looked at the cafe through the bus
window then the bus moved off down a curve downward out of the hills the
young man looked straight forward he heard the other passengers
speaking of other things or they were reading or attempting to sleep they had
not noticed the magic the young man put his head to one side
closed his eyes pretended to sleep there was nothing else to
do just to listen to the sound of the engine the sound of the tires in the
snow I know this poem it touches me there's a so many things that I could
say but um one thing you might say is completely ordinary what I don't get
it why is this called Nirvana it's just some dude hanging out in a
cafe and maybe what if that's exactly what Nirvana is we tend to kind of bring
some of these ideas we might have about heaven or some of these other ideas about what it must mean to be awakened
but what if it's about having a perfectly ordinary life and being
complete content with that ordinary
life no wish for things to be otherwise no insistence that things be different
no little ningling yeah but I want this I don't want that it should be more like this it shouldn't be less like that
instead just being with what is
completely just letting things unfold maybe kind of like a bus that's
going down the hill that's going here and there just trusting like there there's an unfolding of life there's an
unfolding of what's going to happen next without this strong sense of me
controlling things without a strong sense of self making things happen and
ensuring things that go one way and not the other way instead this uh deep trust
this deep intuition this deep sense of things unfolding like I'm using this
expression this uh sense of intuition a
flow of uh life and allowing the life to
flow with us without a sense of this center of it that has to control
everything this Center which is judging this is good this is
bad I love this um there's this sentence in here in this
poem a curious feeling swam through him that everything was beautiful there that
it would always stay beautiful there so this sense of like Beauty and
just the ordinary and we all know things are
impermanent and yet he's saying that they would always stay beautiful there so pointing to no matter what happens
it's beautiful we might use this language
this notion of Grace like everything having this this uh beautiful being
touched by Grace nothing needs to be
different and then I like in the poem he says the young men thought oh just sit
here I'll just stay here so he's sitting and staying here in the present
moment and just that experience because what comes right after the young man
thought I'll just sit here I'll just stay here but then he rose and follow
the others onto the bus so the he is in this appreciation this flow with what's
actually happening but the physical here is changing he going from the cafe and
going in back into the bus and earlier while he was in the
cafe he uh was looking out the window at the snow and then he was uh later he's in
the bus looking out at the cafe and so the the his perspectives are changing
he's in different places and he's looking at things different ways but there's always this we might say this
sense of contentment but contentment with
beauty and what if that's what Awakening is what if Awakening is this sense of
things are as they are and it's like this and it's
okay and seeing the beauty of the moments there's this way in which as
humans we have this sense of we always want things to be a little bit different we're trying to Tumble into the next
moment we're being dismissive of the present moment but what if there is no
more agitation no more restlessness no more sense a complete
absence of the sense of there needs to be more there needs to be more what if there's none of
that it's just this moment and this moment is a sense of perfection sense of
beauty sense of Grace no matter what's
happening there's this way that there's we sometimes we talk about Nirvana as
the absence of greed hatred and delusion so what this means is this
absence of wanting things to be different
is uh seeing things clearly changing the perspective whether it's through the bus
window or through the window of the cafe looking out whatever it
is I'll read this poem one more time again it's Nirvana by Charles
Bowski not much chance completely cut loose from purpose
he was a young man riding a bus through North Carolina on the way to
somewhere and it began to snow and the bus stopped at a cafe in the hills and
the passengers entered he sat at the counter with the others he ordered and the food arrived
the meal was particularly good and the coffee the waitress was unlike the women
he had known she was unaffected there was a natural humor which came from her
the Fred cook said crazy things the dishwasher and back laughed a good clean
Pleasant laugh the young man watched the snow Through the Windows he wanted to stay in that Cafe
forever the Curious feeling swam through him that everything was beautiful there
that it would always stay beautiful there then the bus driver told the
passengers that it was time to board the young man thought I'll just sit here
I'll just stay here but then he rose and followed the
others into the bus he found his seat and looked at the cafe through the bus
window then the bus moved off down a curve downward out of the hills the
young man looked straight forward they heard the other passengers speaking
of other things or they were reading or attempting to sleep they had not noticed
the magic the young man put his head to one side Clos his eyes pretended to
sleep there was nothing else to do just listen to the sound of the
engine the sound of the tire in the
snow I'll say this last little sentence there was nothing else
to do just to listen to the sound of the engine the sound of the tires in the
snow this radical sense of oiness what would it be like for you to
notice and tune into any sense of okayness sense of contentment not uh
fireworks and blist out happiness but just a sense of ordinary
okayness would it be like for you to tune into that
today thank you
wishing you all a wonderful rest of the day
welcome to this week of uh poetry
jie writes I'm looking for it to an extraordinary Ordinary Day exactly thank you that's exactly your
own little poem there extraordinary Ordinary
Day e
sweet to uh read your
comments um asks what was Nirvana the cafe or listening to the sound of the
engine the tires was it both is there a difference what if uh Nirvana is more
a it's not a location or what if it's just an
experience or a relationship to experience Maybe
and I'll see you later in the week with uh some more poems wishing you all a
wonderful day