okay welcome welcome folks uh I got uh the feedback on the
Bell this too quiet I've been ringing the bell at that level for like seven
years this is the importance of feedback it may render differently on YouTube
than when we're all uh on Zoom anyway
I will uh take that into account in half an hour when we are done officially
meditating and um yeah lovely to see uh See all these
names and be with you this week so
um okay let's uh settle in for uh some practice
together
e e
maybe just beginning with u whatever gratitude you
have for having a
path and even though you could say I was
pretty happy before finding
practice there was another way in which life
felt
unworkable that there were
existential questions challenges that I
had absolutely no answer
for and the path didn't answer
everything but it answered
enough and for that
there might be some good bit of
gratitude in your life in
mine so just let the the Gratitude uh you have for your
path just soften your heart as we begin
here
e e
then where the attention goes is much less
important than the qualities of the
attention shinzen Yang defines mindfulness as a threefold
skill set working together concentration Clarity and
equinity the concentration the sense of
stability the stability of the attentional focus the
telescope gazing at the stars shaking
we uh miss the Grandeur of the sky we
stabilize the
attention that means we detect distractors that
go nurture this stability this Fidelity to the object of
attention and
Clarity perceiving phenomena that much higher
resolution could say both temporally and and spatially that we're
perceiving time in thinner
slices we're perceiving the object with greater magnification
higher resolution picture of the breathing or our body or
whatever
the equinity
becoming uh frictionless in the face of
samsara
frictionless even given the tides of pleasant and
unpleasant the tides of change
an we might still have
preferences but equinity Settles the compulsive energies to enact those
preferences for our purposes of Freedom everything becomes good
enough
e
e e
maybe the anchor is your breathing or your body more
broadly maybe it sound
maybe the anchor uh is uh everywhere
nowhere we're cultivating concentration Clarity equinity Moment by
moment undaunted by the
pole of frenzy and
muddiness and
grasping we have some reverence for for the power of those
forces but we're undaunted just humbly Moment by
moment nurturing a kind of alertness and
stability higher resolution fr frictionless
e
e for
sometimes it seems like each moment is freedom beckoning us
and maybe I can't be totally free right now
but I will rehearse my freedom in this
moment I will not underestimate
the Buddha
Dharma
e
e e
don't let your mind to land
anywhere don't give it the security of
conclusions the security of having a place of having a ground of having reference
points having a
story don't give it the security of doubt and
spectatoring don't give it the hope that greed or hate might work out
silent absent walking an empty
road all praise
says
roomy
e
e e
for
[Music]
e
okay so um that's been good good to be with you this
week appreciate it um our
time so uh uh for me getting uh getting
into practice I think uh I saw Jack cornfields P path with heart early in
practice and what I I remember is maybe a chapter or something like that where
he suggested that at the end of our life uh one question will Loom
large did I love well and it was
like that just felt very true and it was sort of like how do I do that what can I
do tell me what to do
and it's a beautiful question and fair enough to wonder what do I
do but it strikes me that uh we we've maybe
overemphasized Cho overemphasized choice and choiceful in
Dharma and sometimes underemphasize the training
Dimensions so we often you know talk about how Dharma
allows us to make wise choices we come to a kind of fork in the road we choose
the healthy the wholesome rather than the UNH wholesome we respond rather than we react we choose Letting Go rather
than holding on and um fair enough fair
enough but it somehow doesn't really capture the flavor of practice for
me and it strikes me that some of the emphasis on choice is about our
preference for control and doing this and a kind of instant
gratification o of uh just giving the agitated energy a
channel into which to flow right because we talk about
being being beingness something like this but a lot of what Dharma teachers
including myself like say is like do these
things and whenever I say something like okay here are four things to do people
just take out their pencils and act like it's the the most important part of what
I'm going to say and I don't mean to belittle it
there's a place for that right
but the training aspects the kind of very quiet accumulation of Merit in the
heart made over a long period of time made by maybe many little micro
choices that strikes me as where the the heart of the Dharma is
and sometimes say that the Dharma is s better at preventing fires than
extinguishing them in other words it it is a training about creating good habits good
momentum elevating the trait level of mindfulness and equinity and love so
that it doesn't feel like a a choice we have to make to love rather than hate
hate is actually off the table but we don't know when that
possibility fell off the the
table if an athlete are being was being coached right in sports match or
something there might be some strategy make these choices do this but mostly it would be about trust your training right
you've been practicing for 20 years right you've been playing basketball for 20 years trust your
body right and so we commit to to
training and part of what that entails is a measure of patience you know that
the impulse to choose something now is that's sometimes right but
sometimes kind of naive we don't have to see everything
change now part of what we're doing is is trusting the logic of the
path the unfolding of the path uh and just making very small gestures of the
heart today not hoping to be totally free of
dukka right now but uh in training ourself in a
Dharma life and part of what that grants us is that we're less compulsive in our
evaluation how am I doing how's it going how free am I right now how much
suffering is is this it's like we're not we're not sampling ourselves every
moment to see how we're doing and in this interpersonal realm
we're not shocked or heartbroken when we get tangled up in the same way we used
to we just recommit to
training the the budha was was not a coup's
counselor or family therapist or organizational
consultant but at the same time so much of what was offered you know so
much of the Buddhist path is a training in loving well this gradual cultivation in loving
well there's really no obviously the Dharma is is aimed in a
sense we could say at freedom but we might also say there's no
part of the Dharma that should make us more annoying to
others you know that's sometimes like my main aspiration like what's your highest
aspiration Matthew it's like I just want to be a little less annoying I know you you all you stayed
through the week so you don't think I'm annoying but a lot of people do I'm trying to be less annoying that's like
my Peak bodh satva vow you know all of the teachings all of the
teachings are a way of um making us
actually uh bringing the the P the practice is
bringing the blessings of this path will inevitably spill into interpersonal life
Sila Samar PA you know ethical training mind
training wisdom this is all a training and loving
well and so CA we train in becoming a kind of
Refuge for others of gradually increasing our ethical sensitivity of
becoming more and more exquisitely attuned to our impact on others
this is um an aspect of CA but also an aspect of our
Clarity and as our ethical sensitivity grows we we feel more um cleanly bad
when we do harm muddled bad guilt and
this whole self story The muddled bad sometimes guilt is just the defense
against the the simple pain of remorse we start to feel cleanly
bad oh that wasn't quite
right no big thing wi uh no just we feel it and we
consolidate Our intention to love well to be careful with the hearts of
others and this Same Love Actually helps us begin to understand the care that
we're worthy of right we won't always get
it but it helps you understand the care the love you're worthy of we learn what
we're worthy of by loving well we don't decide to be good this is
not a choice we become gradually more and more devoted to minimizing harm that
is a training the the the Mind mind training samadi
this kind of broader sense of Mind training that is gradual it has profound dimensions for
our interpersonal life on Wednesday evening was talking
about the place of attention in attention in sexual sexual life
intimate life and attention obviously the training of
our attention has profound place in the whole of our interpersonal
life what does it mean to love is it like the deepest feeling the
strongest commitment is it un ambivalence no no it's not we can love
even with quiet feeling without the strongest commitment with ambivalence we
can love even with that a friend and colleague Mar beler
said um that love is the willingness to pay attention to love a person is to be
willing to pay attention to them it's not more complicated than that actually
paying attention to self or another is Love In
Action Maybe we say like no no no no it's got to be more than that Love's got to be more bells and whistles and
fireworks to love a person is to be willing to pay attention to
them deeply right to be genuinely
willing that's Love In Action when you actually cultivate what what it means to
pay attention you can sense how much love is in
that so we train in the receptivity of awareness we stabilize it we learn to in
this mind training we learn to tolerate more and more energy coursing through
our body and staying poised that's training a lot of the harm we do
interpersonally is when the body is overrun by energy
and we cannot stay poised we train in that
Poise we learn how to deeply melt into the field of awareness to experience
self and other within the same
space our wisdom about um our
existential condition becomes through our clarity through our understanding it
becomes um more poignant it makes love more urgent we learn we learn and then
love becomes more urgent to let anicha truly inform our
love this is a product of learning training in wisdom that we cannot take that in in
one gulp cannot take in a nche in one gulp we train
in living not in light of
immortality but with the understanding of finitude
we live in the light of
finitude n said that truth is a portioned to one according to their
strength
Dharma training makes us stronger makes us
stronger we understand more about craving and love and kindness and re
renunciation if we don't understand that we cannot love well if we don't understand
self-deception and the ways in which much of our life is a confabulation of
greed and aversion it's hard to love well we
are uh stepping out of self deception Rodney Smith
said when we're living in that we confuse ourselves confuse others become
defensive uh we're training in wisdom all of this
is a training and we often look for the kind of
fireworks moments of breakthrough Insight but often we just do not detect
the slow melting of Dua the slow accumulation of the parames of the
the strengths of our heart a function of
training maybe it sounds like all this training yeah but it it it's like isn't
that Baba tanha craving to become so the intricacies of the
Dharma what we can say is uh may it
continue
okay offer this for your consideration and and
uh look forward to uh to uh seeing you somewhere somewhere on the larger Dharma
campus YouTube or elsewhere okay folks you uh you be be
well okay