okay folks uh so welcome yeah nice seeing
names so um yeah let's uh let's let's practice
together um I sort of want to take requests what what to what we sit on but
uh I'll find my way all right let's uh met
in okay
that familiar breath that's
also so fresh
the visual imagery of breathing is often prominent we're feeling our breath but
the subtle visual images even with our eyes closed are like guiding the attention to
the sensations of breathing e
and what if we were surprised that at the end of the in
breath an out breath followed rather than somehow
miraculously another in breath
how do we give ourselves to thinner and thinner slices of
time e
sense of uh intimacy with
the constellation of Sensations that compose our
breathing
for
e
e e
we just let our our breathing awaken the senses
this memory of uh you know putting too
much kind of uh spicy mustard on a spring roll and just blows out
the nasal cavity or something just wide
open that's kind of how the breath can be just for all the
senses even if you're tired
even if it's the end of a long
day e
we elevate a peace above all
else sometimes we abide in peace sometimes we're making
peace making peace with the Loose Ends of the the day or the
life just don't be seduced
by fake
Refuge
e
e e
we forgive our minds for all the
patrolling that they do and all the foraging
foraging in the realm of
thoughts we reconnect with this moment with Dharma
let the breath breathe life
into our attention
just make your home in your breath
it's very soothing when our world of experience
gets simple and small
very SM soothing when uh all
the arrows in our being start to line up in One
Direction and just to be alive is enough just to breathe
together it's enough
for
e
e e
if there's something uh especially sticky in the hard
mind something that uh repeatedly
pulls your attention
maybe good to move into the felt experience of
that stickiness the sense of emot activation in our
body that makes something feel urgent or
draws our obsessional Tendencies
out and maybe we linger with that effective emotional
arousal until it settles a
bit and then maybe it feels inviting to come back to the
rhythm of breathing
for
e
e e
okay so it's uh it's good to say with
you so I thought to to just uh carry on with the theme that uh been developing
at uh the morning morning set skills sets and uh that's if you haven't been
um Dharma and interpersonal life and um I thought to say something about
uh the theme of sexuality and a neglected Dharma topic
and as I was putting together kind of thoughts about this it struck me as
like are the Buddhists going to make this depressing too and by the Buddhist
I mean me and even sex depressing a little bit
maybe maybe a little bit a complicated issue and uh I speak about it knowing
just um the range of experiences and
meaning and beauty and harm and um all of that what's
empowering for one person is very much not that for another it's
um so it's an important caveat on all of this this but uh felt like okay I can say
something about this so to
love to love is to risk and to desire is sometimes to feel
destabilized and I I read somewhere I don't know where don't remember but it said it was
some psychoanalytic writer and they said something like for Freud God was merely
a way of gratifying sexual desire for young
sexuality was a way of expressing a longing for God for the
sacred and I think they're both kind of
right so this is a Zone where
lay life which may or may not but may include sexual relationships it really
must chart its own course and it's not easy to translate
the monastic teachings to this realm and there are some basic
principles of course that are incredibly important harmlessness being obvious but
how to actually enrich and refine SE sexual life that's uh that's
an open question and I have genuine Sympathy for
the impulse to say it's too much it's too complicated sexual desire acts like
a magnet that pulls too many other corrosive forces to the surface
that are painful and even even sex itself which
might be wonderful sexual desire Moment by moment generally
speaking is not Pleasant now monastic many years ago
heard I I heard um say something like characterizing the blessings of the
monastic life referred to celibacy uh the peacefulness of
celibacy and we might say many things about sex but peaceful would not be one
them Leonard um Leonard Cohen um in the last album of his life
singing really about his death uh said uh you don't need a lawyer
I'm not making a claim you don't need to surrender I'm not taking aim I don't
need a lover no no no The Wretched Beast is tame I don't need a lover so blow out
the flame The Wretched Beast is tame and
then there's a kind of opening openness to death and how do we think about that is
that something to celebrate Joseph Goldstein told this
famous story of upand you know the burm Monk and beloved teacher
um was talking about uh sense desire sense craving goes on for 10 minutes in
Burmese and then the translator renders the last 10 minutes with uh four words
lust cracks the brain lust cracks the
brain and I agree with that wholeheartedly
but I don't think that's the only thing lust
does so yes one one must consciously consent to some measure of of suffering
in this realm like a Dua free path is a
fantasy is a a really fantastic uh short
story from liia Davis a story after um after a a brief very intense love affair
the narrator trying to decide if it was quote worth it worth it so he's pricing
everything out everything he loved about her the ecstatic description of passion
and tenderness and care and then it ends and the
breakup and uh Davis writes this this character the narrator I I guess you get
to a point where you look at that pain as if it were there in front of you 3 ft
away lying in a box an open box in a window
somewhere it's hard and cold like a bar of metal you just look at it there and say
all right I'll take it I'll buy it that's what it is because you know
all about it before you even go into this thing you know the pain is part of
the whole thing and it isn't that you can say afterwards the pleasure was greater than the pain
and that's why you would do it again that has nothing to do with it you can't measure it because the pain comes after
and it lasts longer so the question really is why doesn't that pain make you
say I won't do it again when the pain is so bad that you have to say that but you
don't
but we don't and so here we are and can we make the best go of
it and so what what forms of well-being on offer even if we know not that of
course celibacy guarantees its own species of suffering can we consent to the
suffering involved in this whole realm and then look look what are the
possibilities what what kind of forms of well-being are on offer here what forms
of spiritual growth are on offer there are whole Traditions about that that I
don't really know a different scene in the inside world but what are the what are the
possibilities of applying attention to emotional and physical
intimacy attention that kind of most basic
currency of a human life we we know the power of attention when applied to our
breathing or an emotion or meta right we know the power of that
that you do that a certain kind of fidelity just to the
breathing and and a lot can
happen what can happen with attention applied in the
realm of of sexual connection what uh can a kind of trained
open attention do in the context of intimacy how um how intuitive and
embodied and undefended might one be become you know like how completely
might the self melt in this
realm I was talking to a a Dharma friend about this and they wondered like would
as a kind of parallel would a deeply enlightened person feel
grief and they concluded their conjecture was really like yeah
but there would be a freedom in it and that feels right to
me and then they ask like might that also be the case with sexual desire is
that inherently like bondage of some sort or
is it possible to be to experience that in a very free
way is it possible to be free and EXP experience
redeem really redeem desire from the clutches of
compulsivity jezelle Jones um couple therapist and mindfulness person friend
um she said defined intimacy as the the the the willingness and ability to see
and be seen the willingness and the ability to see and be seen and in this realm uh
where we're seeing and being seen in a very deep way you
know and the question maybe is like how unashamed might one
become how unencumbered by a certain kind of self-consciousness might one become how
unencumbered by ideas that create kind of
static when one asks the question what do I
want how unencumbered might we
be sexuality is um you know we do things together right
but sexuality may be like the deepest way of doing something together maybe
raising a child is like that I don't know but of doing doing something
together of coordinating desire and need and
generosity and this is a Zone where the more Supple we get with our roles the
more fluid we can be around power yielding or asserting the yes and no
that I spoke about this morning the more Supple we can be in that uh the more
fluidity there is in the whole realm the
um in other words the sense sense of self um must be flexible to be for us to
be truly available for delight and
connection and there are uh this is also the realm of um where there there can be
a very kind of deep relief from the confines of Duality that is on offer
here where where do I end and they begin you know what what like what what is
what is my desire or Horrors you know it's it gets very Marky
and that sense of being uh confined confined behind one's eyes comes more
and more porous naturally um spiritual approaches
to sexuality tend to emphasize the tenderness and the love and the warmth
and the the nonu non-duality or something like this but uh it's also
a realm of other other kinds of energies it's a realm
where sometimes very usefully anger is diffused or forgiveness offered or nots
untangled somehow better than the words might ever do you know I'm sorry but how do we say
that with our bodies and so in this realm uh
we we must learn to tolerate some measure of
disorientation um disorientation we're playing with very potent forces that's
why the precepts you know around sexual misconduct and harm and all of that so
important this is why um yeah we must be careful with it
because the this Sexual Energy can be like a magnet that draws lots of other
forces to the surface so this is um uh
again the analyst Stephen Mitchell um from uh book can can love last I
think uh the fate of romance over time Mitchell writes um erotic passion
destabilizes one's sense of self when we find someone intensely arousing
who makes possible unfamiliar experiences of ourselves and an
otherness we find captivating we're drawn into
disorientation we tend to want to control these experiences and the others
who Inspire them sustaining romance requires a struggle to resist the
inevitable efforts to draw moving but unsettling experiences under our
control our journey in the otherness of the
other often surprises us with unknown features of
ourselves so wisdom love
maybe sometimes it's just as simple as pleasure but it also can be
wisdom and love soer this for your
consideration and uh please pick up whatever is useful and uh leave the rest
behind okay folks thank you