so good morning everyone and can you hear me all right it's okay out
there so I want to start with a introductory
story to this talk it's a maybe
a teeny story maybe you'll think of it insignificant but it uh represents
something a real a really important turning point in my life so so at some point I spent about 3
years uh doing Zen training at a Zen Monastery here United
States and uh it was quite nice but you know it's kind of you're fully enter into that world it's deep in the
mountains there's uh you know it's 14 miles on a very small steep dirt road to
go into the national for National Forest lands in the middle of which is this
little Monastery and so was completely involved in that world for three
years and Zen training is done with a lot of ritual and there's a lot of ways
in which you uh you engage your body so for example if you want to step into the
meditation hle you you always have to step in with a particular foot first and
you can't just step in without foot and they just kind of casually walk around you have to have your hands in a
particular way as you walk through the meditation Hall and there's a a particular way of walking through the meditation you can't just take the
shortest route to your seat uh you have to kind of take a certain route around the place and and when you get to your
seat you just plop yourself down and kind of pick your nose a little bit and get
ready you would um uh you bow to your seat and then you turn around and you
bow away from your seat and then this particular way in which you turn around and sit down on the seat and and then
classically in then there's a particular posture you sit in and I mean most classically you sit in full Lotus
upright most people don't sit in full Lotus but half Lotus or quarter Lotus or
something but there's a very particular you it's very important that your back be straight and um and um and so there's
all these you know ways of being and being with other people you walk through the Montery and you see someone um you
bow to them and uh ideally you would stop and just stop and bow and so it you
know I think I counted how many times I had to Bow before 10:00 in the morning
and I think I got up to 54 boughs and all the things and that was not including all the people I had to stop
to on the path to bow to and there were some people including me occasionally
who would see someone coming down there and we'd go the other route so we wouldn't have we wouldn't have to
bow but the point being that uh a lot of the day was choreographed and they were
choreographed with these particular forms kind of ritual forms you took and they're quite powerful to to live in it
requires a lot of mindfulness and it requires a lot of presence and the the
some of these things you do with your body carry with them certain kind of attitudes certain kind of feelings that
uh affect you for one it's always done somewhat uh with intentionality and a
certain kind of of fullness you're really there to do each thing and so it
your sense of participating with your life comes alive in that kind of world
uh because you know you don't just sit back well you know go to the zendo when I feel like it and you know stumble in
and might really want to be here and you know you might have those thoughts but your body has to like really be there
and participate and and uh putting your hands together like this and all those bows we do there something even if you
don't want to Bow there's something about that movement that will probably affect a lot of people maybe different
people in different ways but for me it it developed a lot of uh gratitude a
sense of appreciation and and through the day heav bows little doing them
every day so many times through the day and for weeks and months on end
something begins to shift inside the same thing has happened happening for most of you in everyday
life uh in all the little movements that you make in your
body in your voice and your thing and and you're reinforcing something so if
you are going around kind of uh you know just kind of like uninterested in life
and you know everything you do you kind of do kind of like oh I'll get to it oh oh oh it's too hard oh who wants to do
this this is a drag or why we have to do this all those little voices might have
some value to them but the sum total of that kind of attitude it's kind of
dampens the energy it kind of drains a person it kind of doesn't bring a vitality and an engagement in life it's
more like keep pulling back pulling back and there's a lot of attitudes that we
do in our life that we do that we Express in all kinds of small ways and
some of those are not so great uh some I know some people who have an aversive
nature and there's something about saying little aversive statements uh
that little resistance statements that maybe one statement is okay but to do
them as many times as you bow in the monastery they tend to uh create a habit
a momentum a familiarity a sense of this is what I do so it becomes almost second
nature you don't even think about it anymore but have his little little you know pieces of aversion or pieces of
something or something that goes on so we're all in a Zen
Monastery we just don't know it in the sense that we're all doing something with our body our voices our eyes that
are uh expressing something or living something or carrying attitudes and
beliefs and sense of relationships and all kinds of things are being carried with it all the time but most of us
don't see most of what we carry most of what we're doing don't see the impact
that has on us so when I left at the monastery after
3 years where so much of the life was choreographed and it was kind of chosen
for me all kinds of things when to wake up when to go to the meditation Hall and
when to do this and that and how to do these things and the even eating was you
know most meals were carefully choreographed like you couldn't just like pick up your spoon and start eating
when you felt like it um you uh you have to wait for a bell and then you had to Bow a certain way you had to chant you
had to eat in a certain way you had this very unusual kind of eating utensils little bit and so the whole thing was
kind of choreographed and what was marvelous about eating in the monastery uh was we would eat the med in our
meditation posture and uh and just taking that posture that we've been meditating in is
very different than you know sitting at the table you know you know looking at the news on your phone while you're
shoveling food into your mouth which probably none of you
do and um you know you have to real you're really there and this is the this is this is the activity of the moment
you don't bring your phone with you into this zendo you know you know you you you know you're there we didn't have phones
then but I'm sure that they're not allow and and U and uh so so 3 years of that
when I left as soon as I left and came back to San Francisco I recognized something and
this was the Revelation that um now it's up to me to decide how to do
all these things and I had so much more Choice than I ever imagined I
had so I went to talk to the Abbot one day and it kind of formal discussion
about practice and I told him wow coming back to San Francisco you know so many things
are not choreographed anymore I have a choice and when I'm standing I have a
choice in how I stand when I sit in the chair I never thought I had a choice before I just sat
the way I sat I didn't think about it but I have a 100% choice about how I sit
in that chair do I slump do I i' I've sat in couches so so my shoulders were
in the crack you know you know you know all the way down you know just like you know just really
chilled and um and um the um so so do I sit ight do I use
the armrest do I what do I do and so I told him I have a choice and how I sit in the chair and he the abbit did
something very unusual he broke the the rituals or dro bro broke
the patterns of what you expect in a formal Zen setting he's in robes I'm in robes we're sitting meditation posture
having the serious conversation maybe 6 o' 5:00 in the morning you know uh I
told him this and he lifted out his hand and shook my
hand it was like congratulations you understood something really important
now I felt it was a real affirmation that I had a choice I had
had a lot of choices to make and I have much more choices to
make in my life than I'd realized before I started the monastery we have choices actually every
moment of our life we have choices and if you don't see you have
choices you don't have choices but if you see you have choices
does that mean now you have a burden oh more more choices to make it's
exhausting but but we're making the choices anyway we're making the choices
subconsciously and the choices we make make a difference and so what Buddhist practice
has a lot to do is recognizing the places of choice and learning to make wise choices
beneficial choices and um and that involves
something as small as how you sit in a chair something as small as how you stand how you look how you think what
you're thinking about I was coming down here to talk about this walking down here so I was thinking about this so it
occurred to me well Gil you have a choice now how you think about this and as as soon as I thought about
that oh okay uh let me look and see how am I thinking about talking about the
choices we have and I said oh I'm probably a little bit uh little bit
contracted in the mind little bit tense little stressful because after all I'm talking in front of all these people and
I don't have to do that I don't have to be worried about what I'm going to talk about uh I want to talk about this thing
because I think it's important and helpful what if I just shift how I think
and just think kind an easy way and think about it from how it's helpful for people and let me think in a way that's
helpful for me let me think a way that's beneficial for me so I shifted how I was
thinking and became really Pleasant to think about giving the talk I think I became a better person because of it then I had
you know the difference was not that great the shift was you know one degree or something but um but the um right
there there was a choice in how I think about something so one of the purposes of
meditation in Buddhism is not to make you calm and that's it not to give you
some wonderful experience and that's it it not to make you peaceful and that's it but rather one of the important roles
of meditation is to help you into a little
or better State of Mind of Heart of being than you were before you meditated
and I say this intentionally just a little so you don't have a high
bar it means that if you're feeling kind of lousy that day
and you just feel a little bit less lousy you've made it a little bit better so the bar is
low but uh you make yourself better than you are any other if you didn't
meditate and that that way of feeling better now becomes a reference
point for you to understand what kind of choices you want to
make how you want to now to go do what you want to do next next because you can
see if I don't do anything if I don't pay attention here that's a choice if I
don't pay attention you just go back into all the things I have to do pretty quickly I know the what all the demands
and the difficulties I have I'm going to get feel lousy again I'm going to feel really stressed out
again but you know I have a choice here do I just go back Barrel ahead and
forget about my meditation or do I use this feeling better as a reference point and see can I stay
close to this can I be careful not to abandon it how would I CH what do I
choose to do next so I stay closer to that I maintain it a little bit well
maybe I get up and I don't rush maybe I get up and I don't pick up
the most difficult thing to do maybe I get up and don't immediately check for emails because that just pulls me back
into that world maybe there's something maybe there's something worthwhile to maintain
how I'm staying right now and if I maintain it uh not only maintain it let
me not forget forget this state let me stay close to it I'm feeling better
after all let's stay close to it now is that selfish is that
indulgent it can be but if you pay as you do this practice you get more and
more sensitive that's the other purpose of mindfulness practice is not only to give you a better reference point in
which to understand your life but it's also to uh show you give you a much more
cute sensitivity Attunement with yourself that you see
all the little choices you make oh I don't have to do
that right now I'm I'm kind of abandoning right now I'm giving myself
giving giving myself over to boredom giving myself over to disc enouragement
giving myself over to desire I'm giving my over to the
anger is that what I want to do when I'm feeling kind of calm to begin with is
there another way of going about this next is another way of sitting is another way of standing another way
another way of you know whatever you're going to do is there a way of doing it
that makes things better or at least keeps things as better as they've gotten to
be so this last week uh my morning teaching that I did some of you know the
theme was don't make it worse and one of the things I I tried to
emphasize is that this little slogan don't make it worse whatever whatever you're going to do just simply don't
make it worse is very powerful and it encompasses the profundity of the
Buddhist teaching if you really understand uh how far and deep deep this
topic of don't make it worst can go but the Buddha had more to say than
don't make it worse he said make it better and this is a central principle
in the Buddhist teachings for how we live our lives how we engage in our
lives we based on these two things don't make it worse make it
better he didn't use those that language that's colloquial English uh his ancient
way of talking about it um if I told you would put you to
sleep or worse just like oh my God I can't believe all these
words um uh you know sometimes he was so precise and careful in what he was saying that he had a lot of words to do
it and it starts feeling kind of too technical or to something and um but I I can give you a
little bit better colloquial sense of what he said said he
said if you're making it worse
stop if you're not making it worse protect yourself from making it worse in
the future so that's a little bit more
colloquial then he went on to say um if you're not making it better
start doing it if you are making it better and I
think he loved making things better because these first three he said stop
protect yourself from doing it and and start but this fourth one if you are
making it better he said um stay close to it maintain it
don't forget it don't lose track of it
uh increase it make it and a wonderful word in poly
but uh make it abundant what having better be abundant sense of
abundance I mean that's like you know not being less grumpy that's like something
else and then cultivate it and bring it to
fulfillment bring it to its fullness I mean there all these things so that he
was that's what he was was most into if you could do the first three that prepares the ground so you
can really get involved in the last one isn't that good so the Buddha what
Buddhism is not just about not suffering it's about cultivating and
developing and growing and staying close to something you've learned for yourself
that's wonderful something you've learned that's worth staying close to and developing and that
something is and this is a very important part of this is that uh when
he wouldd have said don't make it worse make it better absolutely it can apply
to the world around you but where we have the most choice where we have the most uh
opportunity to make a difference is in ourselves in the quality of our inner
life the quality of our heart the quality of our mind that what's happening there and how we're responding
to the world and reacting to the world that's where we have the most opportunity we can't control the weather
so well usually but we can do the right thing we can get an bring with an umbrella for
example you can't necessarily prevent certain illnesses that happen but you
have some choice about how you relate to being sick you can't necessarily Choose
You Know politics and what party is in office but you can choose something
about how that you allow that to affect your inner life and what do you what do you give yourself over to or abandon
yourself to as if it's has to be that way or there's authority to these feelings these
attitudes there's the place we can make the most difference where we have the most choice is in
ourselves and uh in one way I I love how it plays out in life is that sometimes
we have to make big choices in life and it's hard sometimes to make those decision decisions and sometimes there's
no real way of knowing what's which is going to be the right decision partly because we don't know what's
coming we don't know what what uh will you know that decision will you know
take us to a place in a time and situation where things that are out of our control will happen and affect what
happens and so sometimes every decision is the right
decision or you know two different decision can be both can be equally good who knows what the right one is how some
decisions become right and wrong is not by the decision but how we live with the
decision the choices we make after we make that decision how we live with the consequences of it and that's where we
make the best of it so looking at so we start taking responsibility for the
choices we make and the one that again the Buddha focused on the most for
practitioners was the Cho how these decisions affect our inner life and
that's why meditation can be so helpful because we're learning about the
ins and outs of our inner life we're learning about the operating principles of how we get caught how we get
reactive uh the choices we make the values we live by the priorities we make
the biases we have uh if you start being mindful carefully Mindful and you have a
vantage point of calm a vantage point a reference point of some degree of peace
or well-being uh and you pay careful attention what takes you away from that
boy you'll learn a lot about yourself and so one of the practices I
recommend when you finish meditating appreciate whatever
way you're a little better and then stay you know try not to
rush into your life right away pay attention and notice when you start
losing that when you're not feeling quite as calm or quite as settled or a little bit now
you're you know you're getting starting to rush and you're not paying so much careful attention anymore so when you
find yourself losing that this is probably the most important
moment in the wake of meditation the moments you're losing what you had that
felt good for you at that moment uh
stop maybe sit down close your eyes just just pause and take a good look what
just happened what was I believing what was my attitudes what were the desires what
were the um um attitudes what what what happened that I got caught now so I'm
rushing what what happened now so now that I'm I you know I was fine I felt confident and now I feel
discouraged I was feeling peaceful and now I'm agitated I was feeling happy and now I'm sad depressed
despairing what happened there in that interface and it might happen so quickly
that you might not see the first day the second day but at
some point you say oh look at that um I felt that life was going to
leave me behind and I can't be left behind all my friends will leave me behind if I don't answer all those
emails people will be angry with me and there's oh that's what triggers me
that's what gets me caught I have this belief this little voice inside do I have to believe it is it
true is there another thing that can be done is it worth the sacrifice is it
worth giving up feeling better for feeling
worse and just that question is it better to give up feeling better for
feeling worse is a powerful question to ask yourself it's and if the lawyers of the
Mind come and explain to you all the reasons why you have to make be worse
you have to put up with it because you know you better question
that you better get a new lawyer and you know bring it to the
court and really have a discussion and what we learn over time I
hope is that we learn to cultivate um a healthy inner life and learn how to
stay close to that and value it and see how many benefits come from it and we
learn to recognize when the inner life feels healthy and not so then the Buddha
when he had this teaching about stop prevent the making it worse initiate
making it better and then keep making it better uh what he what he actually said
was not worse and better he used a word in ancient language that can usually
translate into English in two different ways one is uh it translates as
skillful and skillful also can mean ethical is it does it does it is it not
is it is it is it avoiding causing harm it's it's doing the opposite of
causing harm bringing benefit so so skillful is it skillful
but it's also translated into Engish as wholesome is it wholesome or UNH
wholesome and that really takes you into yourself does it feel like a right
wholesome healthy beneficial skillful ethical thing to do we have an inner
reference point the inner sensitivity to feel when something feeds us and
nourishes us and makes us feel better and makes us feel Freer and More Alive
in a good way and we have a capacity to feel when we we do does the opposite
when it makes this feels UNH wholesome it seems it it Den nourishes me it undermines me it drains me it makes me
smaller or contracted or tighter or makes me feel kind of
um uh you know kind of uh stressed by just by the what's going on in the inner
life so we don't always know how to make the world around us better we don't
always know when we can when we're making it worse maybe unconsciously or
by accident unintentionally but we can track it for
ourselves and we can we can and it's in invaluable to do
that and to start doing that in a way you know so that you start slowly but
start doing it to become second nature so that and this is what's happened to me over these years of
practice so much of this is just second nature it's like riding a bicycle your whole body body and mind
makes a lot of teeny decisions on the whole bike ride leaning this way that way it's
going faster slower Shifting the weight of your body where to look and you know
it's making but it's second nature to do it after a while when you first start it's stressful but after a while it's
actually relaxing to do it to be that fully engaged and participate in your life with something you have Mastery
over it's possible to develop Mastery over all these decisions you do
throughout the day how you stand how you sit how you look at somebody how you're
with someone I've learned at some point in that Zen practice I learned that how I
was with people was not their present attentive available
receptive I was turning away feeling embarrassed feeling shy feeling afraid
feeling like um you know like I didn't know what I was supposed to do and I had to be really
small there's all these ways in which I was present for other people that I didn't
know but the Zen training partly because in
Zen you're you're sitting every day many hours in an upright open chested firm
meditation posture and so after a while with that reference point I could see when I
collapsed I could see when I turn my body away I could see all these little
cues that represented not a good way to beat with other people and I learned
what if I just there relaxed full open it's really nice I was I was I saw someone this
weekend this last few days it was kind of facilitating a very
difficult conversation with a group of people and she had those qualities in her it was remarkable every difficult
thing that was thrown at her she was just there and thank you and just like
okay and she didn't cringe she didn't pull down she didn't get defensive she didn't get like trying to um apologize
in some kind of inappropriate way or you know she's just oh okay okay well now
we'll take this into account okay and it felt so friendly and so caring and this
is someone who had practiced for years that she had that ability and it felt to me like it was second
nature so in summary there's something really
powerful very profound in the simple statement make it
better and to use that as a guideline as it go through don't forget that as it go through your life if that's
too much for you if that's too sacran and too idealistic and too like you know
I don't deserve it well then the next best thing is
don't make it worse at least don't make it worse but you can make it better and one
of the purposes of meditation is to give you the information give you a reference
point for better so you know how to do this in your daily life you have a guide
you have a support you have a reference point for it and and don't look for
Grand spirituality don't look for The Big Bang experiences of Enlightenment don't look
for you know great states of Peace build towards that with every with
little one drop at a time with one little moment at a time in these little
details of how you live your life of how you stand how you sit how
you walk how you speak speak how you listen how you
engage with your computer with your device so many people lose themselves in
those and youve probably seen a lot of people out in the world that completely lost and absorbed in a way that doesn't
seem good of course you don't know you don't do that [Laughter]
right pay attention pay attention to how you make
things worse at least try to stop that try to make it
better and you do it don't you don't just do it for yourself you do it for the
world because the more that you learn to do this for yourself the more you're
available to the world in a good way when you cultivate and develop the
wholesome in yourself that wholesome spills out as whole
wholesome interactions wholesome ways of being in the world with other people if we do what's UNH wholesome for
us Den nourishes us it's hard to then come back to the world in ways that
benefit the world as well so so with all this I hope now you
appreciate this little slogan make it better and you see the
value of that so um maybe we're so we're you know it's well
before the usual official ending time here at 10:45 is when we end and uh we
have tea today so I think it would be nice of those of you who would happy enough to do this that you would uh
introduce yourself to a couple of people next to you and maybe have a little conversation about uh did any of this
talk have any meaning for you there was any any reference point in your life for how this could be useful
um and um and uh and you might um consider as
you have that conversation that very principle so it's very easy for for some
of us include myself to respond to things with that's not going to work
that's not right you know and then it's true if you believe that but there might
be one circumstance in your life where what i t about today will be beneficial for you if you only look at how that's
that that's that doesn't work that I I don't believe in what he had to say well that's okay I don't want I don't want to
take that away from you but uh but if there even if it was one circumstance in once in your hundred
years of your life that this teaching is useful then you'll benefit from this
teaching so uh so that's what you know so you so maybe you can try to benefit from the conversation by talking about
how it might be useful for you but you don't have to if you don't want
to so anyway it's mostly just say hello and we have a tea so it's nice with people who are new to be to be met with
someone and welcomed and included here and meet someone and and that way you know maybe you want to stay for the tea
and continue your conversations so we'll have about probably about five minutes just to chat and talk and look around so
that no one's left kind of sitting alone to just look around and invite them into your group or whatever and then um and
they'll ring a bell at some point so we have an official ending and then we can go have tea together thank you so