okay well good morning good afternoon good evening everyone for those just
tuning in for the first time my name is May Elliot and today is the last day of
our exploration of the Buddha's five daily Recollections and today we'll be
focusing on the final phrase um uh sometimes translated in different ways
so I'm going to read you two two versions uh the first is is I am the owner of my deeds and heir to my Deeds
Deeds are my womb my relative and my refuge I will be heir of whatever Deeds
I do whether good or bad and uh secondly I am the owner of my
actions heir of my actions actions are my womb from which I have sprung actions
are My Relations actions are my protection whatever actions I do good or
bad of these I shall become the air so
uh you'll notice that this phrase these phrases have a very different flavor than the last four and we talk about
that today and the Buddha What's Happening Here is he's guiding us into what seems like totally different
territory with this um and I'll also share later on why um
the the word being translated as deed or action is Kama or karma in Sanskrit
um and uh what the Buddha saying with this phrase is to reflect on how our
actions yield results how they yield consequences positive or otherwise um so
uh more on that later more on that to come um uh but let's let's move into our
meditation here as with the other phrases we uh we'll practice with the phrase in two ways I'll say the phrase
halfway through the meditation we'll start by sitting in silence and about halfway through I'll say the phrase and
you'll just drop it into the meditation to let it Ripple through the system kind of like a pebble being dropped in a pond
just seeing what happens and then after that I'll offer some questions for you to uh actively
contemplate for you think about a bit and reflect on okay so go ahead and find your
meditation posture sitting standing lying down whatever works for your
body you might start with a few deep
breaths in in to put aside any discursive thought about the past or the
future coming into the
now and taking a little time to relax the body softening the forehead and the
[Music] temples releasing the jaw
relaxing the neck and [Music]
shoulders allowing the belly to soften maybe hanging forward and down you're in
sitting
posture if there's anything that won't relax andh tension let's see if you can
relax around that making room for that without being in conflict with
it and connecting now with your
anchor what grounds you during the meditation if you get lost maybe the breath where where you
feel it most predominantly where it's easiest to [Music]
feel maybe you're touch points with the floor the
cushion a chair a global sense of the body sitting or the
soundscape traditionally the breath that do what works for
you and take some time now to l and collect the
mind
e
e e
if the body has become tight or tense again taking a moment to tune
in to sense the body and intentionally calm and relax
release any extra tension and then return to the
anchor
e e
now shift to our
recollection and as a reminder this is about karma in other words my actions
bear consequences if I act on a loving or generous intention that bears one result
if I act on hatred that bears a different result with wholesome
intentions and actions bearing happiness and wholesome
harmful actions uh bearing
unhappiness so I'll offer this phrase now and again just allowing it to Ripple
through the system without intentionally thinking anything through just seeing what naturally
arises maybe a thought comes into the mind or words or a picture in the
mind maybe an emotion or body sensation [Music]
I am the owner of my actions heir of my
actions actions are the womb from which I have
sprung actions are My Relations actions are my
protection whatever actions I do good or bad of these I shall become the air
for Simplicity we might try dropping this phrase in
my happiness and or unhappiness depend on
my actions my happiness or unhappiness
depends on my actions
my happiness or unhappiness depends on my
actions I will receive the benefits or Consequences of what I have done
noticing what arises and it may be that nothing arises or confusion arises if this idea is new
for you if you're uncertain
of why it's
included being mindful of any response
setting that phrase down now coming back to your anchor and allowing the mind to again
settle
e
e e
we'll shift now to our engaged contemplation so I'll offer the phrase
again and then uh a few questions you can
actively think about these questions making sure to keep a short leash on the thinking so the mind doesn't get too
lost we wanting to gravitate around the question staying close to the heart of
the matter so again the phrase another
translations time I am the owner of my deeds and heir
to my Deeds Deeds are my womb my relative and my refuge I shall be the
heir of whatever Deeds I do whether good or
bad so your actions follow from your intentions how much attention you pay to
your intentions makes a difference
so the first question are you aware when your
intentions are based in kindness Compassion or
generosity are you aware when you're acting and the intention behind the
action is a wholesome intention like kindness Compassion or
generosity are you aware of this
perhaps you're so engaged in the action you might not notice the intention
intention are you aware when you're acting if the intention is coming from
greed craving desire or hatred
aversion or
delusion are you are you aware when you're acting from intentions of greed
hatred or delusion do you notice this these could
be actions of speech actions of body things you do
could even be thoughts you notice when you're your thinking is coming from
greed hatred or delusion
do you consider whether your actions will cause
harm before you speak before you act do you consider whether it will cause
harm and that could be harm to others or to yourself e
knowing that your happiness or unhappiness depends on your actions and the intentions that precede
them are there any new actions that you want to engage
in or any present actions present habits
that you might want to let go of
knowing that our happiness or unhappiness depends on our actions are there any activities you
want to put down or pick up want to let go of or start engaging
in e
when you're ready coming back to the breath or other anchor and taking some time to
settle
e
e e
the benefits of our wholesome actions of
body speech and mind benefit all beings so they may be
joyful and [Music] happy strong and healthy safe and
protected and so they may live peaceful and at ease
welcome back today we are talking about the
fifth daily recollection I the owner of my actions
heir of my actions actions are the womb from which I have sprung actions are My
Relations actions are my protection whatever actions I do good or bad of
these I shall become the air so as I mentioned before the guided
meditation uh the word action is the translation of the word Kama in P or
karma in Sanskrit and we typically hear karma in the west so I'll use I'll use
the Sanskrit um and so this last phrase It's about Karma I saw a quote on a greeting
card a while ago that I thought summarized karma in more familiar language it said well well well if it
isn't the consequences of my own actions so this this gave me a chuckle
um and uh the lot the part of this of of this recollection that says I am the air
to my actions um we might just say this what goes around comes around kind of the
colloquial version I am the heir to my actions as I will I will um receive the
the consequences of my my previous actions so today we'll be talking about
Karma um but first I want to acknowledge that we've spent the last four days
contemplating aging sickness deaths death and uh the loss of what's loved so
wait a second hold everything you may be wondering uh what on Earth is karma doing here this is a little different so
this recollection is a Counterpoint to the first FL so having recognized the
immediacy the urgency of our situation where can we find safety you know where
we can can we possibly find a refuge amongst aging sickness death and loss so
this the phrase says actions are my protection actions are my protection so
our actions are our refuge they are our protection our happiness depends on our
actions so this phrase is saying if you want to be happy amidst these circumstances these kind of dire
circumstances take great care with your actions and this this is actually great
news the Buddha says that happiness is possible and he was known as the happy one it's possible to be free of
suffering in this life even with aging sickness death and
loss so how do we choose our actions wisely such that the fruits of of our
actions are happiness and not suffering to start uh we need to understand that
when the Buddha talked about Karma or action he was specifically talking about intentional action so intentional action
so it's actually the intention behind the action that determines our future
happiness and uh maybe just a few words to Define intention before we put this
all together so put simply uh intentions are are simply our motivation so our
reasons for saying uh saying something or doing something now we can think of
them as the the about to moment it's the urge that we have before we act so we
have motives or intentions behind every thought every word we speak uh and every
action of the body this is all fueled by
intentions so how does how does intention actually function to bring forth happiness
well if I speak from a place of kindness or generosity uh this will create one
habit pattern of mind uh if I speak from selfishness this will create a different habit pattern of Mind put another way we
can think of our life as a garden and our intentions are the seeds that we
plant so if we want to be happy uh plant seeds of kindness compassion
renunciation non-grasping uh these will grow a beautiful garden this will yield a mind that is resilient
and flexible and joyful if we're planting seeds of greed
of Desire of hatred aversion rejection of delusion uh then that will
grow a very different Garden um so are you planting the seed of fear of self
agiz of self-aggrandisement uh seeds of bitterness insecurity of craving so
these will generate a mind with more suffering you can't you can't plant a
poison ivy seed and expect to get a mango tree uh if we're trying to be
happy and free we don't want to plant poison ivy seeds so we examine our intentions and we act from wholesome
intentions because this conditions our future happiness if we want mangoes we
need to plant mango seeds so this is karma intentional action of body
speeching [Music] so um Good Karma results in happiness in
other words an action based on a wholesome motivation results in happiness and this is why the Dal Lama
says my sincere motivation is my protection my sincere motivation is my
protection but another way my good intentions are my protection so we can't control our
circumstances but our wholesome intentions can allow a safe Passage through life and this is
how um we can have safety um some sense of resiliency and ease and cultivate
happiness amongst sickness aging death and
loss and here's an example about how these um intentional actions yield
different fruit so this might seem like an odd question um but does stabbing
another person lead to happiness or suffering apologies for these somewhat
violent analogy um so uh does does uh stabbing
another person lead to happiness or suffering well it depends on whether the
person with the knife is a surgeon or an as salant so each might use a knife to
cut someone but one has the intention to help someone heal while the other has the intention to harm the Ser the is
going to have a very different um different life than the violent
criminal so here uh my sincere motivation is my
protection uh Rob bbaa who is a Dharma teacher and author heed to say my real
Investment Portfolio are beautiful intentions my real Investment Portfolio
are my beautiful intentions
so we begin to see the way that uh paying attention to our intentions is
really important it lays the path for where we're headed in our life uh so in
a way we could think of it uh of attending to our intentions we could think of it a little bit like a compass
guiding us towards happiness and I want to speak now uh
just for a few moments about sama sanapa or right intention um sometimes
translated as complete intention and some of you might be familiar with this
uh from the Eightfold Path the path to freedom and so one of the path factors in the eight-fold path is s sanapa right
intentional complete intention so there's three facets of right
intention renunciation is the first second is kindness or non-ill
will and the third is compassion or nonharming so we can think of this as
our North Star if you can align your thoughts your speech and your action to
be based around these intentions uh kindness compassion and renunciation you can align your actions
around those you begin to be able to walk North this is how you calibrate
your compass point for where to walk for happiness ah okay North this way
renunciation kind compassion uh whereas uh if we find that
we're acting on Greed hatred and delusion that's going to take us in a different
direction okay so now I want to acknowledge a few facets of
karma first we can't understand the details of the working of K the workings
of karma for example if you engage in a wholesome action with good intentions
we don't know when that good karma will fruit if you plant that karmic seed we
can't know when it will Sprout or how it will Sprout or what that plant will look
like so the Buddha considered the workings of the law of karma as one of the four
imponderables um so don't try to figure it out you can't figure it out so it's
you can't equate one action a particular result and go okay that's there it is
secondly uh not everything is based on Karma so in the commentaries it says that there are
several things that aren't based on Karma weather heredity accidents Etc the
Buddha did not say that everything that happens to us is based on our past actions other things uh can lead to our
experiences besides Karma okay third um often when we act
intentions are mixed that's normal if that's the case focus on the positive on
the wholesome aspect of the intention uh when when I was in college
I made a lot of pottery I loved Ceramics and making art um and at one point I
gave a friend a vase that I had made and when I noticed the intention
for doing so I realized that it really was mainly out of generosity but I also
realiz ized uh that there was little sub intention that I I also wanted this
friend to think that I was a creative and talented artist uh so so in this
case it was say 90% generosity and 10% based in craving and
self- viw so in this case uh uh I still
focused on the wholesome and I still gave the gift one wouldn't want to refrain from giving it a gift because
there's a little sprinkling of selfing in there there's a little sprinkling of less wholesome um
intention okay and lastly as guy Armstrong says don't use Karma as a rear
view mirror meaning uh it's not useful to consider our life situation and then
think what did I do in the past that CA this this is kind of goes along with the first thing I've
said don't bother trying to figure out Karma but specifically don't don't use it as a rear viiew mirror so we can't
see or know um we can't see or know what in the past CA our present circumstance
it's just speculation so instead use Karma as a compass for where you're going in the future or as guy puts it um
the best way to use karma is as a future GPS system it's the science of
Happiness uh so by reflecting on this phrase about Karma daily it be it can
become a reminder of the importance of our intentions the importance of how our
actions of body speech and mind bear results what we uh the intentions behind
what we do what we say and what we think uh through so uh as you practice
with this throughout the day you might consider as you do things what intention
is behind the action so today um maybe try it with food practice this going to
be a really interesting and fascinating exploration am I eating for entertainment or am I eating for
nourishment what's the intention behind what you get out of the fridge uh try it with conversation or
speech practice are you speaking out of care for others or is there a little
Barb in what you're saying maybe a tiny intention to make someone know they're wrong or that they screwed up in some
way are you complimenting your supervisor because you want her to know that you value her and appreciate her
doing it as an act of generosity and authenticity uh or is it because you're hoping to flatter her into giving you a
raise um so see what you discover uh and be kind to yourself uh this work is
humbling so I I hope uh through today's teaching that I've helped help to
calibrate your inner Compass to support you in navigating the path to
happiness so thank you so much for your attention this week it's been so wonderful to have the week with you and
uh to engage in these difficult teachings um even though they're challenging the intention is really to
uh align our life with the way things are uh so that we can uh we can really
learn where happiness lies and we can um align our actions with the way we really
want to be in the world we can set our priorities straight uh and we can live in a way that's conducive to happiness
so um I hope you reap the benefits of these teachings in your life and I look forward to seeing you soon take care
everyone thanks so much