good morning I see some new faces hello I'm Tanya nice to meet you and those I
know good to see you too so today is um Mother's
Day and um so I will weave this theme into the talk um and I'll expand the
definition of mother to include all the growing and
nurturing that we all do inside of ourselves and for others
and um so I'm going to tell you a little bit
about more what I'll talk about and then I'll I'll come back to um kind of this a
few Reflections on motherhood before I start but I want to share a sua with you
today um it's known as the ship or the chick the ads and the ship
um and uh so I'm going to share that sua and it's one of the parts of the suit is
about chickens and hatching eggs
yeah um and then uh yeah like I said I'll sort of start
with this theme of motherhood and then kind of dip in and out of that as I progress I think I just want to put my
hand on my heart uh when I think about mothering and I think about being
mothered um it's not easy and um you know it's also
incredibly uh it's been a huge part of my practice and um both dealing with my own
internalized mother and dealing with myself as a mother
um and all of us have the mother in us all of us
have the mother in us so I read a quote this morning and
I'm sorry I don't have the name of the author but I was just reading Marie papova or papanov she's got this
beautiful um email she sends out and she quotes an author who says about
motherhood it's hard to love and let go at the same
time and uh similarly um it's hard to provide safety
and danger at the same time right the love safety the Letting
Go the danger all are important we actually have to let our kids experience
difficulty we need to experience difficulty to grow right so it's very challenging
thing and um yeah so the wearing
green and um I'm wearing green for two reasons well one maybe but green
represents growth for me in nature and um I have a poem that my son
wrote when he was in um grade school so I'll start with
this I love you the greenest the color of all the leaves the
color of
watermelon and then I'll read you a different uh quote or a different poem
um by uh Rosemary traumer but before I go onto that I'll
say a little bit more about growth and this idea I have a quote from Dr cila
Majid and she was just uh interviewed in tricycle magazine
recently and um she says some beautiful things and
hopefully I'll come back to them but I'll just read or and reread this one quote now we can recognize ourselves as
part of the community of beings forever coming to know forever unlearning what
we thought was reality because we're growing you're not growing if you know
everything so for me this is a huge part of practice in life is this ability to
be present and to continue to evolve and grow and show up for the moment as it is
because it's always different and uh we get pretty stuck in our ideas of what is
our beliefs our expectations it should be and um we'll see more about that when
we get to the suta too so here's the poem by Rosemary
traumer it's called motherhood today again I praise the
beaver who spends her life building rebuilding rebuilding her Lodge where
her young will live with small sticks and big sticks and Tall solid trunks
with logs and rocks and mud with her teeth she builds a home buil it
on moving water because rain because snow because
warm because cold because flow because flow because flow her home is forever in
need of repair and so on a day when a surprise
storm has flooded the stream and washed much of my Lodge away I honor the the
beaver stalwart resilient habitual I notice the longing to move to
land then I gather new sticks of Courage stones of
forgiveness logs of compassion and the Deep sticky mud of
love I weigh to the middle of the current I like all the mothers I build
this home again
so this there's a theme in here which is this um the flow the changing flow right
and growth and in the poem there's this one line where she's talking about the
surprise storm and it's washed away most of her Lodge and then she says I noticed
the longing to move to land which to me is
the the desire to cling to make things solid to move out
of the flow of
life so this is the suta we'll now move into the suta and um I'll be going in
and out and explaining some of the things that the suta says and
um just just to say I'm I'll read the suta and then I'll share what has come
up for me my Reflections in response to the suta this is not to say this is the
right interpretation of the suta but this is how this suta brings
my helps me see my practice as it is right now so as you hear the suta you may have
other things that arise for you as well welcome them it doesn't mean that they're not right
okay all right so as usual they the suit to start with saying where they're at
where this is taking place at savati in this particular suta there the blessed
one said I tell you monks it is for one who knows and sees that there is the
ending of the effluence so I'm going to come back to
that and Define that word for you I'll just finish this section for one who
knows and sees what is there the knows and sees whoops there's
a little the ending of the affluence who is it right who sees the ending of of
the affluence they see such as form its origination its Fabrications its
Consciousness such as its origination such as its passing away it is for for
one who knows and sees in this way that there's the ending of the affluence
so the effluence come the word comes from a Latin verb afflu to flow
out in an older meaning an effluent was a stream of flowing out of a river or a
lake nowadays affluent almost always means wastes that pour out into water or
air so you might think of it as um things that pollute or things that
block right so things that cause suffering from the practice
perspective on the night of his Awakening this is a um I'm not reading
the sutta right now but on the night of his Awakening the Buddha focused his attention not on like concentration and
all these Altered States but actually on the mental process of trying to develop skillful
mental States this would be the opposite of the affluence so he was sitting down to
cultivate skillful states of mind and he did it in this way which was
to not reference himself which is very important it turns
out because it turns out that when we start to think I'm doing this this is mine this is me we are clogging the flow
we stop things up we pollute it with this identification and we're clinging
and it it really prevents this natural flow of life from happening and for
being clear about what it is so without referring to himself right he just
worked on cultivating wholesome skillful states of mind so this is what his he
the night he woke up this was his task
all right back to the suta so now he's going to you know he's
saying this is what we do we sit down and we cultivate this understanding we
see what's happening right we see the effluence End by noticing feeling
noticing our perceptions not ours I should take that word out of it you know um the way that we're fabricating the
Consciousness that's created seeing all this clearly simply without
identification and he says even though you he's going to talk about another
Monk now even though this wish may occur to a monk who's sitting down to meditate
I Want to Be Free essentially but he's sitting without
developing devoting himself to development and I'll talk more about that but developing essentially these
skillful states of mind so a monk that sits down and wants to be
free but hasn't devoted himself to developing skillful States is not going
to get free is what essentially he says and he says why is that because of
lack of developing and then he lists the things that should be developed and the he lists this set of
seven qu qualities or sets of qualities the Buddha has lots of lists actually kind of amazing some of
these lists are really pretty um powerful because they they have this way
of growing building on each other or leading for being forward
leading and so there's these um seven sets of qualities that have been termed
uh the wings of Awakening so these sets these you know supportive qualities that
apparently he developed that night right are the wings that carry us to Freedom
they help us you know we aren't caught in these
effluence and um in other places in in the the sutas the Buddha tells us in
majaya 103 he says if you you know so this is what you think of me you think
of me as the bless blessed one sypa sympathetic seeking our well-being and teaching the Dharma out of sympathy this
is how he was seen and said to his followers this is how you see me he said
if that's how you see me then you should train yourself and the qualities I have
pointed out so it's these qualities in
particular and so um back to the ship the ads and the um chick we are back in
the suta am I bouncing around too much are you guys following me okay
okay okay great thank you all right suppose a
hen has eight 10 or 12 eggs okay if she doesn't cover them rightly
warm them rightly or incubate them rightly then even though this wish may
occur to her oh that my chicks might break through the eggshells with their spiked claws or beaks and hatch out
safely so even though she has this wish but if she hasn't covered them
rightly still it is not possible that the chicks will break through the
eggshells so for me the Buddha is pointing to the fact that we can want to
get free but if we don't do the work if we don't sit and cultivate
and gestate not going to
happen and so then you know there's this language in the suta that says just this that um just you know just like if the
hen hasn't covered them warmed them incubated them rightly in the same way
even though the monk may wish to be free right it's not going to happen
because he hasn't been reled released from these effluence through lack of
clinging not clinging to the sewage the things that cause us
suffering and developing at the same time these seven wings of Awakening one
at a time perhaps or several as they
build and then the Buddha goes on to say um that if there's a monk who's
practicing and he doesn't have or she doesn't have this wish to get
free her mind can still be released by
developing these wholesome skillful qualities and letting go so we don't
have to want to get free we just have to practice
we in the next sections about the hen goes back to the hen the hen doesn't have to want the eggs to hatch the hen
just has to sit on them rightly
right so of course then he goes on to say you know the hen has these eggs sits
on them incubates them warms them does doesn't want them to hatch but they do
right because she has essentially done the things that need to be done so let's take a minute to step out
of the suta and talk about chickens and
eggs this the simile of chicken and eggs is um of course very relevant to
Motherhood but it's um also just relevant to uh
all all of us have the capacity to develop and cultivate um all kinds of
States all kinds of actions all kinds of ways of
being and um some of them require a lot of patience we can't be sitting on our
eggs checking every 5 minutes minutes am I there yet am I there yet is it here
yet is it here yet right or cracking them open or help trying to help the egg you know there's various stories about
trying to help butterflies come out of cocoons and it just doesn't work right
same with chicks they need to get their way out of their eggs
so there's this poignancy for me around our practice and growth and life
and watching our children or our loved ones and sitting back and letting there be this process
happening this undergoing the the flowing of the river not trying to control it too much right and not
getting it too blocked up this love and letting
go and the incubation and the gestation beautiful words right for all of us to think about
there's also like sometimes you'll hear people talking about building a practice
and we're like okay it's like planting a seed and letting the seed grow in the
garden and then okay well let me see how are the roots you
know we have to just trust there's a lot of trust that's required tending patience
trust and the right conditions we need the sun we need the water
right so just like um the chicken creates the
conditions you know the chicken has the egg but the egg really is maybe just a
symbol for what is possible within us all of us regardless of gender
regardless of fertility you know is just what what is possible deeply possible
and so this patience and this practice is you know of of creating these
conditions is really our practice and how we do it and how we understand that we're in this flow and that we you know
consistently help ourselves to remember to let go of all the identification to let go of the not wanting to let go of
the wanting you know just this constant needing to keep meeting and
meeting this moment and S daania says this thing that is um
really you know the Buddha talks about a lot too but it's like the thing that
starts to happen is if we sit long enough the eggs hatch and if we're present for that and
aware when that happens it's it's really really
rewarding and encouraging and um
when we start to have wisdom about how we're showing up for our practice in
life the mind starts to feel Joy as it starts to understand as wisdom grows and
as we see this process we have joy and it grows our faith in our trust it's
very very you know motivating for
us boo osaro um talks about this whole se you know kind of idea of what the
Buddha is talking about in terms of cultivating the skillful and he uses the word karma karma right he says the
principle of skillful Karma formed both the how and the what of that Awakening
that the Buddha experienced the Buddha was able to reach
Awakening only by developing skill for
karma and his understanding of the process of developing this skillful karma is what sparked the
insights that constituted his
Awakening so the Buddha then in the same suta goes and offers this other um
simile to talk about this kind of to this process of growth and
cultivation and he talks about a carpenter
um or the carpenter Carpenter's Apprentice um just as when a carpenter
or a carpenter's Apprentice sees the marks of his fingers or thumb on the
handle of his ads but but does not know today my ads handle wore down this much
or yesterday it wore down that much or the day before yesterday it wore down this much right so the overtime tools
wooden tools handled tools that are handled over and over again they wear
they wear and slowly there are imprints in the wood from the
hands and you know the monk or the Buddha says that um in the same way the
monk doesn't know today my effluence wore down this much
right or yesterday they wore down that much the day before you know it just it
happens and eventually we start to see some evidence of it
so an example of um how this you know kind of can happen
on Retreat for example or in our practice is that you know if we keep staying present if we keep meeting this
moment if we keep staying in the flow and with mindfulness
right we can start to notice the Mind states that
arise we can start to witness it and the closer we are to the moment the more closely we are to witnessing the
hatching and and for me a really beautiful place for practice is bringing
awareness to suffering which I've I like to translate as pain some of you may have heard me
talk about sort of pain which is a messenger and necessary and a signal for
us to pay attention
and so I really like to notice when I'm suffering when I'm feeling
pain and then when I do that and bring my awareness to it you know I can sort
of soften into it with curiosity opening to what's
happening and then sometimes sometimes there's a moment of just all of a sudden
going oh I get it right and maybe it's
as simple as I just have this ability to see the thought pattern that's going on
that's causing suffering it's just this chain of thoughts I'm been caught in and it's
sort of this Loop and it just keeps hurting and there can be this moment of
just going oh I don't have to keep thinking that
way and when you see this in this right
way there's this huge energy that can arise joy that can arise this feeling of
like okay I have a choice here and it's like putting your foot down instead of
going over here it's like going over here and all of a sudden you're just walking on a different path your mind is
just in a different path because you've decided somehow enough of your system
enough of your awareness enough of your wisdom and your heart have all gone I don't want to do that anymore
hurts and if we can then witness oh look this shift is there it feels
better it feels better we we're recognizing the birth of
wisdom and Faith from meeting suffering and that faith that Joy brings
energy or joy and that energy supports our mindfulness our ability to keep staying
present
so yeah it's not going to happen every
time but it will happen if you stay in the practice stay present
right and sometimes it's a big letting go and sometimes it's a little letting go but wow every little letting go is
powerful especially if we stay with it and appreciate it and choose it because
we can also so quickly just go back to what was po painful so easy so
easy so then there's one more simile in the suta it's about um a
ship and the Su goes like this just as when an oceangoing ship rigged with
masts and stays after six months on the water is left on the shore for the
winter it it stray it stays weathered by heat and Wind moistened by the clouds of
the rainy season and it easily will wither and rot
away in the same way when a monk dwells devoting himself to development his feds
easily wither and rot away so for me this this suta really
emphasizes um for me again right this
sitting with suffering sitting with pain just sitting so because I love this like
under the the weather the sun the sun to me is a symbol of awareness of of seeing
of bringing light putting our light on something our Awareness on
something and um so and then this this the weathering of it just just this
awareness just the letting it be seen and the to me the the rain and the
storms feels so much like duat me right and so sitting with this wisdom of
of seeing and feeling the difficulty this just this consistently
over time his feathers easily wither and rot
away the this the weather does the work of letting
go make sense and something that's I think
really important um for us to know when we talk when I talk about like sitting and being with our pain our suffering
you know there's a lot of things going on in life that are very difficult inside of me around
me but I can be okay I can be comfortable when that's happening I
don't have to be depressed I don't have to be
miserable as long as I'm growing as long as I'm practicing
right I know it's going to be
okay being a mom has been a huge motivation for me to
focus my attention directly on suffering and on cultivating skillful states of
being a huge motivation it has given me so much importance and urgency around my
practice at times just deep deep urgency you watch your children growing you go through difficult times you're like I've
got to get this right I have got to get through this and we can't you know we
can see things and know our patterns and our reactivity and we can't just stop
it we can't just you know make it disappear it has to weather it has to be
seen under the light it has to sit on the shore it takes time
so to reinforce this PO Point um there's a back to majam Manaya too all the
effluence uh the Buddha says and I'm going to give this a genderless pronoun
they attend appropriately this is
stress this is the origination of stress this is the cessation of stress this is
the way leading to the cessation of stress this is how we attend and this is
the for Noble
Truths just practicing attending with the understanding of these four noble
truths and then the Buddha goes on to say as they attend appropriately in this
way the feds are abandoned the effluence are abandoned
so um you know we all have our our things
that we want to get free of right I hope
I was uh back to Camila Majid I was really inspired by uh the
way she framed this and her she wrote a book and and um
was interviewed by tricycle and and the book is about um Justice and
racism and um and this is one of the things that I aspire to be free of right
is is these the conditioning of bias and she said that her she believes
the or her for her the fight for justice can be and has been
joyful and this is you know kind of going this is what the Buddha says right that what if we engage with our Dua with
wisdom right if we see it and we H we see that there's another way Faith
arises energy arises Joy
arises and then she goes she says this beautiful thing she says in her view or
this is the the tricycle author in her view Justice is inexorable from Joy and
it involves accessing the inner joy that is available to us when we treat ourselves and others as enlightened
beings she says thee more we step out of what we believe to be our comfort zone the
bigger that zone grows until the whole world is our comfort
zone but it's not comfort in the sense of I feel good all the time we're going
to be very distressed if we expect to feel good all the
time and this is that quote that I shared earlier that I'll share again when we can recognize ourselves as part
of the community of beings forever forever coming to know forever
unlearning what we thought was reality because we're growing you're not growing if you know
everything we have to uh really counterbalance the mind's natural
tendency to under to learn right the in the way that the Mind
learns for efficacy right the brain learns things and then stores it in
memory and the older we get the more we've got stored so the more we have to
unlearn and um and you know we get taught things from all kinds of sources
directly and indirectly could be an advertisement on TV it could be you know
a parent it could be a friend who knows right it all comes in and somehow some
of it gets really stored and becomes a reference point for us our beliefs about what it is to be a
mother about other people about ourselves all of these things have been
grown over time and very unconsciously are stored
within ourselves and we're none of us are free of this we're all subject to
it so if we we can bring a lot of curiosity to witnessing what what the
mind is generating and bring more of a the
awareness of Right Here Right Here Right Now what is this in this moment that's
happening we start to help un uncouple what was
stored most of it without choice and we can recouple if we stay
present with what's happening now with what's in front of us now what's here
now the unlearning and then the learning but awareness is essential for the whole
process being aware and I love this forever
unlearning what we thought was reality because we're growing because it is kind of every time you meet a tree it's a new
tree if you don't watch out you're going to just see it as the word tree however it's stored in your mind right it just
becomes this thing a thing instead of something unique and beautiful and green
and alive and growing so I think that's the end of my
talk thank you all we have a couple minutes so if
anyone wants to ask a question yeah Genie can you get a mic so that it's it's hearable to
others hello my name is jeie and um I really like this talk what you're just
describing at the end is that what you would call skillful Karma because I never heard that before skillful
Karma well skillful Karma so I didn't really go into the you know seven um
wings of Awakening but that's like the the qualities of um for example the the
five faculties are one of the seven lists so they're faculties of
Faith um energy mindfulness calm or concentration and
wisdom so these are skill these are some of those seven wings of Awakening so that would be skillful Karma to have
cultivated these skillful ways of of being present thank you thank you
Tanya was the entire suta about the beavers and the chickens from MN number
two it's um no I think it's uh Samaya samut aaya
22101 uh which one uh s mhm
22101 thank you very much yeah
absolutely I love the forever unlearning what we thought was reality isn't that
great I love that one
too okay question number there
hi Jen uh my question is how you referenced faith I I kind of I was
raised as a Catholic so I'm familiar with what faith has been to me great um but I don't understand it in Great this
scenario beautiful great question I love talking about this too so happy to answer um so first of all I like there's
three words that can be alternately considered for me Faith
which is Faith trust which has been my my Harbor and confidence and maybe it can
be thought of as a Continuum and so and and what the um the
Buddha teaches us is that we don't have to um have just we don't he doesn't want
us to have just faith in what he says he wants us to take what he says and practice with it
so that we grow trust in the practice itself and that we see the unfolding of
the practice we we witness things like I was describing through the practice so
our faith then over time becomes absolute
confidence yeah so uh don't ever just accept anything that is taught to you in
other words there's an the Buddha um didn't wouldn't even answer questions
about um is there a soul or not a soul or any of those kinds of
things
great hi uh my name is Abby and as I
like the idea of forever unlearning things uhhuh
but it invokes a sense of conflict within me MH
because the way I understand it the Buddha says that look at things
like processes rather than solid object right but then that directly contradicts
with the way we live life because our sense of security comes from T being
certain way yeah and so how do we find a balance between like a conventional life
that we like we lbers people live yeah yeah well it's not a problem to live a
conventional life it's not a problem to love people to have family to have
commitments to have jobs to have things it's not a problem to have desires the problem lies in our
attachment to those things and are clinging to those
things and and are wanting to control those things and thinking that they're
ours so it's really about our relationship to Conventional
life not the the objects themselves it's about our relationship to life and
letting life flow life letting people change letting ourselves change even
when we're not really wanting to sometimes yeah does that answer your question
no well it's not going to resolve your problem that's for sure it's not going
to make it easier until you are have moments where you see the the pain
that's being caused by the attachment so so notice where you're
clinging notice where you're wanting things to be different than the way they are or not wanting them to
change and track that space because that's the space of uh where Dua will
arise where suffering will arise where stress will arise where pain will arise and that is your
teacher and we start to then you have to kind of this is where we have to keep unlearning because if we are looking at
what's happening and we keep from a fixated point of view we're not going to see the truth of what's Happening why
that there's pain there and then we're never motivated to let go thank you that was helpful thank you one
more behind you hi I just wanted to express my
gratitude my my daughter and I have been listening to talks from inside meditation center for like 14 years oh
wow and this is our first time in person oh welcome I've come here before and like
just sat under that tree so when you talked about like talking to the trees and acknowledging the tree I'm like that tree out front is really special like at
the bench and I just sat here and like you know was really present in the
moment and I feel like I'm home and you talked about remaining teachable and like I was just talking
about that last night with people I was like I like the more you know the more you know you don't know right and um I'm
just full of gratitude it's Mother's Day and my mom and your share everything was just wonderful great thank you all right
happy happy day to you all inner mothers