so hello again hello and welcome to this rendition of happy hour as we come
together um as a community to practice these beautiful qualities of
the heart so so for today's practice I'd like to invite us to explore um one of
the four Brahma viharas one of the four uh beautiful qualities of the heart
beautiful practices of the heart and the third one today so third one being in in
poly it's called mudita the translation is vicarious Joy or sympathetic Joy or
basically happiness for the happiness of others wow how what a beautiful quality and and whenever I think of of mudita I
think of Joy it just makes me happy when I practice it I especially practice it as an uplift when feel like a do drum I
want to be become happy so I just practice this and and my heart and mind become becomes happier so it's it's just
really an act of generosity practicing um mudita and guess what who who
benefits from this act of generosity of practice I do we do when we practice it
so so um the um yeah the dalama has said
um know when you're just happy for your own happiness you have one chance of just being happy when when you're happy
for the happiness of others you have uh what is it now 7 billion is the
population of the Earth to uh 7 billion chances of becoming happy so so so
couple more words about this practice um basically this is meta which is loving
kindness which is just friendliness Goodwill it's the feeling of simple Goodwill that we have friendliness you
have friendliness for your friends you have friendliness for your neighbors perhaps or for there
for pets for little children you know it's just friendliness good well um and
this friendliness when it when it meets someone who is having some happiness in
their life it doesn't have to be every aspect of their life but it's one aspect that's going well and you feel happy for
them you feel genuinely as if it were your own you let their happiness the The
Good Fortune uplift your heart you let it uplift your heart um and it does and
it does so um yeah the um you'll also say the the
sometimes what masquerades as as mudita is pride the sense of Pride instead of
just just uh and pride comes with attachment when you're really proud of something or someone whereas mudita
vicarious Joy is just abundant they just happy for their happiness without making
it mine like oh what does it reflect on me if it's your child oh that means I'm a good mother or a good parent right so
doesn't have those extra unneeded attachments and the opposite uh also to
say the opposite of um the uh beautiful quality of the heart this
this um vicarious Joy is is Envy um when
you your heart gets tied because you want what the other person is having as if there's it just because they have it
it means you can't have it um so the way to work with that if it comes up and if
it comes up don't berate yourself it's okay the way to work with it is realize there's so many opportunities for
happiness in the world by you becoming happy for them it doesn't diminish you
uh it actually uplifts your heart gives you more capacity to to have more
happiness for yourself in so many different ways that might be available for you so just a couple of
um yeah this is a this is a rich teaching of course we can stay spend the
whole day practicing this but maybe that's enough so let's engage together so let's uh get into our
meditation postures whatever it might be in this
moment and arriving arriving in our
bodies arriving in this moment in time and inhabiting this body
fully sitting sitting up dignified sense of dignity
uprightness
connecting connecting with the sensations in your limbs in your
legs inviting the legs to relax softened
inviting the body to relax relaxing
softening finding your mind to relax liting your heart to
relax whatever is happening in this
moment making space in the body and the mind and the
heart and allowing the breath the INB breath and the out breath to be soothing calming
nourishing
any of thoughts are arising you can thank them and say thank you not now
giving my heart to this practice during this time please come back
later
e
connecting with each in breath and out breath soothing
calming here just here don't need to be anywhere else but here nourishing so
nourishing just to be
here
e
for
this is your practice this is your life this
moment how do you want to show up in this moment for yourself
presence
embodiment kindness or
otherwise
e
now I'd like to invite you to bring to mind someone with whom you have a a friendly
easy relationship maybe when you think of them bring them close to your heart a
smile shows up could also be a pet or a
child and now consider one aspect of their life where there is
goodness doesn't have to be every aspect and one aspect of their life
where there's goodness and you're happy for them as if it were your
own goodness the gift that was in your life as
if maybe they have a relationship with a relative a family member their
child their parent their sibling that is harmonious and you're happy for
them maybe they have a job they
love or maybe their health is
stable stable enough and you're happy for
them or some other aspect of their
life let this happiness make you happy tune into the goodness of this with
generosity with [Music]
kindness if it help helps you can silently saying your heart I'm happy for
your happiness I'm happy for you happy for your
happiness I'm happy for your good fortune I'm happy for this gift in your
life it Delights me I take
Delight as if it were my
own as if I were enjoying this blessing myself I can do
this I can do this my heart is larger than I give
myself credit for I can do this I can be happy for you take Delight in this goodness as if
it were mine as if it is mine
as if I were you as if I am you because in some ways we are
all inter our inter beinging in some ways I am you you are
me I can relish this
goodness as if you waking up in their life enjoying this
blessing as them let yourself really embody
it
e
and stay embodied this is not a thinking practice stay embodied in your
body this practice doesn't mean you start thinking about all
things you like or they have feeling into it feeling with each
breath feeling into the joy the
gladness the generosity of your happiness forth
them as it it's yours and it becomes yours becomes your
happiness and if the person situation you've chosen is not working it's okay
to Bow and choose someone else no
judgment
e
and then turning this mu happiness for
happiness towards yourself is there something about you in this moment
that you're happy about you're grateful
for In This Moment there's a bird outside my
window and it sounds so sweet and I feel happy for for me that
I'm able to hear this mous bird song I'm happy for
my own happiness see if you can find
something this moment maybe sound or
part of your body feels comfortable and and
[Music] easeful be gratitude for the meal you've
just eaten about to eat a shelter you have whatever it might
be a friendship you have happy for your own
happiness which is basically
gratitude
I'm happy for my own good fortune again it doesn't have to be in every aspect of your life but one
aspect one thing is not
be as simple as a bird outside your
window
e
and as we turn to bring this practice to a
close allow yourself to be happy that you have access to the Dharma you're
practicing not judging your practice but feeling gladdened that you
are practicing that you have access that you've met the Dharma these beautiful teachings yay happy from my own
happiness and that you get to practice in community there's so many causes and
conditions that have brought this moment to
be the light Joy gratitude and sharing this goodness with
all beings everywhere these planting seeds of
generosity and kindness may they serve all beings everywhere in ways I cannot
imagine serving all beings including
[Music]
myself thanks everyone thanks for your practice well I know I feel a bit of an
uplift or much of an uplet from this practice and and uh hope you do as well
and whatever happened is fine of course it's fine so so we have an opportunity
now to to engage and and share our joy practice together and the the question
I'd like to ask you is is um the the inquiry for the small groups is
um yeah what what are you grateful for what are you grateful for and you go
around and round and round what are you grateful for what are you grateful for and each person will share one nugget
share something you're grateful for next person will share something they're grateful for and then the third person
and then you go around and round and round so and this we've done this
practice before it's a joy producing practice and believe me you can find something you're grateful for again it
could be as simple as the sound of the bird outside or maybe you're grateful anyway you know you know what to do so
I'm going to create the breakout rooms take care of yourselves take care of each other be kind be generous let's go
in um uh alphabetical order according to first name and what else do I want to
say um yeah each person will offer one nugget for just for your own benefit next
person next person goes round and round many times and and please no advice giving no no uh changing the topic to
something that happened yesterday today tomorrow stay stay with your practice stay with your practice stay with the
generosity of practice Here and Now for yourself and others okay all right I'm
opening the rooms may you be well may you be happy what are you grateful for Here We
Go rooms are closed everybody is back welcome back
everyone [Music] um so what did you discover your
practice today what happened and like to I would love to invite those who haven't spoken
in in the large group uh to pull forward those who have to pull back make space
for those who usually don't speak up for the first round we love to hear
your Reflections what happened and remember you're if you choose to share you're sharing not just
for your own sake but for everyone
Barbra oops still muted let's try again still muted
Barbara there um I was in a group with um two
people that were new to the group and so it was wonderful a wonderful way to
begin because we each shared just one little thing and went around and then went around and around and around and we
just kept thinking of more things we were feeling grateful for and uh so it
was a real um an a beautiful way to begin with the happy hour with you nice
oh sweet I'm that that makes me so happy I'm uh delighted that um yeah as as a um
as someone who's been coming to happy hour for many years now Barbara you you you were um with with you know you're
greeting folks who were here for the first time with this with this fun joy
joyful practice oh that that makes my heart Happy thanks for sharing that red
I see your hand please well as a book into what Barbara
just said I I was in a group with um people I've come to know now for several
years and that was wonderful and
um you know I felt and you know I think most of us felt just real gratitude for
one another but also for you know so many others that we see on the screen here and and for you Nick and for being
able to be part of this practice um many times a week thank you ah thank you for thank
you for that book ending comment Fred that brings joy to my heart in a
different way for for the established connections through this through this
happy hour over the many years as you have um yeah met and got to know each
other and appreciate each other and gratitude also for this um yeah for this
community for this for the all the causes and conditions that brought many
years of um happy hour together possible thanks Fred yeah I feel grateful for
that yay yeah um I thought I saw a hand and
it disappeared I see one question let's see um hi Nikki can you talk about how
comparing oneself to others relates to today's practice ah yeah that's a great
question so um yeah comparison is the thief of Joy
it's basically if you want to um if one wants to become miserable basically it's
you know what one is to compare experiences oh this wasn't as good as that or this was this this thing oh yeah
that was a let down you know comparing comparing instead of meeting everyone new every experience know and then
comparing oneself which is more the question that has been sent to me is uh comparing oneself it's um maybe one
thing I would say is what is really helpful is um consider that each person
each being is born of all the causes and conditions of their life that is so
unique to them um and I can only be me I
can only be the best version of Nikki I can possibly be I can't be anybody else
because I haven't had the causes and conditions of their birth their genetics their upbringing their educa it just
it's not possible so comparing ourselves to others is kind of crazy it's it's it's crazy in the way
that I mean we do that of course um but it's it's it doesn't make sense with
eyes of wisdom when you really truly see that each person has their unique causes
and conditions and I can't compare myself to them because if I compare myself to that other person I have to
compare every cause and condition like go back through like years and years of history of their parents and their great
parents and their great great parents and their conditions and their lives and their upbringing and their it just doesn't right so I can just compare
myself to the best version of me that's all I can do because that's um anyway I
I hope that is helpful to the person who wrote the question to me privately um to
create to help bring a different perspective to loosen that comparative
mind um which is um yeah the thief of joy and thief of gratitude and and
doesn't make sense anyway Through The Eyes of wisdom and if you need more
explanation you can also write in chat and maybe I can talk about it in a different
way any other Reflections questions before
we
turn CL in New York still in New York you're you're muted still GNA ask
you to unmute okay there we go still happy in New York still happy in New
York yes um I thought this is real Quicky but I thought it was very
interesting that two of the three of us keep a daily gratitude list which I totally recommend to
everybody else because it makes such a difference yeah great I just love that
Claire you brought this up many times and I just love that you keep bringing up I love it you're the poster child for
gratitude practice I love it something if it works you know you gota sell it I
love it I just love it we almost had a chance to hear Richard play his guitar
too oh that's sweet that that would bring up gratitude and and and and I'm
grateful for the fun group I was in oh that's sweet that is very sweet yeah
thank you Claire and thanks for putting in a vote as always for the the um
Valley of gratitude Journal yeah I I I used to do that actually for a while at
at first with someone else we' do it together and that was really joyous and then I would do it on my own and then um
and then it became a practice at night whenever I went to bed and I'm glad you said it because I realized I've just
been so jetl recently I traveled to India and back I'm like ah I just kind of lost my you know the the the pract
like you know you have a habit pattern set and you come back from a trip and you're like wait what was I doing what
so I'm so glad you brought it back because I think I'm going to do that again so every so I'll tell you what my
practic is is is when I go to bed at night before I fall asleep basically I
go through everything like every thing that happened through the day with with like with an uplift like Oh yay that
happened yay there's a just a little bit of ding of gratitude oh yeah that happened and I sent that email yay and I
received that and so that's that's my yeah thank you and Diana please
well you just said what I was going to say what I do um is before I go to bed
at night um is I write down a grateful list and not just two or three things
sometimes it just explodes but also with the thought of why I'm grateful doesn't
take long and I've learned I like to do it then because when I wake it's
probably the last thing I do maybe before I go to sleep when I wake up in
the morning I tend to to be very clear and and feel good some something
has happened so that's all I have to say it's it's a wonderful way to wake up in the morning beautiful I love that always
but um with a smile on my face so and I remember something I'm grateful for so a
that's sweet I thanks thanks Diana I like the impact of it right the the morning after the day after and and what
you just said reminded me of um of uh a researcher a gratitude
researcher um who said that uh counting your blessings is a much better way to
fall asleep than counting sheep so so and um yeah because Al you also wake up
feeling happier yeah beautiful thanks Diana I appreciate that and let's see
yes the reflection uh uh from the person who asked about comparison thank you
that's very helpful I often judge myself for not doing what I think others are doing even if I have chosen not to do
those things with some intention I know this isn't beneficial so it helps to have lots of tools to address it great
beautiful thank you so much for for sharing your reflection um and for the
benefit of everyone because comparison is something that we all do uh and it's helpful to to be be um to have tools to
address it it's not right it's not Wise It's not helpful and yet we do it and
kind of like makes us it belittles us so so um yeah it's it's it's important to
discuss that anything else before we close about comparison about gratitude
about vicarious joy happiness for the happiness of others maybe maybe maybe one last reflection and anyone really
got into feeling happy for the happiness of someone else yes yes I see Hands yeah I see a bunch
of hands great lovely awesome anybody want to say anything about it especially if you're new to happy hour do you want
to say anything about it anyone can raise your Zoom hand your
physical hand I may not see I see
Neil I'm gonna say I'm new because every day is new
um good so
so right something I found I did today right I was thinking about my wife she
really digs our dog and it brings her such great joy you know and so I was
thinking about that and then I remembered that she spoken about getting a dog when she was young and how much
joy that brought her and it was very interesting because thinking of her as a young child having Joy right as good as
it was going it like whoosh like open the floodgates you know
and that was a very interesting thing because other people I'm pretty sure have been young and happy kids too um so
it seemed like you know a new trick in the in the you know a new arrow in the
in the arrow thingy I forget what it's called um you know to use you know as to
help you know appreciate right thinking about them when they were kids yeah beautiful Neil I'm so glad to hear you
uh say that and and when you say about you know talk about the arrow and in your whatever that thing he's called I'm forgetting as well but but um it's it's
like being a um you know the idea of not so much making War right because we
associate not errors not just with war but also with with the cupid like you're being a cupid of your own heart right
it's like oh yeah here's another eror swee I'm going to wake up open up your floodgates thinking of someone that you
car about uh being grateful and happy as a child wow what a beautiful twist um on
that yeah I I appreciate your experimenting Neil this is how these practices work we just experiment and
whoa we we come uh to a gold mine very sweet thank you ah I see rain's
hand yeah what was great for me is um I have a lot of I have seven sisters and
I'm really close to my sister Gabriel and she lives in New York and I don't get to visit her often and I was
thinking about all the ways I was so happy about her happy marriage she has a
son that it's really their a little love nest there they um had a lot of fun with
the snow in New York and it was just like I had visited her it was such a warm feeling of wow you know just
yeah oh beautiful thanks rain as you're talking about actually it's almost you're inviting um me viscerally into
this joyous connection that you have and visiting her ah yeah embodiment just
feel so embodied alive Rich this relationship thank
you thank you thanks for sharing this
um Richard I see your hand as well and uh
there oh I just want to tell you I do a joy for form of tonglin where I breathe
in the happiness of others and and breathe out my happiness to them oh my
God I love it I love it that's great thanks Richard I love that we should try
that all of us together maybe next time I'll try that at happy hour yes yes um
beautiful thanks for sharing that yeah beautiful how fun how fun um and I just
realized that the chat was uh to me only not to everyone so so both Neil and
Erica said the arrow thinky is called the quiver so now now we know and uh someone I don't know if this
is intended to be private or not but uh one person said this reflection probably wasn't supposed to be uh private but
anyway something that was said in the meeting room was quote I am grateful and
happy to also share the Silence with both of you and the person says I
thought it was so beautiful and it is beautiful what a oh how beautiful I I
read it again I'm grateful and happy to also share the Silence with both of you what a gift to be able to uh share
silence Silence with one another yeah so dear ons we've come to the end
of our time together and I'm uplifted and feel more connected to you whether
whether it's um you imagining your partner as a child enjoying a dog or
visiting your sister and or what or or taking Arrow what arrows from your
quiver um all the ways that we've shared our practice together uh whether you've
supported new people in the practice connected with with friends you've made
um lots of Joy so thank you all for your practice May a practice be cause and
condition for wisdom and compassion and joy for ourselves and all beings
everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be [Music]
free thanks everyone thanks for your practice I'm going to St