okay friends good morning and I hope uh this is a working
for people I was having a little issue with
uh YouTube uh streaming just a moment ago and hopefully this is okay for
everyone and you can hear me I'm seeing some uh chat messages
coming in
so yeah good morning and good
day yeah just taking a moment to take in as people
arrive I'm seeing various chat messages uh
great yes we're all [Laughter]
back wonderful to be here so I've been sharing uh little tips
for practicing this week and uh we'll continue
today and um I feel like I've said a lot so maybe
we'll just dive in and I'll go through the arriving
sequence again and kind of uh sprinkle in the practice of a
pausing and uh incorporating a little more that I was hoping to incorporate
today so with the sound of a
bell let's
begin as the sound of the Bell Fades
away pausing pausing to
arrive arrive here and
now maybe a few long deep
breaths can support the
arriving
let the weight of the body settle towards the round
earth arriving arriving at the Temple of this
body mind and
heart
pausing so mindfulness sa can begin to
surface to the
foreground
maybe you feel some kind of a
presence there some kind of a presence that's felt in the
body may be felt in the heart
space
Mindful and
heartful there may be a felt sense of a slowing down or quieting
down maybe the energetic field feels
settling
maybe a myriad's kind of
experience without
demanding was that without setting
agenda simply steady study with a felt
sense
the felt sense of the posture may become more
clear as we stay with the [Music]
Sati this is how it feels like to be sitting in this
posture or lying down or standing or whatever
posture you're taking right
now the moments become available to
us are you available to the
moments are you available to the movements of the breath
breath are you available to the fleeting
thoughts a sound is available to
you are you available to the
sound silence is available to
silence
gently becoming available to the lift
experience Here and Now
feeling and [Music] sensing what it feels like to be
available
maybe certain kind of a holding or tightening can release in the
body maybe certain
tension around the [Music] head
face eyes can
soften and maybe the nerve systems around the
limbs the edges of the body can ease
up
being available feels like
this doesn't have to match with any of the words I
say trusting your own inner
experience being available may feel
tender and at times vulnerable
and so we deliberately choose to
align aligning aligning with our heart's
aspirations aligning with our deepest
intentions aligning is not a goal
setting the L is a here and now kind of a
practice there is the there is a felt
sense when we're aligning with our aspirations
in a directional
sense we feel the uplift in the heart in the
body they have a sense of rootedness in the body
there's a wholesome feeling when we're
aligned aligning with the Buddha Dharma and
Sanaa aligning with a
kindness
we being available and aligned
our heart knows this is a protected
field from which we
practice
right here aligned in the B available our heart and
mind can settle become
collected
composed and this is enough
sometimes the felt sense of the body emerge so naturally in this field
feel the weight of the body settling
down there may be a firm
contact of the body with the Earth
floor or the whatever that supports the
body
if you choose you can turn and arrest your
attention and the contact of the body with whatever that supports
you this is a wholesome ground to
resting this is a good
enough
it's also natural the felt sense of the
movements of the body to become
visible felt
movements of the breath the [Music]
flow the dancing
Sensations pulsation
tingling
thring or just simply a sense of Al
liess
wavy emotions another form of
aless thought bubbles yet another form of
aliveness
a poem by David White
enough enough this few words are
enough if if not this words this
breath if not this breath this sitting
here this opening to life we have
refused again and again until
now until
now
for
[Music]
so so this week I felt like I've said a lot in terms
of how to practice and my
invitation is um for you to stay in your
meditative bubble if you choose to do
that and maybe the words can flow in or flow
out whatever whatever may feel feel appropriate for
[Music] you I won't rain Bell to
transition and I have only a little bit on that what I want to share
today um when that's evoked um by the AOA
that I read on towards the end of a
meditation and that is wherever you are
however you are is
enough and remember that we're always practicing as best as we are
able this is another another phrase that I received from a Philip
mothod practicing as best as we are
able just let that phrase drop in and feel and
sense what's happening as that phrase settle in your
system
practicing as best as we are
able when I first heard this phrase and my system kind of relaxed
from inside out maybe a little bit it or something
kind of got released maybe I wasn't quite conscious
that I was just striving for something to happen or I was trying to get
somewhere else and there's a kind of
undercurrent that got released Al there's a sense
of this whatever is here is
enough and maybe more than
enough it doesn't mean that unpleasant went away or the
pleasant continued or the hindred hindrances are
gone but my relationship with what's here
shifted there is a sense of a more at ease with what is
happening Can You Feel The humility in
this you feel the humility in practicing as best as I'm
able we're not pushing around by our expectations
goals results or desires they're not
reality and goals and results uh tend to get us uh trapped um between the
failures and successes and and sometimes when we try hard
we get so exhausted when we practice as best as we
are able much less
pressure so much more space so much more
ease and the Heart can feel
unburdened and as we practice in this way as best
as we are able it doesn't mean that uh we're simply lazy or
unengaged but instead and the heart and mind are not in a big hurry to get
somewhere else we're more grounded in the reality
of our experience I remember one day I was
sitting in a guided meditation that the teacher spent a long
time simply to prepare our mind before the meditation went
on at some point it just dawned on me wow this teacher wasn't going to go
anywhere else and he was so sincere
and there was no some other states to get to or some other territory to get to
he was just practicing wholeheartedly
sincerely with whatever was up showing up for him right
there there's no need for shortcut um bouncing
around as I was so moved by
this practicing as best as we are able allow us to stay honest and true to
ourselves to how we are and we all know that the Habit mind
tends to want to skip over um things that it doesn't want or um Rush um
towards something that it wants to happen but when we stay true to our
experience we're practicing according to the Dharma that's the practice in
accordance with the Dharma there is kind of a through line
alignment with our heart's wish our heart's
aspiration and it takes courage and in Integrity to stay true with our
experience and we when we are um daring and um having a sense of
Integrity to stay and just right here right now that can be a kind of a liess
that come forth uh and this kind of attitude
allows us to unstuck from being uh getting entangled with our wanting
mind and practicing as best as we are able we may also
notice from time time to time there is a kind of a
contentment or SA satisfaction that is in our
experience that is available to us that is in independent of the pleasant
unpleasant this kind of contentment can
exist whether or not you're feeling tired or whether or not your neighbor's
dog is barking Non-Stop or whether you are hungry or
thirsty whatever you're experiencing there can be this kind of
contentment that holds everything and that's
enough I want to end um
with the beginning words of the Matas
suta this is what should be should be done by one who's skilled in
goodness and who knows the path of peace let them be able and
upright straightforward and gentle in
speech humble and not
conceited contented and easily
satisfied unburdened with the duties and The Frugal in their
ways and this is what should should be done
that's all take a moment to settle back into our bodies mind and
heart Maybe saering the goodness of this week's
practice you feel a sense of
contentment by simply showing up practicing together as a
sa Can You Feel The feel field that we're creating
together filled with
goodness and may the goodness that's been holding all of us together in this
Mornings in this days may they nourish our own body mind
and heart May the goodness expand in all
directions may it be a source of
nourishment by all beings everywhere may all beings be at
ease may all beings be happy and may all beings be free
[Applause] thank you dear
[Music] friends be well be
well take good care