so hello everyone and Welcome to our
meditation and one of the maybe unusual aspects of Buddhist
spirituality is its emphasis on absence the absence of
things and with some reflection we can appreciate that how much happiness can
come from absence right now I'm sitting where it's
warm at IMC and the absence of the cold which is outside here it uh looks like
it might rain so it's absence of rain in this room I
feel uh safe from the cold and the wet outside it feels cozy and nice to have
to be here coming down to IMC this morning
there were beautiful sunrise in this slivers of empty space
where the clouds weren't on the horizon so it was delighted
by by with the beautiful colors and and colors were there partly what stood out
was the absence of clouds in those slivers that slices of the
sky so there can be the happiness of not having it to deal with any
responsibilities to sit in meditation and not have
to you know go to a meeting or do the chores or something just nice
the absence feels good absence as a condition for a sense
of contentment and happy happiness AB the absence of desires Happ
AB of conceit absence of hostility can feel so
good so wonderful absence is not something
that we're trained to focus on to look
for the mind's always usually interested in something if we're thinking about a lot
we're thinking about something absence absence of thought
ABS absence of a subject to be thinking
about can be so nice that peace so assuming a meditation
posture and closing the
eyes and taking a few moments to feel your
body maybe rock your body back and forth maybe side to
side as a way of connecting to your body feeling your
body loosening your body and then slowly come to Stillness
with the body and having moved the body a bit the
Stillness might be highlight the absence of
movement can highlight the sensations of the body
that's
still and then taking a few long slow deep
breaths release in tension in your body as you
exhale when I was first introduced as Zen I was taught to Flap my elbows like
a chicken it made me smile but also I learned that that could
kind of loosen things up in the arms so the arms AR somehow
unconsciously held tight
and
if and then letting the breathing return to
normal and as you exhale Relax The Thinking
mind relax the grip thinking has on whatever subject
of thought that concerns your
thinking and also now take a broad Global sense of you sitting
here feeling the body as broadly as you can easily
can and with this broad awareness of the body
appreciate the absence of business of
activity of running around being being in commute
traffic just appreciate some of the ways of being which are not
here and how it allows the body your very
being to have breathing room to have space to just
be and if you do feel safe in the place you're
meditating they appreciate the absence of danger we live in a world where many
people live in danger and they can have a deep sense of
well-being contentment at least for these few
minutes to be meditating in
safety and perhaps to the degree to which there's an absence of distractions
there can be a happiness to just being
here alive breathing attentive engaged in the
practice which has tremendous meaning and purpose tremendous
benefit what a good thing to have this practice
and with whatever Global feeling of well-being that's available to
you let that wellbeing be massaged or touched or
stroked by your body
breathing the expansion of the rib cage the
belly touches moves into whatever Global feeling of
well-being you have
and the exhales letting go with settling
in to the middle of this
well-being one breath at a
time
for
for e
a means of contentment of
well-being is not to focus your thoughts on what's
wrong but to focus on what is absent
here what is absent that feels really good and
supportive that allows your muscles to relax your heart to
settle maybe even allows your heart to smile
so good to just be
here in the Simplicity of this
moment allowing a sense of well-being to
support mindfulness
for
e
for for
oh
and as we approach the end of the
sitting to see if you can feel whatever sense of
well-being there is in your body your mind your heart
if you're a little more calm or settled than when you started the
meditation if you're a little bit more still
quiet is there any
wellbe in that subtleness in that calm
even the slightest sense of well-being in being here and now in this
body in this mind in this heart at this
time let the influence of that
wellbe register for for you AB absorb it take
it
in like the warmth on a cold
day taking in the warmth of well-being
contentment happiness
and then [Music]
imagine that you meet someone who's friendly and
kind and you meet them with your well-being
being you meet them with your
contentment how are you when you're calm and relaxed
at ease how are you in being with someone
who is undemanding who's also kind
relaxed might there be some good
will some friendliness that you have
and if you do maybe you can let your good will now spread out across the
lands let your good will spread to include all
beings may all beings be happy may all
beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free and may your
wellbeing contribute to the well-being of
others don't sacrifice your own well-being because then you have less
less to offer others [Music]
thank
you
e e
so hello everyone and welcome to this second talk on the no that maybe I shouldn't
call it Noble but the truths of four truths of
happiness and um the second Truth For Today is
um the truth of the conditions for happiness
and this is uh chosen carefully because uh rather than calling it the causes of
Happiness there are the conditions for happiness and just that is significant if we if there's cause for
happiness the chances are that happiness becomes too dependent on a cause too
dependent if something has to happen so that we can be happy and the happiness then becomes
fragile and chances are that that uh happiness is not very deep or is not
very pervasive it could be genuine to be caused by
something um and it can touch us wonderfully at times the um but it uh
it's it's not something which um Can persist very well except in memory when
the cause is not there in Buddhism there's a lot of emphasis on understanding the conditions
for maturing in this Dharma maturing in the Buddhist path a path that comes with
it the arising of joy and happiness Delight gladness
contentment so a whole slew of uh feelings that belong to the family of
well-being and they're an integral part of developing this practice but it's there this these things are not
caused by anything but the conditions come in place for them to
arise and sometimes some of this when the conditions come into place um they
teach us something about the availability of happiness and
well-being that uh maybe is here much more often than we realize so because some of the the
conditions are absences so for example the absence of
uh being unethical the absence of killing and stealing and sexual misconduct and lying
intoxication this is phenomenal this is understood in Buddhism to be a source of
U just the feeling of safety a feeling of Happiness contentment a feeling of
relief and and um but it comes from an absence of doing these things absence of
causing harm and um and this is a condition for
something for sense of delight and happiness relief especially if you we
know the alternative uh some people's lives get ruined by being
unethical their lives become very stressful but to not have any of that
and uh and to have the freedom the fresh air in the heart uh can be a sense of
tremendous well-being of happiness and we learn about
that the absence of being unethical and we get a sense oh that
happiness isn't so way is always available it's not dependent on
something happening it's dependent on an absence of something so if we stay close
to that absence it's always available and and um and if we make that absence a thing
and that's going to cause us to be happy then we're already caught and that there has to be a certain way but the idea is
to just trust the conditions the absence of stress in our
lives there can be a sense of well-being that teaches us the same thing that there is a sense of well-being
contentment ease that's possible when we don't have stress so why get
stressed that's the kind of the big question that as a really I think a mature DH practitioner would ask
themselves why get stressed why get stressed when maybe the alternative is so much
better and um and then see what kind of answers you come and maybe have a discussion with yourself or with friends
or people about this whole question why do you allow yourself to get stressed why is it so important question it the
absence of stress can provide well-being sense of ease a lot of goodness that
that can grow and develop it Fosters room in the heart for something to
come so um the absence of the hindrances the absence of greed hate and delusion
the absence of anxiety these can all provide a sense of relief a sense of
ease a sense of Harmony a sense that things are good in the world and at least locally here and now and we're
allowed to feel the goodness of that don't sacrifice that goodness for
anything if you think the conditions in the world political world the whatever is happening in the climate and the
environment um if you give away your inner goodness give away abandon
yourself to the anxiety to the anger to the dismay to the confusion
that those things give rise to that's tragic the uh because it's from the very
sense of inner well-being ease goodness that uh that something
profound can happen even if you're going to be involved in any of those causes
can you do it from that place of your own goodness your own well-being that
comes from the absence of giving yourself away the absence of hostility the absence of greed the absence of
anxiety so there's a tremendous the condition for happiness that can develop
and grow is has a lot to do with the an absence rather than a
cause and an absence then allows something to grow and part of this field
of goodness field of well-being when there's space for it is the growth of
wholesome qualities wholesome States within us um um that we have natural
capacities uh for some things and maybe different for different people but we
have some some people have a natural capacity to care beautiful caregiving
care for the welfare well-being of others some people have a natural capacity for generosity for kindness
friendliness compassion love some people have a natural capacity for um for for
calm and uh honesty and integrity we all have some of this
perhaps and as we have these absences that preoccupy us because breaking the
precepts being unethical a pre requires some kind of preoccupation uh being caught in things
that are stressful and what means we're somehow preoccupied being caught in anger and hostility dismay and anxiety
we're preoccupied to be unoccupied or to occupy ourselves in a
deep way not be preoccupied gives room for wholesome qualities to
grow and these are invaluable in the Dharma and these wholesome qualities if
we act on them like we act from generosity if we act with care or love or kindness or friendliness they have
space in in The Emptiness of G create hate and delusion The Emptiness of
stress to evoke or fuel or strengthen an inner sense of Happiness
well-being and so part of what we do in Buddhism is both an absence appreciating absences that bring us a better sense of
well-being and also we appreciate that certain things when they're acted on are
the further conditions for well-being not that generosity is seen as a cause for happiness but the gener
uh uh sensibility Fosters the growth of more
well-being ethical Integrity Fosters the growth of well-being and so we're more gardeners
than we are cont Engineers we're not engineering ourselves into happiness in Buddhism but
we're planting the seeds we're tending the field we're tending the garden the plants we're nourishing them feeding
them watering them uh keeping the we weeds out of the garden so they can grow
well and so we have inside of ourselves uh
weeds and we going to be very careful with them that they don't um suffocate
or or shade out uh the good plants that are growing
in there appreciate the absence of weeds appreciate the clarity the breathing
room that provides and then appreciate that there is goodness in us there is wholesome qualities within us don't
sacrifice those don't abandon them because then you abandon yourself in some ways the Instinct towards hostility
aversion the Instinct towards desire the Instinct towards
conceit are oddly enough ways in which we give ourselves away we lose ourselves
in those because we're limiting ourselves to particular concern we're defining ourselves a very narrow uh uh
range of what it means to be a human being and so to give ourselves away that
way is quite sad don't give yourself away stay
present in the absence stay present in the goodness
stay present for the whole the breathing room where there's fresh air for your
heart for your body because it's in that Breathing Room things where we're all
there for ourselves that we don't limit ourselves with preoccupations where there's a condition
for the arising of Happiness so if you want to be
happy contribute the conditions for that don't search for a
cause if you think you're going to be happy by going to Disneyland you might
be but that's not going to create lasting happiness
unless you go to Disneyland in this empty
open place with your own goodness flowing out of
it and then if that's the case maybe you don't need to go to
Disneyland because the core happiness is not dependent on Disneyland the core
happiness is already in you and you can do anything you could even go to the
local soup kitchen to support people who are hungry and you maybe feel even
happier than you would if you went to Disneyland so
conditions the second truth of happiness is that a pro profound meaningful
happiness dhic happiness arises from the conditions that are we put in place not
the causes so thank you and um
May you look for the conditions
today not in the world per se but in
yourself that you can stay close to so you go through the day
happier and perhaps you can put a rubber band or a string around one of your
fingers or something as a reminder that through the day you keep looking for how you can create
the inner conditions
absences that you or that you touch into a natural sense of well-being ease
happiness that comes when you don't give yourself away thank you