so uh so welcome all uh good morning to uh most of
you um so uh some folks um requested uh an
opportunity to connect with each other so um we decided
to uh just offer a a short uh Zoom session where can um have breakout
groups or say hello to each other with some faces so that will be tomorrow at 8:00
a.m. Pacific and I put the link in the YouTube
description uh it's also posted at Matthew BRS silver.org on the first page
you'll see the link to the zoom and um yeah that's just a an opportunity to
uh con you know connect with uh uh some
faces and um be together so um tomorrow at 8:00 a.m.
totally optional of course yeah thanks Cindy for uh facilitating
that um yeah and I'll I'll I'll be there and can answer any questions or
something but it's really kind of um uh sa
focused uh okay welcome welcome Salt Spring that's a nice
Island um all right let's
meditate
e
e e
just enjoying the uh Stillness
just pouring your awareness into your
body making your body bright
vibrant with
awareness
e
e e
it's a sense of uh deep
kindness towards uh all
conditioning the uncountable UN knowable
forces that have birthed this
moment and its uh joy and sorrow
and ordinarily we focus
on the effects of that which we seem to have controlled others seem to have
controlled we have focus on that which is uh
conscious but there are so many forces that have come to
shape this moment that we cannot even see
but we can uh bow to our conditioning as
a it's an animal with an evolutionary history it's an
Earthling with a home
maybe this is a way of saying we come
to forgive
history not condone
but open our heart
to the way is the past is
present all the forces that have shaped what we call me my life
all the things you like and dislike
about who you
are we just stop picking and choosing and just
say okay my
life and then there's compassion for your suffering there's
joy for your good fortune
there's equinity for the nearly complete hopelessness that defines any
life and there's a lot kindness tenderness
for what we call me my
life just appreciate your life in this way as we begin our
practice
e
e e
forever we've been categorizing sorting out what is
acceptable and what is unacceptable about ourselves what
aspects of our conditioning are acceptable what's
unacceptable What feelings are acceptable which unacceptable
just end all of that right
now and you may still want to change you may want to
appreciate skillful and unskillful but that comes out of a kind
of radical yes to all of our
conditioning in other words it comes out of acceptance
change comes from acceptance e
but don't accept yourself so as to change
yourself just say
yes to everything that's always inspired a
no okay here I am
the end of
Shame e
don't be annoying with yourself
nitpicking it's wise loving the face of
conditioning then it's all
conditioning
for for
just putting down all the annoying behavioral modification programs you run
on your
yourself the carrot and the
stick just stop running the game on
yourself for just these
moments open your heart to the
totality what you are we'll figure out the detail tells
later
e
e e
maybe feels natural to
uh say something in our minds like
uh man may be
happy may be safe
protected may it be a
peace
e e
for
[Music]
e
okay
I don't know where that meditation came from but somewhere somewhere in
there this hasn't been super systematic guiding of meditation practice to be
honest but uh today we
uh yeah got on some kind of met up uh self-acceptance
train anyway we find our way with practice I don't know what's going to come up in me each
morning so uh mudita
um usually rendered as as sympathetic Joy kind of delighting in the wealth the
love in the face of Good Fortune the welfare of
other and it's kind of known as a little bit of a tricky
one because you you can't you know you can't force
Joy Moda is not supposed to be like those childhood pictures where like the
a family photo where the children are commanded to smile and you can just see
the weird awkward preoccupation and complicity with the
author the prevailing authorities just as
we smile have a lot of child photos like
that when I'm not protesting being photographed a lot of force
smiles and uh this is not that
with kindness compassion the physiological kind of reality of those
States is more more easily evoked than Joy it can [Music]
be you know can feel like not pretending you know to get into Jo you know get
into compassion get into kindness Vita can be a little bit more
tricky and so we don't have to pretend we take
our time with the physiology often it's about putting down other
burdens and then we're freed up for
Joy the sutas
um it's characterizes the an antidote to
resentment which is you know I don't know what the poly word was but but um
that's interesting mudita joy as an antidote to
resentment right we see so much so much resentment so little
capacity to Delight in the welfare of others so from the um the angut
Naya uh there's no way that when mudita is has been develop pursued Ed the
Reigns given a grounding steadied
Consolidated that resentment will still keep overpowering the
Mind colleague uh kind of queen queen of uh mudita to Salah
Seattle and um she sometimes just goes off with the mood that's her favorite
she's Relentless I remember one time I I I think I'll read a a piece
from her um where we were co- teing online and
um I think this is 2021 you so like deep in the pandemic
and uh I don't know she just went off I remember like my face was aching like
literally aching cuz I I was uh she just kept going for like an
hour or something anyway so she says uh I just
transcribed what she said um we've uh come to my favorite favorite moment in
all of d uh I don't know when I opened this Pandora's Box it's not the way I
grew up with this energy I don't know anywhere in my life I would have said oh
yeah Joy is what I would call life I grew up in a very difficult childhood
spent the bulk of my life poor on welfare Joy would not be the underlying
feature of experience I would point out but somewhere in dma I stumbled upon
this mudita it's been a game Cher so let me see if I can try to help
you see where I'm pointing to there's a great difference between mudita and the
kind of worldly joy that we could try to access regularly in our lives I imagine that each one of us on
this call there are 56 of us we all get two Joys two moments of joy in our lives
that's all you get two opportunities of joy and if you're like me we've already
used them up so there's no joy for the rest of the year you've already had it
so the only way you get to access a level of Joy has to come um from someone
else if I start telling you about Joy I have because you're human you'll feel it
if I begin to cry you'll feel that if I tell you about some sadness some
difficulty in my life you'll feel that and likewise I realized I could feel the
joy of another person and there would never be a day or a moment that I would not feel Joy never
it's not possible there are like billions of people on the earth and at
any given moment somebody somewhere is experiencing joy and all I have to do is
be willing to tap into that joy and feel it with them my granddaughter is four years old
she's learning about jokes and she starts laughing she'll say something
like and then they said go away and she starts laughing U
riously and I'm laughing and that's not even funny but I'm laughing because
she's laughing so hard like she's told some great joke it's just another way of
experiencing The Human Condition we're so
interconnected so Joy um
it's um it's important it's important to find ways of putting
down our pain even when that pain can't be
resolved and it feels irresponsible to do that how can I
leave these you know uh Loose Ends of my life
unresolved Joy is a kind of um illegitimate can't
can't risk it but it's important sometimes it can feel like Joy
is a way of of um cheating on your grief
a kind of emotional adultery of some
kind but no all compatible and part of the Dharma is that it makes Mak our
emotional life more and more Supple such that the trace of the last moment
becomes less and less a moment of Joy followed by a Moment of grief followed
by humor and none of the prior States kind of leave a trace you
know we can just be available for the full range of our emotional life
sometimes it's easier to talk about removing deconstructing the
obstacles to Joy rather than creating joy and so what what obstructs
mudita ownership possessiveness comparing mind
andv the The Reflex of ego is to incorporate all goodness into
itself kind of like an amiba right I think I remember that like an amoeba
just incorporating some food into itself that same my ego tolerates no
goodness outside itself it must appropriate everything everyone's
Joy appropriate our own spiritual practice fruits of
that and so we have to snap out of self viw to truly enjoy another's
happiness now I I'm not suggesting that uh mudita is like a
public policy you know meaning that we Overlook all conditions that might
engender Envy the disparities of health and wealth which are
unsustainable this is not a public policy this is about the heart of the
practitioner so um the essayist Joseph Epstein quoting the the uh like this
quote um the seven deadly sins of lust and gluttony greed laziness wrath pride
and envy and uh says uh of the seven deadly
sins only Envy is no fun at all it's really
not envy is usually about two people jealousy usually about three a
triangle and um you know some of this may have
evolutionary benefit right but uh we should not deify
the mechanisms of evolution Evolution doesn't care about it Freedom even a
little you know we're here because we're the sufferers in a
sense this is from evolutionary psychology despite the manifold
unhappiness that jealousy creates jealousy has a crystalline functional logic precise
purposes and supreme Sensibility exists today in modern humans because
those in the evolutionary past who were indifferent to the sexual contact that their mates had with others
lost the evolutionary contest to those who became jealous as the descendants of successful
ancestors modern humans carry with them passions that led to their forebear
success the legacy of this success is a dangerous passion that creates
unhappiness but the unhappiness motivated adaptive
action over human evolutionary
history it's jealousy and then Envy
Envy Envy shows us where we're identified Envy uh illuminates
the the sacred Cows of our go and wherever we're identified it
impaires love identification impaires
love in a sense Envy highlights the
insanity of egoic
life just
it doesn't work it's
painful mat you Ricard in every instance Envy is the product of a wound to
self-importance and the fruit of an illusion what can other people's
happiness possibly deprive us of nothing of course only the ego can be wounded by
it and feel it pain these are the results of our having
forgotten our innermost potential for affection and
peace the more sufficient we feel the more we affirm the kind of tender acceptance
that I was alluding to in the Sith the more sufficient we feel the the
more free read up we are to Delight radically in the well-being of
others we become more fluid inside and that
fluidity um is uh makes the well-being the success
the Excellence of others not a threat to our own egoic fragility but but just a
source of delight there's no comparison in it at all it's just partaking in
goodness yeah and so the Delight of others
becomes totally unthreatening so much joy so much
joy I see I know my nickname is captain buzkill and I talk relentlessly about
suffering but it's in the service of
Joy okay offer this for your consideration and uh we'll gather back
tomorrow uh in the same time and uh if you uh wish to uh join for a social half
hour um links in the uh
description uh and on on my website just my full name.org pr.org
okay thank you all