Peter from Virginia hi Peter
welcome I'm Pat and I'm from selito it's tonight hi everybody hi pad welcome from
saso maranne in Berling gate hi
marann we're Jake Issa and Remy from Golden Colorado hi hi Ja and Remy that's
Remy and that's Issa [Laughter]
H and Issa hi and Jake trees are crowd love it oh that's
so sweet so sweet oh my God that's so sweet me New Hampshire hi every
Neil and bill says hi from Dallas and here from San Diego PMA from India good
morning to you Padma Isabelle from Pacifica California
Julie from Massachusetts David from Fort Worth rain from San Francisco yay the S
has assembled it's very sweet so any last minute hell before before we
transition Susan from wut Creek hi Susan
welcome so let's transition thank you Neil for posting
information about hi hour Google Groups if you're new to high appear uh you are
invited to join the mailing list if you like to get the references and quotes
and things like that afterwards uh after the teachings and at this time I change the settings so that
um unmuting oneself won't be possible and also so that the space stays quiet
and also chats will just come to me but please uh let that channel be um quiet
and and last but not least turning on recording for the sake of Audio
Dharma here we go hello everyone hello and welcome to happy hour lovely to see
you lovely to be with you in this space and uh as you've noticed I've been
teaching this whole week uh because Liz has been uh away on Retreat so I've got
to the opportunity the the the the joy to to be with you almost every night
um not tomorrow though uh bruny will be teaching tomorrow so anyway so for today
I'd like to continue with the theme of this week the theme of this week has been
equinity for obvious reasons because it's been a very busy week with lots of
news and tumultuousness no matter which side you're on it's been
busy and full and exciting so times like or or exciting one way or the other
anyway I'm going to just leave that you know the V the feeling tone might be positive or negative but regardless
equinity is the practice for times like this equinity establishing ourselves in in
groundedness in in uprightness in calm in neither
being pushed away nor being dragged into the sense of um yeah equinity equipoise
that's another alternative translation of uh of opa opa often translated as
equinity equipoise calm balance balance also um another very helpful translation
so I like to continue this week um with equin practice and of course can do
these practices in so many different ways in the past few nights I've um
starting Monday night I entered it in a different way similarly Tuesday and
Wednesday and tonight we'll find our way with in different ways of of entering
and and holding and cultivating equo equinity all right that's enough of uh a
setting a uh framework for what we will do and uh let's begin let's begin
so let's land let's arrive in our
seats there you're standing so whether you're standing sitting lying
down whatever posture you might have in this moment
inviting yourself to connect and really become
aware of this body sitting standing whatever posture
it has really become aware how it is
folded or unfolded it
and inviting your body to relax soften
and your heart to relax as much as
possible receiving receiving the sensations of breathing in breath and
out breath in the abdomen or anywhere else that the breath
is very
clear and whatever is arising in the heart the body and the
mind making space kindly gently L lovingly not
pushing it away it's like this right
now can I be okay with however things are in this moment in this body this
mind and heart and just that that acceptance of
what's present can create a little more
space more balance see for yourself
e
e e
Let each breath in breath out breath bring more nourishment to the
heart more stability here sweet heart here it's okay just be
here with whatever is present it's
okay with meta encouragement
stability trust we can be with this I can be with
this gently kindly give with
space pity equipoise doesn't mean not caring or being
eled it has warmth care
stability care that is so stable
spacious it doesn't get toppled
make sure there's plenty of care and patience to support what's
arising
e
e e
if the mind has wondered at their thoughts contact with the body
breath as weakened reconnect with the body sitting
stably with feet firmly on the earth spine upright strong back soft B
belly each moment of presence and
equinity right here right now
equipoise it strengthens our
ability to be more stable stably caringly
present for the future moments this is the Supreme training right here right
now if the mind was lost had wondered it's okay no problem begin again this is
a fresh moment Begin Again with a
smile how wonderful I get to train myself thus I get to practice
for the sake of myself and everyone else in breath out
breath if it helps to bring some phrases of
equinity you can drop in things are as they are right
now may I
accept may I have stability presence
care with things as they are right now or simply it is what it
is
e
e e
I'd like to invite you to tune
into as if you were tuning
old radio right now they're all digital but if you're turning and a tuning
finding how equipoise even if there is a little bit of it
present balance uprightness
care is a source of strength
source of strength in the
heart and strengthen the body maybe you find yourself sitting more
upright feeling more balanced in your mind more stable more
grounded
just a tiny bit more see if you can tune into
it
e e
e
feeling our strong back strong posture soft
front soft belly
[Music] gently grounded
present holding whatever this
moment is it rising and passing is giving rise to
as we turn to bring this sit together to a close appreciating that we do this
practice in community bringing the goodness the recollection of the goodness of others
our fellow practitioners who are practicing with us bringing it to our
heart allowing it to bring some joy gladness support how they support us and
we support them we support each other as rhda
said we're walking each other home we're just walking each other
Home May our practice be a support to all beings
everywhere may it be cause and conditioned for
peace happiness well-being freedom for ourselves
and everyone may all beings be well may all beings be
happy thanks everyone Thanks for practice thanks for sitting
together ah I don't know about you I feel better
more stable grounded peaceful yeah maybe I'll invite you again tonight
if you wanted to um put a word or phrase in
chat and my word tonight is calm yeah
calmer see there's so many words I could put in but it's one
word chat is now open to everyone if you like
and um balance enlightened hope
reassured nice allowing everything nice tonight and most
grateful deep calm grounded
peace grounded Serene better than before that's good I like that then is
just great that is just great that's
lovely clear another reflection coming in great at home with myself oh that's
lovely oh just loving reading your Reflections everyone less frantic great
great settled it's the next one that came privately so Lov
ly released is one word coming from our
fellow practitioners on YouTube are joining us live it's lovely
yeah so now on Zoom those of you on Zoom we have the
opportunity to take our less frantic more
settled at home sense of flow all the
um words that have come up you've brought in what you're feeling into tuning into we have the opportunity to
inhabit them in interaction so we're raising the bar a
little bit might be easier when your eyes are closed just practicing on your own to feel these beautiful qualities
now keep tuning into them in community you may not say so much you may just
offer a few words and listen more but see if you can keep tuning into these
qualities in community this is this is really great soundbox to see how we can
keep our groundedness our peace or Clarity um calm Etc when we are in
community again maybe you just say a few words may not there may not be a lot of words
tonight but uh but important practice so you're invited to practice meta in small
groups me TTA mindfully listening and speaking
with others staying in your body staying in your body embracing compassion and
kindness whatever rises in the body staying on toping and the topic is how
is uh how can you stay tuned with the quality that you
um had tuned into in community what supports you really this is a
live um interactive exploration as I'm teaching and I want
to stay tuned with settledness with calm oh I feel my feet on the on the
earth I take a deep breath this way I can still talk and share with you and
still have a sense of calm this is important so that in interactions I can
keep this so this is really important prompt tonight everyone please stay with
it take turns briefly let everyone share avoiding cross talk giving each other
advice and again you might just say a few words you may not say much tonight might be very quiet space in the
breakout rooms as you tune into it in real time oh oh okay
well I notice I'm getting a little agitated as I'm expecting myself to say
something profound okay I'm just going to pause you know this is I'm I'm modeling what you might be saying in
small groups I'm modeling on oh okay I'm going to pause take a deep breath okay I
don't have to say anything profound I can just be and say thank you thank you
for holding witness holding me witness anyway in Real Time explore it in real time
so enough instructions enough invitations oh yes and let's uh let the
order be uh reverse alphabetical order first name tonight RSE alphabetical
order and um yeah might be quiet tonight so let's see let's let's see what
happens all right I'm going to create the breakout rooms now inviting you to
to take care of yourselves with kindness each other and here we
go
e
e e
welcome back everyone I see Smiles which is always
sweet so uh let's uh open the the space let's see chat is
already open and um yeah so um if you like to
share any Reflections comments
questions would love to hear from you so what's what's a lie for you how was this
practice for you especially I'm curious what did you find when you tried to tune into eonic the equipoise while
interacting with others what did you find was helpful in real time to keep
your stability and balance and again remember you're sharing your uh if you choose to share
you're sharing for the benefit of others as well as yourself being witnessed
so I see Isabelle's hand let's see there
you go
uh it was really nice to not pressure myself to have to talk say as many words
as I usually do that was really nice I often feel that way and I don't I'm not
in tune with it so it was really nice to have it be okay tonight to do that nice
yeah thanks for sharing this it's always okay it's always okay not to say much
just say if you were and I appreciate you you being in tune with that and naming that tonight that it was
supportive for you it's great Jerry um thank you Nikki and thank you
for the original the direction on the larger group I think I was answering
that it seemed that um anxiety be gets anxiety anger begets
anger so the calmness of people's voices within the small group certainly added
to my sense of um keeping myself anchored
so tones of voices can certainly contribute to nice nice the calm voice
of your fellow practitioners helped you be more calm this is lovely thanks for
sharing this Jerry ah so nice such a great support and yes
absolutely anxiety begets more and fear be gets more fear Etc it's the law of
karma this moment reconditions the next moment increases the probability of the
next moment being of the same ilk if we're angry In This Moment the probability of us being angry in the
next moment increases call it karma call it Neuroscience actually karma is more
holistic anyway not just to reduce it to our just to the what happens in in one
organ anyway Susan so I have been very emotional for the
last even even before the election I've been have an emotional um week and so um it was my
word was balance and when I was in the breakout room I just kept breathing
really deeply and that really helped me do that and at one point I could just by
something that someone said that had it didn't trigger me or anything like that but I get some emotion around it because
it was about women and I was able to like close my eyes and just be in that
moment and have it be okay thank you you yes great thank you
Susan yay we can keep our equinity and equipoise our balance our calm in the
midst of what could be agitating or triggering ah the the world for all of
us would be a much more wonderful place to be both how we are for ourselves how
we interact with others or less we don't fly off the handle this is wonderful thanks for sharing this suan so for you
deep breathing really brought this sense of present presence in what was happening to your body to Dear to
realize okay dear I need to close my eyes just be with this ah it's okay I can be with this lovely yay thank you I
see if you um Reflections in chat bill says what helped me was awareness of the
chair I'm sitting on like part of being embodied great great awareness of the
chair yay embodiment is that is is is exactly feeling where your B what your
body is feeling internally as well as the touch points so feeling the chair is great thanks
Bill Marian says what helped me was saying I will be settled no matter what to myself made it intention yes the
power of intention love it thank you Baran thanks for sharing that very
powerful yeah powerful practice tonight and especially I really Lov how you
shared you really took on uh this practice instruction invitation to
practice with it in real time and goodness if we can take this to our interactions in daily life somebody says
something and we just get reactive and we don't even notice and fly off the handle and stay stay and we might
respond of course but we might respond from place of balance and care than
rather than reactivity so dear ones let's let's
close it seems like it's enough it's been a quiet night we'll have more
silence so thank you all thank you for your presence for your practice for the sake of yourselves and all beings
everywhere may all beings be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves thanks everyone I'll let you unmute in a moment
bar cof when is goodbye but I'm going to stop the recording first stop YouTube