hello on this Monday morning
uh and welcome for those of you who were here on
Friday apologies for our technological challenges here at IMC and uh things had
been changed in the recording uh equipment and not put back
together properly so that it took a while to figure out what the issue was and so we didn't really do last Friday
and and um works out well because uh I'll finish the series
today and then um uh I have a four-part series for the
rest of the week so that works out
so the topic last week was the Four Noble Truths
and the Buddha has this very uh strong orientation to look at conditionality to
look at how one thing conditions another one thing sets up the conditions for
something else to arise and so uh
suffering is not all bad bad in the Buddhist
teachings because suffering is the necessary condition to
really understand suffering to see it to stop for it to care for it sets up the
conditions for having an inspiration a confidence a
faith uh in a path to the ending of
suffering and uh and that is a beautiful thing to have and to have an inspiration an
enthusiasm a confidence a trust the classic word is
Sada which is often translated to English as Faith so whichever one whichever one of
those words works for you and so as we start the meditation
today to call upon your whatever confidence whatever
trust whatever enthusiasm and inspiration Faith you have in this
practice as a way of addressing the challenges of this life so that you can give yourself more
wholeheartedly to the Simplicity of mindfulness the Simplicity
of being aware here now
and it's a powerful thing to be mindful to be aware to understand and know and
feel what's happening because that kind of offering of presence offering of
attention uh re uh takes away some of the energy
of preoccupation of anxiety of desires of
attachments of being lost in thought and takes this life energy of who we are and
begins putting it in a good direction the good direction of simple
awareness so to assume a meditation
posture think of it as a posture of
attention and whatever way that works for you whatever posture works for you
assume that posture with some care that it feels like your whole body
is going to be
attentive gently closing the
eyes and take taking a few gently long
breaths just comfortable enough to feel the rib cage the Torso
expand and as you exhale maybe a [Music]
longer exhale than
usual so that you can relax let go settle in here
and letting your breathing return to
normal and continuing to relax and as you relax the
body feel like you're relaxing into
some inner depth some place deep
inside that where you feel stability
steadiness
subtleness relaxing face shoulders belly
chest as it works for you
and then letting your breathing breathe itself and letting
yourself be quiet quieter and Stiller no longer making any effort to
relax Stiller quieter attentiveness
here to the body breathing maybe an
attentiveness a sensing from within the body
itself for
and in the quiet of sitting here
can you find or remind yourself touch
into whatever you have that's
a gentle yes to being
mindful to being present with
attention to be aware
here and that yes might be a confidence and
awareness a trusting and
mindfulness an inspiration or enthusiasm for simple attention
it might be the faith in this path of
practice whatever it might be I'm summarizing it with the word
yes is there some place in your
body that's the home that's a source deep inside for
that yes for that inspiration
confidence and if there
is rest there
breathe with that place breathe through
it let your yes arise from the place of Faith or
confidence to support simple
awareness of what is here
now maybe with a Simplicity of
breathing in the midst of all other things that you're going
on
e
e e
whatever is challenging for you difficult for you
thoughts feelings if they should have rise as you
meditate remind yourself of your ability to say
yes to being
aware yes to putting your life energy into being
aware rather than
preoccupied
e
for
e e
letting your mindful
flow out of a quiet gentle
yes to being aware
here e
now
e
for
e e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting to appreciate that it's quite
rare for people to stop to be really attentive and aware of
their experience and even more
rare that they know something about how to hold their suffering their stress
their tensions their challenges in
Awareness nonreactive awareness an awareness that
clarifies awareness that allows some deeper healing and understanding
an awareness that
interrupts the train wreck of just thinking over and over
again in ways that perpetuate
suffering and this ability to be
present for challenging es is a growing capacity we learn from
this practice and it becomes a gift that we can give to
others and we can be present without perpetuating the
reactivity that others have that just groups of people have that we can be a calm
clear presence to see
clearly that maybe helps others to be Cal for helps others to be See
Clearly to helps others to be seen well so we don't see them through our
reactivity may it
be that in our yes to
awareness there can well up within us the wish for others
happiness may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful and may all beings be free
and may we find a way today to contribute this into our
world no matter how small the gesture the attention the care that we
give may we support the welfare and happiness of those we meet
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello and today I'm going to conclude the five-part series that I started last
week on the four noble truths to the end of
suffering and um and so the fourth Noble Truth is the
noble truth of the practice the way the method that leads to the end of
suffering that goes to the end of suffering and um and uh the the the the
way the practices that lead to it are defined as the or described as the
eight-fold path and these are
amazing uh practices that are not exactly only
practices they are states of beings qualities of
character almost that can build up inside of us so that at some point they
are not practices but rather who we are they're so integrated into the
fabric of our being fabric of our character our
personality that um they're no they are no longer practices but at first they are
practices but I say I make this point because um the idea is that this is not
importing a practice from outside it's an it might feel like that
way at first but it's really learning to awaken something inside that uh can flow
through us that can uh be kind of our own that of course we're this
way and um so uh the uh eful path begins with of
course I'll be present for suffering of course I'll attend to it
because to not do that will make it worse now if attending to suffering does
make it worse then maybe that's not the right call for now something else is
needed then some other preparation work but some point in this for Noble Truth
process there's a yes to being present for suffering
being present for it so that we can start seeing the cause in attachment and
craving present forward so we can notice first the moments and then the longer
periods where the suffering is no longer there appreciate that it's not constant
but then in some kind of way more attentive more careful we are here in the present moment the more we can see
that um it it does wax and Wayne and when it decreases that's
something important to see and if it decreases enough sometimes by accident sometimes because we're distracted it
shows us it's we're not NE necessarily stuck in our what we call
suffering and so willingness to say yes to attention yes this is called right
view right to attention to suffering and then as we become become more
sensitive to ourselves there comes this right attitude or right resolve which is
to avoid um being cruel avoid being
unkind avoid being attached and caught up in all kinds of addictive sensual
behaviors and actions there's a sense that there's something here deep within that does not
want to harm ourselves or harm others through acts of Cruelty and so care and
compassion become prominent doesn't want to be unkind but rather wants to be
friendly doesn't want to be caught up in addictive behavior wants to be free of
them there's uh as we practice there then it follows then that we want to be
careful with our speech this our speech should should be kind
speech should at least avoid lying our speech should not be harsh speech should
not be um slander not because it's a should that
we have to take on because it grows out of this practice of sensitivity to
suffering and to stress and to the ouches of what are in of course we don't
want to create more stress for ourselves of of course we don't want to create something that's going to harm
ourselves and the height heightened sensitivity we have we can feel that um
harsh language lying language slanderous language is
um harms something within ourselves it diminishes something it closes something
it limits us and the same thing with um right action which is to avoid killing
and stealing and sexual misconduct that these things
also limit us harm us cause difficulties and so uh so if we want to
continue this heightened sensitivity of mindfulness heightened sensitivity to suffering in the end of
suffering we want to live in a way that doesn't go against the grain of that we
want to live in a way that doesn't decrease our sensitivity but actually increases our sensitivity to uh be more
attentive more careful same thing with uh the way we live our life livelihood and Lifestyles
to be careful with those that those don't cause harm and then there's a right effort
which is to be very careful now of inner states of Mind inner states of being
that we can sense and feel the difference between UNH wholesome ways of being and wholesome healthy ways of
being states of mind and unhealthy healthy so we can have the sensitivity
keep growing because unhealthy states of Mind decreases our sensitivity to the path to the freedom
to the end of suffering wholesome wholesome ones increases
it develop concentration develop mindfulness right
mindfulness and right concentration these all support this movement to a greater presence greater sensitivity to
this experience here and so the Eightfold the the the fourth Noble Truth is doing those
practices that cultivate the conditions for a greater attentiveness sensitivity
so that wisdom can arise within so a deeper understanding can arise so we
become sensitive to and inspired by a yes to
suffering being present for it and seeing it seeing the cause of it and
seeing the sensation of it letting go letting go more deeply letting go of all
the things that involve some kind of self harm all the ways in which we
contribute to our suffering our anguish our distress our anxiety the whole gamut
that's under the umbrella term Dua suffering the emotional pain that we
contribute to and so knowing that there are these eight
practices um and they're practices that are pointing us back to ourselves not
taking us away so we have to be very careful how we practice them that they're not holding on to them to like a
like a um life ring keeping us afloat and just uh or as
a you know as a something to do that takes us away from ourselves the four the eight full
eight practices of the eight full path are practices that really help us be
here in Awareness in attention the heightened sensitivity to this life of
ours and they create the conditions these eight practices that create the conditions for greater and greater
capacity to understand to have Clarity to be present and develop kind of
strength behind the mindfulness a strength behind our presence as strength
behind our dedication to a path that ends
suffering and it's not just for ourselves we do this path but we also
can do it for others as we do this path and develop along the Buddhist PR practice at some point it doesn't make a
lot of sense to keep doing it if we only do it for ourselves at some point the inspiration
that comes to keep doing this practice even for yourself is for the benefit of
others so you can be a conduit to benefits you can be an inspiration you could be someone who doesn't cause harm
someone who lives for the welfare and happiness of others so um the hateful path don't
cause Awakening but they lead to Liberation
they are a gradual path that leads to heightened care sensitivity a heightened
wholesomeness heightened letting go that supports us to eventually uh see and
experience the end of suffering in a very dramatic and full
way and at that point the e-fold path
takes on a very different uh flavor very different nature because at some point
it's really clear that the eful path it uh is not not practices anymore but are
ways of living that emerge almost naturally almost part of who we are that
we live this way rather than we have to do them and um and that's a amazing
Tipping Point that brings a tremendous amount of Happiness so that will be the topic for
the next four days of this week I'll start a new series of four part series
um called um for happiness and and uh and this is the uh
what what I'm calling kind of a little bit my own categories but the four truths of happiness or the four noble
truths of happiness because it's directly ties into um the the fruition
of the four noble truths and now there's the four noble happy Noble happinesses
so that'll be the topic and um I will look forward to start starting
that uh tomorrow and um I thank you very much
for being here today and may it be that um you take some of these this yes this
Faith this inspiration or enthusiasm or confidence you have in mindfulness and
see if you can bring it into your life so that it just you you naturally find
yourself more sensitive more aligned with the Eightfold Path the
eight factors or whatever part of it you can
remember so thank you very much and I look forward to tomorrow