good morning everyone or good day and welcome to
Monday welcome to a new day or for those of you listening later welcome to maybe
a new
meditation so one of the qualities that the Buddha said is
supports going deep into meditation is
gratitude a thankfulness not just gratitude as an
idea but thankfulness as a feeling thought a a feeling a inner sense of
inspiration maybe that um and one of those is um
really a deep appreciation for what is going
right there's a lot that has to be going right right now for us to be able to breathe for us
to be able to listen to attend to sit to
meditate and to not be so involved in our stories our concerns
our ideas of past and future what happened and what might
happen to overlook the Marvel The
Wonder of all that we receive at this moment to be
alive alive well enough to engage in
meditation and so uh to meditate with that
appreciation so that the call the
inspiration the relaxing into the present
moment has this flavor this welcome this
inspiration of how good it is all that is that we can appreciate here and
now and one way way to practice this
appreciation uh a wonderful word that might really wake something up inside of
you maybe even Inspire more appreciation
more gratitude um why
not is the word wow
wow this body is breathing even if breathing is difficult it's still
breathing wow I have the ability to be aware where
did that come from this whole universe the evolution of from The Big
Bang this arose this phenomenal capacity
in a sense for the universe to know itself in all these rich and varied ways
that we know recognition and Sensations and
hearing and seeing and thinking
wow and a variation of wow that is a kind of a
Thanksgiving is to say yes to meet whatever is here with
yes yes to this Wonder of being aware yes to this
Wonder of choosing to be present here and now in our lived
life so to sit with appreciation to sit with gratitude for
every breath we take for every moment of awareness we
have to sit present here
now so assuming a posture for an for
appreciative
mindfulness and with this body of yours to let your
attention go inwards perhaps supported by closing
your eyes
going inward like you're dipping into refreshing warm maybe cool of water cool
a pool of
water and gently in inhaling more fully than
usual so you can better feel this body of yours your torso your rib cage your
belly and a longer exhale almost a leisurely long
exhale to settle in here
letting your breathing return to
normal and continue on the exhale to settle
in relaxing the body
softening the mind the thinking mind e
and feeling the weight of your body on your chair
cushion
bed where the contact of your body the weight and the surface that holds you
up reminds you that you are really here now
and then sitting here with the
understanding that for us to be meditating much more is going right than
going wrong right now here
breathing in breathing
out in gratitude in
appreciation with the Quiet quietest possible
words saying [Music]
wow wow to being alive being
present while to being aware even if what you're aware
of is challenging wow
for every challenge there's lots that's going
right to even know you're
challenged for every wow what a wondrous
thing to have the ability to appreciate
for
e
e e
with every breath
appreciation Wonder
gratitude
wow that is stronger than the distracted
mind just here now
wow yes
for
e
e e
and then coming to the end of this
meditation instead of a kind of dedication of Merit I offer a kind of a
dedication or of gratitude
may we offer gratitude for the safety and well-being
we have received may we offer
gratitude for the blessing of this Earth that we have
received may we offer gratitude ude for the measure of Health we have
received may we offer gratitude for family and
friends may we offer gratitude for
community may we offer gratitude for the teachings that I have received
may we offer gratitude for the life we have
received may we walk through the world today in
gratitude for those we [Music] meet things that we do the experiences
we have look for opportunities to be grateful to appreciate
to be wow not to be panish not to overlook the
things which are
difficult but as a way of not doing the opposite not
overlooking the good not overlooking what we can be grateful for because we're
preoccupied with what isn't right
may we live in
[Music]
gratitude thank you
e
so good morning and a good day and welcome to this first five-part series a
talk on gratitude series on
gratitude and um gratitude is a Buddhist
topic and um one of the nice things about gratitude is that with other
kind of foundational practices of Buddhism like
generosity ethics it puts us uh more closely
connected connect to a healthier relationship with others gratitude
that's sincere is a beautiful way to be in relationship with other people and
helps establish healthy relationships being
ethical uh not causing harm but actually working for the benefit of people also
benefits the the relationships the relatedness in all directions and the third is gratitude to
be grateful and uh uh sincere gratitude is
a wonderful leavening for our society for our communities It's a Wonderful sharing of
our hearts with other people it's a wonder wonderful way to see and acknowledge other people for whom we're
grateful the Buddha had this Wonder has this wonderful
teaching there are uh
four qualities of a person who is wise
skillful a good person who maintains oneself without
causing any s self harm who is blameless and Beyond reproach from the
wise and who generates much Merit the only way the Buddha defines
Merit or describes it is with the word happiness it's almost
synonymous one generates much happiness so four things four actions
four ways of living that the
wise uh maintain themselves as a good person what
for goodness in bodily conduct goodness in verbal
conduct goodness in mental conduct
and gratitude and thankfulness possessing these four
qualities one generates much happiness
so it's so this gen uh goodness and conduct is more than just being ethical
it's being generous it's being doing all kinds of beneficial things for oneself
and for others there's a goodness there's a healthiness there's a a
beneficence there's a benevolence there's a beauty uh one of the words for good
actions the Buddha uses beautiful actions so there's doing these beautiful
things but then one of them that's has its own category is a grateful and
thankful and there's two words here because the word for grateful in Pik K
Anu uh kind almost almost a literal English translation would be um
acknowledgement it's uh knowing what's been done for us but knowing it as a
special thing being grateful for it being appreciative of it valuing it and
um and then the other thankfulness uh at least in pully uh
the the um the Grateful is kind of what goes out is towards the person the thing
that we're grateful for maybe an expression of gratitude the acknowledgement of what has been
done the the thankfulness is the feeling the emotional impact of being grateful
so there's two directions that gratitude goes It goes outward to what we're
grateful for an inward to the the heartwarming
effect the inspiring effect the goodness the smile that we're given and smile of
the heart when someone or something H happens that we receive goodness we
receive benefit we receive inspiration we something really nice happens to
us and um and to appreciate both directions uh sometimes uh thankfulness
it's only in the direction of others or to what's being what we're receiving the object of what we that's giving us
something it can be a calculation and a duty and a custom to be thankful and so
it's only kind of uh come you know tongue deep we might
say um and um but if it's only taking it in for ourselves like Ah that's great I
feel so much pleasure it's so nice it's so wonderful um then it's then it
doesn't enter into the world of our relationships it doesn't enter into the richness of our interpersonal life which
is a huge part of the heart itself the heart is not distinct from our interpersonal life so but to do both to
have it Go in both directions is a beautiful thing so this adds points to
the Ecology of gratitude and I want to uh discuss a few things there are the
Ecology of gratitude the first is that um uh part of
gratitude that has to do with the you know what we receive from the world from
others is um uh to appreciate that we've
benefited from someone or something appreciating we're benef we've
benefited from the air the clean maybe if we can the Clean Air that we can
breathe or that we can breathe at all to feel the benefit of receiving
food to all these people who work hard in their lives to provide us with the
benefits that keep us fed keep us uh hydrated to keep us um be able to navigate this world
that provided the internet so that we can be and the technology that we can be
doing this wonderful 7 a.m. together so to acknowledge the benefits the
goodness that comes from something so that's the first part kind of the first level of of this external
gratitude the second uh is to recognize how it comes to us the intention or the
attitude uh the goodness that it comes from uh if someone offers us uh a um
something out of Duty if someone in a store is paid to be
a door opener and they open the door it's nice we can appreciate it and be beneficial for it but if we're
struggling with something and we maybe we're uh you know we're on crutches or something and uh someone goes out of
their way to show up and open the door for us they don't have to but uh they
really they really care about us they want to support us they have some Compassion or care or friendliness or
kindness and you can feel there's so much more than they're being paid for this doing this nice thing for you
they're actually there's just goodness that comes from them friendliness and so
to feel that there's much more being given than the door being opened we're
being given someone's inner goodness we're given someone's love or friendliness or Good
Will and so that so then the Gratitude we feel has a different quality
based on how much people are giving of themselves they giving something of their own
heart and the third is is it done specifically for us and uh sometimes um someone might be
very want to help a lot of people they do a lot of things um but um someone
maybe Cooks a big meal because they want you and other people to be wellfed but
they don't know who you are and they leave the they finished their doing their cooking they gr lab they could do
what they could do they have other things to do and um so you hear this wonderful person has benefited you has
done it with a lot of goodness in their heart but they actually don't know you you don't know them maybe and so there's
um uh so the the ACT hasn't done specifically for you but maybe that
person Cooks the food and then comes out and actually hands it to you uh and says
thank you for being here I'm so glad to be able to cook for you and you know they're thanking you and you know and so
and so now there's a personal connection so there could be these different levels and the third one maybe
is the one that can touch us the most provided it doesn't get complicated for us with senses of
obligation and to distinguish uh gratitude a a offer offer of an offering
that someone does to us from a favor at least in my English a favor sometimes
needs to be returned it's more of an exchange but a a offering is a gift that
someone gives us a gift of opening the door the gift of some food the gift of their time is not meant to be a favor
it's just a gift for you to have and so uh then the the How Deeply that goes
into us can VAR can change and that's the second half of the gr the Ecology of
gratitude is how it how it moves into us uh we can we can know that we've been
benefited there can be a recognition there can be Inspire the mind a light goes off in the mind say wow that's
great but it can be also be a more um a thought an idea an understanding it can
also travel into our heart go into our emotional life we can feel softer uh inspired we can feel a smile
throughout our chest we can feel um love we can feel Delight we can feel a wish
kind of to um meta of Good Will of kindness for
the person who does something for us something melts sometimes something is
inspiring sometimes we can be brought to tears when someone does something exceptional to us that they don't have
to and um and so it can go deeper um and then if it at some point
in this inner Ecology of it we speak out of it we speak thanks we don't just keep it
to ourselves there's something that brings gratitude to a kind of fullness
when we speak it thank you um my the culture that I kind of grew up in
is it's a gratitude culture as I understand it uh in Norway there's a lot
of expressions of thanks that are given there it seems like all day long people are saying thank you for something and
um if you if you uh see a friend when you first meet you'll say thanks for
last time when you finish seeing them and you're going to say go say goodbye one of his Expressions is thanks for now
thanks for the food thanks for um you know all kinds of things and uh and um so to allow the
circle of gratitude which it is the relatedness of gratitude to be complete
or full to speak it or to act it in some way and that's a third thing we can
offer an act in return not out of obligation not out of Duty but because
of the inspiration we have that now we just feel sense of abundance we feel a
sense of goodness we feel a sense of this relationship has a now a beautiful channel in it that the channel of
Communication channel of connectedness that that can be the vehicle now for
wonderful generosity from our part that satisfies or meets these three parts of
of generosity that others can do towards us uh we can do something beneficial for
someone we can do do it because it's really comes from our goodness some good
part within us our generosity our love and uh it can be specifically for
someone else and when I went to practice uh in Japan uh I learned especially in the
monasteries that when you uh give something to someone you give it to them with both
hands and then uh when uh when I study with some of the Zen Masters in Japan
and un united states who are influenc by Japanese culture like one of them I studied with Robert Aken rosi in
Hawaii and in order to become a student you had to do a formal little ceremony and ask him to be a stu your student his
ask to be his student and and you had but you had to give him money a gift of money and there was very particular
instructions about the money you had to give him it had to be $3 three $1 bills and they had to be
brand new $1 bills and and they had to be in a nice envelope and you had to
hand the envelope to him with both hands so the amount of money was
incidental but the the the the whole approach to how it's offered to him uh
the care and you know dollar bills all crumpled up into a ball and thrown at him but it's offered with care and
respect and and kind of an honoring of him with giving him something beautiful the new dollar bills the new nice new
envelope the care and offering it so the three beautiful qualities of gratitude
we offer benefit someone the motivation comes from our
heart uh and we do it personally and those things can when we
receive that on the receiving end we can take it in with acknowledgement of what's happened we can feel the B the
goodness of it we can offer thanks and we can return the
ACT uh through our gratitude so maybe that gives you
something to think about and uh think about the richness and the of uh the
relatedness of gratitude for this day and then we'll continue I'll continue
with this theme on this gratitude week in the United States thank you