good evening welcome
welcome so there's a story that sometimes gets told it's uh in the PO Canon I kind of
like this story briefly it goes like um an individual is uh wandering in the
forest and they we could say stumble upon P like this what looks like a path
like they could tell that you maybe the all the jungle plants aren't quite the
same in this little area so in my mind they're like hacking away
and they uh discover oh yeah this is actually a paved Road or was a paved
Road and they follow it and hacking their way through and they get to what
was an ancient city and with a little bit of work they start
to see oh yeah like here's a wall of a part of the city and looks like of some
uh ponds or lakes or something like this so they don't clear the entire city but
uh enough to get a sense of what was there wow like uh what a
discovery and then they go back and uh tell the king hey I discovered this old
ancient city that's see with this old ancient Road and tells the king that you
know you should maybe like you excavate uh this road and uh the
city and the King does and then and starts to inhabit the city and lives
happily ever after it's one of those kind of
stories and so uh in the poly Canan the Buddha is telling a version of the story of of course you know I'm doing a a
summary of it uh adding a little bit of some of my interpretation in there but the uh Buddha he's saying that
actually he's this is a story where he is the one who made this
discovery and so he's pointing to and this path that he found is the aold path
and this beautiful ancient town is freedom freedom from grief hatred and
delusion freedom from suffering and the King that he goes to tell and that
clears the path and inhabits it is us we're we're the royalty we're the the uh
I don't know Majestic in some kind of way I kind of like this it's not like oh
we're those poor people that have to have everything uh figured out for us but no he's like hey go there and you
can do some of this work and you can live in this city too so there's this sense of like there's
this path that goes to a destination like you could say a journey
and we often say this right we have this expression the spiritual journey and we could also say this
other typical story that's associated with Buddhist studies that is probably
many of you here are familiar with this that is the story of the Buddha himself
his spiritual Journey having there's many different
versions of this story but uh part of the the gist in the version that I'll tell right now is you know having grown
up a life with Incredible privilege everything he wanted everything that was needed and a
lot of extra stuff right so a way to indulge whatever sensual pleasure one
desired I have a way for that to be um have that have those
experiences and uh he was sheltered his father had some concern about what would happen to him when he was late when he
was older so made sure that he had this really sheltered pleasure-filled
life until he's a young man and he leaves this beautiful palace and
encounters old age sickness and death death and some and different
individuals and maybe even uh some versions of the story says he encountered uh monastic as
well and deeply affected by
this that Goa he's not the Buddha yet we'll call him Goa he wants to find a
way there's got to be a way where there isn't this suffering this terrible suffering I don't think he had the idea
that he could end old age or that he could end sickness or that he could completely end death but the suffering
part of it and this is part of the practice right is to be able to recognize there's
this inevitability of the pain we might say the discomforts the extreme
discomforts we might say and distinguishing that from the suffering which is the all the story making and
all the things that the mind is doing associated with it they shouldn't be like this why is this happening to me
these types of things so when he go to my realizing the
futility of these worldly pleasures goes off and seeks the end of suffering and
practices with a number of teachers some teachers realize yep that's not it went in a different
direction yeah that's not it either and then near
death having almost starved him himself to death he uh gains some
sustenance has some insight it's not about avoiding all worldly
pleasures but it's about using pleasure in a way that's
supportive sits underneath the bod tree that's his dedication he's going to
find suffering at the end of suffering he probably he did find suffering while sitting also of course he did but he
also encountered the end of suffering and there's this way that in
so many different ways this journey that he went on afterwards he says you know about the middle way he had one extreme
of this Indulgence and another extreme of aestheticism was one of the teachers he followed and he comes back and shows
the middle way this middle path the journey is in the middle not one extreme
or the other so this whole idea of spiritual journey of this like movement towards
something this development towards something just starting one place and getting in another place as a journey
it's a common theme and certain this uh tradition but something happened this
weekend that made me think about this a little bit differently and I like this idea of a
journey and I could you know talk about my own journey and I'm sure all of you also could talk about Journeys that
you've been not spiritual or otherwise literal or metaphorical but uh somebody said
um I'm looking forward to this adventure kind of like talking about
practice and I thought oh Adventure I want to go on an
adventure like Adventure that sounds like fun it sounds like oh something that's
exciting and thrilling and uh you know that would be uh
enjoyable whereas sometimes this idea of Journey for me it feels like oh
okay okay I guess it'll be a lot of some drudgery and tring through the tough
stuff and you know we have this idea of a hero's journey I don't even know exactly what all the steps are but I
know there's lots of difficulties there's part of them and so I kind of associate that with
journey and so I just started to think about well what would it be like if we considered this practice if we just
changed the language a little bit and started to talk about it as an
adventure instead of part of this spiritual journey this journey because there's
this way in which the language that we use definitely has an impact and I noticed that the way that I
speak or think about things or experience things you know gets expressed differently and maybe that's a
whole another talk on like how I just myself use language a little bit
differently or how we might do that but all of us know that language has an
impact I mean right this is we have whole advertising marketing agencies that are you know built on this and
politicians right all this kind of stuff it's about how we use language so what
if it's an Adventure instead of a journey what of this
idea so what I have some some ways that maybe
to think about this is an adventure also maybe implies some novelty like
something new like oh to like maybe discover something like maybe that first
story that I told about was maybe it was an adventure for this person maybe were just out in the woods or the forest or
jungle whatever and wow this is like such an adventure to discover something and Raiders of the Lost Arc type of
thing you know this like some archaeological find but there's this way in which uh we
might say that the purpose or intention of Journeys versus Adventures are a
little bit different and we might look at this and see as a ways it can support our
practice a journey usually has a defined
destination usually it has or or a purpose spiritual journey I'm going to
develop my spiritual life I'm going to discover more freedom peace ease nibana
whatever it is Enlightenment Awakening happiness whatever it is for
you there's this way where there's not only is there like a destination
Journeys right we can journey to San Jose also but also there's a sense of there's
a progression step one step two step three we go from one place and then the
next and then the next it's only maybe after the completion of step one that we go onto the step two it's only after
getting onto the freeway that we then head south for
example but there's a way
that an adventure maybe has a sense of
spontaneity or this sense of uncertainty it's not so clear what
exactly step one and step two is and it's not so clear like is there a
particular outcome a particular destination and there's this way that
that maybe there's a more of an emphasis on just the
enjoyment of the experience like part of being on an adventure is is the
experience it's not the destination and it turns out this is so
important in this I would say this path of practice using that type of
language not only to like be present for what's happening to be here
now so the sense of time is different or it's not like about a destination that
will be reached in the future but it's about an experience that's being had
right now and a sense of enjoyment there's a sense of the Delight
of being alive the Delight of being present for our
life even if our life is difficult because it's guaranteed there will be difficulties there will be pain this is
what it means to be human it's unavoidable as much as we would like to avoid it it's not
possible so there's this way of an adventure there's more of this spontaneity and uh emphasis on just
being in the present of okay what's happening oh okay what's happening
next instead of like okay I got to do this okay I did that okay check GNA do
the next check right it has a different uh a different attitude a different way
to bring to one's experience and with this is the sense of
adventure is also the sense of exploration like what the sense of
curiosity what's happening what's happening now and with that is um maybe as an
example is this um this idea that if we have this sense
that there's a destination then a difficulty that arises let's say for a meditation period for example we have
the sense of okay I want to be settled I want to have some calmness I want to have some
ease and then we sit down to meditate and we find that uh we're really
drowsy and we just find our s like drifting off has that ever happened to
anybody yeah right right this is part of what happens it's and then if you have
this real clear sense of like okay I want something in particular to happen then this is a real problem this whole
falling asleep and you have to fix it and what are the strategies I have to come up and what did I do last time and
have I learned anything about it or dang it when is this dang meditation period going to end so that there can be uh uh
more energy in the room and I'm not going to fall asleep so much you know there's this whole thing that
happens whereas if this sense of like okay this is an adventure as opposed to
this journey that I have to get to the end of uh when the bell is going to ring then the sleepiness the drowsiness
the sloth and torper what if that's part of the adventure like
wow look at this the mind and the body are like shutting
down and just noticing like wow what is that like I mean this is amazing that
human bodies do this right that they go go go go go and then you know they
sometimes they go to sleep and what's the difference between sleep and awakeness and how does the Mind do this
is it all of a sudden a a shut off or is it a slow slide or is there this long
time where there's this in between so if it's an adventure there could be like some
curiosity and I can recommend this I've spent a lot of time doing this it's
fascinating to bring some mindfulness when you're really tired and bring some mindfulness as best you can to this
watching the I'm doing this with my hands because it kind of feels like this it is feels for me like a slide
into into sleep and sometimes even the mindfulness can follow into into a
little bit of the sleep it's really amazing so it's the same experience
sitting down to meditate and encountering a lot of sleepiness but instead of this journey
like okay I got to get it done it's like oh okay this is part of the adventure I'm just going to be with what's
happening and this is what's happening wow what is it
like and this shift in relationship this turns out to be what
practice is all about this is what practice is all about
is this shift in
relationship so there's this so first is this Journeys we might say have this
defined purpose and destination whereas Adventures have more this spontaneity
and maybe some unpredictability so I also talked about how Journeys are like step one step two
first you go down if you want to leave here and get to the freeway you would
probably find your way [Music] to I forgot the name of this street that
I drive down so many times it's a it's a very nice street I'm sure but I can't remember the
name and you get Hopkins pH that's
it just go down Hopkins and get on El Cino you know this type of thing um
there's this idea of you know step by step and then there can be a sense of
have I finished Step One is it time to do step two or I can't wait till Step One is finished whereas with an
adventure it's just oh I wonder what's going to happen next so there's this
curiosity this openness and this openness this
curiosity what's going to happen next instead of okay okay I'm going to check this off and go to the next step this
curiosity is what helps support this sense of being present and it also
supports this shift and relationship to our experience which is where the freedom is which is where the peace and
well-being lie with this shift in our relationship because all of us have tried to have our life turn out perfect
you know have all the Ducks lined up and I mean even if we do get them lined up
they tend to just swim away and do whatever Ducks do right they don't stay that
way so this idea of an adventure is like just having this curiosity what what's
going to happen next I'm not sure and it allows this natural unfolding of
things because often there's this way that uh
we might we want to try to control things of course we do we we want have
this idea we have this notion that okay if the Ducks were in a row then finally
I'll be happy and it'll be like this lasting reliable happiness if I could just get
these one more duck I got all these other ones and I know my life feels like
that too in some kind of way we could say just like accumulating Ducks but it just seemed like there was endless
always needed more always needed at least one more and then oh no two more
then you know on it goes so this idea of
um having a I'm sorry I just kind of like lost uh
the train I was on there I looked at my notes and my notes have something completely different
here um I was talking what was that you were
adventuring I was adventuring thank you I was talking about this idea now I
remember uh about wanting a sense of control so in some ways we do prefer
like this sense of a journey but I mean we all because it's seems like it would be predictable and
reliable and that it's going to lead us to where we want to go but we can also
remember this idea of you know I'm sure all of us as children for me that's what comes up with this idea of Adventure and
I was remembering I think it's true that uh I think Disneyland has something it's
called a California Adventure right this yeah right so this is something that you know you want to
go on and I said to myself California Journey that sounds like a history class
you know it doesn't sound like the same doesn't have the same sense of you know
what what's going to happen here so we like having this sense of control
but the truth of the matter is we don't
control we don't control nearly what we think we do as much as we think we do
all of us know this I was just telling this little business about ducks right that's just a good example the Ducks are
swimming away or doing whatever they want to do and in the Buddhist language
we would say that things are arising because of causes and conditions we're tired during
meditation there's Myriad of reasons it could be maybe we just don't have enough
sleep maybe we ate a lot maybe we feel really warm or maybe the mind doesn't
really want maybe it touched into something it's not quite ready to be with yet so it's a way to distract or
not be present for something or I mean there's maybe we have took
some medication it has as a side effect to sleepiness right maybe we don't even
know but there's some physiological reason maybe we're getting sick sometimes we feel tired I know I start
to feel tired as a sign that I'm like headed towards some
illness there's so many causes and conditions that we don't even know and we don't control so things arise
due to causes and conditions we don't control them we aren making things happen in the
way that we think we are so in some ways the truth of the
matter is it is an adventure we're trying to turn it into a journey but it
is an adventure in the sense that it's not we're going to go from step one to step two to step three and arrive
exactly where we want to go even let's say you are going to drive to San Jose and maybe this this is a commute that
you do regularly or something like this it's not always the same the traffic isn't the
same the what you're if you're listening to the radio that's not the same the thoughts that you're having isn't the
same the mood that you're having isn't the same it's never exactly the
same you might have like a brilliant idea one day and the other one other day
maybe you're just stewed in something I can't believe they said that and getting
stuck in that or something the truth is it's always an
adventure in some kind of way if we allow it to be and then our life you know comes has
some Vitality some juice to
it and maybe one thing that I'll say also is that some of you might know this
this uh there's these seven factors of Awakening these Seven Elements these
seven qualities that support greater peace ease and
freedom damama Vaya is one of the factors of Awakening
this often gets translated as investigation but we could also
translate it as exploration or maybe like
curiosity like just being open to what's happening so what I'm pointing to here
is a support for awakening it's not I'm I'm not just pulling this out of thin air and uh offering it to you but it's
recognized that this is what's required to find more ease and peace is
it's also what as I said makes our life more
interesting so there's this way in which maybe obstacles can be the ADV
Adventure being in the present moment can be an
adventure this uh even the idea of wow I
wish things were different and how they are maybe that's an adventure opening up to what's going
to happen next because things don't stay the same
we know this you don't need me to tell you this they don't stay the same and it's really amazing if present for it
and all the different ways in which they
change so I'd like to end with a poem this won't be surprising I'm on a kick
when I'm often doing this a different poet
though yeah this is a a poet it's John odonahue he's a was a Irish poet and
philosopher it's a a little bit different style but
um different style than some of the poems um I've read in the in the
past and this poem it starts off going one uh Direction and then it makes a
turn and there's a number of different things that we could pull out of this poem but
this idea of having an adventure I hope is one that will come out of
this so This is called for a new beginning by John
Oahu for A New Beginning by John O
Donahue in out of the way places of the heart where your thoughts never think to
wonder this beginning has been quite medely forming emptiness growing inside
you noticing how you welded yourself on still unable to leave what you had
outgrown it watched you play with the seduction of safety and the gray promises that
sameness whispered heard the waves of turmoil rise and relent wondered would
you always live like this
then the Delight when your courage kindled and out you stepped onto new
ground your eyes young again with energy and dream a path of plitude opening
before you though your destination is not yet clear you can trust the promise
of this opening unfurl yourself into the grace of beginning
that is at one with your life's desire awaken your spirit to
Adventure hold nothing back learn to find ease in Risk soon you will be home
in a new Rhythm for your soul since it's the world that awaits
you I like that this begins this poem begins in out of the way places of the
heart heart where your thoughts never think to wander it's pointing to like this the
poem is called a new beginning but there's some way in which Adventure is a
new beginning it's like a a beginning again
and thoughts are kind of the way in which we're trying to solve something we're trying to fix something we're
which is important we need to do that but there's a part of our life that
isn't n about solving isn't about fixing isn't about
planning it's about opening to it's about unfurling allowing
ourselves to unfurl in whatever way that means for you this opening this allowing this
unfolding and I would say that this idea of Adventure it feels like an adventure
to to allow something to unfold or unfurl to not control it to trust that
it knows how to do this unfolding and then there's this line in
here this expression learn to find ease in Risk because this is what Adventure
includes right is risk but this is what a beginning is is
going into some unchartered territory this going into places maybe we haven't
been having new thoughts having new ideas having new relationships to
experiences maybe the experiences are exactly the same we have the same job s
same life situation same whatever is happening but something new in the way
we're looking at it that new way in which we are experiencing it or a new frame of
reference in which we're looking at it and that is the adventure like oh what
what if I look at it from this perspective I always thought of myself as uh somebody who uh could just figure
everything out myself and I'm making this up well maybe it is true for myself
too I kind of had this idea like okay I can figure this out I don't need no stinking nobody I can figure this out
you know in some kinds of ways this shows up up but then to realize oh actually
there's something in relationship to other people that we learn about ourselves that we learn about Humanity
that can only be done with others and so then to start to see some
of our experiences oh I wonder what this would be like if um I were to work with
this on this with somebody else or if I were to share this with somebody else or
if I were to look at it from how somebody else might look at it just bring this as an
example like the exact same life situation but to maybe do something a
little bit different or consider it from a different vantage
point so this learning to find ease and risk like learning to do something that
isn't step one step two step three we need these step one twos and threes as well sometimes right to solve uh
problems but life isn't only about
this and I think the life that we are hoping to have it's full of Vitality and
that has a a richness and a depth to it which includes ease and Peace and
Freedom is an adventure
and maybe it's as simple as using that language thinking about okay let's turn this into an
adventure I'm not exactly sure how this is going to go and maybe that alone just
different language is something that can allow something new to arise that can be a support for you and your
life so a journey or an adventure I don't know right now today
I'm feeling this idea like this idea of Adventure there might be another time I'm like no it's in a journey and we have to have some perseverance and you
know I've given those kinds of talks too but right now I I like this idea of an adventure idea of an
adventure so with that I'll close and open it up to see if there's some
questions or some comments for you what's the difference between a journey and an adventure or maybe there's an
adventure you've been on recently that uh you'd like to share so yes so back
here so if Enlightenment is I mean the Buddhist says freedom from suffering
right would that be the end destination of the
adventure yes yeah no more suffering so then I mean so after that
like like I don't know I mean no more suffering ever it can't even bother you
it can't touch you I mean that's just you're just there right I mean I don't know is that what it
is it's not being pushed around by greed hatred or delusion it's like meeting
whatever is happening but maybe uncomfortable but it's not suffering
it's like oh ouch uh and responding appropriately like meeting each moment
fully completely without hiding and with
ease so it's it's not uh being I like this expression I heard somebody use
recently it's not being a bliss blob just you know disconnected and uh different from the world it's
just meeting the world fully and doing what needs to be done
and can you say a little more about this falling asleep
mindfully I mean I would love to do this experiment but it's so counterintuitive because I do the
opposite I I let my attention go so how how does how do you do it well this was
never intentional and for all I know maybe it was a dream so maybe I should uh but I this was on a retreat where so
I had a lot of momentum I spent quite some time you know many many hours a day for many days and uh just I
noticing that uh like oh sleep
is like some there was like some kind of like a like a type of Letting
Go and yet there was some awareness of that letting go
so maybe I'm making this up and it wasn't to mindfulness and to uh sleep but I I I know there's uh like some
Buddhist Traditions that talk about this lucid dreaming I wouldn't say I've have this lucid dreaming nor have I aspired
to or tried it but I don't know is that helpful so so you have some some
awareness and and you hang on to the awareness a little
longer so I just talked about language I'll use language a little bit different here it's not like I'm hanging onto
awareness it's like there's like there's like a aess is
there have try what was that I have to try see what happens yes there you go
there you go you could go an adventure with it there you go let us
know hi hi I just wanted to quickly share just kind of
like um I think just in general like this is kind of how I've been approaching my life especially in the
last like couple to a few years um literally I've actually been like
calling it an adventure when people ask me like how I approach life um I can't
say that it makes it any easier but definitely um I I'm very strong into
like like trusting the universe
and um almost like predetermination a little bit like things are already kind
of meant to happen meant to be like pre-written almost like a pre-birth plan
that we have some of these major life
um circumstances that we go through almost like they were pre-chosen um [Music]
so it's like I approach life in more of like a co-creation like I don't really have a
choice but I kind of help I do like I maybe think I have control over how my
life is going to go but actually it's going to go the way it's going to go which is not not in my control if that
makes sense yeah yeah and so I feel like when like no matter like I tell people a
lot all the time especially lately in the last year or two that I don't really
make decisions anymore like I just kind of not necessarily letting life
passively happen to me but in a way yeah just kind of
allowing what's happening to happen and trusting that the Universe has like a bigger picture at play that I'm not
aware of um and just not putting so much importance on my choices and decisions
like if I feel confused about a relationship or um a job decision or something like this
um I feel like it's just an adventure like I'm just going
to and how does that make you feel to use this language of Adventure does it feel like yeah yeah I mean it definitely
helps me with the stress uh that I used to have in making decisions like I feel
I don't feel as overwhelmed anymore I actually don't really worry about it cuz I know people who like be like oh I
don't know what job to choose job a or job B and then they'll just like worry about it incessantly for like weeks on
end or have sleepless nights over it and for me like I've learned that um the
universe will tell you if you just get quiet and listen the universe will give you signs like I'm very into
synchronicity and angel numbers and just like everything that crosses my path is
a sign for me um um and yeah I just like
wait until the last minute and see like what the universe is telling me and then go with my gut either
direction so um and it feels like an adventure it does exactly does that bring some uh I don't know some like I
don't excitement or juiciness to your life or not I'm not sure what uh word to
use there yeah I mean I I try to use it that way you know um for example right
now I'm going through a very um unsettling situation in my life where mold was found in my apartment and I've
been living in a motel slash out of my home for since
Halloween and so yeah it's very like un a lot of uncertainty where I'm
like oh my gosh what does my future hold I don't even know am I going to live here am I going to live somewhere else like and part of that is an ADV vure
like okay the place where I'm currently living I'm trying to look at it that way to make it
more manageable and fun to allow myself to cope better yeah cuz one thing I can
appreciate is what you're pointing to is allowing what's happening because it is
happening and this is It's astounding how often we're trying to pretend things aren't happening or trying to push that
away so there's there's some wisdom and saying oh okay this actually is
happening mold in one's apartment and okay this this is here what what needs
to happen next or something like this yeah yeah exactly yeah and then just
kind of like think instead of like worrying more about the future sure I'm
worried of course but also I try to look at it from an adventure standpoint and
perspective of almost like I'm watching a movie like oh what's going to happen next so yeah that's just how I live my
life so tonight was um I I resonated with it because that's
kind of how I think great great thank you thank
you we have time for one more comment if somebody wants to
uh so I think it resonated a lot with what you said over there as well and uh what's interesting is that I think I
used to uh have this sort of emotion of surrender which is you're surrendering to the moment you're surrendering to what's happening in front of you and uh
you're living your life uh again not like you're not making decisions but you're at least letting the the universe
give you signs about what decisions you should be making but in some ways you're surrendering to it but I sort of I mean
to your point words can sometimes change your frame of mind so um Adventure makes
it a little more interesting than than than the surrender I mean surrender is great you're you're letting go of what
you what you are thinking what you uh have to make decisions on Etc but uh I
think the adventure makes it a little more interesting so that was uh that was fascinating today and uh talking about
science there's one of the my favorite books is The Alchemist uh which is Al about ens and the SS so if you ever get
a chance you should read that one yeah okay there you
go okay so may your joury J home tonight not be an adventure just straight
forward find your way home in a nice way good night thank you thank you