hello from Redwood City at the Insight Meditation
Center and uh so I'm particularly happy to be here
today I was this morning as I turned my attention to the topic of today I
started to feel a kind of smile and delight and joy some happiness just just
from turning my mind in that direction and that's because the topic for today is
Happiness and happiness is a word that I see as a umbrella term for a whole
family of states of well-being that we can
experience and it's a important reference point for Buddhist
practice on one hand clearly Buddhism is an honest meeting of our suffering an
honest assessment and consideration turning our attention towards suffering to be very honest and
truthful about its presence but not so we can suffer more
but so we can somehow resolve that suffering or dissolve that suffering or
solve that suffering in some way so that uh the mind can open to
happiness I like to think of the there's a natural capacity we have for for
happiness that is often obscured by our clinging and our
holding and that as we let go as we let go of clinging
grasping that the mind's simple capacity to feel delight
and joy becomes increasingly important
and so of course it's difficult to to
sometimes be happy and we have many challenges in our lives I don't want
to excuse me for a
moment I don't want to in any kind of way diminish the difficulty belittle the
difficulty we have with the challenges of our life lives and at the same time I don't want
to limit uh uh our
capacity to recognize well-being and these can
coexist sometimes the problem with anything is that when we get fixated on it we get attached to it we make it the
whole picture this is what's who we are we identify with it we become it and
it's possible to be so identified so connected so pre occupied with suffering
that we don't have the bigger picture what's happening for us the bigger context and in The Wider context it's
possible to hold suffering with a sense of well-being with a sense of confidence
with a sense of goodness generosity with
compassion it's possible to hold the suffering even with a in a field in an
atmosphere of something that resembles well-being Joy or
happiness and so to be start becoming attuned start to recognize our capacity
for being for Joy or happiness in the letting go in the relaxing in the
lightening up in the easing up uh with what's
happening so we'll begin this meditation and and I'll put an emphasis
on uh easing up on being easy uh
uh be being at ease putting yourself at ease and as we do so as you be able to
find this see if you can find glimmers maybe more of something in the
family of happiness joy Delight well-being
without getting fixated on anything but even if a glimmer of this well-being is
there let it be the support for you to continue with the practice of being here
and now let it be a support for you to help you um to let
go of anything that takes you away from the present moment or obscures it
with suffering so assuming a meditation
posture and closing the
eyes and gentling yourself into your body
gently almost as with your awareness enter into your body from the so your
your sense of Sensations awareness
aliveness is found within your
body and even if you're feeling some
distressing Sensations or
emotions maybe there's a way to appreciate how even those
Sensations are a form of Vitality a form of being here alive in
the present moment and to tune into it
as Vitality or Activation so we don't
identify with the content the story the predictions the
meaning that we attribute to our
suffering and gently from the inside out to take some long slow deep
breaths as you exhale
shedding stories ideas considerations of the past
the future
shedding the discursive mind that tells stories about how we are
what's
happening taking some gently deeper
breaths and relaxing the body as you
exhale as you relax maybe there can be a kind of letting go into the pool of
gravity well
simultaneously we keep a kind of alertness in the body in the
posture
for letting your breathing return to normal and with a normal
breath continue to relax soften let go of the muscles in your
body and as you do so see if there's any feeling of ease
or pleasure in the letting go in the Rel
relaxing
as you exhale see if you can let yourself be at
ease at ease in your body
or being easy with what's happening in your
body easing up lightening
up gently setting your heart at
ease or being easy with how things are in your
heart easing up any
tightening grasping pressure associated with the
heart and as you exhale maybe setting your mind at ease
at temporary EAS for just
now you can pick up your challenges
later or if the mind is not at ease ease
up on the tension that's
there or be easy with
it lightening up softening the tension and the
grasping and then as you sit
here is there any sense of
wellbeing maybe it's a global feeling that has a slight
glow or Buzz or
warmth or maybe there's a slight sense of
pleasure somewhere in the face around the lips in the
chest in the
hands maybe it's a contentment in the mind
for the opportunity to sit in meditation putting aside our
responsibilities and busyness content with the Simplicity of
just being here
breathing and with whatever sense of ease or
well-being or happiness that you
experience see if that can be the
atmosphere within which you're aware of your
breathing your present moment experience
e
for
and as you're sitting here are you to some degree a bit more
settled Cal calm at ease than you were when you
first sat down to
meditate and is there some
pervasive but maybe very subtle pleasure in your body your heart your
mind in being calmer more
settled more at ease breathing being
here in wherever you feel somewhat relaxed or at ease in yourself
is there a pleasure or a contentment or some form of
well-being that maybe has no reason except the satisfaction of being
connected and alive and with these settled feelings calm
feelings
and giving room breathing room to any feelings of
contentment pleasure
wellbeing as you breathe breathe with it breathe through
it making room in your
body making room in your heart making room in your mind for
wellbeing
happiness
and then imagine you think about or
visualize would it be like if you went through your whole
day rooted in some feeling of well-being that's present right
now you don't give it up for anything so whoever you encounter
whatever you're doing happens together with a sense of
well-being there's nothing you do that sacrifices
it what would that be like for you
and perhaps one of the consequences could be to feel some AUM of well-being
happiness in yourself and to wish that for
others to wish that for the people you encounter
and to not be a force of agitation or desires
or agendas that make it harder for other
people to settle into their own
well-being May our connection to
wellbeing lead us to wish this for others as
well may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free thank
you
e
so hello and welcome to this third talk
on
the the signs or symptoms of non-
clinging so was a kind of reviewing little bit that this follows up last
week where the focus was on mindful of the bundles of
clinging and um the source of a lot of suffering and as we untie the bundles as
we dissolve the the glue that holds
together the infrastructure of attachment of clinging grasping that we
have the the continuity of resistance and
pulling away closing down all the different variations of what Buddhism might call attachment or
clinging that the release of that non- clinging has symptoms has leads to
senses of well-being and uh we start discovering that our clinging our grasping our
resistance our closing down interfere or cover over our
capacity to be happy our capacity to feel contentment at ease and even when there's times of
great challenge it's possible to stay connected to some special kind of
feeling of that being present being here feels
good feels right being connected to reality has a has a goodness to it has a
rightness to it that might not be literally considered be happiness but
maybe we could can call it a dharmic happiness or a kind of symptom of
wellbeing so one way or the other one of the symptoms of letting go well
is in the family of happiness happiness joy ease lightening
up and I've learned uh through too many
painful um experiences that if I let
go and and the consequence of letting go is I feel neutral then I haven't really
let go and because I've been doing this Buddhist practice so long letting go
sometimes can be relatively easy for me and so I've let go of situations where
um were challenging or maybe I was angry or upset somehow and I let go and I
thought I had let go but I ended up feeling neutral it's like okay I'm back to normal or something and inevitably I
hadn't really let go and and like whatever I was holding on to and clinging would come back and bite me
would come would reappear at some point and what I learned was that if I'm
going to let go or if Letting Go happens for it to be full and and healthy there
has to be some feeling of goodness in it some lightning up up some feeling
of uh joyful energy or uh Happy energy I
want to be careful with the words I choose because sometimes we let go in very challenging situations and we can't
obviously say in conventional ways we happy as a result of that but there is something that feels
right a goodness to it a lightening up and easing up a sense of richer Vitality
or maybe not contentment with what's happening but a contentment of now being
more fully present here for it so one of the symptoms of uh of release Letting Go
non-attachment non- clinging is a a a range of emotional states that are in
the family called Happiness the happiness family and
so but if we're not oriented towards that if we ignore it if we somehow think
we're not supposed to be happy uh that somehow Happiness joy is not serious enough for someone who's a serious
practitioner who's just going to go directly to the truth emptiness
nonself um and as if you know just somehow in the seriousness of it and the
directness of it um there's no room for joy and happiness we're doing oursel
a great disservice certainly it can be easy to overemphasize joy and happiness it's
possible to be attached to it to cling to it it's possible to expect it and try
to hold on to it all ways which interfere with the deeper possibility of
well-being that practice can bring but uh don't deny yourself that
don't let don't get in the way of it and what's I think unfortunate is how many
of us um are so busy with what we think is important with basically sometimes
with our attachments our clinging our sense of responsibility our sense of obligation sense of fear that drives us
we have to do something here um that uh we don't Avail
ourselves of the wellbe that's here uh
that doesn't require some great wonderful thing happening in the world doesn't require having the you know
getting something or having some relationship with some person or having
praise or success or you know many of the conventional worldly
things there's a well-being that we can have that's independent of worldly
conditions and it can it's very simple uh it can seem unimportant it can
seem like why why should we focus on it when it is not doesn't relate to my
sense of self my agency who I am and who I need to have and what I need to
do deeper than that or Fuller than that is a sense of just simple
ordinary um well-being a simple Jo the joy of
simplicity uh the joy of just being alive a simple sense of contentment or
ease or or satisfaction in simple
things uh you know the looking at the sky when it's blue appreciating the sun
and the clarity of the air appreciating the temperature or the
freshness of the morning first morning breast outside can feel so nice there's
all these Simple Pleasures in life that we stay for that are help us realize
there's more available here that I'm overlooking by the Rush by
accomplishment getting things done doing the the responsible thing certainly
don't give up some of your responsibilities but uh there's more
well-being in this life that most people Avail themselves to than most people
feel like they have permission to stop for and enjoy to make room for and the proposal
is that if you can start appreciating the joy the happiness that's are available here you also might
begin begin appreciating the sense of well well-being that comes from non-
clinging non- rushing nonattachment nonhostility non
greed and that that is a Val invaluable well-being to be attuned to because that
gives us an alternative a healthy alternative to hostility to this
satisfaction of a good anger or satisfaction of being involved in a
strong desire that seems promising we are shifting the
orientation to get our satisfaction from non- greed nonh hatred
non-fear and to be Rec conditioned by that to be shifted and changed and
transformed by that well-being so to begin appreciating the
happiness of non- clinging so that we can be nourished by it we can
be reconditioned by it some of us have been so powerfully conditioned so
powerfully shaped by The Chronic fear we live in The Chronic ambition or desires
this chronic conceit we live in The Chronic hostility that aversion we live
in it's kind of some people have been so shaped by it they don't even know they have
it and um it's a powerful conditioning to live with those and in Dharma practice we're
looking to change that conditioning to decondition the UNH wholesome forces
within us and to bring forth a conditioning that is uh wholesome
nourishing supportive of what is all that's good within us supportive of that
which leads to greater and greater happiness and well-being it is possible to be
happy and this Dharma practice that we do here is a path to
happiness so a step in that direction is to begin availing yourself of the
well-being of the contentment M of the joy that might here be for you already
if you give yourself your time to realize it to make space for it to allow
for it and um so that would be the challenge
I offer you for today is spend good part of today
recognizing how realistically not uh superficially not
as a holding on or you know kind of uh color coding your life but
realistically is there something a sense of well-being joy happiness contentment
satisfaction that you can have just with a Simplicity of being just being here as
your life is right now granted that you might have challenged
but even with those are there things that you can be are there sources of joy
and happiness that are simple and clear and right here that you can nourish
yourself with recondition yourself so non-
clinging the the happiness of non- clinging so thank you this is also part
of mindfulness practice and remember that uh some of you this is the introduction to mindfulness we're still
doing so in this big kind of package of things we include as part of mindfulness
part of it is the well-being that arises as well thank
you