go great so hello hello and welcome everyone to
happy hour and um I'd like to lead a
meditation uh today on holding peace holding peace in our hearts in our
minds um holding peace both for the sake of ourselves um as we connect and relate
to ourselves with with peace with
balance and also to hold peace for our
inter for for our relational space as we relate to others especially if there's
any friction uh in any interactions we have with others holding peace holding
spaciousness and also so as we relate to the news of the world as we relate to
the world to um to hold peace to hold
peace as we think of others whether they are in a space of um
being um if they're in a space of suffering whether the the perpetrators
or or whether they they the recipients of of of challenges and difficulty in
the world to hold peace to hold possibility of peace to live peace let
the let peace Start From Within um and and peace and meta loving kindness um
are strongly interrelated when we have good will for
others there is a sense of peace that arises in our heart and when we hold this space of peace and balance which is
related to equinity there is a sense of friendliness oh there's a sense of just
like me that can arise so just like me just like me let's
let's also remember just like me in fact maybe I'll share this I was
really touched by this recently I heard on the radio um it's the 30th Anniversary this week
or this past week I guess the 30th anniversary of of uh genocide in Rwanda
and and National Public Radio in the US was doing many um segments um and in one
segment I was quite touched there was the story of of a woman who 30 years ago risked her own
life to to um to save the lives of others uh when there was um
neighbor killing neighbor utus and tootsies and and I was especially
touched by one part of the story where um she apparently lets a couple of
people whom uh uh she and her husband knew in in their Village and she hides
these um these men in their house and then um her husband comes back and in
order to um for the husband not to be startled she says oh these these friends
you've known the they're visiting and and the words she said of course which
were translated uh through um through an
interpreter was you know just like just like me just like us these people want
to um to be alive not suffer just like me and that just like me it it
really touched me because the stance of common Humanity The Stance of common
Humanity you don't necessarily need to be a Buddhist or or be familiar with Buddhist teachings at all Buddhism does
not have hegemony over this simple understanding of just like me other
human beings are just like me just like me just like me and can we hold the
possibility of Peace for all of us on this little blue planet just like me
just like me so with that as Preamble I'd like to invite us to uh to settle
and practice together let us
arrive let us arrive let us arrive in this body in this moment
inviting inviting a sense of
subtleness and peace and peace can start in this moment
can express itself with our stability in the body
letting the body be stable not fidgeting or moving
with kindness with gentleness relaxing the body sweet dear amazing miraculous
body may you be peaceful may you be [Music] calm maybe
well inviting the body to be peaceful
and within the frame of the body inviting the breath to be easeful
peaceful however wants to express [Music]
itself not forcing pushing just inviting allowing
inviting the body to relax some
more to have more peace
and is
and now inviting the the mind to join the body when the mind when the body is
eful and has stability the Mind tends to settle as
well so starting with the body now inviting the mind to settle to
relax to have peace to rest with
peace ding thoughts or worries or plans running
around here and there dear body dear
mind rest rest and hold
peace connecting with the breath to sustain the stability of peace
being peace being peace the title of the book
by thn not Han Zen master being peace can we be
peace in this moment don't worry about the next moment or the previous what just this
moment can I inhabit peace my body and my mind and now my
heart to hold peace in my
heart for myself how I am in this
moment any relationships personal relationships especially if they there's
any Strife or challenge holding peace holding peace it's a possibility
as an aspiration peace and
goodwill and for the world
just like me all these beings in the world just like
me they just want to be happy and
peaceful here sitting like a [Music]
candle it's holding light holding the flame
alive Flame the light of
Peace however that it resonates for you in this
moment
e e
peace what does peace mean in this moment in this body mind and
heart
e
e e
being Peace In This Moment
what does it mean to me in this
moment to hold peace peace with myself maybe that means lack of
judgment kindness maybe if there are a lot of thoughts
means setting them down
peacefully it means thinking about some challenges perhaps with someone to bring
Good Will peace for ourselves peace for them peace for peace for both of
us and similarly for the world doesn't mean to be at
peace to live
peace inhabit Peace In This
Moment
e
e e
can this in breath can this out
breath be known peacefully with stability of
mind
e
e e
feel like if it's helpful to add some
words may I have peace and ease
May those I know those who are near and dear to
me those with whom I have challenges
Those whom I barely know simply lightly
interact with May there be peace May there be
peace in our hearts in our interactions May there be goodwi and
peace May there be peace and goodwi in the entire
world and if it starts to feel too conceptual come back to the breath
come back to the body breathing in peace breathing out
peace may I be peaceful may I hold peace for myself and
for others and my
thoughts and my words and my
actions
e
e e
and as we approach the end of this period of sitting
together appreciating that you showed up and you try to align
your actions actions of the Mind internal actions with your
intentions highest intention I for peace and goodwi and letting go of any
[Music] judgment for what might have come up or
not come up trust that you're planting
seeds as long as I'm showing up just in this moment as best as my ability with
peace towards myself and others with Good Will peace and goodwill when
I'm planting wholesome
seeds may all beings everywhere be happy may have causes and
conditions for happiness and well-being may all beings everywhere be
peaceful and free including myself [Music]
thanks everyone thank you for your practice practice of holding peace
together holding peace together in our hearts in our wishes for the
world in these interesting and challenging
times being peace peace starts within World Peace starts from
within starts from within it's hard to try to
to wish for a peaceful world or have peace in the world if if we don't
cultivate the stability in ourselves in our relational space for
others so we have some time
for those who can stay to engage with
how do we hold peace how what supports our peace what gets in the way of of
living peacefully being Peace So the invitation is a is is an exploration for
your own sake what what supports me to be peaceful what gets in my way of being
peaceful and in this exploration in small groups again let it be an exploration for your own sake you're not
sharing it for the sake of others educating them impressing them you're just writing a little it's as if you're
writing a journal entry um like what supports me what gets in my way and
allowing for other human being conscious human beings to hold witness because
when we're held witness something amazing happens you know this already we go deeper when
we're held witness and we say it out loud it's even more powerful than writing so this exploration let's go in
alphabetical order the first round is is uh what What's what gets in the
way of Peace for me peace internally peace
relationally peace in the world what gets in the way what gets in the way explore that and you offer a nugget the
next person will offer a nugget and the next person um and then the second
round what supports what supports um Peace living peacefully being
peace uh holding in my relationships in the way I show up all of that and then
you go around again and then in the later rounds you can share with whatever
in in either category and again stay close to your practice please do not comment or give advice to others
just let it's a stone soup it's a soup that's made by all the offering so you
just make your own offering you don't correct or um and and yet and yet if um
if you notice that you know the the happy hour uh guidelines or not being
met somebody else is giving somebody El advice it is okay to say you know the
with the with the uh invitations guidelines here we don't give advice we stay with the practice we stay here Etc
so so that's okay too because that comes out of Goodwill and and trying to hold
uh peace for everyone so so can you uh can you hold peace in
the way you listen in the way you speak in the relational space in the small
group of size three can you hold peace for yourself not add to the agitation
can you hold peace it's an interesting practice right here right now not out
there in the world right here in the small groups can you hold peace for yourself and for others how does it work
if you do that you know what do you say lovely what other people say wonderful but but really how we show up tune into
that how are you showing up okay all right okay welcome back everyone the
rooms are closed everybody's back so we have some time for any
Reflections you like to share any questions um anything and I'm also going
to change the chat settings you also welcome to um
type uh type things in chat type your Reflections or questions if you type them to everyone uh then I will read
them and your name if you type them just to me privately I will not read your
name uh but I will just read your reflection so what what uh what came up
either in the meditation or in the exploration holding peace being
peace I'll share with you what came up for me on in the meditation um yeah peaceful I felt much
more peaceful as the meditation progressed and and there were times that
maybe thoughts or plans were coming up and and I would smilingly release them
in in favor of Peace again not judgmentally but oh yeah I want to practice peace in this moment in my mind
not be planning and this and that yeah peace practicing peace and that was quite uh quite yummy ah I see two hands
Jerry you see your hand is first uh
um I like to sync uh topics so what gets me um not difficulty to peace if I'm in
h an acran called halt hungry angry lonely tired that's a difficult Place
hold wait wait that's good hold hry wait hungry hry angry angry lonely tired
lonely tired he h hungry wait what's what this halt so halt oh h t got it
halt okay hungry angry lonely tired love it thanks for sharing that that is such
a great powerful pneumonic am I hungry angry lonely or tired right now yeah
that's great self check so sorry I interrupted with my enthusiasm for you sharing that keep going Jerry yeah and
the alternative is um it came from here uh helping someone else uh that isn't a
direct benefit to myself that uh so I've started not giving money to Beggars but
going to a store and getting them a piece of pizza or a sandwich and so I
wasn't meaning it today to be a public event but someone else saw me go by and
said well you've done your good deed for the day so it wasn't my intention but it
took me out of my hungry angry lonely tired space
thanks for sharing that Jerry that is so that is so immediate I I really appreciate what you shared which is if
we are in that state of uh Hal hungry angry lonely tired reaching out and
helping someone else who's who needs help needs support in that moment and and uh whatever that might be whatever
that might be yeah however that might show up for us uh great thank you thanks
so much for sharing that Jerry apprciate apprciate you thank you Fred I see your hand next
please thank you Nikki um that was a very powerful meditation for me and I
think it was partly primed by something I had been reading be before we sat down to meditate but uh initially I was just
overwhelmed with the perverse opposite of peacefulness and kind of immersion in
the headlines of the day and and then found myself even you know searching
further beyond beyond the uh the the terrible news of the moment to uh you
know what what's going on in my town that I don't know about uh which has its
own sort of secret Horrors and
and after a while you know not a long while but after a while then I I found that I okay can actually step out of
that I can step in to a place where I can um repos in my connection with
everybody and it was some of this came from imagery of what I had been reading
prior to our sitting down tonight and in that sense of you know
seeing the visual image of you know um many many little PODS of light
connected um and equal uh was was a peaceful place to be that that my
existence you know as I forget the phrase you were using but it was you know a sort of visual equivalent of the
phrase you were using about we all
share The Human Experience and we all um we all suffer in ways that aren't
dissimilar and that none of us is really privileged beyond the other um but none
of us is underprivileged in relation to the other either and and that visual image of
those those that uh endless network of connection um without
faces but sort of pulsations of light was a place to that I could sit back in and uh and have a kind of sit back into
the calmness and peace and I was struck by how this was a choice and
that I had a a fair amount of ability to make that decision I I wasn't going to
be swept away by the headlines I actually could decide to step back into what I preferred and into the piece that
we were being directed to be in and that was interesting to see that degree of
bition um and which I imagine has developed from coming here
and sitting on my own but also you know from us doing what we do here in a large
group and in small little breakout groups and what reverberates
afterwards so thank you thank you thank you so much red and thank you for the
the both the eloquence and the nuanced way that you shared what what came came
up for you and the progression and I want to unpack a couple of things that you said for the benefit of others
because I think they're they're very important and and also subtle in your experience I was tracking you but just
to unpack what you were sharing um when you were talking especially
about uh the the you know the U all of us just like me all of us just you all
beings just like me there neither privilege no nor uh nor overprivileged nor underprivileged according to
particular ways of being and I wanted to unpack that because there's there's something very important in what you
said which could be misunderstood so I want to really unpack that because you know there's the idea of privilege in the world and some people are privilege
and you know they they have whatever wealth and some people don't you know all and yet what you're pointing to in
what you said so is with respect to um suffering that the the
unsatisfaction factor of life that the deep duka that all of us have in the
three actually the three marks of existence basically impermanence
unsatisfactoriness and impersonality which it's not we want to have control and choice yet we
don't and when we really see that yeah all of us human beings wow we're all
subject uh we're neither privil none of us have are have it you know we're all
subject let me put it this we're all subject to impermanence uh laws of impermanence
unsatisfactory no uh Dua um as well as
um that this this impersonality that it's not personal things and and and not
only things are impersonal but also they're unpredictable and when you truly see that through the eyes of of um of
insight um and there is a peace that arises that you then the mind and the
Heart can chooses to step you know the the Mind chooses to step into peace which also ties into this um teaching
Buddhist teaching um which is a beautiful one it's actually also used as a funeral chant in ply which is all
things are impermanent they um arise and pass away to live in harmony with this
truth brings great happiness and when you hear this at the outset it's like
wait Buddhists are so negative it's like what are they talking about but there's something about oh yeah the heart opens
up yeah this is this is how it is it's it's this I can see I can live according
to I can live and and as the friend recently put if we live according to in
if we live in harmony with uh uh impermanence unsatisfactory
not expecting it to be satisfactory all the time and not expecting it to be uh
everything that we have control over if we live in harmony with those truths life goes easier instead of us us um
fighting against them so all of this is connected and I hope people can hear the relationship between these points I'm
making and what you beautifully brought in Fred especially this this aspect of way I have a choice I can see through
this lens of of oh I can get you know kind fuff and and keep looking more and
more and more and I know what the feeling there is and and also um yeah I
I can I can choose I can choose to see the the universal truth of just like me
just like me in the world and that brings a certain Peace So I've said so
much and want to invite you if there's anything else You' like to add read or not no thank you yeah thank you
appreciate it yeah thank you so much that was that was beautifully said and
um and couple of I see a couple more hands
and and also there a couple of notes in chat so I want to honor them as
well um yeah I'll I'll I see uh this is
really great contemplation and meditation thank you very much for pointing me and US towards peace another
person said I know we talk a lot about the inner critic uh what can we
practice um when the inner critic is Raging and regular and regular reminders
aren't working possibly due to Halt conditions I like you Jerry your halt is already becoming part of the zeit the
part of the um language of of of uh Happy a um mindfulness of the body to
the person who wrote that question mindfulness of the body and meta mindfulness of the body and meta bring
meta bring kindness bring kindness to the body to the body to the
body and I see Neil has added just like me everyone I meet was born just like me
everyone I meet will die just like me everyone I meet is doing their best to get from point A to point B yes
indeed indeed oh yes one more reflection Marosa can feel like it gets in the way
of of Peace for me but neglecting marasti is even worse and I had glimmers
of marati supporting pieces well uh the marati means mindfulness of death which
is a practice I love to teach yeah this it's a practice because marati mindfulness of death can bring peace can
a sense of ah bring bring a sense of balance to all this yeah this can really
bring a sense of impermanence appreciation of impermanence to all this radical
impermanence okay we've got two quick minutes left there was a lot tonight so
uh Claire thank you uh mine is very quick
actually our group really enjoyed the practice I just wanted to add that but I
forgot one really important one I circulate a gratitude list with two girlfriends every day and that certainly
adds to my state of Happiness there you go thank you for bringing that in again
that that's that's the counter halt that's the counter halt gratitude yeah y
thanks Claire appreciate it yeah and we're going to let Serena also say
quickly uh her reflection
Serena well I'm glad that you're letting me share even if though it's quick um
the um one of the things that I do that helps me is I notice something positive
about the other person I I try to notice something that's positive something that's a alive something that um um and
that that somehow um brings peace thank you ah beautiful thank you so much for
sharing this Ser that beautiful yeah no noticing bringing to Heart a um a a
beautiful quality of of the other person yeah oh I love that oh that just brings
so much joy as I so I bring that to my heart uh and that's especially actually very helpful um to uh especially if
we're having a challenge with someone to bring uh a beautiful quality of theirs
to heart and mind so so dear ones we've come to the end of happy hour thank you
so much for your practice thank you for joining cultivating your heart and mind
towards peace holding peace together these these points point of light these visual points of light that Fred so
beautifully uh brought up um sketched for us so may all beings be well may all
beings be happy may all beings be free and have peace abundant peace for all
beings everywhere everywhere including
[Music] ourselves thank you so much everyone be
well going to tr