hello and welcome
to meditation at
IMC and this is the Friday meditation the last one of this this particular
series and um the introductory words I want to make
is to say that meditation is not for
bystandard uh it's not to be an observer from the
distance but it involves participation participating in something
profound but the act of participation is kind of very unique or maybe different
than how we normally would think where maybe the participation is the idea of
parti ation is active like it's a real doing and it's also not passive like a
bystander just being done to there's something in between between those
two and uh this is where some of the profundity of living from mindfulness
living from the Dharma begins to be possible and
um and the example I'd like to use is is
uh if you're cold and you go stand in the sun to get warm so you have a role
of Mo going someplace where it's sunny and standing there in such a way that the sun sun rays can land on you and
warm you up you probably face the Sun or put your back to the Sun so the greatest
surface area is kind of facing um you know the
Sun and um but then uh you don't
do the receiving of the sunlight and the warmth you don't send it through your
body and but rather uh the body is has these sense organs has a capacity to
absorb the Heat and you're allowing that to move through you to warm you
up and in a sense uh Your Role is to participate in the whole event
that is not your doing uh but you have to be present for it and allow this movement of the warmth
slowly thawing your body warming it up maybe and um so the same way in
meditation there's maybe a sun something equivalent to a sun warming us up from
the inside there's a light that's of that's beginning to like the sun arises
and and uh you might sitting there looking out in the early morning as it gets light lighter and lighter and
lighter and you're participating in this movement of the earth lighting up being
illuminated but you're not doing it but you are participating and it has a
effect on you so there's some there's illumination that can be born inside of
us or there can be love not love that involves any
desire that's desire and love are often confused but uh there's a kind of a love a warmth
that's generated from the inside out that we place ourselves close to and
allow for it like we're standing in the sun allow something to
appear and so it isn't so much that uh
uh uh we are doing something and it it isn't so much that
we are being done to but rather we're placed in ourselves
where the two come together and something wants to be expressed something wants to arise something wants
to appear that uh we participate in that we enter into as we
meditate and um so the initial kind of steps of meditation of relaxing and
settling and kind of staying with a breath are the kind of the early
preparation for particip ipating in a deeper expression that's going to come
participating in the sun warming warming you up and a kind of participation of
being there for the sunlight as it becomes brighter in the morning and so what is the equivalent
for you what wants to be expressed what wants to Bubble Up and be born from the
inside out so not from a desire from the mind
not from ideas what should happen and shouldn't happen or ideas of what will fulfill us
or not fulfill us but something that's deeper than
desire deeper even Than Me Myself and mine almost as if this is not personal
it's something deeper so to assume a meditation
posture and I like to think sometimes the posture is a posture
that of certainly a kind of respect maybe even a kind of
reverence where your posture is being adjusted in whatever
way that works for you so that you're ready to receive
ready to host be the host the respectful the caring host for something that's quite
profound for the Dharma for your heart for love for
freedom and it's not a casual posture but it's not a tense
posture it's a dignified posture maybe the kind of dignified posture you
would use if you literally were receiving the Dal Lama in your house for
tea or or you were creating a meditation
room in your house to invite the Dal Lama to come and meditate with
you so you're making a posture and then to gently close your
eyes and this idea of gentling and being gentle at the
beginning is to begin orienting
yourself to be with something that is maybe maybe not
shy but maybe something which doesn't get easily gets eclipsed easily gets
overlooked something which is quiet unassertive
undemanding something inside that's profound and so to Gentle ourselves as
part of this preparation to
receive to be a host and then gently taking some deeper
breaths breathing in expanding your body your torso your rib
cage your belly
and relaxing as you exhale
settling with a longer exhale it's it's organizing your body bringing it
together bringing everything together together so it settles here all of
you coming
together rather than being absorbed in the thinking
World we're entering into the wholeness of of our
embodied
being and letting the breathing return to
normal and as simply and ordinarily as you can
unambitious let there be a gentling of your
breathing maybe a gentle softening of the belly the
body as you exhale
and a gentling and softening of your thinking
mind if the thinking mind is filled with thoughts and ideas and mental energy
agitation there's no room for the
mind to be a good
host to have space for something different than it's than just
thinking to have room to receive and feel and
sense the sunlight the warmth
something deeper that wants to emerge from deep
within maybe love maybe peace or calm
so relaxing the thinking
mind and then aligning yourself or attuning
yourself to your breathing to the body's experience of
breathing and with your breathing as if your breathing is
holding your hand or breathing is guiding leading
you follow the the exhale
to whatever is for you the
deepest maybe most intimate place
within underneath all your thoughts and concerns and fears and
desires all the challenges and pains that you
have is there any in or
intuition of a depth within
you even if you have to just imagine that rather than to feel
it allow yourself to breathe through and
with and out of that depth Within
shifting from the control tower in the head where we observe and comment and
judge and where we the victim and
the actor shifting from that to deep inside
and like you would maybe stand in the sun to receive the
sunlight be present in your torso be present deep and in deep within in your
heart or deeper
to allow something deep to express itself
to emerge to shine to
radiate and here it's not so important what that is could be difficult it could be
nice as it is that you're the host that you're a profound way
of sensing and
feeling of allowing this to meet you and you to meet it
and you don't need to know what's going to happen or why it's
happening breathe with openness breathe with
acceptance receptivity allowing what's deep
inside to have room to emerge for
for
e
for e
taking a few moments to feel what's happening for
you not to think about it but to sense and feel the global body
as wide a sense of embodiment as you
can to sense and
feel and within that field of embodiment the movement of breathing
and relaxing
softening settling into a place of
quiet within maybe a still quiet
place deep within below
your beliefs your thoughts your reactions your fears your
desires below all those things which are kind of at the
surface deep down inside
and sensing
feeling the deeper quiet place
within if there is such that place or imagining it
there and then feel and sense what wants to be expressed what is
emerging from there what
is radiating shining
flowing vibrating
tingling and if this place within could speak
what word would it say
and perhaps from some place deep and quiet within you can have some sense or
intuition understanding
imagination that we have within us an
alternative to suffering an alternative to ill will and greed and
fear we have the possibility of
well-being being at peace and calm and as we come to the end of this
sitting to wish this for others
others to wish this for others not in the abstract so much as with a sense of
respect care reverence for the
depths the inner depth that everyone has even if it's covered
over May everyone in their depths under the surface of all
their funny ways of
being may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
[Music]
free thank you and to comment a little bit about
this last meditation it was uh meant to be a continuation of
the meditations and the teachings for this week from this week and uh with the idea that building
on that or being supported by all that and you might not have been to the
earlier teachings you might not be in a place where what I talked was relevant for you or something you can t you canti
felt you could kind of understand or do it's that's
understandable and it's easy to be that way and but maybe in sometime in the
future you can relisten to this and there'll be a time when you're ready for it so thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this Fifth and last uh
talk that's based on the the
practice of not making it worse that um maybe you don't know what
else to do you don't understand the situation it seems impossible it seems like it's you know not going
well there's always one thing you may I hope there's always one thing you can do
you can at least not make it worse you can restrain yourself from
speaking if the speaking you think is going to make it worse you can restrain yourself from the actions you're going
to do that if that's going to make it worse there's a a profound way that uh
or very important way that sometimes what's most important uh is
um doing nothing and doing nothing not to
celebrate doing nothing not to kind of imply that that's the only thing we can ever do or that but if we don't know
what to do and all the things we can think we might do is going to make the situation
worse um maybe restraint maybe holding back is the wisest thing we can do and
how to make that wiser so that is not just only restraint and kind of gritting
your teeth or something is to have a practice you can do uh uh while you're doing nothing and
so that's what I've been offering this week and around the acronym worse so you can
wait and uh there's something very profound about waiting
uh you can uh get pull yourself together get organized get oriented kind of let
all the different pieces of who you are your body your heart your mind your emotions be gathered together be
recognized and be be be here you can relax and maybe even more
uh valuable than relaxing you can rest relax and then rest in the place of
relaxation abide allow yourself to be there in that place don't pick up right
away with your thoughts and activities and doings don't relax and then jump up and act uh take in and be nourished by
the gentler softer relaxed fate rest in it for a
while and that allows you to sense and to see so after going through this process
sense more fully what the situation is what's happening in you and when you all
your senses are open to the situation what do you pick up what do you tune into that if if you uh that's different
than if you're only T tuning in through your belief systems through your bias through your preferences what does your
body feel as you kind of be there with the situation feel about the situation
or feel about yourself so sensing and then then uh part of the sensing
world is eyes seeing but seeing is more than just uh
you know uh sight it's studying looking
at understanding the situation um take a good look and what's happening here and you might be in a
better position to look and begin understanding after you've done the first steps in this process of of uh
not making it worse and then we come to the last
today and that is um to express the E is to
express and um and not making it worse is not supposed to be eternally passive
or not doing anything there is a time and a place to speak and so learning how
to speak wisely how to express ourselves wisely has many different dimensions and
it's a you know it's a huge fantastic learning um so for example there's
mindful speaking uh and learning how to stay mindful as we speak being embodied
as we speak there's learning how how to speak uh to speak in ways that um uh
don't diminish other people or don't criticize them or don't judge them uh so
there's you know the practice of making eye statements and uh making statements that
are really expressing the truth of the moment for ourselves and in this regard uh the um
I'm a big fan of mindfulness out loud mindfulness out loud means that
mindfulness inside is just to name and see and understand directly what is here
without any um additions to it judgments
reactivity uh opinions for and against just oh this is how it is now Without
Blame without shame um this is how it is now so that
same way uh can be expressed uh out loud um so rather than saying I'm angry
with you you can say you know this what's how this conversation has gone uh
I'm feeling pretty agitated and pretty upset and somewhat angry um and that shift in conversation
goes from you know maybe I'm angry with you as if you're to blame to not saying
anything about the other person but taking time to speak about yourself that
can make much more room in the conversation for something deep to happen now you're expressing what's true
for you and um and so what what needs to be
expressed what needs to be said what needs to be shared what needs to be uh
come out and then there's a deeper dimension of this what wants to be expressed because uh that um uh if we
can really find ourselves in the deeply connected to the to the wholeness of who
who we are or the Deep Quiet Place Within of who we are um we discover that
there's layers and layers of things that want to show up and be here that are
covered over or ignored or don't have a chance uh that is more as more who we
are more essential or more feels like the fullness of our freedom fullness of
our spirituality of our love then a lot of the kind of surface ideas of Me
Myself and mine and this is what's happening to me and this is what I want and this is why I'm hurt or something
there's something and so meditation is one of those ways we can drop down quiet
to that place of deep deep under the surface
and from there what wants to be expressed there what is the expression of
that uh and I find that meditation at some point shifts from when I first sit
down it's something I'm doing to it shift to to I I'm participating I'm
going along with I'm riding along with uh something deep that wants to unfold
and move within me and sometimes it's just the breathing the breathing wants
to happen and it's not me breathing but breathing is breathing itself and I'm
there receiving that or participating it or allowing it resting in it but deeper than the breath there can
be a deep sense of care a deep sense of love compassion kindness care uh peace
that is also very quiet as in a sense maybe feels nothing to do with what you
want and your sense of self and exchange with other people and what you're going to get back it just kind of it maybe is
a form of love that has no object not about loving something or
being loved back there is just um something
profound and uh or maybe it's something difficult maybe it's grief that's the
Deep thing but there's something fantastically important about this
reverence and care to open up to what's deep inside and make room for it and
feel the rightness of allowing this depth to be expressed to come out to be expressed in our body expressed in our
heart to be expressed kind of from the inside out and so not all
expression is spoken um because sometimes the spoken
expression maybe isn't as deep as we could go um but sometimes we do speak and
sometimes when a situation is very difficult uh there becomes a time to speak not just wait not just you know
organize and relax but there definitely is a time when we have to speak speak up
and um but speak don't speak up automatically reactively go through this process of
wait organize rest sense and see and then you'll be in a much better
position to speak wisely caringly and hopefully in doing that
make the situation better and that in the end is you know I think what the heart most
wants um the heart most wants to not make it worse if that's the
danger but more than that uh we want to make things better we want to make this
a better world we want to make ourselves a better person we want to support others to live a better life and so may
this process we've talked about this uh week be one that supports you in many different ways in your
life so thank you very much so a couple of
announcements so I'll be uh teaching a 3-we retreat for the next 3 weeks at the
inside retreat center and um and U Matthew Bren silver will be here next
week and uh Diana Clark will be here I think the following two weeks and uh
both of these are wonderful teachers and I'm very happy and glad that they're coming to teach and that you'll have a
chance to kind of hear their teachings and and not just their teachings but also their um their
beingness I love them both quite a bit so it's I'm happy to going to be here with
you and um and then um it might be worth saying
that uh I teach every year a Buddhist chaplaincy program it's in person here
we teach it here I IMC it's through the Sati Center and that will start up in the end of September and um it's a been
a very significant for some people training program in offering spiritual care that um that uh is kind of uh
moving into for some people it's a stepping stone to becoming a professional uh chaplain and so it's a
very rich world of stepping into uh care and people who do it are have to uh have
a volunteer role to volunteer maybe in a hospital as a volunteer chaplain or or
in a prison or jail or there many places hospice anyway so if some of you might
be interested in it it's um it's a rich way of Contin in with this practice that
we do and you'll find more information under Sati Center
um uh sa.org there's both an online version and inperson and I'm involved
with the inperson here at IMC and the online is has other wonderful teachers who are teaching it so thank you and um
I look forward to being back here in a few weeks