so good evening hoping that my voice does the
thing it's supposed to do which is you know be malifu
okay so today I received an email from someone and she said um she had this
phrase in it that said it's a busy December but let's see
not staying UNF frazzled for the most part you know you got that double negative in there I wasn't sure whether
she was frazzled or
unfledged but there's this pressure around the holidays that has to do with how we're supposed to feel you know
we're supposed to feel Goodwill happy Holidays happy
holidays and there is the pressure of family or no family gifting or not
gifting short short time or short on cash or am I going to get this done or
not done and of course then there's all the usual things that happen I'm working I'm not working I have my social
activities my financial issues my family issues the social issues stuff the stuff of life times we
feel like we need an antidote to life you know it's just too much stuff and
we're carrying around all of this accumulation of things that we're
keeping track of and it feels like a load of stuff that we're carrying
around and it's quite common to say I'm feeling frazzled or I'm not feeling frazzled and we you know we have a we
have the list of things the to-do list
or the rehashing of the conversation that we had today or the the email that we're writing about something that we're
going to do or you know the conversation I was going to have with my insurance company on why my auto rates went up 50%
over last year apparently that's happening everywhere in
California excuse me and so meditation can seem like a refuge a
respit but what I'd like to do is give both my friend and you a
gift the gift of ease even in the midst of all the rest of that stuff that
doesn't rely on you being in meditation to feel at
ease now if I had a wand I would just do that but you know I left my veryy
godmother Wings somewhere I haven't I don't have them anymore
so here's a quote from Andrew olinsky from his book
unlimiting mind the radically experimental psychology of Buddhism it's a relatively new book of
his Let Me Clear My Throat
again let go for the moment the impulse for sensory
gratification hold off a annoyance toward what you don't like settle down any restlessness in
mind and body stir up energy when you feel sluggish and postpone thinking over
any doubts you may have as you do this successfully for several moments in a
row you will find the Mind gradually becoming more tranquil more focused more
clear and more powerful the Buddha might have said I
know of no single thing more healthy than doing one thing at a time end of
quote now of course I love this quote but it sounds like you've already
acquired the ability to do all these things but I want to put an underline
under the one moment at a time part one moment at a
time because the truth is we only live in one moment at a time and it's only
our tendency to drag our entire life story behind us that makes it seem
otherwise
boy might help let try the
water thank you so uh recently I went to a
conversation at Stanford with uh between some people in Humanities and a man
named Allan Lightman he's an author and he's uh got a professorship at MIT in both physics
and Humanities he's a very unusual guy he's a philosopher physicist and he talked about this
experience he had um that he wrote about in a book called searching for the stars
on an island in Maine and uh he also had a PBS series of a similar title
and the experience in the experience he described taking a boat off to the island at night and he laid down he he
suddenly stopped the boat and he laid down on the deck and he looked up at the stars and as he laid there he suddenly
had the experience of just merging with the Stars and everything just
became one everything was happening now just now
everything now you may have had a similar sort of transcendent experience
yourself everything was included in just that moment now he doesn't try to explain
that in physical terms and neither do
I but what similar experiences to that I have had lead me to conclude is it's the
Now is really important and the question is how do I get into the
now when am I in now and when am I somewhere
else so in the last year I have lost a number
of people really dear to me and so I have moments of grief that sort of
overtake me unsuspectingly so one of those events
happened on Saturday and I was just suddenly overwhelmed and my husband
took one look at me and he said you look like you are really suffering and I said well yeah I
am and he said yeah do you want to go out to lunch do you want to go out to breakfast you know he he wanted to fix
it right away and I said well let's um uh let's go to that exhibit we've
been wanting to go to so we went off to an exhibit at the Legion of Mary
Cassat and the idea in my head was grief is here but so is the rest of my life so
is everything else it isn't that I can ignore grief or make it go away or
change it and there is also this so we jumped
in the car and we went off to the exhibit and we we had tickets you know they have these time tickets and so
while we were waiting we went to we went into this room that had um uh decorated
porcelain it's a fancy porcelain room of dishes different kinds of dishes dishes
made like arti Toes or with certain kinds of elaborate painting on them
porcelain it's a porcelain exhibit and they have a new piece in
there that is uh made with um uh kugi
art if you're familiar with that is anybody familiar with that so kugi is a
te a Japanese technique where they take broken pieces of porcelain and they literally glue
them together with resin that has gold powdered gold in it and so you have
rivulets of gold streaming holding the pieces together
and the resultant pieces sometimes are more beautiful than the originals so so I've recently seen this in a couple of
different places never having seen it before and and they're quite beautiful pieces so this new artwork is a large
sculpture and there must be maybe 20 different plates that have been mended using this K kintsugi technique and in
the center was a um assembled porcelain piece of uh
quen which is the female Buddhist representation of the Buddha of of com
compassion I'm looking at this piece and I'm thinking okay here are the broken
pieces The Broken Pieces Of My Life The Broken Pieces of your life and and they're put together and they're held
together by this shining gold and I wouldn't be experiencing grief if love wasn't there to begin
with and they they travel together they're not separate from one
another and this is true of all the things in our life Pleasant and unpleasant travel
together they're not independent of one another we tend to get stuck in I like
what's Pleasant and I don't like what's unpleasant and I need to fix it human beings tend to want to fix everything we
want to manage it we want to control it we want to make it the way we want it
but equinity is the space between wanting and not wanting liking and not
wanting liking and not liking equinity is not having a preference
for it doesn't mean that Pleasant and unpleasant don't
exist it doesn't take the texture out of life it doesn't mean that sadness and
gladness are not both present it means that we ride the place of not
grasping at one or the other at not saying I must have that or
I can't be happy it is allowing both to be present
in one's life it's a
kugi it's being present with all of what occurs in
life and saying ah life this is what's
happening this is what's happening it's like this today this is
here where we get into trouble is we say oh it's been this way and we start
justifying why we're angry or why we're upset or why we're happy and I want more
of this or I want less of that and we project it into the
future it's going to be like this forever or the way that I protect my future is if I make more of
this the trick the trick to being at ease in life is to give up all hope of a
better past or that we can control the
future neither is possible what we do have some influence
on is how we meet the present how we meet the
present how am I now right now what am I
seeing now how am I
here I'm tired I'm sore I'm upset I'm
happy and what else is happening what else is here what
else it's really an opening up and not abiding abiding only by the story that
we came into the moment with it's seeing that experience is an
accumulation of moments and it's only our our wanting to carry along my story
the story of my life my life that gets us in a
rut that makes us want to justify what's going on now explain it to
ourselves when I was upset on Saturday I knew the proximal cause of why I was
upset I was thinking about a particular person I was upset I can't do this I
can't talk to this person
again and it was it was very sad for me but it wasn't the only thing that was
true it wasn't the only thing that was true it was just one thing that was
true you know we we we're told that we have to let go of uh of toxic feelings
like anger or displeasure or ill will well what if you can't let go of ill
will you know what if you wake up and you're just cranky and you don't know what to do about it or or you're sad and
okay I don't want to be sad well at least be the person who doesn't want to be sad give yourself some
credit but it is not the only thing that's true about you and it's only true in this
moment it doesn't have to be true in the next moment
so what do we do about it how do how do we meet that how do we find ourselves in
a moment without becoming overwhelmed by whatever emotional overwhelm is
there how do we deal with it because it happens strong feelings
occur strong feelings of frustration or being flustered or whatever that fr
how do I become peaceful in the midst of that well the first thing is don't make
it yours it's not my frustration my anger my sadness it's just
sadness it's just anger I don't mean to diminish it or
dismiss it but it's not yours it's just
here this is amazing practice to realize it's not yours and it's not you it's
just
here it's just happening in this moment it's a condition like any other
Condition it's only when we try to explain it to ourselves that it gets prolonged emotions actually have a very
short lifetime neurologically but if we keep telling ourselves the story or explaining it to
ourselves we keep restarting the clock we keep reinitiating the
stimulus so it isn't a matter of ignoring it or pushing it away you're saying it's not here but you can you
know if you have a a plate of uh information a billboard you stick it on it's there it's right out in
front maybe it's in the middle it's right here but there's a lot more space on the board it's not everything and it
isn't mine it's just a prominent notice it's just a notice
it's just
there I had foot surgery ear earlier this summer and it is
frustratingly persistent that I have pain in my foot not where I expected to
have it but in my big toe just will not go away it doesn't
hurt now it only hurts when I walk no problem only when I
walk fine and I walk and I go there's that
toe again it's not debilitating it just hurts it's not even my toe that hurts
it's just pain it's just a signal just like noise like a loud
noise it's not mine it's just a
signal and I have to decide how much attention to play pay to that
signal that's all how much attention do I pay to that
signal and what else am I aware of
there are all kinds of conditions that come to this moment con conditions of that are
determined by who else is in the room whether I'm doing something
interesting hearing something interesting whether I'm bored out of my
mind whe whether I'm at peace for other reasons that influence how important how
much attention something gives if I can look at it and see it as just
that it has less impact on the stories that I tell
myself it is the understanding how the mind works seeing how the mind is
working in the moment that influences how much influence that emotion has on
us seeing it just seeing it that's all it's not control it's just seeing
it and the second thing is to not have an opinion about
it and by that I mean not having a preference for it or against
it now I can certainly say I prefer that my toad doesn't hurt but then in a
moment as I'm walking along I I have to be able to say
okay I prefer walking to worrying about whether my toe is going to
hurt I don't prefer not
walking so the pain is unimportant until it becomes important
the preference has to do with grasping on one side or the other it's whether I
hold on to it it's the preference that is holding on preference that's the problem that's
where the suffering comes it has to be this way but we when
we are just in the moment in this room in this moment it's what's true in this
moment not what I'm afraid afraid is going to happen in the next moment does that make
sense it's not what I'm afraid of what's going to happen so awareness without
wanting this is this is the goal awareness without wanting I'm aware of
it but I'm not wanting it to be other than it is it's the Leaning one way or
the other it's leaning toward or or pushing away so one thing to ask yourself in any
moment is where am
I now this may seem like an odd question to ask yourself but it's an important
question am I here in the room with what's happening or am I in another
place is the Mind here with me or am I thinking about you know let's take the
question of grief am I thinking about this person located in that other place or am I in this room am I thinking about
something that happened before or am I in this room am I here in this
body even though I may be crying in this body my mind may be somewhere else oh
that's interesting I'm not actually here ahuh so where am I is a really
important question where am I or am I worried about what's going to happen tomorrow
oh tomorrow I'm going to feel really bad because this is going to happen now right here how to get into
the now is to say where am I where am I where's my mind where's my body am I in
my body or am I in the concept of my mind it's sort of like when you're following your breath and you're going
in and you're actually breathing out and you say
whoops nope yep I'm back on the breath in your
body where am I it opens up a sense of curiosity and of opportunity gets you
out of the out of the conceptual world where you think you know what you're doing and you think you know where you are and you think when you find yourself
thinking about your condition where am I really where am I
am I here or not here you want to be in the place
of not knowing what is to be known what is to be known you want to
know what is to be known does that make sense awareness
is asking the question what is to be known here not coming into the moment knowing
already give up knowing it everything in Awareness awareness is asking what is to
be known here what is to be known
here the second question is who am I in the room
with who am I in the room with somebody who's not
here am I in the room with you and I'm aware of you or I'm not
aware of you because I'm in my head and I'm somewhere else or I'm thinking about what I'm
going to say to you be so I'm not aware of you or I'm not aware of
myself I'm not even aware that I'm standing in the room who am I in the
room with who am I in the room with when my
husband said to me you look like you're really suffering that re that gave me the opportunity to
to say Here I Am visibly suffering and there's someone in the room with me
what's he experiencing which got me solidly in the room and out of my
head it's not trivial who am I in the room with and the last thing is what is my
intention in this moment to know your intention you have to know know the attitude your attitude
of Mind am I am I sad it's a quick survey
am I sad am I anxious am I angry am I happy am I light am I agitated am I
irritable what is what is the attitude right here it's not the mood so much is
what is what's uh am I just frazzled is it just frazzled
the word you choose is not so important as being aware of the condition the
condition of your mind that information tells you I need
to be vigilant about what I'm doing or I'm peaceful because then you can check in
with what is my intention for now what comes to mind for me is very
often I wish to be kind I wish to be kind in the moment when I'm stopping to say
what is my intention there's a chance for that to arise I wish to be
kind and when I know who's in the room who am I with and I wish to be kind then
I then I have an opportunity in that moment to be really here and
do create the conditions in my mind for the next
moment that's likely to be much more light than whatever the moment was that
brought me here does that make any sense to you so I'm going to tell you a really
quick story so when I was in one of these agitated Minds I
had I was determined to take some packages to UPS I had a half an hour and
I live a mile from UPS and I thought no problem I could do this and I was very irritable I get over to I drive over to
UPS I get my packages I go in there's nobody waiting except the person the UPS
person is in the middle of doing a notary job so if you've ever watched somebody do a notary job it could be 15
pages or one you know it could and I'm thinking oh no you I don't have much time and I can feel the irritability
coming up and I tell myself just you have plenty of time just
be at ease no problem here and she said I'll be with you
shortly I said no problem 10 minutes later now I'm getting itchy I'm thinking
no problem I know it's just irritability is here no problem some other UPS guy comes
in and he's walking really slowly and I'm noticing the mind going why is he
walking so slowly now Maria he doesn't know how you're
irritable this is not his problem
either eventually the woman finishes what she does rushes over it takes her all of a minute to take care of my
packages I leave and I go out and I I'm still hurrying right because I got to
get home for this Zoom call and there's somebody standing very
close to my car and I'm thinking you know if I just get in my car I'm going to scare her and and so I I just said
you know I I don't want to startle you but I'm about to move that car and she looked at me and she goes oh and I
thought wow that was cool just the act of constantly reminding myself to be
kind allowed me to be kind and I thought wow that was great
and the irritability left it wasn't it wasn't like I set out
to do something kind it was like the moment arose because I kept setting it
up in my mind that I intended to be kind it's not like I did it it's not like I
was determined to be kind it's more like what you hold in your mind heart is
what you create in the next moment that's why it's so important to
be in the now and not to hold on to whatever that attitude of mind is
whatever it is just be in the now
kugi with whatever it is with no opinion so I'm going to close my latest
book of poems from Joseph Goldstein who is a meditation famous
meditation person and now okay here's the
poem this is called a January morning unrelenting Gray Bears down subduing
Morning Light it might be enough to dampen our Spirits except except for that secret
Stillness within not wanting not planning not
intending moments of Silence forgetting for some time who we think we
are unrelenting Gray Bears down subduing Morning Morning Light it might be enough
to dampen our Spirits except except for that secret Stillness within not wanting
not planning not intending moments of Silence forgetting for some time who we
think we are so what I wish for you is moments of
Stillness when you forget who you think you are thank
you so any questions comments
Tomatoes to-do lists
yes when you were referencing grief and that
you um you know were thinking about your loved one or whomever had passed and and
bring yourself back to the present moment where you're at who you're with
but I guess I just wonder about the that sometimes maybe you want to
think about um the person that's passed or that it's comforting in a way to
think of them or maybe you talk to them because that brings you comfort to it's
kind of a continuing Bond type of thing so they're not here um in the room
necessarily but I don't know if that makes any sense
so uh so there are different conditions so what I was describing for
before was a condition where I was really suffering
now to in that moment
uh conjure up moments of our conversations probably would have only
increased the suffering oh this won't happen again this won't happen again in other moments in other moments under
other conditions I might want to say oh we had some great
times and and recall that now what's going on in the moment in my heart is
feelings of love and and peace and there's a very different feeling the comforting feeling is different than the
suffering of loss the suffering of wishing they were were here the com the
yeah hold it close to you oh the suffering of wishing wishing they were wishing things were different yeah
wishing things were different is is not the same as recalling a memory that
reinforces the the feeling of uh
uh why why the why the love is here now so I I'll give you I'll give you a
different example that's a little closer to what you were really asking about so
um my brother passed away suddenly this
summer and uh I was very close to
him and what I remember even in in moments of great
grief was one particular conversation we had
when I visited him in prison and he was
uh confessing to me things about his
life and it was as if he was saying and I was holding his hand and it
was if he was saying what if I told you this would you still love me then
what if I told you this and what I remember is it didn't
matter what he told me I still loved him and how powerful that was for both
of us that it was
independent of what he did that love
and that's what I remembered even the moments of deepest grief how
strong the connection to him was so that's a case where both things
were there and it was comforting to me at the same time as it
was intensely painful that he was gone
both things were true at the same time does that answer your
question it also is a lesson for
me that one has to be present for oneself regardless of what one has
done to be present for oneself and that question of who's in the
room has to do with being able to trust oneself to be present for one's own
strong emotions it's it's all when when you ask yourself
who's in the room am I actually in the room it is a matter of do I trust myself
to be here with this strong
emotion and it's only by showing up that you can answer the question for
yourself so this it's all related
can I be present for this emotion this person not the person I was
then this person can I be present for it because in this moment you're a
different person than you were then
for
so there's an alternative poem to the one I read you also from J's book this
is called Dreamscapes of the mind that he's just
published it's similar but not quite the same this one is called Ode to
[Music] non-being and it starts to the quote if now on top of this non-being
is who can comprehend it by
changu so that's the quote he opens it with if on top of this non-being is who
can comprehend it non-being that is what Matrix Keeps
Us wandering in the Dreamscape of the Mind what if the Matrix is beingness
itself castles of sand at Water's Edge where aging children play and Shiva
laughs as breaking waves turn castles into caves in zero all the numbers of the
world are freed who will Brave this Embrace of
peace that mysterious absence terrifying at first and then release
now this refers to the willingness to enter every moment of now without
knowing who you are without knowing in advance who you
are so let me read it again what Matrix Keeps Us wandering in
the Dreamscape of the Mind what if the Matrix is beingness
itself castles of sand at Water's Edge where aging children play and Shiva
laughs as breaking waves turn castles into caves in zero all the numbers of
the world are freed who will Brave this Embrace of
peace that mysterious absence terrifying at first and then
release so just in case you want to take that step toward nonbeing
there is peace and release in not being so sure you are who you think you
are please have a wonderful holiday season good night