welcome everyone so
today we'll continue where we left off yesterday and uh I want to give thanks
to Julie and Kevin the wonderful other wonderful people who support these
morning morning Community Gatherings uh from behind the scenes and they tell me
it's not too late to sort of change the the name of this week's
teaching to the Buddhist smile and I'm going to double down on that today I I'll even show some
images of the Buddha smiling in
meditation and it's interesting uh for some time I've noticed the Buddhist
smile and meditation and I've wondered to
myself what's he smiling about what does he know what um what contentment is being
experienced and because in our practice and in these teachings that come down to us uh things are never
one-dimensional I've also understood that these representations and I'll show a few over the next few
days I mean almost any Buddha you look at in meditation is smiling I've also come to understand
that this is an instruction it's a meditation
instruction to smile when we meditate inwardly perhaps
uh or I should say outwardly perhaps but inwardly most certainly there's contentment to be
found in the meditation and as we explored yesterday the pleasant of the meditation the pleasure of the
meditation can be leaned into can be supported can be cultivated as part of the path and
uh the Buddha's smile and meditation I take to be an instruction that points
that direction so let's continue with that today
today's the the second knowledge that arises in the meditation that may give rise to this sort of smile and
meditation inward possibly outward is the
following this meditation this meditation practice is noble and onward
leading is the way I'm going to characterize it so let's let's bring our uh attention
inward I like to think as I close the eyes close invitation to close the eyes if that's a
comfortable part of the meditation for you um I like to think of bringing the
attention both Inward and downward sort of
inward in a in a gesture towards seclusion
downward into the body to sort of at least initially bring our attention into
the embodied aspect of the experience of
meditation the settl of the body the weight of the body the um slow pace of
the body the Simplicity of the body's experience can be places where we can
first rest our attention in a way that opens up to Greater ease in the
mind and as we settle in today maybe we
can think about letting a smile play over our features this can be internal
or external but it can be quite um instructive actually
to give a little give a little smile to the features
if you ever do this in a mirror with your eyes open you'll notice that frequently when
we smile inwardly and we bring that smile to our features it actually
doesn't register on our features before we crack a a wide grin
there's a very gentle a very gentle uplifting in the
features that for our meditation today can be an expression of any greater ease
that comes with the meditation so settling in with the
breath settling in with the body settling in with the simple
knowing of experience that's available in the
meditation we can bring our attention to Greater ease
and the profound message of today's teaching is that as we do so as ease and body and
mind begin to arise in the meditation we notice about the
meditation that it's in the words of the suta from which I quoted Noble and
onward leading the meditation itself generates
a knowing that the
Mind likes to be oriented toward
freedom and we don't have to create anything make anything up in the meditation a knowledge that arises all
by itself in the words of the sutta arises inwardly as
a a beneficial side effect of the meditation itself is a knowing that the
Mind wants to be free and here too we can lean into this
wholesome wanting to be free as a way to deepen and strengthen
our
practice we can do this in the meditation and we have this wonderful technology of the meditation that goes
like this we're all familiar with this oh who knows maybe one or two of us not
so much but the mind gets entangled it gets caught up in things it tightens up
around oh thoughts of the future thoughts of the past thoughts of other people thoughts of
ourselves and in the meditation practice we when we notice this when we wake up to this we bring our attention back to
Center we open back up if the mind's becoming tight to here to now just know
knowing what's going on without adding anything without
judging just being here just knowing this
now every time this happens far from being uh a source of frustration or
agitation this can be an opportunity to notice that with that return home the
return to Center the return to here now we can touch space with the mind's
desire to be free this wholesome orientation toward
free this is what's meant in this second knowledge touching in with this knowing
that this meditation experience points towards
freedom
e
e e
so as we start to come to the end of this set
let's reorient our attention again
to what we might call the Finer
Things the way the meditation suggests that the
Mind wants to be free and the way it for that
reason brings our attention to subtler and
subtler ways of meeting experience ways of knowing ways of
being ways of meeting our
experience the Finer Things of Life The Meditation
suggests aren't
things and we can keep tuning into this direction that the meditation presents
us with an orientation
toward peace towards ease
towards a presence in our lives that's unmediated by projection
clinging and this too this orientation
toward freedom is something that we can bring
with us into the world of interaction the world of our daily
round sort of keep it always in mind yesterday talked about just meeting
experience with some of that greater ease that the meditation provides
es today we can also think about meeting the world with an
orientation toward Freedom that the meditation
suggests who knows what that means when we meet a particular
situation that's to be discovered meditation provides a
potential uh a prop intensity a momentum
[Music]
so welcome back or welcome if you're just joining
now as I said it as we began the meditation
I want to keep going in this vein of exploring the Buddha Smile by way of by
way of bringing forward from the teachings from the texts these five so-called knowledges or
understandings that emerge in the meditation as a product of the deepening of the meditation without
our having to exert effort uh except the effort of
paying attention to our experience of the meditation and uh I promised that I would share
some pictures of the Buddhist smile this is an interesting book called Lost
kingdoms Hindu Buddhist sculpture of early southeast Asia it was a period of time where there's sort of a combination
of Buddhist and Hindu issues uh sorry images imagery
iconography but throughout here from the little buddha on the top
of the big Buddha's head you can see this lovely little
smile that plays over the Buddha's features in meditation and uh almost in every image
of the Buddha meditation in this book you can see
this and I encourage you to seek out Buddha
images trying to get this in focus and good Lu come on nonetheless you can see the
smile uh and perhaps one more I encourage you to look
around here's a couple lovely ones there's a nice image of it or this
one look around and notice that Buddha images have
frequently not always this subtle Mona Lisa smile and I think it's a it can be
useful to um and supportive of practice when we see that smile to sort of take
it take it in maybe recall this 5-day session on the knowledges the
understandings the knowings that come up in the meditation and that maybe uh bring a
smile forward in internally perhaps a smile that can be seen externally as
well and as I suggested at the outset when we see those
images we can uh take it as
instruction um that is like all things in these teachings there's multiple ways
in which the iconography the images the texts can be read
and here too we can uh we can take this smile that we see in the Buddhist face
as instruction bring a smile into our meditation this is as I said yesterday
this meditation experience and the pleasantness of it is to be enjoyed when we enjoy it we cultivate it we make it
stronger we um enhance the propensity that we will move forward with that
internal contentment and E that's so useful when we meet the
world so the understanding that arises today again being creative with
the translation and again I'm going to read
sort of the whole thing that the Buddha says cultivate the meditation
practice we could say strive to the extent they're striving in
this practice exert appropriate effort I'm going to say to deepen the meditation
practice and as one does so five knowledges arise for us the
first one yesterday is that the pleasure in the meditation is to be cultivated not to be feared that it's part of the
path and today that this meditation experience is Noble
onward leading and the technical term which I'm going to unpack in a moment is
that it's not of the flesh but it's not of the world we could
say I like to think of this maybe as an
awareness that the Mind seeks profound relief profound ease profound
release and as I tried to bring bring our attention to in the guided
meditation being aware of this being noticing that knowing that comes up in the meditation is really useful in
deepening our practice the meditation suggests that the Mind wants to be free and when we
notice that wholesome desire to be free uh it strengthens it makes it a
momentum creates Direction in our
practice so um in the
teachings this um what I'm sort of describing here
as a something that happens over time not a noun but a
verb a creating of momentum a uh uh or an adjective or
adverb instead of again a noun on something in the meditation that's onward leading that orients us toward
Freedom again and again each time we return to the breath each time we return
to a meditation object There's an opportunity to notice that that ease the
Simplicity of experience the pace the slower pace of the body's experience in
the meditation are hints um that the practice of the
meditation leads toward peace and that there's a desire in the mind for
peace I'm realizing that yesterday I introduced possibly sort of radical
notion that the pleasure of the meditation is to be cultivated not not I but the Buddha
recommends this but I I've taken it deeply at the bip practice today I find
myself using language of desire a wholesome desire this too is there in
the teachings at the um wanting the
mind's um seeking of Freedom we may feel come up as a wanting
or a desire and we can recognize oh this is a wholesome one and sometimes when
that happens because we have this idea that desire wanting or to be um let go
in the practice it can be helpful to think of this orientation toward Freedom as an
aspiration an aspiration in our
practice so I'll substitute that word but it's okay to lean into that that that wholesome knowing that the Mind
wants to be free um that the mind can be
free so in the teachings there is uh and and Gil draws attention to this in some
of his teachings on the uh sort of the fundamental texts
that uh teach us how how and where to establish mindfulness and many of you
are familiar I think with the Sati patana suta and the establishing of
mindfulness sometimes we characterize the atti patan suta as the four foundations of mindfulness I like to
avoid nouns so I'm going to say the establishing of mindfulness in four
different Arenas or spheres of experience throughout these teachings
there's this same distinction between things that are noble and onward leading
and things that tie us more to the the
um I think we could even say the physical uh aspects of of
experiences it's a turning from some of that concern with the world
and our engagement and entanglement with the world and the things of the world and an orientation more to the
mind uh and to the knowing that is uh an
effortless part of our experience sometimes this distinction
it's a tricky one and I I'm gonna I don't know how much how frequently Gil does this but I'm GNA mention the poly
terms sisa Anda because they're frequently translated in
ways that are that are can be challenging sometimes this contrast
is um presented as one between of the Flesh
and not of the flesh other times worldly and
unworldly Gil has sometimes talked about the distinction between body body and
mind or between objective and subjective as we refine our establishing of
mindfulness and in each of the mindfulness practices there's this
movement from entanglement with the world to a
free knowing of the phenomena of
experience a movement from entanglement with the with objects with the signs
things in the world the appearances of things toward the knowing of
experience and in the meditation we have this opportunity to rest in this
knowing to return again and again to the here now of experience and notice that
the um the mind can with with repeated
returning the mind can become increasingly comfortable resting at ease
in the the sort of flow of experience without grasping without entanglement
without projection and as we notice that we we
we we develop a momentum and we receive in the from the meditation in the
meditation this orientation toward toward Freedom sort of natural
urge and as I said a moment ago aspiration toward being more free more
are awake in in the world and as I speak of these things and
with some awareness that um they may they may
seem esoteric or um abstract I want to return to the very uh
to the very visceral knowing that emerges in the meditation and that even
now as I speak about these things brings a smile to my features this
smile which I'm using as a theme for the week of this one particularly but the Buddhist smile the smile that comes in
the meditation when we talk about when we recognize when we rest in when we
acknowledge when we become aware of the desire of the mind to be
free is is something that can bring bring great joy to our practice and to our
lives and uh because I neglected to at the end of
The Meditation I'll I'll take this opportunity to dedicate the Merit of our
practice today in this way to um feel in the meditation these
knowledges arising all by themselves we just pay attention we bring our attention again again back to the here
and now and as we do so over time we get rid of the frustration it's like oh dang
I lost track of the breath whatever we just notice that here's an opportunity when we return to here and now it feels
good as we said yesterday feels good to be here and it points
onward and maybe we can bring some of that momentum forward forward momentum
toward Freedom into our actions and interactions today
in a way that benefits others so this is a sweet thing for ourselves generates maybe an internal
smile um and it benefits others to
smile inwardly or outwardly but to bring that momentum toward Freedom into our
actions and interactions freedom is possible meditation makes that clear freedom is a
direction the mind if we allow it to if we encourage it to
if we provide the conditions for that and that momentum can be shared
with others so in closing let's bring bring a smile to the practice when you
look at when you see Buddhist today tomorrow this week going forward notice that smile take it as an instruction
bring it into your practice and then share it with the idea that it benefits
it's not just ourselves but all beings may all beings know this
contentment may all beings find this path to Freedom may all
beings know happiness be free of suffering be
free so thank you very much looking forward to tomorrow already where we'll continue exploring
the Buddha smile thank you