so one of the tasks of as we develop meditation practice Buddhist
practice is to become our own teachers to be able and what that means
partly is to be able to find the path of practice as it opens up in front of
us a metaphor is that if you're going to cross uh maybe it's
a somewhat shallow River wide river and there's lots of rocks and boulders in it
that are Stepping Stones across the river that um the
um and the stepping stones are kind of spread little bit different distance from each other and different angles
some rocks are clearly not stable enough to step on so you would have to kind of find
your way across the river on these stepping stones and go this way way and that way and a little bit longer steps
sometimes and um make sure you stand in the middle of some steps some stones and uh and you have to find your
own path across uh by choosing the right stones to walk on and if you don't you
might end up in the river and um and maybe it's a shallow River it's easy enough to get back up
again so in the same way we're kind of finding their path and um falling into
the river is falling into our thoughts and preoccupations and attachments
reactivity falling into um great hate and delusion and
falling into preoccupations With Me Myself and
mine and uh and to find the PATH the find the Stepping Stones next moment
next moment is to find ourselves in the Simplicity of awareness the simp the
simplest kind of awareness of attention of knowing that you can find for
yourself and uh so simple that it might even be a nonverbal
awareness or so simple that if it's a simple verbal kind of knowing it's no
story connected no judgment connected to it no interpretation just
an INB breath out warmth
coldness calm agitation just really really
simple and um and you can one of some of the ways we find our way is that uh is
some of these criteria we're talking about this week one is you find your way
by not when aware where awareness has
no doesn't harm anything where awareness is there's no sting no stress
in being aware we find it where there's no stories and interpretations views
beliefs that are somehow clouding the simple awareness that we don't need to have any
beliefs to stay on the stepping stones of the simple awareness and we find it
where uh we're allowing something deep within to emerge
to unfold to heal to settle to calm um there's a sense of
allowing the all the things that we know they're
aware of trusting that as we know them in this simple awareness something
that's not us within us the Dharma the natural
processing uh has a chance to unfold we
know that uh we're on the path when that
awareness has a very simple [Music]
maybe um primordial simple kindness or
care for ourselves for what we're aware
of and here we find it finding our steps so rather than looking for a particular
experience we're looking for something to happen we find the stepping stones in
the Simplicity of awareness that avoids any sting any
stress any holding on that avoids any
belief as we're practicing beliefs might have gotten us
to our meditation but then we don't need them
anymore we find the Stepping Stones if the awareness is allowing making space
for what's here to let go unfold dissolve open up
or grow if it's something wholesome and the wholesomeness of a
Simple Kindness this is how we find the PATH
across the river of attachments and
clinging so with that uh again like yesterday we sit in
silence and if you're inclined to be your own teacher maybe some of these words will
uh will point you to the way thank
you
e
for
for e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting maybe to point to the
possibility of not identifying with the thoughts we have the feelings
and emotions we have the impulse impulses we have the
experiences of pain
and suffering happiness and pleasure not to lean into anything or
not to take up residence in any of that
that but instead to know it to be aware of it in the most simple
way stepping out stepping back from the river of attachment River of
becoming River
of being caught in the river of
distractions attachments and stepping back onto the
stable secure dry Simplicity of just knowing
this just this where each thing is allowed to be
itself nothing is condemned nothing is made wrong
where there's a relief and a kind of sense of
well-being and not being in the cot in the river wet in
the flow of
distractions and this simplic it of knowing of awareness is how we find our
way and how we can be bring a very meaningful attention and
care to others to see others without the filter
of our attachments our opinions to see others without being
caught in our sufferings and our hurts and our our angers and our desires and
envies so see them as they are warts and
all with a kind attention open
tension an attention that allows something
deep to unfold
May our ability to listen to others see others know others with
Simplicity support
others to become free of
suffering to experience some peace here and
now to feel safe safe in our
presence and to have the possibility of be being
happy may all beings be happy and may how we attend to others
support that possibility [Music]
thank you [Music]
so good morning everyone and
welcome and uh the announcement before I give the talk is
that I'll be away then uh three weeks of which are teaching uh retreat in the
wilderness and then a week of camping with my
wife and um I think the whole thing will be a bit of a vacation as well
and um some wonderful IMC teachers who will be teaching while I'm away and now
you'll be in good hands here at this YouTube
channel so um so this uh uh week I'm kind
of basing the teachings on the uh uh the
UD suta and I'll read it as I have every
morning it's not easy Anand to teach the dhma to
others the dhama should be taught to others when five qualities are
established within oneself which five the dhama should be taught to
others thinking I will speak step by step I will teach progress
aggressively that dhama should be taught to others thinking I will speak for practical
reasons I'll speak providing instructions in how to become free of
suffering the dama should be taught to others thinking I will speak grounded in
kindness that now much should be taught to others thinking I will I will not speak for material reward
the dhama should be taught to others thinking I will speak without wounding myself or
others so it's not easy to teach the dhama to others and I suppose that's
partly because these things are not easy to do and uh or it's easy to overlook the
Simplicity of these ideas for other purposes in
teaching and um and as I been doing this week these uh wonderful qualities are
also very useful for those of us who are when we're not teaching but when we're just
speaking and uh I will speak step by step is the first one in the suta but
the last one for this week and I'm equating it or connecting these things
to what I've taught last week on and for for last week on Friday it was um the
possibility of liberation and the path to Liberation and so I will speak step by
step I will spech Pro progressively I will teach a path the progressive path
the gradual path that leads onward to greater and greater
freedom and uh the word for step by step um
Anup can also mean um kind of uh P can
mean uh footstep steps they can be the the uh traces of the steps that are Le
behind and so the U uh it could also be
uh kind of be used be the idea of tracking I will teach
tracking how to track how to find our way um
through the our life so we can be our own teachers and so um the uh there and so
particularly uh uh pointing out to how we can step by step gradually find our
way and um and it's easy to maybe teach the most profound Dharma uh of Buddhism
but and leave lots of people behind because they just simply can't understand it's just not relevant for
them and so to teach kind of something that's appropriate for each person um is
part of the art and so for people who are new to practice to offer beginning instructions
people who have particular forms of suffering maybe it needs to be addressed
directly and uh and then people are middling in practice they might need something different and then people who
are have uh quite experienced in practice maybe are ready for some deeper
pointing out that can happen and uh but still it's always uh
step by step and giving instructions giving pointing where to find the next step in practice is um is uh not only to
point it out to people but then to help people understand it for themselves to
give people their own kind of so they can become their own teachers so they don't rely on other teachers all the
time and um so this is how it works this is how it goes this is what you can do
this is what you pay attention to there's this is what's helping ful and
um and uh and one of the eventually what we learned through this practice is to
not be overly concerned with what we're
experiencing but rather how we know what we're experiencing and so there's a
almost like a paradigm shift from being identified or CAU up with or or or
managing managing ing the experience we have trying to change our experience have a better experience to letting the
experience be what it is kind of leave it alone but don't
leave it alone ignoring it leave it leave it alone in the clarity of the of
knowing of mindfulness really know it and uh and uh this is finding your own
path so it's not like find looking for an experience so much as it is looking where that freedom is in knowing in the
awareness and um so in um you know when
we to switch over to the idea of speaking that this these teachings apply to speaking as well is that when we
speak uh don't leap from one thing to another don't leap to conclusions speak
in a way that allows people to understand and follow along what's being said uh
explain the foundation explain the conditions explain the reasons for why you do something or why you think
something uh explain the purpose um step by step provide people with this the
Stepping Stones of explanations of teachings so they can follow what you're saying understand what you're saying so
that we can find our way together with what's going on to make thear narative
statements uh where we just make a statement as as if it's true then um
maybe people can't follow along it's too big of a leap so um so to speak in a way that is
uh gradual that build builds a case Builds an understanding builds a
connection with others um and if if the having a warm deep connection to others
is part of the value of being connect being in relationship let that happen
step by step care for it and you know ask questions of others learn about them
pay attention explain yourself say something about yourself so people get to know you but so the gradual building
and building and so this is one of the Hallmarks or one of the characteristics of the Buddhist
teachings is that um it's uh uh it
there's a developmental model of human life meaning things evolve and develop
over time and for the Buddha there isn't like like instant Enlightenment per se
exactly there isn't this idea of a quick fix but uh just like a child you don't
snap the fingers and suddenly the child is an adult but there's a gradual growth and development of that child um day by
day you know meal by meal um experience by experience a child grows and so in
the same way um uh even as adults there's still this Evolution this
evolving this maturing that goes on and so uh one of the key metaphors
for um becoming uh you know uh growing
in the darai is the idea of growing it's the idea of maturing like a fruit matures a f a plant grows um so that uh
it's a step by step it's a gradual process it's a building putting together the stepping
stones and um and so uh to approach the Dharma approach
these teachings in that kind of way so if we're going to be our own teachers
then it's really important we understand ourselves well and understand what we need next
what helps us to open up what helps us to be more present what helps us to mature in some way and at different
stages of practice um there are different things that are needed uh sometimes what's needed is a lot of meta
and compassion sometimes what's needed is a friend or a companion to talk to and
explore and think about things sometimes what's needed is a therapist sometimes
what's needed is a is um to go out into the world and serve and do something for
the benefit of others um not for the sake of others but that's what we need
that's where our growing and our Evolution development is going to be so
this idea of Step by Step Progressive uh that idea of finding the tracks finding
the so we're tracking carefully not in the not just big leaps
But Here and Now where is the next step now and so to go through a day with that
kind of care to end our session here
together and then taking time and ask yourself given all this given what's
happened now how I am now what what is the next step in my own
inner maturation is it to go have breakfast but how do I have breakfast to
support this gradual growth of the Dharma in me the mindfulness of attention of
kindness is it to go to drive to work great but how does driving to work
support this gradual growth always asking where's the where's the Dharma
here where's the maturation here where's the path to Freedom here where's the path to to um to kindness where's the
path in whatever we're doing and um and if you simply ask that
question of yourself you'll start being your own teacher if you don't ask the question then it's all too easy to live
a a mind a life that is inattentive where we're caught up in what we're
doing that we don't really pay attention to how we're doing what we're doing the Dharma is found in that how
and if you want to be your own teacher then gradually step by step as you go through the day
um um find the path find how you can grow in these qualities that we've been
talking about so thank you very very much and uh
for the opportunity to teach and to be part of this and um I'll be back um I
think it's the very very end of July I think maybe the 29th of July and um
looking forward to being with you again thank you for