okay excuse me so welcome uh welcome folks good to uh good to be with you
it's a certain Wednesday and
um yeah happy to uh to practice good time to
practice um yeah so settle uh settle into your
your posture
just uh set yourself up as right as you
can meaning uh
comfortable maybe even cozy
alert
or some part of our mind it can feel neglectful to stop
clinging can feel neglectful to stop
worrying as if it's our vigilance that keeps us
safe maybe it can feel like avoidant to relax into tranquility
but our agitation and vigilance
clinging does less for our life than we
imagine and so give oursel permission to
relax
e
e e
just let your your breathing fill out your
body sensing your breath in the back of your body
feels like life is in front of us but life's
everywhere so we breathe and sense the sensations of breathing in the back of
our body
and breathe some life into these zones of numbness the areas
of your body habitually neglected
forgotten I'm so familiar with my chest but much less
so with my belly
so unify your body with the breathing breathing
into the zones of flatness or
numbness
e e
so we breathe into the cold places but also the hot
places the intensities and the swirls of energy or hyperarousal
it's the gentle soothing quality of
breathing is it unifies our body our body feels uh
suspended in awareness
e
e e
perhaps with our bodies
suspended in uh awareness
may feel skillful to
turn mind to uh
compassion beginning with the gentle tending
to your own suffering
just here in this
moment wherever there is sorrow or
pain wherever there is grief or rage
age or
fear tend lovingly to
it for
in the gesture of compassion uh we're becoming
unintimidated by our pain
yeah of course it
hurts maybe hurts a
lot compassion is here
and so you're infusing that
struggle and disease infusing it with this particular species of
love the love that tends and heals
heartache
e
e for
I uh care about uh my
pain you have to
Words May I be free from suffering and my heart be
at
ears may I be released from torment
we each find the words the images and their particularity
that speak to our own
heart that remind us of the vastness of
compassion that tie ties
are suffering
to all other
suffering and meeting it all with the
love
e
e e
compassion doesn't need to make pain go
away it's a very patient
love in the face of
suffering and continually The Compassion
says I'm here
I may not be able to do everything but I'm
here and sometimes we find ourselves abiding in a Kind of
Love
e
e e
okay it's good to uh good to sit with you and I just I don't I don't say that
to like put a nice Dharma bow on it it really is I'm sitting too you know not
just faking it you know so um yeah appreciate being together this evening
so I I was um speaking with somebody
who has a struggling with a a personality
disorder psychiatric designation I'll say something about and
um and um I just had the sense that um
the the layers of their suffering were were very thick
and uh not to be uncompassionate or something but just like the sense of the
wrong view felt so visceral
multi-layered and it made me reflect on the ways that the fruit of
Dharma practice is often something like the diametric opposite of you know person personality
disorder and this condition um is
characterized by severe instability in in Emotion
identity interpersonal relationships behavioral disregulation and
um and you know borderline personality disorder which Marshall linahan developed uh you know dialectical
behavior therapy for which are kind of like mindfulness Zen based treatment
right anyway a whole backstory there but um but narcissistic personality
borderline personality borderline personality is something like 10% of outpatients um and um the diagnosis is
um is known to generate a lot of of Agony and Chaos for the person and often
Co a lot of collateral damage for for others in their
life and it strikes me that in some sense uh
personality pathology is almost like The Logical conclusion of egoic life egoic
life taken to its extreme destructive
and a kind of folly and tragedy of egoic
life and that egoic fragility that is almost infinite is a cause of problems
but it's also the attempt to solve great problems the fragility is not merely a
kind of bad problem but a bad solution and the rigid sense of self
then we're all somewhere on the Spectrum the rigid sense of self is an attempt to
um to shore up our pain to manage it in some
way and sometimes in the clinical literature it's characterized personality disorders are characterized
as a a disorder of self self disorder of the
self and we know from Dharma practice a Hallmark of sakad diti self View
is its rigidity the rigidity of self viw this
is who I am it's what's right how we do things what I believe what makes me
valuable and um in personality disorders
um patients persevere in in rigid strategies that don't work right we have
things that are important to us and we have to find ways of pursuing them but
one strategy is never enough to pursue valued goals we have to be flexible and
our fluidity is dependent on some fluidity in the sense of
self if all we can ever do is maintain Fidelity to a story of self we can't be
flexible so part of our kind of fluid Flex ible
coping means that we have to be fluid and flexible in relation to
ourself a Hallmark of sakad diti is defensiveness when
we claim the territory of self we have a kind of um deeply
emotional emotionally charged connection to some aspect of self viw that
guarantees defensive iess right and so the world of ego
becomes split into groups of enemies and
VIPs and all information coming in either goes in the column of the pros of
me or the cons of me a Hallmark of Sak is is comparison
and en the so much of the way the self gets built up is
through comparison and comparison guarantees some measure of Envy so the ego we come
to see it tolerates no goodness outside itself you
know it's um there's no mudita
sympathetic joy in egoic processes the ego must either kind of
align and acquire that goodness or vilify those who represent that
goodness a Hallmark of self-view is the capacity for cruelty
ego is life and so if you have to
fight you fight and cruelty
is an option that's very much on the
table now I'm not in the clinical world anymore but one of the kind of Hallmarks
of Personality pathology is how easily it gets
under the clinician's skin into your
bloodstream and really clinically you kind kind of enter a world deranged by
the kesas by the forces of greed hand and
delusion and in fact one of the kind of diagnostic markers you know the clues
that there's some personality disorder present is the clinician exits the
Consulting room and they have no idea what
happened and there's often a kind of like like vicious counter transference
the experience of the clinician in relation to the patient can be very destructive counter
transference and the symptoms and behaviors of
Personality Disorder they it's like often like heat seeking missiles aimed
precisely at the soft spots in one's own Consciousness the pain points in one's
own heart life and so almost as if by
Magic um these folks Infuse the mind of
clinicians and the clinician is drawn into a disordered world of
experience and it's difficult to stay
clear it's difficult to remember the goodness of the patient to remember one's own
goodness it's difficult to know that hatred does not cease through hatred but
through non-h hatred it's difficult to remember that
this person desperately needs help
compassion so what why why am I talking about this you that may be a frequent
question you have you know why is Matthew talking about
this why am I talking about this um
because uh it strikes me that um personality disorder symptoms of
course constellate at the individual level but it's also like like they
constellate at the national level too the societal
level and this country this one I know we've got
Switzerland in the house and other countries I imagine but this country the
US and its electoral politics and it a decade of Donald Trump and the social
media environment and um all of this is unfolding as a kind of
personality disorder manifested at the national
level and greed hatred delusion um have been disguised and
dignified and thoroughly colonized National consciousness
and good-hearted uh people everywhere are vulnerable to the
symptoms are getting drawn into a vicious counter
transference and so if it feels like you're fighting for your moral
sanity it's because a little bit you
are and I'm trying to find balance to stay with my commitments none of what
I'm saying is uh uh compatible with um political
quietism or something I'm staying with my commitments but I'm trying to find a
pathway between frenzy and n
ISM I'm trying in other words to uh protect my
love and there's a sense of like one stays
sane morally sane only through some
discipline and some softening and through the Buddhist
counsel a mind not clinging to
anything one stays saying through action wholesome seeds planted yeah feels
negligible but acting wholesome one stays sane through
spiritual friendship spiritual friendship that's what we're doing here
you know and um one Stay s through a very
long View unjustice and
love so I offer this for your consideration and
uh may we uh may we be well but see you uh see you next week