good evening welcome welcome
everybody so tonight I want to talk a little bit about this idea that mindfulness practice is about
allowing but when I was thinking about it I was think like allowing that
doesn't sound so interesting it doesn't sound so much fun it doesn't sound like
okay this is something that's going to find make me happy and make all my life run perfectly or something like that
whereas mindfulness you know at least it has that potential for something right something new and
different it turns out that uh mindfulness is so much about
allowing not so much about going out there manipulating and make everything be fine and perfect so that our life
runs perfectly because if you could do that you would not be here on a Monday night
right you would be out there making your life run perfectly there's this way which we
don't even notice and certainly I didn't notice that we are so often maybe even
most often in a subtle or an obvious way saying no no no no no
no air conditioner is too cold it was a little bit too warm earlier or uh it
should be quieter in the whole nope you know nope that should be uh we should have a longer sit we should have a
shorter sit or you know whatever it is there's this little way in which we're
always say no to whatever we're experiencing it somehow needs to be
different and I mean of course this is in obvious ways but also there's like so
many ways in which this is really subtle the way that we shows way this shows
up and when we start noticing all the way in which we're saying
no and instead we allow I'm not going to say that we have to say yes but just the
kind of the softening the no things really can
transform and can change will change will
transform in ways that uh can really make a difference for our lives move us
towards greater and greater freedom and ease so mindfulness practice is asking us can
we in some ways kind of like align with the present
moment can we align with the reality of the present moment what's happening is
what's happening doesn't matter whether we like it or don't like it doesn't matter
whether we are um obviously or very subtly trying to say no or yes I want
some more I hope this doesn't end ever I mean that's what's happening is
what's happening and it turns out that whether we allow it or not doesn't make
that much of a difference I'm saying that much of a
difference because there's a way the stronger there were saying no please go away if it's regards our experience you
know the experience that we're having the longer it'll stay
we've heard this expression right what we resist persists turns out this is
true much do our shagrin right that's exactly what uh we don't want I'm going
to talk a little bit about this but this idea of mindfulness is I like this kind of expression like aligning with the
reality of the moment when it's puts that way it sounds like oh okay of course like why why
wouldn't I align with reality I don't want to be hallucinating I don't want to be completely delusional I I do want to
align with the reality of the moment but there's this way in which we are so
often maybe we could say hallucinate that's a strong word but there's this way in which we have an
idea about how things should [Music]
be this notion completely in our mind 100% in our minds it should be like this
and how it should be usually is related to the word comfortable it should be comfortable in
some kind of way and then what happens is we take this idea and we overlay it
on top the actual experience and it never fits
perfectly and then we like no no no it should match this thing that I made up
rather than how things actually are I've talked about this idea in a number of different ways so
this idea of allowing is to soften this idea of of
how we think things should be and tune into become sensitive to how things
actually are how things actually are and you might think well wait I'm
doing that all the time of course I am are you really I really tuned into how things
actually are maybe there's so much of this subtle of uh yeah but I don't want
to so mindfulness practice and I would say and we could even maybe even expand
this so much we would say Buddhist practice is about
allowing because that's related to whether allowing is related to not clinging which is related to
Freedom suffering is clinging so there's this way what can we
like this allowing the present moment is just this simple simple recognition of what is
here what's happening this
non-judgmental openness to the experience whether it's Pleasant or
unpleasant or neutral just this way of non-judgmental openness like instead of
like this barrier like I want things to be the way that I want having me some openness maybe we
might even say just welcoming experiences instead of like you know slamming the door in their face like oh
okay here's where it is come on in you might you know join the party you
know that kind of an experience allowing the present moment
is also this way in which we're relaxing resistance in fact resistance might be
so familiar with us that we don't even notice that we're doing it we just notice that we're exhausted at the end
of the day or that we have so much tension because there's this way in which we are saying no maybe the body is
saying no even if the mind isn't overtly saying that we could say that um allowing the
present moment is a way in which we're creating space we're allowing the
present moment to be the way that it is and for it to unfold the way it's going to unfold instead of us kind of like
pushing and prodding and manipulating and trying to make it to be be something
instead we're allowing it how it is this means that we're putting down
the urge at least for that moment to manipulate things and to make them
different can we're like oh yeah it's like
this so in this way we're shifting our relationship to experience shifting our
relationship away from one that is um you know trying to make sure that we're
comfortable at all times which you know is not a of course we are I want to
humanize this like of course we want to be comfortable of course we
do but it turns out that just chasing Comfort isn't going to lead us to
greater and greater Freedom instead it's going to lead us to just following our ingrained patterns more and more and
more until they get more and more ingrained and then there's a if that
doesn't bring you just like of ease and freedom then you're going to be going more and more away from ease and
freedom so we're shifting our relationship so rather than like tensing up or Contracting or trying to get more
or less there's this kind of opening up and just
noticing and maybe we're noticing with a flavor of kindness like oh hello or
noticing with a sense of curiosity like what really is going on on
here so it doesn't mean that we're pretending like things aren't terrible
when they are terrible it's not I I I mentioned this I think was it last week I don't
remember that I heard somebody say this and I thought it's just really caught my attention this idea of like the ways in
which we Gaslight ourselves the way that we're like oh it's not so bad get over it we're saying
when it is bad we're not trying to pretend like things sometimes aren't
awful they are awful sometimes this is the truth of The Human Experience it's also the first Noble
Truth right there is suffering there is Dua and there's some and sometimes there
can be a relief like yeah this sucks this is not what I want I wouldn't want this on anybody sometimes there can be a
relief of just like okay I'm acknowledging what it is for just for
that moment it doesn't mean that we're not going to take care of things and I'm
also talking about allowing in the present moment I'm not saying that we're just to be passive and to allow all the
terrible injustices and oppression and all the awful things that are happening in the world that's not what I'm talking
about I'm talking about just allowing this moment this
moment this moment our present moment experience I'm pointing to experience
that we are having and when we do this there's a way
that we're bringing a attitude or quality of
Freedom into that moment this is what Freedom Is Right
Freedom isn't that you ride a unicorn and a rainbow cloud or you know
something silly like that its freedom is still living a life still having a human
body and yet it's not a problem all the difficulties that arise
all the um seemingly barriers or things like this they're not problems they're
just what's arising next and so there's a way in which
allowing is bringing a flavor of Freedom an attitude of Liberation into this
experience right now instead of having this idea like okay yeah there'll be Liberation you
know I don't know when but it'll be later sometime later this activity of allowing is to
bring it into here and now because freedom is not being pushed around by
our experience Liberation is to stop making problems out of
things I didn't I didn't word that quite right Liberation is where there are things don't aren't problems they just
are they just are and so there's this way in
which allowing allows us to not only bring this quality of Liberation into
our experience but it also allows this quality of ease we often don't notice how much we
are like resisting as I said earlier but that resisting it shows up as tension
and it shows up as a like a contraction in the mind and in the body in the mind
of like oh I got to get this I you know get go away I'm I'm trying to you know
get this thing here and that shows up as you know when I'm talking about it my shoulders go up
and my hands come together this is how I kind of experience it when I'm really trying to you know get something and
make everything go away there's this feeling of tightness so allowing is allowing
a yeah okay I can just be I don't have to brace myself I don't have to armor
myself about what's uh happening and so this way like there is
less and less agitation which is just you know a more pleasant
experience and there's this way in which if we're not if we have this
idea like okay allowing the present moment experience it highlights how much we are not doing
that as I've been talking about and then noticing how much we are not allowing
the present moment experience to be just as it is highlights how much we are
identified with wanting things a particular way our sense of self our
identities is intimately tied up with how we want things to
go there's a way in which I talked about we have these expectations that we
overlay on top of our experience these expectations they arise out of a sense
of our self who we take ourselves to be how we understand what it means to have
a good life how we understand our interpretation of what it means to be
anything to be a parent to be a sibling to be a caretaker to be an employee to
be an employer all these types of things they get tied up into our
expectations which then translate into our not being present for whatever is arising instead we're trying to express
our sense of self and make something happen in a way that aligns with our
ideas for example we could say somebody was in the role of a meditation
teacher and they could sit down to meditate in front of a room of people
and they might discover like their mind they were like trying to solve something that happened earlier and they got to
take care of and then there's this idea like oh my goodness I'm supposed to be a meditation teacher I shouldn't do that
this is terrible and there's this all this way in which just was something that just naturally arose all of a
sudden becomes into a big problem it has to go away it would be something very different than like oh yeah okay of
course the mind's busy because there was not too long ago just a lot of trying to
solve something that needed to be taken care of there's this way in which we don't
even notice how these different rules that we have influence our relationship to what's
happening but there's this way that I also want to highlight that allowing
present moment experience is transformational it's not just a way to
have greater ease it's
transformational and there's this way when we are allowing the present moment
to be just as it is and we're observing watching
allowing it allows that experience Whatever It Is racing thoughts
difficulties in the knee trying to remember what was the fourth thing on the grocery list you know whatever it is
that's showing up it allows it to transform that experience to
transform if we're not Tangled Up in it then it's just going to unfold and do
what it's going to do next when we get tangled up in it then you know we're trying to manipulate it and massage it
and to manufacture it or to be some particular way but if we are able to
just allow it to be then it will unfold and transform
itself it will evolve it will change it will be different
the intensity will maybe get greater maybe get less maybe it will completely disappear we
don't know and there's something about just being present and noticing that
change that transformation of experience that highlights a few things for
us that we like viscerally understand it's not an intellectual understanding
one we realize oh that experience wasn't as
substantial as I thought it was it has some insubstantiality it just
changed whereas perhaps we were thinking like no it's this big heavy black box
that we can't see into or something like this right or it felt like it was uh
weighed us down but then when we we start to see a change we realize oh it wasn't as
solid as I was kind of relating to it as it wasn't as fixed as I thought it was
it wasn't as impenetrable in fact it's like different
now and there's this way in which noticing the
insubstantiality of these experiences they are coming and going going and changing really changes our relationship
to them but not only to that to
everything when we start to notice oh yeah this sense of self is insubstantial
also it's always changing just like those those experiences are there are always
changing and then when there's this noticing of the insubstantiality of it and the way that it's always changing
there's just a way in which there's just naturally happens less clinging less
holding on because it just stops making sense to hold on to
something because it's like things are like slip through our
fingers the wait I want that experience but you know that experience is already changed and but then we we're trying to
like make it be that experience again or or uh we want another experience that
we're not having and we can't quite grasp onto that
either so allowing provides the opportunity permits the observation the
witnessing the seeing the experiencing how experiences shift change evolve and
have a quality of insubstantiality to
them and also helps us this if we're allowing and then we're like uh uh
seeing how experiences are shifting and changing and evolving it also highlights
H we don't have to control everything things will do what they do
whether we're there or not and there's something about this to
see this again and again oh we don't have to control it if things actually will unfold in the
way they're going to unfold humans we want to control things this is another way our sense of self
shows up as wanting to control things and make them go a certain way that's
related to right this idea of laying expectations on top but when we start to
allow things to be we notice that they start to change that's the nature of everything to
change we'll see it happen we also realize oh yeah actually the way it
changed I didn't imagine that but maybe it's even better than what we were
thinking and so it allows us to like step away from this secret desire to be
the master of the universe allows us to maybe put down this sense of what's up
to me to make everything right instead we're just noticing oh
yeah okay I I don't have to be in the middle of it sometimes we want to be in the middle
of it and thinking that in fact we're at the center of everything but it can be a relief like oh yeah I don't need to make
everything happen just the way that I want them to be and there's a way that when we are
trying to make things to be a certain way it's because we are looking at them as problems has to be
fixed but if we're allow if we're just allowing them to be they're no longer
problems what a relief it is to not have so many problems you know just the whole notion of a
problem I want to say if I'm going to talk a little bit more about this but before I I go there I want to say what
are some of the pitfalls of this idea of like you know this whole notion of just
allowing the present moment one is we can have this idea of
like okay I'm supposed to allow things to be and then there's this cold
Detachment like I don't care you know there's this this it's a way of kind of
uh it's a slight type of aversion and that's not what I'm being what's being pointed to what's being
pointed to is like no to be there and maybe with some kindness and
some curiosity but there can be this way in which we might think oh I have to be
cold I have to be completely detached that's not what's being pointed to here it's not about Detachment maybe
there's no clinging but that's not the same as
Detachment or there might be this way this the Good meditator
syndrome might arise this idea that we have this um idealized idea of what a
good meditator should look look like and then there's a way in which that creates
this unnecessary pressure and creates some this criticism of ourself and then
there's a way that uh we start to become not so interested in what's actually
happening but become interested in how we look how we look to ourselves or how we look to others and then we have a
whole different relationship or a whole different uh orientation towards what's
happening so there was my might be some of that pitfalls but what are some of these supports for allowing the present
moment and the way that it um is
transformational courage courage to move into the
unknown often we're not allowing things because we don't know what's going to unfold I'm talking about allowing things
to unfold but that means we have to recognize it may unfold in a way that we
hadn't anticipated that we hadn't imagined yet and this requires a certain
amount of Courage which often we don't want to do there's this often we have
this you know um we don't want to recognize the
unpredictability of things we want to think like oh yeah okay I I know how this is going to go or
we want want to be with the familiar and there's a certain uneasiness that shows up if we're just going to allow things
to unfold the way they're allow the present moment to unfold the way it's going to
unfold so this requires some courage and some
trust that if we're not in there trying to control things that somehow everything isn't going
to explode or implode or disappear or I don't know what's going to happen it
requires a certain amount of Courage which maybe it also requires a
certain willingness to be uncomfortable if we're going to allow
the present moment to be the present moment sometimes is uncomfortable can we be okay with
that can we be okay with that can we be in a body that's
uncomfortable it's the reality of the moment and this sometimes you know we
feel like no no no no no I I can't do this but right you know any spiritual
practice any practice actually that's going to um Point our life in a little bit different direction than just
following our preferences by definition has discomfort as part of
it so this idea of allowing is going to require some willingness to be
uncomfortable it's also going to require that we like cultivate some
spaciousness cultivating some spaciousness like observing experience without immediately jumping on it and
identifying with it or judging it or something like this but can we have some spaciousness which we might also say is
a type of equinity type of ease
maybe or maybe there's a way that um we can cultivate this
uh approach to uh uncomfortable experiences or to whatever might be
happening in this uh present moment this approach away from this idea okay I got
to get rid of things that I don't like or I got to get more of the things that
I do like and instead to shift our relationship
what if we like uh think about is just we're just shifting the relationship rather than getting rid of and getting
more of no we're just shifting our relationship to the present moment experience allowing is a way in which
we're just for this moment we're going to allow so it's not a forceful
elimination of any attachments we have but instead it's maybe just loosening
any grip we have on our
preferences so this idea of um maybe befriending our
experience instead of turning the present moment experience into the enemy
is there a way that we can befriend it this way of this
allowing and then it turns out if we're able to do this things move
towards greater freedom and ease may not be the way that you
prefer it may not be in a way that's immediately uh clear like how that
is but there's a way that the there is this movement towards greater freedom
that can start with us just being tuned into what's actually happening in this present
moment and again I'm talking about just this moment I'm not talking about
allowing all the terrible stuff that has happening in the world this your
experience that you're having right then your experience I'm not talking about ideas we have about how the world should
be I'm just talking about feeling the pressure of whatever you're sitting on against the body the experience of the
body breathing the experience of having sounds the experience of feeling the
cold air coming out of there during the when the air conditioner is on can you allow that
experience which is this way of allowing this sense of Freedom into this
moment and then of course you might ask okay Diana that sounds nice but uh how do we even do all these types of
things mindfulness practice and loving kindness
practice these are ways in which we just again and again return to what the
experience is with some warm-heartedness that's all that's being asked for
us this is the way in which we
can allow freedom to arise can allow Liberation peace and
ease to arise in the present
moment so I'll end there and I'll open it up to see if there are some questions
or comments thank you
so for someone like a recovering alcoholic in a 12-step group couldn't
kind of a heartfelt no you know couldn't that come in handy like to keep from
losing his sobriety for
example yes and especially if they feel they allow that experience of a no right
yeah yeah so you're right I'm not I'm I'm pointing to allowing our experience
in the present moment and there is a way in which if they are in soety they
really don't want to also right they don't want to lose their spy there also is a way in which they you know have
this uh addiction as well but yes of course we need
to I'm not saying say yes to everything I'm saying allowing whatever our
experience is but I mean someone feels P if the experiences a pull toward the
drink and that's just say no no no you know is that is what you're talking
about it's a I think I if we're we're very close on what we're talking about with something's a little bit different
it's maybe like to allow like oh yeah okay here's that experience I really
want to drink I really want to drink and to feel that really want to and then
you'll see that that oh I really want to and allow it to arise and go away this is not easy I'm not saying this is easy
but it's a way in which we're saying no I don't want to and then we start to kind of like deny our experience and then as soon as we start to deny our
experience it starts to get easier and easier to get disconnected from ourselves and then go do things that
aren't helpful so there's a way in which to feel it best we can to like feel the
urge and notice how it gets stronger and stronger and stronger and then it will eventually dissipate
and but I'm thinking in terms of like damage control right so you know couldn't that no be the difference
between having the drink and not in that moment you know just yeah of course of course right damage control is important
too but I think what's uh allows one to say no often is just to feel like oh
this urge is here and this is and I don't want to do this sense of I'm working on my sobriety and so here's the
urge and one way to be with the urge is just to acknowledge it and not act on
it MH somebody else have a comment or
question thank thank you um so so one of
the things I I struggle with is physical pain you know and
um the act of being in the body can both accentuate that pain but
give me a Mains to feel it and and kind of let it go right so I think the Buddha
suffered from gout or I've heard that before I don't know if that's true and he had a bad back he talked about his
back hurting yeah so I'd love to you know hear more about that and how this
idea aide of letting whatever it is that we're feeling of
being whatever Spiritual Beings going through a human experience or whatever uh can can help us with that
because I I certainly you know I wake up some days and it's just like oh my God this is miserable right but I don't um
you know want to let it just uh stop me right and so you know sometimes I sit
here and I you know will go through and during the meditation you know stretch
my foot deal with whatever it is you know try try to just kind of see almost kind of medit not meditate on the pain
but you know meditate on how I can feel it and let it go feel it and let it go so anyway just you know would love some
thoughts on that if you know others go through the same thing yeah I would say there's a few things that we can do when
there's a lot of physical pain and like to uh the allowing it to be there is um
sometimes I like to talk about it and we can zoom way out and that is to have a
sense of like for example there's a a pain in the foot and there's I can feel the pressure
of uh the chair or the cushion against the body I can hear the sound of uh
whatever sounds there are so and to kind of like open up our awareness to uh
notice a number of things that can be a little bit hard because when there's a pain there's a way in which we kind of
like tend to collapse into it and becomes like you know the only thing that we're focusing on so then I would
say to like one way we might be allowing that experience is we then uh notice for
example I'll just pain in the foot and we can bring some uh kindness and
curiosity and the Curiosity can take the form of is this like a stabbing or is it
a throbbing is it uh moving around or is it like just in one place
is it a a diffuse area or is it a really precise area you know like a prick or
like something so just bringing some curiosity to it and then this it becomes
uh our meditation and it's not that we have to find all the answers it's about kind of
like shifting our relationship is to bring some curiosity to it because that is the the reality of the moment there
is this uncomfortableness so you can zoom out notice other things besides that
experience zoom in just get curious about the particulars and use adjectives
that are descriptive not uh necessarily like mental words it's yeah just like focus on the
adjectives and a third is um if it feels
that this sometimes works for different people at different times is to
intentionally uh bring your attention to something that's neutral again again and
again neutral sometimes is like maybe the lips touching or uh what the hands
are touching or maybe what the feet are touching and sometimes even to just to
notice you could even just like lips hands
feet lips hands feet sometimes maybe like the pressure against the body can
be a good one too and maybe like even that speed just to go from one thing to the next those are the real of the
present moment as well but it's a way to give the mind like a some breather
because it can be really hard it's very taxing right to be with a discomfort so
those are some things I'm offering of you know how to kind of like be with the reality of the moment when the reality
of the moment is a lot of discomfort and pain thank
you thanks
so where I struggle with the idea of allowing
is oh can you hear me um
yes so the struggle I think uh with
allowing is when a difficult thought or a
difficult sensation or ult emotion arises I'll put on a smile and say
you're absolutely allowed to be here and I'll generate some feelings of kindness
and uh perhaps fake the appearance of
allowing uh in the same way that uh if a guest arrived at my house and I said
welcome and I'm holding a baseball bat behind my back um there's still a deep rooted
no even when I pretend that I'm kind and compassionate and welcoming and allowing
and you know I'm trying to allow but really really deep that real subtle
sense is I'm only doing this to get rid of you nice nice that you recognize that
and so that that's not that that's not
budging so this is fantastic that you recognize this this turns out to be so
common that we don't even know that we're doing this so can you allow not
allowing not allowing feels like this it feels like holding a baseball bat behind my back what I'm saying come on it but I
really don't want it to be here can you allow not allowing
yes but that seems like business as
usual allowing not allowing might be what I'm already doing had I not been practicing any of this not allowing
might be my default State and so if I allow not
allowing that's just my Baseline I see in the absence of any practice I see
I think the difference is that uh without a practice that's maybe what we're doing we're just not allowing but
we're not aware that we're doing and what I'm what I'm pointing to just being aware not allowing feels like this not
allowing is I can see I've done certainly a lot of this this like this
sense of like I'll be mindful of this and then not recognizing in order that it'll go away right this kind
of but instead just to recognize oh yeah there's that little thing
underneath that's wanting it to go away just as you're describing so maybe what I'm pointing to is the recognition that
you're doing that's helpful yeah thank you you're welcome and somebody right behind you has a
comment it's all it's almost like embracing that you
have the bat behind your back acknowledging acknowledging it there's a b behind my back and it feels
like this and that's the allowing yeah but and this part and it feels like this
so just notice yeah yeah and I think the
feeling is the part that maybe we want to go away and that's the part that
you're allowing and you have to embrace that
and like one of the things I do is when that's coming and it's too strong and I
don't want to feel that pain of the emot or whatever is going on I think to
myself oh this is a pity party for one and go yeah but this is real this is
what I'm feeling and so being in that present moment but
not than judging it does that make sense H so you're saying when you notice
that you're again when you notice that you're not allowing is that right then
you're then you tell yourself no when I notice that I am allowing but then I want like he was saying to make it go
away okay I'm allowing it but that's enough and number one like because now I'm feeling sorry for myself or I'm you
know this is not helpful right but it is because the pity party is the part of
the not allowing the allowing does that make any
sense we on the surface it looks like a We're Alone we're trying to convince our
elves that we're allowing but we're not really think this is what he was
pointing to we start to notice actually we're not not allowing and that's what that's the
present moment experience not allowing so I got I didn't quite
understand the pity party part please no I was gon to try to do an
alliteration but I can't on the spot here
like you could get stuck there without allowing that it's not allowing though
oh I'm sorry so allowing the non- allowing so if I am allowing all this
emotion and and I don't have the pity party part
right it feels as if I'm oh wo is me
I don't know how to explain that oh so maybe the sense if we're going to allow like just something that's very
uncomfortable to uncomfortable emotion maybe there's a feeling like this is too
much uh I'm just going to make this up too much sadness or grief or anger or whatever like this here's the thing
things like this if we are just allowing they arise and pass
away but they come back do they they don't come back exactly the
same they come back a little bit different you are a little bit different because now you have a little bit more
confidence cuz you you've seen that happen and it's never exactly the same
it's just the mind that's telling you like no don't go there you know you've been there before but it turns out it's
the way forward it's absolutely 100% The Way Forward things unfold on their own they
want to it's only when we're tangled up with them that they and we slap a label
on them that they seem like that they're the same but I'm not saying this is easy
and I'm not saying this is fast that you just do it once and then you know these emotional difficulties go away I am
saying this is a way for transformation absolutely thank you you're
welcome oh we're a little bit after time thank you
I wish you all a good rest of the evening thank you