good morning everyone welcome so glad to be here with you so I'm uh coming up today from Santa
Cruz where I now live I moved there in the fall to IRC in sight retreat center
and it's interesting moving back uh because I actually grew up there as a little kid uh so I was I lived there
until I was about 10 so most of my childhood memories are there and it's been really fun kind of read exploring
that landscape and um different memories coming up uh one of which uh is about
the Santa Cruz boardwalk um I hear knowing laughter um
yes it's great for those that don't know it's this great uh old amusement park
right on the beach and it has this like really rickety old wooden roller coaster
ancient roller coaster and I used to go with my to uh to the boardwalk with my
my little best friend Binky and um and we kind of like worked our way up to uh
the roller coaster you know started with the smaller rides and over the years uh made our way to the roller coaster and
um uh like many roller coasters there's like at kind of the the Pinnacle of the
roller coaster there's a a photograph that's taken and um there's just yeah
something uh really stuck with me one of the times we you know made it on the roller coaster uh one of these photos uh
the way it came out in it one of us was like gripping the safety bar for dear
life like hunkered down with this expression of total Terror uh and the
other one had their hands in the air just like total
Glee um and it struck me there's just something interesting to me about that
because here it is one ride two very different ways to ride
it so uh we could say that our life is a little like a roller coaster you highs
and lows ups and downs uh and typically we cling to each
state you know pleasure pain gain loss praise and blame we get really happy and
excited when the pleasant things come we get upset when the UN unpleasant things
come so this is this is how we typically do it and it can become a really rough
roller coaster uh when we get thrown out thrown around by all of those highs and
lows and so here here we have this one life and we can cling to the safety bar
totally freaked out uh for the whole roller coaster uh or uh we can learn to
let go put our hands in the air and enjoy the ride and of course you know
ultimately we want to be here for the whole ride I used to have a teacher who would say can you be here for the whole
ride um because a lot of times it feels like we you know we don't we want to we're we're on the ride to get to the
end of the ride like when when's this ride going to be over like I want the safe Dismount but that's not how we want to
live our lives we're not we're we're not living to get to the end of the ride
um yeah we want to learn how to be here for the full full spectrum of Human
Experience so um so this morning uh I want to talk about how to
how to be on the roller coaster without feeling like you're always on a roller
coaster or in other words uh how can we be with the vicissitudes of Life uh the
ups and the Downs um without Feeling unmowed by
them so in other words uh this morning I'll be talking about
equinity this um this great balancing factor of
equinity and as you probably know in Buddhism there's lots and lots of
lists and uh and equinity appears all over the place so it's uh it's the
Capstone of the seven factors of Awakening uh it's in the uh the paramitas it's in
the Brahma the it's the last of the Brahma viharas so clearly an important
teaching and uh the Buddha said that the mind of e equinity is um abundant
exalted immeasurable without hostility and without ill will It's A Beautiful
Mind um what is it exactly um this isn't a
word that's used a lot in modern parland and we don't hear that term if if you're
in Buddhist circles you start hearing that term more but so what is it so the
word equinity it comes from um uh the Latin Aquis
equal and animous mind so equal mind so it's pointing to this uh this the quanus
mind is is balanced it's stable it's unshakable so sometimes equinity is
compared to a m being Mountain like so a mountain a mountain doesn't care whether
it gets rained on or if it gets beaten with snow uh and it's impartial about
whether it's um gloomy weather or whether the Sun's shining brightly it's
stable it's steady just
receiving so we can actually be like that mountain and it's actually like a
pretty extraordinary possibility that it's it's possible in this life to be
imperturbable that we can um that nothing can destabilize the
mind because we typically think that we need to have pleasant experiences uh to
be happy and avoid unpleasant experiences like that's kind of the name of the game um but that actually like a
more reliable a deeper happiness is available um that that's um unaffected
by um uh the changing flavors of pleasant and
unpleasant and to to be clear um I had somebody ask me like wait so so with
equinity are we just like kind of flatlining like turning ourselves into
like an emotion emotionless being and I was like no the goal is not to become a
zombie like that's not that's not actually we're going here uh going for here so yeah equinity it's not cold it's
not indifferent uh that's um like on the contrary it actually equinity provides
the non-reactive foundation for compassionate action so it's um so that
it has heart eonity has heart uh there there's a line by TS Elliot that I think
describes this well he said teach me to care and not to
care teach me to care and not to care so often when we when we deeply care about
something or someone we can get really uh upset and know uh riled up uh in
relation to that thing or that person you know if anything goes ay for example
um and indifference you know that's you know when we just don't care at all so equinity it lives somewhere in the
center of this uh teach me to care and not to care uh you it's possible to
care care very deeply but not in a way that makes us lose our
balance so now there are there are two classic manifestations of of equinity
that I'd like to unpack for you today and this is because the single English
word equinity is actually translating to separate poly wordss in the Buddhist
sutas so um which is interesting because we would never know because it just gets
translated as this what one word um uh but the two words are
UPA and then uh the second is tatra uh tatra majat I just learned a new
pronunciation of it tatra majat so um so the most frequent of the
two that's used in the sutas is UPA so I'll start there so that's what we see like in the Brahma vhar is UPA
translated as equ equinity so uh UPA it means uh maybe if it were like even more
directly translated than equinity it means uh to look
over so when when I think of that to look over I think of like a bird's eye
view so if there's if there's a wildfire uh it's different to be caught
inside the wildfire then it is looking over the Wildfire from above right that
has that's like a palpably different experience so you know with bird's eye view to look
over so in practice to look over our experience um is to be mindful of it
it's to observe it um and when we do this we become less entangled in it uh
we get less caught in it uh so to look over to observe our
experience and when we do this uh when we do this it can give us a feeling of
space and space is a very liberating thing spaciousness can provide a lot of
equinity and when I was first learning about this I was like what like what's so special about space like how does
that actually help uh so maybe an analogy for
you uh so you could probably imagine imagine what it would be like to be uh
to be trapped in a swimming pool with a great white
shark pretty scary uh but let's say we take you and
we take that great white shark and we put both of you into the vast
ocean then what's that like a lot more relaxed yeah so this
isn't hypothetic like most humans are willing to get into the ocean and there are actually
billions of sharks in there um so like uh like practically speaking that space
really makes a difference you know that space really really makes a difference
so uh so equinity it allows us to be um to be with the sharks that are in our
own Hearts um in a way where we're not reactive so we can have we can have a
shark in our mind um and feel about it as though as though we're with that
shark in the vast ocean like there's space there's space inside there's a
safety and the ease that that space
provides uh so I can remember I can remember times in my own practice when I
was plagued by like a painful cell self story or like there was a very difficult
life circumstance taking place um and it was a little bit like living in a shark
tank I was really uncomfortable with those when those thoughts would get uh get
churning um and then I'd go on Retreat uh and I'd sit a whole bunch of
meditation and um not always uh but sometimes the mind uh would settle and
become still and something would happen uh that thought uh would lose its power
over me equinity would grow in the mind and heart
um and that story it might it might float through the mind but the mind
would be completely unmoved by it like it had the the ease of being in an ocean
like in a great ocean and um and the shark became irrelevant you know that uh
it was like being in a pool with a a tiny toy shark um so equinity has this capacity to
shift our relationship to what moves through us to um to what we suffer with
such that we have that same ease um and when uh you know with this
practice when we relax the thinking mind we release the thoughts um the mental
pattern of craving and clinging actually diminishes and with it the contraction in the mind and heart so craving and
clinging or you know felt as a contraction in the body um so when that
relaxes the Mind heart relaxes the body re relaxes and we actually have a felt
experience of more space so uh uh to be clear um you when
talking about bird's eye view and this this sort of spaciousness I want to be really clear that we don't cultivate
equinity by distancing ourselves from objects like that's that's not how we
get to the equinity or experience it um on the contrary uh we cultivate equinity
through intimacy not through distancing through being intimate with our experience intimate with the objects of
our life um so that we're really present with them remember UPA to look over you
know to observe so we're observing our experience uh staying with what's
happening being with our experience um and it's through that process that
that sense of spaciousness can arise like sometimes you might have just had the experience of just relaxing and
feeling like there's just more space so it doesn't have to take much but but um
but it's through being close that that becomes available not through you know pushing away our
experience so returning to the meaning of UPA looking over uh another image
comes to mind uh and that's of of a grandmother sitting in her rocking chair
looking over her grandchildren and um the the the
grandmother is sitting there and watching her grandkids maybe and having
uh their squabbles and uh sometimes having great times sometimes crying
having hard times but the grandmother just watched is it all you know unaffected by the childish
dramas loving um but unswayed and so uh in Zen the equanimous
mind is sometimes referred to as grandmotherly mind or parental
mind uh so um if I find myself kind of Tangled Up in something um sometimes
just bringing in the energy of a grandparent um you know I think it's
Temple Smith who says they there sweetheart Mama's
here Mama's here it's okay so just bring that that sweetness you know and and
something that I love about this term um parental mind or grandmotherly mind and that that attitude is it brings together
uh equinity um with meta like it has it has the spaciousness and ease of
equinity but with the the warmth of love and kindness okay so that's
UPA um let's move to that second word that I shared the second uh way that a
word that gets translated as equinity tatra maata um so if we were to to trans
translate that more exactly um it might be something like standing in the middle
of all this or I think biku bod translates it as um in the
middleness um so right in the middle of our crazy chaotic lives um can we be
upright can we stay standing not be knocked over so that's that's the energy
that this this word is pointing to balanced staying balanced even in the
midst of the chaos or the difficulty so you might have heard of um
there's these little dolls called DaRuMa dolls they're common in
Japan and um they have a little weight in the bottom and I think the rest of it is hollow and if you push it it'll kind
of sway over and pop come right back up so it'll sway over if you hit it pop
right back up um so you can't knock them over um and uh this flavor of equinity
is a little like that you know something might try to to knock you over but you come right back uh to
balance and uh something that I love about DaRuMa dolls uh is that they're uh
like um the inspiration for them uh is uh Bodhi Dharma the uh supposed you know
first ancestor that brought Buddhism to China and so the Japanese name for Bodhi
Dharma is Bod DaRuMa so that's d dolls um and so how fitting that this
little toy that can't be knocked over is is named after a Zen master you know a
great Buddhist teacher um so we're cultivating cultivating the mind and heart that can't be knocked
over so another way we can think of this quality uh it's like standing at the edge of the ocean at the wave break and
a huge wave could come over but knock not knock us down so you're getting a
sense of just you know this uprightness not being able to be
destabilized and you might have you know you can recognize this experience you might have had a a day at some point in
your life where you were just like in a great mood like there was a sense of of like such well-being and something
difficult Could Happen something unfortunate and it just like nothing can ruin this mood like I just like like no
problem and there's just sense of equipoise a sense of um
um uh resiliency so one teaching that can uh
can support us in contacting uh equinity in daily life is a teaching by uh the
Tha Force Master aan Sumo and the teaching
is it's like this
sadness is like this Joy is like
this resentment is like this oh resentment is like this
okay so just meeting everything as it comes and as it
goes no preference really
simple uh I was on a retreat a long time ago um and I was I think I I think I was
ruminating about uh uh I wanted like a change in my job I think I wanted a
promotion or something like that and um all of this wanting mind wanting
mind and um at some point the mind went
oh desires like this and then a little later oh gosh
I've been thinking thinking about this so long like when am I going to get over this like can I finally put this
down oh a verion is like
this oh wow gosh it feels so it it's so settling to be able to see the clar uh
see what's happening in the mind with such Clarity you know to be able to see desire and aversion I feel so
relaxed oh Tranquility is like this so just seeing what's happening in
the mind and meeting it with that that gentle curiosity oh it's like
this ad John Sumo went on to say be the knower of objects not the
owner of objects so typically whatever we experience we identify with it um you
I like it I don't like it I want it I don't want it um so instead of
uh needing to own it to take it as self can we simply know it so rather than
needing to be the sad one just know sadness is
occurring sadness is like this so this uh this act of Simply
knowing uh standing in the middle of all this t ra
Maj so those are the the two words um
and now i' want I want to Pivot a bit to talk a little bit about how equinity functions like how does this actually
work um so to understand how equinity can free us from suffering uh it can be
helpful to start by explaining uh how we get ourselves stuck with suffering to
begin with and this it's kind of an important thing right like we're all suffering in some
way or another and like how does that happen um and typically it seems like
well there's you know Myriad things that cause suffering in the world um but what's so extraordinary about the
Buddhist teaching is that he distilled all of the forms of suffering down to
one single Source it's like wow that's a that's pretty brilliant right
um uh so he boiled it all down to craving tanha craving so it's this and
of course the other side of the coin of craving is aversion so wanting and not wanting desire and rejection this uh
force of of uh grasping hold of and pushing away our
experience and this is of course the second Noble Truth the source of suffering is tanha ah
craving thirst um so this craving or
aversion comes into being because we experience something pleasant or
unpleasant so on a very basic level something pleasant happens at once one of our sense doors you know we see
something pleasant we hear something pleasant we feel something with the body that's unpleasant and then the the
Baseline reaction to that is to if it's unpleasant reject it you know try to get
rid of it or if it's Pleasant try to get more of it it's a very it's a very simple mechanism um so you know this
like uh this food is incredible I've got to eat more of it oh this house is so
beautiful I want to buy it um this idea is so exciting I got to make it happen
or on the flip ah this person is so annoying like I got to get away from him
or like that squeaky door is so obnoxious I need to make it stop or that
sight sound smell taste is so um
uncomfortable I need to get rid of it so it's happening in our life all day long
every day this this mechanism and often if it's minor we don't really notice it
and more often than not even if it's major we're so fixated on the object the
thing that we don't like the squeaky door or the delicious meal that we don't see the mechanism of wanting and not
wanting that's happening in between that's actually running the whole show
um so what's what's fascinating here is that this whole this whole shebang
starts with that Simplicity of just Pleasant and unpleasant right it's so
simple so in your own life if there's some form of suffering you might just
check is there wanting and not wanting or not wanting here and like beneath
that is is there just something that's Pleasant or unpleasant like very very
simple so what's um what's extraordinary is that it's actually
possible to experience Pleasant and unpleasant without reactivity without
that extra layer of then grasping of of desire and pushing away
aversion so so this is where equinity comes in when there's equinity in the
mind we can meet extremely painful experiences so unpleasant extremely
unpleasant experiences without reactivity um without
aversion um without pushing it away so um so I have a a chronic pain condition
and I have spent plenty of time suffering over it uh on meditation Retreats and in daily
life um uh but what I found over time through sitting in enough Retreats and
allowing the mind to settle um it became really clear that at
its most basic level um the pain was just unpleasant um sometimes very very
unpleasant but simply put just unpleasant um the not wanting was extra so all of
the like wishing it wasn't there when will this go away how can I get rid of this what am I going to do and all of
the the stories that can proliferate out uh and create a story about I'm somebody who's sick or you have a chronic health
issue or any stories that could come out of that just distill down just
unpleasant and so uh uh when the when equinity was welldeveloped in the mind
um the pain was just like that toy shark right it there it just had no no sway
over the mind um and the mind didn't have any preference uh for anything else
over the pain so there could be a soft Breeze or a bird chirping outside and um
the the mind was received them all as um
uh as equal visitors uh and so to be able to to know
that it's possible for the mind to decouple the feeling tone the pleasant
unpleasant um from the reactivity from the wanting and not wanting creates a
tremendous amount of Freedom like it's really powerful to be able to know that you have that capacity because all of
the suffering comes from that extra layer of reactivity the wanting and not wanting um so if you can just in daily
life if you can just be in contact with the feeling tone the pleasant or not unpleasant you
that's a it's a big Spectrum right very unpleasant to kind of unpleasant kind of neutral kind of somewhere in between
neither Pleasant or unpleasant kind of pleasant to like you know the most Pleasant thing a human could experience
right so it's a it's a vast range and it can be fascinating to just explore that and get to know it and rest
there so there's a a common teaching pain is inevitable but suffering is is
optional so you can see how this teaching really makes sense in light of
what I've been sharing that there can be pain but the suffering is extra and
that's that's that that uh Second Step of
reactivity so you can you can see from this how how it's actually it's possible
to ride the roller coaster without feeling like you're always on a roller
coaster it's possible to experience the highs and the lows uh without being
unmowed by them without being knocked over by them because you can stay close to like oh this is Pleasant oh this is
unpleasant that's okay no pushing away no rejecting uh no grasping hold
of uh so here's a uh a poem from the uh terata which is the the early Buddhist
nuns if your mind becomes firm like a rock
and no longer shakes in a world where everything is
shaking your mind will be your greatest friend and suffering will not come your
way so how do we cultivate a mind that no longer shakes like how how do we actually
cultivate equinity [Applause] uh so there are many supports um many
different ways to cultivate equinity um including the the three-fold training of
uh Sila Samari and pa uh ethics or um ethical Behavior Sila
Samari sometimes translated as concentration this um uh Act of
collecting and Gathering the Mind unifying the mind and then PA
wisdom so if this sounds familiar if you're familiar with oh yeah Samar I've
heard that um that's the training of the eight-fold path the the eight path factors are can be broken up into Sila
Samar and Pa um so so how does this develop equinity how does how does that work um
so starting with CA um uh unethical actions like killing and stealing and
lying um uh not only only do they create a lot of external harm and Dua suffering
um but they they cause a lot of um inner turmoil as well of course um and a mind
that's engaging in harmful activity uh it's going to be riddled by uh guilt and
shame and a lot of difficulty so if you take that mind um and and try to have it
meditate it's going to have a really difficult time settling down
so um for so for those who are living a virtuous life who are following the
precepts who are living ethically um it's easier for the mind to
settle um and of course there's many other benefits to living an ethical life
but that's that's one important aspect so Sila uh virtue ethical Behavior Support
Samar concentration this collecting and unifying of the mind so um so there's
two two ways I mean there's more than two ways but two ways that I'll mention uh that Som develops equinity so it's
starting with Insight the first the second first is Insight second is seclusion so for insight um when the
mind is steady uh it can see clearly into the true nature of
things uh so it can see the mind can have when when there's concentration
present uh the mind can see clearly that all things are impermanent it can see clearly um the
way suffering truly forms that the source of suffering is grasping uh it can see clearly the
selfless nature of phenomena so it can see into these truths
um some some teachers use the analogy of a a telescope for this so if you want to
see the stars um you can try holding a telescope and trying to see the stars
but chances are you're not going to be able to see them very well because of course um the hands aren't so still
right um but if we get a tripod and put the telescope on the the
triod then we can see the stars so somat is a little bit like the tripod allowing
the mind to collect and settle and become concentrated um it it serves the
same function of the tripod the mind can become very still and when it's still it can see the
true nature of things it can see the truth of um anicha Dua anata you know of
uh uh impermanent suffering not self in the same way that a a telescope on a
tripod can see the stars so uh so if we want to see the stars in our own
practice uh we need uh to engage in this process of settling the
mind uh so when there's in Insight uh when we can see the stars
when there's Insight uh there's wisdom PA so that's just one way that Sila
Samar and Pa can unfold into a mind um that that can be equanimous because a
mind um a mind that sees everything is impermanent is less likely to be
reactive because it knows Everything Changes a mind that can has insight into suffering um it's lessly like less
likely to grab hold of experience um because it knows that that's that's Dua
that's suffering a mind that sees the selfless nature of things um it doesn't
have a reason to cling who is it clinging for so in these ways um the mind is uh
can meet experience it can meet Pleasant and unpleasant but not be swayed by
them so this is one one unfolding of uh equinity in practice
um but uh but Li liberating Insight is not the only way that equinity can come
forth in practice um you know just the well-being of an ethical life um Can in
itself support equinity I just even remembering that equinity is a possibility in in daily life any given
moment can be enough to just invite that that quality in oh and I had mentioned that you know
Som there's you know two different um ways that equinity can come forth uh
through S and I had shared through Insight the second being seclusion um so
in the seven factors of Awakening seventh factor is equinity the sixth factor is concentration so there's a
reason right because the concentration supports the equinity uh so this is from Joseph
Goldstein equinity arises out of concentration because concentration has
the power to keep the Mind secluded from the hindrances this seclusion then allows
for balance and neutrality to be established and the mind to be unmoving
in the face of Pleasure and Pain so
uh concentration secludes the Mind from the hindrances from the wanting the not wanting uh the restlessness the doubt
all of the stuff of the mind so it's secluded and that allows for that neutrality and well-being such that the
mind doesn't get swayed so there's a way that it's secluded so an analogy for this um you
know imagine a little seed that's uh constantly being blown
around by the wind um if that's the case it's it's never
still enough to take root but if it's if it's allowed to be still for long enough uh that little
seed will take root and then even when great winds come it won't be blown
away so in the same way when you sit when you're still and
you commit yourself to being still allowing the mind to settle uh you're a
little like that seed that seed that's landed in one place long enough for its
roots to grow and so your roots can grow deep and
even when the worldly winds are blowing of uh uh Pleasure and Pain gain and loss
praise and blame um you're unmovable you're stable balanced un
shakable maybe like a great redwood tree in a storm right uh and so you can you can
stand upright in the middle of all this in the
middleness and still be free so that's the capacity of this
practice rooted and free so let's sit for a minute
together if your mind becomes firm like a rock
and no longer shakes in a world where everything is
shaking your mind will be your greatest friend and suffering won't come your
way [Music]
thank you very
much so we probably have time
for one question or comment
reflection if there is one Hillary
did you have your holding tight on
the what do you
think yeah other times I'm this
one yeah that was a quick one there's time
for another
question I especially appreciated the two different translations back from
Equanimity both in the midst and and the bird's eye
view thank you yeah isn't that interesting yeah thanks Martha I think there's one over
here is this you hold it like
a um so I was wondering if equinity could be like almost on a spectrum like
I'm thinking for like severe grief or like hard moments if there's like a touching into
it for a few moments or like I don't know it feels like at
times like I search for equinity or like I'm allowing for it in
concentration um and it's like I can touch it but like not be there very long
yeah yeah absolutely I think that's that's an astute observation that um um uh equinity can
come in and out of experience so it's not like some it you know you might um you might be able to touch it for a
moment and like have a moment where you feel just a little ease and then another wave of grief or another wave of anger
and then you know where it's kind of titrated um so that's one way equinity
is experienced on the flip sometimes equinity can be quite stable but often
that takes like retreat practice um and you know not that that even happens all
the time on Retreat um and then there's also a spectrum of um of intensity of
equinity where it can be like more light like um like just a little equinity like
I'm not quite as upset as I would normally be about X I'm still upset but I'm not as
upset um and then you know on the other end of the spectrum where there's you
know that that real sense of equipoise and Stillness and you know completely un
unable to be swayed so yeah they can come forth in many ways yeah thanks okay
I think I think that's it for this morning um thank you so much for your
kind attention and for your practice it was a pleasure to be here with you take care
folks