so good morning welcome and can you hear me okay
great so welcome to IMC and also to the Buddha's birthday celebration that we're
having today it's the
uh this the terad and Buddhist tradition we're in tends to do things
simply and so they just roll all the special days of the Buddha's life into
the same day so it's celebrating the Buddha's birth the Buddha's Enlightenment and
then Buddha's passing away each of them that are classically or traditionally depicted as
peaceful events uh his birth was depicted very peacefully the mother standing under a
tree holding a branch and uh the Buddha was born
peacefully and immediately took seven steps he began his walking meditation
right away and uh his Enlightenment of course was uh he was presented with lots of
challenges and uh and we're all presented with
challenges as we kind of Reach the the the greatest potential all of us have
have to be really discover a non-conflicting peace and he found that peace in his
Awakening and then his death is depicted as being very peaceful that he knew he was dying he knew his time was near he
laid himself down between two Sal trees beautiful trees in India and uh they say that out of season
the Sal trees uh burst into flowers and they they fell around him and all that
and he just he gave his last teachings to his uh people who were
there and he did a very respectful thing he said I'm about to die and do you have
any last questions you really want to ask this is your chance make sure that they were settled
and they said no we we have no questions and then um he went into deep meditation
and uh went through different kind of cycles of depth and meditation and and
at some point going through those Cycles um he passed away in a very peaceful
way so we celebrate the Buddha's birthday as a way of um you know
respecting the phenomenal thing this man discovered and um and I think of it I
think it was 1950s I forget to his name but it was said earlier than that that
it was impossible for human being to run uh a mile and less than a less than a
minute and then the 1950s there was someone who broke that limit and uh and
then after that um lots of people did because now was pum showed it was
possible the buddha showed it was possible to be free to let go in such a
deep profound way that we can experience a profound um goodness of our hearts
profound capacity for the heart to be at ease loving peaceful and uh and we don't have to
live in the grips of our inner conflicts our inner fears our inner ways in which
we carry the weight of burden of our society and of our family and of our
personal history it's possible to release the Yoke that we carry and to be
free and to do that in a way that we we Keeps Us deeply connected to this world
of ours the Buddha even though he was totally liberated um stayed for 45 years
deeply connected to a society of his time teaching and supporting and guiding and being a counselor for many many
people in their lives and so uh one of the first early
teachings I received about the Buddha statue I heard the story of of uh
someone asked Suzuki roshi the founder of San Francisco Zen Center why do we bow to the
Buddha and he said because then we're bowing to ourselves uh that somehow that act is
not meant to be submissive act towards some person who lived long long ago but really
honoring and respecting something in ourselves our potential our possibility are in a sense capacity for freedom and
peace our inner buddhahood that's waiting for us and uh and this idea that the Buddha
that for those now 2500 years later the Buddha represents or or maybe not doesn't
represent but is a kind of a mirror for us that when we look at the Buddha we
see ourselves is the idea and uh I can pretty confidently say that all the
depictions we have of the Buddha are someone's
fantasy we don't really know what he looked like and um and so um you know so
and as Buddhism goes through different cultures uh the Buddha kind of has the facial features of that culture and uh
the earliest Buddha images were made in uh the
Greek colonies kingdoms of Afghanistan and Pakistan the legacy of V the great
conquering that part of the world and so the earliest depiction some of the earliest ones uh the Buddhist images
look very Greek and then they were then they came with Indian pictures and Cambodian and
Chinese and you know on and on so I like to believe it's because
everyone sees themselves in a very profound way our potential our
capacity and um and I was recently in Japan some of the Shinto shrines on
their altar did not didn't didn't have images of any kind of being but had
mirrors and uh and when I asked why is a mirror there and they I said oh so you
can see yourself on the altar is that be
wonderful the some of the teachings of Buddhism and you know these um teachers
like me sometimes overdo certain teachings like let go let go just about letting go it's all about letting go
just let go and uh or sometimes if we go a little bit further we might say let go because
there's no self just like let go of the self let go of the self and um and maybe
there's something good about those teachings occasionally or at the right time there might be quite profound but
um but what gets lost in that is that the teachings of the Buddha much of
Buddhism has a profound respect for each individual each person is a valuable
human being and we have a certain dignity a certain dignity that can grow
into it nobility and uh and it isn't that we're supposed to kind of become Mr Nobody
it's a character from the 60s Mr Natural that uh you know just sits there and is
nobody but um but that um uh we're
letting go of all the things that diminishes our value all things that we we deprecate ourselves or diminish
ourselves or limit ourselves and one of the ways we do that of course is with conceit and um
thinking we're really special but we're not supposed to then feel like we're not special we are important we are valuable
so we'll see in a minute in a few minutes that the uh children are going to bring in the Pagoda where in which
the baby Buddha will be standing and that's usually the centerpiece of the ceremony
here and um and it's um and uh you if you go up and look
closely you see that the statue uh the standing Buddha and he has one finger
pointing to the sky and one finger pointing to the Earth and that's because
U you know after he did his seven steps for he was born and took seven steps
walking meditation or something uh and then he stopped and he pointed to to to the sky and point to the Earth and he
said because he was kind of Prodigy I guess he said um Heaven above Earth
Below I alone am the honored one now you know that sounds pretty
conceited and um but I think uh it's a it's kind of a myth you know he he it
didn't happen that way but uh but what it um represents I think and what I
teach the children is that each of us should be able to say that for ourselves and we each of us can
recognize that everyone else can say it for themselves as well so it isn't like holding ourselves above everybody else
but everyone is the most special one and so to see each other that way and see
ourselves that way and this Heaven above and Earth Below pointing to for me also points to
the way in which the Buddha as a bridge not the Buddha but our practice puts us
as a bridge between these uh variety of or middle way between a variety of
different places we can go we can be deeply embodied grounded here and we can
soar in vast uh ethereal kind of dimensions of
the Mind in meditation and uh and if you choose one or the other you're in trouble
but uh our practice our mindfulness is the bridge is the connection where we can be in both standing there present
Within These different dimensions of who we are our deep kind of way in which
meditation takes us into this very personal world but also takes us into a
phenomenal connection to the people around us and the mindfulness is that bridge that can do both and hold both
and find the middle way between them all so I think it there ways of interpreting
this idea of pointing to the sky pointing to the Earth pointing to and saying I alone am the most honored one
that it's saying something profound about each of us and so the idea is to see ourselves in this the statue here is um but what's
what we have we have here is here right now is on the top is the Buddha in the
in the moment in his Enlightenment time of his Enlightenment the on the laying down is actually he's not sleeping he's
dying it's a statue of his last days and the children will bring in the baby Buddha and the POA to put it here and
then uh on the wall is a tanka CH Tibetan painting of the historical
Buddha as he um renounces his royalty
renounces the life of privilege and wealth and power uh for something that's
even more wonderful better than that and he found in a life of radical Simplicity
that was not bolstered by wealth and power and and status and praise that
often comes with that kind of Royal life and uh so he's renouncing all that
and um and uh and the little footnote to that how I have that is that uh the S
when I got my wife and I were married at this at the San Francisco Zen Center at the green Gulch Gardens in the outdoor
was there some 40 some 30 some years ago and
um and that was the wedding gift from San Francisco Zen Center getting married and the gift was
the picture of the Buddha renouncing and so maybe that's also
presenting us with this bridge this kind of two sides and remember the two both sides are here both sides are
important and um so that's how I have it and um so the children were told that
story about the heaven above Earth Below story and I alone the world honored one
then they they they made this pagota that they're they carry in here in a couple of
minutes and um and we'll do a little bit of um
ritual this is the today is like high church at IMC and so we'll do a little a little
bit of we'll chant the refuges and uh those of you who don't know the refuges
uh just listen and take it in and and um I'll say that I'll I'll we'll do the
precepts in a certain kind of simple ways because the kids are here uh and then um and then at some point um and
there'll be some s some song that um that uh the kids will sing coming in and
then also that uh we'll do here as part of all this and then when it's over everyone's invited Ed to come up and um
wash the baby Buddha there's two ladles and he's sitting in a bowl with water and you come up and you wash him and and
um and then probably you should consider that you're really washing
yourself and what is it that you could wash away is anything unusual in you
that um some of us have some unusual things some Oddities that maybe would be
kind of nice to wash away let go of so that's kind of the
idea so so you might need to move a little
bit aside
[Music]
just kindness and compassion joy joy
joy
equinity loving kindness and
compassion joy joy joy
[Music] equinity equinity
love in kindness and
compassion Jo joy
[Music] joy
[Music] yeah yeah it goes right great thank you
for bringing the Buddha in and thank you so much and we have the ladles in there
too fantastic we have both of them there
great so so this is the baby Buddha has been brought in a certain symbolic way
he just got born and uh and these these wonderful families help bring him to birth and
every day we bring the Buddha to life if we practice and live with loving kindness and compassion and and
appreciative joy and equinity and uh thank you all for making
the pagot and bringing the Buddha to us and um the uh for the Buddha represents
some of the most uh beautiful things in a human heart and families have some of
that beauty when they love each other and uh I thought maybe I didn't ask her
to do it but you probably going do it without preparation the love mix a family song absolutely so this is a song
that was sung at the Spirit Rock Family Retreat for years and there was this
wonderfully dignified I love him Abbot a terad manast monk named aan
pasano originally from Canada and uh he's one of my most inspiring monks that
I know in his Simplicity and ordinariness and ordinariness and dedication to practice and presence and
that tradition that monastic tradition he's in they're supposed to carry themselves in a certain
decorum and they're not supposed to sing certainly not dance and do things
like that and so some of the things that happened in the family retreat was not quite what monastics
do but uh he would sit sometimes in the front of the hall and Betsy Rose would
sing these songs and she sang the song that um that uh Carla's about to sing
and he would sit there with complete upright dignity he looks like with tears
streaming down his eyes this cheek unselfconsciously just like letting
them so but's let's do it because uh the baby Buddha really represents the love
and the best qualities that we can have as as family as a human family
and you want to show the [Music]
oh I don't think I could do that yeah so that the yeah so the hand
signs mean that this means love love
makes a family a family it's like two little birds making an S together
so when we go to the chorus love makes a
familyc makes a family love makes a
family love makes a family love makes a family
I have a neighor who was born in Peru her parents aded
her each Joes through
[Music] their makes a
family love makes a family love makes a
family love makes a [Music]
family Street Generations 2 and grandar parents and a
little baby and their house is filled with [Music]
love makes a love makes a
family love makes a family love make a
[Music] family down the street
[Music] mommy CIA
mommy their family is Happ family is
and F
love love makes a family love makes
a love makes the family
love makes a [Music]
family this is the place we bring our families we GA to learn mindful
Harmony we sing and we play and we sit quietly and we share our family
love love me makes a family love makes a
family love makes a family love makes a
family makes a [Music]
family thank you yeah so that's just the kind of the anthem of the children
program here and Spirit Rock and and uh my kids went through that and and uh
when my son went off to college uh he went and found all of Betsy Rose's songs
to listen to in the dorms these songs so um so then uh we'll chant the
refuges and I think enough of you know it and if you don't it's just take it in
and this is a uh going for Refuge is um the the word in PO is to walk literally so one walks
uh to what's as a refuge what's as a support what is a protection what is an
inspiration here in the Dharma and the Buddha and the S and this is also meant to be found in yourself it's not like
something outside mystical that's supposed to do it for you but really something that is generated by our
practice and our own goodness that we all have that that's um we is mirrored by the Buddha
to us we have a amazing potential so um so we'll chant so
usually you don't have to put your hands together but that's the tradition and usually there's a citation
to the Buddha first so
[Music]
budas budas
Bud s s
[Music]
sang
[Music] s
so one of the ins for me inspiring
things I've heard some teachers say and directly and it's a common thing for
some teachers to say this so it's not new but is that someone come a student
someone is practitioner comes to the teacher and says I'm so grateful and uh I want to do something
for you what can I do for you and the teacher says practice
that's what you can do that's and so practice includes living an ethical life
and so what can you do for the Buddha if we feel grateful for what the Buddha did we can live an ethical life and it's not
just for the Buddha sake but there's a Buddha in you maybe waiting for you maybe you have a little taste and hints
of it at times and that's e and it's an ethical place it's an ethical quality of
what what's deep inside or most integral in who we are so in the sense when we do the precepts it's um it's to
celebrate uh this possibility or this potential this truth about who we are
that's there either we know it or it's waiting for us so um so uh I will uh
lead this chant and so I'll do it in two parts for each one and and you can
repeat after me if you'd like and uh but it has a little bit more value of what
we're doing here today than it just doing it for yourself there's children in our midsts and what a great thing for
children to hear grown-ups have this kind of inspiration to live by the
precepts this is pretty good so
um for the sake of our lives together for the sake our Liv
together I commit to not harm I commit to not
harming for the sake of our life together for the sake of our life
together I commit to not stealing I commit to not stealing for the sake of
our life together for the sake of our lives together I commit to respecting
the body and hearts of others I to Respec the and hearts of others for
the sake of our life together for the sake of our life together I commit not
to lie I commit not to lie for the sake of our life together for the S of our
life together I commit to not intoxicating myself so I'm
crazy myself
so now uh we have uh car so Carla's going to teach us one song the other
brara song and then once we get the hang of it the song then uh the family the
families who are here can come up and now is the time to wash the baby Buddha
you take you yeah you take the I'll tell you when to start and you take that
those two spoons take one of them so two people can do it at the same time come on either side and then you pour it over
the Buddha three times and it and that's a way of that's a way of cleaning your
heart and uh so um so so we'll learn the song and once we've learned it and keep
doing it then we can have people come up I'm not sure if we're thinking of the same song well Hillary was when who told
me me the four Divine abod yeah got a lot of words well maybe doesn't work
then maybe you should you play it but I'm not sure I can teach it oh so maybe just sing it then and you want you want
to have this on uh I don't know did you guys hear the singing
clearly oh did you guys hear it online online online wouldn't hear it
I suppose yes you oh there we go I think we've got it covered
thank you I just have to be able to Che and look at the words yeah we have a microphone so maybe do it a maybe maybe
do it at least so so Carla maybe do a few few rounds of it but let tell me when your
when your first round is finished so is that okay first verse first verse
yeah sure because and after the after you've started the kids will start to come up okay so the first verse is the
house of loving kindness and the second verse starts with in the house of Truth and okay all
[Music] right in the house of loving
kindness I am glad to live How Sweet It Is to open up my heart
and let it give the windows are all open there's
nothing here to hide in the house of loving
kindness that I have inside okay okay you can
[Music] come in the house of true
compassion I am glad to be
knowing every living thing has feelings just like
me all the joys and Sorrows the anger and the
fears in the house of true compassion all are welcome here
[Music]
in the house of joy and happiness I'm glad to
dwell grateful for my blessings wishing you the same as
well the world is full of riches there's enough for you and
me in the house of love and happiness
I'm glad to [Music]
be in the house of balance I am glad to spend my
time coming home from stormy days that shake my heart and
mind I can swing so high and low but
somewhere in between in the house of
balance it is peaceful and
Serene in these four Divine abodes that
live inside of me there I go for Refuge to be happy to
be free it only takes a little
breath a little change of mind to take me to the sweeter boats
where peace and joy are mine just a little breath to change my
heart and mind and take me to the sweet
boats where peace and joy are
[Music]
mine one very nice thank you thank you so
because we're Meditation Center did you guys ever do any meditation in the in
the family program every month so we're going to do a meditation for three
breaths who knows how to count to three yeah some of you
do okay so we're gonna so so you this is a so when you close your eyes close your
eyes and then count for three breaths and then when you do the after the third
breath then do that you know that waving of the fingers again ex ready let's
start close your eyes and three breaths
[Music]
great thank you everyone so thank you for making the pagod
because now the pagota is going to be avail ailable to the people here to come and wash the baby Buddha too so any of
you who would like to do it in in a minute or so you can come up and do that and um now that the kids have showed you
how it's done and um and uh so thank you for
being here and may you find the Buddha in your own
heart thank you