so hello everyone and
welcome and um I was just looking out the window we
have these very high Windows here looking up at the sky Through the Windows and the clouds that are here
and and um
um if the begins to rain
then first there has to be the clouds the clouds are the condition for the
rain and the idea of conditionality that things appear because of other
conditions that have to be there is a central feature in Buddhism that's uh
one of the purposes of which is to help us break through
the the U Break Out of the delusion of permanence that something is there
forever it's and the delusion of self that many of us will live under and the
particular delusion of self is the idea that there is a permanent self that anything defines Us in an permanent
way and uh and there's a movement in the mind of attachment M that is very
closely connected to the ideas of self ideas of permanent selves this is who I
am and the idea is that uh something is fixed and so in meditation practice one
of the ways that the teachings on conditionality can function can support
meditation is that when you're aware of something occur ing in the present
moment whatever it is that experience is a conditioned
experience certain conditions have come together to bring forth this particular
thing and but now that you're aware of it now that you really see it and know
what it is that's happening you've introduced a new condition into the ecosystem into the
into the moment and the idea now is
to uh um trust that that's enough for your part of the for your
contributions to causes and conditions a clear awareness you not try to fix anything
you don't have to think about it don't have to um analyze it and you don't have
to uh use what's happening as a basis for judging yourself all you do is recognize oh it's
things are here for now for causes and conditions maybe it's obvious to see
what the conditions were and um and uh maybe you know your
mind wandered off and that's a condition that when you see that that uh you
criticize yourself that I'm not a good meditator because my mind wandered off that's a delusion of self that's
operating there making a def defining oneself by that as opposed to just recognizing clearly this is the mind
that wanders off to say I'm a lousy
meditator that's a condition for feeling lousy and we feel that lousiness we see
oh that's a rose because I had this belief and each steps alongs the way
what we take refuge in in mindful practice in meditation is Simply Having
the clarity that things arise because of conditions we don't have to take own
them we don't have to Define ourselves by them we don't have to see them as
it's going to be this way forever it's just the conditions of this moment and now I contribute a new
condition and the condition is uh uh uh
being aware of what here and if it's obvious that it's you can see the
conditionality then you can you can Rec that helps the clarity oh this is here because of these conditions but not
because you're analyzing or thinking about it just oh it's here because of conditions and the the goal is to find
Clarity in The Knowing uh Clarity crispness
crispness um openness spaciousness um to just know this is how
it is right now and uh and in knowing in doing that
we you are contributing a new condition nothing stays the same no
conditions stay the same when they're observed that's kind
of the the premise here and maybe if you look at a chair the chair doesn't change
but if you look at a chair and just look at it you change
what we're aware of as we're meditating of ourselves changes because we're aware and don't try to make the change
just be aware and then notice what the how the conditions
change and the conditions are always changing and every changing condition
every condition is an opportunity for further Clarity clear
awareness that's what we contribute so to
begin to recognize the
conditions of what has contributed to how your body feels right
now how does your posture contribute to how your body feels right
now and at the before we start
meditating adjusting your posture is
contributing the proper or better conditions of of the B for the body to
participate in the meditation the body participating in the
meditation the body is just not an appendage that you kind of have to kind of make comfortable enough so you can
meditate the body is here to be part of the meditation and a
posture of
participation and to gently close your
eyes and to invite the body into the meditation to be part of it
taking a few long slow deep
breaths relaxing as you exhale
letting your breathing return to
normal and given the what's happened just so far in
meditation those are the conditions for how you some of what you
feel right now maybe some has shifted
changed and to if that's the case to be aware of it in a simple clear
way and a way of being aware and being clearly aware that
something like giving room space for each thing we're aware of to
be as it
is letting your breathing breath breathe
normally and if you're aware of your breathing in your body
the breathing now is participating in your
meditation as you exhale relaxing
more exhaling and maybe relaxing the thinking mind
maybe relaxing the belly and so the weight of your torso settles a
bit into your sitting
bones e
and then continuing with your meditation on your own in the
silence and from time to time when something new
arises recognize it as arising occurring because of
conditions that's all
and rely on simple awareness of what's
Happening contributing a new
condition contributing being
aware and the more clear the aware awareness is without changing anything
intentionally the more it contributes to a new way of
being it's a condition for what's going to happen
next
e
for
for for
when clear relaxed awareness fills the field of awareness
the field of attention thinking is no longer at the
center
clear awareness a Clarity of [Music]
knowing is not nothing it's one of the most
significant acts
conditions we contribute to this moment and the next
moment
for
e
for e
for
e
for e
and now as we come to the end of this
sitting how do you feel how are you
have the conditions of this meditation somehow contributed to you being different now
than you were at the beginning of the
sitting what might have the conditions
been that contributed to how you are now
and was one of those conditions your practice of
mindfulness of clear awareness clear knowing of the present
moment how was that a condition
and may it be that what we we learn through meditation what we learn about being
aware translates to how we live the world in the world of other
people that we learn to hear listen to
people with clear listening we learn to see others with clear
seeing there's a little saying that says that adults need to be
heard children need to be
seen may it be the practice we do helps us to contribute
a positive conditions to This World by listening and
seeing Others May all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be free
and may the way that each of us listen the way that each and one sees
others be done in safety and peace and
fr offering others to be free of our attachments
[Music]
thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this second talk u based on the upai
suta and um I'll read you that suta again so this is a suta where the
Buddha um talks about what should be established what qualities or Char
characteristics should be established in someone who wants to teach the Dharma so
you know last week last two weeks I talked about the core teachings that I have and but as as important as the
teachings is how we teach and certainly I aspire to teach in
the way the Buddha encouraged us to be the how we teach so I'll read the five
again uh the Dharma should be taught to others thinking I will speak step by
step I will teach I will speak of a gradual
path the dhma should be taught to others thinking I will speak for practical
reasons the Dharma should be taught to others thinking I will speak grounded in
kindness the Dharma should be taught to others thinking I will not speak for material
rewards the Dharma should be taught to others thinking I will speak without wounding myself or
others and when I introduced these yesterday I said that these five care
qualities are equally valuable as as guidelines for how we speak with others
even if we're not teaching them and um so I'll talk about mostly the teaching
side of it but I'm hoping that those of you who are not going to be teaching that uh you consider these as invaluable
way ways of looking at your acts of speech how you speak and today I'm doing them a little
out of order but today coincidentally it's I'll talk about the second one for the second
talk uh the Dharma should be taught to others thinking I will speak for practical
reasons the some translators will translate this uh as a speak uh based on
causes and conditions explaining causes and conditions the um
uh the word that's being used here can also mean instructions and I like that because
rather than teaching people uh truths uh like abstract truths things to believe
in um the emphasis is always instructions of what we can do what we can
practice and now this goes along with what I talked about last week as the second Core teaching principle that I
have that uh that of no views uh not Rel ring on beliefs not
relying on dogmatic ideas and uh but rather relying
here relying on what's practical what we can do ourselves we can see the cause
and conditions uh um and so some people might say wait a minute we have to
believe in things and um and uh then so someone might come up
with the idea that in order to to get water out of the faucet we have to
believe that turning the the handle of the of the faucet the water will come out so this is pushing the this idea of
belief to an extreme um and uh but the um yes there's
a kind of belief but it's a belief that we can immediately see whether it works or not the proof is right there it's
practical the condition for the water coming out is turning on uh uh turning
the handle and so it's not uh exactly a belief uh maybe there's confidence that
it will work because the the whole plumbing system is in order and
um and uh so it's that kind of practical way like this you know that uh we
there's a cause and condition for water coming out uh there's a cause and condition for uh developing this
practice it's a cause and condition for our suffering and a cause and condition for the end of
suffering and um and uh so when we teach we're constantly using that as an
orientation that uh teach practically teach what's useful and um and teach the
cause and conditions so we can really see what's going on there's a wonderful teaching of the Buddha that's called the
preservation of the truth and this is where the Buddha says that um um if you
say something if you have a belief you should uh explain to people the basis
upon that belief so if you believe it because uh you have faith in something
so it's no what there's no uh proof there's no no seeing why this is the
case then you say I believe this because of Faith you don't say this is true you
say I believe this is true because I faith it is so if you say it that way you're preserving the truth because
you're saying you're stating this is my I I base this on faith and so people
know you're not making an absolute claim but you're making a claim for yourself and they
know the Assumption underneath that that people know the basis underneath it so they can be in conversation with you if
you just say something is true dogmatically or declaratively uh people don't know how
to find themselves they either have to believe it or not believe it or or you they can't participate in it in a in a
robust way but if um we preserve this Truth by saying it's based on faith he
goes on to say that if it's if we base it on what we've heard from our
teachers uh uh what I'm say what I believe is based on what's popularly
believed by the society around me I believe it because it's in my sacred books I believe it because um I uh uh I
um I thought about it logically and my logic or rationality led me to uh
believe what this is each of those cases when you say that to someone they can go
back and check with you uh the source of the belief is that Source a useful a
useful Source uh do they want to uh uh do they want to rely on that Source too
but if you just make a declarative statement which then becomes a view then it
um uh you the conversation can't people can't really participate or or you know
engage in a more realistic way to find out what's really going on here so this
idea of speaking based on reasons practical reasons and one of the great
questions uh is uh is asking yourself why do I want to say what I want to
say why do I want to do what I want to do and to take the time to ask ask that
question is uh not to ask metaphysical looking for metaphysical answers but
right now what what am I trying to accomplish what is the Practical re uh
the Practical reason for why I want to say what I want to say and um the first
time I kind of really clearly saw the value of asking myself that was
um uh just before I was going to give a Dharma talk many years ago an old friend
showed up and we had a little chat and I went into the meditation Hall to sit down meditate and give a talk so and I
and so just before um uh I went to sit down I just said to my old friend um you
know I haven't prepared for this talk today and um and because I sat down to
meditate right after saying that I said why did I say that and I realized the reason was I was trying to protect
myself from the my friend judging me in in case I gave a bad talk if I had asked my that myself the
question before i i g said what I said why why do I want to say that I didn't
prepare the talk today I would have seen the reason I did it and then I probably
would have done something different so understand the reasons the Practical
cause and effect relationship the conditions underlying what we do this is the alternative to having uh
beliefs having fixed views having dogmatic views having you know metaphysical views that Buddhism
emphasizes we don't have to have any uh we don't have to believe in anything we
don't uh see for ourselves the emphasis in the Dharma is
come and see for yourself it's a visible here and now and because of that you can
count on that the teachings really are meant to be uh practical be instructions
they're meant to be uh something that uh is reasoned out
there's reasons for how we say it and reasons means it's based on conditions
based on uh cause and effect based on how conditions influence how things
are and um so uh to in teaching the
Dharma uh I interpret this particular uh phrase I that says I speak for practical
reasons I interpret it as um as
um um as explaining the conditions for
why we're uh what we're teaching what are the what are the reasons what are the rationalities what is it can be how
can we see this for ourselves what's the basis for what we're saying and so what I just did now was a
little bit the case I said I'm going to interpret this text way and that's a
preserving the truth that's kind of I'm giving you the reason uh you know uh for
why you know the background for why I'm interpreting this way I'm saying it's an interpretation and I use this
interpretation and the reason for it is I would like the teachings I do to um uh
to um guide people away from fixed beliefs dogmatic beliefs declarative
statements to what they can know and experience for themselves and and verify
for themselves oh this is true I see that this works it's as true as turning
the handle on the faucet and the water comes out um and uh and it's that practical
that immediate uh what we can do so in the
meditation uh I don't want to just make a declare statement that some that can be made that mindfulness is always use
ful what I'd like to say is that um uh mindfulness is useful in many
circumstances and um and uh we can discover that by paying attention to the
effect that being mindful has on us that if we bring clear awareness to our
experience that's a condition that then changes the ecosystem of our experience what's going
on and if you really pay attention to uh what happens when you bring clear simple
relaxed attention um uh then you'll see that this is
useful and um and the place to look to to see where the evidence is is
primarily in yourself though sometimes clear awareness uh that translates into
listening carefully to others listen seeing them clearly does also change the
environment we're in the situations we're in somehow and so we can see that change other people relax other people
feel cared for other people uh feel understood feel respected and you see
that that changes a circumstance so um uh to cultivating clear
awareness is a condition that can have an effect
that is beneficial so that's uh speaking for
practical reasons that uh the reason to be mindful
is to benefit self and others and that's something that you can see for yourself as we learn to do this
practice and in fact we're supposed to see it for ourselves all the Dharma
everything in the Dharma I believe I believe based on how I read
the ancient texts everything in the Dharma should be verified the core Dharma of the Buddha
should be verified in our own experience through our own practice so um may that be for you and
may you see as you go through the day today um May you ask yourself the
question why do I want to say what I'm going to say now or why do I want to do
what I'm want to do now and see if that kind of brings forth a
better understanding of the conditions that uh influence uh your
life thank you