hello everyone and Welcome to our 7 am in
California the community and it's nice to be back
with you after being gone for two weeks teaching two Retreats back to
back and uh oops hang
on e
once again a little rusty and all the buttons that have to be pushed and
U so again uh welcome everyone to
our YouTube community and I'm delighted to be back to be sitting with all of
you and uh and something
very certainly kind of personal and and heartwarming to come down to IMC
here uh in the morning getting ready at home and coming down here and sitting
down here in my meditation posture to be with you to share the Dharma and
and to um participate with you in the
Dharma so um one of the for me remarkable
aspects of mindfulness awareness practice
is the time or the the the transition from awareness
practices mindfulness being being maybe we can call it simply
mindfulness simply awareness to having a clear
sense that uh mindfulness and love
are just about synonymous maybe not exactly in in all their Dimensions but they
can't be te's apart or I don't know maybe they can be teased apart but in doing this practice
I came to a point where they arose together almost as if they are the same
almost as if they coexist like maybe like right and left hands coming
together to bow or maybe like
um um
just comes to mind is petting a cat and feeling affection for the cat
and the petting and the affection the contact the awareness of the cat the participation with a cat is the
same so to sit with
love to sit with love as a reference point and there are many flavors of
Buddhist love and uh the word can be very vague just using it by
itself and one of the flavors is friendliness a basic good will a basic
attitude of meeting our experience meeting others with friendship or
goodwi well-wishing and to be able to meet
anyone we meet anyone at all with a very basic
the basic love of stepping towards
them with Good Will with a friendship a
friendliness it doesn't have to be that we like someone it doesn't have to be that we agree with them it doesn't have
to be that we have what normally would call love as a high
bar but we can have that joy we could have
the the miracle
of opening our Good Will Opening Our Hearts
Opening Our Eyes to gaze upon others
kindly to gaze upon them as if
of course we would look upon others with kindness because to not do
that we have discovered is to diminish
ourselves to not do that means something closes something tightens something
resists something uh is becomes Limited in
US there's a way in which the Buddha
emphasized Good Will can have an unlimited quality
characteristics no limitation that we feel within ourselves
nothing closes nothing resists nothing shuts
down and it's almost as if love and awareness arise together as a
default because the alternative is not
healthy so let's sit here to whatever degree you would like
whatever degree that works for you to whatever degree that you're
inspired to meet yourself with Good Will to meet your difficult emotions with
Good Will to meet your um physical challenges with a level of
Good Will that's good for your heart that's good for the world's
heart so to assume a meditation
posture and
to begin with a posture assuming a posture
that is an expression of good will for
yourself the longer you meditate the more you know how
to enter into a posture of
meditation that feels good that feels right
that feels healthy and beneficial for you and if you don't haven't found
that just the wish to find it can be an expression of Good
Will without expectation without expecting to find it right
away and then with that good will to gently softly not too
much taking some deeper
breaths maybe with [Music] appreciation for the oxygen you'll
breathe in the carbon dioxide that you breathe
out in breathing you're being cared for
even if breathing is difficult it is an expression of your
body caring for
you relaxing on the exhale
relaxing the whole body
settling into your meditation
spot letting your breathing return to normal
and whatever way you're breathing whatever the sensations of breathing you
have breathing has an influence on the body
has an influence on the mind the
heart breathing has an influence just beyond the
edges of where we feel
breathing let that emphasis
let the influence of
breathing be like the softest gentlest
wind or the most comfortable feeling of warmth
that spreads kindness through your
being that spreads the warmth tenderness softness
of Good Will through your being
and whatever your attention lands on whatever present moment
experience comes into
mindfulness Let It Be
received with kindness with good will
let this Soft Wind the soft
warmth of friendliness
welcome whatever there might
be
e
for
for e
at least for mindfulness for how you're
aware is soft warm
kind as if you're meeting a dear
friend so let your mindfulness meet whatever is happening
for you even what is
difficult
e
for
for for
e
e e
is there some way to relax
that allows you to be aware with a
kindness with a
warmth with a willingness to meet whatever there is
with good will even the absence of good
will
e for
and as we come to the end of this sitting
to open your awareness your
imagination to The Wider world around
you and to recall or think about the wider world of friends family Neighbors
strangers out across the world what it would be
like that whoever you
meet at least you meet them maybe
privately with a gaze of kindness
a gaze of wishing them well imagining
them well wishing them well in a healthy good
psychological emotional way that they would turn
around and be more friendly to the next person they meet that they would be kinder
warmer to offer our good good will to the whole
world so that others might be more
disposed to also have good
will certainly not to meet people with some opposite of Good
Will that would predispose them to do the
same may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may the kind gaze we have upon others
the open heart we bring to others spread a world of good
will even in the midst of all the ill will there exists
in the world may we spread the winds of
[Music]
kindness thank
you
e e
so hello everyone and welcome to this Monday
morning sitting and now this Dharma talk and I've been away for a couple of
weeks and happy to be back for this week and I will be away again next week
then I'll be after that I'll be back for a while and the reason again is to be to
teach a retreat IRC I just finished one yesterday and um and I realized well
after having scheduled next week's Retreat that the retreat is during the election national
election so uh we've given some thought to what it means to have this national
election during a retreat and how to um probably many people on the
retreat are anxious to know the results and will probably be trying to find out
what they are or and so how to inform them how to
support them to um process uh the election no matter
what direction it goes might be important for this Retreat we're doing and also it might be important for
many of you and it might be um you know I can imagine that there are many of you
and others who are anxious about what's happening concerned about what's happening and um
and no matter what the who wins who doesn't win what happens with the
election that it could be distressing for someone if not
everyone and so uh maybe if there's an occasion to
it's important enough to have a um I'll have a YouTube Zoom meeting uh for
people uh during the retreat I'll some figure out some way to set it up a time where I can do it and and in a sense
kind of leave the retreat to support those who maybe need some support in
this regard and um and but uh for this week that I'm back I thought that um it would
be important to um teach something that uh maybe would
support you over these next weeks and and it's not just the elections
which has people uh concerned uh and uh some people are are more than concerned
or um and um it's a you know it's quite
difficult for some people what's happening in the world World these days and uh
so I would like to somehow this week try to support you and address some of these
but to do so in a particular way that probably will not satisfy some of you
who are demanding action and and um and all that but um the
um uh I want to offer you one way to transform the world and that's kind
of maybe the title for this week's series to transform the world and
uh and to transform the world uh for the
better so um one of the important questions to
ask all of all of us to ask for ourselves and for each other is
how do we understand how change happens how do we understand a kind of a theory
of change or an approach to how change happens to yourself as an individual to
a family to a neighborhood to a friend Circle how does change happen in The
Wider world how does it happen politically how does it happen socially and
um and this I think this question needs a profound
consideration uh because uh we have I've see a lot of people with very strong
opinions about what should happen what has to happen and um uh but there's no
reference point for how that change Could Happen uh
except that someone out there needs to do it and uh and uh but how does change
happen is I'm not going to answer that question directly but what I will say it happens in 100,000 different ways it
happens in seven eight billion different ways and um and different people have
different opportunities to contribute to the change in our society and some
people do it dramatically and some people do it in uh
in quiet ways that are not seen recognized or held up as being
exemplars and um some of the more exceptional ways that some people change
the world is uh the accidents of history that they were in the right place at the
right time some of it has to do with where they're positioned and elected and
all kinds of things that affect them and uh whereas many people are not elected
many people are not positioned with the power the influence that a few individuals have but how does
how do how does uh individuals how do we involve with change for the
better and uh when I look at my life over with this question uh I've been
involved and interested in uh working for social change environmental change
um since I was 19 or so uh when I went to college and
began kind of getting a better understanding of what's happening in this world that I had growing up and
um and uh so now it's more than 50 years
since I was 19 and you know to I have the
perspective of half a century of what follows that initial impetus to make the
world better place and um and what I'd like to offer you is how I see myself in those 50
years uh maybe it's a little hard to believe with the with
um uh you know that uh I'm now become kind of a some people say a senior Buddhist teacher and so it might seem
like I have a lot of influence in certain ways certain places but I feel that uh uh that my
contribution to change uh I'm uh been more of an earthworm or a
fungus than you know a gorilla or a
elephant that can charge around and do big things and shake the
world and um and so you know so a fungus
in the soil uh changes the soil earthworm in the soil changes the soil
but it's underground you don't see it so much and um but it's uh essential it's
it's uh to have fungi it's essential to have earthworms it allows uh the soil to
be healthy allows it to uh we call it uh you know when dead matter leaves and
plants fall and die in the soil um they Decay but K really is another word for
composting and uh we need fungus to compost and uh digest and to transform
the soil so that we can create um a new
world so we can create new uh growths of of seeds and
growth and um and it might seem that the conditions of the world are so huge and
Monumental that um it's not okay just to be a fungus just to do the small changes
to work on the soil underground and it might seem like we're ignoring the rest of the world we have
to do something we have to stand up we have to make our voice heard we have to demand
change but demanding change is that how change happens is that the best way the
only way for it to happen um there are uh so as I've been
this fungus it started off very small and when I first wanted to be some kind
of to offer Buddhism Buddhist practice to respond to the suffering of the world it was I would say in retrospect
compared to what I'm doing now it was um uh uh pretty modest I just wanted to
have a storefront Meditation Center uh and uh for it was a Zen Center
I was a Zen priest and keep it clean and have the key that opened it and ring the
bells people came to meditate and support people to have a place to meditate I had some profound belief that
that was really valuable for people and I wasn't anything more than that that I
could imagine myself doing I certainly didn't imagine myself being a teacher and
um and then uh so I I engaged and practice and at some point I was invited
to be in a teacher training and that seemed nice and and uh my probably the
highest ambition I had was just to be involved with a local sitting group uh
and mayble support the sitting group or I actually also wanted to just kind of be connected to some of the Buddhist
centers in the Bay Area that I'd kind of grow grown up in and be able to support
those centers in some way maybe with some teaching and um and so I was trained to
be a teacher I I started was involved in a sitting group nearby and that sitting
group grew and uh and I just continued being the the earthworm or the fungus
and things grew around me and as they grew my influence grew as well as they
grew uh other opportunities could develop and happen and so when the
opportunities came then you know we kind of worked on things here at IMC and and
without you know making a big thing to do about it and um and now we have
you know uh we've done many many things over the years and had a huge influence
in certain kind of ways not particularly in political ways but we've done all kinds of things that have promoted the
good in the world that we don't we don't talk about much or celebrate much and
I've been to Sacramento to Lobby the governor I've been to train people to work in prisons to
offer um restorative uh Justice programs in
the prisons I've trained people to do mindfulness in the schools we the very
first National Conference in mindfulness schools have been here was was not didn't happen here but was planned here
organized here from IMC uh we have created chaplaincy programs and sent people to all over the
the the world in a sense to uh develop and and offered spiritual care and
hospitals and prisons and um
um hospices and many things and so slowly things are growing and we've had
kind of false starts we tried to be engaged with engaged Buddhism and there there wasn't much traction for that we
created a Buddhist humanitarian organization that had a glorious couple
of years of life but then it kind of faltered and now it's dormant for a long
time and uh but as opportunities come this earthworm this fungus that can are
working and doing things um and in the process of it having Buddhist
communities that communities now that's spreading across the country a little bit from IMC um and that is spreading this
practice of mindfulness of good willll of care uh training people in spiritual
care uh skills training teachers to go out into the world and um and maybe it's not enough
maybe we should also have a training in political action I would love to have a
program in nonviolent Civil Disobedience that really expresses love and care and
um but is the time come for that do we have the conditions for us to do that uh
I don't know but uh but we're kind of this earthworm is kind of finding its way seeing what happens and we've
started so many things over the years and you know now that I'm 70 how much more can I start than do um but all
behind all this and now I'll end is um
uh I believe that it's essential not to
sacrifice The Good Will in our own Hearts to not sacrifice a friendly
attitude towards all things if there's going to be a change in the world that really is going to for this earthworm
the way earthworm ter can change the world um and Earth orbons in the end are probably more and funguses are more
important than politicians uh that we have to um uh do
the simple ordinary work of love of kindness of Good Will of showing up and
being present for our neighbors and our people we see and encounter with
um with um uh um with an open heart and that's no
small task but if we can't do it do we expecting others to do it if we meet the
world with anger if we meet it with horror sense of horror if we meet it with fear if we meet it with
despair the unfortunate thing is that's what we spread out into the
world and so this practice this spiritual practice that we do in Buddhism is what is meant to support us
to find a way to heal our despair to heal our fear to heal our
anger uh because it harms ourselves it harms us to do to
have those things and in a healthy way to be healed so that we can meet the
world with kindness no matter what comes and that's a teaching of the Buddha no
matter what the challenge we meet to meet it with Good Will and
um so this week to transform the world I'm going to talk about the five
different flavors of love that we could have and today it's Goodwill I mentioned
briefly here and we did in the guide meditation and um and uh and certainly
if some of you can be great I don't know
what great powerful effective people for social change certainly do it certainly
go out and vote certainly go out and do what you can for our world but let's also be in addition
let's be earthworms and funguses composting the anger composting
the fear composting that despair so that we can compost it into
rich soil for the flowering of love into this world let that
be our theory of change to love wherever we
go so thank you and uh I look forward to continuing