greetings friends greetings good morning good afternoon good
evening um wherever you are wherever in the world you are whatever time zone
it's uh lovely to join you um this moment in time this is our fourth day of
exploring the uh topic of sadada confidence trust in the practice
so so let's uh let's begin or sit together let's begin to um um meditate
and I'll introduce the topic of the meditation uh for today and uh um with
the reflections later so let's begin let's arrive settling into our seats settling
into our bodies in this moment in time
arriving together arriving together as a
community spread around the world and arriving intimately on our
own in this body in a way that only I can know this
body
inviting this precious human body of ours in this precious human bird to
relax to
soften feeling the connection of the sit [Music]
bones with the cushion the chair
Landing
Landing through the points of contact our sit bones with the cushion
the chair our feet with the Earth feeling the contact points
inviting our spine to be upright to rise
up on its own without being pushed
up but as if there is An Invisible Thread on top of our head pulling
up vertebrae by vertebrae the rest of the body the rest
of the muscles can relax
and knowing the body knowing the ations of the body
right now in this moment in
time there might be [Music]
tingling sense of heaviness or lightness in various places
of the body
and knowing the movement of the breath in the
body the sensations
e e
and I'd like to invite you to drop in a reflection as the seed for our
practice today and dropping the reflection not in
the head not in your thinking space but in your heart and
your body as if you're dropping a pebble in a pond dropping it
in letting it resonate reverberate thinking about
it as if you're planting a seed see what
happens here's the
reflection may I trust during this period of practice may I trust may I
know may I have confidence
in this practice right
now I have trust that this is the most
worthwhile way to spend these minutes instead of thinking or planning or the
juiciness of Daydreams
I have full trust that this is the sweetest
place the kindest the calmest the most
fruitful place from my mind to be to be mindful to be aware to be present may I
fully trust that trust this know this through my
bones no doubt no
doubt dropping this reflection in I fully
trust awareness presence
is the place for my mind and heart to
be and connecting with the breath with the sensations of the breath in the body
mindfully
after planting the seed of trust
confidence
e
e e
watering the seeds of confidence and Trust we planted
earlier reflecting in our
hearts that this practice of loving
awareness mindfulness what you're
[Music]
seeing is the most
nourishing place for my heart for my mind to be resting right
now more nourishing more onward leading than thoughts of the future the
past planning this and that
distractions I can pick him up later but this is the most
nourishing supportive place for my mind to land to rest right
now it's where I want to
be letting the reflection rest
resonate connecting with your breath sensations of the breath
sensations of the body mindfully knowing what's arising and
passing in this
moment with
presence
e
e e
watering the seeds of confidence and Trust right
here right
now through mindfulness and Trust
confidence and loving
awareness
e
e e
and as we turn to bring
this sit to a close
together paying attention noticing how mind and heart
feel there is any more settledness confidence
stability peace compared to before or anything else that might be
present in the wholesome
States and recognize recognize the shift the
change as Tiny and subtle as it might be
and let it be a [Music] source of confidence to water the seeds
of confidence more of
trust and appreciating
yourself and the community for showing up and for the teachings to be available
in this form may all beings
everywhere benefit from our practice in ways we cannot imagine may all beings everywhere
be happy may all beings everywhere be free including myself
[Music]
thanks everyone I'm going to take a moment to
transition the
recording e
okay hello greetings
everyone and welcome again wherever in the world you're joining from whether
you're an Oldtimer here on this channel on the 7 a.m. SS or 7 a.m. California
time SS or whether this is your first time welcome welcome lovely that you're
joining the community and practicing practicing at this
time so the theme we've been exploring
together the teachings uh this week have been on sadada
sadada the word in poly translated as trust or
confidence and a quick recap of the past few days today is day four so day one we
started with how sense of trust and confidence is needed in practice before
you begin uh there has to be some perhaps borrowed trust oh yeah this
seems to be working for others borrowed trust that later becomes verified trust
verified confidence after you see how it actually impacts your your life and and
um your the way that you are yourself so the importance of trust for beginning
and for continuing practice and then day two we talked about the importance of
confidence trust in the triple Jewel uh Buddha Dharma that um yeah it is
possible someone woke up it's possible for me I can do this too trust in
yourself and Trust in the teachings that the teachings are available uh there are
recipes there have been people have tried them from for for centuries and uh trust in the support of
the S God that I'm not doing this alone I have support so trust in those three and um
yesterday uh day three we talked about
cultivating um um uh sadada uh through um uh through practice
and reflection how the more we practice um actually our confidence in
the practice grows and how by reflecting and uh both during practice uh and also
after practice uh short time frames long time frames we can uh water the seeds of
Sada of confidence in our practice it's through practice itself as well as we
also talked about ethical conduct with which was very important is important otherwise our confidence gets eroded in
ourselves uh in our capacity to to wake up um if we keep intoxicating ourselves
and and or stealing lying just the sense of trust gets eroded um so not
helpful so today building on all of that
uh we um I'd like to uh offer for your consideration the role of sadada uh
trust confidence in overcoming doubt overcoming
doubt so doubt is one of the five hindrances or the five naras the
five um veils and doubt um
uh in ply Vicki kit Vicki kit doubt can show up in different ways
doubt can show up as oh I can't do this everybody's got this I can't do this I
have a monkey mind nobody else does I can't do this or it can show up in the
teachings like yeah I'm not quite sure about these teachings or or
um um or um they're not for me or or um
can show up in the sa in the community I don't know about this community I don't know and also can show up in so many
different ways the teachers they don't know what they're talking about anyway doubt can show up in so many different
ways and S that trust is a way to support ourselves through periods of doubt
now I like to offer a more subtle way to
see doubt which we usually don't so this is we're going to go a little bit off
but you can see how it can relate
so consider that subtle subtle doubt can
also show up um in the ways that our
mind moves in um minute by minute moment by
moment so if we're sitting and practicing for example
and practicing say mindfulness as we did just before and then the subtle doubt
can show up as oh it's more juicy it's more fun it's more rewarding it's more
onward leading for me to to think about my plans for this afternoon so the Mind
goes there instead of instead of trusting that this is the place this is the most onward leading
rewarding uh supportive place for my mind to be right here right now with
mindfulness of the body mindfulness of the breath mindfulness of impermanence so there is this subtle pulling away not
quite trusting that this is it this is the most nourishing place to
be and practitioners report that sometimes
this Insight arises for them when they are really steeped in their practice
this Insight this uh thought arises oh this is the most nourishing place for me
to be right here right now not the thoughts not the distractions not the
this not the that not the desires and thinking wow this is the and it comes up
as a sense of trust this is the this is the most nourishing this is the most
onward leading uh wisdom producing place for me to
be so that is a sense of trust so so trust not just in a larger scale of
supporting our practice but also in the minor scale of supporting our practice to stay to stay this subtle trust and
again remember self- judgment is not the answer to trust it's not like oh you're
a bad meditator you don't have enough trust it doesn't work that way so please
let go of self-judgment um and just come back to trust I trust I trust that this
is this is supportive this is onward leading doubt can
also um show up with in a slightly different way um it can show up in the
subtle way of us not connecting to the practice um for example not being a
regular practitioner like practicing one day and then taking a week off or month
off and then realizing and then remembering our trust oh yeah when I was practicing uh when I was connecting with
the Dharma when I was reading when I was listening to Dharma talks oh I was Kinder I was um less reactive so
remembering tapping into that trust can ofer often brings us back but in those
periods that are we're not connecting we're not connecting then trust is not
as strong right because we're not we don't have unshakable trust that this is what helps my Humanity grow this is what
helps me wake up in this very life for the benefit of myself and the benefit of others to be transformed into another
version of myself um a better Angel a better angel of my
myself so so doubt can show up in these subtle ways of our behaviors uh which
not so subtle actually is is is doubt in in in the practice that can show up in
or doubt in ourselves or um doubt that it's working Etc in a subtle way it's
not a clear expression of that but it's got more more subtle kind of takes us
away it's a lack of confidence that shows up as as lack of
commitment so a couple of other things I wanted to say today
so sadada confidence as an antidote to trust and again we build trust by
noticing by really bringing reflection to how um this is working for us how how
how the shifts and changes are happening and to say that again from the
first day I want to repeat that it's very important for sadada to be um
balanced with PA with wisdom wiom so trust needs to be balanced by
wisdom if not it can fall into Blind Faith or or
blind yeah Blind Faith which is not helpful either not
helpful and in fact it is said that I mean the same way that you've heard the
metaphor that wisdom and compassion are the two birds of the wing of Awakening
also the two birds of the wing it is said uh the two wings of the bird let's
try that again the two wings of the bird that's funny um are uh wisdom and and
Trust so so wisdom needs to support trust so that it doesn't get out of
balance um so there are many stories in the
sutas and maybe I'll just share one with you briefly so there stories of
um various Disciples of the Buddha uh venerable saruta and mallana who were
initially skeptical and had doubt but through confidence and hearing the
Dharma hearing the Dharma they had confidence and and they fully awakened
and became Disciples of the Buddha um there's also another story uh
typical a a story of kemma Terry who became uh a leading disciple of the
Buddha um similar to venerable SAR she was likened to the uh in in in the nuns
orders as the um uh uh as the Sarai in the in the monk orders and the story is
that she was um she was very beautiful and uh part of the um uh and and she was
a con concert of uh of a king king bin basari and uh she was very attached to
her beauty and her Youth and uh King Bim basari wanted her
to practice with the Buddha and know the Buddha so uh they arranged for her to
pass by The jeta's Grove where the Buddha is teaching and the Buddha through her through his um uh Powers
through his um uh um Powers he creates an a vision of a very beautiful woman uh
and and while k um uh while um uh K the
k k the is passing by she sees the vision of this very
beautiful woman and she admires the very beautiful woman and then the Buddha
again through her through his powers creates that having cre created this Mirage makes this beautiful woman
um Decay and get old in front of uh
Ker's eyes and ker in that moment realizes really has insight into
impermanence that beauty and and youth are impermanent they're not they're
they're not for her to hang on to and to to cling to so through why reflection of
impermanence she overcomes doubt that oh these practices are not for me I don't know and then she practices with the
Buddha um and becomes fully enlightened and and becomes one of the uh Prime
disciples so so wise reflection listening to the teachings practicings
etc etc are ways to overcome doubt whether in strong ways or in subtle ways
of of lack of commitment do during practice distractions Etc or or falling
by the wayside or or practice Falling by the wayside okay so thank you so much for your
practice for your commitment for doing this practice for the sake of all beings
everywhere not just ourselves may all beings be well may all beings be happy
take good care oh yes um yeah maybe oh yeah I always want to end with with
invitation notice notice doubt notice subtle doubt in your practice in your
way of being today if there are subtle ways of doubt and subtle way and and and
and ways that you can connect with confidence and trust in yourself in the practice the community today all right
thank you be well take care see you tomorrow