good evening my name is Maria strotman and
I'm here for Diana tonight and I'll be here next Monday night
also so I'm happy to be here seems strange to hear my voice that
bill caught me by surprise so um tonight
uh I'm going to start in the middle of the story so this is what occurred to me this afternoon as I was thinking about
what I was going to talk about is that all Dharma talks kind of start in the middle of the
story because practice practice is hard it's hard to
pull the pieces apart you know everything is related to everything else and so as soon as I say well I want to
talk about this piece well yeah but then I have to talk about that piece and if I talk about that piece well you're not
going to know what I mean unless I talk about that piece and pretty soon it becomes totally
Tangled and really what I want to say is look here look here look at this
thing and pretty soon I'm sitting there full of doubt and
if I'm not full of doubt I'm full of arrogance what's going on here and
that's that's what practice is like we're always in the middle middle of the story we don't get to start at
the beginning and plan it and then you know the control all the outcomes and
all of the conditions life is full of
conditions the vast majority of which we have no input to much less control
over the temperature in the room did you get sleep last night did you have time for dinner
did someone in your family just die we're not even talking about the
topic yet there are so many conditions so many conditions that
affect what's happening in this room but what's really happening in this
room is life we are living we are practicing we are meeting the moment or
not meeting the moment we're missing our lives
so tonight what I'd like to do is try to weave a little pattern just a tiny
pattern of everything and I already know I can't talk about everything we only have a few
minutes here for this everything will not fit in a few minutes but everything is in those few minutes
everything we don't get to cut out anything
life is happening life is happening and that's the good news so so my talk is
about intention mindfulness and the journey sounds simple right intention
mindfulness in the journey or we could call it intention immediacy and
persistence or we could say suffering impermanence and no
self because suffering gives rise to intention and impermanence is what
immediacy is all about why we care about it at all and no self gives rise to the
need for persistence arises out of
impermanence but we're not going to talk about those three we're going to talk about intention mind fness and the
journey so if we're going on a journey we have to have some idea of where we're
going or we're not going to get there I mean you can wander
aimlessly but that's what you're doing wandering aimlessly and even that is an intention aimlessness is an
intention so you have to have an idea of what you intend what's my intention I
want to do X it's the motivation for what you're going to do it's the inspiration the
aspiration I want to do I want to go I want to be I want
that it's a leaning towards something so we have to have some kind of
intention and once we begin we need that intention before we begin
maybe not chronologically but somewhere there is something that gets us on the
journey we take a step because we're going
somewhere that intention is extremely important because it's the source of motivation it's also the things that
provides the persistence the one that allows us to take the Second
Step it's also the thing that provides the faith that allows us to go it's not only
I'm going to do this I know what I'm going to do so I'm going to go do this but it also allows us to take that leap
of faith that says Yep this is the direction I'm going to go this is the
method I'm going to take this is the this is the way I'm going to do this that intention is extremely
important sometimes we set out and we're not really clear about that intention we have a very vague notion of the
intention but as we go along our experience bolsters that intention and
the intention strengthens through that experience and the faith becomes
stronger and our ability to P persist become stronger and more uh confident we
become more conf confident and doubt is less likely to
undermine us but it all comes in the first place
from that intention when I began practicing I had
a really Grand intention and it was to develop loving kindness in my
life and I so it was I was going to be my my primary intention was to be
openhearted that that's good it's a good
intention and over time I decided I finally heard myself
say it a number of times and and I realized that I could just sort of stop
with be open and eventually I got to the place
where I could just be because as I examined that intention over and over again I realized ized that
the intention was really about the absence of protecting myself the need
for all of those things I had in front of myself to protect myself from harm
from being hurt and that that initial intention was
really masking what I really wanted which was to feel safe and
loved and safe in going out and connecting with other people
and it was only through the years of practice I was able to see that and to eventually feel more safe
and to develop a willingness to be vulnerable and to develop develop
vulnerability and to just show up which it turns out is what the
intention was all along so it isn't that you have to know an intention and stick with it forever it's something that
develops along with you that changes with you but you have to be aware of it
it's incredibly important it really guides you across the
way and it informs your practice whatever the practice is it changes with
you it's a living thing this this
intention it is the thing that provides the energy to your
practice you you you notice that I have this intention I'm getting started I'm
starting to see this sort of this sort of makes a difference to me and then you say oh okay yeah and you
get kind of excited you know so when I was when I was doing this
talk I at one point decided I wanted to look up something and the next thing you
knew I had you know four or five Books open and my husband came in and wanted to ask about something truly mundane and
I said oh no but look you know I've got this and I'm looking at that and I'm looking he said look at you you're so
excited I I it's been a long time since I had multiple Books open on my desk researching this and researching that
and looking at the other and I was excited and I was excited because I was
realizing that the last time I had this Books open I was quite
different and there was a different person looking at those books and reading those lines and examining those pieces of of
information and that was exciting to me it was
motivating it was interesting you know sometimes we get
kind of bogged down in how hard we're working on something and we forget that why we're
doing it in the first place why am I doing this what's it
about and that there's real delight and joy in changing your
mind and doing something different and maybe modifying the
plan adapting
and it turns out that the way that we practice you
know there there are the there you know Buddhism has all kinds of lists so one of the lists that ended up being one of
those things that came into my grab bag was the five powers you know the five
faculties the the things that help you get through practice and the first three
are Faith energy or effort and mindfulness which see how nicely they
fit in with the topic right so the first three the faith that comes from from
experiencing what's coming out of your intention the energy that's generated from that and
mindfulness which is the key to all of it
mindfulness mindfulness mindfulness is the thing
that tells you where you are you know we we often think about mindfulness as I
have an object and I know the object right I'm following my breath I'm following sound I'm following whatever
is the object of your mindfulness or I have expansive mindfulness where I'm
mindfulness of whatever arises but the mindfulness I'm talking about is the mindfulness that says
What's Happening Here what's happening here what's going on
right now mindfulness that says here I am right now in this
moment I am registering my awareness with whatever it
is you know the the important thing about mindfulness is you have the object and you know the object and you know you
know it that's the awareness part it's the awareness the being cognizant and
registering I know I'm following this I know I'm here I know that I'm breathing
I know that I'm sitting I know that I'm s that I'm hearing I know that I'm
smelling I know that I'm walking it's that knowing part it's the
awareness that mindfulness that constantly brings us back to here and we
can say what do I I know now what am I aware of now and that
registering what do I know that's the key that tells you where you are what's
going on here what's going on
now it doesn't have to be a grand thing it can be a trivial
thing a trivial thing so let me pause for just a second here
okay so we want to be able to
notice what's happening right so when we're sitting in meditation we can
notice I'm following my breath I'm following my breath the mind wanders off
we notice the Mind comes back like oh the mind has been gone that's the very moment when we're really aware we're
here great Rejoice we're here
yes it doesn't have to only be then it can be anytime so I'm going to tell you
about something uh that's truly trivial that happened to me today and use it as
an example for how this might work so uh I met somebody this
morning and this person said uh would you like a bottle of water and I said no
I've got my coffee here in my in my thermos and I haven't had any time yet for even a swallow of coffee I can
hardly wait and this person immediately began telling me how terrible coffee was
and they had never drunk coffee and it stained her teeth and it really tastes bad and how bad coffee was and she was
so glad that that they never had coffee and on and on and on about a coffee so
my reaction to this was immediately I I reacted you know and
I I I felt the reaction I could feel the the pulling back I could feel the
resistance I could feel a kind of tension and twisting I felt the wanting
to defend myself and then I stopped I mean there
were a lot of things happening this is somebody that it's easy easy for this person to trigger me so I'm always
prepared you know so there's certain topics that I'm really ready and so
there's no way this person's going to trigger me I was not prepared to be triggered by the coffee so here I was
and so I I see I feel it all happening and so I just stopped and in that moment
I said I don't have to be the person who reacts to the coffee I don't have to be
whatever is happening here whether it's I have to be right I'm reacting to feeling diminished I'm reacting to I
thought this was um a friendly gesture we're going to get together and talk
about how great it is to have that first swallow of coffee uh you know whatever the source of my reaction is is not
important I don't have to be the person who reacts it's stopping it's
noticing caught
stop the reason is not important here later you can analyze it but in the
moment just stop I don't have to be the person who reacts to
this the chattering is still going on I'm still hearing about how bad coffee
is but I've stopped and in at
stopping I am no longer Enchanted by my
role I have become dispassionate about it who cares who
cares I'm going to drink the coffee she's not going to drink the coffee it doesn't really
matter who cares suffering ceases
there is no argument here there is nothing now in that
moment I can go back and try to figure it out which is retelling the story and
immediately it can come up again or I can say I wonder she's still talking I
wonder what she's thinking is she thinking why is she telling me about the coffee I offered her water she could
have accepted the you who knows what she's thinking so now I can expand my
awareness to wondering about something outside of me I don't have to make it
about me it can be another story that comes
up now I'm telling my a story about her but now it's she's no longer the bad guy
now I'm wondering there are an infinite number
of things that can happen about what which one can be
mindful about over which one can introduce suffering or the end of
suffering over a thermos of coffee and a bottle of
water doesn't have to be a big thing but what happens is you become used to
noticing tension letting go
Freedom release in that moment relief in that moment even if it comes right back
you can stop again and you can stop again and you can stop
again the Buddhist said right intention right intention is renunciation or not
clinging harmlessness uh he had three things
right wise intention is
harmlessness not clinging
and his third
thing those are the two I'm thinking about right now it'll come to me in a moment my mind
is not clear and I refuse to feel bad about it
it'll come when I don't need it and I have clearly walked away from
my talk here on the paper
so yeah it's okay it'll come but the two that that I can address
directly not clinging and harmlessness not clinging renunciation not clinging not clinging
to who I need to be who I might be who the better me
is not clinging to being right just
stop just stop not clinging to be
openhearted just stop practice that in the
moment the mindfulness of just being aware of what's happening in the
moment in the
moment disenchantment dispassion sensation that's that's the
process to do that you have to be mindful you have to see what's happening
right now
this is quite irritating that I can't find that but there it is I can't find
it one of the one of the real traps that we get into is the Trap of needing to be
better than we are needing to be a better person needing to
be clear more clear than we are one of my favorite quotes is from uh Suzuki
roshi who who noticed that a lot of his students were really uh extremely self-critical and
what he said is you know you're perfect just the way you are and you could use a little
work and the reason I like that is it's it's very clear that you really don't
have to be other than you are and you should not stop working you should not stop following
that intention toward being non- clinging and
non-harming that leaning toward freedom in the
moment that should not be let go of
that should be reinforced that should be cultivated in order to do that we have
to be willing to be to let go of all the opinions we have about what's going on
now we have to be able to see what's going on now it's seeing it clearly so
that we can say oh I don't have to be all the things I don't have to react
to I don't have to I I can
stop it's not easy I don't want to claim it's easy and
it kind it can come right back but being able to feel what it
feels like when you can stop and be free
of that passion to feel that passion go
allows you to feel what it feels like like for a moment of
freedom and I personally just want to add those
up and become used to seeing that so that I can be aware of that in any
moment in more and more moments of my life when the surge in reactivity slows
down then I can reflect on what was going on where did the mind go
what did the mind what was the react what was the form of reactivity what did that look
like I should be careful about that I should be aware of that that's a mind
habit I should be aware of but in the moment the important thing is
stop just stop feel the puffiness go out of the
out of the moment feel it
deflate I don't have to understand everything in the moment I can just
ah so one of the books I had open was uh Joseph goldstein's one Dharma and then
the nice thing about this book is he in it he talks about the various forms of Buddhism that he has practiced and how
while the practices are different the song they sing is pretty
similar and so uh what he I have a quote from him that
I particularly liked he said faith in the possibility of Awakening confidence in the moments
experience and in the nature of awareness itself trust in the direction
of Our Lives all of these settle doubt confusion and
agitation they create an inner environment of clarity Stillness and
Beauty let me repeat that faith in the possibility of Awakening confidence in
the moments experience and in the nature of awareness itself trust in the direction of Our
Lives all of these settle doubt confusion and
agitation they create an inner environment of clarity Stillness and
beauty that sounds really attractive and it really goes back to
knowing your intention practicing with your intention revisiting your intention and being
mindful of that persisting in being
mindful persisting in just seeing being aware being
here ah this is what's happening this is what's happening not judging what's
happening this is what's happening seeing it as clearly as you possibly can
oh this is what's happening I'm reacting to that oh look
at that see that not this is good this is bad this
is more this is less see it see
it the quote from him I was looking for is this
one he he was talking about Enlightenment or Freedom
Liberation and uh he was quoting Renee deal in Mount
analog keep your eye fixed on the way to the top but don't forget to look right
in front of you the last step depends on the
first don't think you you've arrived just because you see the summit watch your footing be sure of the
next step but don't let that distract you from the highest goal the first step
depends on the last you begin with your
intention you have a goal don't lose sight of the intention but it is the intention that
sets you off on the first step
and that first step leads to the last step which is the next step that you
take and then step after that and the step after that and the step after
that live it live that step not the one you took 20 years ago not the one you
haven't taken yet this step this is the only one that you can
affect right now and this is the one that you can
know about
so what you get from that the promise
this is a poem by Jane hershfield mysteriously they entered those few minutes mysteriously they
left as if the great dog of confusion guarding my heart who is always
Sleepless suddenly slept it was not any Awakening of the large not so much as that only a
stepping away from the petty I gazed at the range of Blue Mountains I drank from the stream tossed in a small Stone from
the bank whatever Direction the face of my life might travel I trusted even the
greedy Direction even The Grieving trusted there was nothing like to be
saved from Bliss nor danger the dog's tail wagged a little in his
dream it was not an Awakening of the large not so much as that only a
stepping back from the petty as if the great dog of confusion
guarding my heart who is always Sleepless suddenly slept I wish you all to have Sleeping
Dogs of confusion thank you
so if you have any questions comments I'd be happy to entertain them
yes so I was really hang on a second experience
about the coffee coffee yeah cuz I have recently had a coffee experience
too and I stopped drinking coffee I think what I'm not going to give you a lecture about coffee but 50 years ago
for various reasons and I had some friends coming and I know they're big coffee
Drinkers and I made sure that I could find the coffee maker and all the things
you put in CU I'd forgotten how to make coffee and I was sure to show them and
wanted to make sure that they felt comfortable staying with us to make their
coffee and I didn't realize till they started making coffee I was really trying hard not to react that I didn't
like the smell of the coffee that had permeated the whole
condo and saying to myself this is their vacation and this is a coffee experience
for me that I haven't had in 50 years and what am I going to do with it and I just tried to flow with it and
I didn't make any comments about the smell except of course to my husband who doesn't drink coffee either and
controlled myself from saying about why do you just drink coffee and they went
all day long with only drinking coffee so I'm pausing and I'm watching and I'm
thinking it's their vacation and it's their time away so I don't want to give a coffee
lecture you know I really controlled myself and then I started asking myself
why am I reacting so strongly to the smell we haven't had a talk about coffee
there's been no lecture right there's been absolutely no judgment verbally but
in my head I can't get over the smell and they're with us you know for two
weeks so after the third day I looked at myself and I said you're going to learn
to like that smell and not let it spoil your day because I was thinking about the
smell after they would leave and really thankful when they came back that they didn't and do more coffee and after the
third day finally I was at peace and I said just let it go you know just
release it clear it it's just coffee you know and then I
guess the second week I started thinking about why I stopped drinking coffee because I hadn't thought about it for a
long time you know and I was really happy
that I wasn't drinking it anymore but there was no judgment about why I
stopped so I think it was really good that they came and they drank the coffee
because it helped me to release I think a very subtle reaction that I was still
having to it that it was maybe not so good to be drinking it
but not for them but for me so thank you for your story I don't think it was trivial at all all and I
think it helps you to know that even little tiny subtle things so
small can cause a reaction they can and I I thank you for
that I think it's also important to realize that it it was unpleasant for you you don't have to pretend it was not
unpleasant it was unpleasant it was uh there was there was a poem uh it's not
in this book but it is a Jane hershfield Book and it's um a poem uh and I I wish
I knew it completely but it it basically is U
it's called Cedar something and she the the the idea is I do it I still every
morning wash my face in cold water to remind
myself that it's okay to be with something that's really unplan
Pleasant oh I like that yeah and um I like I like the idea of it also you know
it's unpleasant and it's it's uh you don't have you don't have to push it
away and you don't you don't have to do it in the spirit of I'm tolerating this
necessarily either it's it's just unpleasant you know and it sounds like over the course of the three days you
got to the point where you just said it's just unpleasant and this is something I'm giving my guests is I'm
willing to be with and then as a side you learn something about yourself but
we don't have to pretend it's it's not unpleasant it's unpleasant for you so
you know that's that should be acknowled follow up about harmlessness I was happy that I didn't
really do much harm to them in any way by lecturing about it yeah but when I
finally accepted it the harm that I was doing to myself didn't feel as
bad it felt less so I love that part of your
talk I'm going to find
that third oh non-ill will yeah non- clinging
non-ill will and and harmlessness duh thank you
yeah does anybody else have something
yes uh thanks for the talk um I do want
to go back to the concept of not clinging um particularly like uh when
I'm at work where I typically get very engaged in like you know conversations at work um
and sometimes I get like too impassioned about the topic you know
and there are moments where you I catch myself feeling that way and I'm
present um and I tell myself okay just like let it go it's okay you don't have
to be right you don't have to like prove a point um and and you know you can like
listen um I I think like uh when when that happens for me though um
I typically go the polar opposite and I go like full not full but like a big
disengagement from the topic um almost like a sense of apathy which I also like
don't want to necessarily give off right because like there is like the the the golden mean I guess in between like
clinging and apathy yes um or disengagement so I guess like my
question is um how do I uh like what's a what's a good way to be in that golden mean um
especially when when you're able to like actually catch yourself um which which is very pleasant right like you're catching yourself okay I can like
correct course but then like how do I you know like balance between like being
very impassionate about it versus being just um totally like
disengaged so I think there that that's a great great question and I think that
that an important thing to consider is how important is what's involved right
so I deliberately chose coffee and a bottle of water because you know nobody's impacted by this nobody is
harmed by this nobody's there are no great decisions tied to this uh had I
chosen something like uh where where my husband and I are going to go on
vacation now now there there's more uh there's more invested in that
discussion right so so if uh I remember
in a previous marriage I felt like I won every battle and lost every
war which would be the same sort of thing I I I would win the battle and
then I'd let him have his way right because I I was into uh uh
being a debater you know it was important to me to to have the the uh to be
right but I didn't want to but I felt like Pro protecting the
relationship required me to give in you know and somehow that was totally
misguided way of thinking so it was very destructive to the relationship so that's a case where that just doesn't
work at work um you have to make similar sorts
of decisions you know so is what you're trying to is what you're
discussing uh something that has import or is it a case where you just
want to be right or is it a case where somebody's being bullied intellectually bullied right and you can see that's
happening then you decide am I being bullied am I stepping away
from being bullied by this person how important is that is that affecting my standing or is that just affecting how I
am with this person what's what are the consequences of giving in to this person
so so you kind of have to measure that
in the discussion how you deal with speech is
you know is is it true is it useful is it timely is it
kind you know so you can answer those questions but in terms of this broader
question of apathy versus
argumentativeness that takes that's in the realm of how do I
establish personal space personal space I'm going to call it
and in an appropriate way how do I have an appropriate personal space here and
that's something that you kind of have to measure by by Honest
reflection and consideration of whether the the situation you're in
is appropriate for you overall you know you want to keep the job you like the job you have to get along with this
person it's your boss it's not your boss you know um are there other avenues is this
something that happens all the time is this a person that does you know is it one person that's a problem or lots of
people that are the problem you know there are all kinds of questions so I don't think it's a simple answer but I
think you do have to look at uh you it is not necessary to become the
person who always gives in that's I don't think
appropriate but seeing what's happening is extremely important and not
automatically behaving in a certain way so what I hear you say is um their
response is really based on the context um and there there are things where we have
to like speak up and as long as it's true um timely useful and kind um those
are like good thank you for that by the way good like I guess like compasses um to speech um but there're also like
things that are the grander scheme of things trivial um and those are of
moments where we can choose to kind of just like soften a bit and and not like be so you know like combative about or
or argumentative about stuff so choose your battles yeah no I appreciate that thank you so much yeah
yes thanks for your talk and um
um what uh I my practice lately is about being
aware wherever I am whatever I do and what and then I've become
by being mindfulness and um not not just a
sitting you know mindful of everything that go goes on around
me and uh I've and I'm track I'm practicing this
mindfulness in to be effortless because in order to
be mindful you have to set your you have to pause you have to look at it and then
decide put the intention to do the right thing or say
right thing and all that and
then it's effort it's some effort to put in order to do that yeah so I'm
practicing a lot to be really more mindful of my life and
then I noticed that most of my reaction
is from outside world some some interactions someone says something
someone does something so I I kind of react to anything that goes on that I
hear or I see it these five senses that I'm using to to get the to pause and
look at my my reaction mhm so
um and it it has really helped me and I just feel like you know doing
that without that effort that pause sometimes it just come right out
with no with some reaction that is not based
on mindfulness and say okay this is this
is the process and this is knowing and so on so that's where I like to be clear
that there that that quick reaction there there's a
lot so uh uh it could be asking a lot of yourself
to have total Insight when there's a lot
happening you know in the midst of uh a conversation at work you can't be aware
of everything you have to choose what you're going to be aware of and
so sometimes it's uh
one of one of the points I tried to make earlier is I didn't try to analyze what was what my reaction was only that I was
reacting and that I would stop so that I didn't try to decide how should I be
reacting I ju how should I be reacting I just stopped so that I didn't have to make
all those decisions because I didn't have time to analyze it in real time and
figure it all out to be wise there wasn't an option to be wise all I
could do was stop okay and then later I could think
about what was going on and then I expanded my awareness and said okay
what's going on with her it's too complex to figure out what's going on with me but rather than making her the
bad guy why don't I ask myself what's going on with her as a way of not
re-entanglement because we can become too focused on
figuring out my stuff and just makes it more
complex so uh so that's the only thing I would say about that you you want to
practice mindfulness to the extent that you feel like you are inhabiting your life but not that you're cluttering
it if you're cluttering your life you you're you're doing yourself a
disservice choose choose pieces
because you don't want to make your life into a project you want to live your
life thank you thanks so uh so we need to end if
anybody else has anything else I'll hang around for a while thank you very much may you be well