so there I think that technological Marvels have all been attended
to so they all need their particular
attention so welcome to
the this meditation and as an introduction to it I'd like to mention
that um I have a particular
very special relationship maybe even reverence to places in the natural
world where that are untouched or off bounds for human beings there's a place
near here um in their in the San Francisco Peninsula that's a water
district they have a big reservoir for water for San Francisco and other cities
but some of the land around it uh no one is supposed to walk on it's off limits
and I'm sure that uh some people in the water district have occasion to go on it
but occasionally but it's basically off limits and it isn't like I feel like
it's private property exactly but I feel like it's protected from Human
encroachment and um and I feel I'm so happy that there's a place where in the
natural world that um that it's inaccessible to me it's just there it's
a kind of sacred Place special place where the natural world can just kind of
be it be itself be be its own thing and uh the animals there the deer the
mountain lions they can just be um be outside the the influence or outside the
desires and preferences of humans so I'm sure there's other ways of understanding this water district land but there are
these places in the world that are considered sacred that some people you know you don't visit you can leave you
you stay away from and um and so in the same way in
ourselves there are Realms or aspects of our being our inner
World which um also belongs to a kind of dimension of Life which I feel doesn't
doesn't it shouldn't be part or is not part of our desires and preferences and
what we construct and what even what we interpret and the meaning making we add to it that it's there and it's operating
in its own way as a natural functioning as a
natural phenomena that uh can operate with us
for us maybe even guide us but it's not something we can appropriate it's not
something that we can claim to be ours or that we can
um uh you know that we that we're really
outside the realm of appropriating as mine or me outside
the realm of uh uh how I think about myself all the ideas I have about myself
the conclusions the judgments about my life there's a whole other operation that's operating here and um and it's
found uh or touched into and get be known by a Deep Quiet a Stillness within
a quieting of the constructing mind a quieting of the mind that's
reacting and thinking and planning and judging and um uh making meaning of
things and predicting the future and hanging on to the
Past uh that quieting of the mind that that is concerned with Me Myself and
mine who I am what's what my experiences are what's happening to me certainly
those those kinds of mental thinking has a place in life but uh I don't want to
rule it out completely but um there's something Beyond it something deeper
than that when that gets quiet that there's a natural
operation and part of that are belongs to the realm of Love of
compassion of some deep sense of tenderness or
care and and maybe there the human qualities of nurture nurturing and
nourish nurturing like a parent the nurturing that a parent might feel for a
little baby maybe these are instincts instinctual in us they're deeper
than Bel belongs to the human species they belong to maybe all
mammals that we have certain maybe hormones and chemicals and
orientations that brings forth a a natural capacity to care to
love that um should not be appropriated that should be left alone can operate in us
through us with us but um it's not about us
exactly and uh it's not about how well we can do something it's not
about being successful or not about failing it's about becoming quiet enough
or still enough to be able to
listen on the other side of all our thoughts and thinkings and
ruminations to be able to [Music] feel below the level of our anxiety or
disappointments or desires aversions
resentments there is a place that I think inside that is sacred a place of
that I have certain reverence for that it's not exactly me I can't
appropriate it but it's there and
invaluable and it's connected to very deeply connected to the idea of care and
compassion love kindness an instinct towards
nurturing and so maybe we can sit here with that as a reference point for
today that it's sit to meditate in a [Music]
field with an intention with an orientation towards being comp
compassionate or loving or kind
nurturing for ourselves and whatever is here within us whatever is challenging
within us whatever our thinking mind is
churning up and and
U the way the thinking mind is turning up and casting its
difficulties through our muscles and our body and our emotions it's difficult to be a human
being and deep within us there is a instinct to care to nourish
nurture compassion and love so to assume a meditation
posture perhaps viewing the
posture as a form of love or
care for
ourselves gently closing the
eyes and this closing of the eyes to be done with care with love with
with a sense of
purpose to nourish to [Music]
heal to free this human being from
suffering to become aware of the body breathing not as an
exercise in concentration or becoming
present but [Music] rather as an
instinct to bring care
love maybe a parental or
grandparent love for what's at the core of
yourself maybe the core from which breathing is intimately
connected where we sense that breathing
itself is arises from a deep source
of keeping ourselves alive of nourishing
ourselves providing us with the energy the
Vitality that allows us to be
here so much of our inner systems
keeping us in homeostasis keeping us in Balance keeping us
[Applause]
alive keeping us
alive is for our own benefit allowing this deeper place of ourselves
to care and benefit us that's beyond our thinking mind engineering
mind judging mind to sit
present for our natural capacity for
love
e
for
for for
and as we come to the end of this sitting might there
be for you enough quiet or calm or maybe inner sensitivity to your
body and heart that you could feel
that operating system within that is has to do with nurturing or
caring has gentle Compassion or
love the kind of source of motivation and Instinct that comes with caring for
holding a newborn baby
or holding someone's hand as they're dying
peacefully there are times in our life where we're touched
deeply by our shared Humanity our connections to
others that bypasses the our biases and our
judgments and our histories and our even our created identities
and ideas of Me Myself and
mine and as we sit here and bring this to a
conclusion can you be still and gaze upon the world kindly
gaze upon the world with compassion and love not wanting anything from
anyone being able to gaze upon everyone with no
fear no
aversion be still and gaze upon everyone kindly
and with that nurturing caring
instinct to wish everyone well may all beings be
happy may all beings be safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be free and may all beings
know that there is care and love and compassion in this
world and that it's directed to them as well
[Music]
thank you [Music]
so hello everyone and welcome to this fourth thought for
for fourth talk where I try to articulate the core teachings that uh
kind of under underly what motivates me to teach and what guides how I
teach and um so it's kind of a hopefully a clear way of letting people know what
I'm about because um some of you have been listening to me for a long time and it
feels like it's the responsible thing for me to uh kind of be very direct
about what I think are my core um my core
um you know orientations as a teacher perspectives and uh so yesterday I
talked about uh how there's a strong naturalistic
orientation uh in how I want how I teach and how I I practice
that um that there's a um an orientation perspective
that there is a natural functioning within us that uh that uh benefits us
that we're tapping into and allowing to move through us and allowing to awaken Us in
us that um as we Orient towards suffering and the end of suffering
as we free ourselves from fixed ideas and fixed
views that uh it'll gives room for this this natural functioning of ourselves to
to function to operate and uh just like if you keep
your cut clean it allows a natural functioning of the body healing
to heal the cut just as some of the ways in which
our hearts get broken if similarly kind of metaphorically we keep the heart
clean we don't interfere with its own natural working give room for it get
room for the pain there is a natural kind of healing or movement towards
Health that the heart knows what to do better than our thinking mind our
engineering mind our mind that's trying to figure out or trying to understand and so to sit in meditation
and get out of our own way and uh not only do the practice but
also be practiced be practiced by the practice allow ourselves to be changed
and moved by this deeper Instinct deeper movement that happens within us it's not
uh our doing and we learn over time that a lot of the things that we do interfere with
the movement towards freedom and Liberation so one of the core aspects of
all this this naturalistic kind of orientation is that there is within us a
natural movement towards the the whole category whole to use a category word that the whole uh
phenomena of love the whole uh movements of the heart that we can
have and that uh one of the deepest ones is the instinct to uh nurture the
instinct to care for that which we uh value that's which we love that which we
are touched by or moved by and um and so sometimes that's done
for who we feel closest to sometimes it's done for um uh you know for small
babies uh I think I've to mentioned this that recently that I knew a man who
volunteered in the local hospital working with um uh the prematurely born
babies who uh needed to be held and have physical contact in order to develop
normally and he that was his volunteer job just to hold premature babies and it
changed him softened him opened him over the time that he did it uh some people have this relationship
to animals or little puppies or kittens that uh something happens or an injured
bird that we gently take care of and um or sometimes uh some of us have been at
the bedside of people who are dying and um and when sometimes they're dying
slowly and peacefully and uh and there's a can be a deep tenderness a deep uh
feeling of love and care that in that bedside
occasion and and um so as we settle in meditation as we get quiet in
meditation that there are these uh very human capacities we
have that are operating that are I like to think of them
independent of our thinking mind or our constructive mind our reactive mind our
imaginary mind the mind that builds up stories and uh images of ourselves and
lives in these kind of cathedrals lives in these kind of cities of Concepts and
that are culturally and familiarly and personally kind of created that uh we don't even realize
how much we are conditioned by our culture by our
society by our language by our family and we just think that
uh you know our very idea of who we are as a self and who we are in relationship to other people and even I who we kind
of how we oriented towards others has very deep cultural conditioned
phenomena and we take it for granted we think this is the way it is and so with that comes the idea that of course being
angry or being aversive of course uh setting up strong boundaries and you and
me of course I I have desires and of course protecting myself of course of
course all these things of course this that build up this very complicated world that's very fragile and easily
disrupted easily hurt but if we in meditation if we get
quiet enough and peaceful enough that um that kind of constructing mind the
active mind that makes up stories and uh imagines and has beliefs we get through
layers and layers of them and it's phenomenal to realize how many layers of conditioning we have and to come down to
a place where the there some deeper operating system can can can
function and um and one of those has to do with love and care and
compassion and so that when they with a contact with with suffering in the world
um the the uh it's not despair that arises it's not anguish it's not a sense
of hopelessness or a sense of overwhelm we don't suffer more because we're in contact with suffering but rather
uh it awakens the Instinct for compassion instinct to care for what
they suffering and um this happened to me when I was uh practicing in in the
Buddhist Monastery my first first time in the monastery and I was there for about three years and and that was amazingly U
significant for me I felt that the the experience of PR meditating was um I
some I used to call it like you have these I think it's kind of saltlike things I believe you put on meat to
tenderize meat to make soften it up that uh so maybe it's an unfortunate metaphor
but but I felt like I my heart was being tenderized um softened by the practice
of meditation in the monastery and um and I was amazed at um
there was places of respon respon responding to the world that was
not me responding it's not the usual Gil not how I knew myself but there was it
was it felt like an instinct or it felt like a completely [Music]
unintended uh Awakening of compassion of Love of wanting to respond to the
suffering of the world and this became so Central to kind of who I became who I
am that it wasn't even but it wasn't really me in the usual sense of the term
but it was more me than anything else could be me uh but there was no me in it
kind of and that was uh and that's where I wanted to base my life from and in
specifically uh uh the only thing that M made sense the only response to the
world that I had uh became um um uh responding with
compassion to the suffering of the world and that's where and I decided to devote my life to Buddhism to Buddhist practice
and U because I was in a Zen Monastery to become a Zen Monk and a Zen priest in
order to because that's the only way I knew to address the suffering human
suffering at its deepest Roots many other ways of addressing it that are very important but I felt like
I needed to be able to be because of the depth in which I had discovered I I felt
like it would be I I had to somehow try to respond from that deep place to the
Deep place in others and to bring suffering to an end and um and so that's
when I decided to become a be ordained and uh and that ordination was very
significant for me because it set my mind my my life certain kind of like a
commitment or a or or a or a um or a um
maybe commitment sounds like too much self in it but as a recognition uh clear recognition that
acknowledged or accepted the fact that this was what my life was about to
respond to suffering and um and that set me on a course that uh certainly brings me here
today uh so for the last uh over 40 years this has been my my
life to uh to almost 40 years uh to
dedicate myself yeah more than 40 years almost 50 years now that I just dedicate
my life to um uh to address to meet to care for to uh the suffering of the
world and in the process of it uh uh this many years of practice my
understanding of this deeper operating system that is love that is compassion
that is care uh began appreciating all the different uh uh aspects of it not
all I don't know about all but many different aspects many different flavors in which it takes and in different
circumstances different FL flavors different qualities of it get evoked get awakened and operate for for us
all and um so in terms of my core teachings then that uh this naturalistic
tendency has led me to this deep faith in or trust in or reverence for um this
uh um this this place within that
is is way too limited if I call it mine or if I say it's within me or Define
Myself by it uh it's almost like I get out of the way for this to operate to be
there and so I have as a kind of reverence for this a kind of sense of
that this is really almost sacred because it's not about me it's
about nature nature knowing nature and um nature relating to Nature Nature
caring for nature so um this is a core aspect
of behind my teachings core aspect of who I am and um and uh and I I
would I suspect that uh I would like it that or I believe that uh this is at the
foundation of what um motivates me for pretty much everything I
do so um so thank you for my chance to share
this and so be one more talk on this topic of my core teachings tomorrow
thank you