so hello and welcome and
uh I feel kind of delighted to be back at IMC and to be able
to welcome you all and feel your welcome uh to be sitting here and the
opportunity to share the practice with you
all and um when I was a
child uh sometimes when traveling with my family in a car was sitting in the back seat and i' love to roll if we were
on the freeway I would love to roll down the window and stick my hand out with my
palm flat like a like a wing of a plane and had and move my hand up and down
feeling the lift and the and the push down of um of the of you know the wind
uh and I just put me right there in the present moment I just felt like I was completely absorbed in this kind of uh
constant movement of the wind against my hand this morning I bicycle down to IMC
and there was part of the Time bicycling down especially coming down the hill
where there was kind of exhilarating feeling of just being fully present uh there was something about the
speed the being being carried the gravity that really uh put me into the
present moment Without Really any other cares except the exhilaration of being
carried Along by the bicycle so there's a way of
meditating uh which is relatively peaceful but puts us right in the
present moment so that it feels like in the present in the immediacy of now we're
being carried we're like riding the bicycle or being carried by a wave if
you've ever body surfed or um been carried by a wave
or in a there was a delightful place in West Virginia got carried Along by the
current of the river it was just such a wonderful feeling to be carried
along and uh to be carried along with a right in the present moment on the wave
of the present moment in in the west the Western culture the Futures often seem
to be ahead of us but there are cultures where the future is in the uh in the
back catching up to us and lifting us up into the into lifting us up as we go
along and all we can really see is the past and um which is somehow in this
kind of culture uh in front of us but the past which we can't see is lifting us up carrying along and this idea that
we're on a wave of the present moment and there's a way of exhilarating way of really being
here present for this moment riding that wave riding that Razor's Edge riding
right here and when I was going down in the bicycle down the hill today um there
were lots of things around me to see cars and trees and houses and things but
um those just all kind of receded receded receded I didn't stop to look at
them I didn't consider them I didn't get involved I just was there being being carried along down the down the hill so
there's a delightful way of being fully in the moment in this very little saddles sometimes has been called
a Saddleback of the present uh right there maybe the the um
bike seat of the present uh uh right there and um and allow ourselves let
everything else just kind of be left behind left behind just stay with the
coming the coming stay with the rising the what's lifting us up what's bringing
us into the present what's the wave of time so if this makes any sense uh you
might want to experiment for us for this practice this uh this morning and that
is that it's not simply being mindful because sometimes if uh mindfulness too
cognitive um we're uh we're behind the present moment we we take a moment or
two or three or more to recognize what's happening in ourselves and what's
happening is already changed very quickly and so the idea is to cognize or
be aware in the immediacy of now Carri it along Carri it along and many things
that we could know uh can just fall away Fall Away in as we stay knowing the
immediacy of now so and if this doesn't make sense to you or is confusing for you please by
all means just discard it and practice how you normally would so to um
begin setting set setting ourselves into this saddle seat of the present moment
that metaphor is used because it's kind of like a U-shaped and there's no clear idea of exactly where the present moment
is but it's a little bit includes a little bit of the future a little bit the past
perhaps or the surfboard of the present moment and surf
surfboards are little bit sticking out into the empty space in front of the
wave and a little bit of it's in the back of embedded in the wave and um a
little bit to be on a surf b of time is to have some sense of the the The
Emptiness inead of us the potential the openness in front of us of time and
little bit is kind of being carried by the path into the present in staying
right there balanced so placing ourselves here now
in this body gently closing the
eyes and with the eyes closed to sense and feel the present
moment experience of being in a body and to try to do it without
focusing or being preoccupied by any particular aspect of your body any pain
or discomfort or tension just going to be open to all the
body the full body
experience as if your whole body is a surfboard or the bicycle or
the hand in the
wind and then this whole body experience to take a few long slow deep
breaths relaxing the body as you
exhale long exhale with the extended
settling the weight of your body into here and
now letting your breathing return to
normal feeling your whole whole body and within your
body the influence that breathing in and breathing out has on your
body again not fixating on any particular way if the breathing is
uncomfortable or not to be preoccupied with
that the broad experience of breathing in the
back rib cage the sides of your rib
cage the shoulders deep in the belly
in this surfing on the present moment you might feel it sense it riding
the changing waves are breathing in and breathing out in the
body the inhale is kind of like catching the
wave the exhale is riding the wave being carried by
the momentum of breathing
out being lifted by the inhale
carried by the exhale to the bottom of the
wave right there with breathing is where to ride the present
moment perhaps letting everything else
recede into the background into the past that for
now it's okay to let all things be left
alone except rting experience or
breathing if it's possible not to focus on the ways that breathing
is uncomfortable but maybe there's an edge
of breathing someplace in your
body it let you feel a little bit like the kid with his hand out the
window the hand riding the wind
breathing in and breathing
out
e
e e
following riding the breath and all your thoughts are simply
scenery nothing to be involved in riding the breath riding the bicycle
letting the scenery Fall Away in favor
of writing the breath in the present moment here
now
e
for
for e
as you exhale
relax the
body relax into riding the wave of
exhaling as you inhale open up
release be open to the lifting and
expanding we're being lifted on the inhale expanding
did and relaxing and settling on the
exhale is to be right here in the
present with everything else just the scenery that passes by no need to be involved in
it
e
for
for e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to again settle relax on the
exhale softening the shoulders the belly the face
and perhaps even there can be a softening or opening on the
inhale relaxing and opening the mind on the E as you exhale and inhale
softening the thinking
mind and if you're gentle perhaps you can gently soften relax the
heart as you exhale letting the heart settle
and allowing the heart to open on the
inhale and imagine now coming to the
end that with an open hand an open mind an open
heart you're ready to meet the world to meet
others and to do so with Good Will with well
wishing wishing others well may others be happy and peaceful
and safe may my focus be a little bit less
on myself and more in the well-being of
others and may this be a way of caring for myself May each of you each of
us know that we care for ourselves when we have good will for
others may all beings be happy
may all beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and may how each of us moves
through the world support the well-being of others
[Music]
thank
you e
so good day everyone and welcome to the second talk on the characteristics of the
Buddha teachings the Dharma and the way that the chant that describes these five
characteristics begins it says the wells spoken dhama of the
Buddha and then it goes on and describes it as being the well-spoken teachings of the Buddha
dhama of the Buddha is uh directly
visible immediate inviting
inspection onward leading and to be personally experienced
by the wise and
um the um so these teachings of the
Buddha have these five characteristics and I like to think of these five
characteristics as being a kind of reverse engineering of the Dharma of the Buddhist
teachings that um somehow taking all of it Buddha teachings into account that um
uh if we can kind of get back to the basic principles basic orientation that uh the Buddhist
teachings are based on and um and these are all uh based
on five ways in which we are personally engaged personally involved with the
Dharma with the practice that it's not an abstract form of philosophy it's not
a abstract form of uh reflection and thinking about things um that can be
part of certainly a Dharma life but uh to really be involved with the Dharma
practice which is the Buddha what the Buddha was most interested in was pointing people to practice to the
degree to which he was a philosopher it was all for the purpose of getting people
into uh a deep momentto moment experience or practice that is
liberating and we see this emphasis on Direct experience One's Own Way of being
way of seeing and experiencing emphasized that the Buddhist in these
five characteristics of the Buddhist teachings the well-spoken teachings of the Buddha is something for each of us
to um uh uh directly see for
ourselves that it's immediate in our experience that it invites us these
teachings invite us to look for ourselves this is not a teaching to believe something to take something in
the abstract to uh trust someone else's uh uh idea of what's real but rather to
hear what what the Buddha say and inspect it for ourselves find out in our own experience what's
true and so for today the emphasis is this second characteristic which is aalo
in p and um uh and most literally
aalo the a is a negative prefix for and kalak is a time so not of time and and
uh some people translate it as Timeless and um and some people
translate it as immediate and both translations are good uh I prefer
immediate because it puts puts practice in the immediacy of here and now um I also like the word Timeless if
we understand Timeless to meaning that um it's still relevant today as much as
it was 25 200 years ago in the time of the Buddha that there's some kind of way in which the Buddha is pointing to a
universal characteristics or qualities or practices of the human being that
we're just as human as the people were in the time of the Buddha and some of
the same human issues that they dealt with then are what we're dealing with now the same need to find ourselves in
the present moment and resolve how we get caught and how we get uh tied up and
stressed in the present moment are as valuable now as they were in the time of the Buddha so in that sense the teachings
are current they're Timeless they're as relevant today as they were back
then and um so these two ways of translating alalo but I like immediate
because there's an immediacy to that there like okay here right now not
anywhere else and so there well spoken teachings of the Buddha point to
something that's immediately perceivable for ourselves here and
now and uh yesterday I mentioned that in defining in describing how the Buddha
how the Dharma has these five characteristics the Buddha says that that they're found in the ending of
greed hate and delusion in another place he talks about how we see the how it's
directly visible and immediate inviting inspection um in uh when we've abandoned
a certain afflictions and he lists 17 different ways in which we're afflicted
by emotions which have a lot to do with how we relate to others so uh when we
have uh lust and covetousness when we have clinging desire for others in
certain ways or we covet what they have or what others have or covet things um that uh if we have ill will
and and hatred if we have envy and jealousy if we have contempt for others
and conceit in relationship to others all these things are afflictive
emotions that humans carry all too easily but when we are able to let go of
those in the Letting Go the letting go even though it might seem like a slow
and gradual process to let go but when we finally let go the immediacy of that
experience of Freedom the immed medy of that possibility of living
without um these afflictive social emotions is
um um that's what he's pointing to the Dharma is pointing to that possibility
to experience this for ourselves and for some of us who can't do this immediately fully completely
there's the immediacy of doing it gradually to relax to soften to begin to
lighten up to not be so wrapped up in uh these afflictive emotions but to step
back and to see them clearly to uh make space around them to not be so
influenced or pushed around by them or trapped by them even to do it gradually
there's something about how we can experience that in the present moment in the immedi of now that is a powerful
teacher for us it shows us what's possible possible it shows us the the U
the possibility of a of a continual and gradual path moment to moment of
softening relaxing making space not being caught and so there's something about
seeing the Dharma in the immediate present that uh the Buddha is
emphasizing so it's visible here and now it's something that we can see and we we
don't see it you know in the abstract in the world out there we see it the in the immediacy
of our present moment experience to bring these two together is fascinating that it's directly visible
here and now and it's immediate in our experience um it's directly
experienced here and now immediatly in how we
see so uh it's directly visible but in how we see how we
view uh our experience we can experience the stress or the absence of stress we
can experience the fear and the hesitation and the absence of hesitation and fear anxiety we can experience the
ways in which we tighten up and strain to be aware to see to know something uh
and we can be aware of relaxing in having a relaxed Vision relaxed
knowing right there we can know in the immediacy of now the
Dharma and so we want to begin focusing on how we experience the world so even
if the experience of ourselves the world is uncomfortable to us how we experience
it is something we can change and adjust we can find our freedom in how we know
we don't have to change the world we can find Freedom in changing
ourselves and in changing ourselves we do begin changing the world we live in
if we're not in caught up in greed ha and delusion caught up in afflictive Social emotions that makes a world of
difference for others so to learn slowly step by step
here and now in the small steps and the big steps how to be free
this is how the Dharma is immediate so
um so you might as you go through the day today
um consider this aspect of the immediacy
of the Dharma what is it that you can where can you find
Freedom and how you're present for this life in the immediacy of your
experience and certainly I hope you begin appreciating how we don't find Freedom when we linger
in uh preoccupations linger in uh fantasy and thoughts and ideas and
projections of the future and judgments but there's something even more
immediate than those that where we find Freedom space
openness non- entanglement can you find it even in small degrees as you go through the day
and if you find it in small degrees here and now take that as a teacher take that
as a Way Forward even the smallest relaxation is a teacher for you smallest
relaxation points you to a Way Forward here and now in the midy of now to
greater and greater relaxation openness and freedom so uh thank
you very much and um look forward to continuing all this tomorrow