so good morning everyone
welcome and I find myself sitting here somewhat
quiet so
the background of our discussion meditation today is these four these 10
Reflections or 10 um foundational aspects of a human life
that it's useful to think about and reflect on and uh today the topic is
purpose and in relationship to purpose I would like to talk about
confidence that uh whatever our purpose is to do it
wholeheartedly to see that whatever we have to do in the
moment that what's important one of the one of the aspects of purpose is not the
purpose of the activity but uh the purpose of doing something
wholeheartedly our life is too precious to do things half-heartedly and even if it's a
mundane task even if it's a and not such an important thing that we're doing
seemingly uh that the fact that we're doing it is important and uh and so
to the doing the fact that we are have the ability the capacity to engage in
something if we're cleaning the kitchen that uh to not do it
half-heartedly but to there's something very profound about giving ourselves fully to the task at hand as if it's the
most important thing even if it's not so important in and of itself our ability to be alive at any
given moment and give ourselves to our activity that is
important and um so that is the um task
of the meditation is to give yourself to the meditation wholeheartedly
and
um and what would that look like for you to just this task to do it this is
the per for these 30 minutes the purpose is this is the purpose not to
strain to strain is to do things in a certain kind of way
half-heartedly because we're leaving out so much of who we are but to do it in a relaxed Way open
way inclusive way of all of who we are bringing as much as who we are here into
the experience there's purpose to that there's a way of finding fulfillment not
in the task we're doing but in how we do it the freedom we find to give ourselves
to it in a full wholehearted way
so to assume meditation posture and part of the value of
meditation posture is to do a posture that feels to you that you can now give
yourself to the task of meditation that you can you really can be present for it
in a nice way and um so a posture of attention a posture
of presence being
present gently closing your eyes and part of the purpose for closing
the eyes is so that we're less likely to be
distracted and we can give ourselves over to this Simplicity of just
sitting in Zen they use the expression for meditation just
sitting what are you doing I'm just sitting not thinking about other things
not thinking about what I'm going to attain and what I'm going to accomplish in meditation not uh thinking about what
happened yesterday not judging myself just sitting just sitting here
and in that expression just sitting in Zen is the idea of
a a wholeness a wholeheartedness a fullness of being here for this
experience that there's purpose to that there's value to
that so to have confidence in just sitting just being here with our
experience and taking some deep slow
breaths relaxing as you
exhale as you settle in relax into your body
let your breathing return to
normal and with a normal breathing continue relaxing your body in ways that
are easy there is a way in which relaxing
the tensions of the body allows us to be more whole
or in our engagement in meditation more more
of us can be
included here just sitting just
breathing there's a deep satisfaction in the body and the heart
and the mind to be fully involved in the task at
hand there's purpose to just sitting being present here and
now and through these next minutes to give yourself over to this purpose of
being here gently quietly without
strain willing to let go of whatever it takes
you way from being here fully In This Moment's
experience until you appreciate that it isn't the experience that's
important but rather the wholeheartedness and freedom that
comes with choosing to be aware with this now
for for
for
e
for for
for
when there is confidence or faith inspiration in the purpose of
meditation perhaps you can give yourself over more fully to the task at
hand there's value in a whole wholehearted relaxed
attention to Here and Now
for
for for
for e
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to appreciate that we have the capacity
to bring kindness friendliness to the people we encounter
in our daily life we have the capacity to bring
respect and attention and
well-wishing and then this is profoundly valuable for the people we encounter
and for ourselves in our relationship to
others that there's a purpose to
living with kindness and respect there's value and
meaning to live in a way that supports others in their
lives and thereby supports ourselves and so we end this
meditation preparing ourselves to go out into the world or encounter with other
people to do so in the foundation of
meditation to do so with kindness and Care respect and
well-wishing and so we say at the end of the sitting
as a way of expressing Our intention our purpose our
aspiration may all beings be
happy may all beings be
healthy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful
and may all beings be
free and may we in whatever way that we
can see the purpose live find purpose in these
aspirations so we contribute to making it possible may all be be
[Music]
happy thank
you e
so welcome to this second talk on the 10 profound
Reflections that we can engage in to live a Dharma life a spiritual life a
whole life and these 10 Reflections are not just good
for Dharma practice they're actually very important Reflections for any human
life because they point to the totality of profound concerns profound ways in
which we are animated we are we are motivated to live a full
life and so yesterday I talked about
meaning so today following up and closely connected to meaning is purpose
tomorrow will be agency followed by
autonomy and and then um identity and
dignity community and kinship and then healing and
Reconciliation so each of these is worth giving time to and so we're kind of in some ways going through these quickly
and over these 10 days we're meeting but I'm hoping it gives you a a
valuable orientation for how to think about your life and consider it so today
is meaning uh purpose today is purpose and as I said it's closely connected to
meaning that uh meaning sometimes um provides a sense of purpose for what
we're how we're living our life or in some large way but also the purpose for
the particular activity we're engaged in at any given time and um so even if we're uh you know
stopped in the gas station to put gasoline in our car that um uh you know
we could say what's the purpose for doing that well it's to put gas in my car and then we check it off we we
checked out and recognize the purpose but you can ask the question more deeply
yes but what's the purpose of having gasoline in my car oh so I can my car
can take me places but what's the purpose for that that's the purpose the purpose for that is so I can do the
things that are important in my life visit the people who are sick or go to work and be able to support my
family and what's the purpose for that and so the question what's the purpose
um there's layers and layers and keep asking what's the purpose what's the purpose until we find that uh maybe what
we're doing doesn't really have a import more a really valuable purpose sometimes the purpose just to
become uh wealthy or just become have uh promotions at work might seem very
important and drive a person's Behavior Uh day and night sometimes but um but we
really get down into the roots of our being our life so well that what doesn't really uh support us it does not really
so great uh to have that be the primary purpose of our life and um we go to the gas station to
get gasoline and what's the purpose there uh maybe the purpose is to uh uh you
know go pay cash with a cashier if we still do that and um and to have a human
interaction with someone and take the time to look at them and H you know say hello and see if what what what's
possible part of the purpose we could add purposes to what we do that uh and
and animate it with something of a really great
value but to reflect on what's the purpose of my life what's the purpose of
my work what's the purpose of my activity um am I imbuing it with the
purpose that's valuable and this relates to the Buddhist uh idea that whatever we're
doing um should be uh considered whether it's wholesome or UNH wholesome is it
beneficial or not beneficial is it skillful or not skillful is it healthy
or unhealthy that um and this idea of that it's wholesome means that not only is it
wholesome and valuable in and of itself but it also brings good consequence and so in Buddhism the sense
of purpose is uh to to uh is to do the
things that are consequentially beneficial so do they benefit my own
spiritual growth so how I stop to get gasoline how does this benefit my
spiritual grow growth um well maybe it doesn't really benefit it to do to multitask and to be on the phone and to
um you know uh pump gas at the same time what's
beneficial is to really have the stability and the calm and the centeredness to really just be there for
the activity of doing getting the gas and so it's a training ground for
presence for attention and and over the long term we're really develop veling our capacity to be here and present uh
so that we're not divided we're not distracted that something deep can well up inside we can develop the practice in
some important way or is it beneficial for other people what we're doing how we
pay a cashier uh what are does that have any benefit for them is the way we do it
I've had some wonderful conversations with cashiers in the Market Supermarket um especially sometimes I
like to or early in the morning when there's not a lot of people there and uh and then there's a wonderful chance to
have some connection um and I have uh I don't know if some of the cashiers remember me but I remember them and and
they're kind of have a warm place in my heart uh just because uh they're there early in the morning and and um and it
just had this wonderful nice connection and
um so the idea in Buddhism is to one sense of purpose is there's a path of
practice there's a path of spiritual growth that we can be engaged in and that's extremely valuable it's very
meaningful to be in a path to Liberation to Freedom Liberation from all forces
that are harmful all forces that diminish us us or contract us or um uh
move us away from a path of liberation of freedom of openness of joy of of uh
of generosity and so these are all considered wholesome things and to have
a s a purpose that we think is valuable that uh is motivating that gives us a
reason to wake up in the morning it gives us a reason to go to work for example that's not just to get a
paycheck but to do something more profound for ourselves and for others that whatever we're doing we're
seeing it as part and parcel of this profound found the meaningful thing to do which is to live a a Dharma life a
life that's on the path of practice the Buddha made a remarkable statement that uh inspired me very much
when I heard it first time and still does he said um uh do what is this is my
paraphrase do what is wholesome if it is not possible to do
what is wholesome I would not teach you to do what is wholesome but it is
possible to do what is wholesome so you know that it is
possible we can do this path we can cultivate ourselves we can develop
ourselves we can do what is healthy and skillful and purposeful and so to have a
sense of purpose that uh that has meaning that has value that has really
feel as important for us and so that when we go about our life we're
connected to this deep sense of purpose the sense of purpose also um is
a wonderful reflection to have when you're thinking about anything you're going to do make any decision and to ask
the question why do I want to do this what is the purpose of this activity is
this does this is the purpose really serve what is most valuable for me me or for the world around me what is the
purpose of this and many times we do simple things maybe or things which uh
are meant to kind of distract us are meant to uh relieve us us relieve of us
relieve us of some of our stresses and challenges and difficulties and that might be very purposeful and meaningful
to do but sometimes it actually takes us away from ourselves and actually doesn't
help us do the really important work that needs to happen in in order to heal a it needs to to develop it needs to
help us move into this world in a full and dedicated way and so to ask
ourselves keep checking in with ourselves what's the purpose of this what's the purpose of
this to add to that is there a purpose I can add to this yes I have to do this
and it's a drag but can I now imbue it with a higher purpose um because purpose
is don't settle for the obvious purpose getting gas I'm just getting gas um can
I abue getting gas with a higher purpose um what is it or or a deeper
purpose or whatever metaphor you like for this and um what is the purpose for
what I'm doing why am I doing it and to find a profound or important or a
valuable sense of purpose for our life is invaluable and it can be found any time
at all even if we're on our deathbed that um uh even there what's
the purpose Here and Now is the purpose now as I'm dying to
uh linger in my resentments about what happened 20 30 years ago is the purpose
now to worry about um you know the future that
I have no control over anymore because you know I only have maybe a minutes or
an hour left there is purpose to Letting Go fully there's now a purpose to a
possibility to let go in a deep full way to be really present here and now
without the the um extra of the tension
of past and future worries regrets uh anticipations dreams about
the future just here so fully that even the sense of dying disappears because it
just breathing just here now this is invaluable there's purpose to this kind
of freedom of being here for this so the sense of
purpose and um I've offered you some words of my own on this topic I don't
pres I don't present these ideas as I said yesterday as being the defense ative um discussion
about uh these 10 qualities we're talking about I'm just trying to offer
you uh some of my Reflections on it and what's valuable for me uh with the idea
that um hopefully it to be a catalyst for you to think about this for yourself
and maybe you'll come up with very different understanding for each of these 10 Reflections than what I've
presented but if my Reflections have prompted that reflection great I'm happy
for that and um because these are a really important part of the life and there can't be any kind of uh someone
else's answers to what these mean for any of you so to spend some time now for
the next 24 hours reflecting on purpose
what are the purposes that you live by what is the is there some kind of some
sense of purpose that's really foundational or fundamental deeper than anything else
something that's some sense of purpose that can animate any more obvious purposes any reasons
why you do things you can imbue it with a really deep life purpose or deep spiritual purpose for yourself and for
others so to reflect on purpose why you do things and uh and see what you learn
and keep asking the question uh well I have this purpose now what's the purpose
for that purpose why is that so important and just kind of keep asking that you know and see how deep you can
go or how you can go through the different lay levels and layers of your of your heart of your mind to see to
understand yourself better and better and if you have friends you can talk to or paper you
can Journal about this topic great take it as far as you have time and interest
to do so thank you very much much and uh
then tomorrow we'll do this very important topic of agency that's related
to meaning and purpose thank you