so here we are it's
Friday for some of us it's the morning for some it's later in the day might be
some for whom it's earlier as well I haven't seen people from the Pacific area but there might be
some off to the west of California
so let's uh let's sit together as we
do taking a posture that uh that supports being both awake and at
ease and taking a little time to scan the body breathing
into areas of Habitual tension or areas you feel tension now
even if they aren't habitual just breathing out and allowing
them to soften
and you might take a few uh deeper breaths really letting the in breath
expand the chest and the belly and then on the out breath just
letting go softening everywhere in the body that isn't needed
to keep you upright in a way that supports staying present staying
connected staying awake to what's arising within
your within you and in your experience meeting what's outside you as
well all the things that make up your life right now
it it can be useful to let this balance of uh wakefulness and ease be a kind of
Touchstone in the practice you know in our bodies and inner Minds that
balance just occasionally checking in not you know not
getting really obsessed about it tied to it but just occasionally checking in and
seeing is there a balance is there ease and alertness are they both there are
they balanced in a way that I can stay present to what's
arising right now and trust you know trust that you
have the discernment to see if if the balance is right in this moment if you
you know if it might be beneficial to ease up a bit or maybe to bring a a a
little more energy into the mind and body trust that you know what's
needed this kind of balance is something that uh that we need to attend to you
know no matter how long we've been practicing it's not just advice for
people new to practice we can always take advant AG of
it e
and as we sit this morning I invite you to practice in the way that is most uh most useful to you
or maybe keeping the breath at the center or some other sensation some
other aspect of uh of what's arising or opening to
everything that's uh that's coming up inside you
and then your contact with the environment temperatures and
sounds whatever feels most useful this
morning and as we sit no matter what we're attending to we can be responsive to what's going
on in the body in the mind we can we can check occasionally in an easeful way
not straining to see something but just noticing you know am I awake is there
awareness is there tension that needs to be eased in doing that if it can be done
with little effort and just noticing bringing more interest more
curiosity into um each moment that feels
uh like it could use it it's the idea of balance you know
staying staying alert staying awake to what's going on and at the same time
being in a in a as much ease as
possible as we sit and making the adjustments like
riding a bicycle noticing if we're leaning too far one way or the other it's it becomes
intuitive just making a little adjustment coming back to place of balance a place
of um being
awake being
awake
e
e e
so as we as we near the end of the the sitting period just uh checking again
again to see is that balance of ease and wakefulness of relaxation and alertness
is it still there in the body in the
mind invite it even at this late period
in the sit and just let that balance accompany you as much as you can into
what comes next into listening to the darat into the day as it unfolds and
into your interactions with others with the [Music]
world I notice the effect of
that world needs balance among many things it needs
[Music]
e
I just uh put the put the link in the uh in the chat again and I realized I I had
uh I rang the bell with the you know the zoom noise suppression still on so the
Bell didn't uh come through and then I rang it again so if you did hear it twice you know more power to you
so today is our our last day of the week
Friday and
uh and I realized this week I've offered kind of a lot of content um two lists
you know interacting that uh you know I feel they're really useful to to look at
together and I just I hope it hasn't been too much if it has I I apologize
but there's more today of course I've been uh talking about these six
qualities of the Dharma uh that are mentioned in a whole raft of suas and
that I've always found really inspiring it's a it's a list that I I like to look at again and again to uh and I feel like
it has become part of my practice just uh seeing the Dharma in these ways
so to to recap um the Dharma is said to be well proclaimed visible here and now
immediately effective inviting inspection aaso onward leading and to be realized
by the wise that's uh that's the sixth and final quality that I'll be talking
about today to be experienced or to be realized by the wise
Tabo vui hope I pronounce that
correctly so in the uh analogy that I uh I spoke up before that I once heard Gil
use about having a pebble in one's shoe as a example of
Dua uh the realization is obvious you know because the pain in the foot was
really obvious the cause was obvious and the remedy of course was pretty
clear but um it's not so clear or simple in many areas of life where where Dua
shows up
um often we don't recognize that there's pain in the situations and sometimes we
don't see the pain uh for years um it it
it sneaks up on us and when we start to practice the Dharma we see there are
perhaps attitudes in the mind just very subtle varieties of greed or aversion
that that have been causing uh you know a lack of ease a lack of uh peace um
lack of freedom in us and having an effect on others as well so things like
you know maybe anger or resentment anxiety craving for some kind of of sense contact you know craving for
a flavor or a substance or some kind of experience those can occur you know both
at very very uh intense levels and also very
subtly and uh and when there's an attitude in the mind like uh anger
resentment craving we may not see it we may not see it for a long time because we're looking
through it we're not looking at it we often use that that analogy of a fish
that can't see the water it's it's swimming in you know any attitude in our
minds uh it colors what we see we can go on and on in life
believing that we just need to get a handle on on some on our anger just
learn to be more patient and and uh if we can refrain um you know that it
appears to be very beneficial and skillful but uh and it is beneficial and
skillful but at some point if we're practicing diligently
we'll see that we need to look squarely at whatever is arising in our minds that
is uh obstructive some kind of hindrance some kind of defilement you
know and to become really familiar and really intimate with them not indulging
and not repressing we often use those you know in the middle we want to be in
between not indulging not repressing Dua is to be understood you know that's the
instruction for the first Noble Truth to understand aruka and if we get very familiar with
the obstructive mind States we might begin to get a sense um that uh that
those ways of relating to the world because mind states are you know they
affect how we relate to the world they become the the way that you know the flavor of our interactions with the
world that they arose as defenses against some some pain that we've been
unwilling to feel and then we can investigate more deeply into the pain we
keep looking we keep being curious and luckily in the in the Dharma
we have many uh tools to work with to become aware of of Dua and to release
it we don't just depend on one strategy another strategy of taking off our shoe
and removing a pble we might offer ourselves kindness
warmth we might just be able to see the conditioned nature of uh anger and
impatience for example and and that can be enough Enough To Let It Go just seeing this is not me this is not me
this is just something I learned maybe we see how attached we've been to a particular way of responding
you know that we've identified with being particular kind of person you know I'm a um I'm a judgmental person I'm a
um I'm a really optimistic person I'm a really impatient person I'm a some kind
kind of identification and when we see and recognize that well we see that you know
just because we've learned to behave and to act act out of a certain kind of
mental orientation it doesn't mean that's who we are it's just something we
we've learned gradually any reactivity in US begins to weaken awareness reveals that
what we thought of as our our character our personal ity the character traits
you know character traits they are just simply habits habits that we learned and
they they can be unlearned they can be
abandoned the last thing that uh Sheridan bless in in his essay on
performative literacy is a uh a capacity
uh to Monitor and direct one's own own reading process you know
metacognitive awareness so that's a that's a kind of a
um an interesting term metacognitive awareness so that's a it's a big big
term in uh in the education World um but it applies uh all across um the world of
thinking which is the world of humans I guess it's an awareness of how are minds
work how we tend to approach situations in life awareness of you know it
includes awareness of what we find easy what is more difficult for us mentally
kinds of skills that come easily to us the kind that that we don't that don't come easily to
us so to have that kind of awareness of how our mind works you know learning how
our mind works in the most subtle ways that's really at the heart of how we become free in our Buddhist practice we
see we see where we grasp and where we push away at base you know because those
are the sort of you know the base uh movements of mind um that get us in
trouble grasping and pushing away where there is H good discernment
we begin to see where there is good discernment and where we're driven by old habits where there's peace and where
there's stress and uh and gradually we incline our minds more and more in the
direction that doesn't have Dua in it to become skilled in practice each
each of us needs to be able to discern what where effort might be needed how
much effort that we we need to to apply in a particular situation and what are
this particular skills or qualities uh from the Dharma that would support our growth
so I mentioned um impatience U mentioned it a couple days ago it's one it's a it's one of my uh um
you know companions sometimes on the paath we we might notice that we're more
impatient or we're more easily annoyed than we'd like to be and and we can
apply antidotes to that you know we can take a pause we can cultivate more
patience we can practice loving kindness we can practice gratitude always useful
and we use different strategies at different times depending on what the external situation is and what's our
mental state our mood and attitude what do those seem to ask for in the
particular situation we find ourselves in the Dharma when when we come to learn
how our minds work we we just be we become able to use them in a more
skillful way way and by skillful I mean cusa you know wholesome what tends in the direction
of of uh the end of Dua rather than more Dua so sometimes you know just being
with what's going on in our minds and hearts with mindful attention is you know the wisest choice to uh to as an OP
as a a way of operating and sometimes we need to apply some kind of anid some we
need to take some kind of action and we as as our practice goes on we develop an
inner compass that uh that can keep us headed in the onward leading direction
away from what's unskillful what will ultimately lead uh uh away from from
dooka Dua for us or for others towards peace towards uh towards
care care for ourselves care for others care for the
world so it's useful from time to time to kind of evaluate our practice to see
you know are we just skating along Have We Become complacent um are we feeling like oh I'm
mindful enough my meditations are calm and pleasant so that's all that needed
or maybe we're straining you know maybe we're developing a tight mind feeling like we're not getting anywhere and we
really need to work hard at it and as a result not feeling any ease or
peace and if we have discernment as a result of coming to know our minds
coming to know the Dharma um we can uh
recognize that it might be more useful to practice in a different way to be more relaxed to be more
receptive we learn about how we respond to different situations and what's uh
you know what's the most for us individually what's the best way to
respond to each situation that we that we come across in our lives we each walk
our in own individual path no two paths are the same and as I
said before and is often said you know only we can walk our our own path the
Buddha can't walk it for us no one can walk it for
us so we come to know our minds we come to know all our strengths in all our
quirks and I think it makes a lot of sense to compare walking the path of
practice to its end to its uh its uh complete blossoming let's say to the
reading of difficult texts each one of us is a complex of so
many variables so many threads of conditioning going going back all the way to our birth you know or further you
know if if we're um if we CAU into the idea of rebirth we're all one of a-kind
Creations you know the Dharma is to be realized by the wise that's us only we can realize the
Dharma and realization becoming wise becoming the wise one who can realize it
is a result of walking the path we don't and we don't actually need
to understand the conditions that have given rise to who we are right now in
order to become free but by reading ourselves carefully being open to new
interpretations being willing to change our minds to try new behaviors you know
new ways of looking at our experience he hi Paso come and see for yourself we can
come to see beneath the major conditioning forces of our individual
lives we can become begin to see the commonalities that characterize all
Human Experience the in the Buddhist view you know anicha Dua
anata Inc constancy stress suffering not self treating the path as a long
exploration of what it is that makes up our inner lives it it takes us from the
purely Personnel into the realm of what we call wisdom in the in the Buddhist
tradition we don't become free by taking on beliefs about what life is all about
about who we are in the deepest sense we discover these things they reveal
themselves to us they become visible here and
now they reveal themselves to be immediately affective
itive when we approach our experience with focused attention with C curiosity
with willingness to start over again and again to be in the place of not knowing
to be in the place of of uncertainty of unwillingness to of willingness to
question our views to change our minds to be open accepting and of course to be
kind to come and see again and again that's that's our
practice All Along The Path as we practice and learn we see these qualities showing up these six
qualities well proclaimed visible here and now immediately effective inviting
inspection onward leading and to be realized by the
wise and as we continue I believe will all come I hope we will to the
conclusion that the Dharma is good in the beginning good in the middle and
good at the end I'd like to close um today's uh
darat with a poem from a PO a poet who I really like his name is John Daniel I
believe he lives in Oregon I think he's in Oregan poet he's a Contemporary American poet his poem is titled A
Prayer among friends and I want to share it with
you I need to put on my reading glasses see
it among under other Wonders of Our Lives we are alive with one another we
walk here in the light of this unlikely world that isn't ours for
long may we spend generously the time we are given may we seek a vision that serves
all beings may we honor the mystery surpassing our sight and may we hold in
our hands the gift of good work and bear it forth whole as we were born forth by
a power we praise to this one Earth this homeland of all we
love so that's that's a prayer for us my my friends may we enact our
responsibilities as thoroughly as we enjoy our Pleasures may we see with
Clarity may we each seek a vision that serves all beings may we honor the
mystery surpassing our sight each of us all of us may we see the Dharma playing
out in our lives and share what it gives us freely with
others it's been a a a pleasure a great pleasure to be with you this week and uh
I thank you for your attention and your kind words in the chat uh it's been a delight and next week May Elliot will be
with you and the week after that it will be uh Ying Chan lovely teachers so uh
until we meet again thank you may you be well