so there's a number of different ways in which we can talk about this uh path of practice this movement towards greater
ease and freedom there's number of different ways in which we might like
characterize what it is we're doing here like you know why we even have a meditation practice to begin
with and one way we could talk about not the only way but one way is this idea of
like coming home to ourselves like coming
home the sense of oh yeah I'm at home
certainly this idea that maybe there's some ease when we're at home we're
thinking about home not literally but uh metaphorically this idea of not only
coming home but also implies that like we're not elsewhere and uh I'll talk
about in a little bit more what that means to be elsewhere but instead this
sense of when I think about what it's like to be at home I'm thinking about you know wearing comfy clothes and my
bare feet just wandering around maybe I'm uh like like looking
for my glasses I'm often taking my glasses off at home and I'm like where are my glasses so you know things aren't
necessarily like uh quite as in focus and I don't know there's a certain
amount of ease there what does that mean to come home
to a place where there's a certain amount of ease and this sense of there's
nowhere else to go like there's not this sense that we need to be anywhere else
that uh it's that's just where we are and we're happy to be
there or maybe there's this other way that we can think about coming home is
this idea of like we don't have to be anywhere
else I'm sorry we don't have to be anybody else I know uh when I was working in
Corporate America I wore very this was you know back uh some years ago but I
wore very kind of like formal clothing you know just kind of like buttoned up uh definitely more than I am
here now uh often wearing suits or you know something like this and uh I couldn't
wait to get home like just take all that off you know and uh for my first Meditation
Retreat which uh happened kind of like near well anyway I'll just say so here I
am working in Corporate America and I my first Meditation Retreat was was a 10day
retreat and uh I had forgotten what it's like to spend 10 days just in sweats and
t-shirt shirts it was it just quite something like wow so just this idea of
coming home the sense of like sense of ease uh a sense of and not
having to be anybody else I was partly I was dressing that way at work because I
wanted people I thought they would respect me or I don't know exactly what ideas I had but you know they had to
look the part or people see me in a particular way or you know something like that
maybe we would also say that uh coming home is that we can express ourselves in
a way that feels whatever is the easiest for us maybe that includes dancing around
singing in the shower singing in the Shower dancing around maybe dancing and singing whatever we're doing but just
this way that we can express what we want maybe there's a
way and we speak differently at home than we do when we're with others or in
our professional roles or if we have if we're have professional
roles but maybe there's something that's uh really important about this idea of
coming home and that is this idea of safety of feeling safe and again I want
to talk about this uh metaphorically cuz I want to acknowledge and recognize that for some people being literally being at
home isn't a safe place for them are they emotionally or physically this is a terrible awful thing that
happens but is there a way in which we can feel safe that we can feel like we
don't have to be guarded that we don't have to be bracing
ourselves because there's something that definitely happens with a meditation practice as the mind and the body start
to settle with meditation either during a particular sit or just as we do more
and more meditation we start to become more and more sensitive to the ways in
which we are bracing ourselves or not quite at
ease this way in which we don't feel safe we don't feel like uh we can
be completely like let go and feel content with what things
are and then what often happens is in a in an effort to feel more safe maybe we
adopt communication Styles or just our way of being in the world where we're
kind have this little bit of uh we don't want people keep people at a distance
I'm thinking that's going to help us feel safe and instead that just contributes
to a sense of isolation and loneliness and dissatisfaction with our
lives so coming home to ourselves is a way of maybe recognizing the way that we
are showing up in the world and saying is this is there a way
that uh I can meet myself as I
am at this moment is there a way that I can meet
whatever is arising and maybe not only just meet it but can we meet it with a certain amount
of open-heartedness can we meet it with a certain amount of
ease and this is where um safety often Lies We tend to think that it's uh
having to be tough or it's uh having to
be um like I said maybe like separate from people in some way but you know the
truth is of course that human beings are vulnerable and so many different ways so
many different ways emotionally and physically right but this idea of uh safety is
about more about can we meet whatever is arising instead of trying to get
everything out there you know to be perfectly organized and
nonthreatening there's this way in which you know we don't of course we don't control the our external environment
nearly as much as we think we
do so why is it that we are if we're not feeling at home if we're not feeling
connected why is that like why are we like leaving home so to speak feeling
disconnected and part of it is just this idea that
um we have difficulties in life maybe we don't feel safe maybe we have some fear
maybe we have some unfinished business of the heart as Jack cornfields expression we're having some emotional
turmoil we're having some difficulties maybe there's some real legitimate
difficulties happening in our life terrible diagnosis maybe we uh lost a
job that we really liked or maybe there's some uh difficulties in our
relationships whatever it might be what often happens is we have this sense of
like oh I have to go figure this out and often this go figure this out is a sense
of like going out there and getting
something this so way in which we want to like I don't know read uh all
those books and not all of them but some of them in the bookstore remember bookstores that uh I still love
bookstores I'm one of those people that um that self-help section or you know
all those podcasts or you know go talk to this person that expertise or this
coach or that Mentor or something like this which is fantastic to do right we don't have to do everything alone but
there's also a mindset that can be about okay what whatever uh issue or
difficulty that I'm having I have to go out there somewhere to figure it out and
there's this way the figuring it out means that we're the going out there and figuring out is means we're all in our
head thinking thinking thinking thinking thinking thinking thinking trying to figure it out trying to solve it trying
to understand it better and there's this way that I just
um um kind of like imbue our thinking with this idea that it's going to solve
everything kind of like disconnects us from what we're actually
experiencing from the maybe there's some lonel for
example this uh which can feel like this heaviness sometimes like in the shoulders kind of like there's uh maybe
you know this uh not sitting up straight so much but can feel like this weight on
the shoulders or something part of the reason why
sometimes we don't feel safe is because we're feeling like um we have to hide parts of ourselves and we don't want
other people to see certain things about ourselves so there's a way in which uh
we try not to you know let anybody see some of the ways in which we feel
vulnerable but if we can just be with our
experience as best we can as best we can whatever it is we're
experiencing then there's a way that it feels like this connection with
ourselves this connection to come home so to speak and then we
don't uh feel so vulnerable it might be uncomfortable
feeling the loneliness for example the sadness the anger whatever it might
be might be exactly what we don't want to feel but there's this way in which
it's a sense of like arriving again instead of just being in our thoughts
because there's a way in which being in our thoughts is turns out to be a big uh
source of our not feeling like we're at home feeling disconnected from
ourselves feeling disconnected from others but this feeling of not being at home is so much about the thoughts that
we have about how we should appear or what we should be doing or oh the people
down the street are probably doing that so I have to do something to keep up with them or you know whatever these uh
stories that we have and to be sure these stories are
subtle it's not something that's obvious that we're saying to ourselves there's just this way in which
it's uh influencing the actions we do and
the it's influencing our actions or may like the way that we are speaking to
ourselves and the way that we're showing up in the
world so there's a way in which not only we might feel like we have to figure things out or maybe maybe it's even the
same but I'll use different words we just want to avoid we just simply want to feel comfortable so we're going to
avoid any of this discomfort and uh We've created this uh
society that has endless distractions have you
noticed it's amazing if you think about like media these days like all the stuff
that's available to just uh distract yourself endlessly if you want you can
do that and it's so easy sometimes I find myself uh want to look up a
particular YouTube video a particular talk I want to listen to and then before I know it I'm you know you know going
down looking all these little things like time ticks on and then I'm like oh
yeah so I've set a timer on my YouTube videos that there I guess my phone can do this it'll interrupt me and say are
you sure you want to still be doing on this this turned out to be very helpful otherwise I'll watch K kitten videos all
day or something not that there's anything wrong with kitten videos of course I happen to be a fan of them but
it's not how I want to spend my life energy so watching them but there's this
way in which where we don't feel at home just because we have a we want to avoid the
uncomfortableness or we have this sense that there's like so many to do this
like that are oh well I have to do this and take care of that and email this person and do that there's this way it's
so you know we can just be always busy busy busy and our life just feels like
one to-do list after another or maybe just one to-do list one
just giant uh to-do
list so that's part of the reason why we might feel a little bit disconnected from ourselves and maybe also related to
this I'm kind of like giving a list list so that maybe you can recognize what are some of the patterns for
you but maybe there's a way also in which we have this like The Grass Is Always Greener idea like we have oh the
next you know best thing is it going to be out there and so we find ourselves
you know kind of like ignoring or dismissing like what's actually
happening in our lives right now meanwhile you know our lives are
passing Us by we might be thinking like well you know
I I'll get uh connected to myself maybe we have this sense that we need to
attain something or acquire something as soon as I've paid off the
house got this promotion my kids have left or my grandkids are at a different
place or you know whatever it might be educational goals career goals these
are you know great supportive things but there's also a way in which we can use
them I don't know if we're we are not doing this intentionally so much but you
know as as as a uh justification for not really being
connected to ourselves so then this whole idea of
coming home to ourselves in some ways it doesn't even sound attractive because it feels like oh but then I have to asso
all these other things that are important to me my goals or is my things with my relationships my
professional life pursuing always feeling more and
more comfortable or entertained but there's a way in which
we can feel connected no matter what we're doing
and a lot of that if not most of it is about being connected to the felt sense
the physical body what does it feel like to be
sitting in a chair right now it doesn't take time just to let the
mind just like uh incline that direction and like oh yeah I can feel the pressure
of the chair the cushion against the body if you're using the back rest just feeling the pressure against the
back and there's a way in which if we can use some of these obvious
um indicators of the present moment that can help uh disrupt some of
the momentum away from the thinking mind here we go again I'm going to make
it maybe that's okay is that is the volume okay
we can disrupt the momentum of the thinking Mind by know connecting into
this bodily experience this is where the home is
actually we all know this our thoughts are always like in the p i shouldn't say always but are so often in the past or
in the future that's you know not our home so much the home is you know what's
being experienced and with this sense of ease and
safety but I also want to acknowledge that this whole notion that I'm talking
about like coming home can feel kind of like a let down
kind of feel disappointing like really maybe we started meditating
thinking that we're going to have these astral projections I don't even know what those are
so we're going to have some you know wild experience or something like this
and maybe there's this way in which you kind of want to be dismissive of uh what this ordinary experiences of being at
home literally or metaphorically but the truth is our life
is filled with ordinary things it's filled with ordinary
things so why not be present for it and we can find a certain Delight in
it yesterday I asked a friend to uh help me with the change the cabin filter in
my car never never having done this it turned out to be so much fun I
was like so excited like wow and partly why I was doing this because I thought I had mice in my car turns out I did and
uh there's a little mouse uh Nest there on this cabin filter come to find out
this is a common thing and if you put it on YouTube there's all these things
people take out their cabin filter just like I did I don't know it just turned out to be like such a fun
delightful simple you know little chore but it's like wow look at this okay I
have to come up with you know some I'm going to work with here but it was you know like I don't know I got to
connect with my friend he felt very happy to be able to help me he wanted you know was an easy thing for him
and so why not take Delight in some of these simple
things part of the reason is because um maybe we are afraid of if we have like
let down our the bracing or let down the guard or something like that that it'll be
uncomfortable it will be uncomfortable it will be there's no
avoiding it and that Buddha talked about this right he used this word Dua there is
Dua somehow when we hear this word we think like yeah that's talking about the big existential unst or really big
things but uh I like to think about it there's just this comfortableness
and I've discovered that I have so much more capacity than I thought I did to be
with discomfort and when I'm uh in the role of like a retreat teacher
and I'm meeting people who are on a Retreats and encouraging them to meet
some of their difficulties I see them I watch them discover how they have so
much more capacity to be with their ulties to be with their uncomforta to be
with their uncomfortableness much more than they imagined or
knew so there's there is this way in which we are often like running away but
we don't really need to there this way in which we might
think that all the answers and what we're looking for is somewhere out there and I'm doing this gesture with my my
hand out there and I'm uh saying this word out there but another way could just be we
have this idea that it's all in here it's all the mind that has this idea it's going to be out there and that's
really the experience of out there and you know how many thoughts do
we have a day countless they're just
thoughts it's going to be better out there if I worry enough it's going to be better if I avoid this it's and then be
better those are just thoughts those are just
thoughts but if we're actually home with this
experience turns out that there's this richness and this depth and not only
that there's a um a sense of being
grounded and a sense of okay I I I can see a way forward from
here whereas you know just thoughts lead to more thoughts lead to more thoughts lead to more thoughts and you can spend
your whole life doing nothing but chasing thoughts thoughts chasing thoughts but there's a way in which
we're when we're here there can be a start a sense of oh okay I'm a little bit grounded I can see how I'm going
this direction is not going to be so helpful but going this other direction I
think is going to be more helpful I'm using that word I think we have a sense what going to
be more helpful so it's and there's this way in which we
can meet our experience with warmth and care and often this warmth and Care is
coming from our embodied experience not from thinking thinking
thinking don't don't get me wrong thinking is important we need to do it it helps solve so many problems I'm a
big fan of thinking and if we have the notion that that's
the only way to solve things is we have to like non-stop thinking
then then our life is filled with this with this notion that okay just in
the next moment I I'll figure it out so the invitation is to come home to
ourselves so this kind of this coming home to ourselves in some ways this
meditation Pro meditation practice is a support for this process I would say it's a process I
know for me it certainly was a process of like orienting towards
ourselves but not only that to orient with some warmth and care and
compassion can we meet our experience with a
invitation sense of welcoming sometimes I talk about this
you know have our our experience as uh we see something that's uncomfortable not what we want can we do it in such a
way that we there's this gesture of opening up like come on in you can join
the party the party being whatever the experience is because what we start to notice with meditation practice is how
much we are pushing away pushing away pushing away I don't want this I don't want this I want that other thing over
there I don't want all these things and our life energy is often
spent with this pushing away saying
no saying no to things that are already there being experienced in some ways
that's like denying reality to be clear I'm not saying that
we should say yes to everything we do need to say no to some things we need to have boundaries and to say
no but this coming home to ourselves this like orienting towards ourself with
a with warmth and care you know bringing some of the heart into it softening the
sense of no and so I was pointing to
like the bodily experience you're feeling the pressure against the body but there's a way we can also do this
with any of the senses and like a what's being heard just orienting towards that
what are the sounds or the visual
field just seeing without having to figure things out or make them different
in any kind of way just a very relax seeing without necessarily looking but
just seeing hearing not necessarily without listening I'm sorry
yeah as a way to come home to ourselves and then as soon as we do that then the
mind and the heart have a place to rest and something different can unfold
maybe some new ideas maybe there's just a a sense of
catching one's breath so to speak a sense of more ease and that is part of
the coming home so this connecting with ourselves
in this warmhearted way it's not the it's not the same as
um like judging ourselves and saying okay everything's
good it's about just being with what is putting aside the whole judging we're
just putting aside that whole thing of good and bad and instead is there a way
that we can meet uh our experience and more with a sense
of yeah I'm having difficulties right now
what what can I what can I do here how can I respond to my difficulties with
kindness how can I respond to my difficulties with
care is there this way that we can come home to ourselves is in some
ways the same as welcoming ourselves all aspects of ourselves
sometimes there's these aspects that we're secretly trying to
disown but can we welcome all aspects of
ourselves there's this way in which this meditation practice really supports
this when we often have so much pressure to prove ourselves in some kind of way
some people even feel like they have to like prove they're they're even worthy you know to exist to be
here we have to prove ourselves that we are not suffering that we're capable or
we have to prove that you know I got it together I'll I'll get it done whatever needs to be
done or something like that there's a way in which meditation
practice when we just just sitting we don't have to prove anything to anybody
but just to sit simply with no one to impress including
ourselves this meditation practice allows that kind of like this movement towards
connecting to ourselves with this openhearted warmth and
care and to be open to whatever is
arising so this idea of coming home to ourselves is a way of
connecting with I would say the senses with the body with hearing and
seeing recognizing how so often we are separated from our thoughts sorry that
we are lost in our thoughts separated from our
experience and then just reorient to the senses as a way to come home to
ourselves maybe I'll stop there and uh open it up for some comments or
questions yes can we it's back here
I wonder it seems like some people in the world their outer circumstances are
so harsh how could they come home I mean like I read I just read this story about
a young girl in the Middle East she was raped and then the man married her so he
didn't get charged with the crime and she committed suicide and it broke my heart but I'm wondering it's like some
people were blessed with a middle class life in the Bay Area where some people their outer life is so hard how can they
come home so I yesterday the other day I
listened to a podcast about a person who is s s present sentence for life I don't
know what crime he committed and uh he told the story about
uh how uh he had been a very violent person and in prison the first 20 years
he was in prison it was a very violent life and then um he was able to
participate I guess this is at Fulon prison in this thing it's called a circling where people meet in this case
men in prison and they start talking about the truth of what's really happening with
themselves and he talked about it took another 20 years maybe no it wasn't 20
years I don't know how many years actually but it took a number of years completely transformed his life
the way that he understood himself and all the way that all the abuse that he had had as growing up is why he ended up
having a life of crime and he ended up um being uh
released from prison because they had noticed what a what a different person he had become so I don't know if
everybody can do this I want to think so but he talked about uh that uh it was he
it was the courage to meet what was inside of him and not only that the
courage to meet what is inside of others I felt really touched by this
this idea and so he talked about that he um if you were to look at him he he do
doesn't look like he comes from a middle class he doesn't look like those of us in this room I would
say and he said um if you were to look at me you wouldn't think that um I'm
necessarily the uh safest person but he said but I am the safest person anybody
will ever be with because I have no fear to be vulnerable I have no fear to be
with other people's vulnerabilities and empathy and whatever they might have
I don't know I just feel really touched by this so what you described is just awful right it's just like
sickening but I think that we underestimate
the I want to believe that we underestimate the power of the heart the power of transformation that's
available I want to believe
that thank you for asking though I mean these stories really they're they're heartbreaking they're really
heartbreaking
yeah anybody else have uh something they'd like to
say I like that feeling of coming home do you want to use the microphone here oh that's it you like the feeling of
coming home yeah yeah yeah thank you they may be up
here yeah thanks for the talk tonight um I appreciated it and um especially so
the idea of coming home and it's really just a comment I think what I'm taking away from it and what I want to do going
forward is catch myself whenever there's the
senses I find myself doing this is there's also thoughts associated with them very hard to just sit there you
know feel things or hear things and not have thoughts and so what I want to do
and I don't know if this makes sense but try and just not have the thoughts while the senses are happening so yeah I you
know I would uh I would look at it a little bit differently this idea of not
wanting to have thoughts that's a really high bar instead why don't we just let
them be in the background thoughts doing what thoughts do and just uh be more tuned into sensitive to experiencing the
senses and let the thoughts just do what they're going to do because they have a lot of momentum behind them and we have
a LIF time of fueling them and thinking this is the way forward so instead just
to like just pay attention to the visual field or hearing and this and there's a
way in which the thoughts they start to just just lose some of their Authority they'll just naturally start to lose
some of the momentum if we just aren't highlighting them or giving them
as much attention because if we're trying to get them to go away there's this way of like oh go away thoughts I
want them to go away and then we're all tangled up in the thoughts and then we're thinking that we're thinking I
wanted to get rid of thoughts and then that's a thought again and then that's gets complicated so I I just to offer
this yeah
yeah does anybody else have a a
comment how about to up in the Peggy up in the corner up
there um this idea of the friendly meeting ourselves and what is
with friendliness when um when difficult things come up and I I think of that and
it's but I'm so reactive and it's going like round and around okay what does this mean to be friendly and
um yeah so I I don't know if you could say anything about that you know I try
to think how I would meet a friend and um you know it's just like oh but um it
you know it lasts a while so it's it's tricky for me yeah do what
lasts a while the the my reactivity I guess I see yeah I see so I would say
actually being with the body or like feeling your feet on the ground is a great way to kind of like dis disrupt
the momentum but what will happen it'll be like thoughts feet thoughts feet thoughts feet thoughts feet thoughts
feet feet feet thoughts feet feet feet so it it's not like something that is
going to go but it does it act it can really disrupt the momentum of them if
you can remember the thing I forgot to say is a
lot of times there's someone in front of me I see like that I need to kind of I
would say that's even more so the reason to be tuned into one's feet to like I'm saying feet but like feeling your feet
on the ground so that you're grounded because often what happens is when we get triggered then we're
thinking about other things or what am I going to say or I hope they think this about me or don't think that about me
and the last time I spoke with this person and we're not really uh maybe meeting them in a way that
uh that they are feel like they're being felt or actually maybe I should ask you
is it uncomfortable for you because this is somebody who is saying harsh things to you or is it just yes or perhaps
they've stopped but I'm still in a position where I some sort of response is
required yeah or I guess I could run away walk away I don't know um you could
say I I I'm not quite sure what to do with
that I appreciate the honesty right cuz that's the truth and then you there's a
way of like okay you're coming home to yourself this that's the truth of the moment I'm not sure what to do with that
or wow that that was that was that was a lot that's a good way to put it yeah cuz
sometimes I'm not even sure if it's harsh it might be like a trigger for me so yeah or you could say wow I I I I'm
feeling a little unsettled now I'm feeling triggered just a simple sentence like
this you know kind of the honesty of the moment and then that's a great one yeah thank you
you're you're welcome Peggy and then I think this person right here that's I'm on the step
yeah well just real quick coming back to the home
um I guess in my case having a toddler and parenting and the whole
jumping up everything day is different Discovery but then we had this pause uh
my wife and I decided kids's going to be with the grandparents and we're going to have
three days where it'll be just the two of us and all these thoughts are going in our heads for like couple weeks say
oh we'll go out for a date or we'll go to a movie or we'll do all these other things and yet when it came to the time
it was to be home to make some tea to be in the space to
think about very little things or just the things that grounded us yeah and the few
simple things that we might take care of that gave us
that might have negative energy we wanted to take care of or some positive
energy things that might and I don't want to go into L specifics of that but
we sort of naturally came to that place because all the busyness all the
thoughts all those things we know will come again yeah they will be there and they'll be all those surprises
and all the joy and Discovery and the suffering um they will still be there
but uh we recognized that that was the place to be and that seeking for
everywhere else you wasn't there for us yes I've
had a similar experience not with a toddler but this idea of like you know what it just feels good just to sit here
and uh read this or something yeah thank you thank you okay so it's uh 8:30 so thank you
for your attention and I wish you a wonderful rest of the evening thank you