so good morning again and uh I was saying that I'm feel
kind of delighted to be here partly from having done the half an hour walk from my house to IMC in this uh wonderful
clear cool morning there's something about
uh um the Simplicity of walking in the early morning
and having Many Things Fall away and just being
here and breathing the cool air and the Simplicity of just being that is a
delight so to prepare for this meditation um if
someone uh keeps their hand tight in a fist for a long
time and then somehow or other they have the occasion for it to un to
relax uh it can be a tremendous relief and that relief can come with a surge of
uh kind of J Jo Joy or Delight or that is just uh uh almost distracting from
distracting us from our distractions pulls us away for a little bit from all
the concerns we have and preoccupations and the the thoughts that may be ideas
that were causing us to tighten up the f to begin with and uh it's almost like for maybe a
second or two it's like being on a slide and sliding down and everything kind of stops for the purposes of just you know
wishing down the slide and and uh so there's the relief and
maybe even Joy of everything being letting go of everything so as we do this
meditation um let go just let go of
everything let go of anything you every time you let go of your thoughts look
for the relief look for the the moment of Joy the moment of being on that slide
ah as you exhale there's a kind of letting go and there and I sometimes
particularly feel like there's a slide is kind of as the the sensations in the
Torso in the chest in the belly and diaphragm of releasing the the breath gets
released and um and uh the inhale too can be a
letting go if you let go into the uh into the breathing in the body breathing
in uh let go of preoccupations if there's physical pain
as you sit and ache uh maybe you can't let go of the pain but maybe let go of
the resistance to it or the aversion to it if there's desire for something maybe
that thing you don't let go of but maybe the desire for it for a moment or two can be let
go let have letting go be what you do on this
meditation that every time you be with a breath you've let go of
thoughts but as you do so see if you can enjoy it find the relief
and if you're straining and trying too much to meditate or to follow these instructions maybe the relief in the the
Delight can come from letting go of these instructions and then continuing to
meditate letting go again and again and again but see if you can find the relief
or the enjoyment that somehow um keeps you
contented here and now in the present moment with your direct experience
now so let go
enjoy and if you whatever you might need
to let go of you might have to turn the attention back some deeper
way into the mind to find out where the stage director is off seemingly off
stage commmentating judging coming to conclusions and maybe letting go is
bringing the stage director on the stage so it's seen
clearly and you let go then let go and enjoy let go and feel
the relief
and don't make anything big about this if you're able to let go don't let start thinking about it let go again and
again so assuming a meditation
posture gently closing your
eyes and in a moment taking a deep breath and relaxing on the exhale
before doing that what is it that you can release physically mentally
emotionally what can you release as you exhale so taking a deep
breath and letting
go taking a deep breath and letting go into the body into the present moment
here and after taking a few long slow deep breaths and
relaxing see if you can ever so slightly enjoy now letting go of breathing
deeply letting go of that
effort and breathing in a normal way on the
exhale maybe there's a relaxing in the body relaxing in the mind that is a form
of letting go too enjoy it
the Deep breath and just breathing in breathing
out is there some releasing of thought or the grip gripping to
thought letting go of thoughts and letting go into the
breathing in a way that's a relief a
joy you've probably spent enough time in your life thinking it can be a
relief to let go for this few minutes of your preoccupations in favor
of the joy of Letting
Go Here and Now
for
e e
e
for
e for
perhaps it's useful to let go of
[Music] whatever's caught your
attention whatever you're caught in at every
exhale maybe it's letting go of physical tension in your body
or letting go of the aversion
or to the tension letting go of
thoughts or letting go of being bothered by your thoughts
maybe Letting Go takes a form of
softening and as you let
go notice the
relief or the joy of Letting
Go however slight it might
be
e
e for
e e
and as if when you let go
if you feel any relief or Delight in letting
go allow yourself to have a ever so slight
smile turning up the corners of your
lips just enough so there's a kind of delight in your face
and keep keep letting go with every
exhale maybe with every
inhale and let whatever Joy or relief that
is in that Letting Go let it be registered in your
body your heart
let it be like a wind of
wellbeing that blows through your very being
and as we come to the end of this sitting may it
be that the joy of Letting Go allows us to be more present for
others in a way that appreciates
them where we take the light in the loveliness of other
s or where our joy and our
wellbe is the manner by which we through which we see
Others May we bring joy with us into the
world and in so doing
maybe may we be the conditions to support the well-being and happiness of
Others May all beings be
happy may all beings be delighted in feeling
safe may all beings
be free of their
suffering may all
beings let go enough to
experience the appreciation
the respect that you might offer
them may all beings be happy
[Music]
thank you
so so welcome to this fifth talk
on where I try to offer the a description or explanation of the core
teachings that I base my rest of my teachings on the kind of the foundational
teachings and maybe what uh you know in some ways animates or motivates me to to
teach so um so review what we that I've done
this week so far that um I I place the uh
attention sensitivity to suffering and the end of suffering at the center of
the Dharma that I teach that um the possibility of ending suffering the
possibility of meeting suffering in the world and oneself uh in a deep way is one of the one of
the most profound things that I know a person can do that they're many wonderful things to do in the
world but I believe one of the most fundamental wonderful things is bring
suffering to an end and either for oneself or working to support others to do that and um and that uh then whatever
other wonderful things we do we do in ref reference to that freedom from suffering and then it makes everything
else more meaningful or more more valuable because uh it conveys then that
possibility for others as well and that
um and that that uh end of suffering is supported by not holding on to any views
any fixed views that there's a freedom from use and certainly human beings do
tremendous amount of projecting onto others onto reality onto themselves of
Concepts ideas judgments and bias and we do that with our religious practice
spiritual practices as well and one of the key qualities of the kind of Buddhism that I really kind of uh
oriented towards is uh not holding on to any views uh as being ultimate religious
views this is the even the idea that this is the truth is a kind of um uh
dangerous kind of territory that lends itself to one more view to put on top of
things and um certainly there are understandings and perspectives that are
invaluable but there's a way in which as we practice goes deeper that we rely
less and less on perspectives less and less on views and interpretations and even Buddhist
teachings and um ultimately we need to be freed of Buddhism
too and then uh to uh um the
um the um the naturalis naturalistic aspect of
all this that by the absence of views uh there's a way in which we're being very
present here and now that there is a natural unfolding there's a natural way
in which we operate and um and and that we can stay close to we don't have to
rely on things that require views including views of the supernatural or things we can't know directly for our
own experience so this this direct connection to direct experience because
it's not just direct experience in and of itself but direct experience is a medium through the Natural Healthy
processing unfolding evolving of our heart our mind our spirituality our freedom can
occur and so we want to stay close to that and part of that uh naturalism that
we stay close to is a natural capacity for positive emotions positive social
emotions that involve care care itself compassion loving kindness um empathy
for empathy that this is part of the Awakening of that happens in Buddhism
The Awakening of the sensitive heart Awakening of the heart that can be attuned to the welfare of others to the
suffering of others to ourselves but to do so without being distressed without
being troubled to without being caught up in views of self and others and
meaning and victim and and uh even the views of responsibility and obligation
to others there's a radical way in which the we're setting free this beautiful
human sensitivity that can inform us and guide us and motivate us that is part of
the naturalistic movement not the the projected movement of responsibilities
obligations should shouldn't uh good person bad
person and and so the and so as the sensitivity to suffering
deepens uh so it does to ourselves and the remarkable thing about the path of
Liberation is that it becomes a more and more subtle uh sensitivity to uh suffering
which at some point doesn't be really you can't really call it suffering anymore maybe in the in the way that
popular world thinks of suffering as big big St big things but it's becomes a
very subtle very deep stress or tension that we carry deep in our psyche deep in
our in our minds that underlies everything that we're also addressing in
the path and then we come to today where uh the one of the fundamental orientations
I have in teaching is that there's Liberation and a path to
Liberation and that that the path to Liberation is a naturalistic path that
unfolds it opens up that shows itself as the mindfulness as the stability as the
concentration this steadiness of the heart and mind becomes deeper and deeper
that um we can feel that onward leading nature to the end of
suffering and um and that there's a call there's a motivation there's a a desire
for that end that it's not a projection that's not a attachment but a completely
naturalistic desire that uh is he healthy to adhere to or healthy to go
along with and um and so in this naturalistic way that I like to teach or
like to understand I use a very physical uh ordinary example that uh could be
seen as somewhat reductionistic or materialistic even but it's speaks to the naturalism naturalistic nature of
what happens in this deep kind of path of Liberation and that is uh the example I
often like like to use um is to hold on tightly to your fist really to hold
tightly on it and um and if you hang on to a tight Fist and do a really good job
with a tight fist like like almost so like your hand's going to go numb or it's going to hurt without without
injuring yourself and uh what you'll start feeling uh is a natural tendency to
relax the grip so if you can do that if you want to do this as an exercise um to
really like do a good job like you're going to NE you're proud of how well you can keep that hand constantly tight and
then I'm going to tell a story of uh how in Ancient India there
was a way of catching monkeys now it turns out that monkeys apparently love
sweets so a monkey Hunter would uh cut out a carve out a slot in a coconut
carve out the inside of the coconut enough to put a candy in it and so the
monkey and then you tie the coconut to a tree the monkey comes along and knows
the candy is in there and can only get the hand in through that slot by having the hand flat and it goes in and and
holds on to the candy but then the hand is kind of bunched up and now it tries
to pull out the hand and it can't do it and it doesn't want to let go of the candy and it can't get free of the
coconut and the coconut is tied the Hunter just comes along and picks up the
the monkey and it's caught so as I told that story were you able to maintain
that tight fist were you a little bit distracted by me and by the story and if
you were then you probably felt a little release You Can Let Go Now of your fist if you'd like a little release of uh
Letting Go the natural tendency of tension of holding on tight in the muscles is that muscles want to relax
and let go go so whether it's physical tension or emotional tension or mental tension the
nature of that tension is to want to relax and maybe I'm anthropomorphizing a
bit to call it that it wants to let go but that's the onward leading nature of it it has the nature it has the
characteristic of of it takes energy to keep it going and so and the energy is
tiring to keep expanding so the movement is towards to letting go of any
tension all suffering comes with tension all suffering comes with a certain kind
of work believe it or not and so as that we can feel the work we can feel the
tension and how it there's almost like a desire to let go to
release and um and so that's the path of Liberation opens up through being
sensitized to this and seeing and following the the the movement towards
us deeper and deeper letting go and uh it's what our system our whole
psychophysical system most wants more than any other
desire and um and what we find is that that desire is a natural desire it's a a
desire that comes without tension desire that and I call it again this reductionistic way the biological
imperative to liberation and in the process of uh uh my own
practice and my own path of Liberation um I it's made a huge impact on me how
deep and thorough the possibility of freedom from suffering can be that the Buddhist teaching that there's an end to
suffering this is real it is possible to end suffering and uh the completeness the
fullness of that's possible uh has taught me that even though sometimes it's
temporary uh and suffering comes back afterwards uh it's a radical transformation to experience that uh
even temporarily this very full complete letting go that this tradition points to
as possible and that that becomes then the guide for all the rest of this that
uh yes there is uh uh it's important to address suffering directly and to uh
bring it to an end yes views no matter how subtle get in the way of the deepest
letting go that we can do yes this is a kind of a natural
process we're involved in that we cannot um orchestrate that we cannot in the end
uh uh make happen and uh yes this natural desire
for end of suffering is is a deep form of care deep form of compassion and love
and yes there is a path yes this deep deep Liberation is
possible and uh and uh and so this is
what uh underlies in the background of what I teach and uh there was a time before we
kind had to remodel IMC that in the wall opposite with it where I sit teaching
there was a for the teacher sake high up in the wall was a synonym for Liberation
uh reminding that me reminding teachers that all the teachings are in some way or other are moving in that direction as
well and um and that uh this is what uh this is
about and um and everything else in Buddhism I'd like to believe um is an
extension of this or Builds on that is founded on this uh and
um and I operate under the I teaching that that this is really a worthwhile
goal for the world that we don't just do this Liberation for ourselves that um we do it uh to benefit
and support everyone that some of us need to take this path all the way to the end so that
everyone sees that it's possible there's hope there's possibility it we don't have to keep living in a
world of strife and animosity and greed we don't have to always kind of be
caught in ourselves and kind of building up the self or protecting yourself in a certain kind of way there's a radical
Freedom that is possible that uh that um we can
experience so that it's kind of equivalent to the airlines who say put
on your uh air mask for yourself first and then uh help
others so um so I hope that these uh teachings
have been useful for you to understand at least me and what's underneath my teachings and um and uh I'm very
grateful for this opportunity to teach this way and let you know and very grateful for all my opportunities to be
able to teach I feel so fortunate that um that uh I have these opportunities to
share something that is so profound for me and something that allows me to um to
give expression to my care and compassion for this world that we live in so thank you very much