so good to be with you all um and those who are here in IMC and those who are
online also and so very delighted to be here um
I want to share some Reflections today that's inspired by uh what Gil offered
maybe uh couple of weeks ago um where he spoke about um kind of this natural
unfolding of a Dharma or use the term naturalist
Dharma and I've been reflecting about this a lot uh recently uh inspired by
what she he shared and in my own practice and so I want to offer
something uh based on my own Reflections and learnings with this and there is an
interesting sutta I would like to bring in this is a poly Canon text
um and this is in angut nikaya uh 10.2
for those who might be interested in kind of looking it up and the sutta described a kind of
natural flow U of the Dharma and that started from Sila or the cultivation of
ethical conduct and that leads all the way to Awakening and so I like to read the sua
it's actually quite evocative when I read it uh
first and the translation is based on um
uh uh banti su's translation and it's called making a
wish so here it is practitioners an ethical person who has fulfilled ethical
conduct need not make a wish may I have no regrets it's only natural that an
ethical person has no regrets when you have no regrets you
need not make a wish may I feel Joy and the poly term is
pamoja it's only natural that Joy it's only natural that Joy Springs
up when you have no regrets when you feel Joy you not make a
wish may I experience Rapture and the poly term is pity for those who may be
um familiar with it it's only natural that Rapture arises when you're
joyful when your mind is full of rapture you need not make a wish may my body
become tranquil it's only natural that your body becomes tranquil when your mind is
full of rapture when your body is tranquil you
need not make a wish may I feel Suka or Bliss or
happiness it's only natural to feel happiness when your body is
tranquil when you feel happiness you need not make a wish may my mind be
immersed in some body or concentration it's only natural for the
mind to be immersed in somebody when you feel happiness when your mind is immersed in
somebody you need not make a wish may I truly know and see it's only natural to
truly see and know when your mind is immersed in
somebody when you truly know and see you need not make a wish may I become dis uh
disenchanted and dispassionate it's only natural to
become disenchanted and dispassionate when you truly know and
see when you're disenchanted and dispassionate you need
not make a wish may I realize the knowledge and vision of a freedom
it's only natural to realize the knowledge and the vision of a freedom
when you are disenchanted and dispassionate and so dot dot dot and and
so the Su ended with this and so practitioners good qualities flow on and
fill up from one to the other U from going from the near shore
to the far Shore and so that's the sutta of making a wish
you don't need to make a wish when I read
this I feel myself both um very happy about knowing this
and at the same time like really really is this really like
[Laughter] this so um some of you may be familiar
with another sutta that kind of have a a a similar kind of flow there's a a kind
of unfolding that overlaps with this one to a big degree uh it's the teaching on
liberative dependent arising and it didn't start with a CA
but it started with uh some different um aspect of the the Dharma and then it
also unfolds on just kind of like like this very naturally towards Liberation
and freedom so how is it this possible uh
like this Le for most of us a Dharma practice
doesn't feel that natural as I was reflecting about my own
practice you know lots of ups and downs and and it's bumpy you know and um lots
of Zig and zags and sometimes you feel like you're taking one step forward and three step backwards so so there's all
this range how do we understand this kind of natural unfolding of the
Dharma and so I wanted to unpack this a little bit and I like like to
distinguish uh with two words the word of normal versus
natural what is normal and I looked up the definition a little bit and and
natural seems to mean that it's something that confirms to a certain
kind of a standard or commonality and so other words that we
often use and that are kind of like you know normal is usual you know it's
regular something like that and so it's normal that we stop at the TR traffic light and red light that's kind of
normal we all behave like this and that's the norm of the society and uh it's normal that we line
up in the G grocery line to go through the checkup counter and that's normal
right and there is a kind of a normaly to it a norm it guides how we behave uh
in some way um within ourselves and in the society and natural
um natural is a little different natural comes from this word
nature uh it's a kind of quality that's manifesting
or uh expressing itself according to the nature of
things and kind kind of have a certain kind of alignment or harmony with the
nature of things so it's nor it's natural that we're born
and then we'll die and that's the nature of life
um and uh it's natural that apple trees
grow apples that's the nature and I as I was sitting here today
this morning I just kind of vividly uh realized when we sat for a while and
kind of all the walking and the movements and the sounds settles down
all it's natural becomes quiet when there's not a lot of movements and doing and it's natural to
quiet down and so that's the nature of
things um sometimes what's natural is also
normal and just like this uh you know some part of us know that we're
born will age and we die eventually and so that's kind of normal some part of us
knows that and and yet um also a lot of
times what seems to be normal is actually not necessarily
natural let's take this birth and aging death as an example again
now even though some part of us knows you know that's the nature of
life but if we look at our uh Behavior how we
manifest in how we relate to this nature our normal behavior often does
not match to the nature we don't like
aging we don't like death and um most of the time you hear this a lot and the
various people said this we live as if world would never die and that's truth that's normal way
of how sometimes a lot of times how we live you I noticed when I just sat down
today I didn't not bring my glasses and I looked at oh my I don't need the I'm
going to read this pages okay and then some part of me had this you know um I
don't like it kind of this moment of feeling and that's the normal thing I
don't like what actually pretty natural for us to eyesight deteriorate and deteriorate
and all that but when we're are seeing it we can begin to see
oh and there is this part of normal uh habitual
tendency to not liking it and it can Harden uh for a lot of us
the when we're not noticing it that we believe that is the normal
way you know it should not be happening you know this this shouldn't be here or
um our loved one p passes
away um it's hard for us and uh we really
wish that would not be the case yeah that's kind of a normal
behavior normal tendency of our minds and
hearts and so this behavior and manifestation can be normal but they
actually don't reflect the nature or the natural um unfolding of our lives and
because of that often there can be a kind of inner
tension between the two and I like to
say this inner tension is actually good
news this inner tension itself um
uh carries and this aspect of us that
actually is aligned with nature and a aspect of ourselves that did not want it
to come together uh in some kind of harmony with the nature and so you know that's a hint as
the way how we might practice with this is this may be a good news a worthwhile
to uh explore and not to uh dismiss right away oh you know this is painful
this is not good I don't like it um so and in reflecting about this
and we can see there can be a a host of
seemingly normal ways of relating to ourselves or relating to the world that
actually leads to Dua or leads to suffering and often this kind of
seemingly normal Behavior Uh tends to arrive arise under
a lot of influences of um underlying great hatred delution and that's kind of
the three poisons that the Buddhist teachings uh point
to and instead um of enlivening us and this
kind of a forces when we operate in that mode they tend to take a lot of precious
moments and energy away from us um uh there sometimes at times I would
feel that they're actually deadening uh far more than what we
think I want to use some examples of this um for example
when our body and mind may be distressed whether it's because of
physical pain or emotional pain or mental pain um there can be a normal
Tendencies uh that come up and to try to fix them get rid of them or being scared
about it or being frustrated even angry about it when we can't really do
anything and to to alleviate the pain and uh and then there also other
cases for example that uh remember my son is very
generous with his Praises of some dishes I make at home you know you know tell me
oh this is the best parak paneer I've ever had and so it's
great and I could feel momentary happiness but then at the same
time Bo there can be this sense oh look at me you know there a kind of uh
flowing happiness just tightens up and that becomes you know that becomes about
me and so there can be the all of this kind of normal ways that we
feel and sooner or later through our Dharma practice we can begin to see that
this kind of seemingly normal and habitual Tendencies are actually not
serving us not like a rubbing thoughts on wounds you know if we already have a
physical pain do we think um beating ourselves up
is going to help you know if we're already uh emotionally
stressed and we kind of kick up a big fixing a self-improvement project would
help not really right uh and yet that can be kind of a
norm that we go to
um and so um the big part of the Dharma practice is began uh to little by little
to see through this kind of a patterns that almost feel like
automatic and they are wired in in US somehow and we can begin to see through
this and say oh actually they are harming us
more than serving us and so we can learn to begin um to have different kind of
choices in how we choose to respond to the situation we're
in and so in a way uh we can say that our our Dharma
practice supports us to find the ways from following the norm and the Norms
that don't necessarily serve us and can this kind of a Norms that leads to Anda
and to become more and more aligned with the nature of our
being I'm not saying that somehow all of the normal ways of our manifestations
are problematic and you know lead to Dua that's not true and in fact there are
many supportive um uh Norms or the
culture that we live in that supports us to become more and more aligned with the
nature of our being I'm often reflecting kind of coming to a community like this
IMC uh that that um sits in the culture
of generosity a culture of kindness and when we kind of soak
ourselves in and that's very nourishing to our heart and mind it's in in fact
enlivening to to some degree for us and so our um and so I'm not uh
trying to to say that all of the norm Norms or uh normal way of a being um
is uh is an sort of an issue more
importantly um the invitation is for us to begin to be able to discern what are
the uh ways that we manifest that are supportive to us and what are the ways
that actually leads more harm and so I want to a shift gear uh to
talk a little bit about about how we do this you know we we know there are this
patterns that um manifest in us that often I would say it's not even just
within us we all know that many ways of Habitual ways of engaging in the world
um because it you know it feels normal to us it's also because it feels normal
of you know all around you know and it's normal to be living a very busy or in a
very competitive environment and uh and that's kind of a normal all around
us and how do we find our ways uh to come more more aligned or in harmony
with nature how do we do that and so uh Gil likened um this
process as a kind of a natural naturalist um practicing in line with a
naturalist Dharma and so in a way we're
learning um to be become kind of a naturalist of our own
being um in my mind and if you um think about the naturalists you know in the
wilderness the naturalist often have a a kind of a curious old open uh kind of
Discovery attitude in terms of exploring uh what's out there they not kind of in
a big rush to try to nail something you know they're in this open and learning
and receptive engaging kind of a process and that's the same way in terms
of this naturalist orientation within in our own
practice we're directing ourselves to begin to see being curious about what's
really happening here what is this tension about how does this manifest and how
does it unfold how do we get caught in the normal uh habitual uh Tendencies and how
do we become free and the Buddha Dharma teachings
ofer first this kind of um uh orientation for us to begin to learn to
to look in this way and I would say the mindfulness
practice being present with our own uh being is a big part of this and we're
learning to kind of really begin to see what's happening and the Buddha recognized that
uh in his time and and there are different kinds of a
people and in one of the sutas he spoke about um kind of four
kinds and there is one kind of um people that's set to go along with the
stream and those are the people who take part in chasing worldly Wings some of
you would know the eight worldly Wings the king and loss and praise and blame
and you know these are the things that we Chase and that's true uh in the
Buddhist time as well and in his time that seems to be
the norm because that's the stream people follow along so so there is this
um uh this kind of a person that follows goes along with the stream and um
I remember just reflecting about my own experience for a long while I bought in
in those ideas you know and I had this idea of what I have to do and um to make
myself successful or to have some sort of good life and I went along with a lot
of what you know a deep culture in uh instilled in me and um almost feels
ancestral you know kind of instilled in me and and I keep bumping my head
against this and just um and often after some long while it
just feels like a dead end it's like wow I'm not getting anywhere just keep going
with this and so and there is a second kind
of a person that the Buddha spoke about and the B Buddha spoke about is the
second type of um people and they are called who goes
against the stream that one doesn't take part in
this kind of worldly Pursuits and the person lives a more of
a spiritual life and what's really interesting about this part of U description I'm going to
paraphrase it and not reading the the suit itself and in fact this person this
kind of people going against the stream feels like it's got a lot of
difficulties too so they they're not like they're just oh I'm just happy but said there's a lot of um
difficulties and they actually you know they cry and they have things happen to them
so I loved it and I feel like that's the nature of going against a
stream just to say um learning to be natural doesn't mean it's easy no one
said it's easy and um and so this um going against
the stream is to learn the Dharma practice learn the practice that goes
against the stream of great hatred delusion which is a popular culture we
live in yeah it can feel like a going against the stream and going against the stream of
the Notions of being Speedy or efficient or convenient you know that's that's
what I we hear a lot right and and
um but this going against the Stream
it's not necessarily easy to do even though we're learning to come in line
with the nature more and more and what's natural
isn't easy or
convenient or efficient so the Buddha went against the
stream of his own times and his own circumstances and he went against his
own family and Society culture Norms he lived
in and you know he realized you know his
life wasn't just about power status and a wealth which he lived Le based on the the documentation
and record seems to be the kind of life he lived in and so he left uh all of that and
engaged with all kinds of different kind of practices including quite extended years
of aesthetic practices but it's not until he
remembered an experience under a rose apple tree when he was
little and that he spontaneously entered a kind of um a deep sense of a
well-being being and that is not dependent on pursuing
anything and he realized oh there's something different here that
is um a kind of a natural Wellspring um natural welling up that is
not dependent on keeper pursuing and chasing uh externally and so that's kind
of a a turning point point for him to discover this more of
a naturalist Dharma and so he began to more and more
come in line with this natural upspringing or not natural welling up of
the Dharma and that led to his
Awakening and so that's the um and that's this this aspect
of practicing and you know going against the stream um but becoming a naturalist
of our own being um and being the naturalist we're not going to just kind of know ins and
outs of the nature uh overnight but we keep exploring and keep
dis discovering in the midst of difficulties and challenges
and um and the more we discover within the
more will begin to recognize that the Alternatives of going
along with the normal stream of agreed hatred delusion They don't serve Us in the long
run rage on top of hate or anger
um doesn't serve us or frustration on top of a
fear they're not nourishing or greed on top
of more desire and aversions that's just endless you know
this it's it's endless that's the poly term called some samsara it's endless
you know we can keep swimming in that we can even feel like we may sometimes have a kind of feel smart about it in some
ways but they're just endless in this kind of um
Circle and so the invitation is and that we practice
sincerely patiently gently and
honestly and gradually little by little our practice uh deepens and
enriches and in this way and the practice life gradually they become more
and more part of who we are how we
are and maybe that's um pointing to this kind of a felt sense of the natural
unfolding of the Dharma began to emerge in US and it may you know initially it
may feel like a small stream that comes to us and over time it becomes more and
more natural you know oh you know I'm not going to go to beat myself up and
I'm you know I'm choosing to be kind to myself and so that becomes more and more
natural in the sua
uh it describes this when Sila that ethical conduct becomes more and more
natural our actions speech and a mental activities are more and more aligned
with this kind of deeper sense of inner
goodness generosity kindness
compassion and it's just natural to not go to engage in ways in ways that are
are harming us and I remember um for those who U have small
children or have you know have a chance to observe small
children you see actually lying is not natural in
us the kids little toddlers the first time they lie you would just
know because it just feels off it's
awful it's really not good and you can see when they release
that burden of you know they tell the truth they they release that burden wow
they're so happy they're so
relieved and so we can come in contact with that and that's very natural in US
and I was reflecting you know on know one of night my neighbors do a lot of uh
yard work and um he's um it's very
inconvenient at times it feels like he and um you know he would spend a whole
day caring for some plants and and and and maybe you know other people will
think it's neither convenient or efficient I could
have done something different to make it go very quickly and get
done but he's so happy he's so happy spending that day whole day caring for a
few little plants or a tree what's the trade off right is a
more convenient and more efficient would be better than taking away from a whole
day of happiness and joy and so this natural unfolding when
there is a seala and there is no regret we don't have to wish oh they let me
have no regret it's just natural that's natural that way and when there's no
regret our heart is happy it's joyful it's just like that you know you don't
have to analyze it we know that and so this sutta went on in this
unfolding and this kind of Joyful happy heart and mind it's easy for us to get
gathered and collected concentrated because we're not so busy
thinking about making a big project to get concentrated it's just natural
it's just like that and when we're steady gathered
collected it's easy to see it's conducive for us to see
clearly because that's the nature you know if we're all stirred up
and rocking around it's very difficult to see clearly but if it's a study we're
gathered not um um chaotic it's just very clear things
are very clear and uh when things are
clear it's natural for the Deep kind of insight to
emerge in us we don't have to hunt for them they just come forth for
us and I uh sometimes reflect that Buddha did not have anyone who give gave
him a map he just really curious really there
to look at his own nature and so the Insight becomes very
natural it's naturally emerging to
us it can become easy for us to see oh wow just claiming
something um like you know I'm the best to cook over oh a delicious meal that's
a big claim that's a big leap you're making right it's easy to see wow you're
just making a huge leap here almost feels
ridiculous and that's easy to see that becomes easy to see when we're um
gathered collected and we're really open ourselves to see this kind of a
phenomena and when our mind are um pulled off and inevitably it will happen
pulled off into something and we recognize that's happening and we come back we come back
to the present and so that's
um that's part of the the
natural that's part of the natural unfolding of the practice too that is we
recognize that we're off and then we come back and so there is this a third type
of the person that the Buddha spoke about um which is um called someone who
is steadfast on the path and to someone who entered the
Dharma stream and who is steadfast on the
path and I really like that you know it's not some big Grand fireworks happening but
it's really saying that once we know clearly more and
more we find our way we know the path we come back again and again and we stay on
the path in this steadfast
way and so it's by staying on the path in this steadfast way that one crosses
over to the far Shore and that's the fourth type that the Buddha spoke
about and so may that be the possibility for all
beings so thank
you um we have time maybe just for one short
reflection if anyone okay
Bill Ying you you spoke a lot about what's natural in us um
and I wish I'd knew more biology but I have this idea um about
our natural tendencies to uh seek the pleasant more
pleasant of the four worldly winds and to avoid those that we don't like um you
know I'm I'm sure that it's built into our DNA yeah
to to to uh seek some and do our best to avoid others yeah but um you know I
thinking about it I I don't think it's hardwired I think it's softwired these that these are only very strong
Tendencies but but maybe the genus if I may anthropomorphize of darwinian evolution
is that it it's still malleable that with with uh effort and
conscious awareness and and we can we can morph all that but but how
does that sound to you great sounds great it's hard to use the words you
know completely accurately but yes so in
fact I would say that um it does feel quite natural that we
naturally seek for something it's natural we can see it this way it's also
in that this is um conditioned way in
that when we're reinforcing kind of um in this way it
becomes more and more kind of a part of a norm of us it almost feels natural
that way but when we're begin to see oh it's through us keep feeding this way
it it becomes like that kind of like you saying it's a software it's really
software and yet when we're seeing it that's where we begin to have a
different possibility and you you're using the word we're becoming more conscious of
it when we're not seeing this normal almost becomes kind
of we believe it's natural to us we don't believe that is a different
possibility yeah it's great oh and by the way that suit that you read at the beginning was great I've never read it
before but I will reread it yeah yeah thank you yeah thank you so why don't we end with a moment of
a dedication of a merit
together May whatever benefit a merit that arose out of us practicing together
and learning Dharma together be a source of nourishment for our own heart and
mind and body and may the benefit and goodness be
shared wide open with all beings may all beings be well happy and
may all beings be free
[Music]
thank you friends and I'll be uh just around here if you have any questions
and like to explore a little more feel free to come up and and also say bye to
those who are online so bye-bye