hi folks welcome uh yeah some of you might be started the
stream uh it got started on a private feed I don't know if here somewhere
in some region of the interwebs but uh we're here chatting saying hello
um and uh yeah it's a good good night to be
together so um let's let's settle in and uh and practice together
so taking some uh Fuller breaths
kind of breaths that uh reach everywhere in your
body the kind of breaths that uh soften your belly
kind of breaths that uh signal to the cells of your
body that it's actually okay to
relax e
sit down into your bones
The Head and the Heart can be more like air more like space but the
bones are Earth it's a heaviness to them a
groundedness so as this instruction goes sit in your
bones e
gentle uh sense of the downward pull of
gravity the Earth offering itself unwaveringly
and there's a heaviness to the body but it's not a
dullness it's a heavy aliveness
grounded steady
as the attention maybe dress
upwards towards the head towards the Gaze the kind of headquarters apparent
headquarters of uh visual
thinking just keep pouring the
attention down into the body into your [Music]
bones as if the awareness emanated
from your
belly
e
e e
there's a a growing U stability of our body
kind of
rootedness tianan uses the image of a
mountain body likee
Mountain e
[Music]
relaxation
Tranquility doesn't mean we have to do something means we're
invited to stop doing most everything
whatever strange or effort doing this you can
relax just relax
that and trust that
um the awareness that doesn't depend on you the small self
you that's uh going to be enough that's beautiful
enough to stay awake
grounded sitting in your
bones radical permission for life to
arise
cease
e
e e
because uh the awareness doesn't need
you you that Whirlpool of
contraction that we call
me can
relax
e
for
e e
although this uh stability is a associated with restfulness
Tranquility
peace we cannot forget our debt to love
sometimes the body tranquilized
restful it's like one drop of love just flavors the whole Space
and the blooming collapsing blossoming of Body Sensations becomes a
way of radiating meta loving
kindness e
sometimes we practice met uh not because we're inclined to but
because we know we
must
e e
okay good to is sit with
you when uh when I was young uh even as a young kid but especially as an
adolescent it's not unique to me but uh as an adolescent I remember
feeling um so kind of let down by institutions by
um by school and the religion I was born into and the kind of cultural models
proferred about what is Meaningful what what what's a a reasonable life and
um and in that uh disappointment there was some some discernment some
discernment for sure but mostly I was angry you know and
it was kind of just aversion spraying everywhere sort of fire hose style you
know um and yet like lurking in that
anger was a kind of earnest hopefulness
you know maybe even amidst the cynicism you know it like the cynicism
disguised some kind of utopian fantasies you know just wanting institutions to be
more fair more honest more attuned to What happiness actually
is and again and again my heart would
break and it was almost like the the first Noble Truth
constellating at the level of the group or the institution we know the duk uh
suffering at the level of the individual but but it also constellates at the level of the
group and it's its own unique species of
duka and so against that background years later when I heard the
phrase disenchanted with samsara the disenchant
some Sor I I was very interested you
know and it it seemed oh you know and samsara this kind of Realm of this human
realm of cyclical I I associate it with the kind of Loops of suffering the cycles of
suffering and disenchanted with Sam Sor that seemed almost like the most
profound way of expressing my disillusionment and heartbreak it's like
okay I give up get me out get me
out and there's one way of reading you know
the the Buddha's life the wish not to be reborn
you know as something akin to get get me out of here you know and we know that to be
rooting for the world that guarantees a tremendous amount of suffering for
sure that's not the end of the story so yeah on the one hand
disenchantment is so important because our default position is to be
essentially mesmerized by some sorrow to be mesmerized by samsara means that everything is real
all all appearances all phenomena lead us to forget the vastness of space and
time we become very myopic the appearances all means so
much this thing that thing my
life and all the the problems are problems of conditions the solution is
adjusting conditions and when we're mesmerized by Sam Sora we're often very
self-absorbed just a lot of energy to kind of in the clinging and the
strategizing in the control Lane and
um there's there's a lot of hope you know when we're mesmerized hope that we
might kind of achieve a steady state fix the
Brokenness and yeah some part of me wanted wanted out wanted protection you
know just uh get me get me
out you know it's too much it's too much that phrase that that's a kind of Trope
across the decades for me it's too much and uh as I emerged from a a you
know a 5-day Retreat you know and saw the news and it's like okay same feeling
too much caring too much or caring not at
all I could feel the kind of pull of nihilism I felt that pull at various
points but the Buddha warned really clearly warned about that
you know that nothing means anything a kind of emptiness that acknowledges no
form and rage and disappointment the the the Heartbreak of Institutions you know
aversion that can masquerade as as disenchantment nihilism can masquerade
as disenchantment but what what is it really what is it
really disenchantment lies between everything means everything and
nothing means anything everything means everything is
a kind of recipe for melodrama nothing means anything is
cynicism and between these two we find our
life and but to be in the middle to hang in the balance between
everything means everything and nothing means anything The View must be very
vast to be neither melodramatic nor nihilistic
about heartbreak that takes Incredible
strength there's a a moral philosopher um swick
um use the phrase different context but the phrase
the point of view of the universe and it struck me like that just
intuitively the point of view of the universe that's a pretty nice
encapsulation of the vastness of which I
speak and a view of course is more than
than a belief you know it's um it's not it's not a narrow
cognitive I think visceral visceral it's a felt
sense it's about perception how we actually perceive phenomena The View
informs how we perceive everything and it's about our body the
body I was pointing to in our sit you know the view is is it it's almost like
the body in a certain shape of
openness and the vastness you know the vastness
knows change you know knows change
knows just How Deeply that's woven into the fabric of being knows dukka knows
suffering knows it feels like geologic time the
point of view of the universe is like you know it's just kind of
like my own grandiosity that just this this moment in time means so much this
life this place this space you know and so the vastness of
the view knows like oh almost has this this palpable sense of the vastness of
time and space light years millions of light years of
space and this view doesn't discount suffering
and doesn't discount Freedom the vastness we could say is
simultaneous L uh knowing emptiness and poignancy
emptiness and poignancy
empty phenomena rolling on empty phenomena tumbling on who who can be
harmed what can be harmed you need solidity for something to be harmed
we've been here before it's always been like
this and maybe it's like a kind of very wise Grandma seeing
her 5-year-old grandchild the small cut
crying except uh it's like the child it's the universe
and from that that view it truly does all
belong it can never all work out and yet we engage our
love we engage our
love but it's not a confined love
and if there's even a cintilla of control in the love the heart will break
again and so if we truly understood the characteristics Dua anicha
anata suffering uncertainty not self if we truly
understood the characteristics at depth
how vast would our mind be how vast would the view
be and um I sometimes talk about equinity is
love in the face of helplessness the end of our
power and um in a way the vastness uh
is is a kind of acknowledgment of the near completeness of one's
helplessness but it's married to
love and the love gets big and
peaceful for this we are
consideration and uh I appreciate the opportunity to
uh uh be with you in this way thank you