so welcome to everyone here everyone who's here is very welcome to come to
IMC whether it is your very first time walking in here or if you've been here for decades and welcome also to the
folks who are online we're joined by many people around the world
perhaps so when the Buddha was setting out on his quest for Spiritual
Awakening the story says that he was concerned with the large existential
questions of Being Human so we find ourselves in this life right and that
just goes toward aging illness and death which are suffering so how like what
does that mean how can we overcome that suffering so that our life is not
inseparably bound up with some kind of stress and struggle and difficulty that
was the Buddha's kind of initial question why does it have to be like
this and then after he did awaken it said that he sat in meditation under the
bod tree for an additional seven days and he contemplated what is called
dependent arising so dependent arising is a a
series or a set of interrelated conditions that culminate in the
experience of Aging illness and death or the mass of suffering in general so what
he was doing though is that he was reflecting under the Bodie tree that he
had actually solved the issue he was reflecting back to his original question
how do we deal with this human life and the big questions that come with it
did I solve that problem and he realized yes he had solved that issue and he had
completed his quest so this meant that the Buddha
understood very deeply how suffering comes about and how it can not come
about by seeing that certain things are dependent on each other so things depend
on each other they're related to each other he saw how experiences happen
based on supportive conditions and also how they fall apart when the supportive
conditions are no longer there it sounds straightforward enough when said like
that but how do you solve that problem for the specific case of suffering of Dua could we figure out what is
sustaining it and then not do that that was what the Buddha found and it's not
something that the Buddha have made up or brought into being he said very clearly in one of his Dharma talks later
whether or not anyone awakens to this conditioned nature of experience
nevertheless this law operates so it's fundamental he
discovered something fundamental about how things work and then later the Buddha was
quoted by one of his disciples as saying one who sees dependent AR arising sees
the dhma and one who sees the dhma sees dependent arising so it's quite a vision
you know that he had sitting under the VOD tree and I'd like to talk about this
Vision today in a way that is tangible and practical for us because it's
actually something with which we all have experience it really
is so I want to start by emphasizing this phrase uh that I used dependent on
because it's easy to want to think in terms of causes our minds are kind of attuned to that in in the west it's
simpler for our brain a causes B but we're actually talking about necessary
conditions that support something being there or not so if you think about something like
rain rain happens but it depends on certain necessary conditions being in
place in order for it to happen there have to be clouds with a certain amount of moisture in them the atmospheric
pressure has to be right the temperature has to be right various other things when all those conditions are there it
will rain and when something shifts enough that we go out of some range
right then the rain has to stop for example I don't think we're
going to have rain today because there aren't any clouds it's just not in the
conditions they could form later I'm not saying that couldn't happen but at this exact instant we don't have the
conditions so we don't have the rain sometimes the Buddha also used the
analogy of an oil lamp so an oil lamp Burns Independence on oil a Wick air
also and um but with the oil runs out or the wick runs out I guess if the air
runs out um then the flame would go out right so these are physical examples
that makes them I think pretty easy to relate to but in fact we could relate
this same idea to the realm of the mind you know suppose you're having an
emotion did that come about randomly no there are necessary
conditions for the appearance of a given mind State whether it's an emotion or a thought or anything else and there are
also oo conditions for maintaining that and conditions when they change it will
fall away when the necessary conditions are no longer
there so this General principle of things coming about dependent on
conditions is named by the poly word AA payata and you don't have to remember
that but I wanted to say it because this word um Paya which you can hear in there
it means dependent on so we could kind of summarize this law a little bit
casually as this arises dependent on that and if this doesn't happen then it
doesn't then that doesn't arise that's a little bit casual um
there are actually kind of two different kinds of dependency weaving together one is more present moment and one is more
overtime but um I think I'll wait and not go into that in much detail right
now um but the Buddha so that's the very general principle which I think I think
we can understand in a broad way but remember I said the Buddha was particularly concerned about Dua that's
the word that we translate as suffering or stress or struggle or unsatisfactoriness so Dua the difficulty
that we have in life so he wasn't that interested in clouds actually and rain
and such um but he was more interested in the Practical question what are the necessary conditions for Dua when what
is present will there be Dua and when what is eliminated will duka
cease and then more practically can we discover how suffering or stress comes
about and how it can be released that is a spiritually fruitful
question so the Buddha framed the answer to this question in a number of
different ways in the teachings um we're just going to talk about the most common
one today which is he talked about a series of 12 uh links and I put the word
links in air quotes because it's not quite literally a linear sequence 1 2 3
4 up to 12 um it is 12 sequential conditions but uh they have kind of
feedback Loops within them um that add a little bit comple of complexity and they
also operate on a different various different time scales that can overlap so it ends up being a little bit more
complex than just 1 through 12 um but basically there are 12 lengths of dependent arising and in this specific
form where we're just where we're talking about how Dua comes about then it's called in pi by the term Patia
samua which means AR Rising together Independence
on okay again that's another pow you don't have to remember but I like to say
them because they're meaningful so I'm going to we're going
to go through these 12 just so that um you know them but uh the talk doesn't
focus on dissecting all 12 of them in detail but let's at least go through them I'm going to name them in what is
classically called the reverse order so that we can start with Duke um which is also called in this sequence
aging and death and the whole mass of
suffering so um so remember the Buddhist question was how does aging and death
and the whole mass of suffering how does that come about you know that was what he wanted to know so he he really
contemplated this and he and he looked in his own experience and he saw that aging and death and the whole mass of
suffering arise dependent upon birth if there isn't birth there
wouldn't be death would there I mean that's clear enough um so birth to say
use the language we're using here birth is the necessary condition for aging and
death and birth arises dependent upon
becoming becoming is kind of the the movement toward creation uh that that
feeling we have where we want to bring something into being you know we're moving toward that in when there's an
image given for this step I think becoming is a a pregnant woman so we get
the idea um and so that but is becoming the very Source no it isn't becoming
arises dependent upon clinging so that means that we've grasped onto uh the
idea of what we want to create we have a a vision in mind in some way
or we're just grasping clinging and clinging arises dependent on craving we
want something craving by the way also includes not wanting something that has
the same effect it's a a movement either toward or away attraction or repulsion but it's just called craving because we
need to have one word but is craving the total source no craving arises depending
upon what's called V or feeling tone um
feeling tone being Pleasant or unpleasant or neutral neither Pleasant
nor unpleasant those are the three feeling tones so because experience has this veilance to it where we like it or
we don't like it that's why we want things or not want things right because they're Pleasant or unpleasant to
us feeling arises depending on sense contact so you know something comes in
that's why we have a certain feeling it's because we've had an experience we've seen something we've heard
something we've touched something that's what's Pleasant or unpleasant sense contact arises
dependent on the six senses of course we have to have sense organs if we didn't have them we wouldn't have experience
and in this teaching we say that there are six so there's the five usual ones associated with the body and then mind
is the six so ideas can also be pleasant or unpleasant the six senses arise
dependent on what's called name and form more Loosely we could say mind and body
we have a mind and a body and that arises dependent on Consciousness so the fact that we feel our body and our mind
is because we have awareness we can detect things we can know that something
is happening and that arises consciousness arises dependent on a very difficult to
translate word called Sanara which is usually translated as say let's say volitional formations or mental
formations so there's some movement toward wanting to know wanting to have
experience and all and those S Sanara arise we've made it to number 12 by the
way Sara arise dependent on something called ignorance not knowing something that we
don't know so we won't go through all of these in detail um remember that this is
the Buddha's Grand Vision of how suffering operates in the mind so it's
meant to be deep but nonetheless uh we can get the essence of it we can get the
essence of it so I I just want to highlight a few key
links note notice first of all the foundational link which I read last but it's technically called the first link
which is ignorance so suffering depends eventually on some kind of not knowing
or not understanding something so that's interesting you know that's already
interesting it's not a cognitive knowing it's something you have to discover through practice but there's something
we don't know um and then there's also a key sequence in the middle uh of the ones
that I read so uh dependent upon having sense organs we're impacted by contacts
which we feel as pleasant or unpleasant and then we react to that feeling by
wanting or not wanting the experience so contact feeling craving that's a hugely
important little section of dependent arising so in general let's remember
contact feeling tone craving all supported by ignorance and then after craving
um just to name one other part we go on to create an identity around that wanting and not wanting that's the
clinging becoming and birth part so I just want to say that birth doesn't have to mean literal birth um it can also be
the creation of a sense of self just so you're clear on what those steps refer
to so we have a background
misunderstanding experiences coming in and contacting us they're Pleasant or
unpleasant and so we react by grasping or pushing away is this generally plausible for how
things go in our life anybody agree with that I see a few nods yeah you don't
have to meditate for very long to notice that that's kind of what's going on
so so the Buddha gave this teaching on dependent arising also called dependent
origination you'll also see that that one it's refers to the same thing so that we can see how suffering or stress
or struggle come about because we're clinging or identifying with or simply
misunderstanding something you know the idea The Hope here is that by
understanding the conditions for suffering we gain some ability not to do that not to if we don't fulfill the
necessary conditions then we wouldn't have the suffering so if we could see see these conditions like the oil and
the wick that support the fire of suffering in the mind we could direct
our practice toward eliminating those conditions no oil no
Dua no Wick no dooka no match lighting the wick no
dooka that would be valuable to know right so this is pretty empowering
actually this teaching it's pretty
empowering so sometimes people ask what time frame is this operating on that's a
good question it's actually happening on many different time frames so there's a
classical teaching in the Buddhist text that tries to extend this over three lifetimes
we're not going to go that far today we don't need to go that far actually because I think it clearly also happens
over normal time scales in a human life right when I just asked you that question about do you see this happening
yeah people were nodding you know it happens over uh periods of minutes or hours or days or years we can see these
conditions coming into being interestingly it can also happen quite quickly you know we can see it
functioning in meditation we can sometimes see it function in when our mindfulness is very sharp we can see it
functioning rapidly in just a few mind moments we go through a whole cycle it's like oh wow and you see the mind um very
quickly uh going from misunderstanding something to grabbing it to suffering for
it so we have the case where a bunch of
these 12 link Cycles are happening on various time scales and there's also feedback Loops
within the cycle you might have noticed as I got closer to the beginning of it it didn't sound like it might have
sounded like some of them were a little bit similar or overlapping and there are actually feedback loops within it we
won't go into those in great detail but if you imagine you have a bunch of these Cycles operating over different time
frames and there's feedback loops within it how would that end up looking in our
mind I have a suggestion I brought with me a little demonstration something like this
so this is a a tangled ske of um twine
in this case that was uh it's been sitting in my drawer and I kind of pull off little pieces of it sometimes but
then I just throw it back in So inattention leads to Tangles this is also a Le a Dharma lesson for today so
what I'm trying to show is that our mind is a little bit more complicated than oil lamp I'm sorry to say um so the
Buddhist suggests that this tangle is a pretty good representation of the mental
and emotional patterns that bring stress and suffering into our life and when we
start meditating we can start to sense that yes this does resemble the structure of the ordinary unawakened
mind I mean there's no perfect metaphor but this one's pretty good how many
people have some sense of there being a tangle in your mind yeah okay great so you're in good company actually
somebody back in the time of the Buddha once asked him um they asked him sort of
a a a riddle and they said a tangle within a tangle without this generation
is entangled in a tangle I ask you this oh Goa that's the Buddha who can
disentangle this tangle so it's a little riddle about
solving this problem I'll give you the Buddha's answer to that riddle later um
but for now here we are we have this tangle in
our heart or our mind and it even affects our body um there are two pieces of good
news one is that this can be untangled we can actually get through this that's
the whole premise of the Buddhist teaching and the teaching on the 12 lengths of depend and arising helps
tremendously because we can start to get get a handle on what the components of this tangle
are and then the second piece of good news um which you might have to take a
little bit on faith at this moment but is that we don't have to have the complete Vision that the Buddha had
fully comprehending how every little strand of the tangle Works maybe you need that to be a Buddha but it turns
out to be sufficient for us to just understand one part of the tangle in a
in a deep way so uh once we understand say one link of that chain of 12 we have
significantly loosened it and sometimes we can even kind of collapse the whole structure because it's all dependent all
these things are dependent on each other right and if we could see through just one section really clearly and remove
that necessary condition the the whole structure loses the ability to hold together so this is is also really good
news so I want to I like to sum this up this whole thing we've built up so far as
start anywhere get everywhere so you can start anywhere on
the set of 12 and if and you're working toward the unbinding of the whole
structure so I want let's get practical so I want to I want to give a scenario that helps us see how this works in an
everyday situation and I'll say it first and then we'll go through it again um put pointing out some of the steps
because what we have is the tangle right and the question is how do I find the 12 links in here like how do I really see
what's going on so here's a scenario please uh you know grab me a little leeway on the on
trying to come down with just one one example but suppose you're going to a
meeting you're going to a meeting you're at work you're going to a meeting at your supervisor's office where you're
supposed to present the results of a project that you just did and you also have a chance to ask about getting more
resources for the next phase of the project okay so as you round the corner
in the hallway to your boss's office um you see a coworker just arriving at the
boss's office and the coworker is someone that you've often disagreed with and you didn't know that that person
would be at the meeting your heart sinks you didn't want this person to be
there and while you describe your results because some of your results are a little bit touchy they have some
touchy points that you trust your boss would understand but you don't trust this coworker to really understand uh
and do you know and also you wonder if you and he are going to be competing for the next resources to go forward with
the next phase right so um all kinds of scenarios start turning in your head as
you're approaching the office you're worrying that it will go badly and so you try to figure out whether you should
take a tough straightforward approach which uh might come across as kind of
aggressive or whether you should be more accommodating and Cooperative even though you don't really want to
cooperate so you feel stressed as you open the door and then when you do
actually go through the meeting you again feel pushed and pulled as the events unfold right you make some kind
of choice eventually about how to present yourself either beforehand as a resolve I'm going to do it this way or
on the fly in the moment you decide to be a certain way um and you go ahead and
do the meeting but then later no matter how it went you worry about whether the
way you presented yourself is going to be the best thing for the future you know did I you know did the way that I
came across in that meeting is that going to work out so we've created in our mind
one of these a tangle based on this very simple
scenario so let's go back through it and name some of the um qualities here so
you're going to this meeting with your boss you come around the corner and you see the coworker also entering so we
have ignorance present in your mind you're not very mindful at this moment so we have contact then we have your
heart sinks I said you have this deflated feeling feeling tone unpleasant
feeling tone is coming in you didn't want this person to be there because you
have these touchy results you want to explain to your boss without this competing person there there's craving
you want you wanted it to be a certain way and you don't want it to be the way that it's looks like it's going to
be um so then all these scenarios start going through your mind you're worrying
that it's going to go badly so you're clinging to the idea that it needs to go a certain way
then you try to figure out whether you should take you know how you should present yourself should I be tough and straightforward should I be
accommodating and Cooperative so we have becoming happening in the mind I'm
moving toward choosing an identity you feel stressed as you go into the office Dua has already happened and then when
you actually do go through the meeting you make some kind of choice that's actually Sankara the Second Step you
have a a mental volition toward being something and then you present yourself in a certain way you create an identity
you step into it through birth you enact it and then no matter what happens later
you worry about whether that was the right thing even if the meeting went well was that really going to is that going to serve you in the future so we
have death of that identity and the associated Duca of that there you go you just did them
right there in that 15 minutes of however long that meeting took so we
have some complexity um in in these scenarios and I'm sure you could think
of a similar scenario in your own life that has a lot of these links in it um probably interconnected the way they
were in that scenario so we have this complexity but we also have the Simplicity of knowing that if we could
just remove the necessary conditions for this structure it would have to collapse
if we could completely remove one of the necessary conditions it would no longer work
you know just like the necessary conditions there are a bunch of necessary conditions for these lights being on for example if I remove any one
of them the light will go off if I turn off the light switch it'll go off if I blow up the power plant it'll go off you
know there's multiple ways to turn off the light so maybe we can find a weak spot
in the 12 links something that we could see well enough to change the situation
so probably to fully end the mind's underlying tendency to get entangled is
going to take a lot of work but in any given scenario this like this one scenario with our boss I think we should
be able to make that collapse pretty easily right so you get that there's multiple pictures going on here so when
we are just enacting out some stressful scenario without any awareness then we
are living in the foundational condition of ignorance which supports the Dua suffering actually depends on us not
knowing that we are enacting it but when we see this process operating that
changes things so we've inserted a little bit of knowledge and we've weakened ignorance so the very Act of
seeing dependent arising the very Act of understanding that there are these 12 conditioned things these 12 links is the
beginning of untangling the uh the ske let's say that we've created in our mind
but probably that top level knowing you know just knowing that there are these 12 links that's probably not deep enough
to collapse everything so we're going to do better if we practice with some of
those middle links the ones I mentioned before about contact feeling tone and
craving that little spot is one place where we can often be successful in
removing the necessary conditions such that the stress or the Dua does not come about
the Buddha in his teachings he actually gives lots and lots of practices in the
discourses that we have those are all those big books of the poly Canon right he gives practices that are related to
contact that are related to feeling tone related to craving actually for any of the 12 links there are sutas and
teachings and practices that help us work with that link I think it's not a
stretch to say that everyone of the um for any of the 12 12 links there are
practices associated with them and probably all of those practices are designed to be deep enough that they
would be able to cut the chain at that point if we did them completely if we really did that practice remember when
one sees the Dharma one sees Depend and AR rising and when one sees Depend and AR Rising one sees the
Dharma so but we're just going to focus on these few in the middle because
they're both easy to understand and very powerful
so one of the most basic instructions that you will hear here at IMC is to be
mindful of your experience in a non-reactive way has anybody heard that
instruction yeah so we're talking about contact at our sense doors sounds that
we hear Body Sensations that we feel if we feel a pain in our back that's an
unpleasant sensation right um unpleasant feeling tone and the the aim of the
practice is that we're supposed to be able to be with those Sensations and not get caught up in the aversion not move
on from feeling tone to craving from it hurts to I don't want it so not getting
angry not catastrophizing about needing back surgery not fantasizing about how
if I just bought a better cushion that would probably help you know these kinds of things so and then a little bit more
subtle is also to work with the six sense St you know if we have thoughts or emotions coming into the Mind contacts
that are happening at the Sixth Sense store maybe I should Point here
um how do we be with those in a non-reactive way can we be with fear
without getting into a long uh story about it can we be with the Judgment of
another person can we be with Envy things that arise internally also
so this is I'll read you a quote from the sutas about this practice there is the case where a
practitioner on seeing a pleasant sight with the eye does not long for it or
become excited by it or generate Lust For It their body is steady and their
mind is steady inwardly well composed and liberated and on seeing an unpleasant
form with the eye they are not dismayed by it not daunted not de rejected and
without ill will their body is steady and their mind is steady inwardly well
composed and liberated and it goes on to say the same thing for the ear nose tongue body and mind all the six senses
and the instruction says if you see something pleasant or you see something unpleasant at any of those six sense
doors we would aim to be well composed and liberated not rushing off into
wanting it or not wanting it contact feel feeling tone let's let's not go
from feeling tone to craving that's what the instruction is saying right so we don't go from Pleasant and
unpleasant to grasping and pushing away so the shape of the tangle is affected
by our mindful presence if it doesn't have all the
pieces it needs to hang together then it can can't it can't uh
cohere let's say so you know from experience that if you are actually able
to just be with the pain in the back and not go into all the scenarios it does
reduce the suffering doesn't it there isn't as much duka yeah it still hurts I
get it um but there isn't that there isn't the same amount of Dua we've we've
somewhat loosened the tangle we don't have as much and if we some of you may have had the
experience actually of managing to do it all the way you know like we really are
mindful of the pain to such a degree that we suddenly realize 5 minutes later it's not there
anymore it's gone wow the whole structure
collapsed sometimes that happens we don't always get control about that but this is all you know this is all
straightforward excuse me straightforward mind fulness practice straightforward Sati patana practice
that we teach even in introduction to meditation courses and of course it can be done on deeper and deeper levels as
mindfulness gets more and more developed in us so that's good news is that you
actually already know how to do this why am I giving this talk you already know you already know the fundamental
instruction but remember that there are multiple instances of these 12 links
going on at any given time in our life and they're happening on different somewhat overlapping time scales so that
if we just see one instance of back pain and we're not reacting to it that's probably not going to collapse all of
our duka probably true but nonetheless that particular instance of it could cease
and in doing that through Dharma practice we are slowly moving toward a
larger scale collapse of the 12 links that might actually untangle a noticeable portion
of our Tangled heart and mind so each instance of mindfulness practice every
moment that we do where we're mindful because you can't do it any other moment than this one each moment where we do
this practice is helping to untangle that tangle and the specific practices
that you've already learned are targeting certain very vulnerable um places on this chain
so this is great so I've used an example from practice that you probably already know and what we're doing here is we're
putting it in this larger context of depend and arising I'm showing how this
one practice fits into the bigger picture of the reduction and eventually the end of Dua which is what the Buddha
was doing so even if we're only partway there along this untangling we can start
to understand that that's pretty much what it's about it's about entanglement and non- entanglement or about Dua and
the end of Dua that's it sometimes the Buddha said I I teach
only Dua and the end of duka that's what I teach so he was referring to that very
top level so start anywhere get
everywhere so maybe just to put in a little one other little connection if it
makes sense that's great and if it doesn't that's okay um in the four noble
truths we might remember that's also a very fundamental teaching of the Buddha
it's a compact teaching on how suffering comes about and how it ceases and you
might remember that the second Noble Truth says that the origin of suffering
is craving right so that's a key factor that's one of those links right craving is about in
the middle it's the one we just talked about so the 12 links are a little bit more
expanded version but when the Buddha gave the compact version in the four noble truths he just zeroed in on
craving he said if you could just eliminate the craving that's the end of the duka that was what we just talked
about that that step from feeling tone to craving that's a good place where we
can intervene and be able to see deeply enough that the duka doesn't happen but there's these other you know there's 11
other choices but if we just focus on craving that would be pretty good and that's right in line with the four noble
truths right so we see that connection
so we practice for a while or slowly untangle in more and more sections of
our knot and the knot thins out over time it thin gets thinner it gets
lighter and eventually we get down to the point where things are getting pretty thin and then we discover
something very interesting that's the other thing in my
box so I brought another ball you see this it's not wrapped around
anything so here this is wrapped around a piece of
cardboard but as we thin out these Tangled threads it turns out that we are
also thinning out the cardboard part and eventually we find that it's when we
get down maybe to this last one we can see that there's nothing in the middle
and when this one goes if I could pull this all the way out this would vanish
wouldn't it so teachings on conditionality are closely connected to
teachings on emptiness when everything is depend dep
on certain conditions certain necessary conditions then it has to be that those
things don't have an unchanging Essence to them a stable core that doesn't
change there is no stable core to this it's actually more like
this so things are empty of an unchanging Essence that is very
freeing so the great thing is that your heart or mind can do this we don't have
to be smart enough to do it all on our own by our will or by our cognitive
intelligence it's like the way a wound can heal itself kind of by itself right
there is a lawful process underneath the healing of a wound and all we have to do
is supply some supportive conditions for it right but we don't have to like direct that with our mind and make that
all happen right I I hope not that would be hard um but there are things that we
have to do and in the case of untangling this tangle uh we have to look you have
to be mindful you have to be aware awareness is the foundation and we have to look in a skillful way we have to
look at this as a process and we have to look at it in the way that the Buddha
gives instructions for how to practice it doesn't have to be perfect it just has to be good enough to see the next
thing that we need to see the next thread to pull on that will make it looser and that's always
possible so I said I would tell you the Buddha's response to that Riddle That that the person asked about the tangle
right so um here's the original question and also his
response a tangle within a tangle without this generation is entangled in a tangle
I ask you this oh Goa who can disentangle this
tangle a person established on virtue wise developing the mind and wisdom a
practitioner Ardent and discreet they can disentangle this
tangle so that's us we have our foundation of ethical
conduct of being virtuous in our life we're developing our practice we're
doing it in line with wisdom as as best we can at our level of understanding as
much wisdom as we have and we just continue on and we know that the tangle
is untangling so I hope you will be inspired to just keep on and let the
tangle untangle thank you