ah good morning so here we are today the technology
was operating in unexpected ways we have the software that uh called OBS which we
use to broadcast from the computer to YouTube ah good morning and it was not
uh working somehow took a while to set up and once it figured it out it's not
quite right I believe the video in uh on YouTube it's not really filling the
screen so but that's okay it's amazing that we can even be here this way and
I'm delighted to share this time with you and um and uh hopefully
we'll work out some of these bugs that are
occurring so welcome to our meditation
and um today uh to support the teachings
afterwards I would like to emphasize that uh to stay close to
something that's wholesome something that feels healthy for you in terms of
how you're aware so sometimes I talk about calm
awareness some people might talk about um non non-c contentious
awareness or an awareness which makes room for what's here breathing room and
awareness that's very simple and awareness that's warm and
kind an awareness which is aquanus with whatever goes
on an awareness that is not caught or entangled
reactive to what we're aware of to find a way of being aware being
mindful to recognize what's happening to know what's happening to sense and feel what's
happening in a way that feels good feels nice for you and then stay close to that
maintain it be in touch with it use it as a guide use it as the maybe the bow
of the boat that's moving through the water in a nice clean
way have it be the pedals of your bike that you're always in touch with always
moving let it be the the pitting of the cat the hand
going down gently lovingly pitting the cat we might feel depressed or angry but
it feels good to pet the cat so see let's see if we can find a way to be aware that keeps us aware keeps us
connected so to close your eyes assume your meditation
posture and to relax
soften let there be a gentle of your
body with every exhale soften relax in your
body and then to soften and relax your
mind your thinking mind your thinking activity any agitation or tension in
your mind soften around it a gentling of the Mind
and gentling the Heart
softly kind ly
calmly approach the heart your feeling heart with whatever
way you're feeling and as you exhale a
softening an opening a settling of the heart
and then becoming aware of your breathing but be aware of your breathing
lightly
softly almost as if you're walking
in the park with a friend talking and you're lightly aware of the
trees around you so it's kind of very light awareness
of breathing and the friend to be talking with to pay attention
to is awareness itself how you are
mindful so number of ways to be
mindful it can just be a general feeling of being present being
aware or it could be acts of
recognition knowing what's happening it could be feeling and
sensing through your body or all of the above
see if the way that you can be in the present know the present be aware in the
present be awake in the present can feel healthy feel good feel
satisfying calm nonc contentious
open
receptive and then with that awareness as if awareness
is like a warm friend settle the awareness on the body
breathing where the continuity of
breathing is the means the way that you can stay with a con
continuity of a gentle awareness calm awareness of the
present like you would if you are petting a cat you might
feel all kinds of difficult
emotions but part of you would be G petting the cat gently
softly that would support the cat to
purr so you might be feeling all kinds of things now but let how you're aware
of the rhythm of breathing the coming and going of INB breath and out
breath stay in touch with a calm
awareness some way of being aware that feels healthy or wholesome
or like you're pedaling on a bike gently happily through the park but
there's a continuity of moving the legs having
contact with the
petals
e
for
e e
with breathing as the subject of
awareness focus on letting
awareness be present calm
open
receptive warmhearted kind
in whatever way that's easy for you stay close
to a way of being aware being
present that feels good to you that you
enjoy enjoying the simplicity
e
e e
maybe a small smile BL add a flavor of goodness or
joy to being aware
for
e
for e
it's quite common for people to be
absorbed in the object of awareness the object of their
thinking what they're aware of what they're thinking
about in the practice of mindfulness we're Shifting the
balance so that half of our attention is on the quality of our
attention itself
and that half of attention that goes to that can become of our time second
nature it becomes a way of staying
connected to a nourishing way to be awake to be present to be
here awake
and that 50% attention to how we're aware allows us actually to be more
aware of others the people in our lives it's as if our capacity to be
present for people increases there's more
room more sensitivity more care and may it be so that this practice
of meditation practice of mindfulness is a training and increasing
our capacity for present moment awareness so we can have this nourishing
open attention to take in and feel and know others in a wise way in a balanced
way and in so doing to feel a deeper connection feel a deeper sense of a
shared Humanity deeper sense of people's
challenges and then and our care our our love our warmth our friendship
friendliness can be more present may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful may all beings be
free and may we contribute to that
[Music]
possibility thank
you e
so hello and welcome to this third uh talk that I'm calling the four truths of
happiness and they are complement to the Buddhist teachings on the four
noble truths of suffering which I talked about last week and um these the the two pairs of
four complement each other kind of parallel each other but one of the
things they have in common kind of at this Center of them is they concern our
contribution to our state of mind state of heart or state of
being and uh the four noble truths have to do with how we contribute to what's
called suffering Dua emotional pain and it's not necessarily all
emotional pain but that emotional pain which we do in fact contribute to
uh and the contribution is summarized in uh the word
craving and or thirsting having thirst for stuff they kind of a compulsive
desire and that as long as this compulsive desire is operating uh there's frustration there's expectation
there's tension there's stress there is um uh more elaborate things that begin
happening around that compulsive desire which uh is uh building from a desire um
uh identities layers and layers of identities and stories and realities
that we live in and so we want to be careful and see
how we contribute to the suffering our role um we don't ignore the role of
others or other situations but at least we take care of our our contribution and it
makes a worldly difference for the four truths of of Happiness uh we also have a contribution
to make and uh we don't just leave our happiness to chance hoping that the world will somehow provide it for us
hoping that something out there will do it if we pay enough money or if we you know if we find the right person to be
with there all kinds of things that we're looking out there for happiness but we find it within and we find what
what within contributes to that what we can know for ourselves elves or we can
experience for ourselves what we contri can contribute and that's to contribute uh
wholesome states of being wholesome activities uh ethical live
ethically uh do the things which are wholesome that for our heart feel good
not things which are stressful not things that are dutiful and we should do and to do be the be the right kind of
person but to start learning to touch into it to discover
uh the natural goodness the natural wholesomeness that we're capable of of
and how there can well up from within if we're relaxed enough if we're settled
enough if we're connected to ourselves enough so part of what we contribute to
our own happiness is a practice of mindfulness is a practice of being present and aware so that that can
follow uh that we can then recognize what is wholesome recognize healthy
States and activities and then uh we can call on
them the third truth of happiness is that uh once we recognize
these wholesome states of being and mindfulness itself done well done calmly
not contentiously um equanimous is actually considered to be
extremely wholesome it can be and that's kind of like the bottom line perhaps
there but as we start connect to the wholesome as we start connecting to what feels that brings us
well-being stay close to it uh the Buddha talked about states of well-being
states of wholesomeness are things that we should maintain the causes of suffering are
things we want to bring to an end the conditions that bring about
well-being we want to maintain we want to stay close to it uh I've been many
situations where I felt pretty happy and then uh I had a to-do list to do and I
threw myself into the to-do list and I got grumpy I got irritated I got
frustrated um and U and unnecessarily
so but I gave gave away gave up on my well-being I ignored it in favor of the
things to do other times I felt connected I've maintained my sense of calm my sense of
ease my sense of joy and happiness and I've also had a to-do list
to-do and I did it uh out of that well-being with that well-being usually
what happens then I do a little bit slower usually I do it with more delight and
joy and usually I make less mistakes usually there's less repetition usually
gets done well the first time so while it's slow you know sometimes slow is what
gets things to done done the fastest so this idea of
maintaining uh and that's some message that many Buddhists don't seem to get because there's so much emphasis on
letting go not holding on to anything um and uh so much emphasis on
um me just showing up for the next moment the next moment that there's no
no sense of let's maintain something um so the example that of
petting the cat uh you have to maintain the petting for the cat to keep purring
and you get instant feedback if you stop so that there has to be maintaining
of something so it's our heart the way we nourish nurture pet our heart pet
care for it it needs maintenance it needs attention needs care
this doesn't have to be selfish it doesn't have to be at the expense of others it doesn't have to be um uh kind
of uh done with attachment doesn't have to be done with any clinging um maintaining is not the same
thing as attachment maintaining you know I maintain my car usually I go get the oil
changed but I have no attachment to you know in a sense to do or not doing it
just a matter of fact thing to do so we maintain our heart we maintain the
wholesomeness that's here so that's so we contribute to our happiness and the word
contribute is a choice word because it's not meaning we cause it uh this is uh to have to be the cause
of our suffering and focus on causing it to happen just messes it up but what we do is it's almost like uh
uh uh let me be happy the heart willing kind of an openness in allowing
and trusting because who knows what the heart wants to reveal what's what it wants to show at any given time there
might be unresolved anger or grief that needs to come that doesn't look like
conventional happiness however there can be a way in which it feels good feels
healthy to let it be there feels like there's a healthy awareness capacity to
be present they this is good and this is true this is really connecting to a true
process a true uh depth of what's really concerning me and it's good to be here
with it and so then we maintain the goodness or the healthiness of how we
relate to our anger how we relate to our our um grief um we don't looking for
kind of cheerful mindfulness I mean cheerful happiness we're looking for a way of being that
feels so good that feels right given the circumstance and U and th that's
contributing the conditions out of which well-being and joy can arise the Buddha used a language
a language of uh birth to describe Joy appearing for us a a joy is born it's
not something we cause and so sometimes we have to spend time letting something
gestate letting something mature and Sprout for joy to arise we have to
contribute the care like a gardener would care for a garden and but then so the third Noble
Truth of happiness is uh maintain the well-being
maintain a satisfying form of awareness of mindfulness
maintain care and friendliness maintain Joy maintain Delight stay close to it
stay in touch don't get too far away from it by getting distracted and busy and overwhelmed by the to-do list or
whatever is going on you can do that but uh to allow this Garden to grow
to allow the happiness to grow to allow the clarity to grow and the freedom to
grow uh the conditions the right conditions have to be there not just
wishful thinking not just touching in just a few times a day to some kind of
calm state but for the garden to really grow it needs to be have sunlight on it all
day long so to maintain these good things and maintain it through the
day e said difficult to do but satisfying to do and it becomes
second nature like riding a bike after a while becomes second nature we can
live closely in touch with our inner well-being our inner wholesomeness it is
possible so um so this is a
third truth of happiness and so um today as you go through your
day find a way to remind yourself again yesterday I suggested tying a string
around your finger maybe today do something a little bit more uh reminds
you even even more strongly perhaps or you can put a timer on your phone to
maybe to go off every 10 minutes or something or you you some kind of
reminder and um check in and see if you can tap
into what feels wholesome within and if it's if you don't feel anything wholesome within that's a time to uh
we're finding out how to be aware in a Wholesome Way how to be aware in a way
that feels good feels satisfying feels calm feels spacious feels
um supportive uh is invaluable at the minimum no matter how difficult things
get 50% attention on how we're aware so that how we're
aware um can be nourishing for us beneficial and create the conditions for
other wholesomeness come out to be born and the fact that it's 50%
attention on yourself and how you're aware embodied awareness being connected
here doesn't mean that you does not mean you have to have less awareness for other people or for the activities you
do it actually can give more because our capacity to be aware can
grow and to have this 5050 uh awareness of here awareness here
with how you're aware how you are and 50% with what you're doing people you're with um creates the conditions that the
sum total of your awareness may be triples so you clearly have more
awareness for what you're doing than you had before but you do it with this able
to stay closely in touch with what's happening here so you
can know yourself better but maybe also you can be stay in touch to
maintain what is good maintain the wholesome maintain it through the day so
so I wish you well with that I hope you take this on and see what you learn in
the process thank you