great so hello and welcome everyone to happy hour lovely to be with
you wherever you are zooming in or listening to Audio Dharma later in time
so so for today's practice um invite us to
start practicing sitting together with embodiment with Good Will and um let
ourselves be surprised so um I'm I won't say so much about the practice and let's
see what arises so so let's begin let's begin
so so arriving arriving in this
moment arriving in this body and whatever has been
happening all day busyness whatever has been happening
bowing to it thank you I
will set you down gently lovingly and turn my heart give my whole
heart to this practice right now let's take some time to
acknowledge appreciate whatever has been happening up to this moment
the to-do List's not completed it's okay the busyness running around whatever it
might have been and decide
together intentionally to set it down it's okay it's all right it's
okay and with intention with a sense of presence stepping into this moment this
fresh new moment as if
it's a spring moment which it is for us in the
northern hemisphere as if it's a fresh new moment freshness of
spring and letting this body rest
sit fully
inhabiting the freshness of this
moment with each
breath each in breath felt in the body each out breath felt in the
body take time to fully
arrive
taking time to fully arrive is an expression of goodwi for
ourselves taking time to be fully present
connected
e inviting ourselves with
kindness with a sense of Good Will generosity to ourselves it's okay
sweetheart sit sit relax soften relax and receive the
breath Sensations in the body relax and receive nothing to do nowhere to go
No Agenda no
shs
e
now I like to invite you bring to
mind someone you care about who's having some
challenges and this could be yourself as well you could be bringing yourself to mind if you're having some challenges in
your body in your mind and your heart if you want you maybe let's start
actually with someone else maybe we'll turn to ourselves later yeah let's bring
someone else in so when we know we care about [Music]
about and bring them to our heart space
and and wishing them ease you have ease in the midst
of this challenge this
difficulty may you be free from sorrow from from
Pain may you have ease I wish you
well and it might be that there's only one aspect of that your life is that's challenging at every
aspect and also let yourself have sense of embodiment peace and
ease so there is no sense of
overwhelm of the suffering but you are able to meet it in
your heart with kindness you meet you know there is pain
suffering Challenge and you meet it with kindness in equal measure in equal
measure
and if it starts to feel
overwhelming leaning more into the goodwi and less into the suffering so
that it feels more
balanced may you be well may you have ease May there be every goodness and
blessing for
you being sense a connection with this
being
e I care about you I wish you well may you have ease as you meet this
difficulty and challenge may you have as much
well-being in the midst of it I wish you well I wish you
ease
e
e may you have
ease you have peace in the midst of Challenge and difficulty I wish you
well I care for you may you be free from this
pain
e
now i' like to invite you if you would
you can either stay with this person or maybe another being
you know who's having challenges or can bring
yourself to your heart
space there any difficulties in the body pains
challenges in the heart space or the
Mind wishing yourself well oh dear heart dear being who's
me I wish you well I wish you
ease can NE see yourself as a beloved other addressing yourself as you or or
me whichever works better for you can try them out for
size and I have ease may I have ease with with this
challenge with this difficulty may I have ease I wish myself
well I hold myself with care may I be free from this
difficulty this pain sorrow may I have well-being in the
midst of
it
e
and if at any point this connection with the challenge or difficulty becomes too
much overwhelming and lean more into the goodwi for yourself to the
kindness not in the way of pushing away the difficulty you're pain but to balance it and if it feels too
receded not in touch not connected not met then bring it bring it forth a bit
more so that you're turning towards it not running away but meeting it with
kindness and Care meeting yourself with kindness thank
care it's pain in the body pain in the Heart Meeting it with
gentleness Goodwill
may I be
well may I be well in the midst of
this
e
and for the the last few minutes of this practice period bringing both of you both
yourself and all the beings that you were practicing with earlier may all of us
have these just like me you want to be free from sorrow just like you I want to be
free May both of us may all of us have ease I wish all of us
well you are not so
different
e
may all being everywhere including the person I was
thinking of including myself may all of us have
ease May may we be free from sorrow may all beings have ease may all
beings be happy may all beings be
free thanks everyone thanks for your
practice ah it is so nourishing practice compassion practice for others for
ourselves for all beings there's a nourishment in the
Heart It expands the heart um and as you
noticed I talked about balancing meeting the
challenge whether it's for others or for ourselves meeting it in the mind and
balancing that with with the level of goodness and and goodwi because if we're
just meeting Challenge and pain oh this is hard this is painful oh we Veer into
overwhelm and what's called empathetic distress it just becomes grief and
painful that's not compassion practice uh and if we're not meeting the pain p
and sorrow at all and if it's just may may I be well may you be well that's meta practice which is lovely wonderful
and it's not compassion practice so if you want to practice compassion equally meeting both the challenge the pain oh
yeah my back is really hurting okay may there be ease may I have ease yeah this
is painful so both meeting and holding it with ease both at the same time same
measure so we have have some uh time to engage together to share to um reflect
in small groups and will'll be in uh small groups of three in the moment and
the invitation is um to share if you like for your own benefit not educating
not impressing anyone for your own benefit what was this practice like for you speaking out loud letting yourself
be held with witness just one nugget and then next person will offer another nugget will go in alphabetical order in
first name um and then the third person'll come back to you so you'll go round and round and please stay with the
practice not what happened before yesterday to not um giving each other
advice or asking questions even if you didn't understand what someone said just
it's their experience um Let It Be we're just sharing and holding each other with
kindness and don't try to fix other people's problems we're not here to fix
each other problems we're not here to have our problems fixed we're just here to to to share and be held witness and
see if we can hold ourselves with kindness and other people with kindness that's it's a different way of being um
it's um in in the happy hour um uh breakout rooms and the etiquette guide
is there as it's been posted so so with all that I will open the rooms please
take care of yourselves please take care of each other and here we
go okay welcome back everyone the rooms are closed everybody's back it's sweet
to see smiles when you come back from the rooms um and um yeah we have time for
Reflections questions um aha moments confusions what worked what didn't anything and
everything is welcome here's your chance with practice Reflections and
questions can also type them in chat if you like you can raise your Zoom hand your physical hand I may actually I
do see maran's physical hand I usually don't see physical hands but there you are actually your Zoom hand just went up
ah Zoom has become smart Maran
please I'm thinking that equal measure of equinity not equinity meta and
empathy means not to be become flooded with the empathy is that and is there
any more you wanted to add to it I think I think I felt like I heard that
differently than before and I I think I felt a little confused maybe a little confused but I'm tell me tell me what
the confusion might be I was thinking um I think the re first thing I thought
was to give as much love as as the pain as big as the pain to give that much
love great I don't know yeah great that's so so wait there's nothing wrong
with that either right yeah yeah yeah so what's the so where's the confusion then Maria that sounds very clear to me that
okay is it does that seem different to me than tell me how it sounds different so I
join just joining them but to to join them so they become compassion seems a
little different than saying equal measure of both ah ah yeah
I see I see I think I'm getting a Nuance you're saying it's um I think the Nuance
I'm trying to bring in here with the equal measure with the emphasis on that
is um is not to get overwhelmed with with the pain with the with the empathy
part just as you were saying because compassion is made up of two parts one is empathy feeling another person's pain
U mirror neurons lighting up like oh really feeling someone's pain or we're feeling our own pain this is painful
this is hard but if if we lean into that too much it just becomes pain practice
it's doesn't it's no not compassion and as I mentioned um if we lean too much
into the uh meta practice just Goodwill then we're not really meeting the pain which is fine it's meta practice uh but
sometimes maybe it's as if we're pushing the pain away we sometimes it could be that way if there is pain but we're just
kind of pushing it away and just leaning into meta um which may not be skillful
sometimes depending on what's Happening so so my saying equal measure is to
really bring this importance of of the uh both are important both meeting not
turning away both meeting and and bringing love to it and the way you put
it which is meeting and you're welcome to comment more if you want um which is to meet the suffering with equal measure
of Love is is the same thing is is putting it in the same way so does that
uh yes that's very helpful yes great thank you thanks Maran thanks for
highlighting that I'm really glad you you brought brought that up thanks Nancy I see your Zoom
hand thank you Nikki thanks um I just wanted to say I've I've been sick this
last 10 days and um so I haven't been able to be at IMC in person which you
may know I I'm there a couple days a week at least and uh so it was really
nice to be able to sit with you all uh this evening and uh be amongst my
brethren oh and was also able to you know when we do meta practice
it's so nice to focus on somebody else or others and um so it was nice to spend
the energy and the time to really put that energy out instead of you know not
always being this direction yeah so thank you oh thank you
Nancy so lovely that you could join tonight I'm so sorry to hear you've been
sick for the past 10 years that's a 10 year 10 days gosh I just made it yeah
I'm so glad you haven't been sick for 10 years that was interesting um yeah I'm
so glad and wow only 10 days only 10 days getting better every minute
only that was an unintentional te yet yeah but but yeah glad glad you could
join and yeah lovely it's it's healing to be um practicing meta and compassion for others and and for yourself as well
because you have been suffering it's it's it's not easy to be safe there is something healing about doing that
though is to get the attention you know I think when you're sick you sort of draw withdraw in yeah and it's sort of
nice to remember to put the energy out there too exactly that's right yeah
you're pointing out something very important which is sometimes when we are um sick or we're having challenging time
we get a little um caught in our own suffering in our own pain and our like
poor maybe even going to Poor Me Like H and then when we when we practice M and
compassion for others oh just like me oh yeah there are other people I wish them well so it expands our perspective it
makes it lighter it make makes our s our our pain our suffering lighter it's not as heavy it's like carrying this thing
oh yeah it's it's a little lighter so I so appreciate you you you bringing that in yeah yeah it actually feels healing
to me somehow yeah very much so yeah it's it's um and when you say this I'm
reminded by um what I remember reading uh some time ago about um um you know uh
there there many um uh instructions or invitations for example if somebody's
not feeling well or if they're depressed one of them is to reach out to somebody else who's having a hard time to give
them support so call up a friend who's having a hard time if you're not feeling all that call them and give them help
you know so that you're not be being self uh um not self-centered but you
know self yeah self prup exactly yeah or something about what you were talking
about balance keeping the balance too that um is feels right there too yeah
yeah anyway thank you ma'am thank you thank you Nancy so glad you you can join
us hope you feel better soon thank you thanks
Vicki hi Nikki hi yes I I really liked this combination of the balance also and
appreciated you saying that and I I too wanted a little more thought on um just
how you gave that example to help others if there's anything else in Wise mind
when when one is in an emotional mind you know how how you
shift yeah so so let so thank thank you for
that reflection and question and and I'm going to ask you if you would um as
you're asking the question give me a little more specificity so that I know which direction to go yeah I was
thinking today as I was you know finishing up taxes and I was getting a little bit of a hanging at myself I
thought for not doing it sooner you know and I thought you know give it a rest I
could say that to myself but I found my body feeling more uh tense than I wish
it were and so how you um sort of talk yourself down when you know it doesn't matter
you'll get it done and just you know give it a rest it's the puppy thing you know
yeah yeah I'm so glad you gave the example so so what
um I'm I'm still working on my taxes so what I'm what I was hearing you saying
give myself a ranging why don't you work on it sooner why don't you get it and
and my you know where I go when I when I find that there is a judgmental mind like what are you doing it's like it's
okay sweetheart it's okay sweetheart I literally tell my it's okay sweetheart it's all right it's okay it's just it's
like it's okay it's okay um so it's it's an expression of of kindness and that
it's okay and also equinity right because you give that voice you listen
here yeah I listen to myself it's okay sweetheart it's all right it's okay it's
okay it's it's it's um um It's a combination of equinity like it's not the end of the world it's okay and it's
also a compassion like yeah you're really beating yourself up and this is not helpful right now it's okay sweetie
it's like like lay off like it's okay but but focus better if you just you know stop it yeah yeah but it's it's
more gentle it's like yeah it can we can we can drop this we can drop this with gentleness and kindness so that's my
invitation yeah with with taxes yeah especially
taxes thanks Vicki yeah thanks ah and I see um couple of
Reflections in chat let's see um yeah Jerry says to give someone your
full attention to me is a for of Love indeed agreed and um one
reflection uh from one of you is feeling sad for someone very different from feeling empathy to me it feels same in
my heart um so feeling sad for someone is that the same as
empathy um it it can feel the same it can be the
same for some it might be more physical when you were feeling someone else's
pain the empathy could feel more visceral for some people could be expressed as sadness for some people so
we're all different so for the person who wrote this yeah it could be for you
feeling the empathetic pain of someone could be feeling sad with them it could
be that but and it can express itself in many other many different ways as our
mirror neurons can can fire and express themselves in many different ways given our individual makeup
so and Richard says the middle
way yeah not sure that probably referred to something I was saying in real time but yeah I like the middle way maybe
that was about the balancing the the two uh empathy and and love
so so thank you all thank you for showing up the happy hour practicing and
cultivating your heart your mind for the sake of all beings may all beings be
well may all beings be happy be including ourselves I'll ring the bell three
[Music] times a thank you how sweet to be with
you tonight how sweet thank you all I'm going to stop the rec