so hello everyone and welcome to the meditation and one of the
characteristics of mindfulness meditation that's meant to be a characteristic is
Simplicity and now we're I think on the 19th part of this 25p part introduction
to mindfulness meditation that's a lot of instructions and lent itself to the idea that it's complicated a lot to
remember but uh one way of understanding this instructions is that
um you've come into a new park it's a large Park and you never been to it
before and you have a guide and the guide takes you to the different parts
of the park and so you know where they are you know what they are you know how to relate to each part part part of the
park and so next time you go you go alone and now you're not lost you're not
searching for the way you just know okay now I'm here now I'm here now I'm here
and so now it's got become very simple each part of the park is a simple thing to be in because you're well familiar
with the territory so there's a lot of instructions but it's kind of like just
laying out the map of the territory and the mindfulness is meant to be very
simple and um so each of the different parts come into focus at different times
when you're in different parts of the your inner Your Inner
Park and um so part of that Simplicity is this radically simple just
knowing what the experience is and that's how we started this
uh series at the first very first uh teaching the Simplicity of just knowing
what is happening but now you know can hopefully recognize more of what's happening the richness the different
components of what's happening and as you're kind of have understand the the
the the ecosystem of the present moment it's easier to be aware simply just know
it oh this is what happening know it now there's a thought thought just know the
thought and in The Knowing there is some freedom in The Knowing there's some peace in the knowing there's some way of
not being caught in the experience now I just know a
thought being present for the thought now I notice that the thought is
connected to some emotion knowing the emotion look at that there's an emotion
as opposed to oh oh no there I'm thinking again oh no not that emotion
just an emotion and then you're aware with the emotion then because you know the
territory it becomes kind of second nature to notice oh this is a physical part of it this is where it is in the
body and there might be a little bit of guidance you give yourself because you know the territory but um it's the
guidance just to notice where is the most appropriate Place uh to offer your attention now
what's the most obvious place and keeping the awareness very very simple and one of the ways to keep it
simple is to uh one of the kind of the toolbox of Simplicity if is mental
noting just a very quietly name note label the experience you're having then
the actual label is not that important what's important is the kind of deeper
acknowledgment that naming provides if someone you know you haven't seen for
a long time and they say hello to you with your name then you know they've remembered you and they've acknowledged
you more fully it feels good if you're in a room with a lot of people um and uh someone's going around
saying hello to everyone and they see you and for a moment there's a glimmer of delight in their eyes and they come
to shake your hand and as they shake your hand their hand goes limp and they're already looking over to the next
person person and it feels kind of deflating like oh as the person connects
with me I'm not they're not really here for me with mindfulness Simplicity of mindfulness is kind of
like to know it to acknowledge it and name it so it's really acknowledged and
we step closer to it and so that so the naming if we do it is not the end of a
process it's not like a checklist It's A Gentle Beginning of an opening to The
Experience more fully and um so we're
thinking it can be very useful to name the thought label it and um and uh and so it can be just
thinking it could be planning it could be remembering it could be fantasy it
could be storytelling the idea is not to spend a lot of time searching for the right
label but to name it with a Simplicity of
mind we're using a thought the word thinking for example is
a in in the mind is kind of a thought to better acknowledge that we're
thinking so the thinking relaxes so we're not so caught in it and we're
using this thought that's a very simple recognition ideally from a calm maybe
deep de peaceful place calmly peaceful and then this is what it is
sometimes it's helpful to be more specific what it is not just thinking uh something about a fuller acknowledgement
to clear clearly recognize it's helpful so as we do this meditation
we'll do it mostly quiet and as you begin to think turn your attention
and look your thoughts right in the eye with no idea that it's wrong to
think or you shouldn't be thinking just turn to it and like I see
you I see you planning but not I see you like your
problem but uh I see you my friend I see you
planning but not that you're participating in the planning but you're stepping back and just peacefully calmly
ah I see you planning and then as you when you say planning
then unless the planning goes away right away just uh do spend three breaths just
opening to the whole experience of planning and this is where as you open to it you might notice the words that
it's images that it's the emotions the physicality of it you might notice by
the third breath there's someplace you can relax and let go and then Begin Again
with your breathing so that's the instructions main instruction is just look think whatever thoughts you have
right in the eye ackowledge it's there I see you with a label planning
remembering and um and see if you can make that really simple
where The Treasure of meditation is not found can we say it in
the meditation that you're trying to to do but the treasure is found in the
knowing in the how you know whatever is happening so today uh I'm going to just let the rest
of the meditation be silent and you can kind of settle in the way you want and
and hopefully do this meditation uh instructions as it works for you and
fits
you
for
in the last few minutes of this quiet part of the
meditation experiment or discover cover maybe the quietest
way of naming acknowledging being aware of
thinking without being without
participating in what you're thinking
about
for
and now as we come to the end of the
meditation open your attention more widely to take in your whole body your
whole being here and in some simple
way let yourself tell yourself I see
you in a way that you're saying I'm here with you here to support you care for
you saying this to
yourself where the emphasis is to really acknowledge and see in a simple way with
kindness and then opening your awareness more
widely but not leaving yourself out kind of like you're part of a
whole and now gaze upon some form of the
community that is around you in the building you're in and the
neighborhood you're in the town you're in some sense of
broader sense of
community and acknowledge not exactly yourself not ex
exactly them but acknowledge this is a community this is
a somewhat related set of human beings that
contribute to a whole a community a neighborhood a
town and look upon all of you together in
kindness recognizing this is a
community however whatever challenges it might be within it it's
still a whole of sorts gazing upon it kindly recognizing it
and expanding it beyond your neighborhood out into the whole world all people
everywhere you are part of this wider kinship of
humans Kindred Spirits kin in some way or
other and there's a hole often it's very divided with
antagonism and Wars but for a moment to acknowledge we
are a whole we are also a community of Kindred Spirits beating Hearts breathing
lungs and wishing all of ourselves well the whole
community may this wider Circles of community be
happy May these wider Circles of community that I'm part of be
safe may these wider Circles of community be
peaceful and may this Wider Circle of community be
free free of Oppression free of poverty free of
attachment may all beings everywhere be
[Music]
happy
thank [Music]
you
so now we continue now with the fourth talk on mindfulness of
thinking and thinking is an important part of being a human being and it's
best not to be in an antagonistic relationship though it's I know that for
many people their thinking is often a challenge uh get pulled into thoughts
which would you rather not have and
um and what keeps thoughts going is the interest that something in
our system has for them the attachments to certain things
the uh resistance or the being bothered by things we're in a relationship with
our thoughts that is feeding them it's keeping them going and one of the things
we can learn in meditation is if we if we are aware of them directly
fully but we're not feeding them sometimes they go away really quickly
and some people get confused in meditation when they do mindfulness how quickly their thoughts will disappear if
they just note them and see them and recognize them and it's because when with the full with
when the attention itself is not reactive then we're not in a relationship that's
actively giving the food of attention to the thoughts and so this is where even
if we have uh if we really dislike our thoughts and really troubled by them don't want to be involved in
them all that attention and not wanting and being aversive to them that is
actually fueling the thoughts more it's like giving it more attention to continue or not may may not the
particular content of the thoughts but the the tendency of thinking is just
getting reinforced and so sooner or later it's a very valuable to learn the art of not
being bothered by your thoughts not being troubled by even the most you know ugly thoughts a person can
have just just step back and know it from a place that's not entangled or
caught in it and for some people that Equanimity that disengagement from
thoughts while we see them is supported by a simple mental
noting and uh labeling and some people will only use
this technique of labeling for their thinking because it really helps them to
step away and acknowledge and not be entangled in it but to do that you have to have some
sense to Discovery what it's like to know without being attached without leaning into or pulling away or being
reactive to it and one way one thing that supports that is uh to listen to if you're using
a word in the mind of melting like your voice says thinking or remembering or
planning um is to listen to how that is being said in the mind and it might be
that you're not so uh equanimous about it after all by
the tone of The Voice or the strength by which you're saying it some way or other
maybe if you um don't you know if you don't like it uh maybe you're a versive
to it the the inner voice might might say you know you know planning you know
like there's a little bit of you know aversion in The Voice or if you're
having some wonderful fantasy and you really enjoy it maybe the mental
note has the way you say it has a sense of indulging or or or um uh
enjoying like you might say oh fantasy oh that's so good kind of more like that
and you can find you know the relationship we have and find out how to know without
being an active relationship with it just letting it be just seeing it for what it
is of course this is not always easy and um but you can always be
mindfulness even when you're not doing it this kind of way if you're be being
mindful if you simply recognize how it actually is so one of the little phrases another
thought label that can be helpful for some of us sometimes is actually to say
um this is how it is now whatever is happening recogn oh this is how it is
now it's just this how it is now um and whatever it might be if you're
distracted if you're caught up in your thoughts if you're spinning if you're reactive oh so this is how it is now and
this movement this is how it is now is kind meant to be kind of a movement of kind of relaxing stepping back opening
up acknowledging oh without this is how it is without being for or against it
just honest recognition so we can always do oh so this is how it is now and hopefully with
that kind of understanding it protects us a little bit from the idea that uh
meditation is not going well we're failing the very moment you just
recognize how it actually is for you and one of the great labels that I've used
for myself when it just everything was so complicated is I say oh this is chaos
chaos right now and um and and that just creates this great big kind of space for
just the whole catastrophe but with a mindful way chaos and then as I stay
present for that then it kind of I get closer I see oh there's a lot of churning in the chest there's a lot of
fast thoughts and then it's coming closer into knowing something a little more
particular and um so this uh so as we do this was thinking oh this is planning
this is fantasy okay and then there's space to
get see it better and one of the things we can see is uh the glue that between
us and the thinking the pull the gravitational pull the stickiness that's there and that's valuable to know too oh
look those thoughts are sticky or I'm sticky with it I'm attached to it I'm
leaning into them I'm there seems to be a very strong bond between the thoughts in me thoughts in
the mind no wonder I can't let go because I can feel so it isn't just kind
of idea of knowing you're attached but feeling the sensations of stickiness or
strong magnetic pull or or um even the
sense of that oh we're really like stuck together here now and so rather than being upset with that
again never upset just oh look at that this is stickiness this is the glue that keeps the thoughts going and so you now
you're seeing a different part of the experience oh this is how it is this is how it
is so I want to repeat what I said in the beginning of the guided meditation
for those of you who might not hear that um all the instructions we give in
mindful meditation might seem like a lot to remember a lot to do and very
complicated it's meant to be simple and uh what I'm trying to do in
this series of in instructions is to describe the territory that you'll of your inner
experience so that you know how to recognize it that it's there what's happening and know how to how to be
mindful of what you're recognizing of what's Happening so that it's not just one big buzzing confused kind of sense
of suffering or challenge you start seeing that oh in fact there's different parts of it and I'd like to propose the
simile of a park that uh you know maybe you can approach your inner Life as a
Nature Park a natural Preserve or something which in some ways we
are and um and that you've never been in this park before and a nature guide
brings BR you in for the first time and takes you around and shows you all the parts of the park the paths the The
Groves of trees the ponds the whatever it is it shows you around and it turns
out that um you know you don't exactly remember everything in the moment but
when you go in by yourself you kind oh yeah this is where I'm now I'm by the pond or this is by The Grove this is by
the meadow and this is you know where the path goes or and you know you feel
confident you know the way way out um because you you've been told all the pieces of it so that's a little bit what
I'm trying to do here is to show you the territory of Your Inner Park as you end
up in it and then you learn to when you come to the different places you recognize oh this is how it is now this
is how it is here and um and as this recognition this opening this centering
on the experience maybe there can be something inside of you can relax something is
seen something is known something is not struggled with it's it's just recognized
instead of struggle ah this is fear ah this is my my irritation ah this
this is how it is now naming it seeing it I see you so the same thing we're
thinking and thinking is a made up of many component parts it's like a whole
part of the park that is is different paths different pieces that come together to make the whole and so at
different times now you might notice uh these are thoughts I'm thinking in words these are images I'm
think thinking I'm in images this is um fast thoughts this is slow thoughts this
is active thoughts now my thoughts seem angry now they're quiet and calm now they're harsh
now they're now they're this way now they're connected to grief now
they're connected to enthusiasm and an wonderful anticipation and and this is what the
emotion is like and this is where the source arm of thinking so this is not analysis or thinking or searching to
understand but it's just over time as you get more and more familiar with the inner par you can acknowledge oh this is
what's happening now now I see the component parts this is what's happening and um and finally as a way of
not making it complicated kind of a protection from that uh I of I suggest that people use
breathing as a default just come back to the breathing and if you spend some time recognizing thinking the parts of
thinking you might kind of use the the ref the the standard of about uh the
three breath Journey with everything for about three breaths recognize your thinking maybe not
thinking and then open to it and be present and breathe with the experience of thinking for three breaths and then
begin the breathing or if the breath feels like there's a lot of tension in the body notice out tension and just be
with that for three breaths and then back to the breathing for however long it works so that you don't get pulled
into or entangled in relationship with what you know and it's very easy easy to
get caught in that entanglement with things without knowing you are and so
just like a short time three breaths and then back to the breathing so everything is respected
carefully and well but you don't have to spend a lot of time with it you might
come back to your breathing for a while three breaths and then you might the way you're thinking might still be prominent
so you might know it again and then back to breathing that calm going back to the
breathing centering and then maybe going back to your thoughts thinking this is how it
is so um so as you go through your day
today and you notice that you're thinking which I hope you do now you're little more familiar with the territory
in the way experiment again with uh how simply
you can know your thinking and as you know
it what is your relationship to it is it simple or are you in fact leaning into
it or bothered by it and if you are just say oh this is how it is
now so thank you very much so we have one day um more to do
thinking