good day to you a warm welcome to this time of practicing
together again it's wonderful seeing um all of you in the
chat uh very connected with the fact that um how widespread the S
is so for this morning's uh today's meditation I'd like to touch upon the
quality of trust or faith in the practice um the poly word is
Sada it literally means to place your heart
upon Sharon Saltsburg defines it as trusting or own deepest
experience it refers to an inner quality that we all have which unfolds and grows
as we learn to trust that experience when we talk about faith
we're talking about heartfelt confidence in the possibility of our own
Awakening of our own deep
happiness when we place our heart upon the moment we're wholeheartedly present
fully here and we can trust that that is enough to pay attention to whatever is
in front of us whatever is
here and as mindfulness strengthens so does her confidence not to
cling to not try to control resist or manipulate or
experience and often when things are challenging the most important thing to
have faith in have trus in is the trust not to cling to trust the ability to meet the
moment with our open heart so let's
sit taking a comfortable and alert
posture and gently closing your eyes
settling into your meditation [Music] posture take a little time making any
small adjustments so the posture feels confident
dignified allowing yourself to be centered in this body sitting or lying with
strength with dignity now allowing the
attention to meander throughout the body relaxing any obvious tensions that
can be relaxed just that your own pace relaxing
the face the shoulders the
belly whatever is tense letting go of any tensions or
Holdings connecting intimately with this body relaxing this body
and from within this body you might become aware of your
breathing the Simplicity of an inhale and an
exhale just knowing your breathing in knowing you're breathing
out you might take a few long slow deep breaths
and with each inhale connecting more intimately with a moment with each exhale relaxing a
little more deeply Letting Go settling into the round the
chair the
Earth connecting and
relaxing e
and letting your breathing return to normal and staying close to the
breath place think your heart upon a
moment being aware of your experience nothing else is
needed staying
simple allowing any other physical Sensations emotions or thoughts that
arise allow them to come and go see them when they arise
let them leave when they're ready to leave without clinging to them or
resisting them
placing your heart upon the
moment
e
e e
allowing the breath and Body Sensations to remain in the
foreground with the peripheral awareness we can be aware of the
spaciousness that's all around and in this space there can be an
awareness of the arising and disappearing of any sensations of
breathing any movement any thoughts or feelings as they come and
go any mental activities as they arise and pass away
the vast open field of
awareness if agitation arises no need to be disturbed by that awareness is room
for it it's just something that arises and passes
away it's just a ripple and the vast field of awareness
awareness has room for
everything any wanting or not wanting that arises it's not a
problem there's nothing to push away we can just allow allow it to come
and go just waves in the vast ocean of
awareness
there's nothing to do nothing is needed resting in awareness
allowing experience to unfold in its own
time trusting in not clinging to anything in
the
world
e
e e
if the attention has wondered in a friendly
way guiding it back to the
present trusting in Awareness trusting in the
moment
e
e e
we in the sitting I'll ring the bell in a moment when I do you might take a couple
of slow deep breaths again before opening your eyes
for
in this uh fifth talk on the topic of knowing and not
knowing I'll focus on another aspect of not knowing and that's the difference
between the hindrance of doubt and wise or skillful doubt doubt that's useful
so in the hindrance of Doubt um that that hindrance can be one of the
trickiest because it causes that not causes us to not fully apply ourselves
in the moment it makes it easy to get lost in our thinking you know going back and
forth within decision you know just holding back from applying ourselves in the
moment and we can question our own ability We can question method we're
using the teacher or the teachings you might think I you know I
don't think I can do this or am I doing it right or should I try another method
and go back and forth maybe I'll try this maybe I'll try that is it true what the teacher said
about the meditation is it true what the teacher teaching said about practice about the
teachings every one of those doubts might be useful but not during
meditation I like to think of the hindrance of Doubt as premature
questioning it just isn't the right time it's not a useful time it keeps us from going deeper in
meditation from really engaging in the practice because when we're caught in
doubt we're no longer seeing we're no longer seeing the moment we're no longer seeing what's happening we're lost in
thinking and when I was young I decided to learn to walk a tight rope it was uh
all of six inches off the ground um but I didn't know that if I could do that
and I was pretty hesitant it was re it was a reasonable doubt but when I actually got on the
rope that that doubt the question distracted me from walking on the Rope
the only way I can make it across was to steal my mind from anything else and my
feet on the Rope after I fell off countless of times
I finally made it across and so I learned that I could do it but the only
way I could answer my doubt was to
practice with other questions such as am I doing this right or is it true what
the teacher said again those could be very useful questions outside
meditation maybe we do need to understand the method or the teachings better we may talk to a teacher or read
or study about it skillful doubt inspires us into
action to one understand and can be very helpful for mindfulness practice
the teachings refer to three kinds of wisdom and all three are important in
practice and the first one is wisdom from learning such as what we do from
teachers from Dharma talks from study and where we develop a clear
understanding of the teachings a clear intellectual understanding of the
teachings and the second one is wisdom from reflection and that's we actually
mindfully think about a topic maybe reflecting on some of the
bigger questions of spiritual life what's my life's purpose why do I
practice what are my priorities where am
I what are my edges and practice we can reflect as a practice in
itself where discursive thinking is us useful we can also reflect discussing
the topic um with a friend a Dharma friend or a
teacher and the third form of wisdom is the wisdom for meditation the Insight that arises from
practice from formal meditation practice um we might have personal
insights or psychological insights all the way to the liberative insights that
completely free us from suffering from
clinging so the hindrance of Doubt is not productive or
useful it drains us and disconnects us it keeps us unwilling to apply
ourselves might even give up it's important to recognize it and
when we do to fold it back into the meditation not to ignore it but to
actually see it we can question doubt directly is
this a useful question if it is then we can honor it and put it aside to consider after
meditation and maybe take steps to resolve it but we can very clearly just
say oh yeah this is a great question what a wonderful question and I'll do it
after the after my sitting or schedule it for
later and we can turn it back um to you know turn the attention back to applying
ourselves in the moment we saw
out maybe insecurity is there I can't do it or some version of my experience
isn't the right EXP experience we can first recognize the hindrance of doubt we can turn the
attention from what the doubt is about what the thoughts were lost in turn our
attention from the thinking to the experience of Doubt how does the body
feel um are emotions predominant how do those feel in the
body or maybe our attitude is one of resistance we don't like What's happen
happening and we're resisting as we engage in the present moment it disentangles us from being
caught in the pattern of doubt that vacillating world of back and
forth and as her Minds get quieter and quieter the hindrance of Doubt can still
arise but it can be much more subtle and sometimes it's more difficult to
recognize we can get lost in think thinking about it but because the mind is still kind of calm we tend to think
of those thoughts are being even more valid this is a time that doubting or
doubt can be very helpful and the phrase that I like is to
not believe everything we think we can question a thought directly
is it true
now as I mentioned one of the practices that's really important wise questioning in Wise Wise
doubt um it's um wise reflection it's important to not confuse
formal meditation with formal reflection I mean sometimes we do
reflect on things spontaneously and that can be wonderful but it can also be helpful to take time periodically to
reflect on purpose for important questions I find
it helpful not to do it on my cushion but to either go for a walk or sit
somewhere that feels particularly peaceful and maybe sitting on the sofa
looking at the window um yeah somewhere somewhere that
makes us feel kind of cozy and comfy it's helpful to not to demand that the
reflection lead to a conclusion it's an open-handed
exploration it allows us to do this without the pressure of accomplishing
something and sometimes I found it's about finding the right question we
might start with one question but end up with another you know I've asked questions
about my deepest purpose in life I've reflected on impermanence on
death or the question who am I or questions of whether my lifestyle
is supporting my purpose or how to relate to politics or
other challenging topics with an open heart
sometimes even though we actively and carefully explore an issue we still
don't know we can stay open to the possibility
that it will become clear at some point in the future but in the meantime what's
helpful is to patiently rest in the not knowing to accept that we don't know
to be at peace with not knowing sometimes in life we have to
make a decision and we just don't have enough information to make a clear
decision and we may have to take a chance we just don't know and it can be
very uncomfortable not to know the Mind wants certainty and it's really helpful then
to recognize the stressfulness of not knowing in that
situation it's stressful it's Dua and to be compassionate with
ourselves when that happens and instead of being frozen and
decision when there's no way to figure it out we may need to just take a chance
and move on and jump into something
so Sharon salsburg said that faith is the quality of the
heart that stays open beyond or current level of
understanding it's the quality of heart that allows us to persevere into the unknown in meditation
practice and in our daily lives for the insights into to the
deepest Freedom we need to be able to
trust entering the unknown if we knew we'd be free
already so repeated faith is the quality of the heart that stays open beyond our
current level of understanding and that's a not knowing
mind a beginner's
mind so I'd like to end with a quote from from Gil franel I think you most of you have
heard of him right you have doubt about
mindfulness of the value and importance of just being
mindful borders and having doubt about the value of being present for life in
general because mindfulness and being present
for life is the same [Music]
thing so thank
you let's sit with you in silence
and read your
messages and I just wanted to again thank you for this week together this
week of your practice
and to extend our
wishes the benefit of this practice to the entire world wishes of
Peace the wishes of
wisdom the wishes for Freedom May the whole
world be at peace e