hello everyone and welcome and welcome to a
practice that is meant to place Us in the middle of our
lives and to see it through eyes of
wisdom place it in the middle of our life and to see things clearly as they
are and so there's a kind of in that call for seeing things as they are is a
call for a certain kind of realism certain kind of honesty and
truth about what's actually happening here and now and the emphasis to over
well for much of what wi Buddhism has to teach is
to become wise about what we're experiencing here and now at this time
the city of wisdom and the word PA the poly word for
wisdom sometimes I think the way it's described and understood it could uh
maybe better be translated by the English word Insight in that it's about seeing or
understanding something that's right here certainly there can be AB abstract
wisdom but that kind of encompasses many things and we carry with us but Insight
is something we do here now there was a story I heard many years
ago about a Sufi story about a person who goes to a Sufi master and says I
have this ring and can you engrave a piece of wisdom that's always going to
be useful for me on the ring and the Sufi Master says okay come
back next week and the following in week the Sufi
Master had the ring ready and on it it said this
too will pass this too will pass in Buddhism it's a little
different but it's related to that this too will
change anything that is a experience that touches our senses that is
something we can think and any thinking any thought any this too will change and so these
eight worldly winds this too will
change and there's something meant to be very profound about keeping this in mind
the Buddha emphasizes this over and over again a wise person knows this too will change
and if
uh there are certain places in the world where I learned not to worry too much
about the weather when I lived in Hawaii because it changed quite
quickly there' be torrential downpours over it last a
minute or two and then it would be 80° outside and sunny this too will
change when I lived in Tennessee they said if you don't like the weather just
wait five minutes this too will
change and the question is not whether you believe it or like that piece of wisdom but the real Wise Way of relating
to this piece of wisdom is how does this wisdom how does
this understanding that this two will change how is it beneficial for you how does it
support you how does it benefit you how is it nice for you how does it
free you this too will change
so so the assum a meditation
posture and to to take some
time to notice what changes for you as you assume the meditation
posture as you tune into it and maybe make small adjustments Here and Now
to be a to tune into your body the position your body is
in adjusting
it is a way of developing and entering
into a living awareness
of here and
now and gently not too much just
right take some deeper breaths so that you feel in the inhale the expansion of the rib cage
maybe the swelling filling of the
belly maybe the lifting of the shoulders
and then relaxing on the exhale and if you maybe if it's
comfortable to allow yourself to Exhale more longer than
usual in the part that's longer than usual there's some way
to drop deep inside the body for a deeper relaxation of the body
and then [Music] to let your breathing return to
normal and and then notice what a a simple ordinary breath is for
you and if you're controlling the breath in any way or doesn't feel comfortable
that's okay the emphasis is on knowing how it
is you're breathing with an open
mind almost like with a little bit curiosity
not judging it or needing it to be any particular
way
continuing for a few breaths with relaxing on the
exhale settling different parts of your body
releasing e
and then gently
notice as the body breathes it's a continual flow of
change changing movements changing Sensations
relaxing the thinking mind relaxing the mind that strains to pay
attention instead
allow the changing sensations of
breathing allow them to be
sensed where there's no separation between sensing and
sensation where it's the body's experience of breathing
more than an mental exercise of looking or
knowing resting with a changing flow of breathing
and whatever happens during the meditation
gently understand that this too will
change where that understanding is a way of helping you
relax around what is happening be less reactive or caught
or resistant this too with ch will
change allowing whatever is there permission to be
there so in its own time it can
change
for
e
for e
if you find yourself involved caught
reactive in a loving way caring way remind yourself this too will
change where the purpose of saying that remembering
that is to relax around What's
Happening Here and Now relax the
reactivity relax the whole holding or the
resistance
for
e
for e
and then as we come to the end of the sitting to understand that the
wisdom that this too will change is not meant to pass judgment or
just to see the world in a particular way but rather to help
us not cling or resist or hold on to
anything to allow us to shift our relationship from one that can be
understood as reactive to one that is
responsive from some of the wisest places
within and one way to respond to this changing
world changing world of our experience is to meet it with
love the different all the different flavors of
love so if what changes is difficult difficult for people for
yourself to meet it with Compassion
Care if what changes is is a positive thing to meet it with appreciative
Joy appreciation if what happens in the
world is near neither suffering nor great but just something
happening love can take the form of being friendly
kindness Good Will and if what happens in the world
is difficult for us and we cannot intervene or do
something about it but we have to against all our preferences there has
to be some acceptance of it or some not getting caught in it love can
take the form of
equinity where there's a love for others and ourselves we don't allow ourselves to
get worked up or caught or reactive in a way that interferes with
the flow of open love care
compassion this too will
change and in this changing world may it be that this wisdom
supports us to enter the world with kind
heart with a friendly gaze with a Caring Heart
may we go through the world not with hate but with love may
all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings everywhere be free
[Music]
thank
you
for e
so hello everyone and welcome to this last talk on the the eight worldly winds
and this is a kind of a summary talk or concluding talk about it and um the uh in the in the Buddhist
teachings the word wins is actually not in in how he calls this uh he calls it
the eight worldly Damas dharmas which in this context I like to
translate it as the eight worldly forces eight worldly processes that and
he says in describing this that these eight worldly forces turn the
world and that the world he repeats then the World Turns on these eight
forces and um and so what we're talking about here is the human world and
primarily in this human world uh if we read the newspaper if we look out across
the globe and history and what people are doing we see that uh that uh a lot
of the preoccupation a lot of the reactivity and involvement people have in the world can be uh caught up in gain
Greed for more and and loss and the despair over uh you know losing wealth
and losing our things and not succeeding to become um you
know wealthy you know sometimes at least around here Silicon
Valley and then um the the world roles
revolves around uh Fame and disrepute and not a few people have had their
life uh destroyed in the this very
shallow Fame of social media and that is the rise and fall of Fame and Instagram
and friends and Facebook and um but politicians and
celebrities and all kinds of people the pursuit of Fame and despair
when it's lost and then there's praise and blame and some people live on that that they
their sense of self is based on what other people think and so praise and blame is the
pursuit and then there's uh Pleasure and Pain comfort and discomfort and um and uh forms of
happiness and unhappiness so the involved in that
these are what turns the world the human world keeps it going keeps it
spinning and so the Buddha uh is talking about this the emphasis is not on that
these other worldly forces but rather is our relationship to it how do we relate
to it how do we live in these in these forces and these winds do we participate
them do we get involved in them are we caught in them and um and the particular thing that the
Buddha emphasizes is that a wise person knows
that these forces all the things that come with them that they are um
inconstant that they will perish that they're changing and so this idea of that is
knowing they're changing reminding ourselves so that when there is Gain No
this too will change and um and not a few people lose
their wealth not a few people what they thought what they had gained disappears
and as tragic or difficult as that is there's something about knowing that
that world is perishable it's changeable that we don't put all our bask all our eggs in that basket so our happiness is
100% dependent on on what we've gained you know so a house that burns down
a stock market that crashes a wealth that is stolen as tragic as
those is there's a way of reminding oneself oh this is changeable this is
perishable so that they're not quite surprised by it the point being not to
have a judgment or a view about it but what is the what is the wisdom that
allows us to keep our peace to stay at ease to not get despairing or crushed or
so disappointing that we kind of just shrink away is there a way is there
wisdom that keeps us free is there wisdom that keeps us peaceful wisdom that keeps us calm and wise and and
loving and this is one of the ones the Buddha offers and so if you don't like it you don't have to use
it but in terms of these worldly forces uh to be reminded this two it will
change and um and then that does that allow us a healthier relationship to the
world a better relationship with the world a relationship where we are can
enter into the next moment freely so to show up at your car and see
that that uh you have a flat tire or two flat tires um to oh this too tires
change this too is perishable and uh and now I've encountered this part of our
world now how do I relate to this to be remind a little bit of that do that take
a little bit the edge off the reactivity the the surprise the sense of Injustice
or that the world now is out against me um and uh is there a way of
staying with a degree of ease or peace or what wellbeing or calm in the face of
all the changing Natures of this world especially for these eight
worldly forces that are so much what people get caught in so that's the the
um the kind of the overview of these of these some people have uh some of their
lists sometimes of these eight worldly of uh forces instead of calling the
first one gain and loss will call it success and failure and this is another
one that people often get caught in in the need for success and maybe in a
competitive world or need for success and where our identity is tied to being a successful person and that if we fail
that somehow we're somehow less than and I love as myself stories of
people who conventionally or you know in some ways fail but it doesn't uh stop
them they continue with what they're doing I love the story of people who
have success but they don't kind of hold on to the excess or wear it you know as
a kind of a medallion to show people they're happy with succeeding and then
they go on to the next thing to do they just love doing they love being engaged and the idea of holding on to something
even success um it's just doesn't have quite the the um the interest than it is
to engage and step into the world for the next thing in a full and open and clear
way so praise and blame there's these are not necessarily bad things uh that
people appreciate us not bad things that people point out are faults and our mistakes so is there a different way of
relating to them that all praise is you know that we don't have to push it away
but we don't have to hold on to it we can new way of Rel relating is to be open and allowing and make room for what
is healthy and to ignore what is unhealthy and not be involved in it gain and loss is not a wrong thing to
have um that we can appreciate the gain and we can be wise about the loss and um
but the idea is to find our freedom and this is the central theme I'd like I tried to get across this week that um of
these eight worldly forces there are better ways of living than
tiing our life to these things and the Buddhist practice hopefully is showing us a better way of living of being alive
that we have a a very satisfying feeling of peace or calm or Joy or happiness or
Freedom lightness uh that um that is it
alternative to these is being caught or involved or depending on these eight
worldly forces and so that it's not a matter of judging them or or having
critical of them or but rather it's a matter of not losing what's better not
sacrificing the what's wiser and a Freer and more loving more caring way of being
in the world because we know that we've learned that and so even though Everything
Changes in some way uh it doesn't mean that things are chaotic and random or
that we are without preferences and there are things to have preferences for
and preference without attachment to peace preference without attachment to a
sense of well-being and joy preference without attachment to being wise and
caring preference without attachment to being um grounded and settled here at
this moment so we can be present for this world not reactive to
it and um and so to know that there's something
better so one of the wisdom pieces that I've offered recently the idea of don't
make it worse at least don't make it worse but if you know what's
better perhaps it's easier to avoid making it worse so thank you and uh I
um appreciate that the chance to teach these teachings and I'll be back here on
Monday and some of you might be interested in coming with me on Sunday
evening at 6 six o'clock in California time I'm going to be be on Zoom at
Spirit Rock to talk about my new book a little bit the everything is practice
the book is a kind of a manual for doing Insight Retreat uh Retreats like
Retreats at our retreat center and uh so I'm going to use part of that evening uh
to really talk about Retreat practice itself not my book and um and one of the
great things that Spirit Rock does is offer a month-long Retreat and I'll talk a little bit about that monthlong
Retreat and and how wonderful it is I taught it for many years and uh sometimes I say that for
people who are inside practitioners that um like for a Muslim
once a lifetime they're supposed to go to Mecca I'd like to say that for inside
practitioners once a lifetime uh to do a month-long Retreat Insight
Retreat so um so you'll find the information about
it on uh Spirit Rock website and also an IMC is what's new that on the homepage
uh there's uh uh Reflections from Gil there's a a link to that if you if
you're at all interested so thank you