so welcome to our Friday and end of this week on
the instructions on mindfulness of the
body and uh strictly speaking the way that I was taught mindfulness in Burma
at the place called the mahasi center the
um we weren't practicing exactly mindfulness of the body that wasn't precisely the description more precisely
we were practicing sensory awareness there was
a referencing almost everything you experienced to how the how how it was
felt in the body in terms of Sensations and uh it was a wonderful
Adventure because so many of things that go on even even thinking which the thinking itself might
be disembodied but uh uh the process of
thinking the energy of thinking the the pressure of thinking can have a physical
component emotions uh we probably wouldn't even know what emotions we're having unless
they were somehow connected to our body and uh Body Sensations that we
feel and uh and so to refer everything back to the body to the sensations that
U make it up now
um today ID like to offer you a little different uh way of
practicing um what we taught so far this
week and that is to uh have a centering or a a home base in the
breathing but you don't have to stay there for very long don't feel like you
have to kind of develop concentration on the breathing for this exercise but rather it's the default you
come back to it regularly and maybe maybe it's only three or four breaths it could be longer
if it's enjoyable to do so and then you let the awareness take
in some sensation in your body perhaps the strongest sensation in your body or
if you've already recognized that a few times to recognize something else whatever one one way to do it is just
whatever comes to you if you open your awareness to the body what what sensation come into
view and um and then know them feel them like you we exercise a few days ago like
feeling the hand feel that place of your body take it in but in both of these the
breathing and the sensations see if the the thinking mind
can be quiet enough that it's not projecting projecting its ideas on
what's happening ideas can give rise to a feeling of permanence or constancy or
but if we can feel or sense instead make a sensory awareness exercise out of it
then with the breathing you'll see that there's a a flow or Kaleidoscope of
different Sensations that come and go on inhales and exhales the sensations of
inhale are different than those of the exhale and to kind of just take those in
and then when you bring your attention to some other part of your body then um see if you can be quiet
enough in the mind calm enough enough that you can start becoming aware of how those
Sensations are also um Dynamic that they are coming in
and out of appear they appear and disappear come in and out of awareness they move they shift they dance um it's
fascinating to get really clear or Lucid
awareness of some strong sensation and see that it's not constant it's kind of
flowing and moving and jumping around in all kinds of ways and
uh and uh and then the way to move between the
breath and something else then back to the breath and something else in the body back to the breath is to do so in a
very calm flowing way like uh like you're just kind of moving in a relaxed
way natural way between them and the the the reference point
that I like for that is if you have if your eyes are looking at something anything maybe her mountain or the sea
or a river going by or something in your room and your your eyes are just roaming
gently landing on something and then floating away to the next thing landing on floating away and there's a ease or
relaxation in how awareness flows and here we're flowing to the breathing then
flowing to a body sensation flowing to the breathing and feeling maybe three or
four breaths and then the length of time that you're with those that breathing uh when
you flow to a body sensation you're with maybe maybe that's that's all the length of time you're
there and if it's a painful sensation knowing that you're just doing this briefly can be very helpful because you
don't have to get stuck on it or reactive to it just oh just tapping in kind of like just being present for it
like touching it with a soft cotton ball just oh I'm here a few breaths feeling it and then
going back to the breathing so assuming a meditation posture
and gently closing your
eyes and becoming more established here and now in your
body by taking some long deep
breaths
and then to let your breathing return to
normal But continuing maybe on the inhale feeling tension holding in your
body and the exhale relaxing the
body
for
and then settling into how the body experiences
breathing and the areas of your body where breathing occurs
there too as you exhale relax that whole area
soften the breathing
process
and then to begin the practice of
today maybe you can do a three breath
Journey staying with the breathing closely and in a friendly soft
way and then to after those three or four breaths
too let your awareness be relaxed and open to or receive the
strong sensation in your body or some sensation in your body and
feel that for three or four
breaths and then returning to your breathing
and if that is too fast for you you can stay with your breathing longer and stay
with the sensations longer but track yourself so that you don't get caught in thoughts
or reactive so the awareness
stays soft
light
for
e
and then continue with going back and forth between breathing and Sensations in your
body but as long as it's comfortable to stay with one you feel like you're well connected
and not becoming distracted stay with the breathing or
stay with the
sensations maybe until there's a Clarity to know that now
it's time to switch something else needs the attention
now back to the breathing back to some
sensation
for
maybe it's not that the Mind moves attention moves
which is a metaphor anyway but rather that
awareness doesn't move it just receives sometimes it receives
breathing sometimes
Sensations
so the mind is soft and
relaxed
and when the thinking mind becomes quieter so we we can sense more fully or
deeper see if you can notice how Sensations are
changing shifting
moving pulsing flickering in and
out
for
e
for and if it's easy
enough let go relax any holding or
fixating of attention any contraction or pressure
tension in the mind espe esally in relationship to breathing or Sensations
doing this practice when you switch from breathing
to Sensations Sensations to
breathing let it be a welcome occasion to let
go let go of any holding or fixation
for
e
and then coming to the end of the
sitting as if the curtains are
pulled let your awareness now take in be aware of the wider
world with an awareness with an
attention which is relaxed and peaceful as possible easeful attention for the
world gaze upon the world with Good
Will wishing that the practice of mindfulness that
you're doing will benefit the people in your
life people in your communities your society and the whole
world and may it be that all of us here in this meditation
collectively benefit a few people even in small
ways on this day and so collectively we have a huge
effect on the world spreading care goodness
generosity may all beings be
happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings everywhere be
[Music] free
thank [Music]
you
e
so my friends so this is the last talk on this
having to do with instructions on mindfulness of the body and next time will be mindfulness
of emotions the um I was reminded Yesterday by
someone that she had asked me many years
ago for some books to read on Buddhism and I had told her that the
only book she needed to read was the book of her own body and um apparently this was made a
very good impact on this woman this prct this practitioner
um and uh so the idea that our body is a book
to study the body is has information has wisdom everything you need to know about
Buddhism can be found in your own body and the meditation practice that I
did in Burma that when I was really learned this bipasa practice was as I've said was was a
sensory awareness practice more than anything else certainly we were mindful
of the mind and mind States and mind activity but there was this default to always feel and sense how it is
physically the S sensory level of it and part of the advantage of that is that
um Sensations are not thoughts thoughts and ideas and stories and Concepts is
often where we live or or it's often the filter through which we see our experience and so we see things a little
es skew because of those ideas we have those Concepts and even Simply Having a
concept of something the concept can have a kind of enduring quality a
concept is like platonic concepts are unchanging and so there's a kind of
feeling that things can and if we see through that filter it can feel like oh nothing changes and so if you see your
friend um always in through the filter of some difficult experience you had 10
years ago then you're not seeing how the friend is changing or different every
day or every occasion and every minute and every hour but you're suck in that that lens
that perspective so to begin meditation where we begin quieting and calming the mind
and settling in and getting somewhat concentrated or still that it's not the purpose of not
just to become calm but rather to be able to have a kind of more Lucid
awareness of the sensations of our of our direct experience unmediated by
these Concepts Concepts ideas might still come into play they might be there as part of
the bigger picture but they're not the lens through which we're seeing and we're able to perceive or to
feel much more directly the direct sensory experience experience and uh and then to begin
seeing how that is Shifting and moving the seeing the inconstant impermanent
shifting changing nature of Sensations has two major benefits that I can think
of one is that um
um that uh the tendency to fixate on
something uh has usually a lot to do with holding things in kind of permanence or thinking things are
permanent or trying to make them permanent trying to make things as they are and there's when things are shifting
and moving it's it's more likely like we realize we can't quite grab them or hold
on to them or kind of begin relaxing the grip and this is one of the reasons why
breathing is so relaxing for some people is that the rhythm of breathing in and out it's constantly shifting and
changing and it's settling it's opening and it's a kind of focal point for the
mind not to get tight or or straining as it might be with it when it's thinking
about plans or resentments or desires or hostilities we have uh when thinking
about things from the perspective our conceit and so to begin loosening up the
ways in which we're stuck by breathing helps things to relax so the same thing
with the sensations of the body if we start feeling difficult Sensations pain for example as shifting and changing
Sensations then the extra added layer of lens of reactivity of judgments or fears
or projection into the future it's always going to be like this begins to soften and relax as
well and so that's one advantage is that um uh it's easier to be to relax to let
go and to kind of just be with this the river of change within us the second
benefit is that when we're just at that sensory awareness level of our
experience the sensation level um we're not again we're not
imposing our desires we're not imposing our expectations or our Concepts or
ideas and so it gives more room for those Sensations to to be
themselves uh uh if um if we're tense in some way or say like I'm angry and I'm
making a fist If I Stay it's looking at whatever is you know thinking about
whatever I'm angry with the fist stays clenched but uh if I feel the clench the
tightness in the fist feel how tired the hand is becoming feeling the pain of the
clenching just feel it closely uh and start feeling it more as shifting
changing Sensations sometimes my little finger sometimes my thumb sometimes the back of my hand sometimes the palm of my
hand my fingernails going into it it's very sharp the stretching on back of my
hand feeling all those Sensations something begins relaxing there
softening the the natural tendency for the clenched hand to release has room
now to relax it doesn't have that room to relax If I Stay seeing the situation with
anger so so there's something about creating that uh this awareness of s
sensation sensory Awareness stuff is um allows things to
be um flu uh makes it's like kind of like giving
room for things to move towards health things to begin flowing and moving in
the way they should should and the amazing thing is that
those things that are byproduct of tension a byproduct of clinging or
holding strain attachment those things begin to
dissolve and those things that are byproduct of an openness of a generosity
of kindness of of uh emptiness spaciousness
those things begin to grow and this wonderful re movement that
the things that cause suffering things that have to do with attachment begin to
dissolve if we make space for things and room for things and like the clenched hand begins
to relax the open hand and the sensitivity of the Open Hand um the um the uh this
gesture here mudra here in Buddhism it means the Buddha do does sometimes is the gesture of
friendliness and the gesture of the Open Hand pointing down is a gesture of
um of um safety offering safety to people and
so there's something happens with the Open Hand something releases and so and so in this process of feeling
and sensing and discovering our body in a deeper way the sensations and not being stuck on anything but being open
and receptive something begins shifting in our body shifting in our heart shifting in our
minds and and uh because the body is so closely connected to the mind and the
heart as the body changes so the Mind changes as the body relaxes and softens
so the heart does the same so in this sense um reading the book of
your body is so profound so significant the body in some ways the experience
body the body that we experience to a great degree uh it uh how we experience
is is influenced by our thoughts our minds our judgments our priorities a
selectivity process that we select what to pay attention to maybe based on our
desires our fears our conceits and so to stop making these selectivity
process but allow it to open up is um is really
great there are some schools of uh vasana inside meditation where they do
body scans systematic going through different parts of the body over and over again and so that the whole body
steadily over time is visited with this kind of generous attention and seeing
and feeling and making room for that part of the body to show itself and be seen and maybe relax or unfold in a good
way in the tradition that I teach in we don't generally do the body scan
systematically but it's more like we have the idea is that um the body knows
what needs attention so the basic instruction is to let the breathing be
the default if that works for you and um and develop mindfulness on
the breathing develop attention on the breathing um develop concentration on
the breathing and breathing is a shifting changing flowing series of
Sensations so a lot of the benefits of just doing sensory awareness practice can be right there with the
breathing but if some other sensation becomes more predominant then the idea is to switch
your attention from the breathing to that predominant sensation in your
body and um and just be with it as long as it seems to need attention and be
present for it and feel it when it's acknowledged enough or it's or it shift
and changes and and it kind of faded away or become less strong then go back to the
breathing and so it's a little bit random where the Mind might go what part
of the body might speak over a long period of time much of the body get
our attention but it's not done systematically uh uh the body knows what
you need attention to and so this idea that the wisdom of the body operates
whether that's literally always true I I don't know but it's a wonderful
attitude that oh the body knows what I need what needs attention now so rather
than saying oh no this shouldn't be happening oh no I shouldn't have this pain oh no I shouldn't have these these
Sensations the idea when we do this practice is oh yes the body is speaking
to me now it this is the body is saying here now this needs
attention and you don't make it any more complicated in that the interpretation but uh just a very different attitude
the body knows and then feel and be with it and then come back to your
breathing if there's a lot of strong Sensations in the body maybe you there's a long time
before you come back to your breathing that you would just kind of maybe go from one sensation to another and just
tap into them and be with them for a while and when in doubt come back to
your breathing be with your breathing and if breathing is not a good object for home base for you then uh
some people's home base is just Body Sensations all over the body and just kind of gently
letting the attention just flow and move between the different parts of the body the body speaks and shows you what needs
your attention so thank you so
this last week talking about breathing and this week about the body um is very
important in many ways but for what's coming it's extremely important as a
reference point as a basis of foundation for practicing mindfulness of emotions
and mindfulness of thinking which is also coming we can be more wisely present for
our emotions if we're really grounded in the body so I won't be here next week I'm
going on Retreat and I'm delighted that um uh Nikki mapori is coming to uh teach
next week wonderful teacher here and it's been subs suting for me regularly for uh on this YouTube uh
teaching and um so you're in good hands and then when I come back I'll pick up
this the series on introduction to mindfulness with mindfulness of emotions so thank you all very very much
and um and um if you'd like some homework
during this time I would encourage you to review uh what we did this week about
mindfulness of the body and the homeworks of different days that we did just for the just kind of deepen your
your appreciation deepen your connection to your body for this next uh you know 10 days while I'm gone and um see if you
can become a much more a better friend with your body well
connected thank you