welcome uh welcome folks nice to see uh see some names over there yeah a lot
of um warm associations so so welcome uh we'll sit as we do I'll
guide something I don't know what we'll see what uh the moment brings and
um yeah can uh enjoy each other virtually
so just gently take your Dharma posture posture of your
heart for
tranquility and alertness in some Dynamic tension
sometimes we stretch up towards the
sky our
spine but then give the rest of our body
to the downward pull of the earth
gravity e
craving clinging holding on
attachment creates waves of
tension it's so hard to control
experience some part of us never wants to go let
go maybe another part of us
is really ready to surrender
surrender to the goodness and the imperfection of this
moment and in that gesture of surrender
the possibilities become more
apparent so before we even try to pay attention to something
we notice the little whirl
pools of holding on and control of shaping
ourselves of proving ourselves getting
somewhere and we deeply
relax
and yeah you don't get to have the exact life thought you wanted
nobody gets the exact life they
wanted so whatever heartache there may be in a
very small microcosm way or big we we just breathe into
that for
and here here is my life this moment this
breath this is what it's like to be me to be human
then let me honor
it by not pushing and pulling on it molding
and shaping
and so now paying attention to our
breathing is not a a
test it's not a
task but a kind of
pleasure
for
e
e for
that we can influence our life creates the illusion that we control it or we
own it but we don't exactly own our
life and meditation is a way of honoring
that e
in management it said uh you give an employee a lot of uh
responsibility very little power so very painful inheritance very
compromized and that's kind of how our mind
feels a world of responsibility not much
power and so we're very
anxious frantically adjusting any knob we can get our hands
on
can we
trust
awareness
e
e e
thinking is
coping nothing wrong with
coping but uh maybe
we don't uh need to cope with this
moment but inste can receive it heart can be penetrated by
it can trust this moment to become wisdom
love
e
e e
okay so uh yeah good to good to sit with you it's a little bit of a somber
meditation but um my heart is
good so um question that was submitted some some
weeks ago um says uh uhen goenka
Goa says attachment and suffering are always found
together he says we're addicted to the condition of craving the object is
secondary craving becomes a habit we cannot break is interesting to me because when
I look at the object of craving then it fades a kind of letting go could you
talk about the condition of craving and how to feel that seems it would be uh
going more to the heart of the matter
so um I thought to let that be a kind of
I'll kind of try to answer but uh let that be the launching
point so the the the bud said um to
study study the the the Dharma is to study causality cause and effect cause
and effect causes and conditions supporting conditions this is the realm
of course of uh of science where in in a in an experiment
you sort of control everything to isolate the cause and then see what the
effects are and generally in Buddhist circles
the interest is in one particular effect effect namely
suffering and suffering is the the effect of of causes of the the tradition
highlights craving and clinging attachment clinging is the kind of
elaboration and strategizing sponsored by the
craving so but suffering um is is also uh is not merely an effect it's
a Cause right it can be the cause
of um of tremendous goodness or tremendous destruction are
suffering a lot of our path is like okay how do we how how can suffering be a
cause of goodness our suffering leads to the critical realization of like I don't
know what's going on exactly maybe I've been wrong maybe there's a
path suffering can be a cause for purification the untangling of the heart
from greed and hate suffering can be the cause of love and understanding and
suffering of course can be the cause of more problems bad
strategies that grow out of our suffering uing meant to manage suffering
but compound it the cyclical nature of
it normally the formulation is
craving leads to suffering craving and clinging lead to
suffering but I think as step Bachelor added also suffering leads to craving
the reverse suffering leads to craving unhappiness leads us to
Crave so much of our compulsive acquisition and materialism and is a
function of that right so much so much fantasizing about
some perfect pleasure you know that that that that fantasizing emerges out of
sense of incompleteness but it's not just
um objects that cause craving it's not that there are things out there in the
world and that causes the craving right even if
Donuts had never been invented no human had ever heard of a
donut I would still want
donuts it's not that the objects cause craving craving
points us back the seeds lie
within and maybe we say craving is the condition of
needing anything to
change it's a kind of tension and craving is the sort of natural response
to suffering when we do not have Equanimity
Clarity it's the natural response to suffering something's wrong all right what do I do crave
something crave some answer some soothing some pleasure
some the riddle to be resolved right and so craving is is a craving suffering
very very closely knotted together and I say that that's kind of
bold language in a way but don't you know it's not don't get idealistic about
it should I not crave oxygen not crave food or something no just don't try to
find the you know the kind of far end case and then sort of reason
your way out of it no just study your mind study your mind to be uh free of craving free of
compulsivity that is at the heart of of freedom and there's something in us that
so deeply longs to be free from craving we essentially want that more than the
object right we can only imagine the end of craving by getting What We crave
getting fill in the blank right but
um sometimes I almost see that as like the whole world like
longing for nibana longing for for the
Dharma and yet we try to get there
through Amazon whatever right what we want is the
cessation of craving because it's so
painful and yet in this cycle of dissatisfaction and
craving and acquisition that's been reinforced just endlessly
endlessly and so it's something like we could talk about in different ways
but um it's something like incompleteness or
suffering craving acquisition partial
fulfillment partial heartbreak repeat until we
die I I try to be careful about uh what's called like concept creep you
know using a word like uh addiction or something which is
the example at hand using a word in broader and broader ways defining it
down and I want to be careful about that but there is some parallel with this
kind of like I I don't want to say that a you know a casual longing for a nice piece
of clothing or a tasty bite of food or something is the is is addiction or
something but there are some some parallels to the
cycle and um George CB who's a kind of prominent
addiction researcher leads National Institute on uh alcohol abuse and
alcoholism um characterized the this this cycle and
so Cub writes uh addiction can be conceptualized as a thre stage recurring
cycle binge and intoxication withdrawal and negative
affect feeling and then preoccupation anticipation
craving that worsens over time and involves neuroplastic changes in the
brain rewards stress and executive function systems goes on to say like the concept
of an anti-reward we normally talk about drugs as like rewarding Pleasures as
rewarding right but there's an anti-reward system was developed they
say to explain neuro adaptations in response to the excessive
utilization of the brain reward system it's compelling evidence that the brain
stress and emotional systems are recruited as a result of excessive
activation of the reward system and provide an additional source of negative
hedonic veence unpleasantness the combination of a deficit in the rward system and the
recruitment of the brain stress systems provides a powerful motivational
State mediated in part by the anti-reward system the
our body punishing us when we don't get what we are conditioned to
want as a bad cycle there's a lot of pain in
that and that reaches its peak in the context of
addiction um but they're even below the thresh hold of addiction
we can recognize ourselves in some of that so how do we deal with with craving
well it's partially maybe we say the the whole path but
um a few things uh come to mind
so partially we become awake to the disappointment involved in that process
the disappointment in it you know we we don't focus on the object of
craving we we actually start to notice how painful the condition of craving
is even for that which we love we pay attention to the
unfulfillment the partial heartbreak the withdrawal the negative
feeling the cyclical loopiness of the whole
thing and sometimes we really renounce for a
while like retreat or even just a sit for half an
hour we really renounce and that actually winds up
sensitizing our system to pleasure just like kind of anti-reward system in
response to the bombardment of our reward system to
actually sober up and then we actually become more sensitized to pleasure we need less of
it to feel really good to feel happy and maybe
just the a nice day nice Sunset is more than
we need sometimes we bore
right into the kind of the belly of the Beast uh equinity with intense feeling
you know craving is a kind of commandment to
act everything it feels like every cell in our body is conspiring to get us to
move to make a move and we just stay
and then sometimes just in a moment sometimes very gradually we get happier we get happier
on the path
and the more fulfilled we are the less incomplete we
feel we don't need to be completed we already
are and so
craving is a a kind of strategy that at least
temporarily is unnecessary I offer this for your
um consideration and uh happy to to uh
dwell in this uh path with you be uh away next week back on the the
14th so hope to to see you then and
uh I wish you all well