so uh so welcome good morning to uh for most
um yeah lovely to see uh See the names over
there um yeah we we will uh check into uh the
recordings I don't know if I'm supposed to post those or they're being posted but uh it was
recorded and um we'll get that up okay uh let's um let's practice
together e
so just uh just beginning with the kind of uh
sweetness of community spiritual
friendship which is not uh its own kind of silo
but actually a sense of um
belonging and shared
sensitivity that uh allows us to uh
meet the intensity sometimes brutality of the
world we we've genuinely cannot
do this
alone
e e
just settling into your your posture
and take not Hans says like a Nector settling to the bottom of a glass of
juice
but it's not like we push the nectar
down we just let time
and Stillness become our allies
there's entropy but there's order two let me just let the Dharma
order organize our body
mind
for
e
e e
and how many things might you stop
doing how many of our routines do we associate with
practice that are actually just a kind of reiteration of our
self-doubt agitation
e
for
e e
how simple might awareness become how simple might you
become so relaxing all of the push and pull
all the self-improvement and all the
acceptance all the moving to and
from all the ways in which we continually hum The
Story Of Me Mine my
life all the willfulness and control
how simple can we
be
for
e
e e
the sense of self is an avatar we
use to organize our greed and
aversion e
maybe it's safe enough in this
moment to put that down
e
e e
[Music]
okay so
um that's good to uh good to say with
you um so uh non-hate love love is the theme
this week and
um sometimes we have the sense that disliking
liking loving are are three points along the
same spectrum and um that uh you know when I
I you know I might hate you I might like you I might like like you or I might
love you right but
um that's not right to my mind uh love steps outside of the realm
of ordinary hedonic
preference in other words um love
is not another species of
wanting the the the Buddha suggested that uh that wanting and fear
are are two sides of the same coin the coin of
clinging and it seems like we wanting fear such different
states but at the
um excuse me at the at the felt experience level
of wanting and fear what is shared is is a certain kind
of motivational desperation and there's some interesting
brain silence science that um highlights the some of the shared kind of
neurobiology of wanting and fear kind of motivational
pressure salience that's either negatively or positively valanced making something
wanted or feared and both
States contract the Mind both States make this moment in and of itself
essentially meaningless you turn the moment into a
transaction fear and wanting turn life
into uh a dollar store or something and met uh is the Mind Made
vast loving kindness practice is is stepping out of
wanting and fear and so love is not like some strong
form of wanting it's an entirely different motivational
stance it's an openness and a receptivity it's what's
left in the wake of letting go
love is what's left when the motivational desperation Fades
away love uh met you know um loving
kindness It's many things functions in many ways but first there a purification
practice and you know by purification
practice uh you know technically I mean Extinction
learning um much pain depends on
avoidance not all but much pain depends on avoidance
and the medicine is often to approach the avoided experience the
feared experience to drain the affective charge from our anxiety and
avoidance and um mindfulness is one type of
approach moving towards a lot of the instructions we give are about moving
towards right love in a sense is an even deeper
approach than mindfulness not always but often the more fully we
permit ourselves to experience what's avoided the more completely we're
released from that pain the more efficient the extinction learning is the
more thoroughly discharged the knots of
uh pain avoidance anxiety untangle and love love is like the
fullest approach we can make we get so
close you know our our love to um yeah to our our our pain or what
whatever may be that it it starts to unwind this is this is kindness as a
kind of purification practice
we should unpack you know what's meant by love that's not everybody's favorite word I know some of you probably are
cringing you know like love love love love
um so what's meant by this well uh a mentor years ago once said
like Matthew there's a difference between kindness and
niceness and you're being nice
okay the kind of love I'm speaking about is not is not
niceness there is a love that um in is Tangled Up with
possessiveness and a love that relinquishes control entirely a love
that's a kind of pure generosity giving Donna
there's an you know an attached love and that's okay like that's I'm not dismissive of that we're
not uh monastics and we're going to have to pick our
spot and partners parents children ethical
commitment some attachment I feel is irreducible you know to those
those relationships um a friend I've known for many years
since since um his now teenage daughter uh before she was born and uh
not so long ago I asked asked him how how are you you know and he quoted Susan
orene to say uh a parent is only as happy as
their least happy
child I thought about a line uh from uh
from the uh songwriter an an def Franco said something like uh all be your lover
even after our atoms are dispersed will be pushing up daisies and
my crush would just be getting worse it's kind of romantic
yeah can we consent to the the Dua in that we
know is encoded in that not be surprised that that's going
to hurt can we bear that with Grace and not
resort to some utopian fantasy of the love completely devoid of all
attachment is not a perfectionistic path we have a tendency to try to shoehorn
our spiritual ideals into every aspect of our life is not
natural and so we we recognize we live in some measure of ambivalence we can
consent to the forms of possessiveness inherent in some kinds of Love even as
we try to let go and we
cultivate a love that is devoid of possessiveness that uh loving kindness
is a kind of um uh a love that seeks no control
the proximate cause is um the capacity to
see goodness love in the face of goodness that is
what the Wellspring of meta love and the face of
goodness and amidst the the ascendency
of hatred and confusion and
hypocrisy um I I become so so sensitive
to goodness forthrightness honesty it it sometimes Feels Like
Oxygen like my heart is just like longing can we be
honest can we uh recognize
goodness and in in in Psychology there's um there's
a phenomena uh known as moral elevation whereby witnessing acts of moral Beauty
they might be huge they might be um seemingly
trivial uh witnessing acts of moral Beauty inspires elevates we become more
devoted to goodness you know just witnessing somebody being
kind in small or dramatic ways makes us more
pro-social it's important for us to see
that and loving kindness is its own kind of inner moral elevation in the sense
of you become moved by your own
goodness you become moved by it and you touch into that not in a
self- congratulatory way not even the sense that this qualiity is mine mine no
it's the melodrama of self again but we sense into these qualities
of the heart and we become uplifted in the same way
that we might become uplifted in seeing moral Beauty in
another and we abide we abide vihara rest a place of of of uh of
rest an abode abide in
love the sense of the warmth radiating from our own body mind it's maybe very
quiet no control no other side of our love
nothing
excluded and part of the function is just to
um the kind of healing and rejuvenation for the heart in
that and part of the function of of that practice is
to uh dramatize the pain of hatred and divisiveness of
Separation aversion hatred in other words hatred is meant to become less and
less tenable it will still grab us
but we abide in meta to make it less and less
tenable so offer this for your consideration and uh please pick up
what's useful and uh leave the rest behind okay see you uh tomorrow