okay folks so uh welcome
um so in a moment we'll uh we'll sit but just to say that
uh a lot of different ways we can break down sitting but
uh illuminate the different facets of what is entailed by meditation
but one distinction that feels important to me is uh we're we're learning to
train the attention that kind of attentional Spotlight uh and we're learning to uh
stay open to not let the awareness collapse even when intensity is running
through our system through body and mind
and we can get overidentified with the attentional facet of practice Focus this
breaths the kind of Stillness seclusion um but uh part of why we do
that actually is to strengthen the capacity just to stay uncollapsed amidst
intensity and we study collapse at a kind of micro level it may not happen in
some major meltdown during a sit but there are little micro meltdowns
where something is even just the urge to to um you know to scratch an
itch is a is a subtle kind of meltdown that we pay attention to okay how did
that happen how did we get kind of overrun uh and we pay attention to those
little micro collapses because
is they happen in more significant ways in our lives so what does it mean to actually
stay stay open even as the kind of channels the affective emotional
channels are stimulated and might lead us to the kind
of awareness collapsing into that intensity so we're directing the
attention and then keeping a certain kind of uh Poise amidst amidst uh the
intensity so let's uh let's
practice
so without laying too [Music] many conceptual maps on what meditation
is we just uh take our posture take our
posture
we kind of trust that there's enough uh goodness
here to fuel our meditation
forever
the intensity that is life seems to
beg the awareness to collapse kind of
claustrophobia of problem
solving but
we practice staying open broadening the
awareness
raising the kind of threshold of intensity that can be
tolerated without devolving into problem
solving
and we we notice with um patience forgiveness we notice the
ways that uh intensity lures us into the problem solving
mode awareness
collapses
very innocent movements of our
mind and here we're exploring just
knowing intensity without being seduced into the
fantasy of solving it
so we establish this
openness a certain kind of reverence for the first Noble
Truth that there is duka
intensity
and then when we direct attention to our breathing or
body
soundscape the attention doesn't feel so
brittle
the seclusion settledness Refuge Stillness is
supported by uh
relinquishment
any given moment is uh
imperfect but awareness makes it good
enough
we're attending in a simple way and we hear that kind of siren song
of uh maximization
optimizing the moment solving
problems carefully tracking threat opportunity awareness
collapses you just reestablish that openness by blessing the
intensity with uh okayness
reestablishing a sense of the open field of
awareness and maybe before it feels safe again
to just be with a kind of attentional anchor the breath or the body may just have to reestablish the
sense of okayness of intensity it's
okay let the energy unwind in the
body
the only thing better than solving our problems
is not solving
them
all
okay good to say with
you the only think better than solving our problems is not solving
them I mean what is that I don't know where that came
from sorry you know uh it makes sense in the moment you
know okay so
uh Faith doubt
um the uh the Buddha said that uh if we if we get stuck in in doubt uh
it's like being lost in a desert without the map you know
and one one conception of information
information is that information is the reduction of uncertainty the reduction
of uncertainty and every every um moment is rif with
uncertainty you know we're so hungry for for data to clarify exactly as the
Buddha said moment so open hungry to
reduce the uncertainty of the moment and the information that we get
is through um through our senses and through the mind and this is this
reduces the level of uncertainty doubt doubt is the
absence of trustworthy information and so
uncertainty indecision abounds and we don't know what to trust
in doubt we don't know what to trust where to look where to harvest data from
where there's this kind of like frenzy in the
looking hungry for information but can't find it and we don't know how to
interpret what we do encounter what we do encounter and so it's like
um uh you know all all noise no
signal and people in in doubt um they tend to kind of like really
bounce around one mindmade narrative to another
kind of swinging between vacillating between different stories that may be
highly incompatible it's like this grappling with the static the static and doubt
and all these kind of yeah mindmade plans ideas Frameworks but they emerge
not out of any kind of deep sense of groundedness embodiment they're just
like just trying to Overlay some conceptual narrative on this basic sense
of uncertainty and in that state
we um might be especially kind of influenced
by the the views of others over trusting others we look to kind of like okay
what's the prevailing views or something maybe that's it maybe I get my information you
know from there and um we tend to uh to really get
lost in a world of thought and rumination and
um thoughts just feel so so real they feel like the the most important
data and it's a little like um we we sort of keep taking our
thoughts out for test drives but the ride never feels quite
right test float it float
it now part of why people get um get
Meed in doubt is that they ask the practice to do things that it can't
do we get mired when we are asking the practice to do things it can't do the
practice will not insulate us from the ungovernable tides of Pleasure and
Pain the practice cannot insulate us from from the
changing this of all things we we get mired in doubt when we
try to out outsmart the first Noble Truth that's part of what I was alluding
to in the sit was like okay can we just not collapse amidst the intensity of the
first Noble Truth even just here on this day together in this lovely
s just to stay still is intense and that kind of
encounter really with the first Noble Truth um uh can lure us into the fantasy
that if I just kind of could think hard enough could Harvest
enough information from my thought I'd find the answer but often there there's no answer
there's not an answer exactly to the first Noble Truth dukka
is coming for all of us regardless of what we are thinking and so to try
to um to imagine the kind of dooka free path when we're at some fork in the
road that leads us into doubt out you we know those moments where it's just like
oh let me let me I'm at this Fork like maybe if I is it just a two two-pronged
fork or something can I go is there a third way is there some some Dua free
path and we just spin in
doubt sometimes um our our craving for
certainty is what actually creates the doubt certainty is going to elude us
right but our craving for it is what what leads us to spin into
doubt so um Aristotle said something like wisdom satisfied with the degree of
precision that the nature of the subject admits and doesn't seek exactness where
only the approximation is
possible in formal practice doubt doubt manifests
as um sometimes as like uncertainty about
technique you know should I do vasana or meta is like this kind of like Dharma
fomo you know like there's some I'm missing something something you
know or doubt manifests as the kind of rush to fit all the puzzle pieces of the
Dharma together you know just to like make
everything square with everything else or doubt manifests as getting mired
in in kind of theoretical um questions you
know of sometimes doubt is like with a sense of like oh yeah we're performing
meditation for someone even if that's someone is just our own inner audience
our own you know meditation super ego or something or performing for the teacher
or something but it's like that that that's an expression of a certain kind of doubt and faith
faith simplifies things so much relaxes
amidst Faith
we're we're no longer hungry to uh confirm that we're on the right
path we're we're no longer uh kind of so preoccupied with
doing it right we know we're just going to keep going like and of course we're doing it right and wrong and we're going
to learn we're going to grow Sharon solsberg uh speaks about um Faith as uh
you know written her book of Faith um as the process by
which uh you come to trust your own experience I think that might even be
the subtitle of the book it's like coming to trust your own deepest experience
there's a kind of power in that in our faith a certain kind of Independence
grows we start to know what to
trust and it engenders patience
and uh you know it doesn't matter anymore how long something takes how
long the path is going to keep going
and uh aun aun suito likened Faith to
like a hinge point on the door and once once that hinge is set the door is going
to swing open sometime you
know the teacher's job is mostly to get you know maybe it's to get people to
to the point where that Hing is set or the point where in a sense there's no no
going back you know and once once a person's there once
there's no going back mostly the job of the teacher is just cheerleading you
know and um that door will swing open that door
will swing open and so the Dharma doesn't doesn't feel
like a choice we have to keep making doesn't feel like a choice we
have to keep making there's
Faith so offer this for your uh your
consideration and uh
yeah I wish you uh wish you a rich day of uh of practice of attending of
staying open poised amidst intensity uh and uh entrusting your
heart to what's trustworthy okay see
you tomorrow
yeah