so hello and welcome
and if you I'll find a little amazing that this is the
24th talk of these 25 on introduction to mindfulness
meditation I feel fortunate to be able to spend this time on these the basic
take instructions and develop it this way so thank you for the
opportunity and um so
today one of the Hallmarks of mindfulness practice is its
Simplicity there's a lot of instructions that can be given but those instructions should be
considered more descriptive than prescriptive in the sense that they
describe what we come across as we're present attentive attuned to our
experience the instructions in a sense are a map of your the range of important
range ranges of your experience that you then bring the Simplicity of mindfulness
to or say it differently you allow experience to come
to you and then you have the Simplicity of
recognition oh this is how it is this is how it
is it's this way now and you might try this little
sentence as you practice either saying it in your mind or just
recognizing it silently that this is the way it is
now this is the experience now keep it that
simple but the word now at the end it kind of reminds you that it's
just the experience of now it's not forever it'll change in some way it'll
shift and change become something else become an appear in a different
way this is the experience now in the course of this now sometimes we experience breathing
sometimes the Body Sensations sometimes emotions sometimes thoughts sometimes
sounds and what I'll introduce today is attitude the general mood or attitude
with which we're being mindful mindful often is not so simple
we come along with subtle AG subtle or big agendas like we want something to happen we want something to go away we
want to attain something we want to hold on to something an attitude of this is
difficult or attitude of um you know this is too easy and I'm
I'm a sophisticated person an attitude of being for what's happening or being
against it and as an attitude what it means it's not really articulated
it's not exactly you know a thought or even a belief or you wouldn't if you just rely on what
you're thinking you might not even recognize this but it's the background mood with which you're being
aware and it's a little bit of a windrag to mindfulness it keeps it from being
simple it gives it weight it gives it tension strain uh
hesitation and it isn't that we have to fix this
attitude it's just one more thing that's recognized it's like this now this is
how it is now and to see it clearly recognize it
clearly and keep it simple so simple that in the
recognition there's a freedom or a in the simplicity
there's a peace in the Simplicity and if it seems boring that's
just one more attitude oh this is how it is now so we'll sit this way for the rest
of the sitting silently you can settle in on your own relaxing and
settling and then um maybe if you'd like you could use this phrase
it's like this now or this is how it is now but keep an eye
out from the beginning middle and end of the sitting for the
attitude with which you're being mindful if it's not obvious don't worry
about it but you might keep an eye out and see what it is and see what happens
if you simply recognize it oh this is how it is
now hold it in awareness and then maybe continue with
your breathing so so we'll start quietly silently this
time
for
whatever is happening recognize it as simple as you
can recognize what's obvious in the moment and if what you're aware of is
vague just know it as now I'm experiencing
vagueness if the mind is drifting off a lot this this is what a drifting off
mind is like any
attitude any feeling of being for or against
something any background desire
aversion this is what's happening now
no need to go
searching and if you are searching recognize that you're
searching simple mindfulness of what comes into
awareness now
for
with the reference point of keeping it simple
with a reference point of just now you might feel or
recognize the pull away from that the drive to do other things
besides just the Simplicity of now this
experience and it's possible to know and recognize this is the drive away
from the present moment this is a drive away from
mindfulness
for
and then as we come to the end of this sitting take a few moments to
recognize whatever sense of Simplicity is
available if you're a little bit calmer or more
settled or if the awareness is a little bit more [Music]
clear or if there's a little more acceptance of the challenges that are
here and in this Simplicity to be still and gaze upon
what's what happening
kindly and then to bring into mind that you're going to come out of
meditation soon and maybe return to what is your
normal life or more complicated life
and from the vantage point of the meditation to be simple for a few
moments and gaze upon it
kindly considering the people you'll
encounter both people you know and people you might don't
know you'll pass in the streets meet and in stores or work
anywhere and imagine yourself with kind
eyes a kind friendly disposition to everyone you pass or see
or encounter
and is there any attitudes that get in the way of that Simplicity of
kindness and if there is recognize it this is what's happening
now and then returning to whatever degree of kindness good will you can
have and Aspire even if you can't do it aspire to be able
to wish everyone well-being may all
beings be happy may all [Music]
beings be safe may all beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free May kindness be carried in my gaze of the
suffering [Music]
world [Music]
thank [Music]
you
so hello and welcome to this pen
altimate teaching on introduction to mindfulness
meditation and one of the useful distinctions to
make is instructions in meditation which are prescriptive
and those that are descriptive and uh same instructions can be offered in both
ways and in uh prescriptive means this is what you do and so you apply yourself
to do something and descriptive means um it
describes what you'll be aware of the first is a little bit more
active and some people find it very helpful to engage actively with meditation it's kind of like play for
them and or it's they just naturally kind of enter into the world of doing
something um and so it's really nice for them to kind of engage in the
instructions like this is what you do and and uh and one way to do that is to
have a checklist to go through and you can do the what have the the the core
elements of this these five weeks mindfulness of breathing mindfulness of
body mindfulness of emotions mindfulness of thinking you can almost kind of go through and do a kind of little bit on
each one uh start with the breathing then recognize what's happening in the body then emotions and then uh
thinking or you can do the other way backwards and some people find you know to just have a very clear program like
that keeps them engaged keeps them focused and you know it's becomes an uh
you know prescriptive of what they do other people find that that's not helpful and other people find it's more
helpful to kind of sit back and not be so much in the active mode of practice
directive mode of practice but be more in receptive mode and uh and there the instructions
then become more descriptive that if you are present with an open available
awareness to the present moment experience then different things will come at different times whatever is
loudest in the sense maybe and um and so um and so sometimes you're aware
maybe the sound of a neighbor making and that's what's most predominant uh or maybe it's uh you know
sometimes it's the breathing sometimes it's an emotion sometimes thinking and it varies what comes into awareness
maybe it feels almost random but it feels so so relaxing and nice to not to
be the doer and just be in this kind of available present moment with this now
here this and um and sometimes it's useful to
know both ways and that there are times when we're more active in the practice
more prescriptive which is what we're doing and other times it's more descriptive we're just describing what
we're what comes and arrives in awareness so for example when we start practice
it's usually a little bit more active but as we settle and get
concentrated um still there's less and less that we want to be doing and we
more and more enter into a more uh maybe a receptive mode or um and
if if you go further even receptive is too much doing we're just there here and
phenom PHA experiences arise and um without receiving them or going to them
to experience them they're there and um so um so to be aware that
there's there's different modes in which we're being mindful sometimes a little more active sometimes more directed
directed to the breathing sometimes more I don't know if the word passive is
the right word but uh less doing and more being
aware and rather than directing the attention it's um there's there's no
choice or direction for what we're aware of except what comes and arises and uh and then there's a
combination of the two which is a little bit more what I like to teach and that is that um we all the default is always
to have the attention somehow directed or available or receptive to the
breathing the rhythm of breathing the experience of breathing um so there's a
steadiness and a subtleness and a as we go along and so the Rhythm the beat of
the breathing is a bit of a protection from mind wandering off uh
unknowingly and we spend a long time just drifting off in thought because we're kind of keeping breath at the
center we kind of more likely notice when we start drifting off if the mind is just receptive and
quiet and available to everything then kind of in a certain way everything seems okay and the mind drifts off and
we hardly notice it and uh and there isn't a Clarity of knowing oh the mind
is now thinking and um so the the com combined
to this kind of active and more receptive modes is to use the breath as
a default but then whatever arises in any any direction any place that is more
predominant uh that becomes the focus of meditation so if it's a sound outside
then we do listening meditation if it's a sensation in the body we do sensation
mindfulness of sensation if it's uh thinking mindfulness of thinking if it's
um you know and it's an emotion mindfulness of emotion and it might seem random and it just as it as it works
out sometimes as the mind gets quieter Stiller more concentrated sometimes it's
like we go through layers within us and the different layers different parts of
this stand out sometimes more body sometimes more emotion sometimes more the cognitive
um um aspects of the mind and all along we want to kind of be
attentive to is there an attitude being cared buried in the mind is there some
subtle kind of mood that the it's in the awareness in the mindfulness maybe
there's a subtle or maybe not so subtle striving trying to get something maybe
there's subtle sense of of um in the Buddhist use of the word conceit some
idea that I am and it's I have to do it I have to be successful and I'm the
controller the agent the doer that is a little bit extra it's kind of like a mood or a flavor that's there that adds
a little bit of uh weight or a little bit of wind drag to the mindfulness it
does it it keeps the mindfulness to being really clear or just kind of open in a in a relaxed way
simple uh there might be attitudes of being uh background attitudes we carry
with us of being little bit aversive to everything that happens or every or it's
always an orientation to what we want wanting something and so this Le
slightest little Movement we become aware of something and we immediately it's like I want that
or I don't want that it's kind of in the in the way that we're aware where the
aware the awareness is selective to see where can I where's that button I push
to make it go away or something and
um but in terms of the Hallmark of meditation of mindfulness meditation being
Simplicity the um the uh mindfulness is being Des mindfulness practice
instructions being descriptive that it just describes what comes into awareness
sometimes is a really good reference point for remembering to keep it simple
learning how to keep it simple that uh trying to not have agendas and trying to
in the active mode it's a little bit too easy to have agendas that are coming along with that purposes values desires
that we have that are more complicated than things need to be and um and so
sometimes going back and forth between a little more active and a little more uh receptive kind of mode can help us kind
of work through some of the attitudes some of the extra baggage we carry so that the basic practice becomes simpler
and simpler just being here just showing up just being present with
this this is what I'm experiencing now this is the sound this is listening this
is a sound now this is an in breath now
this is a sensation now and and then with each each movement
of now like this it's like the doors have been open the windows are open and then we allow
ourselves to feel that experience more fully so that cognitive part that's
something like this is my experience now is kind of like a Prelude to okay
this and experience it for a moment or two or just allow yourself to really
feel and experience the experience of the moment and as I've said earlier in this series
sometimes it's even nice to take three breaths just be with some that's Arisen
this is the experience now and then breathe with it three times and then
return to the breathing so um I hope that uh what I
said today doesn't uh promote your more complicated meditation for you but uh
maybe gives you some options or some understanding of some choices you can make to try to keep your meditation
simple and do it in a way that's appropriate for you your way now what's
needed for you and um
so final thing I'll say is that um a
good reflection to do maybe near the end of the meditation when the meditation is over is to think back about through the
meditation what happened in the meditation and uh uh could you have been
simpler could you have been more Mindful and what would it have taken so
at the end of The Meditation to reflect how it went to learn from how it went so
for example it's easy to drift off in thought and think about something that's
really unnecessary and not really know it that you're doing how much time you're spending that way but when you go
do the review so wow I just spent 15 minutes
thinking about I don't know the Great American novel I'm going
to write but I I don't even know how to write but I'm just kind of in the fantasy um I think I could have woken up
earlier I think I could have been a little bit more diligent in being present let's try let's try to do a
little bit better tomorrow so that review of meditation and seeing what you can learn and where the traps were where
you got off track can be very helpful so you become your own teacher how to find
your way with this practice so um so we'll continue tomorrow and uh the
last in these 20 25 talk series and uh also tomorrow at uh when
we finish at 7:45 in California in 24 hours from now uh we'll switch over to
zoom you can stay on YouTube if you want but then you won't be able to participate in a zoom kind of way and um
and uh we'll have a community meeting which means that uh uh I might have some
things to say that I would like to say maybe about our YouTube and community
and what's happening at IMC um I can take some questions from you uh and I'll
offer the responses I have we'll do a breakout group where some of you can meet each other and say hello and maybe
see some of them meet some of people who've chatted over this time and um and so it'll probably be
about um you know uh 45 minutes we'll do
that maybe a little bit longer but um and um so those of you who come I look
forward to having you there and I'll post the information on the imc's what's new and probably by this evening and
also I'll post it on the chat tomorrow and uh a number of times so the beginning end of the sittings and stuff
like that so you can find it so you you'll be more instruction tomorrow and
um finally I'll say that the the the password it'll be password protected the zoom room and the password will be meta
so the the poly word for loving kindness It's spelled m TTA and this will all be
clear yes in the other places as well so thank
you
for