good evening again welcome
welcome so tonight I'd like to start with a story that we find in the ear the
literature of early Buddhism but part something that I think is remarkable
about this story is that it's not only captured in the Buddhist literature of
ancient India but other religious Traditions at that time I think that I
think it's in the Janes and I think it's and some like Proto Hinduism stuff so
this was like a story that was kind of like float this is my interpretation know some Scholars would say this as
well a story that was kind of like floating around and then different religious Traditions as they do kind of
like sucked it up and Incorporated it and made it their own so uh this is a
something that comes and maybe you've heard this heard this story I know I've heard it uh in different settings a
number of different times and then um I'd like to use it as a springboard to jump off on to talk
about uh some topics which you'll hear about
shortly so there's a king and uh he asks somebody to uh round
up some of the people that have been blind since birth individuals who have
never had the site faculty who cannot see
and the um individual does this it's a group of uh I don't know like maybe 10
or so people who have never seen before and then the king instructs uh the
person show them different parts of an elephant and tell them that this is an
elephant so show them an elephant but only one particular part so the person says to the king okay
and so he shows uh one person the elephant's head showed another person
the elephant's ear you know these big flappy things uh the Tusk the trunk even
for me this is interesting that it's listed out specifically right the trunk the elephant's body the elephant's foot
elephant's hind quarters the tail and the tuft at the end of the tail so all
these different parts of the Buddha I'm sorry of the elephant and uh so to each person he
shows them he like brings their hands and allows them to touch this particular
portion of the elephant and he says to them this is an
elephant so one person's with the test at the end of the tail one person the tail one the air ears etc etc and then
the person who's doing the king's bidding tells the king okay I did that
and then the king says um oh no the king says to these individuals
directly the king says tell me what is an elephant
like what is an elephant like and one person says it's like a
pot this is the person who touched the head and the other person said no no no it's like a fan this is the person who
had touched the ears and another person said it's an arrow it's a pole it's a
room it's the wall of a room like this is the person who was touching the big side of the elephant uh it's like a post that's the
person who was touching a leg was like a mortar it was a pestl it was a broom that was like the little tufted on the
end of the tail I thought no no no it must be like a broom and then they started to when the
blind people when they heard other people saying what it was like they were like No And elephants like this it's
like a broom it's not like a fan it's not like a fan it's like a broom it's like a uh the wall of a store
room it's not like a arrow or a pole or a pot or you know so they're all
disagreeing an a an elephant's like this it's not like that you wrong I know what
an elephant is like I felt it and it feels like
this so then they uh got in you know arguments as you might imagine and they
started to get in fist fights saying no no no I know what's true and clearly you
don't know what's true and the King was
delighted he loved this this it was like entertainment to see you know these
people like fighting and uh disagreeing like hold having a particular View and
holding on to it and um getting into fights with
others and so maybe that's kind of like just how the story ends like okay this was just
like entertainment for somebody else there's a lot of stuff in this
story actually there's a lot of stuff in this story but one thing that maybe I'll
start with here is that often that we don't
really um hold on to or pay attention
to and that is what we see happening in this story is there's these individuals
they are having an experience they're touching a portion of
the elephant so they're having like tactile
experience like there's this is nothing that uh really can be denied or disputed
or argued about right I mean they felt what they felt and then they made the this leap to
a mental construct of me they it's like this an object that they made up I mean
they didn't actually feel a pot but they said it's like a pot it's like a pan or
sorry a fan or a post or a broom so they made this transition from
what's being experienced felt to an idea
this is natural humans do this all the time of course we do right we need to uh
um makes we like to make sense of our
experiences but there's this way in which we don't even notice this that
thoughts are like the map of the territory we've heard this expression before right the map of the territory
thoughts are the map the territory is the actual
experience and sometimes it doesn't matter that there's a distinction between the map and the
territory but here we're talking about people getting into fist fights getting into conflict kind of blaming each other
say I'm right you're [Music] wrong and they're basing it on a thought
that they have after having a sensory
experience and this is a big part of what Buddhist practice is about what meditation practice is about for us to
learn what is the distinction between a thought about
something and the actual experience of
something the difference between a Concepts you know ideas views beliefs
opinions thoughts these all fall in the same category they're just mental events
I shouldn't say just mental events they're really important and they're helpful we need
them and it's helpful to make a distinction between these all these mental events and then what's actually
being seen what's actually being heard like the experience of hearing the
experience of feeling the experience of seeing because there's this way that
thoughts they are creating kind of a if we wanted to compare it to the
experience of the sensory experiences there's a way in which thoughts are like
kind like flat and two-dimensional and
fragmenting like it's this not that as opposed to an experience
is just an experience it's not a way in which we
are drawing all these lines and uh distinguishing it from that or the other
thing it's just an experience a scent that we smell is just something that we
smell where as soon as we start to bring Concepts in and Views and thought
thoughts and beliefs we start to uh start to be making divisions just
natural of course we do this it's partly you know how we make our way through the world just to this is a chair uh not a
frying pan or you know something else I don't know we can make up something
else but there's a way in which that um sensory experience we
might say is uh vibrant and it's fluid right it's not
like there's this clear delineation where one sense experience absolutely
stops and then the next one begins like with vision or uh feeling or what we're
smelling or something like this whereas with thoughts we like to draw straight
lines make clear distinctions and make judgments and often we kind of like or
assigning like okay this is good and this is bad which can be helpful and valuable
and a useful thing to do but there's a way in which we can do
this that we get completely disconnected from the
experience in the same way that a menu is not the same as the meal there's a way that we could get
into fights about what's on the menu and forget that there's even a meal we can
get into fights about the map and get disconnected from the actual
territory which is our experience our life's
experience so maybe in this example of the uh blind people and the Elephant we
could imagine that they could have said it's instead of saying it's like a pot
it's like a fan it's like a broom they could have said h i experience it as big
and kind of round I think it's a pot I experien it
as flat and kind of big I think it's a fan that's really different than saying
it's a pot and something is wrong with you if you think it's a fan if you think
it's a broom I don't know what you're smoking but that's not it or you know whatever is going on with this
right so there is this way that if we talk more about experience if
we tune into our experience it creates a way in which
there's some maybe some openness some spaciousness and there's a way in which
it can be onward leading I experienced it is really
big instead of insisting nope it's a store room or that's the way they're
calling it in the poly the word is story room so that's one thing that's happening in this story there's this
translation from an experience into you know a concept about what it's like but
then not only that these people are coming to fist to cuffs because they're really cling
they're really holding on to this idea that they have based on their
experience and there's this way in which uh they're really invested in their beliefs like people wouldn't come to
fist to cuffs if they didn't really care okay I think it's a you think it's a
broom yeah so what okay what's for dinner but no instead they are feel like
really entrenched and that they have have to somehow um
defend their belief here so in my mind I I'm imagining like
what what makes a person think that it's you know this is so important enough that they're willing to fight physically
fight harm others and harm themselves risk themselves getting harmed maybe
there are some underlying beliefs under underneath the concept
that they're holding on and these under underlying beliefs are something like I know what's
right or maybe it's something like how dare they question
me who don't they know who I am or maybe there's something like uh
that's very disrespectful to question me so I have to uh stand up for myself I've
been disrespected in some kind of way because they don't agree with me with uh
my experience or maybe there's something that they're thinking like oh the king
is here I better look good for the king I don't want the king to think that
other people can push me around and so something that's common
with all of these thoughts or these beliefs in here is that they are
self-referential it's all about me it's all about the way that I look
the way that I think not me as Diana but right you know these self what they're holding on to
you is tied up with their ideas that they have about
themselves and it's quite something if we start to really look at uh the things
that um get us agitated or things that we find
ourselves getting really wrapped up in and Tangled Up with we'll discover that
there's a way in which there's this uh sense of who we think we are needs to be
propped up or bolstered or defended it's tied up and often it's not
maybe the first thing that we're noticing but it's a belief underneath this underneath of this
feeling of uh maybe there's something like well I don't want people to know that really I I'm not quite
sure but so I'm going to pretend like I'm really sure or you know something
like this I don't want people to uh know that I have this doubt this doubt about
myself or doubt about why I'm even here why did I get uh us to touch this
elephant or maybe they have a life of uh their life experience we don't know
maybe they's Shame about their they not being able to see and they're feeling confused about uh why the king asked
them there and they think that well maybe this is an opportunity the king needs somebody who's never been seen and
I got to make myself look the uh biggest or the best so that the king will choose
me for something to so I can get out of this life of poverty we don't
know but there's all often around this sense of I have to look
good or I have to defend myself in some
kind of way this is often what's uh behind when people are really holding to
some beliefs or ideas that they have and we know this right kind of like in
the Buddhist teach teachings this is a a theme that we see throughout so many of the teachings about how ginging holding
on leads to suffering holding on to our beliefs
leads to suffering and suffering being this you know one word that has this giant range
of meanings from just this slight irritation to just the most horrifying
thing ever this single word for this big big big range of
meanings and so some of we could say that the suffering in this setting is just being in
conflict and feeling like having to defend ourselves but there's this way in
which thoughts and beliefs and our views
they're important they serve important functions we need
them and they can lead us astray lead us astray away from a life
of Greater Peace and Freedom and ease and well-being if there's a way in which we
are overly attached to them just clinging holding on to them and if we're
mistaking them for reality if we're forgetting that they're the map and not
the territory if we're think we think if
we're thinking that uh these mental events which are they just come and go right for any of you who have ever tried
to meditate and all of you did right you sat here for 30 minutes quietly maybe
you were planning your Thanksgiving meal but for those of you who weren't trying to meditate you notice like how many
thoughts come and go and beliefs and uh views they're in
the same family as thoughts right they're just mental construct they they are completely
insubstantial so there's this way that just to recognize
that clinging and I've given um other talks on this this idea that just
clinging to our views clinging to our beliefs I'm not saying we shouldn't have any beliefs and I'm not saying that we
shouldn't have any views it's when we're holding on to them
so tightly that we think it's okay to harm others based on
them that we think it's okay to um just like
abandon things that we know that are harmful to ourselves and others and and
so that we can hold on to these views and I appreciate that part of the
way that that Buddha when he spoken about an awakened person somebody who has complete Freedom complete
ease part of the way that he described them was person who doesn't get involved
with disputes because 100% guaranteed as soon as you
start clinging to views and beliefs there will be somebody who has a
different one and you will be in
conflict and may have disputes so the Buddha describes a
completely awakened person as they are not an enemy to any Doctrine seen heard
or thought out not forming opinions not shut down and not desirous they are the
wise ones who have laid their burden down the wise ones who have laid their
burden down so what is this burden the burden is having this sense of self that
has to be protected and bolstered and defended at all costs sometimes it feels
like and so this isn't a belief that you have to adopt about the not being this
permanent self this uh entity that's at the core the essence of us you don't
this is not something that to be believed whether I tell this to you or whether you read it in a Dharma book or
hear it in other Dharma talks or something this is something that comes from
experience this is not something I mean it could be a view you could adopt of course but it's really not until you
have the actual experience and usually it's a meditative experience experience not always that you start to see like oh
yeah there's actually nothing here except just a whole collection of experiences a whole bunch of them moment
of seeing a moment of feeling a moment of hearing a moment of sealing a moment of thinking feeling and that's just
what's happening that's it but sometimes we want to grab onto
them and uh create a a separate self that we is enduring
but there's this way that uh trying to defend what we
think this separate self is that we hold on to views but there's this way not
don't that this holding on as I said causes suffering but part of the way this suffering shows up is as this
dogmatism or this sense of conceit like
I know it I don't know what you guys out there are doing but I know right when we
have these things that we're holding on to this sense of uh there's some must be something wrong with everybody else who
disagrees or maybe there's this self-righteousness or this
indignation which just leads to
division I'm not saying that we have to agree with everybody and I'm not saying that we
can't have values and Views and beliefs but there's a way that we can have
values views beliefs that aren't causing division
aren't causing harm that instead promotes our own
freedom and the freedom of others this is what the Buddha was pointing
to I want to talk about this for a
um in a moment but before I do I want to say one more thing about this story
that uh impacts me that uh for me there's just something that you know the
story ends with the King being delighted like this is entertainment for him to
get people to have different views and then get all riled
up because it occurs to me that in contemporary times this kind of the same
thing is happening right we have different people that uh are having different experience
es different life experiences different news
sources and there think that one thing is true and these people have different life experiences and different news
sources and they think something else is true and there are others that have a
vested interest to see conflict happen when there's outrage I mean this
is what the media industry depends on right they are not for profit I mean they are are for-profit they are not
nonprofit right they depend on us feeling
outrage this is what politicians depend on say feeling
outrage this is what advertising feels on maybe it's not outrage but uh for us
to you know have our feelings manipulated in some kind of way so that we'll behave
differently so there's vested interest for us to get agitated and and want and
to want us to really hold on to our views and beliefs and not to treat each other with respect to not treat each
other with care I'm not saying that there aren't uh
that everything is okay and uh that that that feels uh like some gaslighting or
something that's inappropriate there are clearly things that are are happening oppression is happening terrible things
are happening but we don't have to in our own lives be holding on to views and
opinions in such a way that we are in disputes with
others and I admit that part of the reason I'm giving this talk on a Monday before
Thanksgiving is sometimes families get together and sometimes not always
sometimes sometimes there can be some uh Flames or there can be some there can be some disputes
and I appreciate uh very much what
um Ezra Klein said uh I I don't know when this was he's uh you
know what I'm not sure he's in the media might I don't know what he does exactly
somebody sent me a clip of him so I can't quite pull out what the context of what this was but um I I appreciate very
much that he's um he said somebody asked him about he's
a he's a commentator of some sort maybe political commentator or something like
this asked him like well um I heard that uh your family is kind
of angry about one of a position that he had or something like
this and he said you know it's actually
I love my family and it's not my job to in my
personal life to police and change the views of people I love and care
about I'm just going to love them they're my family and he admitted there was people in his
family that had radically different views than he did I think this is so fantastic it's not our job to police the
views of other people in our family and then he went on to say that
uh somebody had told him of a rule that he was trying to follow in these family settings and he
says before trying to persuade anyone of anything
and in particular we could say family he's saying ask them three
questions so somebody who has a different view than you do a different opinion and you are going to engage with
them rather than getting into disputes he said ask them three
questions about their view ask them how they got to their
position how did you know what what is it that uh bringing bringing them to
this position and ask what does it mean to them is it something that's meaningful
to them or does it stand for something or what is it that makes them hold on to
this and the third question is what is behind it so maybe in some ways these
are all the same but just to ask
them about their position because
because if the truth is if we're ever going to be persuasive to
anybody which let's be honest doesn't happen so often right that we change other people's mind it just doesn't
happen I don't like it when somebody's trying to convince me of something you know and they're using their loud voice
and trying to convince me like it just doesn't work but um as we Clin in this um I wish
I could remember exactly where this came from uh I remember the name so and I but
um he says you know if you're ever going to help change or persuade somebody it's
because they feel safe with
you it's because they feel seen by you
it's because they feel heard by you then they might be willing to listen
to something
so it might be that you encounter people who have different views so one thing we can do
is kind like maybe open our hearts to them if we're having a Thanksgiving meal
with them be o open to what they have to say
listen to them ask them these three questions how they got to their position or what
it means to them or what's behind it maybe what's behind it is maybe they're
all related these three questions but ask them three questions and then we might
say that there's this uh part of engaging in this way
is part of a bigger picture of how to work with conflict
and this is uh Gil fronal said um I think he said this a number of years
ago and I think you said it more recently this phrase be
still and look upon everything kindly be
still and look upon everything kindly so look upon everything kindly we
could say part of that is this look upon everyone that you're uh interacting with
kindly when you're in Conflict I'll say a little bit more
about that but I want to talk a little bit about this be still
part because be still is there a way can we quiet the
mind because often when we're in conflict or we're really holding on to views there's a certain amount of
agitation in the thoughts can be racing okay I got to make a good uh uh comeback
for what they're going to say and wait until they hear this or you know this type of thing but there's this way that
uh that well our thoughts that might be spinning and agitated and our labels and
our beliefs they are useful we need them in our everyday life but also abst
ractions like holding on to Concepts they also
divide that's just their nature and they create conflict because
as soon as you divide there's a conflict so just recognize that thoughts will
always be like uh perpetuating a certain amount of
conflict but is there a way that rather than getting lost in thoughts as part of
this be still can we shift towards our sensory
experience like what's being felt I'm I'm uh putting my hands on my
clothing here because it's soft and it's something that I could feel maybe that's something that you could do too like oh
yeah there a little bit softness here or if you're at Thanksgiving dinner maybe
flavors just tune in you know at a moment just kind of tune towards what's
actually happening in the the moment feel your feet on the ground listen to
The Sounds maybe there's kids play running around Maybe not maybe there's a
football game on you know different different families have different ways that they celebrate
Thanksgiving and not everybody celebrates Thanksgiving so I'm offering this if uh you happen to be in any
situation in which there are some uh conflicts
happening but there's this way that this shift toward sensory experience not only
does it kind like bring us into the reality of this moment but it disrupts the momentum of the thinking of like
trying to defend whatever we were going to do but it also helps like loosen our
identity with the thoughts this loosens into like okay I'm they're being
disrespectful for me towards me or those types of feelings and instead it brings
us to well the truth of this moment is that maybe the chair you're sitting on is
getting uncomfortable you've been sitting there too long or maybe you're hungry or haven't eaten enough like
that's happening also the same time that maybe this conflict is happening but if
we're only tuned into the conflict and what we're going to say if there's just going to exacerbate get bigger and
bigger so be still and look upon everything kindly be still part of it is
to just be with our sensory experience the senses what's being felt
tasted smelled heard seen at this
moment so there's this also this way about
to look upon everything kindly to look on to if you're in a
conflict kindly what would it be like to give the
other person in which you're conflict with a
victory what would it be like to say huh you may be right I hadn't thought of
that H okay I can see that part Mak sense
yeah okay yeah I'm not sure I agree about I I'm still not on board with this
but yeah I can see that I hadn't heard that
before even if you don't do that give them a victory but even just the idea
what would it be like to give them a victory that just like shifts the relationship right it kind of like
shifts the whole ecology instead of like okay I got to show them or I can't believe I'm related to
somebody who has or that's invited to this meal that has these thoughts or these views or but instead even the idea
what would it be like to just give them a victory why
not why not it's another way in which to look
upon everything kindly I'm kind like unpacking gilsa expression here some
kindness I heard uh Ken Wilbur maybe this is in one of his books that I read
maybe some decades ago which I appreciate so much he said there is
nobody on this planet that is such a genius that they
can be 100% wrong like you could like you would have
to like just like to be 100% wrong means you would would have to have created
your whole other you know I don't know something other than the laws of physics
that we have currently thinking all this other stuff so nobody's 100%
wrong so then maybe I'll I'll add here maybe
this verse that often gets said again and
again hatred never ends through hatred by non-hate alone does it
end this is an eternal truth hatred never ends through
hatred by non-hate alone does it end this is an eternal
truth I'm translating this word by non-hate alone does it end and Polly
that's how it is literally some people will uh say it by Love by Love Alone does it end
but for me I feel like love feels idealistic in a pretty high
bar but nonh hatred maybe nonh hatred
is being willing to listen being willing to engage somebody
with respect ask questions maybe non-h hatred is uh this
willingness even for us to question ourselves and to see oh yeah you know
what am I holding on to why am I defending this so much something like
this so maybe I'll end there there's more I could say and maybe I'll follow up in some uh later talks about this
idea of conflict and to recognize that you know
the map is not the territory our life is actually filled with sensory
experiences and I used to think that life was all about what was in the mind and I certainly was rewarded for this
and academically and professionally but life is you know we have senses as
uh this is what life is about and with our thoughts we need them
but our thoughts can get us into trouble too so with that I'll end and I'll open
it up to see if there are some comments or questions thank
you so in World War Two my grandfather was in the Army and I'm wondering that
in some cases like someone like Hitler right I'm sure no one is completely wrong about everything but sometimes
isn't even appropriate to fight with violence against something like that and you join the military and try to stop
the Nazis from you know dominating the
world so can you put your question in the context of what I was talking here
so you're saying yeah can can you re yeah so in other words like so in the case of World
War II the Nazis Hitler right and I'm like I'm sure Ken Rob was right no one's
completely wrong but in that case it seems is really appropriate to want to
join the Army and fight against the Nazis yeah yeah so this is interesting
so for you to go to the like the extremes I don't know about the extremes I've never been there I hope I never
have been in World War II like that's just awful awful awful right what
happened but can we bring it into our lives something that you and I can work
with you know that I can work with in my life you can work with in your life I don't want to say that uh not fighting
the Nazis that that just doesn't seem make any sense at all but I don't want to my saying that say that uh negate
kind of what I was talking about here but I I agree right I mean like I don't know that's just so
terrible even to think about that we wouldn't have uh um fought the Nazis in
Germany that was that's not or even like now in Ukraine right fighting against Russia I mean sometimes it seems like
even that kind of violence is
Justified I don't know it honestly I don't keep up to date
on all the news about uh Russia and the Ukraine and I don't really want to I
don't feel like I'm in a place to say what is right and what is wrong and what we should do and shouldn't do I have
very limited information based I'm like one of those blind people who felt just a little bit
of the elephant and I'm thinking like I felt the ear I'm thinking oh it's like a fan so I don't feel like I can make a
comment on it is that
okay yeah here
Sor yeah maybe this is more of a a comment uh for the talk and
um one thing that I it's about something that I um struggling with is I think
even when we can try and um see if I can articulate it um I think
even when when we as individuals can notice when we're only touching one part of the elephant and have some humility
to say okay like I don't know everything um when it comes to others sometimes
um I find myself realizing they're not necessarily giving themselves that same level of humility and so right I find
there's a frustration there but what would help is being able to articulate we'll call it like the source
of suffering in that so I I do find that there's a suffering of like why is this other
person you know or other people um not realizing you know or missing the
fact that there's a um they're clinging to one part of the other and so is it me clinging
to you know wanting that control or I guess that's where
um I'd like to better articulate what that source of suffering is I see I
found it difficult uh thinking about the uh this this talk so well I I'll say
that uh uh there's a an there's a person in
my family has very different views than I do and I started to think like you know what if I was a born and raised in
the same community that person was if I was the same age as that person if I was
the same gender that person if I currently lived in the same place that person lived if I currently uh had the
profession that I did I probably would think the same thing that they do so it's just this recognition that
you know people come to their views and the beliefs just because there's so many
causes and conditions that are uh supporting it it's not like there's one
uh like we believe what we believe because we've been exposed to whatever it is we've been exposed to and have had
experience that we've have experienced so for me that kind of helps me to say
oh okay this is this is what makes sense to them based on their life experience
and then I kind of feel like that their Humanity like yeah okay and then maybe
the suffering gets uh reduced I don't feel like I have to convince them otherwise even though they might be yelling or doing whatever they're doing
is that helpful definitely it sounds like a lot a stronger doses of loving kindness um
get us to that place um where you can like empathize or kind of piece together
where they're coming from yeah yeah kind of like humanize them and recognize them as a product
of their life in the same way that we are in the same way that we
are we you know we came to our conclusions based on our life experience and news
sources okay so for those of you who celebrate Thanksgiving I'm wishing you
all a wonderful holiday time thank you and if you'd like you're welcome to
come up here and uh talk to me and have some questions or some more comments
otherwise I wish you a wonderful rest of the evening and the safe travels home good night