okay welcome uh welcome folks uh good to uh be with
you yeah nice to see the
names um so uh so Gil's uh teaching Retreat
and uh here we are so um
yeah let's uh let's let's practice together very happy happy to uh to be
with you so um yeah please uh please settle
in
e
e for
relaxed and alert that's what we're aiming to
inspire with our
posture kind of openness in your chest whatever phen amena arise come what may
um
available for
don't be in too much of a rush to assume your inner Dharma posture just
uh just give yourself a little
time e
be uh patient in other words with the the process of um settling with the
Wayward longings with
the ways in which um before we settle it feels
like we have to worry just be
patient with your mind as it gets enough reassurance from
samsara that it's okay to
relax
for
e e
and then we we use our breathing to speak to
our
vigilance we breathe in such a way to
uh signal to our body that's okay
to put down the
defensiveness to signal to our body that are are clinging is not what's keeping us safe
in this moment
for
e
e e
almost anything you your worry can do your
breath can do
better our whole life looks different from the
perspective of
Tranquility it's very hard to determine what's actually worth
worrying about when we're in a state of hyperarousal
so we breathe we keep surrendering to the sensations of
breathing keep surrendering to silence to not
knowing
e
e e
being alive is amazing but the project
called my life is a burden
it's a burden at least to hold it as a project in all moments
and so we keep surrendering into the Simplicity of the
moment knowing yeah we will pick up the weight of the project called my
life
again but we don't need to carry it in all moments
what would it be like to be alive to
breathe without any sense of uh project
meditative or
otherwise just put it
down
e
e e
as we uh seclude ourself in the
moment and settle even just a little
bit the Tranquility connects us with the the whole homeness of the
Dharma the burden of holding on the
relief and letting Go the
fire of hatred this
soothing tenor of uh love
kindness we settle down a little bit and we can start to sense how actively
our nervous system Longs for the Dharma
for forgiveness and love
sensitivity
care for
peace
e
e e
[Music]
for e
okay it's good to uh good to sit with
you sort of feel my brain coming online as the meditation
unfolds 7:00 is a little early uh the caffeine drip started a
little late but uh I'm getting the hang of the
the hour and um yeah happy to uh to practice with you
feels good so
okay
um when you um when you become committed to uh to
love it matters a little less how everything is
going still matters but it matters a little
less and for sure you root for things to go
well but when they don't and you know they won't uh you you know you have um a
Secure net to fall back
into and when you know I'm going to have to love my way
through this life when you really know
that things actually change the
the texture of life changes but you have to know that that
deeply you have to know that in your in your
bones and yeah I often ask myself the question
How Deeply entrained is love in my
heart you can't always tell sometimes it's hard to know how deeply you've
trained the love into your heart until
you have a a fantastic opportunity for
hate and maybe you've had such a
moment some some s this this realm human realm is not is not
Utopia there will forever be things to object
to Forever there will be things that might
be hated and the truth is even if
we we're not in a highly imperfect world even if somehow some way we managed to
find our way into Utopia we'd literally start hating
rainbows no no I love rainbows we'd start hating
rainbows we'd start hating rainbows because it feels
like that's not the title of this Dharma talk hating rainbows but we'd start hating them or
something like them because it feels like our problems find us but that's often
merely illusion often it's our pain finding a
placeholder it's got to be placed somewhere and the best thing I got is
rainbows so I'm beginning to talk about uh um non
nonh hatred non-h hatred non-h hatred lies at the the
intersection of many Buddhist teachings and
uh non- clinging the teaching on on non clinging un Letting Go
hatred we sense this this is what I was alluding to in the
the sit that when we get a little bit quiet a little bit
still we can sense that hatred requires us to hold
on love is fully compatible with letting
go non-h hatred intersects with relatedly with renunciation the F flavor
of relinquishment is is quite alien to
hate the pain the pain of
hate becoming truly sensitive to aversion to the state of aversion
sometimes there's sometimes aversion is is the best we can do in a moment but it's
never the last word and start to become more and more
sensitive to the pain the burden on the heart that's created by
it non-h hatred is illuminated by the teachings on on Sila on
Sila um Sila uh ethical conduct and the the
indivisibility of goodness and well-being not not
separable as much as it might look like it people are pulling a fast one on Mother
Nature looking like they're happy even amidst
shamelessness no it's not possible actually given or nervous system
and then the there are all these teachings um about love all the species of
love you know uh usually kind of Brahma Brahma
VOR and so here's here's um Ain saito's
idiosyncratic description um met loving kindness
willing something which comes forth is willing it's offering
itself compassion Corona senses something to be
protected here something to be protected so it's
quieter spread over strong
sensitive mudita sympathetic Joy
mingling mingling you can enter into something play
happily in it the quality of swimming body
swimming mudita in the water celebrates itself celebrates the
medium and here of course we're looking at the medium of skillful
qualities doesn't matter who where they are we light up
equinity Serene Stillness still but not rigid
gently the open wing of a bird when it's hovering sensing the
currents turbulent or quiet sensing like the wing of a great
bird spread over hovering wide
span equinity
so yes meta willingness
willingness sense of um very gentle offering da Donna it's
the generosity the spirit of of Donna and
compassion um something needs protection what is
vulnerable needs protection and so compassion is this
kind of strength but sensitive attuned not
intrusive and mudita the celebrating the medium of the skillful qualities
rejoicing rejoicing in that and uh unthreatened by the welfare
of others and then uh then equinity sensing
the currents hovering poised
open this is um a beautiful
list and um and is meant to be not some
kind of Hallmark idealistic you know
um values that we just sort of um Elevate in some artificial way it's like
no this actually meant to be where our mind comes to rest
increasingly where does our mind rest what is the default position of our attention where where do you return to
when you're done paying attention to me or to life or to where do you go back to
what's the default position of attention when you don't need to do your
life where do you go where does the mind go and the Buddha says we train in such a way so that it
rests with these species of love that it returns to the Brahma
voras and to do this we actually have to train in
love Buddhism you know you can get the sense that we're having to make effort every moment of every day no matter what
we're doing to be mindful to be loving to be tranquil to be patient to let go
of hate all this stuff it's too much it's too much can't I can't sustain that
effort efor we actually have to entrust our life to the momentum of good
habits and so we train in love such that hate takes much more energy than
love these places of uh dwelling are meant to be varied enough so that uh one
of them is often a good resting place no matter what's happening in the moment
one of those species of Love is
medicine a a birth or death a marriage or divorce a a
war or a piece one of the Brahma
voras uh has you and like the path um Love has a
depth Dimension and a breadth Dimension and the the depth Dimension refers to
how radical love might be experienced in a moment our mind pervaded by love the
only thing of which we're aware and there are Janna you know I
this you know samade Jas meditative absorptions the Pana janas that kind of
insight uh Jas and perhaps we need like love Jas
you know of course love can be an entry way into the the Stillness but um but
maybe we need something like that so there's depth and then breadth
how many spheres of our mind and our Behavior remain encumbered by aversion
by apathy hate and so we spread the love downward to
the depths and outward in all directions the
breath and this is Grand but not grandiose this is um not idealistic not
moralistic in fact the more loving we become the less judgmental we are of
non-l the more loving we become the less judgmental we are of
non-l so this week um you're invited to
uh to pay attention to how aversion constellates in your
mind and be flexible in how you meet it have to be we have to be
improvisational we have to be willing to learn to be surprised by our own minds
to be surprised by Love by Hate by all of it and this
week I'll unfold these uh themes these different species of love and
um H it's touching to um to be together
so I offer this uh for your uh consideration and uh wish you a lovely
day we'll keep going tomorrow