hello from the Insight Meditation Center in Redwood
City and um welcome to this guided
meditation and we're in the middle of a five part series on the faculties
of of uh Faith energy mindfulness concentration and
wisdom the supports that we have within us waiting for us to their their potentials within
us waiting for us to use to engage to support us to be
present to overcome the way the mind obscures the present moment with its
distractions and preoccupations and
um so today it's mindfulness and mind mindfulness is such a
fantastic potential capacity we have and
it it's it's uh such a rich aspect of our capacity for
attention and we have many capacities many Senseo for attention we can pay
attention with our tongue as we taste nose as we smell ears as we listen
and eyes as we see and the body as we have tactile contact with objects in
the world and um and then there's other forms of uh perception that we have
there's mental forms of attention that we have we can observe things quietly
from The Mind's Eye we can uh know cognitively what's happening as it's
happening and all of these together contribute to what can be called
mindfulness and because it's and more so mindfulness is a kind of
multifaceted uh domain of
attention and so because of this over time I I Delight in having different
words to translate the word Sati or different ways of understanding mindfulness
today I would like to use the word accomp pment that as we practice mindfulness
we're accompanying our experience standing close to it standing
near being near remaining close and um in the in the ancient world
there the word the word expression for the practice of mindfulness is Sati
patana Sati is mindfulness and patana can mean standing by standing near
standing uh being approaching to be close
to and um so today I'd like to suggest that we practice accompaniment to to
accompany ourselves and exactly what that means is varied depending on
situations just like if you're going to accompany a friend who is grieving or is
Disturbed or troubled by something it depending on the friend depending on circumstances we may be was how close we
are uh how close we accompany them as you know you know we hold them by the arm we give them a hug we sit a little
bit further away we give them space um different situations we need to but we're always there we're there
accompanying intentional standing by uh being a companion being a um being there
with our experience and just this idea of accompanyment
requires some kind of attention and requires something from within us some kind of presence act
activated be present and maybe we're to be accompany
ourselves calmly as you would a friends maybe accompany yourself
kindly accompany yourself as if you're listening deeply what is this here
without asserting your opinions your conclusions your
preferences in the situation as if each thing that's happening to you each thing that comes in Awareness the respectful
thing to do is to accompany it as it is listening sensing
deeply without interpretation Let each thing in a sense
speak for itself and you accompany it without
judgment so assuming a meditation
posture a posture of care of
respect for what you're going to accompany that
you're going to show up and be present sometimes when you're with a
friend you want to be with them so they so that they see that you're attentive
you're present you're interested you're listening you're there with
them and sometimes that's done with a
posture and for here we're doing this for ourselves being our own
friend dare I say our own best
friend so then gently taking a few long slow
deep breaths and as you exhale relax and settle in to be here for these minutes
meditating just
here
letting your breathing return to normal and continuing as you exhale
relaxing your body so that there's a softer more
receptive way of accompanying life as it happens to you
here
and then settling into your
breathing and having the practice the orientation
to accompany your body breathing breathing has accompanied you
for your lifetime and now you're accompanying
breathing returning the
favor letting go of distractions
preoccupations so you can listen or sense more deeply the experience of the body
breathing in any other way that you are that's
pulls you away from breathing don't be troubled by
that it's the call of something that needs to be
accompanied stand close to it for a while even if it's just your thinking
mind but don't listen to the words
listen to what fuels your
thinking listen to what's deeper than words and
images accompany your experience as it unfolds in the present
moment
e
for
whatever is happening for you to accompany it with all your all of
yourself that you have to offer maybe even
by breathing with the
experience so you're accompanying you're not
participating you're accompanying not
resisting accompanying not being pushed around
by
for
up
and then as we come to the end of this
sitting to again spend some moments
actively accompanying yourself from the inside
out an accompanyment that is
energized by confidence and faith in the value of being
present an accompaniment that's
wholehearted with a kind of courageous
effort yes this is phenomenally important
to be present here and then a kind of certain inner
activation that activates accompanying our experience
being there with
it and as we feel tensions in our body
to soften and relax around them so the accompaniment becomes more
sensitive more
receptive and then
to turn your attention outwards to the
world around you people
in close to you further away in your neighborhood in
town people you'll encounter today known and
unknown and then imagine imagine as we come and bring this to a close that you're there
to stand with whoever whoever you meet to accompany
them and standing with as an English meaning of supporting someone
or maybe supporting that which is deepest and most valuable in each
person we're there to accompany to listen to be present
for where we have confidence in our capacity to
accompany that confidence that makes room for kindness and
friendliness we're wholehearted accompanyment of course it comes with
Good Will anything
else is a limitation in our
presence and wishing well for everyone you'll encounter
today imagine iming them happy faces that are
smiling imagining them safe and content
and happy and may it be
so may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peace peaceful and may all beings everywhere
be [Music]
[Music]
free thank you
hello and welcome to this third talk on the five
faculties and um sometimes they're called the five controlling
faculties so the word control of course is complicated but in the good senses of
the term it means that uh we have some choice and and capacity to engage in
this practice ice that we're not uh living a life that's at the whims of fi
and and uh at the whims of whims that we have some ability to
change the direction of our life and change the direction of our mind and our what's happening for
us and so one of those is to activate
choose to activate have the capacity to activate our uh attention for a
awareness in a useful way awareness or attention is present
for human beings all their waking hours maybe even when we're sleeping to some in certain
ways and um and if we don't
choiceful uh engage in activating that
capacity using that capacity then our capacity for attention is used by things
which are deeper subconscious within us they're hijacked in a sense so if we are
not taking control or taking ownership or taking engagement with our Attention
our attention might be swept away into our greed or hostility and and U
Marshal uh you know recruited for supporting those things or for Fe fear
we get hijacked into the fear and attention kind of is food in a sense
food for these things so the more attention is hijacked by fear and anger
and ill will and greed and envy and doubts and things uh the the the more it
thrives the more it gets those things get stronger and which is to our
detriment and so we need to have some choice some agency to engage in
mindfulness so it's not being taken over by other things and um and so uh this uh
engagement this activation of mindfulness is in the in the family of
things that I've been calling action the Dharma was a the Dharma is a lot about
the actions we engage in and mindfulness is one more thing that we practice M
practice we it's an activity that we engage in it's an action of
sorts so uh the first faculty confidence
is a confidence that there are things we can do that are beneficial we could
practice and in in in uh in core thing in the Dharma practice we the the
confidence in the activity of mindfulness and then there's the uh
heroic in engagement with that confidence is more I think of more
as a quality of the heart heroic effort courage is much more the
activation of the embodiment of who we are to be show up in a full way and then
mindfulness is more of in sense more of the mind but we're activating something
from the mind so we're have a higher capacity for attentiveness to the
present moment and so I give an example if uh if a friend of yours is
quite distressed and you're walking in the park and uh you're much more
interested in talking about the movie you watch last night last night and you were fascinated by it and had insights
about it and but your friend is really distressed and and actually as you talk about the movie you kind of notice that
they're kind of like they're getting quieter and their posture is sinking and they look even more distressed on the
edge of tears and at some point it occurs to you wait a minute I don't think that talking
about this movie is what's called for here right now my friend is distressed and so then you might decide
let me be present my friend let me turn my attention to my friend and and really
kind of accompany them or be with them check check out what's going on here and so there's a choice to activate a
certain kind of attentiveness that wasn't present when we were just kind of Carried Away by your fascination with this movie so
something's something's being activated out of choice let's listen to the friend let's be accompany my friend in a deep
way and one of the good ways to accompany people or listen is to pay
attention to how we listen so you might notice that you're now have tension in
your body because maybe you feel like you've blown it and you your friend is going to be angry with you talking about a movie and so you you you you take
respons ability for how you are so you can accompany the person well so maybe
you're able to relax and settle and put aside your self-c concern in that way so
that you can just be really there for your friend and um and as you're there more
and more it just seems easy to be there and it feels like now you're kind of attuned to the person and you're not
interested in anything else and you don't have to work to be present for your friend and you don't have to track yourself so carefully because you're
keep being distracted and you're just there in a nice easy way and you see
that your friend responds accordingly and their mood lifts a little bit they seem to appreciate the attention it
seems like you're starting to coming a little bit more in harmony so it all starts by activating a
kind of attention another example would be say that you are um really impatient but you
decide to go out for fresh air but you're super impatient restlessly impatient so you find yourself kind of
speeding around the neighborhood and almost bumping into all the people on this side walk and the kids on the
tricycles and because you hardly notice anything after a while uh you start
noticing wow you know I'm really something's not quite right here and you notice how impatient you are and how
fast you're walking and um and and so you decide to activate something that
you activate your capacity to slow down you activate the capacity not to give in
to expressing the impatience in how you walk trip you know tripping over the kids and their
tricycles and so you slow down to pay more attention slow down to be with yourself
more and then you say then you've learned about mindfulness you learned it's useful to pay attention to your
body and you find out there's a lot of body tension with the impatience so you
relax your shoulders you relax your eyes your belly
softens so you're choosing you're activating the capacity to relax as you walk more and slowing down
you find that it's useful for you to kind of rest in your body and just kind of be carried by the body accompany your
body and you find that kind of that kind of settle something and now you're not so much racing off into your thoughts
and and in fact now you're it's easier to pay attention some point attention
seems more receptive than something you're activating and oh this is good receptive
presence and so you decide to in a certain kind of way to be engaged in the
choice to be more receptive receptive to the
experience each step along the way there's something you're we're activating we're
engaging but it's an activation which is not leading to more restlessness or
busyness or agitation it's actually activation that allows something to
settle and be quieter and more receptive so this activation of and the
core thing here for mindfulness is the activation of our capacity for attention
present moment attention and exactly what that is is less important than the
activation of presence present moment attention that almost feels like we're
activating a capacity to accompany our experience here and now and I love the
expression for mindfulness accompanyment because that allows whatever attentional faculty we have
that's useful to be be activated so if it's um you know if
there's something that you're um um the uh so yesterday I went walking on
the beach and um and and uh and I felt this is really great to feel the wind to
and uh I have a long history of the Wind part of the reason I was at the beach was to remember things in the past um to
honor someone who had passed away and um and so the the I activated a capacity to
feel the wind for all the times I'd been with this person with um when it was windy at the ocean and so I was
activating capacity to feel and be present through my skin and this in the cold as went through my clothes and it
was really a delight so this capacity to activate the sense door that's needed
for any particular time is um is a um and then it but the
word activation for people do mindfulness might seem like we're just getting
busy but when we give our activate a wholeheartedness something that all the
other activations all the ways we're scattered all the ways we're fragmented and being pulled away from ourselves
those can settle there's something deeply healing even about activating a
full wholehearted attentiveness accompanying our experience being really
here in our experience that allows us to become whole and as we do that to be when we're
honest about what's going on to be carried away from that into distractions
that's where things get off a little bit that's where there's a tension or a a alienation or doesn't quite feel good
but to enter into this world here fully in an activated way allows for some deep
relaxation uh maybe not initially but there is a kind of in the beginning it's
maybe we have to work at it and then eventually we have to uh it becomes
easier so I'll end with another metaphor for cultivating developing
mindfulness that I've read that there are now stationary bicycles you can pedal that can charge create electricity
and so imagine you have such a thing and all electricity and you require
batteries to generate lights in your house to not generate but to have lights in your house but all the batteries the
battery is dead so you get on the bicycle and you're you're you're charging it you're pedaling around and
very slowly the battery has enough charge that it can turn on the lights in the house but it there's not any stored
B uh electricity in the battery so you have to keep pedaling and pedaling until
there's enough stored energy in the battery that then you can start to stop pedaling and the lights can
continue and so and then there's kind of you can just relax and just enjoy
seeing things that were in the dark before so the same way with mindfulness
we're kind of engaging in it activating it in a certain way uh charging the
inner battery and at some point when the battery is full enough then we don't
have to work so much at being aware the light has been turned
on uh and this so and mindfulness is when the light has been turned on the
practice of mindfulness sometimes is getting the charge going but then once
the charge is there when we're in the groove of being present then the light is turned on and it's wonderful to be
activated and then we use that light to then be you know to shine the light on
different parts of our life as we accompany it so um you might for this day those of
you know doing your mindfulness practice through the day to consider if uh it's interesting to to understand it as
accompanyment and if you accompany yourself accompany others accompany your experience of life in the present moment
as it's unfolding mindfulness will come along you cannot help but be attentive
when you're accompanying so see how that goes for this practice of mindfulness
faculty of mindfulness thank you