good evening welcome
welcome so tonight I'd like to talk a little bit about um something that I
often I'm pointing to in indirect ways or multiple ways and here's yet maybe
another way this has some overlap of some other teachings I've been
doing but this idea of that this um
possibility of this deep sense of not
being agitated this comforting sense of not
being agitated and there's like so many ways in which we're agitated without
really even noticing it in fact we might just think that's just the normal way of
being but it's so common just to have this sense of like there's got to be
something better let me go find it you know this like whatever it is you know
like yeah okay whatever is happening yeah where's this this something better
that's in the next moment maybe we're not even sure what exactly it is that we're looking for we
just have this sense that whatever we're experiencing right now it ain't it that
somehow you know doesn't measure up to some of the ideas that we have
about what practice is about what happiness is about what uh peace and
well-being is about whatever we're experiencing now we often have this
feeling that uh it's not here and
implicit in that is this agitation that might be so familiar that we don't even
notice it and it's not until we maybe have some deep meditative experiences or
something that that we start to recognize like oh wow compared to that amount of Stillness I see how the way
that I'm moving through the world and walking around has has this uh sense of
tumbling forward all the time or tumbling into or distracting or
diverting ourselves or our attention all the time so the Buddhist teachings they do
point to there's like this deep uh sense this deep meaningful sense of
okayness which does not sound
glamorous kind of sounds like what you know okayness but there's a way in which we
can understand this as maybe as a different type of happiness because when we use this word
happiness not in the Buddhist sense but just in the usual way that we think about this there's
often this happiness is associated with uh getting what one wants that that's
that's that'll make us happy so part of this agitation is just be able to get what we want whether that's a material
object or some experience or something
something but instead there's this type of Happiness that's we might say that's
a contentment and it's really different than the happiness that uh we often is
spoken about in um contemporary times these days about getting what you want
whereas contentment is about not wanting it's about not
wanting because have you noticed that as soon as you get something that you want you know how long does that
last not very long right and then then there's the next thing like just because
you have this fantastic perfect cup of coffee very satisfying it's really great
you're going to want another one soon right the next day or whatever it's not
like we finally get satisfied as soon as we get things that we want it's not like oh I never need to have ice cream
again I never need to you know have a new phone or you know whatever I might
be so this contentment that's being pointed to is instead just this the not
wanting which is pointing to the absence of a sense of lack no longer having a sense of you
know something's missing I need more and so to clarify this contentment
it's not a sense of complacency or it's not a sense of just
tolerating or resignation or it's not a sense of like okay I guess I'll be I'll
be okay with this because I can't get what I really want okay I'll be okay
with this and nor is it just like passively accepting everything that's here kind of
like a way in that we can be like disconnected from our experience and like okay yeah this is fine and it's
fine because we're kind of disconnected we've like uh in tumed ourselves a little bit uh kind of surrounded
ourselves with this cottony kind of uh bumper so that thing bounce off us or
something like this and then I want to say also that
contentment um I can feel like a booby prize can feel like yeah okay if I can't
have the fireworks knock your socks off kind of experience okay I guess I have
contentment and more specifically if you have this idea that like you really um
want to have something like you just this strong sense of lacking that you need things this whole notion of
contentment can be horrifying like what no no no no I don't want to get rid of this sense of there
needs to be something more and there's a way in which without our even noticing it we could have this just sense of
inadequacy we could have this sense of being insufficient in some
way and so there's a way that wanting more not only does it distract us from
this terrible feeling of inadequacy but it also kind of like uh
gives up something to a promise of yeah yeah yeah okay this
feeling is going to go away as soon as I get something so this contentment is
like putting aside the way of getting something it's horrifying because then
we have to put away the idea that I'll be fine later just as soon as I get
something attain something achieve something do something stop doing something something like that that can
be scary like wait you mean this current version of
myself can be okay this can be really like having to
put aside the self-improvement project and say no no no I'm fine just
this way can feel uncomfortable in itself so instead we're just tumbling forward into
this always looking or maybe you know different people and different seasons
of life and maybe have different intensities maybe you're not somebody that's feeling like okay I got to get
more maybe it's more like get away from me this kind of
feeling and if we have this we're accustomed to like grumbling and
complaining like this shouldn't be like that and that shouldn't be like this and I got to fix this world World fix this
environment then this idea of contentment can feel like a failure like
oh but everything's still you know it's not perfect out there in a sense of contentment of just
saying well things are okay but if we're filled with aversion
towards people them those people over there that are making all the problems
them you know them if we have kind of like that sense then
maybe there's a way like no no no I can't be content because then that lets those people off the hook and they
shouldn't be let off the hook they need to be fly right and shape up and do what
they should do and maybe it's hard to put down those ideas maybe there's a way
in which we're kind of identified not kind of we are identified with there's us over here or doing what's right right
and there's them over there who are doing what's not right it can be hard to put that
down it can be hard to kind of put down the way that we kind of like bolster
ourselves up that we're us over here on the right side so we can learn something about
ourselves about how much we dislike this idea of contentment like yeah okay it
sounds good Diana but later we'll do it later some other time
that's certainly how I thought about it like oh yeah okay but first I have to fix this and take care of that achieve
this you know there this kind of this list of things so part of the teachings of
course is that uh I'm saying of course because this shows up in so many different
ways is that uh what supports contentment are you know certain causes
and conditions of course it's not like just you know contentment arises out of
magic nothing arises out of magic there's things that flow for a
reason and so what are some of these things that can support contentment like maybe right now there might be this
sense of H okay this deep sense of contentment this deep sense of nothing's
wrong everything's just fine nothing needs to happen nothing and if something
happens that's okay too so there are some of these conditions
that support that and what are some of these conditions well maybe I'll say something
like this um something that I appreciate about the Buddhist teachings is like we're not being asked to just adopt a
bunch of beliefs here just you know believe this and you'll be fine don't
ask too many questions just believe this instead there's a real encouragement for
us to discover for ourselves for us to practice for ourselves to have experiences for
ourselves and it takes a certain amount of maybe I'll use this word faith to even like do the practices so you can
have the experiences but there's this encouragement to okay for us to find for
oursel what are some of the things that lead to contentment what are some of the activities thought patterns that really
support a sense of ease support a sense of Freedom support a sense of
well-being so there's this like invitation for us to investigate and to
discover for ourselves and I'll give you some
hints Simplicity Simplicity supports
contentment we can if we think about it kind of makes sense right to just put
down some of the agitation that arises when that there's some busyness or too
much or agitation or something like this some Simplicity really supports
contentment and I'll talk more about that but first I want to share a little poem I'm on the streak with poems these
days so here's a a poem by Rosemary traumer it's called
ambition it's called ambition I'm a person news you I wouldn't in the past
called I wouldn't have characterized myself this way but now looking back I
can see where I've had a lot of ambition or you know I wanted to do
something and you know that's works until it doesn't because it seems like there's
never an end at least for this person here it seemed like oh it was just one thing after another to U go out there
and get and Attain so here's Rosemary trummer's poem called
ambition I am so far from the woman I want to be so far from humility and
simplicity I dream of clearing not only the shelves not only the closets but
also the cluttered inner rooms that crowd out the
Divine every day I search for ways to best meet the day with poems beautiful
meals with songs with praise so many ways to be
radiant but I suspect all the day wants is for me to
meet it and all that comes into my path with kindness and
spaciousness in my effort to be good good to be whole I make it so difficult
this life the day doesn't seem to hold my exuberance against me it shows up as
always generous as a new tomorrow quiet as
[Music] Dawn so I appreciate in this poem this
opening line I am so far from the woman I want to be just kind of what I'm
pointing to this sense of however I am is not enough not good
enough in some kind of way and this is like just the
opening sense of like whatever I'm doing it's not right and this uh
agitation it brings some complications as some of these complications are just
because we're trying to distract ourselves from this feeling of it's not quite right
and you know that Buddha was pointing to this right to the the truth of Dua and I'd like to say this is Dua this feeling
of whatever I'm doing it's not quite
right and then in this poem Rosemary traumer includes this line every day I
search for ways to best meet the day again this like this agitation of
searching instead of just being with what the day is
offering and she includes in my effort to be good to be whole I make it so
difficult this life so she's uh the poet here is recognizing this uh that we
are there maybe this agitation that we we make things more complicated so often
than they need to be this trying to make it be better just
ends up complicating so much in obvious ways and not so obvious
ways so what was what would it be like to keep things
simple keep things simple we could say that uh there's a pow
Nama that um is a can be translated as simply licity there's other translations
for it as well but we could say it's uh Simplicity and it's a one of the parames
it's one of the um pract one of the qualities to
develop as a support for awakening that's associated that when it
uh becomes ripe is really a support for awakening so what does it mean to have
Simplicity I'll offer are some things but again the encouragement is just for you to answer this question for yourself
what does it mean for you to have some Simplicity what are some of the ways in which your life seems complicated
unnecessarily so one is maybe keeping our external life
simple not being too busy this is kind of right it's kind of
a funny thing for me to be saying this because I have spent years very busy
doing this and that and the other thing and real you know realizing that there's
a it didn't give me the kind of like the space to just allow things to
unfold the other day I was in downtown U Redwood City just running an
errand and uh went to get into my car the car doesn't
start you you know I have triaa call triaa love this
organization reliably come and help you with whatever it is that's happening with your car but there was a time in my
life I'm like oh no I have a meeting and so it's and such a time and you know how is this going to happen and I to take
care of this and get this done but you know I have a little bit more space in my life so I didn't have to get
complicated into like oh my goodness my all these things that I had to do and
doesn't mean I'm a bad person because I scheduled things too closely and now I'm going to have to do this you know this
all the stories that can happen it's like well I guess I'm going to
wait and I'm going to practice a little bit just meditate here in this parking
garage why not the W the weather was okay you know
it wasn't like unbearably hot or unbearably cold so so there's this way
in which just is there way as much as our life allows us to have some space
not to be too busy because there's a way in which
being busy is also just a cover up for this sense of inadequacy that we might
have this sense of insufficiency I got to do more I got to do
more so then there's something else about Simplicity is to keep our
environment you know clutter free as best we
can this way the complications are often that's well I I need this object okay
I'll get this here or oh yeah I need to take care of that and then oh yeah I
want to remember to do this but before I do that I have to take care of this and that's so okay so I better keep
everything on my desk so I don't forget and this is what happens for me and then my desk ends up with all this stuff and
uh starts to feel a little bit overwhelming
so there a way to keep our environment simple we don't need so much
stuff as I've mentioned a number of times I've done a lot of retreat practice and for me something that's
been really powerful about Retreat practice is just how simple it
is you know and I've lived months in just a small little room with just a few
things and been very happy you don't have to make so many decisions what am I going to wear well
there's not so many choices what am I going to do not so many choices what am I going to eat not so many choices and
there's something that there's this sense of Freedom about that it feels like ah turns out to be a
relief so Simplicity is you know what we do with our time what we do with our
space just something for us to think about how the way that it's not simple
is often an expression of this quiet agitation and then it's agitating to see
the expression of agitation in those
ways and it's also can be interesting to notice like if there's this hesitation like oh I don't want to clean up I can't
clean up or something like this to notice I noticed this recently when I
was a cleaning out a closet it's like oh yeah if I really
donate this then I'm really acknowledging that I'm no longer
the person that's going to do this particular activity that took all this
equipment is that right like but I liked being that person that was doing all
that activity that took all that equipment but am I really still that person and it was just kind of something
to say like you know no I'm at a different season of my life now and sometimes it's hard to to say nope just
is you know my life is going this direction and to say goodbye to yeah you know that was a particular season of my
life and now maybe somebody else can use this
equipment so what else about Simplicity support simplicities you might notice
that just being present for this
moment pretty simple the just feel the pressure
against the body and what you're sitting on pretty
straightforward feel our feet on the ground it doesn't have to be
complicated our practice can be about being embodied partly because it interrupts
the momentum of all the mind it just because this is where all the complications are right the lack of
contentment it's in the mind the body is just doing what bodies
do it's the mind that's putting on top of an experience saying this isn't
okay this has to be different The Experience itself is just the
experience it might be uncomfortable it might be very
uncomfortable but this is what it means to have a human body means that sometimes it's
uncomfortable and the mind likes put on top oh no no no no this is going to this is terrible what does this mean and I
have to you know maybe there's a long uh story associated with it if only that
thing didn't happen before if only I had remembered to do this or now I have
people are going to if I adjust my posture then I'm not going to look like I'm a good meditator and but I need to
adjust my posture and but maybe my knee's going to fall off if I don't or
you know whatever it might be so what is it to just be
embodied and one way to think about this is to
just be present for our bodies when we're moving more specifically when we're
walking this is something that we do you know those of us who can walk if you
can't walk the other ways in which you're mobile or if you're not mobile the ways that uh you are able to move in
some kind of way whatever movement one does is can we bring mindfulness to the
experience of moving it doesn't have to be anything like takes additional time and it can
start with walking it can start with uh feeling the like how the body feels as
it moves through space and this is like such a vague thing to say as the body
feels as it moves through space like what does that mean and the invitation
here is to discover for yourself what does it feel like to be
moving cuz so often we're not present when we're moving because the mind is on
where we're going I got to go to the kitchen to make sure all the contents in there are just
fine all the contents in the refrigerator are still there sometimes
that feels like I'm like opening up the refrigerator like now why am I doing this close it
again so this can be really helpful if you are walking noticing the pressure on
the bottom of the feet notice maybe the uh feeling of
clothing moving against the body any times that you're moving this doesn't mean doing anything
slowly we're just doing it at the same time but just doing it in a more embodied way sensitive way being tuned
into the experience that we're having it
might be very mundane it might be boring seemingly but it turns out to be really
interesting and there it brings a sense of aliveness to our experience to really be
embodied instead of a sense of Life passing Us by we start to feel like we're really
present so is this way that we can just be with the
Simplicity of the moment of having a
body and maybe I want to say that I'm not saying that you have to be mindful
for every step that you take for the remainder of your life I'm just saying
just start with one step a few steps and set this as an intention maybe the five
steps that it takes to go down the hall to the bathroom or
something like this it's this turns out to be simple
that maybe the difficult part is just remembering to do it but we can remember it the more often we do it so just an
encouragement to just be embodied for movement however you're
moving and then as a support for Simplicity it's also a support to look
about to look at well what is making it not be simple what is complicated like
what's complications and if we really look at
it as I said earlier it's about what's actually happening in the mind
the mind is making things complicated there's this notice we could
feel into when there's these extra elaborations Beyond just the bodily
experience the way that there the thinking has like expanded into um this
uh Buddhist word that I really like papancha maybe some of you have heard this maybe
papancha it's just just I just like to say it Poncha it just means that like
elaboration and just kind of going on and on and on in thoughts this idea of
like oh okay well as soon as I get home I got to remember that um to make my
lunch for tomorrow and what should I have tomorrow well there's peanut butter and jelly yeah but I had that last week
and you know peanut butter this person over here said that they like creamy peanut butter but then chunky is really
better I'm sure it is and oh yeah the bread you know just how we just start to go on
and so there's this way that there's ordinary thinking that's
just an ordinary part of life but then there's this extra kind of like the the
elaboration that we're doing and sometimes we do need to elaborate we need to solve a problem we need to plan
we need to figure things out that is part of our ordinary lives and so part of this practice is
noticing when have we slipped into what's extra when have we
rehearsed you know for the fifth 50th 500th
time that conversation we're going to have the next time we see that person or the thing that we're trying to remember
just saying it over and over again or replaying how that person didn't treat
us respectfully or something like that
so just to notice when we're lost in thought and a thought that's just feels
like it's just ongoing and then in a simple relaxed
wave just to come back to the B embodied experience much like we're doing in a
meditation practice but this in daily life is just a relaxed easy kind of
flowing with what's going without this pressure of having to stay on the
object it's more just an encouragement to feel embodied and if you're embodied you also
notice what does the body feel like when the mind is busy with papancha you'll
start to feel this kind of like slight maybe like this tightness or this agitation sometimes there can be this uh
leaning forward that happens with the
Pancha so maybe there's this I'll summarized by an
end here with this there's this invitation in this practice of what it's pointing to is this greater ease and
Peace and Freedom and contentment this ending of things this
idea of things need to be different this ending of wanting something different to
be this subtle sense of agitation
and then a support for this contentment is Simplicity and then we could just think
for ourselves discover for ourselves what does that mean for all of
us maybe it's uh letting go of that idea of was it inbox of
zero and not getting agitated maybe just choosing to about the number of emails that were in the Inbox and do something
skillful with them but uh you know not uh feeling agitated by them or maybe
it's wor looking at your environment and saying you know maybe I can tidy up here
when we do a meditation Retreats online maybe some of you have attended
them but um we even like put a time for people to straighten up their practice
area just because we recognize it's really a way to kind of like honor and
respect your experience like okay I'm just going to make a space here that's going to be where I practice and I'm
going to be intentional about it so Simplicity can be with our
physical things external things out there but it also can be and a support for it can be being
embodied which turns out to be pretty simple and then of course not being
embodied is being lost in thought which papancha so can we notice when we're
lost in thought and instead come just be to the Simplicity of the body which supports this sense of contentment this
sense of peace and ease and well-being then maybe I'll close with uh
reading this poem
again poem is ambition by Rosemary trummer I am so far from the woman I
want to be so far from humility and
simplicity I dream of clearing not only the shelves not only the closets but
also the cluttered inner rooms that crowd out the
Divine every day I search for ways to best meet the day with poems beautiful
meals with songs with praise so many ways to be ra
but I suspect all the day wants is for me to meet it and and all that comes
into my path with kindness with spaciousness in my effort to be good to
be whole I make it so difficult this life the day doesn't seem to hold my
exuberance against me it shows up as always generous as a new tomorrow quiet
as Dawn so thank you and now I'll open it
up for some questions and comments
thanks I think we have a comment back
here so isn't a c amount of wanting healthy I mean why else would we deal with graduate school um you know things
like that things that I mean you know have to go to graduate school but you don't even have to go to college but
isn't there a certain amount of wanting in life healthy yeah so this is part of the art
of practice is to recognize what is the healthy wanting and what is the wanting
that's coming out of a sense of inadequacy what is the going to graduate
school going to college or whatever it might be um a sense of yeah this is the next right thing to do and somehow it
just comes from a sense of happiness and ease as opposed to like oh I got to
prove myself and here's one way to prove myself or something like that but I mean college is so stressful I mean it was
for me anyway you know just dealing with the deadlines and the papers and the test and you have to I had to really
push myself to even stay I mean so if it seems like if I didn't want it I might have just oh what the heck I'll just you
know drop out yeah I I can see this is part of the um
maybe one's life is to recognize okay what effort is even though it's uncomfortable is worth enduring and
finding a way and what effort isn't and this is so much about I would say kind of our life is figuring out what is
worth uh putting that effort for yeah yeah and what isn't and often in college
you know we're young at that age and uh we kind of are just often doing it because Society are supporting us maybe
it's a good thing turns out to be a good thing but um as we kind of like mature in our lives and mature in spiritual
life we can uh be more sensitive to like what is what's really being born out of
uh a love for what is and what's being born out of trying to just make myself
feel better instead of and not addressing the underlying sense of inadequacy or something like that
yeah thank you anybody else have a comment or
question thanks going off of that question you you mentioned that it's
it's up to the practice use the practice to identify what is something that you'd
like to achieve for your own sake versus because of an in in adequacies so with
what you said how do you use the practice to be able to identify that like through meditation like at a
microscopic level in this inside tradition how do you use the practice to identify that yeah get familiar with
what agitation feels like just like in all the gross and subtle ways you know
the obvious and subtle ways and then just start to notice like oh yeah this is agitating this isn't and and then
what has the opposite of agitation would be like ease and getting more um
sensitive to like oh yeah this is more easeful and part of how we do that is to
be embodied because often the agitation and the ease is showing up and like
whether we're having our shoulders up like this or you know or we maybe our postures were leaning forward uh all the
time or or maybe we're kind of like this or something I'm exaggerating to show this but there's a way in which being
embodied we can really notice um what what what is seg more agitating and
what's more easeful so and then maybe there's
um so your question was how can we know which way
is what was precisely your question yeah yeah like how do we identify it with
with the practice like how how does a practice help us identify those you know
when it whether it falls under goals that are healthy versus hey I'm doing this because I feel inadequate like how
does a practice help us get to that point yeah so one was sorry so thank you for reminding me uh get really familiar
with agitation and its opposite and get familiar with this feeling of inadequacy
if it's there and is there a way that uh we can
nurture and honor and respect and take care of that feeling in such a way that
it feels seen and that it feels taken care of and so that it can heal itself
that it can um I'll use that language heal itself or something like that so that's
the second thing is to you know just get to know like oh yeah here's that
familiar feeling that I'm uh not good enough or insufficient or inadequate or whatever words uh that we have for it
and um and can we be okay with it because it's not going to go away by just by chasing you know doing more and
more more things it's more about uh it's um it's about honoring and respecting
it is a way in which it can soften and go away and get integrated as opposed to
being something that's quietly pushing us around in our life quietly fueling
like so much as that we do and the way that we show up is is this helpful yeah
thank
you I might add that this is getting to know that feeling of inadequacy is often
precisely what we don't want to do I'll just add that right because so much that
distracting and diverting and busyness and all this kind of stuff is a way for us to really not be with that feeling
and so you know there's ways in which different ways in which we might
do that one could be in a meditative setting maybe a therapeutic setting is appropriate or I mean there's maybe
there's with friends or family or I there's different ways to approach that but I just kind of want to acknowledge
I'm just s like I get to know that sense of inadequacy it's it's there's a usually a lot of uh
resistance to this lot of resistance for us to get to know
that and then maybe I'll just add one more thing you guys don't mind right I'll
just do a whole another darat talk here um a number of years ago if it's helpful
I did a series on the inner critic um with a happy hour which was
something that um happens online Monday through Friday at 6: PM so on uh this
YouTube channel and I did I don't know how many 15 20 something like little
talks about uh working with the inner critic and it was in the context of using some uh Brahma vajar practice some
of the like the heart practices with it so that also can be we can like do
particular practices that support some equinity and support having a sense of
uh well-being and compassion for some of the difficulties and stuff like that so
I'm just offering this that there's some resources out there if people are interested in
this I think I did a 7 a.m. series also on the inner critic so you can you can
find stuff there's not just me there's lots of people doing stuff on that
okay well may you have an okay
evening thank you wishing you all a wonderful night byebye