so warm greetings everyone and today we're going to do the second
day on a series this week that picks up on the introduction of to mindfulness
Gil has been doing and it's different elements of
mindfulness as we talked about in my talk yesterday in the Q&A actually afterwards
we're going to be speaking about another layer of response or
reaction on top of Vena and that is the wanting or the not
wanting so with that very brief introduction and
a warm good morning greetings back to everyone invite you to settle into a
meditation posture something
that exemplifies alertness and
relaxation maybe starting with a couple of longer solar
breaths intentional
breaths and allowing yourself so
soften relax on the
exhale and then allowing the breathing to return to normal whatever that is for
you this day this time
and again scanning through your body just a gentle good morning or good
day or good evening
scan noticing any places of tension or
relaxation Pleasant or unpleasant
just acknowledging them letting them be there just as they
are and then setting the intention to have mindful awareness
mindfulness at the Forefront of attention for these moments of
meditation
allowing the attention to set on breathing more Body
Sensations hearing whatever feels like the most natural anchor for your attention
today resting dedicating the
attention to the embodied experience of the moment
noticing the alignment of your posture whether you're
sitting standing or lying down
and encouraging your body to be
balanced and then noticing
too the internal posture of the heart and
mind is it balanced or is there a leaning towards
or away movement wanting or not
wanting
from time to time throughout this
meditation the invitation is to check in if there's a leaning towards or a
away the movement for or against
and for now [Music]
settling softening into the breath the body the
moment
in any Pleasant feelings associated with breathing or just
[Music]
being noticing any unpleasant
Sensations and allowing other one allowing the vast territory in
between noticing any leaning
towards or
away
from time to time refreshing the
awareness and perhaps checking in what the overall
mood or attitude infusing this moment might
be allow knowing what is in
mindfulness
and in these last few minutes of our meditation
together opening the heart and the
mind to the fullness of whatever is here everything that wants to flow
through noticing bowing
resting
and casting your mind back on these moments of meditation
together Gathering up any goodness mindful awareness patience
ease and savoring that any good
qualities and being with as kindly as possible anything
difficult that may have [Music]
Arisen and with that kindness turning your internal gaze
outward to the others in your
life everyone your life
touches may they may others be
safe happy
peaceful and free and may our practice here
together be a cause and condition for that greater happiness peace and freedom
to
arise
thank you for your
practice
so good morning everyone good morning delighted to be back with you
today and delighted to see the bows and the greetings in the chat
it's really
lovely special welcome to those of you who slipped in a little bit late
and happy you could join us so today is the second day of a
five-part series building on the introduction to mindfulness that Gil has been unfolding over the last number of
weeks and these are other skills capacities
elements of mindfulness that are really helpful to bring to the
practice so today is building on yesterday yesterday was a mindfulness of
the very basic attribution of feeling tone or Vena Pleasant unpleasant neutral
that happens in practice and in life it's really basic today is kind of the next layer
our minds tend to add onto that experience which is a wanting or a not
wanting a leaning towards or
away a grasping or a pushing away this is um known as attitude of
mind or mind State generally and this wanting or not
wanting can otherwise be known as greed or aversion greed or aversion and it can
range from the mildest wish to extraordinary
desire or the mildest tiniest pulse of irritation all the way up through
hostility and hatred so there's quite a range here the most way I'm going to talk about it as wanting or not
wanting the um these attitudes of mind can really distort
experience like for example desire can be like those Rose tinted glasses
everything looks beautiful everything looks
nice desirable or a dyed bowl of water is the
ancient kind of similar in the Buddhist discourses whatever that water reflects
takes on the cast of the Dy so it influences it tints
everything for aversion hatred anger hatred tinted
anger hostility the ancient discourses talk about oiling water a roiling boil
and you can kind of get a sense in your body of what that feels like another dramatic simil that's used is that
hatred or hostility is like picking up a hot coal to throw at someone else
well who gets hurt first so this kind of reactivity can be
very um obvious and like a pulse like I'm describing with the hot coal or it can be pervasive and kind of
hidden or unconscious it can be very strong or
extraordinarily subtle in any case it tends to be instinctive thoughts can build on it all
by itself these attitudes emotion emotional reactivity that I'm talking
about aren't the sort of movement of emotion that Gil was talking about last week but
more default moods atmospheres ways of being
that can shape the very way we take in experience when pervasive unconscious
attitudes are there it's more like the waves under a boat the soundtrack to a
movie a filter a tint over the image the general atmosphere of the
sky and in general these kinds of attitudes mind States can be broadly
helpful or unhelpful today I'm talking about the unhelpful ones I will cover helpful ones
more tomorrow but unhel ones within the context of mindfulness
meditation can be kind of like an old rippled pane of glass or a Hall of
Mirrors distorts whatever is seen and it can feed this recursive process of
building more and more thinking or delusion on top of it it it can even distort the process of
mindfulness itself which is not so helpful
so a simple example here I used to work at pain clinics for many years teaching meditation and um many practitioners
have discovered that being mindful with unseen aversion to for example knee pain
actually cultivates more aversion and it cultivates more pain more perception of
pain this is a well documented
phenomenon being being mindful with the attitude of greed can also increase
greed greed for more experience Greed for more of that pleasure another
state in either case sooner or later often
sooner this kind of wanting this leaning in or pushing against increases
suffering and it I mean part of it is that it's
inherent the greed itself has the function of
wanting it also has the function of narrowing The Gaze of
tension of kind of a leaning outwards that isn't so pleasant in of itself
regardless of how pleasant the object of attention seems
aversion has the function of wanting to separate right or even destroy strong
aversion and it also it also has the function of creating more
tension creating more stress so what to do a mindfulness of
wanting or not wanting greed or aversion inputs something different into the
system so these are subtle here it's mindfulness with the aversion or greed or mindfulness of it and it flips it
from being a distortion filter to something that's
seen and this just like noticing feeling tone offers space it offers a
choice a choice it's possible When approaching
this these kinds of States greed aversion wanting not wanting as objects of meditation we can notice them as
events as processes in the mind mind and heart which rather than allowing them to
have Authority or masquerade is truth or reality then they're seen they're no
longer in control and that's good news it's the difference between
meditating with a default state or an attitude versus noticing and the noticing can come with
a bit of clarity mindfulness and perhaps even a bit of kindness or
equinity and this is kind of the magic of mindful awareness it transforms
what's seen instead of believing in it feeding
it pumping it noticing without spinning out allows greed and aversion to become
a basis for wisdom for self-awareness they become food for
discernment rather than fuel for
delusion so it can be super helpful to cultivate
curiosity interest with these attitudes and one way of getting interested is to notice
cause and effect notice the effect on your body
the effect on your mind
with mindfulness our systems begin to recalibrate towards ease Simplicity and
a way away from stress or tension and it's possible to take respit
in the presence of mindful awareness itself to begin to notice whatever
attitudes arise with interest patience even
Joy over time this can transform unhelpful attitudes of wanting and not
wanting or worse and cultivate helpful ones especially a stronger
mindfulness especially a stronger Equanimity compassion even stronger
wisdom so to recap these attitudes attitudes of
wanting or not wanting greed or aversion are just a microc away a nanc away from
Pleasant and unpleasant there is a space in between and there's also space to
incorporate them into mindfulness afterwards and this
itself can help us utilize them as food for wisdom
and Awakening rather than continuing to be hooked by these
states that's my little wrap today and as we did yesterday rather than talk at
you talk at you talk at you I want to offer a moment or two for questions in the chat we have a lag so I'm going to
mute and have a sip of tea and wait for the questions to come in but thank you very much for your practice it's a real
gift it's a gift to the world
oh a question about the guidance where the guidance for this kind of um
practice comes from Sherry I can't think of a single one discourse off the top of
my head it comes from many many discourses but it's included in the
um in the Sati panas to the four foundations of
[Music] mindfulness so as a Buddhist and chronic
pain practitioner how much do you of your Buddhism do you bring to treating patients I don't do that work anymore so
much but it is is very much about the compassion the kindness the
acceptance okay and then Andrea I'm not sure I understand your question I did
give an example of knee pain getting worse if we're aversive to it it gets
much worse the alternative is to back away and notice
the attitude towards the pain rather than the pain itself and this principle
works with all kinds of things in meditation if there's an attitude toward
something that's making wor making it worse you can always take a step back
and notice your relationship to that emotion that attitude that allows for um a little bit
of space so it's taking a step back taking a step back
okay I'm having trouble keeping up with all the chats here we got one minute left we'll see what I can
do
so there two excellent questions Julie yours is going to take longer but just
to Simply say that mindfulness absolutely is a mirror reflecting back
what is however greed or aversion distort the mirror the ripples in the
mirror or like a funhouse mirror and
equinity wisdom causes the mirror to be completely clear whereas delusion might
have you might have a Mist over the mirror or fog or another Distortion and then
[Music] um re-explaining mindfulness if
[Music] beneficial there's a difference between leaning into a
verion and being mindful of a verion so noticing the noticing of the
aversion actually starts to transform the aversion into information into
information so that's the best I can do with a few seconds left I hope that's
helpful and then finally um a couple of people were
asking about Vena neutral Vena so um neutral Vena is a shorthand
for neither Pleasant nor unpleasant feeling tone and that really is the vast
majority of our experience the vast majority of it is neither Pleasant nor unpleasant it's just kind of filtered
out or ignored there is an association sometimes not always with
neither Pleasant nor unpleasant and with
delusion so I hope that's helpful the topic today
isn't really vad anymore so I'll try to address this in a blog post later in a couple
weeks thank you all very much for your practice thank you for your questions
your engagement and um I'll look forward to being back with you
tomorrow
thank you everyone