greetings everyone thank you for coming and for
the folks at IMC and in the USA happy Freedom
Day for our meditations this week are based on the Buddhist
discourse on how to practice mindfulness of breathing Monday we drew on the
introduction to this discourse in which the Buddha suggests that we should meditate in some
place empty so that the mind can be available for staying close to the
breathing Tuesday we meditated with the first two steps of the Buddhist
instructions to know our breathing intimately knowing the texture and
quality of each in breath and each out breath
such as whether whether it's long or [Music]
short open or constricted and yesterday we followed
the third step in which we moved from knowing to training by experiencing the whole body
as we breathe in and breathe out training is a bit more active than
knowing and we'll continue in training mode today and
tomorrow with our attention still anchored in the
body but we're also continuously aware of the breathing in our peripheral
awareness today we'll work with the fourth step in which the Buddha
instructs us one trains I will be breathe in calming the
bodily constructs when trains I shall breathe
out calming the bodily constructs so these bodily constructs
are the translation of um Gils translation of the poly word
Sankara where which literally means making together and is often translated as
formations the idea of making together suggests that the Buddha is talking
about the unity of body and mind our bodily constructs include all
its tensions movements or activities whether
subtle or gross these tensions in the body usually have
their origin in the mind so essentially the task today is
relaxing the body all the while keeping in our
peripheral awareness the whole cycle of
breathing again as we did yesterday we're ating awareness of the whole
body but today we want to see our holding patterns and whatever tensions
we may have and then we do our best to relax
and let go with them or if that's not possible to just
try to soften them a little we can trust that the body
doesn't want to stay tense and if you find something you can't
relax maybe just acknowledge it by gently breathing into it it's
okay so let's begin our meditation on relaxing the body by
gently closing the eyes relaxing and softening any small
physical tensions around or behind the
eyes taking a moment to formulate your deepest intention
now assuming a calm stable and grounded
posture that can help you avoid any inclination to
move staying with the breath and bringing compassion and care
to the body as we do a soft body
scan straight stening the spine and relaxing everything
else downwards head to the
face the neck relaxing into the
shoulders the [Music] arms and
hands relaxing the front and back back of the Torso and letting go in the
pelvis the legs and the
feet still aware of the body and the breath establish your mental
posture by letting go of having to be someone
now feeling how it is to take a lovely long
calm deep breath
and gently letting the breathing return to normal as you stay
grounded resting in relaxing the body
breathing breathing in breathing out
spacious and caring as we bring calm to our precious
body keep practicing like
this
e
e e
the Buddha says that tranquility is the food for
tranquility so whatever little calm or Tranquility you
have be sure to take it in and let it
register
e
e e
often in images of the Buddha meditating we can see a slight
smile on his face so bring your attention for a
moment to your face and see if you can relax anything in your
forehead again your eyes your cheeks your
chin your jaw and feel
free to let your lips Express the smile
of the Buddha
and you trust relax it relaxing the
breathing relaxing the body and mind if
possible try not to move knowing that stilling the physical
body goes a long way to also quieting the
mind
e
e e
earlier we practiced noticing if there is anything calm in our
experience and now the invitation is to notice if there's
anything Pleasant in your experience of calming
the body as you stay with the
breathing or perhaps you can even enjoy being here in the body breathing
calmly if so let that enjoyment
register
e
e e
as we come to the end of this sitting we'll return to our circle of
compassion for ourselves for everyone meditating with
us today and for all
beings may all beings be safe and protected
being safe may all beings including ourselves be happily at
ease may all beings abide in
peace and may all beings everywhere be
free so to end the meditation perhaps we can all join our
hands together and bow to each other honoring the sincerity of
everyone's practice
here
e e
readings everyone good to be here with you
in our meditation just now we focused on relaxing the body while staying with the
breath and this is a further step in strengthening our
mindfulness because it also helps stabilize and concentrate the
mind yesterday we talked about s The Faculty or power of
trusting taking refuge in the path of
practice and sadada also refers to having faith in
yourself I'll begin with a passage from Joseph goldstein's book one
Dharma the heart qualities of faith confidence and Trust are actual Powers
we can cultivate in Buddhist texts they are
likened to a magical gem that settles impurities in
water faith in the possibility of
Awakening confidence in the moments experience and in the nature of
awareness itself and
Trust in the direction of our own
lives all of these settle doubt
confusion and agitation they create an inner
environment of clarity Stillness and
Beauty yes Beauty
again earlier in the week I stressed that the good news is that we have
agency and one of my heroes Deepa
ma said you can do anything you want to do
it's only your thought that you can't do it that's holding you
back Faith grounded in wisdom is also one of the seven mental
qualities that support the development of
equinity Sada opens us to what is greater than
the ego's concerned we open up to the possibility of
freedom and come to understand that our limitations our
separateness our fears are actually the material through which we discover the
truth of our
wholeness having faith in the present moment lets us be with whatever
arises and that in turn allows us to investigate whatever difficulties
arise The Awakening factor of Investigation is what gives us the
wisdom to make wholesome choices about what we do in each moment
the reason that the hindrance of Doubt is considered to be the most
dangerous is because it can knock us off the path but
everyone starts out with doubts and we can learn a lot by
studying them here's a poem by the founder of the
soo Zen tradition dogen zenji the great
ancestor he says the peach blossoms begin to bloom
in the breeze of spring not a shade of Doubt is left on
the branches and the leaves though I know that I shall meet
the Autumn Moon again how sleep Sleepless I remain on
this moonless
night so uh in the Zen tradition the Moon is often uh a metaphor for
awakening Clarity in the mind but it it's pretty amazing uh that
even dogen contrary to the beach tree knows the without
doubt and what's important is that we don't identify with our
doubts instead we can watch the whole process of
doubting asking who it is that doubts seeing how doubts come and
go and another um problem
with doubt is that it takes us away from the direct experience of the
moment so if you have doubts see if you can step outside of
them so that you're no longer victimized by
doubting trust in the practice gives us the energy to bring our lives
into alignment with our highest aspirations and if
your inspiration Fades your faith can keep you
going in the proximate CA suta the Buddha explains that we all experience
suffering and when faith or trust rather than doubt or despair is born of that
suffering this sets in motion the whole chain of liberative dependent
arising which actually begins with suffering and then leads to gladness and
joy and all the way to complete liberation
and what this means is that we're not stuck with our duka our
difficulties if we trust the practice our difficulties are just the starting
point they lead to gladness when we have no doubt that we're on a path we
trust they the hindrance of Doubt manifests in two basic ways doubt in the
Buddhist teaching and doubt in
oneself I'll never forget how I felt when I first met Suzuki rosi as he bowed
to each of us as we filed out of the little meditation space at sooi in San
Francisco and in that bow he wordless ly communicated that he literally saw me as
a Buddha and I was moved beyond
words six days later I heard him teach and somehow I
knew beyond the shade of a doubt that I was in the presence of a great teacher
and I'd give up anything to become his disciple and ever since then my faith in
the Dharma has been unshakable
but having faith in myself has been a lot more
challenging I know it's true that many of us tend to be loyal to our
suffering and to seeing ourselves as inadequate or damaged
one of the challenges for me has been the tyranny of [Music]
perfectionism a powerful lesson from my childhood was that if I'm not perfect
I'm not safe but actually we can trust that
we're all fine just as we are which means that we can all shine
just as children do and when we see how
perfectionism doesn't serve us and can start letting go of
it we can become contented and
peaceful with just doing what we
can and this in turn counters agitation and fosters
Tranquility a useful mantra for me has been good
enough I love what Walt whitmann says in his song of the open
road I am larger better than I
thought I did not know I held so much
goodness it's important not to be afraid of feeling
insecure after all uh in this practice our
priority is to cultivate non- clinging and as human beings not
clinging to anything is profoundly
counterintuitive Gil tells us that we can trust that the safest place to be is
in our field of awareness it's a lot safer to be aware
than it is to be identified with a self and there's great Freedom when
we're deep ly and we deeply understand the Buddhist teaching on the truth of
not self we can all stop worrying about our
supposed inadequacies this practice is pointing
us to a place of the greatest safety which is
portable internal safety we can take into the world where
things may not not be so safe and as we learn to abide in
Awareness we learn to carry our internal safety with
us awareness as the pure natural quality of the
Mind awareness is often said to be like the sky where everything is
okay knowing that all our mental storms Ms are just
clouds that don't change the nature of the sky we can trust opening up to the sky
itself in our meditations this week we've cultivated knowing feeling and
relaxing and these three work together to bring forth the calm and the
confidence we need for awareness to be more
here in our experience taking a moment for knowing
feeling and relaxing allows us to be less distracted from what's happening in
the moment and when we connect with our Pure mind in a way that's relaxed and
balanced our experience of the world is also relaxed and balanced
bed and a mind even momentarily empty of distractions feels
beautiful and we can't help but enjoy
it as the Buddha says with a mind that is open and uncovered one develops a luminous
mind and my hope is that each of you can grow in having confidence in yourself
just as you are resting your inner
goodness and
wisdom in the meditation today we practice trusting relaxing and in the talk just now I
emphasized the importance of trusting yourself so if you'd like some homework
for the next 24 hours reflect on what you personally
might do in order to cultivate trusting yourself are there any mental or
physical habits you may want to let go of or how might you pause and relax more
often or take a piece of paper and jot down a few ideas then get in touch with a friend to
share your thoughts thank you for