okayy let's so let's go ahead and get started for those of you who didn't hear
earlier um Gil was always planning to travel at the end of this week so it was
arranged that I would be here with you on Thursday and Friday so very nice to
to see you all there many familiar names and welcome to anyone who's just
joining so for this meditation um I want to bring up an kind
of an image there's a there's a book from the probably the 70s and I don't
remember the details of it I think it's actually called Zoom and I know Zoom has
a whole different meaning now but this was back in the 70s and it starts out
it's a series just a it's a picture book and there's a picture on each page and
it starts out I don't remember what the first picture is maybe it's a a dog and
then on the next page you see that the dog is uh sitting by a pool and there's
some people there and then on the next page you see that actually that is a
picture on a postcard that somebody is writing while sitting aboard a ship and
and next one you know it goes back and back and each time you see that what you
saw and conceived as what the picture was was actually just a little piece of
something bigger going on and as you can imagine it goes back and back and back
through this um so that we have to get the impression as the book goes along oh
there's a lot more going on here than just this one little thing and my
understanding of what it is from the little context I have so this I think can be a valuable
idea for meditation also kind of a valuable image to keep in mind is that
each thing that's arising it has some place maybe in a bigger picture that we
can't see completely and it becomes less appealing once we go through a book like Zoom to
decide whether something belongs or not what its function is whether it should
or shouldn't be there it's like we don't we don't quite know that in the moment so might as well
let everything arise and be itself so this can be a very
valuable idea for meditation so let's go ahead and sit finding a a
posture where you feel comfortable
relaxed closing the eyes if that's appropriate for
you and bringing the attention inward
soft gentle gaze at the body the mind as it is now
just kind of taking in what's there
softening the body inviting some ease in the
shoulders belly down into the
legs inviting some EAS in the mind
a softness to our
awareness sense of tranquility
and protection of this time we're here having a chance to
sit just for now there doesn't need to be anything
else
maybe taking a couple of long slow deep breaths and on the out breath softening
the body and the mind and connecting them so there's some sense of
the body being part of the larger picture of what the Mind knows
and letting the breath return to normal it's fine as it
is I'm beginning to notice the changing
experience that the mind is naturally receiving sometimes it notices the
body maybe the contact points or the
breath or something that feels uncomfortable in the body or some
energy and sometimes it's aware of an emotion or a thought
with mindfulness we can know that we're knowing sometimes that becomes
prominent might see if we can see these different
arisings as part of some larger
flow that we're not quite seeing all of which is
fine each thing comes in supported by
its conditions has its
place and Fades away or maybe persist for a while
but bringing in this sense of I might not have the whole
picture can support a relaxation in the
mind to let everything arise and have its
place we can't really say that it doesn't
belong so why not
relax and if there is a sense of judging or rejecting or deciding about something
that's actually one more thing that can arise and have its place
oh there's a pain and there's the sense that it
shouldn't be there there's fear that it will get worse
okay that too is part of this bigger
picture in this way experience becomes
free of our limitation of
it through deciding what it is
already can we rest with
that
for e
we may notice that sometimes
mind grabs on to something in
experience because it thinks it knows what it is and what it should be
and how it can be changed it wants to chew on it or fix
it get rid of it in some way and we can notice that
movement as one that feels St and [Music]
limited and release the experience back into the flow as if we've pulled a fish out of a
[Music] stream and how much better it feels to
toss it back in let the stream keep
flowing keep letting the big picture unfold and be
itself three of us in a
sense
e
e e
sometimes what arises is expected or
[Music] agreable we think that it fits it's
right it's what we wanted and
sometimes what arises is unflexed or
disturbing painful in some way so quickly we decide that's not
right that shouldn't
be but that response is one more [Music]
arising take some Trust to allow something unpleasant to be part of
the bigger
picture and yet that's the invitation of a practice that sees
things as they
are but we offer just a bit more trust that the big
picture can include everything and our
awareness can be there for everything as it
is
e
e e
in the last few minutes of this [Music] meditation perhaps taking a moment now
to look back at yourself at how it has
been in this sit to try to allow this bigger picture
this sense that we don't know everything and so we can't say what
belongs and doesn't [Music] belong what impact has that
had on your own inner
life it can bring sometimes a sense of spaciousness
or sense of respect that there's something bigger some
humility to us can also bring some fear or
uncertainty maybe we're not so much in [Music] control and all of these are part of
that bigger picture too part of how it is to be a human in a changing and
unpredictable world
and maybe as you go out into the day or the
evening could carry some useful part of this sense that there might be something more
going on that I don't know maybe this person I'm talking
with is having a hard time right now and that's
why they're not paying as much attention to me as I thought they
should maybe [Music] something has broken
but no it was much older than I thought it was or it was just the
time maybe something seems to be lost or
gone but it's making space for something new or it's
not we can't know but the bigger picture is unfolding
and we are always a part of it and we can have a choice to
participate in a way that is that is a true participant
that allows other people other things to be
as they are and we respond without reacting
without rejecting without trying to fix and judge
and make everything as we want it a bit more
grace we may find mind that other people respond
well to a bit softer
approach so may it be that each person can find their way to
be in this bigger picture may we give them the space to do
so including
ourselves may we each find the balance the
perspective the peace that allows us to just calmly know
what is unfolding and be a part of it
so this week Gil has been talking about the
hindrances from a particular perspective and the framework is that
the five hindrances are UNH wholesome strategies that the mind has adopted to
handle the challenges of a human life and one of the ways to become free
of these hindrances is to see clearly and honestly that each one is UNH wholesome
or unhealthy and to actually feel that in the moment as a somatic
experience and then in the calm knowing of that and the the willingness to feel
what is unhealthy hey about our mind strategy we reduce the stickiness of
that hindrance and eventually learn to navigate life more freely without
collapsing into these patterns so we're going through them
backwards because doing that highlights the fundamental that the fundamental
issue is in the fifth hindrance which is usually translated as doubt or certainty
but it more specifically means that we aren't clear on what is wholesome and
what is UNH wholesome so if we don't have that we can't discern when the
other hindrances are present so that's kind of the the root of it in this um
perspective that we're taking the good news is that through mindfulness practice we're strengthening
that ability to discern and if we keep paying attention to our experience
whatever it is with this understanding that there are healthy ways to be with
it and also unhealthy ones and we want the healthy ones then we'll enhance our
ability to see clearly So today we're moving on to the
traditionally the second hindrance which is called ill will and this is about
reacting to the challenges of life with hostility or rejection or pushing away
anger blame judgment those kinds of reactions and maybe it's good to start
with understanding that not all instances of Turning Away which is the
literal meaning of averting or reversion not all of those are unhealthy there can
be times when it's a skillful for our well-being to say no not right now or
thank you but we're not going to engage with that or sometimes even
stop um the hindrance but the hindrance is the ill
will that comes along with that it's kind of a a negative regard of a person
or a mind state or a situation um or even a wish for harm to
come and the underlying sense that that's bad
that's wrong that shouldn't be that is what covers over um the mind's ability to be with
the reality of experience remember that the hindrances are coverings that's
literally what the poly word for that's translated as hindrance means so if we
have this sense of that shouldn't be here um we can't quite connect with and
engage with experience fully the moment that we're experiencing may be very
unpleasant um what's being known may be very unpleasant um but it is still
unhealthy to attack that or to reject it with
hostility so one issue with ill will is that it gets tied in with other
hindrances very easily so it can pull in agitation or activation hindrance of
restlessness and anxiety these kinds of things uh ill
will can also lead to sinking down into what you'll call rigidity or torper or
shutting [Music] down very we're rejecting experience we
can slide into that so it can easily be entangled with the the other ones so
it's important that we get to know this quality of ill will the Mind often has
to really feel it in the body and feel actually the UNH wholesomeness of it
before our ill will has any impact on the situation or the person that we feel
hostile toward it has a damaging impact on us there's um there's an image in the
sutas where the Buddha Likens anger to grasping a stick with the intention
of attacking but the stick is smeared with excrement so before you have any impact
outwardly you have touched something really unclean I think it's meant to
point to a visceral feeling that we can have and the the trick is to feel the
ill will itself and not just be caught up in what we're feeling a verse two
because that's where the Mind goes you know it sees something that it doesn't like or that it feels is impacting us
imp pleasantly unpleasantly and then it jumps on that that's the thing that is
wrong it needs to be gotten rid of or reacted to and we don't quite turn and
see what that feeling in US is so you know when we when we pick up the stick
we might feel powerful and right um and we might think this the stick is
going to be effective in dispelling or hurting what we are angry about and so
there can actually be a pleasant feeling when we pick up that stick there's an a feeling of energy um Power strength that
can come through ill will it's um it's a pleasant feeling but it's not a wholesome Pleasant feeling but it is
pleasant and if we tune only into that we might miss the
excrement so another image that the Buddha gave for anger is that it has a
honeyed tip and a poison root so that points to the fact that
anger comes from the root of hatred the root of what's called Dosa um so in a given moment of
hostility there might be both a pleasant component and an underlying feeling of
disease the excr part so you know what about the
stress that arises in the moment of anger you know when something is
irritating us or we're feeling hostile there is some kind of clenching or
contraction or a distortion of the energy in our system it can almost be um
nauseating in some cases if we really turn toward what's happening in us so if
we're careful with our mindfulness and we're willing to see and sense everything that's going on we can feel
this um this poison root uh another image given for ill will
is that it's like a disease a literal illness and being caught in ill will so
identified with our anger or our aversion is like being sick we not in
Balance not in harmony not with the flow of Life the texts mentioned specifically
about not digesting well um I think this points toward one of the
uh focuses of Indian medicine but it's true when we're sick we don't digest our food very well right
and when we go around with a negative and reactive way of being we aren't
nourished in our life there is nourishing beautiful food
available around us but it's like we don't benefit from it so people who are
habitually hostile could be said to be starving amid plenty you know they've become
unhealthy from the inside so it's important to start to see
this pattern operating in us which means in the moment in real time we don't need
to reflect abstractly and this quality of calm knowing that we've been pointing
to this week is so helpful we can cultivate the calm knowing of two things
one is the object that we find repulsive or upsetting that triggers the ill will
it's important that we um use mindfulness to step back and see that clearly before the mind has its hostile
reaction this is a lot of what um mindfulness first allows us to do is create that little Gap so that we're not
just automatically reacting and then second which is actually more important is that we can
learn to calmly know ill will itself as a hindrance so it's not just about being
more accepting of unpleasant objects or people or experiences and learn to
tolerate them although that's a good start we also want to turn back and look at that reaction in the mind and see
that ill will is simply a reaction that our or confused mind comes up with when
it's trying to navigate a challenging world the world does have a lot of unpleasant things about it um and in a
particular human life is not easy it's not that easy to live in this body and
navigate living in the in the world so it's also important that we
don't have to bring in ideas that we shouldn't have you know this this negative feeling that spiritual people
aren't angry Etc that's just adding more ill will more judgment more negative
regard of ourselves so if you find that there's
every now and then a little moment of ill will um I certainly have some ill will
in my system still um there's no need to identify with that and say oh I
shouldn't be there or oh I'm such an angry person we we simply see it and in
doing so we have a measure of freedom in that moment
one time I was on a retreat and we had group practice discussions that were
held outside and our group was sitting out under a tree and there were birds in the
tree and one of them pooped onto the head of someone in the group and she
reached up and realized what it was and her face contracted in repulsion and she
she looked up toward the bird and said dirty little thing and then she went off
to the bathroom to wash but she was a strong practitioner and she took it as
an opportunity for practice and actually by the time she came back she was
smiling um she had had a wonderful opportunity to see the sequence of an
unpleasant experience and then a reaction to that that included hostility
toward the bird in this case the bird was not to blame and it is probably appropriate to
find bird excrement unpleasant and to want to go wash it off that's taking
normal care of our health it's not it's not clean right but can we do that with
just calm awareness and here's what happened we've got the bird poop in the
hair and I can respond appropriately and go and take care of it so with ongoing
mindfulness practice maybe we can learn to receive the bird poop of life if you
will and just do what needs to be done so the the Buddha says that we can
stand free of the influence of ill will and we can do that and we can if we do
that in a moment we will AB lied with care for the well-being of all beings
that includes ourself wanting to be free of the poison of ill will and it also
includes care for others for the world and all of that is enabled by this calm
knowing and clear seeeing so it's true human life and this
world that we live in does include very difficult things that are unpleasant and
painful but letting go of ill will is is not about denying that to live in some
kind of a blissful fantasy but we can we can we can do it all without the hostility the
reactivity which harms us before it does anything else out in the
world so I hope this will give some flavor of how we can learn to see and
meet this reaction that we have of rejecting of will and learn
to include that as one more thing that's going on so that we can um to use Gil's
image from yesterday we can ride our bicycle more freely not always getting
drawn in so perhaps that can be your guidance for
today is to remember there's probably a bigger picture there's a way that we
don't need to reject what's going on we may not be seeing it all just to respond
as calmly as we can so thank you and be well