so hello and welcome everyone to this edition of happy hour um lovely to be
with you [Music] so so for today's practice um I wanted
to bring in this idea that we always bring in
actually in at the end especially when we do medic dedication of Merit that we
do this practice not just for our own sake but do we do this practice um practice
of cultivating our hearts our minds towards kindness uh mindfulness awareness
equinity all these beautiful qualities of the heart that we do it not just for ourselves but we do it for others for
those we are entangled those we are those we love those we care
about um our friends our family those we are in Tangled with and and all beings
everywhere we do this practice not just for ourselves but for others and there's a beautiful
aspiration in in both doing it for ourselves and for others there's so so
much goodness in that so I uh recently heard some um research
actually uh and let's see if I can quickly uh find the name of the re
researcher I wasn't necessarily going to talk about it but now I feel inspired yes David joer Dr David joer who's done
a lot of research on this and the the um one of the uh uh aspects of the research
it it shows that um not no not just for meditation but for worldly actions um
one way to to help motivate ourselves and especially motivate young people
people in the world it's not just the benefit that they get out of it not um
only that for example they'll graduate and they'll have high paying jobs or whatever it might be but that that their
work their their study their U cultivation of skills is of benefit to
others is is benefit to greater good and as I was listening to this research I
thought yes of course yes and especially his research shows that when things are
tough if if we're just doing it for our own sake and and there challenges or
maybe there is a lack of success and and and um there's a different mind mind
makes a different kind of meaning out of it that oh you know I failed and and when it's personal when it's feels more
perhaps personal and just for myself or maybe selfish has a different
orientation challenges feel more difficult whereas has if we do something
that seems challenging or difficult but it's for the sake of not just our ourselves but everyone else there's a a
uh a uh uh what I like to call a wholesomeness an uprightness there is a
dedication there is a and and the way his research I forget the words he was using but there's a sense of people
arise to the challenge because it's not just for themselves they arise to the challenge I was thinking about that in
our meditation practice um also that this these are skills the that that
we're developing not just for our own sake especially if things are challenging or become challenging at any
point in the meditation practice we're doing this for the sake of all beings
and perhaps if we bring up the the um thought of people we care about and and
the sense of dedicating dedicating this practice to others um it's it supports
us so couple of things I wanted to bring in and David dieger has a new book out
about all these research and and uh so you can learn more anyway so with that
as Preamble let's practice not just for our own sake for but for the sake of all
whose lives ours touches directly or indirectly so let's
begin let's begin by arriving AR diving in our
seat let's arrive together and
settle allowing your body to settle allowing our mind to
settle this invitation to settle
and what if we thought about this moment of settling our minds relaxing the body
and connecting with the breath with the in breath and with the out breath bringing awareness
attention ever so gently kindly
receptively to the sensations of INB breath out
breath and what if we considered that this moment right here not hypothetically but this moment moment
of receptive
attention with the in breath and out
breath is both for the sake of an
offering a gift to ourselves in this moment and feel
feeling that feeling as if we're giving ourselves a gift this person who is me I'm giving
them a gift of calming settling training their
mind their attention giving myself a gift in this
moment palpable
keep giving yourself this gift in this moment really connecting
with the gift the goodness
of this offering to yourself with care with
kindness
and now consider at this moment
of connecting with your breath attending
receiving relaxing and receiving the breath in the body is also for the sake of your future
self the person you will become cultivating this moment
of calm kindness in this moment it helps
you become a better version of yourself in the future calmer higher Remer for the sake of your future self
whom you haven't met yet whom you haven't met yet but you like them you appreciate them you want to do your best
for them you're giving them a gift sending a gift into the future by
attending wisely kindly to this moment moment's experience right
here for the sake of your future
best way to support the future self is to stay right here connected this
moment e
and then now as if you're looking through the rear
view mirror as a gift to your past
self a person whose efforts challenges you know you
know too well the appreciation to everything they
have done all their perseverance and strength as
supported your present s to be here right now
and give yourself to this practice in this moment as a gift as an offering to them as a thank
you practicing In This Moment connecting wholeheartedly wholeheartedly with the
practice right here this in breath to have breath
bringing more dimensionality to This Moment's
practice e
in breath out breath just this one this in breath this out
breath
e e
now if you would expanding this Circle of
Care bringing in a few beings
people pets animals people from your past people from the
future beings other beings you care
about or have cared about and appreciating that this moment
of cultivating awareness with the breath with the body with kindness
it's both for your sake and their sake so that you can be a Kinder gentler wiser calmer version of
yourself for their sake for the sake of the people you
interact with you care about who care about you so that you can show up ni kindly
and wisely this
breath in breath out breath this
moment e
and make sure after you have evoked the sense of others you come back to your
body to your breath so that it doesn't become a thinking practice you just evoke that this is not just for yourself
and then you come back to your body to your breath with kindness
letting others be in the wings but not the direct focus of this
Practice Center piece of the practice is connecting holding receiving the breath
in the body the gentleness kindness spaciousness
ease presence
expanding the circle further including all beings path present
future all beings in all directions in the ways we don't quite appreciate or
understand our practice reverberates and impacts those we know and we don't
know having evoked sense of our inter connection our vast
[Music] interconnection dedicating our hearts to our practice even more more
wholeheartedly this moment right here I'm practicing for all
beings and for myself for all
beings each breath each
moment your heart Delight in the wholesomeness and the goodness of
this greater than me sense of our personal
practice
e
e e
and as we bring this period of sitting too close
together appreciating our practice for the sake of ourselves is
being who me was vastly interconnected whose life whose life is
so miraculously amazingly [Music] interconnected in speechless
ways with all beings in ways we can't quite
understand May our practice be support or The
Awakening of all beings everywhere may all beings be happy may
all beings be free including myself
you so much for your practice
everyone nice it it is it does make a difference
when we expand our perspective and really see the truth
of of how interconnected we are and we're not doing this practice just for
our own sake it really gives it so much beautiful dimensionality which I hope
came in for you in whatever ways it did so um and now with this dimensionality
of interconnection that we don't do this practice just for ourselves as we're sitting with our eyes
closed but also in in engaging with others um I also learned from the
research of David the acre that one of the best ways to really um own
um a a something that you learn is to share it with others explain it to
others so in that that way of sharing it with others really making it our own uh
you know that's that's a big bonus of teaching being in the Dara seat um that
I need to walk my talk really own it all these practices so so so um you get to to
engage and and share explain the the benefits the inner
process the challenges whatever it is uh with one another what a privilege to be able to do that have this space that
other people are interested in this too fellow practitioners so we'll be in small
groups of size three mostly other there would be some smaller or bigger groups
and the invitation is to um share a bit about how this practice was for you how
it shifted moved um or perhaps challenged you and again you're really
speaking for your own benefit for your own sake to to internalize this practice
and and explore your relationship to it not to educate or edify others it's
really for your own sake so let's Go reverse alphabetical
order uh according to first name each person will offer one short nugget the next person the next person will come
back to you and you'll go around and round a few times and again please be kind be sensitive to yourself to others
this is really how we practice kindness as it meets as the rubber meets the
road and um I'm going to open the rooms and please take care of yourselves and
each other here we go okay welcome back everyone the rooms
are closed and and uh we have a few minutes for Reflections and and um
comments questions what did you discover and oh I'm going to also change the chat
settings so you are welcome to to uh type your Reflections in chat um and if
you type them to me only uh I will um uh
read only your reflection not your name and if you type them to everyone then I
will uh read your reflection and your name and um for the first round of
Reflections I want to invite folks who haven't spoken recently actually uh just
to you know move back move forward allow folks who haven't
spoken in a while orever to have a chance to reflect and comment and so
um yeah haven't heard from you then would love to hear from you how was this
practice for
you what did you discover during the practice what did you discover S I see
your hand we haven't heard from you for a while hi Nikki hi thank you I have a
question um you mentioned the future self and the past
self and when I think about the future self I think about what you sometimes mentioned which I really love the
planting the seed it gives me a sense of hope uh but I'm not sure what you
exactly meant but that future self is related to that and also the past self I
I think as still my mind goes to the past and like kind of
navigating what has happened not always in a positive way also dealing with like
the traumas of the past and the challenges of the past and and like this
planting of the seed is very hopeful but I still struggle with like the past and I wonder
what you you what was the intention here right instead of going down the rabbit
hole of of yeah exactly um that's a very good
question and I appreciate that you're bringing this up
so so the idea here is first of all the big picture idea to bring a lot more
dimensionality instead of the small self of me in this moment but really bring
dimensionality in in lots of different perspectives not just other human beings other beings
that we know we don't know expanding the circle that way but also expanding the this circle of concern through time
through this other dimension of time and and the way um the
idea of our future self is you know
um it's the teaching of Karma and the appropriate correct teaching of karma is
This Moment's actions precondition the next moment and the next moment so
it's an actually a very empowering teaching so in that way oh yeah this
moment of being empow being Mindful and kind oh it's planting the seeds for my
future self I'm S as if my future self is my child you know someone
I'm bearing um giving them the best opportunity for kindness for for uh
equinity by how I am in this moment so just invoking that and then coming back
to this moment inhabiting this moment more fully it's not just for it's it's like oh there other dimensions here you
kind of keep that and then instead of analyzing and and hope is a nice way to to think about that too this
um and then with respect to the past I appreciate that it can become a thinking
and and you know what did I do all of that getting entangled in that and and it's helpful to notice if that's
happening and come out of it and and yet again the idea there is oh it's you know as if
you're the child this moment you're the child of this being from the past you're
their child they you know they had hopes and dreams and challenges and you're their child you're like thank you Mom
thank you Dad you know thank you it's like oh there's this there's like oh
this is the gift this is the gift of this is this moment it's um there's a
whole some this in this moment that they can they can benefit from retroact you know in in time I I hope that makes
sense in a in a um um in a time in you know in a
holographic way it's an H you know this moment being a hologram of many moments so that's the idea of oh yeah inhabiting
the dimensionality uh and just again evoking the idea of a past self as as as you
would evoke the idea of a parent whom you're oh yeah you're dedicating this moment of kindness and and wholesomeness
to the to a parent instead of thinking about your relationship with your parent and it's just evoking them it's the same
same idea with your past self oh dedicating oh this is not just for this moment but for for me but also all the
versions I have been uh it's that that kind of a dedication does that make sense yeah it's uh youing
yes very much the last piece just brought everything together for together
great I appreciate you asked the question s thank you
and I was told that Joy whom I guess we haven't heard for a while has had their
hands up and Serena I see your hand I'll come back to you after I the this first
round is again for those who haven't spoken recently so Joyce let's see where are you Joyce us ah there you are I see
you there I was just going to say the the
joy of being able to meditate together with people with your guidance and what
you what you bring to the group to meditate with it's lovely thank you
blessings oh thank you Joyce thank you so much for being part of this group and
and bringing your precious self to this group and practicing together thank you
beautiful thank you Joy by the way I think you're great ah you're very kind
thank you I think this this whole Community is
great um okay let's see and Mima I haven't heard from you for a while
please thank you Nikki um yeah along the same lines with the um the future self
what I shared in my group with was that who I was several years ago when I
joined this group and who I am now because of happy hour and this joining
and conversing and sharing the experience after after a brief talk it's
transformed me and that was who I was and this is who I am now and so I've
literally took it to this group today and I felt like wow yeah that what I did
a long time ago is is this is the fruit of it today and so I'm very grateful I'm
very grateful to this practice and we we shared how um I've learned I shared that I've learned so much from you and um I
see the fruits of it now so thank you ah thank you Mima Oh yay makes me so happy
thank you so much so beautiful in the way you beautifully expressed yeah you
you feel the fruits of this past self who's come has been practicing
consistently and meditating and sharing and I see the hearts uh others
appreciating what you shared yes yeah that's exactly it yay yay appreciating
this wholesomeness of the past self and and and the future self beautiful great
now opening it up to everyone so S I see your hand please
you're un yes thank you thank you sure thank you uh yes I want to share something
that I've become aware of today and that is that um you know how we say that we do
the practice for old beings not just for ourselves and
um it occurred to me today you and you know and we also have this idea that we
we reap the fruits of our past actions the good and the bad and what occurred
to me today is that when one being you know uh comes from a place of
Enlightenment and uh has reach a certain state of being
that the karma The Good Karma of that being actually affect changes the karma
of a whole bunch of other beings and I never thought of that before but but it
occurred to me today that actually the um the fruits The Good the good fruits
of our Karma my karma your karma other people's Karma actually
affect uh for other will will impact other people's karma in a good way you
know it automatically does just but us being present and it's never occurred to
me before uh so this this was an awareness that I I gain today thank you
great thank you so much for sharing this Serena indeed yes we we affect one
another and as we um shift and change so that our actions are internal actions
actions of the Mind actions of speech actions of body are more wholesome it
impacts it invites others it impa it encourages others it impacts others
wholesomely positively for them to be the better angels of themselves of
course it does of course and of and ditto negatively if our actions of the
Mind our thoughts are UNH wholesome and our words are UNH wholesome and and our
physical actions in the world are un wholesome it in it unfortunately it inspires perhaps others to to it it
brings the worst out of people so yeah thank you Serena thanks for sharing this Insight you had today beautiful
important and
clear I just thought I'd give you a little laugh I was not watching my timer
at all on my computer and uh was very happy doing what I was doing and it was
finished too fast all of a sudden it was over I couldn't believe it I went looked
at the clock it's so thank you very much it was a
total Joy thanks Claire yeah time flies when you're having fun it it yeah it
fell Too Short too but and yeah yeah thank you glad it felt that way sweet me
too thank you thank you and I see Jerry's question who is
asking what is the proper definition of karma
so the um so cause and effect is the
translation and um cause and effect and
effect the um kind of the effect is the
karma vipaka in poly so karma is short for karma vipaka which is the the cause
and effect the effect of an action in the world so uh that's the proper
definition but really as a as a teaching very briefly is best to think of karma
as an onward leading as a forward movement as a as an
empowering teaching that what I do in this moment it preconditions the next
moment and the next moment and the next moment it's really best to to practice it that way not backwards looking which
can be actually very detrimental what did I what did I do in my past life that
I'm suffering this like oh ouch that's just or other people you know they must deserve what they're getting because
they did something awful like those are those are unhelpful please don't go down
that rabbit hole with yourselves with others with societies cultures people
it's just like that's the whole other talk but very helpful to think to
practice this is is as a forward um onward leading practice of how can I and
and actually also ties with it ties in with the Neuroscience research of what
what and also what the Buddha has taught whatever uh you frequently reflect and
Ponder upon becomes the inclination of your mind so whatever you're thinking whatever you're doing if you're thinking
Goodwill thoughts wholesome actions calm kindness that's how you're going to
precondition yourself if you're angry in this more feeding the fire of anger and hatred well guess what that's just going
to become the Habit pattern of you become kind of an angry person we know this anyway so that's I hope I that
answers your question Jerry so thank you all thank you for practicing for the
benefit of not just ourselves but all beings all beings how beautiful just how
Grand may all beings everywhere be free may all beings everywhere be
happy including all beings here in this community ourselves thank you all I'll
ring the [Music]
bell thanks everyone be well take care