good morning good day good evening
Sana warm greetings to you nice to be with you
again love hearing and well not hearing but seeing all the warm greetings in the
chat and just sensing in the much wider group of people practicing together in
silence that your chats represent and I'm imagining comments
about hearing that you can hear me which would be
great just confirm that would be great
great thank you those of you who respond about sound I appreciate
it oh offering your warm greetings those of you who are to others and those of
you who are offering or not offering greetings externally please offer warm
greetings internally to yourself
[Music] perhaps taking a slower longer
breath and ATT tuning to how this body this
heart this day is living within
you taking a moment to adjust your posture take a LP of tea
and then allowing the eyes to soften perhaps
close and setting the intention to show up wholeheartedly in
this moment this time set aside
for your own
cultivation after a second or third longer longer slower deeper
breath allowing the breathing to be natural normal
and noticing your
surroundings as they contact your
body a sense of air or cloth on your [Music]
skin the weight of this body a cushion or chair
softening the eyes the [Music]
tongue noticing sound and sensation
and bringing mindfulness awareness to the Forefront
tuning in to all of the little
Sensations movement signals of aliveness in the
body
choosing whatever anchor of attention feels best for you
today mindfulness of
breathing allowing the attention to settle inside the experience of the
breath
a full flow
rhythm of breathing
noticing when there's an in breath there's an in
breath noticing the out breath on the out breath
noticing the change in
between in this cycle of breathing
receiving the awareness with each in
breath and offering yourself your attention completely
to the out breath Letting Go
relaxing resting in The Still Point at the end of the out
breath before allowing the next
inhale e
allowing the center of gravity of your
attention to move Inward and downward
within embodied
experience e
you notice thoughts [Music]
emotions any phenomena anything at all that pulls the attention
away perhaps smiling
internally this
toe and graciously receiving the return of
awareness ATT tuning to the
body the
moment
e
e e
the last remaining moments of this meditation
together the invitation is to reflect back on this time these
moments reflecting appreciatively
acknowledging any challenges or
difficulties with compassion
trusting that this too is part of the season of
practice such difficulties can be composted
are composted by the light of awareness
mindfulness especially when kindness is
present then turning that kind attention
to
savoring harvesting up any of the good
moment Cal or Joy mindful awareness or
patience searching all the corners of the heart and mind
Gathering them together and letting them nourish you your
practice by appreciating
them then casting that internal gaze outwards
to your fellow practitioners here near and
far anyone who does or
has supported your
practice sending them a pulse of Goodwill meta
and then opening your
heart and sending those good wishes to the others in your life including yourself too
may they be safe
happy healthy may they be
peaceful at EAS and
free May the goodness of our practice Ripple outwards and outwards
through our lives to all of the lives we touch and all of the lives they
touch may all beings everywhere know safety Peace and Freedom
[Music]
thank you for your
practice e
so dear sa we reached the fourth talk out of
this series of five on dhic reciprocity this kind of unfolding Journey in quiry
that I'm exploring with your kind attention and your ideas
sometimes so I'm going to open right away with a
story this is a teaching story that um the Buddha has recorded of having
given once upon a time there were four brothers sons of a king
princes and over the years their father had told them about this kind of almost
mythical hardto find tree which the ancient language roughly
translates into something like a thingumy tree or a Whatchamacallit tree and um they grew
curious and decided to go find it for themselves but the way they their
schedules work I guess prins are busy The Chariot here could only take one at a time a few weeks apart or a few months
apart even so the first one travels off and
sees um is taken to this clearing and shown and shown this tree that looks
like a gigantic charred stump just blackened and there's little green specks little buds all over
it and then returns and then sometime later the second brother goes and sees
this what looks like a gigantic banion Tree on his journey
big leaves fresh and green huge canopy the third brother goes sometime
later and what he sees is this just flame of
color red and pink and um the fourth brother goes
still later and sees in that clearing strips of bar hanging down and
the tree kind of Limp weighted down with these huge
fruits so after he returned they had a discussion and one of them talked about the tree as being a blackened hulking
stump next one said oh it's a Banyon tree and the next one said oh it's like
Flame or a cooking piece of meat I find that an odd description of a tree and
then the fourth said oh it's an ACAA tree and they disagreed they got into you
know a mild argument over who was right so at some point they had a chance to
have dinner with her father and um explained the disagreement and said who's right what is this thing that
you've been telling us about the father smiles and gently chides them asks them
why are you all confused you didn't check with the charioteer as to what the tree is like
in other Seasons so I think that's kind of a
sweet family Story the Buddha though told this teaching story to underscore
the freeing power of different forms of meditation
different manifestations of it equally powerful
practice insightful practice useful practice can look different in different
seasons could be due to the different external
conditions just as the temperature and the amount of light and the season changed the trees cycle or it could be
more about an internal cycle without quite as
obvious external conditions our age Health the amount of
concentration or energy available biological processes
what's unfolding in emotional life practice during grief is different
than practice during the joy of a new baby these different internal
conditions can be honored expressed acknowledged
recognized so the encouragement of this story is to honor these natural seasons
Cycles rhythms regardless of season meditation
practice can be deeply helpful especially if we open to some of
the other gifts we talked about offerings we can offer our practice this week this trust whether borrowed bright
or verified wholehearted attention and respect a dedication to non-harming
this word the story and the word season are kind of Lucky fortuitous in another
way the ancient language poly has a word for meditation bavana
that translates as meditation cultivation as well though
cultivation mental cultivation internal cultivation and within each person's
process sometimes it's time to to till the soil sew the seeds develop capacity
lay the groundwork build skills of mindful awareness over and over
again other times it's definitely time to compost trust that even what stinks
could be a cause and condition for more growth later if we attend to it properly
kindly appropriately other times it's the
season of growth and this could be a slow gradual process of growth and
maturation over time or a growth SP just like that little baby is going
to have a growth spurt kindly observing with the sunlight
of awareness watering the practice watering our relationships with kind
attention that that creates the usefulness the
benefits of the practice over time and in some Seasons it's time to
harvest gather the fruits reap the benefits the
Bounty of the meditation practice whether they be benefits of insight
confidence beautiful experiences or a simple simple maturation and grounding
steiness maturity or something else in my own experience this Harvest Time often ends
up cycling right back to one of the other seasons of meditation
practice so to be gracious to recognize the moment the season the UN
folding that you're in that your practice is in in the
moment this kind of offering up of this attitude of graciousness
okayness brings much ease Joy steadiness
Simplicity all of that can come from flowing with the season of The Practice
can be a real gift season also or timeliness also
applies to ATT tuning to the amount of effort or Acuity that's possible or
helpful on a certain day during a certain retreat in a meditation
session or over longer cycles of time months or
years it also applies within a single moment
it's so helpful not to assume but rather to attune to what
is humbling forward into the future or looking back in the past comparing not
so useful and if you do it we all do it sometimes kindly recognizing it and
recognizing okay this too this is this moment that help
disengage from these potential blockages to the practice in other words attending
precisely to this experience this moment this now and letting go into
it is an art and the purpose for the purpose of
mindfulness meditation the immediate process letting go to now is helpful
because the only time we have is now it's the only present moment you
get one moment at a time the sense of timeliness and
Precision in the practice connecting sustaining honestly with the fullness of
the moment of each moment can open
into a potent kind of timelessness flow of the Dharma of
meditation and this can be a beautiful experience and very
nourishing mindfulness of this larger scale of time unfolding of seasons is
incredibly helpful when contemplating afterwards as I guide us to at the end
of each of these meditation sessions it can also be helpful beforehand in developing a broader sense
of context before entering a meditation session or a longer formal period of
practice and then I probably don't need to tell you that all of this applies to
relationships timing and relationships reconnecting with them
recognizing when it's time to reach out when it's time to support when it's time to give
space all of this applies to relating to
others every bit as much as it applies to relating to ourselves and our
practice as we've been exploring all week these relational and internal
applications kind of mirror each other and flow into each other they affect each
other timing of whener respond when to speak when to stand up or step
back all of these are dimensions of wisdom too as I was contemplating this morning
this talk I was considering how a sense of timing and wisdom are so
closely interrelated being able to settle back and choose when or graciously be with
this moment when as naruna says I'm on the side of
those who side with reality because reality always
wins and that doesn't mean we can't be involved or or or impact or influence
what's unfolding but rather is an encouragement to have a deeper
understanding of the larger flow of cause and effect as it unfolds over
time conditionality and offering with a sense
of that the seasons the larger ecology that's part of what we'll
explore tomorrow so thank you for your kind
attention and your assignment for tomorrow should you choose to accept it
is to notice how you relate to timing and the
seasons in your life the season of this Autumn if you're on this part of the planet between now and
tomorrow and you're welcome to add thoughts about that in the chat or to
reflect on them silently in this moment as
well so thank you all be well
be with you tomorrow