yes good morning everyone welcome to IMC and hearing this idea that it's
Thanksgiving week and I suppose the right theme would be Thanksgiving thanks
gratitude but that's not what I have on my mind and I
will you know somewhat you know amusingly defend myself by telling you a
little story that um Joseph Goldstein who's one of the founding teachers of this Western
Insight movement um still alive very senior teacher now and brilliant man
great practitioner uh he uh said once that the first time he was asked to officiate a
wedding um he was expected or asked to give a little Dharma talk as part of that and the D Dharma talk he gave was a
talk on death
so that gives me a little bit of license here for for what you're going to
hear so um the topic is the five
remembrances and I'll tell you what they are as we go along some of you know they're kind of a famous set of things
to reflect on and the Buddha said uh when he taught them he said this is something that uh all people whether
they're Lei or monastic should regularly reflect on these five
remembrances but I'll start with a first a little personal anecdote and lead to a
little story about the Buddha uh and this kind of points to one way in which
these five remembrances carry a certain kind of value for me or emotional
Association or meanings meaning when I was
11 uh I was with my parents visiting Nepal which back then I was visited
again 20 years later and I was uh amazed how radically it had changed I don't
think there were any asphalted roads in Katmandu and it was like a small town
almost and um but uh one day we were
walking around town and uh near a river and we saw some uh people carrying a
stretcher uh with a body wrapped in blankets and the body was small enough
that it was certainly that of a small child and they were bringing it down to the river as far as I could tell to um
to cremate the baby cremate that was a baby I think it was a small child uh to to cremate it and
um and that was my first encounter with someone who had died I couldn't
actually see the person because of the blanket and uh it did make an impression
on me uh it didn't it wasn't like an unfavorable impression or a frightening
impression but there was something um in retrospect like I think about it these
days uh I was witnessing something that had been going on in the ancient world
maybe ancient Indian subcontinent for thousands of years later 20 years later I did go to
varasi and where they do have the famous uh burning Pires where they cremate
people and was there to saw some of that and but there was something kind of almost like natural almost like part of
the natural world as an unnatural as we might say it as the death of a child
there was something uh very simple and natural about what they were doing it
just seemed like it was a Timeless kind of event so I never thought about it too much but
there was something that kind of was in the back of my mind or in my heart this event as a
child and then when I came to Buddhism uh I learned about uh the
Buddha before he was enlightened and he also had grown up as maybe this young
person had in what is now Nepal uh in the fill of the Himalayas so
it was nearby where he he grew up and uh there's a story that Buddhists tell
about his upbringing and that is that he um didn't predict had been predicted at
his birth that he would become he might become a renunciant go off and be a monk
a religious Wanderer who has no possessions and engage in spiritual
practice but this was not to the liking of his father who was the king who
needed and wanted to have his son follow in the family
business and uh so the father did what he could to prevent his son from
encountering a suffering in the world to keep him entertained or engaged with
education with entertainment with sports with probably all kinds of warrior
trainings that was important for the royalty at that time so uh the young
Buddha to be was quite engaged and so he lived inside the Royal compounds and
there were apparently three of them so between different seasons he could be moved between the different places and
kept kept distracted from fundamental human
experiences of suffering and he wasn't as 11-year-old out there in Katmandu
seeing the child being carry down to the Pyers and not until he was 27 that he
began getting restless and it was a little bit like The Truman Show those of you who know the movie so so at some point he felt
like he had to kind of go go beyond the walls and um and he did he went at night
or early in the morning and and uh with his charioteer and they went driving
through town and around and the first time they went they saw an old person
and somehow the Buddha had never seen a really old person before and um and so he asked the
Chariot here what is that and the Chariot here said something like well that's an old
person and it's the nature of all of us to become old and the story doesn't say this but I
could almost imagine the Buddhist said really and then the next day they did it
again and this time they saw a sick person quite sick and
um and the Buddha asked again what is that and the Chariot Chariot here said
well that's a sick person it's the nature of all of us to become ill
really and then the third time they went out they saw a dead person maybe the
symbol or scene that I'd seen someone with people carrying a stretcher with a body wrapped in shrouds and taking it to
the to the burning fires and uh so the fact that Buddha saw
this you know I imagine you know the scene that I had in Nepal and by the river Katmandu was it wasn't a village
but it was you know it was dirt roads and you could just get out to the river easily and it was this you know it had
clo probably closer to the ancient times than it is now and the smog is there
and um and uh so the same thing happened the Buddha said what is this and Jer here
said it it's a dead person we all have the nature to
die so then the Buddha went
out the Buddha went out uh a fourth time and this time they
saw a renunciant they saw a religious mendicant walking through the
streets calmly state state stately way just calmly
self-possessed walking the Buddha had never seen a person in this kind of way this kind of calm this kind of
peacefulness this kind of stately kind of way that being kind of mindful and present for their experience as they
walked and uh everyone else is running around doing things
and the Buddha said what is that and the charot here explained well that's a
religious mendicant that's someone who has left the home life to find out
what's true and to become free and uh so then the Buddha so the
these four uh sites the Buddha Saw made a big impression on him and perhaps
being 27 you can imagine like if you hadn't seen anything like this before I mean why wow this is part of life
too and um and then the very thing his father feared the Buddha did then he
jumped over the walls and went with his charioteer uh across to the to the river
I guess the border of the country and gave all his royal royal Garb and jewels
to the charioteer and crossed the river and into the woods to live auncient life
to to find his own Awakening which it took seven years for him to
find and when he did then he started to teach and his teachings have continued
to today and his leaving the home life to go off
and find his Awakening is one of the conditions for all of us to be here today we wouldn't be here we'd be doing
something else today um but somehow that set in motion something that brought people here to
places like IMC that people find very meaningful and very important and
supportive to for them and maybe for their own uh seeking their own discovery
of Freedom their own kind of waking up to this life and contending and dealing
with the fundamental human sufferings that we all have to approach at some
point and so uh so that's Su somehow sometimes summarized under this
expression sickness old age and death and um there's a famous story that kind
of in this in this theme that a few hundred years
after the Buddha there was a king king Asoka who's considered considered to be
the first emperor of of India the first one to kind of conquer all of India and apparently he was a cruel king and a
vast vast Army and and um you know and conquering the territory
but one day and he eventually became the what the Buddhists say the first Buddhist King dedicated to
nonviolence but uh but when he before that he he was going around having these
big battles and after one big battle that he won uh he walked apparently by
himself across the battlefield and AC uh walking through
all the carcasses of soldiers who had died apparently it was pretty awful thousands and thousands of solders had
died and I we don't know what impact it was for him to walk through all that death and Carnage that he was
responsible for and then lo and behold walking through the field was a Buddhist
monk and the Buddhist monk uh was walking calmly with certain
kind of self-possession peacefully mindfully and the contrast between the
Carnage and this peacefulness of this Monk um uh made a big impression on the
king and the King went to talk to him and monk explained he was a disciple of
the Buddha and the King said something like you know what does he
teach and uh the monk responded
hatred never ends through hatred by Love Alone does hatred end
this is the ancient truth and with that the king renounced
violence renounced war and he still stayed King and Emperor of ruled this
vast territory but supposedly that was the turning point for him to become um
dedicated to nonviolence and supporting people and apparently he
created hospitals or for for animals and just took care of things kind of made it
dramatic turn and so uh so we come to us we come to the
five remembrances and this is one of the teachings of the Buddha he said as I
said that this is something to reflect on on a regular basis so I'll read them to
you and then say a few words well actually before I read them I
wanted to introduce them another way
that creates a context maybe for hearing this so we practice mindfulness here
that's what we're known for the primary thing we do and mindfulness is
something only you can do for yourself no one can do it for
you you can't uh you know Farm it out to someone call up the local you know Uber
like mindfulness service you know and and you know hire someone who comes over and does it for
you and and spare you the effort that would be nice right you have a lot to do why why spend time doing it
when you know you can get someone to I'm sure you can get people to come to your house to meditate for you I might even
come [Laughter] if and um so um but it doesn't it's not
really going to do any good for you in a deep way mindfulness is something we have to do for ourselves and there has
to be done out of free will it has to be done with your own capacity to decide to
engage to choose this is important and it belongs to a a family of inner mental
states that uh only only work if we choose them only work if we self-manage
them monitor them uh engage in them that we engage the capacity of choice to
track what's going on inside of us choose what to participate in and what not to participate in uh the monk who
was here in September Tanis abiku uh he has this teaching that he Likens the
mind to a corporate board where uh you're at a board
meeting and uh and all the board members you know you he the the chair has no
control over what the board members say they say all kinds of crazy things however the the chair has one
thing that the others don't have the chair has the veto power over anything
and so the mind is like that you don't have control over what your mind thinks and does but you do have uh veto power
you do have the ability to choose not to participate not to continue that not to invest in it not to Grant authority to
to whatever those things are and that difference makes a huge difference difference and for that kind of
monitoring and tracking and managing your inner life uh only you can do a lot
of this stuff it's really up to you and a lot of the practice is to learn how to better self-monitor
self-regulate and find Freedom in doing so uh in the autonomy of really being
able to you know manage yourself so that
when the Mind goes in a Direction that's going to make it more difficult for you you can you can say no you can let go
you can choose to engage the mind use the mind in ways that are supportive make things better make you
better opens up to something and in using that ability to choose that comes
from this kind of careful self manage management that mindfulness provides uh we find our
freedom we find our freedom to choose the freedom to be independent from
anything in terms of not being um not not being um the the servant of our
compulsions or the victims of our feelings and ideas and thoughts rather we learn and stay close
to that place of freedom and um and that's a remarkable
thing to learn that to become free of greed hatred and
illusion because we choose to VTO power which chose not to give into it to find
a place where we're free from attachments and
clinging that we're free from um needing to have an
identity or needing not to have an identity that we're simply
free in the world of having identities and not identities free even from
thinking about it and engaging in thoughts that participate in that it's a remarkable journey and part
of this journey of mindfulness is a journey of growing autonomy just like a young child or a
baby the Journey of a baby to adulthood one way of understanding it is is steps
in increasing degrees of autonomy first they maybe learn
to eat for themselves then they learn to walk they learn to to dress themselves
they learn to take the bus to school by themselves alone they learn how to leave
home to go to college or go off to work find a home for themselves take care of their own finances and so you know
there's it's all this autonomy that that we learn growing up to become an adult I like to believe as an adult that
process of maturation continues but that sense of autonomy as an adult becomes
increasingly internal it's increasingly and that's why mindfulness so helpful increasingly
be able to track ourselves know ourselves well enough know what our impulses are our compulsions know what
our choices are know our biases and our beliefs more and more so that we're not
caught by our inner life we're not we don't caught in our
autonomy and uh and uh so that if we get angry we don't have to act
angrily so that if we are feel shy we don't have to act shy we can we have the
freedom to act in spite of it all these ways in which as we grow up we learn to
not to be caught in the things that limit us inhibit us that act for forces
us to act in ways that later we regret and so in all kinds of ways we're
learning this as we kind of until that lesson of learning that autonomy and
that freedom to track oursel and know ourselves kind of comes to a
culmination when we're going to die I think of it as the last time that
we have a chance to learn this lesson no one can die for
us you can't you know call up the you know the dying people and say can you do
it for me now I'm busy so I
can't and uh it's really a very personal thing and there's some people die people
die in so many different ways but this kind of the general kind of image I have
of dying in a gradual kind of healthy way is um is uh things start fading away
and sometimes eyesight Fades away hearing Fades away um people sometimes are closing their eyes the external
world really doesn't really pull them anymore even if the loved ones are there it becomes a very internal personal
world there's no one to help at that point and so now it becomes the last
place to learn that autonomy can we find Freedom there too is there freedom in dying or are we
going to die afraid angry worried what's what is the you know this whole process
of autonomy can come to a final conclusion here to learn it there as
well so with that as introduction I'll read you the five remembrances
so it's um stated in the first person meaning the Buddha saying this is what
you should be doing on a regular basis have these remembrances you should say to
yourself I am subject to
aging and I'm not free from aging I am subject to
illness and I'm not free from illness from getting ill I am subject to
death and I have not gone beyond death I'm not free from
dying that's three the fourth one I will become different and separate
from all that is dear and appealing to me I'll become separate from some way
from all the people that I love one way or the other that separation will
happen and the fifth one I am the owner of my actions heir to my actions
born from my actions related to my actions and have my actions as my
refuge I should be the air of whatever Deeds I do whether beautiful or bad
the word Deeds is same is karma whatever Karma I do whether beautiful or
bad so these are the fundamental kind of in a sense truths of human life maybe
they're unwelcome truths maybe we don't want to call them truths maybe some people would call them
realities that uh the Buddha was kept distracted from maybe because he was so acutely
aware of what happened to him growing up uh he as he teach gives us teachings the he
says the reason he's teaching it is because uh it's so easy to get um um uh
enamored intoxicated absorbed preoccupied with
youth to get lost lose P perspective of how this world really is uh when we're
healthy and to get also in Amed and lost and enthused by the idea of being
alive or we forget we're so enthused by our loved ones that we forget that
sooner or later we will be separated maybe that's why Joseph Goldstein talked about death that death is part of being
married one of them if you stay married chances are one of you will die before the other it's can certainly be
tragic but just say I saw that child being carried Down To The
River To Die there's something ancient that goes
back thousands of years or more that one one part of a couple dies
before the other it's part of built into this world that we live so is this does
does this evoke horror does this evoke evoke protests does this evoke running away and finding
you know seize the day and just let's go out and party or you know just ignore it
just live it up while we can the Buddha is suggesting otherwise he's suggesting
keep this in mind remember this and it does a few things one is then you're not
surprised when these things come and that that can count for a lot
you're prepared maybe for the Buddha he interpreted as a
as a as a meaning or as a indication that you should really
practice you should be prepared for this you shouldn't and you know it's very hard to practice Freedom non- clinging
compassion love for all in times of Crisis unless we've we're prepared for
it we' built up the strength of mindfulness the capacity the skills of self-
understanding and so it's better to start when you're young it's better to
build and grow with that and mindfulness will help
dramatically with this process of growing autonomy growing
freedom in relationship to our inner life which I propose is one of the
important tasks of adult life and um and so to remember I too
have the nature to get old I too have the nature natur to get sick I too have the nature to die I to have the nature
of being separated from everything that I love and and even care about one way or the other things change people change
all kinds of things so given that can we find
autonomy Freedom Choice decision making about our inner life in
relationship to health and sickness Youth and old
age being alive and dying being with what we love and being
separated from it can we turn inward so that we're not
on automatic pilot the compulsions the habits the the automatic impulses of our
beliefs our biases our expectations don't have the upper hand we have the
veto power so that we don't become a victim to these things we don't get
overwhelmed by them we don't go get agitated disturbed by them does that mean that we should just
accept them happily The veto power is has an amazing
capacity it can both say no to rejecting something
and to accepting it what's the third
option what where is that place of neither accepting nor
rejecting I suggest that's where your freedom is found if you have to accept
something you're not really really free and remember when you're neither AC
when you're accepting you're doing something when you're rejecting you're doing something is there a place in the
mind maybe a place of awareness mindfulness maybe a place of
Stillness quiet calm peace within that does not need to accept or
reject anything it can allow it to
be because that still quiet place within
is not being battered by the conditions of the world it's not being disturbed by
it it's not afraid of it it's not there's no clinging associated with it no attachments Associated we have this
place of freedom of non- clinging of
nonidentification of non um
reactivity there's a autonomy a freedom a from reactivity in this place of
freedom and what happens when we go to our
deathbed without practice what happens when we enter into a final phase of
life and we're sitting there and we watch the
Mind sitting there laying there in bed maybe watching the
mind and now we know we're familiar when certain attachments certain beliefs
come up that maybe we say no thank you don't have to do
that there was a woman here at IMC who died so maybe
12 14 years ago and uh she died uh she became
amazingly aquanus and peaceful in her last weeks of her life it was really
remarkable and maybe some of you here who knew her went with people here IMC
would go to be with her at her last weeks partly because it was like being
with a saint it was kind of like being with this beautiful radiant peaceful person it was like contagious Daran
almost with her and I was I was with her and the few hours before she
died and uh and she was agitated after these weeks of so much peace
and she said to me the practice is no longer
working there's no idea no you know we don't know that our strength of our practice and mindfulness is going to be
there even so what happens when we can't even rely on
practice is freedom still possible is autonomy still to be found with that as
well so I and she was having a little bit of hallucinations I think that was part of it and she didn't know quite to
deal with these hallucinations and strange thoughts that were coming on because I think there were you know
brain chemistry changes and and um so I told her uh all you have
to do is don't believe them you don't have I said you don't have to practice
anymore all you have to do is don't believe those delusions those images and
things like that and she calmed down immediately the agitation went and then
and I wasn't there but a couple hours later she passed away she used the veto power don't have
to believe them she found her peace and there's a remarkable peace to
be had I believe because it's possible to become so in the moment so present so
much no longer participating in the normal course of thinking and believing
and and um imagining and judging and commentary
and having ideas about the future and ideas about the past where all that
quiets down there's a place inside where it's a it's a reference point to a place that's
an alternative to that where the past in the future
disappears not from the wherever the past is not from wherever the future is
waiting for us but it disappears in our mind disappears in our active engagement
and concerns and it's possible to find this
place of Stillness quiet of awareness inside as we're
dying where there is no
dying of course you're dying but thoughts of dying dying concerns about the future in 2 minutes
are irrelevant they're not interesting I you know how much the more time do I
have you know uh oh only two minutes you know I better you know
balance my checkbook before I go or I need to call my credit card and complain
about the extra bill I got I have important things to do no
no that you you have you have a much better thing to to
do you know better things to do than checking the clock
or you have know you have better things to do than to imagine two minutes from
now there's a place where there is no death in the mind that doesn't think
about that in the mind that's aware and awake that's not operating in on these
Concepts there is a place of no aging there is is a place or a state or
a way of being that's absent of sickness even while you're
sick and to find that place to find that way of being to be able to say no thank
you to all the forces to take us away from that is part of the veto power that
we have part of the letting go that we have and to learn that autonomy to learn
that capacity for freedom and
Independence I hope that that's one of the last things you do before you
die what a wonderful way to die I hope none of us die
afraid angry confused I hope we die
peacefully and that's what the Buddha did he learned that
he taught that and then he did it and the and the
image that's the Buddhist tradition provides for this is that
um uh he was walking back to his home country because that's what you did back
there was walk across across Northern India and it's kind of touching that he was walking
back but even for the Buddha he didn't make it he had his last wish I guess to
go home but he didn't make it and he knew he was dying and he laid himself down between
two flowering Sal trees Majestic trees like the redwood trees of India I guess
and he laid himself down there and let people come visit him and have the last kind of words to the monks who were
there ask them are you sure you don't have any more questions about the teachings are you sure and they said
yeah we we have no more questions and then um he closed his eyes
and he went into a deep states of meditation deep states of peaceful meditation deep states of meditation
where past and future don't exist life and death don't exist in
terms of Concepts and orientations of things where there's freedom and peace and from there he passed
away what a great reference point for how we can live our lives to have
that as a as a model so the five remembrances and the
last one is um we are the heir to our actions and this this represents the uh
what we do makes a difference and what we do creates habits
what we do follows us what it do what we do shapes us who we are be care careful
with what you do what you say your actions how you live and um and that
care is exercising your capacity for autonomy
your capacity for decision making for yourself to make a decision to live a life a better life a good life
that brings you all the benefits of a life free of clinging to craving and
selfishness conceit so the five
remembrances you might remember them if they ever become
relevant so uh we have a few minutes before the polu and given that it's a polu it's it's nice if uh you set hello
to each other especially for those of you who might be new it's nice if someone says hello to you but everyone
including those you knew then can welcome the person you say hello to and you can talk a little bit about this
ideas of the talk how it's How it landed for you and what it evoked for you if you want there anything you want but
what I'd like to ask so say hello to maybe you know maybe one or two people next to you but uh but once you're with
someone look around make sure no one is sitting there alone because sometimes accidentally some people just turn the
opposite directions from you and you're like what do I do now and it's awkward right so just
everyone keep an eye out and include everyone say hello and and then when you're ready you can leave and and uh or
stay for the potluck and they'll take a few minutes for them to get everything set up so it's a nice thing to do here
so thank you for being here