welcome everyone welcome nice to see you all and to
practice
together so tonight I wanted to talk a little bit about some attitudes that we might bring
to practice that might uh unknowingly have a big impact like some of these attitudes we
might we might not even know that we have them and yet their influence is really
great not only in our practice but in our life but we can see them and maybe
work with them in a particular way with our meditation
practice and one attitude in particular is one that would like I want to say of
course we have it kind like living in these uh Modern Times And that is we might have this
mindset or this idea that it's so important that we're always making
progress we have to be like moving forward we have this idea that uh we
have to always always be improving or moving closer and closer to achieving
something or have to be advancing or developing or getting better and you
know all this things you kind of get this idea right the sense of like okay we have to be going forward of course we have this
idea of course we do I mean our kind of like there's a
developmental model right just like human development is that as we age in theory we're maturing and
getting wiser and wiser and learning things but not only that that we have
kind of a um society that kind of promotes that and how many podcasts and
YouTube videos are about how to fix yourself or be more productive or how
many apps are all about uh this kind of thing right it's such a and then
certainly that um when I was working in Corporate America you know there was a
with the people that reported to me we have a little developmental plan for them here's are the some of the things
to work on if you wanted to get a promotion here's what to do you know this type of stuff
right of course we bring that to our meditation practice
too but that only works until it
doesn't and it actually doesn't work nearly as well as we think it should or
ought to or we often like are bringing this idea so we may think that somehow like
when we're meditating somehow we should be like making things
happen this sense of you know movement or progress or like you know it's
certainly I'm getting better or learning something or something's going to be different now
or this sense of well even if I'm not like making things happen then I should
have some kind of special experience because I'm sitting down to
meditate and whatever medit type of meditation practice you do here primarily we do or teach about uh
mindfulness we might have this feeling well because I'm doing this mindfulness practice something special should happen
even if we're not even clear what this special thing should be it should be
special or maybe we have the idea maybe it's not even clear clearly articulated
in our minds but we have this idea whatever it is it shouldn't always be how it was before like it should be
different or you know somehow the sense of easier or something not not like the
last time not having anything difficult or
uncomfortable but here's what's happening here's what happens and this is really subtle this is partly why I
mentioned that we can see in our meditation practi is often we can't see it in our daily
life but if if we have this expectation this attitude of we should
always be making progress then that introduces this subtle little bit of
agitation whatever is happening right now it's not quite good
enough we have to be better there has to be this way and
somehow it has to be uh different than how it it was was before and there's can be this sense of yeah well this isn't
good enough I should be progressing whatever it is we're
experiencing so often we there's this subtle little sense of yeah okay whatever but what's
next or are we there yet am I there
yet this little subtle agitation that is kind of like uh even
the we're always like looking to what's next and like okay there's to be something better or something or I
should be whatever is going to happen next and this subtle little agitation
just really shows up in so many different ways that we don't even notice it in fact it might even be so prevalent
in our experience we don't even notice it or we think that's of course it's
there I can't be with this present moment don't be ridiculous Diana
there's this way which we always need to be thinking about the next thing or somehow have this expectation that it
should be better or we should be moving forward or we should be making progress or something like this and we might say
this agitation is a subtle form of
disappointment oh this again even if it's a little bit better than
before I still don't feel like I'm completely awakened I'm not a Buddha
yet so there's this little you know subtle form of
disappointment and what is disappointment disappointment arises when our expectations aren't met but
what are expectations one way we might consider
expectations is that we come up with a scenario in our mind
100% in our minds it only exists in our minds the
same way that we have that fleeting thought like oh those are nice shoes or
oh yeah maybe I'll have a sandwich for breakfast or lunch or you know these are just thoughts right that just arise and
pass away and how many thoughts do we have throughout the day countless but some of those thoughts are
about what should happen What should happen we've painted
a scenario 100% in the mind it's based on you know experience
so we're not crazy having this but still it is 100% in our minds it has the same
substance the same durability the same
um fleetingness or lack of substantiality
has the same thoughts of oh you have to remember to pick up milk when I get
home why is that person driving so slowly what's I wonder if my favorite
podcast has a new episode right these are just all these thoughts that we have expectations are our having a
thought and then transposing it onto the
experience there's What's happen happening with the body
experiences feelings in the body like Sensations in the body
emotions there's that what's happening and then on top of it is something
that's just got cooked up in our minds and there's a
gap of course there's a gap like how could there not be a gap we never like
100% you know know exactly how everything's going to be everything's always a little bit different and this
Gap is this where this sense of agitation or the sense of disappointment comes from because not only do we have
this thought that uh how the present moment should
be accompanying that thought is the idea and there should be no gap between
what's actually happening and the thoughts we have about
it then this in some ways there's this uh sense that well
somehow our experience should change to match what's in our
minds and there's this agitation when it doesn't
happen this is one way in which we my think about this
is that the truth is is what's happening is what's happening
the the experience that we have in the body right now the pressure of the chair or the cushion against the body the
sounds of my voice or whatever sounds the visual things that we're saying
that's what's happening also there's this thoughts in the mind but there's a way in which
without our really being aware of it we have this expectation
that things should match what's in our minds and when they're not there's a
sense of agitation so our experiences they won't
change at that moment is that moment it's the experience as it is of course
it's going to change the next moment but it's not going to change to precisely
much our expectation it's not going to change to
make that subtle sense of agitation go away it's not going to change to protect
us from the feeling of disappointment or maybe it's not disappointment maybe it's
frustration maybe it's impatience maybe it's anger that arises when what's in
our mind doesn't match our present moment
experience for example not too long ago I was uh driving in the East Bay and I
had this expectation for how long it should take me to get to where I was
going and as it happened that the whole entire freeway um Highway 680 was closed
uh was a couple of weeks ago I guess they were doing some I don't actually know what they were doing my assumption
is there were some planned construction so it was closed for the entire weekend well we the traffic was very
different than I expected and so just because I had this sense of
like okay it should take this long but in fact it's really taking much longer
it's not going to change right it's not going to take me any faster to get there just because I had the
idea and my saying this seems silly but it's funny how sometimes we
have this idea if I get angry enough maybe it'll change if I get emotional enough maybe it'll change if I'm
disappointed enough if I complain enough we have this idea that somehow like
strong emotions or any emotion is somehow required or appropriate or
necessary when we feel this gap between what's actually happening in our idea
about what's happening doesn't matter what emotions
we have it's still going to be exactly how it is maybe now there will be emotions with
what's happening happening but it doesn't make it move to meet our
expectations this is such an interesting thing to think about like how we somehow
want things to be different and meditation is a place
where we can look at this and explore it and play with it and like and work with
it because not only these things like about you know how long it takes to get
somewhere but we also might have expectations really giant expectations that show up in our lives and that bring
some agitation to the quality of Our Lives for example we might have an
expectation that somebody else is going to make us happy or it's going
to heal us or is going to make us feel
whole whether that's somebody else is a intimate relationship a psychotherapist
a spiritual teacher a good friend whatever it is we might have this
idea that somebody else is going to solve some of the whatever we feel like
needs to be solved or heal whatever we feel like needs to be healed and this
expectation is not often explicit like most often it's hidden
underneath a a number of layers like so many of the expectations that we
have and maybe we might say of course we have this expectation too how
many what is it romantic comedy movies or romance novels or how many uh just
you know fairy tales or something kind of like support this
idea and I think all of us have had relationships that don't meet our
expectations and sometimes that's you know okay and
we work with it and we mature and we grow and sometimes it's not sometimes it
turns into be something that's uh really stressful in our lives stressful for us
and maybe stressful for the other person or maybe stressful if we have to rearrange our life in some kind of
way so this idea of the expectations we have the kind of like the attitudes that
we have to so many things in life just leads to this agitation that can be
really obvious or really subtle about this kind of disappointment that this
present moment isn't precisely how I thought it should
be so this practice this practice of mindfulness is teaching us like how can
we cultivate the conditions so there can be the arising
of an unagitated heart create the conditions in which there can be some
ease and no longer this expectation or if there are expectations
no longer any agitation about noticing when the Gap is
there and it turns out that this is so much what practice is about we don't talk about this explicitly a
lot we just emphasize you know come back to the present moment come back to the present moment but one of the reasons
some of the power of mindfulness practice is that this repeatedly
returning again and again to whatever is the present moment
independent of uh whether it uh is what we want that's what we expected but just
to come back to the truth of the experience then somehow the thoughts we
had about it stop being as important they stop being as
authoritative it's like okay yeah that's just the mind doing what the Mind
does but this moment is like this so there's this way that just returning
again and again and again to the present moment experience is this way that the the
agitation of the present moment not meeting our experience just kind of like
softens and goes away and this is so much what about
mindfulness practice is about is being able to bring all of
ourselves to whatever is happening maybe we could even say
especially if it doesn't meet our expectations because in this gap between
what's actually happening in our expectations this room is where there's a lot of strong emotions and we can slip
into losing Touch of our wisest versions of ourselves
or with anger or frustration or sadness or disappointment or whatever it might
be so there's this way that mindfulness
practice is about seeing things as they really
are not about getting anywhere and so often we might use it
that we have this sense that uh you know we want to use it to support us and make
our lives better and it can and it will
and part of the way it makes our lives better is to help us more and more to be
with what's actually happening what's actually here what's
the experience even if it's
uncomfortable even if it's exactly what we didn't
want the truth is it's there and there's there's a way in which our trying to wish it otherwise just leads to a life
of agitation a lot of agitation because mindfulness practice
is about seeing things as they seeing things as they really are not so much
about getting somewhere but instead to recognize and
allow whatever is
arising if you have moments of great
irritation maybe because your expectations weren't being met but with
mindfulness practice you're learning how to be present with that
irritation oh irritation feels like this restlessness in the legs perhaps or
for me sometimes I get restlessness in my arms I'll be sitting here quietly but there's like this energy in the arm
or maybe there's this way of uh this sense of irritation is feels like um
some tightening in the throat sometimes there can be or clenching of the jaw
these are subtle bodily experiences this irritation but while we're in meditation
we can just notice oh yeah medit irritation is like
this and we take the next breath as best we can we come back to
the sensations of breathing and we have this sense like okay I have this container until the
timer goes off until the bell rings I guess I'm just going to be with
irritation and then as we get practice with being with these uncomfortable
Sensations the problem drains out of those situations yes
irritation feels like this it's uncomfortable and it's not a
problem just imagine what your life would be like with all the uncomfortableness is that we encounter
in just having a human body and just being in this Society what if the
uncomfortableness wasn't a problem
it's just
uncomfortable it's quite something to think about that like we can with this Pro with this
practice we are increasing our capacity to be with uncomfortableness but how
many times are we agitated or doing things thoughtlessly or with a whole
bunch of emotion behind it simply because we're uncomfortable
able so meditation is not about trying to get
anywhere else it's about allowing yourself to be
exactly where you are as you are and as we do that the expectations
just kind of melt away as that Gap goes away the expectations go away
and there's this way that I mean I um allowing ourselves to be just as we are
allows us to be more open to others as well allowing others to be the way that
they are and I'm not saying that uh we have
to accept absolutely everything and there aren't injustices in the world I am not saying that
I am saying that we can bring our wisest versions of ourselves if we can stay in
the uncomfortableness because we have
aspirations of course we do we want to make positive change we want to make positive change in ourselves and in the
world we want to make things different we want to improve our lives improve other people's lives improve the world
of course we want to do that so I'm not saying that we have to give up all of our aspirations of or goals
about uh what's possible and directions we want to go
I'm not saying that because to improve the lot of the
world is appropriate it's part of what to practice enables us to do and it's a
very real possibility but it turns out that just
by sitting and being with
ourselves whether it's comfortable or uncomfortable in this small but not
insignificant way you already have made a
difference you've decreased the amount of agitation in yourself and in the
world you've decreased the amount of discomfort
or maybe I'm using this word agitation just this you know the frustration or anger or
impatience just by being with your experience
wholeheartedly recognizing and allowing it to be there
and the Paradox
is that by being with things how they
are is how we change the world is how we change
ourselves this is a paradox because of course we have this idea that no no no I the things I have
to like do things but there's this way that if we
get out of our own way and we give ourselves over to the present moment and
Trust in this recognizing and allowing without pursuing anything at
all the sense that nothing needs to happen it's very
counterintuitive but when we start up when we give up this sense that we're
trying to make something special that is something
special trying stopping putting down this idea that things have to be different letting go of wanting
something better instead to just be
here then we can maybe realize that something special is already
occurring it's our life that's
occurring it's the present moment that's occurring it's our capacity to meet
what's arising with some openness and clear-headedness
open-heartedness be able to meet with what's just arising and that turns out
to be quite special and people respond to this we
respond to it ourselves but people around us respond they notice oh this
person's like actually here and present and not busy with themselves but can
meet with what's arising don't underestimate how this how powerful and
transformative this can be partly it's powerful because it's not easy because
most people are so used to being distracted and busy with themselves that they aren't meeting others but when
somebody is actually pray present with what's actually happening and meeting
others with what's actually happening there it has an
impact in our hearts and in the hearts of others so there's a one way to describe
this which I first heard on a retreat uh years and years ago and it had a such a
big impact on me back then so maybe like this talk so far we
could summarize it like this we have this idea that we want to get to point
B maybe we're not even clear what point B is it's just something there better
whatever's going to happen next and how to get to point
B I'll tell you exactly how to get to point B to what's
better be completely at Point a
that's how you get to point B and this is like a paradox or
counterintuitive or something that maybe you just need to practice with or
explore rather than just listen to somebody like me say
this but can we put aside or can we let go or soften
this attitude of oh there's got to be something better and maybe it begins by
just recognizing by how often this shows up in our lives I mean we can see it in
a more subtle way in our meditation practice but probably it shows up in you know not subtle ways in our
life so the attitude that we're bringing are we bringing this attitude of well
there's got to be something better or it should be progressing or developing or I
need to be somewhere else or just this natural sense that we bring to so much of our
life can we notice that attitude and gently investigate
it and maybe it shows up in a really obvious way in your meditation practice like being really ambitious and striving
and and pushing really hard and so to instead to recognize is
this balance or Paradox or counterintuitive about to have the goal
being to not have that goal or something like this
right this way and just to maybe to recognize can we have this
sense of having an aspiration having a sense of what's
possible for us and for the world and at the same time just to be simply with
what is not abandoning our
aspirations but noticing how that creates some agitation I I'm always
doing this with my hands I'm touching my fingers because it kind of feels like that this like this rubbing or something
like this so showing up and being present for
what's really here is a way that can help us get there
wherever there is thank
you in order to get to point B just be completely at Point
a so now I'd like to open it up to see if there are some questions or comments
anybody would like to
make it's sort of an observation but one of the things I kept word that kept coming to my mind that you you didn't
use is control uh because I find in my
practice in my life that if I have the illusion of control everything's okay
but it's the loss of control that uh is really hard for us to deal
with I would agree 100% the loss of control and I would say
even well maybe I like I think I might do a whole talk on this but maybe I'll just kind of say a few things
here is there much is there much worse than the feeling of complete
helplessness complete helplessness so we like to perpetuate
this idea of being in control but we're not in control as much
as we think we are and that's very uncomfortable when we realize that but I
think you're pointing to something that's really powerful and important yeah thank
you over there and then we'll go to here first we'll have you here first and then
yes do go there and then we'll come to you okay yeah um I was just wondering so
I think you had just said to get to point B just be completely present in point
a but what do you trust in to get to point B and I know this is probably the
Paradox uh but it's maybe also kind of in line with your question about control
um it's like what do you put your faith in
yeah yeah cuz right if we could control things we wouldn't have ever have this gap between
our expectations and our experien we have this we envisioned it we have this
idea exactly how it should be and it's usually not that so if we really could
control things there would not be this Gap so what is I think this is an
excellent question so what do we put our trust in if we're not if we can't control and make things
happen then what what do we have confidence in how do things happen what
do we have faith in this is a great question and it would be great if I had a really simple answer for
you that would make you feel better and that we could all go home and like oh okay well at least I have that but uh I
think part of uh this practice not I think I know part of this practice is
really deeply experiencing that we don't control as much as we do and that being
okay and in fact it being a little bit of a relief cuz that's another source of
agitation trying to control everything it's
exhausting thank
you thanks for the Liston um and when you were talking about the
Gap is that all the emotions that we are dealing with I mean the metaphor for traffic we
can apply it to everything that we deal with in life
and then the emotions that is not aligned with the expectation
and or um doesn't meet the expectation then
we have to deal with all these kind of frustration and all of it
so can we can we put it in this category in this box that it's the emotion
dealing with our thought thinking and then observe it and let it
go some it's um out of my
practice I feel like when I'm
um I I catch myself with all these emotions that I don't like to have and
my only solution is to be silence
and maybe breathing and then um feel the
looking I mean thinking of my blessings in life and but the emotion is still
there it's less so can that Gap
is emotions we deal in the we have in
life I'm not sure that I understand your question so you're asking is are are are
the emotions we experience due to this Gap between what our thinking is and what we're actually experiencing yeah
what experiencing is through our emotion right frustration and
um angry or and would that
be I I feel like I like to look at it as dealing with all sorts of emotions that
come up for me and I have to I and I'm conscious of it and I'm
aware of it and deal with
it so there's I I so the of course
emotions arise when there's this when we have this experience and then you were saying like sometimes the experience is
the emotions and then how do we be with that how do we be with just like emotions is that part of what you're
saying yeah yeah that's this is a great uh question and so uh there's a few
things and um I've given some talks on this but uh I can say just really
briefly recognize oh there's a an
emotion that's happening and as best you can allow it oh I feel
angry and then instead of piling on I shouldn't feel angry and I shouldn't not
feel that I should not feel angry but said like okay here's angry feel it in the body instead of the
thoughts feel it in the body anger often has heat kind of like a flushing like this and this energy coming up and maybe
like you know wanting to move or something like this and
then we then I'll say te's apart so r a f t recognize allow feel in the body and
tease apart what's actually happening from your reaction to what's
happening and then if that feels like way too complicated like all these steps to be with
emotions uh some things is very simple feel your feet on the
ground and bring your attention to the breath in a relaxed easy way as best you
can as best you can that's the key instead of beating ourselves up that we
should be able to handle or be with whatever emotion So yeah thank you you're welcome you're
welcome you want to send it over to um I think like what comes up for me
with being in point a and being fully in point a um is kind of like how we
practice or how we hope to practice empathy with other people like whenever um you know a friend or your partner or
your um family memb has come to you and like confide it you about like their problems um typically we want to have
like control right we want to like oh you should do this you should like uh um do that or like stop thinking about it
or whatever but being fully in the moment with that loved one or the person
that we care about um is so powerful to your point like they feel it right like
that you're just there with them not trying to like fix them but just like being there and I think like that by
being there fully with them not trying like solve everything or like control everything um might be like what they
would need to like get to point B and if I'm just kind of like thinking about how if we can extend that level of empathy
to ourselves which sometimes actually might be harder than extending that empathy to other people that we love
it's like maybe that's a way that I'm kind of like interpreting what what this talk today is do that resonate yeah yeah
that's very nice and that's a very uh wise way to do that sometimes we have this sense of like um well how
do I help take care of myself and we're like well you know how to take care of others do the same thing for yourself
yeah thank you thank
you oh I had four or five things just want to burst out of me this was
um um I think it's a really important point you just subtle
corrosive chronic sort of dissatisfaction or that difference between our expectation and
reality and that's a really good concept to have I hope I can remember remember
it and um I came to mind was I think it was a punk song during the 80s or
something somebody kept saying is that all there is and it's kind of the refrain of the song
and I think that sort of you seem to be pointing at that as kind of a mental
condition um and then I I guess I wanted to know it well first of all when you were
saying tease like what is h you sort of you're discriminating between like what's happening and what you our
reaction reaction maybe we're mad that we're mad yes it's sort of a second order frustration or something um that's
a really I never really understood the teas part before so that was it helped
anyway Illuminating and then finally uh when you're aware that you have like an
experience or emotion coming up in your meditation or actually even just think about like the the perceptions of our
body the weight on the floor things like that how verbal are you in that
awareness like are you sort of narrating your experience that seems kind of um
tiresome I don't know but or do you is there a a best practice in that like you
sort of do some of it and let it go or does that a useful question yeah this
is a good question so often it depends on how agitated one is so if there's
just a subtle sense of agitation then there's just a mind there's a way in which the mind can just feel without Nar
without putting a label or a concept or a note on it just feeling the pressure without saying pressure just noticing
the sensations or what whatever it might be but if the mind is like really edgy I
can't believe they did that I'm going to say they don't want BL you know like then it might be really helpful to say
in the mind pressure and then just because that's a way to bring the Mind back and then zo the mind will go again
and like this and then like okay inhale like and to say these words in the mind
as a little way as a support to help bring the Mind back and then the mind will eventually kind of calm down like
this reping the agitation with yes yeah giving the Mind something to do yeah and
I want to say I love this word corrosive that you use I think that's such a great word kind of I was using the word
agitation but corrosive is a good word thank you I love this how we kind of crowd Source some of the information
here these talks that seem like that just so powerfully undermines like our
well-being yes and our sense of well-being yeah
yeah okay so I think we're uh at the end of
our time together so thank you very much um I'll stay up here if you um somebody would like to come up and have some
questions otherwise I wish you a lovely rest of the evening thank
you