okay so hello again hello welcome to happy hour
so so for today's practice I want to invite us to
um yeah to pause to pause so maybe the title of this this uh
of today's practice is in Praise of pause in Praise of pause so
so uh maybe I won't say too much about our practice before we get into it I'll
say more later um maybe that's that's enough right now so so let's begin let's
begin Landing in your body arriving arriving
together arriving with wholehearted intention
with kind intention should for ourselves for
others taking a pause from the
busyness from the distractedness from switching
channels this Channel and that channel and this other channel taking a pause from all
that taking a whole whome
pause and resting arriving in this
body arriving in this moment in
time
and inviting inviting the body to relax and
soften fighting the heart the body and the mind to take a
pause
a kind pause a pause of
kindness
e
if thoughts are arising and passing it's
okay let them come and go let your body and heart rest with the
pause we don't have to follow after everything thought that comes up every
memory perhaps imagine that you're
sitting in the comfortable chair very comfortable chair
in the middle of say a cabin the middle of
Nature and all around this cabin and there are doors and [Music]
windows and little animals Birds show up say
Hi and then leave we don't have to get up and follow
every little creature that shows up the doors and
windows but we can have kindness for ourselves and for everything that's
arising in this simile the doors and windows
are sense doors the five sense
doors or Sensations sounds
smells Etc arise and the sixth one the Mind
door in Buddhism is where thoughts arise
with the replaying of all the other senses sounds music we can replay it in
our minds so all these doors these sense
doors these creatures come they greet they want to take our attention
away and we can rest with kindness rest with
kindness there can be many distractions in the
world many distractions we don't have to follow
every every thread every little animal that shows up every
chipmunk it's just a [Music] chipmunk it's just a
chipmunk no need to pay attention
Let It Come Let It Go not important not worth your
energy not worth your
attention making a pause making a kind [Music]
pause one breath at a
time
e
and taking a pause taking this pause one breath at a time out of
kindness for [Music] ourselves out of
kindness for the world
e
see how this taking a
pause can be an expression of kindness for yourself and also for others and the
world so that you can become more available to
respond to respond wisely compassionately to the needs of the world needs of others and
yourself through taking a pause from it
all
e
see what happens in your mind in your heart if
you just pause if you just stop can pick it all
up in a few minutes and pick it all up what what if
you just pause press the pause
button the Whirlwind of activity the mind and the body in the
heart and just say to yourself dear one dear
heart we will hit play in just a few minutes right now I'm going to hit
pause friendly pause loving pause a loving pause and Praise of a
loving
pause the nourishing pause just a key presence with the
breath as the conductor of the pause as the conductor conducts an
orchestra and hear the breath
in breath out breath it's holding a baton conducting
the paths for the orchestra
Within
e
and if you find that mind is still busy in thoughts and
emotions it's okay no reason to to judge yourself it's okay thinking
is what Minds do be kind be
gentle and see if it's possible to put it down
gently promising you'll pick it all up in just a few
minutes and ask the thoughts the memories the emotions if it's okay to
just take a pause for five minutes you'll be back befriend them befriend them all
don't have to make enemies out of thoughts or emotions
they probably say yes it's okay you can take five minutes off to take a
pause and then take a pause and loving pause in breath out
breath
e
you can tell your thoughts let's take a pause let's take a
pause
e
and as we come to the end of this meditation session
together however this pause
was appreciate that you took a pause as much as
possible a loving pause a wholesome pause to be more connected available for
wisdom compassion for yourself others and that you have planted seeds
not judging how this period was but trusting your planted
seeds and together let's share the goodness of all
these seeds we've planted together with all beings everywhere may all beings
everywhere be happy may all beings be free including
ourselves thanks everyone thanks for your
practice I enjoy taking a loving pause I hope you did
too a so I'll share a practice there was a
there was a time when there was this this planning mind coming up planning for something I need to do planning
planning and I realize wait I'm taking a loving pause and and I shared i i as
actually said said in my inner voice to the thought oh let's take a pause and
the planning mind agreed okay we're going to take a pause we're going to plan about that thing later so so I hope
uh this was supportive for you as well and we have a few minutes now for or for
engaging together in small groups um to to share with one another
what works to for you what works what doesn't work to take a loving pause
taking a loving pause through the day do you do that what would support you to do that um maybe during this meditation
what was it like to take a loving pause uh was it challenging what worked what did you discover what can
you take forward so we'll be in small groups of size three and thank you Neil
for posting information about the HH etiquette and um how to support
ourselves and each other in the small groups and um yeah groups small groups
of size three which is just such a privilege to be engaging with fellow practitioners speaking for your own
benefit not educating not impressing but really speaking for your own um
exploration as if you were making a journal entry out loud and the other two people are just holding witness they're
not asking questions they're not giving you advice it's it's we're just supporting each other to to explore um
what is what is a mindful loving pause what's can we do that throughout our day how um how can I bring more of this in
how can it be supportive to to to myself I know that anyway I can say more about it later H everybody is back welcome
back everyone and would love to hear from you what uh what did you discover
what was it like to discuss taking a uh loving pause and um yeah would love to
hear from you so you can uh if you want to raise your Zoom hand or also I will
change the chat settings here so you can chat um in Zoom your discoveries
Claudia I see our Zoom hand hi um so for me I I love the lab of
loving pause because one of the things that I've been working on as I shared
with my group is this um you know the gap between stimulus and response and I
have called it taking a pause but now I'm going to call it taking a loving
pause because it's not only just for me but it's also for the other person
because if I take a loving pause it's like the third or fourth solution that pops in my head is probably the best
instead of the first one that seems to be like the one that I really want to do and I want really want to say but you
know what if I take a loving pause it's both loving for them and for myself so I
love that thank you NY oh beautiful thank you Claudia thank you so much for
for um enriching the the the and and enriching
with heartfulness the meaning of this for you and how you're going to be practicing it I love it it you're your
um your deepening deepens my appreciation of it thank you thank
you Sandy please yeah so three things one I teach
preschool and I was talking to them and I was like oh my gosh I'm channeling Nikki right now with my smooth voice and
it was like really they love it so thank you and number
two that's sweet I'm happy to be channeled any time dear Sandy that's so
fun it was great too they were all like so calm D number two when I do this I'm I
feel like I'm like Terri I'm not like really good my Minds writing or reading and I'm wondering if this is normal I
still get a benefit out of it's bad as I think I am at this yes I still feel better afterwards is that normal yes AB
oh my God I am so glad you named it Sandy because it's it's you know we
judge what it we we judge our results in in short term like oh my mind is
cluttered or busy or is is not working or a bad meditator and and and yet this
this practice as you you just reported it has a different way of working
through our bodies brains Hearts this this shift I don't want to just say
brains even though you know in our zit guys there is so much of a focus on our brains but but that's limiting the impct
of this practice there's something that it just shifts in the way that we are we are taking a pause and that shifts so
absolutely this works in ways we cannot imagine we don't quite understand so
don't cut yourself short by saying oh you know you're not saying that but like oh um I'm distracted like yeah I I sat
that's why at the end of every meditation I try to say don't judge it don't don't judge that it was this or
that planting seeds they're going to to flower they're going to germinate in
their own time in the ways in and according to a natural law a lawfulness
that we don't quite get we we appreciate like yeah this thing is working and yet I feel like I'm just thinking I'm doing
thinking meditation and yet it's working somehow so that's exactly it Sandy yeah
more power to you like that's exactly how I feel I don't get it and it's I definitely benefit from it I don't
understand you don't we don't have to get understand it for it to work this is just great just just accept be kind be
non-judgmental and keep beginning again keep beginning again keep beginning again lovingly with your monkey mind
which we all have you're yeah thank you thanks thank you Sandy so
much get I see your hand
please to to both your points I had a very um to me strange experience um I
was yesterday I was unexpectedly verbally hurt like in front of others so
very uncomfortable situation and uh my normal response would be to um make sure
like the typical loving kindness oh let's understand everybody else and I really feel comfortable and also
professionally it's something that I do and I had this I don't know where it came from Sandy to you at a point the
sudden awareness of no no no no this is not kind to myself here so I um found
ways to set boundaries and um showed up for myself and was very
aware that that's what I was doing which is the weirdest thing um it wasn't planned obviously couldn't have been
because was also unexpected and um while there was discomfort in this situation
um you know all those considerations what do others think what do I do the right thing because I did something sort
of character for myself in the in this particular situation no issues standing
up for others and professionally setting my boundaries but this was very personal so it was very very interesting how also
it helped me process um it felt like the space we're always talking about giving
things the space and it was almost the opposite of what I had interpreted to be
a loving pause it was a loving pause not with gentleness but a bit of force and
um it had a positive effect so when you asked for this uh today um it it allowed
me to reframe it in in in this loving kindness context which I thought was fascinating so so thank you for that
yeah thank you so much for sharing it and you know compassion can be gentle
compassion may show up as tender and gentle compassion can show up as fears
fears compassion and we've talked about it here uh and happy hour many times compassion can be fierce can be very
loving and and fierce so what I'm hearing you had to do was to to um have
that loving pause and realize ouch this hurts and sometimes actually um when I'm
so befuddled when something like that happens to me and I'm just befuddled like wow this just happened somebody
just hurt me or publicly I just say ouch it's it's like wow this this is painful
ouch as a way to to express so I'm I'm uh appreciating that yes loving paw can
can be uh Fierce love can be gentle tender there are many different ways it
can show up as long as there is wisdom yeah and one would hope a net a net
kindness effect not adding more hurt to the situation exactly exactly and and
and the reason why I I brought this word in ouch is ouch isn't you know it doesn't hurt others it's not a dagger
that you're weaponizing it's like ouch this hurt me and maybe the other person didn't quite realize so again this quote
unquote boundary setting so much more to say about boundaries but um this quote unquote it's really out of love like oh
I've been hurt and and you know I care enough for you that I want you to know
that this is not appropriate for you either for your karma and and for what you're producing in the world
so yeah thank you K and let's see I I see two more hands I
see Vicky
please hi Nikki thank you mine is is much more superficial but it it was
really right on the money for me that uh you said it was a chipmunk we don't have
to get distracted by every chipmunk and right before meditation I was quickly
writing this long email that in in the process of meditating I thought it could
be about one line and make a phone call so it was very much the wise mind too
nice stop yeah thanks nice thanks Vicki thanks for that love that the Chipmunk
isn't that a great metaphor when we it really is like it's it's just a chipmunk just like little running hero get
going yeah that is great yeah thanks Vicki and Elsa I see your
hand i'm in Balden by a person in our small group who when she first spoke
said that what she was about to say was somewhat different than what others had
said and so I'm emboldened by her courage to say that and um for me um the
pleasure of the pause is a kindness to
onself is the beginning of being in the actual world world of
meditation outside of the personality issues outside of the body feelings
outside of anything but the breath I was just
um wow and then the next thought that I thought was and how to
have balance and Poise and not get knocked around by whatever you want to
call it stuff baggage monkey whatever you know distractions noise in the room
the birds tweeting right yeah yeah great I appreciate it Elsa yeah this this
sense of thank you for sharing um this you know the the Paw being able to step
out of the narrative sometimes this personality and this and that yeah that's that's a beautiful way also to
think of this loving Pa thanks a couple more uh uh Reflections before we close
rain I see your
hand um yeah thank you um and I I want to say thank you for this weekend's
Saturday's Retreat I was there and um at that Retreat used the word
embodiment a lot and I found the irony tonight was we
were saying you know to take a pause but I have a problems with PTSD
and I space out a lot I think I'm pausing all the time I'm not being present and I what was really helpful
for me was to take this as a moment to being in the moment but more from an
embodiment of I always just checked my breath or touch myself just oh yeah I have you know get back in here so it was
we talked a little bit in my group about like the r word like relax doesn't work for people but it was kind of iron
ironically for me to stop pausing and spacing out but actually be in my body be present
that's so interesting yeah thanks rain I appreciate you sharing this the different connotation that the word has
for you and and yes on Saturday we talked so much about embodiment and about mindfulness and and body fullness
actually we talked about body fullness and and actually it's interesting um and
of course I appreciate that this word pause has um for you has the connotation of spacing out and and for me has a way
of has a connotation of embodiment and and let me share how I was trying to bring it into the guided meditation and
um when I was saying oh imagine you are resting in a comfortable chair like an
easy chair I think I almost said easy chair but like in a comfortable chair in the middle of this cabin where all these
doors right so there's a sense of embodiment you're not getting up to go and greed every chipmunk and every an
like oh yeah you're staying in your body you're staying in your body you're
staying in your body you're staying this com comfort of this home this chair this
this um uh comfortable um abiding where you are and not leaving so that's the
the image the metaphor I would like to share with you as a way of oh taking a pause from all the things that are
coming and going if that might help reframe it and if it doesn't help reframe it then don't use the word pause
it's fine yeah thank you thank you thanks Ray
wonderful great so um yeah let's see before we
close uh question how do I join the Forum when I click on it I don't see way
to join it says I don't have access I'm not sure it's it's the small groups uh
we'll we uh stay for a moment at the end Jessica uh uh and and also I wanted to
just remind everyone that when we do go into small groups I do try to set it up
with a lot of care and there is that um document that thank you again Neil for
sharing the document about happy hour etiquette and again it is so important
that we stay and we talk about the practice um so important to uh uh talk
about the practice here and now and um and not so much Here There and
Everywhere just and and if we are talking about something that happened again relating it to the practice that
we're doing tonight it's it really helps and supports everyone uh share and feel
supported um this is um yeah thank you again Neil for posting information about
happy hour etiquette please please if you haven't looked at it please click on
it now as we're coming to a close refresh your memory as the the ways to
hold ourselves to hold each other uh in the small groups we really want to support everyone in the small group um
and um and in the large group I'm here to support and and and yet in this small
group it's really up to us to to to be a good Community member um so so with that
um yes I think Sandy and and Jessica Anil is going to help you join the uh
yeah I think joining the Google Groups anyway so so thank you all for taking a
loving pause together oh yeah and I also wanted to say um
um tomorrow um tomorrow is the Persian New Year around 800 p.m is is um is the
first it's the beginning of Spring it's yes yes so so happy Persian New Year
happy first day of Spring tomorrow 8:00 p.m. or so I'll be celebrating yes norus
exactly getus says happy norus thank you nor mobarak to those of you who celebrate I know who you are and those
of you all of you celebrate why not the more the marrier so happy norus
happy um first day of spring to everyone and and may we um yeah let's share the
Merit of our practice together may all things everywhere um in ways we cannot
understand or fathom may they benefit from this practice from these planting
of seeds may I benefit may all beings all people I'm in touch with I interact
with directly or indirectly may all beings be well may all beings be
[Music] happy okay thanks everyone B