so hello and
welcome to our meditation session delighted to see the names I see
there and uh some names I don't see very often
just very happy
and so yesterday
the theme was saying yes not to accept
everything but to say yes to the possibility of neither accepting or
rejecting I didn't say it that way but to say yes to when we let
go let go of our clinging preoccupations and concerns we're not accepting or
rejecting our concerns we're saying yes to something better saying yes to the awareness that
knows it yes to the freedom yes to
the maybe you can say metaphorically to the space between the
knowing and what is known that there is a distance there is
a spaciousness and to enter into this quiet still awareness knowing
recognition of things in a peaceful way is so good so whatever comes into
awareness we say yes not to reject it not to condemn it
not to accept it not to praise it but to say yes to that which holds it that
which is bigger in a sense or Freer in a sense yes and so it doesn't matter what
we're saying yes to uh the the object that's just coming into awareness what's
important is uh that the fact that we're aware so the same movement can happen
with saying no and sometimes no is really
helpful sometimes you know we're partly when we're meditating we're not just addressing
our conscious mind who we think we are when we're thinking and what we can observe about ourselves but sometimes
we're we're addressing uh subconscious parts that uh maybe are not so rational
maybe are not so um uh wise even or maybe are not so
developed maybe there's a childlike part of our subconscious and I learned raising
children that they were actually AR happier sometimes when we made very
clear lines of what they could not do we said no and then they knew the limits
and they felt secure then within it they okay now we can find our way and we know what to do but when they don't have
limits they were trying to kind of stretching against the against the uh outer rim to see how far they could go
where where where is it still safe and where can they actually be and it's almost like they needed to have clarity
about the zone of safety so there might be a subconscious part of
you where a no the loving
no um is really helpful so rather than an automatic
pilot or as a habit going off into thoughts and concerns rather than
repeating the same Loops of desires or aversions over and over again um for the
subconscious to hear from you no
no this is not healthy this is not necessary this is not the way forward
just a know and that know then can be the same thing and then with a no to that there
becomes the alternative not to move away from something or reject it but a wider more
expansive way of being so if we said no to our young kids
we didn't say no and pivot around and walk away that it was no and we would
stand there and just be be there loving and clear and available and when they're
really small kids sometimes we get down to their level so that they would not see us towering over them and say no you
can't do that so no so if you find yourself
preoccupied caught up in thoughts desires caught in feelings reaction to
things for this meditation gently
kindly but clearly with a Clarity to it maybe even
a kind of non-aggressive strength to it say
no and you might have to experiment with saying that a few times until you find
how saying no is being said from a very quiet peaceful Place deep inside that is
independent from what you're saying no to you're not rejecting it you're just
kind of stepping becoming bigger more expansive you're creating the larger
room to hold it without so it but it so it knows you're
here and you're safe but I'm not going to play with you no
so assuming a meditation posture
and if you're sitting cross-legged kind of on the floor maybe it's kind of nice to be at
the level of your
subconscious and to gently close your
eyes and to take a few long slow deep breaths settling in as you exhale
and letting your breathing return to normal and with a normal breath for a
few breaths continue to relax your body settle
in e
and then centering yourself at the place that is your
central focal point for breathing even if you have a wide
area Center yourself in the middle of that area and for a few
breaths relax into settle into that Central Focus point for breathing
on the exhales relax relxing the thinking mind
and then again centering yourself on your
breathing and you might limit the no
practice to discursive thinking to thinking about anything
which is not the meditation
and whenever you inhale let that inhale come along with a
gentle kind no to whatever thinking has
arisen and on the exhale letting the thinking mind be
quieter Stiller
saying gently to yourself know as you
inhale no to thinking
anymore where the word no has a delight
ful word play between n
o and k n o
w
for
e
e e
and to keep you engaged you might
reverse will you say to yourself on the inhale no KN n o
w know what's here know if you're
thinking and on the exhale let go of
thinking with a no n
o maybe an extended no
that's almost like a
mantra
e
for
e for
and as we come to the the end of the
sitting to take a few moments again to relax the body as you
exhale maybe relaxing micro muscles throughout the
body softening
relaxing micro muscles in the mind in the brain in the head where you
think a softening
on the exhale softening
relaxing your emotional Center maybe in the heart area wherever it might be for
you maybe the micro muscles associated with feeling emotions
mood attitude
and appreciating whatever degree of calm more
subtleness re relaxation is here for
you in the body in the
mind in the chest
and for a few moments appreciating how you are breathing with how you
are with a gentle no to anything that takes you away
from the settled way that you
are so you can better feel it and sense how you are at the end of this
meditation
and and with whatever way you're aware in your subtle
State gaze upon the world
kindly bring to mind the people and activities you'll be doing
today and wish everyone your self
included wellbeing calm
peace support love
care and may we end this meditation with a wish to bring with us
into the world today an
aspiration to live for the welfare and happiness of all beings self
included may all beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all beings be peaceful
may all beings be
free thank you e
so hello everyone and welcome and today I'm introducing continuing to introduce to you this
ancient text it's maybe the earliest teachings we have of the
Buddha and um the language is archaic the context is old before um the all the
teachings of Buddhism built up in maybe over the 40 45 years in which the Buddha
taught he slowly built up and expanded on his teachings and organized them in
ways and we certainly know that after he died his teachings kept being organized
and expanded and added to and much of how we understand Buddhism as a
religion uh wasn't really wasn't there the very beginning where the message was
very simple and I have this image of this man who is uh living you know Outdoors mostly
wandering around India as a monastic uh meditating much of the much
of his time available to meet people and walking around encountering people and
people being inspired by his peace his presence and he would offer teachings that were very simple
and um and uh these teachings in this book that I I call the book of AIDS the
poly word is atava which can mean the book of eights is um in my in my book that I
published through Shambala called the Buddha before Buddhism and I'm going to talk today
about the first of four themes that exist in this book and uh
and the First theme is letting go of views letting go of opinions and uh
about religious doctor spiritual ideas uh having a view that we should
stop for red traffic lights is not a problem but having views that are metaphysical views about Ultimate
Reality views about what is really true that people often want to know what's
true and want to hold on to that the truth they have the truth they know the
truth and for the Buddha he was very sensitive to the movement of clinging to
to called so-called truths to clinging to doctrines clinging to ideas sometimes
clinging to things that can't really be known for yourself but are clung to out of Faith out of some intuition that it's
true in some logic that it's true in some kind because my teachers told me it's true because it's in my sacred text
it's true and um and none of those sources of the truth were interesting
for Buddha the Buddha or reliable for him what was reliable was what we can
experience for ourselves and the primary thing that uh he kept pointing to in this early text was non-
clinging not clinging to anything the absence of clinging that's where peace
is found as long as there's any clinging at all for the Buddha he understood that
any clinging there is that agitation without clinging there's no agitation and um and one of the primary
things he was concerned about in this ancient text talks about it repeatedly is clinging to religious doctrines ideas
of what is Ultimate uh clinging to what we think is ultimately true the greatest Truth at
all and he was very aware that in saying this he was going against the current of
all the different religions of his time in India the lots of religious teachers
uh who held up this is true this is true this is true and in fact back then the
parently there was a whole Rich culture of debate where religious teachers come to together to debate in the presence of
Judges who would then judge who had the best arguments and who you know to Champion the
truth and the Buddha didn't participate in these debates and as you'll see today
um uh he just saw the debates as being kind of pointless so just uh but so
views um the predominant teaching regarding views is the important of not clinging
to any opinions philosophy doctrines or religious teachings that's a powerful
message and as this is from my introduction to the book this includes views about ultimate religious
truth the text teaches that to find peace a follower follow follower should
shake off every view without embracing or rejecting anything shaking off views
without embracing or rejecting anything and this includes views about
views a number of verses are critical of any assertion that one's owns religious
beliefs are the truest or best While others are
inferior for many readers this seeming no view teaching is a radical message it
undermines the importance of doctrines that underly Many religious Traditions including some Buddhist
ones the teachings in the book of eights provides no support for the idea that one should believe teachings just
because they are found in certain Buddhist texts including this
one and finally the goal of practice is often described in terms of letting go of
views those who have realized the goal called the sages are not attached to
views and so avoid debates quarrels and any conceit that their view are better
their views are better than others letting go of their attachments sages
have no need for any Doctrine in terms of theories abstract Concepts or beliefs
with no no Reliance on any doctrines the wise person does not oppose anyone
else's Doctrine so this is a wonderful teaching that appears in this text not
to oppose other people's teachings have no views including uh views about other
people this is stated explicitly in the following
verse they the wise ones are not an enemy to any Doctrine seen heard or
thought out not forming opinions not shutting
anything out and not filled with desires they are sages wise ones who have laid
their burden
down so in the ancient India there was a lot of emphasis on Purity uh attaining
some kind of some relig some religions were a lot about becoming pure doing rituals to purify ones themselves and
somehow tapping into the highest Purity there is so this whole that notion of Purity was a very important Doctrine or
idea so the Buddha says they say only here is Purity only here in
this these doctrines they say no other doctrines are pure entrenched in truths of their own
they call good what they're attached to
lusting for debates and plunging into assemblies they take each other to be
fools they speak relying on what others have said passionate for praise they
call themselves skillful so a lot of this now is going to describe the debate
culture among religious teachers of the time wishing for praise while debating
in an assembly they became they become anxious refuted they become depressed criticized
and shaken they seek their opponents faults one whose doctrines is called
deficient by the judges rejected will then Despair and grieve
the inferior debater moans I have been defeated renunciant are elated and
deflated by the disputes that arise among them seeing this you should
abstain from disputes they provide no benefit other
than being praised when being praised for proclaiming their Creed and assembly
they laugh and become conceited having gotten what they wished while that
conceit is a basis for distress they still speak with arrogance and pride
seeing this one shouldn't dispute disputes don't lead to Purity
say those who are skilled wishing for an opponent you
roar like a hero nourished on Royal food run off oh
hero to where the fight is as before there is no fight here in other words
the Buddha is not going to debate with anyone that's not the place to get into a debate
if grasping to a view and disputing they say this alone is true tell them in this
dispute you have no opponent here what opponent would you get from
those who live without opponents who don't counter views with views who don't
grasp anything here as ultimate for now that you've come here
speculating Thinking Out viewpoint with your own mind you're paired with someone
cleansed and so you can't proceed there's no way of engaging in debate
with someone who is not involved with debating with right and wrong with ideas of ultimate
truth and um so I find this delightfully refreshing and it uh without wanting to
criticize any views uh it uh
it it's a critique of any clinging to views but it's not even a critique of
people clinging to views it's simply that the sage the wise person doesn't
get entangled in the world of views is not involved in being for or against
religious ideas spiritual ideas even Buddhist ones it doesn't they argue for
you know the true teachings of the Buddha this is what's really important it's all about not self it's all about
emptiness it's all about this or that and this is the most important thing and
we have to teach this more or debate this and explain it to people this is what they have to
understand what the what this ancient text points to over and over again is
not a Doctrine not a belief but the simple Act of not
clinging simple but profound a non- clinging that brings with it a peace to
be deeply at peace deeply experience a deep
sense of well-being the primary goal in this ancient text is defined by peace not by
Enlightenment I think I think the word Enlightenment exists in the texts not by Liberation I'm not I think it doesn't
exist in the text as well these are more important later in Buddhism and they're a little bit more falling into maybe
that the idea views and ideas of what is but
peace is something simple peace is something human and I love the human very deep
human Quality naturalistic quality of this teaching here Find Your Peace by
non- clinging and then live a life engaged and active in the world but
don't give up on that non- clinging there's a gentle not you can say to any
tendency to cling to anything stay close to your peace so thank you