good morning good day hello and
welcome to our Monday beginning of the week
series and I'm continuing we're continuing with a introduction to mindfulness
meditation part two and um for the
meditation today today I'd like to emphasize or point out that one of the
primary characteristics of uh mindfulness meditation is
Simplicity and one teacher mono manindra G who I met in India vipasa teacher he
said that if it's not simple it's not vasam and the idea of radical
Simplicity includes uh and this is the part that's difficult
in the Simplicity includes not uh
projecting our mental constructs onto our
experience if we're thinking about the past or thinking about the future that's a mental construct that in
a sense is projected on the past and projected on the future uh the past doesn't exist the
future doesn't exist in certain kind of existentially real way and so it's there
has to do with memory or prediction constructs of the mind and these can be
fine in important part of life but when we sit to do mindfulness
meditation we're not even interested in the constructs of the Mind
here theas are kind of radical Simplicity where we allow our direct
experience to be itself free from comparisons free from
ideals free from what should or shouldn't happen free from our stories
that we have about it free of what we think other people will say about it
just sitting here in a radical simple way with the experience of this so
radical that we don't even impose on the experience Me Myself and
mine those can be fine Concepts but in the Simplicity of
feeling the warmth of the body this weight of the
body we can experience it without adding me myself and mind just
warmth just solidity just the in breath bre and out
breath moving through the body so to assume a meditation
posture where somewhere in the posture there's a sense of
intentionality like you're physically engaged to be here if you're sitting on the
floor it might be the Torso that's upright
if you're sitting in a chair using a back rest maybe there's a way of placing your hands on your lap that it's kind of
like saying here I am Palms down on the thighs here I am
intentionally if you're laying down maybe you're you can point uh your
forearms up forearms up to the ceiling if you're laying on your back so there's
something intentional that is support for being here and
now and then taking a few long slow deep
breaths softening the body as you
exhale
letting your breathing return to
normal and with an exhale relaxing the think
mind softening a quieting of
thinking as you exhale a quieting of the Heart
Center relaxing in the chest
and then softening the
belly letting the belly hang forward and maybe a little bit
down sometimes a soft expanded belly can feel like it provides you a
stronger foundation for the upper torso to be
here or it supports a more relaxed rhythm of
breathing
bringing your attention into your
body
maybe as if you're entering a peaceful maybe sacred grove
of trees so you go into your body so you
can experience the be with the body's experience of
itself the body's experience of
breathing and here in this
body to be very
simple with staying present for the Ever Changing Sensations of the
body as you
breathe
e
for
with whatever experience is happening in the
present to be simp be simple with
it
to free the experience from the constructs of the
Mind the ideas the concepts the judgments the
desires and if those things happen be very simple with
them and you don't have to believe
them just something arising in the moment soon to be
gone
e
for
can you be simpler here
if you need to think think with radical
Simplicity about what's actually happening here in your direct
experience without interpretation or stories or attribution to Me Myself and
mind
e
and then as we come to the end of this sitting to
consider review this meditation and could you have could you have been
simpler could you been less involved in thoughts and
judgments anxieties or
desires to sit here with Simplicity of
being that might even include a contentment just to be
Simplicity of being is not a diminishment of who we are it's a
radical respect for who we are where who we are can just be
itself without adding anything on top of it and as we come to this end of this
sitting may we prepare ourselves to go into the world with that kind of respect for
others that we're careful with our projections our desires our
assumptions our bias the complicated ways in which we
overlay our perceptions of others with our beliefs and
ideas conditioning but to put those aside even
maybe put aside the
past so we can meet people as they
are have profound respect for each person allowed to be as they are free of
our judgment may all
beings be happy may all beings be
safe may all [Music] beings be
peaceful may all beings be
free and as a minimum may they be
free of the limited view in which we look at people our judgments our
bias may people be free of our
[Music] projections
thank
you
e
so hello from Insight Meditation Center on this Monday
morning and today I begin a new new kind of series within the wider series longer
series on uh introduction to mindfulness part two and
um one of the uh important areas of mindfulness is not
just what's happening in our experience to be present here and now uh to body breath emotions feelings
thoughts also to be present for to recognize the ways that we are attached
the ways that we cling the ways that we grasp the ways that we clamp and down or
tighten up up or constrict and um and uh this is Central to the
Buddhist practice of mindfulness because attachment is considered to be one of
the primary or made primary cause to optional Suffering The Suffering that we
add to our life by the clinging itself clinging itself is a kind of
suffering attachment is a kind of constriction a contraction a resistance
a tightening up a a um weighing down that uh we can
experience and to lighten up to
release to free up uh wherever part wherever we're attached as part of the
Enterprise of the Buddhist teachings on mindfulness so to do that we want to start becoming cognizant of how we
cling what forms of attachment we have the ways the physical the direct way in
which attachment is felt and experienced generally even if you feel
like it's valid to cling to something to be attached to something if you really
feel uh the cost of the attachment the impact it has on you you can feel that
it's stressful feel that it's uh um uh is a limitation it's a irritation it's a
it's a um burden it's a it's a it's it's a
it's a kind of um it brings along a kind of contraction
which doesn't feel good and it leads to further contractions part of the problem
of clinging and attachment is one attachment gives birth to other attachment they grow on each
other and so the practice of mindfulness is a practice of radical
Simplicity where we're trying to be simple enough in the present moment just with the direct experience we have so
that direct experience can highlight the addition we put to it of clinging of
attachment and so the Buddha so there's two things there's what we attach to
what we cling to and the clinging in and of itself and um and so in the in the
teachings of the Buddha he put a lot of emphasis on five areas that we
cling and uh and and and just not just any clinging but these five areas are
offer Al also for the Buddha the primary locations primary
areas uh uh through which we cling to a self sense of self regardless of what
you think about there is or isn't a self there is a clinging to self clinging to
Identity clinging to who we think we should be clinging to roles clinging to
variety of things and that clinging is a for uh is
how self self attachment can create tremendous amount of
suffering people act on their attachments act on clinging and when we do so then it's usually not very
skillful very helpful so these five areas are appear
our appearances how we appear and how others appear to us um the uh uh sens the basic
sensations of Pleasure and Pain comfort and discomfort uh the perceptions or the
conceptions by which we recognize things the simple ideas we have of things which are often
not simple enough because they come along with a whole host of associations
meanings projections onto things uh and then uh the stories we
live by the larger constructions of the mind that interpretations and philosophies and memories and histories
and imaginings of the future and finally to our very simple
capacity to know not just what we know but just that
we do know it's such such a fantastic capacity and some people cling to this
so these are five areas and the way the Buddha referred to them in the way that
I kind of understand it is uh he called them the five
bundles uh sometimes they're called the five Aggregates in English but I think the word Aggregates kind of obscures
what they're about he talked about how they um uh uh uh different experiences
that we have that we gather together into a larger
collection to be through our clinging so not just not just that we cling to
something but it's one of many
but uh we understand form here to be the shape of things the how they appear but
because it also includes hearing and smelling and tasting and the other senses it's how things appear to the
senses but appearance is in the eyes of the beholder that um uh we're we're not
passive and innocent perceivers of things but appearance is something we
select we select what's important for us in the world of appearances we see an
attractive person and it might be that it's the clothes they wear it might be
the shape of their nose or there might be the the quality of their voice that
somehow we're predisposed to maybe tune in to certain aspects of a person and
that's what we find attractive and so how they appear in our mind the
selection Choice we've made is um is not an innocent kind of just seeing things
as they are where of all the things that person is we're tuned into particular
aspect of them and that happens to us as well and
um you know you know as I grew up over time as a child uh there was a
progressive increase concerned with my appearances how I appeared for others I
the earliest memory I have for something like this was I was probably about um I think I was maybe about
um 6 years old and before that I I called my parents mama and papa but I
was returning to Norway to visit with the family there grandparents there and
I remember um uh I was getting off the airplane at the airport in Norway and
literally we were kind of there was time to get up from our seats and walk down the aisle and so it was a time to say
something that there would be no conversations about it so I turned to my mother and
said uh from now on uh you're going to be in Norwegian um mother and
father so mother and father uh and the reason was I didn't want to be
embarrassed looking like a small kid in the eyes of my grandparents I wanted to
be a little more grown up say mother and father and um so how I appeared to
people became now concern and then when I was maybe eight
I remember the first time I got classes I also changed schools when I got glasses and so in the new school I
didn't want to wear my glasses in school because I thought people would make fun of me and that I would look
funny and um and then progressively as I got older there were concerns about back
then 1960s how long my hair was and uh concerns with what kind of clothes I
wore concerns with um all kinds of things they grew and grew
and grew and I don't know when they stopped growing and I added to them but
um but this whole idea of how I appear and how other people appear to me when I
was 19 I traveled with some friends to Morocco and uh back then many most of
the men Moroccan men wore these beautiful long uh uh robes think they
called jalaba and um and I was walking around the streets of Morocco and I had a
strange feeling that I couldn't quite understand something was a little bit lighter or more open in my mind and I
couldn't understand it until one day I realized that um because all these men
were wearing clothes that I had no associations with I was not associating
I wasn't projecting judgments and ideas on them whereas in other parts of the world in the West in America uh you
could tell something about the People by the clothes they wear and walking down the streets I had judgments about people
and my mind was kind of busy kind know like almost almost subconsciously evaluating judging people as I went and
the Morocco I I couldn't do that and it freed part of my mind and that was kind of a lovely
feeling to have to not being not not have the ability to judge because I didn't have context for
it so appearances we can sit down and meditate and how we appear uh can be um
you know what we start noticing we're attached to we're attached to our body parts how we are here and how it looks
uh some people spend more time more care with the clothes with the clothes they
choose to wear or the hair or they arrange or all kinds of things than they
do with care around the word words they speak and um because how we appear is so
important and it's partly important because others take it as important do people do judge us based on our
appearances and how we are and so we get pulled into this world of being
preoccupied with how we appear and our appearances and preoccupied with other people's
appearances and so this is one area of attachment and sometimes you can feel
the clinging attachment to appearances can be a heavy weight to Bear it can
create anxiety the clinging to you know how am I going to be accepted a
fundamental human uh need is to be to belong kind of to be accepted and the
fear of rejection and so because we we navigate so much the world of appearances unfortunately that people
put so much store at in that world and um and then concerned about uh
appearances with um you know you know with our our hair size of our nose or
fingers hands wrinkles as we get older and uh and this can be quite depressing
for some people but it is a construct it's ideas some of them are culturally created that
our culture kind of infects us with so we think in the way that a culture
around us things and um and to sit in meditation and be radically simple and leave
ourselves leave our body leave our appearance radically alone so we can
breathe and be quiet and just sense Let the
Body uh finally let the body be left alone free the body from the heavy
weight of all the ideas and projections imaginations
all the concerns we have about rejection and and uh dismissal and trying
to build up and create a more important kind of appearance for the world the
radical Simplicity leaving ourselves alone so that something inward inner can
evolve and flow and give us a feeling of being content and happy and and um and
alive free of any clinging to how we appear and uh we're allowed to be as we
are independent of what Society tells us what's good or bad or desirable
undesirable so there's a lot of self related to appearance self-making
self-building the attachment to appearance is not an innocent thing it's
uh something that we gather together into bundles and there's a huge bundles
of of these attachments that people live with so that's the first of the bundles
the Buddha talked about and today as you go about your day you might get curious
about the how much of your time is spent concerned one way or the other with your
appearance with your clothes with anything at all and um and then kind of
you know kind of be curious kind of kind of tilt your head down a little bit
what's this you know with a question what is this what this about is this needed what's
uh why am I so concerned about it what's the purpose of it and and just explore
it and get to know it more and maybe in the process of that you'll recognize one
or two attachments you have about appearance and maybe you'll look at
um The Suffering the stress that might come with that
attachment thank
you