good morning sa good morning good to be back with you this is
um a warm greeting from Santa Cruz California and it's also a
soundcheck great thank you and thank you for whatever thoughts are Reflections
that you're holding in your hearts or sharing with others over this week of
practice this theme of dhic
reciprocity so the invitation once you've had a
chance to settle in welcome yourself
here offer a warm welcome to the day or the
evening to settle Back start to move the attention
inward maybe adjusting your posture taking that La last sip of tea or
coffee and start starting with a couple of intentional slower deeper
breaths receiving on the in
breath and letting go into the practice
relaxing softening on the out breath
perhaps at the end of the next out breath allowing yourself to rest in that
Tiny still point that moment of transition between the exhale and the
inhale
and then allowing receiving the breath as it naturally
wants to be in this moment
allowing mindful awareness to be at the
Forefront of your attention for this half hour of
meditation noticing the Sounds in your space the warmth or cool
of this body and the air on your
skin a sense of weight or
lightness noticing too whatever [Music] mood
attitude is in your heart
perhaps gratitude or
calm intention or the momentum of the
day letting that be there too taking
nourishment from your aspiration to practice
whatever the
conditions allowing a soft
smile and the [Music] tuning attending to whatever anchor of
attention
feels like it will help you stay in this present
moment here just here
acknowledging and including all of embodied
experience and then resting
settling on each breath this
breath where for this sound this moment
noticing the effect perhaps soothing
effect of centering the
attention resting and
Sensations coming and going
however life is showing up in this
breath e
if an emotion sound sensation
thought becomes
compelling including this too
in mindful awareness of this
moment respect
care and if it fades becomes less
predominant as it will you're turning the
attention to your home this
body this
breath giving over to the moment of
meditation
e
e e
time to time rededicating the
attention to the felt sense the flow of the
moment
e
e e
in the last few minutes of our formal meditation
together the invitation is open the awareness wide
if you haven't already to all of present moment experience
unfolding notice sound
sensation breath but mental or emotional
activity flowing through like flocks of birds or
clouds in a vast
Sky then two
noticing the quality of that observation the
appreciating the capacity for it
and then casting your mind back over these moments of
meditation acknowledging any
challenges with respect [Music]
compassion and trust that they become part of the compost
growth in this
practice and then two especially noticing
recalling any little glimmers of goodness
peacefulness or calm steadiness a finger snap of
kindness a droplet of mindful
awareness and breathing those into your heart your emotional Center
being sustained by them savoring
them and from that pleas sending those good wishes outwards
to the others in your life other
practitioners and those your life incorporates in other
ways those here near and far wishing them
well may they be safe
happy healthy may they be
peaceful at ease and
free and then two widening the circle allowing that
goodness to Ripple out offering the intention may all beings be
safe happy peaceful and
free noticing the effect of that wish on this heart this
mind In This Moment
[Music]
thank you for your practice
for
e e
so warm welcome sa warm welcome to the last day of this 5day
exploration a special welcome to those of you who slipped in late
and what I'd like to cover today this last day of the Buddha's
teachings about giving and reciprocity
Reflections on how that resonates in our own
practice is um sort of the last thing on one of the lists that I've been reading
in this obscure little um section of the poly Canon which is that a good person
with Integrity gives with the view that
something will come of it something will come of it in other
words that there are effects for What from what we give cause
and effect condition it how different conditions come together to expl to kind
of form this moment to form what
is and this teaching many of you will recognize is very closely related to a
big topic Karma the Buddha made it clear that if someone tries to wrap their head around
Karma all of the implications of karma their head would explode so in the
interest of keeping everyone's head intact today just going to offer the
simplest definition of Karma and it is the the fundamental
definition which is action action of body speech or
mind so action and result K viaka karma viaka
is what people are usually in ort of mainstream Buddhist English talking
about when we talk about Karma and of course you don't always know the
results however we can trust and know that there are
results Choice regard for consequences and
results are actually key to the entire process of Buddhist
Meditation so karma is not fate actions have results those are sort of the core
teachings and one of the key actions in these early Buddhist
teachings is giving and there's a particular frame on
it it's giving with attention to the effect of offering on your own heart and
mind your own practice your own way of being and perhaps this is also not
totally knowable however it's way more knowable than the vast interplay of Ripples and
conditions out in the world from the Buddha perspective in
these early teachings on giving the most helpful reason to
offer is to en Noble the heart and mind to prepare for deeper Insight
wisdom and to increase that kind of wisdom generosity and goodness in the
world so it's not giving to get and it is definitely not offering out of
obligation and this points to there being a real power
in giving with no strings attached
that creates a certain kind of resonance a nonlinear
reciprocity those of you who've been here all week might remember the story I started
with being in a temple in Thailand a monastery practicing there and how the
people there would give excess food excess water to the
villagers around them and in this kind of oceanic cycle of gener osity the
excess water on this arid Island the only water that came from rain rippled down through their sisters
cascaded back into the ocean and what felt like an expression
of trust that somehow that moisture that
life sustaining fluid water would cycle back to
them I find this inspiring to bring in another ocean simile the
Buddha likened existence all of our existence to AV void across the
ocean the destination the far Shore freedom but much skill is
required in the voyage across the ocean as well as a
compass compass being nonharming and a guiding North Star
where wisdom and nonharming Ming meet together so in a real sense the person
on the voyage we don't control the weather or all the conditions of the
ocean we do have influence over how we respond and wisdom about what weather
patterns to enter into and what directions to take that
Voyage is a collaboration with what is
in a real sense where we give time attention material goods and especially the
actions of our body speech and mind determine the quality of that
Voyage so this lens on giving invites
discernment it invites choosing to give up ditch the excess weight
of unskillful qualities and make room for skillful ones so the Buddha invites us to
notice notice the effects of attitudes and actions on your heart on your mind your
practice on that crucial relationship with
yourself what we offer to practice matters even more than the detail of
what's offered how it's offered
matters so this is the core of the teaching of giving and for that
matter of karmic action and result paying close
attention to the effects on your own heart and mind and life
has benefits that's especially true when combined with some of the other
qualities we've been exploring this week a benefits of considering the effect
[Music] of offering wholehearted
attention mindfulness respect appreciation of
timelessness and of season all of this begins to reorient to a
different very beautiful Compass so how to do
this noticing the effects Moment by moment like the Buddha taught his young
son rahula this is a teaching I've given many times Dharma teachers love this teaching he taught his seven-year-old
son to notice before during and after an action of
bodies speech your mind is this harmful if so stop
it or don't do it to begin with OR make amends for it if you notice
afterwards and resolve not to do it again is it
helpful if so keep doing it and learn from that either way learn
from that
anything anything we give offer or do affects us first the Buddha offered the
simile of hatred or hostility directed outwards being like picking up a hot Cal
to throw it at someone else who does it burn first on the other hand if you're
offering kindness beautiful things beautiful attitudes like meta loving kindness that
Sublime intention touches This Heart first your
mind first so this is transferable
wisdom across life and it's also transferable wisdom in choosing what to
receive or not there's this story of a person coming coming to the Buddha with a lot
of hostility and blame of some kind who knows what and the Buddha ask them if
someone shows up at your doorstep and offers you something you don't want do you take it and the person said no and
he said just like that I leave your hostility with you I'm
not picking it
up I don't have to receive that gift on the other
hand receiving the gift of Dharma offering the gift of Dharma in the
Buddhist teachings is considered one of the highest perhaps the
highest expression of generosity and to receive that the
Buddha advises that to notice assess for yourself the wisdom
for you in your own heart and life of whatever is being offered and if it seems helpful to
respectfully receive it and do your absolute best to practice with
it so these teachings are
offered out of a love and generosity for the
Dharma and the high highest gift that I
receive is trusting knowing that you will find what works for you and keep it
set aside the rest and continue to practice sincerely
and beautifully giving over wholeheartedly
into this practice deepens its transformative
power there's all kinds of beautiful gifts all kinds of resonant
reciprocity that can flow to you through this practice and
eventually it becomes the giving the offering becomes both the beginning and
the end letting go into Freedom beneficial cycle offering for the benefit of
yourself and others so thank you very much for your
practice for your presence and for your kind
attention May the benefits of our practice here together Ripple outwards and outwards
through our lives all of the lives we touch and all
of the lives they touch may all beings benefit from our
practice here together
[Music]