well good evening everyone welcome to
IMC Diana is not here this week so
she sent me a email on Saturday asking if I would give a talk
tonight I looked at my calendar book I have a paper book that I use to U keep
my appointments in and I noticed today is actually it had three sort of
holidays printed on it uh the first one is Columbus Day
it's um marking the day that Christopher Columbus um found that indeed the edge
of the Earth wasn't somewhere out in the Atlantic Ocean but there was two
continents on the other side of the ocean which the Europeans didn't know
about um another day of today is
celebrating is indigenous people's day so something like somewhere between 14
and 25,000 years before Columbus people came to the uh North and South American
continent spread throughout it created um cities
cultures um and
uh so that's being celebrated today that that these people who had been here for
tens of thousands of years and then the other holiday today is Canadian
Thanksgiving so I thought I would talk about Canadian Thanksgiving I
was aware of it because I have several friends who are Canadian you know so
they um have had parties and um I've enjoyed
that um Canadian Thanksgiving I the the first
recorded one was like in 1579 so quite before Canada existed or
the United States existed and it was related to the Harvest festivals of France and
England so this idea of giving thanks for the Bounty of the Harvest each year
uh goes back a long ways I'm sure it goes back well before the
Europeans this notion of uh giving thanks uh for what we get what we
receive what what sustains
us I don't think the Buddhists have one particular day that they call
Thanksgiving Day
um so I started to think well what does what does Thanksgiving have to do with
Buddhism what what's the connection
and what came to me as I was uh contemplating This
was um that the practices that the Buddha taught the path that the Buddha um
pointed to is a path of Peace and
Freedom and primarily it's a path of inner peace
and inner freedom and the freedom is to be free
from greed delusion and hatred those
three uh forces you might say three habits of
mind that um we seem to be susceptible to as human
beings can keep us from having a sense of
Peace So it's important to be able to look at
what what Su what keeps us what keeps
greed delusion and hatred going and so how do we how do we um
work with them so that was one of the thoughts
that came to me was how how does Thanksgiving relate to becoming
free and then the other one uh so
peace what keeps us from being peaceful is
conflict and you might think of the conflict as being outer conflict conflict with other
people or groups of people
um governments societies
um conflict with reality um but also there's inner
conflict right I mean there's we have different
impulses um desire Ires uh
beliefs habits and they don't always align with each other so there can be inner
conflict uh yesterday there was a class on the eight-fold path which is a
description of what the Buddha taught the path that he taught um
um and it occurred to me as as I was in that that one of the parts of the eight-fold
path is about right action and in that
is a willingness to be honest to be
truthful so if you want to address conflict both inner and outer
it's important that you're honest right you know that you that you're honest at
least at least with yourself but also with others as to how you see
things um you know without honesty um it seems pretty unlikely that
you're going to be able to resolve any kind of conflict um
you know and even internally you know you need to be honest
with uh what's going on with you what's going
on inside the thoughts the uh physical Sensations the
emotions and if you want to be free from greed delusion and
hatred um this honesty is also required you know you need to be honest about
what is it that you're trying to get and how can you get it and how can
you get more of it or what is it that you hate and what are you trying to push
away or with delusion what what are you deluded about what
what is it that you're not seeing clearly
so I think at the the one of the the really important parts of this
path is a willingness to be
honest to be honest with yourself to be honest with others to see things clearly
as clearly as you can
and so I think that's what brings me
to uh Thanksgiving that if you're really
honest that if I'm really honest with myself about what supports me in this
life um how did I get
here that
the notion that I'm a self-made man that I've got here strictly through
my own efforts strictly through my own uh
doing isn't really the
truth the truth is there's many people that have supported me throughout my
life
and so I thought that I would talk a little bit
about the people that supported me and the the thankfulness that I feel for
them and I have to admit right away when I as a child when I was first growing up
I don't think thankfulness was really on my radar at
all thankfulness was something that my parents told me that I had to
express I had to thank my aunt for that dress shirt that was Itchy and Scratchy
and uh I didn't you know I'd much rather have a t-shirt than this dress shirt
that she gave me but I was told no no no you you need to be thankful you you have you have to
thank you know thank Aunt Betty thank thank grandpa thank
Grandma um so it wasn't you know it didn't come to me uh naturally to to
want to to thank or or feel grateful
um mostly what I noticed was what I didn't get
uh in the mid-50s my grandparents were I think the first people that I knew that
to have a color television that was a big deal back in the the
mid-50s and so every Sunday night we'd go to their house and they we would watch the wonderful world of Disney
followed by bonanza in
color and I really really wanted to go to Disneyland I mean it just you know
watching it on the television and it just looked like it was so much
fun and I would plead with my parents you know can't we go can't we go well we
lived about so several thousand miles away from Disneyland so going there
wasn't just a day trip I mean it would have been you know quite
a you know quite inexpensive and uh arduous
Journey but that's what I remembered you know like I remembered what I didn't get I didn't get to go to
Disneyland
um and the other thing was at the end of Sunday night when Bonanza was over that
meant going home going to bed and facing a whole week of school so that was like
the end of ananza meant the end of the weekend and going back to school and
uh which I was at best sort of um neutral
about as I got older um
it began to dawn on me all of the ways in which my parents had supported me that I
didn't didn't really recognize or uh
acknowledge uh growing up they made sure that I I was in school
I I started at the age of three and ended coming out of graduate school at
age 29 so I got a lot of Education and the first part I'd say
wasn't so interesting to me um but they made sure that I went
they made sure I you know did my homework and then uh by high
school I think it became more interesting to
me so they took they took care of making sure that I got an academic
education uh they also took me to church I don't go to that church anymore
but um I think two things that I remember
about that number one is there was teaching of Ethics you know that you
know the basic Ten Commandments that should not kill and steal
lie and so I think even though I really didn't like going to
church that was not that was not fun um again with the stiff dress shirts and
everything else but
um but it taught me ethics you know
non-harming being um
you know living a life that didn't involve
um any kind of antisocial
behavior um the church we went to there was you know no drinking or any anything
like
that which I clearly ignored once I turned 18 but um
um but I think it it it it really gave me a a solid
basis uh in ethics the church also taught about
love and in a different way than I would get
through watching television or movies you know like you watch television and movies love love is about romance right
it's about two people you know kind of getting
uh into some you know state of
infatuation but the church also taught me about loving each other you know more
than just loving one other person but love is a important part of being a human being
so I'm I'm thankful for my parents for having sent me to school getting an
education um getting a
spiritual uh education
um you know providing food clothing shelter
uh Medical Care
um so I think it it took decades before I could really feel the the gratitude
for my parents for how they they raised me you know to to forget about the
things that I wanted that I didn't get and just recognize all of the things
that I did
get I'm also thankful for my grandparents my extended
family and then going forward from that the um the teachers that I
had
um I've often heard stories of of people that had teachers that were you know
strict disciplinarians and you know kind of wrap people on the knuckles with
rulers and things like that for the most part my teachers were much more
um uh I'd say kind or
skillful in providing discipline particularly when I got to
high school um I had science teachers that
got me interested in science they were not only provided you know talked
about the the knowledge you know the what was in the books but they also brought their
um their love of science you know their you know a sense of Vitality
what uh a sense of
excitement and so I had a you know biology teacher that
um loved to tell jokes and really brought an enthusiasm
that made at the very least kept me from falling asleep in in class
and then my High School uh chemistry teacher
um really inspired me to become a chemist you know he you know he was middle-age and still
working on his PhD you know he wasn't sure whether he he'd ever get it he said
his committee was right on the border about whether they would award it or not but that didn't seem to distract or that
didn't seem to deter him at all he just loved what he was doing he he was
excited about it he shared us shared it with us
um he even demonstrated it you know he he demonstrated a a type of explosive
that you could set off with just a feather on a long stick and uh
um you know he he brought in some of the things that he was doing for his own research and
just you know just made me realize that
um science isn't just about knowledge there's also some in some
excitement and some curiosity and so
um so I'm I'm thankful for those the particularly for the science teachers
that I had in high school um you know they really imparted
they they really brought science to life for me that it wasn't just book
learning
um when I was in graduate school I had a a thesis advisor who was very hands-off
let me kind of try all sorts of different
things uh you know in addition to learning about chemistry I learned you
know electronics and glass blowing and machining and working on
supercomputers um
in some ways it might have been better if he wasn't quite so hands off but but I'm thankful for all the latitude that
he gave me and all of the resources that he afforded
me um my research
Group by and large were people that all got along well and uh we supported each
other so
I'm thankful for that while I was in graduate school I got
married and although it didn't last forever
um she my ex-wife brought a lot into my life her her social um ecosystem system
like her family her friends uh provided a sense of
belonging
connection um which I think I didn't even realize
how much I appreciated it until we split up and then suddenly I was no longer
part of that ecosystem more somewhat peripheral to it
um and then I'll and then finally I'll talk about coming to the Dharma you know
that I um came to IMC when we were back at in
paloalto and Gil gave a talk about the four noble
truths and it was so eye openening for me
because I had never heard anybody talk so
um I don't know I won't say seriously but so
um matter of factly about the import importance of paying
attention to suffering paying attention to what to that sense of uh disease or
unease or dissatisfaction
um I thought living a skillful life was avoiding suffering at all cost you
know I don't know either running from it or uh numbing yourself from it or
something um but he was the one that really that really pointed
out that this um dissatisfaction the sense of
suffering is really a teacher it's really if you want a good teacher pay
attention to your suffering and that that was not the message that I gotten anywhere
else um you know and that there was not only
that paying attention to it but there was also a cause for it and there was
the possibility of release from it and that there was a path so there wasn't
just some kind of existential despair that there's suffering in life and
you're stuck with it that that there's something to do so I felt very thankful
for uh finding my way to uh IMC and to Gil in
particular and then
to the example of the Buddha to the Buddhist teachings and
then also to the s to the I found when I first talked with
Gil after maybe six months I told him you know this this is great stuff I I
want to talk to you one on-one once a week and he didn't say no well I guess
he did say no he said I've got a lot going so the most I
can see you is once a month so if you want to make an appointment you know I can talk I'll talk to you once a month
but he said but most of what you're going to learn you're going to learn from your
peers you're going to learn by talking to other people like other people in
this room um and so I started getting into Cita
groups groups of people that uh are interested in this in this
path as well and can share both their struggles and their
successes you know what what are you struggling with what you know what
uh what don't you
understand and so I think I've been in Cita group since I think it's what uh
the year 2000 and um uh I'm thankful for
them so I've led a very I'll say fortunate
life and only more recently I'd say probably somewhere starting in my middle
age did I really recognize the importance
of being thankful for everything that I received and I think thankfulness is a
um like for me it wasn't something that I was born with that I you know
automatically um acknowledged the ways that people were helping me and
so I found that it's it's for me it's been a practice a practice of um
recognizing how you're being supported how you're being benefited how you're
being helped and then thanking the people that are doing that
um I started very simply by just um every time I'd go into a Starbucks I'd
always not only give them some tip but I'd always make to the best of my
ability make eye contact with the Barista and thank them for my drink you
know that it isn't just some transaction where
um you go in and say I need a soand so
uh you know cafe latte or something like that but to really acknowledge that
they're um that there's something Beyond just
the exchange of money going on here
here I think over time it's gotten easier but it's but it still
takes it still takes reminding myself the importance of thanking others for
what they do for me um and so I would encourage you all
to think about way in which you're supported by
others you know throughout the day you know whether it's
um you know cashier at the at the supermarket or uh Barista or
um somebody in a medical office
um that that it's quite a practice it's not that hard the hardest part of it is
remembering to do it um and even if it feels awkward over
time it can get easier so um on
this Canadian Thanksgiving I encourage you all to
consider um
you're your Bountiful Harvest so thank
you and if anyone has questions or would like to share something about um what
they're thankful for or what they struggle
with um we have U microphones
yeah thanks for the talk Jim it was uh really inspiring to hear all the
different ways we can be thankful and have this reminder to do
it um so that's something I'm going to take away and want to do more of and I think
it's in the line of loving kindness uh practice as well um to be
thankful um I was also interested in uh hearing maybe a bit more about the
types of SAS like I think you mentioned K on a groups as one and like to hear
more about maybe like how you came across that one or you know are there ways of looking at other SAS as someone
that's new to this practice sure sure
well there is a a signup list for neighborhood groups uh over on the side so you can
you can do that um that's one
way uh I was fortunate enough to start
doing uh residential retreats in the I think my second first or second
year and so I met other people uh Andrea Fel was one of them she
invited me to a uh to join a group back I I think it was in
2000 um yeah so the neighborhood groups are one option
um what kind of neighborhood groups Oh there's uh neighborhood groups
for um meeting to talk about uh
practice I I think there's a signup sheet and it it's usually kind of goes by ZIP code you know so
that um I'm in one group that's spread out all over the Bay Area and it's a great
group but it's also really helpful to have a group that
um you can meet with locally that' be nice yeah there something in par yeah
yeah I think I I think there's probably probably one um I've met people
through uh volunteering here at IMC so you meet other people that
way and
there's also things like the IMC book group that meets I think once a once a
month on Fridays so those are some of the ways to do it also there's um once a month
there's a potluck here so you can meet people at the
potluck and then once a month there's a tea after the Sunday morning sit so
those are some of the possibilities of um connecting last Sunday of the month I
think yeah the the last Sunday of the month is the potluck and then just this last Sunday
was the tea I think so like the second Sunday of the month I think is the tea
well if there's no other comments thank you all for
coming and I wish you a
happy Canadian Thanksgiving