welcome folks welcome to you
all um okay let's uh let's meditate
Maybe be just to examine what you started to do when you
started to
meditate but you think it means to begin to
meditate Maybe stop doing all the things you began
we can pick up certain efforts later but for now put
all of them down anything you can stop doing stop
doing
e e
it maybe feels like we have to do
something but uh sometimes the feeling of having to do
something to make something happen it's a certain lack of trust in
our mind so what if
you begin to trust your
mind begin to trust the
awareness that doesn't depend on your willfulness
just enough with the suspicion
suspicion of yourself your mind
I give you an intentional anchor and uh say to uh attend to your
breath attend to your body attend to
soundscape are beautiful
instructions but uh it gives a lot of room for a self to
be born
the self that uh takes my
instruction and orchestrates the attentional focus
so what can you trust that uh doesn't depend on
you the truth is whatever depends on
me not so reliable
e e
maybe we could say the anchor is
everywhere
e
e e
in a sense the uh self's job is
willfulness if we don't give self a
job do we need a
self
e
e e
the self one of my friends said is experienced as
tension so if we do anything
we
relax and we trust uh awareness to find
us
e
e e
we just keep uh letting our doing
this dissolve into the openness of uh
awareness e
maybe the the only job we give ourselves is to
uh surrender Trust
your meditation practice doesn't need
you
e
e e
maybe maybe we can say self is death
and awareness is life
how alive may we
become
e
e for
okay so uh
this friend mentioned him before a long time uh
practitioner and um it's really it's kind of like he's
living in a Dharma talk he's just it's inspiring actually it's like just always
actively working with something in his practice and so whenever we talk it's
like he's like Midway into like a really good Dharma talk he's giving to himself
then he just starts giving it to me and um he's uh he's
persuasive and um I remember one conversation he was like you know we say
to everybody let go and open to anich open to uncertainty comprehend suffering
comprehend Dua you know he said it's too much much it's just too
much we need to teach pleasure I'm in this path of pleasure
right now you know and he wasn't talking about like Hedonism exactly but the path
is indeed about a certain kind of pleasure we call happiness
peace there is um such a thing as uh the
wholesome Pleasant wholesome Pleasant the pleasure that uh leads not to more
craving but to actually to well-being to to satiety like we are
full you know craving never culminates in
satiety but in a cycle and so um I
wanted to speak uh a little bit just about the kind of like some of the different species of Dharma pleasure but
more centrally what are the functions of Dharma pleasure what are the functions
of Dharma pleasure so the species the species of
Dharma pleasure you know many things we could you know go on forever probably but um
few that come to mind for me just the pleasure of of having a path
that there is a path that has been walked by uh other Dharma ancestors before us
that there's a path actually a path that someone has made sense of the
intensity of The Human Condition there's a lot of pleasure just
in that there's pleasure in having one's
Dharma heart known understood seen not
misconstrued we call it s the the Delights of spiritual
friendship kalana there's the pleasure of uh more
closely aligning our deepest ethical intuitions with our
behavior and maybe there's always some Gap between what we know and what we can
do what we can pull off but Dharma practice brings us into deeper
alignment between our commitments and our acts and this feels very
good there is the pleasure of um of non shame non shame because we've sort of
worked through all the ways that the self constellates shame we've worked
through all the ways in which we're out of step with our values we've worked through all the things that um feel like
they testify to something wrong with me there's the pleasure of just we we
can't be found out anymore you
know can't be found out it's not that there aren't different dimensions of our own
being uh but we we can't um we've sort of left no stone unturned with kind of
like this this um yeah fearless self-investigation
and wherever there's shame we a it out we air it out we
realign and there's a sense of like ah can't be found out
there's the pleasure of love all the species of love of kindness and
compassion and Delight Joy gratitude all these they feel so good their
pleasure their pleasure we know hatred simply does not work given the
architecture of our nervous system it it cannot work it cannot
work it's inherently painful and love is not
there's the pleasure of concentration the unified mind we say
samadi and samade is the kind of resolution of
ambivalence the resolution of being pulled in different directions Ambi
veent and it feels so good anytime you
know in our life we've come to resolve some measure of ambivalence it feels very good not to be
split feels very good for the mind not to be split against itself for our
wanting not to be split against itself there's the pleasure of reverence
reverence just like we all need something to
rever you know and you see when people don't know what to rever don't have
something to rever they go
crazy the highest happiness the the Buddha says is uh
peace the phenomena not stimulating chitta not stimulating heart
mind that was just a beginning kind of catalog of darn d ma species of Dharma
Pleasures okay but what what is a different question what's the function of pleasure how does pleasure function
on the path other than just feeling good and that's very
good well one function of Dharma pleasure is simply to keep us going on
the path if it's all grind sometimes we can stay with it for a while but it's
it's harder it's harder and so in other words
um excuse me uh faith is induced by
Pleasure this this weird way in which we we really deeply link pleasure and
progress and sometimes that's really wrong but in this case okay yeah fair
enough that Dharma pleasure signals something this is a worthy
trajectory Dharma pleasure is um it's it's Rich it's Rich it's a satisfying
pleasure that doesn't generate more craving and there we know the pleasure
that kind of compounds the cycle of acquisitiveness getting tasting whatever
the pleasure is the partial satisfaction and partial heartbreak of
it and the kind of disappointment and then the doubling
down and the reiteration of that cycle Dharma pleasure is not like that
it um doesn't doesn't reinforce the cycles of
compulsivity and it Dharma pleasure replaces some of the other sense
Pleasures we might be busy chasing and so yeah generally speaking
like we continue to do activities that are rewarding it's like operant
conditioning because in the early parts of practice and early Parts might be
many years there is a lot of thawing of delusion that's painful there's a lot of
uh purification and tumult and intensity and uh there's maybe not
so much Dharma pleasure and the motivation can kind of wobble and so the pleasure sort of helps
us consolidate our motivation when it starts to kick in meditation starts to
be actively rewarding and It prepares us for deeper
growth pain generally attracts the Mind pleasure broadens the Mind pain and
suffering it it Narrows our attentional Focus it's like it's almost inherently
suffering is inherently self-absorbing you
know they're like suffering and the rigidity of self the contraction of self
the attentional claustrophobia those are all correlated
and so um yeah this this kind of um this
pleasure is about beginning to broaden broaden the mind broaden the field of
awareness and it's it's notable that um that happiness some kind of Happiness
some kind of pleasantness some kind of pleasure precedes concentration and
Insight normally we think well I want concentration I want some AUD I want
Insight so that I can get happy but it's actually happiness that's
the precondition for those
goodnesses sometimes sometimes yeah I I for sure pain can be very good for
concentration there's nothing but the pain and I
spent a lot of time just like that in practice but um the Mind fatigues if
that's all if if all we ever do is see what's right in front of us you know
like that kind of focus the way pain Narrows the attentional
bandwidth and so that can be useful but we also enjoy right as humans as animals
looking out from altitude over distance right and amidst pleasure we
sort of perceive our life from a higher altitude and the vigilance that we often
live with that dissolves the landscape of the mind is more
open and there's a feeling of trust because we kind of just biologically
trust pleasure it signals there are no problems to be resolved
and so much of our Insight on this path comes out of our kind of the noticing in
the peripheral view when we're looking for for kind of
goodness or understanding for Solutions right here right in front of
us it it can contract the mind and pleasure helps widen the field it's
almost like when I'm looking very intently right here right in front of me where's my insight where's is my
goodness where is my concentration when I'm looking in that way there's a kind of like more rigid
model of the self and it's almost like new discoveries about who what we are new
models of what we are need to kind of sneak up on us and our narrow focus is a kind of
reiteration of self sometimes and with the broadening
of of pleasure there's sort of like we start to to learn from our peripheral
vision a lot of learning comes from
there with the deepening of pleasure uh there's more room for purification which
is still always going to be a part of our path until we're done and the path is a kind of dialectic
of feeling good and feeling bad efficient
suffering a dialectic of feeling good and feeling bad and there's pleasure and love and
refuge and delight and Purity and then there's purification and the pleasure makes uh
more room to digest the pain the pain of our past the habits
that get us into trouble the pleasures kind of like almost like a robe that uh is Broad
enough to wrap up our pain and so
uh yeah many functions many species of Dharma pleasure many functions of
it and um yeah let us not be anym afraid
of uh pleasure
uh yeah offer this for your consideration so uh thank you and
uh we'll uh we'll gather back next time uh here next
week okay folks you uh take good care okay