good morning Richard Shanklin and welcome back to IMC thank you good
morning so we're good to go no announcements good to okay all right so good morning everyone
I'm happy to be with you let me just say what I have in mind
um I I just I have a little bit in the beginning I actually want to try to keep it quite short just to kind of get us
started and then I hope mostly to open it up for disc discuss if there's questions and that can often be a good
discussion if if there isn't much I'm prepared to you know talk more if I need
those of you who know me I I can talk so so but that's kind of most what I'd
like to do um the ending time um is scheduled for 10:45 we want to respect
the time um I was told that if things are going and we want to keep going five
or 10 minutes after that's okay but we want to also for some of you need to leave so at 10:45 if you need to leave
just take care of yourself go and don't matter of fact at any time you're not stuck here just take
care of yourself you'll stay when you need to stay go when you need to go it's all good so uh that's kind of what we'll
do yeah so you know I was reflecting coming here because I used to I live in
Oakland and um way back I used to come here you know a fair amount but I haven't been here much really for number
of years just don't get here at all so I was wondering there's a few people here I recognize from way back but I was
wondering am I going to know anyone as I look around really I don't I don't know
really anyone here there's a few people but there's no one here I know well so I was reflecting so what would be of you
value or interest to talk about given that I don't know the group I don't know you I don't know your
goals right what you're as a Dharma practitioner or meditator and you know we don't all same
obious viously share the same goals and I don't make assumptions it's certainly not for anyone else to tell us what our
goals should be we need to come to that oursel I hope we'll reflect on Dharma teachings as we kind of get clearer
about our goals but then we're each going to find our own way you know in the tradition there's this idea of um
you know Nirvana that's the Sanskrit or neana and ply and some we that's a whole
discussion and uh we don't know if we'll get into that today but some of you may think like that I'm guessing most of us
probably don't uh you'll hear words like um
Enlightenment realization Awakening Liberation all these different terms they all have different connotations for
each of us um they're not all the same thing but uh that's a whole another discussion
um so but I feel pretty sure that probably
there's a few things we all most of us probably do share in common you know you may not have a sense of of your goals
sometimes we're drawn to these practices and it's just it's not clearly articulated maybe we're just we think
there's something there of value I when I started out I was 18 years old and you know I
was drawn to these and I just thought you know I didn't know but those people
who are doing that meditation and going whatever real deep is there's something they got
I want that and there was just a sense of something like that and um but I
hadn't some of us may have a sense of uh just wanting to live in a way that's uh what we suffer less probably that's true
for all of us right want to suffer less or live in a way that's um I don't know you have to F in your own words
um I bet all of us want to live in a way where where we have a Kinder heart more
empathetic less ill will anger hatred right probably all of us um I bet
probably most all of us want to live if you think about it would who wouldn't want to live in a way where we're more
clear non-reactive and um uh what would you say more wisely responsive as
opposed to being reactive and life maybe something like that
um present awake wise you know there's lots of different terms you have to find
your own adjectives one way
I bet all of us want to live in a way that creates less and less suffering for ourselves and for others
and wants to create more you could say happiness or well-being for others than ourselves that's a simple I actually I
like that right and um who wouldn't want to do that so anyway you have to find
your own way um but assuming we're up for something whatever our goal or aims
are then the question is what's going to support us to to be able to actualize
that so it starts with a nice idea and then maybe it becomes actually more
alive and when many of you will know for your own practices that you've seen lots of fruits and benefits in your practice
I was just speaking with someone a couple of days ago he's been a Dharma person for maybe five years and uh when he came
to our our group is up in Oakland we're called the metad Dharma Foundation we're kind of like you guys here we're smaller but uh you have our weekly group we run
Retreats and all that kind of stuff and um he came and good person everything
and he said himself that he had a lot of anger and a lot you know I'm just saying what you know kind of things he was
sharing about himself and just even in this five years you know so much has transformed and he was sharing yesterday
or two days ago with me that he had someone working where he lived and they uh accidentally destroyed a plant that
was like his favorite plant there was a big deal about the plant and
he was saying how it used this may not sound like that much but he he said it used to feel like that would be
something he would have just it would not have gone over well with the person who accidentally did it
and he said this time he noticed that he just kind of walked away and and um and just
thought well you know things happen and he noticed wow what a shift in himself and he said to me
um things are better when you're a Buddhist uh you may not identify as a
Buddhist uh that's a whole another thing maybe I'm suppos not supposed to talk like that around
here uh since it's a Buddhist place I've I've been a Buddhist
uh Allin for many many decades I've been meditating like I don't know 55 years 54
years uh I don't identify at all as a Buddhist anymore just totally dropped away
where's Buddhism just in the aliveness of the present moment right but I don't really tell people that all wait we're
broadcast we're we're live casting right oh man so anyway I shouldn't said that but
um you know I'm not using notes so it kind of can go like this in a talk but
you know the Buddhist Buddha wasn't a Buddhist that let's not don't I don't want to make a big deal of it and don't tell people up at metad Dharma I said
I'm not a Buddhist I don't want them to freak out um but anyway but I am a Buddhist but
anyway um so we see that's real fruit you know it's not like this Nirvana or something
he can actually look and see a shift and I bet many of you can some of you may be
waiting when am I going to get what this thing that's supposed to start happening waiting for something to happen and it
can be like that I can relate to that so you have lots of company if you feel that way so don't worry about
it you just show up the best you can whatever that looks like it doesn't
matter don't you will see if you don't come talk to me if you if you don't know this
sometimes it can take a lifetime but it actually profoundly transforms people's experience of being it's a real thing
right lots of people experience stuff like that so fruits come but we don't have to wait just look back in your own
life is there anything you can see that used to be
challenging difficult that's even one thing that's a little better now that's
a shift don't invalidate that so anyway
but I'm happy to chat with you or hopefully there's people here you can chat with around that if you're can't find what's working or
can't find your own goodness or anything like that because it's not hard to find
sometimes we need to help pointing it out so what's going to help us actualize
these beautiful qualities of our hearts and Minds more and it's not one way the you know
here there's I have again I'm not around here as much as I used to be so I I
don't really know exact I know a lot of the teachers from way back maybe things have shifted but I have a general sense
of how things are taught here you can see for yourself you're here so obviously it's it's a powerful path and
will work well for you you might practice in other ways but in some way I think um probably most of these
practices bring together a few main qualities in our tradition that can really help us one of them is learning
to steady the mind more sometimes I use this word concentration it's a terrible
translation for the word somati we're stuck with the word concentration because everybody uses it
but it's just it's it's okay but it has so many connotations so we just need to be clear what we're
talking about when I say that it's okay steadying however much just so we're not
a little bit even steuding the Mind mindfulness we talk about Insight we talk about qualities of the heart how
you develop these and in what combination in what ways um that's highly individual for all of us it turns
out what I'm about to say here is you know I'm not trying to be controversial
but uh if I say something and it's different than what someone else is say it's okay just it's not a big deal just
find what works for you but uh because what I'm going to say here is okay here it
comes it doesn't matter what you
do I mean you want to do something that's not creating suffering and but
within the Dharma world and the practitioner it does not
matter pick up on whichever thread Within teachings and practices calls to
you we can get more specific when we have questions if you want but um follow
that listen to your calling not someone else's way they're
different than you they have to find their calling if you don't know what it is you just pick something and stick
with it a little bit and it'll either say wow I I feel connected with this it's resonating for me I'm feeling
results or you know it doesn't feel like but huh I picked up this book over here and wow that's interesting there was
somebody who um um actually just this week who I was
her first Dharma teacher she's been in it for about a couple of years and uh we have a great relationship everything's
good and um she's just recently gotten drawn over into Japanese renai
Zen which I know a little bit I used to there's a rinai C called Zen Mountain
Monastery up in Upstate New York and the Abbot liked my first book so they used to bring me there I didn't know anything about rinai Zen but I would aw me to
come and teach and it was nice to go there it's just a different thing and so we had a discussion um um
and she felt all guilty because she's going working with a new
teacher and coming in a New Direction and everything and that was nice of her to you know want to care and but it's
not like that if renai Zen's becoming alive for her
and she did not follow that then I'd be worried right but she thought oh she she
didn't want to feel like she's not with me it's like no it's not like that it's about each of us so I appreciated her
and again caring right so that's what what or it may not even be in the Buddhist world I don't know it may be
your anyway you get the idea right because and this is the last thing I'll say and then I how you do this is the
details I'm just trying to kind of give you my sense that um I mean it very
seriously I have come to feel like so used one more thing I'll back up for a second so I've always been identified as
a somati or Jan teacher uh that's become more uh around
more but back in the early days way back it was like me and one other guy Lee braisington and that was it and it was
like oh man you guys aren't Insight teachers and it was a whole big thing right back then and of course it's not
true we've learned and anybody who Who develops samati knows that the Insight
the mindfulness the concentration the heart it's all there but if you're not doing somati or Janna and you're just
doing pure mindfulness the concentration the mindfulness the Insight the heart it's all there whichever doorway or you
pick it they all parts have elements are there and come in in the right way for
you right so it's kind of like that so so we have to find our way so it used to
be even up into the really only even the last seven or eight years as I've really
come to appreciate that even talking about Janna that word won't mean much to you but it's these deep meditative
States that's too restrictive because it's kind of defined in a certain way it's still
good the real path this is the part that I have to say again it may be different
than what you've heard but it's all right I really see that the path as we
we we train ourselves to be able to connect more deeply and authentically within
ourselves and then we learn two things to actually experientially what does
that mean to be connected with in ourselves because that's hard for some of us and easier for others it's just different for each person
and then to listen to that and let it start to lead the way so that um and we
learn to distinguish between like our likes and dislikes and our greed hatred and delusion and our authentic voice
because they can mask right we think we're following ourselves and really it's just your opinion or whatever right
so we we learn to really recognize something that's authentic our own Spiritual Awakening and path and then it
starts to open and then the the whole path is we know how to follow and then it knows how to lead us and open and
find show the way and there's no limit on what that might look
like it's a vast vast word and it transcends Traditions
methods systems we use all of those systems that's important we're in a
tradition we practice we have teachings they're important you know there's all
the Buddhist lists we use these things techniques people are doing the same
thing from other Traditions too but once you connect in and the aliveness reveals itself that's the whole path there and
and then it can open up I can say more about it's just amazing some of the ways that can reveal ourselves and we really
come to some to it's really I mean it sounds kind of like happy Feelgood talk but really I
think it's it's finding the pathway uh deep into
ourselves yeah and sometimes we can find places of
amazing beauty that we just had no idea was there or Liberation or Enlightenment or all kinds of things that we that that
that was there but we were just had lost the connection and it can be kind of like that anyway so um I'm going to stop
there and um again if if that was to I don't even just forget it and and uh we we can
just open it up if anybody has a comment uh about anything I said anything else
question yeah bill please go uh hi Richard um
hey um like maybe everyone here when it comes to my practice I've got my
strengths and I've got my weaknesses right uh and uh I'm I'm extremely
grateful for my strengths they've made all the difference in my life I'm comparably happier than I used to be and
I feel like my strengths are are real strengths I'm happy for them um my
weaknesses are uh discipline and if you
will concentration um my you know my my daily
practice is not really there as far as formal sitting practice is concerned
even though I think I ought to be doing it I'm sure I'm sure I should and the concentration
when I'm sitting my uh ability to follow the breath is is poor I me I can go off
on a 10-minute Daydream without barely even being aware that I'm doing it um
it's it's hard for me to follow the breath I'm just just not natural for me um so um when you say it doesn't matter
what you do uh correct in a way um that makes me
feel good cuz you know go with my strengths right but but I'm wondering can you say something since you're the
samat guy um if I was able to develop the
concentration practice skills and and and do them dedicatedly regularly uh
what kind of difference do you think that makes I think it will transform your whole life say more it will
transform your life and
that's everybody I know and I think it's just because of my books maybe I tracked
people here you know um over the years I still do uh you know from all over every
person without exception I've ever met who's a who's appreciated the power of
samati a lot of them come what we call Pure Insight tradition everything everyone sees the Power and the benefit
of it and that it supercharges everything else the mindfulness the
Insight the heart qualities having said that so and you're smiling but I just
want to say so that's all real but there's no like got to get
anything because let's just imagine someone didn't have any concentration at
all never did it you sat down to just be present with yourself actually when you've got
concentration it's easy to sit with yourself that's easy cuz you've got the power and the support of the samade to
meet all the challenges and the ups and downs and everything it's a heroic journey to sit and be present
with yourself without concentration when your body's hurting your mind's out of control you're either so Restless you're
going to jump out of your skin or the opposite you're falling asleep and everything and to be with all of
that that's the heroic practice right there for real and everybody who's done
that knows that I've been through that a lot myself and so everybody has if you could just do and sit to be
with yourself and just in the FI it's not always like a fire but just in that
with your suffering with the ups and the downs and be with everything learning to just that would there's a purification
and a letting go and a non clinging that would come just to learn to let go just by doing nothing we don't talk
about Som we don't talk about anything just a can I just be present and for all the times I can't be present how do I be
with that and everything so that's an example when I say it doesn't matter what you do I don't mean in life it doesn't matter what you do I mean I
guess you could say that but I hope we all would want to I'm talking about when we're doing different practices within
like the Dharma and everything you're everyone's going to show up with their a combination of
their strengths and their weaknesses if you want to call it that I don't I use different language because weakness but
just the way we work along with whatever Our intention is how we want to consciously aim our
practice and then a whole big piece and
is we have some intentions but then we practice in a certain way that's aiming
us but the whole trick of the whole thing is we let the present moment teach
us and inform us that's the whole thing how you do that as a learning that
comes in a skill over time because a lot of times we're just caught and we were reactive but if we with time everyone
can learn we we come to see like just what's going on in the present moment and
during the times when every the body's cooperating the mind's clear we're steady we can practice in ways and just
develop the concentration side and it doesn't matter because on its own there's going to be times when you can't
concentrate mind's not cooperating emotional stuff's coming up and everything
and people say oh I had a bad meditation there's literally not such a thing as a bad meditation absolutely not
there's just what is happening in the present moment and how do we work with it and if we can hold that attitude we
do and we do the best we can because a lot of times we don't even
see the way we're caught we're reactive we can't so we do the best we can
meeting the present moment with as much clarity as we have you don't have to be better at it than you are you just don't
cuz if we had to be better at it than we are well you're screwed I'm thinking my son is he's in
high school he's a a jazz trombone player he's a pretty good player for high school player he can he can play
and he sounds great and uh he's pretty good and he's on this you know Jazz Ensemble and everything so sometimes
I'll get his trombone and try to play and I remember when he started playing was in the third grade when he started couldn't do anything no skill no ability
nothing that's how it is for me I try to play if you any of you play a brass instrument uh it's hard you have to
develop your Essure it's it's tough but you with you don't have to have any
skill you don't even have to know how to get skill you just show up with I mean you
get a teacher you start to blow and you just do your best to try to get it and starting from
nothing you can get like really good it's like that with our Dharma practice
with life with meditation we bring the best we have you don't again I'm not
just I mean I am trying to make you feel good but it's not just trying to make you feel good it's literally
true that you start with what you have you try to remember the best you
can to let the present moment be your teacher you're going to forget that you you know right a million
times you're going to be pissed off at the present moment and you're going to remember this talk you're going you know
damn that shankman and you know because you're going to be suffering welcome to the
club we're all sufferers there will be times when you can remember and you'll do the best you
can to let go around your suffering and over time it gets
better I consider myself to be of average natural ability as a meditator
but um but I put in the time most people by the way most people
in this room don't have much of a daily meditation practice I've just learned over time it's just how it is it's
hard I used to teach I started I used to do a lot of prison Dharma work I don't anym this is but I started a couple of I
was a prison chaplain volunteered at a couple of California state prisons I started a bunch of dharm they're still
going and uh I remember um one was Selena's Valley
State Prison that's a tough level four Prison it's like Pelican Bay kind of a thing we'd run our group going every
week and then sometimes there'd be a violent incident they would have a lock down and until they sorted out for a few
days a week a month or something you know and so once they had this lock down everybody's in their cells they bring
them they feed you in your cell you just don't get out I think once or twice a week individually you get to come out
and go shower or something that's it we couldn't run the group and when when
we could when the lockdown was over it been I think a month or something a long time we came back we were going around
the group asking how are people doing some people were they managed okay
as you can imagine it was rough on some people and I said well how's your meditation going one
guy said I don't know I I just couldn't find the time to to
meditate I I've heard you say this before that's my that that's true that's
real that's my favorite story
because it's not your fault and I cannot tell you how many
people judge themselves in their Dharma practice by
how well their daily meditation practice is kept
up we won't do it but I guarantee you I've just been on the scene long enough
if we there's what 40 or 50 people here in this room if we went around
here a lot of people would have that feeling so you're not alone I've been
there myself even today like my somis and I'm
by the way I'm just going to say a little about my own practice it's no big thing many people so don't I'm not
making a big claim I've been doing a long time uh when I sit to meditate my concentration is
good it's great and I can have times I'm sitting
in this thing and I'm like way in it's really good and I'm restless and bored and I want to go check CNN if Biden did
whatever and and I'm sitting here Bliss out in meditation it can be like this we're
human beings we have all these forces we do the best we can
find the style of practice you like oh wait I've got to add one more
thing this is so important here's a question I think I already know the answer it's it's more
of a rhetorical question or you can answer if you want in your daily life as you just go
about your business a lot of times we can just be caught up in things we call it losing our mindfulness and we just sort
of sometimes people say the person went unconscious they're not unconscious we you know what they mean you're conscious
but you're just kind of it's like being on automatic pilot or something like that when you're not on autoptic and you
wake up if you will and you know what's happening in the present
moment and you notice say there's reactivity in the mind do you do your best to kind of let go of your re
activity best you can or do you go no I'm reactive I think I'll just go with it no you
don't when you wake up out of automatic pilot and you notice there's ill will do
you say yeah sometimes we do because the F the power can actually be strong
but or do you say you know I have an intention to live in a way this is actually one of my intentions to live in
a way where my heart never closes off ever I have plenty of work to do for
sure but um um I mean things get better but uh you know but that's that's that I aspire to
that when I wake up and realize oh there's reactivity in the
mind even if the energy of it is like no I'm going to tell that person or it's going to I have to go back to my
intention and realize wait a minute I don't feel like letting go of my ill will now I still have to do it because
that's my intention if I'm going to want to live with my heart doesn't close off don't you do the same thing or
whatever your intention is or do you just go no you know I'm pissed off and I know I am and I should have a kind heart
but screw it I'm just going to no you you do you use the time when you know
what's happening when you're not on onop pilot the best you can we all do what
more can you do that's full blast Arma practice so if you're judging your practice by just how well or poorly your
daily sitting is yeah get support sit more it's better if you can do it sure
but it's it's it's an in uh inaccurate way of judging
yourself actually judging yourself by how well or poorly you show up for anything is is is
um I would say maybe this is uh hubris for me to tell you what your criteria
should be but I'll just throw it out there um how well rep portly you show up or or
are or in any situation that that's not that's inaccurate way to judge yourself
how well you that's just reactive patterns of your mind that's what we're working on your intention is a much more
accurate um I would say uh
criteria how well you pull it off is that's just how well you've worked on your reactive patterns that's the
process that's the lifelong process we're all in but you're but your intention if
you've got a good intention to live in a way that creates less and less suffering for yourself and others and to create
more happiness and well-being for yourself and others when you lose that
and you're just not being such a great person in the moment you haven't your intention still
there you just lost contact with it it's all this happened it's still true for
you you just forgot and you get caught up in the energy of the moment your good
intention is still true for you and that says a lot about your good heart so that's I would say a better way to judge
than how well you meditate so if if um
if you're are able to maintain a good daily practice um with the benefits thereof
you're more likely to remember that good good intention and and to stay with
it it's like
anything my son's trombone playing is way better when he's more regularly
practicing and when he doesn't for those of you who play a brass instrument I don't but I've learned enough like you
lose your Ure there and you and it gets weaker and he loses his control doesn't have a sound he needs to get it back and
and then he's and then he's back in it so and then he's naturally flowing and when he's really flowing he tells me
he's not even thinking just musical feelings and I'm not a musician I don't know what this is like but just the
musical feeling and comes out and he's not even thinking where he's moving a slide it's just
flowing that's where can go so it's like that as Dharma practitioners and at some point you know as the Dharma becomes
more alive the lived experience of the living
flow of it is just becomes more and more like a set point for us yeah the other
thing I would just say I I picked up on this I don't this you may not be right for you but you said sometimes it's hard
to be with the breath now you've been a meditator I've known you from way back so I don't know your practice well but
it could be that breath medit is not the best practice for
you and if that's true then there's a question how do I find out if that's true I talk to me or maybe there's
others who could talk to you but that's a whole different thing because everyone can find their best practice and it's a big
world well when you have a moment I have an online online question oh yeah yeah go go yeah okay
um a Mystic writer uh visha Vargas a Mystic writer online
question if possible following what's alive in the practice can it be applied
to intentions and actions in our own lives if we have a talent we want to
develop that that doesn't sound like a question sounds like just a a sharing and a comment right yeah well I pre that
sounds wonder I like that that's great thank you for for the wisdom and that's another thing you know we also there's a
lot of Collective wisdom here obviously on the live stream or whatever I'm not sure and so thank you I really
appreciate that person for putting that wisdom into the
group just one quick thing before you just go here so I'm just watching the time here because I can see the clock
it's 10:35 and I'll say in about 10 minutes It'll be 10:45 just so those of you who need to go go and for those who
want to hang back if if it's still alive we can still go a few minutes so anyway so please go
yes um I've been thinking a lot about um my
name is Sylvie I've been thinking a lot about ethics lately and uh when you
started the discussion uh today you know you are trying to help us find words
that were coming that were alive for us on why we're practicing and and you came
up with this um definition that seems to be common denominator for all of us of
wanting to increase well-being um for ourselves and other and I want you to
continue let me say that was me saying that yeah I don't know that everybody would sign up for that I'm guessing most
people probably but yeah I was just yes so please go yes um so I sign up for
that um within that that context
um I'm I I've been trying to connect this to you know what we call ethics in
the real world outside of Dharma Circle um because I was having this
conversation with someone who is not a practitioner
um and
when I came to meditation my motivation or anything I
heard about the practice was not ethics and somehow from meditating I've become
more sensitive to well-being and suffering and what causes it and and all
of those things and so I'm kind of getting closer to ethics I'm finding
myself but can ethics be realized without
mindfulness of course in how would you be able to have an
ethical life if you're not aware of the suffering you're causing yourself and
others well I don't know I mean that's a big question um you know I don't know if
I know the answer to that but there were two things first of all without you said can a person just be ethical without
mindfulness it may be that plenty of people don't think about mindfulness maybe they're caught on automatic pilot
a lot but the natural response maybe no none of us are perfect but the natural response is one of empathy of kindness
of care it's just out of comes out of how they naturally are so I don't think you have to say someone has to have
mindfulness now if we don't have what we call mindfulness which is so to me you know mindfulness my
definition of mindfulness is many definitions out there mine is not being on automatic pilot there's the practices
of mindfulness but the mental state of mindfulness you actually know what's happening in a present moment instead of
being lost in it then sure if if if you don't have that and we're caught up you
could say that we don't have freedom or choice in those moments because we're just reacting out of the
habitual uh patterns uh uh mental uh um
tendencies in Our Minds when we get a stimulus and there's response so if we want to make changes we have to have
some awareness to to make changes sure so uh yeah I guess where I'm I'm should
you have to want to do it and then be aware of what's Happening
sure where this is coming from is there is a lot
of enormous amount of harm that is being caused in in the world by all of us
human beings um but at the level of consciousness of the
humanity there is a very low awareness of that harm right and it's
not like it seems that we make assumptions that you know those people
are unethical those people are ethical those are good not good but most of the
people I've spoken to I find that they naturally want
to do something that's ethical right um
but what's the what's the question or what's the problem question is is if you're completely
unaware like you're the intention you keep talking about the intention right I
I my intention is to do good but I'm living my life I'm not talking about
myself but you know so and so is living their life on autopilot yeah right but their intention
is to be good we don't need to think about them we just need to think about
ourselves right that's more of a I I don't mean to kind of shut down what you're saying but
it sounds you know and I I hope I'm not coming across that way uh but it sounds like you're sort of having more of a
um I I don't mean mean this in any negative but maybe like a theoretical discussion of how it might be for other
people if they don't have mindfulness or something I I I don't know if that's right but um so you can correct me you
know if if I'm not if I'm missing what you're saying but so to me when I hear that it's like well I mean I don't know
I don't know brain science I don't know a lot of psychology you know what motivates people how they'll be that's
kind of the bigger questions but we can each look into ourselves and here we are
how we got here why want to be mindful why we ended up as Dharma practitioners they could have gone many many different
ways it's a big big world and we can tend to ourselves so personally I and I
just don't know the answer for everybody else and and and I don't know if it's that
useful like what what are you going to do if if say I said I knew the answer and answer what can we do with that
information we're not going to go around telling everybody um hey you you better be mindful
well it's not it's not telling people you're going to be mindful but it's you
know I'm in in my life in my work and what I want
to accomplish with my life I'm seeking to reduce human suffering in certain
sectors of um and a lot of it
is creating a wellness um yeah but what's the question
I'm I'm still just I think I'm missing what you're I guess my question is
what can you give me maybe your definition my your definition or your
understanding of how you would explain the relationship between what we call mindfulness and
ethics and you know it is connected but how would you you mean as as practicing
and developing it or just the state of what however you Define mental ethics
just being acting and living and manifesting that as opposed to cultivating it as I'm just not I'm
having yes manifesting I try U because I I think there's a way to connect what the both
of you are saying and I think when you're talking about Good Intentions yes that person might have good intentions
but it might be tainted by greed hatred and delusion so then it doesn't it's not
the purest but then what you were saying um was how does it relate to us and I
don't know about you and I hope it's okay for me to share what I've kind of been reflecting on but when we think
about the violence that's happening right and it's caused by hatred misunderstanding and all those things
sometimes I feel the same thing in my heart when somebody cuts me off or
interrupts me or you know things like that and so it's like how do we make
sense of it on a personal level it's like well we sometimes I see the same
tendencies in my own heart that's not you know wanting to like shoot someone
but it's like the same kind of aggression inside um and so you check yourself in those moments but I think
when we have like these ethical like discussions or debates a lot of people are just thinking about it in their
rational minds and but but the rational mind is subject to Greed hatred and
delusion I don't know if that makes sense at all yeah we're all so maybe we
can if we want to continue this maybe at the end I'm happy to chat more about it but um um all of
us um have plenty of greed hatred and delusion in our minds every one of us
everyone you're ever going to meet has it even if you get a guest teacher come
here and everybody's bowing down at their feet and I'm not being disrespectful they're human beings and
we're all doing the best we can a lot of people have a lot a lot of Purity I'm not being disrespectful people I respect
tremendously and when I've had conversations with many people whose names would be well
known they would be real about being a human being still being on this path it just gets subtler and subtler one of the
ways I think about the path if any of you know like mathematics when you have a graph there a thing called an ASM toote and they'll graph something you
know maybe the the the graph will show a line coming down like this and maybe there's this xaxis and the line comes
down and then it approaches it curves down and the way they're graphing the graphic gets closer and closer and
closer and it goes out to infinity and as it goes further out it gets infinitely close it never really gets
there but just closer and closer and Clos and I wonder sometimes um if it's kind of like that that it just gets
better and better and closer and closer but so maybe work to be done or is there this because we've built up in the in
the in the various spiritual Traditions the Buddhists have done it too we've built up this
Perfection and don't want to be disrespectful maybe there is a Perfection out there uh nobody actually
knows um um nobody knows but we're all on the path to find
out so we went a little over so I'm happy to so you're grabbing the mics so are we wrapping it up or actually I just
wanted to uh tell you Richard that I remember years ago you um you gave a
talk and you said that you had on your altar correct me if I'm wrong on your altar you had a picture of George W bush
and you tried to not Harden your heart and and I remember hearing that because
that was a fail okay by the way that reminds me so
I haven't had an altar for years I should P I don't I'm just don't do that anymore but I should pull actually make
one but now George W bush that's kids
play who would have thought that I would yearn from from the good old days some
of you are too young to know oh my God
now listen
that's kids play little did I know I didn't I didn't appreciate what I
had is people a lot of people are getting up does it feel like we're kind of done or all right and a lot of people are
going in about 5 minutes over it's 10:50 so here's the thing um thank you all uh
for letting me hang out with you and we were kind of all over the place I hope it was useful and if not can be like
that sometimes um I'll hang out a little bit if any wants to chat it's okay or you know I don't know what time the
people because at some point the people who are running things do want to be able to leave also people could just L
up okay because we want to be respectful of those of you who are you know managing here okay thank you so much and
nice to get oh and if any of you happen to be interested you may not be you know there's a lot of Retreats you can do here through IRC but if you are ever
interested in connecting up with me up there by that Donna table you can put your name on a little sign up list and
there's an email there for for um kind of Retreats I run and just one more
question uh where would we buy your book wherever Dharma books are sold okay
thank you